Thanks, Matthew.
So yeah, today I'll be talking about the making of Little
Inferno, or the many mistakes we made while making Little
Inferno, because there were many.
So quick overview, Tomorrow Corporation is myself, Kyle
Gabler, and Alan Blomquist.
We met roughly 10 years ago at grad school at the
Entertainment Technology Center in CMU.
After that, we all kind of got jobs and internships at various EAs.
I went to EA Tiburon all the way down in Orlando, and Alan and Kyle were kind of local here.
Kyle left to start 2D Boy with Ron Carmel in, I guess, like 2007 or 2006 or something like that.
They made World of Goo, which I'm pretty sure everybody's heard of here.
And then they brought on Alan to help with the Wii port.
I stayed on at EA and worked and pitched Henry Hatsworth,
kind of internally, which was a DS game,
about a British guy that drinks a lot of tea
and gets in a giant robot and kills things.
Um, so what is Little Inferno?
Uh, Little Inferno is kind of like that Yule Log,
uh, station that comes on for 24 hours,
kind of around November.
Um, I don't know if they have that anymore,
but you can see it on YouTube for much, much longer.
Um, but being that this is an indie title,
we couldn't just be inspired by one thing.
Miyamoto is famous for drawing inspiration from all of his hobbies and you know that kind of stuff so
I guess gardening kind of led to Pikmin and wandering around in caves and killing bats
with a sword led to Zelda and then getting ripped I guess led to Wii Fit.
We were kind of inspired by ordering lots and lots of things from Amazon Prime,
and then waiting and tracking the shipments to see when they would arrive,
and then getting them and opening them.
It's all very exciting, as anybody who orders things knows.
So, Little Inferno is kind of the mixture of the ULOG with Amazon Prime, in a nutshell.
Um, and in the game you basically buy and burn lots and lots of toys that you get from the Tomorrow Corporation catalog.
You buy toys with Tomorrow bucks, you burn them, they give you more coins, and that kind of increasingly escalates in a bizarro economy.
And packages take anywhere from five seconds to five minutes to arrive.
We kind of found that adding that delayed time increases delayed gratification.
Also gives items some value because when we didn't have any time,
people would just buy everything at once, chuck them all in, and not see what anything does.
Each item does something kind of unique, so we wanted to highlight that.
But you can speed up the shipment times with tomorrow's stamps, which you get as either random drops or from
completing combos
Our combos are all kind of like
Wordplay so the movie night combo is burning like a TV with a corn on the cob which makes popcorn
and then they get really obtuse later on so you'll have like the
Burning the uncle Sam fireworks with the rushing nesting doll is like the Cold War combo
So yeah.
But, you know, despite the fact that this is kind of like a really weird game,
people seem to like it.
We've since then released on six platforms.
We were there for one of the five indie titles for the Wii U launch,
which is pretty awesome.
We're on PC, Mac, Linux.
Last year we popped up on iPad and then later on iPhone.
And then at the end of the year we're up on Android.
So that was pretty cool.
Also, it's in seven languages, so if you live in Europe,
chances are it might be in your language.
There were some IGF nominations last year,
and we ended up getting the Technical Excellence Award,
which was pretty awesome for Alan,
since that was like a one-man thing.
It was totally confusing for just about everybody
who played it, but it did sell over a million copies,
so that was cool.
So yeah, why make a game about something so mundane about just throwing shit in the fireplace and burning it?
So we noticed this bizarre trend in games, kind of, I guess, around the time we were thinking of this,
where there are these really cutesy kind of games with, like, really nice repetitive tasks,
and they stretched on kind of endlessly.
and some of them have weird economics
of indentured servitude and stuff.
And we're like, man, what if all of these awesome games
had a horrible secret underlying them
that's just festering below this cute facade?
So we decided to make Little Inferno,
and I will play the trailer.
Oh, audio?
Oh, hang on. Do we have? Is that my system? Hang on a second. Uh oh, computer fail. Sorry guys.
Um, should I restart quickly? Nah, it's okay. Anyway, um, yeah, thanks Windows.
I would sing it if I knew the lyrics that good, my voice was good, but anyway, it's
basically children, if you haven't seen this stuff on YouTube, but it's about kids singing
about throwing things in the fire and breathing in the flaming potpourri.
Which they're about to do right now.
Um, there we go.
It's a little inferno just for me.
Anyway, yeah, so it has a really, like,
the trailer has a very, like, kind of cute facade,
and now the kid's like,
oh, but I thought burning things was bad.
Well, you're right, but up above the chimney,
way up in the sky, it's been snowing for years,
and we just don't know why.
Sorry, Kyle.
Our world is getting colder, but, oh, man.
All right, sorry, it's been a while, guys.
But there's no need for alarm.
Just sit by your fire, burn all of your toys,
and stay warm.
So here's where we get dark.
Sing Little Inferno just for me.
I've got the fireplace that burns at 100 million degrees.
It's Little Inferno just for me.
And that's it.
So yeah, we released this decidedly grim trailer
that starts off very cutesy, kind of like Log,
if you guys remember Ren and Stimpy.
And so Little Inferno is kind of a game that has a secret.
And everything in the game kind of
drives towards that gradually.
So the whole game is supposed to make
you feel really uncomfortable the more you play it.
So you start off with the first catalog burning really
innocuous things, like letter blocks, batteries that explode.
corn on the cob that spits out kernels of the Internet's popcorn.
By the second catalog, you're burning kind of stranger things.
So, like a leprechaun that gives things kind of leprosy,
or an unhappy elf that has dynamite strapped to his chest,
or a cat that shoots out huge amounts of excrement and launches upwards.
And then, as you start playing, you start to get letters from other people in this world.
There's Miss Nancy, who owns Tomorrow Corporation, and made Little Inferno,
who kind of walks you through, and she's like a Paula Deen-Oprah mashup.
There's the weatherman, who kind of tells you about how the weather is increasingly getting colder and colder.
And then there's your neighbor, or a girl you find out is your neighbor, spoilers, Sugar Plumps,
who, as the game progresses, she's kind of the character that's one step ahead of you and is playing the game.
And eventually, as you become better and better friends, even though she's sending you letters and you don't really have a way to respond,
She burns down her house and dies, and the game gets kind of dark there.
So that's like 90% of the game is constrained to this one view,
and you're basically looking at this fireplace for the vast majority of your playtime,
in between, you know, looking at this bright, cheery catalog.
And that was pretty intentional.
Towards the end of the game,
once you get your last catalog,
you get a letter from this mysterious character
who kind of hints, who starts convincing you
that maybe you should burn down your house.
And we'll see.
I do need sound.
Actually, sound is less important for this one, it's cool.
Oh, you're gonna pipe it in?
All right.
Technical assistance here.
I don't know if that's going to do it.
Anyway, so you get a letter from this mysterious shadow
character, who tells you, now we've got to skip ahead.
No, it's cool.
go really fast. This is a problem with a lot of slides.
So you get a letter from this character. She kind of tells you how to escape your house.
Anyway, so you get all of the items that you've been kind of gifting to your friend Sugar Plum till this time.
You burn them together. It triggers this magical tenth combo which overrides the
fire safety controls in your Little Inferno fireplace.
and all of a sudden everything goes kind of crazy
and you find yourself outside of the fireplace in this outside world.
There we go, eventually it's going to come crashing down.
So suddenly we go from this fireplace, this really casual game, and now it's an adventure game for like the last 10%.
And there's an entire town that you're kind of just walking around. It's pretty deserted. There's like nobody out there except for you.
Everybody's inside playing with their little inferno fireplace.
You meet the mailman, who's this guy that's been actually delivering all of the mail to you behind your back.
You never turn around and there's this guy that just kind of comes in and drops off all the packages.
And you just kind of wander around until you get to Tomorrow Corporation,
which you eventually find your way in by talking with the gatekeeper and get past their high security.
and just wander down the hall until you meet Miss Nancy,
who tells you that the world is gradually freezing,
and the whole town, everything is kind of freezing to a halt,
just before she jumps into her giant pink rocket ship
and takes off, presumably to better pastures.
And then you kind of just leave the outskirts of the town
and go off with the weatherman, jump in his balloon,
and sail off to kind of a better future, we hope.
So that was mistake number one. It's really risky to put all of your cool content at the end of the game.
Which will go directly into mistake number two. So we overthought everything.
So back when we started working on this game in like 2010,
or maybe 2009 even, we were like, man,
this is going to be six months.
Our working project name was My Fireplace at that point.
Ended up taking like two and a half years.
So yeah, like five times the length.
And back then we were thinking like, man, it'd be great.
So you buy digital stuff, you throw it in this fireplace,
and then there are catalogs, and you
can buy stuff from the catalogs, and then they'll ship to you.
And then like the.
items get really weird. You have like flowers that pop up. There's like popcorn.
There are these wooden idols that kind of sing when you burn them. And then one day you get a
package from the mailman which is a button that allows you to leave your house. And then you can
wander around in this town. It's a snowy kind of town. And you quickly discover it's been snowing
for as long as anybody can remember. And, uh,
And then there are all these characters, there's Miss Nancy, there are these Christmas carolers, there's another player, there's the mailman, and a bunch of other ones.
Which kind of sounds familiar.
Um, except, yeah, we went crazy and overscoped.
So that was the game we wanted to make.
That was the game we ended up making.
In between, we kind of went a little nuts.
So first, we were going to do this whole giant world.
And it was going to be mostly an adventure game.
And then it was going to be, there's
this weird fireplace mechanic.
And you're trading items with people in town.
And we would have all of these adventure game-y puzzles
because we like adventure games.
Maybe you have to launch the school bus into the stratosphere,
or talk with these time-traveling futurists.
There's all sorts of kind of odd things.
But your character is trying to get to Tomorrow Corporation
because they burned down his house
and he's got a legal case against them.
And we had all these weird characters
that you were going to meet in town.
There's Back Alley Bob, who deals with bizarre off-market items,
and this game nerd character.
the original developers of Little Inferno, who are now
homeless and crazy, and this coffee guy, who's
also a motivational speaker.
And then there are all these fabulous Tomorrow Corporation
employees, and more developers, and people just kind of
standing around outside the gates.
And then we started working on maybe looking
at different art styles for this world
that we were excited to build.
So really early stuff.
And then we were like, man, that's not really enough.
So let's add the subway, which travels through time.
And in there, you will buy tickets.
And you will use those tickets to advance,
to accelerate time so you can get your packages faster.
So all of a sudden, you know.
need to go a couple minutes or like a couple of hours or some days and yeah
why not just hop on the the timeline express we were gonna have this really
crazy puzzle where I guess the last thing you got took 10 years to ship and
you either had to figure out some way to break the train to do it or maybe set
your system clock forward by 10 years but then really again nobody's gonna
want to do that so
And then of course there's a home decorating metagame because, you know, badges and virtual hoarding is kind of what makes games.
So obviously we need a home decorating section.
And then we're going to turn this into like a weird Katamari-style game where you're burning shit in a fireplace and then that kind of burns down and suddenly you're in the neighborhood and you're burning bigger and bigger things and then you're in the city and you're burning bigger and bigger things.
And then finally, you're at the world,
and you're burning planets, and satellites,
and abstract concepts.
And it just kind of got out of control.
But fortunately, the Wii U became this thing.
So we kind of took a long, hard look at everything
and just went back to kind of the original,
tightened everything up, and made it in time.
So that was cool.
Um, yeah, mistake number three.
So we made a game that no one could talk about,
um, including us, which is a problem.
First of all, it was kind of a weird mechanic
that nobody had really done,
and when you say, what do you do in the game?
Oh, you throw things in a fire and you burn them.
Oh, that great, that sounds like fun.
So it's kind of like, that's kind of a weird concept,
but then there's also this kind of secret ending to it
that nobody, we didn't want to tell anybody about
to spoil it.
And then there was also, this was also kind of at a time
when indie games were being ripped off
kind of wholesale rampantly.
So we're like, maybe somebody will beat us to market
with their own fireplace simulator,
weird game with Amazon Prime.
So we should probably keep that under
until we have something.
So, after working on this for two years,
we finally started to release details about the game
less than five months before launch.
So we announced it on June 28th.
Just the name and this image, nothing else really.
About four months in, we released the trailer
with the little musical teaser
that I sang for you guys.
And then, less than which, we started to get interviews
because, man, that was a weird teaser.
So people wanted to know more about it.
And we were able to talk about parts of it.
But we couldn't really telegraph the end.
So we started using really unclear language.
Something else is burning.
And then after that we ended up spilling the beans to Nintendo Power, since we were shooting to be there.
And we were really expecting that somebody would spoil the ending,
and we were really concerned about, like, man, maybe that'll get out, that'll be kind of horrible,
nobody will play this thing that we've been working on forever.
And we gave them all of the images for the outside stuff, which they put in there.
I mean, they're there.
It's kind of cool.
They never mention it, and nobody actually ever
thought that any of that was going
to be used in the final game, I guess.
Just scouring the internet, nobody made that leap,
which was awesome.
And then finally, we launched in November.
And we kind of waited to see what people were going to do.
What are people going to say about this weird thing
we've made?
And we were kind of hoping for like,
a crying game effect, because their whole marketing thing was,
if you know the ending, don't spoil it, don't ruin it.
And we were like, yeah, that's great.
That's exactly what we should do.
And that works really well for movies, because, like, man,
you just do the same thing.
You sit there, and you watch something, and that's it.
But in a game, obviously, oh, the ending is really cool.
But up until then, what are you doing?
I don't know.
You're burning stuff.
So we started to get reviews and comments
from people who had played it and had enjoyed it.
But all of their comments were kind of like,
well, this is what you do, but you don't really want
to know what you do or what this game is about.
I don't want to spoil it for you.
You don't want to know.
And that may have hurt us.
So there's that.
Oh, this is a fun one.
So if you, mistake number four,
the message will be missed or misunderstood.
So if you have a message in your game,
which ours does, Kyle likes messages,
chances are, you know, people aren't gonna get it.
And that's, you know, that's cool, that's fine.
So a lot of people thought the game was about global warming.
And we have a lot of cool illustrations from people.
And I guess it could be, but the truth
is we wanted to make a fireplace simulator,
and it doesn't really make sense to put that in a world
where it's always hot or where you have regular seasons.
So you kind of want to set that in a place
where it's cold all the time.
So the world was kind of bent around that.
So, yeah, not about global warming.
And then there was like, man,
is this a commentary on freemium games?
Because people hate freemium games, I guess.
And, I mean, not really.
We did like the bright aesthetics,
and some of the loops are kind of fun.
But I think a lot of people just don't like freemium games.
you know, that's cool.
A lot of people I know that play them
just kind of try to play this metagame
where how much of the content can they see
without actually spending money.
So no, it wasn't really about that either.
I mean, what we were trying to convey
was kind of something just a bit simpler.
Indie games tend to deal with the team's neuroses,
and ours was, we were all hitting 30,
so we were starting to feel like old men.
and we were kind of concerned just about time and making most of it and not wasting it.
So it was really more about just kind of getting un-rutted, getting out of your kind of rut,
whether it was a job you hated or a bad relationship or anything like that.
In Little Inferno, everybody's just kind of stuck doing the same thing over and over and over
and don't realize there's kind of this whole thing outside of it.
this whole world. And after a while, people started to pick up on that message.
Aaron's Signal was a prominent YouTuber, I guess, kind of got it dead on.
And we started to see other articles that were kind of also grasping onto these themes.
So that was cool. And then eventually, we even saw YouTubers
started kind of correcting each other.
So yeah, the first guy thinks that the Earth has...
going to freeze up and the sun is getting bigger so everybody has to escape to other
planets.
And the other guy's just like, nah man, you're totally wrong.
So thanks, brigiers.
And then our last mistake was not changing the background,
which was kind of, I mean, we,
I mean, obviously we're making a fireplace simulator,
so it should be in a fireplace.
But that led to other problems.
So the game feels like a really small game,
which, you know, to some degree, it's a fast game,
you're supposed to be able to play it
in about the length of a long movie,
so you can see the kind of cool twist ending and everything.
But we ended up actually making a lot of stuff for this game.
So we have something like 150 unique assets.
All of the art is different.
They all have their own sound effects, VFX.
You know, everything has kind of a unique reaction,
which is way more assets than World of Gouhad and, you know,
Henry Hatsworth.
So it's just a lot of stuff to make.
The tech was also kind of nuts.
So every item has bones and physics and joints
and can explode or freeze or disintegrate or affect
gravity.
They all have unique kind of things that they do.
You can pick up a lot of them and just shatter them outright.
They also have to know when to blacken and deform,
depending on how close they are to our fluid simulator.
And then, you know, from there,
to make the fire look believable,
the fire has to have, like, you know,
good fluency, also heat distortion,
also particles, also a whole bunch of other stuff.
And this was all created by one guy,
cause he's, Alan's pretty rad.
So it was like, man, yeah, there was a lot of stuff
kind of going in there to make this fireplace simulator.
But kind of at the end of the day, it was like, man,
you're still looking at the same screen.
And when you burn something, it eventually
disintegrates and disappears, and you're just
back at the same screen.
So what can we do?
And our kind of fix was to divide the fireplace up
into three distinct phases.
In the first act, when it's just you by yourself before you figure out you have neighbors,
it's just a fireplace, there's nothing else kind of there.
And in the second act, when you make friends with your neighbor, Sugar Plum, she gives you curtains that are fireproof.
So, alright, it's already cozier, and maybe we can change the ambience slightly.
And then when she burns down her house, the fireproof curtains are kind of destroyed.
And, you know, it's the third act, it's kind of somber.
You're supposed to be kind of wondering if, you know, if there's something else going on,
and, you know, feel her loss and everything.
So the fireplace kind of reflects that as best it can.
But at the end of the day, none of that really helped.
The fact that we were probably linked to one environment
made a lot of people feel that this was a very small game.
And that just in the end probably
ended up hurting us quite a bit there.
Um, but in the end, uh, you know, we made something we were, you know,
Little Inferno was a pretty great, uh, experience for us.
Um, we got a lot of cool, uh, emails from people that had played it and said that
it helped them get over a relationship or, you know, they cried at the end, or,
um, maybe it made them rethink kind of what they were doing with their own
lives, which is kind of weird and awesome for a fireplace simulator.
Um.
And, like, on a personal note, for Tomorrow Corporation, it kind of helped Alan and I get out of our previous jobs and into the exciting world of indie development.
And now that we're basically done with ports and localization and everything, we're just looking forward to moving on to the next thing.
So, that's it.
So yeah, I don't know if we have any questions.
Show the trailer with sound.
I want to know how you know if the miss is actually effective.
How the, say again?
How do you know if the missing is real misses?
The misses were real misses.
Oh, we saw a lot of comments where people were either confused why it doesn't work on
their like 10 year old Razer phone or why it's not a free Flash game.
So if you...
Say again?
Oh sorry, the question was how did we... it was in regard to the last mistake with the
background, how do we know that the people felt that the game was too small?
So...
Oh, any of the mistakes.
I mean, I guess we can't really know.
I do know that when we overthought it and it took forever, that was definitely a mistake.
We wish we could have taken those years back and made some other stuff too.
That would have been cool.
Um, but, and, and the last one for sure, just from the way people have reacted to it over
time.
But, um, yeah, I guess that's our best guess.
Um, anybody else?
There are also microphones up here.
I don't know if they work.
Do you have any stats on how many players reached the end?
Say again?
Do you have any stats?
On how many players reached the end?
No, we could not track that, unfortunately,
without probably getting kicked out by piracy stuff.
I don't know.
So when you kind of mentioned the scope,
kind of how some of this original idea was so huge.
and how maybe because of the box you guys were given for time and what have you,
you ended up kind of focusing so much more on just the burning mechanic.
Do you feel like...
the previous design was really large in breadth, and then you started evolving the design in depth,
in kind of one core mechanic, or was it always going to be as deep as it is in that mechanic?
Oh, for the burning? Yeah. Yeah, we kind of wanted the burning to be...
The burning was meant to be about as deep as it is now,
and that was... just took way longer than we were expecting.
So we would have loved to have built a world and done this kind of huge thing, but with like three guys and only two of them doing art, and only one of them doing art well, my art kind of sucks.
It was just too much for us to take on.
And it was also really good to focus. I don't know if having that would have added a whole lot more.
Cool.
Cool. Time for one last question, maybe?
All right.
Oh, sorry.
You, sir.
How long did it take to get the front half
to be able to be installed, compared to the back half?
Just merge them together?
Jeez.
Well, the front, I mean, the burning took the longest,
obviously.
Just the technology kind of took,
that in itself was probably a couple of years.
And nailing in on the back half was,
I mean, it's quite a bit faster.
It's known that it was probably a few months, I guess.
But we were doing all this kind of stuff in parallel.
So, cool.
Alright, thanks for coming guys and remember to write us online if you like it.