I'm really honored to be speaking to this audience, a room full of the most talented,
most creative, most hardworking game developers.
And I'm not also only honored to be speaking to you, I'm also a bit terrified of reading
the title of my talk, which is...
Oh, no one cares about your game.
There should have been a big explosion gun sound,
but it didn't quite go off, but you get the gist.
This is not only ...
I mean, the good news is that, of course,
people care about your games, and the even better news
is that I think this no one cares about your game mindset
is one of the most helpful sentences
and mantras I've learned in my marketing career,
and I hope in the next half an hour
I can explain to you how it's hopefully also helpful to you.
So how this talk came about is that I think in the recent years,
generally marketing, games marketing has gotten a lot better.
People just got more professional, took it more seriously.
There's more talks online, more resources.
And there's just great stuff where you can figure out how to set up your Steam page,
there's guides how to plan a marketing campaign, how to do TikToks.
All of that is getting great.
I think what's sometimes a bit missing is the qualitative aspect,
so you don't only do things right.
You make them good.
How do you make them connect with people?
So there was a bit the idea and the basis for this talk,
like some guidelines, how you just get the right quality
of whatever communication you put out.
So it's kind of an attempt of a system
that is a quality check for communication and assets.
My name is Thomas Reisenegger.
I'm the co-founder of Future Friends Games.
We are indie games PR agency,
but we're also indie games publisher.
In my career, I've worked over 100 games.
Stop counting, it's probably a lot more.
Some of our clients are games like Vampire Survivors,
The Forgotten City, Exo One, What the Golf,
the best game ever made, Frog Detective.
So, a lot of different indie titles.
And what we do for these games is quite different.
I really believe that every PR campaign that is really good
is quite tailored for the game and for the needs and for the times.
So, sometimes we do press outreach, sometimes influencer stuff,
we make store pages, we make TikToks, try to go trending a lot.
Do Reddit posts, loads of different things.
I hope that knowledge across loads of different games,
across a lot of different disciplines
is gonna be helpful for the talk for you.
So let's talk about the main topics for today.
First is the Avengers problem, of course.
And then secondly, we talk about
how this no one cares mindset is gonna be helpful
at a micro level, but also on a macro campaign level.
So let's dive right in, and not to be dramatic, but.
We need to talk about the Avengers problem.
I think it's one of the cause why a lot of communication is held back a little bit from game developers and agencies
And it could be better and resonate with people easier
And I think understanding the core of the problem is going to be really helpful. So we just imagine a
game developer a marketing PR person just someone who needs
Starts promoting the game and what you do naturally if you start doing that
You will copy what you already know.
Very human thing, makes sense.
That's a good starting point.
The problem with marketing and PIs,
the most stuff that you see that is marketed at you
is the big stuff.
It's the Avengers, it's the Last of Us,
it's the God of Wars, it's the AAA games,
it's the 1% that you see.
that are really, really big.
But if you think about how those campaigns work,
they put, you put out like a little teaser tweet
and people go crazy.
And then you put on the first teaser trailer
and everybody goes wild.
And then you have another trailer
and everybody knows every scene and analyzes it.
And then the next one and you build up hype
and more hype, hype, and then you launch
and it's like a big explosion.
And that's really great.
And that's just not how it works for like 99% of all games.
So I think understanding that you,
unless you work on those games or those big things,
you're just gonna have a very different experience
promoting your stuff.
And to put it a bit more into context,
and I think to make it easy to understand,
if we imagine we're at a music festival
and we're trying to reach this person,
that's our customer, and in the festival context,
it's someone we wanna make friends with
because they look cool.
We have a quite different position than the band.
The band is like the AAA games,
because the people in the audience,
they show up for them.
They already know a little bit
about what this band does probably.
They're gonna watch them do a five minute drum solo
because what else are they gonna do they are here anyway
to get bombarded with that information
no matter if they want.
They're gonna pay attention.
If the band wants to charge them or make them jump,
they're gonna go along with it
because they just have this real power
of being in the spotlight.
Whereas you, again, 99% of all,
definitely all indie games,
but probably a lot of AA games as well,
or smaller AAA games,
they really have to work from a quite different point of view
because you're just like a random person in the audience
and you try to reach that other person.
So if you want to get their attention,
you probably have to stand out immediately.
You probably have like, when they look over,
you've got like one second to do something
that's noteworthy or funny or catches their eye.
They might turn around and forget you again immediately.
So you really have to just start from a different point of view
and work different to get their attention on you.
And the other problem is once you've convinced them
and once you got their attention,
they maybe tell their friend that's next to them
or two friends, but then there's still the whole other crowd
that has like never heard of you
and you still got to convince.
So I think that's kind of the mindset
how I approach PR marketing for indie games.
And now we look how we can make that work on a micro level.
And what I mean by micro level is basically
everything you put out.
It could be a Reddit post, it could be an email,
it could be your trailer, all form of communication.
And I hope those four rules that we're gonna go through,
the no one cares about your game rules,
they're gonna help you whenever you do those things,
kind of like as a checklist, to keep those things in mind
and make sure your communication is
Avengers proof so you make sure you treat it like a person in the crowd and you don't treat it from a triple A perspective
The very first rule is, get to the point quick.
And that's probably not a big surprise.
You've probably heard this in other marketing talks,
but I think it's really, really important.
And as running an agency, a big part of my job
is just telling people this, get to the point quick.
It happens all the time.
You've probably heard it.
Indie game makes a trailer.
It starts like, you know, with a logo,
and then another logo, and then it's environment shots,
and then 90% of the people are gone.
So front loading most of your assets in communication
makes a lot of sense.
You show immediately what you have
within the first few seconds,
you wanna get your point across.
What I've also like observed and learned over the years
that for some games it's really easy.
Some games have a really obvious gameplay hook
and you just show them the beginning and that makes sense.
But there's other games that have interesting concept,
interesting hooks that are maybe not gameplay driven,
but you still wanna get a point across in a few seconds.
So here's an example of
The launch trailer for Frog Detective 3, it's a GIF that we made out of the trailer, but it gets its own point across and it's gonna start now.
That's it.
You just zoom on the frog, it zooms out, it goes on the scooter, frog detective jumps
away, it looks a bit weird.
It really gets the point of this game across immediately.
If you like, like, quirky humor, if you like that art style, you probably don't need to
know straight away that it's a narrative game or, like, an adventure game.
That's also interesting, but, like, the big selling point of this game is just the humor of it.
So we tried to get that across in the starting scene.
And of course, like you know, no opening, nothing,
it just like zooms right in.
Sometimes you want to get a point across
that is maybe a bit less obvious.
And then you need to not get to the point straight away,
but you need to have something
that keeps people hooked long enough.
So this is a game called Clone Drone VR.
It's like a robot sword fighting VR game.
And we made a post about the new loading screen,
and the loading screen got 300,000 views.
and how we did that was we said we added the most useless and best feature to our game yet.
So that gets people hooked immediately and we showed a nice gameplay in the background.
So we tricked people into like staying on there, obviously the TikToks it also goes
with the sound which is not on here, and then we showed a loading screen.
Big success.
You also see a lot of the examples I'm going to bring today are TikToks.
The reason for that is...
TikTok is really, really good in telling you if people are interested in your stuff
because their main metric is watch time.
So as soon as people swipe away and don't watch your post, you're out.
But those posts that have a good watch time, they go trending.
So it's a very good indicator to test out footage or gameplay hooks and see if they're interesting.
If you want to see more how TikToks are made and learn more about that,
there's two really good talks. One is from Grace Curtis from Future Friends as well,
and the other one from Jared Tan, also from this GDC, about how he did the Cult of the Lamb TikTok.
So I can highly recommend if you want to know more about just TikTok specifically.
Getting to the point quick is also essential on store pages.
I always say Steam store page, eShop page, your store page is your most single important marketing asset.
90% of all people that are ever going to see your game, it doesn't matter how much marketing
you do, they come for your store page.
They just randomly stumble upon it.
It's a really big user base.
This is how most people find your game.
So getting a lot of things across really, really quickly is extremely important.
Here we see Townscaper, for example.
It says instant town building toy.
You immediately know it's not a complicated game.
You know it's a toy. It's a very short sentence.
It indicates it's a small game, a small price.
So you get a lot of information across quick.
But sometimes also getting the point across quick,
meaning getting the point across slow.
So if you look at a strategy game or like a crafting game
that is really mechanics heavy and deep,
You often see on the successful one on the Steam page,
they have a wall of text.
That's obviously not getting to the point quick,
but that just immediately makes clear
that this is gonna be a really deep game.
So I think just keeping in mind
what point you wanna get across
and what format you wanna use is really important.
The second rule, make things work for newcomers.
That's probably the most underrated,
the most often forgotten rule.
Again, I think that comes from the whole Avengers thing.
I think indie games, or general game developers,
are really good at talking to an audience
that's already on board with them,
because you're used to that.
You know how to...
update people and keep them in the loop.
But making things that work for newcomers constantly is quite hard
and also can just be a bit boring if you're a game developer,
you've already made this for seven years.
But keep in mind there's still so, so, so many people
that have never seen your game.
So one example I want to talk about here is Vampire Survivors,
where we helped making the launch trailer.
And this, of course,
was a quite specific problem
because Vampire Survivors was in early access
and then went into 1.0,
but it's already sold millions of copies into early access.
So I think a quite natural thing a lot of people would do
is to really focus on making clear
what's new in the 1.0 update.
But for Vampire Survivors, we knew that on launch day,
there's gonna be hundreds of thousands,
if not millions of people that have never heard of the game
and they're gonna find it on Steam that very day.
So it was really important to make
this two-folded message that works for existing and new players.
So what we did here is we start off by saying
120,000 positive reviews, zero vampires, be the bullet hell.
If you're an existing player,
you see the number of reviews, you're like, yeah, I'm one of them.
You see the zero vampires, which is an in-joke,
there's no vampires in Vampire Survivors.
You probably get that and you think it's funny, hopefully.
And then also in the background, you see new characters from the 1.0 update.
So that's great if you already played the game.
If you've never played the game, you don't care about the new characters.
Well, you probably see the number of reviews and you go like,
okay, that must be a good game.
You see the zero vampires.
You probably have no idea what that means.
Well, you probably get that it's quite a bit quirky.
It's probably funny.
And you know that's going to be indicating some kind of humor in this game.
And then be the bullet hell explains the gameplay.
Another example of making things work for newcomers,
again, really important on TikTok,
because 90% of your traffic on TikTok always come from new people.
is Clone Drone VR again.
There's a post with 900,000 views
where we cut the robot's hair,
so we just take it apart a little bit.
And this is like a fake post now with the text,
where it says, hair cuttings with robot.
And this is how I see a lot of developers,
how they would post it.
And that is perfectly fine
if you talk to existing players.
However, if you talk to people who have never seen your game,
you need to do a lot more framing.
So what we did here is we say,
guess our VR sword fighting game is now a robot hair cutting sim.
So with this short sentence,
we make clear for someone who has never seen this,
that this is not a let's play,
this is not a mod of another game.
We say it's a VR game, we say it's usually a sword fighting game,
and we say it's our game, so they know it's the developer account,
and then we show the developer playing it on top.
So you immediately also visually see it's a VR game.
So just with a simple sentence and a bit of extra visuals,
you have set so much more context
and really get people in that don't know your games.
You lose people immediately if they don't feel included
and they feel like this message isn't for them,
then they will just move on.
The same principle also works in emails.
This is the announcement email for a game called Europa that we work on.
And again, because it's completely new, we just try to establish context and get people on board.
So we say it's from Exo One publisher, similar game.
We say it's Ghibli inspired in the headline.
Also really important, on all the links we say this is new.
I can highly recommend that if you email press influencers, also players that may be on a newsletter.
They often miss stuff.
They often didn't read your last email
because you were on holiday, or they just missed it,
or they just skimmed over it.
So just making like really clear what's new,
it makes a lot of sense to feel people more included.
Of course, there's nuances to this, like to most things,
like how much do you need to really explain
everything to newcomers?
If it's on your Steam page, if it's on TikTok,
it's like super important.
If it's for your Discord or your newsletter,
people have signed up to that,
so they probably know a little bit what your game is.
So there's nuance, but again today I really focus on the other side of it, because a lot
of game developers are quite good at talking to existing players, but I think are less
good at talking to new people.
The third rule is think of the environment.
That doesn't mean the planet, which you should also do,
but in this context, it means more that
whenever we make any kind of asset,
any kind of communication,
I really try to imagine who is gonna watch this and how.
I think it's really easy to fall into trap.
Like, you know, you make a trailer,
you put it in your big 4K screen,
you press play, and you watch every second perfectly.
Nobody watches trailers like that.
How most people watch anything is like sitting on their sofa,
they probably watch Emily in Paris.
At the same time, they're like on their phone,
they switch between Twitter and TikTok,
they maybe talk to their partner on the side
and they think about what dinner to order.
So if you make any asset emulate communication,
I think making it visually and text-wise easy to read
is essential.
Here is the example for Gourdlets,
which I think is great, like a really short,
small looping video.
It's really straight to the point.
What I also really try to do for really important assets
is that I put them in my video editor on my iPad.
and I skim through them.
I try to look, if I look at them really quickly
and in a small screen, does it still read nice visually?
Because this is how most people are gonna see this,
before they actually pay attention to it.
Also thinking of the environment makes a lot of sense
in terms of what platforms people use.
This is a game called Figment 2.
I think they were like, okay, successful on most social media, did a great job.
But one thing that really, really took off for them was TikTok.
And the reason for that is because it's a game with musical boss fights where the bosses
are singing, which you're going to hear in a second.
And that's of course great.
This is the one social media platform where people watch with sound.
So if you know something like that, and then honing in on TikTok makes a huge difference
to keep the environment in mind when people watch it.
Figment2 has multiple musical boss fight.
Everything here is nearly dead!
Wake up while you still have the chance!
Yeah, there's a party waiting!
So get out of your head!
Rule number four is know your next step.
This is a sales funnel.
This looks boring.
This is boring.
But it is helpful.
You maybe seen it, it basically means first you try to get awareness,
and then you get the interest of people, and you try to like funnel that down,
and in the end they're going to buy your stuff or wish list or whatever you want to make them do.
And I think it's really, really important that you always know when you put something out,
what is the next thing a person should do.
You know, should they wish list, should they find more info,
should they share it with your friends, and where they can do that stuff.
So I've seen it like too many times that you see a trending post,
but there's just no link to it or no more information to find.
However, this is a really good tweet from Ooblets' launch and you see no call to action.
because it's in the next tweet.
Because I think call to actions can be really cringe,
especially a lot of marketing people push for that.
Guilty, happens.
But I think it's really important on socials
that you are aware what's an acceptable moment
to push information.
Also on TikTok, if you ask people to,
hey, there's the link, and you put it on screen,
they're not gonna do it.
Just have the link in your bio.
Just make sure there's some more information to find,
but be a bit more subtle about it
and just see how it works on this specific platform.
So the micro-level checklist, does your communication get to the point in the first few seconds?
Does it work for newcomers?
Keep the platform and environment in mind, and also, does it point to the next step?
And now we go to the macro-level.
Now we go to the whole campaign planning and think about how the no-one-cares mindset can be helpful.
Again, just showing your game is incredibly helpful
and I think something people don't do often enough.
Vampire Survivors, millions of copies,
every day there's new people finding this game.
Every day you see new people in the Steam forums.
If you go through GDC and ask people,
there's going to be loads of people
that have never heard of this game.
It's one of the biggest indie games
and we're at the Games Developers Conference.
Like I can't overstate how big the pool of people
is that don't know your game,
even though if it feels repetitive to you
to just basically introduce it into them again.
Another example is Exo One, where we had loads of trending TikTok posts, 5-6 posts back to
back, all millions of views, half the comments, what's the game called.
It always reached new people.
This is another example of games we worked on.
One is called The Last Clockwinder.
The other one, Ziggy's Cosmic Adventure.
They both had trending posts before on multiple platforms.
When we started working on them,
the first thing we did was just like,
let's just make two posts that just introduce the game.
And they've been trending again.
The reason for that is, again,
The people on Reddit that saw it this time maybe weren't on Reddit a month ago.
Maybe they were on honeymoon.
Maybe they didn't check Reddit.
There is so many examples where people just come to a platform, or you have just missed it.
Whereas a game developer, I think it can just feel like, you know, you've done Reddit.
You had five trending posts, and you think everybody knows it.
Absolutely not.
There's loads of people who will not know it.
There's also another good example of a game called Shotgun Farmers, which I think is one
of the best TikToks accounts out there.
I can highly recommend.
And they've got loads of different posts that really go into the community, talk to them,
introduce new features, really cool.
But you will also see loads of posts that just introduce the game, or just like the
history of the developer, how he quit his job to start making this game.
And again, every time this post goes out, they can go big and they can reach new people
that have just not been following you.
a bonus rule, know your money shot.
I think knowing what is the one shot that is really, really good for your game can change
a whole campaign.
Obviously, you then should use that one shot for your store page, for your launch email,
for everything you put out that's important.
And I think what we've done recently is use TikTok kind of a way to beta test and
find out what this good shot is.
For Clones Drone in the Dangerous Zone and Exo One, we made like 50 TikTok posts.
And you suddenly notice, like, whenever we use this certain scene or a very similar one,
we always go trending.
Because the TikTok algorithm is so good at keeping track of who keeps watching or who swipes away.
So we kind of with that figured out what is our money shot, what is the shot that people really want.
And we purposely put them in launch trailers, we purposely start our launch TikToks with that.
And as you see by the numbers, it did pay off. 2 million views, 9 million views.
So it can really help to use TikTok as a beta test for your best shots.
Now we go into a PR campaign evolution,
what I think a PR campaign can look like
with this no one knows your game mindset.
Firstly, you've got to make a game.
That's pretty hard, but once we're over that,
we look at a regular PR campaign.
That's actually a slide from one of my older GDC talks.
And it's quite, that's basic.
Like you reveal your game,
you do some PR stuff in the middle,
and then you launch it.
And I think the next step in the direction is rinse, repeat.
Make sure you keep repeating what your game is.
Recycle trailers, you know, change a little bit.
Put them out again.
Try a different platform.
We also had examples where people launched a game
on Xbox and Switch, and then they go to PlayStation,
and all their marketing just talks about the new features
of the PlayStation version.
But that doesn't make sense, because the PlayStation people
have never, ever seen your game.
For them, it's a completely new game,
so you've got to treat it like that.
Again, just explain to them what your game is.
And the fourth step.
Is adapt.
And I think that's the whole matter of a really, really good, masterful PR marketing campaign.
I can't overstate, like, I think doing like step one, two, and three is incredibly hard.
Like just doing the stuff repeatedly is like 90% of the work and it's hard to pull off.
And well done if you do.
I think if you want to go to 100% and make it perfect, just keeping an eye open what works.
And honing into that can make a huge difference.
We had campaigns where we tried lots of different things and suddenly,
Imgur really takes, so we did lots of Imgur posts.
We put out a demo, kind of not thinking much about it,
demo takes off. It's like, cool, let's do a nail demo and a preview version
and push the demo on TikTok.
So just like, planning your campaign, great.
Being flexible, really, really big plus.
And the last kind of macro level learning for today,
or recommendation, is understanding
the reach of multipliers.
Because no one knows about our game,
we want to make sure more people know about it.
So we need to reach as many people as we can.
And those are all multipliers.
Probably know most of them.
And they all have a ceiling.
If you post on TikTok, you can post quite a lot.
You can get millions of views.
to your account and probably like high thousands of people to your store page.
If you do press outreach, it's great for profile building, but maybe it's going to be less
thousands of people that actually then go to your store page.
So all those things have different ceilings.
Don't sue me, that's not scientifically proven.
That's just like gut feeling from working loads of different games.
And they all have a different importance.
But the main point I want to make on this slide, there's one thing that...
has a lot more reach than anything else.
And that's your store page.
Can be a Steam page, can be a PlayStation console page,
it can be a VR page, whatever it is,
the store page is the one thing
where you have incredible reach.
Like, way better than the others.
So that doesn't mean you shouldn't do the other stuff,
because the other stuff is super important to get featuring on store pages.
If you have loads of social media followers,
if you do great press outreach,
you maybe get better featuring from Nintendo,
you maybe get into a Nintendo Direct.
If you have loads of wish lists, you trigger the Steam algorithm.
So you've got to do all those things anyway,
but I think just being aware
that the store page is the one thing that can make the biggest difference.
It's important if you have to prioritize,
if you have only a day left and you can decide
if you send another press release
or you could improve your Steam page,
please improve your Steam page.
So I think that's the point I want to get across here,
know what the main multipliers are.
So the micro-level checklist, show your game, show it a lot.
On the campaign planning, keep reminding people forever.
There is no such thing as hype.
It's really almost impossible to build hype for an indie game
because most people keep forgetting about it.
That's why wishlist is important,
so they get an email on day one.
Reuse, recycle, rinse, repeat, reuse your assets, recut them.
Again, show your game as many times as you can,
show as many features as you can.
Don't feel like you can spam people.
It's almost impossible for an indie game.
It's possible with multi-million dollar marketing budgets.
It's not possible if you're just like a person
that puts out stuff.
Embrace the chaos and adapt
and figure out your multipliers
and then prioritize accordingly.
Thank you very much for listening.
I should remind you to fill out the evaluation forms.
I'm also going to be taking questions.
I also want to wish you a really nice rest of your GDC.
Thank you.
If anyone had good questions, you can walk up to the microphone.
Otherwise, I'm also going to be outside later.
Hi, thank you for the talk.
It was actually amazing, and I learned a lot here.
But one thing that I wanted to ask
was, do you think there are some type of advices
you can do to integrate the design
process of your game to better market,
or I guess try to optimize the marketing process as a whole?
I think it definitely helps if your game markets itself.
It's not for all game types.
It's going to be hard for narrative games.
But I think you're going to give yourself just a way better
chance if you have something that's easily marketable.
So I think building a game with marketing and PR in mind is
extremely helpful.
Thank you.
I have two questions. I mean, thank you. Thanks again. Really, really nice talk.
To the pre-reveal, I mean, once you have not revealed the game yet,
could you have one, two insights there?
Is it just finding out, you know, like, what are the right visuals?
What will people pick up?
And the second is, is there a way...
that you say, show your game, show your game.
But is there a time where you put up your Steam page too early?
I mean, all of a sudden it takes one, like, you know what I mean?
It's like, is it one year? Is two years too much?
Is it one and a half years? Like, what's your experience there?
It's a really good question.
And I think it's also something that, like, changed over time.
I think what we see at the moment is...
Game announcements that go big in the beginning and you get a lot of traffic straight away.
You get something that we call wishlist velocity.
So your daily wishlist are then really, really high.
So with that in mind, I think it can be too early.
But if you have a really small game that probably you won't have that big reveal anyway.
In that case, I think I would just go early and start building from there.
Especially with store pages it's more tricky.
I think on socials it's like pretty hard to be too early
because you can always say I'm just working on that.
It's just a prototype.
So I think as soon as it's interesting
and you communicate that this is not all finished
or you might be trying out things
but you just start building an audience
I think you almost can't be too early for that.
I'm great. I'm Grant by the way. Lovely to meet you all. Thank you for the lovely talk. It was really useful and really practical.
I really like that message about the fact that people don't really care about your game. And I think that really resonates.
Do you have any good examples of things that you've done
where you've kind of got people really hooked in
that maybe they started to kind of, you know,
care a bit more about those games
and really kind of brought them in closer?
Maybe could you go into a bit more detail
with some of those?
Yeah, of course.
Like I said before, there's loads of examples
where once you get people hooked in,
they want to know more
and they're really super interested.
Just like again on Vampire Survivors, it's a massive fan base.
You have a lot of really, really hardcore fans.
And they look for really inside jokes in the games, in the code.
They just find everything.
So there's obviously a certain point where people get interested and they do care.
But I think often that's not the problem for the game developers,
because again, that's your experience,
how you as a consumer usually interact with those things.
Once you're interested, you know how to keep up to date,
but the big majority of people just getting them on board is the challenge.
Thank you.
Hello there.
I have a question for you.
First of all, I enjoyed your presentation, but I'm thinking about how we as a team can
develop our game.
Our game is free, and it has educational resources as well.
But how, as a team, here in America, how can we really target market this as a free game
for educational purposes?
Yeah, I think there's like a specific niche where a lot of those more classic gaming channels
are maybe harder to reach or interact with.
I would think there's definitely avenues.
If you find the right subreddit, I'm sure you could have success.
And again, TikTok, I think, is a great platform because it's so specific how it targets people.
And if you're a bit personal, I'm sure you could find people that are interested specifically
in that kind of game more than in traditional YouTubers or gaming sites.
So I would probably look into social media that's good at targeting, for your case.
Thank you very much.
Cool. I think there were all the questions and yeah, I'm going to be outside if anybody else wants to have a chat. Thank you very much.