Hi, oops, wow, okay.
Hello everybody.
Clements, so I'm gonna be talking about
how we rewarded exploration in
Deus Ex Mankind Divided Praxedat.
Actually, I noticed yesterday that it wasn't
written in the program, that it was about Prague,
so it is about Prague, I'm gonna talk only about Prague.
I've been working on it for four and a half years
at Eidos, so yes, I will try to make it less than an hour.
So, let's get started.
I'm gonna talk about me very briefly
because I would rather talk about the actual game.
I used to be a game journalist
for various French magazines for about seven years.
Then I became a QA tester for a number of games,
including Rayman, Heavy Rain, and Remember Me.
Oops, Remember Me, being made by a company
named Dontnod Entertainment.
You might know them for Life is Strange as well.
And in the actual Deus Ex project, I've been working first.
You seeing anything?
Okay, cool.
I've been working on this map,
which is also located in Prague.
It's Palisade Bank.
I've been a part of the side mission team for about a year.
And while I was doing all these things,
I was also trying to nail how our exploration
could reward players, what the navigation would be,
the challenges that you would encounter in Prague.
So yeah, lots of things in four and a half years.
But today I will mostly talk about exploration,
how we designed it, and first,
how we design meaningful exploration content.
I'm gonna talk.
About exploration setups, that's the cute name we gave these things and
this is what you encounter in the city hub as you play you can see the setups that tell you stories that challenge you and
to me I define them as slices of life designed to tie narrative exploration navigation and challenge together and
It's we are sorry I have a delay
So expression setups, sorry about this
So why do we need these exploration setups?
Why did we make them?
It was our own task.
We didn't have an exploration team.
It just started with me and my colleague
who is a senior designer.
His name is Jeff.
There were two of us for the better part
of two years on Prague.
So we were trying to nail what we were gonna do
and we decided to make this meaty part of Prague.
So obviously we need to keep the player interested and busy in Prague.
I don't know if you've played it, but you come back here a lot.
During missions, you come back here three times.
It's not an open-world city hub.
It's, as the name says, a hub.
So it's not that big, but it's quite dense.
And we need to get people interested with challenges and loot
and nice little storytelling.
And we also need to flesh out our universe.
If you don't know what a Deus Ex game is about,
it's a...
It's a game about transhumanism.
It's set in the near future.
It's a game where lots of people wear prosthetics
and it's talking about lots of modern day issues
like prosthetics, actually.
Maybe you've heard of the science advances
that we're living right now.
So an interesting deep lore and as a level designer,
I found it very interesting to flesh this universe out
in exploration throughout the game
and throughout Prague, mostly.
So, with that said, the main story does that.
I guess you're gonna tell me that it's the job
of the main story to tell us more about our universe
and I would say yes, that's true.
The main story is the core that makes us understand
the state of the world, what it's about.
And the big topics, the segregation, as you may know, our game is not a happy one.
There's lots of people who are sad. They live in ghettos. They are taken away from their home.
Augmented people, the ones who...
A quick recap, if you haven't played Human Revolution,
the previous game, at the end of the game,
millions of augmented people go crazy
and start beating everybody else to a pulp.
So they became, you know, kind of outcast
and people hate them.
And yes, the main story again,
it's depicting huge stakes.
They have multifaceted characters, conspiracies.
Puppage comes back.
It's always there.
And same missions are another big part
of what makes Prague interesting in the game in general.
They take the player deeper into that universe, that world.
And yes, I've been part of the team,
so I'm not objective, but.
They offer truly unique experiences,
both narratively and gameplay,
because among other things,
they offer complex, scalable conversations,
lots of trust and consequences.
It's very scalable.
You can play a side mission 10 times
and have 10 different results.
And they offer exotism,
like with these bald-bearded guys
takes control of your augmentation.
It's something the main path cannot always do.
And going back to the topic and why I'm saying all this,
the third layer of content, we defined it
that there would be exploration setups
and they complement existing content.
They're meant to be discrete.
They're meant to breathe life into the city and its people
in too many tiny details.
So they're not meant to be in a competition
with NFMS, they're just meant to complement
and tell us about the world.
Let the player connect the pieces via environment,
storytelling, little bits of stories.
And hopefully they also meant to make the world fun to navigate around.
So all this to say that we have three levels of complexity and three levels to tell story
and I will speak about the latest one, the smaller one, but hopefully not less interesting.
So that's a video, if it plays, of what an actual expression setup is.
And there is no sound.
So I will...
speak over it. So it's a pretty small one. It's something that they used to do a lot
in human revolution in Detroit and Hengsha. This is what you encounter most of the time
when you explore a little setup that tells you a contained story, some narrative, a little
loot. That was pretty much it. It was very interesting. But for Mankind Divided, me and
Jeff, we wanted to expand this
this concept and make it richer.
And we did it with two things, connectivity and density.
And I will explain connectivity later.
Basically we wanted to connect exploration setups together,
locations together, NPCs together,
so you would hopefully make a connection between locations.
But first, the nice part about Prague is that, as I said, it's not an open world.
It's a hub.
And it's very dense.
And that's a nice moment to bring up a quote by someone you might know.
Warren Spector said that.
And I didn't know about this quote before two weeks ago.
But I added it anyway.
And that's exactly what we try to do with Prague CDUB.
We try to make it as dense as possible.
So there is.
no wasted space anywhere.
Everything that we put in Prague has a meaning.
It's supposed to complement the world,
make it richer, make it better,
and make the experience of the player really cool
for those who are interested in this kind of thing.
So the image shows an example of,
it's pretty early work, it was four years ago.
We tried to place our exploration locations around the city.
So as you can see, it's pretty dense
and it's maybe four times denser now.
Just gives you a little idea of how we worked
at placing our content.
And we did it with very few modules at first.
As I said, we were four, a team of four,
for two years in Prague.
We were two designers, two artists,
and I was a junior, so I was trying to do things.
And we did it with these modules we were trying to nail.
what could exploration look like?
Where would we put our content?
So we had modules.
We defined that shops, apartments, and storages
would be our main ways to convey exploration setups.
And we would place them around the city.
We would think that maybe the player's gonna go this way
because they have to go to a mission,
they have to do a side mission.
So we would place these little bricks everywhere
and we would make challenges around them
based on augmentation and player skills.
and navigation and that's how we started doing it.
Pretty rough, but it helped us define
what exploration would be.
And as I said, connectivity, in addition to density.
We thought that we would connect location
by using proxying, using environment,
meaning that if two locations look the same,
maybe they share a connection.
And that's something, I know it's ugly,
but it's actually something that we had in the game
four years ago, or something.
And I would put, I had this idea of a setup
of an alcoholic woman who you could visit her apartment
and then you could visit also a liquor store
that we set up in Prague.
And I just scaled up a huge bottle of wine
and I put it in her apartment and in the store
and we just would test this setup to see if it worked.
And that's the idea, like maybe there is a link
because the prop scene looks the same.
But this is not something that we use 100%
because you don't want.
You don't want to rely on only props in an environment
because places that look the same are often boring
and you don't want boring.
So we tried to find various ways to diversify
the look of our setup and show connections in a subtle way,
whether it's narrative or visual.
And that's the very same setup four years later
of this alcoholic woman.
whose apartment is pretty hard to reach,
so that's another part of what we did with Exploration.
We tried to vary the challenges as with the Deus Ex game.
You need to have a lot,
you need to support every player style.
So Exploration is always meant to challenge you.
There's nothing that is given.
And so in his apartment,
yes, you still have lots of liquor bottle.
And you can stumble on some emails and I'm spoiling,
but this email is from the liquor store,
which is called Hemingway's.
And maybe if you walk around the city street
and you stumble upon maybe this store,
which is gonna appear very soon,
yes, that's how you make the connection.
Maybe if you paid attention to the emails,
you notice that maybe these are linked.
And the stories themselves of this alcoholic
and the store owner, they're not linked in the proper sense.
You discover a whole new setup in there
and you can loot the whole store if you want.
and drink lots of liquor.
But yes, that's the way we try to connect things
in a subtle way that the careful explorer will notice.
Hopefully.
So from this, from what I just showed you,
we extracted.
Key principles for exploration setups,
they are supposed to offer a challenge,
like we saw, you need to work to get there.
We're not limited by main story
and critical path constraints.
We don't have to give the player easy access to our things,
which is the actual cool part.
And they have to grant rewards,
and rewards can take many forms,
and I will talk about that later.
And we create subtle links between locations,
and they're meant to tell compelling stories
about the world, as I say,
make the universe look deeper and better.
And there's another concept about expression setups
that I had bits of struggle explaining it
when we were designing it before to my hierarchy
that there's no sense of progression.
They're not missions, they're not locators that you follow.
We were very insistent on it because usually people want to have a, they want progression,
they want you to go from point A to point B and it was suggested at several point during
the development that these apply to.
The idea came that we should have locators and the sense that in order to see an expression
set up you had to go through a first part and then a second part.
And we didn't want that at all.
So there is no sense of progression.
You can explore connected location
in whatever order you want,
and you're always gonna get something
whether you make a connection or not.
And quickly, what are the rewards?
Obviously, I'm gonna talk about it a lot during this talk.
They can be functional, loot, lots of loot.
Things to pick up.
Narrative is its own reward.
I'm gonna talk about narrative quite a lot.
but not too much, and navigation.
So I'll also talk in another part of the talk
how exploration helps making missions better
with navigation.
But there is no sense of progression, as I just said,
but we still have types of exploration setups,
and it's only.
for tracking purposes, because some setups,
as I said, it wasn't a team,
it wasn't, we weren't an official exploration team,
so every request that I had for these,
they were level design requests,
they were not tied to any budget,
so I had to be careful how I was measuring my setups.
So we created 24 of them, the ones I documented,
there's many more that I just did.
And 20 of them are stand-alone.
They're the very first one I showed you.
They're very simple.
They only have one location.
They're just contained.
70%, so the majority are the medium one.
They connect at least two locations together.
The one we just saw with the alcoholic lady.
And 10% are large one.
And large one are interesting,
and I'll show a video of that right now.
And I'll explain why they're kind of tricky to do.
So we don't have sound so I'm gonna explain it.
You enter this apartment and there's people talking
about who's inside and people talking in our game,
it's very expensive so for an exploration setup
to have people actually talking, it's pretty cool.
It gets us excited.
And you can see these pictures of an unknown location
that you will visit later, so it's supposed to intrigue you.
And then stay in your memory.
And in these emails, you find out that this guy,
this painter guy, who has picture of, again,
his ex-wife is escaping from somewhere,
you don't really know, and that's the paint store.
Again, we still link location via PropSync.
You discovered another piece of this story.
And it also extends to Golem City.
This is a map that is outside of Pride.
It's a critical path map that you have to go to.
And you pick up another part of this story right here.
So maybe you make the connection
because the name is similar.
And if you do, it's good.
And then last part of the game,
if you remember the first location,
there were photos of this very place, the theater,
which only opens later in the game.
And you can basically find the same pictures
that you found in the first location.
But you can also, as I said, no sense of progression,
so you can just visit any location
and make the link yourself, or don't make the link
and just take the loot and the codes.
And that's fine by us.
You can do whatever you want.
But the thing that was hard with this particular setup.
was that with anything that is big and spread out
between various locations,
especially out of a natural map,
this one connects out of Prague,
it makes comprehension very difficult
and memory work very difficult as well.
And that's a lesson for the future, actually.
I had to find a sweet spot between invisibility,
something you will never notice, you will never connect,
and overexposition, something kind of vulgar
that takes you by the hand.
or the impact suffers.
And for this particular setup, I think,
the rewards were not very balanced.
I was too involved in this story.
I liked it very much.
So every time you would stumble upon a piece of the story,
like in Golem City, you would just have an email
and nothing else, and that was pretty cheap of me.
So in the future, I had to try to vary what I give you.
And another interesting example of big setups
and how we try to entice exploration in Prague.
This is your headquarters.
Please play.
Hmm, that's a video.
Okay, that's your headquarters, this is where the hero,
Adam Jensen, works.
And this is a place that is interesting for two reasons.
First, we take something from you in this area,
we remove your ability to shoot people
because we don't want you to shoot your boss
or your psychiatrist, which is a shame,
but it's still like that.
So we thought it was a good way to actually...
balance it, the fact that we take something from you,
we would give you a lot of content
in terms of narrative and exploration.
And everybody isn't someone
who is gonna explore on their own.
So for people who, they're kind of new to the game,
they don't really know what the city has to offer,
we thought it was a good idea to place
lots of little connections to the city hub,
like what you just saw, I picked up a code
that was talking about a case from one of my colleague
about a storage locker he wanted to investigate,
this very storage locker.
And maybe it's gonna entice players to explore Prague more
because you have to come back to this area.
It's critical to come back to the task force a lot.
And to us it was a good way to entice exploration in Prague.
And maybe, as I just did,
I messed up my colleague's investigation.
So, too bad for him.
Another interesting thing, and it's again,
it's a lot of narrative.
Deus Ex is a very narrative-driven game.
And as level designers, it was our job
to expand the universe and make interesting stories
in our map.
And the main thing that we wanted to depict was
Now that society has fallen in our game,
with, as I said, segregation, unhappy people,
ghettos, it sucks.
So everybody who was augmented,
who close to augmentation business,
we wanted to talk about what happened to them,
what are their issues now,
what, you know, the artists, the augmented,
people who were forced to get augmented for their job
by the megacorp, how did they survive?
And we do that by, in this video you have two example
that I think are interesting in exposing
how the socioeconomic class was affected.
We had this woman who was a neural implant programmer
and now she's turned into a programmer of crappy house AI.
You actually hear these house AIs
in some location in the city hub.
And she's not happy about it and she's secretly developing,
I won't spoil you there, but she's developing some AI
that is a direct reference to other AIs
that we find in the Usex universe.
And on the right, this ballet dancer,
of course she used to be very successful,
she used to have a nice place at the opera,
and now she is just a bar owner.
with secrets because everybody has secrets in Prague.
But to us, it was very important to talk about these people,
the little people, the simple people,
the citizens who were impacted by
this semi-apocalyptic event.
And that sums it up.
The stories, all of the stories we create,
they meant to fit the universe key events
and how they impacted people's life.
So topics like the hog incident,
segregation, police state, and classes.
And we need to talk about all kind of people, even the ones that we would hate in real life.
Because it's easy to talk about people we would like.
But we have to talk about the assholes as well.
So that's just some pictures that we threw around that we thought were interesting in
fleshing out the universe.
And that's something that I was struggling with a little bit, a little at some point,
because I wanted...
everything to be very interesting.
And as I said, I was a junior,
so I wanted everything to be super top
and best stories, best characters,
and best environment storytelling.
And I had a discussion with
the former lead side mission designer.
He told me once that my
stories were impacting his submissions character because they were too complex and
They were meant to be more invisible than this and it was kind of shutting casting a shadow
Over his own characters, and that was just weird and that's what we call the small what things
I don't know if you ever heard this word is the feeling that everybody
everybody is awesome and they live next door to each other.
And that's something we really wanted to avoid.
And as a practical example, I had this guy,
that I, the actual conflictual guy, this was...
I want to put all that into him, all his ideas, how to make him interesting.
So I would justify how to make his apartment interesting in an environment way.
I wanted lots of good props for him.
I wanted his apartment to be connected to another map.
I wanted it to be really huge.
And that was way too much.
And so I finally understood what the side mission lead
was trying to tell me.
And so further on, we designed these people as ordinary
with a twist, because they need to have something
interesting, but very discreet and subtle.
And yes, that's about finding the right balance
between the dark secrets and the ordinary routine
of a relatable person.
keeping them human, it's not about making the story
absolute crap and uninteresting,
but you have to give little interesting brain crumbs
and let the player do the rest.
And final lesson about this,
I used to get very panicky when I saw empty space,
because again, we were alone for a long time in Prague,
and I would just start...
propsing a place, putting stuff in it,
and if it was empty, it was making me uncomfortable,
so I would over-complexify things that didn't need to.
And as our narrative director said to me once,
he came to help me at the very end of the project,
making these stories a little less convoluted.
He used this a lot with me because,
yes, I wanted everybody to be awesome,
and that's not a good thing you want in exploration.
Exploration is supposed to...
be very, very discreet.
And the player has to make up their own stories.
And last, about narrative,
then we'll be more talking about navigation.
We have several very characterized areas in Prague.
There's the red part of this image is the old district.
It's where tourists live, middle class.
The blue area is business area,
so businessmen during the day and hobos during the night.
Downtown LA was our main reference
from what our creative director said.
And the yellow part is the poor district.
Poor people, augmented people, sad people, and drug addicts.
But that doesn't mean that you have to be absolute about it.
We really try to explore the universe
and to find out ways to twist our stories
and make them less absolute because
it is not because you live in the poor district
or in the sewers.
Well, actually the sewers is not a good example.
It's not because you live in the poor district
that you are an augmented hobo with an addiction issue.
Or a purist who hates all orgs
and would report them to the police.
And an example of that is that I was reading a document one day, a creative direction document,
and it was saying how in this particular poor district there's 70% augmented people who
live there and 30% non-augmented people, so 100% human, we call them I guess.
And I thought it was interesting to give a twist
to an expression set up in the area that I created
about this group called Ad Astra,
who was actually trying to help bridge the gap
between augmented and non-augmented.
It was a cute little story that was pretty optimistic,
and Deus Ex is not optimistic.
So I was actually trying to do something different,
and rewarding with narrative and XP point like this.
Now, I'm done with the narrative part of this talk.
It was pretty important to talk about it,
in my opinion, to help you understand
how we try to design our world and flesh it out.
But exploration is not just about telling stories
and environment storytelling.
It's also about rewarding every other part of the game.
And in our case, we have to benefit using exploration
and navigation, every aspect of the game,
and make all type of content shine.
from the most important, like main missions,
and side missions, to the best kept secrets,
things that people will usually never find.
So, most exploration setups are standalone and original.
Some of them feature special reward
that provide unique advantages during mission.
It's too bad I don't have the sound,
but you can photo that video that gives a vibrant example
of how exploration complements an existing mission.
That's my greatest puzzle you just saw there.
Turn off the TV to find this story item
that is connected to the Palisade Bank.
And if you make the connection,
you go to this area, the bank,
and you meet this guy and you can tell him this.
Use your item to make him like you.
he's not happy that you're an augmented guy and he was taking real pleasure in telling you to
screw yourself. But because you've explored, congratulations, you find this item and you
bypassed, now a whole area of the bank is open to you, your client, you stole his identity,
shame on you, but it allows you to bypass something that would have been very hard
otherwise because the bank is a very difficult mission, full of people like this guy.
So that's one of the way we found to reward main missions
using exploration.
And it's not just about finding story item,
it's also a lot about pure navigation,
so pure level design,
and connecting exploration, narrative,
and how it can connect via sometimes.
alternate path like we like to use in Deus Ex.
So this area is interesting because it's an apartment
of some artist, you don't know what happened there.
There's blood, it's a mess.
So it's a nice little story on its own and I added,
yes, it's an errant, I know people troll about errants,
I'm sorry, I really tried to keep them very small in print.
And this area offers another route towards main mission,
which is a color shop.
And yes, I put a little storytelling piece in that event.
I think it's important to keep events interesting.
And it offers you a new path.
So it's also about connecting various areas
using exploration setups.
And as you may know, when you design a platforming element
for a first person game like ours, it's very weird.
So we try to avoid having a 300 pounds guy
standing on flower pots.
And we do that in different ways.
So that's actually pure visual language,
we need to be very careful about how we entice
our expression routes, how we make people want to
explore something and how not to deceive them.
So we need to have clear, enticing,
integrated navigation platform,
that's a lot harder to do than it looks.
And identifiable navigation threads
from all levels of navigation.
These are just quick example,
I could talk about navigation for hours,
but I don't have time right now.
We have to be able, basically the rule,
where we have to be able to identify a route.
for an exploration setup from anywhere from the ground,
we would see all of these platforms connecting together
and we would know that something is accessible
because in a Deus Ex game,
you never want to lead the player somewhere they cannot go
because we let the player explore everything.
We want the player to be able to access everything
that he sees.
That's the Deus Ex experience.
So we need to remove the navigation clutter
because they betrayed the player's expectation.
That's called affordance, actually.
And it's something that we were very careful about.
If it meant deleting balconies that led to fake windows,
we would do it a lot.
I think I deleted 100 balconies without the artist knowing.
But it's a good thing.
Do it.
And another thing about navigation is that sometimes
it was, we were reaching a point where we didn't really
know how to make it better.
It was too clunky.
At many places it was too weird, you would grab a ledge and you would fall to your death
and it wasn't that funny.
So we used this, the curfew, is, actually it was really a nightmare when it happened
because Prague was never designed.
This is something that happened very late in development.
We had to...
make the city an actual mission,
because there would be cops everywhere.
You walked when you come back from a certain mission.
You cannot navigate the streets however you want,
because people shoot you, police shoot you on site.
And that wasn't something we planned.
We always planned to be able to create chaos in Prague
and let you deal with it.
But we never planned to have a whole map
that would support stealth and combat inside of Prague.
In the end we ended up using it to make everything else better
because navigation had to be really tight for this part of the game.
It had to be possible to escape the cops.
And with this example, it's an area that sucked.
Before we had this constraint.
It was very hard to navigate and because we really worked hard to make...
this possible for the player because we had to,
well it's still pretty hard, this section,
but we had to make it possible.
And it involves tweaking navigation a lot,
so it would be able to do these kind of things.
And bypass cops, or just kill them.
And sometimes we would use,
maybe I shouldn't say that, but we cheated.
If you have the occasion to do it without it showing,
we added collision boxes in some ledges
so you wouldn't fall all the time
and it wouldn't show because you don't see your feet
and it's cool.
But yeah, we cheated a little bit,
but it made the experience a lot better in the end.
And that's an example of how a really tough constraint
helped us make navigation better for the whole city hub
because what we did for the curfew
impacted all of the other visits of Prague
where you don't have to staff around police.
And it's a good idea to think about it.
Now, as in any Deus Ex game,
we give a lot of freedom to player again.
We always have to offer multiple ways to enter a location.
So our navigation always supports every pillar that we have,
so stealth, combat, exploration,
killer profiles, every kind of play types
we have to think about.
And so we put a lot of efforts into avoiding magic locks.
And that's something that always annoys me in games
when they do this kind of thing.
I don't like this kind of thing.
It's putting propping in front of doors.
It's something that we don't.
It's forbidden in Deus Ex to do that.
But sometimes the ID just comes in.
This was an ID that was brought up by someone
a long time ago to prevent an access to one of the banks,
the Palisade Bank, which is a map in Prague, again.
Prevent the access using this.
That sucks.
If you want to block navigation and exploration,
if you want an area to remain locked out
for narrative reason, for critical path reasons,
we tend to do it very clearly.
This is a grid, so it doesn't look very...
I mean, it's still a blockage.
But it's OK, because this area is the Red Lake District.
This is where people go to see naked women
and do other things with augmented women and men.
And it's so enticed when you play,
when you go to Prague and you walk around the street,
everybody explains to you that the red light district is,
it only opens at night, so during the day,
don't expect to be able to go through.
So it's so well integrated into the game
that we know why it's closed.
And if you have to close an area,
if navigation must be controlled,
it must be crystal clear why,
and it's tremendously important.
for us and maybe for you at some point.
And a good example of that, that was the same path
that when I showed you the broomstick in front of the door,
this is what it was meant to block.
This is the secret path to the Palisade Bank
and again, sorry for the spoilers,
it's supposed to be a hard one.
But this area was supposed to be blocked off.
because someone wanted to block it off for,
for no reason, but I had to fight quite hard
to not have it locked.
And we do that because, as you can see,
when we reach this area, this is the,
this is the bank's vault shaft.
This is where you can go anytime you want
because you're gonna find key cards in Prague
if you explore.
They were very well hidden,
so if you found some, congratulations.
And you can go there at all time
to loot these vaults and interesting part of it
is that this is supposed to be an exit to the bank map.
It's not supposed to be an entrance,
but if you really, really are a good explorer.
you can actually enter this area and it's very rewarding in its own way and it's something that
it was worth the fight because it makes the city really more interesting.
And side missions, quickly about them,
they have very different constraints than the main path.
And when I came onto the team,
I was wondering how I could help them
benefit from what we developed in Prague.
And the interesting thing is that side mission
in Human Revolution, they had to put their things
into an existing layout, nothing was made
specifically for the side missions in Human Revolution.
So it was pretty hard for them.
And from the very start of Prague,
we, the level designers, the two of us,
we talked to the side mission team
to help them integrate their missions into layouts that
would be made specifically for them.
And it's very important to know because when
they needed some location, they would come to me
and they would tell me, can you create something so that we
could put our things?
And that's how the sewers came to life.
The sewers are great if you don't know them.
And they're meant to help the side missions thrive
by having their own layouts.
And that's how every location that I made
for the side missions, they take expression into account
and it helps making them really harmonized
according to the, with regard to the rest of the game.
And another thing with SideMission is that they have a very small team, a multidisciplinary
team that works very well.
They have a writer, designers, scripters.
But sometimes...
They're really wild, so they might not always respect
their sexist peers.
For example, when I came onto the team,
you would get ambushed in this very location.
Some guys would just jump you, some pike your smirks,
and they would just start a fight with you
in the middle of the street,
and that's something that might sound cool,
but in this kind of game,
you always have to let the player have a choice
to fight or not to fight, so I removed that.
And the cool thing about it is that I moved this setup
of people attacking you in your own house
because it was already planned for exploration.
There's a multi-pass, multi-options already.
You can escape via the windows.
And I think that's something that is important to do
when you have a team that is working.
on the side and you don't have a lot of contact with them.
It was, in our case, it worked,
it made the mission better,
it made the conversation that you have
with the key character better.
It supported gameplay better,
you can stealth your way out.
Now you can fight these guys, you can just hide.
And it wasn't the case before,
and it's very, very important to know
what these guys are doing.
Because, as I'm saying here,
when a place perfectly fits within the world's world,
it shows.
And for side mission,
it was very important to keep an eye on it.
And that's another thing that I tended to do a lot,
in addition to over-complexify my stories,
is I wanted to connect everything,
because I wasn't always realizing
that other people were doing cool stuff,
because we were alone, I'm gonna repeat that a lot,
we were not a big team, we were experimenting,
we were doing a lot of things.
But sometimes I just wanted to, yeah,
I was over-designing, and it's not sexy,
it's not sexy because the word design is in it.
And yeah, too many connection.
I want to connect side missions to expression setups.
I wanted to connect main stories with whatever.
I was trying to connect the world.
And it was just, again, small world feeling.
We want to avoid that.
And many connection makes the world look fake
and convenient.
So it's resisting the urge to do that.
And now, philosophy on not blocking stuff
is actually another thing that I had to fight about.
We both had to fight about it, me and Jeff,
the level designer who worked with me.
We wanted to keep exploration content there at all times.
We didn't want to block anything from the player.
And then some of the guys in our team,
they wanted to make exploration.
in steps in some way.
They wanted some contents to be locked during a visit
and then you would come back to Prague
and this would be magically unlocked.
And as I said, with magic locks, they suck.
So we had to fight for it because simple reasons.
In Deus Ex, you don't have skill objects like in Zelda.
Our skill objects are augmentations.
And you can get augmentations or not.
You can get whatever augmentations you want
and we have no way of tracking
what you're gonna be equipped with.
And yeah, none of our augmentation are given through the main story.
So we offer, Prague offers, and the whole game offers,
skill-based exploration and not progression-based one.
And that's what we explain to our leads and directors
to not let them block accesses.
Because when you see something, when you see an apartment
and a balcony, you have to be able to get there and...
we took specific care into making all these little
augmentation challenges.
So someone who gets augmented,
they can have a party in Prague
and be very happy about exploration.
And that's good for us.
And if, the thing is, if people explore
the hell out of Prague and have seen people do it,
read about people who were spending 10 hours in Prague during their first visit there and
they were exploring everything.
And some people were not happy about it because what if we don't have content later to offer
them?
And me, I was very excited about it.
I was very excited about people finding everything during the first visit.
It was cool, but it's a matter of respecting the game speeler.
But there are exceptions, of course.
We cannot just open everything all the time.
If a setup is tied to a mission's timeline,
we need to lock the out-of-context content.
But if you have to lock something,
you must make sure that the explored area
remains interesting and useful,
and tease the player into coming back.
And that's something that is very hard to do, I think,
is how do you convey to the player
that if he comes back to a location later,
it's gonna be different.
there's no really magic things to do there,
but what we did with this exception, this example,
is that at some point you're gonna reach this apartment
and you're gonna see these pictures of you
and Vega, which is another key character in our game.
So you see these pictures and hopefully...
It teases you into coming back later because it's personal.
It's a picture of you.
So it involves you directly, and I
think it makes it easier to convey the message that,
if you come back, something may be different.
And when you come back, it's actually different.
There's a pragma.
There's some guy apparently is talking to you.
and you don't know who the hell it is, he is.
And he's waiting for you in an area.
And another thing that is interesting with that setup
is that I couldn't have this guy being here
before a certain critical path mission
because it wouldn't have made sense at all.
It's something we discussed with Mary Dermal,
which is our executive narrative director.
She said that it didn't make sense to have this guy,
this train station cop who suffers from PTSD
after the explosion that you witnessed
at the beginning of the game.
So I do something that usually never do, I spawn him.
After you read an email and for exploration,
something that we never do, but in exceptional case,
like this guy, it's essential because else,
actually before, you would encounter this guy again
in a bike alley and he would just jump you
and force you to fight him and yeah,
that couldn't stay in the game.
He had to remain consistent.
Another thing that I just said, visiting the same place twice, most people don't do it
because it doesn't make sense. They have no way of knowing if it's going to be different.
And in our case, in our game, if a location is going to change,
it should be the result of the player's action.
Most of the time, we have...
This is the example, I don't know if you remember,
but the very first example I gave of an exploration setup
is this guy, this crazy augmented dude
who's apparently stealing things from the street
and putting them on his little archway.
I made three different versions of the props for this area.
visit one, visit two of Prague and visit three. It's all going to be different. It's going
to offer you some rewards, some narrative, little pocket secretaries with codes in there
and you're going to discover what this guy is about, what he's doing. And since it's
very easy to do, this propping, it's a very accessible area. It's worth it to do it if
it's really cheap. Changing the environment for no reason else that I found it cool. But
it still is an exception and you should do it pretty often.
And that's a video.
Without the sound, it's gonna be pretty boring.
But it's a cat lady, it's a side mission apartment.
And it's, the thing I was saying about
if you have to lock content,
the area must remain interesting, sorry.
So this apartment is a side mission character.
It's not active yet, you don't have the mission yet,
but you can find all of these cool cat pictures
and there's a cat shrine.
And we made sure that it was intriguing and interesting.
And you didn't hear it, but when you enter this apartment,
there's a cat sound, meow, every time you enter.
And this is my greatest accomplishment.
Thanks for the audio guys for doing this.
And that makes this apartment tremendously
important and interesting.
So, a little conclusion with a twist about design,
because I'm not really done yet.
Everything I just said, so I can sum it up with these phrases.
Know what your people on your team do and how your own work can help.
And that's my work with the Sight Mission Team
that allowed me to really, really take that into practice.
And play one to explore your world.
If you need to block an area, justify the hell out of it.
No crates before doors, please.
unless it's the topic of your game
and you want to explore this concept.
Every constraint can have benefits.
Think about how a constraint can enrich the experience.
The example of the curfew, how it helped us
make navigation better is a good example of that.
And don't change things for the sake of it.
If you want player to notice,
find strong way to convey the message in.
Yeah, that's what I did by putting the pictures of you
on the wall of this guy so you would remember that.
And LDs, we are keepers of the experience,
but it doesn't mean you have to be rigid about it.
Find ways, smart ways to twist the experience
and it's something that I learned also by my contact
with the side mission team who are like wild cards
and they do all kinds of exotic stuff
and it's very interesting.
But, as I said, I'm not done yet.
With this part, I'm gonna talk about what I've learned
in a more personal way.
Because as I said, this was a four and a half years project
and we were a very small team in Prague for a long time.
And there were some personal struggles
that we've had to face.
And me, as a junior, I was not always, you know,
very detached from what I was doing.
And if I'm just stepping back a little bit,
I'm gonna explain the growing up process, I guess.
With examples, I had exploration setups in our game
that became main missions.
And I'm gonna explain to you why I had issues with that.
I don't know if you played the game,
there's two missions, one is called Alicent Complex
and the other is called Otar Casino.
They're two main missions that used to be only explorations.
So I was making them in Marlene Corner
and I was happy doing my things.
And at some point, they became big missions and I had problems, personal problems with
it.
I was afraid that because it was going to be part of the main story, it was going to
be streamlined and less interesting in terms of design, that all of the cool stuff, the
hidden stuff that I would put in there would disappear.
And that was just because I was actually giving
too much attention to the 1% of hardcore explorers,
and I wasn't seeing the big picture enough.
And that's why I took things so personally as well.
So if I have this example of the casino,
it was a simple exploration setups.
It looks ugly, but I had the help of an artist.
We were doing it kind of under the radar,
and it was a lot better looking than this.
We did it in secrecy.
I gave it to the side mission team
because they needed a location.
to put one of the setups in.
And someday our gameplay director, Patrick,
he just stumbled upon it somehow
while exploring the many ways of the sewers.
He decided to make it a main mission area.
So now you have this debate with this mafia guy.
And it's a really cool location.
But to me, it was a lose or lose situation.
I would have trouble getting out of my comfort zone, actually.
I was afraid it was going to suck, that a lot of people were going to work on it and
were taking basically the map from me and I was angry about it.
And I wasn't talking to anybody, so I had to get out of my seat.
and had to actually grab the people who were working on this area after it became a main story mission.
There were like 10 people now working on it and before that it was just me as a single nerd working on it.
And yes, I had to fight to keep the interesting content in it.
It's not because it became part of the main mission that it's not interesting anymore.
And another example of it that was pretty close to me is this guy, Joseph.
He had this very nice apartment with lots of candles and an obvious reference to Hyperion for those who know it.
And it was a really nice apartment and one day...
A map named Allison Complex came to life and my setup and this map had the same topic.
It was about people trying to reach the machine god and trying to connect to some mechanical
deity.
So I was thinking what is going to happen to my guy?
And at this point I was actually afraid again because we were very isolated for a long time
in our team.
I was kind of afraid to again lose some cool exploration things.
But again I had to think how to make this setup part of the main story
without ruining all of its intentions.
And actually I was kind of forced,
because I was afraid to talk to...
I was free to talk to our executive narrative director, Mary, she's very nice, but I was
kind of impressed by her, so I wasn't, you know, I was shy.
And one of my colleagues forced me to go talk to her and explain to her what my intentions
were with this setup.
So I set up a meeting and I was surprised that she was so open.
to, you know, I wasn't expecting it.
And what I've learned is that people usually
strive for good compromise and new option,
but three years ago I did not necessarily know that.
And now Joseph is happy again, he's still dead.
But he has a nice little custom animation pose
that I could never have gotten if I was,
if I remained alone with my little setup.
Like, again, a nerd.
And this is what his setup looks like now,
and the cool thing about it is that by actually moving my,
But to talk to the people who are responsible
for the experience, to Marie, to Jeff,
to our creative director, it actually made
the whole experience better.
Now this location has a lot more content
now that it was in the radar of our direction.
It got lots of resources put into it.
We have custom drawings, we have even conversation,
the absolute most expensive ingredient
that we have in Deus Ex.
And it's still cool, it's still a subtle little environment
setup that you can stumble into, it's very interesting.
Yeah, this guy is, he looks weird, but he's, yeah.
That's an additional conversation that is linking
this setup to the Allison complex mission,
so the two of them, they work separately,
and they can work together as well.
And that's...
the lesson from it.
So from two optional setups,
done in secrecy with no money,
we got two polished critical missions
supporting all of our pillars,
and some cool exploration areas
with their own storytelling reward in secret.
And what I've learned from this is
that optional content is great,
but it doesn't have to die
if it becomes part of a greater plan.
And if more resources are invested in a setup,
then it gains more chances to reach the quality
and content you originally wanted for it.
And that's something I didn't know before.
I thought I'm gonna do things on my own
and everything's gonna be fine, but really not.
And the last thing I'm gonna say,
and then I'm gonna be done,
is why so many secrets and why the fear?
Why did people from our direction
stumble upon locations that I did?
Why didn't they know everything?
It's the tricky part because things don't always go perfectly.
We have trouble communicating sometimes.
And in our case, we were feeling frustrated, the two of us, Jeff and me, the two designers
on Prague, because everybody else was working on our vertical slice and we were, we spent
a long time alone with ourselves and it drove us a bit crazy.
And yes, we lost perspective on what we were doing.
And we thought we had to do everything on our own
and talk to no one.
And it's partly our fault, it's partly nobody's fault.
But there's also another lesson that I've learned,
it's about the process of communicating things to people.
I was using this document, don't try to read it.
It's awful.
It's actually a working document that I made to detail every setup that I had.
And I made the naive mistake of sending this to everybody, asking them to read everything
and come back to me with...
And I was doing this document because I was feeling the need to justify myself all the
time because a lot of designer creating stories, doing things and trying to make things validated
by people.
It was making me very awkward with myself.
And I was overdesigning these things.
Overdesigning again sucks.
And now I learn from this that sending documents to people
and expecting them to read them and understand exactly what's
in your head doesn't work.
And it took me a while to realize it.
So now this detailed document I keep for myself
and I use more of this summed up version
that I made up a long time later.
I used this document, I was summing up pretty
what my intentions were for exploration content
and I knew that it resonates with Mary and Jeff
or creative director because they would,
they're interested in keeping our universe interesting
and yeah, short sentences.
And.
That's actually what my point is.
Is that I was criticizing control freaks.
Whoops.
Yeah.
But I became a control freak.
Every time someone would,
because the cavalry came in Prague later in the project.
Three years later, lots and lots of people
came working on Prague and we were overwhelmed.
Me and Jeff, we were like,
what are these people doing to our stuff?
It was scary.
But in the end,
I was overprotective, but I learned more and more to detach myself from my work because
it was just making me very sad, and it was not serving the project properly.
And yeah, who created what, it doesn't matter in the end.
And I had to care about the work and not how I felt.
That's the important lesson and if I have to give some human experience takeaways about my
four and a half years doing Prague, is that yeah, there's nothing magic. And the lessons are
designing for the 1% as I did a lot. It's okay as long as it doesn't take 100% of your time.
And it happened to me. I was thinking about it too much. Get back perspective and that
means letting go. Again, if you, it's a lot of ego. I wasn't realizing.
that it was an ego thing, but it actually was,
and I had to take a step back and think about
what my ideas could bring to the project
and that my ideas were not my own.
The beautiful thing that happens in video games
and any creative media is that ideas are cool on their own,
but they only get interesting
when they travel into other people's brain.
And that's actually the last point.
your ideas need to get dirty, driving into other people's mind and you stop being too
protective about them. And yeah, escape the intention to squeal all is an interesting
one because I was tempted a lot of times to just say it.
Okay, screw you all.
I'm just gonna not, I'm just gonna give my minimum.
But, because I saw some of my colleagues,
I shouldn't say that, but some people I knew,
they just gave up trying.
And it was really depressing to see.
It was like they were broken,
and I was trying really hard not to be broken.
And it's possible not to be broken if you,
yeah, if you put your mind into it.
And in the end, that's what I did.
I kept nagging people about everything
to make the game better,
because the game is not about what I feel.
It's about making the coolest experience you could ever have.
And in the end, it got good.
I had the help of a nice British guy
who came to help me at the very end,
and it's now a continuing collaboration that came late,
but hopefully it's gonna last for a long time.
So thank you, that's all I wanted to say,
and thank you for all my teammates
for listening to this over and over again.
I will pay you many beers.