Hello everyone, I'm Victoria and thank you for coming to my talk where I'll be basically
talking about all the work that we've done behind the scenes to make Boyfriend Dungeon
a success.
So a little bit about me.
I'm the community developer at Kitfox Games.
Talk more about that later.
Previously, I've worked on a bunch of other games.
I've been a community consultant slash social media person
for a bunch of games like Omensight, Leap of Fate, and more.
I have been trying every bubble tea place in San Francisco.
It's almost disgusting, but that's okay.
And I'm also half of a thing called Peach Butt Comics,
which is a game development comic
about the culture of video games
and making it from the game developer side.
And that's on Twitter if you're interested.
And of course, you can also find me on Twitter,
at the V-Tran.
I'm there, shenanigans everywhere.
Yeah, so Kit Fox. So Kit Fox is a small independent Montreal indie studio.
We're a team of eight and we've made
quite a few games. We've been around for six years.
Our most popular, I guess, developed game that's out so far is Moon Hunters.
We call that our personality test RPG. That was also a Kickstarter, which I'll be also talking about later.
You've maybe heard of Boyfriend Dungeon, which I will delve into, and we've also kind of like dipped our toes into publishing and will be publishing Six Ages, which is the spiritual successor to King of Dragon Pass and the legendary Dwarf Fortress onto Steam, which is very exciting.
You'll see also on the photo there, so the five people there, which includes me, we're the development team behind Boyfriend Dungeon.
So it's only a team of five, so there's some things that happen there,
and the rest of the kit foxes are great,
but they're not part of Boyfriend Dungeon.
Sorry, they're also wonderful.
But I just wanted to point out that kind of little group
because this Kickstarter was not just me.
It was the work of many people, including consultants,
and a lot of help, and I just wanted to make sure
that you know that it's their work, too.
Okay, so Boyfriend Dungeon.
If you don't know, Boyfriend Dungeon is a dating simulator,
dungeon crawler mashup where your weapons turn into beautiful people
and you take them out on dates,
and that makes them stronger in the dungeon.
It has male-female non-binary romance.
It was wonderful, and you're probably here
because you heard about our Kickstarter.
Our Kickstarter went pretty well.
In just over six hours, we reached our $65,000 goal.
That was wild and I was not prepared and in the end we ended up being funded for like
$272,000 again wild and amazing and I kind of just want to talk about all the success that we like all the success we found
And how we did it
So the first step is actually just to have a good game like have a good idea
Post it and then you will profit. Thank you for coming. You can all leave now
Obviously, this is not what happened.
This was not an instant success.
But the thing is, from the outside, it definitely looked like it, right?
So this was our announcement tweet.
Obviously, impressions doesn't necessarily mean everything, but just to give you a sense
of how big it became, we almost got a million impressions.
When we first announced it, it got viral.
Got 50,000 total engagements.
And then when we announced the Kickstarter,
and this is again just a Twitter
because this is mainly our focus in terms of community,
it also went viral again.
And it just basically looked like it blew up.
We had a huge following, et cetera.
We also got news coverage from some of the biggest gaming news
sites and then some, like some general entertainment ones
like GQ.
And basically, it felt like it blew up.
And it was everywhere.
Some people asked me if we paid for reviews
and got ad space and stuff.
And I can assure you we didn't, because I
get a grand total of $0 for my marketing budget.
And it's just like something's invisible
until it's suddenly visible, and there's nothing in between.
And it's really hard to kind of unpack that.
So, what I'll be talking about is all the stuff we've done to try and set it up for
success.
And this is all the invisible behind-the-scenes work that the team put into Boyfriend Dungeon
that people don't usually hear about.
We didn't know if it would work, to be clear.
You can know all the stats and all the best practices, but there's no guarantee.
If someone guarantees you that it's going to go viral, don't trust them.
I mean, or trust them.
I'm not going to run your life.
So Kitfox has released three games
and has announced three more.
And what I want to talk about is what
we found to be consistently useful in getting
some form of attention across all our games
of varying genres and themes.
So this is the agenda, with a focus
on getting noticed first and foremost, hence the title.
And basically making sure people hear about your game.
Maybe you'll find it useful, and maybe the stats I show you
will help you gauge your own levels of success
and what that means.
All right, so the first thing that I find the most important
is basically the hook.
It doesn't matter how good your game is
if literally no one finds out about it,
which is unfortunate.
There's already been a lot of great introductory resources
on various marketing aspects, like growing social media,
creating a press list, et cetera.
I can't talk about that.
Well, we're moving on from that.
One thing that continues to be the most successful parts
of Boyfriend Dungeon are its hooks.
Hooks are basically things that grabs a person's attention
into learning more about your game.
There can be multiple different ones.
There's like the description, there's the art, et cetera.
We'll be talking about that.
But the best ones are the ones that create
an emotional level of connection to them.
So ideally, how long do you have to take,
how long do you have to capture a person's attention?
Two seconds.
That's however long it takes to scroll past you on Twitter,
see you on the upcoming games on Steam, et cetera.
And what you have to interest them in these two seconds
is tell them you want to learn more,
ideally give them some idea of what the game is about,
and stand out from the hundreds of other games
that are being released every single day.
So I'm going to quickly break down Boyfriend Dungeons' hook
by giving you a glimpse at how we built the Steam page.
I'm using Steam instead of Kickstarter
because I figure more of you will have that
than a Kickstarter page, but you know, who knows?
So the first one is the title.
Of course, this is really difficult
and you want a title that has good SEO.
So when you Google it,
it doesn't autocorrect to something else
and it doesn't sort of like,
you don't find another more popular thing.
Like if you named your, I don't know, your game Google,
don't do that.
That's a bad, that's bad SEO.
We also have the trailer, which of course isn't playing, but this is one of the biggest pulls in terms of hooks.
Visually, that's what a lot of games are about, and of course games do well without great visuals,
but it is a really easy way to grab someone's attention and kind of form that emotional connection.
We had a tagline called Romance Your Swords,
and this is really good because you usually want
a one sentence description that anyone can say,
anyone who isn't in games and is in games can understand
and kind of draws that emotional reaction.
Shack and slash is a really bad pun,
and I'm very proud of it,
and it's also a pun that,
like puns are actually great hooks because, you know,
again, you have that like kind of guttural feeling
of either like this is the best thing in the world
or this is the worst thing in the world.
Genre can be a really good hook.
For us, it was dating sim dungeon crawler.
Could be different for anyone.
And of course, the steam capsules themselves
are really important for when people are scrolling through.
Again, this is just a really brief overview.
So one of the hardest hooks I think to nail
is the description of your game.
I wanna talk about it here because I find
that's the one people most struggle with.
So my question to you is, what game is this?
It's a fast-paced 2D action adventure
with challenging combat, a rich story, and gorgeous art.
It's actually Boyfriend Dungeon.
It might also be Hollow Knight.
It could possibly be Dead Souls.
It might be The Messenger.
But my point is it's really easy to put a game in there.
So my favorite thing to do when I'm creating a game hook
description is to remove your game name and all other nouns
from the description.
Replace it with a game that's a competitor or maybe
similar to yours.
And figure out if it's basically indistinguishable.
If it is, then you need a better hook.
If you need some help making something unique,
take out everything you would usually use to describe your game
and try to describe it again without these words.
For example, don't use the word story-driven,
don't use puzzle, don't use narrative,
don't use mystery, action, Metroidvania.
Please don't use fast-paced.
I've seen the word fast-paced in so many...
games and it means nothing to me now.
But does it still sound interesting enough to play?
So all of these descriptions that I've put on the screen,
these are from the games themselves.
And I just basically just removed words from them.
And it still sounds really interesting, right?
You would still understand the game.
Any normal person on the street could probably repeat it
and kind of understand what it's about.
Essentially, your hook needs to elicit some sort of strong emotional reaction.
This can be good or bad,
and it's not necessarily informative about the game.
This is why cinematic trailers can still work,
and even if they tell you nothing about the game,
as long as you embed a feeling in the player when they read about it,
even before they start playing.
And oftentimes, what the team finds most technically
interesting doesn't translate well
to what the general public is interested in,
though that can depend on your demographic.
So every game is different,
and different hooks have different values.
So for instance, procedurally generated
might be good in one respect,
or maybe if you're trying to describe it
to a more general audience,
you can just say it's different every time.
In a similar vein, know what not to say about your game.
This prevents disappointment
or narrow assumptions of your game.
For example, we don't define Boyfriend Dungeon
as a visual novel because that kind of feels like
it erases the fact that there's any dungeon crawling at all.
We use the words dating sim
because it feels more like interactive,
a little bit more gameplay, that kind of thing.
It's also important to know your key differentiators.
This is via market research done ages before you even start prototyping your game.
You have to see if your hook has already been used or if a similar hook has been already used,
and if so, why it did or did not work.
And remember, not all hooks apply to all games equally.
Definitely a narrative game values things differently than a shooter.
You just have to really find yours and do the market research.
So note that with hook strategies,
this doesn't describe a small aspect of your game.
It should actually be core to your gameplay, right?
Like we do actually have dating simulators
and dungeon crawler mashed up together,
and that's the entire game.
Again though, hooks come in different forms, such as cinematics or art, and we had previously
announced Boyfriend Dungeon, you know, in its existence way before we did the Kickstarter.
I think we announced it existed in October 2017, and the Kickstarter was in August 2018.
So we knew for the campaign we would need something really fresh and exciting.
to show things off and get that explosive reaction
that we wanted from the crowd.
So we put a lot of work into creating
this transformation sequence that we got from Particle Beam.
It paid 10 times over for sure,
and in addition to all the original music.
It's an example of knowing what your audience wants
and trying to get that emotional level from them,
and it elevates the game's look, polish,
and helps people literally understand
what the game is about when we say
your weapons transform into people.
But this takes so long. It takes forever and that's okay.
The best descriptions are ones that everyday people can repeat themselves and it's memorable.
Take the time for it and make sure it works.
You know, and you can practice it.
The best places are at conventions when you're pitching your game.
The longer it takes for you to pitch your game, probably the shorter you need to make it.
Okay, so now that you've solidified your general impressions on the community at large,
it still matters that you think of kind of different hooks when you're contacting press,
whether they're content creators or journalists.
Why?
So I asked one of my game journalist friends
to send me a screenshot of their inbox.
They write for a very large games outlet,
and they don't write full-time for this.
So keep in mind this is like a part-time journalist.
This is from their review codes folder, which specifically
picks out emails with certain keywords.
So there could be more in their general inbox.
If you check the dates, they get at least two press emails
per day.
And here's even more of their inbox
with even more press emails.
And here's another.
I got tired of blurring out information,
so I just blurred out the entire thing here.
But the point is, there's a lot of emails.
And when you email press,
you better have something newsworthy to tell them.
We strategically made sure never to show
or tell certain aspects about our game
until it was time to announce it to the press.
Again, there's a lot of resources on how to write a good email, but I want to stress
a good title may be more important than what's actually inside the body of the email.
So in this case, the outside counts more than the inside, and I'm sorry, but that's how
it is.
Because after all, if they don't even click your email, it doesn't matter what's inside.
Personalizing and figuring out what press people like will be beneficial here.
The first email title is one that I sent to a general press member that I'm not really
close to.
The second one is one that I talked to on Twitter and I realized they really like butts.
It worked.
They replied.
And this changes depending on whatever news outlet
you're talking to or the people you're talking to.
For example, this is Dwarf Fortresses.
I think I sent this last week almost.
And this was an email I sent to people
who might have not necessarily known what Dwarf Fortress was.
And you need to know what's really
interesting about your game in order
to properly email the press.
And you know, Kickstarters by themselves aren't newsworthy.
When we emailed press about our game,
we barely even mentioned the Kickstarter.
The whole marketing beat was the fact
that we had a new trailer with a cat at the forefront.
And why the cat?
Because the glimpse of the cat during conventions
when we showed off the trailer
actually got the biggest emotional response.
Like people just asked, was that a cat?
So when we decided to email press,
we basically just put the cat in there.
And yeah, I kept track of every single comment that we got in our trailer.
And this is why you really want to pay attention to what people are talking about.
So if you nailed the announcement and pressed contacts,
that's not what the entire marketing thing is about, right?
You have to keep people interested
so that by the time your game actually releases
or the mid-campaign slump comes around,
you have something for it.
Being a team of five on Boyfriend Dungeon
means we often had limited resources
or found we couldn't do everything
that would be considered best practices.
And my full-time job is to do the best practices.
I had no time.
So that's where the community helps.
So we're not big forum people, so usually I'm really bad at posting on Reddit and reset error and all those things.
Sorry if I'm a failure of a community manager there, but it's okay, because that's where the community steps in.
Community and social media are helpful catalysts in increasing your chances of being noticed.
A strong community approach means they'll reach more places you'll never be able to even think of,
and also if you give them opportunities to help you, you can be honest, and they will want to help.
But let's be clear about one thing, though.
Social media is not just about memes.
Social is helpful as a compass to direct your community
and signal what's so cool about your game
and without them having to read entire articles about it.
Because let's be real here, not everyone does that.
And it's also great for word of mouth,
which is way better than any marketing you can ever do.
So when you find those people that are willing to help,
make sure that you reward them and you pay attention.
Because they will be your fans for life.
And it's great.
OK, so let's talk about some Kickstarter optimizations
we did to try and get more people to kind of notice us.
So even when the Kickstarter itself launched,
we had certain techniques to help increase the hype
or make it more exciting to people
who wanted to back the game.
So one of the things that we found really good
was actually the limited time early bird
instead of a limited number early bird.
We made it under a 24-hour limit.
Psychology-wise, people tend to want to back a Kickstarter
that looks like it's close to being funded
or already funded, which sucks in its own way,
but that's how it works.
you want to basically try to have the most hype
near the beginning and get as much funding as possible
because that will really incentivize people to back you.
We also had hidden stretch goals.
This made it an exciting piece of news to look forward to
and it meant every time we announced a new stretch goal,
it was its own newsworthy piece.
For a goal, fun goals actually turned out
to be pretty good too, not necessarily
because it motivated people to fund us,
but it would actually spawn just nice insight jokes
and kind of like a community sense
for those that followed the Kickstarter.
And of course, I'm gonna talk about a little bit
of stuff that didn't work out,
because I think that's really important.
One, we revealed stretch goal costs too early.
When we announced our stretch goals, they were secret,
but we announced the cost up front,
and we should have kept that hidden
in order to account for any changes
that would come up later, and they did.
And another thing that, in relation to the money thing,
is that we tried to price in American, so USD.
We should have priced it in Canadian.
We thought pricing it from a USD standpoint would be better
since most of our backers came from America.
But since we're Canadian, it actually
ended up making our numbers look super strange.
And due to currency fluctuations,
sometimes our Canadian goal would be reached,
but our USD one wouldn't.
And it made for some really confusing moments
where backers weren't sure if they got the stretch goals
or not, but that's OK.
We also went to PAX West during the campaign.
We didn't actually see a huge spike from going to a convention in the middle of the campaign,
though we did meet a bunch of passionate fans and we got more press coverage than we ever did before,
which probably helped our visibility a few days before the dates of it ending.
But again, not too much in terms of money, so...
Who knows?
Add-ons, we didn't do any of those
because we wanted this Kickstarter
to be as straightforward as possible for us.
I've heard of a lot of devs that, you know,
didn't make more money because they had add-ons,
but also it was a bigger headache.
So you pick and choose what you want.
And we also had no console goals.
And I believe we would have had more money, again,
if we did stretch goals for consoles, perhaps.
But I don't know.
We didn't want to make any mistakes with porting,
and we wanted to work on the base game.
So again, kind of pick and choose what you like.
And we also didn't have a $1 pledge tier with no reward.
We thought that would create an anchoring effect, which
basically means that people, when
they see the rest of the stretch goals,
they wouldn't want to kind of back it at a higher price
point.
Okay, so just a quick note.
It isn't just about being noticed,
as much as that is important.
Impressions mean nothing without engagement.
So your game needs to have some actual weight to it.
Different games may need different value points
or gain trust and legitimacy in different ways.
Either way, if you're a new developer on Kickstarter,
know that emphasizing this has weight and value.
So Boyfriend Dungeon in particular had a lot of people
asking if it was just a gimmick.
And this makes sense, right?
It's kind of a silly game premise.
And they wanted to know if we made this
just because we knew it would have a strong like,
oh, like emotional reaction, we're gonna be viral,
and then we would disappear and fade off into the distance.
So we had to spend a lot of time increasing our trust
and like legitimacy to the community,
whether that was through pointing out our previous games
or accepting any and all.
interviews about knowledge, sharing our own knowledge,
and other games, for example, like 2D platformers,
might have the opposite problem.
You might need to prove why your game is so unique
and special and different from the other 2D platformers.
All right, so how did our noticing efforts go,
considering the Kickstarter campaign in particular?
This is a super quick rundown of how our campaign went,
with all things considered.
Mid-campaign, we were averaging about $4,000 to $6,000 a day,
which is great, since normally you think we would have
saturated our niche after the first day.
But word of mouth kept going and we kept pushing,
so that was wonderful.
Here is a very large graph of our top 10 referrals.
Or in other words, the places that converted
the most people into pledges.
What I want to point out is actually our Twitter,
which was very strange because according
to our Kickstarter contact, the conversion rate for Twitter,
which is the percent of pledge column,
is usually less than 1% for video games.
Our Twitter alone accounts for 17%, which is cool.
That's where we put a lot of our efforts into.
So it was nice that it turned out that way.
And Warframe Dungeon in particular
is very community oriented.
In comparison to our previous Kickstarter with Moon Hunters,
it did way better in terms of social aspects.
So here's a comparison.
Moon Hunters Kickstarter was in 2014.
And this was kind of before we were really
building our community.
So we only had like 12.5%.
making up the grand total of referrals,
and boyfriend dungeon is almost twice that at 23.28%,
so that was really nice.
And the most popular times
that people visited our Kickstarter page,
but didn't necessarily back it,
was obviously in the beginning, which was very cool.
A fast drop down because...
likely a lot of people saw it, etc. It went viral during that time.
But there's a little spike on August 23rd because we were featured on the front page of the Kickstarter website.
So that's really nice to see and of course
there's a tiny spike near the end when people come in to check to see if your
Kickstarter looks like it's going to be funded or not and then they decide to throw in their money.
And they also get like a little email reminding them to back the game from Kickstarter if they are following it.
And here's our social growth for the campaign.
On the right were the call to actions near the top of our page,
and the ones with stars next to them mean they weren't directly linked on the page.
Personally, I think having social links near the top is extremely important.
Chances are no one is going to read your entire page,
even I struggle to read our entire page,
and keep up with your updates, etc.
So getting them on a quick and easy platform that they check often is important.
And know which ones you can promote the most, by the way.
I didn't put Facebook and Tumblr on there
because I knew I didn't have the time for them.
But Twitter, the newsletter, and Discord
were really important to us.
So you want to know where your quality audience is.
All right, so we have some last minute tips before I wrap up.
Look at failure and learn from them.
Often these are the ones that make it like ours,
have a lot of survivorship bias, and you
can learn a lot from failure.
We only improved parts of the boyfriend dungeon game
that needed to be shown.
Literally, the rest of the game was super broken.
And it worked because everyone thought it looked really cool,
and we were really ready.
And then someone thought that we could make the game in six
and we could not.
I'm so sorry, random Reddit person.
Get brutal feedback, like seriously.
Set up an anonymous feedback form if you really have to.
Because you can show your Kickstarter page beforehand to some other game developers maybe who have done it before,
it's really valuable, it really puts things into perspective, but eventually it's your call.
You know your game the best. And of course, don't forget people don't read and have very little patience.
So again, you want that emotional reaction from everything.
So, it's a lot of work if you're doing Kickstarter,
good luck, but I'm sure you can do it.
Make sure to get some rest, you're gonna be okay.
That's discoverability, thank you.
Thank you.
Cool, and I think we're doing questions now,
if people have them.
Don't ask hard questions, please.
Or no questions?
Oh, yes, hi.
So how many followers did you have
across your social media things before you
started the Kickstarter?
Yeah, before the Kickstarter or before the announcement?
Sorry, I didn't catch that.
Both?
Either one, okay.
So the question was how many followers do we have
before we announced, I guess, the Kickstarter
or we announced Boyfriend Dungeon?
Before we announced Boyfriend Dungeon,
I believe we were at 7,000 Twitter followers
and Facebook was like 2,500 maybe.
I don't post on Facebook often.
I don't like Facebook, sorry.
And then during the Kickstarter we had just less than 10k followers.
So yeah, we definitely had a sizable community.
And we also had been building up our newsletter at every convention.
So that's really important actually.
Newsletters are fantastic and will convert a lot of people.
So basically at any turning point we had,
we would recruit people to social media or newsletters.
But yeah, I rambled.
Are there no more questions?
Are we good?
Woo!