So today I am going to talk to you about luscious colors,
which is totally a pun because I love puns.
So this is about color grading in games.
And I know HDR is a thing, and look up
tables are being updated.
But I'm hoping to explain some of the theory
behind a lot of color grading.
Hi, my name is Izzy Graham, and I'm a photographer and games developer, and I unashamedly love
color.
But I particularly love color grading because of its subtleties.
This talk today is to run you through my personal color grading process and show how research
can help inform color grading decisions.
There's an overwhelming aro-
There's an overwhelming amount of tools for color grading,
which is why for this talk,
I've tried to aim more in a theory direction.
However, if you do want to geek out about Photoshop,
Lightroom, or even Unity post-stack stuff,
please, please at me on Twitter.
I've tried to give more,
some, a couple of tool tips throughout this talk,
but it is very much a one-on-one
and how to understand color grading
and helping you trying to define the look.
So, the second thing to know is there's a huge difference between color grading and color editing.
Color editing is often balancing the colors, so you're making the image look decent,
but then there's also color grading, which is more of a look for a set of scenes or images,
and it tends to be more creative and can very much focus on the storytelling.
So, I really love telling stories.
The first time I realized this difference was in 2014.
I was quite depressed, and I happened to be doing
a two-week course on photography.
The lecturer told us you could take any photo you wanted,
but it had to be with a purpose.
As part of the course, we went to go to Daylesford,
which was supposed to be a happy place,
full of happy people, which was cool, great, mm.
But when we got there, it was dark and foggy.
Like really dark and foggy.
And honestly, I had the best time making the photos
look as depressing as possible.
So that's when I realized that you could grade things
how you feel.
For this look, I called it Sad Wes Anderson
because who knew how much fun it was to revel in your misery?
So, since then, I've had a grand old time grading things and how I want them to feel.
I love coming up with different grading styles for different moments in my life and taking
on colors to remember them by.
I'm also an indie games developer, and I'm working on a game called Intergalactic Space
Princess.
It's a narrative adventure game, and when I started making games, I came from a programming
background.
I joked a lot that my art was kind of glorified programmer art, and I was too lazy to use
anything but a touchpad.
However...
I kind of hid behind color to make my assets look maybe semi-decent,
even though I was very bad at drawing.
So I'm going to talk to you a little bit about the game later on,
but for first, let's go into tools.
So color grading in games sadly isn't spoken about all that often.
It's my first time speaking here,
so I hope that I give you a broad overview of what color grading is.
And it's...
And turns out the games industry is really good at producing tools.
But when you're faced with too many, it's easy to get overwhelmed by them.
So I decided to focus my talk today
isn't about explaining every single one of these sliders,
but it's about coming up with your own ideas,
breaking them down, what you want,
and then diving into these tools
to give you exactly what you want.
Think of it like picking out candy in a candy store.
It's chaotic and it's so much fun to try all these things,
but if you try too much, you kind of get sick
and lost and lost sick,
and then you're stuck in some kind of slider hell.
So it's good to go in with a purpose.
It's the way I do this for myself is to make my own rule set.
Think of it this way.
When you create a lookup table, you're creating the rule sets
telling how the colors how to behave.
Why not use the same logic and create some rules for yourself?
So let's go into color history.
So before these nice tools and sliders were a thing,
color grading was actually called color timing.
What timers used to do was a chemical process that tried to predict the film and grade it all the same.
This meant that they had to knew exactly what they wanted before they went in.
This film here is a is a road to position. While Sam Meadies did spend a lot of time and effort
with cinematographer and lighter Conrad Hall, he considered using a bleach bypass on the film.
However, he opted instead to keep the lighting in and to instead subtly remove the pinks and
to saturate the film overall.
Color timing was never a replacement for good lighting, weather conditions and mood.
They simply used it to enhance what was already there.
Once tools, especially color timing versus grading, started developing,
color could start to give films a lot more distinctive looks.
Jean-Pierre Jure, I'm very bad at pronouncing names,
spent two years coming up and experimenting with a look for Emily.
So the other thing about color grading
is you can use it to quote different things.
So this is the movie Stalker by Andrei Tarkovsky,
and this is the film Annihilation.
So films often quote other films,
referencing the things before them.
Tarkovsky said he hated color,
however I think Stalker has some of the prettiest colors,
and he used a film called Ektachrome,
which is like a three-step technicolor process.
It's quite easy to see how Alex Gallin tried to do a similar process
in achieving a three-strip color look,
giving off similar green tones and powerful reds,
despite reds not existing much in the source material,
which I think that's the thing I love most about grading.
It's so easy to quote things and give off similar vibes,
and color grading is really, really powerful
because it's all subconscious.
So this is an experiment I tried.
So all my learning in photography has been through films.
The way I started photography was getting inspired through cinema.
And then through other mediums, and then eventually more abstract things.
Because who says grading has to be realistic?
So one thing about grading is you can't polish a turd,
but you can absolutely roll it in glitter.
So these two shots were taken about 20 seconds apart,
but I have graded them two completely different ways.
So you can really define a look
just by tweaking, tweaking, tweaking the colors.
And if that's all you do,
you end up having a really easy way to get a look.
So for this one I was kind of like trying to go for like those like late 80s like posters
have like the cool sci-fi stuff um and then for this one I kind of went for like the full
trash kind of 80s and galaxy leggings because just because.
So, for grading, it's important to know what exactly it is you want before you go in.
I once got told my work was a little bit too postcard-y to ever do well in photo competitions,
and like an absolute normal human being, I was like, whatever, I like postcards, and
then completely leaned in.
One day when I was in LA, I felt like taking some nice postcards for myself.
Like, you know the super old vintage ones that you find in the back of your drawer?
Like, oh Cheryl, there's a reason why I haven't talked to you in 10 years.
So I kind of decided to upgrade it like that.
So, the first step I usually do is to put together a mood board.
I did a little bit of research and I had a look at the old 60s postcards.
I was particularly interested in how postcards faded rather than whatever film stock was used.
I noticed particularly that the deeper blues had increased in saturation and the lighter blues would fade out.
This is because of the printer technology and the ways the dyes stuck.
So I started developing a rule set for myself.
The dark blues would become deep and saturated,
however the light blues would be faded and murky.
The greens would be more desaturated
and more towards mint.
Reds lean in, so that means that if it's a standard red,
it would either become very pink
if it had any kind of pink hues,
or it'd become orange if it had any kind of orange hues.
And the rest of it kind of just faded away.
So with the example image that I showed before,
this is what a grading process might look like
if I put in those rule sets.
And then this is the process that I came up with
for making the little postcards.
I definitely tried to,
I did actually tweak a lot of the colors
to make them look a little bit more refined
than some of the dyes,
but I still tried to keep the minty green tones
and the deep blues as well as the faded lighter blues.
So it's important to know exactly what it is you want
before you go in there.
Still don't want to photocop.
So the other thing about color grading
is it's good to understand colors, and especially
how to get there.
So when I was driving in a road trip with a couple of friends,
I was staring out the window.
I really love my friend Emmy Spicer's work,
who uses a lot of disposable cameras.
And I kind of felt like it was just
this disposable fleeting moment.
So I put together a bit of a mood board and had a look at some of her work and I found that disposable
cameras are generally made from plastic. They have an incredibly low dynamic range. That means that
the blacks get crushed and the highlights get blown out incredibly easily on a really bad curved shot.
which I had really fun making,
it would kind of look like that.
So everything kind of would exist in the middle
and there would be no highlights and no shadows.
And if you just wanted a quick way to do it,
you just kind of draw like a weird S
and that way you can just like clip your highlights
and crush your shadows and you'll be right to go.
So for the research, I started breaking down
by what exactly disposable cameras are.
it's easy to kind of like slap on a fielder and be like yeah nostalgia
but for this I was like well I kind of want to work out how disposable cameras
work because a lot of the scans that you get
of disposable cameras are incredibly unreliable and incredibly inconsistent
so I did some research and broke down exactly what I was trying to quote
And I did some research on the properties of the cameras.
For example, how often disposables have wacky light
meters and use cheap films.
That meant that I could deduce what film stocks are used, but
also that they're likely to be either
underexposed or overexposed.
So, once I figured out what kind of film they used, I know that there's a lot of film stock
online that can teach you exactly how the colors behave.
I find this research really interesting, and if you're, say, doing an 80s film, you can
look up what kind of films they were using.
or if you're doing like a 60s film or even like a 1920s film, you can really break down the research
and find out exactly how they achieved the colors they did. And then if you can't find reference
material, you're able to look at color charts to be able to work out exactly how they behave.
The other thing that I was looking at was how plastic versus glass lenses.
So what are the, how does that affect the image?
So I know how cheaply disposable cameras are made,
but my research suggests that the cameras and Holgers are quite similar.
So then I looked at colors behaving on plastic lens and finger smearings.
Once I've done the research in this,
I begin to create a rule set and understanding
of what colors I want to use.
There's a lot of different tools for the job.
And while this isn't a tool talk,
maybe hopefully the next few process slides might be useful.
So the broad overview is sunset creates very pink tones
for a lot of the cheap films.
So that's a pink overlay.
The blacks and shadows get crushed to green.
So you can have green shadows.
You want murky colors.
So you add a brown overlay.
Greys come to purple, blues go to grey, which you can just use using hue and saturation meter.
And it's really about like experimenting and working out these rule sets and then working how to get the colors and then going through your own personal sleigh to hell.
So this is a quick step-by-step of that process.
So first, I had a pink overlay.
If you're using something like Unity,
you can add a color tint over the top.
That works really well.
I then crushed the curves.
That's creating that little S shape.
I then created green shadows.
You can either do this through curves or those three
will.
I've just had a mental blank.
And then you can add browns, desaturate the blues, and usually add like a dehaze and reduce
the clarity.
And you thought color grading was based on feel.
The other thing about color grading is it doesn't have to be realistic.
What if you want to just pick out something out of the blue?
You don't have, like, how do you do the data set from...
What if you have a very limited data set to be inspired from
and trying to work out how the colors work?
So...
If you are using a reference image
and you don't know what colors exist,
you can pick it out and isolate the colors
using a grayscale overlay.
So the first thing I do is easily isolate the colors
with a gray overlay.
I tend to do this a lot and break down the properties
of something I want to quote.
I definitely know there's a lot of purple and orange in there
but I'm trying to uncover what the other properties are.
By doing a saturation map, it's super fast,
and hopefully I don't have time to explain it,
how to actually do it, but it is very Googleable.
You can work out exactly what colors are used in an image.
This is very useful when you're trying to break down exactly
how something looks the way it does.
So when you're doing reference boards for color grading,
you can really see what colors are used.
Essentially, you basically create a map of where the most saturated bits of the image
are, which I was white, and the least saturated images, and then you have an overlay of the
original image over the top.
So it makes it really easy to read.
This gives me a colour scheme to work from, and I love using data like this because occasionally
your eyes will lie to you.
The, sorry.
So I worked out that the colors must be
purple, blue, or orange.
When you are color grading, it's important to make sure
that you have at least three colors,
otherwise an image can start to look monochromatic.
For example, this image here looks a little bit nicer
than this image here where I took out the orange.
I also wanted to, I spent a lot of time tweaking the temperatures of these images.
And you can really work out how color grades behave with each, when you have a rule set and then you adjust the temperature.
It's interesting to watch how all the other colors relate to that.
I completely underexposed it because that gives it
its flat and moody look, so if you look at a histogram,
it's like all in the left part of the histogram,
and it gives a very underexposed tint feel.
So with this in mind, I used those same rule sets
to create a simplistic color scheme for the next three
images, and then the three after that.
Seeing how a rule set can behave in different light
and applying subtle changes is always incredibly interesting.
you don't have to base your grading on something
that already exists.
All you need to do is create a consistent rule set
to work out how your colors behave.
Honestly, there is so much more to grading than this.
Some of the things that I haven't Googled
are secondary grading, masking,
transitional grading, consistency.
There is so much to talk about,
but for now I'm gonna get onto video games.
So, one of the cool things about, even though this is not a video game, it's Steven Universe, which is great,
but one thing that I love looking at animation is how they get inspired by other things.
So, Steven Universe and Being Puppycat clearly took a lot of inspiration from Sailor Moon.
There's been a lot of really fantastic color grading examples in games already.
So like Leave a Mar by Florian is an amazing example of how you can do an incredibly awesome
color scheme. Dead Static Drive by Mike Blackney is also a really good example of how he uses a
lookup table throughout the game to create an inconsistent look. Mirror's Edge was one of the
AAA games that really did do a very expressive color grade
and had a very clean-looking city.
And Firewatch is another game that
is very good at color grading.
So I'm going to show you my dang game.
So this is my game, Intergalactic Space Princess.
So the protagonist is Malene, who's
a 14-year-old girl with opinions on things.
The colors reflect said opinions and communicate to the player
how she feels about the environment.
Her hometown is beige-y and dusty and she finds it incredibly boring, but when she does
find somethings interesting, like the fridge or falling down the intestines of an interdimensional
worm, it's colourful.
So when I was making assets for this game I ran into a problem.
I had done an asset pass in the milk bar and I wanted the milk bar to feel clinical,
kind of like that gross plastic tarp that you have on those barbecue tables outside.
Mmm, chemicals.
So I chose the color scheme of mint, red and beige to convey that look.
However, it really didn't go with the rest of the game.
Malene had the same opinion of the milk bar as she did with the house and the street.
But luckily, as of my experience with photography, I knew a little bit about color grading.
So I decided to...
tackle solving this. So the color scheme for Lane's house was beige, yellow, and blue. The color scheme
for the street was just like 50 shades of beige, which is awful. And I like to think that color
grading is the bow. And all of there's all the presents in front of the Christmas tree. You know
which presents you got from Auntie Sandra because she uses the same bow and despite them all having
different wrappings, you can tell that they're from Auntie Sandra because she uses the same ribbon.
So I wanted to give the whole town a feeling of past nostalgia,
kind of like those bad phone apps that make your phone look like those toy pictures.
I also wanted to make sure that the accent colors didn't get lost, especially Marlene.
So I started developing a rule set for myself.
I wanted there to be an overwhelming amount of brown,
but not the realistic, gritty, video game brown,
but a cute, kind of animated, fun, steppier brown.
So I did a lot of tweaking to the saturations.
I also wanted the game to be desaturated
without looking as desaturated as a lot of other games.
I also wanted the accent colors
not to get affected so much by the brown,
but still stand out as accent colors.
So the image on the left is the one that is the new grade,
and the image on the right is the old grade,
where basically a lot of the characters
are kind of getting lost.
So the Milk Bar is still standing out.
I'm using Unity for this, but honestly,
there's a lot of stuff doing the same.
You can use Photoshop to grade a lot of your things
and then import them as a lookup table into Unity.
And I really recommend doing this
because it's really easy and really cheap
and I really like grading in Photoshop,
but I'm really biased.
So this is where a lookup table can come in really handy.
So instead of defining
So it yeah
So first off I wanted to make it look like late afternoon
I had a go at putting the initial lights in that I wanted to give it a yellow ambient light and a very subtle blue
filter for the character
Once I did that I started to work on the post-processing stack
It was still very yellow and it still really didn't go with the rest of the game
So one thing about grading is it's generally good to grade neutral.
My game is small enough that I know that I can do a lot of bespoke grading through lighting
and then tweak it to get it exactly how I want.
However, if you want your game to be fast and consistent,
it's incredibly important to have a neutral base
to work on when color grading.
This is where lookup tables come in really handy.
Because they have a low dynamic range,
it means any kind of overblown highlights or shadows
will get lost because they are a low dimension.
I can't words.
It's important to keep the scenes quite desaturated as
well.
Well, not too desaturated, but make
sure your saturations don't get crushed either.
So yeah, just grade neutral of Log C.
So I wanted to make it look like late afternoon,
so put in the initial lights.
And then after that, I really started
to work on the color grading.
So that's where I put in.
like a lookup table that was a Fuji-based film filter.
I edited the curves to make it, like,
give that contrast that the rest of the town had.
And I really started overlaying
and tweaking the color balance
to make it go with the rest of the game,
but still being able to keep
the colors of the characters the same.
So this is the before and this is the after.
So the final steps for, so the summary for color grading is,
so the step one is to figure out
exactly what you want to achieve.
Do you want to make it look like the 80s?
Do you want to have a clinical look?
Do you want to go for a sad indie band cover?
It's up to you, but it's important to decide what exactly it is you want.
The second step is to put some research together
as to why you want the thing for your game.
Do you want to make it look like it's from the 80s?
Research the film stock they use.
Do you want to make it look like Blade Runner?
Start researching how tungsten film behaves.
You don't have to go by research,
but research helps a lot when you're trying to be consistent.
And the step three is to establish an internal rule set
for yourself.
So this is coming up with rules to be consistent,
and it's okay to be inconsistently consistent
as long as you just have to decide that's what you want.
Oops, I'm just, ah, there we go.
So research makes things easier in the long run,
which is one of the tips.
Grading doesn't have to be realistic, just consistent,
and grading neutral.
So, that's the talk. Thank you.
APPLAUSE
Any questions?
We have to go up to the mic.
Hi, I had a question.
Thanks for the talk.
So you covered a lot about 2D games it looked like.
But if you have any thoughts on doing 3D,
if you plan to do a lot of color grading and a lot of color
post-processing, would you recommend maybe doing
less color in the lights that you're placing in the scene?
I guess, what are your thoughts on that?
Yeah, so the question was, if you're doing 3D color grading,
what do you do about a lot of the lights and that?
Yeah, so when I was recently helping out a friend
grade his game, and he had a lot of overblown stuff in Unreal,
and it was really hard to kind of come back down from that.
So when he made the things a lot more neutral,
that's when it was a lot easier.
and the lookup tables that we were kind of creating
really started to stick for the rest of the scene,
so I'd definitely go neutral.
Thank you so much.
Thanks for the talk.
I have a question.
How would you deal with HDR?
As you talked about a lot of lookup tables,
low dynamic range, but now I want to do an HDR.
What do you do for color grading?
Um, so I don't have that much experience in HDR because I am using a lot of like my
game is for mobile so but it I guess it's similar to the way you use raw colors in photography.
Um yeah I'm so sorry I'm so flustered at the moment. Sorry.
Oh, great talk.
I was curious if you have any hardware calibration
that you do and any process to check
your colors across different platforms, different monitors?
Yeah, so what I always do for this is I tend to color space
is incredibly important.
So what I tend to do is in Photoshop,
I tend to have a big canvas and make screenshots and paste
all of the different color spaces.
And I know it's not the most accurate,
but it is kind of like a way to see like,
oh no, is anything getting crushed?
Like are any of the tones getting like dead?
The other way that I always do it as well
is to view things on my phone
and I have this really crappy monitor at home
and that's great to tell if something is like really bad
because you can just tell it straight away.
So I don't ever try and get true color,
but I do try and get, try and.
get, what's the word, I try and get edge cases
to make sure that all the colors look okay.
Cool, thanks.
Hi, my name is Danny.
That was a beautiful talk.
Thank you.
My question is, I work on a VR game.
And especially when working on mobile devices,
I can't actually do any post-processing.
So I'm wondering if you have tools
to do color grading without using post-processing a lot.
The ones I could think of is doing color grading
on my baked lighting or directly adjusting the textures.
Is there anything else out there?
Yeah, oh man, so I was actually having this conversation
like two days ago.
So Ted Denola, he works for Oculus,
he's a great person to contact
because I'm having a lot of mental planks at the moment.
But he had some really great advice about that
because yeah, I think he was saying bacon lining
and everything like that.
I'm so sorry for just having a biggest brain freeze.
But he's a really good person to contact, Ted Denola.
And he works at Oculus.
I think that is it.
Thank you.
I'm so sorry.