Alright, I'm gonna get started, uh, since we're about five minutes off now. Alright, so,
like Tim said, uh, I'm Mike Junkerbluth, I work at Zenimax online, uh, currently we're
finishing up Elder Scrolls online.
And prior to ZeniMax, I've really worked at a handful of different studios on an assortment of
different games. And it seems like at every studio, on every game, we seem to run into a
similar problem. Which is, how can we essentially take all that great awesome stuff that
Jalil was talking about, all that stuff about really studying a performance and figuring out
what's unique to the character. How can we do that, not just on these main characters that
are featured on the covers, but actually to all those secondary NPC characters in the game
that never seem to get the right amount of love, right?
Of course the big reason why that doesn't seem to happen is
what we always hear, right? There's not enough time, there's
not enough resources, so unlike the main characters, which
usually have defined traits and objectives that everyone on the
team is aware of, NPCs often times are just a name on a page
with maybe, at best, a short bio, some random abilities
assigned to them, which of course leads to characters that
can feel generic, unrelated to the world, to each other or to
the player, right?
And to top it off, everyone on the team may actually have a different idea as to what
any of those traits are for a character when they're implementing their aspect of the character
into the game, right? So, with so many characters and production time always limited, what we
really need to do and what we want to do is create a dedicated process for creating an
ecology. Alright, so what do I mean when I say ecology?
Well, the textbook definition is, it's the study of how
organisms interact amongst their environment and one
another. For our purposes and for the purposes of this talk,
when I say ecology, what I mean is how a character fits into the
world. So, what follows are some of the approaches I've been a
part of on different games to try and do that, to create a
process for establishing ecology.
Because most oftentimes a lot of these problems
actually become most glaring mid-production,
they really are created to be adapted
into any workflow at any point.
But of course, like anything, the sooner
you can get these into the pipeline,
the sooner they're established, the more beneficial they'll be.
All right, so the first step to create a process that
allows you to find a character's personality as quickly
as possible.
The way to do that is, of course,
with defining their objective.
every single person in their life operates with some sort of objective, right? It could be that
the objective is enough money to, you know, to save up enough money to buy a house, that could
be one. Or to be liked by someone in particular. Or simply just to survive. Whatever it is,
without a provable and concrete objective, a character has no connection to their world and
we're really unable to empathize with them.
Oftentimes, the objective of an NPC is really simply defined as either impeding or helping
the player, right? But we know that's way too broad for animation purposes and honestly
it's even too mechanically shallow for designers, right? But oftentimes this is all we have
to go on when we're given a new character. So let's start from there, right? If that's
all you have...
Let's get a universal touchstone that we can use to quickly establish a character's specific objective.
For my purposes, I like to use Maslow's Hierarchy of Needs,
as it can quickly classify a character and give focused direction on how to brainstorm.
What each level of the pyramid depicts is the needs that drive the decisions and lifestyle
of the person living within it.
Everything below the level that they're at is already established to them.
They don't even care about it.
They don't have to worry about it anymore.
So essentially, how a character that functions within the esteem block...
right, which is focused primarily on respect, how they react to the world
would be entirely different than someone in the physiological block
who's driven by the bare essentials to survive. Alright, so let's see how this
works.
This is when I used it on Elder Scrolls Online.
So the problem was, we started with a graveyard that was full of skeletons.
And we were trying to figure out some animations we could give them to spice up the scene a little bit.
But in a way that didn't make them seem like the normal undead zombie creatures you've seen a million times in a million games, right?
So I went to the hierarchy and I looked to see where they might fall.
And it was pretty clear that they don't really have any physiological needs, right?
Like they don't need to breathe or eat or drink or anything like that, right?
So then I move up to the next one, which is safety.
And instantly a lot more ideas came into what they could be doing.
The way I saw it, skeletons were essentially guardians, right?
With a single focus in their actions, which was to protect this graveyard, right?
They were essentially like the soldiers posted at the tomb of the unknown soldier at Arlington, Virginia.
And, you know, instantly, there's...
their whole purpose became a lot more clear, right? They didn't seem like zombies anymore,
which exists really only on that physiological block, right?
The need to eat, or being driven by that want to survive,
you know? And I think that's a big reason why when...
you don't have something in place. Oftentimes, since physiological needs are the go-to behavior
because they're so basic of what everyone understands, when you're not given time, that's
where you're instantly going to oftentimes put characters and creatures and probably
explains why zombies are so prevalent and easily successful in games, right? Because
they match. But to take it even one step further and complete the undead holy trinity, uh,
we can also define ghosts, which is important because we have a
lot of those as well. Um, and those are above both safety and
physiological needs and operate really only for emotional
purposes. So they're driven by love and belonging as that's
often the unfinished business that keeps them from passing on.
So by using the hierarchy and simply identifying where all
three of these token undead types fell, uh, they can feel
unique to themselves but still be grounded within the same
world.
But that's only the first step in this process.
Because oftentimes, even within those hierarchies,
you're going to have overlap in specific defining traits.
So to drill down even a bit further,
but not lose their driving objective,
rather than create that typical character lineup
you've seen a million times, we had an idea
of why not try to line up the groups.
And the way this came about was to fix an issue
we kept running into while doing R&D on Shadows of Mordor
at Monolith.
See, how intelligent enemies were in regards to one another got really muddy and we were kind of
in the weeds about how it should work. A sticking point that we kept getting hung up on was that
while cave trolls are rather dumb, we wanted a version that was more intelligent. One that might
have been able to be trained and educated to actually command an army, not just be a wrecking
ball that runs through it. And...
While we wanted that, we still wanted to make sure that they maintained that core feeling of a troll, right?
So that they still had their objective.
So when we tried to do a traditional lineup, that you've seen, where we thought everyone would belong,
our opinions were all over the map.
So the idea of, you know, why not try lining up the groups?
So the way that works is, I started with enemies that were animals, and those were, you know,
obviously easily grouped by their nature, as well as being primarily physiologically
driven on the hierarchy, which is signified by their red bar. On one end of the lineup
was spiders, right, they're not very intelligent, but on the other end was wards, which are
apparently quite intelligent creatures.
Then as more creatures needed to be added to the lineup, we can easily do so while still staying true to the needs of their hierarchy.
So if great eagles became enemies, they would go to the end of the block and push the wargs towards the middle.
Then you bring in the next group. In this case, the root of our problems, which was the trolls.
Again, you do the same as last time, but this time also line up the group in relation to the animals group.
Here we can see that a warg would scoff at taking orders from a cave troll, but would
certainly respect the commands of a more intelligent captain.
On it goes, so we bring in the next group which is goblins.
They're much more communal, as you can see by being yellow, and driven by some basic
sociological needs on the hierarchy.
So while they are higher on it, they're clearly not much smarter than trolls, making it clear
that they could be commanded by a trained troll.
bring in the orcs, who are driven by needs of respect,
esteem, and achievement, yet intelligence-wise,
grunts could still be dumber than a troll or a goblin.
And then, as a reference point, the elves who just are way beyond everything else
of those brutal creatures, right?
So, while a standard lineup of characters can give you a lot of the same animation, or the
same information, by grouping them you can quickly identify and modify the relation of key
traits while maintaining the consistency of their objective and needs, right? And if a new
character is created for the game, it can quickly be added into the group without throwing the
other groups and characters out of whack. So there, there it was, that's what we were missing.
Kind of a big picture that we could establish and maintain quite easily.
like everything, that's not enough. And we needed to drill down even further. Specifically, we
wanted to be able to quickly compare individual characters against one another. But the
answer to this one wasn't creative or methodical, actually it was very methodical and it
comes from math, right? It's a coordinate graph. So this one we didn't come up with on our
own. I found this in Jesse Schell's The Art of Game Design. Who owns this book?
Awesome. Everyone in here should own it.
Without a doubt, this is one of those game design books
that every animator should have on their shelf
right next to the Illusional Life.
Alright, so the way this works.
You start by creating an axis
with two sets of binary traits on each end.
For our purposes, we needed to define how characters applied or modified the intelligence
within what we used in the groups, um, to one another. So we used sly to inept, wild to
civil, and then on the second graph, uh, dominant to submissive and evil to good, as those
often seem to come up as well.
Then create a key with the characters you want.
Again, use the colors of the hierarchy.
It helps to keep the needs and visual language consistent
across all this stuff.
We also added the player character as a reference point.
So to start, place a dot within the spectrum
that represents each character on the game.
So the warg is certainly wild, yet slightly sly.
It's also rather evil and slightly dominant.
And then on it goes with each character.
And quickly you'll find how similar or unique
your characters are.
If you find a few characters are plotting almost identically,
then either move one to an open area of the charts,
or if you need to, cut it.
Likewise, when a new character is being created,
you can easily see where an opening exists
for that specifically needed personality.
So we needed somebody in like civil and inept, right?
Maybe that would be a good buddy cop or I don't know.
Lord of the Rings had buddy cops, right? I know the lore.
Uh, uh, but in cases where characters are inherently rather similar to, to others in
some ways, such as was the case with the orcs, they kind of were close to some others. You
can, uh, quickly compare one against the rest, uh, using coordinate graphs as well. Simply
place the character's dot in the center of the graph, like the orc in this instance.
Then plot the other character's dots in relation to the specific traits of the orc.
Instantly you'll see how they would behave if one another was in a scene with each other,
and how the social hierarchies would be established and actually play out.
Alright, so by this point, you'll know what their objective is, and how they would go
about their life within the world to try and achieve it, right? You've got that base knowledge
kind of figured out. The last visual chart I like to use then is a path chart. And what
this does is, this will show how a character is meant to path throughout the world, so
when you deliver the animations to designers and world builders and audio people, their
pathing is going to be consistent with the personality of the animations you created.
So let's return to the skeletons and zombies of Elder Scrolls to show this in practice.
So the skeleton which we established was like those militant-esque robot guardians, right?
They would travel in like straight uninterrupted lines like you've seen in other games, right?
And when they need to turn, right, they wouldn't just turn like this.
You know, they're going to stop, turn.
and then walk, right? That needs to be consistent with how they're actually moving in the animation.
Contrast this with how the zombies would move, right? And they stumble and lurch to their
destination. They're all over the place, right? I mean, it's, you know, it's like they're
sensing that next bit of food that they want or they've even forgotten where it is they're
going.
And then when it turns, you know, it's not gonna turn like
that, that same robot, uh, skeleton. It's gonna, you know,
it's gonna go way out and then come back in. Whatever. Make it
messy. Uh, right? I mean, these are, these are obviously the
behaviours you're building already into the animation,
right? But if a zombie's given a path, like a skeleton, no matter
how successful your animation, I mean, you got, if you got this
and it's in a straight line.
That just, it feels at odds and it's not going to feel as good as if you actually paid attention to that pathing.
Alright, so now that you've established and defined all these charts, right, for your purposes.
You want to create a one sheet with all of these charts together that you can have to quickly remind yourself when you're coming back to a character or as you're working throughout it.
Not just for yourself though, but so that you can hand this off to other people working on it, because remember that's half the problem, is everyone might have a different opinion on how these characters should work in the game.
And that's the beauty of these charts, right?
Once everyone working on the characters
knows the visual language that's established,
you can quickly refer to the one sheet
and get all the information that's needed
without reading or, let's be honest, skimming, right?
A giant, lengthy bio.
Think of this as a visual, you know, TLDR.
So, in the case of the goblins,
by looking at their one sheet,
we know they are highly communal.
We can see how intelligent, submissive, and cruel they are in relation to one another.
We can also see how they would move through spaces, often stopping to inspect the world
and others around them.
And they're also aware or scared enough of other things in their ecosystem to always
be looking ahead and turning or getting out of the way of others long before the movement
is actually required.
That should be enough to get everyone onto the same page in a flash.
And if they really want more info, they can go back to that giant lore bio or whatever
if they really need it.
Okay, so that's the first half of ecology, right?
How they interact with one another.
But the second half is equally important, and that's how they interact with their environment.
And for this, we refer to everyone's favorite principle, staging.
It's one of those 12 principles that always is cited as being lost to game animation, right?
But we know it really isn't lost.
It's simply in the hands of other disciplines oftentimes.
So, level designers, world builders, content designers.
Oftentimes, they're the ones in control of staging the character using your animations.
And they might even just have a giant large database
that they're pulling animations from, right?
That you don't necessarily have control over.
So it's important to empower them,
to give them a pair of glasses
that will allow them to see the world
in the same way as you're trained Animator Eye.
recommending books, writing docs, all that's fine first step.
And honestly, they're pretty helpful for you because they allow you to get
incredibly specific with the principles and explanations and put all your
thoughts in the paper in long form.
But just like when we were defining the character's personality, and when we're given a bio,
a wall of text isn't the end goal.
And even if it is read, it's not really probably going to be returned to after that first viewing.
So how can we make a more visual and quickly digested approach when we're talking to designers and other creators?
Early on when I started at ZeniMax, a part of the group I was on was to help define and improve staging of areas within the game.
To get away from a wall of text, I took a screenshot, so this is a few years ago, and it was of the Mages Guild.
And I asked the questions that I thought most important to the scene and the player.
Who looks to be the most important person within the building?
If I was going to ask someone here about joining the guild,
their name's the magister, who would that be?
Which characters look to be trainers,
and which character is the vendor?
So in the big picture, I don't know if you can
tell any of that stuff.
Alright, so these are the answers, right? And there's a few issues here. First off, everyone's
really far away from you the moment you walk into the door, right? This is supposed to be a big
lived in place, but everyone's in the back. Worst of all is the magister, who's, you know, the
admissions officer for all intents and purposes. And they're the front facing person of the
guild, why are they back there? The vendor is appropriately behind the counter, but they're
lost within the pillar and missing a perfect opportunity to be framed within the environment.
And the trainers aren't in places or postures
that would be associated with such a role.
So using my quick and dirty Photoshop skills,
I restaged it so that they could see quickly
how the scene could look better.
So make it so that the moment the player enters the space,
you break the room into three planes of foreground,
middle ground, and background, with thought
given to which characters the player would most often
be interacting with when they're coming into the space.
The magister is brought up front to greet visitors and talk to new prospects.
The trainers are moved to the middle ground and given actions that are appropriate to their title.
And the vendor is moved to be framed within the archway of the bookshelf, while still being behind the counter.
And a role that I thought was missing, that of a headmaster or person in charge,
was put up on the walkway above, using the verticality to imply higher social standing.
So, with a few pictures, essentially eliminates a lot of a doc's need, right?
But even that, they're going to see that and they'll go,
OK, how do I?
I didn't know that stuff.
How do I think about this stuff?
How do I keep it in mind all the time?
So what I wanted to do is give a cheat sheet that they can
stick up at their desk for reference.
You've gotten Post-it notes and all that stuff posted to
yours, they need something similar.
So for our purposes, I broke that picture
into a few sections.
First up was finding the character's objective.
What do they want?
What actions reflect that?
And what emotions are they feeling?
And to answer that last question, I included visuals of the seven universal emotions.
Not to mention having the faces on there adds some life to the page, as well as subtly influencing the person reading it to always be more aware of the mood of the scene.
That's really important, keep that in mind like Julia was saying.
You need to think of what happened before and after and what they're actually feeling.
Next, how do these characters fit together?
What are the relationships and social hierarchies?
Who's the star of the scene?
where do they expect help or danger to come from?
In all of these, right, it's that one sheet becomes important again,
because a lot of that's defined for them already.
But the characters, the NPCs, aren't the only ones in the scene,
and their reaction to the player, of course, needs to be taken into account,
as that's often either a direct help or hindrance in completing their objective.
So...
Are they expecting the player to arrive?
What were they doing before the player shows up?
And what do they want to do after the player leaves?
And then finally, a reminder of the shot elements
that were used within the example.
Where is the primary entrance or exit of the scene?
Define the three planes and make use of framing devices
within the environment.
In all of these little cheat sheets,
I was conscious not to have more than three bullet points.
Because honestly, at that point, people are just going to stop reading and you want something
they can quickly glance and hopefully internalize, right?
And then of course, the most important thing, when in doubt, act it out, right?
So once you've got a doc and a one sheet and all that good stuff, you need to get it out there to
people as, as many ways as possible. Email, put it up on an internal directory, print it out and
give it to the people in each department, you know will evangelize it and really glom onto it.
Hold a workshop that, that covers it and allows for Q&A. Sit down with people one on one to
help put it into practice. Relying on only one or two of these methods isn't going to cut it.
I've tried and it fails every time.
Okay, interactions between characters, check.
Their environment, check.
The final piece of the puzzle
and how this all informs their personality
is specifically how they engage with the player,
yet maintain their established ecology.
Here's a story I imagine sounds like
one that you may have experienced yourself.
On Singularity, while many of the creatures
had defined personality traits within their animations,
all their gameplay and abilities seemed to boil down to really the same thing. Uh, they
had a melee attack if you got close, a ranged projectile attack if you stood far and usually
some sort of scream when they became aware of you. Making their combat match the personalities
we put within the animation was honestly something we were really struggling with.
But when armed with what makes characters tick,
there's actually a great tool inherent to the medium
that we can use to help define and connect their gameplay
with their personality.
Remember when in doubt, act it out.
I've got like one minute.
All right, let's go.
Our solution came from the game's multiplayer,
which to give it a more unique spin,
had creatures as playable on one team
and soldiers on the other.
While originally we were worried it would force us
to change the personalities we had established
within our animations,
actually once we took control of them,
it was the gameplay weaknesses that came about
because the animations had the personality.
forcing ourselves to actually role play,
to step into their shoes within the game,
we knew what they wanted to do in a way
that just acting them out at our desk actually couldn't.
So in the instance of the revert,
which was that dreaded zombie affliction again,
we didn't know what to do for a long time.
And while we had the personality
of like a wounded animal that would have
this interesting contrast of agony
versus adrenaline emotionally,
playing it actually helped us figure out
how it should actually attack and fight.
We wanted to make it a bit slower and pack a harder punch
with a high tolerance for pain, right?
Like a wounded animal, they don't necessarily feel that
because they've got all this adrenaline going.
And we realized that we had this charge and rush attack
that just wasn't appropriate.
Honestly, they should force you to come to them.
So we gave it a proximity mine, like a mucus thing,
so it could corral soldiers into a desired location.
It was given a medium-range vomit to blur their vision
so they couldn't escape.
And then a sonar-like ability to see through walls
and plan your ambush.
And just like that, the idea of a wounded animal
really started to match the personality
and the gameplay and the animation.
Alright, and that's really what it's about, right?
Like, role-playing, acting.
You know, we want to sit and we want to focus on that cool craft stuff that Jaleel was talking about.
We want to sit there and think about these little tics and moments.
But, oftentimes, we're not setting ourselves up to a point or given enough information
to be able to spend the time to think that, because we're having to define the space layer.
the quicker you can come up with a system like this.
Use this one, create your own, whatever.
The quicker you're going to be able to get those core things
of knowing who that character is out of the way,
so then you can really take the time
to figure out what makes them unique within themselves.
Thank you.
I don't think there's a.
I don't think we have time for questions, but that's my contact information on Twitter and email.
I'd love to talk to you guys about this.
I think we're also going to have overflow Q&A today after 6 in an overflow room.
We can figure that out.