Welcome everybody.
All right.
So today we're going to talk about game studio management.
This is my 20th GDC.
Yeah.
And what better way to celebrate than talking about game studio management.
OK, so for people who don't know about my situation,
I've worked at a lot of places over the years.
One place I got a lot of education
about studio management was at Disney Imagineering,
where I was the creative director of the Disney Virtual
Reality Studio.
Also for the last 12 years or so,
I have taught at the Entertainment Technology Center
at Carnegie Mellon University, where at this point,
I guess I've helped oversee hundreds of different teams
make various game projects.
And also, for the last 12 years, I've run my own studio,
Shell Games, which is in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania.
We started out with about five people.
And over the years, we have gradually grown up to our
current staff of 100 people.
And so part of what I'll be able to talk about today is
some of those transitions and some of the
things you run into.
So first, I would like to ask, who here is really excited
about management?
Raise your hand.
All right, I see a lot of ironic hand raises there.
And then I see a lot of, yeah, and there's no way, no.
And I guess I have to wonder, like, really,
did you see what was on the door?
I mean, it's a management talk all up in here.
Because one of the things we find in the game industry,
let me ask this question, who here is excited
about making great games?
Raise your hand.
Yeah, there's all the hands, right?
And that is the thing in the game industry.
People are not super excited about management all the time.
Some people are.
But everybody's excited about making great games.
But the management still needs to get done.
And so a lot of it is bad, as we know, because people just
aren't that into it.
Because most of us, when it comes to management, we're
kind of this guy right here.
I'd much rather be focusing on my games and not having to
deal with all this management BS.
And this often leads to a lot of problems.
So some of the common problems that you get from bad management, right?
You're in a situation, you're like, I don't know how to structure management because,
hey, I didn't, I don't have an MBA, what do I know about this?
I don't know how things should be structured, particularly as your studio is growing.
I've got this one project, I'm not sure what's the right way, what is the best and optimal
way to manage this given project?
Oh my God, we had another miscommunication with a client.
You know, we thought they understood what we meant when we said we were cutting the
combat, but no, they didn't understand.
So you've got that.
And then tell me if you've ever had this problem.
Too many meetings, right?
I don't think I've ever been anywhere where people haven't
said, oh my god, you just have too many meetings.
Low morale.
It's embarrassing.
It happens sometimes.
And you went into games because you wanted to be awesome.
And then if you're going to work every day and it's not
awesome, then that is not awesome.
Now the next one, I'm sure, has never happened to anyone
in this room.
Late games.
Late games are not an accident or, you know,
you can't just blame it on the creative process.
Late games is bad management.
That is what that is.
And then the last one, the worst one,
the one that we never talk about at GDC, our game sucks.
Oh, man.
Damn it.
We worked on this a year and a half, and it sucks.
Right?
So those are things that happen all the time.
They happen to everybody.
And the key is finding a way to fix these things.
OK, so when I was trying to understand this stuff,
because I don't come from a place where I'm like,
had some super amazing management education
or anything, particularly as my studio started to grow,
it's like, man, what are we going to do?
And thinking kind of broadly about it,
I couldn't help but think about ants and bees.
Because, you know, ants and bees.
get a lot done.
Oh my god, they get all this stuff done.
Like, look at this.
The bees built that.
They got together and said, yeah, we're going to build this.
And they did it.
Look how perfect it is.
There's no design document.
There's no daily scrum.
There's no deadlines.
They just like, no, we're just going to get together.
We're all going to do this, and it's going to be awesome.
So how is that possible? And check this one out. Here's this guy. He's really into ants.
So he finds abandoned anthills and he gets a big five-gallon drum of dental plaster and
he pours it down slowly, slowly into the anthill, waits for it to harden, and then slowly, carefully
digs it out and hangs it up. And that's the interior of an anthill. Those little spirally
things are tunnels.
going down, sort of corkscrew tunnels that the ants make,
and those little flat leaves hanging off are rooms that the ants have created.
Most of the lower rooms are kitchens where food is prepared
for the rest of the colony. And they do all this with no meetings.
So I want to understand how is that possible, because I'd like to live in a
world with no
meetings. What's going on?
So then I read this book, The Superorganism,
by a couple of guys who really studied the heck out
of insect societies.
And they explain a lot of it.
And one of the key quotes I liked
was actually from another book.
The formation of a higher level unit
by integrating lower level units will
succeed only if the emerging organization acquires
the appropriate technologies for passing information
among its members.
And I think the key phrase there is passing information.
It's really weird to think about ants and bees having
information technologies.
But that's exactly what they have.
They have systems of communicating with each other
in evolved, organized ways so that the right information
gets to the right insects at the right time so that they
all know what to do for the good of the whole
organization.
So it's very efficient.
OK, so I got thinking about that.
Man, that's cool.
They sort of do have meetings, but they're just really,
really efficient.
They're so efficient, you don't even notice
they're having them.
So thinking about that, then thinking about other things, about this notion of information.
A lot of philosophers have been talking about information lately.
We used to talk, you know, philosophers used to talk about the universe made of matter
and the elements.
And then they started saying, no, the universe is really made of energy.
And now the modern thing is, actually, the universe may be made entirely of information
and nothing else.
And that's an interesting idea.
and then i got to thinking about kind of eastern medicine and body meridians and
acupuncture
and when you talk to western doctors about it a lot of time they say well
that doesn't really exist she energy flowing around the body you'd show me
it's not there you can see it it doesn't exist it's not there
this is a placebo effect
but anyone who's
had a massage or meditates or
uh... or has undergone acupuncture does tai chi
uh... has
experience
this energy flow
and i've often wondered if
well okay maybe she isn't like electrical energy or
or something or some mystical force flowing around
What if it is a kind of information traveling in the body?
Because we know that our body is a big information network.
It would be like if I said, hey, here's the internet.
There are viruses on it.
Point them out as you look at the physical network.
You might conclude that, no, they don't exist
because they're invisible.
And Christopher Alexander, one of the greatest geniuses of our time.
That's another talk for another day.
In his books, he talks about space being defined by channels of energy.
And I think we've all...
experience this. You know, as you move through cities, there are certain channels where there's
good energy and bad energy, and even in your living room, there's the spots where everybody
kind of moves through, and then there's that dead corner that everything's kind of weird,
and you realize, I should move the couch, and that's why, because that corner feels
weird and bad. So you have that kind of, that may be a kind of information flow. And in
our studios, there's everybody working away.
And you can see people working, and you can look at their
emails, and you can see that stuff.
But the thing that you can't see is the relationships
between people.
And the relationships end up defining an awful lot of how
things happen at the company.
But they are invisible, unless Google comes out with some new
app that lets you see that.
But we can't see that just yet.
Oh my god, that's why Facebook bought
Oculus, I just realized.
Anyway, so as Saint-Exupéry said in The Little Prince,
what is essential is invisible to the eye.
And so just because these things are invisible
doesn't mean we shouldn't focus on them.
And in fact, maybe it means we should focus on them
all the more.
A book that was very influential on me is this book, Design Yourself, by Kareem Rashid.
It has a lot of really kooky advice in it, but the spirit of the book is what influenced
me the most.
His fundamental idea is that you should design your life so that you like it.
You shouldn't just live your life or just deal with things.
You should look at the things you don't like and say, okay, you know what?
This is a design problem.
I'm going to design this so that I like it.
And when it comes to how to get studio management going,
if you don't like the information flows in your studio,
you need to design them so that they are good.
But in order to do that, you need to know
what is the information in your studio.
And that's a little tricky, because, again, it's invisible,
and we don't always see it.
So let's meditate for a second on the notion of information.
Can we get the sound up?
Yeah.
All right, maybe we'll get some of that.
By hook or by crook, we will.
Right, so getting information is difficult.
And it may take a lot of hooks and a lot of crooks
in order to get it out of a studio.
So at first, it seems kind of daunting.
Like, let me look at all the information that's
flowing around in my studio.
So I tried to come up with simple things,
and I couldn't do it.
I was taking this top-down approach
of trying to dissect information in the studio
and was kind of failing.
And so I sat down with Chuck Hoover.
And we started making a big list of like, well,
let's talk about all the many, many kinds of information
that are in the studio.
We just made this big, crazy list
with hundreds and hundreds of elements.
And here's some samples.
We took a very bottom-up approach.
You know, hey, there's a change to this project.
Hey, there's a new project.
Hey, we got a new studio policy.
Hey, there's a best practice for the right way
to do C-sharp coding.
We're having a birthday party on Friday.
Hey, the project's in a little trouble.
Hey, I'm really uneasy.
Oh, I'm super confident about this.
I'd like to throw a red flag on the way that we're documenting everything.
I need help.
That Benson guy, I don't trust that guy at all.
Hey, clients, we got something to tell you.
Wait, no, who's good at what?
Are you good at this and are you good at that?
I'm blocked.
I can't, I've got nothing to do.
Hey, I've got an idea.
Hey, we're out of paper towels.
That Benson guy, he's an idiot.
Oh my god.
Right?
All right.
The studio mission is this.
I'm from Idaho.
This information that I'm telling you
is very, very secret.
I'm really upset right now.
I'm about to start coding this module right now.
Anyway, so there's all these kinds of information.
And it seems sort of overwhelming when you're like,
yeah, this is all flowing around.
What am I going to do?
with this. So looking at it and kind of shaking it around, we started to come up with categories
and I realized that there were some simple categories of information. One of them is
sort of obvious, facts. Duh. A lot of information is facts. Okay, everybody knows that. And
then other information is opinions. Sure, okay, we know that. There are facts and there
are opinions. Okay, that's an information hierarchy right there. But then there's something
else. Emotions. Now some people would say, no, no, no, those are just opinions.
And I said, no, they're not, right?
They are not.
I am mad at you.
That is not opinion.
That is a stone cold fact, right?
So weirdly, emotions are actually more facts
than they are opinions.
But they're not like pure objective facts.
They're very personal kind of facts.
So I find it a good idea to separate those out,
because emotions travel differently
than normal facts do.
So those are three kinds of information, facts, opinions,
and emotions.
And they are about things.
And what are they about when you're in a game studio?
Well, a lot of times they're about projects.
It's like, hey, we're working on this project,
and I have facts, opinions, and emotions about that project.
Separate from that, they're about processes.
Processes outlive projects sometimes.
Sometimes they live within a project.
But processes are really kind of separate from projects,
the way you do things, how you do things.
And then the third one is people,
because people are doing these projects.
OK, well that's a thing.
Maybe you can break that out.
You have facts, opinions, and emotions about projects,
processes, and people.
Well, OK, that's something.
Does that cover everything?
I don't know.
It's not perfect.
But going back to the spreadsheet and going back to
the big thing, kind of made the six columns, and started to
kind of check it off.
And it's like, yeah, new studio policy, that's a fact
about a process.
Well, hey, I need help.
That's an opinion about a project.
And I'm blocked.
That's a fact.
And it's about a project, and probably about a process, too.
And we found, like, yeah, this seems to cover things.
So that's kind of cool.
That's kind of interesting.
OK, well, so that's a way to break down information.
Now we need to look at, like, where does that information go?
Because information is not static.
The first thing to think about is the fact that we ourselves are information networks.
We are not just like a point on a graph.
We are a complex information network inside ourselves and inside our minds.
And if you've ever tried to think of a name and you can't think of it, and then two minutes
later you thought of it, like, yeah, that's because the information was in there the whole
time.
It just had a little trouble.
It got caught in a router somewhere and could not find its way.
So first, we are information networks.
But then, of course, it's hierarchical
because you connect up with other people in the studio.
So there's internal information flow
and then there's external information flow.
And then it's hierarchical again
because the studio communicates with other entities.
Maybe a publisher, maybe with your players,
maybe you've got a licensor or the press
or outsource partners or all kinds of other things.
So you have these sort of hierarchies of information flow.
All right, so that's useful to think about.
But now, the way all information flows is not created equal.
In the business world, we tend to use four main ways
of communication.
Face-to-face, we do a lot.
More and more, we're doing Skype, sort of video conference,
phone calls sometimes, and then lots and lots of email.
And as much as some people like to believe that all these are
equivalent, they certainly are not.
We have lots of evidence that they are not.
And it's interesting to wonder about why.
The key seems to be that the things at the top you're getting much more
information and the things at the bottom you're getting much less.
Face to face communication is a lot of information because yes, you are
hearing my words, but you're also hearing my tone of voice.
You're seeing my facial expression, but then it gets even weirder and deeper
than that because that's all with your conscious mind.
Your subconscious mind is very good at communicating with other people face to face.
There's well documented notion of micro expressions.
Micro expressions are generally when there's a conflict within you, you want to communicate
one thing but you want to hide your emotions.
You can't hide them perfectly.
And so there is a period.
of about 40 milliseconds where you make these tiny expressions that show your true emotions.
And you can't see them very well consciously, but your subconscious totally picks up on them.
You ever have that moment someone's saying something you're like something's not right
about that, that guy's trying to pull something. It's often because your subconscious picked up
on a micro expression.
Now, given that those last about 40 milliseconds,
and given that Skype, on average,
gives you about 20 frames a second,
you are unlikely to pick up microexpressions through Skype.
Um, so that's important.
Uh, another one is, this is gonna sound really crazy,
smell.
we, a subconscious picks up on the smells of other people and emotions are communicated through smell.
There have been studies done, it's a weird study, right? We have two groups, one group's going to watch a comedy movie,
the other group's going to watch a horror movie, and they each put pads under their armpits,
alright, and they watch the movie, and then the pads are collected up, and an unfortunate third group of people
is asked to smell the pads.
And better than average, they can tell which movie was being watched.
Because you really can smell fear.
But you can't smell it over Skype.
Yet.
No, I don't know what that means.
Anyway, this is important because fear is an important thing on projects.
You know, hey, are you going to get that done by Friday?
Oh, yeah, yeah, I'm going to get it done, right?
Yeah, really?
Right?
And anyway, so face-to-face is really, really important.
Tone of voice is really important,
which is why even a phone call can be better than email.
But you know, so choosing the right channel of information
at the right time is really important.
So now, when it comes to scaling,
people often feel like as their studio's growing,
you hear a lot of thoughts about scale.
There are some people who say, you can never
do a good game with more than five people.
and then as a people's it never do again more twenty people
and and uh... but then you see big studios to do the games and what's
exactly
is happening
and why is it different with more people what is it the changes
well the key thing is just simply
this
The number of interactions between people
goes up in kind of an exponential way,
technically the triangle numbers pattern, right?
Three people working together, you just, it's easy, right?
You just, the channels of communication are really simple.
But even when you get up to something
as small as seven people,
like look at all those different paths of information.
And this becomes really important.
If you were on a team of five people,
every day when you come in,
you all talk to each other every day.
When you're on a team of 20 people,
you're not necessarily going to talk to everybody every day.
But you'll probably talk to everybody,
at least have some minor contact with them once a week.
Once you get up to 50 people, you might go four weeks, six weeks, and there might be
somebody in the studio who you have not exchanged one word with in all that time.
And it may be that they have some super important piece of information for you, but you wouldn't
know it because, you know, because the place is big.
And so what we do is we try and set up organizational structures in order to try and get the right
information to the right places at the right time, because it's not going to happen simply
organically this way.
So this is why we have org charts.
Here's a picture of the org chart for Shell Games.
And org charts are typically organized by discipline.
We've got our production team, and our engineering team,
and our design team, and our art team,
and our operations team.
And that's pretty simple and straightforward.
But nowhere in there do you see reflected
anything about our projects.
We do six to eight projects at a time.
But you sure couldn't figure that out by looking at this organizational chart because the point of this
Organization is not to talk about projects
But to talk about specific discipline things to talk about things that have to do with art or talk about design
So a lot this is really very much a chart about mentoring and just sort of getting
Information to the right people about their discipline and so for studios to do more than one project
This is why it's become very common to use a form of matrix management
Matrix management is a simple idea.
The idea is that you sort of report to two people
when you're on a team.
You report up.
If you're a programmer, you report up
to the head of engineering or head of programming, whatever.
And you work with them on things that
are about long-term mentoring and coaching.
But on your project, someone else
is in charge of your project.
At our place, we always have a producer and a director
at the head of every project.
The director is responsible for the creative vision and making sure it's great.
The producer is responsible for making sure it's done on time and that everyone has everything they need.
Now some people say to me, that's a bad idea. You can't have two people in charge of a project.
That's like having two gods. It doesn't work.
And I say, no. I think it's more like having two parents.
It's kind of a good idea sometimes.
And there's a lot of good reasons for that.
They have different areas of expertise.
The people running your project are focused
on two different things.
And then similarly, backing out to the matrix management
point of view, there's the people in charge of your
project and the people in charge of your discipline.
And it's good to be able to talk to the two of them about
two different things.
people at the head of your project about project issues,
and the person at the head of your department
about longer-term issues.
And if you've got a problem with one of them,
you can go to the other and say, man,
you know, I'm hitting a logjam with this guy.
Can you help me?
And then they can often help you out.
So the reason matrix management seems to be a good idea
and is used frequently is because it
allows two different kinds of channels of information.
So organizational structure is one tool for managing your flow.
A second one is office space.
Now, everybody rolls their eyes when it comes to office space.
Nobody feels good about it.
People rarely get excited about, yeah, man,
our office is so incredible.
You don't hear that.
People are like, ugh.
It feels bad.
It feels corporate.
And that's often because.
It's not well designed.
Now, it is a hard, hard design problem.
But if you work at it, you can certainly make it better.
So there's a lot of things to think about when you're
designing your office space.
One thing is to realize that a little distance is
a lot of distance.
So here's an illustration of a thing I literally saw right
outside my desk one day.
We had a project.
There were four people working on it.
and three of them were sitting right next to each other like that.
And then in the middle, you see this kind of a low counter,
that green bar up the middle, was just a low counter.
No big deal.
Like people stored things in it.
And on the other side of that counter
was this other guy with his other desk.
Couldn't have been more than 15 feet, OK, from those three
desks to that one desk.
And but we were observing that there was some bad communication problem
where that one guy kept getting left out of the loop.
And we're like, man, that guy, is he dope?
Why isn't he talking?
Is he just lazy?
Is he ignorant?
And then just watching, it's like, oh my god, I could see it happening.
Someone would be like, hey, I've got a problem.
And the guy next to him would say, yeah, what is it?
Well, it's this and this and this.
And the guy over there is kind of like, wait, you guys talk?
And you can see he's kind of listening.
He's like, no, I don't want to interrupt him.
I'll get back to work.
And he was just left out of the loop.
We simply moved his desk over next to the others,
and the problems got so much better.
So thinking about that is really important.
A lot of notable companies have really
gotten aggressive about office space.
Pixar is one that's very notable.
A lot of times you walk into some big fancy company,
and you go into this big open space.
And you do that here when you go to Pixar.
And that open space is full of weird sculptures
and creepy security guards.
and like you don't really see it doesn't have any point or purpose of the into
intimidate you or whatever
when you walk into pixar
you're in the cafeteria let me know that the band is in the places people sit and
eat in the cafeteria you walk right in
it's it's the central hub of the building and
the whole space is designed very much to get people to cross through this space
as many times as possible
all the bathrooms for example are in the central space
the offices are often like always the go out to the sides
and people are forced to cross through this many times.
All the meeting rooms, you see all those glass walled things
up there?
Those are the meeting rooms.
You can stand in the middle and kind of see,
oh, there's where that guy is.
Oh, look, there's a vacant meeting room.
You can see all that stuff.
It's very, very much designed.
Interestingly, Steve Jobs was very, very involved
in the design of this particular space.
We've tried to take a very similar approach in our space,
trying to have things be very, very open.
You know, we don't have 1,500 people like Pixar does.
We have about 100.
But we are big fans of open plan.
And so you can see there's most of the folks kind of
working down there.
The way groups are organized is by project.
We move desks around all the time.
Anytime there's new projects, we get desks
so people can get together.
And you'd think we would maybe organize them
by those kind of islands that you see,
but they're really organized by canals, okay?
So people with back-to-back are the ones
working on projects together because
someone could say, hey, can you take a look at this?
And they can just turn around and take a look.
It's very different than, oh, can you walk all the way around
the island and come and see us?
It's just a small design thing, but it makes a big difference.
Okay, so office space is really important.
There's so, there's a, that's, that's,
I could talk about that for, for days and days.
But let's talk about other things.
Another really important flow management tool is ritual.
And our most common ritual is meetings, right?
And people mostly don't feel great about meetings,
because there's a lot of bad meetings, because no one
bothers to design them.
Well-designed meetings are awesome.
You go in, you get stuff done.
It was like, oh, that really helped me.
You come out thinking, man, now I know what's going on.
That really helped me.
Now I can work with more confidence.
I know exactly what's going on.
Badly designed meetings are awesome.
I don't know, the ninth level of hell.
They're really, really bad.
And there's a lot of ways to design meetings.
People who do, actually, hands up, people who do Agile.
I'm curious.
Look at this.
There's a lot of Agile here.
And there's a lot of people like, I don't do Agile.
Maybe I should.
I don't know.
Or I hate Agile.
It's stupid jerks.
You know, it's a lot of things.
But anyway, one of the key elements of Agile
is the notion of the Scrum meeting.
And this is very, very much a designed meeting.
The idea is it's very short.
You're talking about a very small number of things.
And often, part of the design is people say,
this is a standing meeting.
There'll be no sitting down in this meeting
because we want to get this done and get back to work
and not turn this into a waste of time.
And so that's cool.
Look at these happy people having their scrum meeting
right here.
And you know why they're happy?
Because they're out of those horrible cubicles
that they're in.
Look at those.
Those are like the worst of both worlds
when it comes to cubicles, right?
Because look at the height of those.
You go back and sit in that.
Do you have noise protection?
Are you like, I'm in my isolated pod?
No.
There's all the potential noise of the studio is there.
Can you see where anyone is or what anyone is doing?
No.
Even if you stand up, you can't.
You've got to peek up over the wall.
So it's like this illusion of, I have a big important office,
but with all the horrible aspects of that.
I am not a fan of the six foot high cube wall.
OK, so talking more broadly about Agile.
Agile is really just a system of coordinating and organizing
information flow.
right?
You've got your product backlog.
These are all the things that we would
like to put into the game.
And then you organize sprints, these little two, three, four
week sessions where you have a very specific goal.
Everyone knows the goal.
You've communicated the goal clearly.
We're going to deliver this at the end of 30 days.
And then once a day, you have your Scrum meeting
where what did you do yesterday?
What did you do today?
What problems are you having?
OK, good.
Let's get back to work.
And let's change it.
so that we know what we're doing.
And that's all very much about organizing information flow
about what we're doing so that you can optimize continually
on the project.
Fred Brooks, author of the Mythical Man-Month,
you know, he was looking at how bad software projects tend to go
and someone was saying,
look, I don't understand you software people.
You said it was going to be out by this date
and you were a year late.
I can understand somebody being two days late
or a week late, a year late.
How are you a year late for something?
Yeah, don't worry, honey, I'll meet you at 5 o'clock.
Oh, sorry, I'm a year late.
Right?
And his answer is, you get a year late one day at a time.
That is how you do it.
And so the idea is to do this sort of daily management so
that you can steer the project, get the right information to
the right people.
and steer your project.
OK, so Agile is really a system of information flow.
So another popular thing, popular with some people,
less popular with others, is the notion of 360 feedback.
People tend to dread feedback reviews at work.
Most of the time, the people giving the reviews
don't know what they're doing because they're not
experts in this.
It's super awkward.
You're having this awkward conversation
about what you're good at and what you're bad at.
And like, do I trust this guy?
And is this guy going to believe me?
Often this is because it's badly designed.
Well-designed 360 feedback is an opportunity
to collect feedback from all the people
that somebody works with and get all the information
that maybe they say to each other, but maybe they don't,
because it's really awkward.
Like, dude, your BO is killing me, right?
That is not a conversation that two employees will often have.
But sometimes it's the sort of thing that will come out in anonymous 360 feedback.
If it's anonymous, and you can guarantee the information is not going to go,
it will often go up to one of the managers who can kind of have this conversation.
Which makes it essential that the people who are giving these reviews
know how to do them well and understand how to do it tactfully and usefully.
If a good manager collects the information from a bunch of people, processes it,
so that they figure out, okay, these are the useful things I want to pass on and discuss
and hear this person's feedback about,
and it becomes a conversation. And if you do this right, people don't dread
the reviews. They get useful information that helps them,
and it can be very, very positive, but you have to take it
seriously. One thing we recently did, because we realized...
you know it's tough to fit these in your like i want to focus on the game i don't
want to focus on filling out forms and
and um... and i sit down having uncomfortable conversations
c ten to put it off
and we've been doing that
and that really sends this message that
if you put this off it must not be important
but it's super important this is all about
making everybody the best person they can be
so we've rescheduled it now instead of doing all once a year or uh... once every
uh...
uh... six months
We spread them out so they fit into people's schedules
so that they're not an intrusion.
And that's made it much more comfortable.
And again, it helps send the signal that, look,
this is important to us.
We make time for this.
So there are many, many types of meetings.
Any kind of meeting that you have
is a sort of ritual that your company has.
And you want to design that so it's good.
Some of those are short and daily.
Many of them are weekly.
Some of them you do every, like, four times a year.
And then there's some you do annually.
One that we do that was worked out really well for us
is this notion of Jam Week.
We stop everything that the studio is doing once a year,
and we say, you know what?
Let's have people work on projects
that they are excited about,
that they think might be good to go somewhere.
You know, just something good could come with this.
Either my personal development, or maybe just something
that would be really good for the studio.
Now, is this an information flow management situation?
It totally is.
People have ideas for things that they'd like to do,
and it's blocked because it's not
part of their regular daily project.
This creates an opportunity for like, hey,
that cool idea bouncing around in your head.
We're making time.
It's important to us.
We're making time for it to come out and for you to experiment
and connect with other people.
And good things come of it.
Last year, one of ours was this Enemy Mind game that came out.
And everybody liked it so much, after a one-week prototype,
they were like, let's turn this into a real project.
And it got a Best in Play award last year at GDC.
And one of the ones we did this year
is this Orion Trail game, which we currently
have in Kickstarter.
And it's in its final week, so please back it.
I think we're going to make it, but it's a little close.
So anyway, if you could back that, that would be great.
Anyway, but it's exciting.
I mean, people get really energized
when the things they're excited about come to light.
And you have to make channels for that to happen.
But there's lots of other rituals.
There's this great story I read about on the Harvard Business
Review I just love.
This company where
They didn't have a modern coffee pot.
They had this clanky, old, percolator coffee pot.
Only two people in the office knew how to operate it properly
and not get grounds in all the coffee.
And so when they would make coffee, they would get the coffee going and they'd say,
you know, hey everybody, coffee's ready.
And everybody would come for coffee and everyone would hang out in the kitchen,
chatting and stuff, and a lot of useful information was flowing around.
And the guy who was the head of the studio, he's like, yeah, no, that's great.
Look at this.
This is so cool.
I love our little coffee times and everybody's talking.
This is cool. This is cool and good and useful.
But jeez, I feel terrible that everyone's got this terrible coffee pot.
Right? So you know what I'm going to do, because coffee time is so important,
I'm going to get one of these fancy, modern, K-cup things.
That way you guys have awesome coffee, customized coffee,
just the coffee you want, any time you want,
one cup at a time, and coffee time went away.
And this really useful ritual that had been part of an information passing thing
in the studio went away, and it led to problems.
These things are super, super subtle.
And I know it's silly to kind of talk about things centering around food, but food is
super important to us as humans.
In our triune structure of the brain, the back part, the most basic part, is like very
interested in food and it has strong opinions about food, right?
Go into any college cafeteria, right?
You go into a college classroom and you look at like people sitting around and you're like,
wow, look at this international mix of people.
And then you go to the cafeteria and look at the segregation
that happens in the cafeteria.
Because there's something in us that's like,
I want to eat with people like me,
because those other people might take my food.
And then further, it goes the other way.
It goes the other way.
If you eat a meal with someone you haven't eaten a meal with
before, your brain's like, that dude didn't take my food.
I can trust that guy on a kind of a deep, fundamental level.
So a lot of studios, they do a thing where, we're so cool, man.
We got free lunches every day.
We got an omelet chef who comes at 3 o'clock every day.
And you never have to leave the studio.
Isn't that great?
No, that's not great.
Never leave the studio.
It means you're kind of stuck in the same rut all the time.
And what do you do?
You go in, you're the omelet chef.
You get your omelet.
You go back to your desk.
There's no conversation, right?
So I don't like to do that.
We do that a little bit, a little free food once in a while.
But like every day?
Because what you want is you want people to get together and go out of the studio,
because that changes their point of view, and you want them to kind of bond up in social situations.
The hunting party, man, that's an old fundamental notion.
And you see it.
Someone's like, hey, you guys want to get frozen yogurt?
I'm like, oh, OK, yeah, let's all go.
And they're going.
And you see that walk.
There's that walk they're doing.
They're just going down to hunt down to host
his Twinkie or whatever.
But still, you see it.
And there's a sort of bonding that happens around it.
And that happens.
And a lot of useful conversation happens there.
So when you give out free food at a studio,
you're often blocking really useful information flow.
Also, I'm very cheap.
OK.
So another flow management tool is just social factors.
So much about information is about who likes who and who
likes talking to whom.
Look at this team.
That looks like a team that is going to
communicate pretty well.
You can tell just by kind of looking.
Like, these guys are very, very comfortable with each other.
They're going to be, it's going to be easy for them to share information with each other.
So now there's been a lot of research about this.
Some of the most interesting, I think, is this research by Dr. Anita Woolley.
And it's all about the notion of collective intelligence.
We've had intelligence tests for years and years and years.
We understand about measuring individual intelligence.
Her question was, what about the intelligence of a group?
How does that work?
Now, a lot of people would say, well, that's easy.
You just take the IQs of everybody in the group
and you average it?
No, you take the maximum?
No, you take the min?
I don't know.
What do you do?
And she found it has nothing to do with that.
The intelligence of the people in the group
individually doesn't matter very much
in terms of the collective intelligence of the group.
Her studies found that there were exactly three factors.
that were critical when it came to the intelligent behavior
of a group.
And she did this by giving groups these different tests.
So here are the three factors she found were really relevant.
The first one is, how do people perform on the eyes test?
Okay? So the eyes test is this interesting test
where you see a lot of pictures like this.
Right? How is she feeling right now?
A, B, C, or D?
So think about that.
See if you got the answer.
All right?
All right. All right. Hands up for A. Hands up for B. Hands up for C. Hands up for D.
Okay. The correct answer is A. Okay.
All right, you can go, Harley.
Anyway, groups that had people who performed really well
on this test, because some people are great at it,
and some people are really bad at it.
Groups who had people who were really good at this
ended up being more intelligent.
Second one, conversational turn-taking.
They measured the amount of times
that people interrupted each other.
Groups that interrupted each other a lot
behaved really stupidly.
Groups that let each other talk, let each other finish,
and had a good balance of conversational turn taking,
they behave very intelligently.
And number three, get ready.
Boom goes the dynamite.
More ladies in the group made it behave smarter.
Now, so, and groups with no ladies, they had certain pathologies that were really, really
bad. And I'm sure some of us have seen this, right? You got a group of dudes all together,
and they're like, we should put in nine features. No, let's put in ten. No, let's put in eleven.
That's awesome, let's do it, right? And then that's how you get a year late, right? That's
totally how that happens.
But there's something that happens.
It's not that if there's a woman in the group,
it's not that the woman comes in and says, no, everybody, stop.
Everybody behaves different.
Again, the back of the brain behaves a little different.
The male brain behaves a little different
when the ladies are around.
It's like, let's put 9, no, 10.
No, actually, maybe we shouldn't be so dangerous all the time.
Maybe we should actually play a little safer.
So there's something in that.
Now, I got together with Dr. Woolley
because I'm like, OK, Dr. Woolley,
I've seen a lot of student teams, a lot, like thousands.
And.
I've seen certain pathologies with all male groups,
and I see certain pathologies with all female groups.
I've seen some all female groups do some really nutty things that
are really, really different.
And she said, yeah, you know, honestly,
we didn't test the all female case.
And she's like, I'm working on it now.
But she's like, yeah, I see the same thing,
that when there's a mix is when it's best.
And so that's really interesting to know
and interesting to think about.
Exactly why is a little unclear, but it's
a thing to think about.
And given the game industry isn't very well balanced
this way, it's something important to consider.
OK, so we got all those things.
Those are some tools you can use.
So now let's talk about what blocks information,
because there's a lot of things that can block information
flow in your studio.
A lot of times, oh, man, it's too much trouble.
Yeah, I was going to tell them, but I'm busy,
and I'm just not going to do that.
Another time, oh, man, I didn't know.
Oh my god, you guys are building like a vector-based calculation
system.
I didn't know we've got one.
It's already done.
Oh, I could have saved you three months of work,
but I just didn't know that you needed it.
Another one is noise.
Now, of course, there's lots of kinds of noise.
There's a lot of kinds.
There's certainly the noise in your head.
You're worried about some personal problem,
or oh my god, oh my god, I'm going to get fired, whatever.
Noise in your head is not going to help you.
So you want to find ways to reduce the noise in your head.
There's actual noise in the office.
That can block information flow.
Anyone who's ever been to a party at the minute gallery
knows about that.
Hey, man, I haven't seen you for a year.
And then DJ Earbud comes on.
Doot-de-doot-de-doot.
for an hour, and you're like, oh, anyway.
So that doesn't usually happen in the office.
But sometimes, you know, offices can be really noisy.
In our place, we put up sound padding around
because there was echo that was a little irritating.
We put the sound padding, and it was better.
The communication was a little clearer.
But then there's other ones, interruptions.
People come in and bug in you all the time.
A lot of places have developed kind of an informal code
of, hey, if I've got headphones on, don't bother me.
I'm busy right now, right?
Another one is lying.
Lying is a kind of noise on information.
Someone's delivering information,
but it's not the right information.
It's all noised up.
And one that we get a lot, noise from the publisher.
You're trying to make your game, and the publisher comes in
with some weird thing.
And really?
That's not a good.
And it kind of noises up a lot of your information.
There's a lot of meddling that publishers do.
and people get frustrated about that, but Stephen Beeman explained this with the Beeman's
Meddling Matrix. So let's talk about this. It's very important to understand the reasons,
the good, excellent reasons that there is so much meddling from a publisher. So let's
look at these axes. Okay, let's look at projects. Some projects succeed, some projects fail.
Some projects have a lot of meddling from the publisher.
Some projects have no meddling from the publisher.
OK, so let's look at these four different axes.
Think about this from the producer
at the publisher's point of view.
This is the guy who's got to oversee
this stupid group of game developers
that we hired to do this, and they're so crazy,
and what are we going to do?
So this guy's got to decide, how much
am I going to meddle on this project,
because I want it to succeed?
What's the right amount of meddling?
Well, let's look at this case.
So let's say it's a really successful project,
and the guy meddles a lot.
His conclusion will be, my meddling worked.
That was excellent.
OK.
So then let's look at this case.
He doesn't meddle, and it succeeds.
Then he's going to be like, oh my god, I'm useless.
If anybody finds out how little I was involved
in this massive hit, it would be bad.
So man, that would be bad if that happened.
So that's incentive to kind of get in there
and meddle if the thing's going to be successful.
Now let's look at this one, a failed project
where the publisher was super hands off.
That guy's going to get so beat up by his bosses.
Like, this thing failed.
What'd you do?
Well, I wanted to let them go their own way.
And oh my god, they're going to get fired.
It's really bad.
And then we have this last quadrant that we see quite a
lot, projects where it failed and there was a lot of meddling
from the publisher.
And then what do they say?
I did all I could.
I couldn't have possibly done more.
I was in there every day.
I was in there for two hours every day talking to the team,
and they still failed.
I don't know.
I gave them so much direction, and I micromanaged all the hell
out of it, and it still failed.
What more could I have done?
I don't know.
So like.
It's easy to joke about this and stuff, but you can kind of
understand that there are incentives to kind of get in
there and kind of be involved in the communication, which
makes it super important, if you're working with a
publisher, if you're working with a client, to design the
information flow so that they have what they need, so that
they feel confident, so they feel like they're doing the
best they can to make it really excellent.
Okay, other things that block information flow.
Mental ruts.
I've always been doing this the same way,
and I don't really want to change it,
and so I'm gonna ignore this new information.
Secrets.
Shh, don't tell anybody.
You can't tell anybody this.
That's what secret is, an information flow blocker.
and then fear all man
fear there's so many kinds of fear in the office all man they're all over the
place right
people never do and fears the mind killer yes
all right so many times all my god that the boss of the really
mad if i if he finds out about this to keep it a secret
also his feelings of the hurt if you tell her
how much
her art
socks
rights of don't don't tell her that
if i if i tell people i really feel about this project of a laugh at me
Man, I might make a mistake and everyone would find out.
Oh, don't tell the client.
They'll be so disappointed if they find out.
Just keep it quiet and hope it gets better.
Man, I could lose respect to the team if I tell them.
you know, I really blew this and I don't want people to know, so I'll keep that a secret.
And then the one in everybody's heart.
Everyone will know that I'm a fraud if I tell them how I really feel about this.
Okay, so that's fear is an information blocker and you've got to be aware of it in yourself,
you've got to be aware of it in other people,
and you've got to find ways to reduce that fear so that it's okay to share the truth.
You want to create opportunities for the truth
to go through.
I've found as my studio's gotten bigger,
it's been super hard for me, because truth to power
is really, really hard.
The bigger you are and the higher you are up the ladder,
the less people want to tell you the truth,
because they're scared of getting fired,
or you being mad, or whatever.
So you have to work really hard to find ways
to make sure people are comfortable
and getting the information out.
So related to this, fascinating research
by Casciaro and Lobo here.
Okay, they're looking at what makes people succeed in companies.
Okay, so here's the thing we often think about.
The relationship about competence, we all know about that.
We all know about some people are good at what they do.
Some people are bad at what they do.
Then they were looking at the question of how important is likability in the office?
Because we all know people who are really great at what they
do, but everybody hates them.
So where do you want to be on this chart?
Obviously, you want to be up here.
You're highly competent.
Everybody likes you.
Everybody wants to hire that guy.
That's obviously where you want to be.
Where don't you want to be?
Down here at the bottom.
Incompetent jerk.
Guy sucks at what he does, and what a jerk.
Oh my god, I can't stand him.
That's obvious.
These guys didn't study that.
These guys studied the other two boxes.
Hmm.
So the question they asked was, hey, managers,
if you had to hire one of the other two boxes,
who would you hire?
Would you hire the competent jerk, great at what they do,
I want to wring his neck every single day, hate that guy?
Or would you hire the lovable fool?
Right?
Not very good at what they do, pretty bad at what they do,
but everybody loves that guy.
Everybody, oh, it's fun to have around, so nice,
everybody likes him.
I feel really comfortable around them.
They found that generally, managers, if you ask them,
who would you hire?
They'd say, well, given that choice,
I'd hire the competent jerk.
Because he might be a jerk, but he'll get the job done.
But if you ask people, hey, who do you want to work with?
People would say, if I had to make that choice,
I'd pick the lovable fool.
Because yeah, they're not great at what they do,
but at least they're not going to screw everything up
for everybody else.
At least they'll do very little damage.
So that's interesting.
Then they looked at, OK, let's do a profile of a bunch of
companies and figure out which side they favored.
Do they favor competent jerks or lovable fools?
And then given that, how does that relate to the success of
the company?
And they found that successful companies favored the lovable
fool.
Now that's really weird.
Successful companies favored incompetence.
right? It's weird to think about. So they thought, this is really strange. Why is this
the case? And what they found was, the...
Competent jerks we know are a problem.
Because yeah, they're good at what they do,
but they wreck everything for everything else.
They block information for lots of people.
They keep secrets.
They make other people want to keep secrets.
You always hear people say,
oh man, I hate big companies.
So much politics.
There's politics.
What does politics mean?
What politics means is,
I have something that I want to tell somebody,
and I feel like I can't,
so I tell somebody else.
That's it.
That's all politics is.
Anytime that happens in your organization, you have politics.
If you can remove that,
then you have no politics in your organization.
Jerks make for a lot of politics.
Now, on the other side, this lovable fool character,
like, they don't mess things up.
Everybody likes having them around.
They might not be good at what they do.
And here's the thing.
Somebody's got a problem.
They're all pissed off about something.
Oh, man, that Benson.
God, I hate that guy.
Who are they going to tell?
The lovable fool is like super likable.
People you like, you tell them stuff.
You can trust them.
And you're like, man, that Benz guy, he's pissed me off so much.
And guess what?
This person's got a lot of time.
Right?
And part of what makes them so likable is they care about what's going on.
They're like, oh, really?
What's up with Benson?
Oh, man, he's in this meeting.
He said this.
Oh, geez, that's terrible.
I'm so sorry.
I'm sorry that happened.
And then it bothers them.
And then they go.
And they try and work it out a little bit.
They might go and talk to Benson.
Dude, do you know what people are saying about you?
Or maybe they'll go talk to Benson's boss and say, man, a lot of people are really unhappy
with this guy.
I'm not trying to be a jerk.
And what happens is all this blocked up emotional information flows through them
and gets to where it needs to be and makes everything better.
And you know what happens over time?
Because everybody likes the lovable fool and they're always helping him,
they often get better and better and better,
and they move up to the lovable star category
because people get better at what they do.
The competent jerk, is he going to get more likable over time?
No way.
No way, that doesn't happen.
So talking about jerks, I found this interesting book,
Never Check Email in the Morning,
some interesting business advice,
but it had this statement that blew me away.
There are exactly six kinds of jerks.
I'm like, no way, I could name 150 right now, right?
But I went through their list and I went through my list
and I'm like, goddamn, if they hadn't had all my 150 jerks
like sorted into six categories.
And the thing that blew my mind was, of these six kinds of
jerks, of these six kind of jerks, they were all
information blockers in different ways.
The inaccessible jerk.
Oh, I can never get a meeting with that guy.
He has what I need.
And I just, oh, I can never get through to this guy.
He doesn't answer his emails.
Damn it, that guy.
Unreliable.
When are you going to have that done?
Oh, I'll have it done.
I don't know, Wednesday.
Near Wednesday.
Hey, is it done?
Oh, no, no, no, sorry.
Sorry, it's just not.
Oh, you're killing you because they're unreliable.
Someone who's too rigid.
They're like, nope, this is the only way I do it.
You're like, but Bill, it's killing the project, man.
It's killing it.
And they're ignoring information.
Someone who's disrespectful.
You're worried they're going to spread bad information about
you, about other people.
And you're worried things are going to get
twisted and noised up.
Vagueness.
You know, when's that going to be done?
I don't know, when it's kind of done.
Oh, that's not even information.
Like, you're pretending it is and it's not.
And then the unfair jerk.
You're worried, man, this guy doesn't treat people fairly.
If I tell him the truth, he's going to use it against me.
I've got to block it and keep it secret.
Anyway, so that's interesting to think about.
So looking at this.
Remember, our facts, opinions, and emotions about projects,
processes, and people.
So we have an org chart.
That's one of our tools.
And what does that tool do?
It manages facts and opinions about processes and people.
OK, makes sense.
And then we have our project hierarchy,
like how we manage individual projects.
That's about facts and opinions about projects.
That covers things pretty well, except emotions
are left out in the cold.
And if you look at the
The Castellaro and Lobo research, they use this phrase
affective hubs.
That means people you like who spread useful information
through the studio.
In other words, they're like the emotional router for your
studio, right?
These people are really important because what they do
is they route emotional information, some of the most
important information, about projects, processes, and
people.
If you manage not just one org chart, but three of these,
and you consciously think about these,
it makes a giant difference in your studio.
I once had a team that was having a lot of problems.
And I realized, man, it's not that they're like a skill.
People are a little rigid.
They weren't always great communicators.
And a resume crossed my desk for somebody
who was very inexperienced, but like.
It was super likable.
Someone had a reference.
And I'm like, you know what?
Let's try that.
Everything changed.
This person with very little skill comes on the team, but
all of a sudden, all the bad toxins came out of the team,
and everything got better.
OK, a few more final tips here.
I love this book, The Advantage, by Patrick Lencioni.
His argument is that your biggest advantage in business
is a healthy organization.
And what does healthy mean?
He's basically saying an organization
with healthy information flow.
And he gives a lot of tips for how to make that happen.
Some of his best ones are, if you're running a studio,
you have to decide what is important.
let people know about it and not just let them know you need to over communicate it
i love the phrase over communicate
because uh... it just means i'm gonna tell you a lot of times more than is
necessary because i tell you more than is necessary improves the chance it's
gonna get through
we don't like to repeat ourselves
uh... we don't like to repeat ourselves we don't
like to be ourselves
But things that are important should be over communicated.
Things like a mission statement.
Oh man, that's so corporate and bad.
No, it's not.
It is the reason you are doing what you are doing.
If you don't know what it is, then what are you doing?
You're just wandering around.
And if you haven't figured it out and clearly communicated
it, no one else really knows what you guys are doing,
either.
Because this is a weird thing to say.
People don't just want a job.
People want a religion.
right? They want to come to work and be like, damn, what I'm doing is important.
It is important and I know why. And if you run a studio,
it is your job to make people know and feel that and understand about that.
Now, there's lots of other ways of over-communicating things, too.
Steve Jobs was very famous for this, right?
How did Steve feel about the new prototype?
Everyone knew.
It was no secret how Steve felt, right?
And he wanted things to be excellent.
And he wasn't like, oh, yeah, this is excellent.
This is really bad.
This is kind of in the middle.
Nope.
In order to communicate that, only excellent
was acceptable in his vocabulary.
When he would evaluate your work, it was either excellent and amazing or it was total shit.
Right? Now, I thought about that a lot when I read that.
I'm like, man, am I really going to run around the studio telling everybody whose work is kind
of at the B plus level that it's total shit?
No, I'm not going to do that because that's just nasty and rude.
Right? I just, I can't live that way.
There's too much bad news.
But there is a word you can use.
And so I will give you my very, very useful magic word, unacceptable.
Right?
Unacceptable is an objective word that is very, very clear.
I see what you're doing, and it has its benefits.
But man, this thing has to be perfect.
So currently, this is not acceptable.
This is unacceptable.
We need to get this better.
You can talk about that in a very clear way.
Another tip, an excellent book.
Anybody who has a brain and a mouth or ears
should read this book.
It's all about how to deal with difficult conversations.
Because difficult conversations are massive information
blockers.
There's awkward things that you want to say,
but you don't want to say.
This book is all about how to do it.
And the key is that it's listening.
There's something you're really pissed at a guy about.
And the key is not to go in and say,
I'm going to tell you this and this and this and this.
The key is to say, listen, I feel this way about it.
And.
and I want to understand your point of view.
And then get as much listening as possible.
And they give a ton of good tips in there.
And if you want to practice listening, oh, my God,
there's this website, 7CupsOfTea.
Here's the idea of 7CupsOfTea.
The internet is full of people who
are full of strife and trouble.
And they can go here, and trained listeners will just
listen to their problems.
and talk with them about it.
They don't give advice.
They listen.
And you can go on there and take a 10-minute video training
course about how to become a listener,
and you can start doing it today.
And oh my god, it totally works.
It's crazy.
It's crazy how this little 10-minute video can make you
into a much better listener.
OK, so wrapping up, here's one other book
some people may have heard of.
Matthew 7-7, Seek and Ye Shall Find.
People always say, oh my god, you
can't get a studio past a certain point.
We're going to hit these problems.
The thing that is true, any problem that you have
organizational in your studio, if you want to solve it
and you're focused on solving it, you can solve it.
They're all solvable.
There are organizations that have 10,000, 100,000 people.
These problems are solvable.
But if you say, I'm not going to worry about this.
I'll let it take care of itself, that's
when you get in trouble.
But if you look for the solutions, you will find them.
But you do have to look for them.
OK, so studios with good information flow, they say,
I know how to structure management.
I know how to manage my project.
We know I don't have miscommunications with clients
because we have the right information flow.
We have the right meetings.
Those meetings we have are good and useful.
Our team has good morale because everybody feels good
about what they're doing.
Our game is on time, yes.
And our game rocks, yes.
Those are all things that you want.
So I'll close up with this quote I love from John Lurie here.
He's a Zen master.
If the energy is really flowing freely,
the brush paints by itself, the camera photographs,
the sculpture forms, the words write, the dance dances.
The creator of the art, the subject of the art,
and the expression itself merge into a single process
in which there is no reflection or evaluation,
just the art manifesting itself.
When you have solid information flow,
that's what the creative process feels like in a group.
Thanks very much.