Hi.
I wasn't expecting feedback, thanks.
That's the talk, everyone, we're done.
Okay.
Welcome to Embracing the Co-op Studio Model in Indie Games,
featuring us.
We have a different slide, there you go.
Today we're going to just talk about worker cooperatives.
Show of hands, how many people know what a worker cooperative is?
That is way more than I thought, so that's great.
At the start of this, we're going to, the format of this, we're going to give you a
really very, very, very basic 101 on just what co-ops are, and then we're going to each
share our experiences of how our co-ops came to be, how they're set up.
kind of the ups and downs of that,
and then we're gonna do some Q&A at the end.
But at the beginning of this,
we're just gonna dash through some really quick,
like the elevator pitch of what a co-op is.
So what is a worker cooperative?
There's a lot of different aspects to them,
but if you wanted to boil them way down
to some very like core shared ideas,
it's a business that's owned, operated,
and controlled democratically by its workers
who share in the profits of their labor.
You can already see how that's very different
than probably a lot of the places you've worked.
These are businesses where decisions, all decisions are made democratically.
People discuss their salaries and work these things out together.
There is, you share in the profits of your labor, meaning that there's not
some, like, there's not someone like way over your head that's sucking up kind
of all the surplus value leftover from your labor, you know, after you get paid.
a lot of that money that you make goes up the chain.
And worker cooperatives, everyone is sharing in that
and discussing kind of democratically how that's working,
how those things are distributed,
which leads to a lot of co-ops
having very egalitarian pay structures.
and revenue share and that kind of thing.
There's a lot of ways of organizing worker cooperatives
from very, like everyone just sits around a table
and like talks.
Some larger ones have more,
a structure where there are managers of certain,
you know, there's like boards of directors and stuff
that are elected by the workers involved.
But it comes down to an idea of one person, one vote.
So it's not like your art lead has five votes
and someone working on like environment art has like one.
or something when it comes to these larger decisions.
So it's just kind of this democratic sort of setup.
And I think Bethany's gonna tell us
a little bit about the history.
All right, so cooperative societies have always existed.
It's basically just a group of folks working together
to get through life.
But worker co-ops as we recognize them
started more during the Industrial Revolution.
It's mainly just started by workers
who are trying to protect themselves,
either physically from unsafe working conditions.
their actual jobs, their skilled craftsmen,
they're just worried about the new machines coming in
and them being replaced with unskilled laborers.
And just your livelihoods, wages going down,
and you're not able to afford rents or basic necessities.
This was around the time when there was a,
you could start to see the vast inequality
between the bosses and workers,
and all of that exploitation that was happening.
So they were just coming up with new.
techniques to try to get together and survive.
And yeah, over the next couple centuries,
they grew and expanded all over the world.
They kind of are just empower workers
to democratically own and run their own workplaces.
Usually, they have a focus on serving their local communities
because kind of what regular companies can or won't do.
Yeah, and then often during times of large scale crises of labor and economics, there's
kind of another burst of co-ops that kind of come up.
And I think like today, that's what we're currently witnessing, like a growing wave
of like worker organization, unionization, kind of more interest in starting co-ops.
And this panel is kind of part of that.
So yeah, we're kind of in a spot.
I should probably get up on the mic before I start talking.
We're kind of in a spot right now.
Just even the fact that this panel is happening
is kind of because we're in part of this moment, right?
Where there's more unionization,
there's more organization kind of happening
because we're in kind of a difficult time
in a lot of ways.
So that's cool.
It's cool to be here in this room
and be like, oh, we're in one of those.
One of those moments right now.
Okay, so I talked a little bit about,
I alluded a bit to how co-op structures
are a little different than your structures
you may be used to in other kinds of businesses.
Now, I've created two slides,
and they're pretty complicated,
because business is complicated.
So just bear with me, we're gonna get through it.
There's a lot of moving parts of this, okay?
Okay.
So.
I know there's multiple circles on there,
so I'll try to walk you through it.
This is a very, very, very basic breakdown of how this would work.
Now a boss could be a whole team of bosses, it could be shareholders, it's all these people
up here who are making these decisions, right?
And then there's workers kind of below.
And your company could be really cool.
You could be like, oh yeah, but like my boss,
we get together and talk things out.
And they take a lot of our opinions on board.
We like to think of ourselves as a family and a community
and all that kind of stuff.
However, at the end of the day,
your boss has that power, right?
Like there are people that are not you
and not like you don't have...
very much say in what your schedule is, how much you're paid, that kind of thing usually.
The expectations are not being set by the workers.
The expectations are being set by someone else.
And what worker co-ops do is kind of upend that entire thing
where there aren't bosses anymore.
Or rather, everyone's a boss, or everyone's not a boss.
That whole distinction kind of fades away.
There are still people who do things
like the administrative tasks that you would associate
with someone who's kind of at the top.
of a company.
Like, there are tasks that still need to get done, but they're getting done by every, you
know, by your fellow worker as opposed to your boss.
You make decisions about hours, deadlines, salaries, all kinds of just things.
And it does, and we'll probably all talk about this a little bit in our own way, it changes
the dynamic of how you work together.
in a way beyond, because like I said, a lot of companies,
particularly a lot of companies in the games industry,
are like, but we're just a big family here,
we all just have so much passion, and we're working together
and that's great, why not a structure
that actually makes you, you know,
so, you know, a community where you are working together.
and not just saying that in that sort of way.
So why go work a cooperative if you're kind of starting
a studio or you already are one and you maybe want
to migrate into doing that?
There's shared control and ownership of the workplace
and the products of your labor,
and that's kind of a big thing.
There's not like one rockstar developer at the top of it.
no pun intended, who is getting a lot of the credit for it,
necessarily.
You can actually, as a group of people, go like, yeah,
we did this.
We all share in this success in a way
that you just simply can't in a more standard, top-down
structure.
There's greater accountability and participation.
There's greater accountability because you
have to talk about stuff.
If you're making a decision in a healthy co-op that's running, you have to get together and
talk and you have to vote.
We vote in a Slack, we each have a little thumbs up button and stuff, or over Google
Chat or whatever.
You have to participate and you have that accountability for that reason in a way that
you simply don't.
in a more hierarchical top-down structure.
There's greater job security relative
to top-down businesses.
You are still dealing with selling games,
trying to make it through,
like this doesn't obviate all those problems or anything.
However, you are probably making decisions
that are based on you all trying to not.
have to lay yourselves off, basically.
Since all the workers are coming together
to make these decisions, you're less likely to be like,
okay, well, we're done with the game.
Half of you leave now, because you just kind of
can't necessarily easily do that,
which has its own ups and downs, but it's just different.
There's more equal share of profits,
because you are talking about that and negotiating that.
This kind of goes without saying.
Studies show that there's an increased quality of life
at work, and people are kind of more invested in it
because they feel like a sense of ownership.
They're not just working at a place.
They are part of a thing that they
are building and maintaining.
And there's a real sense of community
and kind of emotional support.
And a lot of these things, or that's often the case,
because you are getting together and making these.
collective decisions and sharing responsibilities and sharing the ups and downs of that kind
of amongst yourself.
And there's a last thing is you're not depending on the benevolence of an owner or an employer
for everything I just said, right?
Like, you know, you could have the coolest boss ever, but like they could go and get
like the rabies virus and 28 days later, like over the weekend, and then it doesn't matter
how cool your boss was on Friday, they're still your boss.
And you don't have to rely on just the whims of one person
or some people up here to make all these decisions
for how your workspace will be and what you put into it
and take out of it.
And there's a lot of, like I said,
there's a lot of conversation right now about unionization,
worker organization, all kinds of stuff.
And that's awesome.
And worker cooperators fit into this in different ways.
We're giving power and ownership directly to workers.
You know, unions exist to bring workers together
so that they can have a greater leverage
versus the bosses, right?
There's that kind of inherent sort of dynamic there.
Whereas in co-ops, we're just kind of I guess,
skipping to just not having bosses to begin with.
We kind of point to horizons beyond what we're told
to expect as workers.
I think a lot of people hear about all this,
you know, unions and everything, but co-ops,
and they're like, oh, like co-ops aren't new,
but they're new to a lot of people.
So it's just like, oh, we can make new things.
There might be better ways of doing this.
history hasn't ended.
And we can also stand in solidarity with other workers who are fighting for power.
Because we have an understanding of, yeah, we wanted to create less exploitative structures,
we can recognize and maybe stand in solidarity with other people who are trying to create.
less exploitative structures in their own industries.
And also, there are unionized co-ops,
there are co-ops that work with unions.
There's all kinds of interplays
with how these things work together,
which is pretty cool.
This is all just really exciting,
and these things exist a lot elsewhere.
In the US, this is like,
I guess saying this is like lost knowledge almost,
just because it was suppressed.
But it's building right now, and it's really exciting.
So we each come to our work as cooperatives
in very different ways.
We're all very different in how we're set up,
and with our different,
assumptions and how we run things and where we're from.
And it's just like any other kind of business.
And I think we're all going to share a little bit about that
right now, starting with Ted from PixelPushers.
I didn't do the introductions for everyone.
I'm really sorry.
I'm Scott from the Glory Society.
Yeah, that's me.
Hi, I'm Ted.
I'm from PixelPushersUnion512.
I'm Ian.
I'm from Tailspinners.
I'm Steve, I'm from Motion Twin, we made Dead Cells.
And I'm Bethany, I'm also from Glory Society.
Yeah. Alright, now Ted.
Alright.
So, as I said, I'm from Pixel Pushers Union 512,
and we are a worker-owned game development team.
I'm the artist on the staff and we are currently working on a game called Tonight We Riot.
So if you've heard of that, I'm the one who made all the pretty pixels.
Anyways, so I've been doing games for a long time.
I got hired real young into the industry and without naming names of places that I've been,
I've been doing it almost 20 years.
So I've seen...
you know, benefits go away, I've seen paid internships go away,
I've seen Crunch become something that was just kind
of like it happens occasionally to something that's actually
planned, which just blows my mind.
And so with all that in mind, after doing this for so long,
you know, I figured there's got to be a better way to do this,
you know, instead of looking for jobs every two to three years.
and kind of like what Scott said, being at the whims of either shareholders or, you know,
the top brass at any given studio.
it would be interesting to try something new.
And I've always been a big fan of history.
And so what Scott was talking about,
like the idea of a suppressed history in the United States,
I started looking into different ways of doing things.
And I ran across a group from roughly 100 years ago.
How many people here are familiar with the IWW,
the Wobblies?
Wow, that's really cool that I saw so many hands go up.
Well, I was watching a documentary about the Wobblies,
and it just struck a nerve.
I was watching it, and I was like, this is great.
The idea of workers owning the means of production, the idea
of working collaboratively in a democratic way to achieve
whatever your goals are.
And there was a line, it was a quote, that one of the workers
said when they were confronted by a group of hastily
deputized drunks, where they called out and they said, who
are your leaders?
And I said, we're all leaders here.
And I've always taken that to heart.
So at Pixel Pushers, we're all leaders.
And no one's in control of everything except for us.
And so when we vote on things, even though I'm the one who
kind of got the ball rolling, I get outvoted pretty
routinely, which is great.
It's very liberating.
So with that in mind, that's kind of what we
call shop democracy.
So inside our shop, we are democratic.
We vote on major things to do with the game and major things
to do with the team.
So we even voted on me being here today.
And I'm here.
So obviously that worked out.
But it's also good because even as a small team, especially
if you guys are indie devs out there and you've got your
small team, it's kind of good to start with best practices
going forward.
And we started talking about, OK, so if Tonight We Ride is
successful and we become self-propelled, how do we want
to handle things in the future?
Should we grow?
talking about democratic management, the idea of voting
your managers into position as a means to kind of separate
the idea of salary and management, and the idea of
separating management from workers would kind of go by
the wayside.
Because if you're just voting amongst yourselves in your
department, and there's no salary linking you to that
management position, you're probably going to be less
concerned with holding on to that power than you are of
being a good manager.
So if someone's not a good manager and they're not
comfortable with it even, it helps both sides.
So if someone wants to step down from management, they
totally can.
If they're not doing a good job, the
workers can vote them out.
Easy peasy.
So like I said, we're working on Tonight We Riot.
And I'm a big believer in the idea that the personal is the
political, that everything about our lives cannot be
separated from the context of the lives we live and the
lives of other people around us.
So with that in mind, I decided to make a game
that was about workers' liberation
and really use that as a means
to propel the ideas of our studio.
And it doesn't mean that like every game
we're ever gonna make is gonna be politically motivated,
but this one is kind of especially so.
But, you know, it's kind of like,
No matter what you're making, you're going to be making it
based on the experiences you've had, the upbringing
you've had, the place where you live, and the culture and
society you live in.
And so with that in mind, we really wanted to push those
ideas with our game.
And we also think that it's a better way to develop.
We have a lot of efficiency and flexibility.
There's no real taboos.
There's no worrying about whether or not your manager is
going to handle being questioned, or your boss is
going to deal with the idea of a subordinate.
you know, raising a hand in a meeting. Uh, everyone has a voice, but also everyone has
accountability too. So there's no one who's, you know, kind of a sacred cow at the, uh,
company that can't be questioned or, you know, that their word is law. Uh,
And also on top of that, it's lower development costs.
Now this changes from studio to studio, but with the way
that we work, our team, we all start with the same base
salary, and then depending on the game that you're working
on, everybody gets an equal share of the
profits from that game.
So no one's making a huge hand over fist amount over anybody
else in the studio.
And that works out quite well,
because you're not having to pay for a C-suite
of executives at the top of the company,
or making sure that a certain percentage of the profits
go to a group of shareholders.
It goes right back into the hands and pockets
of the people who actually made the game.
So, yeah, it kind of covers
a fair distribution of profits.
And oh, and there we go.
And that's pretty much it.
So I'm gonna lead on over to Motion Twim,
with Steven here.
Thanks all.
Thank you, that was cool.
So as I briefly mentioned earlier on,
I'm from Motion Twins.
We're based in France.
Motion Twins been around since 2001.
Functioning as a workers' cooperative since then.
Officially sort of legally set up as a workers' cooperative
a little bit after that.
And we made the game Dead Cells, which hopefully some of you
might have heard of.
So yeah, our logo is a red star.
As you can see, that's a little screenshot of our old website which was kind of steeped
in constructivism and very much that mentality.
So just a little bit of a disclosure, I'm going to be the black sheep of this talk.
I wanted to talk about some of the complications of running a workers' cooperative and some
of the hard parts about it.
being directly in confrontation or in discussion with your fellow man or woman at all times.
So, you know, Motion Twin is kind of like the classic start up story, you know, but with
communists. It was just a bunch of dudes making video games together and they were like, man,
this is awesome. We love making video games. And they started making money from it and
they were like, hmm, okay, well, we're going to have to pay taxes because, you know, the
government exists.
So we need a legal structure to handle that. So they set up a company and a standard corporation
in France comes with a whole bunch of implications in terms of how you actually distribute power.
Someone has to be a manager. There actually has to be someone who is legally responsible
in that person.
well, they have their heads on the line.
And so that comes with all kinds of complications.
However, in France, there's something cool called
the SCOP, Societe Cooperative d'Ouvrier de Production,
so basically a workers' cooperative in French.
And that actually allows you to have an official, recognized
by the state, legal structure that
sort of perpetuates the existence of this workers'
cooperative.
And so we went down that path.
Obviously when I say we, not me.
I was probably like 12 when they did that.
So it's managed to survive.
And I think there's a couple of reasons for that.
I think one of the major strong points over Scott
is that it really pushes the bar in terms of what we do.
So because everyone has the right
to have a say on absolutely everything,
me being like the marketing and business dude,
I can come and.
say to the game play programmer who's sitting around here somewhere
that what he just did sucks and that I think we should change it.
But that can be difficult in the sense that sometimes you can get, okay if there's
eight of us
you can have seven different opinions from every single one in the room all sort of saying
we think you should do this and you have to try and pick through all of that
noise and come up with a consensus. But it also definitely helps because
no one feels illegitimate in saying hey I'm not happy about this aspect of the
game
can we do something about that?
So some of the issues that we've sort of run into with the structure of the scope is that
there are peculiarities to the legal structure of the court.
which means that once money goes into the co-op it becomes the property of the co-op
and of the national union of co-ops. So it doesn't technically belong to the workers
in the co-op, it belongs to the workers in the co-op and all the potential future workers
in the co-op. So that actually makes it very difficult to put money aside because once
it goes in it stays in the company and if we take it out to spend it on a game it has
to come back.
If it doesn't come back, that can leave the workers in a sticky situation as to why did
you spend all this money and it then not come back for the future workers of the co-op.
If we keep making games that keep making money, that's not a problem, it's a cool thing because
it perpetuates the structure but it does also make us cautious about having a huge amount
of reserves.
Not all fun and games, limits to organizational efficiency.
I was really on my A game when I made that title up.
So at Motion Twin, there's zero hierarchy.
And there's three sort of fundamental pillars
that we talk about.
So it's equal pay, equal say, and equal work.
Apart from that, based on that, we're all entirely equal.
what that means is that probably we're limited in terms of how much we can grow. We will
probably always stay small. Maybe 7. It's kind of that Amazon discussion about feeding a team
off a pizza or something like that. Just because once you go past, you know, you go past 10, all
of a sudden you need to have much more rigorous internal structures about internal communication,
making sure that everyone is talking to each other. When there's 8 of us you can literally
shoot someone with a Nerf gun and say, what do you think about this?
And what it means is that you have to have probably a lot more rules and a lot more systems
than what you would have in a standard company, or at least a lot more tools that allow everybody
to have that accountability and to know that everyone else is doing the right thing.
So time, we track time quite carefully.
Generally not because people are slacking.
When you're an owner and a participant in your own company, there's lots of motivation
to work.
and the problem is that it goes too far and quite often you have people who are
coming in the office on the weekends just because they're like, man I'm so excited about
running my own company, this is awesome
and that starts to create a little bit of a culture of crunch and so sometimes you have to be like, dude
take a step back, go home
hang out with your family, play with your dog, do whatever you have to do but don't put
pressure on the rest of the team by working insane hours. Responsibility. My famous quip is
when, it's not mine, someone else said it, when it's the responsibility of everybody, it's
nobody's responsibility. You see that with the dishes, for example. The dishes never get done.
And when they do it's someone who grumpily goes in washes all the dishes and leaves an angry message on slack like why don't
You guys watch your dishes or something like that. So you got to make sure that you have tools in place
to take care of that for us. It's a little sign that says wash your dishes now and
Us regularly looking and making sure it's like it someone leave the dishes here so that it doesn't pile up
and that can be the dishes, that can also be dealing with administrative tasks that no one
wants to deal with like for example if we get audited by the tax man who has to go and sit with
the tax man while he goes through three years worth of accounts. Not me. Crunch again when it's
your company and you are responsible and you're also interested in absolutely making a game
of success then there's kind of like a mentality that happens where it's like okay we're going
to get this done, let's get this finished, we're about to ship.
And we don't, you know, there's nothing like the crunch that exists in the industry, but
it does happen and it's something that we have to be very vigilant about because it
can snowball and it can definitely lead to us all sort of feeling like at the end of
a project like, whoa, we need to take some time off.
The cool thing about being in a workers' cooperative is that you can just have a discussion
where we say, hey man, you guys tired?
Are we tired?
Let's have a take two weeks off and we can do that.
So that's great.
So fatigue as well, fatigue is a big one because when you have seven other people coming to
you and saying we're not happy with what you're doing or questioning your decisions particularly
like
Transcribed by https://otter.ai
I felt that particularly strongly when I first arrived because I was the only non-productive
member on the business and marketing team, the only person who sort of specialised in
that subject.
So I've got as many opinions going from people who don't care about that stuff and aren't
really specialised in it coming and telling me, we should be doing this, you know.
Okay, and so you have to defend that.
You can't just say, no, no, no, I'm in charge of this.
You have to defend your point of view and explain it rationally to everybody, which
takes a lot of time and can be tiring.
So we covered washing up. The other one that sucks is telling people that they're fired. Or
how you deal with what happens if something doesn't go right. So what does happen if it goes
pear shaped? I put the little survivor icon. If you've ever seen that television show, it's
awful. But it's a little bit like that because no one has the authority to fire anybody else.
So it's kind of like Game of Thrones mixed with Survivor. You have to democratically.
say okay we've decided the majority
that you are not pulling your weight or no longer fit into the team and you're
going to be out
and that
I can tell you from experience, is awful.
It stinks.
So some of the systems we put in place to avoid that kind
of situation, hiring.
When we're hiring people, it's kind of like getting married.
It's a super big commitment.
We generally have people do two consecutive six-month
temporary contracts.
So that gives us plenty of time to say, OK, this person
fits in, or this person doesn't fit in, before we
bring them in.
Most of the time you know in the first two months, you're like, yeah, these guys are
going to be a great fit.
Or sometimes you don't.
So we have to protect ourselves from that moment because getting rid of them is...
heart wrenching. So then questions about risk. So for example, dead cells, when I joined
the company I was brought on to help do a switch from web to mobile. We hadn't had a
successful web game in years. We tried mobile and didn't like it. It wasn't really what
we wanted to do. We didn't have any success on mobile. By the time dead cells came along
it was kind of like a last ditch effort. And when you're part of a co-op,
You can do all kinds of amazing things, but some things that are kind of also insane.
And we bet the farm and basically said, okay, well, we're going to make dead cells.
We're going to do something that we love doing and either we'll go out in a blaze of glory
or it'll work and we won.
So fortunately it worked.
We're all still here, which is cool.
But those kinds of decisions, managing risk can have a different sort of mentality when
everyone's like, well, you know, we're either going to do this or we're just going to go
do something else because this is what we love.
And if you're used to a traditional sort of business structure as I was when I came in, that sort of seems like it's insane.
And then inequality, like just individual difference and personal inequality.
Some people are leaders and loudmouths and want to get involved in everything.
And some people have direct confrontational styles for discussions that are going to sort of crush out the more introverted people.
So how do you create space so that everyone who is a different type of person can express themselves?
How do you give, how do you make sure that you can give responsibility to the people who won't put their hand right up and be like,
yeah, I'm going to do that, you know, and say, okay, well, you know, we noticed that you haven't been asking for these kind of roles.
Is there something going on? And we try and sort of organize around that.
But that takes time.
and it's a management of the people that you're working with and everyone is doing that at
all times.
So again, none of this is a reason not to do it.
It's awesome fun.
But it does come with a whole bunch of different dynamics that you just don't have in a standard
workplace.
So I'm going to hand it over right now.
Thank you. Hello, I'm Ian. I'm from Tailspinners. I'm based in the UK and was a bit surprised
to be asked to this because I hadn't realized how little US seems to know about co-ops because
we have really large scale co-ops like international, multinational corporations in the UK and across
Europe who work in this way. We are multinational. We have one guy in Toronto.
But yeah, so we're coming at this from quite a different angle because we're not a development studio.
Tailspinners are a writing studio, an outsourced writing studio.
We help everybody from indie to AAA, but mostly kind of indie to mid-level
with story for their game in whatever form that might be.
So we're a studio of people who all work together to do that, but that's not really what we are or what we were,
because we started as two freelancers who went...
Well, we seem to be visiting an awful lot of the same potential clients, why don't we
team up? And we thought about all of the reasons why that was a good thing and we adopted a
company name and a logo and we made a website and suddenly people started treating us differently
and the conversations that we had radically changed as individual freelancers.
They stopped asking us things like, are you available?
Because you're a company, and clearly, therefore, you are
always available.
And they stopped asking for things like writing tests in a
lot of cases, because we have a cool logo or something.
you can do the job. So it was very strange and that set us thinking about how the whole
thing holds together and about the gig economy and I'll talk about that in a little bit.
But it went very well, we expanded, we always had, we'd come up with a way to deal with
the fact that we might have too much work because everybody thinks we're available all
the time by having other freelancers to help us out kind of on call or for specific if
they had skills that we didn't have in-house.
And then we needed to grow and we thought about it and went well
Why did we get together in the first place? Well actually it was for mutual protection, right?
So maybe we could talk to some of our freelancers and see if they want to join and be part of this and that what
Happened so we've grown into a group of what are really freelancers
But a group of freelancers who will collaborate and cooperate and actually work together day to day
And this gave us a load of advantages, some of which we
thought about up front, some of which only really turned up
later on.
So these were our original reasons.
And these were kind of the pitch also that we gave to our
prospective freelancers to say, why don't you join us?
Creative support is a big one.
So if I'm writing something, I'm writing a bunch of
dialogue, and I could immediately then send that to
the client and say, hey, here's the dialogue.
What do you think?
But they haven't been trained in dialogue in any way.
The ability to pass it over to another of us internally and say,
can you just have a look at this?
Am I doing something insane here?
Have I got it all wrong in some way?
Do you think the client will like it?
You know, is it story wise, you're trained in story, does it hold up?
And they can do that for you.
And the brilliant thing is because we've signed an NDA as a company, we can talk
to anybody else in our company who has particular set of skills or whatever
it is about that piece of work.
So if one of us is much stronger in design and we've got a design issue and
that the person who's writing it is stronger in dialogue.
they can just pass it over.
If I'm banging my head against a brick wall
with a story problem,
I can call up anybody else in the company and say,
hey, here's my problem, can I explain this to you?
And as normally happens, when you start doing that,
you come up with a solution yourself.
But because they're under the same NDA, at least you can
talk to them about that.
So creative support is a huge thing.
Emotional and social support.
And I can't stress strongly enough how important the
emotional side of it is.
As an individual freelancer, you are on your own against
the world.
You have nobody to help you, possibly your partner at home
or something like that.
But it's a very lonely existence.
And you're dealing potentially with a string of clients.
And you might see them for a few months.
That's the social bit, right?
We're dealing with different people every day.
and you have no kind of ongoing conversations,
even about what movie did you see last night,
any of that sort of stuff.
And being able to be in a group with people
who can emotionally support you,
whether it's, I'm really struggling with this client,
can somebody help me out?
Whether it's, I'm writing a knee-jerk response
to this client, can somebody shut me down
before I press send?
Or any of those kinds of things.
It's so valuable to have other people just around you
and feel as, we've talked about family here before,
and feel like that family.
From an external point of view, there are huge advantages to being a company.
I've talked about the kind of just the feel of having something like a logo and a website
and all the rest of it, just that professionalism.
But it also brings a lot of weight with it, which you don't have as an individual freelancer.
If you're struggling with a client who isn't paying their
bills for some reason, as an individual freelancer, you
have not a lot of weight with that.
You can threaten legal action or something like that in an
email, but there is as much to think, well, you're a tiny
company, you're one person on their own, how are you going
to afford a lawyer?
Whereas if we look like we've got more weight than that as
being an organization, being a company, and actually, we
might have engaged a lawyer.
I'll talk about that later.
But an email on properly headed paper that looks like
it's come from a proper company makes a huge
difference.
Internally, being a company is useful for economies of scale.
So we need an accountant.
If each individual freelancer had to organize an accountant
and pay them accountancy fees and deal with accounting
systems, that cost, not only does it cost money, but it
costs time for each individual freelancer.
But we only have to do that once for all of us.
Same for legal stuff, same for websites, same for PR.
Same for, for example, being here at GDC.
There are two of us here at GDC.
If we wanted to do that before, as a group of individual freelancers,
all of us might have had to pay our own way to come across here,
to all do our kind of business dealing
and actually be fighting each other for different deals and clients.
That's just pointless.
And it means that we can afford to stand here at GDC
as a group between us, which works brilliantly.
Practical support.
I'm ill or something and I need somebody else to answer an email or I'm busy here at GDC,
then we've got people within the company who can do that, we've got people who can cover
each other, we've got people who can, you know, oh God, I forgot something, can somebody
mail me something from that thing back from the UK or whatever it happens to be. So just
the practical support of having other people around you is great. And just strengthen numbers.
If you think about it from a freelancer point of view, you've got a list of contacts, but
if we've got four, six, eight of us, that list of contacts is magnified hugely and we
have all of those different relationships. And if we as a company get a contact from
a particular possible client, we can go around to everybody else and say, yeah, has anybody
had dealings with this company before? Is there any connection? Is there any link we
can make here? And often there is. And it just magnifies that strength in numbers.
So we've done that for a while and it's worked very well.
And we've discovered some other things and thought about
it a bit, which are really good.
So the safety net is a really important thing.
So how it works is we do a job for a client.
We get some money in.
A small percentage of that goes into the company coffers
to pay for things like accountants and that sort of
thing, and the rest goes on to the people who
actually did the work.
We put slightly more in the coffers than perhaps we might need to, just as a sort of fighting
fund. And we came up with a use for it which we hadn't expected at all, and we should have,
but we hadn't expected, which is when a client didn't pay and suddenly an individual freelancer
who was supposed to be paid by that job didn't have any money coming in that month, which
is every freelancer's nightmare, really. But we have this safety net, we have this fighting
fund, and while we couldn't pay the whole of that fee, we could pay some of that fee
to tide them over until we'd sorted out the invoicing and got the client to pay up.
And that we did it once for the first time and suddenly went,
well, this is a thing that we should just do.
We should put it in place.
And you could do that as an individual freelancer.
You could save.
But it never really works out like that, does it?
And we've got everybody putting money into the pot, so
the pot is commensurately bigger.
So it just gives us that kind of fallback and that safety,
which is something which is really valuable in this gig
economy.
Skill development is something that didn't occur to us, but of course we are all different
people with our different skills, areas of expertise, and we have the ability to cross-train
each other in that as freelancers. If I'm doing a voice direction session with somebody,
one of the other people involved can be listening in, sitting in the background on Skype or
however we're doing the voice direction, and they can pick up those skills. If we're doing
a story workshop, we can have two or three of us in there to learn how to do story workshops.
We're cross-training each other all the time.
And something I should have said last slide, I guess, is
that the strength in numbers thing applies to the skills as
well, right?
So I might be really good at dialogue.
We have Matt, who's excellent at archaeology and that sort
of thing, alongside what he does.
And we have somebody else who's very much into narrative
design, and those skills all feed off each other and
improve each other.
And it means that if we go to a client, we have a much
better offering, right?
So we can't just say, well, yeah, I can.
I can do the dialogue, but you'll need somebody else to do the narrative design.
We don't have to do that, we can do the whole thing.
The gig economy.
So this was the big revelation really, because we kicked this off at about the time it was
becoming obvious that the games industry was changing, particularly amongst indies and
mid-level, which is, it's much more like the film industry now.
It is a small creative team comes up with an idea, they maybe get some funding for that
idea, they hire a bunch of people on temporarily.
and they get rid of them towards the end of the project.
And that's happening at big studios,
it's happening at very small studios.
That's the life we're in, and that's difficult to unionize.
I wouldn't say it's easy to unionize big companies,
but you can see how it might work.
You can see how all the workers
at a particularly large company can go,
no, we're not having any of that, we're gonna walk out.
If I walk out as an individual freelance writer
of a project, they go.
goodbye and hire somebody else. So we're sort of micro-unionizing by being in this co-op
together because of all of the benefits I've already talked about. I mean, things like
I need my contract checked. Well, we have a lawyer as part of the company. Things like
the safety net. And things like just having that logo and that weight with the client.
I don't know how many other freelancers are out here in this room today, but I strongly,
strongly recommend you think about teaming up with other people, if only for the key
thing to me is that emotional safety net, is not being on your own and not feeling alone.
And that's terribly, terribly valuable.
And I'll hand that over.
Back to Scott.
I already talked a bunch, so I need a drink.
All right.
All right, thanks everyone for talking, that was cool.
All right, so we just launched this
like a week and a half ago publicly,
which is funny, because it took like forever to get going,
which we'll talk about in a second.
But Bethany and I are two-thirds of the core team
that made a game called Night in the Woods.
Afterwards, we're working with a really fantastic artist named Ren Farrin.
She's not here.
But we needed to form a team after Night in the Woods for our next game.
We had a bit of money coming in from Night in the Woods, so we're like, okay, let's get
this going.
Now, what you're supposed to do...
is one of a couple things.
You hire on some people.
It's like Bethany and I are like, we started this,
and then they do like magazine stories
or whatever about us or something.
And then we also brought on this artist
and it was super cool or something.
Or more likely, it's just Bethany and I working.
We bring on a bunch of freelancers and contractors
for like short-term things here and there
and you know, staff up and then staff down at the end of it.
And so we were getting into that,
but it just kind of seemed like wrong, right?
And like Bethany and I, we've worked a bunch of jobs,
a lot of service industry,
and also just being kind of struggling artists for a while
until we kind of fell through the side door
into making video games.
So we've had like a lot of like bosses over the years.
We've been very aware of that dynamic
between being an employee
and kind of being the person in charge.
It just didn't feel right.
Something just felt like, eh, about it.
We're like, you know, we like Ren a lot.
Why would we want to be Ren's boss, right?
Her voice is as valuable as ours is.
So I angsted about it pretty hard for a few months
because I just didn't know what to do, right?
I was like, we need to make this thing
that I don't know how to do.
Ah, this doesn't feel right.
And then I heard about this whole worker cooperative thing
and was just immediately like, wow, this sounds great.
Yeah, this is before we got into all the complicated part
of actually doing it and everything.
But at least at first I was like.
This is fantastic.
And it took us a really long time,
because as I've said a couple times,
in the US, there aren't a lot of worker cooperatives.
They're in the hundreds.
They're growing now.
But it is, I've been saying it's like lost knowledge.
It's like when you have to read the item descriptions
in Dark Souls to get the story.
It was like that.
That's what it felt like sometimes,
just getting little bits here and there
of how to do this in the US.
So it took a lot of legwork and research,
and a lot of Googling, a lot of trying
to find local people who were involved
in cooperative, pro-cooperative building organizations,
and all that kind of stuff.
Ted here talking to our friend Salim up at Co-op in Montreal.
a bunch of other people, and just getting kind of ideas.
So we began acting basically as a worker cooperative in 2018, and then it took us a while to get
our legal entity because the government shut down for a while, and we couldn't get our
paperwork through and all that.
But then we publicly legally launched it just last month.
So why'd we do this? There was a history of projects that Bethany and I have been in.
I co-founded an international indie animation collective called Late Night War Club a few years ago.
Night in the Woods was very egalitarian. Like, we did vote. We knew there wasn't a hierarchy in that.
But it was all informal.
And so the idea of formalizing that, making that an actual structure that we were really a part of
and not just, oh, we like to keep it pretty horizontal around here.
type of thing. That sounded dirty. Anyway, there was also, I think, experience also with
IWW, knowing some IWW folks. We're in DSA, Democratic Socialists of America, labor organizers
there, and Game Workers Unite, which is the worker unionization, worker organization advocacy
organization in the games industry that a few of us are a part of.
And also just a lot of years of bosses.
It kind of made us not want to do this, right?
Like I had good bosses and bad bosses,
but they were still bosses.
And the good bosses, I would have liked them a lot better
if they weren't my boss, you know?
And so yeah, tired is bosses and employees,
but wait, I messed up this thing.
It was supposed to say wired.
Tired, bosses and employees.
Wild.
worker owners, right?
It's not like it's gonna get rid of all your problems,
like as, you know, Steve was talking about.
There are complications that come with this,
but it's not like being involved in a more hierarchical,
like boss worker, you know, thing,
gets rid of problems that you're gonna have.
So other reasons why we did this.
There's creative benefits to working like this.
I've worked in a lot of creative scenarios where there was like, here's your project
lead and then there's like the boss or whatever and you're kind of just coming in every day
going.
All right, what are we doing today?
Or like, oh no, the scope expanded over the weekend.
Like, oh my god, I left on Friday and it was one thing,
and I came back on Monday, it was another.
And now I have to do all this work,
and someone set a deadline, and I have to.
There's just a lot that we can talk and plan that.
It's way harder for me to walk in and go,
okay, everybody, we're doing this, or something.
We talk about it.
There's creative benefits to that that we've found.
We have kind of like, you know,
it's not as though we all get together,
and when Ren draws something, all of us get together,
vote what the cat looks like or something, you know?
There's a term that I heard a while ago,
actually in a documentary about a construction co-op
that's a horizontal organization and vertical deployment,
meaning that we all come together
and talk and make these decisions,
but at the end of the day, we all also have our lanes.
that we operate in.
And so while we can talk about things and vote on things
and discuss things, we also trust each other
to be able to do what we do best.
And it's not like you can't have creative direction.
Like I'm kind of operating, again, voted on by the team
as kind of a creative director,
kind of nudging us along in a certain direction.
So you can, it's not like it's a giant free for all,
you know, there's still like, not hierarchy,
but there's still organization in how you do stuff.
And there's creative benefits to that,
because people feel empowered to talk, you know,
to speak up, because you have to get some consensus,
you have to build consensus with each other.
You do have to look out for like personalities
that just do dominate those spaces.
That's something you really have to look out for.
But it tends towards there being more
kind of creative collaboration.
because as multiple people have said,
you do have to talk about this stuff.
There's the material and organizational benefits,
which I've kind of gone over.
Material is, we talk about where the money's going,
what money we're putting into it,
how we're paying, who's getting paid, that kind of thing.
Oh, we need to bring someone on.
Okay, let's all talk about this,
because this isn't just like, oh, they hired someone,
and I walked in and there was someone there,
and now the company's like, oh, we gotta lay people off,
because, no, we talk about that stuff.
before we make those decisions.
There's the interpersonal benefits of.
I remember talking to Ren when we were first
talking about this, and she had just left
a mobile studio that was particularly crunchy.
And I kind of, like, okay, so we want to do
this worker cooperative thing, blah, blah, blah.
And she was like, after I kind of explained it,
she was like, why aren't every company,
why isn't every company working this way?
Because it's one of those things where
you suddenly realize, like, oh, like,
once you get rid of the boss-employee distinction,
so many things change, right?
like overtime stuff, okay, we need to talk about that.
Like crunch, okay, we need to talk,
oh, do we need a deadline, do we need to sprint
through the next week to hit like an E3 demo or something?
Cool, let's take a week and a half after that.
We can just talk about that.
That changes how you interact with each other.
There's friction, there's all kinds of other stuff
as you come to a,
an agreement or you come to consensus on something,
but there's not one person just telling someone else
what to do and it has all of these implications
that you don't even realize when you put them into place.
Like it trickles down into all these things
and there's this toxic nature that you,
there's this toxic dynamic that you get
with a more hierarchical system that just kind of
doesn't apply as much when you're.
working cooperatively.
And it's just really personally fulfilling.
Everyone feels like they own what they're doing
because they do, legally own what they're doing.
There are three co-owners in our company.
We'll be staffing up to probably five by the end of it.
And as we kind of build to a fuller team,
but we all own this.
Like we're all on paper, you know?
So it's not just, like I said at the beginning,
it's not just like, oh, we like to think of ourselves
as a family and we all own it.
It's like, no, we legally do.
And it's different.
And we went from this dread to this excitement
about how we structure our labor and our relationships
together as workers.
Because like I said, it's not like it solves every problem.
It's not like everything is.
Sunny skies forever, but like it's exciting to be able to do this. It's exciting to own what you're making. It's decided
It's exciting to to not just you know. Oh, I work here. I'm part of this team, too
It's like no I work together, and we constitute what this is all of us. There isn't one person
doing it and then we all just work for them.
It's like, no, we all work for ourselves and for each other.
And that's just really different.
And so, yeah, that was, that's pretty cool.
I think that's why we like it so much.
And so, what we're gonna do now
is opening it up to some Q&A.
There's a microphone there.
I can't see it because there's lights.
I think we have a few minutes left.
Yeah, we have about 10 minutes left.
So if you want to come up, say your name, where you're from,
and just speak your question as the microphone.
That is a long line already.
Jeez.
Exciting.
And you can ask just general questions,
or if there's anything specific from anyone.
Hello, I'm Gabriella from Argentina. I
wanted to ask you if you know about
big corporations and
if you have any idea of how to apply it to
by your game
Enterprise or whatever
You're talking about corporations in the US
No, it's like B corporations. I don't know how it's said like properly in English is
Empresas B. It's like an organization that certifies you that you are a
corporation that both helps like...
Okay, it's kind of hard.
It's kind of about B corps. The kind of corps that are good for society.
B corps.
Yeah, it helps both in monetary, but also helps the society and the environment.
So, it's not like you own a corporation and you make donations to...
to fulfill some things or avoid taxes,
it must be on your, I don't know,
I'm wasting so much time.
It's like a mission statement?
Yeah, on the organization.
Part of your reason to exist is to benefit society.
Yeah, so it's like the next step for.
like the future of enterprises, it's that.
But it's most used in physical things.
So maybe you buy stuff that is manufactured.
Yeah.
I don't know if someone wants to come and help me.
Because I knew.
in products that are not physical, I don't know how I can apply it.
So, well, if you don't know, it's okay.
You can look at it.
I mean, I don't know of any off the top of my head,
like any game companies who have a, like, as part of their reason to exist,
changing the world for the positive.
But I can see how it could happen.
I mean, you could start a game company that has...
a purpose of creating educational content with the idea of changing...
Actually, isn't there a guy on the panel doing something like that?
You're making a game that is a political statement.
I mean, the idea is to influence political discourse.
Yeah, I mean, that's kind of what we're trying to do with our game is we realize there really
wasn't a game like that with the message that it had that was unabashedly positive.
that there wasn't like you know kind of a last minute reel in of like both sides are just as bad and
yeah so the other thing we we have in the UK things called CICs community interest companies
And there are certainly games adjacent companies in there.
There's things like SpecialEffect, which is trying to give people with disabilities access
to ways to play games in different ways.
And they're a sort of non-profit community interest company.
Similarly, we have a company local to us who has set up a retro arcade and co-op working
space for developers to work in, and that's done as a community interest company.
And it actually opens up a lot more things like government grants, because they're giving
money to you to help you improve the community.
So it's actually a really interesting structure.
But I've not seen it from the point of view of game developers directly.
And Toby Salkin, the founder, is an advocate for other game
companies to become e-ports.
So I think there's a lot of interest in that.
OK.
We'll check later.
Thank you very much.
Hi, my name is Jamie.
I'm an independent developer based in Phoenix.
My question for you all is, how do you go from already
having a small studio or a small LLC to actually biting
the bullet to make this change?
It seems like there's a lot of interpersonal lifting and
convincing that has to happen.
a studio that's primarily engineers, we're not terribly good at talking to each other
part.
So, do you have any suggestions or tips or strategies for how to drive that conversation
and actually become a co-op?
Yeah.
There's a lot of what we mentioned that's pretty nuts and bolts, right?
You know, a lot of us have some like, you know, political ideals that go into this,
but you kind of don't need those.
You can just go, here's how this would benefit all of us.
You know, there's a pretty like, this will be...
There is an efficiency aspect to it.
There is an aspect of transparency
with each other, accountability, where we have to hash this out.
Even if there is that solitary life of the engineer,
you can get together and say, OK, well, we all
want to have some control over this space
and what we're doing with our company.
So you can just, the math checks out, for lack of better words.
I think that you don't necessarily have to be all super high-minded about it.
It's pretty mundane.
This is just a system that can work better and can avoid a lot of problems that we'd
hit down the line.
So it's not just job security.
It's just things can make more sense because you're talking about them and discussing them
and working them out together.
And honestly, I think the most practical thing to do, we didn't approach it really from a
political point of view, it wasn't a practical thing.
And the most practical thing we did is simply write it down, is just list, if we changed
this structure, what would change?
What are the benefits?
What are the dangers?
What are the costs?
And make sure that everybody in the company understands that.
And if you can, for us, we really clearly saw the benefits fall out of that.
And if the same is true for you, then that's the thing to do.
And if it isn't true for some reason, then maybe don't do it.
Well that and like, you know, kind of what you were talking about of like getting people to talk to each other and stuff.
I mean, it's all about everybody's schedules and stuff and you don't want to get in the way of other people's work, of course.
And you got to trust people in their departments to do what they're supposed to be doing.
Because that's a big part of, you know, at least my beliefs for worker co-ops is, you know, trust your workers and trust yourself.
But you know, if you need to, one thing we've done is every, I think it's like pretty much every month, we kind of just tap each other on the shoulder and say, hey, what are you working on? Do you have any concerns?
Like, you know, let's talk about the months ahead and kind of keep it succinct so it doesn't just ramble on and then everybody goes back to working on what they're working on.
Yeah, at the risk of rambling on, we haven't really talked about communication in huge depth here,
but communication is vital to any of these things.
But it is to any company, right? If you're doing a company right, it should be all about communication.
Yeah, like one of the big things that we're continuously talking about is how we do that.
Do we do like a structured stand-up, you know, every day, like, you know, agile development and all that?
Or do we do like a once-a-week thing? Like, how do we keep in contact?
And it is, you can't get around the human side of talking to each other, unfortunately.
Alright, gracias por todos.
people eventually who are doing a job that is not something you can do, or not
something that's sort of in your core skill set. How do you deal with
subcontracting? Do you do that, or do you staff up, or what's the process for
bringing on more people? Especially if you're starting with a low budget. So one
of the things that we did was we kind of just discussed amongst ourselves like
What are the things we're going to need intermittently?
And do the people we're talking to, do they have other skills
that they can bring to the table?
Because with a small team like ours, a lot of us
wear different hats.
So I'll handle a lot of the business side of things and
talk to the publisher and arrange travel and stuff like
that, even though I'm.
artist on the team. But when it comes to stuff like needing concept art or animation or stuff
like that, we'll contract out. But we kind of have it in our best practices that we always
make sure that no one works for free. We pay all of our contractors. And if we can't, if
like someone comes to us and they're
you know, fees are outside of our budget.
We're honest about it.
We're like, you know, say, hey, we think you're great.
We love the stuff that you're doing,
but it's outside of our budget
and we're not gonna make you, you know,
lower your prices just because
you think we're fun folks to work with.
So we wanna make sure everyone comes out of this
feeling good and feeling like their labor was worth it.
I think for us, like,
the way I think about that kind of stuff,
because this is, as someone who was a contractor
for a long time, I think about this.
And it's like, if we're a co-op, right,
and all of us together open a pizza place,
we're all just gonna make pizzas.
What we do is make pizzas, right?
We all put in our money and we get a shop and an oven
and we're making this stuff.
But we're gonna have to hire someone to paint our sign
or design our menus.
We don't do all that stuff.
Or design our furniture once we get big enough
to have a nice dining room and all that.
At least with us, there's an idea of, yeah, what are these
core skills that we bring to it?
We don't want to end up in a situation where we have
someone who's basically just a contractor, but they just
don't have a vote, and they're not on the team.
Yeah, I was going to say, how do you avoid the co-op
becoming the bosses of the subcontractors that you're
working with?
I think that part of that is there are certain situations
where there are, yeah, when you contract someone in, there
is a task, and you do talk to them.
There's all kinds of ways that you can actually make that a non-terrible process,
which I think anyone who's been a contractor can list out really quickly,
the things you should do.
Crediting, prominently paying.
having very, like, and talking to them like you would talk with anybody else.
The people who actually get to vote in the co-op are the people who are in the co-op.
When people are kind of onboarded, like, like Siva was saying, there's kind of like a probational period
so that you can decide if you actually like each other enough to kind of enter into this kind of thing.
But with contractors, you just do the best that you can
and don't end up in a situation where you're relying on them to be the workforce for your co-op.
and stuff. So it's one of those things you have to keep yourself accountable on.
Last question. Sorry everyone else in line.
I think some of us might hang out afterwards to talk to.
Alright, well we'll keep this quick then. I'm MJ, I'm from Salt Lake City.
I'm a graduate student in games and production. What advice do you have for
somebody who is a leftist who wants to enter the industry and wants to work
under a co-op to
get your foot in the door in this area that's more exclusive?
Well, as Scott said, there aren't that many places that
are doing it yet.
But as somebody getting in the industry, I mean, for my
money, it would be kind of following what I've been
saying, which is find other people to team up with.
If you have a set of skills and you're entering as a
freelancer, then maybe consider doing what we did
and see if you can find other people with those skills who
are equally looking.
And you've got double the power to do that.
That's one way to approach it.
Just jumping in to be part of a cooperative, I guess it's
find a cooperative.
I think also, like, it is very, now is the time to get these things started.
You don't have to, like, all of us came to these, like, differently, right?
Like, there's freelancers and gig economy workers.
There's people whose studios transitioned into that.
There's, you know, Bethany and I, we had enough money to get a studio going, and so we decided
to go with that thing.
But often, like, a lot of co-ops, they don't start with everyone working full-time together
all the time, right?
Like, you can start something like this.
while you're all doing contract work
or working with something like that and build it up.
Like that's kind of what we did with Pixel Pushers.
Yeah, that's what we did as well.
Yeah, so it's not just always like a off the,
right off the blocks, we found it a co-op
and we're like running and stuff.
Because there's difficulties, there's like,
you know, you have to build up resources,
you have to see if you work together as a team,
you know, you have to work out your like bylaws
and all kinds of stuff.
And actually go to the co-op resource.
URL up there for all kinds of information on this kind of stuff.
So I guess it would be kind of like just be flexible with it.
And maybe start something with some like-minded folks and kind of build it up into being the
thing that you want it to be.
Because it doesn't have to be your full-time job immediately, which is good because there's
not many of them.
And if you're just starting something, it might take a while to get it to the point
where it's, you know, your life.
And stuff. So that would be, I think, that's a big smattering of advice.
Cool. Thank you.
Okay. I think that's it. I think they're going to kick us out.