Hi, my name is Stefan Dillie and I'm the Head of Frontend Engineering at InnoGames.
After focusing on browser games for close to a decade now,
InnoGames recently switched to a mobile-only strategy.
This means we are heavily using cross-platform engines like Unity instead of rolling our own now.
In my talk titled Data Binding Architectures for Rapid UI Creation in Unity,
I show you how I created the foundation for our new games.
I will show you how we allowed our artists to work independently in Unity.
This means they can design, iterate and test all their creations without any help of our
developers.
I hope to see you there and show you what we learned along the way.