here to see zero to one million, two different studios
with different success and different strategies.
I'm Tanya Short.
And I'm Richard Atlas.
And we're going to do our best to take turns
talking about our studios in a totally natural way.
We definitely practiced a lot.
We did actually, but.
More than once.
We'll see how it goes.
So you probably know me as the captain
of Kit Fox Games primarily.
We are a studio that started a little while ago.
We were primarily known for Moon Hunters,
which came out a couple of years ago.
We also released Shrouded Isle last year,
Shattered Planet some time ago,
and we've announced Boyfriend Dungeon.
Woo!
Yeah.
So we have officially been working together
for about five years now.
and in USD I think we're up to about 2 million total in revenue and we have 5-ish full-time
staff.
Everything's a little bit ish in the indie world, but that's kind of where we are.
And on our end.
So I'm Richard, I'm the CEO, general business person,
take care of some marketing and PR, a little bit of design,
a bunch of other stuff at Clever Endeavor.
We have a game called Ultimate Chicken Horse,
which launched a couple of years ago on Steam
and launched on PS4 and Xbox in December.
I started working about 2015 and on our side US dollars around 2.5 million in revenue.
We also had a cool cake that was made in ultimate chicken horse style.
And we're also five full-time staff members.
So pretty similar looking studios from the onset.
So I propose this talk partially because I think survivorship bias is rampant in the
business development community.
It often makes us act like our methods are the one true way to do business and if we
succeed that is the correct way to do things.
Some of you are probably here hoping to hear some steps to follow in order to make your
first million dollars and unfortunately that's not going to happen.
This is not a talk about what to do or a formula to apply.
There are lots of different successful strategies.
And although our studios have a lot in common,
we're both commercial indies, we're both based in Montreal,
we're both around the same size,
it started around the same time,
even so we have very fundamentally different ways
of running our studio successfully.
So the point is not to follow either of us.
at all. We're going to walk you through our thought processes so that you can inspect
your strategies and make your own decisions that are best for you. Okay?
So we're going to go through what goals our studios have,
how that impacted how we diversified our development
or not, our burn rates, our revenue, and our projections.
We're going to get very deep into the numbers of things
as much as our business partners will allow.
And we'll see what differences and similarities we can find.
So why do our studios exist?
I mean, OK, we want to make games.
apparently.
And what are we trying to achieve?
As we put together this talk, we did realize that our goals
are very much the same.
We wrote them out separately, but then they actually were
kind of actually the same goals.
So when we started looking at these studio overall goals, we
noticed that they're very similar.
So we're going to break them down a little bit and sort of
run through these.
So at Clever Endeavor we want to make sure that our employees are always developing in
terms of their skill and that we feel that they're growing as individuals in their skills
and in their work throughout the work that they're doing with us.
Yeah, I would actually say that improved skills or craftsmanship, as we call it, and personal
growth are really important to Kid Fox, maybe the most important at this point.
We really do want to make some of the best games that exist, and that ambition means
that with each game we have to keep raising the bar a little bit.
We actually didn't discover this goal at first.
We didn't think of it on day one.
We kind of realized after we finished Moon Hunters
that we had this ambition, and we
felt we could realize it together.
So now part of what we're going to be talking about
are plans to enable this self-improvement and this team
growth together.
And now one of our first goals from the very beginning
was to treat ourselves like professionals,
but also to take care of ourselves.
So we do occasional overtime, but in the past years,
we've never worked on the weekends,
and we've never had sustained overtime.
I personally, as the captain of the ship,
say you're not allowed to work on Kit Fox stuff
after a certain hour.
Feel free to work on your own stuff.
And we work smart pictured here are the original four co-founders of kitfox although Mike is no longer at kitfox
we still miss him and
On our end we're in the same boat
we look a little bit different than them, but we also try to avoid overtime and crunch pretty vehemently and
We want to be able to work on the things that we want to work on
obviously, but that leads to a better quality of life and we want to
take careful attention to make sure that our employees and the partners themselves,
our lives come first before our work.
So if there are issues, if there's whatever things come up,
we know that the priority is on our lives and our stress
and our situation before our work directly.
The next thing is sustainability.
Of course, we want to survive.
So our goal as a company is to become
a long-term sustainable company
that can survive for many years,
pay competitive salaries.
Like we talked about, skill development,
have our employees develop their skills.
We never really had the goal of growing a company
to become huge and flipping it, selling it,
and then starting something new.
That's not really the way we see it.
It's more of a long-term, slow, steady rise.
Yeah, it was the same for us.
We put survival as a number one priority.
I wanted Kit Fox to exist in five or 10 years,
and now it's been five years, so goal one achieved.
And so in many ways, this did translate
into safer, less risky, more conservative business
development practices.
The primary of which is actually that we
felt diversifying our studio into developing
multiple different kinds of products
was what was best for us and our goals.
So this decision of whether or not to diversify into multiple products or to develop just one game at a time
Does impact everything else it determines what your studio is good at?
How it grows over time it's a cyclical thing or as soon as you start either diversifying or focusing on one game
Your personnel changes your strategy for dealing with crises changes
And of course you can change your goals midway.
You can start to diversify after developing only one game.
You can start to focus after deciding
that diversifying was bad for you.
But the way that you develop even your first project
could change depending on how you want to orient
your studio and its strengths.
The short answer is that Kit Fox is very diversified oriented.
Some successful studios diversify, such as Clay.
Clay is one of my favorite game studios.
And honestly, a lot of the advice
I'm going to give you today is actually advice
that Jamie Chang of Clay gave me back in 2013.
And I immediately started trying to act on.
Lots of game studios are happy to bet it all
on one big release, especially they have.
Nothing to lose.
You're making your first game, why not make it your big only thing?
But I preferred, again, to bet on survival and calculate our risks and
take the safer bet.
So when we were in the middle of developing Shattered Planet,
I saw an announcement online that the Square Enix collective was going to exist.
And there was no call for pitches or anything like that.
I just cold emailed Square Enix saying,
can I please pitch something to your weird new thing?
And they said, I guess.
I don't know who you are, but OK.
You have to get it in by Friday, though.
So we hadn't even soft launched.
our first game yet, Shattered Planet.
We had four people, and when I told the team,
I was like, no, no, no, let's stop for two days,
make a pitch document, and send it to these randos.
They were like, what are you doing?
We're behind schedule, we have assets to make.
And our business partners also, our investors,
said maybe you should be focusing a little bit more, Tanya.
This is a recurring theme with me.
It worked out. We actually pitched the Moon Hunters, which was our next game,
and it was actually a really great opportunity for us.
And we had no way of knowing that at the time, but we decided it was worth risking two days
to explore this new opportunity for diversification, because I had already known
that I wanted to be developing multiple projects in parallel as much as possible.
So over time, Kid Fox has become maximally diversified,
like maybe way too diversified, actually.
In five years, we've released three major projects
and we spent a year on work for hire.
And 2018 marks our very first time
with two games solidly in production together,
even though I was just here on Monday
talking about how Moon Hunters
had initially disappointing sales.
So there's good and bad sides of diversifying and developing
multiple games at once.
I mean, sure, yeah, it's lower risk, obviously.
If one project does well, we can split it up
into multiple other things.
And if no single failure can close the studio.
And because we're having multiple little revenue streams,
things are generally more stable.
We don't need to rely on one individual sale.
Of course, it's still a little spiky because Steam,
but more games equals a stronger back catalog
and steadier flow, and I sleep better at night.
And our team members are quite flexible now
because they've worked on lots of different projects together
in lots of different configurations.
Hybrid team members stay more excited and refreshed
because they're not working the same thing
for years and years and years.
And so people are less likely, I think,
to feel cynical or bitter on a project
because they know they have other options.
And if there isn't one right now, there probably will be soon.
So we can adjust to change
according to team members' interests pretty quickly.
And with a large number of projects,
we can experience a very junior team member
can join in straight from school
and experience from pre-production
all the way to shipping very quickly
because they can see the whole life cycle
of a project happening right next to them.
So there's a lot of different opportunities
from start to finish.
Unfortunately, hybrid team members are also not particularly specialists.
I mean, this is no new problem in indie.
We're all kind of wearing a lot of hats.
But this is another thing altogether when you are doing something
completely different on a different kind of project every year or so.
I mean, at this point, we have specialized a little bit
into system-driven RPGs, I guess.
But the art styles are all over the place,
the technology is all over the place.
So you can't say, like, we have the world's best.
person at anything. They're the best at making that one game that one time.
And we also start projects constantly. Thankfully, I like coming up with new ideas. I don't really
mind having blank pages all the time, but it is a little bit stressful to say, oh,
we got to start again every year and a half or so.
But at least it's better than finishing projects.
Finishing projects is the worst.
I mean, I don't know how many of you have survived a game.
Games are terrible to finish.
And diversification makes that worse
because every time you shut down one crisis,
there's another one coming in the door.
So we do have regular upending of priorities and tasks.
The good news being that we definitely have to prioritize.
well, but as the director, I mean, I still do end up with more difficult decisions per
week.
Last fall, we were actually shipping the Shrouded Isle while also hiring up for Boyfriend Dungeon
and shipping Moon Hunters on Switch, and also our tech lead was doing R&D on his own personal
project, so we had like four projects for six people.
Not ideal.
This is what diversification tends to look like for us.
So on the left you have the spend per game and then on the right you have the income
per game.
Or maybe it's the other way around.
Which way?
We forgot to label that one.
Yeah, no, it's income on the left and revenue on the right.
Yes, because on the left, you see
there's a canceled project that we spent on, which oddly enough
did not make us any money.
But yes, so Shrouded Isle is a special case, by the way.
I keep referring to it as if we developed it, but in actuality,
we published it.
So we spent almost nothing on development.
It was a side project of one of our members.
But then we also don't get to keep most of the revenue,
unfortunately.
So the other hand, the other side of this
are the companies like Supergiant Games,
who focus on one game at a time.
So Supergiant, you might know from Bastion,
then Transistor, and Pyre.
They manage to make amazing games every time,
all the time, somehow.
And they're only focusing on one at a time.
In our case, Ultimate Chicken Horse was a game that
came out of a game jam originally,
so we kind of fell into this one game that we were starting.
And throughout the process, we'd have to make the decision,
okay, we're working on this,
do we want to start another project,
or do we just full steam ahead?
And we've still been working on Ultimate Chicken Horse.
Like I said, it came out March 2016 on Steam.
We're still on it, and we're still adding stuff to it,
and while we're going to start prototyping new stuff,
hopefully soon.
it's still been the main, well, the only moneymaker,
and it's been worth our time to continue it.
So with these goals in mind,
or the idea of focusing on one project at a time,
there are, again, some pros and cons.
So one of the positive things that we think that we can try to achieve high
quality by focusing on one thing we don't have to split our mind between
many different things. We know we can focus our design efforts and our feedback
on this one game and hopefully the same way Supergiant do it we're going to try
and achieve really high quality in each of the games that we're working on.
The next thing is that there's a simplified cash flow, pretty straightforward, less projects to spend money on.
But not only simplified in terms of the sales and in terms of the budgets, but also in terms of if you're going to pitch to people,
choosing which events you're going to, what kind of business development you're doing, that is very much more simplified.
So the decision process is simplified as well as the actual spending.
Project management is a similar thing.
As someone who's helping manage the project,
it's a lot easier to know that all of our employees
and our partners know what everyone is working on
at all times because there's only one thing.
It simplifies the process quite a lot.
So we're all on the same page,
we know what other people on the team need.
We're not gonna bug someone to pull them off a project
for a second because we need some help
last second on this thing.
That simplifies it a lot.
Zing.
Another sort of interesting point, which might be debatable, but I was thinking of this one
when we were writing this, was that I feel like we can meet the expectations better by
focusing on one project.
What I mean by that is if we were a 30-person team making three projects and spent putting
10 people on each of those teams, the expectation is that we are a 30-person AA or III or whatever
you want to call it, those kind of teams, and that we're going to...
produce something that has that kind of quality that kind of Polish well if it's
actually 3 games made by teams of 10 people we're probably not going to hit
that far so I think the expectation can be kept consistent with the size if you
well if we're focusing on this one game.
On the other hand, as I was saying the opposite of the the many eggs in many
baskets is that we only have one revenue source right so there's no other
additional revenue streams everything is coming well almost everything as we'll
see in a minute is coming from this one game.
If it fails, it fails.
You don't have any additional resources to,
well, you're not getting any additional revenue sources.
So we think this can be balanced out
by the high quality argument,
but I guess that's to be seen in the future.
The next thing is after a game launches,
there's a lot of pressure to produce, right?
So right when the game launches, you say, okay,
we're on to the next thing.
Well, all of a sudden, you've got X amount of money
and X amount of time to survive,
and you have to be creative right away.
Having projects that are dispersed,
more like Kit Fox is doing,
gives a little bit less pressure to produce.
So that's something that can be tough
for the people running the company.
It can be tough for the people
who are forced to be creative.
Like, hey, we need an art style right now.
You have a week to go.
That's not ideal either.
So these are our charts.
They're a little less complicated.
So most of our money went to Ultimate Chicken Horse
and most of it came in from Ultimate Chicken Horse.
But just because it's a simplified thing
doesn't mean we shouldn't be careful
about how we spend our money.
So with that I'd like to talk about burn rates.
Burn rates is how much money you spend.
So it's going to be how much money you spend
within a given amount of time.
And that can be a weekly burn, a monthly burn,
yearly, however you want to call it.
Either way, you have to make sure that you're aware
of how much money you're burning
and hopefully not actually burning,
but spending on useful things for game development.
So there are some obvious things
that your burn is going to go towards.
Things like salaries, rent, software,
if you're using game engines, et cetera.
There's the next level that we call,
there are things that are a little bit more under the hood.
So they could be contractors or outsourced work.
That can be things like employee training,
things you probably consider,
but aren't necessarily at the forefront of your mind
when you're thinking of these things.
Beyond that, there's the things
that you really don't want to think about.
And often we fail to realize how important they are.
things like taxes, loan repayment, and royalties, and things like that.
We'll see a little bit later.
It's not ideal when at the end of your quarter or your year,
you find out that you're losing 40% of your money to taxes.
So you got to be aware when the money is coming in, of course,
what you're spending it on and what you're going to be spending it on later.
So our theme of Kitfox is scrappy survival.
And so we do what we can to save up enough money
during release years to make up for our lean years.
And part of this means that we pay ourselves much less
than we could probably get at a bigger studio.
We all decided that together,
that we were more interested in stability
than in cash out right now,
so that we can invest in projects for longer years to come.
And we try to minimize the numbers of recurring payments
that we're spending on as well,
because that also helps increase the longevity of the studio.
So cut out all those extra subscriptions if possible.
I'd rather take the team out to lunch than have a,
I don't know, recurring thing, but.
I mean unlike a lot of indie studios, probably most,
Kitfox exists because we did find an investor on day one.
None of us had significant savings,
none of us could bootstrap, nobody had much leeway.
One team member, me, I am supported somewhat by my spouse,
but
that was it. All of us had rent to pay, all of us had to find income from somewhere. So
that stability of revenue that I mentioned from diversification
was very important to us and we continue to do that.
So the diversification approach does bite us here a little bit
because burn rates are very complicated for us
to calculate, which makes some business partners nervous.
So I act very confident.
I hope no publishers are watching this.
No, we can't quite to the dollar say exactly how much we're
spending on any one thing because someone's
spending 40% of their time sort of on this project.
I'm sort of 5% on this project, et cetera.
And we also try to avoid loans where possible
because the more we lean on them now,
the more we'll pay later,
but we obviously didn't have a choice early on.
So because stability is more important to us
and continues to be,
some loans are worth the peace of mind,
even if it means in the long run, we're going to lose money.
So early on, like this is a couple years ago now,
payroll was so dominant a cost
that nothing really came close at all.
But then, I mean a side effect of shipping things,
that when they sell okay,
you start having to pay those loans back.
And pay royalties that you promised.
So the last year hurt a little bit more,
but that was because we were more successful.
And remember that cost chart that I showed you per game?
This is how much we spent per game, right?
Totally, totally sensible.
Except that I have no idea how to turn that
into actual spend because a lot of those costs
are across multiple projects.
There's often some back of the napkin things I can do about rent was sort of 60% on this project and sort of not
But at the end of the day, I kind of know what we spent per the year
But it's very hard for me to calculate specific burn rates per project
So the clever never story is a little bit different at least in the way that it started so
the first thing was that we did start pretty much completely unpaid for a year and
There was a Kickstarter in there, but the Kickstarter raised about enough money to pay us,
I don't know, let's say well below minimum wage for about a month out of the year.
So not huge in terms of salaries.
But at that point, actually, I'd sort of counter
to what Tanya was saying, was two of the three
of the partners who started the company were living at home.
We didn't have any expenses.
We don't have any kids, didn't have any kids,
no cars, et cetera.
So it was a lot cheaper and we were able to do that
for about a year.
After that, there was investment and so on,
and we'll talk more about that in a little bit.
But on our side, we have a slightly higher burn rate.
We're around 30 to 35 USD, sorry, it's really tiny here,
per month.
And so this has been partially due to the game's success.
We've been able to increase salaries.
And so salaries have been good.
We're trying to increase employee salaries
and keep them competitive, of course.
But one of the interesting things that we have admitted
to or are going to be accepting doing
is partner salaries that are variable.
So we understand that if a game's doing well,
then the salaries can go up.
Of course, the employees, you're not going to tell them,
hey, you're earning less this year than you did last year.
That doesn't work.
But the partners are very aware of the fact
that if the next thing doesn't take off,
we're accepting the fact that we might be taking significantly
lower salaries from one year to the next.
So most of the burn comes from salary.
And that's the same thing as we've seen across many studios,
including the two of ours.
And lastly, this is just a point that I figured out
fit into the slide, because it just seems to make sense.
I really want to say not to ignore your own pay.
It sounds almost like the opposite of us
not paying ourselves for the first year.
But what I mean by that is that I've
seen a lot of people in the indie dev world,
especially in the startup world in general,
who will spend two years of their lives
working 60 hours a week not paying themselves.
And they don't realize that that's not sustainable.
you really need to pay yourself a certain amount or be able to sustain a kind of lifestyle
where you're going to be earning enough money to survive and not working 60 hours a week
every week.
So I just wanted to make sure to say that we should pay ourselves.
I mean, I think even if you can afford,
let's say you do go two years without paying yourself,
you should be mentally tracking
what would that burn rate have been.
Because if you go around, I've seen this happen,
if you go around saying, oh, you know,
I'm 1,000% ROI or whatever,
because you didn't pay your salary,
like that's not actually something usable going forward.
Yeah, the break-even point when you spend no money
is not very high, right?
So this is a breakdown of our 2016-17 fiscal year
in terms of what we spent.
And so you see that giant big green beast at the bottom,
which is taxes.
So I'm putting that in the spend,
this is I guess just money out in general.
That was somewhat of a surprise,
but of course it's a mixed sort of blessing and a curse
because if the taxes are high,
it probably means the revenue's high.
So that year we had done well and we're paying more taxes,
but again, you have to keep in mind
that that's a number that you have to pay.
The next thing was there was some royalty repayment,
that's loans and royalties that you see in blue,
that was paid back to investors.
And then the rest of it is payroll.
So if we ignore the big taxes part,
you can see a big chunk of that,
majority of that, the remaining chunk is payroll.
So we also looked at some other studios in Montreal,
and we asked them what percent of their monthly burn
was payroll.
Now, there is a caveat here.
We're not entirely sure if they were including things
like loan repayments in their burn.
So these numbers might be a little steep.
Or taxes, even.
Or taxes.
We're not sure.
But across the board, you can see
that the minimum is around 55-ish percent, up to 90%
payroll.
So obviously, that is a big chunk of everyone's spending.
So there are different companies that have different ways
of spending money, and in this case,
we wanna talk about how companies
reinvest in their employees.
So one of the things that some companies do,
like Kitfox, is slow and steady raises,
and they wanna try to basically slowly keep that up
and keep their employees happy
by keeping those raises coming.
There's another company in Montreal called Spearhead Games,
which we got permission to talk about here.
They do a sort of profit sharing.
So once the game has made its money back,
and that means let's say the game costs however much money,
once it makes that back, anything beyond that,
profit, sort of net profit, is split,
10% of that is split among employees.
It doesn't matter seniority, it doesn't matter salary,
it doesn't matter any of that.
If you worked on the game, you get a cut of that.
There are some other ideas that we've thrown out here.
So one of the things is game performance leading to bonuses.
The game's doing well, you can give it out in bonuses
without necessarily increasing salaries
because like we said before,
those are hard to bring back down.
So you just give bonuses instead if the game's doing well.
You're considering something like that.
Yeah, and this is something we've considered as well.
Another idea is to designate some sort of source of revenue as bonus money.
So one idea for that was, let's say you're going on sale for, you know,
Steam had recently the lunar, lunar, what was it called? Lunar New Year sale.
And so you could say, okay,
anything above our baseline that we make during that sale,
that will go as bonus money to employees and partners.
Also, if you're living in a region that happens to have tax credits, you could then designate
that money as employee reinvestment money.
Whatever it is that helps you kind of separate it emotionally from the rest of your income
will probably help you see it as employee money.
Yeah, so we're all decently good at spending money.
That's not the hard part.
But how do we make money?
Our money comes from lots of different places, right?
So yeah, we're maximally diversified,
but again, most of our money doesn't actually come
from sales, or it didn't for the first million.
Because we can't handle bootstrapping,
we had to go out hunting for other sources of cash.
Our first game, Shattered Planet, there,
did not make back its initial investment for like a year.
So how did we survive?
Well, there's lots of different places you can get money from.
I don't think I've technically done every single one of those,
but almost all of them.
And it's not really much of an exaggeration.
So here are the major ones in chronological order.
I can leave that up.
I see a few phones are taking pictures.
But yeah, you should definitely investigate
each and every one of those if you're looking
for another few thousand to put in your pocket there.
So first we had Execution Labs.
They were our very first believers.
They invested about 85K USD.
And about nine months later,
we started running out of money.
And so we panicked a little bit
and we applied to lots of different places, actually.
And a lot of them paid out.
So we had, technically we had venture capital.
In reality, it was actually kind of
through a government weird program.
But there are startup programs in lots of different places,
like places you wouldn't expect.
So you might actually want to ask your local officials
about any kind of entrepreneurial thing,
because everyone wants to be the next San Francisco or whatever.
But we also ran a Kickstart.
Sorry.
Sorry, San Francisco.
So Kickstarter also gave us a little bit, which was great.
We also did a very small contract with Cartoon Network
during this time.
But around that time, we, oops, nope.
We also started doing some work for hire.
Something I mentioned on Monday was that
Moonhunter's initial sales were not great
and I was worried that they would be zero.
So in preparation for that,
I actually set up a contract for work for hire.
although that didn't end up really going anywhere,
it was still helpful for us to keep going
and surviving through to help moon hunters get nourished.
And I'm calling it loans here.
The Canada Media Fund, although it sounds
like a grant organization, is actually a loan organization.
So it is a very favorable loan,
but theoretically we could have also gotten
that kind of loan from a bank or something like that
at much worse terms, but that is also a source
that we could have looked at.
uh... so our sales are mostly from steam
our sales are very steam focused but consoles aren't doing bad either
we've got almost nothing from mobile uh... that was even back in two thousand
fourteen so i imagine it would be worse now
We are focused on premium games, and I do think that in an ideal world, we would do more direct sales by kitfoxgames.com.
There's a really great blog article recently from Jason Rohrer about how he's doing really well selling his games on his website in 2018,
so that's definitely worth checking out because Steam does add value, I think, and they earn their 30%, but being able to get my own 30% would also be nice.
So here we go again.
Remember this simple, clean chart?
Well, those sales are only half the equation.
So in reality, although everyone only asks about sales,
everyone only talks about sales,
in reality, the survival of a studio like Kit Fox
is only possible through having lots
of different sources of revenue
and being able to put aside my pride for a little bit
and be willing to pay some interest in a few years.
We still have years without as much income as other years.
We're still a little bit spiky because that's
how premium game launches work.
But unless we're willing to transition
into games as a service, which I don't know, it could happen.
But this seems kind of unavoidable for now,
but we're making the best of it that we can.
So from Clever Endeavor's side, Ultimate Chicken Rice,
like we said, has been the only real revenue source
except for a small investment, which we
got before the game launched.
So we're going to talk about that in a second.
The first million dollars and overall game sales, of course,
have been the major source of revenue for us.
So if we look at overall, this is
going to be the all-time revenue sources,
and then I'll show you one with just the first million.
So we see PC sales is really high.
Console sales are there, but we've only
been out on console for about two, three months.
So hopefully that red piece will start getting bigger.
And there was a small investment that you
see there as well, along with the Kickstarter.
So on the PC sales side, most of our income comes from Steam.
About 91% of our.
around 91% of it is from steam.
The next highest contributor is going to be Humble Bundle,
which included two Humble Bundles,
as well as just being on the Humble store itself,
which I believe is on this part.
So our PC console focused so far,
that's what Ultimate Chicken Norse has been launched on.
And we sort of plan to stay that way,
but we're not really sure.
Right now we haven't had any interest in mobile
because none of the.
people on the team are really mobile gamers.
But obviously we're not going to close any doors.
So we'll see what happens.
We're not...
Yeah, actually, let's not get into that.
I had a note about mobile, but yeah.
So the other thing I wanted to note is
we're not on a lot of the small stores.
So we have the Humble store
because they helped us set up a cool four-pack deal
and we're on Steam.
But we're not on a bunch of little stores because we take the contracts that we sign very...
We scrutinize them quite closely.
And we've seen a lot of really, really, really, really awful contracts.
And I think the amount of money and time we would spend just sorting that out
is probably more than the sum of all that we would make on all of those small stores.
So we're going to leave that out for now.
If we look at the first million...
this is again a little bit simpler than than what could Fox games has you can
see investment is a small chunk and the rest of it is simply game sales.
So again like with the burn rates we talk to some different Montreal studios
about how much money or where their first million came from and we had a
pretty wide variety of of revenue sources in this first million so the
first 3 that you see on the top are just sales.
The next one, the purple and the blue, is 75% Kickstarter and 25% sales.
And then there's one on the bottom that's a mix of work for hire, government funding,
and I think there's something else in there.
And then the last one, interestingly, was all from a publisher.
So this was an advance on sales that they made the first million on that, and I don't
know how much they might have made after that.
But the point is, the revenue sources obviously can be quite different in the first million
dollars that you're making, or in the first $100,000 that you're making.
So I mean, obviously, this probably isn't a representative
sample of the entire indie community.
But I think it's interesting that in a city as indie
healthy as Montreal, you still see that only about half
of the companies who are still around,
it looks like who answered my email,
were initially bootstrapped, apparently,
because they didn't get any money from anywhere but sales.
So the next thing I want to talk about is projections.
I think you should do projections.
So we talk a lot about the cash flow,
the money that's coming in,
and cash flow in terms of revenue sources,
also in terms of burn rates, how much is going out.
So we try to look at the runway that we have,
which is basically how much time we have to survive
based on the money that we make.
It's fairly simple, it's the revenue minus the burn.
And this way you'll be able to see how many years
or months you can survive in your current situation.
There's a few things we want to point out about this
before we get too deep into it.
So the first one is to know your limit.
Obviously you can't project accurately
five years down the line.
So if you're spending hours calculating pennies
five years down the line, that's probably silly
because we can't do that.
The next thing is to always add contingency and to estimate high.
So every time I make budgets for anything,
I always make them quite a bit higher than I expect.
And I can tell you from experience,
you'll be happier when you're $1,000 under budget as opposed
to $100 over budget.
So the accuracy might be less, but you'll
be happier if you didn't go over the budget, even by a bit.
Also, it's nice to find you have extra money based
on the budget that you've made.
The next point is somewhat obvious.
Every situation must be considered,
but I want to point out the way in which we look at
every single situation or try to think of every situation
is to look at it from, so my perspective is
the business marketing PR perspective,
but also try to think of it as,
okay, well if I'm the lead artist,
maybe there's gonna be software I need,
maybe there's gonna be.
things that are going to come up, maybe we're going to want to hire people, what does this company do?
They must have had to consider what was happening when they did this promotion, or this, or this, or this.
So really trying to think of everything from your perspective,
but also from the perspective of other people in your milieu,
will help you to get a good handle on how much money you're going to be spending,
and how much money you're going to be earning.
Yeah, so I find money really scary.
I come from humble origins,
and the idea of the number of dollars
that we spend per month is literally terrifying.
And it can be really emotional at first.
But I also very much believe in projections,
and we do a very basic calculation every six months or so.
It is definitely completely worth it.
So here's some example numbers.
They're a little bit fudged,
but it gives an idea of how we calculate.
So as a small team, our variance from month to month
can be very high, because although salary is the.
the majority of our spend.
We still, you know, when PAX comes in
and blows our budget by an extra $10,000, that's a lot.
That's like, you know, half of our usual burn.
So between travel costs, like in 2016,
our month-to-month costs varied by up to 50%.
So we couldn't just take a random month
and then multiply it by 12.
That absolutely wouldn't work.
We have to actually see what the average is
and what the variance is, both.
So 15% is what I've heard tossed around as an average contingency plan or in the budget
for projects.
But even last year, in our fourth year of existing, Kitfox still had a variance from
month to month of 34%, which is still high, but maybe it'll slow down a little bit over
time.
So if we hire two more people this year, which is the plan,
that does increase the monthly burn
by a certain amount per month, right?
And then you multiply that by 12,
and you have an idea of what you might be spending in 2018.
And then if I see how much money we have left in the bank
and pessimistically add how much we'll get this year,
again, very, very rounded numbers, but you get the idea,
and divide how much we spend per month,
it looks kind of like this.
So it's like, oh, we kind of have enough for about a year.
And in six months, I can calculate that again
and see if that's actually true.
And I know this is a little bit crazy.
Actual business people are probably like,
what are you doing, Tanya?
But I do actually put in our burn
as if it was at its highest, like continuously.
And also, what if suddenly steam crashed tomorrow
and didn't give us any money, or there was a legal problem?
I don't know.
But I still am seeing in the very worst case,
Can we survive six months?
Yes or no, because I feel like we absolutely have to.
And if that ever becomes a no, we're
not really sure if we're going to survive for six months.
Then I'm suddenly no longer a game designer.
I am now a business developer full time.
And I don't like that, so I try to avoid it.
And this is how.
and so yeah we check in on that that's that every six months
and because we're spending conservatively
and we can also
have a moment where the whole team takes the day and they guess how
much will we sell before we launch. Now of course nobody has an idea. Nobody knows
how much their game is going to sell before they launch and anyone who tells you otherwise is lying.
But having your employees actually go through the mental exercise of how many
would I think it would sell is interesting because it is kind of like a
cross-disciplinary learning moment because people don't even realize what
assumptions they're making, what expectations they have until they put
them on paper and look at what other people's expectations are. It can be
really wild.
So this is the kind of thing that I do with the team.
I tell them these are some example sales.
These are not actual sales, these are my guesstimates
based on, by the way, Steam reviews times 12
at a certain point in time.
I don't have any secret source for sales numbers, I'm sorry.
I actually think that multiplying Steam reviews
is a better source for this kind of thing than Steamspy.
Steamspy is wonderful and amazing,
but I don't use them for sales estimates at all
because of bundles and stuff.
So anyway, I give the team this kind of thing,
like here's some comparable games and their sales over time.
So what do you think it'll sell in a month
compared to these things?
Of course, the scary thing is that employees stop here.
They don't really need to know the rest of it.
They don't need to know the financials.
I mean, if they want to, I don't mind.
I'm a transparent kind of business owner,
but most people are stressed out like I am
when they see lots of zeros and things everywhere
going out of their bank account.
So for them, all they need to do is say,
oh, I think it'll be about 5,000 in three months.
That sounds reasonable.
Of course, in real life,
sales are very rarely in the middle.
and that's a whole other lecture for a whole other time.
But I generally, I like to sense,
are my employees feeling very pessimistic
about the sales coming up?
Are they feeling optimistic?
What do they think it will perform like and why?
And that is an interesting thing.
You'll get a different conversation
based on whether you're talking to an artist
or a programmer or what games they play
or if they're in this genre, that kind of thing.
Or just a pessimistic person.
Yes, yes, I have those two.
So yeah, we do lots of pessimistic things,
and we're very conservative.
So I go back to this kind of projection, or this sales idea,
and actually calculate how much I need to make
before I spend on a game.
So I know I made a big fuss about how my burn is
very hard to calculate, but I still
want to know a general idea.
In a general way, am I going to spend $100,000 on this game?
Am I spending $400,000 on this game?
Am I spending a million on this game?
and I actually calculate all of that and I see how much I feel like I would need to sell at a minimum.
These are basically all of my numbers that I use. This is as deep as I go. I'm sorry.
But it generally works for me that I can see whether I have a realistic expectation.
Is it realistically...
possible for this game to sell the number of copies that I need?
Usually the answer is maybe, but that is still a better answer
than literally no, I cannot find a game on Steam that is like this at all,
that has sold anything like this.
That is a scary reality.
That was actually true for Boyfriend Dungeon until Dream Daddy came out.
Oh my god, that was the best day.
And projections are really hard without historical data.
Unfortunately, in the first couple of years of Kit Fox,
it was much, much harder than it is now.
The more data you get from your own games,
the better you'll get at your own projections, obviously.
But it's, like I mentioned before,
it is dangerous to assume your game will perform
in the middle, because almost no games do.
We've been really lucky that way.
We've been very middle-classy, release-y developer.
But usually you'll sell either very poorly
or very well, unfortunately.
But yeah, good luck with that.
I'm very uplifting, I'm very uplifting.
I am an optimist, this is part of why I hate money.
Anyway, so assuming that we've met
our long-term goal of survival,
now we reach this existential moment in Kid Fox's history.
I think we're actually gonna look back
at 2018 in the future.
Because we have money projected to be coming in,
how can we best meet these other goals?
Do we have other goals?
We need to think as a company, now that we are surviving,
what is our third goal?
Should we give ourselves better raises?
Should we hire more people?
We've actually talked about maybe moving to Japan
would be a fine trade-off.
Like, we don't really know.
I mostly just want to keep designing cool games.
So I guess, wish us luck.
But in the meantime, Clever Endeavor
does a little bit more than we do on the projection side.
Also, we're going to try and make sure that she stays in Montreal.
That's hard.
Yeah, so we have a little bit more of a complicated system that we use at Clever Endeavor.
I should mention, I didn't put this in the slides, but you're talking about the employees
making projections, and we actually did that.
three, well we were just three partners at the time,
made projections before our game launched,
and we got a very wide range,
like I think it was like 10,000 units
to like 400,000 units was the range.
That was the most pessimistic and the least pessimistic,
or the most optimistic, and only three people,
so you can imagine.
Any who, so yeah, so we're a little bit more in depth.
Part of that is because a couple of us
kind of like playing with Google Sheets
and formulas and things.
And part of it is because,
well we think there are some upsides
and we'll discuss the upsides and the downsides
after I go through this.
So we have this big complicated document
that we update monthly or whenever we need
to make an adjustment.
It's not that complicated, but it'll look complicated,
but I'll try to explain.
So,
This is the main tab of the projections document.
And you can download this.
I actually made a template that people can download,
and I'll show you the link to download that
throughout the slides and at the end.
So this thing is gonna help us consider
many different scenarios and play out
different scenarios in our minds
and see how long we have to survive.
So just breaking this down a little bit.
So we see there's one section with cash on hand,
that's whatever money you have, bank accounts,
if you have investments or anything like that.
The next section is gonna be receivables.
So that's gonna be money that you're expecting
to, that's coming in from Steam,
let's say that you haven't received yet,
or whatever money that's coming from a deal in the future.
And then you've got all the stuff that you have to spend in general and it's
sorry when I say projections document, it's not just projections, it's all the
cash in all the cash out and then this sort of runway calculation. So this
this other part is expenses which are broken down based on monthly or annual
expenses or per project expenses or simply one time expenses so something
like audio have to pay per project where something like accounting fees,
let's say maybe that's monthly or yearly. So I allow for breaking that
those down into the different categories.
and then when you're doing your actual projections,
you can see the highlighted part here
is how many months ahead do you want to calculate
and how many projects you think you're gonna make.
So you say, okay, 36 months,
we're gonna make two new projects.
So that'll pull the per project costs
and that'll put that in the calculations
and it'll include the monthly costs
based on how many months.
But look at all those tabs.
There's a lot of tabs.
So each tab is a separate chunk.
And I try to make it simpler by having these tabs.
The idea being that each tab can be one chunk.
So salaries, for example, is one tab.
But the power of this was that we have a list of employees
and how much they're being paid.
This isn't actual numbers.
These are just made up numbers.
There's also, so you can see the employee
and how much they're getting paid.
There's also government contributions.
So in Canada and Quebec, there's a certain amount
that you remit to the government for taxes.
I presume that in the US there's similar things.
So it allows you to calculate
by whatever government contribution,
so you can find out how much your company's actually paying
as opposed to just the gross salary.
The other thing is you can put potential raises.
So you're saying, okay, well what if we gave everybody
a raise of this much?
What would that do to our bottom line?
and the other thing is you can put potential place they're thinking okay
what if we hire two employees and we give a raise to one employee
uh... how is that can affect it
and all that gets fed back into the main sheet which gives us our our final
output which is okay you have fourteen months to survive or whatever
So the game projections are done in an interesting way that was done by one of my colleagues, Alex.
And we've sort of argued about it and fixed it throughout the process.
The page looks a little like this.
So the way it works is...
We say if the game is already out, we know how much we've earned one month.
Most games do this sort of, you know, curve down,
and so we assume that our game is going to do the same.
And what we do there is that we can choose if we want a fast decay rate,
so it means it's going to go down very quickly,
or a slower decay rate if we think the game is doing well.
The nice thing with this is that we can actually check back
after each month and say, okay, how are we doing
compared to what we're calling the medium estimate
or the slow estimate?
You can also flip this and just make it immediate.
So it decays immediately, you stop making money forever.
That's the super pessimistic thing you were talking about.
Except that it's interesting to me that we both had a better year two in our major game
than we had a year one, right?
Yes.
And that's why, so actually there's a couple things in the slide that I'm, I guess I have
a couple minutes, I'll go into a bit of detail.
So there are also percent bumps that you can do, so you can say, okay, well we know summer
sale is happening at this point, we expect we're going to make 200% what we usually make.
So then you put that in and that will just bump it and bring it back down to
the same decay that it was using before.
But I believe this is...
Okay, yeah. So it is somewhat complicated looking,
but it does allow us to think of actual scenarios.
So we will think of a scenario that's, like I said before,
hiring two people or giving one person a raise,
or starting a new project, or going to Gamescom and GDC and PAX.
How does that affect us?
And another thing which I didn't mention here
is that there's also for future game projections,
so future game sales, we don't do this decay thing
because it's about as useful to pick a random number
and decay from there as it is to just have an overall.
But there is a sheet on that spreadsheet
that gives you a breakdown of,
you set how much money is going to a publisher,
how much money is going to an investor,
how much money is going to the platforms
that are taking their cut.
and then you can see how many copies of games you have to sell at what price to
be able to make a certain amount of money. So there's just this big table and
you can kind of find out like, oh, if we're selling our game at $40, then we
only have to sell half as many and things like that. You can grab this
Cashflow document thing at cleverendeavorgames.com slash cashflow or
I wrote a Gamasutra article about this that was just sort of a really short
blurb and it links to this website as well.
It'll also be on the last slide.
Yeah, it'll be on the question slide as well.
And as Tanya was saying, it's kind of hard
to know how your sales are going to be
in the future, which makes this an interesting endeavor.
You can see our launch was the first little tiny blip, which
is somewhat rare.
When you look at most games, the launch is obviously higher,
and they scale down.
Ours launched really tiny.
there for summer sales big and then our next winter sales even bigger and
somehow our winter sale after the game was almost two years old was better
than our winter sale after the game was one year old with the same discount.
So there's a lot of things I mean at that point the game was probably more
popular more people who had wish listed it and so on but the point is that
it's not always it's not standard across the board for sure.
And it's always good to be pessimistic because you never
know if your second year winter sale for some reason
is going to do better than the first one or significantly
worse.
So there are some pros and cons to this.
So one of the pros is that you can see where you can save
money.
When I say pros and cons to this,
I mean going in depth about this.
And that is, like I said, you'd flip one employee on or off,
and you can see how much extra money
you're going to spend or save.
The other thing is you can understand your sort of short term decisions.
So if we go to PAX this year, how much is that actually going to cost us in terms of
months of survival?
You can also think about longer term strategy.
So that was again with employees or starting several projects at once or going into a new
office space.
On the other hand, it takes time,
and there is certainly a strong argument to be made
for maybe you should spend your time making better games,
and they're gonna sell however they sell.
So that's definitely an argument that can be valid.
The other thing is that we're never actually sure.
This isn't a super reliable thing.
Like we said before,
you can't predict five years into the future.
But we like doing it at Clever Endeavor.
Tiny doesn't like doing it quite as much,
but they still do some amount.
And I think that across the board,
regardless you should be thinking about this
and you should be doing these projections,
the level of detail is, of course, up to you.
So, how do we wrap this all up?
So, oh, that's incorrect.
So regardless of how you feel, I do think that it is important as a business owner to
think about what strategies you're going to have.
And even beyond strategy, I actually think that it's maybe most important to keep your
eyes open and stay reactive to what opportunities come available because that is definitely
the most common thing across both of our strategies.
is that we were opportunistic in some way.
We had an amazing opportunity and we had to keep,
we had to do that.
Whether it was me jumping on Moon Hunters
or it was doubling down on the success
of Ultimate Chicken Horse,
you really have to respond when you get new information.
So I mean, different studios obviously
have different methods, different goals,
different constraints.
There's no one right way to run your company.
And I think anyone who claims otherwise
is trying to sell you something.
But as a business owner to other potential business owners,
treat your employees well.
Maybe allow them to unionize.
And think carefully about why you're doing what you're doing.
Calculate your costs, your risks, your consequences.
And you'll have a strategy that works for you
and for your team to achieve your goals.
Thank you.
All right, so we have time for one or two questions.
There are microphones there and there, but if you leave, I'm not hurt at all.
So please, any questions?
This is mostly for Tanya. Do you find it hard to resist kind of or do you feel pressure to
Keep investing in your existing games and like do the games as a service thing and how do you sort of resist that and make?
Sure, you're putting resources into your new game
For Moon Hunters, we did end up reinvesting quite a bit.
We were porting it to multiple platforms,
and even when it wasn't selling very well,
we had decided to make a free DLC
for six months after that.
And part of that was that we didn't want to leave it
in a state that we weren't proud of it.
So that was kind of an emotional, like, can we survive making this thing?
Yes, then we probably should because otherwise we'll just have this project that we're always kind of embarrassed by, whereas now
I don't, I don't feel that way. I mean, I'm not gonna go around saying it's the perfect game,
but I'm not embarrassed by it, and that was more important to me. I think
It is a question of personality,
whether you enjoy LiveOps or hate it.
I personally enjoy LiveOps.
My first few jobs were on Live MMOs, actually.
I was hired onto Age of Conan right as it launched,
and it was the best job ever.
So I don't have a good answer for you,
except that some reinvestment is probably wise.
And obviously for us, porting to different platforms
has definitely been helpful for us
and making those business relationships.
Every time we've released on a new console,
our Steam sales have boosted.
So for us, we've decided that simultaneous launch,
although it's common wisdom, is not best for us
because our community is fractured
and it's all over the place,
and by having it have new news cycles
and press cycles and influencer cycles,
we can actually make our primary platform, Steam,
sell better.
Yes, I should also add it is an opportunity thing, right?
Like we're continuing this because the game's doing well.
If it wasn't, if it tanked, then we would say,
well, forget it, we're onto the next thing.
Not to say a game that is doing badly
can't be sort of revived,
but it is like we talked about, really an opportunity thing.
Let's go on this side this time.
Well, first of all, thank you for your talk.
My name is Nacho, like the Mexican food.
Anyhow, I have a quick question regarding ecosystems,
for instance.
I, I am from Mendoza, Argentina, right? Uh, and one of the issues we have over there is
that our ecosystem doesn't provide any sort of help. So, uh, the only solution that we
have is bootstrapping. Uh, uh, how would you say, uh, uh, I mean, is bootstrapping for real
the only option we got down there, for instance?
I mean, there's Kickstarter, there's, I mean,
every country has the idea of loans,
but it depends how favorable they will be
and who they will lend to, obviously.
There's also the idea of starting working part-time or working full-time while working
on your project part-time, a lot of people do, to get started.
And then sometimes that, again, it's a different ecosystem, but in our ecosystem, if you have
something that you can show, that's a lot more likely to get some publisher attention
or someone who can put some money into it.
So maybe the project starts part-time or remote or something, and then you're at a point where
you might be able to more favorably get a loan.
Like one of the most common ways to survive for a studio that we almost never talk about is work for hire
Which is taking some or all of your employees and working on someone else's game and they pay you to do it
And that gives you experience it gives you contacts and it can level your team up a bit
The problem is getting those contracts when you haven't made a single game together before is very difficult.
Because like me, I wouldn't contract you out, I wouldn't give you money to do work for hire until you've made a game.
So before making your first game, one thing that we didn't mention on any of our slides
is the fact that we can't account for the number of studios that have closed.
Like that Montreal Studios thing, like those are six studios who still exist.
as opposed to all the studios that probably almost existed
and then didn't.
So short answer is that yes,
it is absolutely much harder in some studios,
or some cities and some locations,
and Montreal is maybe an ideal place in a lot of ways.
But if you can't bootstrap,
definitely find money wherever you can
and think about what services you can provide
to other people and businesses.
Well, thank you very much.
Thank you.
Welcome.
Thanks for the talk, guys.
It was really cool.
I had some questions about early investment,
and the projection stuff was really neat,
but when you were meeting early on with investors,
what kind of breakdown were they looking for?
How much of that was on the creative side?
How much of that was, hey, can we see your projections?
Do they feel accurate to us?
So for us it was really, it was a standard program actually for both the VEC-ish thing
and the Execution Labs incubator thing.
They were both a situation where they had a certain amount of money set aside for these
kinds of profiles and then I just had to convince them I was that profile.
So like the more information I could get about what they wanted to hear was the best.
And in those cases, I mean, they assume that it's all going to be payroll.
Like, they know that you're not going to spend all this money on a Lamborghini or whatever.
So it really wasn't about, like, tell me exactly where this dollar is going.
It was more like, how much are you paying yourselves?
How many people do you have for how long?
And they can do it in their own head to figure out, like,
oh, if you pay yourself minimum wage, this will last you this long.
If you pay yourself normal salary, it'll last you this long.
And that's kind of...
been fine. I mean even for fairly late stage like publisher money it was still
kind of what is your burn rate was the number one question rather than how much
are you spending on audio or whatever.
And I should say, when we were pitching investors,
so we ended up actually having a fortunate situation.
We had a family friend investor, and then a bunch of family
sort of jumped on.
And so we got favorable terms, but we still
did the full pitch thing.
And for us, the big thing was comparing other games that
are out already and comparing their sales and saying, OK,
if we do badly, then we're sorry.
There are some that did really, really badly,
and we think this is why.
there are some that did fairly badly
and you'll make your money back
and this is what will happen if we do fairly badly.
And this is the upshot.
So it's kind of like show the probable situation
and then sell the dream
and they understand that that's the dream
but that's what they're investing in, right?
So there's the burn rate
and then there's what you think you're gonna make.
And if you have comparisons,
I mean, Boyfriend Dungeon will be harder
because there's not as much comparison
but in our case, it was a lot easier to find games
that were like, well, here's seven games that are similar
that have all done this well.
Oh, I absolutely told a venture capitalist at some point
that we were intending to grow to 100 people
and that was a total lie.
But thank you, it was put to good use.
Yeah, so we are past time, so thank you very much.
We will take more questions over here.
Thank you!