All right, so good morning everybody,
and thank you very much for joining me
on the talk about Hitman Go.
At this point I would like to remind you
to turn your cell phones on silent mode,
and also please don't forget to fill out
the speaker evaluation at the end
to tell GDC how awesome or how bad this talk was, I guess.
So this talk is gonna be a postmortem
on the game Hitman Go, but at the same time
I'm gonna try and document the creative process
a little bit that went into the making of this game.
A little bit of an introduction about myself.
I'm Daniel, I'm a game director with Square Enix Montreal.
Before that I used to work as a designer
for both Square and EA.
And at the same time I'm kind of an independent developer
on the side in my spare time.
I ship these three games by myself.
They're iOS games if you want to check them out.
And so to tell the story about Hitman Go,
I think we have to look at three things.
We have to look at the circumstances
that allowed this project to happen.
We have to look at the idea that initially started off
the project, and we have to look at a process that refined
this idea into the game that is now
downloadable on the App Store.
And to be honest with you, the circumstances,
this is not really the story that I can tell.
This is the story of management, I guess,
of studio management that allowed this project to happen.
And I was not part of that at that point.
But I still want to give you a little bit of an introduction,
a little bit of an overview to give you
the necessary information.
And so the story starts here with Square Enix.
In 2012, the summer, the winter of 2011, 2012,
Square Enix decided to start a new studio in Montreal,
and someone had this brilliant idea to turn up,
side down, the E from the Square Enix logo,
and make an M out of it.
I always thought that was pretty brilliant.
And so it was the winter of 2011, 2012,
and there was a new studio to be started.
And for that, three people from IO Interactive,
Mez, Karsten, and Rasmus, who used to work on Hitman games
and who had also worked on Kane and Lynch.
They relocated to Montreal to start this new studio
and hire people.
And I was lucky enough to be one of the first hires
and within a year or so, I guess,
we had grown to around 40 people.
Yeah, you can see this is cold Montreal in the winter,
that's what it looks like.
And so our mandate was to make a AAA Hitman game
for consoles, this was in 2012,
so this was still when current generation consoles
weren't announced, so this was a very exciting moment.
I was working on this as a designer.
But as you know, plans, they don't always turn out
as you expect them to.
And so after about a year of development of this game,
our project was canceled.
And furthermore, Square Enix decided to turn our studio
from a AAA development studio
into a mobile game development studio.
And as you might expect, this is quite a drastic change
and this kind of shakes up things quite a bit.
But I'm pretty happy to say that management
did a very good job at kind of transitioning
from AAA into the mobile space.
There was a lot of changes, as you might expect.
Some people lost their jobs.
A lot of them actually just left
because they didn't want to make mobile games.
But at the same time, again, I think this transition
was as smooth as you can possibly make it
with these circumstances.
At the same time, I think this was a pretty exciting moment
for everybody because getting to start working
on something new is always exciting
and management realized that and they started
what they called an incubation moment.
So they allowed everybody in the team,
everybody in the studio to come up with ideas
for mobile games within the Square Enix brands.
And we started off with Hitman.
And they called this the incubation
and basically everybody could participate
and make their own games.
And so the mandate was to come up with an idea
for a mobile Hitman game.
Really, this was the top level kind of idea.
And there was not many constraints around it, right?
So we were almost giving carte blanche on this one.
We could come up with our own ideas to whatever
we thought was good to make this game.
As I said before, not many constraints
other than it has to be mobile
and it has to be a Hitman game.
And as you might expect in these kind of situations,
we're always kind of inclined to think outside the box
and come up with crazy things
and be really creative.
But at the same time, I have to say that I think there was a sense of false optimism amongst us in that studio,
even though we were very excited about making and tackling this new platform,
we believed that we were the pros, right? There were around 40 people of AAA developers.
We thought we knew it all, and that mobile was some sort of thumbed-down version of what we were doing,
and this could not be very hard.
And so we thought we're going to be shipping a game within six months of the initial pitch.
And so incubation began.
And I guess my experience as an independent developer
also brought me to this point.
I really like to work with strong constraints on projects.
I find it very hard to start off
with a blank piece of paper.
And so I was looking for constraints.
And again, I think independent game suit us very well.
They're very aware of.
the kind of limitations that they have,
be it resources or creative constraints.
And I think one great example for that
is the game jams, where a lot of games
are actually created out of one single theme
or constraint by themselves.
But these constraints can be very arbitrary, right?
We would not want to make a Hitman game based on the color blue, for example, right?
This could be a game jam thing, but for Hitman it wouldn't make that much sense.
And so, I guess I was looking for more meaningful constraints and constraints that were related to the mandate.
And so in research for this talk and kind of trying to see
if this is something that's also applied outside
of video games, I came across a very interesting quote
by Charles Eames, who was, as most of you know,
one of the very most important industrial designers
of the 20th century.
Together with his wife, Ray, they were probably best known
for a series of furniture that has become truly iconic today.
And so Charles Eames.
In 1972, when asked about, I think it was a Q&A or an interview,
when asked about if there's constraints to the design process, he says,
design depends largely on constraints.
And so this was in 1972.
Please note how I skillfully constrained Mr. Eames' right eye in the letter P there.
That's pretty meta.
So he says, design depends largely on constraints.
And furthermore, here's one of the few effective keys
to the design problem, the ability of the designer
to recognize as many of the constraints as possible,
his willingness and enthusiasm for working
with these constraints, the constraints of price,
of size, of strength, balance, of surface, of time, et cetera.
And then he says, each problem has its own peculiar list.
And I thought that was pretty great,
because even though I didn't know about this at the time,
us working on the Hitman mobile games,
I thought this was pretty close to the actual mindset
that we were in at the time.
And so again, he talks about price, size, strength,
surface, balance, time, et cetera.
And we can imagine him talking about furniture
or industrial design, and maybe even about this chair here,
dining chair that's beautiful, beautiful furniture.
But the question is, is this really that far away?
Is this really that different, making a chair,
considering all these constraints from making a game,
or in our case, making a Hitman game on mobile platforms?
And obviously, as indicated by Charles Eames,
a lot of these constraints depend really on the product that you make.
And I think, in this case, size, strength, balance and surface,
all these kind of material properties that don't really make sense
when we're talking about games.
we can substitute them, we can come up with other things.
And I think price and time, I think we can keep them.
Maybe like consumer facing things,
such as how much is the game going to cost?
How long is the game going to be playable?
Like what's the playtime of the game?
But then more importantly, we can, using this model,
we can add different constraints.
We can add.
probably the most important constraint is the brand, right?
We're working with a brand that is very established,
that has gone through many iterations
that have come out in different platforms before,
and a genre that comes attached to it.
A very important constraint, obviously, the platform
that we're gonna make a mobile game after all.
An audience that has expectations
towards what we're building.
And production constraints, very important.
We were a studio of AAA developers
ready to ship the game within six months.
And obviously other things such as business models.
So I guess this list can really go on and on,
but this is kind of just laying out
the key important things that you wanna consider.
And so I guess to illustrate this idea a little bit better,
we can take this chair and instead of having
this beautiful DCW chair here,
we can come up and think about different chairs
that don't really do that this well.
And so we can think about a chair
that doesn't have a surface to sit on, for example,
which seems silly, but it might be
very pleasing to look at, right?
If it's well done, it might be very beautiful.
Another good thing about this would be that it would probably be cheaper than building a regular chair
because we would need less material but at the same time it would have very low usability, right?
We could not sit on it.
Maybe as a product of art this might be interesting.
If I was an artist I could build this chair.
But as a designer I don't think this would fit any of the needs that this product would have.
And so the same thing going back to Hitman.
We can come up with some very quick ideas.
For example, we could make a Hitman endless runner.
would probably work pretty well on the platform,
on mobile platforms, but it would greatly conflict
with brand identity, and to be honest,
it would also be kind of aiming for the wrong audience.
And maybe another example could be
if we made a port kind of thing
where we used like a third person.
point of view with virtual joysticks on mobile.
This would probably come pretty close
to the original experience that people know from Hitman.
It would have very low usability
and I guess also would be kind of the wrong platform
because people that want to play these games,
I guess they play them on consoles.
And so kind of just laying out these constraints here,
you note that I put four of them in black.
I think depending on how you work or what you focus on,
you can really empathize certain things
and also depending on the product that you're building.
But for us, I think the main important constraints
really were platform, brand, audience, and production.
I didn't put business model in black there
because right from the beginning,
it was clear that we're gonna make a premium product.
And so we didn't have to really work with that
during the development.
And so the question here is how can we use these constraints to come up with a great idea and a great product?
And unfortunately I don't think we can, because what we're looking at is a pure top-down model.
This is a pure analytic and strategic and also very rational model.
I think this is pretty interesting to look at it that way, but this really doesn't lead to any ideas,
at least in my case I don't think that led to any ideas.
And what we're looking at is more like a set of tools
that allow us to evaluate the creative developments.
And as you probably expect, the very contrary approach
to this would be a bottom-up approach,
where we're looking at a more experimental and random,
and also maybe personal and intuitive
kind of way of building things.
that has kind of the idea to become the raw material
of what we're working with.
And so you've probably heard this before
and you've probably seen GDC talks about,
or any other talks about this kind of top-down
and bottom-up approach, which is very popular
in many different fields, not just game design.
And it's really this idea of top-down evaluation
and bottom-up creation.
And there's many different ways of putting it,
top-down, converging thinking,
versus bottom-up diverging and making.
But the way I like to call it is being smart and being stupid.
And so this doesn't mean smart and stupid in a sense
that you have to be dumb and smart,
but more smart and stupid in a sense
that you have to have this high-level approach
where you have to consider as many things as possible
and being stupid and kind of reckless sometimes
to come up with ideas that seem impossible
or seem out of the beaten path.
And I think Diesel did a very cool campaign at some point.
They had this kind of photographs
of people doing weird things.
And they always had these taglines kind of building
on that saying, smart critiques, stupid creates.
Or this one, stupid might fail, smart doesn't even try.
And so, kind of building on that, we needed an idea for a game.
And for that, I decided to be completely stupid and bought him up.
And at the time, I was talking to my friend and colleague, Antoine,
who became the technical director of the game.
I told him, listen, I got this all figured out.
I know how mobile games are made.
There's only two types of mobile games that need to be made.
Only two types.
Very simple.
There's games that have a very short individual session,
so games like Temple Run that are in real time,
but failing at Temple Run doesn't really matter
because you can just replay.
And it's really this overall, this big level goal
of grinding coins, of the meta game that makes it important.
So you can play this in between two bus stops,
and even if you get interrupted,
it doesn't really matter so much
because every session is kind of replaceable
with another one.
And on the other hand, there's turn-based games
like Triple Town.
turn-based games that obviously wait for the user to interact with it and so we
can put them down, pick them back up easily and we don't get interrupted for
anything. And since I didn't feel like making a kind of fast-paced game and I
think Hitman is more like a strategic and smart game in a sense, I think
turn-based was a great inspiration and so I said let's make a turn-based Hitman
game.
And this is probably looking pretty stupid, there's no kind of rational thought behind this.
And also looking at it today, believing that there's only two types of mobile games is a pretty silly idea,
but I think at the point, at the time we were building this, this was enough of an inspiration,
kind of initial spark to get started on something.
So we said turn-based simplified Hitman.
That was going to look like The Sims.
Top-down, 3D, lots of characters, lots of details, fully animated.
Because why not?
And so we had to be smart.
We were, as I said, we were working
in this incubation moment.
We had to convince our colleagues,
and then later down the line, the GL board,
about making this game.
And so we came up with this strategy of saying
we want to make a game, a Hitman game,
that's basically based on three things.
We want to base it off making a highly accessible game,
so a game that you can pick up and play
without knowing anything about the game.
the previous experiences, the previous Hitman games,
but at the same time, you want to make a deep game,
a game that has the full Hitman experience,
that really starts off simple,
but gets more complicated and more interesting as you go,
and a game that has very high production value,
because we are Square Enix,
and people have expectations towards what we build.
And that worked pretty well.
People really liked the idea at the studio,
and then later we were allowed to go to Greenlight with it,
and within a short amount of time,
actually, we managed to go into development of the game.
And so we entered this kind of process,
and I guess even before that,
we did this kind of round of prototypes,
so there was four people.
And during two weeks, we built this prototype,
actually iterating a lot,
building a lot of different prototypes,
but it's this one prototype that really led everything.
And for that, again, taking a very bottom-up
and stupid approach, coming up with game mechanics,
was what we tried to do.
And so, having worked about a year, I guess,
on big AAA Hitman game,
we identified these five things that were essential
to the Hitman gameplay experience.
And you might say this is pretty dumbed down and stupid again,
but again, I think this is just to prove the point that
something seemingly silly can spark an idea and interest
into something that you then later can refine.
So what we kind of dissected, what we distilled
from the Hitman experience was that there's five things.
There's Agent 47, there's a target I have to assassinate,
there's enemies that can try and stop me
from getting to my target.
There's an environment that I can be in, or that my enemies can be in,
and there's tools that I can use.
So this could be weapons, this could be simple things like patrol paths, and so forth.
And because we had this kind of box full of these kind of board game pieces around at the office,
we thought it would be a great idea to kind of use that and to rapidly prototype ideas
before we even went into coding anything.
And so, inspired by The Sims, we printed out these kind of architectural visualizations
of apartments, these renderings, and I remember drawing like little dots with lines on top
of it, and then starting to move around these kind of wooden pieces around, and hoping that
we would come up or stumble upon a great idea for a game design.
And it didn't work.
And I think, looking back, I think that was mainly because of one reason, and it was,
the reason for it was this very piece.
And if you look at it, it might not be obvious, but when you think about stealth games, one
very important thing about stealth games is the notion of being seen.
or being hidden. So in this case Hitman is hiding behind the corner there and two
characters can't see him but if you look at our board game piece this guy has no
direction so what we realized after a while is that we had to give these
pieces a facing direction basically. We didn't add googly eyes like I did on
this one but I remember putting some some paper pieces on top of it to kind
of start playing with that notion of direction.
And that was a pretty simple learning,
but I think it greatly helped us
to come up with a game design.
Because this kind of standard stealth game material,
we started off with using vision cones, right?
I remember Dishonored came out around about the time
when we shipped, when we started working on this game,
and they had this really cool 3D visualization of view cones.
And so obviously, I guess this and many other games
influenced us into starting to work with these things.
And we thought that was pretty great,
and that we had found a pretty good game design
for our project, but obviously it wasn't the case.
Especially in a scenario like this, if we expect the blue character to turn to the right,
it becomes very hard for the player to know which one of these kind of spots is going to be hidden
and which one of these is going to be detected.
So unless we get measuring tape out or we start to do some crazy calculations, we can't really know.
And this is something we really didn't want.
We really wanted to not have in our game.
We wanted it to be deterministic for people to really understand what's going on
and to really learn from.
the mechanics and I guess in this case A would not be seen and B would be kind of
in between so again would be too complicated and so we simplified it and
we came to this conclusion that just aligning the pawns on the grid
So basically on the nodes and the lines that go outside of it
would be a great idea.
And we were pretty happy with it.
And we thought we had found a great design for our game.
But obviously, this is not the end of the story.
Because as soon as we started playing around
with more complicated and more interesting AI,
like this guy here that actually ended up being in the game.
as we shift, the guy that walks back and forth in a straight line
seems fairly straightforward, especially in this case.
I guess we can imagine the blue guy going up and down on this axis there.
But what if there's a more complicated case like this one?
Do we expect the blue guy, after moving forward,
to be expecting to move left and right, left or right?
or maybe you can go back.
And I think even though we could have come up
with some sort of rule and programmed that rule
and mechanic, kind of a hidden logic,
we wanted to be visible for the user, right?
We could have said, like, if there's a certain angle
that has to be satisfied, or if there has to be
some sort of a flow, right?
We could always say, character turns right
if he can't go forward, but we didn't want to do this.
We wanted to be as simple and straightforward as possible
because...
Again, looking at it from a top-down view,
considering platform and audience,
we're looking at small screens,
and we're looking at people who have possibly
never played complicated games before.
We went with this more simplified approach
and said, just straighten it out.
And then, I guess, at the end,
coming up with this very simple and distilled way
of creating the mechanics for the game.
And we thought that was pretty great.
And spoiler alert, I guess if you've played the game,
this is pretty close to what the game design ended up being.
And even though you might say that this is very simple
and almost a bit bland, I think working on this
so intensely and actually simplifying it
and building it down so much helped us building this core
that actually held up up until,
actually throughout the whole production of the game.
And so this was really the most basic building block
that we used to build it.
And from there we could extrapolate and we could come up with all these cool mechanics
that existed in stealth games and in hitman games and we could then fuel them back into
our experience.
And so we added distractions, we added civilians, social stealth like hiding in a crowd, trespassing,
disguises, multiple player pawns, weapons, hacking and so on.
But obviously a lot of these didn't work out.
throughout the iteration, trial and error, I guess,
prototyping many things, we found out that a lot of these
things actually didn't work from a brand perspective,
or were too complicated, or just not feasible,
or just out of scope for the project that we had.
But we added new ones, and we did cycle kind of
a couple of times, and I guess this is how
the set of mechanics that you played today
in Hitman Go came to happen.
And so again, four guys working two weeks,
I guess this core was really built within two weeks
on one prototype, and then later we extrapolated from that.
There's only one elephant in the room, which was The Sims.
We had promised to make a game that was beautifully animated
and fully 3D and everything, but we came to realize
that we had to be smarter about it in terms of production.
If we had six months to build this game
and we had already kind of a cool design,
we would never be able to make and ship this game
within the time constraints that were established.
And so looking at the material that we were playing with
to kind of prototype and come up with the idea,
we thought that this would be a great idea
to kind of simplify also in terms of scope.
And we used this board game aesthetic
to kind of come up with a better scope for the game.
And this was great because we didn't need animations,
we could work with static environments,
and there was no SFX needed.
And at the same time, this kind of...
just opened up a lot of new ideas, again, very bottom up.
We came up with this diorama and scale model vision
that just was very related to the board games.
And so we went into kind of figuring out
what our direction could be.
Again, pretending to be very stupid and very bottom up,
looking at these scale models, and I think
Yeah, I think when looking at these,
it is very tempting to just go crazy and say,
we want to build these beautifully modeled
and beautifully lush environments
with a lot of characters.
And obviously the first thing you see
if you Google these kind of images
is a lot of these kind of train sets
that I guess grown men build in their apartments
and then forbid their kids to touch them.
And I think that was cool, right?
It was a great inspiration, but at the same time,
again, being smart, looking at it from a brand perspective,
it didn't exactly work.
Even though there was some potential in it,
I think it still felt a little bit too nerdy
and a bit too obscure for what we're trying to build.
And so, working with Rasmus, who was the old art director
on the AAA game, who had experience working at IO,
and then also with the people still at IO,
I think we managed to kind of get to know the brand
much better, and really distill down the essence
of what Hitman means and what Hitman is.
And there's a couple of things that really struck with us.
So there's this kind of notion of globe trotting,
hitman traveling around the world
to these kind of exotic locations and luxurious mansions
that he has to go and take out this evil people
that he has to assassinate.
And then there's things like sterile environments,
like even though these people have these huge mansions,
some of them are pretty empty and it's kind of boring,
as you expect from rich people's places.
And there's this very interesting notion of voyeurism
in stealth games in general.
So.
if you're navigating an environment and you're not seen,
that allows you to overhear and eavesdrop on conversations
of people and NPCs that don't expect you to do so.
And I think if you've played stealth games before,
again, this is a very big thing.
I think especially in Hitman, they used this to.
Tell these kind of weird and funny stories every once in a while you overhear something
So there's the story in absolution
There's this moment where you hear a guy on a phone talking about his doctor and getting a note that he is not
Ill or he's not sick
And the minute later you throw him out of the window. So there's this kind of weird
funny notation of voyeurism and also this kind of rational cold kind of
atmosphere to to assassinating people I guess in general and on top of that this
really understated and slick feel that Hitman games have.
And we really thought that we need to capture this better
instead of just building a train set,
or train model environment,
and really get to know what HIPMAM was.
And here's, I guess, the four inspirations
that we then used to really come closer
to this brand identity.
And the first one was architectural models.
And so, instead of just looking at scale models
and these kind of little figurines,
we really like the aesthetic of architectural models
because it's more about a global
and a more approximate kind of way of building something.
It's more about materials, it's more about shapes,
much more than just details and little things.
And if you see an architectural model,
maybe once in a while there's a little detail,
there's a figurine, but it's mostly there
just to indicate scale and it's not there to tell a story.
And then there's the voyeuristic nature of these kind of
stealth games that I thought still could be portrayed
pretty well with the scale models.
If you look at these kind of dioramas,
you always see these freeze frames,
freeze frame scenarios of people talking,
of people arguing, or people just enjoying themselves.
And so you could almost like see how you could
interpret that as.
watching people doing things and kind of watching on them.
And then obviously the rational, cold thing
that we kind of learned from chess and board games
in general, very calculated, just moving pawns
on the check board like you would in Hitman.
It's basically playing puppeteering and engineering,
I guess, situations around.
And then last but not least, the luxurious and sterile
that we borrowed from the blog Rich Kids of Instagram.
I don't know if you're familiar with that, but it's a pretty great Tumblr.
It's basically a curating site.
My friend Eric, who was a narrative designer in the old AAA days, had got me onto this
and it's truly brilliant.
You should check it out.
It's basically kids from very rich backgrounds taking pictures and this website curates them
and shows their daily lives.
It's pretty impressive because even though it's a very luxurious lifestyle and it's everything
you can possibly imagine, but at the same time...
there's this kind of bland and sterile look to it
because these places are huge,
they show they're huge houses,
but they're always kind of empty,
it's always the same kind of goods,
it's always the same cars,
it's always the same purses and so forth,
so it's really worth checking out.
And so having that, we really felt like we had
a really solid base, but again, making that happen
was not just a matter of art direction,
but it was actually a matter of producing levels
and producing level art.
And so, again, just to emphasize this kind of
two-tiered approach of being bottom-up
and being top-down at the same time,
we were greatly inspired by these two main references,
which were architectural models and
scale models, dioramas, and we kind of identified
a couple of cool things, the physicality of things, right?
How are things built?
Is it made out of wood?
Is it made out of cardboard?
And how could we portray these material properties
in the game?
Then there's this idea of variety,
because everything is handmade,
we expect things to not be entirely perfect, right?
Especially if you look at scale models,
there's a lot of this variety going on,
because everything is basically put on by a person.
And there's this kind of imperfection,
something really interesting, artifacts.
If you think about dioramas, especially like things
like paint being scratched off a little bit
through the production of the diorama itself,
or maybe a little bit of glue that sticks out
underneath a grass surface and so forth.
And in general, just adding a lot of detail,
we thought that would be the right way to go
to really portray this view and this vision
of this kind of physical environment.
But again, looking at it from a high level perspective
and considering production,
this was still very much out of scope.
And so, we proposed a very different system.
And I guess this was one of the early sketches I did,
just modeled this quickly for a prototype,
but the idea was to build the entire game
out of these four by four meter cubes,
or blocks, I guess, with different heights.
And as you can see, there's different pieces for pool,
there's pieces for roads, for house,
for grass, and so forth.
And this seemed pretty wacky at the beginning,
but it actually ended up being the exact pipeline
that we did for the game.
And so if you've played the game,
you might recognize some of these places.
So we built entire sets for tennis courts, the greenhouse,
the pool, the mansion, and so forth.
And also, if you've played the game,
you'll notice that we had these different locations.
So we had different boxes of environments.
And for every of these boxes, we build actually a set of pieces.
So it's pretty much like LEGO bricks, actually.
You could just snap them together and play around
with them.
Then on top of that, we had little pieces,
little detail pieces that we could then
add to kind of break up the rhythm
and break up this kind of pattern-like behavior
of the modules.
And I thought that was pretty great
because we could run level art and design in parallel,
right, we were really fast with this
because as I was building the levels in Unity
with this editor that we had,
the level artist could basically model the blocks
and then I could play around
without having too much dependency on each other.
And it also greatly helped us creating this unified look
that I think is always very hard to achieve in games
in general, making something that looks like it's only made
by one person or by one general idea that brings everything
together.
And obeying this very strict system
helped us greatly to achieve that.
And even though it is kind of hard to work with,
I think also again, constraint on a very low level,
it applied these very interesting constraints
that I guess were very inspiring also for us
to come up with different locations,
different sets, different environments and so forth.
And so this is I guess a couple of screenshots to show you.
how this actually worked in an applied sense.
So this is the screenshot from the editor, Barebones.
I guess we had this really cool tool
that the programmers built,
where we could just place out these little circles
and connect them with lines.
And then on top of that, we replaced the pawns,
I guess the spawners for the pawns
and the spawners for the tools,
like the distraction you see here.
And then obviously the extraction point
where Hitman has to go to.
And then the next step would be take all of these pieces
and kind of play with it and arrange them a little bit
and start coming up with a cool environment.
Obviously doing a lot of iterations to this,
considering the different environments that were before
and the levels before and after,
but really starting to play Lego with this.
And once we were happy with a certain design,
we kind of put that closer together,
added a little bit more detail,
like this wooden frame that became pretty iconic
to the game, and maybe a bit more detail,
like the grass hedges there.
And then later on we would add more small detail like the trees
The little figurines that would tell kind of the story going on and so forth
And then the last step would be to just light the levels with lightmap
classic lightmaps, I guess
And so really this kind of initial model
of focusing on physicality, focusing on high variety
and then artifacts and a lot of detail everywhere,
kind of was refined into a model
that was more focusing on composition,
especially because of the modules,
the modular system you had the chance to be very iterative
and to do a lot of different, just trial and error,
a lot of different variations on these levels.
And so we really got to work with this.
and at the same time capturing that idea
from the freeze frame life from scale models
and really putting in these characters,
trying to tell a little bit of a story,
a little bit of an environment.
Working with cross sections, like you can see there,
the pool being cut in half, I think is a very strong
kind of image and makes people really think about this
as a manufactured object or something that you would have
on your coffee table or maybe in a showcase and so forth.
And instead of having detail all over the place,
we actually decided to be way more selective about it.
And so even though, one thing that's quite interesting,
even though a lot of people consider Hitman Go
to be a very naturalistic-looking game,
there's actually only one texture, as far as I remember,
that is truly naturalistic, which is this wood piece.
Everything else is either untextured or has textures
that have nothing to do with the original material
that we're trying to emulate, for example.
the grass, I think it's a sort of a carpet
that just looked really good on the screen
and on what we're trying to do with it.
And this helped us greatly with readability, right?
Again, looking at it from the constraints
about the platform, we wanted this game
to be able to be played on small screens
and on tablets, and so having high readability
was really important for us, and I guess
focusing on these things helped us manage
to create a game that was very readable.
And so there's one last anecdote, I guess,
before I want to wrap things up.
And so, a very important thing, I guess,
to making AAA games transition into mobile games,
which is the story aspect.
And this is a pretty tough one,
because as you might expect,
AAA games focus a lot on story,
and mobile games don't do so as much.
And so again, being very bottom-up in this field,
whoops, sorry, we looked at our inspiration again.
And again, as I mentioned it before,
these kind of little figurines, these stories,
like this car that broke down
and the guy's trying to explain to a police officer
and the boy's doing something in the background.
This is just a moment of life
and we can totally come up with a story in our head
after we watch these.
And we were greatly inspired again by this.
And at the same time, I mentioned that we had
these modular systems that were developing pretty quickly
and we were really inspired to just play around,
bottom up, be very stupid as I would call it,
and come up with cool ideas.
And so we created this set of pieces of blocks
that were based around roads and networks.
And so you can see here, this is like a suburban kind of environment with a lot of roads, street signs, and these trees growing in between the lanes and so forth.
And we thought that would be a really cool testbed for our ideas with stories.
So the initial idea was to have these kind of developing stories from multiple levels.
And so on this one we did a test where we wanted to have like a car accident,
like this guy is trying to get away and you're following him on a...
highway and then he crashes and he tries to run away and at some point in some
level you would actually then get to kill him. And there's something that was
really interesting is that no one really understood that we did a test with this
and no one really got the coherence between different levels right no one
understood there was like a continuous story going on in between levels
I think it's hard to say why that's the case,
but I think it's also just because people are very focused
on solving the puzzles much more
than just observing the environment
and also kind of breaking these kind of abstract pieces
apart from each other
and not having one continuous experience
because you go through loading
and level selection every time.
It just didn't allow people to understand these stories.
And I guess one great example for this is something that we only refer to as the
gas station at Square Enix Montreal, which is kind of this weird thing that
everybody fears. And so this was I guess our idea to make an entire mission, this
was supposed to become the first mission of the game, an entire mission about a hit
and assassination that you would have to do around the gas station. And you can
see this was not just environment art, we also did game design on it, we had these
kind of notes.
And you can even see like, yeah,
obviously it looks a bit different now,
but it's pretty close already to the experience we have.
And so the idea here was that Hitman had to infiltrate
this kind of gas station environment
where it was this guy that you had to go and kill.
And there's two things, like for one, Hitman was able to go through the sewers, as you can see there.
That was pretty weird, I don't know why we came up with this.
And then the other thing was, in the top right corner you see this kind of soda machine.
We thought that maybe coming up with a story where you would have to follow a guy who would really like soda,
and he would drink these cans of soda, and would leave a trail behind him
to kind of explain people why you would follow a person's kind of like breadcrumbs.
Yeah, I don't know why, but this is what we tried to do.
And so we had to ask ourselves, is this really Hitman?
And especially, I guess, looking at the AAA counterparts,
this was not Hitman as in infiltrating these luxurious
and exotic places, trying to kill the top evil people
in the world, but not doing that.
It was, in our case, it was Hitman on the beach.
trying to bypass a guy in blue there,
but can't do that because there's traffic cones on the road.
Yeah, this was actually a level that we built.
And so again, I think looking at it
from a high-level perspective,
even though I think that there's a lot of great development
and a very creative kind of atmosphere around this,
but looking at it from a high-level perspective,
it just didn't fit with the brand.
And so Rasmus, again the art director in the AAA days,
he made the sketch for us that I think was very important
at this point during the development.
And he kind of took this idea of these little pieces
of levels that we had already built
and he designed a kind of a sketch.
around what he thought a mission or a hit should look like.
And so he did these kind of key moments
in this kind of infiltrating and exfiltrating,
going through a hit, going through an assassination.
So it's this kind of hitman arriving at a gate,
and there's probably security there
that he has to take out,
and going through some sort of a courtyard,
entering a house, there's a watchdog,
and then getting to an office,
taking out the bad guy, and then leaving again.
And this was really, I guess, a cornerstone for us in the development.
And also looking at the game today, I think it's cool to see how we actually used this
and built the levels around it.
So this is the first chapter of the game, a couple of the levels, and then so in the
first one you can see Hitman arriving to this kind of place, to this mansion, and then going
through some sort of a gate.
bypassing this pool area that we've seen in many screenshots now and then, just
all these kind of classic locations that you've probably seen also in other Hitman
games. The tennis court, a little bit of a pool house there on the left, going
through a greenhouse with a lot of guards and then entering a mansion where
finally we get to assassinate our target. So really building up this kind of story
and this approach of Hitman that we also know from existing AAA Hitman games.
And so, I guess, these are kind of four anecdotes to explain a little bit this approach,
this creative strategy of not being afraid of doing seemingly stupid things,
but then again, also not back off from looking at it from a very rational and kind of high-level angle.
And so the game mechanics, the art direction, the story,
and the level art, I think they're all great examples
of how we use this approach to make Hitman go.
And really, as I said in the beginning,
don't be afraid of being smart
and forcing yourself to be stupid every once in a while,
to just kind of not be afraid of coming up with things
that don't seem to be lodging.
And so on a day-to-day basis,
I think this could be really described
as keeping a balance between the two modes, right?
I think Hitmango was recognized as a game that did something that was pretty unorthodox.
A lot of people that saw the game initially, they did not really get what we're trying
to do with it.
But at the same time, I think really keeping this idea of the impulsive and almost intuitive
kind of way of making games, but looking at it and evaluating it from a top-level view,
making sure that these ideas are not just crazy for their own sake, but they actually
make sense within the big picture of the brand, the franchise.
the platform and so forth.
And I guess another example that,
if you're developing games,
you're probably very familiar with is
switching the team to two modes,
bottom-up and top-down.
It's very easy to kind of fall into one of these extremes
and just to kind of stay there.
So if we're top-down too much,
I guess it becomes very easy to just shoot down ideas
because they seem too weird or stupid from the get-go.
And if we're purely bottom-up,
I think it becomes very easy to get lost
and not see the big picture anymore.
And so I guess to wrap up and to kind of come back
where I started with this presentation,
I think now would be the time to see if I actually,
if this actually makes any sense.
So going back to this idea of this comparison
between the chair and the game that we've been building,
looking at Hitman Go on mobile phones
and looking at I guess our four core constraints
that we've established in the beginning.
And so looking at production.
We didn't manage to ship before Christmas 2013 within six months.
I think that was just a little bit too ambitious for everybody involved.
But we were pretty close.
We actually managed to finish the initial release in February 2014, and I think still
today that this, given the fact that we're a AAA development studio and we had very little
experience making mobile games, this was a great achievement.
We managed to stay a small team between four and twelve people throughout the course of
the development.
I think also forcing this kind of dual kind of mode of being top down and bottom up is
something that really works with small teams that I've experienced and I think we really
capitalized on that.
And as I said before, I was actually the only person who had made mobile games before so
I think it was a great achievement for everybody to do this transition to make a successful
game afterwards.
And if we look at the brand, many people actually recognized Hitman Go as a true Hitman game,
even though it seemed so weird at the first time, at the first time we showed it, and people looked at it.
And I think we can also say that it managed to open up, maybe because of that,
managed to open up the franchise to new audiences and bring people that maybe knew about Hitman,
but had never played a Hitman game, and so on.
As far as the platform is concerned...
We managed to ship on phone and tablets at the same time,
even though in the beginning we were actually
just aiming for tablets, this was the mandate,
and then we kind of shifted during production.
And we were extremely lucky to get,
and very happy also to get, Editor's Choice from Apple,
and being very much featured by Apple and Google.
So there was a great recognition for us
doing something specific for the platform
and really working on that.
And last but not least, the audience. As far as the audience is concerned, you might expect AAA fans being a very tough crowd,
especially if you announce that the next installment of your franchise is going to be on mobile games.
And I guess we can look at it this way.
When we announced Hitman Go on February 13th in 2014, we just showed a screenshot and a little bit of text.
This is what NeoGAF looks like on that day.
So a guy saying, what the fuck is this?
term-based strategy hitman just kill me now.
Is this a little too early for April Fools?
Is this a fucking joke?
47 deserves better than this.
I guess this is a classic.
But then, about a month, no sorry,
two months later when we actually shipped the game
and people got their hands on the game
and even very like vocal people.
Same forum, different thread, but after the release,
it looked completely different.
And I think it's kind of a very nice thing
to look at today and to see how people actually
got time to spend with the game
and actually changed their opinion on it.
So we can say, going back to the slide,
very positive direction, reception by a very broad audience.
And we got great reviews and a lot of coverage from press and so forth.
And that's pretty much it.
Thank you very much.
Thanks.
Sorry about that.
So I guess there's a...
A little bit of time, sorry that's very unprofessional.
A little bit of time left for, actually 15 minutes left
if there's any questions.
There's microphones if you have questions
about the development or maybe the idea
of the creative strategy that we applied to it.
Hey.
Hey, first of all, good job on that game.
I really loved it.
Were there any, did you set any constraints on the size of the grid that you were using?
And determine how much people were willing to scroll as far as, you know, looking at the level?
Yeah, actually this was a big part in developing the levels and the design in general.
And I think it's two things, it's basically the size of the level but also the camera
as you mentioned.
And we did a lot of iteration on the camera, actually we started off with a very free form,
like you could pan around, you could rotate and even zoom in and do a lot of controls.
But we felt that it was kind of like not slick enough and it wasn't intuitive enough for
people that maybe weren't experienced gamers.
And so also in the beginning we had a lot bigger levels,
right, we wanted to tell more of an environment,
more of a story, but I guess in kind of a compromise
between the platform, again the constraints of the platform,
looking at that we decided to make these kind of
bite-sized and more smaller levels.
And I think even though you might find a couple of odd ones,
like there's probably levels still there
that are bigger than the average,
I think in general we ended up making these kind of
like four by five kind of, that's probably
the average level that we built.
Hi, can you talk a little bit about the design,
how you designed the puzzles, like the actual
just making them hard logical puzzles to solve?
Sure.
So we had this editor, I think the process
was very important because we didn't really
know much about this, there was not a game
that we could base ourselves off,
there was not a design that we knew
that we could just use and kind of reproduce.
And so I guess in the beginning with these
kind of board game figurines, I think that was
kind of the first moment where we saw
that there was something cool there.
But then I think really the usability of the editors and the tools that we had helped us greatly in kind of just iterating and making a lot of these puzzles.
And I mean it's safe to say we produced a lot of puzzles that were never used in the game and we tested also with playtests.
And so I'm not sure if there's a strict logic
to making these puzzles.
There was a lot of trial and error,
and evaluating, especially in the beginning, right?
But as development goes on,
I think you start to identify these kind of patterns.
So there's, if you play the game,
there's these kind of recurring patterns of puzzles.
Like there's this kind of.
idea of synchronizing characters.
And so this is one thing that we started,
that we kind of realized and we started using
on levels going forward.
And there's kind of a couple of other different patterns
that we kind of emerged from the development
that we then used, but there's no like a black magic
or a secret sauce to this, unfortunately.
I don't know who was next.
I'm curious if there were any discussions about
the business model and
which fitted best with the project or if it just came as a design constraint from the very beginning or
you had any discussions? Sure.
Obviously there were a lot of discussions about this. I think 2013, the summer when we started,
described us the summer of Candy Crush.
Everybody was talking about premium at that point.
and so were we, right? I think that's safe to say.
I think there was a couple of things that really got into the, that made this
decision at the end. There was first of all, there was kind of the brand value,
right? We knew that people playing Hitman games...
they expect like a triple A product,
they pick Spock something that they pay for
and thought that might be a better transition
to start off with a premium product.
But also I think the design that kind of
was built for the game, it really didn't lend itself
for a free to play game, right?
And when you look at free to play kind of puzzle games,
there's this compulsive nature to it,
to many of them and our game was purely.
deterministic so to speak.
So our game was purely reproducible.
Every level, if you played it once,
you can replay it over and over again.
It's always the same solution.
And so there's just this missing component
of randomness and luck that makes a lot
of these free-to-play puzzle games work.
And so at the end, it was really this kind of evaluation
between different business models that made us stick
with, I guess, the original plan of making a premium game.
Thanks Daniel, I loved the end-to-end journey you took us on there, thank you.
Thank you.
You made it sound effortless and I was just wondering if you could share any of those
moments where you were really banging your head against the table and you just thought
this isn't going to work.
No, there was none of that.
No, obviously, I think looking at some of these scenarios,
especially the early days, I think
the story might be the biggest point.
We had very high expectations towards that,
and especially having a full studio of AAA developers.
A lot of them were actually into this whole storytelling
and making that really visible in a game.
And so we had probably too high expectations for that.
And I remember being very frustrated about realizing
that a lot of people didn't really get this kind of
continuity between levels and the story that we're trying
to tell with these little figurines going from one point
to another.
And I think it was hard for us to kind of accept that.
But I think at the end of the day, this is what helped us
to really ship the game and also make the experience that
it became today.
Hey, so, right here.
Sorry.
So you brought me into the Hitman universe, and because of that I'm not really familiar
with the previous Hitman game's sound design.
So I wanted to know what were some of the decisions behind the sound design.
I know it's kind of minimalistic.
There's I think one theme that you hear, like the Ave Maria theme.
Yes.
When you're about to assassinate your target.
I wanted to know why you guys didn't have other themes throughout other levels.
What was the decision behind that?
So you're, I guess you're talking specifically about music, not just the, okay.
And the sound effects as well.
Well I guess to talk about music.
we tried different things and I think it became very clear in the beginning that
this is a very calculated and a very kind of brainy type of game and when you
look at these kind of experience you don't want to have music that just
distracts you too much and everything and so we were really sparse with it
from the get-go.
While we had commissioned music, actually there's this kind of soundtrack that plays in the menus and that we also use throughout the levels as a build-up.
And that worked pretty well. And then at some point we were really looking at different ways of bringing more of that Hitman identity into our game.
And then having this kind of composition actually always works like this.
In a set of levels there's always two guys you have to assassinate.
two levels before that, there's a little bit of a change in music pace, and then the one before that, it really picks up.
And then the last one, where you actually get to assassinate, there's this theme, Ave Maria, right, that was used by Schubert, that was used by
the IO Interactive when they worked on other hit mangas before. So it really was, for us, was a way to connect with the audience
again, and I think a lot of people recognized and really appreciated that.
And maybe about sound design, I think there was this discussion really early on how literal
we wanted to be.
We had this kind of board game idea, aesthetics and everything, so it was very obvious, it
could have been very obvious to say, oh, let's make these sliding pieces moving back and
forth.
But I think James, our sound designer, had kind of great ideas about how to maybe break
that a little bit.
And so I think it became this very interesting blend
between putting sounds on something that you expect,
but also I think there's sounds in there
that don't make any sense, quote unquote.
For example, like when you throw a distraction,
you actually hear a guy being, making a sound like this.
So I think it is this kind of charming mix
of different effects that we ended up
being really happy with.
Thank you.
Thanks for your talk.
One of the really interesting.
player constraints in Hitman Go is the fact that you need to make a physical move each turn.
You need to move to another spot. I was wondering if that's something that you locked in on really early,
or if you did experiments with a weight or something or anything like that.
This is a good question because this came up during development all over and over again.
And so there was almost like these kind of two camps in our team.
So people that believed that there had to be this kind of, I guess inspired by classic Hitman games,
a feature where you had to wait, where you had to be able to wait and kind of just have the situation go on.
And on the other hand, we have the learning that if you make puzzles, you have to make them really tight.
Antoine, actually, I'm a technical director, had this really good analogy.
It's like building a set of IKEA furniture and then at the end having a screw that's left over.
It's a very unsatisfying process, right?
And I think making these puzzles very tight so that you...
feel constrained again, I guess, in that sense,
and don't have the option to kind of just make everything
go back and forth was kind of the obvious choice.
And I guess, especially with the game design,
if you've played the game, there's this,
as I said before, this is kind of synchronous patterns,
right, so if I'm on an odd node,
then all the enemies that are on even nodes,
I can take them out and so forth, and vice versa.
And this was pretty much the foundation of the game design,
and by having
By allowing people to wait on a spot, we basically just would have thrown out this design as a whole, and so we decided to stick with it.
Absolutely. Thank you.
Hi, I was just curious about the, if you have a comparison, profit-wise, for a mobile game, which you're charging $5 for, versus making console games, where you're charging $50.
Sorry, I'm not sure I understood the question.
Sorry, the mic sounds a little weird.
I'm trying, I'm curious.
Give me my phone.
I'm just curious about the profitability
of when you're a mobile game versus a console game,
where you're charging $5 for a mobile game versus how much
you would charge $50 for a.
Okay, I'm not sure I can, I'm really the person to talk about that to be honest, and also I think this being a project of like a publicly traded company, I'm not sure I can really disclose any information.
Again, I worked on this AAA product before, but I wasn't really involved in any of the kind of financial background in it, so I guess you would have to ask the people being involved.
I guess in charge of that too.
Would you say the production's a lot simpler for a mobile game?
I think simple is maybe a way you can put it, I think maybe thinking back about the
slide I had in the beginning where we said that mobile games are easy to make because
they're kind of like a dumbed down version of triple A games.
I don't think it is that way, but when you look at, I guess, production constraints and when you look at scope projects on mobile, you can get away, quote-unquote, much easier with smaller scope games, right?
Because that's what people kind of want, also in many cases, bite-sized experiences.
And so, yeah, I guess you can make cheaper mobile games in general than console games.
Okay, thank you.
Hi.
We are running out of time here, so here's the last question.
During the presentation, you talked about,
you come up with a conclusion that for mobile,
there are only two kinds of games that are worth making.
One is fast-paced, short-section kind of game,
and one is turn-based.
And I'm curious, how did you guys come up
with that conclusion?
I don't know, honestly, that was just a random thought that I had, and I think this is really
the idea of this underlying concept of being a bit stupid every once in a while and not
being afraid of doing so.
I was pretty sure this was an amazing idea and I was pretty sure this was the way you
make mobile games, you make successful mobile games.
Obviously today we know there's a lot of other mobile games that are not falling into either
of that category.
but I think again at that point all we needed
was an initial spark, something to actually start working
and I can't tell you where it came from originally,
maybe some sort of an article that I read
or just a random thought I had,
but I guess that's how it started.
Thank you very much.