Good morning.
Thank you for coming.
My name is Emma Kidwell.
I'll be moderating the session on behalf of Celia.
If you have any questions, you can type them
into the chat box next to the session video,
where I'll field them to Celia, pending if we
have time for questions.
Celia, I'm going to hand it off to you.
Thank you, Emma.
Hi, everyone.
I'm happy to be here at GDC Summer.
And I hope that everybody is doing well, as well as
your loved ones.
So my name is Sylvia Houdent and I have a PhD in psychology
and I've been working in the video game industry
over 12 years now.
I've worked at Ubisoft, I've worked at LucasArts
and I worked at Epic Games.
I was director of UX at Epic at the studio level
and I worked on Unreal Engine, I worked on a bunch of games
and I worked very closely with the Fortnite team.
I left Epic in October, 2017.
And ever since then, I'm a independent consultant.
And so I help a lot of companies, like AAA companies,
smaller companies, to develop their UX mindsets
and to develop processes and train people and all that.
So this approach of emotion is going
to be through the lens of UX.
My framework for UX is to break it down into two big pillars.
So you have usability and engageability.
When you try to anticipate problems
from happening in your game and you try to...
you know, improve things. There are two big lenses. Usability is the ability of the game to be used,
so it's more about the functionality. Are people understanding what to do? Can they accomplish
the objectives they need to accomplish, like if they need to craft in your game?
can they understand how to craft?
So that's the usability part.
And a game can be usable, but boring.
It's not because a game is gonna be easy to understand
and easy to use that it's gonna make it engaging.
So we also need to look into engageability,
especially for video games,
because the whole point of interacting with a system
and when you play a game is to have fun and be engaged
and to interact with the system.
So engageability is more around stuff like motivation, emotion,
and game flow.
So this is a framework that I've been
using to tackle problems like UX issues
so that we can understand where they come from,
and then we can fix them.
I did a bunch of GDC presentations on the topic.
They are called the Gamer's Brain, and part one, part two,
part three.
So you can just go back and see that if you're interested
and you haven't seen it before.
But here, we're going to tackle emotion in this framework,
and again, through the lens of UX and by understanding what's the science behind it,
and how we can use it to improve the user experience of a game.
So there's gonna be three big parts in this presentation.
We're gonna start with the science of emotion.
I'm not gonna go super deep, of course,
but it's just for you to have a broad understanding
of what's going on in the brain when we have emotions.
And then we're gonna talk about the UX framework
to use emotion in game design.
And lastly, we're going to touch on ethics considerations.
Of course, there's a lot of stuff to say around emotion.
In 45, 40, 45 minutes, I really don't have time
to talk about many things.
So the idea is just to give you an overview.
And during the questions, I can also
dive deeper into some elements.
So the limbic system is what is thought to be responsible for emotion in the human brain.
There is a broad consensus around it in science, but it's not completely clear. There are some
scientists that actually don't agree that there is such a thing as the limbic system.
But for the sake of simplicity here, let's say that there is some sort of consensus around this.
And so the limbic system, it's a lot of parts in the brain
that take part that are in this system.
You can see here just a few of them,
and these ones are very deep down the brain.
So on the thalamus, hypothalamus, hippocampus, and amygdala,
the frontal lobe is more on the cortex area.
And the hippocampus is an interesting part of the brain
because we know that it's also taking part
into memory, into souvenirs.
And the amygdala is oftentimes the part of the brain
that we mention when we talk about emotion and fight
or flight restances.
So it's just for you to have a big overview of what
we call the limbic system.
And so usually when we talk about emotion,
it's to say that it's guiding our behavior.
We need to survive in this world,
and so we seek pleasure and we avoid pain.
This is how we can find food and mate
and carry on with our genes
and avoid getting killed or getting hurt.
So overall, emotion is very good for that.
If we try something, it's pleasurable.
We're going to remember that, we're going to do it again.
So we do need to remember that.
And that's typically like the amygdala
and the hippocampus is helping us do that.
And of course, if we're experiencing something
and it's having a bad outcome,
this is where we remember not to do this again.
So it's really important to have these emotions
so it can guide us through our lives.
Oops, sorry.
So we learn to recognize and avoid unpleasant situations.
So here's an example.
If you've been, if you've experienced being bitten by a dog,
you will remember that.
And we learn some elements.
There are some, there's a very natural, I would say,
but some that we learn.
and we can reduce that in video games and of course artists do that very well.
For example, if you see an enemy that has very sharp teeth like here in Mario,
you don't need to really experience what's going to happen when you get close to it.
You understand that this is an enemy, that it is dangerous, and that you should avoid it. Otherwise
we're gonna probably get hurt. So through emotions, that sort of emotions, we can guide our players
to understand what's a good outcome and what's probably dangerous.
That's pretty basic, but a lot of people misunderstand conditioning a little bit.
Conditioning has a bad name today, and sure enough, when we think about conditioning,
we think about the Skinner box, and we think about the experiments that he did
mostly with rats and with pigeons, and they had to tap or to press on a pedal, for example,
when there was a light lining up.
to get food, but they also need to learn to press a pedal
or to not press a certain pedal to avoid
getting electrical shocks.
So this is what conditioning is about.
You learn to, this is more specifically
operant conditioning, so you see a stimulus,
you need to do a certain action,
so press the pedal, for example,
in order to either get a reward or to avoid a punishment.
This is something that we use in our lives all the time.
If you think about shaking hands, for example,
we've been conditioned to, every time you
see someone doing this gesture, like raising out
to reach out to your hand, we have
been conditioned to do the same because this
is a social construct and we need to do that.
Today we can't do this anymore and so we have to repress that movement.
Now today we got used to it but for a moment it was hard to, at the very beginning of the pandemic,
it was really hard to repress ourselves to shake hands and that happened to me very often
and that's because we've been conditioned.
to do that. And so in that case, we need to relearn because we have, like, for example, people, if
I try to reach out to you, and I see that you're looking at me like, no, I mean, we need to be
careful. This can be interpreted as a negative outcome. And because social relatedness and
social elements are really important for humans, we're going to react. We're going to change our
our pattern to react to this to have a better, more adapted response.
So this is what conditioning is about. It's about learning to repeat certain actions that lead to
pleasurable outcomes and to avoid certain actions that lead to non-pleasurable outcomes or dangerous
ones.
I'm going to make you listen to this sound effect.
So be careful.
It should not be too loud, but just like if you have headphones, just be careful.
This is a sound coming up.
So listen to this sound.
I didn't hear anything.
I don't know if you heard the sound in there.
I hope you did.
I did not have feedback on that.
Um, so this was the sound from Metal Gear Solid.
So if people have played Metal Gear Solid,
this is a sound that is very recognizable
and that you've been conditioned to react to
whenever you hear it,
because you know that it's the sound that we hear
whenever there are enemies around
that are about to spot you.
So you've been conditioned to either hide very quickly
or go into the open and shoot at everybody.
So this is an example of conditioning
that is pretty powerful in a video game
because it can guide us.
And it's also creating some emotional arrestments, of course.
It's raising your awareness because we
know that there is danger around,
because this particular stimulus has been tied to danger.
So that's an example of how we can use emotions in games
and use conditioning, and not in a way that
is going to be tricky.
We're going to talk about dark patterns and emotions that
not so good, that creates some manipulation is not so good,
but conditioning is very important in our lives
and this is a very efficient way to learn.
For example, another example of real life
is you've been conditioned if you start driving
and you forgot to fasten your seat belt,
then your car's gonna beep and we react to that beep
because it's super annoying by.
fastening up our seatbelt.
This is the restlessness that we've been conditioned to do
so that the annoying beeping stops.
So emotion guides our cognition, and this idea
that we need to be emotionless to reason appropriately
is not true.
You have the same neural networks
that take part into emotion, also take part into reasoning.
And so cognition and emotion work together.
We need emotions to be able to have an adaptive response
to our will.
Music is very particular and
and our brain because we have a very special resonance to music for some reason. So it's
one of the most rewarding and pleasurable experiences for humans. And it's modulating,
it can modulate activity in the regions that are associated with primary rainforces, such as food.
or sex. So it's particularly powerful, and that's the reason why we can have goosebumps,
or we can cry when we listen to certain music. It is particularly powerful in humans, and so,
of course, we should use that in video games, when you have games. I know that on mobile,
a lot of people turn the sound off, so it's, of course, creating some constraints. But in the...
other games, it's really important to polish the sound design and the music, but without
forgetting about accessibility and players who have hearing impairments or are deaf,
so that they are also taken into account.
So emotion guides our behavior.
But what's interesting, it's also
influenced by our cognition.
So we saw that emotion is making us do stuff
that we're going to interpret later on.
So emotion guides our cognition.
But also, our cognition is influencing our emotions.
Then I'm going to take an example.
I'm French, so I'll take an example
with a bottle of champagne, a fine bottle of champagne.
If you have two bottles of champagne,
like this one is Dom Pérignon.
So if you know about champagne, it's
a very expensive brand of champagne.
And the bottle looks really, really nice.
It's really appealing.
And let's say you have another bottle of champagne, it's like a plastic bottle,
and it looks super cheap. And we ask you to try the champagne from both of these bottles.
Most people are going to have a tendency to think that, to feel that the champagne coming from a nice
The very fine bottle tastes better than the one from the plastic bottle, but of course,
it's the same champagne.
And so this is how our cognition, our expectations is changing actually how we feel about things.
This is what we call appraisal.
We judge of situations based on what we know, based on our culture, based on social constructs.
And so this is in.
impacting our conscious feeling of things.
So that's appraisal.
And that's really important to understand
because we know that our perception is subjective.
It can be cultural-based.
And so this is going to have an impact on how we feel
about things about art.
And so we need to take that into account.
So that's appraisal.
You also have reappraisal.
So reappraisal is when you have some bad emotion,
like some negative emotion happening,
let's say you just lost a game.
And reappraisal is when you try to get over it,
and it could be seen as seeing the glass half full
instead of half empty.
Here's an example in a multiplayer game, Overwatch,
an old screenshot, where they do that pretty well.
In any multiplayer game that is competitive,
you're always going to have some players that are going to
have some negative emotions because they lost,
and so it's going to be important to help them
reappraise the situation.
Here's the screen that you would see when you were on
the
on the victorious team.
So for those who don't know, Overwatch is a game
you play six versus six.
And this is what you would see when you win.
So you have badges and your XP is going up
and it's all great.
When you're on the defeated team, you actually,
so you have the feedback that you lost,
but they don't insist on how crappy you are to have lost.
It's not like, oh, you suck, you lost.
They tell you that you are defeated.
But they try to help you rephrase the situation by showing you how you got better against your own stats.
So they don't emphasize how you compare to other players,
because it's very likely that we're not on top of the charts.
In the 6v6 game, there's one player that's on top of the scoreboard and all others are not.
But if you compare people to their own stats...
It is very likely that we're going to get better because we played more.
And so as we practice the game, we are very likely to progress.
And that is a very good feeling.
So one of the elements that I showed you from the framework that I'm using in motivation
is intrinsic motivation.
One part of this is competence.
We need to feel competent in an activity to be motivated to keep doing that activity.
And so in a game where there's a lot of competence going on,
it's really important to see ourselves progressing.
So if it's a skill-based game and we practice,
we are likely to get better.
And so if you emphasize how the player is getting better
against their own stats, it's helping them reappraise
the fact that they lost.
So this is an example of how by understanding
a little bit better how emotion is working,
you can help designing for some experiences that
are going to be more pleasurable emotionally for players.
So that's to sum up this part.
Emotion guides our behavior and cognition,
and cognition in return influences our emotion.
So now we're going to talk about emotion in game design.
And to talk about this, we're going to start by talking.
about emotion in design.
So Don Norman is a UX designer and a kind of scientist,
and he's the one who coined the term UX back in the 90s.
So he's like the father of the UX mindset.
And he has a book called Emotional Design
where he explains a little bit
the three levels of processing
when we interact with an object or a system,
we're gonna process the system
through.
three levels that are going to create some emotions. So the first one is visceral. That's
the level that is very based on appearance. It's like your gut feeling, like the term is pretty
self-explanatory.
It's visceral, so it's how things look.
Bright colors, for example, or how things taste.
The look, feel, the sounds.
This is really like you just look at something
and it looks amazing.
If you're into cars, you know,
they're the cars that.
there's a lot of, um,
like, like, like, like, like
Luke, uh, had like lines that
are either aggressive or they
really feel that they're
powerful. This is all about
visceral design. And so that's
really important in games as
well, of course, and, uh, all
about presentation art, um,
direction, but also game feel
we're going to talk about
The next level is behavioral.
So it's how do we interact with that system?
So it's the pleasure and effectiveness of use.
So this time, it's less about how it looks,
you know, how beautiful it is.
It's not about the aesthetic.
It's about the functionality.
It's about am I able to accomplish the things
that I want to accomplish?
And so in UX, we call that usability.
We make sure that a system like a video game
is going to be designed to be used by a human.
This is what we call human-centered design.
We make sure that it's usable,
so that we understand the sense and feedback,
that we understand how to use the system.
We have form follows function,
function comes first, and we try to make sure
that the functionality is conveyed
through the shape and sound of the element.
All of these things is about behavioral level and of course accessibility is in there.
And the last level is reflective.
So this is more about the self-image
that we get when we interact with the system.
Maybe we felt guilt or maybe we are proud because we won.
So that's self-image.
Personal satisfaction, memories.
So it's all about the meaning of elements.
What it makes you think about.
If you think about Star Wars, if you're in your 30s or 40s,
you know, you have like that memories
that are attached to it.
And it's more about, you know,
the battle of the good against evil,
more than a political movie.
So it's all about the story, the narrative,
the meaning, what does it mean to you?
So it's not now, not about the functionality,
but it's about how you reflect.
on this. Novelty is also a part of it. We like to have novel experiences, and so we
can reflect on these elements. So this is the baseline, the three levels of process
when we interact with anything. So these all happen at the same time, and this was very
well described by Don Norris.
Here I'm going to show you how we use in game design emotion
more specifically.
So there are two big notions in game design
to tackle emotion.
The first one is what we call game feel.
So there's a book by Steve Swink that describes very well
what game feel is about.
But basically, it's how good it feels to interact with the game.
So there are three very important notions in here.
The first one is what we call the three Cs.
And I'm going to describe that a bit later.
So it's a camera-controlled character.
It's also about the sense of presence.
Do I feel, is there anything preventing me from feeling
that I am inside the game?
And the last one is the sense of physical reality.
Is it believable when, I don't know,
if there's a game where you explode balloons,
do you have a believable physical experience in there?
Balloons popping with a specific sound effect,
VFX, et cetera.
So to be more precise, the three Cs, like I said,
it's camera, control, characters.
So camera is gonna have a very big impact
on how we feel about the game, of course.
So if you have a game that is godlike,
most of the time you're gonna have a top-down
or isometric view of the game
because you feel that you can control things
and you're managing it.
all this world. If you want a game that's more about the thrill, about being scared,
which is the visceral level, like being scared about something like a roller coaster or horror
movies is the visceral level. And to accomplish that, we're going to use a first-person camera
and most of the time we're going to have a narrow...
field of view, so it feels like you don't see around, and it's much easier to jump scare people
when we do that. So the choice of camera is going to have a big impact on how the game feels, and
it's of course very important. It's one of the main elements that we need to tackle in a game.
Another very critical element are the controls.
how the players are going to be able to interact with the system and what are the controls?
Is it going to be easy to do or do you feel like an octopus to accomplish some very common
actions in the game?
I'm showing here the controls from ESK because it was a very interesting use of controls.
So ESK is the game about skating and instead of using the face buttons for the tricks,
they used the thumbstick.
The idea was to try to recreate with your thumb
the sort of physical feeling that you would get
while skating.
And so that was an interesting approach to control.
So the controls and how could they feel,
if they feel natural or is it kind of weird?
It's not by chance that we have...
that we shoot on a console game with the triggers because it feels like a trigger from a real gun
so and it's and you hold it and it's you have a good grip in your hand so.
Controls are also very important to nail in your game.
And the last one is character.
So the main character is the avatar of the player, of course,
but all the characters in the game are gonna be important
and they need to convey some emotions.
So of course we care a lot about who are these characters?
What do they transcend?
And so here's an example from Hellblade and you have Senua.
She's the avatar, she's the heroine of the game,
and you see, for example, there's an element from this character model,
as she has that rat that is growing on her hand every time she dies.
and while we time the player dies and she experimented in her world and so you see that
thing growing on her arm. So all these elements are really really important to have a good game
feel and many big studios they are tackling camera controls characters first during their
pre-production so that they can nail that the best they can.
So that was for the three Cs.
And then I told you about presence and physical reality.
So presence is, do I feel present in the game?
And by that, I don't mean removing the HUD.
It's not by removing all the things
that you necessarily can have a bigger sense of presence.
Like, imagine if you drive a new car that you don't know.
It's not about removing all the controls
and all the dashboard that's going
to make you feel that you're on the road.
When these.
controls and dashboard are not in the way and feels natural and you can just concentrate on the road.
It's the same thing with the video game, you have the controls and you have the interface and you
have the head, but when it's not in the way this is when you can feel that you have presence
in the game. So of course usability is really important to nail that.
Presence is also, do I feel that I'm part of the world?
So if you look at a game where you have a crowd AI,
is the crowd reacting in a realistic way to what you're doing?
So for example, in Assassin's Creed, if you're doing something weird
or you assassinate someone in the street and people see you,
if the crowd is reacting to that, it makes you feel present in the game.
In 2D, for example, in a mobile game like Clash of Clans,
you want to build a new building
and you feel that sense of presence
because as you say, yeah, I wanna build that,
you have the little characters that come over
and they start building.
And so it makes you feel that you have a real presence
into the world and the game world is reacting to you.
The narrative also is really important for presence.
The story, you know, can I make choices
that are gonna be meaningful for the story?
All that increases the same with presence
and music and all that.
I can't cover it all, but it's like pretty important.
And physical reality, is it believable?
So I told you, like, if you pop balloons in a game,
do you feel that it is balloon?
Is it doing like the pop sound
that you would expect from balloons?
Do you have particle effects?
If you have a very strong character
that is running towards you,
you might have like a camera shake
every time the character, like as it runs,
the foot hits the ground.
So all these elements are about physical reality.
It is not about photo realism.
Again, it's more about is it believable in the game?
So here I'm gonna show you an example from Fortnite.
Again, so it's old.
It's from the closed alpha around the loot box.
Why I'm showing you that?
Because it's particularly the game feel,
and this is particularly well done.
You can see that the loot box is not just a box,
it's not just a chest or a card pack that you would open.
It is in the shape of a llama pinata.
So that's all about presence.
You know, it's also about the narrative.
You know, how does it fit the world?
It's also reacting to you when you move the mouse around.
Its eyes, they are following you.
And when you're about to hit it,
so you have like a, it feels,
you have that sense of physical reality,
and then you have particle effects and all that.
So I'm gonna show you how it looks like.
Hopefully you'll have the sound.
It's a lovely day for loot.
Have at it.
Oh, I am feeling lucky.
Hey, check out this nice loot.
Alright, so you see, you know, there's stuff happening, and oh, you get something cool,
you know, it's changed in color, and you have all this, all this stuff happening.
So all of that is about game feel, and it's really important to polish it and the game
to increase the emotional connection that we have to it.
OK, so that was about game feel.
And arguably, we can talk about hours about that.
But I just want to move on so that you
have an overview about all the things that you can talk about.
There's also the brain is pretty reactive to novelty
because anything new in our environment
can potentially kill us.
So we have a tendency to.
to pay attention, to raise our awareness when something is new
and that can be potentially dangerous.
So that's the reason why we love novelty.
We love to have surprises and to discover things.
This is why learning is pleasurable most of the time.
And we can use that to sustain engagement so that players
are not getting bored.
If you always do the same activity,
even though you like that activity, at some point,
your awareness is decreasing.
because you don't really need to pay attention.
So that's the reason why novelty,
so discovery, surprises, curiosity,
all things that we can use to raise engagements and awareness.
So some examples of that.
In Zelda, they teased players a lot.
They teased players' curiosity.
So in this old screenshot from A Link to the Past,
you see the cracks in the wall.
And these are new cracks from this wall.
It's a different wall that you've never seen before.
And so players see that for the first time.
And they're like, oh, that seems new.
And how do I interact with that?
And this is how you.
learn that you need a super bomb to explode this particular wall.
So through something a bit new, it cannot be too new because then it can be very scary to have
something completely new, but we like to have some novelty and to have our curiosity teased.
Another example of that is
Uncharted 3, in Uncharted 3 you have a section in the game
where you're in a ship and the ship is sinking.
As it sinks, it's rotating, it's tilting at 90 degrees
and all your controls are rotated 90 degrees as a result.
So it's creating some sort of some new surprise
and that's tied to game feel, so it's tied to controls.
And so for example, if you try to move forward,
your character is actually moving left.
And that creates some sort of novelty.
So it's good to do that once the player is already
used to the controls.
So that brings some sort of novelty
that is raising your awareness.
Another game does that.
Limbo does that.
You have a level where it's a side-scrolling.
platforming puzzle game and at some point you have a level where your gravity is upside
down. So you arrive in the sub-level of Solemn EQ.
you get stuck to the ceiling.
So all these elements are something new
that's happening in the game,
at some point when you're already used to the game,
so that is raising awareness.
Another example more tied to narrative
is on Fortnite or on Diablo, you have the mimics.
So you think it's a chest,
and you don't even pay attention,
you just like hold to open it,
and surprise, this is not a chest,
it is an enemy that's trying to destroy you.
So all these things bring some novelty.
The problem with that is you need
to make it novel quite often to work.
And that's the reason why we need to always have
new elements in an online game that is live so that players
are not getting bored.
So one of the ways to do that is to have new content,
so DLC or new seasons or new characters or new maps.
Multiplayer games can be more engaging in the long term
because every time you play, it can be with different players.
So it can bring something new.
Or systemic, procedurally generated games
can help with that because every time you play,
it's going to be a little bit different.
Arguably, it's taking a lot of time,
and it's also making...
The game workers crunch quite a bit,
so it does have its downside, for sure.
Just here are a few books if you want
to dive more into the topics.
So Emotional Design from Don Norman, Game Film
from Steve Swink, and How Games Move Us
from Catherine Neswister.
And again, think about emotion.
So in my framework, I explained that emotion
is here to support motivation,
and this is what you really need to do
to think about game feel and presence and surprises
and how this can support player motivation
in terms of competence, autonomy, and relatedness.
So for example, if you have particle effects,
it's even more meaningful if it's because
you just want something or you.
accomplished a goal, and so you feel competent.
So the last, so yeah, this is it for this part.
So remember to use game feel, spaces, presence,
physical reality, and novelty to sustain engagement.
And the last part, I'm going to go fast
because I'm already, it's really late already.
So.
It's all about trying to manipulate emotions ethically.
There is no such thing as neutral design.
And the thing that we design is going
to influence people to interact with it in a certain way.
For example, if you have a handle on a door,
this is influencing you to grab the handle and pull.
So sometimes these doors need to be pushed
and that's a bit annoying.
So it manipulated you into a wrong behavioral response.
So it's not the end of the world,
but everything that we create, everything that we design
is gonna have an impact on people's expectations
and behavior and art, of course,
is about manipulating emotion.
So we need to understand that nothing we do
is gonna be neutral and we need to ensure
that this is not gonna have a negative impact
on our players, of course.
So I told you that we need emotion to think rationally,
to accomplish our goals, and to be able to reason.
The problem is emotions can trick us, of course.
So here are just a few examples that have been
studied by behavioral economics.
You have the example of scarcity.
When something is getting scarce, like we had a few countries like that,
where because of the pandemic, all of a sudden there were a scarcity in toilet paper.
And so when there's scarcity, even though you don't care that much about toilet paper,
now we want it because we might not have it.
And so scarcity works a lot with the fear of missing out, the FOMO.
because we know that maybe it's gonna be gone
before I get there.
So anytime you see sales,
this is the fear of missing out is used,
like, you know, it's ending tonight.
Or so like, you have to be there.
You have only like one more day
to benefit all of these awesome discounts.
loss aversion, we are very averse to loss more than we like
gains. And so anytime we feel that players are going to lose
something, we play on loss aversion. So example would be
streaks when like in Snapchat, you had the snap streaks.
And like every day you interact with a certain person,
it's going up and up and up.
And if one day you don't interact with that person,
it's going all the way back down.
And this plays on loss aversion.
So we don't want to lose all that awesome streak.
And so that's encouraging us to keep interacting
with the system even though we didn't really want
to do it that day.
And the last one of my examples, there's many, many more.
It's anchoring effect.
We also see that in sales.
And when you see the original price
and you have the straight through on it
and you see the new price, the discounted price,
we have a tendency to base our decision on an anchor.
We compare things.
And this can persuade us to buy something
that we did not really want.
So this is all the things when Emotion trick us
and has been used in tech and in marketing
and many situations for a long, long, long, long time.
The thing is we have to be careful
and see how it can impact negatively our players.
When we do UX, we think about humans first
and not the business first.
Of course, we need to make sure
that the game is gonna be sustainable.
But we don't want to trick players because this is not what we do.
Here is an example of one of these emotional tricks that sometimes people use.
I'm going to use the example of Amazon because...
They're pretty infamous for that.
So for example, like here,
they use the loss aversion,
like, oh, you don't want to subscribe for
Amazon Prime and therefore you're ready to,
well, they don't use the term lose,
which is making it a bit better.
But so, oh yeah, you agree to not save some money.
So it's also implying that you're a bit dumb.
So it's playing on your emotions.
So of course, we're going to have that in video games,
because again, art form is going to manipulate emotion
by definition, but we need to be careful at what
is it we're manipulating.
And if we're using some of these emotional tricks
not to serve gameplay or not to increase
the experience for the players, but to increase our business
goals or to make players come back.
or to make them spend more.
So I'm not saying that it's an easy way
to define where's the line,
like the crops dying or the time at Gucci,
it's difficult to have that experience
of these sort of games without that last version feeling
because things are decaying if you're not here.
So I'm not saying that it's very easy
to define where the line is,
but we certainly need to think about it that way.
so we can understand what impact we have on our players.
Especially when we are targeting kids,
or we know that our game is played by kids,
because kids don't have a mature.
Prefrontal cortex, I don't know if you remember
the one of the first slides.
I showed you the limbic system.
And it's interacting with the frontal lobe,
and more specifically, the prefrontal cortex.
This is the part of the brain that
is avoiding automatic behavior.
And sometimes, this is when we stop and think
instead of falling for the trap or falling for loss aversion.
going to stop and think, and that's thanks to the prefrontal cortex.
The problem is the limbic system develops way faster than the prefrontal cortex,
and the prefrontal cortex is maturing around, completely around 20...
three to 25 years old.
So it's not to say that teenagers are completely
lost before that, but it is harder for young children
and even teenagers to resist some of these tricks.
So we definitely need to be careful, more so than when
we're addressing adults.
So I'm going to leave you with that.
If you have a game that is rated T or E,
make sure to avoid all these tricks
and reconsider them in all the games.
So guilt tripping, loss aversion if you're missing out,
loot box tied to monetization because it's using
conditioning, et cetera, et cetera.
So manipulate emotions ethically.
Emotions are going to be manipulated in an art form.
It is normal, and it's good.
We want that, but we need to consider
the ethics of the manipulation in our art form.
So this is the reason why you can take a look at ethicalgames.org,
which is an initiative that we just kicked off.
And we have a panel at GDC Summer on Thursday at 10 AM
if you're interested in that topic.
All right, I talk too much, so I'm just right on time,
but I don't think we're going to have enough time for questions.
But you see here the books that I wrote,
and you can book me on Twitter, and you'll
find some resources on my blog.
And let me know, Emma, if we have time for maybe one
or two questions, or if I should take it offline and answer
questions on Twitter or on chat.