Hello, my name is Matthew Gallant, and I work on combat design and AI at Naughty Dog.
I'll be speaking at GDC this year about the development of Uncharted 4, A Thief's End.
In the previous Uncharted games, the flow of combat was very tightly authored by the design team.
However, we had some new design goals on Uncharted 4, and that gave us a chance to re-evaluate our approach.
Our plans for open-ended gameplay in large, complex environments led us to explore a more systems-driven approach to AI.
I'll talk about how we oversteered in that direction, but ultimately found a balance between authored content and systemic behaviors.
I'll be covering topics such as how to decide which aspects of combat AI should be authored by designers, and which parts are better handled with systems-driven logic.
How to make multiple NPCs spread out intelligently in a large, complex combat space.
And how to focus on the player's experience when developing new behaviors for NPCs.
You can catch the talk on Thursday, March 2nd from 4 to 5 p.m.