I'm Tyler Sigmund. I'm the co-founder, co-president, design
director, trash man, I don't know, whatever. It's a small
company, so we all do a lot of things. Red Hook Studios.
When I was putting this talk together, so it's a postmortem,
we're going to try to cover things that went well, things
that didn't go so well. But as putting the talk together in
particular, I think on the what went wrongs, I'm going to focus
a lot on one thing, not because there is difficulty in finding
lots of, there's no hubris of difficulty in finding lots of
things that went wrong. But I think there's just a couple of
things that were more interesting. So hopefully you'll
forgive it's not an exact standard five and five, like the
old GDMAG format.
So darkest dungeon is a turn based gothic horror light
fantasy RPG about the psychological stress of
adventuring. And this is, we throw this screen up the minute
you start up the game to make sure you know what you're
getting into. And of course no one reads it because no one
reads tutorials. But this gives us the ability to come back
later and say we told you it was going to be bad. And this is
what it looks like in practice.
Come on, healer!
Baby, you gotta go!
Survival is a tenuous proposition.
That's okay, come on, healer!
Sprawling tomb.
Come on!
Healer! Healer!
Come on! Come on!
That's fine as long as you give me one more fucking hit!
Don't do it!
Fuck!
...that's timeless after all.
So that's Ezekiel 3. He actually still likes us. And did play
darkest dungeon after that and has actually played it since.
And so, yeah, that's nice. So he has gotten some more enjoyment
out of the game. One of the things we set out to do with
darkest dungeon that made it unique is trying to create
emotional attachment. So I think we succeeded. Sometimes maybe
not exactly in the ways that we planned. I mean, I wouldn't say
that was like one of our design goals.
But when we were coming up with the game idea, so Chris
Brasso's, originally his idea, Chris and I were friends and we
would get together and talk about working on games together.
We had worked at other studios in the past. And this one kept
just, it had so much weight. Every time we would talk about
it, we'd get excited. And the main thing is we're RPG fans,
and there's so many great RPGs out there.
I've been playing them my whole life on and off the computer.
And one of the things we were really conscious of is just that we didn't want to just make
an RPG because we love them.
We wanted to make an RPG only if there was something maybe different or new that we could
add that might make it stand out.
The real concept here is the idea that heroes are human. And
Chris likes to say it's about the sword arm, not the sword.
It's not how big your shoulder pads and giant glowing sword
are. It's the human wielding it and how willing they are and
able to fight.
And so along with that becomes the whole range of human
emotion. So moments of despair, these uncomfortable decisions
we're putting you in as the player confronting you with loss
and permanent consequences. But the real secret is we're not
actually sadists.
The moments of despair are there only in so far as to create
moments of triumph. Because what is an act of true heroism
without the possibility of cowardice? And we felt like a
lot of RPGs are all about heroism. You have one hit point
and you're fighting the dragon. Whatever. Hang in there. Oops,
didn't go well. Reload. Try again.
A little bit about my background because it's relevant to what's
next is I designed a bunch of games on and off the computer
and a bunch of different genres. I like to say every time I make
a game I enjoy I have to do pendants and make a racing game,
which I do not enjoy and am not particularly good at.
But I think that diverse range of just non-collectible card
games to weird hybrid action games to turn-based really
helped because Darkest Dungeon has a ton of systems in it. It's
a small game made by a small team. When you look at
something like The Witcher 3, it's ridiculous for me to say
there's this big scope to the game. But I think there was
unexpected scope.
The main pillars of the play experience are this town,
exploration, combat and camping. And we talked a lot up front
about how much time should the player spend in each of these
phases. Combat by far is I think, well, combat and
exploration together are the lion's share of your time. But
that's not to minimize the importance of the time you spend
in camping. Or some people spend an awful lot of time in town
looking at their things and putting their guys into
treatment. But generally you're walking side to side through a
hallway finding things.
built around those four cores though are a ton of systems. And
one of the challenges of the game was that a lot of these
systems are
innovations, I guess, which is not trying to say that always
worked, but the affliction system was the real hook of the
game. That was something, you know, it's like how do we
psychologically model these heroes? Meanwhile, the cost of
entry making an RPG, you still have to do all the other things,
combat, leveling, quests, monsters, you know, all these
sorts of things. So when you start layering in affliction
system and torchlight and some innovations, it was a lot at
times. So
I think one thing that went well is that a lot of the systems are
not particularly eloquent. Some of them certainly deserve a
second pass, a third pass that maybe never got it. And some of
them are outright clunky. But together it all worked. And
sometimes I guess I say it went well because it's just a great
It felt like at times that any one system that didn't do its
job was just going to ruin the whole mix. Like you're
overseasoning the stew and I can't recover it now. I think in
this case one of the things I'm just most proud of in the game
is just that it did all hang together, duct tape and bailing
wire and chewing gum and the whole bit to support the goal of
the game which was the heroes are human.
And part of that too, it's really important what we didn't
do. For all those systems that I just showed, there was a lot
that we wanted to put in and these are just a couple of them.
Crafting or the idea of a more meaningful upgrade system, more
meaningful gear, loot system. The characters have this armor
and weapon progression. It's just linear progression. You can
go from level 1 upgrade to level 5 in armor, level 1 to level 5
in weapon. You have two trinket slots and.
Of course we could have done a whole bunch more. We could have done paper doll, etc., etc.
But that would have taken away, especially with our team and with the budget that we had set out to make the game with,
if I was spending time on that, I wouldn't have been spending time on the inflation system.
And that would have been a mistake.
Similarly, and this was led really strongly by Chris, the creative director,
is our focus on emergent narrative.
meant that we weren't doing these other cost of entry RPG
features like extensive dialogue trees, going into the Abbey,
talking to the Abbot before you commit treatment, like, hello,
Mr. Abbott, what's new today? What rumors have you heard?
None of that. The quests are not particularly in-depth. They're
kind of the equivalent of go get the 10 wolf belts. And we
really avoided heavy lore at every possible opportunity. And
that was a creative choice, but all these also support kind of
what we were trying to do. We
You know, your ancestor called you to the estate and you need
to go to the wield and fight things or the ruins. So it's
very archetypal, but in doing so, that means you have to
construct a love story in your head. And ultimately what we
wanted to do, what we were really after is the idea of
kind of like these old roguelikes where you make your
character and you go on these crazy adventures and then you
can stream together this story of like, well, that time with
all the slugs in level 10 was rough. I barely got out of that.
Thank God I drank the random potion and polymorphed and got
away.
We wanted you to do that with the heroes. So the more we force fed down your throat, that
wouldn't have worked. So it was very important for us not to do things. Our design process
also went well. Chris, so, you know, I'm designer on the game, design director, but there's
a lot to do with this game and a lot of design and a lot came from Chris and I working together
very early. And this isn't always the role. I filled on every game. It's kind of funny.
In this game it very much became this role of Chris drawing all day long and having time to
think because he can draw and think at the same time. I cannot spreadsheet and think about
anything else at the same time. So we would just be spouting ideas. Well, not always spouting.
He carefully thought of something. I kind of got into this role of batting stuff back over the
net.
And then sometimes he really, really, really wanted to talk
about it again, and I could sit with it and get comfortable
where it might have gone. In fairness, also my role in the
game was to wrangle all these things and then do the detail
design. Like, okay, afflictions, how does that work? How are we
doing stress? What triggers an affliction? What kind of things
can they do in the affliction? But kind of managing that whole
cloud of red stuff was at times just completely maddening but
also fun.
And the creative direction of the game, having that established really strong up front, was what we needed to be able to resist that design feature creep. I mean, I think, you know, I'm a designer and it's, we all make games and it's really hard sometimes. You wake up and have a shower and you think of this awesome thing you'd like to throw in and maybe it goes into the game and sometimes you've got to resist the temptation. And then also don't want to minimize the rest of the team as coming up with great ideas, being there to like reject something that is really bad that, you know,
It just doesn't fly.
And sometimes it was hard because you can't listen to all ideas from all places, but the
rest of the team was really important.
Also with vetting and trying and all sorts of these things.
So the system is the hook of the game. And that's really what we
call the whole system for your heroes being human and sometimes
basically being a bunch of unrelieved toddlers. And that's
built on events and situations. If you think about it, being an
adventurer is a really, really terrible job. You might be
running out of food. You're in search of this elusive gold. It's
kind of like start-up culture.
You're in the dark, running out of light, could die at any
moment. So there's these events and situations that lead to
stress. And everyone loves to make fun of how you can read a
book and it can just blow your mind in our game. But that's
very Lovecraftian, to be fair. So stress builds on the heroes
once it reaches 100. We have what's called a resolve check.
And that's a test of their mettle. And that resolves one of
two ways. If you're lucky, they become virtuous. Excuse me,
But more often than not, they become afflicted. And then this
manifests in their behaviors and their stat and bonuses or
penalties and narratively in the things they talk about.
The inspiration for the affliction system was not games
really, although I have to show an image. It was more human
experience. That's fictional, dramatizations, movies, TV
shows, et cetera, but also just life. Being a manager, we talk
about a lot. Being in a relationship, all these things,
your human experience, it's pretty easy to mine that for how
we react to stress.
And that's a really important point. Darkest Dungeon is not a
game about mental health or mental illness. Darkest Dungeon
is a game about the human response to stress and those are
very different things. So this is an image, I really like
Band of Brothers Europe, obviously based on real events.
And there's this character, Buck Compton, I think that's his
name, played by this actor, Neil McDonough. He's tall, he's
handsome, he's tough. He's been on a bunch of missions. He's
kind of just this gregarious, energetic guy that's holding the
squad together in a way.
And they're in the battle of the Ardennes and getting shelled
through the winter. And he watches a shell land in a fox
hole with a couple of his buddies and they're just gone.
They're there one minute, the shell lands, they're gone. And
there's this great scene where he just comes up and he just has
the thousand-yard stare, shell shock, takes off his helmet, and
he's just done. That's it. His war is over. And I think that
was really a moment that in a way we wanted to capture.
Game over, man. Hudson and his, he's the most boisterous. I love
watching, especially extended cut, I think there's even more
talking, him at the beginning just being total boisterous
asshole and then of course the minute things go to hell he
can't handle it. And Ripley is the one civilian that shouldn't
be able to handle it and is made of steel. But war games and
things have done morale for a long time. And to some degree
what we were doing is bringing a morale system into an RPG.
And so these aren't necessarily new ideas. It's just kind of
maybe packaging them in a different way. The affliction
system had seven afflictions, four virtues. And one of the
neat things is we have 15 different character classes in
the game and we've got custom strings and multiple variants
for every single class, every single affliction virtue, every
single act out they can do. That's one of the things we
really invest a lot in and paying out. I think the game
has about 70,000 words of text now. And that's funny for a
lower list game with no dialogue trees. So it snuck up on us.
And if you play the game, they say it might be a little hard to
see here, but here the hellion is being masochistic. He's
like, please cut me. I want this. Here I think the highway
man is being abusive and basically berating his party
members. And this is too hard to see. It's a little small. More
of the same. Someone made some fan art which captures the
feeling you get in the game a lot.
If you can't read it, can you people hold your shit together
and hit something for five minutes, please? That happens a
lot. So the important thing about the inflation system is
it's really the hook of the game. I mean, you know, the
game is universally allotted for a lot of things, but this is
kind of always there. And if it didn't work, the whole game
premise falls down. And it's built up of really pretty simple
subsystems.
And we purposefully obfuscate part of that. When your
character is masochistic, we don't tell you what could
happen. We don't tell you exactly what act outs they might
do or how they might run to the front or reject healings. We
want you to discover that through play. We don't want to
have a tool tip or as much as I love tool tips, Chris knows I
love tool tips.
I never met a tool tip I didn't love. But at the same point
here, we don't want to show you everything. We want you to
discover it. But it's really important. Stress we could not.
We thought about it. We toyed around with obfuscating stress.
But then we could have the characters talk as they're
getting more stressed. Like, hey, I'm getting stressed. But
then you never really know where the breaking point is. And you
can't make any tactical or strategic decisions of how far
to press or what to do or when to camp.
If you don't know. So it actually worked out really well to just make it like a health meter.
We worried it would be a little boring, a little dry.
But that certainly enhanced the game, certainly enhanced the system.
You know they're about to break.
And that was really important.
The fliction system also features the loss of agency, which I'll talk about a little more.
Yeah, it worked. And I mean, that's why I say it's something
that went well. And I think one of the biggest reinforcements to
me that it worked was during early access, which we were in
for roughly a year, we made very, very few changes to the
affliction system. I mean, frighteningly few. We thought
we would go back and we would add a million more act outs and
we would double back on some things that were really rough.
And other than a little bit of tuning and maybe improving the
flow of a few things, like I think now, like if they balk the
heel, you go to heal them and they balk.
We don't penalize you your turn. They don't get to heal but you can still use that character.
We made a couple changes like that but in general we didn't.
And the reason we didn't is because the community was very clear of many other things that they didn't like.
And I think that's important though.
The squeaky wheel gets to grease a little bit because this was working
and I think it realized the potential of what the affliction system was supposed to do.
As you've seen with the ZKL video, we successfully not
only made your heroes afflicted, we made the game
players afflicted. How many of you have rage quit Narcos
Dungeon? I don't know if I should ask this. How many of
you rage quit but came back and played again? Thank God. How
many rage quit and are never going to play it again but still
came to the talk anyway? Thank you for your honesty. That's
it.
Thank you for the honesty. I have met people who are like, I like the game, I can never play it, I will never play it again.
But it may help you a little bit in your hearts to know that we also made ourselves afflicted a lot.
Through development we developed a vernacular vocabulary for
understanding how stress was impacting us. And actually you
should try it on your teams. It works quite well. So we would
see that, hey, maybe don't talk to them today. They're really
close to afflicted. Or someone would send a nasty e-mail and
then we'd...
Don't worry, they're just abusive right now. They'll get
over it. And to put myself out there, my affliction is a
rationality. As my stress builds and builds and builds and then I
become triggered, then I'll pick some really stupid thing to just
panic about. And maybe, you know, just, yeah, coffee or I
don't know what it is. Or make some small point about the game
that I want to fight tooth and nail about that's completely
meaningless. So that's me.
A little bit about this is just to show like this is what we
call the trait library which is this is how the afflictions are
actually hooked up. This isn't particularly sexy but what you
can see there and these slides will be on the vault later is
like a series of buffs to the stats and then situational act
outs is what we call them. Like hey, there's this chance of if
it's your turn in combat and you're abusive you might do
this. Or if it's a reaction act out. If someone tries to heal
you and you're paranoid you may reject it because you think
they're trying to kill you. That kind of stuff.
And this brings me to one of my favorite things, the Microsoft
Excel. And I think you were saying Ed Fries said hello. Ed
Fries was head of Microsoft games. I like to think of him
because he worked on Excel. That's his best accomplishment.
So anyway, Excel is my favorite thing.
Excel is huge. And not Google sheets, I will add. Google
sheets are like for collaboration. I'll use it. But
Excel is the thing. Excel, when you're a small team, you need to
figure out ways to move faster. And one of these sheets is
the monster library. There's 200 monster files or something.
And that was really useful to automate that. And so usually
things made their way from sprite sheet into a JSON or
darkest. So it's not like we had the best pipeline ever. But the
programmers were busy doing important things and making the
game. But we had enough to get through. And so that's where I
think the BBA exporters and things like this.
We're so helpful, especially when you're a small team.
So setting up these parametric equations so that you can decide all monsters in the whole
game need a little more help and you don't have to go through.
I'm a big fan of formulas, obviously.
So a lot of that went well, but there's definitely some gaps where we're missing key exporters
that I always thought we'd find time to make and never did.
So it became a little confusing working.
We make a change for a new feature. Is this an exported
file or a hand edited file? I don't know. I have to look
through my 27,000 spreadsheets. So that sometimes led to
problems.
Something that went well is our bad design. So there's a few
areas of bad design that I want to focus on. So loss of agency.
That's one. So in other words, your characters do things that
you don't want them to do. They pass their turns. They reject
healing. They basically just make your life difficult. In
talking to my partner Chris, it does sound like maybe being a
parent.
And, you know, we're owning a pet. And that's kind of what
they are. And generally that's bad design. Because, you know,
you should get positive feedback for the actions you do, et
cetera, et cetera. But it was very, very important for
darkest dungeon that you were not in control. I mean, that's
really just like a founding principle. And so even though
we knew it would frustrate the heck out of you sometimes, like
in the Ezekiel video, you know, it came to one of the characters
turns, I think they passed, and then of course he lost the
whole, he had a party wipe.
But this was necessity from the heroes are human idea.
This made it a little hard sometimes because Darkest
Dungeon has a lot of numbers and a lot of systems and it's
kind of a tactics, it's a turn-based combat game. And so
how do you, you know, sometimes you're worried about balance
like, hey, this character has like, DPS is like, you know,
undersized by 5% compared to the other characters. And then you
have this system in the game that basically can just rob you
of a turn entirely. And that was sometimes a hard balance to
tread and to get people to expect. Because I think for some
people they genuinely enjoy Darkest Dungeon as just
It would be really cool if not for this affliction system that
keeps getting in the way. Like it's a neat turn-based combat
cool roguelike whatever. So that was hard sometimes to balance
because ultimately there is all this kind of stuff that's taking
control away from you.
Our save system, so if you're familiar with the game, it
saves all the time. Actions are permanent. There's no saves
coming. You have to go through great lengths to do some saves
coming. And so permanent consequences were what we were
after. We want you at all moments to be like, should I go
a little further, maybe get a little more treasure? Do I think
I can make it to the end of this quest even though these two
characters are afflicted and this one is almost dead? And to
do that, we needed this terrible save system that is just really,
really mean.
And it's exceptionally mean because in Ezekiel's video, he
crashed out of the game. I guess he calmed down the next day,
came back to play, booted it up, and it had saved right before
the hit that killed his characters because he crashed
out. But it had already rolled, and the action was fixed. So
he's like, okay, we're going to do this. He had to watch it
happen again. So that wasn't intentional.
We did not make a use case for you crashing your computer and
out. 15 unbalanced hero classes. So we chose to do more heroes
rather than less. And sometimes the cost of that was balance and
attention to each individual hero. But it was a conscious
choice because every hero you add to the game gives you the
ability for more party formations.
We always thought of heroes as loot. It should be exciting when
you're waiting for a crusader and a crusader shows up. When
you're waiting for a grave robber and a grave robber shows
up.
And it's funny to watch people tweet about this, because full
disclosure, there's no crazy systems in that we detect what
you want and we don't give it to you or anything like that. But
you know, some people are like, you know, I'm 20 weeks in and I
haven't seen a god damn alien. So, yeah, that's just roll of
the dice. But it should be sort of exciting when you really
desperately need another plague doctor to fit, you know, because
you lost one from your A team and you need to bring one back.
And
We made the conscious choice, though, of not to try to balance them all.
This, to varying degrees of success, but it wasn't just because it would be difficult.
We actually wanted it to feel a little spiky.
You know, like first edition D&D. Like, it's crazy.
Monks and, you know, monks and magic users are basically just like babies in radio flyers
that you have to pull around for the first couple levels.
You know, but then by the time they get to level 12 it's crazy.
They're wiping out entire armies and that kind of stuff.
And I think that spikiness is really fun.
You know, sometimes there's this like crusade to balance the hell out of your game.
I think it really depends what you're trying to accomplish.
If it's a multiplayer, you know, it's Hearthstone, yes.
If it's a single player RPG where, you know,
You don't like aliens or you don't like highwaymen as much.
It's not a critical issue. We even had conflict in the team on
this. There was times that people would kind of bring these
things to me and I'm just like, I'm really not worried about
that problem right now. And I think it was hard for people to
understand but it was a conscious choice of I'm worried
about the inflection system right now or I'm worried about
something else, not the highwaymen's DPS.
And also I think something that's forgotten is that
characters are the sum of their entire usage throughout the
game. In particular combat and camping. And so a lot of times
again to reference DPS we like this character's DPS is too low.
What about their camping skills? What about their versatility?
What about their range of skills and where they can be positioned
in the party and things like that. And there were plenty of
times where a character was underpowered across the board
and not intentionally. And so we did that early access was great
for that. But I think a lot of times people look at the
immediate usage of something and not kind of the entirety.
Another thing that was really bad about what we did, but good, was everybody's favorite
lord and savior, RNGesus. We have a lot of RNGesus in the game. A lot of variants. A
lot of variants. Intentionally so, which is not always great.
If you make all the right choices in darkest dungeon, you
plan, you assemble a great team, you are experienced, you pick
the right quest, you et cetera, et cetera. We want you still to
get your ass kicked sometimes basically. Now, I want to be
clear, we don't have an AI director system so similar to us
talking about the stage coach. We don't have something that
detects you're doing well and then we swoop in and make it
harder for you. We just rely on the beauty of RNGs and
variance. The darkest dungeon is poker.
Poker, everyone has bad beats in poker if you play poker.
And oddly enough, everyone's bad beat story is exactly the same.
It's just told differently.
I was winning.
I should have won.
I didn't.
And we want you to experience those in Darkest Dungeon.
We don't want to, like the tuning part, the craftsmanship,
the design, is how often, right?
How often do we want you to experience that 2
thirds of the time?
No, if you prepared and planned and took the right party group
into the right dungeon.
And provisioned appropriately and didn't grab every bookcase
in Iron Maiden if you didn't have the right stuff for it. You
should do well. But every once in a while.
Things go badly. And we want to put you in that uncomfortable
space of I should be winning right now. This is getting away
from me. Do I run? Do I abandon? Do I change my plan? Or do I
hang in here and push through? And there's a couple of you
know, this can go a variety of different ways. Maybe you make
that gut check and you hang in there and you win. And that
should be a moment that you love the game. You should also
applaud yourself for having the self-control to retreat and go
back to town and lick your wounds. And I think that
It's hard to communicate that and that's why we put that
first screen up when I showed you like darkest dungeon is
about making the most of a bad situation. We're conditioned to
play where you expect success, especially in the last few
years with mobile games and things. You expect success. And
it's really just a matter of solving the problem to get
there. And if you don't have success, you reload and try and
try again until you get there.
And we fundamentally wanted to change that.
And sometimes I think it's hard to communicate that to players,
that they'll buy the game and then this will happen.
It's just like, what have I gotten into?
And the game is not intended for everyone.
And that's something that I think went well,
but it also caused us an amount of grief as well.
Another thing that, you know,
on my role of just doing things that you shouldn't do.
We, you know, on our final boss, so I'm going to show a little bit from the final boss,
so if you don't want to see it, cover your eyes, if you're still working your way through the game.
And I'm personally not...
I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
Explain it.
Father and mother and Alpha and Omega.
Father, mother, Alpha and Omega.
Our creator and our destroyer.
You are the heart of the world.
I feel a sense of guilt for being so slow.
Alright, let's begin the game.
Come on to your Mako.
what
What do you want me to do?
Do I have to choose one?
Wait, I have to choose one and kill him?
So yes, we did just completely kill a character that had
raised to level 6 with no death's door, no nothing. We
just took them away. By that time you probably put, I don't
know, 10 hours in that character, maybe a little more,
who knows. Actually, if it was Raynald or Dismas, that's all
the more meaningful. The tutorial characters, of course.
So yeah, that's a terrible design decision. That's a rage
inducing thing.
But we're so happy we did it. We couldn't be happier actually.
Anyway, there's a whole, I don't know if you got a chance to see Chris' talk yesterday on the creative direction of the game.
But that was really important in paying off this cosmic horror in the overall narrative.
And when that goes up on the vault, I encourage you to check that out.
He'll talk more about that battle.
But we wanted you to experience that final battle in a specific way.
And Darkest Dungeon has been about loss the whole time.
And so yeah, we were a little cheap.
And we make you remember that even more during the final battle.
I'm going to get a little faster through some of these so we can go through.
Another thing that was pointed out very often to us about poor design here was healing versus
damage.
The amount of healing, the numerical values do not keep pace with the amount of damage
you receive.
That was repeatedly reminded to us. And we were like, awesome,
by design. So the quests are a battle of attrition. The longer
you go, eventually your character should die and become
afflicted and stress out. And the whole game is about
Can you get to the end of the quest before that happens or how
much loss are you willing to stomach. If this is your
favorite character, are you going to gold breaking it or
whatever where people always want their guys fully healed,
don't want to make any risk. So you could get one third in a
dungeon and be like screw this I'm out. Whereas other people
are like I'm willing to lose two heroes to get through this.
Even Ezekiel when he lost that third hero,
He held it together pretty well. He knew he was trying to kill a
necromancer and it was worth sacrificing characters. He only
lost it when double death blowed at the end, which to be fair I
think would do it to anybody. So one of the things that worked
really well in the game is just breaking some rules. You know,
the save one is the one I always come back to. The way I love to
play games, I like permissive save systems. Who are you to
tell me how I should and shouldn't save my game?
But when we talked about Darkest Dungeon, we realized that would not work. It would rob the
player of the experience that we intend them to have. And that was an interesting thing to be
advocating and fighting for something that you don't even agree with normally. You agree with
it for this game. And I think that's a really important point. You should never lose sight
that you are designing for that game, not all games or rules of thumb or like make sure you
never do this. So break the rules.
I'm going to hustle through this. Combat is interesting. We
didn't end up at this exact orientation initially. We were
going to do an ultimate style top down, maybe 2D. At least
that's what I was really interested in at first. We were
very inspired by this classic age, Bards Tale. I think you can
see the DNA in the old Bards Tale. It would be like the first
four characters can attack in melee. The next characters can
attack in range. I think you see that in our system in that the
positional requirements in some classes are definitely more
geared towards melee attacks than others.
This is a little more the art side but the gold box games
pull radiance. I know we talked about how effective it was. They
just had an idle and an attack. They sit there and then they
just go. And not to undersell the amazing freaking art that
these guys did. But we're not a game that's fully animated with
all these crazy key frames. They made the most of kind of a light
amount of assets. A ton of work I will add before they kill me.
They're eyeing me right now. It makes me nervous. We did a lot
of visual prototyping. This is something that worked well
working with Chris. This sometimes saved us having to
code things up or make things and try them. He would sketch
stuff out. We would talk about the system, kind of mock up what
it might look like, find the holes in that. And I think that
was helpful. Here's an example of realizing, hey, not only
with this new system and the slots, but we can have
characters that are bigger.
He was working out what poses might be required, trying to
figure out tool tips, which is I think at one point I was
nicknaming tool tip or something.
I don't know.
It ended up like this.
And I think combat is something that has really
served the game well.
Probably one of the biggest unknowns of combat for me was
will there be enough depth in this 1D system. And it was
still something, honestly, I fought even up through the last
dungeon, the cove. It was starting to get like, okay, how
many more weird moves can I think of or status effects or
ways to pay off this. But it held together and I think there
was definitely enough depth to pay it off. So that was good.
And in particular I think one subsystem of death's door that
was effective was this, or of combat, excuse me, was death's
door. And this didn't start in there. We were playing combat
and as you might imagine without the death's door mechanic, so
the death's door mechanic essentially means you can't be
killed in one blow. So without death's door you might be
sitting at two-thirds health, someone gets a crit, your
character's dead. And with permadeath that's crazy. Like
you can never be safe. Even at full health you can never be
safe. And we didn't want it like that. Because then that robs
you of all the
You're either tense all the time or you're never tense
because you're just like we're all already dead so what does it
matter. So in this case, you know, a damaging attack, the
most it can do is reduce you to death's door and then you have
potentially a chance to heal or do something to that character
before they die. Now you can still die, obviously, because
sequences of events, you know, you might not get a turn in
between. Your hero may be afflicted. The character you're
trying to heal may be afflicted, et cetera. You may have not
brought healers.
So there's plenty of death. But this door, I think it's like
for such a simple system it's been so effective in raising
attention. I love those moments where your character goes to
death's door and you're nervous and you're confronted with the
law. Should I retreat? Should I try to heal? And that's worked
out really well.
Narration is huge. We brought this narrator in for our
announcement trailer. I don't think at that point we had even
thought about using one in the game. But he was so amazing.
Chris had found these Lovecraft audio books read by Wayne June.
We contacted Wayne June, got him to read for a trailer. And it
was just like, okay, we have to put him in the game. There's
No way we can't. A little side tidbit is Red Hook is named
after the story. We're not in Brooklyn. I wish I would have
thought of that before. We're right next to each other. We're
in Vancouver. But we just thought Red Hook sounded cool.
It's kind of a classic story of power and corruption. Not maybe
the best in terms of Lovecraft's cultural sensitivities. So in
retrospect we feel bad for naming it after that story. But
Red Hook sounds cool.
It's really, yeah, just this quote, the narrator has done so
much and by remarkability I mean just virality of the game,
people talking about it and things like that aside from its
quality. And this happens all the time. It's crazy. You post a
trailer and it will just be strings of comments of the
narrator lines. Or a Reddit post or Twitch channels. And that's
really fun to see. Even pop in places that aren't darkest
dungeons someone will say one thing and it will just go.
And audio as a whole worked really well. This is a design
talk but the reason I want to mention it is it reinforces the
gameplay experience. If any of you do play racing games without
the sound on, I don't understand you because I think they're a
lot more fun with the sound on. And it's not just enhancing
like the experience, it's enhancing the game design, which
I'm grateful for.
Narration here is just where I started to block out where
should he speak, what should he talk about, what kinds of
things should he say. And just wanted to play a couple lines.
The human mind, fragile like a robin's egg. There can be no
hope in this hell. No hope at all. Grievous injury, palpable
fear.
More dust. More ashes. More disappointment.
On that note of disappointment, it's a good time to switch into
the other side of the talk. On the narration side, I want to
say Wayne is awesome, power up master the lines and did the
effects. Chris and I did writing. Chris did most of the
writing. Some of the lines are just really fun to see. I think
even recently someone is like, where is the trinkets and
bobbles line? I haven't heard that in a while. I don't know.
It's like a bug. But someone remembered the line so well,
they were very upset it wasn't playing.
So I love just listening to it. And I think for a gimme one
time power up had Wayne record some other joke lines for each
of us and it was really fun. So yeah, he's got that voice that
sticks out. But yes, disappointment. So how many of
you are familiar with the corpse, the great corpse event?
Okay. Not that many. Okay.
That's good. So we pushed this during early access. We pushed
this amazing patch called the hound and corpse or corpse and
hound. It had all kinds of awesome stuff. The hound master,
sanitary features like new and awful diseases. Steam cloud
save, which is kind of cool. But not as cool as diseases. Corpses
in combat. We were so excited about it. There's even a bullet
point.
This is going to be a little relevant here. But if you
remember the end of the dark night where basically things
start going poorly for Batman. Batman takes a lot of blame for
some things. Leading up to the corpse and hound. So we
launched early access on February 3rd of last year.
And it did, I mean there's no two bones about it, it did far
better than we thought it was going to do. We were launching
into a climate of early access really being looked down upon.
There had been some kind of high profile maybe disappointments.
And there was even this whole early access is dead. Everyone
likes to proclaim the death of the next thing. So early access
is dead and we're like, okay, we're about to launch.
And we launched into that environment. We put our best
foot forward. We delayed because in the fall we wanted to launch
early access. It wasn't ready. We delayed. We were running
extremely thin on our personal runways. And we kind of had to
launch there. We're like, all right. But we had no idea it was
going to be received so well, to be honest. And I think you
could ask, well, actually, Keir. Keir thought it was going to be
received well. The rest of us were nervous as hell. A month
later, my dad died.
So I went from the highest high of my professional life, no
question, to the lowest low of my personal life. I'm grateful
he got to see the launch. I got to share with him how that was
going. But when you're a small team, you know, and
Any one discipline that is taken out of action, your whole team
is derailed. I mean, everybody is not taken out of action, but
how are you going to push a patch that incorporates all
disciplines when one person is out of action. This is my dad
in his natural environment. So we had planned this fiends
infringing patch, which was our first real big non-support
update. And originally it was probably going to try to go in
March or April, but that didn't happen. I was kind of out of
commission for a while.
And so we pushed it in May and it was received pretty well, I
think. Yeah. And things have been just rolling, you know. So
the corpse and hound was really our first time. Because the
fiends and frenzy had been preplanned in a way. And aside
from some game play tweaks, it was sort of preloaded. And the
corpse and hound was the first chance to really collect
Collect info from the community and step back and go what game
systems are not working, what's not working the way we want,
what can we do? And one of the things, it technically wasn't in
the corpse and hound, it came in fiends and frenzy was around
that time was heart attacks. So what had happened is the players
that were getting good at the game could do these dark runs.
They would basically push their team to full affliction and they
realized that the afflictions were not incapacitating so far
that your team couldn't function. And so they just stopped
caring about stress or torchlight or anything and they
would just go.
They would just go run these people through.
And that definitely wasn't the feeling we want in Darkest
Dungeon.
We want you always to feel in a precarious situation.
And so the heart attack system came into play, which basically
was at 100 you have your affliction check and then that
resolves.
But stress continues to build.
You have a little bit of a shock absorber there.
But if you get to 200, and the smiley face, you're dead.
No warning.
It filled a very important role in terms of what we were trying
to get you to experience. And at the time, actually, there was a
little bit of, oh, this is a little rough, but not outcry. So
then in the corpse and hound, we did corpses, which was
So what you see here in this screen image is a corpse in the
front there. And so there had been a dominant strategy, the
table saw strategy, which is focus fire everything on the
first enemy, take them out, and then that collapses everybody
forward. And the enemies in back, generally they just like
heroes had skill prerequisites. So if you're an archer in the
back, you get collapsed forward, you can't use your attack. And
It was just too strong to focus fire on the front and it kind of
reduced the rest of our combat system to maybe irrelevance in
terms of like positioning, ranged attacks, debuffs, buffs,
et cetera. So the corpse is the way they work. You kill the
enemy. They leave a corpse. It remains there. They hold their
formation. They don't collapse forward. And the corpse will
eventually go away or you can spend some extra actions or
resources to eliminate it. And this enhanced, this did a lot of
things. It fixed the dominant strategy. It enhanced the
systems that we had built.
And we thought it did so thematically. We didn't
implement it up to our usual standard and that's partially
for reasons I'll get to in terms of like usually we try to blow
you away visually and this was no fault of the artist. It was a
game play experiment in a way. So every corpse looked the same.
We didn't have custom corpses per enemy and things like that.
And also we had thought of a lot of other ideas, or at least I
had in terms of we could buff up the front rank melee enemies to
generally be a lot tougher, these sorts of things. So it was
better than the other design options.
Oh, yeah. Well, I thought people were going to love it. They lost
their minds. It's really hard to overstate how much they lost
their minds. It's definitely, I mean, at least for me, but I
think Chris would agree it's the hardest thing we've had to deal
with on the game. And we've had a lot of challenges on the game.
And hardest probably just emotionally.
It splintered our community which had been big and growing
and excited and generally, really we had had it very, very
good. It was very positive. Everything had been received
well generally and people were kind of patiently waiting for us
to plug some holes in the game. It created this changing wave of
sentiment and it was an easily told story, this promising game
gone bad. That wasn't fun to look at Steam and look at the
helpful reviews and see literally four pages of nothing
but negative.
This is a whole story in itself but this also coincided with
people that were not just unhappy that we had added this
into the game but that decided that we were basically the most
terrible people on the face of the planet and remain to believe
that way today. And I think this narrative versus truth was hard
for us because what I mean by that is people who played the
game and said I don't like the courses, we respect that
opinion. People are like, I heard they ruined the game.
It's like, well, where did you hear that from? That was tough
because we were also still continuing to develop the game
and we had been excited by how well the game had been received.
This patch launched in July and I remember thinking, you know,
people are going to grouse a little bit. It's a big change,
but then they'll get used to it. And I was in Colorado, so my
father had been cremated and went back to Colorado where
we're from to intern him and be with family, et cetera.
And I remember it was either the night before we were going to
bury him or the night after, Chris calls me up and we're
having this talk and he's like, it's getting really bad. I
don't know what to say. They're not getting used to it. The
community is blowing up. It was a tough time.
And this is one way to illustrate it. In July we were
really lucky to have a very popular website that serves a
lot of gamers that are exactly the sort of gamers that we want
to reach. They put us in this top 50 RPGs of all time. These
are games like Ultima are on there. And it was a huge honor.
They're like this is the only early access game that's even on
this list. And this was just like, yeah, it was hard to
overstate our excitement of that. That was July. And we
pushed the Corpse and Hound patch. This was August from the
same publication.
So I'm fully afflicted at this point for sure. Just pegged at
like 190 stress and we didn't have our desk door mechanic in
the heart attack thing yet so that was rough. And I kept
hinging on these three words, a sad fate. When I read that,
something just clicked in my head that just...
it was just hard to even comprehend. Because we were
still in early access. And we had been this example of an
early access game done right. And now basically we were being
left for dead on the roadside. They took this great game and
they drove it into a concrete pillar.
And I couldn't get over fate. We're still working on the game
here. And this fundamentally changed my view of early access.
I'm super pro early access for the record. I would happily do
it again. I think we're just, we know more what to expect. But I
thought early access would be a time to experiment with gameplay
mechanics. And I don't know that that's really true.
Especially if your game is already working. If your game
is not working, I think you have the onus, you need to improve
it. But massive changes to people that have already bought
your game, it's a thorny problem. It's even ethical.
They paid for the game. Now you're changing it. That's hard.
So Chris and I spent a lot of time talking. A lot of time
talking. A lot of Google Hangouts. Some drinking. Some
pity parties. Some anger. The full range of emotions.
But what it always came down to is did we do the right thing.
And I remember just thinking like, okay, guys just lay it on
me. Just tell me, was this a horrible mistake? Because
corpses were my idea and I had sold it up through the team.
Just tell me. I don't care. I'll eat crow. Whatever it is. I
just want to make the game right. And I was losing my
ability to see objectively. So it was great because Chris and I
spent a lot of time switching positions, devil's advocate, all
these discussions about what to do.
Meanwhile we have this community management crisis. It's
not like we have time to do this calmly, et cetera.
And one thing that was also relevant is just the psychology
of change. I mean, in other organizations it's a whole field
of study, change management. Some of you may be familiar.
People don't like change. Who moved my cheese and all that.
And not to throw a team member under the bus, but one thing
that had been in my mind before we did this change is that
combat had been working and Chris and Pierre worked to add
this combat camera which fakes it to look like 3D if you
notice in the game that.
I remember putting in and one of the guys on the team saw it
and said, I think this is verbatim, this is the worst
fucking thing I've seen in my entire life.
A week later, two weeks later, I was like, this is cool.
So I thought that would happen with corpses.
So the long story short, and I got a hustle because I wanted
to leave a little time for Q&A, is that we decided it was right
for the game.
It was the right mechanical decision.
It was the right thematic decision.
We stood by it.
You know, that's, of course, a hard decision to make, and we
respect the opinions of people that disagree.
So we're in this weird dilemma of do we remove this and make
what we consider a worse game to make people happy?
And this is something that got us through the next six months.
I'm going to hurry through here. But Chris kept bringing up,
things had gone so well for us, to be honest. It's like at some
point you're going to make a mistake. You have to fall off
the peg. And I was like, I'm going to make a mistake. It's
This was hard. I say fast forward six months but the last
six months up until launching January was pretty rough. We
were sitting here and going is the final story on darkest
dungeon going to be a promising game that was ruined. And
living with that uncertainty I think is instructive just
because you think we would be riding high on early access to
sex. No, we were riding low on what's the legacy of the game
going to be. Fast forward I think an interesting part of
change management is we're not going to be able to do that.
Ultimately the changes were received well. And even people
that had expressed concern in July when they reviewed the
game, they're like, I see why they did this. So that was good.
What got us through is just holding to that creative vision
and investing in more community management. I mean, these are
things we did wrong. We didn't invest in community management
up front. We were too precious about how to present the game
to people and force our way of playing it down their throats.
So we added toggle options. And I think that's something that
we needed to do. And we learned from this experience. And it
also reminded us that we had always said D.D. is not a game
for everyone. And this reminded us that that was the case.
So that's the key learning about early access. Content is always good. I think that, you
know, sustainable gameplay changes, you want to have community management in place. You
want to warn them of the changes. We do this better now. Hey, this is coming down the line.
Just be aware of this. What do you think about this? We push it in a beta branch. Let people
try it out.
That was stuff we really learned. A few other things I'm going to skip through and then leave
just a couple minutes for questions. The bold points are what I want to emphasis. Other
things, we have a lot of grind in the game. We didn't even add the end game until full
launch so we didn't get the benefit of tuning that through early access so we're doing that
tuning now. And certainly I think one of the things we've been repeatedly deemed on is
this grind. We like a consequence, but losing your full level 6 heroes and having to rebuild,
it just causes some people to just throw the game away.
We don't want that. So we've been doing some things to help
with those. Exploration was a really tough design mechanic. I
still believe we haven't totally paid off the walking and the
quests and the curios. In particular, the game started, it
was this auto walk. They kind of walk down the hall and then
things happen. It was terrible. And we almost were going to
restructure all of exploration. When we made it active, it just
made it so much better. So that was something that we spent a
lot of time spending our wheels on.
Everybody's favorite mechanic hunger. It's not that we can't
improve it, it's just that we're, you know, it did enough
and after the corpse thing, quite frankly, we're like, if we
make a hunger system and it's worse, oh, man.
The jostled free, we had these events where you'd be walking
down and pull an event card and something would happen. One of
them was this jostled free. It's like, hey, you're walking down
the hallway and something falls out of your pack. And it just,
can you imagine the rage? You're nice trinket just took it away
randomly. This was really good because it brought up what we
call the jostled free rule.
is, you know, we do a lot to you, but don't arbitrarily with
no, you know, another way of saying it is this.
Yeah, never fully, it's like go get the 20 wolf pelts. There was
a lot of stuff that we could have done. I'm going to skip
right through here because I want to have a couple minutes
for questions. In the end, fortunately the dungeon isn't
too dark. Here's some of the stuff. I want to say about
retention, we didn't design with retention in mind, but the
interesting thing about it is just that it's a sign of do
people come back and play more. And that's important to us. When
you played it and started it, you come back the next day
because you want to play again. And that mobile, you know,
PC, whatever, that's hugely important. More than all those
things is we feel like we made the game we set out to make and
that feels good. We're ready to live or die by that vision and
I'm really, you know, we're incredibly grateful that people
have enjoyed it. A little bit about what's coming. We're not
done. We're still pushing some features. We're coming to other
platforms. We're going to enable modders, stuff like that. And
this is news to even the Red Hook team. Today I'm happy to
announce game number two from Red Hook studios.
Brightest kittens. All right. We've got a couple minutes for
questions and then afterwards we'll move out and we'll probably
get kicked out in a minute. We have five minutes. Okay. Great.
What time period does the game take place in?
We narrowly refined the time period to roughly 500 AD to 1800 AD.
You've got the Hellion which is kind of almost a Pictish barbarian on up to the highway men
with his little scarf and pistols.
That's kind of part of our lore. We wanted the crusader and his heavy metal armor all the way up to the musketeer.
We purposefully have created this alternate universe that isn't super defined there.
Can you speak to the level clamping that was done where the high level characters are no
longer able to go on the low level journeys and what reinforced that decision?
Yeah, sure.
So what he's talking about is basically as your characters level up we prevent you from
taking them on lower level quests and power leveling your younger heroes.
It's not super popular all the time. But the bottom line is if
you can do that, the game is robbed of its tension. And this
is kind of like maybe something that isn't incredibly eloquent
from a design perspective. We're kind of hitting you on the head
with a hammer. But it was absolutely critical to make sure
that we keep you in this risk.
So we loosely justify it and say as they level up they get big
heads and they're like I don't want to waste my time down in
your, you know, you're the FNGs, you guys go on your mission. I'm
sticking with the experienced guys. I think even band of
brothers had a cool thing like that where they're like as they
progress they're just like the new recruits are coming, don't
talk to them, they're new. If they've lived through a couple
missions then we'll talk to them. But we're not able to
express that. But it's ultimately because we want you
in a position of risk in the game.
If we let you do it, you can just grind your way through the
game and actually not be tense. And we'd rather have you have
fun and be tense than succeed and not be tense. Thank you.
Hi. First of all, thank you very much for the talk. It was really great. I'm not sure for what it's
worth, I think you made the right call. I think the game that you wanted to make, all your
decisions to go towards that and the community will probably get used to it eventually. As far
as the question, you mentioned that when you were in early access a lot of the stuff that you
changed obviously was in the corp stuff. What was some other stuff that you changed during
early access and did any of it surprise you?
Yeah, we did a lot of hero changes based on feedback. A
lot of stuff we planned out, we knew we were going to make the
new dungeons, things like that. I think one thing we changed in
the sanitarium was we split treatment into diseases and
quirks. We allowed the ability to lock quirks in and also if
some negative quirks could become permanent and those would
cost more to unlock. So I think that was really necessary to pay
off that system more. And that wasn't something we knew exactly
up front.
I'm trying to think of some other things. You know, more
mechanics. Every hero that we tried to put in, we tried to
usually do a new mechanic. I mean, the houndmaster had his
pet and the dog treats. The man at arms had the riposte. And so
that was really fun. And also challenging because every time
we added a new mechanic, we were like, oh, man, I wish we could
retrofit this through the whole game. And we weren't always able
to do that. I think it's one reason that a lot of people like
the code monsters the best mechanically because they came
the latest and we were able to make full use of the whole
palette at that point.
So often times in design you run into situations where parts of the game feel like they're
fighting themselves.
Like for instance, you talk a lot about creating the human connection with the units.
But then also because you get such a large supply of them, it's almost better for as
a player to not connect with them so you don't get all tilted when they die.
Similarly, you talked a lot about how you put so much effort and work into the affliction
system where the players spend most of their time trying to avoid afflictions.
They spend a lot of the time trying to avoid stress altogether.
So how do you kind of deal with that as a designer, figuring out where to kind of draw
the line of what's helping and what's hurting?
Some of it we intentionally don't totally draw a line.
The hero one, for example, and Chris talked about this a little bit yesterday in his talk,
but people play the game differently.
So some people get very, very attached to naming their heroes.
We encourage you to name your heroes after your friends and loved ones.
And then when they die, you lose your mind.
That's awesome.
We love that.
And then some people become very jaded, and they look at
them as meat bags that are basically means to an end.
And they don't even name them, or they name them like
Crusader 2, Crusader 3.
Or sometimes a little bit like Baldwin 1, Baldwin 2.
So they had a name originally, and then they
keep his lineage up.
But a lot of people post.
I love reading these posts.
They'll say, this game, I have these heroes.
They're dead.
I hate it.
What am I doing wrong?
I'm terrible at the game.
And then people will say, okay, you're thinking this all wrong.
You need to look at these.
You need to just go in there.
You need to run them to their desks until you get some money.
Dismiss them.
Pick a few select heroes to really invest in.
Let the other ones just, you know.
And I love that interplay.
There's no right way to do it.
So there we let that kind of...
As far as the affliction system, that's hard. We want you to be
afflicted. That's a balance issue. If I watch streams or get
a lot of feedback that people are going through and never get
afflicted, I'm like, that's a problem. I want people to get
afflicted. That's a game balance issue.
Hi, so speaking of naming characters after your family, you mentioned high level characters
dying and that being a really big turn off.
I know the same thing happens in games like XCOM.
Was that something you...
didn't think you would be able to fix or was it something that
reinforced that hopelessness motif? And in a perfect world,
would you add something that would help getting your feet
back? Yes. So we just did, actually. We just pushed
something to help get your feet back last week. So now we have
in the stage coach there's an upgrade tree that allows you to
unlock the ability to hire higher level heroes.
And so that's really important. And then the, what else, we
increased the power leveling benefit from heroes that have
been to the dark's dungeon come back and have the never again
trait. So I would say that originally we wanted that sense
of loss, but one minute left. We wanted that sense of loss.
But really getting wiped on a full level 6, no, that's too
much. It's too much if someone literally walks away and doesn't
play the game again. We want you to be angry for a night and
then come back tomorrow and be victorious. And so I think we
just kind of had to think of how to do that. And we're losing a
level 2 hero is no big deal. Losing four level 6s is a big
deal. So, yeah, we're actively trying to improve that.
Thank you.
All right. Last question, I think.
When should a game go early access?
Ah, when it's ready.
My advice is wait as long as you can.
Because early access, we've now had a number of successes.
There's been lots of good games in early access as well.
And I think that people will always be receptive to more good early access games.
But they will very quickly jump on games that are not fun, not buggy yet.
So you really have to make those hard choices.
you know, is this game ready for prime time? I think a game that
fundamentally has its loop in place and it's fun but maybe out
of balance and missing some content, that's where, like if
we do our next game, I think when we know it's fun, we don't
know about the balance and it's maybe, you know, 50% content
complete, that might be a good time to launch. I think if
you're like, let's throw it out there and see where it lands, I
would do your own sort of private play testing first
because it's really hard to come back from the perception that
it's a bad game. All right. We'll sneak the last one.
Who's on your A team? I don't play this game. It's too
stressful. Thank you very much. Please fill out your reviews.
You know, when you get the e-mail, it would be great to
know and maybe they'll invite me back again. After brightest
kittens.