So, my name is Justin Corey.
I've been working at Servios for about four years
as a lead artist.
Joined the company in 2014, worked on raw data,
and then once we wrapped that up,
moved to this awesome music experience called Electronauts.
So, Electronauts is not a game, it's not a tool,
it's an experience.
It's a music creation experience.
And it's one of those things that...
You can't quite put your finger on it,
what you're going to do with it, because it's just,
the art is driven by the engineering.
And OK, quick shout out to Raw Data,
first VR game to generate 1 million in less than a month,
and the first VR exclusive game to top number one
on Steam's global sales charts.
And we just released Sprint Factor recently,
where we patented the fluid locomotion technology.
And again, top number one on Steam and Oculus.
So let's talk about the visual language of electronauts.
So what you'll see here is our electronaut.
He's pretty funky, he's pretty awesome.
He's an astronaut who plays music.
And let's go over the story.
Electro-universal.
In the future, humanity harnesses the power of the harmonic wavelength known as the electro-harmonic
grid.
While rippling through the depths of the universe, a great disruption in the harmonic fields
causes the electronauts to become separated, lost in four different quadrants of space,
cosmic, technology, alien, and psychic.
You must groove through each zone and use your melodic resonance spheres to make the
universe dance and unite.
It's time to get the band back together.
And okay, first term, one of these terms was used often
when describing the electronauts and something
that we adhere to, which is synesthesia.
It's a perceptual phenomenon in which the stimulation
of one sensory or cognitive pathway leads
to automatic involuntary experiences
in a second sensory or cognitive pathway.
Best way to describe this is you hear music, you dance.
It's one of these things that you just can't control.
And yeah, it plays a big part in the game here.
And when I first heard this term, it was by a man named Tetsuya Mizuguchi.
If you guys work in games and you don't know his name, for shame.
He's been around for quite a while.
Worked at Sega, responsible for the Sega Rally series,
Rez, and Space Channel 5.
So he says, the majority of music games fall
into the category of rhythm based or time based,
Mizuguchi says.
That's not where my interest is.
Rather, it's more about how the layering of music
with visuals changes the world that you're in.
And that becomes an experience in and of itself.
So very cool.
It's not just about the game.
He's more interested in just getting your attention.
So let's talk about the music reality engine.
This is something that Servios developed.
It's our core technology for electronics.
Okay, so you might say, what is the music reality engine?
It's essentially a technology that allows a person to be a performer,
even if they are not the most musically inclined.
It's a beautiful piece of technology because for me, you know,
I've tried to play instruments all my life and never fully succeeded.
And then, you know, the minute I touch this game or this experience,
it just changes everything and you can have fun with it, you get lost in it forever.
So moving on to our inspirations,
and again, Tetsuya Mizuguchi.
Space Channel 5 was, again, one of the first games
that we discussed when we talked about kind of
the fun nature and the language of the game.
It's one of those things that as you play,
the experience grows, the environment moves more,
the colors shift more.
It really rewards you for performing well.
And it's just something that we kind of inherently
built into the Electronauts game.
EDM also a very big influence on our game.
The colors, the strobing patterns, the embodiment of nature and science and math,
lots of geometric shapes, lots of movement.
You'll see these heavily used in our visualizers.
Space, another big inspiration, especially in terms of color palette.
You'll see a lot of these nebulas share very similar and almost cosmic-like colors
that inherently just kind of happen to be included in our game.
And yeah, it's just such a beautiful thing to look at and really just, again,
you'll see it everywhere when you're just carooning through the space.
So let's move on to the Prodigy One.
Prodigy One is essentially the hub.
It's the place where you start any song
that you're about to play.
It's essentially a radio station in space.
You're broadcasting yourself out,
and you see this tunnel, you get launched through it
every time you go to your next track.
So this concept was originally done by Brian Higgins.
Great guy, very, very awesome and talented person.
So when I joined the company,
or I mean the project more like it,
there wasn't really a very clear direction
in terms of where things were gonna go.
We were going very hard sci-fi,
and while it's cool,
didn't exactly reflect the kind of experience
we wanted to bring.
So really without trying to shake up things too much
or change things too much,
I kind of tried to make a few quick
adjustments to the visual style of the game.
It was really just about bringing the color palette
to something that matched the mood.
So we kind of moved into this direction.
Incorporating more music into the environment.
Turning the look of the sci-fi to something
that you'd find more in a, like a, you know,
audio equipment.
So looking at the materials that you'd find
in audio equipment was like a big inspiration
for the kinds of shapes that we'd use for the environment.
You can see at the bottom right corner,
that is your launch tunnel.
And we wanted the decorator to look like a stage
like if you were performing at a concert.
For me, I think that was the biggest selling point,
is that because people are about to go off into these zones,
you want them to feel like they're about to, you know,
enter a stage.
So that was a big, big selling point for me.
And these are the concepts again.
These are a combination of some of the modeling blockouts
that I did in conjunction with paint overs that Brian did.
So here is the in-game shot of a very epic sequence
where you're flying from space,
you enter into this ship through a large tunnel,
and then you land into this hangar,
which is there where you'll launch out to your next song.
So this is the Prodigy 1 interior in real time.
And here's our launch tunnel in real time.
This environment.
was very, very intimidating to build.
The scale of it is just absolutely massive.
When you see a character inside of this environment
in relation to everything else, it's just, it's dwarfing.
And the trick is to find the right balance of scale
and the balance of detail, and also get it done on time,
which was not much time to do.
But you'll see we've got, you know, a lot of the colors
that the nebula is represented, all represented here.
Very unified.
And when you're in there, everything's just bumping.
Music's going.
Speakers are moving.
Lights are strobing.
It's very, very awesome.
So here's the Progeny 1 exterior.
So remember when I told you we fly into this ship?
Well, this is the ship that you fly into.
Again, another awesome concept by Brian Higgins.
So my goal here was to try and recreate this as best as possible while also making it performant.
Not the easiest task.
So let's look at the literal translation of this into 3D.
So here's my take on it.
We move away from concept and we start getting some details in there.
And this is the polished piece that is now the Prodigy 1.
The rail gun on the front is kind of like...
A really powerful image to look at because it just makes you feel, you know you're just
getting shot straight out of there.
It's very clear, it's very direct, it's just incredibly interesting shapes.
And again, attaching speakers to everything was just a big motif.
Wanted to beat you in the head with it.
Here's a back shot.
So, you know, one of my difficulties,
yes I'll get concept, but then I don't necessarily know
exactly all the details that need to go into it, right?
So, again, trying to look at references of audio equipment,
just general turntables,
everything that I could get my hands on,
I start incorporating that into this ship.
Get a little closer here.
Again, in this year's scale of these things, the biggest trick is balancing the small details
to the large details.
And you'll see here to your right is the back end of the ship, which you need to get probably
the majority of the love because that's what you see the most.
And I'm very happy with the end result and, you know, I think ultimately it really served
its purpose.
And once you fly into that back end, it's pretty epic.
So moving on, then we have the Wave Rider.
Wave Rider is, again, this is what you're always
flying through or flying inside of
as you're going through your visualizers.
It's a very fun looking ship.
Originally I wanted it to be like a Cadillac,
like a space Cadillac,
because it's kind of like this motif
that I've always thought about for quite a while,
especially when this game popped up.
But ultimately we kind of settled on something
that was a bit more unified
for the look of the entire environment.
But yeah, still very cool, got equalizers,
speakers everywhere.
I think the idea is that everything is propelled forward
by sound, audio waves.
And then here's shots of the Wave Rider in game.
Pretty good translation, you know,
not exactly ideal or identical,
but still very happy with the look of it.
But yeah, it's a,
very cool place to be on in the inside as well. Unfortunately I don't have a shot of the
actual interior of that. But you'll hopefully get a chance to go down and play it today
because it's on the show floor. Okay, so let's talk about our Electronaut. So we had a
wonderful character concept artist named Keegan. He came on board in the middle of the
project and was really just spending
a lot of time just kind of fleshing out the design,
trying to take it to a little more fun direction
than just straight sci-fi and astronaut.
And ultimately we ended up moving into this direction.
Very colorful, very vibrant,
matches the environment, matches the ships.
Just very fun and wacky.
This character model was done by Daman Woods.
He's our lead character artist at the company.
He's a busy man.
He does a lot of character work for us.
And here's a look at some of our visualizers that we designed.
These were done by Gabriel Valdivia.
Gabe is also a tech artist at the company,
and a very talented guy, very creative guy.
Really, really, really enjoyed the inspirations
that he put into this game.
And also, you can see in this image
is a couple examples of our instruments.
The spheres you see in front of you are the harmonic spheres.
These are the initial instruments that you
use to generate your audio.
Very, very intuitive, very simple, and very fun.
Disco balls were a big inspiration for these guys
because initially the visual look of the game
was not dictated by the art direction,
but more by the technology, right?
And what the designers put in.
So it was all very, very prototyped,
but once you started using it,
you didn't want to change it.
You didn't want the art to then take over the experience.
So we had to kind of accommodate those things.
The things below you are your decks.
You'll see these nice hovering
or these nice holographic patterns coming from the bottom.
And these cubes that are inserted
into each one are your different instruments
and your different ways to interface with the.
the whole experience.
On our left, we have our backtracks,
which you can queue up and set up.
And then we also have filter cubes to the right of that,
those gray cubes.
And then to the right of the center,
you'll see that there's a few other colored cubes.
Those are your other instruments,
and there's some fun stuff there to play with.
So.
Another great visualizer by Gabriel.
I believe part of the Tech Zone.
It also has one of our other instruments
called the Lava Loops.
So this was also again a very gray box kind of thing.
It was just a cylinder with a cylinder on top of it.
And you know.
You don't really know what to do with something like that because again it's an interface
and you don't want to change the way it works.
So I just said, okay, well, you know, why not make it a lava lamp or something like
that because, you know, as a kid I remember having those in high school and, you know,
they're kind of a part of the whole psychedelia.
They can be totally related and everybody recognizes these in some fashion.
So yeah, I think it turned out pretty well.
I like what they did with it.
And again, once you see what the interaction is
with these things and the music and the sounds
that they produce, it's pretty awesome.
And then two of my, actually,
one of my most favorite is this synth orb right here.
It's kind of like one of those plasma globes that you get when you're a kid where you touch it with your finger and the electricity sparks to it.
That was like one of the initial things as we were playing with it, and it had a few iterations, but
Of course, when you touch it, you kind of didn't know what you were getting out of it.
And once we turned it into this plasma type effect, it became very clear how you interact
with it.
It has all kinds of layers to it.
It's a 3D interaction, so you can move inside, outside, up and down on it.
It creates some very interesting noises.
And then we have a harp that's kind of like...
It's a very fun one to play with.
There's also kind of a tough one for the designers to really...
to really believe in but I think they kind of figured out how the interaction should work
because plucking something in VR is actually not that simple. But they solved that pretty
nicely. Let's see... Here's one more visualizer... And then... Okay. Actually this is also
cool. So these tracks on our right, we just recently incorporated audio, I mean voice work.
So before it was all just...
instruments, right? And then getting actual voices into the game was a tough challenge.
How do we get vocals to work? So one of the most interesting and one of the last things
that kind of got into the game was this vocal track system. And again, please do try it
when you get in there. It's a ton of stuff to play with.
And lastly, it looks like we have our audio grenades.
So these are things that are kind of like one offs
that you can throw into the air and just have fun with
and they explode and make a cool noise.
And again, I would say when it comes to the visualizers,
I can't speak for Gabe and his inspirations,
but for sure this one you see right here
is one of my favorite
and I don't know if you guys have ever played OutRun,
but it's an old Sega arcade game.
Essentially, as you're playing and hitting the instruments,
you're going to see these waves fly by that
are like cars on a track.
And I think, in general, a lot of the look of these visualizers
were heavily inspired by the 80s and the synth wave, which
I think is just a very cool thing to see come back.
The 80s had a big part in the overall visual direction of this game.
Kind of gaudy, kind of outrageous, very colorful, very neon,
but ultimately, it really sells the idea of technology, the future,
and then the type of music that we're all interested in, which is electronic music.
And then, that's pretty much it.
So, thank you guys for letting me come out.
I really appreciate you taking the time to listen, and I hope you guys get a chance to get on the show floor and play the game.
How are we doing on time by the way?
Plenty, okay.
Questions, yes.
Like how much time did it take to create each one?
It really ranged depending on like
from concept to execution.
I think anywhere between two to three weeks.
Luckily, a lot of the elements that make up those visualizers are relatively simple objects,
but it's more about how do you tie all that together.
They're also very reactive to what you're doing.
They're not just these things that are looping behind you, but colors are shifting, scales
of things are changing, the rate of these things are all being affected by your performance.
Gabe will love you for saying that.
He worked very hard on these visualizers.
And another guy, James Littlejohn,
he's one of our VFX and tech artists.
A lot of the effects that you see,
all the instrumentation,
every little detail that's not readily apparent
is all done by him as well.
And those guys work very closely together
to help create that look.
So I had a quick question.
Sure.
For folks who naturally play instruments and stuff like that,
they obviously have a leg up.
But those who are new to it, what kind of visual language
did you use to cue them as to when
would be a good time to hit a crescendo or stay on the beat?
Or did you guys problematically just push it to stay on beat?
I think at the end of the day, because
of the
music reality engine and what we're doing under the hood,
no matter when they decide to hit that orb,
it's going to sound right on beat.
As somebody who is more musically inclined than others,
you're going to have a much better time at performing,
right, but for those that are just,
they've never really picked up an instrument,
they don't know how to dance,
or they don't know how to keep a beat,
it's gonna make you sound as good as it can,
and it does pretty well.
I mean, you can go pretty crazy on that stuff,
and it just ends up sounding really great.
But yeah, for those that are inclined and have some experience, it's going to only enhance
that that much more.
I mean, what I show you in those images does not really explain the amount of depth that
that thing has.
It's just absolutely amazing how much you can actually do.
So you can queue up sequences, you can have all kinds of modulation going on.
It's just, it becomes just an experience and then becomes more
of like a production environment if you want it to be.
So the layering is just absolutely crazy.
I remember just when it first started it was just the orbs,
right, and it was just that alone was enough
to keep me going for a long time.
And I mean anybody who gets in there winds up playing
for 45 minutes to an hour straight and you have
to pull them out because they just won't leave it, which is.
pretty much speaks for itself in how awesome it can be.
I think inherently everybody wants to be a performer,
everybody wants to be able to be the cool guy
who's playing and DJing at the club,
and it really gives you that opportunity to do that.
I mean, we got, you know, awesome thing,
we got to be at South by Southwest,
and we were performing on stage there,
and it was a great feeling to see that.
I was really proud for the guys.
And another thing to keep in mind is a lot of the audio tracks that you hear in the game are not just
musicians but the engineers that made the game. So these guys are, you know, they love music, they
really believe in music, they take it very seriously even though it's a very fun and wacky game, but
they spend an insane amount of time building the technology. And all I did was come in
and kind of try to help make sense of what they built
and give it some visuals to it, right?
I certainly didn't join the project as an art director.
I'm just the lead artist who is there
to help get things done and help move things forward.
And since I did come in so late,
it was kind of like, we just knew we had
to enhance everything a bit more.
Because I mean, I always felt it could stand on its own,
to be perfectly honest.
I was just happy that I was allowed to come in
and add some extra speckle to it, you know?
Cool, thanks.
Mm-hmm.
Hi.
You mentioned that the engineering was the one that
influenced the art direction.
Yeah.
Was there a point during the development
that it was the other way around,
like the art direction influenced
how things would be made or the design of the game?
I would say absolutely no.
I mean, when it comes to something like this,
My job is just to enhance and help, right?
I have no interest in letting my art dictate
how you interact with things
and just how you are supposed to experience everything.
I just wanna help drive what they've built
and make it something pretty to look at
and something fun to look at.
Again, if there was really nothing else but making the music, I still think it would just
be amazing.
So it's hard to say.
Like the only major influence I had overall was just this introduction sequence that many
people have not gotten to see yet.
So visually speaking, I noticed that you changed the design of the first area where the ships
were to match the color scheme.
How did, like, how was this process of balancing, like, say, the visualizers color schemes with
the overall color scheme of the game?
Because I feel like it can get pretty distracting if you have, like, a bunch of, like, yellows
and oranges with a bunch of, like, blues and purples in there.
Well, it's one of those things, I mean, if you go to these festivals, you go to these concerts, right,
it's all about the distraction. It's just an eye festival, it's eye candy everywhere,
and part of that is just the culture of it, right? It's, again, psychedelia. It's all about
trying to overload your sensory, your sensors with whatever you can, be it the music and then
the visuals. But I do worry about, like, if that inhibits the player from playing the game, like...
I certainly think, if anything, the player is always just focused on what's in front of them.
You know what I mean? It's very rare that you're taking your eyes away from your instrument, right?
Everything else around you is there for everybody else to observe and enjoy.
It's not necessarily for you as a performer.
So really, as people are playing their music...
You want these really bombastic visuals going on in the background.
You do want these strobing elements.
I mean, it's just the nature of the electronic music scene.
Right.
So they'll be able to stay focused.
Oh yeah.
And even if you can't focus and you're just like, Oh my God, I can't do this.
Like you just, you're smacking the orbs and everything sounds great and you're
having a blast and people around you are having a good time.
All right.
Hello.
Great talk.
I'm curious about the iteration process.
Is there a point where?
as the music comes in, the visuals change or vice versa?
Like is there, like how does the synergy work between that
and how does the iteration process?
So the visuals themselves, like the visualizers are,
were completely dictated by, you know, Gabriel
and the audio itself is completely separated
from that experience, right?
The only thing I can say is the way that they tie
these things together is just through the technology
of what they built in their engine.
And then how do we transition from one song to the next
and one room to the next is also its own
interesting experience.
We kind of, they've done an amazing job
of being able to merge the worlds together
and blend them together.
You're not just loading in and then loading out
and then loading in.
You actually feel like you're traversing
and kind of just ripping through space
and ripping into these zones.
And just the language of it all
just was handled very nicely.
I mean, it's kind of, it's one of those things
that's so abstract you can't necessarily
describe these things, right?
It's like the game is.
The game is a very, very, it's very out there.
It's just like everything about it is just,
you can't put, it's hard to put words to.
I mean, if you saw half of those visualizers,
how would you even begin to describe
what you saw really, right?
Cool, thanks.
You're welcome.
How much time was spent on the concepting stage?
Concepting?
Oh, that for me is impossible to say.
All I can say is when I joined,
because again, I was finishing up raw data,
and as soon as I finished it,
I was moved on to this because it was like,
they needed somebody to help comb
and tie these things together,
and then just put polish down on it,
and they had already done.
I mean, I could show you all,
even from the visualizers,
I mean, I've dug through everything.
an insane amount of conceptualization went in from the instrumentation to the visualizations.
And then of course when we got to the ship itself, I mean, that was I think one of the
toughest times.
So quite a bit of iteration.
I mean, for me to collect all that stuff to display would have been quite a bit, and I
was already feeling, I'm quite surprised how fast I kind of just talked through the whole
thing, but there's just an insane amount of stuff that they did.
So it's just...
If at some point we'll probably have these these things available online
It would be great for us to collect all of our art and just kind of share it with everybody because you would be shocked
How much has changed was a mostly 2d painting type stuff or like?
Well, it's a combination of the boat, right?
It's like start with all the geometric patterns and all these really hard surface shapes these very precise elements have to be you know
It's best to do them in 3d and then add everything on top of it
Thanks
We good? Everybody cool?
All right, well, thank you very, very, very much.