Okay, hi, my name is Jonny Jungstedt, I'm art director at DICE.
And I'm here today to talk you through the journey I was to make a Starlight's Edge,
Starlight's Game, like Mirror's Edge.
Everything from an idea to how it was conceptualized, and how we then iterated and refined the style,
and then how it ended up in the game.
So this is not going to be a technical talk in any way,
it's going to be purely focused on the aesthetics and the design process around this,
and how we were thinking about making the universe.
And if you want to know more about the technical aspect,
then you can listen to Fabian Kristins presentation
he held earlier this year in San Francisco.
So first, short about me then.
So I've been now in the gaming industry for 15, 16 years.
And actually, most of those years have been here at ICE.
So it's a great company.
I can highly recommend it.
I guess I've been doing the most things
you can do as an artist.
I started as a 3D modeler.
And actually, the first game I made was.
a game called Legacy on Rosemont Hill.
That was a horse game for ten year old girls.
And don't ask me why we did that one, but it was a game.
Actually, the first game I made for DICE was a game called Shrek.
It was done to the GameCube.
And a few young people here may be don't know what a GameCube is,
but that was a console that existed a long time ago.
And actually, that game actually scored
three out of ten by IGN.
Maybe not my proudest moment in life but at least it gave me a chance to work with games
and I started to get an understanding for how it is to work with it.
It gives me some really nice... I just wanted to learn more about it.
So then I learned level art, and then moved on to VFX,
did lighting, character art, and then became a lead artist
on Bat Company 2 in Vietnam, and then after that,
art director on Medal of Honor, some Battlefield expansion
packs, and now art director on Mirage Catalyst.
So that's all my journey.
So if we just quickly can raise your hands,
how many of you actually played the first Mirage Edge game?
Oh, okay, great.
And I'm a new played Mirage Catalyst.
Okay, great.
So actually, I can see that you already know
a little bit about this universe already.
Let's just do a really quick recap.
So the first Mirage came out in 2008.
And it's quite iconic, quite distinct,
you know, with the white city
and the bold use of accent colors.
It was a first-person parkour game,
where you heavily focus on the movement.
And that game was actually done in Unreal.
And there they pre-baked the light maps,
which is what helped to create this really interesting
stylized game in terms of light bounce and color bleeds.
But that also meant that their level was going to be static.
And their level design approach was more direct
and it was more linear as well,
versus what we wanted to do with Mirror Search Catalyst.
Who's that in the window?
It's a damn kid. Get her!
Dogen sends his best.
Enjoy your freedom.
Faith Connors, wherever I turn, here you are.
The only language you and your kind speak...
is destruction.
It's good to have you back, girl.
I heard some runner got out of juvie today.
What are you gonna do next?
I'm gonna run.
I'm gonna send a clear message to Kruger.
Then you'll have to shoot me too!
Come on, girl.
Save us all.
What is that?
That is your future.
So this was actually a reboot.
Now we want to retell Faith's original story.
We wanted you to give yourselves a chance to know
more about Faith and her friends and his universe.
And also, we wanted to create a more immersive
storytelling, and that's why we moved away from 2D cutscenes
and then we made in-game renders instead.
And we also want to give you.
the freedom of choice. The freedom of choice of traversing the space the way we wanted
you to do and just have fun in this massive city. So that's why we opened up the city
much more for you as a player. And we also wanted to create a city that was dynamic and
full of life. And that's why we investigated a lot of technology and time in developing
the Thamuday systems, crowds, traffic, LMS, anything that will help us make this city
feel very rich and very vibrant.
So that meant that we couldn't pre-bake the lightmaps
that we did in the first game.
So even if we wanted to, we couldn't just recreate the look
from the original game.
That's why we had to do something different.
So we knew from day one that this game was
going to be different.
Then I had to sort of establish the what, from a visual
perspective, what's going to be different and why.
Then how should we think about when we're
creating this universe?
And what we decided to go for was to create a very distinct style and tone.
And this style and tone was sort of going to be affecting everything we do from art, animation, design.
And this was sort of being the glue for this experience.
And I guess here's what's the first lesson I learned.
That is when you are working with a stylized game, it's really important you create very simple but clear design rules.
Define strong keywords, then you're going to use them over and over again on the team.
And it was also about exposing them to images and mood boards.
Anything that sort of reflected the style and the vibe that we were going for.
We just filled the visual libraries with these images.
Because essentially I just wanted the team to live and breathe this style and tone.
And the keywords we decided to use for our style and tone
was believable, it was elegant, and it was aptitude.
So we wanted to create a believable world, a world that the player can accept and can relate to.
So we just immerse ourselves in the fiction and in the story.
So it was then important for us to ground it into something the player can recognize,
otherwise we would risk creating something that would feel surreal or artificial.
If you think about it, it would be impossible to keep a white world white the whole time,
because the forces of nature, pollution, mankind, all of these things would affect it in some way.
That's why, in order to keep it real, we have to make sure that we did add some wear and tear in there.
We need to use different tones of whites, and also we have to have a great understanding of how materials react to light.
That's why PBR helped us a lot.
And our fiction is also taking place somewhere in the near future.
So even though this world was going to feel futuristic, it was still important that it felt recognizable.
So it was going to be a high-tech world, but we didn't want to push it so far so it became something that was sci-fi.
And that's why I used this quote to sort of reinforce that.
And that was something Steven Spielberg said when he created his fiction for Minority Report.
That too was something that was taking place in the near future.
And he said, you don't have to reinvent society in order to portray society.
And that was exactly the mindset I wanted us to have when we created this fiction and this universe.
You don't have to reinvent and redesign everything in order to make it feel like a stylized miniature game.
That was really important for everyone to understand.
So the ratio I use between believability and futuristic is sort of 70-30.
So that meant that 70% of what we create,
we can actually base or present them today.
And then we just apply the other 30%,
it's gonna make it feel like a stylized research game.
I also wanted to create an elegant world.
A world that is bright, pristine, and exclusive.
This is like a world taken to perfection.
So elegant for us means it's white.
And if you strip away all the details and all the unnecessary noise,
take away the greys, the browns and the dirt,
by default, our game is going to feel elegant.
It is going to feel inviting.
And where elegance for me is us, as well, is minimalism.
And I'm pretty sure all of you have heard the expression,
less is more.
And if any game would follow that, this would be that game.
Because you don't understand, this society is all about control.
The conglomerate of controlling the media, the broadcast,
it's cameras everywhere.
They tell you what to eat, what to wear, how to behave.
And for me, minimalistic art style reflects that sense of control.
It's about controlling your design, controlling your space,
removing all unnecessary noise.
Just focus on the core of your design.
And don't hide the flaws in more and more detail in there,
like you do in other games.
And by removing all this unnecessary noise,
that's going to make something that feels very exclusive
and very expensive.
But you think, look at the bag there, for instance.
Look how simple and clean that is.
And the only concentration of detail is around that logo.
Then that makes that logo stand out and read as important.
And that's exactly what's going to happen with everything
we put in our game.
Everything is going to read, everything is going to stand out.
And that's why it's so important that if you place something in there,
it needs to be there for a reason, it needs to have a purpose.
And we also wanted to create a world with attitude.
And what attitude means for us is contrast.
Everything from open to enclosed, from large to small,
warm to cold, etc.
And I sort of wanted to use the attitude to balance back some of the elegance.
Because everything is going to be elegant and white and pristine and exclusive.
But you risk creating something that would feel surreal, artificial, more like a dream world.
And then you would break the believable rule.
And attitude for us is also angular.
So you're going to see that we use a lot of angular cuts and folds and lines.
In everything from key art to character design, architecture, and even on faith, for instance.
And that, for us, is also about being confident.
And understanding that these people, this society, is all
about climbing the corporate ladder.
It's about portraying yourself as somebody
successful and strong.
And that was how we created a certain manner.
So the way you would talk and move would have some sort of
sense of control in it.
But we still had to make sure that it was relaxed and
natural, because we didn't want to have something that
felt clumsy or tense, just over-exaggerated, because
then you would break the elegant rule.
And confidence for you as an artist is being confident in your design.
It's about controlling your shapes, controlling your details,
and dare to be bold and dare to stay minimalistic.
Don't clutter your space just because you feel that it feels a little bit empty.
Always remember, less is more.
So that would be the what, you know, what we want this universe to feel like
and what we want you to think about when you're designing it.
Then the how, how is this interpreted?
How is this translated into something that we can use and
base this universe on?
And that's where the concept of discovery starts.
So now it's about interpreting the style, understanding the
universe, understanding the characters, know how to look
at references, and how to use that to your advantage when
you're creating this universe.
And this was a really long journey for us.
In the beginning, I kept it fairly open.
I think it's important when you're designing something, especially that early, that you really push it too far.
Then when you feel like, okay, now it's too far, that's when you start to dial it back.
Don't do small, intricate steps when you're designing something new.
I think that's really important to remember.
And you can see here now we've explored a lot of architectural details, shapes and forms, softness, diagonal lines, futuristic and so on.
You can see here now we've tried different locations, like in a city, even like how would a wasteland look like in a research world.
And this was also an opportunity for me as an art director to see, you know, how would the artist interpreting this style in a tome?
What happens when it becomes elegant, believable and futuristic?
Another thing is important is sometimes to stop and start questioning yourself and question your design
and ask yourself, why does it look like that?
Sometimes we tend to create shapes and forms just for the sake of creating shapes and forms
and then you're in the wrong way
because you start to lose some of the functionality of it and the believability in the space
So now we're identifying what you like, and more importantly what you don't like and why
And when you know the why, that's when you can start creating guidelines and rules around that.
That's why concept discovery is so important and necessary for you to go through.
At the same time we're doing this, we explore things in the game as well,
everything from shapes and forms, same things.
So we had tons of these images, lots of interesting spaces,
but I still felt that it wasn't grounded enough.
It felt a little bit too experimental.
It was hard to define what it is we actually are doing.
And that's why I think I learned my second lesson here,
was that by giving it too open to interpretation,
it was really hard to define something concrete,
something that would say,
you know, this is a new research style.
And that's why we sort of had to stop, stop and analyze,
get a better understanding of the translate
and how to interpret the style.
And here's also where I felt that, you know,
I had to narrow it down a bit.
I needed to give us something more concrete to base this on.
That's where I took the team to Tokyo.
So Sony needed to give us a chance
to experience something different than something new.
And for you who haven't been in Tokyo, I would really recommend you to go there because it's really interesting space
with architecture and infrastructure.
Even the culture is very different from Europe and the West.
And the reason why I chose Tokyo was because...
If you look at this image here to the left, you can see all the small-scale buildings
and the cluster against the large, massive contemporary structure.
That, for me, is a really nice symbol for how this society functions.
We have the strong, the powerful, the conglomerate towering above the small, the rest of the mass.
So visually, this was like a nice echo of the society.
And you can see as well that Tokyo has a lot of contrast in terms of large and small, but also from old and new.
where you can walk along, look at this really nice, fast, commercialized street
and all the building for say, is a structure in there
which is really detailed, nice and polished and clean
but as soon as you step in a little bit
it was really old and dirty and badly maintained
and I really liked that contrast
And talk to yourselves
about organic and asymmetrical architecture
You can see here, you know
it feels very playful, the way they use the shapes and the forms
So I felt that, you know
If we know how to look at this and analyze it and take away all the things that we don't need,
this will give us a really strong foundation in creating something very distinct and unique.
Of course, we took tons of these images from facades, rooftops, people,
anything that will help us visualize this new style.
So now we have all of these references.
But what would be the difference now versus before?
Because before, when we did do the concept discovery,
we did use tons of references there as well.
The big difference now was, okay,
now we said, let's narrow it down.
Let's, you know, let TOCA be our foundation.
Let's base it on that.
And then we applied the right 30% on top of that.
And also, now I actually wanted to show people
how they could interpret references
and how they can use that to their advantage
when they are designing research.
It was about making people understand and appreciate the shapes and the form in a space,
especially talk in this case.
And remember that you don't have to redesign and reinvent everything in order to make it
look like a research.
And it was also important to show them that you don't get stuck in the detail, especially
not that early in the process where you were.
But when you can see past the detail and you can see past the noise, just analyze the space itself and look at the big structures and the big forms.
You're going to actually see that, like I said before, take away the dirt and noise and all the unnecessary detail, make it white.
Then you're going to have something that feels very elegant.
So you can see that, you know, if we wanted to, we could actually just copy, and talk about one-to-one.
Because for me, that is my research world.
But of course, we had to push it further than this, because we needed to give it a little more edge to it.
But still, it was important to show the people that you don't have to reinvent and redesign everything you do,
because Tokyo has so much things to offer for us already as it is.
Because when you can see past all the data and all the noise,
just look at an image for shapes and adapt functions.
You can actually see, you know, that...
What a building really is, is just a containment for the details.
So not the details themselves are going to make the space look interesting.
If you want to have an interesting space, then you need to think about the big picture.
You need to think about composition.
And if those two are not strong enough, then it doesn't matter how much detail you will throw in there.
Because that's still going to make the space look weak.
Because if you think that you can create an interesting space by throwing in a lot of detail,
You're just doing it the way other games are doing it.
Here is the way we should think about this.
Take away as much as you can and still make it look interesting.
Because if you look at this image and just analyze it,
you can actually see that this image is actually kind of flat.
You can see the building shapes, the building blueprints,
all have the same size.
And the silhouette is actually kind of low.
Everything sort of feels the same.
So sure, it has the elegance.
It's believability.
It has an attitude.
It has a contrast.
I remember what I said before about Tokyo.
You had large contemporary structures.
Now you have the smaller structures clustered next to it.
What happens if you would throw some of that in there?
What does that do to your space?
And all you hear now, you can start to see it creates
some drama, some tension between large and small.
And it was also about telling a story with your space.
and not just randomly throw details in there in order to try to make it feel interesting.
Everything needs to have meaning, and everything needs to have a purpose behind it.
For instance, you know, the story here could have been from new to old.
You can see here I kept the modern, cleaner structures closest to the camera.
That could be the only way to maybe commercialize fancy area.
Then I kept the interior image, the small intricate details,
that could sort of be on the way, maybe,
to an older residential space.
So then you would have this journey for the player
to go through modern, clean,
something that's more intricate, dirty, and old,
and to a residential space.
That would be like a nice journey for the player
to experience.
And then you can turn a big structure into,
in the middle to a landmark,
or that would sort of help you with readability
and navigation.
So you can see here really that, you know, with very little effort, you can actually
create a very interesting space without having to redesign everything.
It's a matter of understanding, you know.
Take away the noise, take away the detail, add back the right 30 percent,
and you're going to have something that feels very stylish and very interesting.
So we did these concepts just to show the artists.
I remember the quote, you know, don't reinvent society in order to portray society.
You don't have to reinvent and redesign everything you do in order to make it feel interesting
and research.
As you can see, our world has so much to offer.
It doesn't matter about your understanding.
Take away the detail, take away the noise, and add back the right 30%.
Then you're going to have something that feels very interesting.
For instance, what happens if we change up the roof of material on here?
What does that do to the experience?
Or, you know, how much did I strip away before we start losing the believability in space?
Or, what happens if you throw in some color in there?
What does that do to it?
Or, when you push it really far, maybe create like a fancy rooftop bar, a restaurant up there.
And for me, I read believable.
I see, you know, the big structure, so it's a partner, a related each other.
I can see, you know, the white, the pristine, the elegance.
I can even see some attitude in there.
So that's the style and tone.
Now we have the keywords.
And I've already showed you how you can interpret references
and how you can use them to your advantage
when you are designing something.
Then now then, let's see what happens
when you apply it to new concepts
and then into something that's actually used in the game.
So now we have a better context.
And for you to know, our city is called Citoglas.
And we want each and every district in Citoglas to have
its own signature in terms of atmosphere, colors, and life.
And even the audio scape would change depending on where you
were in the district.
So here's what it could look like in downtown, for instance.
And the whole idea with downtown is that downtown is
this hip and cool place.
It's very loud.
It's very busy.
This is what it would be like if you wanted to heartbeat
of Citoglas.
And the architectural language for downtown would be organic.
So we wanted to use a lot of narrow and angular streets.
You can see we worked with a lot of intricate details,
the radial shapes just to create some nice silhouettes.
And we also wanted downtown to feel retrofitted.
I remember what I said about Tokyo.
You would have, like, facades facing
important commercial streets.
Look very nice and pristine and very exclusive.
But as soon as you get on the rooftops and in the back alleys,
those are going to look less maintained and dirty.
I also want to work with a lot of contrast in downtown.
Same way again, like Tokyo.
Medium and small scale buildings clustered against large, massive contemporary ones.
Anything that sort of creates a nice tension in the space.
And we also want downtown to feel a little bit older.
We also wanted to give it some more history.
That's why here you will see more wear and tear.
I hope you can see that because sometimes it's hard to see because of all the whiteness.
I mean, yeah, you can see, you know, we wanted to use a lot of intricate details and noise
just to create an interest in space.
And the reason behind that is because, I remember, everything is to have a reason.
The reason behind that is that, you know, the society doesn't really care about maintaining these rooftops
because the citizens, they're not supposed to be up here anyway.
They should, you know, be out in the food doors, in the factories,
working hard or, you know, down on the streets, spending their money.
That's why they just leave this as it is.
But this is fakesome, and this is what she knows.
So you can sort of see that this beautiful picture
this society is trying to paint is just false.
It's literally just a facade.
And of course, you know, the people who live
in higher up here need to sort of reflect this kind of vibe.
So you wanted to keep downtown quite busy
and quite noisy, and touch with details.
You see, we use some exposed machinery,
these cables and stuff.
Then to contrast that, we would have anchors.
And the whole idea with Anchor is that these rooftops,
you almost feel like you are supposed to be on them.
That's what we want, to feel very nice and clean
and reflective.
And the whole idea with Anchor is that here you
would come to do some expensive, exclusive shopping
and go to fancy rooftop bars.
So and only the selected elite are allowed entrance
into Anchor.
So if you are in Anchor, then you will need a lot of money.
And the architecture language for Anchor would be?
vertical. So we wanted to create, you know, believer spaces very high up, but still one
has a more sense of weight, no towering above it. And it was also about making anchor feel
very exclusive. So we used clean and simple forms, a lot of vertical lines, and you can
see a lot of reflective expensive materials. Anything to make anchor feel very expensive
and very pristine. And of course, you know, the people, the lives, and this area needs
to reflect that kind of vibe.
So you can, you know, to anchor to spend money and enjoy yourself and go to clubs.
And to contrast that, we would have the view.
And all of the view here is to make it feel very soft and very inviting.
And the view is, I mean, it can be like the final stepping stone before you get elevator,
inviting to Sky City.
When in Sky City, that's where, like, the elite lives.
So if you get to the view, then you have succeeded in this universe.
So we wanted the view to feel very calming.
That's why we put it very close to the water.
Then you get a really nice change in the
aural scape as well.
And we also wanted the view to feel cultural.
So you can experience art installations, museums,
operas, and so on.
And we also wanted the view to feel very soft.
That's why we used the soft interior spaces here.
And here you can also enjoy nature, for instance,
cherry trees.
I remember what I said before about minimalism and about control.
For me, the ultimate power of control is when you control nature.
And of course, that's what this society does.
So for instance, if you're in downtown,
you have the low-cost and the mid-cost working and living.
Over there, you're not allowed to enjoy everything.
But here in the view, now you have succeeded in this universe.
Here, you can enjoy everything this city has to offer.
So you get this really nice contrast and tension between the spaces.
You would have like the controlled and sterile downtown
versus the soft and inviting the view.
So we have these different locations.
Each and every one of them has their own signatures in terms of color,
shapes, form, atmosphere, life.
This is where we create like this really broad palette for artists and designers to use
and for you as a player to experience.
And of course, there are much more errors than this, but I can just not fit more mood boards in here.
So I guess you have to buy the game and play it if you want to experience some more stuff.
So this is how a rich and vibrant city of glass can look like when you apply the style and tone to it.
So then what happens when you apply the style and tone then on character design?
I think it's important, you know, when you are designing characters.
that needs to reflect who they are and what their purpose is in the universe,
and to know the function behind the design and the reason behind it.
I like to challenge the artist a lot and ask them, like, why is that thing there?
If they cannot give me a good answer, I just tell them to take it away.
The more I remember, the less it's more.
Believer means, on character design, means natural border proportions, strong material definition.
You're going to feel high-tech in advance, but you still want to make sure that it feels,
or you didn't push it so far so it became sci-fi.
And elegance here, it means form before function.
So we are actually un-nudging some of the believability in order to create stylish, interesting designs.
But I mean, I do it for a reason, I do it with a purpose.
and also I'm an art director, so I'm allowed to break my own rules.
And attitude, of course, is posture.
The way these people move, the way these people walk and talk and so on,
it's some sort of sense of attitude and control to it.
And you're going to see that we use a lot of diagonal lines and folds
to give them some more attitude and edginess as well.
And for me also,
attitude is material separation.
For instance, you can have a cotton shirt.
They may put something reflective and leathery on one
of the arms.
And the way those two material meets, for me, that's cocky.
That's attitude.
That's what we use a lot in archaeo-design.
So you can see how it looks like when we apply that to
Krugesek.
And in Krugesek, you've got the bad guys.
You're going to encounter this a lot in this game.
So the high level idea is high fashion meeting, militarized tactical details.
Then we merge that together through the Stalinton.
And you think about, you know, military clothing and police outfits.
Those tend to be a little bit loose.
You get like big and long draping folds.
And for me, that's not elegant.
So we design something.
We look more like a Marni suit.
The fish are very tight and very slim.
Then we apply the tactical details.
And then you get the design that looks like that.
You can see, you know, I've used some diagonal lines on the sleeves and on the legs to give it some attitude.
And you can especially see that on the Hunter drone and the VTOL.
Armour plating has lowered down the lines.
Anything that makes them feel really aggressive.
Now you have the runners.
And the high level of there is high fashion meeting, sports gear.
And the runners, you know, they need to look like people that can take the fight against
this oppressive society and Krugeslag.
That's how we get this really strong, confident, athletic look.
And you can see, you know, we use the same language again.
I've already analyzed the skill and some attitude.
And of course, you know, runners need to feel agile and movable.
That's why you're here.
We work more with lighter and thinner materials.
And what you can see here as well is that, you know, we never exaggerate like the body proportions,
especially not the female.
And that's something you tend to see in a lot of other games and designs,
that you need to sort of objectify and sexualize the female body.
And for me, that's not elegant.
We don't do it here.
You know, I still want it to read as confident and strong and beautiful.
You always need to remember the elegance.
Then we have the Black November.
And the idea here is high fashion, meeting old and worn,
thick materials.
Because Black November, they live deep underground in the
tunnels of re-zoning.
And down there, it's going to be very cold and very wet.
That's why these people will need more layers of clothes,
thick materials to keep them warm.
And in our world, these people will be considered as bums or
people that live on the street.
So even if they are in a very harsh circumstances, on the border to starvation, and these people
are fanatics, I still didn't want to be in the ugliness in this world.
And that's what we gave them, this very cocky, confident look with a lot of attitude.
So we have many different sorts of classes in this world.
And each one of them has its own signature,
into the materials, colors, and so on.
But I don't have time to go through all of that today,
because I need to cover the next part.
That is, how we actually created this universe.
So now I'm gonna talk about
our different production phases,
and how then we ended up looking in the game.
So our pipeline was divided into four phases.
Phase one would have been when you reference gathering, put
together mood boards, design simple concepts.
Phase two is when you actually get something you can play on.
So now we're laying the foundation for City of Glass.
So now it's about you showing me that you can create a
believable space.
You understand composition.
You understand how to create strong framing.
You know how to scale proportions of building and how
to relate to each other.
And also you have to understand how you can create an interesting space with very simple shapes.
And for me this was the most important part of designing City of Glass.
And if you don't know how to create a strong foundation with very simple shapes and forms,
then it doesn't matter how much detail you are going to throw into that space.
And this was a very difficult phase for some people.
So I guess here is the third lesson I learned, that this
phase was a bit abstract.
It was hard for some people to understand the space.
It was hard to visualize what the final product would look
like, so in the end, we ended up throwing in more details
just to help with the scale, proportions, and depth.
Then for phase three, and now is sort of when we're starting to be more creative.
So now we started seeing more architecture detail in the spaces.
And actually at this phase, we had the whole game up and running,
which meant we can play the whole game from the beginning to the end.
And that sort of helped us assess if something needed to change or removed or even deleted
before we moved on to phase four.
And phase four is when we apply style.
now it is about the details.
And are you doing it in the right time, in the right context?
So now is when everything comes in, light, colors, atmosphere.
And phase four of us consider as done.
At this point, your area would be ready for ship, essentially.
And we had roughly around
10 months to take the whole game from phase 3 to phase 4.
So there was a lot of work going in there.
And we had to push really hard there.
And after phase 4, then we actually had some polish and
some bug fixing.
So some areas got some more love and attention to them.
But an area after phase 4 actually did hold up to ship.
So it was really good work there by the team.
So that's the production pipeline that we went through, creating shitter glass.
Let's look at how it looked in the game.
So you can see downtown. It is in phase two.
I think this was probably one of the most successful ones in terms of composition.
You can see there's a really nice tension and contrast between large, medium, small-scale shapes.
Creates a lot of interest around the centerpiece.
And overall, yeah, this is like a really strong foundation.
Then through phase three, when we started applying the details,
now we've started to get an understanding for
how the game looks like,
sort of feels like a residential space.
So now, yeah,
the player, or sorry, the people
understand that, you know,
how it's going to turn into later on.
And then for phase four, you know, when we apply this style,
in this case, the style of downtown,
and that one's going to be more busy, more noisy,
have more wear and tear, a lot of atmosphere,
then it'll end up looking like this.
What you can see, though, if you compare that to phase two,
nothing really changed in terms of composition.
all the big shapes, all the big structures were in place
and they hold up all the way through the production pipeline.
And that's why it's so important for
people to understand, you know, that you need to create a strong foundation
because then you just apply, you know, the details within those shapes.
Here you have an area in anchor at phase three.
Quite rough, but still, you can see the big structures.
Remember, anchor was going to be very pristine, very
exclusive.
The rooftops here should almost feel like you are
supposed to be on them.
And there is an interest there in the center, in the middle.
There's some sort of personalized rooftop.
So the big structures are in place.
Then for phase four, we apply the style.
We end up looking like this.
So now you can see the shine and the reflections and stuff.
We try to hide away some of the unnecessary noise
as much as we can.
You can see how we use the colors as a sort of guide.
The player and the eye in goes towards the residential space.
And in there also, we throw in some nice water
and some nice waterfalls just to make it feel really expensive.
Here we have another area in downtown in phase three.
And actually, not all the spaces were at phase three at the same time.
You can see this one, for instance, is very rough,
only like the big structures are in place.
But at least you can see sort of the lines,
sort of points inwards into the image.
And then for phase four, when we applied the style,
it ended up looking like this.
And this part of downtown was going to be a little more industrial,
so we worked a lot with smaller intricate details to create some nice silhouettes.
And you can see, you know, the way we used the colors, this place got its attitude.
This is another area in Anchor at Phase 3.
And at one point in time...
you know, we did have the time of day up and running,
we actually didn't have time to lit the space.
Or sometimes, you know, the artists will actually break
and light and then everything just turn black.
So it was quite hard to read and navigate sometimes,
but if you just look at the picture
and just look at the big picture and the structures.
You see you're standing on a plateau, looking down into space.
These are shapes down there.
On the right there you can see some long structures going along a road.
And then for phase four, we apply the style.
It ended up like this.
And again, now you're applying the right details with the right context.
A lot of vertical lines.
We clean up the space, make it feel very nice and reflective on the high end.
You can even see how we get some of the rooftop spark up there to the left.
and then you apply the palette of Anchor.
And then I end up looking like this.
Here is another fancy rooftop bar in Anchor.
It doesn't need just reading, or reflective,
and expensive, and luxurious.
You just want to be here with your friends.
Maybe not for phase three, but for phase four,
when we're done with it, we end up looking like this.
I think here is a perfect example of how the artist translated the style and tone.
I can sort of see the soft elegant curves. I can see the diagonal lines.
You have the attitude. You have a nice tension in this place.
At night time, you know, these lights would actually pulsate and make this space feel really vibrant.
So overall, this was a really good interpretation from the artist.
Here you can see another area from the view at phase three.
Remember the view was about making the field very soft and very inviting and over here also you would enjoy nature.
So you can see the big structures are in place, so now we are supplying the stylenton and the details, they end up looking like this.
You have to understand that, you know, there's a lot of thought process going in behind taking something from phase 3 to phase 4.
And maybe you think, you know, how hard is it to create a minimalistic space, you know?
Take away 80% and you have it.
But believe me, it's really not that simple.
And I would argue to say that it's probably more difficult to make a minimalistic space.
Like I said, you know, it's about understanding the shapes and the forms,
taking away the right detail, and then back to the right.
And then also about, you know, this space also needs to be traversable and readable,
and it needs to be fun to run around in.
And in a game, there is so focused on movement.
Every square meter is super important.
That's why it's so hard to balance this component
against each other.
So in overall, I'm really happy to see how the people on the
team have translated this style into just being fun and
be creative with it.
So now I'm just going to end the whole presentation by
showing you some more of these locations.
And I actually not going to talk more.
I'm just going to let you enjoy it.
So that's actually all that I had, so I guess that's it.
And I say thank you for coming and enjoy your day.
Thank you.
Bye-bye.