Thanks for coming to the Independent Game Summit.
I have the pleasure to introduce Jen Sandercock, who's going to talk about focusing your indie
career.
Let's give her a warm hand of applause.
Hi, hopefully you can hear me here.
I was gonna stand there,
but then I realized all you'd see was my head,
so I thought I would stand over here instead.
So yes, I'm obviously Jen Sandercock,
and I'm gonna begin with a little story.
Once upon a time, once upon a time I didn't make games.
I used to work at the Australian Department of Defence doing air operations research.
I then switched to do a Masters in Artificial Intelligence at,
and I was looking at how to create diverse character personalities in sort of very academic games.
I sort of thought I wanted to do games, but I was like, oh, games isn't a real career,
or, you know, that's not going to be a thing.
And then when I sort of realized games was a real career,
I'm like, oh, well, I'm like coding,
maybe I should be a coder.
And I met a bunch of people who are a lot better
at coding than I was.
And so I was like, oh, that's not so good.
And I don't know if I necessarily enjoy coding
that much to do it full time.
I then had an epiphany.
I'm a game designer.
I'm not really a coder.
I can code, but it's not what I'm best at.
So I set out, I gave myself a new goal.
I just wanted to get experience in games.
And thus began my non-indie games career.
The first job that I had in the games industry,
I'd gone for the interview and then I got the call
that they wanted me to take the job.
It was working on L.A. Noire for Team Bondi
as a junior game designer working on the tutorial levels.
The company reputation wasn't particularly good,
shall I say politely.
But at the time, my only goal was to get experience.
And then I sort of looked a little deeper
at the game as well.
And L.A. Noire, although it's sort of a first person shooter,
it's also an adventure game.
And I love adventure games.
It's also set in the 1940s, which is a period of time I very much like.
And also, it was a contract position, so I knew it wasn't going to be forever.
So I took the job, I worked at LA Noire, we shipped the game, awesome.
And then next, I went to work on a little educational game that was teaching Australian
12, 13-year-olds how to, teaching them English.
It was a relatively small team and I ended up having quite a bit of responsibilities.
I somehow became somewhat the lead game designer on the team and then I was doing some producer
stuff and I just didn't feel like I had the experience to have such a role.
I wanted to learn from other people.
So I packed up and moved to the USA from Australia because I felt like at the time the Aussie
industry wasn't going to give me that experience that I wanted.
I started working for Disney Playdom on some hidden object games,
and hidden object games are also sort of adventure games, somewhat.
And then I quit my job.
I quit my job because I had a boss who was making me feel really miserable.
I was crying a lot of the time,
and even though quitting meant that I might have to leave the country,
I was like, there has to be something more,
I shouldn't be crying so frequently.
I stopped to kind of look around at my career and I sort of felt like it had been plateauing.
I wasn't really sure where I was going, I wasn't really making progress.
I'd worked on a bunch of different genres, but like nothing was really holding it all
together.
Now, I didn't really know what I was going to do about that, how to make that work at
all.
But I did have an idea for a game.
So I thought, great, I'm going to work on this game.
And so I went indie.
So hopefully the majority of people here are indies.
And being indie is basically freedom.
It's freedom to make whatever I want.
I can work on whatever genre I want to.
I can kind of work with whoever I want to,
because I don't have to work with somebody I don't like.
And.
The big problem is there's a bunch of creative decisions
that you've got to make.
You know, there's all this freedom,
you can do whatever you want, what will you do?
So my first decision was what is my game company all about?
What is Inquisiment Inc. that I had just founded
going to be all about?
So I created a list of my core values.
I'm just going to pause for a moment here
because you might have noticed
that art is not one of my skills.
And so this little image here is supposed to somewhat be like a sphere and then there's
like a hole in it and that's like where your core values go.
So just thought I'd better explain that because it may not be obvious from just looking at
that picture.
Anyway, I created a list of my core values.
It was basically three things that I wanted in the games that I was working on.
I wanted to make games that foster friendship, curiosity, and challenge.
Now, what do I mean by that?
Well, so friendship to me is about,
I think that people in the world are pretty lovely people.
Sure, there's some not great people,
but I want to be reminded of the nice people in the world.
There's a bunch of games out there
where it's somewhat violent,
you're going around killing people,
and I didn't want that in a game.
I wanted a game that either within the game itself,
was talking about friendship so that you would have a new understanding of ways you can have
friendship or a game that outside of the game was encouraging you to be better friends with
the people, your friends you have in the real world.
I want to work on games that foster curiosity.
So I think the world is pretty amazing.
I think we can create amazing digital worlds as well.
And yet a lot of games kind of just push you through.
They're like, do this, do this, keep going.
Don't stop and look at the sunset, blah, go, go.
And so I want to work on games where, you know,
you're somewhat encouraged to take your time and explore.
There's a bunch of different options
and there's not really big penalties
if you choose one over the other.
I want to work on games that foster challenge.
So there are a lot of games out there
that aren't necessarily super gamey.
They don't have a set of game rules
and you don't necessarily win or lose.
But I like games that make me feel like
I've accomplished something and done something.
And so that's what I say when I say challenge.
So I explicitly listed out my core values.
This is a picture of me at the little office space
that I had at the time.
And initially it was just meant for my current game,
Glimpse Friends, that I was starting work on.
But then I realized I could apply
these core values to a lot more.
So this is kind of where we get to the guts of the talk.
I'm gonna talk to you about how using your core values
can answer a bunch of questions that are gonna come up
while you're developing games and in your career.
And I'm gonna use some examples of how I've used them.
So for example, you might ask,
what feature should I implement next?
Should I implement multiplayer or a new level
or maybe local co-op
or perhaps some like quality animations like this?
I mean, is this not quality?
Wouldn't your game be better with this?
Or perhaps in-app purchases or, you know, smell a vision.
So I'm going to give an example of my game A Glimpse Friends.
So in A Glimpse Friends, it's a mobile phone game
where you are taking photos and sending challenges to friends.
So basically a friend might have sent me this challenge,
something that makes you smile beginning with E.
And I would go out in the world and I would go,
ooh, here's Alamo Square and some elegant houses.
I would take a photo of that and then I would create a challenge
to send back to my friend and we would go back and forwards.
So it's about taking photos and exploring the real world,
looking up from your phone.
So when I was working on it, I had a decision
between what features should I put in next.
Should I put in messaging with friends from within the game
so that you could say, hey, sorry about that last photo.
It was tough or wasn't that funny.
Or should I put in offline mode so that you could play it
like on the airplane or wherever you were?
So because I want a game that fosters friendship, curiosity, and challenge,
offline mode doesn't really do that at all.
So I didn't implement that.
Another big question you might ask is how can I market my game?
So what are the key themes of the game?
Which con or expo should I go to?
What social media platforms should I be posting on?
Should I just put on a sandwich board and walk around GDC?
Or maybe I should like beg press to, you know, be nice to me?
Should I be targeting teens or 50-year-old women?
Should I be, for my merchandise, should I be making posters or t-shirts or like underwear?
Who knows?
So in my example, I work on a game called Simple Weed Park.
It's an adventure game in the style of Lucasfilm games,
so some of the games that came out in the late 80s and early 90s.
It's a single-player game, but when I was younger,
I remember playing adventure games with my brother and sister,
and it was very much about my friendship with them
and working together to solve these puzzles.
So when it came to, I had to create a booth for us at PAX,
I set up the booth so that they had two stools per station
and also had two sets of headphones.
And this was so that people could sit next to each other
and take their time to play.
So it's a single player game,
but I'm adding friendship into the game.
So another big question you will ask is,
what game should I work on next?
Should I work on a zombie shooter?
Or an arty walking simulator?
Or maybe a kid-friendly indie darling?
An audio-only game?
Or a white-hearted political game?
Because politics is light-hearted, not?
So, I mean, like most game developers,
you probably have a lot of ideas
of what you want to work on next.
But many of these will not fit your core values.
So, for example, back in 2013,
I did a personal project for myself
where every month for the year,
I came up with a different gameplay mechanic
and I implemented it.
So one of the goals of the game
was to actually implement games
and feel like I was doing something.
Another goal was I wanted to make games that gave me hugs.
And when I say hugs,
I don't necessarily mean physical hugs,
although they're lovely.
I kind of meant that feeling of being accepted
for who I am and being loved.
So I created these 12 games, and they all gave me hugs to some extent or less.
But if I'm considering, like they were all somewhat small games,
because I did them within a month, and it was just one gameplay mechanic in each one.
So how do they rate if I'm now considering, should I work on one of these more?
Should I build it out to be something bigger?
How are they going with Friendship, Curiosity, and Challenge?
So for example, my first game was just a little game
that you played on the back of business cards
that I could hand out at GDC.
It sure, it was about friendship
because I was making friends
by handing these cards to people,
but it wasn't really about curiosity.
The next game I did was a game where two people
are on the same keyboard and they're trying to navigate
their little characters in sync with the other person.
Again, about friendship,
but there wasn't really anything curious about it.
The next game I did was one of my first edible games.
So a game where you eat the pieces.
In this game you would actually, you know, you'd be around a table,
you would compete for ingredients and then you would make cookies
and eat the cookies at the end.
So it was definitely about friendship
because you're eating cookies with friends
and that's what friends are about.
But it wasn't really about curiosity other than
is this going to taste super gross or nice?
But by the time I look at this fourth game, Marie's Mr. Right,
this one does meet all of my criteria.
The game itself is a little text-based game
where you get one line of the story at a time.
And you need to decide whether that line
of story is important to remember or not.
If it is important and you remember it, then the story will branch differently and you'll
end up with different endings.
So it's about friendship because it's about this woman deciding whether she should be
staying with her boyfriend or whether he's really just a friend and not a romantic interest
at all.
It's about curiosity because you're just sort of exploring these like weird little paths
and seeing what happens.
And it's about challenge because it's actually very difficult to get what I call the happy
ending.
So I can keep going through and looking at all of the other games and kind of rating them.
So there's like a game where you've got Dixit cards, you're telling stories.
I did an audio only game because people said they liked the sound of my voice.
I worked with a team of other people on a game about, we've got like a comic strip
and you're editing what people will say.
This game, The AI with a Broken Heart, was basically about breakups and this was not
about friendship.
It made me feel horrible.
It was very depressing and I learnt I do not like to work on depressing games.
So, keeping on going through, this is one of my favourites, Dragon Whisperers.
This is a game where you're sitting next to somebody else and you each have half of a
dictionary and you're trying to work out what the dragon's saying to you.
It was a game where there's two sisters dividing up what their father has left them in his
will.
And then there was a very stressful game which was about driving on the road and calling
out guesstimate and being wrong and it was not a good game.
Anyway, in summary, 50% of these games are not suitable for me to work on currently
with the current set of core values that I have.
So that's great. I don't need to consider the other ones.
So pushing this idea further, back in late 2009 I did another personal project
where I came up with a different game idea every week for the course of the year.
Now I didn't implement these games, they were just game ideas.
And that created these 52 ideas.
And then if I now go through and consider the lens of friendship, curiosity and challenge,
I can kind of mark each one and go, yep, tick, tick, cross, cross, whatever.
And in the end, there's only 17 that would fit my core values of friendship, curiosity
and challenge.
That's under 33% of those games would be suitable for me to work on now.
So another big question that one might ask that Core Values can help you with is who should I work with?
Should I work with a team of 20 people? Should I work by myself or with some billionaire who's going to pay me tons of money?
Or should I like work with my best mate?
The important thing to note is that other people don't need to share your core values.
You need to talk to the other person about what your core values are, and then you need
to ask, am I going to need to compromise my core values to work with this person?
Are both of your own individual core values compatible?
So all of the decisions that you've been making kind of lead up to this how do I
build a legacy of games that I'm proud of? How do I create like an oeuvre of work,
a portfolio, or whatever you want to call it? How do you kind of get that coherence
like you're really making something bigger and making progress? And it's kind
of what I was lacking before.
So, well, the answer is pretty simple.
You just follow your core values because if you follow your core values, you'll end up
having games that all have something very much in common.
They'll have those core values in common and they'll feel like a wholeness.
So let me talk a bit about some of the games that I've worked on since I came up with my
core values.
So A Glimpse Friends, as I said, is about staying in touch with your friends.
So it's definitely about friendship.
It's about curiosity because I'm encouraging you to put your phone down and look at the
world.
And it's about challenge because you're actually sending individual challenges to people.
Now this game was a total and absolute financial failure.
I spent like two years of my life on it.
I hardly had any downloads.
I made like.
It was financially terrible.
But I am like super proud of this game.
This game is very much the epitome
of friendship, curiosity, and challenge.
So that brings me to a side benefit.
If your game fails, but you followed your core values,
at least you can kind of feel okay about yourself.
You may not feel great because your game's failed,
but you're not gonna like hate yourself in the sense that,
hey, I did something that I didn't really like
and it failed and wow.
So another game I've been working on since I came up with my core values is Thimbleweed Park.
And as I said, it's not really about friendship within the game because it's a single-player game
and the story itself is about two agents who don't like each other in a weird town.
But it's about the people playing it and the way that you play it.
So we've brought in a bunch of playtesters and we often bring in a couple to playtest.
And what's fascinating is that since only one person can control the mouse, the other
person often doesn't even necessarily notice that they're not controlling the mouse.
They feel like they're part of the game and they're contributing just by saying, hey,
how about you try combining this or doing this.
The game is definitely about curiosity because there's a bunch of really pretty environments and places to explore.
There's a library that's filled with over a thousand books to read.
And the game lets you take your time with it.
And it's about challenge because there's a lot of puzzles in it, adventure game puzzles.
And they're adventure game puzzles that kind of respect you, they're not super obtuse.
So I've been doing a series of edible games.
And there's a lot of things that you could do with food
that aren't really very friendly.
For example, I could make people eat really gross things
or have people competing a lot more for food
so that you're backstabbing each other.
But I choose not to make games like that in my series
because I really want to have games
that are encouraging people
that actually like the other people around them.
In terms of curiosity, many of the games themselves aren't super about curiosity,
but for me, while I'm coming up with all these games, I'm like,
ooh, what can I do with food?
And so I'm really exploring my own curiosity.
And I always try to make sure that the games actually have challenge,
so you're not just sitting down and eating food,
you have to earn the right to be able to do that.
So for example, one of the games I came up with is called Gingerbread Friends.
It's a slow game about getting to know friends and asking these very awkward questions of people.
I showed this at Babycastles in New York and one group of people who were playing
were mostly strangers before the start of the game and then by the end they were exchanging
contact details and had basically become friends, which seemed perfect to me.
This game, The Order of the Oven Mitt, the game itself doesn't say that you have to play
cooperatively or competitively, it's totally up to you and the friendship that you have
with the people you're playing with.
It was fascinating, I showed it at XOXO and I think absolutely everybody at that festival
played cooperatively.
They were like, hey, which things do you like best?
If I give you that, will you help me have this other candy that I like?
Whereas other places I've showed it, people have been a little bit less friendly.
But still generally pretty friendly.
It's about eating cookies, that's friendly.
So by now, I bet you're thinking, hey Jen, these cool values sound like super awesome.
But Jen, I'm not really into friendship, curiosity, and challenge.
It's not really my bag.
That is totally cool.
You need to come up with core values that work for you.
So how do you do that?
You basically come up with a big list
of a whole bunch of words that might mean something to you.
Maybe you want to have a sense of empowerment.
Maybe you want to create amazing cinematic art.
Maybe you just want to have a sense of joy.
So you basically list out all the things
that you could possibly care about.
You then start bunching them down into groups.
And then once you've got those groups,
you try to pull out one word that might mean
most of the stuff in that group.
And you try to reduce it right down to the bare minimum.
Three is a nice number.
And you're aiming to make it really short and memorable.
Partly so you can remember it yourself,
but also so you can tell other people.
So you can be, hey, I'm doing this thing, and it's awesome.
You need to update your core values regularly.
Life changes, you can change,
and your values can change too.
Now, sometimes you've got to do a project
that compromises your core values
because you need to pay rent.
You should totally pay rent and be able to eat.
That's super important.
You shouldn't, you know, core values come on top of,
like, the basics of living.
Sometimes you want to work on a project that isn't really 100% in line with your core values,
but maybe you want to do it for more experience, or you want to do a favour for a friend,
or perhaps you just want a little extra money would be nice.
And that can also be okay too.
But you need to be making that decision consciously.
If the compromise that you're making on your core values
is minor or the timeline is pretty short,
then sure, that's fine.
But if you're making like serious compromises
on your core values, maybe you need to check to see
if your core values need to change
or you might end up pretty miserable.
Because at the end of the day,
being indie should be about freedom.
If it isn't, you're doing something wrong.
So in summary, you should find your core values,
list them out explicitly,
use them, believe them, and live them,
update them as life changes.
So just follow your core values,
make amazing games you're proud of, and yeah.
That is all.
Don't forget to fill in evaluations
so I can come back some other time.
Cool, do we have, I think we've got time for questions.
Any questions?
Not so much.
Oh no, somebody's coming up.
Yeah, thanks for the nice talk.
Did you update your core value along the way?
You talked about updating your core value, right?
So, have you done that?
Yeah, well so I guess initially my core value was just,
I just wanted experience.
And so that was all I cared about
when I was starting out in the industry.
And so now I have my friendship curiosity and challenge.
If I find that's not working for me,
then I will definitely reconsider
and change what I'm doing.
Cool, well, thanks everyone for coming.