Good?
Hey guys, how's everyone doing today?
All right, I want to hear way more energy than that. All right, good morning everybody.
Oh, you can do better than that. Come on. I know it's Friday, but really.
All right. Everybody's home.
Okay. Welcome. Just to make sure you're in the right talk, which I know you guys are,
it's killer portfolio or killer, wait.
Killer portfolio, killer.
It's up there.
It's that.
If everybody can actually turn off your cell phones, that would be awesome.
And let's begin.
My name is Allison Kelly and I'm a consultant to top tier gaming companies.
And we'll start from Sean.
And also if you could, Sean, start with what is your number
one pet peeve that you see with portfolios?
Wow.
All right, well, I'll start with my name.
Sean Robertson.
I was animation director on Bioshock Infinite, lead
animator on Bioshock.
I'm currently art director on Ken Levine's current project,
the negative Lego thing that he had talked about at GDC a
couple years ago.
biggest pet peeve for me on portfolios is lack of
presentation, hiding what could potentially be really good art
behind really bad presentation of that art. I'm Gavin Goulden,
I'm the lead character artist for insomniac games. I just
worked on sunset overdrive. We're working on ratchet and
clank, edge of nowhere. Prior to that I was with Sean working on
Bioshock infinite.
You want my pet peeve too?
Your pet peeve, please.
I have so many though.
I would say having a game art portfolio with no game art in it.
Basically just having a lot of really nice ZBrush sculpts but no technical pieces in a game engine.
No game art, no textures.
Just pretty sculpts.
All right. I'm Greg Furch. I'm an art director of Fraxxas. My
most recent stuff was X-com 2 and X-com Enemy Unknown. My
biggest, I'm like Gavin. I got so many. So like, I guess the
biggest thing is, is when I see a portfolio that has stuff that
potentially looks good, but it's not shown in a way that I can
actually see it.
example if you have an environment piece, if you just
give me a screen shot and I have no idea what anybody did or
what's yours or being able to break it out, it kind of makes
it a little confusing to understand what's actually
happening and your thought process is kind of my biggest
thing. My name is Steve Scott. I work at bungee up in Seattle.
I'm the special effects art lead.
Our most recent title was Destiny of the Taken King.
My biggest pet peeve for looking at portfolios is that I do not receive nearly enough FX portfolios.
They're very scarce.
I'm Wyeth Johnson.
I've been at Epic Games for 10 years now.
I've held a number of different roles, art lead, art director, technical art lead.
I think my biggest pet peeve is probably...
when I like something from somebody's but I can't do what I
want with it. So a good example would be a flash portfolio that
I can't just right click, save as, put it in a folder,
somebody I want to look at, somebody maybe I'm interested in
but they're not quite ready and I want to follow up. Difficulties
accessing the content on your site drives me nuts. I want to
be able to right click.
images, put them where I want them, copy out your information,
get a really quick PDF of your resume, all that kind of stuff,
put it right there in my face and let me do what I want with
the stuff on your site. Greg, is it true that AAA companies don't
hire recent grads and if so, why?
I don't know that that really is something that's locked solid.
I think it's different for a studio you go to.
But the biggest thing is a lot of times I think people who are entering the industry
get turned off by the, you know, we want five years experience or three years experience.
You know the bottom line honestly, I mean that does matter but all that matters is your work like the first thing I do
When I get a link is I look at your work the second thing I do is I look at your work
The third thing I do is I may look at your name and your resume so like if the work is good. I
I'm not going to know that you have five years experience
or three years experience or a year of experience or none
until I actually get to your resume.
So the portfolio is all that matters.
All that matters is the work.
And so I've seen people that are coming out of school that
perform like somebody who's got three or five years
experience. It just doesn't matter. I've seen it reverse.
You know, guys who have multiple years experience and it
doesn't look like they have that years experience. So don't get
caught up on those things because, again, you can't
control that stuff. You control your work. And that's honestly
the artwork is all that matters.
Or would you even say a lot of students get hung up on writing these big resumes that
worked at a movie theater.
In the end, like you said, you don't care about the content on the resume.
It's all about your work.
Well, I mean the content needs to be relevant, right? So like, you know, like
It should be the things that you've done that that would have
an interest to the person hiring you no matter
Whether you're looking for a game job or any other job, but but uh, yeah
It should be it should be more relevant and it matters but that's again. That's like for me. That's the third tier
I don't know what your gender is or nationality is or
I don't care.
You can be purple as long as you can help my game.
That's all that matters.
And so, yeah, it's, you know, just focus on the thing that matters.
Make sure your resume is clean, though.
A lot of students also seem to focus on the tools heavily, which none of us care at all about. I
will teach you any tool in three months. I don't care if you're maxed like the back of your hand
and I'm weak in Maya and stressing about my Photoshop thing. Do not care. It's only about the
finished product, the stuff that's in the portfolio that's game art, just like Gavin said.
Pretty sculpts are pretty much meaningless. But if you have a great portfolio that has really
good game art in it, I do not care what tools you know.
Put them in there just in case we're kind of curious what we might be dealing with,
but it shouldn't be half your portfolio is, oh, I'm really good at Excel.
None of us care.
Why, this actually brings me to a topic that you always are drilling down.
It's all about quality, not quantity in portfolios.
So talk to me about it.
Oh, it's crazy important.
And actually, a better way to couch that conversation, I think, is...
you're only as strong as the weakest thing
in your portfolio.
The reason we always say quality over quantity
is because what happens is people end up
hiding their weaknesses at the end of a strong portfolio.
We see it all the time.
They kind of arc from an amazingly good introductory piece
and it tapers down.
And what we're always gonna do is just flip to the last page first and look at what we think
Mentally you believe is the weakest thing on your portfolio because you're gonna hide it you're gonna well
Maybe they won't make it to the end trust me
We're gonna look at the last piece first and you're all you know what happens is is we question your quality bar
We question your taste level
because if you have a really, really strong piece, maybe that
was one that you worked on for a long time or you vetted with
the community, maybe you got feedback from your peers. But
maybe you went off into the corner just to fill your
portfolio with more stuff and there's some weak stuff in there
that you weren't able to edit out, you couldn't see it for
yourself. And so you always have to be editing your portfolio
and constantly culling stuff that's weak so that we're only
seeing the strongest thing.
I'll second that. I think the weakest part of your portfolio is going to leave the lasting impression.
This may be a dumb metaphor, but think about a nice meal.
Somebody brings you a nice steak meal.
It's got potatoes and a nice cooked steak, and then there's a fly on top of that.
And you're going to focus on the fly. You're not going to focus on the steak.
Like I said, not a perfect metaphor.
I think pulling back and pulling away,
like rather than showing 15 pieces that are, you know,
10 good and five mediocre, leave the mediocre ones out.
Let us be interested in what else you have
rather than showing everything up front.
It's about a story of the artwork that you're creating
and leave us wanting, you know, the curiosity,
like, oh, what else does this person have?
I'd like to see more, rather than,
oh, they put all this like really bad stuff in,
so I kind of get a sense where this is going.
We've hired junior environment artists that had two pieces in
their portfolio. They had two environments, three images each
and they got hired. So Steve, how important is my general
presentation and what can a person do to improve upon it?
it's mostly important. As these guys will tell you, it's the
content that we're going to be looking at. But the presentation
is going to impact our perception of that quality. Well,
imagine a game with a really bad UI and a really bad
introductory experience, but really good game play. It's hard
to get into that and to find that quality, right? Portfolios
are the same way. So if you're looking at a game and you're
why you mentioned a flash presentation that you can't right click and save on those assets.
It's going to be really challenging for us to be able to drill down and really consider
that work if we can't access it. In terms of improving, well...
Make it work.
Make it work. Test it out on your friends. Have them look at it on their browsers or different formats.
Do you guys have any other ideas for how to improve that?
Well, I will say a Tumblr blog is not a portfolio.
That's such a common thing where people are posting their work and it's kind of timeline based and it almost feels stream of consciousness.
I don't see, you know, the first thing that any of us see
should be your absolute greatest thing you've ever done.
And a Tumblr blog is the exact opposite of that, right?
Where it's just a timeline of things that are happening.
I'm interested in that.
Maybe put that in your resume so I could scroll through it.
Although, honestly, that's a pretty bad presentation anyway.
But that would be another thing I think is, you know,
you need a dedicated portfolio, right?
That deliberately shows us what you're best at.
I want to chime in with one more thing in terms of presentation.
Your images are important, your reel is important, but a good quality presentation without spelling
errors, with reasonable formatting, even if it's simple, shows us that you have the attention
to detail that it takes to not just bring your art skills to bear, but complete a project
and close it out.
So it's pretty important.
I mean a great example is in the past I know we've had students who go in for their portfolio
reviews with one of these guys and it's their presentation is not loaded, it's not ready
to go or it breaks.
Fair enough.
Ultimately we're all artists and we have to present our work.
and ultimately all we're doing at a game studio is presenting our work to people who are paying for the game.
And every day that's something that we're conscious about, that we have to present our work to you.
So when we're looking at someone who wants to be on our art team, we want to know that they have an eye for presentation,
because that's only going to help us not just make a pretty model to put into a level, but how do you present that model,
how do you present that UI, and make it appealing and make people want to get drawn into your game.
And Sean, is it acceptable to show your own interpretation on a company's IP or should
you completely create your own?
I think it's absolutely fine to do that.
One anecdote I have is that
A woman named Claire Hummel had done a bunch of Disney princesses, historical Disney princesses.
We were struggling to find a look for Elizabeth at the time.
We saw her artwork floating around and we contacted her and she ended up designing the
student Elizabeth, the one with the white shirt and the blue skirt and the two lutesses,
the two red hair, because on merit of us being interested in her, because she had done some
Disney stuff.
it wasn't the only thing that she did that got us interested
in her and we saw her entire portfolio and saw that she's a
really, really good artist and that we really wanted to work
with her. But that initial interest level was because she
had done something that kind of was making its way around the
internet. And we do get a lot of submissions from people that do
Bioshock stuff. The rare occasion, and this is really
rare, it's not common, but we had one guy do a poster that
was so...
damn good that we ended up putting it in the DLC because it looked like it was you know we paid him for it we
Wrote up a contract. We you know we got the rights to put it in the game
But that was unsolicited piece of fan art
So I think normally it's okay to do that stuff, but you got to have other things to back it up. It can't just all be
Copying other people's work or doing your own your own thing on other people's work. I think it probably has to be
really good to, because you're basically submitting work to a
company that has been staring at this work for like three years.
So if you want your work to get scrutinized, I think it has to
be good enough to hold up to that kind of judging.
When should a portfolio be a real and when should it be a still?
Anything that's animation based is a demo real.
When you're talking about actual traditional animation, we have to see it in motion.
The other key part of that is visual effects.
If you're an effects artist, we have to see your effects in motion.
that doesn't mean stills aren't all so interesting
in those avenues, because a lot of times,
when you think of traditional animation
or you think of effects animation,
you're actually thinking about the different states
that those things travel through
over the course of how they animate and how they resolve.
And so thinking about it from kind of pose to pose,
either as an explosion or as a traditional animation,
like character animation.
showing that progression and thought process is nice. But
for the most part those need to be video reels. For my money as
well, and I generally talk to these guys about this, also
environment work.
We often get environment reels. I hate that. I want to see
really great still images of the environments that you've
created. You can include a video fly through as well. But to me
the primary way to see the environments that people are
making is through still imagery. Because there's this ability to
see every little detail, to see the overall sense of aesthetic.
It's not blurry. There's not motion blur and camera artifacts
kind of hiding things. So that's one of the things that may or
may not be a little controversial but I feel like
that's a crucial component.
Great. Gavin, when should my portfolio be as broad or should
be more into specializing in given style and technique?
I would say specialization over everything. I mean, when you're
starting to make a portfolio and you're applying for your first
job or whatever, you should really be focusing more on
quality. So rather than having
I'm applying for a character art position, but I've got an
environment, I've got a gun, I've got a car, I've got some
concept art. Here's a shader I made and stuff like that. Every
one of those pieces is going to end up being weaker overall
because you're not focusing all your energy on being the best
character artist, being the best effects artist, being the best
environment artist and things like that. So.
I mean, it's getting good first and then branch out to, you know, you have stylized art and
realistic art or you have some props with your character or you have environment art.
But first is, you know, like Wyeth was saying, quality first and then...
Edit, edit and edit again.
And then reduce your portfolio by half.
Exactly.
I was actually just talking about this the other night with somebody and they said something really interesting.
Because that's frequently a student thing, right?
Like, not exclusively students, but typically it's like, okay, so I did this class sophomore year, I did this class junior year, and they don't...
remove, right? Like hopefully you're better your senior year
than you were sophomore year. So get rid of that stuff. But he
said something very interesting. While you're looking for a job,
you have a job. Your job is to replace all of the work from
college with new stuff.
And I think that that's a really healthy attitude to have
for people who are graduating from school
and looking to get in the industry.
Like, while you're looking, you have a job
and that's replacing all of your student work.
And a good approach to have, too.
I feel like your portfolio's also kind of
a representation of who you are as a person, too.
So it should show your interests,
what you really want to do,
like what you could spend every day of your life
devoting yourself to.
I mean with school I don't think that's necessarily the case.
You're going to have a curriculum and you have to finish these courses and do whatever
and get a good grade.
Then after that is when you start finding your own voice and start being your own identity.
So then Wyeth, any particular standout or failures in construction of a portfolio that
you've seen?
I touched on the flash thing and the Tumblr blog approach. Those are big ones that we see.
Another one is, it kind of piggybacks on what Gavin was talking about, but lack of specialization, it can be really, really confusing for us.
we're not getting the impression of what it is you actually want to do.
You know, you're kind of, we see this a lot with students, right, where you're basically comparing
yourselves to your peers around you, like in the class,
and you're kind of saying, well, you know, I'm looking at the people around me
and I can model character, and in fact, I think, you know, overall,
maybe I'm stronger than the guys around me.
what you're not doing is comparing yourself to the
industry and to the people on, you know, the people without a
job on poly count or whatever who are just kicking ass and,
you know, you're kind of, you're in your little bubble. And then
what happens is you build your portfolio around that bubble
where you're like, I dabbled, I took a character art class and I
created a character that was kind of compelling and so I
threw him in there and then, well, I went and I did a tech
art thing for a little bit and I learned how to write some
shaders so let me ram those in there as well.
point of view is dead in that approach, right? Because it's
this kind of five-spoked wheel and we don't know, no matter
what you say, oh, I'm applying for character art position, if
those other pieces are there, we can't get your point of view.
We don't get your taste level. And that's a, you know, at the
end of the day, we're hiring somebody that has good taste,
right? We're hiring somebody that we can trust to invent and
create and take something like a rough sketch concept and go
interpret it in a way that we think is going to be applicable
to our game.
We're looking at your taste level and we're looking at your kind of passion.
That's what we need you to show us.
That's how you need to construct this portfolio and this house of cards that you're building.
That's the thing we need to see.
So the other thing that I want to touch upon is how all of you
guys, as many times as you're applying,
continue to apply to a lot of these companies
because you never know when they're
going to need that person, right?
So it brings me to Sean has some experiences with this.
I'd like to offer up the rest of the panel to bring in their rejection letters at some point.
When I first was trying to get a job in the industry, I sent my portfolio, as bad as it was, everywhere, all the time.
Like, I would go back to the same place every three months and just annoy the hell out of them, keep sending it.
And I got rejection letter after rejection letter after rejection letter.
And I still have these at home just to remind me of how long it took for me to get a foot in the door.
And no doesn't always mean no.
No means could sometimes mean we're not ready for you yet.
We don't have a position for you at this time.
There is an example of someone I had met.
Seen his portfolio, thought I was pretty decent.
But I didn't have anything for him.
It was a four effects art.
A year later.
coincidence. We had just decided that day that we needed a
position open and he e-mailed me the next day out of the blue.
So that's kind of like a feel good affirmation like
coincidence has happened. But the point for me there is that
Despite that it happened literally the next day
I was still gonna call him like he was still number one on my list because at that point
He is the best portfolio that I had seen
So even though I didn't have something for him the year before when I talked to him
The quality of his work definitely stuck in my mind and he was on my short list for getting in contact with but Sean
Like how did how did you keep going with that?
lots of alcohol and tears.
Lots of Kleenex, right?
I had a lot of good friends at Ringling that really pushed me at the time and I think I
came out of that school with just a very strong drive to never be satisfied.
And I think as artists if you have that drive that you know you keep driving towards the next thing like this isn't good enough
I want to do this. I want to try to make it better
You're going to get better
you're going to improve and if you can improve at a rate that you can keep sending your portfolio out and
Don't worry about the mistakes you make you're going to make mistakes
One of my teachers always said you know you had like 10,000 bad drawings, and you just you just got to get them out by practicing
I mean it's
Lame and cliche advice, but I think you just you gotta just put your nose to the grindstone and keep doing it
You gotta make sure you don't take it personally right like like we were not your rejection letters are never there frequently
They're almost always
it's not right now, not no, and it's not a critique on who you
are. Your timing might be bad, the company's timing might be
bad. The other thing is that companies are generally slower
to react than you want them to, so things move at a little
slower pace than you'd want.
But I think not taking it personally and like just okay.
The other thing is if you completely replace your portfolio,
I'm probably not gonna remember.
So it's like a fresh slate.
So I think that's good too.
But you can't take it as a personal slight
and you just keep plugging away.
If it's your dream, do your dream.
don't believe in yourself. Surround yourself by people that care and want to help you, too.
There's one thing where I, on the opposite of that, after I got a job at Looking Glass, I went to
visit another company at the time. I can't remember the name. They're out of business now. But when I
was talking to the art director, this was like two years after I sent my portfolio to him, he had
one of my pieces stuck to his cubicle. And I was like, what?
like I really like this piece but it wasn't really what we
needed for the company. So you even get that side of it. People
remember you and like the stuff but sometimes the company is
your client, right? If you're
You're not going to be sending super like hardcore realistic
Gears of War stuff to Media Molecule.
So you kind of have to know what your audience is
and what that company is going to want to get out of you.
Yeah, there's a tangential thing in here too
that I think is really important as well,
which is that you guys are not capable of judging your own work.
nobody is. This is not exclusive just to people who are students or people who are trying to break in.
We are not capable of judging our own work.
You get better at it and you gain an instinct for what's working and what's not and that's kind of as your skills increase
you start to be able to filter a little bit better, but
that's, you know, this is the relationship we have with our
companies all day every day is we make something and then
somebody else comes in and tells us whether it's working or not
because you just can't see it. You're too close, you're too
myopic on it. You can't see it. So this is why the communities
that are out there to support people who are up and coming,
like the poly counts or whatever, those are the most
valuable thing. You can't
filter it yourself. You need to put it out there to your
teachers, you need to put it out there to other people in the
community, you need to put it out there to your peers, put it
out there to even just send something to a company that you
like and say can you look at this, I'm not applying, can
somebody there look at this? They oftentimes will and they'll
give you feedback. I've done that before. But you're not
capable of judging your own work. You have to absorb that,
put it in your soul and just get the fear out of the way of
showing your work and show it off as much as you can and get
that feedback.
So I'm going to ask this out to the group.
Have any of you guys had a very successful candidate story?
An applicant?
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, I think.
I mean, I know that you, we have hired some people looking at portfolios.
What was one that really stood out?
Some things would eventually come back.
Where, you know, a guy that we, we did a portfolio review, right, and then like a couple months
later, you know, he had pretty good stuff.
You know, it didn't happen here, just to be clear, like, no stress in the other room later.
But you know, he had good stuff and he was looking for work once school graduated and
he contacted us again and it just so happened we had a...
contractor job and I was like, hey, why don't you move out here
and work for a year with us? And he came out and we hired him
probably about three or four months ago. Just worked out that
a position came available and he was doing great work.
and we kept it, you know, so it all happens kind of weird like that, you know.
It's just timing. In a lot of cases it can be timing.
I think to your point, Greg, though, like...
your point of contact, like that person made contact with you
and you saw his portfolio, he's probably making contact
with dozens of other places, so you have all these irons
in the fire, so to speak.
So you're not just solely relying on your one,
you know, the one place that I'm only gonna work.
You know, you really have to cast a wide net
because you really don't know where these companies are
in their terms of hiring.
Even what's on the website could be a month or two old
because it has to go through so many people before.
a job listing even shows up on a website sometimes.
Gavin, how important is it to be able to talk
about your process and working in general
when you're reviewing a portfolio?
I mean, I think it's important to be able to be
knowledgeable about how you created something
in your portfolio.
I think, depending on discipline, though,
and what you're actually showing.
it's more important for some than others.
And I know it kind of changes for like art director,
like maybe like Wyeth has one opinion and Greg has another,
but for me, for character art,
like I don't want to see speed sculpts.
I don't want to see sketches.
I don't want to see anything like that
because it's not really showing your quality.
It's not showing, you know, what you do on a daily basis.
It's just kind of like work in progress and throw away work,
something you'd kind of keep in a folder
and you're messing around with it, but not really, you know.
something that will be making it to the game or anything like that. For concept art, for me,
that's what I would rather see for a concept artist because most of your job is going to be
talking to the art director about getting an idea across, so you're banging out a bunch of
different sketches, you're banging out a bunch of different ideas, and eventually one will make
it, right? But for character art, that's not the...
It's not the same, not the same deal.
I think for effects, it's very much a process-oriented discussion.
When I get a reel, an effects reel, I see that as the beginning of a conversation between myself and a prospective artist.
And when we have the first phone conversation, we talk about process, we talk about that iteration loop.
I mean, you know, it's a very discipline-centric thing,
but for effects, the loop between looking at a piece of work,
making adjustments, seeing it back in context,
and then going through that over and over again until you.
put together something that works within the confines of the game is the job. And so I want to
be able to know that you can speak to that and have a good understanding of what it's actually
like with the day-to-day operation and not just be able to go away, lock yourself in a room and
come up with something pretty that we check into the depot and goes into the game. Like I said,
that's very specific.
to effects and character art is a little bit different,
but I just wanted to offer that different perspective.
Also, chiming in on concept art,
the word concept is in the definition of the job.
Conceptualization is in the job title,
and that's something that gets lost, I think,
almost immediately when you're thinking about,
oh, I want to be a concept artist.
You're not an illustrator.
You're not a painter.
You're not anything other than
somebody who is generating ideas.
who is an idea factory.
And if we don't see the thought process of the ideas
which leads to a finished piece,
which if you're talented will also be
maybe a beautiful illustration or a beautiful painting
or incredible line art or whatever,
all that stuff is ancillary to why.
Why did I draw the thing that I'm showing you?
We have to know why.
We have to know your brain cranking away,
oh, these are my references, my inspiration,
these are some of the silhouettes that I'm presenting.
The why is crucial.
Remember the conceptualization is literally in the job
description there.
For character art, I guess for a process to showing how you
actually constructed it is important though, just to make
that clear.
So having good topology, having good UV layout, having an
understanding of physically accurate materials and stuff
like that is definitely important.
But how you come up with an idea as a character artist, it
doesn't really matter to me.
So Wyeth, do you guys at Epic look at other aspects of
people's online presence when applicants are applying?
Everything that you do is fair game.
Any way that you present yourself out in the world,
whether it's on forum posts, whether it's on Twitter
or Facebook or your blog or even your personal blog
because you really love brewing beer on the side,
I'm gonna go read it.
If there's something about you out there
that tells me your taste level,
that tells you your passions,
that you're interested, that you're not,
whether or not you're a dick.
is really, really crucial.
I mean, we have to be in a room with you
for 40 plus hours a week.
You have to be somebody that we think is passionate,
that's hungry, that's talented.
So yeah, anything is fair game, right?
And your presence out there in the world
is something that we're interested in.
I mean, we don't always go crazy deep
and we're not weighting that insanely heavily
compared to whether or not you're a good artist.
But if we're on the edge and you're somebody who's,
wow, maybe we'll take a chance,
you don't have any experience but your work is really great,
but then we find your blog and you seem
just not like a great person,
we may just tip us just that far over to go,
you know what, maybe we'll try somebody else.
Maybe we'll dabble in, you know,
take a risk, a chance on somebody who doesn't quite,
you know, we don't think is a cultural problem.
Be aware that we are definitely looking at all of the ways you present yourself.
I would also warn everyone that the industry, despite what it seems like here on GDC, is
very small and that chances are you're a friend of a friend of somebody in a company and word
travels fast if you're hard to work with or a difficult person.
We all talk to each other.
There's no reason not to have a good attitude about working
Well, and look, you know, like the online stuff like we're not gonna go look at your Facebook page, right?
Like nobody cares about but um, but when you're on poly count or whatever
came up last year, I told a little story about how we had
actually interviewed somebody and at a certain point some
things maybe triggered that kind of caused us to, because I think
we were discussing poly count. So we actually went and looked
at feedback. And, you know, it wasn't favorable. And it wasn't
that anybody is too blunt. Anybody that knows me knows that
that's really not a problem for me.
But chemistry is important to the team.
And we all take that very seriously
about the personalities we add.
And so, you know, it spurred a little bit
of a conversational poly count.
And you know, like, Gavin is, you know,
Gavin, it does more...
he's more out there with his work than probably the rest
of us on the stage, and so he's, this is a guy
who's doing it right, right?
Like, he talks a lot, and a lot of good stuff.
Possibly too much.
No, but it's all good stuff, but you're the example of,
to me, of a person who handles themselves
in an online presence the way it should be done.
Yeah.
Professional.
Yeah, I think, like.
at the risk of sounding too much like Kanye up here, you've
got to kind of look at yourself as a brand. Everything you're
putting out there needs to reflect you as a possible
employee or as a professional or whatever. It's not like
everything you ever say has to be on point and super
intellectual and I'm the smartest guy in the room or
whatever. But
it's a super small industry, it's a quick search to see if
someone is going to fit with your team. You're hiring the
person as well as a great artist. You have to sit
shoulder to shoulder with this person for years working on a
game and you'll be stressed and all of this. So it's really
important to always have that in your mind when you're
you're giving feedback on a forum, like if you're a
complete ass about it or if you're just always railing on
games or different people and stuff like that, it's going to
hurt you. You can always be blunt and honest as long as
you're being professional. At the end of the day, you don't
want to wake up and go, well, I probably shouldn't have said
that. And once you've tweeted it or you've put it on
polycount, it's done.
something to think about.
Well, I mean, you're working on a multi-million dollar product, right?
And you want someone who's going to represent the brand and your company respectfully and
correct because it's also a recruiting technique.
So yes, Gavin, you really, when you go out and you talk, you actually aren't going and
attacking people or making these random comments.
You're actually being constructive and actually putting forth something for the industry to
take away from.
I think we all up here, the reason why we are trying to drive this home is for a reason.
We have seen lots of problems online and don't think when you are applying people aren't
checking.
Fair enough?
Yeah, definitely.
Okay.
So Steve, what are the, what area of game are
production do you see more demand than talent for right now?
Well, like I mentioned at the beginning, effects is definitely an area where I feel that there's
more demand than available talent. The other two areas that I would say are UI, user interface,
and technical art. I think that's a big area that we're trying to address.
much better perspective on the various types of technical
artists that are needed now. It is interesting because it's
fracturing now where you've got tech animators and that's a job
of rigging, I'm making sure I'm supporting the people who are
doing animation by giving them good bones and guts to work
with and good tools.
and then you've got kind of the shader side, which is, hey, I'm
making tech art that's relevant inside of the game engine
itself, doing, you know, materials work or landscape
work or blueprint work, visual scripting, that kind of thing.
And then you've got the kind of bones and guts underground
tools guys, like I'm writing Python scripts for import,
export pipelines, or I'm, you know, getting really, really
deep into the technical side of, like, tool support, almost
tool programming, but not quite. So that's three different
things. And all of those jobs, you could.
we will hire a great person immediately. I know every other
game company on the planet pretty much is the same way.
I'm seeing effects.
grow into much more than just particle manipulation and more
into shader application for glowing armor or shield bubbles
in the case of destiny all of the space magic is starting to
get more and more like actual physical models with interesting
shaders applied to it and that is a discreet skill which is
becoming more and more important as the industry moves forward.
I'd like to take this time to, if anybody has questions, to take this opportunity and
line up at the podiums.
The microphone is on the side and while people are lining up I'm going to ask one more question
before we get to the Q&A section.
Sounds good?
So we're hearing a lot about ART tests.
Does anybody have any comments on that?
I test everybody.
I believe it's important only because there's so many art
thieves out there. It's showing commitment to the application.
It's showing how you can work with a team at a very small
scale. So handing something in, getting feedback from an art
director, addressing that feedback and how you're going to
respond. By that being said, it's not.
The way that I do it isn't testing literally everybody who applies. It's you know, you could filter down you
Potentially are a good fit. You have a great portfolio
Get tested and then you know, basically start that process
I would just add on one thing. Don't be too intimidated as well. And we're the same way.
Everybody tests. I don't care if you're a 30-year industry veteran. Everybody tests.
But there's another side of it, too, which is don't be super intimidated if you get a
test and it looks like the scope is way out of your comfort zone. Like, oh, my God, I
don't know if I can do a whole character in two weeks or whatever they're asking me to
do. Try. Because a lot of times what we're doing is we're actually designing a test that's
kind of too hard.
it's a little bit too tough for the parameters in which we're
giving it to you because so much of the skill is cutting the
right corners and showing us, well, I wasn't able to model the
whole guy but I got half done and I did a symmetry modifier
and did a little bit of extra stuff above and beyond that to
show some asymmetry and we're going to see, okay, they cut the
right corner to finish the test even though it wasn't exactly
the parameters. So sometimes we're actually doing that
intentionally. So don't get too crazy.
correct. So let's begin the questions. Okay. So you guys
were talking about, you know, like internet presence and
stuff. I was wondering, is there like an effect if someone lacks
any kind of like presence on the internet? I don't think that's
any, as long as your portfolio is strong, it's not really, we're
not hiring somebody because of Tumblr skills or Twitter skills.
I think that we're really looking for a solid artist.
The social media stuff can help,
like if you have other work on your Tumblr site
that we can flip through, whatever is fine,
but it's never a mark against you.
Okay, thanks.
One thing I've heard a lot is you should really tailor like your resume and your cover letter to the company you're applying for
But what about the overall portfolio?
So like I've kind of heard that you should have like a portfolio for this company and then a portfolio for this company and something
Like that. I think you're probably gonna burn out
After a while, you know, I mean
for me, I would tell you to do what you really want to do, you know, like if you're
really want to do stylized stuff, if you want to do like
League of Legends art or something like that, but you're
throwing your portfolio off to, you know, Activision or, you
know, Naughty Dog or something like that, I mean, if you don't
really want to do that day in, day out, eventually you're going
to get tired anyway. So I mean, I would focus on the one thing
that you want to do, make it as best as possible and just hit up
the companies that are in that wheelhouse, you know?
nice. If it's a forum cover letter. Anything you say in
there is always a nice little touch. Again, we don't get to
that until probably the third or fourth thing I'm going to look
at. But yeah. Thank you. I was just wondering what is an
effective way to present technical art like materials and
shaders and visual blue printing and stuff. Is it
you guys were touching on whether to do a reel or whether
to do stills. I was wondering on your opinion of effective
presentation of technical art. Tech art is super broad. Some
of it is the avenue of tech art that you're in. If you're doing
a rigging reel, even if you're just doing technical stuff,
you're going to need to show the effects of that rig on deforming
meshes. We're going to need to see that stuff in motion. And
then breakdowns of the offline stuff that goes around it like
here are the scripts I wrote or whatever. You're going to want
to see that.
it comes to shaders, we almost always want to see that stuff
in motion. So I think some stills showing, hey, here's some
of the shader graphs, here's the logic, maybe here are the
functions that I derived my math from, here's some of the white
papers that I read that inspired the tech that I'm doing in the
game level itself. And then seeing it in motion with some
real samples is probably the right thing to do. You know,
when in doubt, a combination of
stills and video can work very well when you're really not sure
if just one or the other is the right category for you. So I
would say, you know, if something you need to see it in
motion, do the video, even if it's just for that section, kind
of break it down piece by piece. And that's fine, too. And we'll
do the work of scrolling through it as long as it isn't crazy,
you know?
you have an awesome material, stick it on a cube. Does it
matter that it's not on the prettiest model or the best art
but it's an awesome shader or material?
Presentation matters. If that would look better on a high
quality model, find one from somebody else or download one.
You know what I mean? And make a note that says this isn't my
model but look at how good the shader looks. We're going to
want to see that. Also it shows us he's got good taste. He
knows it would look better.
character rather than just on a sphere and you made that choice
and you lit it and it has nice aesthetics or whatever. So the
presentation matters for sure. But if you're not a modeler,
don't try to do it. Then we won't be able to get past the
bad model. Again, like you said, find one.
that would be the fly on the stick. I think there's ways
around it. If you're doing a skin shader or something like
that and you download a scanned head but you're applying for a
technical art position, no one is going to look at it as, wow,
you modeled a great head. It's just a scan? Shitty. But the
opposite would be true. I'm trying to do technical art but
it looks like garbage on a cube or something. It's, you know.
going to be bad. All they'll be able to look at is that cube and not focus on what you're
actually trying to show.
And just make sure you're accrediting other people's work so there's no confusion.
Totally.
Thank you.
Hi, you guys touched on
If you're planning for a character artist to put your
character art or environment to just tailor your portfolio to
what you want to work for. What are your guys' opinions on,
because I've heard about specializing to get it and
usually you want to specialize to get into a triple A studio,
but you want to work at a smaller studio, then generalist
might be better because you'll be doing more things. What's
your guys' opinion on that?
Go ahead.
I think overall that's a true statement.
The smaller the studio, the more hats you're going to have to wear.
Once you get into, you know, 100 plus people working in a studio, then you have the luxury
to really specialize and one person can be really the best person at that one particular
thing and you just hyper focus on that one thing.
There's always exceptions to the rules, of course, but I think as a rule of thumb, I've
generally seen that to be the case.
The big thing is just edit, right?
So if you're not really, if you took one figure drawing class
and you have a couple of crappy figure drawings,
we don't want to see those, you know?
It's like you have to edit and still show solid work
in all those categories.
30-second gestures don't really do it for us.
Yeah, totally.
So you just, again, you have to be able to edit
and solid work in those categories,
even if you're trying to be a generalist.
You have to make sure that they're elevated
to a point where you're comparing yourself
to the quality of the industry.
And pay attention to the job description itself.
You want to make sure that if you are putting together a portfolio for a specific description,
maybe you are looking at a description that says, hey, we want someone who can model and
rig and texture.
And then you can show proficiency in those, assuming you follow all the other rules.
But if you're applying to a larger company that is asking for specialization in the job description,
I'll usually tell you it's like, oh, this is the only thing that we want to see is this specific area.
Thank you.
So I'm very interested in doing game design, game mechanics.
And I wonder if at studios, for game design and game mechanics,
would people have a demo reel?
Or would they just submit more links to their games?
Or how would that process work for more into game design?
Industrial design?
So like level design or game mechanics and things like that.
I don't know if you guys know.
More like game play and actual design.
Yeah, game play.
Yeah, the designer portfolio is a bit of a black box.
I mean, when you're hiring a designer, you're looking at different things
than looking at what we call architects or level builders,
the people that are taking the art and constructing the space.
keeping mindful of tactical considerations and line of sight
and how it's going to stream in.
I mean, again, it's specific to what are you trying to do.
If you're trying to be a level builder that's going to
construct worlds that the player can walk around in, that
may not necessarily be built out of the models that you
have built, but you're placing the models to create the
world, I think you need to show those spaces, even if it's a
level we can download, because nowadays most engines you can
download for free, and you have a package that you can load
this level and walk through it.
or it can be a fly through, unless of course it's
environment, art, and then wife will get mad at me.
design really can only be experienced through play, and so you have to have something interactive.
And that's just the be all, end all. You can't show good design in a video. It's just not
possible. You can show good theory and you can talk about it in Flip Portfolio, but at the end
of the day, if we can't put our hands on it, touch it and play it, that's the end of the story.
Also I will say this, with art candidates, a lot of times they apply, and if they've
past the art test and the portfolio review,
we're interviewing them for the most part as a culture fit.
By the time they get it, they're footing the door
and in the building.
You know, we realize you're a good artist.
You've already tested, we like that.
You passed those gates.
With a designer, oftentimes we play
and we experience what it is you've done,
but there's a big component once you get on site
of talking about your philosophy of design
to the people in the room.
And so those are, you gotta come prepared
for both of those things.
Thank you.
Hello, I was just wondering, what do you guys look for in a level design portfolio?
What stands out to you and what are things that shouldn't be done and or should?
level design. You mean environment art or level design
like building the level that will get arted up by
environment artist? Building a level of game play and what
not. Sort of similar to the last question. Yeah, it is
pretty similar to the last question. I think one of the
we hired a guy on XCOM 2 that
he had come in for an interview, first of all he had made a site
that had dissected everything we did in XCOM enemy unknown and
had like sequence shots of like the level and what was happening
there. He had figured out all of our mechanics and then came in
for an interview, as if that wasn't enough, came in for an
interview before we could even respond to him.
he had gone home and applied all the new mechanics we had added
and made a totally different level and sent us basically a
gray box of that. That was a pretty good move. He was going
to get the job anyway. But after that it was like there's no way
we can't hire him. But, yeah, it's a little bit different. I
think you have to show your thought process as well with
level design. It's a weird
It's a little bit of a weird one and I've seen it done various ways for instance on bash like infinite when we were looking
At level designers we were very concerned more more concerned with how they could tell a story in the world
Then if they were good at like setting up tactical space because we had a design team that would you know that that they would
Work with when it comes to setting up tactical space, but we were much more concerned at that point with
can we bring somebody on that is good at telling a story
of what has happened in the world.
So we were looking at that specifically,
not so much like tactical walk space and things like that.
So again, know your studio.
All right, thank you.
So you were saying that the UI and technical art positions were
less competitive than some of the other ones. So what would
you say the specialties that are more competitive versus ones
that are less competitive? Character art? Concept art?
Character art? Those are pretty hard. Lots of competition
there. Yeah.
I mean, again, you look at the majors and schools and stuff
and where things tend to gravitate.
And it's a broader stroke.
It appeals to more people, I think.
And so I also don't think people think about, wow, I mean,
you mean I could actually do UI and motion graphics for a game?
I just don't think that that hits.
People that do that much, like graphic designers,
would be natural fits in a lot of cases.
They just aren't thinking about games all the time.
But again, modeling and animation
tend to be your kind of go-to's and concept, of course.
But just the competition's more fierce
because those jobs have existed longer.
So.
I think it's just like naturally,
like a good UI no one notices.
Yep.
Like everyone notices a bad UI.
and paired with that, everybody wants to make monsters.
So if you can make a career making monsters,
you'd probably gravitate towards that.
There's not many people that are like,
I can't wait to make health bars, that's going to be awesome.
So why if you were talking about like a portfolio that you came back to
Because you like something about it. I was just wondering have you guys experienced something similar and
Did you eventually hire that person and why did you come back? Why did you stay?
What kept you checking out, updating?
Well, so for me it was somebody who was really, really good.
It just, they're real, didn't, you know, satisfied something that we didn't need at that moment.
And usually in that case I'll just put it into a special bookmark folder of...
people that are good that we don't need at the moment. And
then every once in a while, it's all deeply categorized by their
specialty and what they do and when I found them. I actually
have a pretty good system for all of that. So if something
comes up, I'll go back and look through that. So that was just a
simple case of, oh, you seem really good. Maybe someday we'll
need someone like you.
I mean, talent is talent. And when you see somebody who has a
lot of talent, you take notice. You tend to remember them. And
similar to Wi-Fi, I have the same folder where I'll just keep
dragging images or website links into this folder. That's kind of
like my save for later.
And if something comes up and we need a very specific role to be filled then I have people that have already
Kind of vetted then that'll be my starting point, so I don't have to start from scratch
In the case of the person I said that we had hired a year later
it just you know at the time we didn't need an effects artist and I
His portfolio is really good a year later
I had remembered it and when an effects position became open he was the first person I was gonna call and we ended up hiring him
But that was because it stuck in my mind.
His work was good and his process was good
and he knew what he was talking about.
He was very solid foundation of what he was doing.
So that kind of stuck with me.
So the best story I have for that is that
I had a guy I met at GBC,
I guess 10 years ago now.
He was one of the IGD scholars
and we got to know each other.
He went off to work at a couple of different major studios
and I kept checking on him every now and then.
And we had an opening up about a year and a half ago
and so I called him up and I said,
hey Morgan, you want to come interview for a job?
And he's like, yeah, I think I'd like to do that.
So a kid that I met nine years ago.
I ended up hiring about a year and a half ago.
And so it just worked out that way.
What I needed was what he had actually gravitated to
and it was just a great fit.
But yeah, it took nine years to get there, but we got there.
I had an applicant one time that the timing just wasn't right,
but I liked him, we had a good conversation.
But there wasn't a good fit for the company, so I actually
called up a friend who worked for another local studio
and pushed him over there, totally self-serving.
But a couple years later I called him up and said, hey, we have a need for these skills.
Do you want to come over?
looked at his portfolio, it had been refreshed, all new stuff, and it was a pretty easy hire
after that.
Thank you.
Good day.
I just wanted to know, you were mentioning the tumbler thingy before.
I was wondering if the same rules apply to websites like LinkedIn, for example.
Do you guys check that out?
Do you have a LinkedIn account or something like that?
I use LinkedIn.
I've had a number of applicants reach out to me through LinkedIn and show me their portfolios.
I think it's a great tool.
But it's not an art display tool.
So all it is is a communication device to find people like us or hiring managers or
whatever.
So you still need a portfolio.
You still need a dedicated website that is a portfolio site.
I have two more questions.
What would you call the art display tool?
What do you mean by that?
The purpose for LinkedIn is to be just an online resume, right?
And anything beyond that would be like your portfolio, your art station page, something like that,
where it's specifically just art content, just your best work.
And then the final question is going back to the generalist versus specialization. When you work
on a big studio, my guess is that you also have a very open line of communication with your
programmers or directors and stuff like that, right? Ideally. Hopefully, right? So my question
would be, wouldn't it be more efficient?
If someone that has many skills show you that he can do, well, I can do 3D art, but due to, you know...
situation, I can also do, let's say, programming and stuff.
Normally when a big company is hiring for a position, they have
a very absolute need for that position. So let's say character
art. We need a character artist. It's great if a character
artist comes in that can do effects and concept art and
other things, but we don't want to see that until we see that
your character art portfolio is amazing and we want to hire you
for that. So the rest is just bonus.
So you wouldn't communicate to say your programmer
and he'll be like, hey, by the way, I need a new programmer
because last one got sick or had a crash or something?
Nope, no.
All right, thank you very much.
Hi, I was wondering if any of you have any advice
for people trying to cater their portfolios
to studios that are NDA and haven't released their title yet
specifically for art position, possibly tech artists,
more art-oriented?
Wow, that's a tough one.
That's a tough one.
So you haven't seen anything that they're doing?
You don't know what it is that they're kind of doing?
That's tough.
I mean, again, I would just put together your best work, put together what you think is
good, what you enjoy doing, and if it's not a fit, they're probably not going to call
you back.
But if it's a fit...
You wouldn't be there anyway if it wasn't so
You know you're kind of shooting in the dark a little bit
But you know yeah showing a strong point of view for what you want to do all day every day
It's about probably your best bet yeah when we were stepping up for destiny
And we hadn't shown anything about the game to the world we were still like we needed people
It was a big game with a lot of work, but we couldn't tell people what we were working on
but
Generally, people who are applying were familiar with our previous titles and were delivering
portfolios that were kind of in line with the nature of work that we did anyway.
So even though it's a little bit of a black box, you can kind of look to a company's track
record and try to cater to the company rather than the project.
At that point, would it be okay to take a step back if you weren't sure for Bungie and Halo,
could you take a step back and be a little bit more generalist with what kind of art that you show in your portfolio?
Would that be all right or is it better to just stick with your guns and be a specialist?
I think you could probably even guess too.
I mean with Bungie, even though Destiny is a million times different than Halo,
I mean I think you could probably guess that it's going to be in that realm of a game, right?
Versus like...
you know, you guys are making the new Skylanders or something like that. It's absolutely completely
different. I think it's kind of rare for a company to take such a hard turn.
We wouldn't have gone completely left turn and go cell shaded, funny animal games.
So no Snoopy games, huh? No. I'm a fan of the Snoopy. So, you know, again, it's a matter
of like sort of.
Checking out what the wheelhouse of that particular company is and sort of driving towards that
Due to time we can only take one more question
Thank you, so that is you okay? Hello
As was mentioned just a couple minutes ago
Character art is extremely hard to get into
What can a prospective character artist do to make their portfolio as competitive as
possible?
I'll ask that of you.
Oh, all right.
I mean, it's essentially what I've been saying, like all, you know, the whole hour.
I mean it's just quality, it's self-editing, it's having every piece that you have being
something that you're really, really proud of.
I mean to give you a rough stat, I have an opening for my company and I've had 500 plus
applicants.
you get a lot of people. You get concept artists, you get
sculptors, you get everything coming in. So there's a lot of
noise. You really have to stand out. What will make you stand
out is not being obnoxious, it's being like your professional,
your work is really solid, it's hitting modern technology, it's
looking like it should be on Xbox One, PS4, something like
that. It already fits. Because you're competing with
everybody who is competing with your class. You know?
Well, thank you guys very much for this. And we're really
excited to be doing this talk and we hope to be here again
next year. Please be sure to fill out your online forms
or whatever. And also we'll be doing our portfolio room
reviews in the next room, 132, which is that way. So we'll see
you there.