Ladies and gentlemen, PCG Shotgun.
Let's welcome them.
Thanks.
So when Dave told us that he wanted us to come up and speak
for 60 minutes about procedurally generated
shotguns, I didn't really think we'd have enough time to
fill all the content in.
So each person's going to talk about different types of
shotguns and how to procedurally generate them.
So I hope you guys all know what you were prepared for
when you came here.
And take lots of notes.
So I'm going to introduce our first speaker, Mithu.
And Mithu's going to take it from there.
Go for it.
All right.
Thanks, Tyler.
Hi, everyone.
So where are my slides?
Are they here?
Here they are.
Okay, cool.
Hi, okay, so, hi, I'm Mitty.
So I do a few things.
I make games as the Tiniest Shark.
I'm a member of faculty at the NYU Game Center.
I'm also Chief Creative Officer at Spirit AI.
So this is actually the second of three talks
I'm giving in the Just the AI Summit this year.
So some of you may have seen my talk yesterday on Reactive.
storytelling through agent-driven design.
And I'm going to talk about some of the work
that I've been involved with lately,
sort of touching on some elements of that,
so apologies if you saw that talk.
But also, I'm also doing other work
kind of at the opposite end of that spectrum.
So, and I've been thinking about this as a spectrum,
actually, so this idea of agent-driven stories
versus story-driven agents.
So, there are quite a few of us on this panel talking about various kinds of procedural
generation of characters and so I think part of the reason I'm going first is to frame
that work with some definitions and some tips for sort of working at both ends of that spectrum.
So firstly, why should we even tell those kinds of procedural character-based narratives?
The boring but true answer is replayability, longevity, etc.
The more interesting answer is that I think all procedural systems are kind of driven
by a philosophy, right?
It's an opportunity to discover a certain knowledge space.
And there's lots of opportunity for very thoughtful, very nuanced stories to be told.
So procedural narratives can allow us to explore and unpack the philosophy of an entire story space
rather than just one story, of course. So let's go ahead and start with some definitions.
So what I'm calling agent-driven stories are those which are based around simulating the
interactions of lots of agents which can sort of tell us something about that particular
world through having the player sort of interact with them, etc.
And the way that stories are told in that particular world is through a mechanism of
noticing really, so that's kind of the mechanic.
sort of noticing how agents are set up in opposition to each other,
which ones are different from the others,
and why those particular properties
might matter in the context of that particular world.
So, agent-driven stories rely on lots of agents.
The storytelling comes from noticing.
So, these agents are supposed to be moving,
they're not animating for some reason, but that's fine.
Let's imagine all these agents moving, and they're all moving differently.
So I want to talk about some PROC GEN considerations, given those sort of psychological strengths,
right, the sort of mechanics of noticing.
On the other hand, there are also what I'd call story-driven agents.
So those are agents which have been crafted to know a lot about a particular story space.
The way that you learn about the story space is by interacting with that particular agent
through some kind of dialogue or even some other set of interactions which act upon that
particular agent.
again my animations are not working.
Imagine one of those agents is like super huge
all of a sudden because that's the agent
that you're really interrogating.
Okay, so that's kind of the spectrum
of types of character AI.
So those of you who saw my talk yesterday
on telling reactive stories in an agent-driven world,
I sort of talked about what I'm doing at.
that's sort of this end of the spectrum, the agent-driven story's end of the spectrum,
as The Tiniest Shark, where I'm working on a game which is called Little Invasion Tales.
So Little Invasion Tales is a small city building and citizen management game all about defending your citizens from alien attacks.
I've also previously worked on a game called Redshirt, which was a kind of bleakly Machiavellian social networking simulator.
So, and that world was really set up through the mechanics of noticing, right? So noticing that characters behave differently
because
We don't really understand people, right?
Like, nobody really does.
We don't have a complete model of human behavior.
And the best we can do is express
a particular point of view.
So the limits that we impose on a sort of system
that we create are expressive.
They have something to say.
And we need to be cognizant
about what we're actually saying.
We need to be conscientiously reductive
when we're designing character-based games.
So for example in Red Shirt the space created was kind of about using people as pawns
and so a lot of the attributes that characters had
were kind of in that sort of negative space.
So they had things like vanity, fickleness, bigotry, etc.
That was like the world and those were the attributes
which set up characters in opposition to each other.
Then on this side of the spectrum at Spirit AI, we're building tools in middleware to
help people write story-driven agents.
So M Short just gave a talk in the Narrative Summit more about what we're doing, so I'm
not going to go into it.
But we're basically...
made an SDK and a set of tools for helping you create characters which are more deeply expressive.
One particular demo we have is about interacting with a robot who you're interrogating
and the system is able to sort of improvise off scripted dialogue that you've defined for it
and it has an agenda.
So it uses sort of a space of knowledge, like a knowledge space
that it has about its own world and uses that to let you interact with it.
So I think that those types of two sort of procedural character-based narratives
affect writers and designers in different ways.
So I think that one of the opportunities we have
is to sort of bring writers more into the fold of
sort of, you know, creating these sort of story-driven agents.
So with story driven agents, the shift moves more towards writers.
So and one of the things I want to sort of impress is how do we as humans,
if we're making character A.I. or just in general as humans,
how do we find out more about each other and our agendas like, you know, as real humans?
Generally, we do it by talking to each other. Right.
We sort of ask each other things.
We converse about our opinions, even when that's difficult.
in recent times especially.
So language is super important to humans.
And with Little Invasion Tales,
I've tried combining instances of language
into an agent-driven story,
which is basically the talk I gave yesterday.
One of the missions that I'm trying to accomplish
with Little Invasion Tales is bringing
sort of a wider audience into the fold
of understanding procedural narrative
and kind of what happens,
like the fact that we,
sort of look at agents interacting and we have like an implicit narrative that arises
out of noticing those interactions, but actually making that explicit through text and voiceover,
so using language to help us notice.
And so also related to that point, so this is, you know, I've already touched on how
redshirt worked.
And also...
Procedural characters need to be expressive about their world.
So again, in Little Invasion Tales,
they're expressive about their particular world
through talking to each other.
So the system in Little Invasion Tales
for passing knowledge between characters
is one that's inspired by the system in Left 4 Dead.
So it's basically like a query system and characters can share knowledge between each
other but also be able to sort of trigger all kinds of actions as well.
But also I want to point to besides language, what are some other solutions, particularly
if you're sort of at the end of the spectrum where you're making agent-driven stories.
So one of my go-to solutions to try and hit that sweet spot, which I've enacted across
both Redshire and Little Invasion Tales, is letting the player just see the process of
character creation, like using character creation to help us notice, right?
letting the player fiddle with sliders and variables
so that they can understand what the underlying model is.
So character creation is a form of communication.
This is the character creator from Little Invasion Tales.
So the last thing I want to say is that I'm really interested
in what we can come up with when we bring both sides
of the spectrum together.
What kinds of procedural character-driven narratives
might be possible then, right?
So again, my animations are not working,
but let's just imagine these floating and becoming one
and other things that the animation is supposed to do.
So yeah, imagining...
what would happen if we had a system where we had lots of agents sort of
interacting in the world, sort of, you know,
interacting with each other according to the underlying social model,
but then you could interrogate some of them, right?
So you'd have a few of them which you could interrogate more deeply and find out
actually, you know, what is their agenda within this world?
So using the mechanics of noticing and using the mechanics of language.
So yes, there we go.
So the little agent which is supposed to be animating
is saying, see how I act in relation to my world.
Talk to me about what my agenda might really be.
So that's it.
So that's my set of definitions.
You can see what we're doing at Spirit
on the language-based interaction
in North Hall from tomorrow.
Thank you.
Hello everyone. I'm Tanya Short and I'm going to give you some tips for maximizing the impact
of your generated personalities. I actually hadn't heard Mitu's talk before just now,
but I think you'll see some interesting parallels.
So yeah, if you're generating personalities in your game,
you're first going to need to pick a reasoning,
a motivation, and then a behavior,
which is what a character does and why they do it.
So now you have a generated personality, congratulations.
But is it an interesting personality?
Does the player understand what that personality is?
Are the connections between the reasoning and the behavior
actually satisfying to discover?
That's the goal.
Normally we would assume that reasoning drives behavior,
because that's how we experience our world.
Not only does science actually have a few factoids
and studies that disprove that,
but you might want to consider the opposite for your game.
In Moon Hunters, for example, the player's behavior,
such as being nice to everyone,
was then measured and determined
what personality trait was assigned to them,
such as compassionate,
sort of retroactively explaining their behavior.
through their motivation.
And from the player perspective,
they can encounter each of them,
or both simultaneously, depending on how you frame it.
Even if your engine is starting with reasoning
and then going into behavior,
it might make sense for the player to see it the opposite,
see it at the same time,
because to understand the simulation,
the player has to understand both the cause and the effect,
even if a given action is both a cause and an effect.
In human-authored media, it's common to start with the behavior and never show the reasoning.
It's common to advise show, don't tell, which means displaying a behavior and allowing the
audience to interpret the personality according to their own internal lens.
This is more natural.
This is how we encounter real people in real life.
Getting to know someone is about interpreting their behavior or their reasoning from their
behavior.
But most procedural personality games up until now
have gone the other way.
They tend to tell the audience about their personality traits
and their reasoning, and then later on display the behavior,
at which point it's the player's gameplay to notice.
and interpret what the algorithm is actually doing
with that reasoning.
The advantage of this approach is that AI systems
become core to the gameplay.
Noticing is the gameplay of understanding the systems.
And this is great when you're worried
that maybe your behavior will seem rather random
because now the players have built
their own model of reasoning.
However, that can result in a lot of information
for the player.
Many procedural personality systems, such as our beloved Dwarf Fortress,
and games I have worked on as well, tend to expose a lot.
And as our audiences become more accustomed to procedural content,
maybe we won't need to expose as much to convince them it's not random.
But part of the problem is that compared to other procedural content,
procedural personalities are very subtle,
because in real life, even, personalities are very subtle.
They are abstract, they are invisible, they're fourth dimensional,
they take place over time.
And even if you lean on well-known archetypes,
people will still need to pay attention to see the pattern.
You can't rely on instinct the way you can with physical attributes
like hair color or height or gender.
I was stunned when I joined the Age of Conan system design team because I had played the
game for a month.
And after playing for a month, I joined the team,
and I looked at their scripting engine,
and I found a beautiful, modular, elegant version
of a Maslovian hierarchy of needs for these monsters
that I had been slaying and observed no such thing.
Every single character first would seek safety,
and then seek shelter, and then seek food,
and companionship, and self-actualization, yes.
Even though the internal design team's motto was combat, combat, combat, and correspondingly
most of the players just killed everything.
But the real problem here was that there was no way as a player I would expect that to
be the case, and there was no sign to the contrary.
There was no reason for me to expect that reasoning was going on, and there was no communication.
So they had this beautiful system, which I used a lot for designing boss fights and things,
but this living, breathing world aspiration kind of took them into this
wasteful use of energy for years, developing a system that didn't need to be there.
So if you do hide information about your personality systems,
it can really help to be obvious about it.
As in Civ 6, which came out recently,
you can see some coy hints about what's hidden.
When something's hidden, it's very obvious.
This encourages further experimentation and exploration
by intriguing the player.
And that's part of why we're being really up front
about hidden villager personalities
in The Shrouded Isle, which is a game coming up published
by Kid Fox Games.
the discovery of those personality traits becomes a player goal, which is then very
intrinsically satisfying to discover, as if you're getting to know someone in real life.
So in addition to not hiding your whole systems,
you might want to look at what kinds of personalities
you're generating, because in games like Crusader Kings 2
or others, more extreme personalities
are easier to notice.
When you have subtle traits like irritable,
not only is it harder to see, but it's also
harder for the character to express
through your various gameplay systems.
For example, Roth.
It's easy to imagine what a Roth person might do on a battlefield or in political negotiations.
But irritable?
Does that really have a meaningful gameplay impact?
Probably not.
And finally, when you pick traits, even if you're going extreme, extreme passivity might
still be hard to see.
You might notice that in The Sims, it's not just that shyness, for example,
makes someone avoid conversation.
Avoidance is just really hard to see.
So instead, having specific behaviors for each extreme is important.
Even in real life, of course, when people are shy,
they don't actually cover their face and maybe withdraw awkwardly
from every conversation.
But if you don't do that, it just looks like a lack of behavior
rather than an active behavior.
Arguably the most successful personality type in King of Dragon Pass was the trickster archetype.
And I believe that that's because they clearly stood out among an otherwise reasonable panel
of people.
They were the one that really caught your eye when you were playing.
In short, it's a risk to hide almost everything in procedural personalities, because there's
no good reason for players to assume that there's any complexity there.
Of course, if you go too far in the extreme, everything becomes a bit silly, but even if
you don't get silly, players might still be laughing because...
Well, it's natural.
Authored characters have the advantage of immediately reading as human.
All gameplay systems in authored games tend to support the notion that this character's
personality is natural and it's expressive, whereas in a procedural game...
you tend to have overtly intellectual gameplay.
You tend to be having system-driven gameplay
in which the players are actively exploring the logic,
not leaning back and submissively
suspending their disbelief and becoming immersed.
Your characters are symbols of people
in this kind of gameplay.
They're not real people
and they're not even like authored people.
Exploring procedural systems and the chaos of simulations
is kind of the opposite of immersion.
I mean, even if you do achieve immersion and portray drama,
the player has to internalize all of your systems
in order to reach that point where
they can look past all the numbers and the spectrums
and whatever and see humanity, which takes time.
And during that time, chaos and surprise
is almost guaranteed in system-driven worlds, which
makes comedy even easier.
So when you're designing your player experience,
just keep in mind that things will
be a little bit funny anyway.
A third tip for maximizing your impact of procedural personalities is that if the same
event produces two contrasting reactions in characters, it's much more economical.
You can learn much faster about both characters than if you're relying on each of them acting
independently.
So in this example, if a character dies and one character laughs and the other one cries,
you're learning something about both of them without needing to set two different contexts.
And in fact, as in redshirt, you can more quickly process a whole crowd of reactions.
If you have a crowd of 10 people, imagine trying to keep track of each of those 10 each
doing their own separate activity versus 5 of them crying and 5 of them laughing, which
tells you not only about each one, but also their relationship to each other.
And finally, I recommend changing your procedural personalities over time rather than setting
them static at the beginning.
Because people change.
That's natural.
They change for so many different reasons that players will justify almost any transformation.
We've told them enough kinds of stories.
We're used to seeing people get stronger over adversity or weaker in adversity or getting
stranger.
So as long as the player is given a before, a trigger, and an after.
it's probably enough fuel for them to build their own pattern
of why the change happened and what it means to them.
I just want to take a moment to note that when I reached out to David Dunham, a designer
of King of Dragon Pass, he actually explicitly warned that these risks can be overcome.
And it's true, there have been procedural personalities that have been subtle and dramatic,
and they're great.
But the reason I give these risks is not that they're bad, it's that we want to engage with
these risks intentionally rather than discover them halfway through production.
So I recommend being...
careful with your subtlety and otherwise maximizing the impact of your procedural personalities.
Thank you.
Okay, so I'm Tarn Adams, the co-creator of Dwarf Fortress with my brother,
and I'm going to talk about, I mean, I was invited on an AI procedural generation panel
and I came up with the most naive thing you could do.
I have AIs making stuff, so this is a discussion about that.
So here we have, just naively, we have procedural generation.
You have some sort of algorithm that's going to make something.
You have an input, you have a random number generator.
And rarely in practice does it actually turn out that way.
We massage our results.
We add a lot of algorithms.
You can put your sort of personal touch into it, and it
can get out of control.
Sometimes you have to throw things away.
But in the end, you have a lot of levers once you've made
your final sort of algorithm when you're thinking about
generating any type of content.
And it's great to have all of those levers available
because when you have an AI making something,
you can just swap in personality traits
for your initial state.
You can bias your random number generation
with these traits to sort of restrict the output
into what could be created by this agent.
You can think in isolation of an agent creating things
as just a restriction of a general algorithm,
although in.
in practice you'll find that they do much more.
So what am I talking about here?
Making anything really.
I mean you could have simple crafted items,
you could think of like Diablo type stuff,
or furniture, visual artwork.
I know you don't need to actually generate
very good assets, but anything really.
Location maps, stories.
You could think of AI behavior itself
as being a result of a procedural generation algorithm
if you want to be reductive about it.
really anything you want in this talk.
And they think about the knowledge of the world,
what things have happened, what sort of locations there are,
also their relationships to people.
You can put anything at all, their personal beliefs,
into these objects they create.
But, I mean, coming from Dwarf Fortress,
you might think I'm talking about,
like, generate your whole world,
and then you can make a game, too, or whatever, right?
That's not what I'm saying here with...
with events these could be handcrafted, this could just be one small generator that exists in a
completely handcrafted game. You just have to systematize things. So, specifically with
events, when I'm talking about things that happen, those could be things that the player
does. We're talking about in-play generation after all.
and we have the AI agents running around doing things.
But you can take your, if you have an IP or something
or just some backstory that you've written,
you have your books and video logs and so forth,
but along with those, you can create a skeleton,
just a skeleton of what happened in a systematic way,
homogenous with these player events
so that they can all relate to each other.
You can use the same functions to generate objects.
that tie the player events in with back story events and so forth.
And you can systematize larger groupings if you want to reduce something down to just
say the biography of this person even though it contains many events.
So more importantly, I guess for things like emergent narrative,
you can also take your outputs and turn them into inputs.
You can think about things that other people have made,
your agents can think about things that the player made,
they can think about their own stuff, they can think about other people's stuff.
And so let's do some examples.
So a simple example is the player is elected mayor of a
city.
This is any game where that could happen.
Someone could make a statue, a commemorative statue.
It's a very simple AI thing.
You'd need to say that the AI doing this, of course, this is
their profession or something.
They know how to make statues.
But they know that this event happened.
They created it.
Or they could try and systematize something a
little more.
Personal to them like their belief in the value of friendship. They could write a book about it
That doesn't mean like generating the text of the book or anything. They just create this in-game object that stores
Data you this is the kind of the what the biggest takeaway of the talk is the more data you store in your objects
The more little gears you have to bump against each other to make emergent narrative
So you actually store the data inside the book and then it can be used
People, like most naively, could create copies of objects.
People would understand that they're making a copy of a sort
of a statue of the player
if they're just making knockoffs for some reason.
Or they could be reviewing the book.
They can talk about it.
They can think about who is the author of this book
because that's stored in the book.
They can think about what do I think of the value of friendship?
What do I think of the writing style?
Because those things are stored in the book object.
And it also allows you to do exposition.
If you have data in the objects that your agents have made,
then you can speak to other events that have happened.
It's sort of a way to indirectly propagate information
by scattering things around the world.
It's difficult to get the player to suck in this data stream,
right, there's so many things going on.
It's the exposition problem kind of.
Both of the previous speakers have gone into a little bit.
And this is just carrying a little data in your objects
lets you do that.
It also lets you have reactions to the objects
that make the world seem more alive.
So if someone doesn't like the player,
they can see that the player is related to that object.
They don't need to care about this mayor thing,
but just the fact that that piece of data is in there
allows a reaction.
And the same thing if you don't like the...
value of friendship, you could burn all the books and hunt down the author.
But more subtly, you could just learn the basic existence of that event, so you can
propagate knowledge through these indirect objects.
And you can also change people's minds.
This is, it's kind of the sort of, I don't know if it's the holy grail of personality,
but that's, like Tanya said, change is gold, making things that actually seem like a character
arc.
And that's what I'm going to talk about today.
And I hope you enjoyed it.
And I'll see you next time.
Bye.
where someone would pick up this book and learn the value of friendship finally.
It could be something that happens.
I mean, in Dwarf Fortress we have people propagating books around and sort of pushing philosophies
one way or another just like this.
So for the last bit here, we have...
The game, there's the game.
Your player has done things in order, right?
I mean, it's simple.
You have these events.
They're systematized.
Their location, what the player did, if there was
someone else involved.
We also store reasons and circumstances to the extent
that we know them at all so that people can think a little
more deeply about the game objects.
And as I said before, you can have your historical objects stored the same way. This is not
necessarily a procedural history, but just if you're doing some kind of comic book game and
you have 20 back issues, you could make a systematized version of them and be able to
refer back to them and have sort of content emerge from that. The same goes with future
events can be stored the same way. So you can have some kind of psychic prediction or
prophecy that's supposed to be met.
And then when the AI crafters come along,
thinking about these things,
they can start to do stuff that's almost literary,
right, at this point.
I mean, it's not gonna be high art or anything,
but you can start to draw allusions to past events,
and you can start to use literary tools,
like substituting, say, the player,
whatever happened there to the poor red thing
that didn't seem to make it to the end of the game.
in event B could be something similar
that happened in history,
and then when someone makes a statue,
they could sub out the antagonist
with the antagonist from the past,
but show the player defeating the antagonist from the past,
and then the exposition,
they'd kind of either explain what they did
or at least what they were getting at,
so the player doesn't have to guess
that these things have these value,
they can just be told about them.
Unless, I mean, there's something to be said for not telling them everything.
In any case, we have finally, you can introduce your conceptual objects into this sort of
thinking.
So, in Dwarf Fortress we have, say, 40 intellectual values that people have in different sort
of degrees numerically.
And you could give.
the basic events, like this, say this reconciliation
that maybe happened at the end here,
could have friendship tagged with that simple event.
Just a simple table of events linked to conceptual types.
And that's, I mean, it's basically a symbol, right?
So we have this book of friendship then,
doesn't need to have text, it could just have
a simple set of friendship-related events
that the person wrote about the player.
They just need to describe them somewhere,
say that the player was involved,
and somehow involve the, in the exposition,
say that the symbol of friendship was involved,
and that's an allegory, right?
So you can do any sort of artistic literary type
you can think of can be involved
with fairly simple systems.
I mean, there's not too many objects here,
but you just, kind of what it says on the tin
when you go to Wikipedia and read about allegory, right?
There's some just simple concepts that you link together
to produce these things.
And you don't have to produce the text, right?
I mean, that's the thing.
You just need to produce a description,
allow the person to say what's going on.
and then allow people to react to it and be changed.
So this book of friendship might actually describe events of this,
these fictional events that the player didn't actually do,
and then someone could come up to you and thank you
for teaching them about the value of friendship
and you wouldn't know what was going on until you found the book.
So, yeah, that's it.
Alright, who here likes math? It's about to get really gritty, so buckle up.
My name is Zach Aikman, I'm the technical director at 17-bit.
If you haven't heard of us, 17-bit is a medium-sized indie studio based in Kyoto, Japan,
with a satellite office in Seattle.
Our first game is a turn-based strategy game called Skulls of the Shogun.
But more recently we released a 2D space shooter called Galaxy on PlayStation 4 and PC,
and right now we're working on adapting that game into a mobile version to be released later this year.
As lead engineer on Galaxy, I was responsible for developing a number of different systems,
but the one that I had the most fun with, and the one that I'm going to be talking about today,
was the system for generating procedural levels.
We made the decision halfway through development to switch from handcrafted dungeons to procedural content
to put more of an emphasis on the parts of the game that really shined, namely combat.
And so just to help put this talk in context,
here's a top-down view of a level in Galaxy's early prototyping days.
all the rocks, the camera boundaries,
the decorative objects, enemy squads,
all that stuff was hand placed.
And we realized that this was not gonna be
a feasible approach for generating a lot of content
with a team of our size.
And in this animated GIF about how levels
were being built procedurally near the end of the project,
explaining everything that goes into this
would be pretty exhaustive talk,
not one that we have time for today,
but I wanna touch on some of the main points
and the takeaways that we learned from them.
I'm going to go out on a limb and assume that most of you are somewhat familiar, or at least
vaguely familiar, with cellular automata, popularized by Conway's Game of Life.
Using a simple set of rules that gets iteratively applied to each cell based on the state of
its neighbors, you can generate incredibly complex, self-sustaining patterns.
Here we see two examples of cellular automata, one very simple and one very complex.
With the right rule set, cellular automata can also be used to generate
very organic looking cave-like structures.
As soon as I saw this image I knew that cellular automata
were going to be used in Galaxy's Dungeon duration in some form.
But obviously there's more to building levels than just generating geometry.
A cavern of this size would pose serious problems when it comes to placing
points of interest
and guiding the player through the level.
So instead we opted to use cellular automata to generate chunks of a level
and then stitch those together into a contiguous path.
This first animation shows a room-sized automata being refined from its initial seed into the
cave-like structure over the course of several iterations.
And the second animation shows how we were able to control the spaciousness of a room
by simply seeding the starting pattern with more or less living cells.
So in the end, we wound up using cellular automata patterns as a basis for room creation.
The generated rooms were then overlaid with additional layers of metadata using a custom tool that we built.
Designers could place spawn points, squad patrol routes, deco and lighting data, etc. to be applied to the cavern after it was generated.
Initially we tried storing the seeds for the automata and generating the caverns at runtime.
It seemed like the most cost-effective way of storing a whole lot of room data with just a handful of seed values.
But this turned out to be an inefficient and unnecessary step.
What we gained in storage space we lost in processing time, because it can be kind of
expensive to run 10 iterations in every single room on a grid that's 64 by 64.
It really starts to add up.
So a better approach was to instead store a run-length encoded version of the generated
pattern.
Run-length encoding is especially efficient at storing exactly these types of images,
which have little to no variation in the interior of the cell.
So once we had these cavern cells,
we still needed a way to stitch them together
into a cohesive level.
And we knew that we wanted levels to occupy
a certain amount of rectangular space in the game.
And we also had to fix the cell size
that worked well for the amount of content
that we were trying to place inside of each room.
And furthermore, the cellular automata chunks
had been engineered to accommodate orthogonal exits
for north, east, south, and west.
And we didn't want to deal with diagonal exits
or some sort of hexagonal connections between cells.
So we experimented with a number of different approaches
for building level layouts within a fixed region,
including BSP trees, minimum spanning trees,
and other well-known algorithms
that you'll use a lot in Proc Gen stuff.
But nothing really seemed to fit
with our unique constraints,
so I attempted a slightly less orthodox solution
that doesn't exist in the Proc Gen toolkit.
My coworker suggested Z-order curves
as a potential solution for connecting
the interior rooms of a generated dungeon.
And Z-order curves are functions that map multi-dimensional data to one dimension
while preserving the locality of those data points.
So as you trace through that curve,
all the rooms that it connects are nearby each other,
but you can sort of walk the path using a single index
instead of worrying about two-dimensional coordinates.
But they're also recursive, as you can see in this image.
The higher-order curves are composed of lower-order curves,
which makes them scalable to grids of any size.
Zero-to-curves were too jaggy for our use,
but being clued into their existence
led me to find another kind of space-filling curve
that was much more amenable to our constraint
of connecting rooms orthogonally.
Hilbert curves maintain the mapping of 2D to 1D space
that we were after, but do so orthogonally,
allowing us to connect rooms with north, south,
east, and west exits.
So imagining that we want to fill a four-by-four grid
with dungeon cells, this is a Hilbert curve
that could be used.
The H value represents the distance along the path,
starting in the top left and ending at the top right.
And that can be used to control things
like difficulty ramps,
the probability of finding treasure within a room,
you can increase that probability as the H value goes up,
all sorts of things like that.
And the math for converting Hilbert curve indices
into 2D coordinates is extremely simple and pretty fast,
which means that you can use them interchangeably
very easily.
But the most glaring problem with this approach
is that all Hilbert curves look the same.
Even if you rotate the curve, players are going to pick up on the pattern after just a few playthroughs.
So our solution to the problem was to generate a higher order Hilbert curve
than was actually needed, and then use a sampling kernel of the desired size.
So by sliding this kernel around and sampling the path, you can get different layouts
from the more complex Hilbert curve.
This really couldn't have worked out better for us.
It was kind of the perfect approach that we stumbled upon.
The higher order curves contain more detail
and thus more variety.
And if you rotate the curve,
you can get even more combinations of paths.
So using Hilbert curves was a non-traditional approach
that worked out better than we expected.
I'd never even heard of Hilbert curves
being used in game development before,
and it was really gratifying to try to implement
a technique that I'd never seen used elsewhere
and have it actually work.
And I've talked about Hilbert curves
in other settings like GDC,
which has led to two other games utilizing them
for their own level building needs.
And seeing someone else implement your algorithm
is not only really rewarding as a developer,
but it also leads to incremental improvements,
which you can then fold back into your own project.
Hilbert curves are definitely not a perfect solution, nor are they even a good solution for most games, but they fit our needs really well.
So I want to shift a little bit from level generation
to talk about how we made the enemy units
in Galaxy feel more alive.
This is funny because I'm going to touch on something
that Me Too mentioned in her talk, serendipitously, I guess.
So frequently during combat, enemies will fire off
little quips and exclamations, things like,
I see him when they spot the player,
or help, I'm under attack if they need backup.
And we call these interjections barks.
But getting these barks to sound organic
and non-repetitive is a really interesting challenge,
one that we solved by looking to Valve's
Left 4 Dead series.
So, Alon Ruskin at Valve gave a fantastic presentation
at GDC 2012 about the contextual dialogue system
that they built for Left 4 Dead series.
I'm not going to rehash the entire talk,
but I can't recommend it highly enough.
It's a really interesting, really detailed,
and very easy to follow explanation
of how they laid out their dialogue system.
But the gist of the approach is that your engine maintains a global state of world facts that are constantly updated as the game state changes.
Facts are really nothing more than key value pairs that track things like how many enemies have been killed or how long has the session been active.
Additionally, many other local states are stored containing facts unique to a particular entity in your game.
For the player, this might include things like how many bullets are left or how much damage has been taken.
And your writers will then author all dialogue triggers
as piles of rules or queries.
And these rules can be as specific
or as generic as you'd like.
For example, if the level has been active
for more than five minutes,
and the player has less than five health,
and an upgrade item is nearby,
then play the dialogue line just in time.
And the contextual system will always try
to find the query with the most number of rules matched,
which allows you to write dialogue
that's as specific or as generic as you need it to be.
Alon goes into much more detail in his talk on how to best store these facts and rules
and how to optimize your query functions and other interesting topics like that that really
matter about the implementation.
So again, I'd encourage you to check out his talk or his slides if you're interested in
those details.
But despite the versatility of this approach,
our implementation suffered from a few problems
that I wish we had been better about addressing,
and I'm hoping I can pass on some of those lessons to you.
One is that the sheer number of rules and facts
that you can generate can lead to
an overwhelming amount of content.
I think in Left 4 Dead 2,
they said they had 10,000 lines of dialogue,
which is no small amount of content to manage.
And for a large team with a dedicated writer
who's regularly working in your tools
and is really involved in the project,
it may not be an issue.
But for a small team like us,
it was more of a burden than it was worth.
We also neglected to write an adequate system for bug testing rule queries.
Many of those queries can grow to be really complex, and if you don't have a system in
place that allows you to easily manipulate the world or entity fact state tables, it
becomes a really tedious process to try and track down errant lines of dialogue.
And this was the one that hurt us the worst, I think.
We had a really bad content pipeline.
Due to the way that certain game data in Galaxy was edited and stored,
we had barks to find in both Excel spreadsheets
and Google Drive spreadsheets.
And rebuilding the barks data consisted of
downloading the Google Drive spreadsheets
and running an access database merge on multiple sheets.
To make matters worse, the merge was handled by a Unity tool which relied on a certain
access plugin that only ran on the 32-bit version of Unity and certain versions of Access,
and it was an extremely brittle pipeline that could have broken at any point in time when
we upgraded Unity or Access.
Thankfully it did not, and we made it through the project, but it's not something that I
would do again.
Thank you for listening.
That's it for me.
If you have any questions, shoot me an email or opt in to the panel.
I can grab you.
Thanks.
We've got the clicker on the top.
Cool.
Hey everybody. My name is Luis Kruel.
I'm a senior technical artist over at SetFX.
We make a software called Houdini.
And this is a pet project of mine that I'm going to be sharing in a little bit.
So I was in game development for about 10 years before joining software development.
And I still have that itch to make games.
So this is my kind of little love child.
So this talk is about me and then I have a little bit of content from Antonio Liappis
that is over at University of Malta and I'm going to talk a little bit about how we met
and basically how that relationship evolved.
So what we have is a little project that I came up with where I want a procedurally generated
first person shooter at triple A quality and
This is part of my other talk later today
on the AI crackpot, so you can see how weird
and awful it is, but this is the first steps towards that,
and I wanted to show where we are in the process,
and I think we're gonna get really close
to that realization.
So we have a small team, we wanna be building
AAA content, and we wanna basically have
as much proceduralism and as humanly possible,
and it needs to be a multiplayer competitive FPS.
And we worked in like the team, everybody has kind of that frame of mind and that experience.
So that's why if we're going to put proceduralism into some game, that's the kind of, that's our jam.
So it's like, that's our muscle memory and that's what we know how to do.
So the way I like to think about proceduralism and AI is like in TechCart we have
proceduralism as this little black box of inputs that basically the artist will drive
and they'll kind of draw little volumes and everything.
But if you shove AI into that, now we basically have something that can just pump
out content really, really, really fast.
So that's where we want to get to.
So I started to think about this project and then I went to a.
a conference, there's like a ton of academics and they're all talking about procedurally
generated and all these cool ideas and I was like let me just shoot a blind email out into
the ether and then see what shakes out. So I basically shot out to procedurally generated
Google groups and was like hey man we can run this project, anyone interested in helping
me out? This is what I'm kind of going for. And then Antonio actually came back and he
was like hey I have this thing called this ancient sketchbook and we can just make maps.
And then it's a web based API and then it basically just starts by randomly pasting
nodes around and then continuously evolving based on constraints and all of that is kind of data driven and it works really well.
So I started kind of playing with it a little bit and seeing what how far I could get to it.
And so here's a little bit of the kind of process to where you have like the random initial seed
and then you kind of start evolving based on rules and constraints that I define as an artist.
The web API had a little bit of less what than what we needed so he was just super nice and
was like tell me what you need because I was like he.
kind of craved that actual AAA side of things.
And he was like, I want to see this academic stuff
being used in context, and I wanted to use academics.
So we kind of met in the middle, and he actually
started giving me kind of custom executables
that I could use.
And we made some modifications.
So the first one is the ability to have second floors
to our maps, which is kind of something unique
in procedural content generation.
He gave us something I'm gonna talk a little bit about
later, which is like further evaluation of the data
so I can tell where choke points are,
where dead ends are, where cross ends are.
and then being able to lock down the entrances,
which is really crucial for me,
and I'm gonna talk a little bit about that later.
And then just being able to,
like procedural systems tend to,
and he talked a little bit about it,
where you just, the walls kind of creep in,
and it'll try to fill up as much space as possible,
and it's very maze-like,
so that's the opposite of what you want
on a first-person shooter.
You want these big, nice, open areas
that you can kind of run around
and kind of connect together.
So he basically added another constraint,
which is I can control the degree
of how many walls get placed.
So the output data that I get from the system
is ASCII so much like the Dwarf Fortress stuff.
So basically we have a little text
that is E is for entrances,
I get basically stairs or jump pads in my case,
and then spawn points, weapons.
I can specify a lot of things
on basically where I want things to spawn
and how many of each I get.
So that basically I have a little Java.
I have a Python wrapper to a Java executable
that just have a bunch of parameters I can create.
Ideally, we can kind of extrapolate this up
and then make more rules and kind of build this out.
And then basically I can just make
as many maps as I want to.
And yeah, the addition output data is.
I have the original map and then he can also as well with the maps I can get uh that choke
points, dead ends and crossroads. I'm not using this currently but for like as you people
want to kind of start using this, this is super kind of crucial data um that you might be
able to use.
So making sense of the data. So first like the ASCII stuff is really hard to read. So first I
wanted to translate the ASCII data into 3D. So I just kind of built a grid and then I just
color coded it so I could see what the hell is going on. So now I can see the entrances of
everywhere and then the blues is where the jump pads are going to be so we can go from one map to
the other one. And then the reds is where the weapons are going to spawn and then the greens
are going to be the spawn points.
But then I can make really cool single rooms,
but then we get to the point again,
that's like how do you stitch this together?
And then the traditional methods again fell short
because they're really built for dungeons
to where you kind of have the spidery vein
of things growing.
We talked about like adding teleporters
to the end of the rooms to kind of connect it together
to try to get a flow.
But where we landed is actually just let the designers
come up with the top-down map,
and it takes them like five minutes to build it,
and then they can just explicitly say
where the entrances of each rooms are,
what sizes they are, how it all connects together.
And then I can take each of those individual rooms
and then run through the system.
So it's kind of a backwards approach
to procedural content generation,
which is actually working out really well for us.
So traditionally, people will pre-make the rooms itself
and then kind of procedurally stitch them together.
We're doing the opposite, to where we're pre-making
the kind of high-level flow of the map
and where we want the rooms to be,
how we want the exits to go.
And then the inside content, it doesn't really matter for us.
It's like, that's where the flavor's gonna come in.
So the way it works is I take that,
a top down map, I bring it into Houdini, I just parse the data and then I can isolate where the
exits are, I can kind of get a little bit of a height variation, I can calculate the dimensions
and know where all the door placements are. I can then run that through the generator that I can
then get as many variations as I need, then now they're all color coded, I get the rooms back and
then I just kind of do some basic extrusions and then I isolate the rooms, I boolean them
together and then I actually place the game objects.
And these are the results.
So right now we're at the kind of white stage map
and we're kind of taking production as we would
in a regular game development.
So first you have like a white box
and then we're gonna start arting out.
The whole thing is gonna be procedural
but we wanted these safety spots
to just kind of reality check where we are
and be like okay, does this feel fun?
Before going all the way,
just like you would in a regular game,
just does the system works before I kind of make
all terrain and everything procedural
and everything looks beautiful,
is the game fun?
So we actually got to the point now that
It's actually pretty fun to play and you can kind of get it in Unreal.
And we had some bots in there and it actually feels like a real game,
which is something that I'm super excited about.
And actually the designer that I'm working with,
at first he was kind of like, yeah, okay, procedural,
like I want complete control.
And now after seeing this stuff, he's like, okay.
I can see with the force from the tree.
I think this is possible and I think we can do this.
So I'll be, again, at 1 p.m.
I'm gonna talk about the kind of massive vision
of what this project could be,
but I just wanted to share the kind of interim step
of where I am.
And yeah, that's all I got.
Thank you.
So everything that is procedural is pseudo.
And I want to talk a little bit about how
pseudo random generation, you need to treat it
as your friend and not your enemy.
So everyone, show of hands, everyone knows what
pseudo random generation is, right?
So here's the question.
Raise your hand if you've used an actual
random number generator.
Actual random, not pseudo.
Oh, and the hands shrink.
So the thing about computers is we can't actually
make true random generation, we have to use pseudo.
But you can use pseudo to your advantage.
You can create experiences that use the pseudo nature
of random generation to ensure that these experiences
that people get that have some sort of random entity
and it can be reused, reutilized,
and kind of taken advantage of as your players and designers.
So I don't know if you guys have recently heard,
in 2014 there was a group of Russian hackers
who went on to a whole group
of these Novomatic casino machines,
and they were able to record data of those machines,
watch them play multiple rounds,
and through doing so, they could actually figure out
what the current seed was
and know when the next big win was gonna be.
So there's this current big rush of casino companies
all over the world getting rid of all these old machines
because their pseudo-rando generators were just too pseudo
and not random enough.
In games, we don't really care so much about that.
I mean, if someone can figure out potentially
what a seed is, if they could reverse engineer,
hey, this is a seed that causes
this interesting experience,
that can be a positive thing for a player.
It's something where they can intentionally choose a seed
or kind of direct the seed generation
to make something interesting and experience for them.
So I would guess probably many people in many situations,
they use the wonderful trick of setting your OS time
as your random seed.
Can I see a show of hands of who has done that?
Yeah, okay, so that's the quick, easy, dirty trick.
It ensures that it's somewhat random
and you're not gonna get the same seed.
And that's great for something if you just need
a quick, dirty, random result.
But there's a lot of times when you actually wanna do
a random seed that has value for the player
or can be reutilized or the player can choose
which seed they want.
So there's a couple different options here.
One of the most common is let the user input a seed.
So this is something like Dwarf Fortress, like Minecraft.
Put in a number, put in a string,
I convert it to a number and that's the seed we use.
This is great because it allows you
to share it with someone else.
Hey, you know, check out seed PCG shotgun on Minecraft.
I was gonna share a photo of that
and it's actually a really boring start spot.
So like.
Sorry.
But the idea is you can take a really cool,
hey, put in my name and see what happens
and let's run around in that world.
And it becomes a shareable random experience
because you can recreate that exact random generator
and pass it on to someone else.
Also, if you do this, you don't actually have to tell them
about their input.
You don't have to say, hey, I'm gonna share a seed,
write it in, and this is what it is.
I'd love to see some games, and I don't know
if there's any examples of this, so please find me
afterwards, where you actually use something like
the character creation to determine the random seed.
So someone puts in their profile name,
that becomes the seed generator.
It's the same thing as I just showed with the Minecraft
seeds or with Dwarf Fortress, except you're not explicitly
saying to them, hey,
this is your random seed.
What makes this really interesting is it essentially
creates a cheat code base for your player base
that they can discover as they play.
Like yo, I just found that if you put in the name
Yossarian, it creates this really awesome level
and like it's this very special space
and the first room has like the best gun in the game.
It creates this really interesting conversation
among your players because they're looking for seeds
and they're trying to discover seeds
through this input system that are really interesting.
I'd also love to see within this like loading screens.
You have a lot of now we can do interactive loading screens
again without being sued.
So do something interactive with your loading screen
and take that input and make it become a random seed
generator for any content that you have
coming after that loading screen.
You can also take a seed and break it into its sub elements.
So if you have this 12 digit number,
you can take that 12 digit number
and each number can actually be a specific chunk
to place into like a level map.
So like Luis's example, each one of those rooms
could be like, okay, we're using room format one,
room format two, and you actually take the seed number
and switch it out like that.
What's really nice about that is then you can treat your seed as a flexible number,
or flexible string.
So rather than it just being this big long number that you don't do anything with,
you can make small adjustments to it.
You can take this, switch two of the digits,
and you still have the general layout that's been defined,
again using like Luis's example of like a hand-generated flow.
but now you have two different formats have changed.
And then within the internal elements
of each of these rooms,
you still have a lot of individual things
that are using this seed to decide
what items drop, what characters are there.
So you can get some bit of consistency
across the full experience,
but then have small shifts to the random generation
without completely regenerating the whole system.
You can also, this is quite popular,
is taking seeds from many values.
A lot of games such as No Man's Sky,
you're generating a galactic space,
you know, a whole galaxy.
In order to do that, you need a lot of seeds.
And the best way to do that is to take XYZ data.
Take your X, take your Y, take your Z,
concatenate them together.
That's a unique random seed
that will only be available for that item.
So when you generate a planet, you generate a star, you can use location data, you can
use color data.
Someone color picks or, you know, it's randomly generated colors.
You use the RGB data to create a seed through those multiple pieces.
You can also use a user ID.
So many of us, if you're developing anything for mobile,
developing anything for PC, possibly with console,
I'm not sure how, but if you can get a specific user data ID,
something that's unique to the user,
you can then use that as a random seed.
Create something where there's a random data for them
that is actually not random for them.
It becomes a static experience for that specific player.
So this is again like a UDID, a MAC address,
any type of information that you can pull
that's unique to that player.
Assign that as a random seed,
and that actually becomes a seed
that's no longer random for them.
So if they have a first level that's generated,
they always get that same first level,
but they're the only one who ever gets that first level.
No one else will experience that level or that space
or that specific combination of random generation
because it's locked to them.
And that brings me to my last point
is the idea of a lifetime seed.
So.
We've all experienced random generation,
we've all played games with random generation.
Every time you play a game,
every time you go through that replay,
it's a new random experience.
But using something like the user ID seed
or a lock seed to each individual player
ensures that even though we have randomness
across each of our experiences,
those experiences are unique to us
and we will always experience those same results.
This again will create a wonderful community involvement where I can talk about my experience,
I can talk about, hey, you know, the purple potion in this roguelike always kills me.
You say the purple potion always gives you health, but it always gives you health.
Every time you replay, you don't have to drink that potion and wonder what it's going to
do this time.
It is specific to you.
And I'd love to see games do this with map generation,
with character generation,
with anything with a procedural system,
because then you create consistency across the replays,
across those experiences,
and it gives the community an opportunity
to kind of talk about their specific seed
or kind of their specific space that they have,
and they get to feel ownership to it.
It's unique to them.
they know that that one random dwarf or that one random character in red shirt always shows up
for them every time but no one else gets that character. So it gives them more authorship and
more ownership to the random generation instead of feeling like full random craziness. And
that's it for me. So thank you everyone.
So we have two or three minutes.
We're going to do a little fun activity here.
Each one of us is going to go through and kind of talk
about a game that we absolutely love,
but would love to see have more procedural generation.
Does anyone want to volunteer to start?
I would love to see a procedural layer of any kind
added to Princess Maker 2.
I always wanted to see Xevious with procedural levels, because it has like the weird little
eagle you find on the ground, like a little bit through there, and you're like, what is
this doing there?
But it would be more like a cultural exploration of a randomized civilization that I guess
you're also blowing up at the same time, which is kind of sad.
I'm really a big fan of music games, so Rez would be my top choice.
Like, Rez has some procedural elements to it, but it's like, it's more music-generative...
Reactive and generative, but like, more, you know, procedural instruments or synthesizers
or patterns and things like that.
Like, I think it's rich for that kind of thing.
I'd love to see a game like Oregon Trail have procedurally generated characters or personalities.
Like, start from here, get to here, long travel experience,
but with actual more personality that's procedurally generated.
I'd love to see Mega Man being done procedurally to where the weapons are procedurally generated
on the bosses and then the levels are procedurally generated as well.
So I'm going to cheat slightly and I'm going to point to a game that I'd love to sort of bring together those sides of the spectrum that I defined, right?
Like, so, like a version of Papers, Please, where you have these like procedurally generated characters coming up to you and then obviously you're looking at their documentation, etc.
But then you can interrogate them further and find out more about their sort of motivations, their...
and have, I can imagine that being a game where
sort of, you know, the context of the world is set up
through noticing the differences
between the different characters,
but going deeper on that, so I think that'd be.
Awesome, and that does it for us for time.
I guess some of us will be in the wrap-up room
and Dave will say some words, so.
Thank you guys.