Alright, good morning everybody. Thanks Joel for the introduction. This is a little design in a day and
this is a talk, a topic that's near and dear to my heart, solving puzzle design. A bit of a background on me, I began my career at Telltale Games as a cinematic artist and a designer and now I'm a level designer at Ubisoft Studio SF just around the corner on the new South Park RPG, The Fractured But Whole. Think about it.
So why puzzles?
I love puzzles because designing a good puzzle
means you're combining tons of different concepts
in game design all together to make a really cool
unit of game, a good game nugget.
So you have your mechanics, your level design,
your narrative, balancing your difficulty, progression.
These are all things that go into puzzles
that make a puzzle a great experience for a player.
So in this talk, I'm just going to start with exactly what a puzzle is,
defining that in the context of level design,
talk about what makes a puzzle good,
and then we're going to go into the elements of a puzzle,
rational puzzle design,
how to build a puzzle,
and then some tips for troubleshooting puzzles when they just don't make sense.
So let's start off with what is a puzzle.
So puzzles are kind of hard to define. Again, we have the level design domain to kind of work within.
But in general, one of my favorite definitions for puzzles is it's a game with a dominant strategy,
which is when you have choices that are offered to a player, but one of them is clearly better than the rest.
Now this usually is not a good thing in game design.
You want a player to be able to choose what they want to do.
You want them to have decisions they can make.
But you can still have that with a dominant strategy.
And that's because puzzles are games with one solution.
That's what they are inherently.
And that's because while games are played to win,
puzzles are played to find a solution.
At their very heart, they are about finding that strategy.
So your gameplay finds in the challenge
of getting that dominant strategy nailed down.
So a puzzle is a challenge.
But it's not a competitive challenge, it's the player stopping and thinking about a challenge that you as the designer have given them.
You know, adventure games are a great example of this, this is Grim Fandango.
You're gonna, you know, you're playing a detective, so it's all about finding clues, figuring out who you need to talk to next, learning about the world and applying that.
You're always stopping and thinking the way a detective would.
I also have up here Angry Birds. Now Angry Birds is also a puzzle game because if you think about it,
there is a ideal way to destroy all the pigs in their home.
That's a message with like the kind of the star system. There is a dominant,
an ideal way, a most efficient way, using the birds you have
to solve the puzzle of breaking a bunch of pigs' homes.
So what makes a puzzle good?
Does anyone know?
So fun is important to a puzzle being good.
But that fun should come from the challenge.
And that challenge happens when the player feels a sense of trust and respect from the designer.
Now, how do you get that trust and respect?
You invite the player to find a solution. You don't hand them one. You let them try to find it themselves.
But you also make sure that solution is attainable.
You don't challenge, you don't, you know, be the awful GM who just kills all your players.
You're always letting them at least get out of the situation by their own merit.
And so, if you do achieve that, the player has a sense of accomplishment of getting through something themselves.
So, thinking about it that way, it's players learning how to get out of a situation.
Learning is fun.
And learning is fun because knowledge is power.
You know, games are all about feeling powerful in your surroundings or well equipped to handle
a situation.
And so, providing knowledge, that provides power.
And you know, when you're in a situation where you're stopping to think about a puzzle, feeling
powerful means knowing how to solve it.
So this is a talk that was at GDC last year.
It's called Precision of Emotion,
a New Kind of Fun Approach.
And this was given by a woman named Erin Hoffman.
And her theory on fun is that the search for knowledge
that a player undergoes is this emotional journey
by which they achieve mastery, mastery of a situation,
of a concept, of a puzzle.
And so she called this emotion of finding mastery Sophia.
So an emotion of mastery.
And a lot of it's actually built on Jean Puget's
cognitive development studies from the mid 20th century.
So it's all about how humans find knowledge
and how they're engaged in finding knowledge.
So this is a chart kind of, I keep going off the mic,
this is a chart illustrating kind of
what Hoffman calls the Sophia Loop,
which is this emotional journey one goes through,
a player goes through when they're solving a puzzle,
going through a game.
So at first.
The player is confronted by fear. They have an absence of skill. They don't know what to do. They're afraid.
And then they go through this kind of cycle of emotions.
They all fall under the general idea of surprise or being surprised.
But you know, all things that go into speculating, being curious, discovering something, finding insight.
And then when that all comes together and they do find that solution, they experience happiness.
They have a happiness of a mastery.
The Sophia feeling.
And in puzzles specifically, I like to call mastery insight,
because that's really what you're finding,
is you're finding insight into a solution,
into how to do something.
So this loop, if you guys have played The Witness,
I think we all feel this a lot when we play The Witness.
You know, you see this like Lisa Frank nightmare,
and you're like, what do I do about this puzzle?
I have no idea how to solve this.
But then you think back to the puzzles that you learn,
and you're like, okay, well I know I need to go
from A to B, I know how to solve this puzzle.
So you go through this kind of cycle of surprise,
of discovery, and then come out victorious.
Another example I'll walk through because I don't want to spoil the witness is this is the flinging puzzle from Portal 1.
So this puzzle comes in about midway through Act 1 of Portal, about like level 10.
And throughout the beginning of Portal, you've been crossing gaps kind of simply just by putting a portal next to you and hopping through it.
And you have an easy time getting across that gap that you couldn't before.
But then you come to this place and what happens is you look around and you see your gap.
But then you don't have anywhere to put your portals around. You can't cross that gap the way you've been crossing gaps
for the first 10 levels of this game. So you feel fear. How do I get across here? A gun doesn't work.
But you have the knowledge of the game, so
you can kind of say, okay, well, I know
orange portals are usually by the goal, so this orange puzzle might be near the goal.
And then you look below you in the pit,
in the pit you're trying to cross,
and you're like, well, I can put a portal on that.
That's cool.
And then you realize, oh, the exit's there.
That's how I get across.
And so you have this moment of surprise,
and then this kind of happiness that you discovered,
oh, I know exactly how to cross this gap.
I know why that portal was where it is.
I know what to do.
So now let's start digging into puzzles
and talking about what they're made of.
So the elements of a puzzle.
So at the core of puzzles, you're always basically finding a key that goes into a lock.
And sometimes the puzzle is finding the key, sometimes it's finding the lock, sometimes
a combination of both.
Like any game, puzzles are this creative combination of mechanics and theme.
In puzzles, I like to break mechanics out into verbs, so specifically mechanics that the player can use, things that the player can do in their level.
So, on the theme side, we have narrative and presentation, which kind of go hand in hand.
But they both contribute to giving the player a context for the world and a context for
your puzzles and what they can do in it.
A strong narrative in a puzzle gives a player a scaffold into which they can kind of find
relationships between different things, different information that they've learned, things in
the world that they see.
And it disguises the design.
You're not throwing a Rubik's Cube in their face
and saying, solve it.
You're disguising it in some way.
It turns pressing some buttons, Simon Says style,
into a thing I did in the game,
a story I can tell about what I achieved while I was playing.
So I want to focus on verbs.
I thought long and hard, because in level design,
you kind of have these two camps of types of player verbs.
So I wanted to find those and talk about how they differ.
So I have two games up here, Legend of Zelda Wind Waker
and Sam and Max Hit the Road, which
are two very different games.
I had a hard time defining these verbs, but I kind of landed on homogeneous verbs, systems-based
verbs, and then heterogeneous verbs, context-based verbs.
So you have homogenous verbs with this grounding and systemic actions that the player does just while playing the game.
When you're using a homogenous game verb, the action has a very specific outcome that the player can anticipate will happen.
The meat of that puzzle is figuring out how to apply the verb's specific problems, either alone or in combination.
So here we have the grappling hook from Wind Waker.
You can always target a horizontal pole, like the one up there.
and it will have link shoot a grappling hook and create a rope bridge or a rope swing rather
to swing across gaps.
And then that gets expanded upon.
You later see additional horizontal pulls.
And while they still, you can still count on them
to create rope swings, they also might do things
like pull switches.
The rope swings might be in large,
they might create larger gaps.
There might be more challenging things around them.
But the player can always count on,
if I target.
a horizontal pole with my grappling hook, I'm probably going to create a rope and I'm
probably going to be able to swing across some kind of gap in some way.
And then with heterogeneous verbs, this mostly applies to your classic adventure game. The
player's verbs are usually examine, get more information on a thing, or use a thing on
another thing. So in this example we have Sam and Max and
Max is the rabbit, if anyone doesn't know that.
So the player plays as Sam.
And in Sam and Max, in general, Max likes violence.
Max likes to do bad things.
He likes to do violent things.
So if the player needs to do something violent, they know
they can use Max on that thing.
So in our top puzzle, there's a cat here who has a piece of
paper you need.
And you use Max on the cat to pull the
paper out of his stomach.
And then on this bottom puzzle, there's this tunnel of love that you're trying to stop
so that you can get out and kind of go in the secret door.
So once you find the fuse box with the flashlight, you can take Max and use him on the fuse box.
And Sam actually dunks him in the water and uses him to short out the fuse box.
So those are two really different things. Using max isn't really predictable. You have a theme.
Your theme is telling you, oh, thematically I use max. He's going to do something violent. But it's
not something systemic that I can count on. It's always very special case, very
per situation and that gives it a lot of flexibility.
Sam and Max is based on this comic book,
so when you play the Sam and Max games,
you feel like you're just playing the comic book.
Dunking Max in the water and shorting out a circuit
is a story beat, you know, it's something they can do.
But yeah, the importance, you know, not either verb you have,
whatever type of verb you have, it's that consistency that's
important.
But whether it comes from systems
or whether it comes from narrative,
just keeping a consistent world for your player,
something that they can hook onto so
they understand how your world works is what's important.
Now I want to dive into difficulty.
So difficulty is kind of the secret element of puzzles.
And it's kind of that special sauce that really gets us that
feeling of the player feeling trusted by the designer, but
then also being challenged by the designer.
So to get to the appropriate challenge you want to give the
player, we should understand the elements of your puzzle
that can be manipulated to make the puzzle's difficulty
level appropriate to them.
It's the absolute hardest thing to get right in puzzles.
Hands down.
Getting that balance is always difficult.
And we'll go into that a little bit later in the talk when we start more about building
and troubleshooting puzzles.
And one more thing.
I'm going to illustrate.
I have three steps for difficulty I want to talk about.
They're witness spoilers.
So if you haven't played the witness or don't want to be spoiled, turn around.
So, the first aspect of a puzzle that you can tweak to make a puzzle easier or harder
is how many steps it takes to solve the puzzle.
Or in games where the puzzle's state of being solved isn't super explicit, it's the amount
of steps and amount of time that passes before the player receives feedback, either positive
or negative, about how they've interacted with the puzzle.
So the tutorial pains in the witness are a great example of this. They feel they feel much easier because
You're being guided through each step of a puzzle
You're getting feedback every time you learn even a nuanced new concept of the puzzle that you're trying to solve and they get progressively
harder because they add complications
But they aren't overwhelming because you've been led into them very gradually
in succession
And then you have something else this puzzle on the top
you know, it's kind of a clue, but you have no immediate application to it.
You don't really, you can't look around and understand what this clue means.
So inherently that puzzle is going to be a little harder for the player,
because, you know, even though the solution is very explicit,
you know, it's very obviously a puzzle that you're solving,
the player still has to kind of keep that in their mind,
they have to travel to that destination,
they have to find where it's applied to,
and then know that the solution they have is in their brain
and they can apply it to that.
that gap of time, those different steps really add to the difficulty of a puzzle.
So the next kind of dial you have for puzzle difficulty is revealing new mechanics or
revealing new information. So the first panel here on the left, that's the first puzzle,
The Witness. All it's teaching you is you can draw something from the start
and to the end, and that's all it's teaching you.
And the middle puzzle complicates it a little bit.
It says, hey, you can make wrong turns sometimes.
If you go to a dead end, you haven't completed the puzzle.
It also teaches you things like you can't loop around.
The path cannot touch itself.
And then the last puzzle takes all of that
and applies it to another mechanic.
It adds a new mechanic of these colored dots.
And the player has to discover how
to deal with those different dots and learn what they mean.
And then our third dial is kind of related.
It's new applications of those mechanics or information.
So same mechanics, same info, but you're kind of applying it
in a different way or finding it in a different way
than you're used to.
So in this example.
Up till now, most of the puzzles that you've been solving have been, the solutions have been on the panels themselves.
But in this example, the solution to the panel is not on the panel, it's above you.
So you have to kind of, the player has to make a mental leap to go,
oh I need to find information outside of this panel and look at this tree,
and make that connection and understand,
okay, I can now get information about panels from outside.
So we have, oh, so witness spoilers are done if anyone was hiding.
So our difficulty dials, steps to solve, new mechanics information, new applications of
mechanics, that's half of the puzzle.
Well, the puzzle, no pun intended.
So you're not going to find the appropriate level of difficulty just using these.
You can't do that in a vacuum.
You have two forces acting on your designs that are going to influence the difficulty
as well.
difficulty considerations.
So you have your intended audience who's playing your game and
where your puzzle is in your game, in your level, in your game.
You need to consider where the puzzle is going to be experienced and how.
When it comes to your audience, you're always really asking yourself,
why am I making this game and why are there puzzles in this game?
You might be making a more narrative-focused game,
and you don't want the puzzles to be too hard, you don't want the player stuck,
you don't want... and you want many players to be able to play this game and be very...
you want the game to be very accessible to them.
So you might have a difficulty that's a little lower
than you might want, or think that you would.
And then, but if then your game is more challenge focused, if your game, if the point of your
game is to challenge, if it is to do gameplay, if it's for an audience that you know wants
that challenge, wants to solve puzzles, then yeah, your difficulty is going to go a little
bit higher.
And then for progression, we're going to break out into rational puzzle design.
And what rational puzzle design, or well, rational design in general, is introducing
concepts in an orderly fashion and preserving your macro flow.
What does that mean?
Macro flow sounds like a rap name.
And what that means really is just looking at your game from top to bottom.
It means understanding everything that you're making for your game.
Where does it go in your game?
And when does the player experience it?
Or when can they experience it?
So it's really taking your game.
breaking it out into a piece of your game, finding the level it's in,
then finding your puzzle. This is our portal puzzle. We know it's in
the game of Portal, it's in Act 1, it's midway through Act 1,
it's midway through the level, and here's the steps to do the puzzle.
So I'm going to do a pretty deep dive onto,
with using the portal puzzle as a case study,
just kind of go into a deep dive of how
you can kind of break a puzzle, or find a puzzle,
where a puzzle lives in your rational level design
and apply difficulty to that.
This can be applied to any game.
Starting from your story,
starting from your big picture view of your game
is usually the best way to make puzzles
or find how to build your puzzle.
and it always gives you a roadmap. You'll always be able to go back to this flow and remember
why is this puzzle here again? What is it achieving? What is it teaching?
So this this roadmap is a really great thing to think about. So start with your story.
I know these are narrative beats. They're not gameplay beats. These are narrative beats. It's
Chell performing tests.
Chell escaping the facility, Chell fighting GLaDOS.
And we've applied it to kind of our Freytag pyramid,
which isn't the perfect narrative structure,
but it works to show kind of that increase in action
and that increase in tension.
So we can kind of turn that into acts.
We have our three acts of what our game, our gameplay kind of falls onto.
And we can map difficulty on that.
You know, you expect when you're exposing things, when you're starting the game off,
it's going to be easier, a little bit medium difficulty, and difficulty goes up from there.
and then we have our levels. Now, of course, Portal knows how
many levels it has because it's a game that came out. But as you
develop a game, you're going to be able to kind of figure out
how much you need, how many levels you need or how many
pieces you need to get the player up to speed with where
they have to be. Like, obviously at the end of Act 1, the player
is pretty competent at using the Portal gun. They know how to do
it. They can think with portals. So it takes 20 test chambers to
do that in this game. You know, your game might be different.
But it's good to kind of map, like, OK, how long am I taking
on that?
So now we can kind of see, this is a breakout of all those levels I just showed, but this
is them on a graph organized by steps to complete.
And remember, steps to complete is one of our difficulty dials.
So although there's a ton of levels in Act 1, note how small they are.
Note how few steps they take.
And that's because they're just kind of trying to get them out and teach concepts quickly
and cleanly.
They're not difficult puzzles. They're really there to help teach the player,
this is how you shoot a gun. This is how you walk through a portal.
This is where a portal goes when you shoot a gun.
And if you see, it kind of has the same shape as our Free Talk Pyramid.
It kind of has that gradual rise, a slight decline.
And on a more detailed level, you see this pattern repeated.
You see a lot of crests that suddenly drop,
and then gradual crests that suddenly drop
over and over again.
And this is kind of, these dips are usually employed
after a long or a particularly difficult puzzle.
And again, this is only steps, so there are levels in here.
There were a lot of new concepts are being taught as well,
adding difficulty.
So.
these, what I like to call breather puzzles, these kind of dips, are there more to kind of bolster the
player's confidence, really show them like, hey, you solved that thing, you did it, you found
insight you need to beat a thing, and then really just like reinforcing that. Usually it's a
repetition of beats or just a simpler version of something they've done already.
So back to our story progression graph.
Let's dig into those new mechanics and new application dials just for a second.
So again at the end of Act 1 you have a pretty comprehensive understanding of how to use
portals.
And we can see that, you know, flinging is a pretty advanced technique.
I think that's the first time in portal a lot of people go, whoa, now I'm thinking with
portals.
So there's...
A lot of concepts that have to go into that.
Specifically, firing a blue portal and understanding that you can't fire portals into walls.
Remember, those are both elements of that puzzle that we explored.
So those concepts are taught much earlier than Chamber 10.
Chamber 2 and 7 respectively teach those mechanics.
And they don't just teach them like right before our puzzle,
our really complicated, we're going to teach you how to use
momentum puzzle, they teach them very early and they let the
player get really used to them. So they almost take them for
granted by the time that they get to this new challenge of
fleeing themselves across a gap. So the flinging puzzle from the
beginning of the talk is actually the second of three. It
kind of sits, it's nestled in the middle of chamber 10.
So the first puzzle that's in that chamber is actually a simple puzzle.
You can't get to the door because the floor is too high.
So you solve it like you've been solving every other puzzle
in the earlier part of Portal, which is firing a blue portal
and going through it.
Easy.
And then of course you do our flinging puzzle where you learn how to fling.
And then you get this third puzzle,
which is much harder, or it appears much harder. You see the gap, the gap is
larger.
You still can't put any portals anywhere.
And this time, your orange portal is on the floor.
So you're actually challenged, based
on what you learned from where the portal was
placed in the previous level, you're
learning where to put your blue portal to get the same effect.
So the game gave you an example of how to do something,
and now they're having you apply that to the level itself.
And you can get to the exit.
So here's.
Here's what the puzzles look like in the context of their level with their steps.
And again on top we have kind of where this lives in our game.
So we know exactly where this lives in our game.
So as someone who's analyzing this puzzle, they have a really good idea of how difficult it needs to be
and what needs to be taught there.
So here we have, you know, obviously the steps of the puzzle.
The blue, or sorry, the purple, the purple boxes designate a step that's
new to the player. So having to find a wall
is an escalation from puzzle one.
Placing the portal on the top rather than on the floor
is a new concept the player is learning.
So we can see, like, even through our level, there's been these steps added, there's been
new applications of mechanics added to challenge the player more as they go through the level.
And what's interesting about level three also is that if you notice the first three steps
and the last three steps in puzzle three are the same, they're actually the same.
steps. It's fall through a hole, shoot a thing on the portal, fall through a hole, shoot a thing on
the portal. And it's not because it's boring. It's because they're teaching the player how to do what
they did again. They're giving them confidence. It's those breather puzzles I talked about earlier.
That subsection of puzzle three is really just, hey, you figured it out. You figured out how to
put a portal here and you got here. Now do it again. You got it. It's just bolstering confidence.
So mapping this stuff on Portal is really easy to understand
because Portal is very linear.
You can kind of plan for what the player is going to do.
All players are going to have kind of the same experience
through your game.
But it's important to understand you can also apply this to nonlinear games like Braid.
And what's great about how Braid does this and The Witness does it too,
is that the only thing that's gaining the player is their own understanding
of a gameplay mechanic or technique, and not the game.
The game's never telling them they can't try something.
It's always telling them, please try this, please explore this,
and find the solution yourself.
And they do this really well in World 2 of The Hunt.
you kind of just jump on, you jump on enemies to kill them and
it opens the door and it's just basic platforming skills. But
then in world four, it's the same exact set up, but you have
an added mechanic. And if you haven't quite figured out how to
kill enemies with this mechanic added, there's like a
and like rewinds time and brings them back if you jump on them wrong.
So if you haven't mastered that, the game says, okay, continue on.
You can still complete the game.
You just can't have a like full completion of the game,
but you can still move on and continue other puzzles.
It never says, you're stuck here.
Finish this puzzle the way your mom says to finish your broccoli.
But linear or not, it's critical to have a firm grasp on when
that player, on what the puzzle that your player is going
to experience, finding when it's going to be encountered
or when it might be encountered, just so you can
ensure that that challenge is correct.
Because again, you want that thing that's challenging, but
still solvable.
You need arithmetic before you teach algebra.
You need to have a progression in what you're
teaching your players.
So now we're going to go into kind of a step-by-step of building a puzzle.
So now we have our elements and we're going to apply them to building a puzzle.
So the most important thing is knowing the player's goal, because
if you don't know the player's goal, then they won't.
I can guarantee you. So remember that, you know, it's always about at the heart of a
puzzle, it's getting a key into a lock. It's finding that.
message that. Make sure you're messaging what is your key,
what is your lock and message the steps to whatever that goal
is. So a lot of homogenous groups that we talked about
earlier, they'll use specific props and messages in their
levels. They'll repeat props. You know, Zelda has the very
classic like broken rock that says, hey, this can be, a bomb
can go on this. There's a lot of cracks in this rock. Blow it
up.
So it's easy to kind of just place it on your level.
Of course, it's important to understand what a prop does and where it goes.
There's a lot of, you know, it's easy to find a broken rock in a Zelda environment because
it's a fantasy environment.
You're in a lot of nature.
It fits really well.
So...
You'll see them get a little more creative with things that don't quite fit in nature, like the horizontal poles from the grappling hook example.
They'll often modify that horizontal pole to look different depending on the temple you're in.
They'll consistently keep this kind of shape on there. It's like the yellow shape on the pole.
but they'll use ways to modify that to make it fit better in the environment.
So it's this kind of struggle to make a prop that is very clear to the player,
you understand exactly what you do when you interact with this prop,
and also make it fit in your world because you don't want it just sticking out like a sore thumb.
And in adventure games, this is even more critical because often you are trying to build
a world, you're trying to tell the story, and you don't want a bunch of repeated props.
You want a bunch of repeated broken rocks just scattered around your game telling you
to solve a puzzle.
You want a very cohesive world that looks like the world you're trying to build.
So in our Sam and Max examples.
all the things that you interact with in Sam Max are very obviously interactable.
Especially your fuse box. It has these lightning bolts coming out of it. It's bright. It just
begs to be looked at. You also do this in cameras. And so, you can
In Walking Dead, again, we wanted to keep the world consistent. We didn't want to just kind of have big arrows pointing at stuff to use it.
We wanted to make sure that the player was just kind of very subtly guided to things.
So, these are a few screenshots from a puzzle in Walking Dead Episode 3.
And the story we wanted to tell was that someone is stealing drugs from your survival group.
They've left this broken flashlight.
please figure out how they're doing this.
And so the narrative was, you find these broken shards,
and then around the corner, you see this X on the wall.
It's this signal that whoever this perpetrator is
has been messaging to somebody that they're
taking the things from your survival camp
and giving them away.
But we wanted to make sure that you saw them in that order because if you just kind of
found the pink X without any information or context, you're probably just going to look
at it and go, okay, well, that's weird. Neat. Okay. So we wanted to make sure it was tied
to our broken flashlight, tied to our perpetrator. So ‑‑
We made sure that you have to look at the broken glass first
before you even see the broken X, or the chalk X rather.
So the bottom screenshots here, they're actually the
navigation cameras we had in the level.
And the X is on this wall, the wall that's
the facing screen left.
So you can actually see the X. We actually hide it from the
player completely with our cameras to make sure that
they're more enticed, more willing to click
on the broken glass.
So when they do, we actually played a cinematic and that revealed the X.
It actually showed Lee, the main character, himself, like making a mental connection between,
okay, I just found the pieces of this flashlight, and now I'm finding this really suspicious
mark.
So it kind of preps the player with the narrative to say, hey, you should be thinking about
these two objects together.
These two objects you just found have a relationship.
And we build that kind of with this narrative.
We also build up the cameras.
Every camera in that scene is moving up and to the left.
Every single one.
And that's because we know when you go back to navigation camera on the bottom left here,
we want you to go there.
Like now go into that corner, go look at that wall, and continue to move that way.
And so we're always pushing the player, hey, make a connection between these two things
because there's a narrative there and it's part of the puzzle.
If you don't highlight what you want your player to click on,
you get something like this, which is a very classic adventure game pitfall
called pixel hunting.
This is a puzzle in Indiana Jones and the Last Crusade
where you have to find a book on a shelf.
and you have no clues of what that book looks like, you literally have to just click on
the books or hover your cursor over the books until something happens.
And at best, this is very frustrating.
Your player is just brute force clicking around.
They're not thinking about the connections between the objects that they're looking at.
They're just kind of clicking mindlessly.
At worst, your player doesn't see that this is a puzzle at all and skips it.
So it's only important to message your clues, but also
message your puzzle in general.
So props aren't the only way, of course, to
message your puzzles.
And I'm going to go back to braid, because braid also uses
patterns a lot.
There was a pattern in the hunt example that we had
earlier that you understand.
OK, I know how to solve this.
I have a new mechanic in play now, but I still know what the
ultimate solution is.
to this section.
And this is another example on braid
where there's two platforms kind of moving
and there's this one piece of geometry
that's moving vertically
and it's stopping the horizontal platform,
but the horizontal platform's needed to get across
a bunch of horrible, fiery spikes.
So in the first level, it's really just about letting that happen.
It's about letting that platform move over that danger and using it to get across the
gap.
But then in world, this is four or five, the ring level, suddenly the vertical platform
is moving a lot faster.
And so you're like, okay, I've seen this before, I understand that there's this platform has
to go above this vertical platform.
do I do that? This one is moving much faster. Luckily you have a mechanic that slows things
down when it's near it. So the player is kind of building this relationship. They're very
gradually building a relationship of these things together.
I also want to talk really briefly about chunking, which is a psychological process of taking
information, chunking it, and putting it into larger units.
Something that was a big touchstone at Telltale was we never put more than around five things
that were part of a puzzle on screen ever.
And it's because humans can only hold so much information.
We really want them to make those relationships
between the clues they're finding.
So we don't want to just dump a bunch of things on them
and have them find them.
Because that's just as bad as clicking
a bunch of random books.
Clicking a bunch of stuff just to click on it
is just as mindless of a task.
So we want players to be very thoughtful
and think about what is next to each other
and what they're seeing in a sequence.
What's grouped together.
So it's important.
So our next big bullet point for when you build a puzzle,
you have your goal, you've messaged your goal,
you've created your challenge.
The next important thing is giving the player feedback.
You need to let the player know how they're doing
as they play your puzzle.
And you can do that by rewarding and encouraging your player
when they're on the right track.
And you can also do that by communicating to the player
when they've hit a dead end.
These are both very important things.
So it can be really difficult for a player to know when or when not is a valid option to interact with something.
Especially in adventure games, you'll often get the, I can't use these things together.
And it's not great. It means, okay, we didn't have the scope to give you an interaction with this.
But it's still feedback. It's still telling you.
hey, you're on the wrong track. You know, this is like a dart
board full of axes and knives and you're like, oh, obviously
Max should do something with that. He's super violent. But
it's not. So the name just says like, hey, no, sorry. But it's
important. Otherwise the player might just kind of go down a
rabbit hole. No pun intended.
And then in Walking Dead, we actually solve this by kind of
actually restricting the amount of verbs a player could even
use. You know, Lee has a whole inventory. He has, you know,
there's two items in his inventory right now. He
normally can look at stuff. But when he's using a zombie, he
only can shoot it.
and that makes sense because if you saw a zombie and you had a gun, that's probably what you're going to do.
You know, it's a lot of content and a lot of time and a lot of steps that a player has to go through
to kind of look at a full verb option wheel and go, what if I look at the zombie?
What if I use my clipboard on the zombie?
You know, it's a lot faster and it's a lot more meaningful in the moment to just say,
you probably want to shoot the zombie. Lee's pretty afraid right now of the zombie.
Then when you find out the zombie is dead, we give you back your verbs like examine,
look at, because they're relevant again.
I've gone from action mode from I'm scared of something to okay, now it's time to figure
out what's happening.
It's time for me to sit and think and look at the scene and understand what's happening
here.
Another important thing to remember when building a puzzle is to be kind.
Just be kind to your player.
It's a contract of challenging them, but then not making things impossible.
Repetition isn't fun.
Making a player replay something over and over again because they failed isn't fun.
and checking your skill checks. And what I mean by that is, you know, if you have a verb-based,
a more systemic verb-based game, you have a lot of physics in your game, the players
challenged to move through it, that's good, but make sure that those skill checks are informed.
Make sure they're not making the player repeat a lot of things. I was just talking to a friend of
mine. There's this Forsaken Fortress in Wind Waker.
And I hated it. I stopped playing Wind Waker. I didn't play Wind Waker for a long time
because I played this level and it has a ton of skill checks where you can fall. And when you
fall, you have to repeat the entire level over again. And to be clear, I love Wind Waker. Zelda's
great. Thumbs up. But man, that killed it. Like, and think of how good Wind Waker is, but just
having to repeat those puzzles over and over again.
They're puzzles, so you have a dominant solution, you found a
dominant strategy, you know what you're doing. If you know what
you're doing but you can't execute it, it's extremely
frustrating. And to go back to Portal again, they do a great
job with this because whenever you fail in Portal, they either
put you back very close to where you failed, so you're kind of
learning, okay, this is the last place I was before I screwed
everything up. I can now think about that.
So the deaths in Portal or the failures in Portal are also teaching the player,
hey, you were right up to this point.
So try again.
What you did was wrong, and now try a different solution.
The last thing when building a puzzle is integrate your story into your puzzle.
And that's why it's so important to have that macro chart, that progression flow of your
game, because when you have your story mapped out and you'll understand where your story
is in your puzzle, where it is in your game, you can always go there for inspiration.
The picture on the left here is from a game called Quadrilateral Cowboy where you're actually hacking.
And when you're hacking in Quadrilateral Cowboy, you're moving through a level.
You're actually getting like take your laptop out and hack and like open a door.
And it's very integrated in the game. It's a part of the story.
You feel like you're this secret agent hacker who's opening things.
Whereas in Bioshock, you're just playing Pipe Dream.
If you played Bioshock, it's not about playing Pipe Dream.
So the hacking puzzles in that game are a lot weaker because they're not integrated in the story.
There's kind of this weird mini-game that happens.
So always look at your story.
And then remember the golden rule.
Always be kind to your players.
Let them, give them a challenge, but give them the materials they need to complete that challenge.
If you ever watch Sherlock Holmes, it always cracks me up when people...
say, oh, you can follow along Sherlock Holmes and solve the
crimes with him, because you can't. He has a ton of information that you don't have.
He's just saying, well, didn't you notice that his hand has four calces on it?
He's a tennis player and the specific shoe print we found is a
Nike tennis boot. This is information you didn't have.
And so, you know, when you make your players feel like Watson, just kind of
staring at Sherlock, it doesn't feel good.
So remember, puzzles are fun for the player, not the designer.
Don't get super excited about feeling clever.
Just make a good experience.
So lastly, I want to talk about troubleshooting, because as I said, you know, difficulty among
other things, it's really difficult to get right.
You know, even with all these tips, it's going to take a lot of iteration, a lot of considerations
to get your puzzle to feel good and do exactly what you want it to do.
And you do that with user testing.
And you do that as much as you can.
Seriously, you do it as much as you can.
There's no excuse for not getting user testing.
It's so important to capture as much of your tester's
thinking process as possible, because that's going to really
tell you if your difficulty levels are appropriate or not.
There was a great postmortem for Myst in GDC 2013 that I definitely recommend checking
out because Robin Miller was talking about how even before Myst was a game, even before
they were able to throw it on a hyper card stack and make it a thing, they were doing
it D&D style.
They would actually describe to the player, this is what you see.
can you solve this? And as you know, Myst is very open and it
is allowed to be that way because they did so much testing
with here is literally as open we can get. Here is a D&D role
playing game. Can you solve this puzzle?
And then later in their testing process when they did have something implemented, they
actually would always test with two people.
They'd usually test with couples.
And that was because they liked to talk to each other.
So, you know, obviously puzzle games are very heady.
We get in our own heads when we're solving them.
But when we're solving with another person, we're talking a lot more about what we're
thinking and about our thought processes.
And it's a really great way to see what a player is thinking
and having them argue for a solution is going to give you a
lot more information than them just kind of staring at the
screen and blinking a lot.
Oh, I missed that.
Oh, but yeah, so always know where your players get stuck.
And then, yeah, look at this.
Next is coming a self-check to examine
why they're getting stuck.
So if your player says, that was too easy, which is very
rare, but you'll get it.
did you give them a chance to solve it themselves? Did you
just feed them the answer? And if they think it's too easy,
maybe you already taught that concept before. Maybe that
mechanic was already really effectively tutorialized and
you're kind of getting repetitious. So look back at
your chart and say, okay, maybe I don't need as much
tutorialization as I thought.
They may also mean that it was just lock and key.
It was very obvious.
There weren't enough steps between your lock and your key
to find those things.
There weren't enough variations in your verbs and applications.
If you guys ever played Pokemon, they have the cut mechanic.
And at first, you're like, oh, I can't break these bushes.
I have to cut down these bushes.
How do I do that?
You learn cut, and you can cut down bushes.
That's all you can ever do.
It never escalates to that.
It's always just, there's no thinking anymore.
It's just like, OK.
taking my rat-a-tat and like another bush down okay it's not thinking it's just
lock and key it never evolves past that door so too hard which is a lot more
common you'll get a lot more too hards and just ask yourself like was it did I
give information to solve this puzzle how long ago did I give that information
ago because it might just be not relevant to the player anymore and can
they get back to it like is it lost forever can they reference that
information again
And then of course, is the goal clear to the player?
And this is looking at your level layout, looking at your visuals, making sure your
path is clear, all the stuff that a level designer does when just making things obvious
goals.
And then check your dials.
Are there too many steps in your puzzle?
This is very, very common.
I see this all the time.
People just put too many steps in their puzzles because, again, it feels clever, or they've
been playing their own game like a thousand times, and they're like, well, obviously,
you know, these hundred steps, this horrible Rube Goldberg machine equates to this puzzle
being solved.
But on first blush, a lot of players aren't going to get that.
And again, check your mechanics, are you teaching them well?
Are you changing the context of a mechanic?
And this is what I was talking about with consistency.
It's great to make new applications of mechanics,
it's great to change them.
But if that new way is unintuitive
or hasn't been tutorialized, the player's
going to have a hard time with it.
So your golden rules.
take a picture of this when it's done. It's going to come in as
bullets. A good puzzle challenges the player without
hand holding or being unfair. Fun for the player, not the
designer. Don't be Sherlock Holmes.
Puzzles combine a game's theme and mechanics and rely on the consistency of each to make sense.
You know, consistency is your friend in puzzles.
And look at your puzzle in the context of the game as a whole to judge its difficulty.
It's the best way to figure out if your puzzle is doing what it needs.
Oh, there's one more!
Watch others play your puzzle and check for assumptions you may have made.
You know, we're all different human beings, we're all different people, we're from different cultures.
We all think differently and that's the fun of puzzle design is you really get to watch people think
and watch people work through problems and learn new things.
And that's my talk.
This talk was really two hours long, so I encourage you guys to also take a picture of this slide and just check out some of these really great articles.
You know, lots of rational level design stuff, some great GDC talks from past years, all good stuff.
And then, I think, how much time we got? We're in five?
Yeah, I'll take like a couple questions.
Yeah, if anyone has questions, feel free to come up to the mics over there.
And thank you, everybody.
I'd like to hear thoughts on dynamic difficulty from the point of view of, I'm sure everybody
in this room has hit a puzzle and literally walked away from the games, and I mean I've
done this many times, but there's kind of like two ways.
Some games do kind of like, you know, the voice comes on and gives you a hint, but some
games do it too early.
There's ones where you're walking through and you're thinking, okay, I'm just going
to, and they'll go, oh, look at this, and it's a bit too much of a giveaway, but I mean
from the point of view of.
Are we able yet really to have a puzzle and you try something and it doesn't work?
And you try something else it doesn't work and not just to give away a hint or there's the key but to
dynamically change the puzzle because it's like you've detected that the person's tried five things and it hasn't worked and
We we don't want them to give up. We want them to keep playing
Yeah, so a lot of games have tried this. You know, to hint systems, I think some hint systems are
garbage. Some hint systems are just really bad because they do just tell you go, there's the
key, go do it, what are you doing, you idiot. And yeah, that's always bad because it's still that
same problem of I'm still not letting the player solve it themselves. It's the designer kind of
giving up on you. It's your teacher just saying just copy my answers, just go. It's that same
feeling. So.
I think there are good hint systems up there. Actually,
mist had a really good hint system. Not mist, mist uru, the
third one. It was really because they wrote them well. They were
very careful in their language. They were careful in how they
gave them. Eventually they got pretty on the nose. But there
were a lot of them. Granted, that's a lot of content. But
there was a lot to give them. I've also seen diamond. So
What you're describing I think of a dynamic puzzle changing. I've also seen that in Silent Hill, I think had that.
And the problem I see with that is that you're suddenly, what Silent Hill did was they had easy, medium, hard.
And when you played that game on those different difficulties, the puzzles actually changed.
And they used the dials we talked about, like often the hard puzzles.
had more steps or more connections you had to make.
But it's a lot of content because they literally
made three puzzles for every one puzzle.
So I think that's a big barrier,
is just that amount of content you have to make,
you're suddenly tripling your scope.
Because there is, you know, puzzles are so tightly interwoven, it's tough to kind of get, it's tough to just kind of take away or put in steps to add difficulty.
So...
So you think it's too much of a design, it would just be too much of a challenge for the creation of the game?
I think it's a great challenge to try. I think it's a good design challenge.
I think the scope is where you're going to run into trouble. But, maybe I've got a ton of money.
Thank you.
We have one more I think we have two minutes left in this session unless we want to break out to a panel
Hi, I'd like to hear your thoughts on like
How it can be hard to teach somebody something during an intense moment like how it's probably easier when they're things are very calm
and you have your own, but if you're like
doing an FPS or
More action a game like how to teach the player
Even though he's in an intense or she is in an intense moment like if there's an action a lot of action going on
Any advice on how to teach players to things if it's supposed to be high intensity game
How do you teach players or have puzzles in there?
Well, I think even in a high intensity game, you are going to have points of low intensity.
Like if your game is only high tension, it's just going to feel like you're getting hit
all the time and you're just going to become numb.
So there is definitely finding those points of low intensity and using those just to like
kind of bolster the player to teach them those basics.
It's great when you can say, hey, you learned some basics.
Now you're in a more tense moment. You're you know difficulties added through a time a timing element or something like that
but
Yeah, I think it's more just like making sure the player again has that tool set they need.
They have that knowledge in there.
And then when they're confronted with this stressful situation,
you can ask them to do something like that.
You can ask them to test what they know or challenge themselves in some way.
But I think it's really just, that's how much more work you're going to have to do
to really scaffold their knowledge and their skills.
Does that answer your question?
So you generally just try to avoid teaching players too much
new stuff during the tough moments,
and then just have them apply that knowledge
in a different way, rather.
Yeah, I think so.
Because your action, that's a new setting.
I suddenly have a lot more things to think about.
So that's all new information, new stuff
that's adding to the difficulty.
So there's not really much more you need to do from there.
You're already giving them something
stressful to deal with.
OK, thanks.