Hey everybody. Oh, I guess I have my own mic. Perfect. Well, we're going to jump in there.
So here we are, like at GDC, right? It's a week about talking about our favorite games.
But just for like a very quick moment, I want to stop talking about games and instead talk
about people, right? Because society has this nasty habit of celebrating the final product
instead of the people and their journeys to actually make that final game or that final
product, right?
So hopefully you've noticed this recent trend, especially in the game scene, where no matter
what kind of team you're on, no matter what size your team is, no matter who you are,
people are starting to really prioritize the communities that they surround themselves in.
And today we'll be talking basically on how to build a
co-working space, right? After our own bumpy road, and with the
hope to both warn you, but also inspire you. So most of these
lessons come from GameNest. GameNest is an independent,
inclusive co-working space just for indie game developers,
right? It's a place for...
It's a place for experienced indies, for motivated students, all different kinds of developers,
and again it's those folks who want to surround themselves with people who really understand
the challenges of making a game and what that process is like.
It's a co-working space, which means it's pretty much like a shared office.
People bring in their computers, they rent desks, we have a lot of events like an internal
feedback Friday or maybe large monthly parties.
It's also important to give context for what GameRest is not.
So it's not sponsored by any...
Also being in San Francisco, it is more focused just for indie
game developers. So it's not just a general tech co-working
space or incubator or anything like that. It's a co-working
space for indies and indie game development.
So for a brief history, we started planning this all in
October 2014.
We opened our days on the very first day of January 2015.
And then the people crazy enough to try this was yours
truly.
My name's Dylan Jones on the bottom.
That's Jannevin Nordhangen, Jim Fleming, and?
Hey, everybody.
I'm Danielle Swank.
So.
Co-working. There's pretty much five basic steps to starting and running your own co-working space.
And the first thing, and probably the most important thing, is your people.
You really, really have to find a group, because co-working exists in a group.
So, you know, there's this...
Gameness started kind of officially as an idea back in IndieCade at 2014.
And I was in the audience just like you.
And I was listening to this person from Glitch City talk about their space
and what they were doing together, and I'm like,
oh my goodness, this is the most amazing thing ever.
I want to go and I want to do this.
And these are all my friends and this is them down in LA.
Well, not all of my friends, but you know.
And I got them all together and we all got drunk and we stayed up really late planning
what this space might look like.
And I woke up in the morning and I realized I was actually serious about it.
So I got on Craigslist, looked up a couple of spaces, and I sent out an email.
And the next day, Dylan was back in SF looking at spaces.
It was really amazing.
GameDesk isn't just here and isn't just these people.
It wouldn't exist without a larger community.
And so for us, that means meetup groups.
So for the past couple years,
both Dylan and I have been running different meetup groups.
Dylan runs one focused on indie developers.
It has about a thousand members.
I run one focused on learning how to make games
that has about 800.
And you really, really want to start with this kind of core group of people in order
to round out your space.
Because the one thing that you don't want to do is open the doors January 1st and there
be nobody in the space and all empty desks.
So that's great.
So you have a bunch of people.
What do you do next, Dylan?
Well, you've got to find the spot to put them where they all are, right?
So you've got to find that home base.
And that's that second step in this process, right?
And as always, when you're starting something new,
you're going to be filled with a long list of questions.
And that's okay, right?
That's fine. Don't be afraid to just ask.
That's what we did.
Literally, sometimes we had friends,
sometimes we would just cold call or email people, right?
And, you know, if you're thinking of doing that,
Or if you're thinking of building a space like this, just shoot us a note.
Shoot other people a note. This is the game industry.
It's filled with a bunch of awesome people that want to help out.
We talked to folks down at Glitch City who told us to go a little bit bigger.
Robin Hunneke over at Phenomena was kind enough to give us some great San Francisco real estate advice.
I used to work out of a closet with some other indies at Double Fine, and they gave us some good culture tips.
Again, so the moral of this slide is...
Just ask. In addition, know where you can compromise. This is always a big one, but consider public
transportation so it's easy for folks just to swing by your space. Consider if your building
is ADA approved and can you do anything to make it more ADA.
How many square feet do you need?
Keep in mind that when you're talking about square feet,
there's a Goldilocks there.
So you might want a big, massive space for events
to house all your friends in there.
But you don't want it to feel empty on the day-to-day
when people are actually working there.
So where is your sweet spot?
And that'll change.
Does the layout allow you to have enough members to pay your
actual bills? And if that's the case, how many bathrooms do you
need? All those bizarre little questions like that. And since
for us it was just all out of our pocket, price was definitely
the biggest one. And please know that the cheaper something is,
the more time it will probably take you to fix it up. Like,
this is a shot, we almost moved into this funky butcher shop
here. It had like a
We fell in love with this spot on Valencia.
But if you're used to making games, you're probably not going to say, hey, we should
check the zoning laws here first.
That wasn't my first impression of it.
But when we went to the city planning department, which you should totally go to no matter what
city you're in, check your property, the city planning department, we realized we could
actually get in some trouble for building an office thing and maybe a residential zone.
But eventually, funnily enough, I found this cell phone picture
of a computer screen that was showing a Google Maps street
view of the outside of this property.
Like, that was the entire profile for this real estate
piece of property.
And I said, well, this is either like a classic Craigslist
scam, or nobody else has visited this place, and maybe
it's the only spot we could afford, and it'll be perfect
for us.
It turns out that it was the latter.
So it was a great space, though it needed a ton of work.
But I tell you this story because, I mean,
this co-working space is on the very brink of not happening
at all, right?
And if you can find, or if we can find a spot in the real
estate hell that is San Francisco, I assure you,
all of you can go out and find much cooler spots
anywhere else.
Keep in mind, though, we made those compromises that I was
talking about.
Sometimes we have a line for the bathroom, and you'll have
to make compromises, too.
Know where you want to settle on that.
Know what your criteria are.
Know what's specific to you.
Really think about this stuff.
Is it with your group, if you have some founding members
with that, do you want a grungy spot?
Do you want a cleaner spot?
How big is it?
Do you want a conference room?
Do you need a kitchen?
Again, how many bathrooms do you need?
To warn you about this process, we'll see if this
It is to show you, you can find it online, it's a little flash forward GSC video.
But it is literally us on our hands and on our knees redoing all these floors, literally
like construction work.
And thankfully Danielle knew a ton about construction.
But it still took us...
I'm going to show you how to do that.
Hopefully you can check out that video and see it.
It's a fun little video, but what it also does is it also
edits out the really hard parts. That's the nice thing about nice
little videos. It's this great little montage.
Please know, just like making a game and when you're getting into this stuff,
you can do this.
I mean, be prepared for burnout in there, right?
I don't want to be up here and hand out rose-tinted glasses.
There was some incredibly physical and also emotionally
hard work in there.
And I mean, you can get, just like a game, kind of stressed
out and emotionally burdened at times.
And be prepared for that.
Yeah.
The other thing, other than construction, the other thing that you're going to get
really familiar with when running a co-working space is spreadsheets.
It's all about numbers.
And I wanted to show this slide because what stood out to me when I was pulling pictures
for this presentation is the time step up at the top.
So that's taken at 10.51 p.m. on a Friday night, and what we're probably doing is pouring
over this document.
So this is GameNest startup costs.
We started GameNest with a budget of $24,000, which sounds like a lot of money.
Sounds like, I mean, it's a lot of money to me.
That's $6,000 from each of the four co-founders.
And what you have to know is that landlords don't necessarily like to rent to new businesses.
It's very difficult.
It's not like running an apartment where they just want first and last.
They may want first, last, three months or six months of rent going in.
So with GameNest, we had to give our landlord $16,000 just to get in the door.
That's huge, right?
So we were left with only $8,000 to do everything.
And that's getting chairs for 20 people.
That's getting desks for everybody.
That's paying all our business license fees.
That's getting a router.
And it's all the construction.
So it's painting.
It's ripping up the floors.
That $8,000 goes by so quickly.
Like boom, boom, boom, boom, boom.
Hi. And so, you know, just know that. Like when you're in the
process of doing your build out and you're spending a lot of
money, things don't, maybe don't seem like they're that big of a
deal. You just want to be careful and aware because
otherwise you'll overshoot your budget by a couple thousand
dollars. And for me, that's a lot of money. So I just, you
know, and you'll make mistakes. Like this is a receipt where we
spent $25 on a roll of tape.
You know, it happens. Try not to make it happen on a regular
basis. Or maybe things are just surprising. This is one that
surprised me. When I was in college, like, mini fridges, I
think, are about $100, right? Like, that's about how much I
paid. However, the mini fridge that we had to get for GameNest
was $400 because it had to be big enough to get everybody's
lunches but still small enough to fit under our counter and it
just had a bunch of weird requirements. And so our mini
fridge.
Cost $400.
The other thing that you're going to really, really want to
pay attention to is your local costs and your ongoing
operating costs, not just your build out.
So this slide, if you look at that up in the upper right
hand corner and that blue box that's highlighted, that's our
running cost for the year.
and we did this spreadsheet ahead of time.
And our actual running costs came out to be about within a couple thousand dollars of
that price.
That is what it takes to keep GameNest up and running.
And so, you know, that's a number.
And that number is neither good or bad, it's just something that you have to be aware of.
And then once you have a number like that, what you have to start doing...
math and matrix math. So, like, what does that mean? That means
there's going to be a sweet spot between how much I charge people
and how many people I can get in. And for us in San Francisco,
that's $350 for a full-time membership.
The other thing that you want to do is you want to look really carefully at the bottom of the spreadsheet and our projected members number.
So I said earlier that Dylan has a meetup group of a thousand people and that sounds like a lot of people, but there's a huge gulf between people who like the idea of co-working in theory and people who actually give you money to co-work with you.
And so you want to be, when you're doing the numbers, be as negative as possible.
Like, be...
mean. So like our numbers were like 16 of those will show up.
And I had the names of each of those 16 people. And I'm like
okay. And in the next month maybe I can convince another
four people to join up and then maybe another four after that.
So I would do your budget with that kind of math in mind. For
us our break even numbers are 24 full-time people in the space.
And we do that, but those are also really nice and conservative.
The other thing, too, is if you have a lot of members, the quality of the space can start
going down because it gets really noisy.
So there's a lot of balancing act that goes on.
The other thing I really want to recommend with running your space is, and helping you
with the numbers, is co-working software.
So we use Cobot, and that's a screenshot of it.
And it's wonderful because it automatically builds our members.
So we can take credit cards, which is huge.
I don't have to have a credit card account set up with a
bank or anything.
I can just take them.
Because what you don't want to do is you don't want to chase
down all your friends every month, or a check, or get in
some cash and not keep track of it.
It saves you so much time.
And I want to wrap up with the fact that indie game
development is very boom and bust.
I think everybody knows that not always, you know, checks don't come in for a publisher,
or we maybe don't make enough, or just things happen.
So we take a security deposit equal to one month's rent.
And that's important because if somebody can't make their rent
on the first of the month, what I don't want to do is kick them
out on the second. They're my friends. So we just use the
security deposit and if their checks come in, if everything
works, they can re-op, everything's fine. And if they
don't, everybody has a month to get used to the idea that the
relationship is changing. So those are the big numbers that
I'd recommend.
Yeah, absolutely. And you know, you really need these tools so that you can get back into making your game full-time, right?
Instead of organizing the space full-time. That's vital.
And, you know, the fourth step here is staying true, right? It's staying true to what you set out to build.
We encourage you to make your own pillars, like really decide what you want early on
as your small group, write them down, post them up on the wall, save them.
We came up with our pillars as being diversity, community, and great games.
So for diversity, what's the best way to make sure that you're an inclusive environment and keeping it a safe space?
Well, we have basically an application that says, hey, what kind of games have you worked on in the past?
What are you looking to get out of a co-working space?
Do you identify as any traditionally marginalized groups?
And mostly that's for us so that we can get a high level
understanding of where we sit so that we know when we need to
do further outreach and start getting the word out there more
and more. Again, if you have any ideas about this or anything
else in between, please come up and say hi. We're always
looking forward to hearing that kind of stuff. And for our
second pillar is community. And one of the ways that I reflect
on our progress that way is basically looking at a series
of
I'll scroll through some of ours but this is only to get you
excited about your own moments that you're going to have when
you open your own space. You'll have these nuggets, these little
memories that will make it all worth it. I'm a sucker for
for nostalgia. But half the reason I post pictures onto the
GameNest Twitter is so that we have like an almost scrapbook
kind of thing. And I encourage you to actually catalog your
fun, right? This is when we hosted Lost Levels. We highly
recommend events because it helps get the word out there for
new members, new potential members to join you. It also
keeps all your current members really engaged, right? It also
makes it a destination. And most importantly, it unites your
local scene, you know, your local game development scene all
under one roof.
and get involved with local ARG artists or real world games.
Help make your space like an actual destination,
if that's what you're into, right?
One of my favorite moments was when we had the racket
throw this crazy murder mystery extravaganza thing,
and I had a friend who actually found out about this event
like randomly and showed up.
And I said, whoa, what are you doing here?
And like, honestly, if that doesn't get you excited,
that's kind of like as good as it gets
when you're running a coworking space.
So, you know, maybe it's the little things, like you just want to get lunch with some
friends and talk about the latest games you've been playing.
Maybe it's being able to harbor indies from out of town and they need some internet, right?
Maybe it's having the perfect place to host your favorite game jam.
where it's a giant, giant tutorial room for teaching new
developers how to make games, right? And really, where else
are you going to find an indie video game themed Halloween,
right? Unless you make that space, that awesome may not ever
exist, right? You have to go out and build that.
And that was one of the things actually that we really learned.
It was really, you know, once you build it, it's so easy to
enable these things.
You know, really all it takes is just encouraging your members
to make their own events.
Some of the most successful events we've had are like Game
of the Fortnite, which is like imagine a book club but with a
video game, so you all play the same thing and then talk about
it.
And also these monthly giant out of the shell parties that we
have.
So these are just some posters that people make to, you know,
get the word out about the space.
And again, also we're having a party on Thursday. You're all
totally invited. Check that out online. But, you know, just out
of the shell fun parties like that. Again, that third pillar
is helping people make great games. And, of course, like that
is mostly up to the creator. But when you're in these spaces,
right, like you can actually totally help with that. So, I
mean, maybe it's pooling together for a booth at GamerX.
Maybe it's just exchanging some information or saying the latest, greatest tips on showing your game at IndieCade.
Or maybe it's all having like, at this case, like a GameNest booth.
Where people at a play-crafting event, you know, could come and be giving you feedback.
It's just easier to organize that stuff.
And you're actually helping make games get better with feedback and everything else in between, right?
And get the word out, of course.
Yeah, so, all right, great. You have this wonderful spot, you've organized a bunch of people,
you came up with all your startup costs, and you have all these great engaged members.
Next thing to do is survive. And there's a bunch of unexpected stuff, like
IKEA couches don't fit in Honda Civics. Who knew?
But on a more serious note, actually one of the big things that we deal with is security
and access to the space.
So there's a couple different ways you can approach those things.
One of the cheapest ways to do it is just to give your members keys.
That presents a lot of problems, though, in that people lose keys, people leave and they
don't return them, and all of a sudden there's a bunch of security holes.
And at GameNest, in your co-working space, you will probably be a target.
You're asking your members to leave their valuable, expensive laptops, tablets, all
the stuff that game development requires in your space, and other people will want that.
So you just have to be aware of those things.
For us, what we did is we got a 24-hour access card reader.
And that was surprisingly difficult to get.
We had to have somebody come out from a company, and it
took them about two months to come and install it, even
though we're calling them pretty much every day.
And we're like, I want to pay you money.
And they're like, eh, we don't care.
So just be aware of that.
And every time that we've been broken into, you know, we've had to do more stuff and spend
more money on security.
And the other thing that isn't necessarily surprising, but...
is maybe a little bit more of a factor than you might think, is stuff like dishes.
You know?
Like we have a cleaning service that comes in twice a week, and it pays, and it cleans
the place, it does all of our kitchen, it does the bathrooms, that's all phenomenal.
But what are those off days?
Like what happens when people like leave dishes in the sink?
You know?
Who cleans those?
It's probably going to be you.
Just saying.
So, be prepared for all that.
You know, or like random stuff that happens in construction.
This is a window that got broken in GameNest and that happened the first day that we moved
in and it took us another two months to get it fixed.
You know, just stuff is unexpected.
But it might not even be unexpected due to cost, it might be unexpected due to time.
The other thing that I didn't realize about my co-working space is that all the lights are different sizes.
And they're all different wattages.
And so I'd go to Lowe's and I'd think I'd have all the information I need to buy my stupid light bulbs.
Well, guess what? I had to go back and forth to Lowe's like five times in a day.
It took an entire day's worth of time when I'm trying to get this co-working space up and running to get light bulbs.
And as much as I love my members, sometimes people do stuff that you'd probably prefer
them not to do.
So you also have to talk through those things with them.
A good way to do that...
is we have weekly founder meetings where we all touch base with each other, we talk
about issues in the space, we get ahead of problems, we also have a slack that everybody
in our space is on.
So if things come up and things are issues, we can know about them right away because
it's better to deal with stuff proactively.
And then I guess one of the last things that was a positive surprise, there are some I swear,
was I underestimated how valuable Gameness would be as an event space.
So we've had companies, and you'll have a great bunch of indies who are excited,
and you'll probably have companies reach out to you and be like,
hey, can I host a launch party here? Can I do a developer event?
And you should say yes. That is excellent. They paid for my couch.
And you'll find your own surprises too.
And I encourage you to do so.
Definitely.
I definitely undercharge some game corporations sometimes to have fun events there.
So, most of all, it's just go for it.
When we started this, we had no idea how to run an indie game co-working space.
So ask questions.
Again, just go for it.
And seriously, if you have any questions...
Just send us a note, right? Send anybody a note.
Hit us up on Twitter, whatever is best for you.
And most of all, we're definitely looking forward to seeing all these brand new indie game coworking spaces.
So, thank you again, everybody. Seriously. Yeah, cheers.