Hi everyone, welcome to the GDC Twitch channel.
My name is Brian Francis, I am a contributing editor at GammaStory.com and I am your community
manager for the Game Developers Conference.
I am sitting here today, unfortunately not playing a game like I usually do.
We are unfortunately watching some pre-recorded footage, but the game we are checking out
is a little game called Knights and Bikes.
Knights and Bikes comes from Foam Sword Games that had a successful Kickstarter a couple
years ago.
Um, uh, principally, uh, its designers include a one, Rex, uh, I should have really figured this out beforehand, is it Crowl or Crowley?
Crowley's good, yeah.
Crowley's good?
Yeah.
The Y, not having the Y there, um, made me hesitate.
Um, Rex, how you doing? You, you worked on this game, right?
I did, yes. Yeah, I'm very good, thank you. Yeah, it's me here.
Cool, thank you. Hey everyone in Twitch chat, we're happy to have you here. Feel free to
drop your questions in Twitch chat for Rex. We are taking them.
Knights and Bikes came out a few weeks ago. It is a two-player co-op adventure,
or you can play it single player like I did here, featuring a couple kids on a,
I think it's a fictional British island, right? It's not a real one?
That's right, yeah.
Yeah, it's a fictional island going out.
It's a game about a kid who's on an adventure that's a little bit Goonies, a little bit,
um, if I say it's a little bit Stranger Things, it's only because Stranger Things is a million
things that, from the 80s already.
Um, but thankfully, what's interesting is unlike a lot of other 80s themed games, some
of which we've checked out here on this channel, it's not evident that it's like that, but
it does have that like kinda kid-focused adventure vibe.
Um, that kind of appeals to everyone, the kid that's inside everyone, I'd say.
Is that fair, Rex?
Yeah, I hope so. Yeah. I mean, it was definitely a choice to try and get some of that coming-of-age stuff that you get in films like The Goonies.
And I think a lot of the, well, to me, a lot of the best coming-of-age stuff, maybe it's because I was a, you know...
similar age at the time was films in the 80s like The Goonies and Stand By Me and things like that.
So yeah, that was a big influence like really early on in the project.
You know, and we took a decision not to go like, you know, over the top with the 80s references.
You know, I think Stranger Things is cool, but it is quite a sort of...
I think it's a cleverly put together package of the greatest hits of the 80s and I don't always think that it's necessarily adding a lot to that.
Whereas we wanted to go a bit more, kind of, I don't know, tell our own story whilst being influenced by those kind of films.
Right on. I guess we haven't given Knights and Bikes a fair introduction yet.
Rex, would you mind explaining where Knights and Bikes came from and what kind of game you were setting out to make,
besides just being like an 80s game, which really it sort of isn't.
Yeah, so it is an action-adventure about these two girls.
One girl called Demelza, who is the one currently on her bike with the red hair.
And the other girl is called Nessa.
And they are exploring this island, trying to find a legendary lost treasure.
And, you know, like with any of these things, you know, that's the big quest.
But along the way they're learning a lot about friendship and about, sort of, I don't know,
they're like pushing slowly at the edges of like...
of their childhood experience. They're starting to get independent.
That's very much what bikes, the bikes of the title, represent for us.
When you're a kid and you get your first bike, then you can actually go somewhere without your parents.
It's just on that edge of kids that are still young and have a lot of emotions on their sleeve.
you know, just be very expressive and open, but at the same time just trying to play it
a little bit cooler and kind of, you know, gain some independence and, you know, just
grow up a little bit.
Right on.
Moving on, Rex, is it accurate to say that your title on this product is kind of art
director and kind of co-creative director, along with Mew You?
Yeah.
I mean, like you say, I mean...
You know, it is a tiny team. There's just two of us at Foamsword, which is a company the two of us set up.
So there's me doing like art, animation, writing, yeah, all of that kind of stuff.
And then Moo is doing like the tech side and like holding the company together and doing the business and all of that side.
So, you know, it keeps us very busy.
But yeah, it's kind of.
Fun as well to be able to make a game just sat at your kitchen table like I am now.
And even though there's just the two of us, we have a couple of great collaborators as well.
So we have Kenny Young, who was audio, head of audio at Media Molecule for a long time.
So that's where both myself and Move met.
So, you know, we both know Kenny well and he's a great friend and an incredibly great
sound designer as well.
So we have him on the project, helping us out.
And then also the music is composed by a friend called Daniel Pemberton, who's a big shot
film composer these days.
He doesn't work so much in games, but he's recently done Spider-Man Enter the Spider-Verse,
and he's just done the new Dark Crystal series as well.
So he's a very busy guy, but we had a little bit of his time as well.
Um, yeah, uh, Rex I guess I'd say like here's a question, when you you and I guess talk about you and Moo real quick in your work,
um, it's one thing to sort of talk about Knights and Bikes being an adventure, but there's also kind of a specific...
there's a specific way this game plays, um, uh, there is kind of a top-down, you know, uh...
one's a brawler, one is a brawler, one is melee, if I were describing it sort of can- sort of bra- candidly,
but there's- the way you interact with the world and the environment is not...
like you aren't on a dungeon crawling adventure, it does feel like...
You're in this lived place and it's sort of how two kids sort of poke and prod at the world around them.
Um, uh, what was your guiding principle for making gameplay and sort of, there's like,
I sometimes I feel like games like this can sort of fall prey to, they have with, between
Incredible Animation, um, the game itself, the gameplay itself doesn't have its own identity,
but thankfully you all here have your own identity with this gameplay. Like, what was
kind of your guiding principle for making this thing interactive?
Well, I think, I mean initially, I think it can help to just
pick
like another game to be inspired by so that you have some kind of basis, you know, like when we
worked on LittleBigPlanet back in the day, you know, we knew we wanted to make a sort of 2.5D platformer
and that was very useful because then you could be quite experimental within that framework. So
for this game
I think the two of us, we had slightly different obsessions.
So for myself, it was Earthbound.
It's one of my favorite games of all time.
And I just loved the combination of the real world being given a video game twist.
The different abilities that you got always made sense,
and the fact that you were fighting bullies and people that had listened to too much jazz music.
It was really memorable, and obviously the story, and there was quite a bittersweet element to it.
So that was definitely an influence.
And then Moo, he loved Secret of Mana.
one of his favourite games,
you know, from a similar era as well.
So we knew we wanted to make this kind of top-down,
well, semi-top-down perspective
to be able to like run around in the world quite easily.
Like early on, we actually tried turn-based battles,
but those didn't really quite work so well.
I mean...
You know, they're two energetic kids running around, like, you know, getting up to trouble.
It felt a little bit strange to be just sort of like, you know, sort of sitting there and
stroking your chin and pondering your next move.
It didn't really feel like what, you know, the kids in the game would do.
Mm-hmm.
So I guess, you know, a lot of the gameplay is just thinking, well, how would I react
to that if I was just a mischievous...
kids who just wanted to look for treasure and dig up the soil and check what's under
each rock and just be really curious about the world.
They don't really have so much of the pressure of what slightly older kids would have.
At the moment, in the video, we're actually referencing the fact that Demelza, she does
have some quite.
on dark things in her background in that her mother's just fairly recently died and she's
kind of processing that.
Right on.
I'm going to reach into my question pile for a minute.
In the meantime, chat, I can see some fine folks up there.
We'd love to hear your questions.
If you want to hear more from Rex about his art process, about Knights and Bikes design
process, or if you just want to know what album he's listening to right now.
Ask away.
Uh, Rex, I know that there's something very particular going on with the audio in this game.
If you pay close attention, I left a little bit of audio up for folks to hear it.
When the dialogue is happening there's kind of this plink plink plink.
It almost sounds like rain.
It's either rain or it's something falling on wood and it hits every kind of...
String by string it hits every word that's generated.
What's driving that? That's a really cool...
Yeah, here it's a drum. It's like a little drum for Beardy Man.
And it's like... Yeah, could you dig into that system?
Yeah, I mean, well, I don't know if I can dig into it that much,
because, you know, I wasn't quite so involved in that.
That would be something to really discuss with Kenny,
but I think we were sort of thinking that...
You know, in a little bit like...
What's his name? Charlie Brown, you know,
You'd have like the sometimes when the adults are talking they're just making
like wah wah wah wah wah and you're kind of as a kid you're just like whatever
you know I'm not really I'm not really concentrating on what you're saying.
And I think it it does create a nice sort of thing of feeling like
you know our two girls they've got their own way of communicating.
They often talk with these subtitles that are just popping up very quickly at
the bottom of the screen and they're quite in tune with each
uh whereas
You know, when they come and talk to an adult, you know, suddenly it's like the sound of, you know, pots and pans falling down the stairs.
You know, it's a very alien...
A very alien tongue to them, really.
The adults, like, you know, they see the world completely differently.
I mean, if the adults had come into this room that we're in now,
I don't think they would be imagining a little puppet theatre with some...
with some shrimps talking to each other.
Okay, so that's what's happening here.
I was so wilded out.
I went into the stream and I was like,
what is happening?
Like, is that the curse?
Yeah, I mean, there's definitely,
um, you know, I've had a lot of fun with just,
um, you know, with each part of the game,
you know, like things are worked on in a very iterative way of just thinking,
Oh, I'm sure we could, we could bring a little bit more out here.
Uh, you know, if I was...
If I was a kid running into a warehouse that just had lots of seafood on the ground,
could we maybe do something with that a little bit more?
Rather than just crunching around in some shrimps,
actually bring them to life.
Here, Demelza's having a conversation, not with the fishmonger, but with the fish.
And the fish doesn't have a lot to say.
Just trying to...
Trying to just create this quite different dialogue between the characters and the world
than what the adults would have with that same location.
I don't know if it's interesting, but weirdly, I've actually got...
I didn't know you were going to play this bit, because this is like two hours?
Two hours into the game, something like that.
I've actually got... because I do all my design work in sketchbooks.
Yeah.
So I've got, I mean, you know, I've got stacks of them.
Like this.
And I just thought it might be interesting to just see a page.
Yeah, let's see it.
So that's the space that you were talking about.
I don't know how well you can see that, but, you know, I've...
You know what's...
...create the map and draw it out...
Hold on.
So your image froze just before you held it up.
Ah!
So you got to see me rather than the sketchbook.
Your face is just kind of hanging there and this is quite awful.
Hang on, everyone.
I'm going to pause our footage real quick.
I'm going to...
Rex, I'm going to redial you for a minute.
This is all going to happen live on stream.
This is the art of live video, everyone.
Rex, one...
I will call you right back.
Alright everyone, sorry about that, this is what happens.
I'm in California, Rex is in the UK, getting some Skype.
Anyway, we got a few folks out there.
How are you all doing today? Feel free to...
Okay, Rex, we got you back?
Movement.
Alright, let's see the sketchbook.
Sorry, I just had to rate what the quality of the call was like.
So I gave it one star.
Yes, so this is, I don't know if you can see that, but a page from this area.
And I try and sort of map everything out in sketchbooks and gradually, I guess my process
is really to...
Get everything written down on paper so that you can really externalize it and look at it and think about it.
I think tooltools aren't necessarily the best tools for actually thinking.
They're really good for doing and making results,
but not necessarily good for planning stuff out and going off at strange tangents.
I try and use my sketchbooks more like a visual journal, really.
Sometimes it's more specific, like this,
we've got the map,
and then maybe on the next page is figuring out
what abilities, what are the things that the kids can do at this stage of the game,
what could they interact with,
and just keep going.
Right on. Um, Rex, you did a GDC talk this year, um, uh, the, about the art of Knights and Bikes.
Um, you talked about, uh, to make the characters and to make a lot of art for this game, you would start by doing kind of a vector paint, uh, or, um, a vector drawing, and then you would do, um, a repaint with two specific brushes.
Um, and then that was kind of like, you would do that, and then there was like, then you showed off there was that, and then there was the final pass.
Would you mind talking about that specific process for giving this game a really specific look?
Because it's got a two-dimensional look that is papery, but it's also a three-dimensional look in that you move around the space.
I really appreciated what you said in that talk at the time.
Well, I think the thinking behind the art style is really to try and...
give the sense that you are slightly seeing the world through the eyes of the kids.
And that comes, a lot of that comes from the way that it's, as you say, it's all painted
with these two brushes and those brushes are kind of similar to like chalk and pastels.
So kind of like the materials that these kids would have to tell their own kind of tales,
you know, if they needed to.
At the end of the game, if they needed to write it all down to tell a friend, then they might make something with similar materials.
But at the same time, I don't want it to look...
I want it to look like one of those stereotypical grown-up does kids' artwork.
Kind of a stick person with a 2D house and that sort of crayon style.
So, I'm trying to give some elegance to it as well.
It needs to be believable. You don't want to feel like you're just running around in like a crayon drawing.
So, you know, it's a constant balancing act of trying to stylize things and make them look intriguing and different,
but also keeping it very believable as well, so that you really do feel that you are in this.
It's Cornish seaside town and you're exploring it and it's got a certain atmosphere to it,
it's got quite a run-down feel.
So, yeah, I mean, a lot of the process is basically taking a screenshot of the game
and then painting onto that screenshot with a new item.
I find it quite useful to use the game as like the canvas, essentially.
So that, you know, then you're like matching the style and it, you know, it feels like it all ties together.
Yeah, so that's, you know, the majority of the kind of the painting side.
Like you said, some of the things, particularly the characters, were designed in vectors first,
just because it's very quick to like move things around and make different choices.
But then they'd be repainted with those brushes.
I think the brushes are really useful.
Just limiting to just two means that it ties everything together.
If you're going to make an entire universe of all kinds of different environments and different...
Yeah, well just very different kind of regions and characters and what have you.
It's useful to have some kind of unifying thing that pulls it all together
and it's definitely been that sort of painterly art style that's really helped bring it together.
And then, you know, it's obviously not a static painting, you know.
It animates, so the animation was a really big thing to figure out with the game.
I'm trying to get a feeling of both the energy that kids have, you know, that they've got
endless energy.
They're just expending it the whole time.
They're running around, you know, they never sit still.
You know, they're sitting on a chair, you turn around, you turn back, they're like sitting
with their legs up the back of the chair, and next time you turn around they're sitting
completely differently again, you know, always moving.
So it felt like the...
The art needed to be very, you know, have a sort of dynamic quality.
So, I mean, you can see at the moment there's lots of, you know,
the little sort of flower beds all blowing around and flags blowing around and things.
And they're all pretty much all just hand animated, like by drawing multiple frames.
But some of the elements.
I tried to get a sort of stop motion feel, where it's drawing attention to the fact that
it's being redrawn each frame.
And there's kind of the animation term of line boil, where things are wobbling and vibrating.
I think it's useful to convey that energy of the kids.
And it's also useful because it has a sort of painterly look as well,
so it kind of brings those concepts together.
I was going to say something else about that.
I go off on a big old spiel about art.
Um...
Yeah, so I mean the characters are a mixture of, um...
like rigged animation but then with some hand drawn elements like Demelza's hair you can
see there, her little red bunches, those are done in a stop motion line boil style, trying
to convey both the fact that she's always moving, she's got lots of energy, the fact
that it's a very stormy environment so the wind is always blowing in her hair as well,
but also it's...
I like to think that it's also representing the aspect of the game which is that the kids
are like adding to the world with their imagination.
So the movement of her hair almost represents the idea of fizzing out of her head.
And throughout the game we...
use the hand-drawn style to actually draw things onto the landscape as the kids are imagining it.
So, you know, there's a bit later on where they see this car crusher in a scrapyard.
And, you know, that's kind of a cool thing for kids to see anyway, but, you know,
their imaginations get carried away and they see it as a dragon.
So, you know, we use this style where I like draw like a white.
sort of ghostly stop-motion version of what the kids were imagining over the landscape.
We haven't seen like too many examples of that in this bit because it's quite
relatively early on in the game but yeah it's I think the art
gives us lots of ways to like play around and kind of be more creative with the way it looks.
Right on, um, uh, speaking, actually, I think those, uh, those white speed boosts are a good example, um, of that, of those white lines coming in over the, over the sort of normal landscape.
Um, Rex, this game goes, uh, it does have that, it's a, it's a adventure with two kids on a small island, um, mild spoilers, there is...
A supernatural component to it that pops up really early, within the first hour, and you're about to see more of it as we enter this next area.
How do you... oh dear, this is when my controller just straight disconnected.
Okay, past me got it working again.
What would you say is a defining when you have a game where you have you have a world you have how the kids see
the world
And you have a supernatural component to it that follows
How did you set like like add in that third style?
I guess like like this kind of when kids are already using their imagination and imagination lends itself towards the otherworldly
How did you then define the style that, and implement a style that could keep the player knows,
that's real, that's ghosty, that's kid's imagination?
Right, yeah. I mean, I think audio helps massively there, because, you know,
if you see some of my kind of, you know, hand-drawn sort of wobbly imagination-type driven things,
you know, that...
If there's no audio cue, then everyone knows that it's kind of there, but it's not really there at the same time.
Whereas if you suddenly see a knight's gauntlet, which comes to life and starts charging at you...
With the audio that's associated with it, you know that's going to hurt you.
That's a bigger deal.
Just kind of an example that just popped up.
Those little pink stripes that just popped up.
There was a poof as they vanished, which kind of gave me a clue that something was up when I was playing this.
Yeah, those are little court jesters.
Yeah, because all through the game, obviously, it's called Knights and Bikes, so bikes is a big element, you're seeing lots of cycling around.
But also, the knights of the title refers to this ancient treasure that's hidden somewhere on the island that the kids are trying to find.
And that treasure is protected by a kind of evil curse, which will kind of reanimate things that are not animated.
And that's the main video gamey aspect of the game, which you have to deal with enemies
and that creates the drama.
On top of the more coming of age story and all the themes about childhood and end of
childhood and all of that stuff.
Right on.
Um, uh, let's talk about level design.
Um, I think this game's interesting in that, um, it's pretty linear.
Um, like you're going through area by area and there's kind of a pace and flow to things.
Um, but I noticed there's an exceptionally windy logic to all the spaces you go through.
Um, some of it's natural, some of it's natural, like the natural shapes, some of it's just
houses or other objects getting in your way.
What was kind of, um, sometimes I feel like, uh, games like this can fall into a space
where...
They do have a great look they do have a fun combat loop, but then
Sometimes the player can just sort of be walking from circle to circle where where combat is happening
And I noticed that nice and bikes does a lot of work to make sure that the player is constantly using that joystick to like
Weave around the space. What was did you do you have any thoughts about making?
What the world felt like from a movement perspective, especially with the bikes, right?
Yeah, I mean it's
It's interesting that in our first ever prototype, we actually had a completely 2D game.
And, you know, it looked cool, it looked like a painting, and you were moving around in it.
But there was no sense of discovery because, you know, because the camera wasn't moving,
you never had things like being revealed as you moved through the environment.
And as soon as we switched to this view that you can see now,
where it's lots of 2D things but rowed up in a 3D environment,
it suddenly became much more interesting because as you moved through the world,
you know, things would be revealed, like, you know,
either like being wiped off the screen like you just saw there,
or, you know, some lever that you didn't know was there,
you know, slowly appears as you move around.
So...
The visual style definitely helps spur that on.
In terms of level design, I think each is...
I mean, up until this point, we haven't really, on the stream,
seen what I would call a proper level.
We're just going into one now, which is a bit more, like you say,
more linear once you're inside it.
We've been looking up until this point at the more sort of like open world.
You know, and that part of the game is there to try and give the feeling that the kids are, you know, pushing outside of their local, you know, their kind of sphere of comfort almost.
And they are like diving off into the bushes and...
They can cycle wherever they want and there's kind of like a carefreeness but also like a slight
well sense of a slightly ominous sense as well because you know they are going slightly into
the unknown but when they get to a level like we're just about to get into now which is a
a theme park but a theme park like out of season then the game becomes more
I was really pleased with that visual gag.
I don't know if the rest of the world finds it as funny as I do, but I think I was really
amused by the idea of just seeing someone...
with all the skin missing off their face,
and thinking that's horrific,
and then realizing that it's just a biology book.
And, you know, I remember as a kid,
there was a, like, a pop-up book that we had in school,
which, like, showed how the body works.
And when you opened the pages, you know,
it would show you, like, here's the human body,
but with their skin removed.
And it was just horrific, you know.
I mean, I don't think I've ever seen anything
as quite as disturbing as that book, so I guess that's it.
I've sneaked into the game.
You, so what you viewer are seeing is me wandering back the way I came looking for some crisps.
I'm checking the buses and such because I was just told to find some crisps.
Instead of paying attention to the very obvious, when we get back up to the top of the map you'll see there's a white line
that would have guided me right towards where I need to go and there I would have found said crisps.
But instead I went back and kind of tried to follow park logic of like,
okay where can I get crisps at the edge of a park?
So, maybe I'm just dumb.
Maybe I'm a dummy.
Maybe I'm a big ol' dummy of a game player.
But Rex, what are your thoughts about when you're using these familiar but painterly
components to making, helping players understand what they're doing, what they're looking
for, etc. in a game space?
Well, I think, yeah, I think it is all about little clues, like you say with that white
line that leads you through.
It's very...
It is incredibly tricky, I find, to know how to balance those visual clues and, you know,
hit that sweet spot where it guides you but without you really noticing that it's helping
you.
I think if there's, you know, something that we used to find on LittleBigPlanet was, you
know, we would sometimes...
sort of stick in, like, because of the way that in LittleBigPlanet you could just sort of like stick up, put actual like stickers on the environment.
And sometimes we put like big arrow in to help you.
But it really takes you out of the fantasy just having an enormous arrow just pointing where to go.
So then we replace that with just certain shapes that maybe like guide your eye in a certain way.
One of my favorite things to do on this game is to just put...
If
you have any questions, feel free to post them.
Rex, we lost you sadly. We were trying to bridge this call between the UK and California.
It was difficult. Could you repeat, after the animals run away, could you repeat what you were saying?
Yeah, I mean just that they, you know, an animal is, you know, they're moving.
They're just something you want to interact with.
Whether you're like a mean kid and you just want to, you know, run up to it and cause it, you know.
some kind of mischief or whether you just want to go and pet it.
You know, it's something that I think players respond to,
and then if that bird flies off in a certain direction,
then you're led that way.
So I think, you know, there's lots of little tricks that you can put in
that just guide in a very subtle way.
Right on. Are there any other tricks you like? I noticed in this level the orange and blue lines that we saw in the map back there show up on the ground.
Are there any other particular visual tricks that you think your developers should consider when trying to get players to go the right way?
I think, I mean it's interesting just thinking about what sort of space that you're designing.
So I mean this is a theme park and obviously if you're running a theme park you want to make sure that you're
People are able to move through the theme park, so this was kind of an easier level
because you could just use some of the design tricks that an actual theme park designer
would employ.
So we have these paths on the ground that you know that if you'll just follow that orange
line that will at least take you on a loop, and then there's also a blue line that's going
off a different way.
So...
Those are kind of useful.
I think sometimes things like if a level is more linear in terms of you need to move from, say, left to right,
then just the way that the wind is blowing through the level, that can really help.
If everything in the world is steering you in one direction, that can...
I don't know, it's just you don't feel that you're having the friction of...
of the world pushing against you.
I remember a friend who, Peter, who worked on Blaster Burst, he was talking once about
how all the staircases, you always felt like you were going the right way because of which
side your weapon was on, and if you're kind of going the wrong way then the staircase
is obscured by the weapon, and if it's the right way then it isn't.
cool stuff like that I really like.
Obviously this isn't like a first person game, so you know, you can't use tricks quite like that.
But yeah, I mean there's definitely a lot of sort of subtle signposting.
And then, you know, like, you know, we have to experiment and through playtesting
some of the areas in this particular level.
Once you sorted them out, their doors would open and you could continue a loop and revisit earlier spaces.
And actually, that didn't really work so well for players.
I kind of liked having a little bit more...
It allowed you to explore more and walk back over scenery that you'd already seen,
but the problem was that, obviously, once you...
If I opened up one of those loops, then a player can just start going around that loop forever
without actually going off in the direction that they're supposed to be going.
So, yeah, lots of playtesting and responding to that.
It's interesting how even after everything you've described was a very thorough process,
these are thorough tools you use to get the player figuring out that they sort of just
need to go forward.
And it's interesting how players will still, like just reflecting on myself here in this
level.
Um, you're gonna see me backtrack of my own volition because I believe, like, I'm sorta stuck where I am, so I backtrack to see if I'm missing anything else.
But you're right, friction is sort of what tells play, or at least, for me, friction tells me a lot.
Instead of going the right way, it's that line about, I think, Halo.
Um, you know you're going in the right direction if there are enemies showing up.
Um, uh...
Uh...
Yeah.
I'm sure they also had complicated tricks related to
like your- your friend who worked on The Last of Us, but
Um...
It's- I guess like...
I- I- I don't have much more to add besides it's interesting that players will still do dumb things, I guess?
Mhmm.
Which as a designer like how do you and when you're trying to make something it's a little more...
There are games that keep the space for dumb things open.
If you're talking about more open, systems-driven games, we had Astroneer on.
The Astroneer devs on here a while back.
Games like that are very attuned for that.
If you do something dumb, it may be the answer to do something right.
But if you're playing Knights and Bikes, if you do something like Backtrack,
you're genuinely losing.
It's not that a game needs to be played efficiently, but you are in a state where the game is not being played the way you and Moo and everyone else wanted it to be played, right?
Like you wanted the players to be constantly engaging, constantly finding the fun stuff you guys made.
What's sort of your thoughts about that and how to...
Do you have any thoughts about that space for letting players...
Either letting players or accounting for when players do the dumb stuff that you're gonna see me do?
And you've already seen me done. I play games dumbly.
I think, I mean, it's definitely...
I would always like a game to allow players to play in it as well as play it.
So, for instance, there's various interactions that the two characters and the goose...
We haven't really talked that much about the goose, we've got a goose for him.
You guys beat Untitled Goose Game to the punch and they unfortunately ate your lunch on the goose run.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think it's...
Particularly in a game that can be played co-op, it is good to be able to play with each other.
So that you're not just constantly needing new content.
And sometimes I get frustrated when I play very beautiful, very dramatic games where
you're running down a corridor and the floor is falling away.
It's very dramatic.
But as a craftsman, I guess I get very stressed playing that kind of stuff sometimes because
I'm just like, I want to look at all the care that's gone into this corridor and it's all
just disintegrating.
So, yeah, that's just me as a player.
But I think...
Yeah, I don't know.
Hey, I'll take it. I rambled.
You're allowed to ramble.
Anyway, we are coming up.
We've only got 15 minutes or so left in the hour.
We would love to...
We do genuinely like having yous your questions.
I sound a little desperate, but I genuinely want to hear...
We have some great folks who ask great questions to our guests and I miss them.
I want to hear their thoughts.
It's Twitch.
Twitch is not just us, it's you.
It's the viewer.
That's what I'm told in the emails they send me daily.
Rex, you have a really great part of your GDC talk, which is sitting there in Twitch, which I've linked earlier in Twitch chat.
Um, you talk about, uh, how you listen to audio to, to help guide your, your craft and the things you want to make.
Um, people should go watch that talk. There's some really choice audio bits, um, that both just sound like knights and bikes, even though they're not knights and bikes.
And also, they're just great. They're just great, um, weird British things.
Um, uh, I'm really sorry. I've like...
This is a very abstract question, but what is your thought process for converting the
things you're listening to into visual styles?
You talk about both recordings and just general cafe noises, two things that you like listening
to.
I think often it's...
I think people will often...
You can think of influences as being visual things often.
Especially if you're from an art background like myself.
I always come at things visually first.
That will be the focus for me.
I find that it's actually quite useful to use audio as your main influence,
rather than other visuals while you're working.
Because looking at other visual styles and other visual work
can be quite distracting because you're operating in the same space.
I don't know, it just overlaps too much.
Whereas audio is really interesting because it sort of augments what you're feeling
and pushes you in strange new directions.
For me, a lot of making games is not just about the look, but also about the feel,
and about the atmosphere, and the tone, and all of these kind of things.
And music will just transport you to a completely different world, like magically.
straight away.
If you just open up your
music library and just hit a track at
random, it will just totally change
the entire mood you're in and
the environment you're in.
So I find,
you know, obviously, it's
just great to
put yourself in these different
spaces while you're working.
I think because I used to
do a lot of trailer editing and
like make all the trailers at Media Molecule back in the day, along with other stuff.
So, it's...
Yeah, you can just really take players on a fun journey with audio,
as well as, you know, influence yourself.
And we don't have footage of it today, but the opening of the game
has quite a dramatic opening.
with this wild punk track which Daniel wrote and recorded.
And it features one of our friend's kids
who's eight years old, just like absolutely,
he's like screaming his lungs out.
And the idea of that track, it's very punky,
you can hear it on our launch trailer,
was to sort of set an intention of
These are kids with too much energy and anything's possible.
We didn't want to have one of those slow openings with just lots of establishing shots.
Particularly as it's a two-player game, you want to be right into it straight away.
So having this wild punk opening track really set the tone for the rest of the game.
Audio is the best.
I always really enjoy working with audio people because
you're trying to achieve the same goal and there's total overlap
between what you're doing but also there isn't any at all.
I don't feel... I would never lean over and start tweaking the synthesizers.
Whereas it's quite easy in other areas to...
Get a bit carried away yourself.
Boss encounters, kind of.
Um, what are your...
What are your?
Earlier I fought a bulldozer.
Um...
It uh...
It wasn't on camera, unfortunately.
Um...
What do you think makes a good boss fight in a game like this?
I think boss fights are interesting because they used to be, you know,
the high-water mark for the skill you taught the player.
But, Knights and Bikes is only just loosely...
The new tools are like you said, it's more about poking and playing and prodding.
Um...
What do you think makes boss fights work in a game like Knights and Bikes?
Uh, that's kind of an interesting question because, um, uh, I actually hate boss fights.
No, no, that's, that's okay. I'm pretty ambivalent about it myself.
I am not a big fan of them at all. Um, I find what really kills me is if, particularly these days,
when games have become more open and more experimental and, um...
You're just able to play them in your own style.
I hate it when I get a boss battle where I just have to do a very, very specific thing.
It's like doing a puzzle where you are being shot with lasers and, you know, everything
else is being chucked at you at the same time.
And I don't particularly enjoy...
That, and I don't really enjoy the just constant failing over and over again.
Particularly, you know, if you're really enjoying a game and then suddenly you hit
this massive difficulty spike and you're like, well I'm never going to get past that.
Um, you know, we've kind of got the only, uh, really the only, um, medium where
people don't get to the end of the experience that they've bought.
Um, which I, you know, I always find frustrating if it happens to me.
So, I mean, our boss fights are, you know, they're there for some drama.
They're there to give you a good moment to like high-five each other afterwards
and sort of congratulate your co-player, if you're playing a two-player.
But, you know, they're not there to just prevent you from progressing.
There's some...
It's extra drama, but not too taxing, hopefully.
I think it'll be a long time before I feel that I want to do a boss fight that matches
up to REZ, which is my favourite game ever and has the only boss fights I really love.
I should follow up, what about Rez?
We... there... I need to plug more GDC things I guess,
but we have a great Rez Postmortem sitting in the GDC vault,
which I guess I'll drop in the chat, but what about Rez makes it really resonate?
Rez-o-nate, for you.
Hey!
Rez-onate with Rez.
Um... so...
I think it... you know, it is that perfect fusion of...
of all the things that make games great. It's the audio-visual, interactive experience. Everything
you're doing just feels so good. But it's so surprising as well, the way that... I don't
know, it's just brought a lot of different influences in. It's not like you've gone into
a computer and it's all like, you know, techie and that's it. There's the whole of like...
The whole of history is in that computer.
Yeah, just seeing the artistic vision of that game is just incredible.
Yeah, I love it.
I play it just all the time.
Right on.
As we close out our stream today, I guess we have time to talk about...
Knights and Bikes was launched on Kickstarter.
I know Moo is kind of at the business end of things, but I'd love to share your thoughts
about connecting with a player community.
What do you think has been important in getting this game out in the world and connecting
with people individually?
And being able to sell this game too, I guess is the next part of the question.
What do you think has worked for you as a team in that regard?
Well, Kickstarter has worked really well for us.
I think the thing that we have really concentrated on is just making sure that we have really
good and constant communication with our backers.
It doesn't take a huge amount of time each month to just put together an update.
We always put an update out on the first of the month.
And that's good for the backers, they can see that the project's moving forward.
Our project has taken a fair bit longer than we initially thought it would.
But just keeping them in the loop and making sure that they all feel like they're on the journey
and they're getting to see progress.
You know, there's quite a lot of backers that are just like, no, you know, take as long as you want, you know, take longer.
We're enjoying seeing the, you know, the how it's all coming together.
And from our side, it's really useful because it gives a bit more structure.
Like doing a backer update on the
first of the month always means that like in the last week of the of the month previously,
You're kind of thinking, oh, you know, what can I show?
It's almost like doing like a milestone for a publisher.
You know, you're kind of like, well, you know,
we've got this big giant system that's all very clever,
but it's not an easy thing to show.
So you try and sort of get a nice mixture of like,
you know, here's some cool thing that Moo's done.
Here's like,
You know, here's something much smaller, but kind of maybe more characterful,
is like a little gif or something that maybe I've been working on.
Here's a photo of like Kenny with like a bike up on a desk with 100 microphones around it,
trying to record the sound of the wheels turning, you know, all of those little details.
I think it's really good to share them and it's kind of fun if you do.
You know, I don't really understand why you wouldn't,
if you go to a Kickstarter and...
Take a lot of investment from people.
Like, you know, it's just fun to share it with them.
Yeah, so we've always tried to make sure that even though we're a tiny team,
that we are always there and communicating and keeping everyone in the loop.
Right on, well as my characters venture into scone grotto,
and I bede to learn the art of making a proper scone.
I'm going to start wrapping things up for this stream today.
Rex, thank you so much for joining us.
If people have questions about Knights and Bikes, where can they ask them?
So they can ask on Twitter, at Foamsword Games,
or on our website, knightsandbikes.com.
There's a good spot. We've got a Discord as well.
You know, we have lots of places you can find out about it.
Right on. And like now, just like a person who does not make a scone correctly, I shall venture into the sea.
With that, everyone, thank you so much. We would appreciate it.
Dear viewers, if you were to click the follow button on this here Twitch channel,
if you like chatting with Rex,
you would also like the fact that we interview a lot of other game developers here on the Twitch channel.
In fact, in just another hour, we are going to be talking to the fine folks from Gunfire Games.
I believe we're talking to John Pearl.
I think that's what we're talking to. I hope I got his name right here on the air.
I did. Cool.
Okay, we're talking to John Pearl of Gunfire Games about Remnant from the Ashes.
It's a really cool, it's a third-person combat game that's got...
A lot to pay tribute to for Dark Souls, but it's got a lot going for it on its own, setting
and combat-wise, that makes it different.
So we'll come back in an hour and we'll be talking to Jon, and if you are interested
in joining us at GDC next year, if you have a talk to give...
The GDC Summits are now taking submissions, so go by our website, gdconf.com, and you
can find out more information about that.
If you would like to join, if you're a VR developer working in AR, we have XNerdEC going
on in October, you should also join us in San Francisco for that.
And if you're just a person at home who just likes video games and likes learning about
how they're getting made, we super appreciate having you here, and we hope to see you next
time we go live.
Which...
It'll be in the next hour, and then we're going to go live many more times this month with many more great game developers.
Rex, thank you so much!
Pleasure! Thank you.
Have a good day, everyone. Bye!