Good morning everyone.
All right.
Now we can have our talk.
Hi.
This is us.
I'm Adam.
Dirk.
Will.
Chris.
And we're happy to be here and talk to you guys about our experience creating immersive VR worlds.
We've got a little introduction and then each of us is going to do less than five minute
kind of micro talk and then we're just going to have an open discussion and then we'll
leave plenty of time at the end for questions.
Let's jump right into it. So I like to infuse music into my talks somehow all the time. And if
you hadn't picked it up, it's in the title of this talk. Use your illusion.
The epic double album Guns N' Roses, released from 1991.
So I thought I'd just give you guys a little Guns N' Roses trivia real quick.
Both of these albums were released on September 17th, 1991.
They both debuted at number two.
One sold 685,000.
Two sold 770,000.
The second album spawned all of the hits for this double album release,
You Could Be Mine, November Rain, and Don't Cry.
Both of these albums represented a lyrical, songwriting, stylistic growth from
The kind of previous turning point for the band, the seminal Appetite for Destruction,
these albums had a more mature sound, despite many of the songs originating back to the
more raw Appetite for Destruction era.
Despite the global success of these albums and their tour, the double albums ended up
splintering and destroying the band.
Specifically alienating guitarist Izzy Stradlin, who was kind of the songwriting engine of
the group, and he left and it kind of just eroded the band.
Their next album was an album of covers called The Spaghetti Incident that no one remembers.
And then, well you know the rest.
I guess they're back now, kind of.
So cautionary tale about double albums, guys.
And excess.
Maybe in video games.
So that's what works.
So we're here today to talk about kind of immersive worlds and how they're achievable
in VR.
And for me and for these guys and probably for many of you out there, the first time
you put on a VR headset, if it was a good...
experience, it really kind of changed how you look at things. And we want to share our
experience making VR worlds and what we've learned and kind of what we think works and
what doesn't. But I look at something like this and it's kind of the possibility I want
to go to there. So I'm Adam Orth. I'm the creative strategist at First Contact Entertainment.
I've been making video games for a long time, and I'm starting my 18th year making games
now.
About five or six years ago, maybe even a little bit earlier, I started becoming really
bored with the traditional way of making games and the kind of minimal, medium progression
between long development cycles.
I was becoming embittered and just hostile towards the whole thing.
I just didn't want to do it anymore.
I was just searching for...
whatever the new thing was.
Like, how am I going to express myself in this interactive medium?
And I just didn't know what to do.
And I was just really kind of stuck in a rut.
And I started working on this game called Adrift, which is...
It's a VR game. If you haven't heard of it, look it up. It's pretty sweet.
But I kind of considered this moment of a career and life reset for me.
And it just started as a way for me to just try to do something new and different.
And I wanted to tell a really deeply personal story in an interactive experience,
but not through shooting someone in the face in a video game.
So...
Around that time, right around that time, the Kickstarter for Oculus Rift happened and
my partner and I were backers, we were early backers, and we had a very basic prototype
for Adrift and we got this DK1 and we magically somehow set it up and it worked the first
time, which never happened again after that.
Um, and so the first time I saw this new generation of VR was with something that I was building,
and I just lost my mind.
It, it, like, it changed everything for me, and I realized that this was the thing that
I was searching for, and I instantly knew that I could tell the story that I wanted
to tell with this new hardware and technology.
It was just kind of mind-blowing.
So...
We put those two, mashed them together, and Adrift was kind of a traditional game experience
up until that moment.
And we put it all together and then it just, everything kind of fell together for us.
Completely creatively re-energized, just totally into exploring in the dark and peering around.
So that little prototype in the Oculus Rift became this, but in VR.
And it was just the perfect way to really express what we were trying to get,
and we just had never experienced anything like that before.
Adrift, at least for us, was the perfect setting for VR.
It was this kind of seductive and universal power of space that kind of resonates with
everyone because everyone knows what space is and they have their own idea and they're
either excited by it or scared by it, but everyone has kind of a foundation to build
on and it really...
kind of everything is kind of lined up right there.
And it's just it took me someplace that I could never go in real life.
And and that's when I really kind of saw the power of VR.
And I became one of those kind of early adopters and evangelists for the tech.
And we basically worked with Oculus kind of from the beginning,
not in any kind of official capacity, just.
We loved what they were doing and they loved what we were doing.
And we ended up becoming a featured Oculus Rift launch title and that first wave with
the Vive.
And it was just an awesome experience to be part of.
And currently I'm working at First Contact Entertainment.
AAA VR studio in Santa Monica.
My role as creative strategist is to kind of guide the vision of all of our VR products and the creative vision anyway and
ensure that that kind of strategy is moving forward safely in the future and then
creating new new experiences as well.
I'm focusing now on
multiplayer VR. Drift was a very
Kind of solo, closed off experience and I want to take my passion of the virtual space
and bring other people into it and do awesome things.
So that's what we're doing.
Now Dirk.
Hi everyone, I'm Dirk Van Velden, I'm from Belgium, I'm the captain at iIllusions and
we made this game called Space Pirate Trainer.
I don't know, who has played Space Pirate Trainer before?
It's cool, it's a lot of people.
So yeah, I'm the founder and project lead on Space Pirate Trainer.
My illusions was actually we were doing work for hire for the entertainment industry and
the communication industry, so we were creating games for fairs.
And then we ended up creating our own IP like four years ago on Steam pretty early.
By that time we had some contacts at Valve and we had a Vive pretty early.
My current role at iIllusion is mostly gameplay programming.
I'm an interaction freak, which is great for VR, because there's a lot of interaction going on.
It's about subtleties in movement and subtleties in the way you grab things,
and so that makes experiences better.
I've been a very early VR supporter, so I was also a backer for Oculus.
But my problem was, the first thing I played on there was Half-Life in VR.
And I'm super susceptible to motion sickness.
And I just went to bed for a couple of hours and actually said to myself,
I'm never going to create a VR game.
So, that's something I actually said.
Two years after or three years afterwards I got noticed, I got the Vive and tried it
on and I was blown away because I wasn't getting motion sick, mainly because of the positional
tracking.
So...
I'm...
This is one of the screenshots of 1.0 Space Pirate Trainer.
So we're creating actually environments around the current environment.
There's some more stuff coming with 1.0 which is going to release next month.
So it started out as a room scale demo.
So we actually made Spacefire Trainer for Vive and for room scale.
It was a free demo.
It was released on the forums like in December before the Vive came out.
And just because it was some, there was nothing like a shooter even.
So we had one demo with a bow and that was it.
So we just tried to create something new.
And back then the wave shooter was actually something new that no one had done.
And there's a lot of wave based shooters now.
I think Space Pirate Trainer was one of the first ones.
So was Space Pirate Trainer a success?
Well it sold more than 150,000 units, so we can only be a team of three people, so actually
for us it was also a commercial success next to being just great to work on.
One of the reasons why it became a success is probably because it's very pick-up-and-play.
You get most of the stuff immediately. You can just start. It's super easy.
You just have the shield in your bag that people will show you.
Someone like Dan Kaminsky on Twitter said,
My favorite part of Space Pirate Trainer is that you get access to everything immediately.
So you couldn't actually, if you create a game for just desktop PCs, you can't imagine a game where you get everything instantly.
Normally you should unlock things and stuff like that.
But I believe like in this first wave that we had of VR entertainment,
it was a good decision that we just unlocked everything for everyone so people could just show stuff.
And we're trying to keep that strategy for 1.0 as well.
And it's very difficult because if you give everything at the same time, it gets kind of overwhelming.
But yeah, that's something you have to figure out. One of the reasons why it's very popular in VR arcades
is also the same thing. You get everything immediately and people don't have to unlock stuff.
This is another screenshot of 1.0. It shows a boss fight
with the boss bigger than the platform. It's pretty crazy in VR, not so much in 2D, but yeah.
So that's upcoming
mid-October.
So about environments, one of the decisions we made is we have one environment, right,
so it's very open.
The thing is you want to create an environment that people want to look at constantly, but
if you have a corridor and there's something at the corner, people would actually love
to check it out.
If you don't have any locomotion system, like people are always in the same place and running
out in the same square meters, you have to create stuff that's interesting, but not something
that you have to look for.
You have to make sure that people aren't feeling that they're missing out stuff that's happening
around their world.
So we tried to move the action around the player.
Also like with the other screenshot that you saw, we actually move a spaceship or a big
spaceship around the whole platform.
So it feels like a totally different environment.
Just by checking and changing the stuff that you didn't, you have to use locomotion.
So that's one of the things we did.
Also the reason why the front side of Swiss by Train is pretty empty, just a city with
some...
Skylights, it's mostly a distraction issue.
Like if you have too many spaceships flying around
or if you have too much detail,
you actually can see the little droids flying towards you.
So you have to be careful if you're adding too much content
to the thing you have to focus on,
things get distracted quite easily.
Also, there is object interaction that was pretty important for us.
So people love to interact with stuff.
And if everything is at a certain distance and you can't use a locomotion, you have to
find some solutions.
So we had a Volton.
It's kind of a device where you can grab droid switch and you actually pull them towards
you.
We're going to even in 1.0, we're using it for powering up turrets and stuff.
So we're actually adding interaction with objects that are actually far away.
So yeah.
was one of the solutions.
And then the final point is, so you have, actually, Space Pirate Train is only using
210 degrees of action.
So most of the action is going out in front of you.
And that wasn't always the case.
Like in the first prototypes, it was just droids flying around you, and you would go
nuts because...
It just can't remember all the droids and where they are and how they're flying around.
So that was a design decision that people felt so much more secure if everything was
happening in front of them.
So that's probably one of the better decisions we made for Space Pirate Trainer because people
that are in VR for the first time, you just don't want to overwhelm them.
They can look around and they can see the environment, but the action should be in front
of them.
So I think that's most of the stuff I have to say about Space Pirate Trainer.
I'm just going to give it over to Will Smith.
Hi everybody, I'm Will Smith. I'm the founder and CEO of FooVR.
Before that, I ran...
We make the FooShow, among other things.
The FooShow was an early prototype that we built to show how our animation technology works.
What we do is actually animate believable human avatars
using the three points of data that you get from a VR headset and hand controllers, like Vive.
The Foo Show is something where we take people and put them inside video games with the people who make the games.
We can talk about making games from inside the games. It kind of spins off of what I did at Tested before we started Foo.
Everybody watched this on YouTube, it turns out.
We had like 100,000 downloads across all the platforms,
but the YouTube views that some guy captured off of a headset
with full head bob got an order of magnitude more traffic.
So I think there's an important lesson about nascent platforms there,
but I don't know what it is this early in the morning.
I'm Will Smith.
I think I got in a little bit different order.
I'm not this one.
I'm actually this guy.
This is from my time at Tested.
The thing that we did, the thing that was really compelling was we went out and found
people who made amazing things on all sorts of scales.
From a guy in his garage making WALL-E robots that actually drove around and were fully
articulated to cooking for the International Space Station with Chris Hadfield to just
testing goofy stuff in the office in San Francisco.
We talked to the people who made these things in a way that was very relatable to other people who make things,
and people who are aspirational.
The challenge with it was it was only really good for tangible things.
Video is great. I can point at something, I can say,
oh, why did you make Wally's head work this way?
Why does this juicer have a feed like this?
If we wanted to talk to people who make games or other intangible 3D, you know, digital assets,
you know, it's kind of boring.
Like, hackers kind of did this thing, but...
Nobody wants to watch a video of somebody sitting in front of a computer typing, ever.
It's really boring.
So, that was kind of the impetus for the Foo Show.
I wanted to be able to take these intangible assets that people created
for games and science and all these other mediums
and have those same kind of conversations with the creators inside those spaces.
And that's what we do.
We make these intangible places feel like they're real with virtual reality.
So what have we learned so far?
For human animation, believable,
it's much, much more important to,
you know, we're never gonna get one-to-one tracking
with three points of data, right?
The thing that we learned incredibly early is that if you hold your hand out,
the hand orientation we can get, but if your forearm in VR doesn't line up with your forearm in the real world,
a lot of people get really, really discomforted by that, and it's something to be avoided.
Avatars actually work.
When we recorded the first episode with the Firewatch creators,
Sean Vanaman and Jake Rodkin from Campo Santo,
I didn't know if you were going to be able to interview somebody with avatars.
We literally put the headset on for the first time, and we'd used the technology a lot in
house, but we'd all spent hours and hours and hours testing this, and we were familiar
with the avatars.
We were used to their body language.
We were comfortable with them.
And the first five or six minutes of the Firewatch recording, it was unclear if we were going
to be able to have the kind of human interaction that we have when we're looking at each other
in the eye, and you kind of read the body language that comes across when you're having
a conversation with somebody.
That's the other interesting thing is that the body language actually does come across
even with only three points of data.
So when I shrug, I get that reads much better in VR than it does even on a Skype call or
something like that.
If I'm tilting my head like I want more of a question, I want more detail on the thing
that the other person is talking about in a conversation, they can pick up on that and
they'll give me that.
If I'm moving my hand as if I want to interrupt, they'll see that too.
And all these things get lost in video.
But they're present in VR, and when you're interviewing somebody, when you're talking
to someone, whatever, it all transfers.
When you're building these VR worlds, and I think we'll talk about this more in a minute,
but being deliberate about what you make real and what you make magical is super, super
important.
You want the real stuff to behave very predictably and follow a set of rules that are, they don't
have to be set in stone, but they need to be internally consistent with the rest of
the thing that you're building.
And then on top of that, we layer some VR magic.
So we do what we call diegetic UIs.
Basically it's a pop-up menu that's a device that lives in the world.
And instead of blasting up a big 2D pane with UI on it, we give people a thing that they
can interact with that's basically physical widgets.
And it's important to use that stuff sparingly.
When you're doing a social thing like our recording studio, if you want them to follow
the rules of the real world, not invading people's personal space, not zooming around
recklessly while you're having a conversation with them, your world needs to behave enough
like the real world that their reptile brain says, oh yeah, I know how to do this.
I stand here and I look at this person and I nod when they say something that I agree
with and I shake my head when they don't.
And then the other thing that we learned relatively early on is that the VR audience, at least
in the first year or so, wasn't big enough to pay the bills, even for a small three-person
studio.
So we started doing some other stuff.
We used our animation tech to make a live weekly television show.
It's digital, but it's essentially a 30-minute sports call-in show that features Carl from
Aqua Teen Hunger Force.
every Wednesday night at 7 and he talks about football.
He loves the Giants and hates everyone else, basically.
We've also done some commercial work and we've done a couple of other pilots that I can't really talk about.
But it turns out, building a virtual reality animation studio
that works like a live television studio
It empowers the people who make traditional animation in really interesting new ways.
And then I have what's next.
So, we're continuing to work on the animation.
It turns out taking three points of data and turning that into a believably animated human is challenging and difficult.
We get a little bit better every version.
I think we're on like the 10th or 12th version of our core software now.
The 2D content pays the bills.
It turns out it's nice to have food and a house.
But we still believe in the future of VR,
despite the fact that we're using VR to make 2D video.
I think that the upcoming wave of hardware that's coming,
the price reductions we've seen earlier this year,
and the standalone headsets that we'll see next year
are making VR, AR, MR, whatever you wanna call it,
it's all still a super relevant thing and really exciting,
and the place that we wanna be.
And the stuff that we're doing for 2D
actually will spill over into the...
The VR adjacent stuff.
And we really believe that the current gen desktop hardware are dev kits for the future.
I think that the standalone headsets are going to be huge in two years.
And that's pretty much it.
The last thing I'll say is that don't get hung up on labels.
Just make stuff that you think is cool.
So VR, MR, AR, whatever, it doesn't matter.
Just make cool games and things.
And I'll hand it over to Chris.
Hello, good morning.
I have a policy about slides with text that I don't like them.
And I made these slides and I sent them over to Adam about a week ago.
And I'm like, hey, what do you think of the slides?
And he said, yeah, yeah, they're fine, these will be fine.
And then a couple of days ago, he's like, well, I'm having some trouble fitting them
into the template.
Because we have a really impressive slide template here.
And then last night we had dinner.
I had to stop using the template because of your slides.
Because of my slides.
I broke the template.
Then last night we had dinner and he's like, I got to tell you something, I had to rewrite
your slides as text.
And I was like, so I'm going to bring to you these slides that I drew with a pen that I
forced Adam at gunpoint to reinsert into this deck last night at about 11pm.
So I hope that you enjoy them.
My name is Chris Pruitt. I am an employee at Oculus.
My job there is working with folks like yourself, third-party developers.
I run an engineering team that helps folks like yourself optimize your code,
or design your games, or do whatever it is you need to do to make your content really good.
Under the cover of night, I'm also a game developer.
I founded a studio called Robot Invader in 2011.
That studio continues to run and my role these days is sort of to paw through the code at
night and introduce bugs.
Robot Invader produced a game called Dead Secret, which I was the designer for.
This shipped in, its very first version shipped on Gear VR in 2015.
And I'm going to talk about it a lot today, but it's essentially a murder mystery horror
game.
So here's a slide about Dead Secret and the important part of this slide is that you should go to DeadSecret.com to find out about the next game which is called Dead Secret Circle which is currently in development.
Okay, so the reason I'm interested in VR worlds is that I actually want to scare you.
I'm interested in making all of you quake in your boots.
And the reason that I'm interested in horror games is really long and complicated and I'm going to get as much of it as I can in the 30 seconds I have left.
I started studying horror games about 15 years ago.
These were not VR games, these were just regular horror games.
And my theory at the time was that horror games are interesting and they're different
than other types of titles because they are going for emotional manipulation.
If you're building a horror game, you have a very, very specific goal, and that is to
make your players feel a very, very specific thing, which is generally stress or tension.
And that's more specific than most other types of games.
Most other types of games are like, oh, I feel great, I'm having a good time, the adrenaline
is running.
I'm a space ninja or whatever it is.
But horror games are like, no, no, I'm going to make you concerned about what's behind
that door right at this moment.
And that's a very specific type of design and I was really interested in that concept.
I spent a long time working on it. I don't really care when I say horror games about
like jump scares or monster closets. What I care about is an environment that over the
course of experiencing that environment you are worried about. You become unsettled by.
And actually what I'm going for is what horror game designers have been calling sense of
presence for a lot longer than we've had VR.
The idea of presence in VR is well understood.
You're in the world, you believe you're in the world, the world is self-consistent, you
accept that you're there.
And outside of VR, horror game designers work really, really, really super hard to produce
that.
And in VR, it's almost automatic.
And that means that a scary game, or a game, even if it's not scary, that's built on the
same principles as a horror game in VR, has the ability to speak intimately at an emotional
level with its player, really, really easily, in a way that other types of experiences do
not.
And that is super fascinating to me.
My goal is to get you to stop thinking about the game as a collection of mechanics.
When I play a video game, I play a lot of video games, and I kind of can see through the mechanics a lot of the times, and I'm like, oh, you know, like, the health pack gives me three health points back, but if I take a hit, then I only take one point, so I can take two hits before I have to use a health pack, and then I got to ration the health pack because, you know, I have to do three more guys before I get to the boss, and he's going to hurt me harder, and I'm, that's like solving a Rubik's Cube, and that's fun, and I enjoy it, because Rubik's Cubes are pretty good, but when you're playing a horror game, what I want you to think about is,
What is the significance of that symbol that I just saw on the wall?
I'm pretty sure I've seen that symbol somewhere before.
Maybe the killer left that symbol.
I want you to think about the context.
I want you to think about the story and the environment.
And that is entirely built out of what I call contextual thinking
rather than systemic thinking, which is normal for a regular video game.
That's kind of what I want to talk about today.
And I'm going to cut it off there because Adam said he'd kill me if I go more than five minutes.
But that's my piece. Thank you.
Okay, I need the mic gun.
Is this on? Okay.
Thanks guys.
So when I put this, the idea of this panel together,
I was going through a period where I was just like,
working on a new thing,
and the environment was not working in VR.
It was something that was kind of set in the real world that you can actually go to and
experience in real life.
And I just found it wasn't clicking for me.
And I started thinking a lot about environments.
I wanted to talk about it.
And I wanted to talk about it specifically with these guys.
They're my friends, but I also really respect what they've done in VR.
So I wanted to have just...
Even though they're kind of rote at this point, but the idea of transportation...
Not locomotion, but being transported somewhere.
Presence.
and immersion. Those things have been talked about to death.
But the kind of interesting thing here is I want to talk about those things
from, through the lens of these guys' experience.
You know, I made a very narrative-driven, environmental VR experience.
And I want to kind of hear how these guys, and have you guys hear how these guys
Think about those three words
from making an arcade game or a VR TV show or a horror game or and especially in Chris's point from
point of view as
an employee at
arguably the best VR headset out there. Some may disagree, but I'm an Oculus fanboy.
Because I think it's interesting, I think there's a lot of interesting stuff to be said there,
especially from Chris's point of view, from, you know, what does Oculus look for in these things?
So, I just want to open up, I'll start out by saying, you know, when I was working on Adrift,
I researched a lot of...
You know, what do people who go up into space, how does it make them feel?
How does it feel to be able to look down on all of humanity?
And they all had a really different experience and they were all very changed when they came back.
But the one commonality was that they had a sense of presence in the universe and in space
that made them feel like...
It changed them forever. And I wanted to kind of use VR to capture that in a narrative game,
so space was like an obvious choice for me. And like I mentioned just a couple minutes ago,
I've done some things recently where I haven't been so successful with the environment
because it's not magical enough, right? And Will brought that up a little bit.
Well, you can either be really real or really magical, right?
You don't have to be both.
Sorry, I didn't mean to take your mic.
But yeah, so we take, with the Foo Show,
we take stuff from video games.
And there were two things that we learned really quickly.
One is that we have this opening segment that's
like 2 and 1⁄2 minutes long, where we introduce
the developers, and it's in a studio where you can teleport
around a little bit, but there's literally nothing else to do
but watch us talk, and then watch the clip that we play.
On the other side of that, we go into the actual environment from the game.
We made all of the props that were in this Firewatch watchtower interactive.
So you can pick them up, you can look at them.
We talk about them, we pick them up, you can grab the things that we're talking about.
And the feedback, we analytics the hell out of it,
which I recommend everybody do on there, especially when you're experimenting with stuff,
so you can see what people are touching, what they're spending time with.
The feedback we got after we did playtesting was
the opening part was about 10 minutes too long, it was two and a half minutes.
The second part could have been twice as long, and it was 17 and a half minutes.
So, you know, we had a 20-minute total experience.
The part that was two minutes and we thought was as short as we could possibly make it was too boring.
And, like, one of the things that you did with Adrift—
you did two things that I loved in Adrift.
One was, the first time you went outside the space station,
I felt like an astronaut for the first time in my life.
Since then, you're floating in space,
you're looking at the whole world,
you can see the entirety of the world below you.
And I understood a little bit more about the things
that I'd read in all the memoirs of the astronauts
I've read over the years.
It's something that connected with me very personally.
Google Earth does a similar thing.
When you're in space looking at Google Earth,
you get that same kind of feeling.
But you also gave the people lots of stuff to interact with in the world, which I think is really important.
The thing that I'm curious about is with your game, Dirk,
like you basically, your interaction is that you can shoot stuff or grab it.
And your game is much more, like I've spent way more time in your game than I have in mine.
So, you know, I'm curious, yeah, like, is shooting just a core, we just have to shoot as people?
Is that a question?
I mean, do we have to shoot his people?
Do you mean like, is this mic on?
Can you hear me?
Yeah.
So, no, actually you don't have to shoot.
But yeah, if I'm...
I mean, is it a core imperative of the human experience that we have to shoot other things?
I guess.
One of the funny things is with 1.0, I'm going to spoil it, you can actually finish Space
Pirate Trainer 1.0 and you do it by just not shooting the first droid because the first
droid doesn't shoot you.
So if you just hold it and caress it for a couple of minutes, you unlock the, you finish
the game.
It just, it just flies away.
So if you ever want to unlock it, don't tell your friends, they'll go mad that you finished
the game.
So you don't have to shoot as a human.
It's because you...
I really wanted to do that.
You start the aggression.
So that's when they start shooting at you.
That's why the first droid's not shooting at you.
People were wondering why that was.
It's also easy, the first droid's not shooting.
But the interaction part with the Voltron,
we saw that in virtual environments, people...
tend to try everything, or try to interact with everything.
You saw it like in Job Simulator, in a lot of games.
They try to do random stuff, and the best way to figure out what people will be doing
is just to playtest your environment.
I think the guys from Walking Me Labs, they just put people in there,
and they start throwing stuff or shaking the bottle,
and they said, maybe it should actually spray or something if you shake it too much.
So you can actually, you have to predict what people will do, but you can't predict everything.
We had the same thing, for example, with the Volton.
You could actually interact with objects that were far away from you.
People were trying to use it on everything around you.
They were trying to use it for the ship to move it around.
You could actually use it on the grenade, for example.
You could pull them back.
So one of the new things was creating more interaction around you in your world.
And by creating more interactivity, it also makes it more believable, I guess.
And you spend a lot of time on details that people will probably not see,
but it just makes all of it more believable.
That's a good segue for Chris, because I spent a lot of time in that house.
Yeah, I think there's a lot of...
I mean, one of the nice things about VR, as you alluded to, Adam, is that there's...
It's new and there's no real rules and nobody really knows what the rules should be.
Particularly, if we're talking about core video games,
if you're making a first-person shooter in this day and age and it's a core video game,
you don't have a lot of choices when it comes to how the character is going to move
or what the action button is going to be.
Those things are baked as precedent.
You can't mess with them or players won't understand how to play your game.
In VR, all bets are off. Nobody knows how to shoot a robot.
Maybe you should grab it with a gravity thing first.
The grammar is unwritten.
In particular, you have an opportunity with each new world to write your own grammar.
I think the trick is that...
Once you define that this is what the interaction grammar or
this is the rules of your world, they have to remain consistent.
So the thing that is great about SpacePirateTrainer is that you
can do all that stuff. You can use the objects in a way that
you didn't expect people to use. It's also true of Job Simulator.
They're saying, I'm going to give you a very high fidelity
interaction here. We have a lot of...
We've got a lot of physics interactions. And then all the stuff you might think to do is
going to totally work. Because we coded it to work. You want to put your head in the
photocopy machine? We thought of that. So when we did dead secret, this was pretty early.
We didn't have motion controllers. We were building originally, although it ended up
shipping everywhere.
Building originally for a mobile device.
So we had like a trackpad and a click.
We didn't really have very high fidelity input.
So we went the other direction.
We actually kept the interaction super duper simple
because I didn't want the rules or the believability of
the world to be broken by sort of an inconsistent rule set.
If I say, well, you can pick up that object, but you can't
pick up that object.
Or you can throw that one, but not that one because we
couldn't figure out how you should throw that one.
Then it will feel like a system again.
I don't want to feel like a system.
I want to feel like a.
Scary house where somebody got killed.
So when you talked about, earlier you talked about the symbol on the wall, right?
When you first go into that house, it's so well put together in terms of that, like, it feels like a character.
The place felt like...
A character so what were like the like point out just a couple things for those who've played Dead Secret
That were really key into
Making that magic there the care. Yeah the house. I mean is the character and very specifically
It's the character of the guy who's died so the the setup is that you know you're
Investigating this murder that's occurred and nobody believes it's murder except for
you and you break in there and find the evidence and blow it wide open.
You kind of get into the house and figure out that it's significantly more complicated
than you might have imagined.
The very first scene...
is that you step into the sort of foyer, and there's a mirror, and you can see yourself
in the mirror.
And this was like a pain in the ass, engineering-wise, to do properly, because it's hard to render
mirrors.
You end up rendering the scene four times, right?
Once for each eye, and then once for each reflection.
And I'm running this on a mobile device in 2015, so I worked a ton to make that freaking
mirror work, but it was important because...
I think everyone should give Chris a round of applause for that, because that's really
hard to do.
Yeah.
Just...
I spent an inordinate amount of engineering time on that stupid mirror.
But the reason was you had to be able to see who your character was.
And once you step into this space, you're going to be immersed in this other dude's life.
That's what his house is. It's a record of his life.
And he had a weirdo, messed up life.
And I have very, very few opportunities to tell you about your character.
And your character in my game is not...
You can see that it's not an everyman, it's a very specific person, and she has very specific traits.
And some of them I'm never going to tell you about, like she's got a broken arm and I'm not going to tell you why.
But you need to see that she has a broken arm so you know something about her.
And so it was really important for me to design the house such that I could do that very early on.
Once you get past that foyer point, you are into sort of the house itself.
And what we did was we went for a small...
A physically small space, I mean the whole game takes place in one house, that is high
density in terms of detail.
So there's a zillion documents to read, you can look under the covers, or you can pull
up the futon or the couch pillows and look underneath them.
We tried to make sure that there was a reason to investigate every little area.
Because
If you do that, again, I think you're going to be thinking in context rather than thinking
about a system.
But also, you're going to be focused, and you're going to be a really close reader.
And if my goal is to scare you, then once you're focused, I have a lot of opportunities
to do that.
So, Dirk, one of the things I love about Space Pirate Trainer is the first time I played
it, I grew up in the 80s.
You know, arcade games and all that.
And it really felt like a natural evolution to that.
And I just remember, like, feeling like it was a real place.
Like, not just, like, an arcade experience.
Like, looking out in the vistas and, like, the Blade Runner-esque kind of ads and stuff up top.
Like, how did you decide to go to that place?
Because I think that...
For me that that sells the virtual environment and it makes Space Pirate
Trainer better and more unique than everyone else who copied it.
That's actually the look we were going for because I just remembered when I was first
playing VR games, I just remembered the times when I was at an arcade and playing those
games and I just wanted to have that same kind of feeling.
I think the coloring in the Space Pirate Trainer, like the broken red and stuff, it's one of
the reasons why it feels a bit 80-ish.
The first time I actually imported the whole model of the building into Space Pirate Trainer.
We thought it looked great on my computer and in the level designer, but when we saw it in real life in VR,
we actually noticed that there's a lack of detail.
Like sometimes if you create something for the first time in VR, you look at things in a different way.
For example, the ground floor under you.
It could look nice in your level editor, but you're so close to the ground that it needs
extra detail.
So we spend most of the time detailing everything that's very close to you.
So the first thing people do when they're in VR and they're holding an object, like
for example in Space Pirate Trainwreck Gun, they actually look at it very closely.
So we spent a lot of time just modeling the gun because it just gives you a seal of quality
if something in your hand that you're looking up close is high quality.
So the closer things get to your face, the more time you should spend on making something
that's high fidelity in terms of quality.
Same with, for example, the floor.
Make sure there's a detailed texturing and stuff in there.
It's just tiny details that make it feel more realistic.
I don't know how many of you guys have played Lone Echo, for example.
It's very AAA.
It's probably one of, next to Adam's one and Robo Recall, it's one of the big AAA titles.
And you can see, if you just take a look at the way they did the locomotion, the hands...
Like it actually grabs around stuff and the detail they put into the hands, it just gives you an immersion immediately.
I think having stuff with high quality very close to you and stuff with less quality a bit further away, it just makes the whole experience better.
You just have to, the first, the most things you do in VR just needs, like, it just needs, the first time you put an environment in VR, you always feel it needs more detail in my opinion.
And of course, Will, with the Foo Show, like, he's got the best of all worlds, no pun intended,
because he gets to go into all these other worlds and have an experience in them that
they weren't created for.
Can I ask you a question about that, actually?
Yeah.
I had a question.
So, I really liked going to the Firewatch Tower and playing with it, and I think that
The setup was that you're talking to the developers of the game and they're talking about how they modeled the assets and you're looking at them, but also kind of turned the world into a set, right?
How did you feel about that? Because once you can pick the things up and they have, you know, oh look it has no back or it has no weight, you know, there's no attempt to make it realistic, you're just showing the asset.
We're showing props, we're showing what it's like to go on Warner's backlot, basically, yeah.
How does that... was that intentional? How do you feel about that?
I'd like to say it was intentional, but really we recorded that episode, I think, on March 3rd.
And we released it, let's see, it came out on the Vive on launch day and it came out on Oculus the Friday after launch.
So, that was maybe three weeks of development, basically, from the time we recorded.
We recorded it as a test to see if we could do the recordings.
And then we shared it around to some friends, I sent it to some folks all over, and people
looked at it and were like, you should release this, this is really good.
And we're like, well, it's like 10 days until the headsets are out.
I don't know if we can...
And they're like, no, you should really release it.
We hunkered down and a lot of the decisions we made in that were not intentional.
So things like, we knew that we wanted everybody to be able to look at the same object at the same time
without having to huddle around each other because then we knew it would feel cramped.
So we let them spawn clones.
But if we let them spawn clones, then conceivably somebody could just make a million clones
of the same object and fill the tower with garbage and chunk their performance and make
them feel nauseous.
So most of our decisions at that point were around making it a pleasant experience for
the viewer and letting you access the things that maybe you couldn't reach if you were
on an Oculus with a gamepad at the time and didn't have room scale.
So we had like a force pull thing where you could grab stuff from across the room, which
worked surprisingly well.
Our teleport system was very rudimentary.
All of that stuff was rough.
But the benefit we had was that we drafted on something that a really talented team of
like eight people had spent two and a half years making.
It turns out that bringing assets from other engines into Unity is a little more challenging
than we initially anticipated.
But yeah.
The other benefit that we've had is we can go places that don't exist in the real world.
This is one of the important things.
If you're going to...
I
talked to a biochemist who makes nanomachines out of DNA.
And we literally start out in his lab, which he's recreated for reasons I'm not going to
get into here because he's awesome and a little bit crazy.
And then we do a powers of 10 thing.
We go inside the equipment in the lab and then we go into a microscopic scale world.
And then eventually we end up, when we finish the episode, standing between the lipid layers
of an E. coli cell.
And that's a thing you can't do in the real world.
Like, you just, you can't see it.
We can see the constructs.
We can see the way that he builds the nanomachines with these phage viruses.
And you can handle the phages and you can see how the stuff chunks together.
And that's something you can't do in any other medium that I'm aware of,
which is what we're trying to do.
So that's coming out soon.
So do you guys agree?
I want you to agree.
Because it's something, like I said, I've been having issues with it, like, like, when you make a place in VR, like, it can't just be a normal place, it has to have these some kind of magical quality in it.
I mean it could be a place that doesn't, it could be a place that's inaccessible.
Like I would love to spend some time in the Oval Office and kind of like walk around and
see what it's like or in a missile silo or places that aren't, places that are, you know,
International Space Station.
That Oculus thing was amazing.
But the Oval Office is kind of like space, though.
It's not some place you can normally go.
Right.
Right?
So that's magical in that sense, I guess.
Right.
Because I made a gas station and it was really terrible.
It was like...
Do you get to...
Do the kids that are going off to Chris' house roll up in an RV and they're like,
Hey guys!
And you're the grumpy old man that has to send them on their way to their doom?
Yeah, I mean like...
Well, I just wanted to feel what it would be like to go to some place in VR that I could
just walk down the street and go to.
I can see how that wouldn't work out.
Yeah, it just didn't work.
But I had to do it.
And you know, now I know.
Now everyone knows.
If you create stuff that people already know, you see a lot more detail, because you know
how it should look and how it should feel.
It's the same thing if you're visiting stuff like a certain church in photogrammetry, for
example.
It's great, because if you've never been there, you can actually see it, and maybe you can
go to places that aren't available for the public.
But if you've actually been there, and you remember the smell and the sound of it, it's
great.
There's just something different that you feel like you're losing something.
It's like a shadow.
That's why you have to show stuff that you haven't experienced yet in our environment.
I mean, the same thing applies...
Like, we realized that early on with the avatars, too.
If you try to make...
Like, our avatars, the animation's pretty janky.
But if you put it in a cel-shaded context, you put it in a low-poly context,
the people's brains forgive a lot of the errors that come with doing procedural animation live.
It turns out there's a fair number, and it's a challenging thing.
We had the same thing with, for example, the Space Pirate Trainer guns.
They don't have hands.
I had a lot of comments about that.
And the reason why I didn't put hands in it is because it's very hard to know.
Next to the arm thing, it's very hard to know where the fingers are.
And it just breaks the illusion if it's not correct.
There are ways to handle this with the new controllers, because you're actually checking
what you're holding.
But stuff like that breaks the illusion.
It's still just inferred from other data.
It's not measuring one-to-one, which is kind of what you want for that.
All right, this is a good time for us to open up for Q&A.
So we're talking about all the visual stuff now, about environment, but I believe there's a lot more.
For example, don't underestimate stuff like first feedback.
Audio is super important.
Those two things actually spend a lot of time on all the first feedback in Space Pirate Train.
It's one of the reasons why it feels good.
Because every type of gun has its own kind of force feedback curve.
And so people actually feel which gun they're shooting, even if they're shooting blindly without sound.
Same thing with audio. Even if there's no music at all, there's still this environmental sound.
It just dips you in the whole environment. It's super important that the thing combined makes the whole experience.
And it makes the whole environment look so much better just because of those extra impulses.
I'm going to go on record and say I think for a believable environment, audio is more important
than your visuals.
Properly done audio with spatialization and in a good, you know, with the user having
headphones, you know, with no friction there, you can sell an environment with a black screen.
Yeah, no argument there for sure.
If you close your eyes and just have some audio of a forest, you actually are there
already and then the visuals come next.
We totally showed that on the Firewatch episode.
All right, anyone have any questions?
There's a, I guess there's a mic there,
other people can hear.
Would you like to, there's a microphone?
Yeah, there's a microphone.
I have a question for Will Smith.
This maintains a particular interest of mine.
I'm wondering if you're working with or thought of working with embryologists
so that we could relive our journey from conception to birth inside the womb.
Have that be very, very real for us.
I haven't, but if you know anybody who has 3D assets that they've built,
then connect me and I'll talk to them because it sounds like that would be fun.
Hey, this question's for Chris.
We heard from the others about their thoughts on
representations of the mundane world.
And with all your ideas about language and the language of
VR and stuff like that, I was wondering, you were the only
one that didn't answer that.
And I was wondering what your take on the role of the
representations of the mundane would be.
I think that
Adams' assessment is correct, which is that there needs to be a reason for the environment
to be interesting.
I mean, we could, it's true if we write a book, if I write like a very, you know, well
Well, if I was to write something that's a great description of a gas station, you may still not want to read it.
It has to have something. There has to be a reason for it to exist.
My game is probably, in terms of locale, the most mundane of the folks we have up here.
It's just a farmhouse in Kansas.
But I try to make it interesting by having things that happened in it,
or the objects in it be out of place,
or have objects or things about it that the viewer can't immediately understand,
so that there's a...
There's a story that's waiting there.
It's like a thread that they're going to have to pull out.
And it's actually OK that the environment itself is sort of
a relatable place.
In fact, it's important to me to
for that particular game, for you to be able to believe that this could happen to you.
We chose a non-realistic art style.
It's not super cartoony, but realism wasn't something we corrected for.
Because I actually think if the sound is right and if the world is consistent, even if the
location is sort of generally mundane, if there's something there, I think that's what
Adam's talking about when he says magic.
If there's something there, a reason for you to be there, a reason for you to explore that
world, then that is why you're there.
And all the world really has to do is reinforce that and be consistent.
About 30 years ago, Gerard Lanier used to hold fantastic VR classes at the universities
around town.
And the technology was very modest.
It was low-end Macs usually, Mac classics, running simple, you know, 3D packages.
But they were VR classes.
And a lot of the point he was raising in his lectures and workshops had to do with a kind
of attempt to identify...
You know, what he was looking for was a kind of universal language of communication within
VR, akin to, he called it body music, a kind of, you know, body language communicated through
simple gestures over a distance.
You know, a little bit like HTML and the web were an attempt to universalize text over
a distance, right?
And, you know, because universal ways of communication were the...
common thread in the early 90s.
And VR looked to be, at that time, another branch of that attempt to universalize communication
at a distance, except the ontology was one of continuous movement.
So with VR, you have the 360 experience, but also the gestures of the person.
There seems to be a tension now between an attempt to standardize this stuff because
the technology is standardized and the delivery mechanisms are increasingly commercialized
and standardized.
What are your views on that kind of legacy of the language of VR as a 30, 40, 50 year
set of research inquiries in relation to now?
Well, I'll just say one quick thing about that is we shouldn't be standardizing anything right now.
It's too early.
I mean, we're essentially in like 1905 with film right now.
I agree.
I don't think...
I think that the pace at which the technology related to VR is going to continue to dramatically
change is pretty fast.
We are a year and a half out from the very first commercial headsets.
The Oculus's touch controller shipped less than a year ago.
There's a lot of obvious technology that doesn't exist at a commercialized level today.
We should track your face. What if we knew your expressions?
What if we knew where your shoulders were doing?
What if we know where you're looking in the headset?
Yeah, I mean like, I feel like there are a number of sort of,
I won't call them low-hanging fruit, but clearly achievable in the next couple of years
sort of technologies that could...
Significantly change the way that we express ourselves in a virtual space and the fidelity
of those expressions.
So I think that probably the things that we see today are only very vague footsteps in
the direction towards what you're talking about.
The thing I'd say is that the standard is going to be what you can do with your human
body, not what Facebook says we can do or what Valve says we can do or whatever.
I agree.
Hi.
There's a few virtual worlds popping up
that are based on user-generated content.
And I was wondering what mistakes
you think a user might make when they're
building an environment, and what tools
you think users need to make virtual environments that
don't suck.
I mean, they'll make the same mistakes we made, right?
You just try stuff and you put your friends in it and they tell you that this makes them
feel bad or they like this and you just keep iterating until you find something that works.
I mean, maybe these guys have smarter answers.
Well, no, I mean, I think you're, I mean, the tricky thing about comfort is that
We can meet a certain level of comfort for a large percentage of people just by having good hardware.
We have a lot of good hardware now.
But that's actually not enough to make all experiences comfortable.
In fact, there's a huge swath of experiences, like Half-Life, for example,
that even on good hardware is going to make everybody sick.
So, what you don't see in the final product is that all the things that, you know, we tried in the production and it made people sick, we cut.
Because we don't want to make people sick.
So, there are, and there's just like super fascinating differences between the way that people feel discomfort.
I had a person tell me in early development of Dead Secret that they were uncomfortable because I placed them too close to a wall.
And they felt that they were, you know, their shoulders should be touching the wall but they couldn't feel it and that made them feel bad.
Yeah, I mean...
I think that users who are building this stuff for the first time
will just go through that same learning curve
and you'll have a lot of content that you cannot guarantee is comfortable
and the folks who are consuming that have to be sort of okay with that.
If you're not susceptible to motion sickness,
it's really good to have somebody on your team like Dirk, who is.
Yeah, I mean, I think Will was on point by saying you can make all the mistakes.
We built and deleted Adrift three times before we finished it.
It just, it didn't work because it was new.
It's amazing to have all the tools and it's amazing that people are out there making VR,
but you're just going to have to...
So that's how you find the good stuff, peering around in the dark and then accidentally figuring
something out.
And that's what's awesome about VR.
With user generated content, you're limiting, you're actually, probably the most common
use is just creating levels and stuff.
But most of the interactivity or the core thing is already programmed.
So I think...
Even for believing in a realistic world, it's all about these small interactive things and
the way you push a button and stuff.
So that's already done by the developer.
So we already made those mistakes.
If you're creating user-generated content, you're just going to create some mistakes
concerning environments, but not the interaction design, because that's what's already done
by the developer.
So I think it's just part of the mistakes that the developer made.
We got time for one final question.
Thank you.
Hello. This question aroused when Quark Cannon was speaking.
But anyone can answer it. You were talking about how you have to change the view of action
and going on in front of you and behind you. When is it appropriate or what type of games
would it be appropriate to have action going on behind you? I guess is my question.
It depends on how overwhelming something is.
If you put someone in a game and they use a lot of audio cues, for example,
where the user should look at, then you can try to implement some 360.
So, you don't know where people will be looking at.
So even when I put people into Space Park Trainer, they can't find the menu because
sometimes it's behind them.
So you have to direct the user where they're looking at.
And if you're creating a... you could do 360 experiences, of course, but you have to...
show the user where to look at.
And we do it, for example, when we're opening up the angle
for enemies, for example, like at first they just come
in the 60 degrees of field angle,
but they open up throughout the wave,
so they get further and further away.
And so one of the problems were if you weren't using audio
and it wasn't loud enough, you actually weren't looking
at where the droid was shooting from.
And so we implemented a system that was flashing
the right side of your HMD, so you had glow.
And then we actually felt like, oh, there's something happening in that part, and you look around.
So these are all cues that can be helpful for creating experiences that are more like a 360 and not 180.
So it's about audio-visual cues most of the time.
All right. I want to thank everyone for coming. I want to thank Dirk and Will and Chris for agreeing to do this with me.
Thank you very much.
Thanks guys.
And thank you for coming. Don't forget to fill out your evaluations and have fun in VR.
Enjoy VRDC.