How to get a job writing for games.
My name is Zach Aris, I'm the creative director
at Deck Nine Games.
I'm Tracy John, studio lead of narrative design at King.
So, thanks for coming.
Yeah, thanks for coming.
Why are we giving a talk about how to become a narrative designer?
It's because game writing is awesome.
It's one of the most, I think, privileged things you can do for a living,
is getting to craft interactive story.
It's really fun.
But the industry is really difficult to get into.
There's an opacity about how to get a job as a game writer
that we really want to kind of challenge and talk about.
And both Tracy and I have very different journeys
through our careers, and we thought it would be really fun
to kind of talk about what our stories are
from both angles.
So, we'll start, I'll introduce myself.
I'm Zach.
The first game I published as a narrative designer
was Kingdoms of Amalur Reckoning.
I worked on several RPGs before that
that were never released.
Then I went to college later in life, because I'm kind of a weirdo.
I studied classics, so ancient history, ancient myth, Latin, Greek.
Then I worked in TV for a bit.
Worked on the show Criminal Minds Beyond Borders, did some indie stuff.
And my last game was Life is Strange Before the Storm,
where I was the narrative director at Deck Nine,
and I was responsible for hiring and training
and leading the writers room that produced
a 1,500 page script for that game.
And I'm currently the creative director at Deck Nine,
driving our story-driven studio.
And a little bit about me.
So I had a bit of a weird career as well.
Weirdo in a different way though.
I started off actually as a games journalist
where I interviewed a lot of developers
and learned about the process of making games.
So I liked that so much I applied for a job
and got a job as a narrative designer at Gameloft
where I worked on licensed games and original IP.
After doing that for a couple years, I took a break from games and I went to do some corporate work.
But I included UX design for mobile apps and VR and doing some work for advertising.
But after that, I miss games so much, so I came back to King, where I am now.
So that's just to give you a little background about us,
but we can launch right into our tips
for the application process.
So first thing we get a lot of questions about
is the portfolio, where you want to present
your summaries of your best work,
and you want to be specific,
and you want to contextualize it.
So of course, CV, duh, you should definitely include that.
But also your published game work, if you have any.
If you don't have any published game work,
published game work, or published non-game work
is also great to put here.
But with that, also do whatever you put,
your best writing work.
So whether you've been published or not,
pick the stuff that you feel represents your best work.
And then from there, you want to, of course,
put work that's related to the jobs that you're applying for.
For example, if you're applying for a mobile game company
with a lot of match-three games, make
sure you have stuff that exemplifies that and not
just 100-page movie scripts.
So just think about that kind of thing.
And then of course, don't put too much. You don't have to put your entire body of work in your portfolio.
A lot of times employers won't necessarily be able to look through everything,
so pick your top work and put it on there.
And I would also say here, don't necessarily put writing tests that you've done for other jobs.
I just think, that's my personal opinion, I think Zach feels similar, but I would not do that.
It's more just to show that, you know, I don't want to see that you've necessarily applied to all these other places.
I don't want to see the great work you've done for other game companies, even though it's a lot of hard work.
Keep that for yourself.
Sorry, I'll show me. So some other tips though, as well for portfolio. I would
say if you can get help from a graphic designer or use a lot easy to read
website templates, there's a lot of stuff out there now. There's kind of no excuse
for a really ugly, illegible portfolio, even if you use a WordPress blog, a
Tumblr, there's a lot of templates out there that can really make your
portfolio legible.
If you can, describe what you did for the game.
I get a lot of portfolios that show me
like an awesome trailer and splash image
and there's nothing wrong with including that.
But maybe tell me a little bit about what you did.
Did you write the opening cinematic?
Did you write VOBarks?
Did you write the UI text?
Give me, you don't have to put the actual scripts
for those things, but at least explain
and give a little bit of context about what you did
for this amazing launch trailer game.
Yeah, so if you've never actually published a game,
or if you're working on something exciting,
but it's under NDA and you can't talk about it,
which is super frustrating when you have to apply
for a new gig, there's still ways that you can demonstrate
your skills and what you've learned.
I'm curious if I can ask the audience,
how many people here want to become a narrative designer?
How many people here have published a game
as a narrative designer?
OK, OK, awesome.
Congrats to everyone who has.
And for those of you who haven't yet, don't despair.
So what I look for when I'm interviewing writing applicants,
narrative design applicants, who can't talk about something
they published.
I ask them to talk about the themes and the elements of their work,
if they're not allowed to talk about it under NDA,
talk about the themes and the sort of foundational principles
of what makes it exciting to them.
Because I'm not interested in just hearing some title or IP.
I want to understand your mind at work.
I want to see you and hear you talk critically and passionately
about the elements of your story work that you find compelling,
that you think is exciting.
So maybe you're working on a new Walking Dead game and you're not allowed to talk about that at all
But you can talk about what it's like to write about
human existential dilemmas and how everyone's a fucking monster when zombies are in around or don't say zombies because
Because maybe that would break your NDA
But if you can talk about the work in some way that shows me your passion and your heart and your your critical thinking at
Work, I'm gonna get what I need from that conversation and I'm gonna get a better insight into who you are as a writer
Okay, so the cover letter.
It's basically an introduction.
You're telling your story to the company
that you're applying for.
Think about it like a story with an arc,
and the culmination of that arc should be
that you are destined to land comfortably
and naturally into the arms of whatever company
that you're applying to.
So tailor that story really to make a plausible case
for why you belong wherever you're trying to belong.
Include in that information about your writing experience,
published or not.
Talk about why, specifically, you want to work at the particular company that you're
applying to and demonstrate in the answer to that why an understanding of who they are
culturally, what their values are, what their body of work is like, and how you as a writer
will be able, through your writing sample, to immediately create value for them by writing
to their style, but to their voice, because that's what they're looking for.
And then maybe this is obvious, but include the name of the company in your cover letter.
Include an understanding of who they are and make it really, make a deliberate effort for
your cover letter not to sound like a form letter where you're just swapping out Blizzard
instead of Bungie and sending off the same cover letter over and over.
Awesome. And so now that you've gotten your cover letter down, submitting the
application. This is a little bit of housekeeping stuff but employers notice
these things. So I'm gonna harp on some really minute details here but you want
to keep it clear and concise but label the file names clearly with your name,
CV and cover letter. We get hundreds and hundreds of applications and if you just
simply put your name on there, you want us to be able to find you quickly when I
look in my folder of like oh I really like.
you know, this person's stuff. I want to be able to easily find it, so it's simple
stuff but please do that. And then when you do that, please label it clearly with
the name of the correct company that you're applying for. To Zach's point
earlier about Blizzard or Bungie, like I don't, this has happened to me where
I've gotten applications and they put the name of not the game company that
they're applying for but clearly another one.
just check those things because that even though you may have a fantastic
cover letter or CV and body of work, it's those little things that
like that attention to detail that's really like can be off-putting if I see
that you're you know put bungee and you're applying to King or something so.
that kind of stuff and then if the job description doesn't ask for writing
samples, send your portfolio link or a relevant sample anyway. I think some
companies might be either for legal reasons don't specifically ask for
samples or maybe it's a new person putting up a job
description and they don't include that but I think that if you just submit one
that will save the employer a lot of time because that's happened to me once
where someone for
someone, my HR person who forgot to post at please submit writing samples didn't
for like two weeks and then I got all these resumes but then no one submitted
writing samples with their resumes and then the ones I like just the CV, I had
to go back and ask them for their samples when I just feel like that
should just be a part of your application package. So just again, minor
housekeeping things that I think matter a lot for when you're applying for a job.
Yeah, so if you're applying for a junior role and you don't have any experience,
you're almost definitely going to have to take some kind of writing test.
You're going to get a prompt, a challenge, a window of time to complete something,
and then you get to demonstrate your writing ability under deadline.
How to do that well. Don't be late.
Game development is all about executing to a very specific and rigorous schedule.
If you're late out of the gate with a writing test, it's really going to hurt your chances.
If for some reason the deadline that you're given in the middle of the recruitment process
isn't something you can hit because of whatever's going on in your life, that's okay.
proactively ahead of time, communicate with the recruiting officer, whoever
you're talking to and say, hey I'm not gonna be able to hit that thing Monday
because I'm graduating from college on Saturday, can I get a couple extra days,
I'll be able to do it Wednesday by 5 p.m. Ahead of time, awesome. That's proactive,
that's a commitment that you're making and then execute and hit
that commitment. When it comes to the prompt itself, don't just jump in
and rush through.
Really think about what the prompt is asking you to do creatively.
Think about what the company you're applying to needs and what they want.
Usually a lot of thought has gone into the crafting of the writing test.
So really demonstrate an engagement, an equal engagement with sort of that level of care
and write something you're really going to be proud of.
On a higher level, consider who you're writing for.
and really try to demonstrate in your prompt
that you understand their voice and their style
and that you can execute to that level
and that if we were to hire you tomorrow,
you would be able to start creating value
writing within our voice immediately.
And then this is really crucial,
enjoy what you're working on.
I work with writers all day long at all levels,
and it's something that I have to remind people of
all the time.
But if you as a writer are not taking joy
in what you're crafting, I'm not gonna love reading it.
So even at the test level,
I think especially at the test level,
have fun with what you're crafting.
You're building something that's supposed to be
entertaining and compelling for your audience.
Focus on that and you'll generate something really great.
Okay, so you get through the writing process, the test,
and now you have an interview.
I want to encourage all of you to think about interviewing
not as demonstrating your worthiness to some institution
or body of experts.
It's not all on you.
You're really, it's a two-way street.
And ideally, applicants that I really resonate with
and want to work with come to the table
sort of striving to find whether or not
my company is a good fit for them
as much as they're trying to demonstrate
what they're capable of doing for us.
So do that.
I would say take time ahead and prepare questions
about the role, about the studio culture,
about the job and the other teams you'll be working with.
And take some time to think about difficult questions
that you'll get asked and prepare answers
in anticipation of that.
And look at your resume and say,
okay, so if I was gonna throw a really difficult question
at this person, what would it be based on their experience,
based on their body of work?
And then you won't be caught flat-footed,
except you definitely will be caught flat-footed.
But don't dismay.
I think in the middle of an interview,
if you get a difficult question, if you get a question that you
feel like, man, I really should know the answer to that,
and I don't, be honest, be humble.
One of the best answers I ever hear in an interview
is, oh my god, that's a really hard question.
I don't know the answer to that.
My best guess is this.
As devs, we are constantly confronted with things,
and we don't have any idea how to solve them.
We want to work with people who have humility
and have honesty, intellectual honesty and creative honesty
in how they talk about the work
and how they approach problems
that they're not necessarily sure about how to answer.
It's a process of discovery.
So demonstrate that honesty, demonstrate that humility,
and you're gonna be demonstrating a person
that I want on my dev team.
And then the same thing with the writing test,
enjoy the experience of interviewing.
Have fun with it.
Be excited to meet devs and talk to them about their work
and what they're working on.
Be excited to advocate for yourself and your experience
and your story.
Have fun, and you'll be performing a version of yourself
that ideally people want to work with.
And just also some additional tips based on the interview. I mean to what Zach was
saying before in terms of preparing, you know as employers I'm definitely gonna
ask you if you've played the games that we work on. You'd be surprised at how
many people actually don't do this before an interview. So it's not like you
have to finish them, it's not like you have to memorize them or complete
everything about them.
I would expect that you at least check them out
and have some general thoughts
or even just the context around it.
So, you know, Wikipedia's there.
Just, you know, look it up.
And don't, but definitely don't lie about it.
If for some reason you didn't play it or whatever reason,
don't say that you finished it when you haven't.
Don't, we will be able to tell.
So we'd rather you have an honest dialogue about it
than lie about it, so don't lie about it.
And of course be prepared to talk about the narrative design of either the games that the company are working for.
This goes to thoughtful preparation, but as well as just your thoughts on narrative design in general or games, you know, that we may ask
what's your favorite narrative design in other games? And so be able to talk about those in a passionate and informed way.
Be prepared to talk about your writing test.
We're gonna ask you your thought process.
We know that we gave you an impossibly short amount
of time to do it, so don't feel that you have to be
on the defensive about it.
We just wanna ask, why did you do this?
What did you think about this?
So it's not so much as a sort of critical feedback time
as much as we just wanna see why you did what you did
in such a short amount of time.
And yeah, more of a housekeeping thing, but a lot of times, this goes back to Zack's point about thoughtful questions,
but at the end of the interview, I'll usually ask like, do you have any questions for me?
And you know, I love questions about craft, how I manage you, you know, specific things about games we've worked on,
process, but a lot of times too, I'll get questions about like, oh, how many vacation days and things like that.
And those are all important, for sure,
but I would expect that you would ask those
from the HR person and not me,
and that makes me just think that,
oh, did you not have any other questions about the craft?
So just be mindful of that
when you're about to ask those kinds of questions.
But if you do the writing test, the interview goes well,
and then you got the job, hooray!
But now what?
Thanks, Zach.
So now that you've gotten the job, though,
we also wanted to talk about, if you get the job,
what happens afterwards.
And Zach is going to talk a lot about craft.
OK, so narrative design.
If you do everything right that we're talking about
with regard to labeling your CV, how
to navigate the writing process, the interview process,
but you are not growing as a writer.
One, I don't know that you'll actually get the job, sadly, but it's true.
But two, your work will grow stagnant and you're going to have a difficult time navigating
your career past this first opportunity when you finally get your foot in the door.
Okay, so the high-level question I ask all writers of all levels that I hire.
I asked them to define what their goals are as an artist.
And I would challenge all of you to think about that.
Almost agnostic of where you're working now
and where you're applying to next.
You should always be asking, who am I as an artist?
Who am I as a writer?
What are the stories that I want to tell?
What are the stories that are invigorating me
or challenging me?
And the purpose of asking those questions,
you should have answers to those questions,
cultivate answers to those questions.
That should change over time as well.
If you as a writer are not changing,
if you're not actively asking yourself
what you want to be in your artistic praxis,
and the answer isn't shifting to some degree,
then you are potentially falling into a place
where you will not grow.
OK, so who do you want to be as a narrative designer,
as a writer?
What kind of work do you want to work on?
As you're navigating the answer to that question,
curate.
a deep understanding of narrative media.
Maybe you only want to work in open world RPGs,
that's cool, play mobile narrative anyway.
Watch TV, watch film, be able to talk about story
in any and every way.
It matters at the interview level,
it matters in the day-to-day work,
and truly great writers learn to steal from anything.
And then in your own artistic praxis, not just as you're applying for a given job or one project after another,
just as you're building a body of your own work, be critical. Challenge yourself.
Recognize the fact that you are building a body of work,
and be deliberate about what it is you're choosing to write, where you're choosing to spend your creative energy,
in service of this larger question about what kind of an artist you want to be.
A really helpful aid in that journey is finding a writer who's more experienced than you are,
who will read your work, spend time with you, talk to you about what they're seeing, give
you notes, and challenge your thinking.
And they're not going to be right all the time, but you don't have to take every note,
but be committed to that kind of discourse about your work, and you will improve.
Abandon any kind of discourse about your work at that level, and you will not.
And be courageous.
And part of what I mean by that is...
I think bad writers fall into a habit of not challenging themselves to craft new things.
They either work on one thing that they've written that they like and they never put
it down and they keep polishing it, or they fall into a very specific niche with their
work.
They write for comfort.
They write because they fantasize about this particular job they want to have somewhere,
and that's really good, but in terms of growing as an artist, it takes courage to push yourself,
to write things you're not used to, to write in new media, and to write stories that are
maybe non-traditional for you. You will learn from that process.
Some more notes on crafts, but in addition to defining your goals and cultivating your interests
Take the initiative to improve yourself
And I think this goes for new narrative designers aspiring designers as well as experienced narrative designers
There's always always looking for ways to improve so some tips
whether it's your first narrative design job or your tenth
Always strive to learn about the other disciplines and departments and work together.
See what their thoughts on narrative are and how do you fit into their process and culture
as a narrative designer.
This will help you at any job that you go to.
Watch GDC talks. Thanks for coming to this one.
But there's also a ton of great stuff that happened this weekend and in previous years on the vault.
So, you know, everything is easily available now thanks to the internet.
So there's definitely no excuse and there's no shortage of narrative design media in terms of videos and books nowadays.
So there's definitely stuff everywhere. So no excuse to not check out that stuff.
Network, yes, that's why we're all here, isn't it?
But network, it's super, super hard.
As writers, I know we're all introverts,
and I mean, even me being up here right now,
I'm like, ugh, I gotta talk to people, but no.
But it's super important.
We wouldn't be here where we are without networking.
I mean, every job that I've ever gotten
was through someone I know or through a friend of a friend.
I think Zach's had some same thing.
So networking is super important.
So it's great that you guys are here at GDC.
But even if you can't come to GDC every year,
or you have friends who can never make it to GDC,
there's definitely local meetups that you can go to.
There's IDGA.
There's tons of stuff out there.
Or start your own group, and just
get people in your local community interested.
And you guys can all talk about narrative design
and share advice.
There's also a Facebook group that I'm a part of.
I could talk to you about it after.
That is all aspiring game writers and narrative designers.
So there's a lot of great places to network,
not just in person, but online.
Be critical of yourself, sure, you can always improve,
but also don't forget to be kind.
Narrative design and game writing is hard.
So, but with that being said, also be hopeful.
So, you know, throughout the years
I've gotten tons of rejections on stuff,
on jobs, on things I've written, on written pieces,
but you know what, never give up, never lose hope,
keep trying, you know, the first game's job
is the hardest one to get, but once you get that,
then your career will only keep growing, so don't give up.
Okay, so I give advice to people a lot of the time when I only have 30 seconds or
a minute, I basically distill all of my advice down to one thing.
which is being a good writer is about discipline.
I think we often get into this business because we're really excited by the things we consume,
the things that inspire us, we're passionate about it, and we think what if, it would be
so fun.
The actual practice of becoming a great writer is not, I think, succeeded in short bursts
of inspired creativity.
You find success when you develop habits.
Habits of production, habits of challenging yourself,
habits of writing and of networking
and really pursuing, almost aggressively pursuing
your growth.
And that just takes discipline.
If you can find that as a writer,
you will succeed, definitely.
We got the five-minute sign. So I'm gonna blow through the key takeaways to make sure that we have time for your questions
But overall don't forget
Be clear choose the best work that represents the job that you're applying for
Be concise choose samples of your absolute best work. Don't include everything and most importantly be yourself
Don't be afraid to show who you are
and your interest and your passion for storytelling,
no matter what it is.
Just authenticity really shines
when it comes to both your work
and in-person interviews.
Okay, so we said do lots of stuff the right way,
don't do other things the wrong way.
That's all good.
I love that bullet.
Just to calibrate your thinking,
this is what I tell aspiring narrative designers
all the time.
If you adopt a healthy practice of applying to places
and you accept the fact that you're gonna get rejected
100, 200, 300 times, I have been way more
than any yes I've ever gotten.
If you can accept that fact, you can almost court.
knows you cannot be afraid of rejection because it is inevitable.
It's not a question of if I get lucky, it's a question of when I find the right place
at the right time for my craft and the right studio.
And I, when I was desperately trying to get my foot in the door years ago, I derived a
lot of comfort from that.
And I know a lot of other writers who have too.
And then when you do succeed, remember to help the next person along the way.
Okay.
Thank you very much, everybody.
So we have a few minutes, but really we
have as much time as anybody wants, because there's no talk
after this one.
If any of you would like to ask questions,
I think there are microphones.
OK, we have a microphone.
Raise your hand or whatever, and we'll
stay and answer whatever you got.
Can we have everyone make a line, possibly?
Yeah, maybe a line makes sense.
Let's do that.
Hi, thank you guys for the talk.
Very happy to be here and listen to all your wisdom.
Question, so I have a lot of experience
writing poetry and prose,
not a lot of experience script writing.
And I've heard that when you apply for jobs,
you just submit screenplays or teleplays.
Can I get your feedback on that?
Yeah, okay.
Yeah, I'll answer, did you just take a picture?
Okay, I'll answer that.
It depends on what you're applying for.
So if you're applying for a company
that does cinematic work,
you should have a strong cinematic script, absolutely.
If you're applying for something that's maybe more prosy
and there are game studios out there
generating products like that,
I think prose is perfectly fine.
One of the last writers I've hired at Deck Nine,
the vast majority of her experience
is fan fiction and prose.
and we make highly cinematic content.
Her work was really great.
And so we were, and we talked in the interview for sure
about like how comfortable are you writing,
cinematically writing screenplays.
And she's much more comfortable with prose,
but I can use that tool in our process for sure.
And this I think goes to a higher level
piece of advice I'll share.
Build a portfolio that has an excellent cinematic piece,
a screenplay that you're really proud of,
a prose piece that you're really proud of,
and maybe start there.
Next level would be a Twine interactive something
that you're really proud of,
and you can submit the right piece for the right gig.
And then also, if they ask,
show the versatility that you've acquired along the way.
Thank you so much.
Hey there, first of all.
Again, thanks so much for doing this.
My name is Nick.
I'm a narrative designer and writer from New York.
And one thing I was interested in is, you mentioned the idea of finding a mentor, like
someone who you can develop a long-term connection with and who can really help push you forward.
My question for you is, do you have any advice for how to go about finding such a person?
Yeah, so I think that it's really hard.
Share your work in digital spaces, for sure.
Go to events like this and introduce yourself to people.
And then I think local meetups are probably your best bet.
You might find them themes toward narrative,
I'm sure you will, but even if they're just larger
IGDA groups, you can just walk around,
and I'm the worst at this, I hate networking,
but it's so important.
Go to those events, awkwardly introduce yourself,
talk about what you're passionate about,
and when you find someone who you think like,
oh, that guy's local, and he's awesome,
and he likes this thing that I also like,
and he's published that, ask him to read a piece.
I usually start with that.
Be like, hey, I really like what you're doing.
Would you mind reading one of my scripts
and telling me what you think?
And maybe you get one round of iteration,
that's more than you had before.
Maybe it starts a conversation or relationship,
a mentorship relationship
that you can get a lot more value of.
I would add to that, like online communities for sure,
and just like see who bites,
because I feel like I could do a whole micro talk
on mentorship because, you know,
be respectful of their time, like, you know,
pick your strongest thing and stuff like that,
but I think like there's also like IDGA,
Women in Games definitely has a mentorship
where you can even sign up.
I don't know if there's one for broader narrative design,
but maybe it's something we could start or look into,
but yeah, I think.
You know, online is definitely your best bet to start if you can't find people in person here.
Yeah, good question.
Hi, so first of all, a quick question.
You mentioned a Facebook group.
What is the name of that?
Just so I can look it up.
I think it's Game Writers, but, sorry.
I'm part of a lot of Facebook.
It's very, yeah, it's super generic,
so let me find that, and then I'll share it.
Whoever afterwards, off the mic, I'll share that with you.
So, with regards to writing samples,
what are you looking for in terms of length?
like shouting. Short is better than long. 10 pages of anything is a lot for me to
read right now. The best thing you wrote is 35 pages or 95 pages. That is not what
you should submit. Challenge yourself to write something new. A 10-page screenplay
that shows some witty dialogue, a clever arc, a fun moment, a filmic understanding
of narrative.
That's great, that's all I need to see.
Something that makes me laugh, out loud once,
and I'm like, oh cool, okay, I'm interested in this.
I wanna move the conversation forward.
But I've probably read about 750 to 1,000 submissions
from writers over the years now.
I've had people apply with 300 pages of work.
I don't even know where to start and so I don't read anything.
Because I don't have time because everything is on fire.
But like a ten page something and I'm looking, yeah, I'm going to read it.
So I really, that's where discipline comes in, but really focus on something, something
really tight, something short.
Just to add to that, I mean, it's more mobile,
so definitely if it's not 100 page scripts,
but even if you have, I don't know,
a movie script that's 50 pages or something,
I would say distill it down to your best scene,
but then also give us context for it,
so that way we can still get an idea of those few pages.
So that way you also aren't only writing,
I mean, if you have 10 page screenplays or less, perfect.
But if you have something that's longer,
but you still wanna show it,
I would say choose the best small portion of it,
but give us.
prose paragraph of context before we go into reading that. Thank you.
Hi, I'm curious what is the value of secondary skills when you're applying to
a narrative position and what is the best way to present them to a potential
employer? So by secondary skills do you mean like coding?
Yeah, coding art.
Yeah.
That's very valuable, I think.
The most important is your writing.
But the nature of the work that we make at Tech N9NE,
I don't hire any writer who can't code a little.
or pick it up very quickly,
but that's asking a much higher investment from us.
So if you have any experience in any scripting language,
that's great for me.
That never hurts in game development at any level.
Take one introductory CS class online
and you'll have everything you need as a narrative designer.
So include whatever language you did that in
and that's wonderful.
Did you have any other secondary skills?
None specifically.
No, but to that, I mean, for mobile,
I don't necessarily need coders, although if you
could do that, awesome.
But if you're an artist and you do storyboards,
or if you can draw somewhat and you do rough storyboards
to go with a piece that you wrote or a script that you
wrote, that's awesome.
if you have project management skills,
when you talk to me in the interview,
tell me your narrative process,
but how you've dealt with other disciplines.
So producer project management skills,
that kind of works as well.
So it depends obviously on what the secondary skill is,
but there are definitely ways to frame it
in this helps me as a narrative designer context.
Does that make sense?
Hey, I'm the... I serve as the dungeon master for my friends and Dungeons & Dragons and whatnot as a creative outlet
and, you know, making adventures and stories for my friends to overcome.
And recently I've considered maybe like writing those down to like little adventures and PDF files.
I was wondering if that's something that may be worth sending to potential employers as a work sample of
something that's not only writing but kind of design in its own way.
Yeah, that's a great question. I think it depends on the nature of what it actually looks like.
So if you're applying for a narrative design position, I would, unless they're asking for something like that,
what's a campaign you've designed? What's a story-driven campaign that you've designed?
It's actually a really cool question to ask applicants, but unless they're asking for that,
they're usually asking for something else very specifically.
Definitely have that other thing.
whatever it might be. I would say that that sounds to me like something that
could be a really interesting thing for me to find in your portfolio. You have a
website where it's listed, I discover that and I look at it and I'm
like, wow, this is really nerdy and really cool and it's showing a
design skill set that could accompany narrative really well. I think
that's great, but I wouldn't lead with something like that because you really
want to demonstrate whatever specific writing skill, the role you're applying
for needs.
I guess one more question would be,
so would something like a short story be more,
what I'd lead with?
Yes.
All right, thanks.
It could be a D&D short story, that's great.
Just make it good.
All right, guys, the AV tech is gonna have to,
you know, shut the mics down,
but you can still get your questions in,
just, you know, it's gonna be a little bit more intimate.
Everyone's gonna start, you know, sharing warmth.
Everyone huddle together.
But, yeah.
If you guys want to stay in here.
Can we stay in here?
Yeah, absolutely.
OK.
OK, we'll stay for like 20, 30 minutes if people want to talk.
Come on down.