Hi!
Merge Dragons is this game that came from seemingly out of nowhere to define its own
genre with this strange mashup of puzzle-like gameplay, little simulated creatures, and
building up a camp.
And then it takes this concept of merging and jams it very intentionally directly into
the game world.
What's up with that?
In this session, we'll answer, what's up with that?
Where did Merge Dragons come from?
And then we'll look at some of the design philosophies that helped shape it into the unique and wonderful experience that it is.
From how we think about merging everything, to why the design team worships discovery,
to the idea that merge dragons should actually be more of an activity than it is a game, and why.
And since it's free to play, we'll also talk a bit about how the game makes money,
including one balancing adjustment we made.
Which was pretty simple, but that fundamentally changed how players consume the game,
and in effect rocketed it from mere failure to great financial success.
And that for me as a designer was both astounding and somewhat unnerving.
So we'll talk about all that and plenty more, but my main goal for the session is for you to leave inspired.
If by the end you are inspired to think about design in new ways,
and you're even more inspired than you already are to make fantastic games,
Then the talk has succeeded.
So I hope to see you there.
It's Friday, 10 AM.
Bring your friends.
Let's pack the room.
It'll be great.