Hi everyone, my name is Emmy Jonasen and I'm the co-founder and CMO of Snowcannon Games,
an independent video game publisher.
I'm also the creator of IndieGameGirl.com, a blog that offers marketing advice for independent
developers.
My GDC lecture is going to be about marketing, Steam, and Vikings, or what we're calling
Viking enthusiasts.
More specifically, though, my lecture is about how Steam has become, especially over the past five years,
one of the most competitive platforms that developers can publish to today,
and how because of this, it's becoming more and more important that developers expand their game's
audience outside of just traditional Steam gamers to increase their chances of success.
Using the example of The Frost Rune, which is our point-and-click Viking adventure
developed by our clients Grimnir,
I'm going to illustrate how we tapped into a non-traditional Steam gamer audience of Viking enthusiasts
to generate results for our Steam campaign.
And while we think Viking enthusiasts are the best,
this lecture is not about us recommending that everybody market to this audience.
It's about detailing the scientific approach we took to identifying Viking enthusiasts
as a viable target market.
and the campaign that we crafted that generated results among them,
so that you can do the same with your game.
I'd also like to add that my lecture is not going to be a bunch of marketing fluff.
I'm going to show concrete examples of our campaign execution,
as well as real data from our campaign,
so that you can leave my lecture with actual advice
that can help you improve your own games marketing.
So if that sounds good, or maybe you just want to learn a thing or two about Vikings
and Viking enthusiasts, my lecture is going to be on Wednesday, March 1st from 11.30am
to 12pm.
And I hope to see you there.
Thank you.
Bye.