All right.
We're good to go?
So I've been told to tell you guys
before I start to turn off any noise making devices.
This is being recorded, so anything
that's not distracting from the presentation would be great.
Also, after the talk, if you could fill out
your evaluation forms, that's really helpful.
So please do that.
So.
First, I just want to thank all of you
for coming to my presentation.
It's a huge milestone for me,
and something I've wanted to do for a very long time.
And my apologies if I stumble over a few words.
I'm more than a little nervous here.
There will be time reserved after the talk
for what I'm about to show you.
If you have any extra questions,
we're gonna try to reserve time at the end of the talk.
The room that we'll be in is room 3000, which I believe is right across the hall.
Let me start by introducing myself.
So for those that don't know me, my name is Gavin Goulden.
I'm the lead character artist for Insomniac Games,
working on our upcoming Xbox One title, Sunset Overdrive.
Prior to this, I was the lead character artist on Bioshock Infinite for Rational Games,
and it's following DLC, Burial at Sea.
While working on these projects, I was mainly responsible for the look and feel of our characters in the game,
managing a small team, developing and maintaining best practices,
communicating with other departments to deliver what they needed on time.
Working on this project taught me a lot of lessons.
One of these lessons that I truly believe in
is the importance of iteration during development.
I feel that artists, and especially younger artists,
are told earlier in their career
not to get married to their work,
but aren't really given working examples
why they shouldn't be.
In this talk, I'll be using my team's work on Bioshock Infinite as an example, showing where we came from and where we ended up.
How if we had settled on the first idea that we had, it would have looked like a totally different game, and probably not as done so well.
I'll share the struggles of development, the processes taken, and the ideas developed along the way, and how we ended up with our final product.
Just gonna work this thing. Greg.
Alright, so during this talk, I'll be covering the process of iteration using examples from three different departments.
How their needs changed over time.
and how it required us as a character or team to change.
Narrative, the storyline of our game,
the driving force behind the final decisions made.
Overall art direction, aesthetic choices made
on environment side that influence our character's appearance
and the combat design more intense
than any game Irrational had ever made.
Most importantly, the lesson that I learned
from this project and hoping to show with these examples
is the need to embrace the organic nature of change
during game development.
Not everything can be planned for.
Features are cut once they are tried out,
and new features added.
Entire directions can change,
and it's our job as production artists
to adapt to those change and deliver high quality assets.
Before we get into these examples though,
I want to get some backstory.
This is how Bioshock Infinite started.
It was a dark, gloomy world with an Art Nouveau inspiration.
This is essentially a flying rapture.
Low visibility, populated by mutants,
and fantastical machines with a touch of horror.
These worlds were so similar that the development team
actually started referring to the world as Flapture.
Eventually, we felt we were not pushing ourselves far enough.
That the game would feel like a Bioshock 3, and not a Bioshock Infinite.
Which is a totally new game, and had plenty of fresh ideas, and a unique storyline.
Here you can see a great comparison showing what Emporia,
which is one of the final levels in Bioshock Infinite, originally looked like.
It's filled with carnival imagery, harsh lighting, and heavy fog.
It was a totally different world, and one that definitely belonged more in Bioshock 1.
This is another example of how extremely different the world was.
This is a shot of a level that would eventually be dubbed Town Center.
It's just an average environment for the game.
We intended to introduce the player to our setting.
You can see in these images we are holding on to our Bioshock 1 roots
into Rapture.
In a lot of ways we were holding back and just playing it safe.
It would have been easy for us to make this game as a lot of the team had already made it years earlier.
We wanted to do more.
We wanted to embrace the bright blue sky
and the idea of replacing New Year's Eve
with the Fourth of July.
This is the town center that everyone has seen.
It's an impressive reveal to a city in the sky,
above those thick clouds from previous shots,
replacing clowns for founding father statues,
and following the idea of having horror in broad daylight.
It was a huge departure,
an idea driven by our creative director, Ken Levine,
but embraced by the entire team.
It was fresh, it was a game we needed to make,
and we knew that as soon as we saw the changes side by side.
It felt new. It felt like we were no longer making just a sequel, but a game that would stand out on its own, and more importantly, stand out from other Bioshock titles.
Even though it was the right decision, that doesn't mean it was easy at all.
A change this big came well into development after lots of assets had been created and caused all departments to rethink.
how they were working and what their end goal would be.
Initially, there were some hard feelings,
lots of cool assets were getting lost,
and everyone loved the feeling of Bioshock 1,
but it was hard to argue with the new direction.
It was more ambitious, it was refreshing,
and it challenged us to move outside of our comfort zone.
And a major change came with Elizabeth.
Elizabeth is arguably the game's main character,
and what the entire story of Bioshock Infinite surrounds.
She needed to seem human,
she had to show a range of emotion,
and the player had to want to help her.
She needed to be interesting
and not feel like a burden during gameplay.
She was a major part of the story,
and not just a friend that you had to protect
from point A to B.
She wasn't just an escort mission.
Without question, Elizabeth became the backbone of our game,
and one of the major design pillars during development.
That wasn't always the case.
Here you can see all of the different faces of Elizabeth.
Many of which show up at some point during the game,
but a lot of the versions that were completely finished
that we just had to scrap because they weren't hitting the mark,
both from a narrative and aesthetic point of view.
In this section, we will touch on all these different versions
and cover the choices made along the way
to go from Gibson Girl to Femme Fatale.
Like many game companies, we start from a piece of concept art, ranging everywhere from thumbnail sketches to fully rendered illustrations.
Our concept artists try to convey the story we want to tell in the form of guidelines from modelers.
Just to get approval before jumping too deep into production on building a character.
In this case, our concept artists tried many different angles and the result is a more classical look for our companion character inspired by Victorian era outfits.
Our team went into putting this version of Elizabeth,
who at this time didn't even have a name,
into production.
The model came out great,
but her purpose had entirely changed.
The decision was made to have Elizabeth speak.
And though that may seem obvious now, she was originally intended to be a mute.
A quiet, mysterious character that would only show up during key moments in the game.
It became clear that this wasn't engaging to players.
This didn't help us tell a story because, well, she didn't say anything.
Without having that dialogue, it was extremely difficult to inform players
and to have them interested in helping Elizabeth along her journey.
This required us to go back to the drawing board.
Our story had evolved into a fairy tale-like arc,
where the player would rescue a young girl from a tower who had been there since birth.
While the purpose of that mission was dark and surrounding mature content,
Oh, sorry.
As far as I'm concerned, on your mature content,
the character needed to seem innocent.
She needed to seem like your help was needed
and that you as a player wanted to save her.
This meant dropping the formal gown,
putting her hair down,
and making her seem young and aloof
to the world outside of her prison.
We started to embrace the idea that Elizabeth was completely unaware of what acceptable fashion was.
Wearing a nightgown and boots with a roughly cut hairstyle that she did herself.
This implied that she wasn't used to being around other people
and certainly wasn't expecting company.
The problem we realized though,
as the model was complete and functioning in game,
is that none of that information was obvious.
It didn't read at all. It was too obscure.
Out of context, she looks like she could belong in any time period.
An outfit too generic to speak to a specific time period,
not detailed enough to stand out as a major character.
When put into a crowd, Elizabeth would just disappear.
Another thing that we had to consider
is that Elizabeth was now our main character.
She was the face of what we were doing.
She would be on posters, she'd be on game covers,
and hopefully be recreated in other forms of media.
She was the face of our game, and we had to ask the question,
do we really want the face of our game to be a girl in a nightgown?
The answer was no.
We needed to push harder and create something that stood out,
an outfit that was more iconic and unique to our title.
we had to give up details from our older versions
and just built her outfit completely from scratch.
This took back and forth from our concept artists
and modelers, trading paint overs and feedback
to really nail something special.
At this stage, we had also gotten more comfortable
with our tools and were ready to give Elizabeth more polish.
This meant developing technology just for her.
Our team created custom shaders, implemented Apex cloth,
authored unique textures, and took multiple passes on an animated rig
to literally make her one of a kind.
These changes also came with the pressure of our up-and-coming reveal.
A video of our game would be seen by the public for the very first time,
and it became all hands-on deck to make sure that it was impressive.
Elizabeth would be front and center, showing off her abilities and giving a fairly good example of how you would interact with her during gameplay.
Reacting to minor feedback after the reveal and addressing minor polish that we had been meaning to work on as an art team, like revising her facial features, costume tailoring, and her hair rendering, we had landed on our final Elizabeth.
As you can see, like I had mentioned before...
She broke all of the rules,
and had a budget that blew most of our assets out of the water.
A poly count almost three times higher than the average character in Bioshock Infinite.
Skin materials and hair materials seen on no one else,
and are tailored specifically to ideal viewing conditions just for her.
A completely unique rig for her character, with a facial rig having cinematic controls,
and at least double the amount of draw calls as everyone else in the game.
Having these specs on every character in the game would have had our rendering engineers hating us.
But for Elizabeth, it was necessary.
She needed to stand out. She needed to be the best looking asset in the game.
In the end, assets were tailored around her to ensure that she looked ideal.
Lighting was revised to make her look good, and budgets were adjusted around her just to make room for her assets.
And when you compare what the final Elizabeth looks like
compared to her initial version,
even in earlier test cases,
it is a night and day difference.
It took lots of days from different departments
to get her just right, and it shows.
Embracing changes that needed to be made
to create the best end result.
Once we had settled on our Elizabeth model,
we felt that she was straying away from the original idea
that she was an innocent person trapped in a tower.
The corset version of Elizabeth had all of the notes that we needed to for later in the game,
but wasn't fitting the first impression that we wanted to give.
We had to show that the character progression throughout the game and sell the story that the Elizabeth that you meet at the beginning of the game
isn't the same Elizabeth that you leave at the end of the game.
We decided to have different outfits represent different stages of her evolution as a character.
The first outfit would push that she was considered young and an innocent person who was unaware of the outside world.
Our concept artist referenced children's uniforms at that time to help show the ideas
and we put into practice creating a brand new model.
This led to another problem that couldn't be predicted.
With level shifting around in the game,
areas being cut or shortened,
and key story moments being tightened throughout the game,
we realized that the Elizabeth in the corset,
the one that we had spent so much time
developing and perfecting,
was slowly taking a backseat in terms of screen time.
The younger Elizabeth is now becoming a more major asset,
and not just something brief
that you see in the beginning of the game.
With more attention and focus, this time we needed to spend more effort into making her asset more appealing.
The initial take, while accurate to the clothing of the period, was looking too frumpy and almost too childish.
After trying different color combinations and passes on trying to improve the fidelity of the model, we needed to do a complete overhaul.
Around this time, Ken had seen redesigns of Disney princesses done by an artist named Claire Hummel.
We had always considered Disney to be a great reference for Elizabeth
and wanted to capture that same sense of wonder in the designs that Claire had done.
So we just contracted her to create a design for our younger Elizabeth.
This new design had brought Elizabeth to a more relatable age,
had a cleaner color scheme, and still fell within our turn-of-the-century time period for clothing.
With our Elizabeth assets locked down, we could focus on taking her further in other ways.
We created damage states in each of her models that would be swapped in throughout the game.
This helped tell a smaller story and keep things fresh and interesting
and show minor progression with her changes to her model and textures
caused by things like major combat in the game,
crawling through vents or over rubble.
We made these model swaps whenever Elizabeth went off camera,
essentially despawning one version of her and replacing her with a new version.
It helped make Elizabeth feel more alive,
and was a fairly quick thing to create that really went a long way.
Another level of polish that we added to Liz is her ability to spot things throughout the game.
Play custom animations and comment on them, on the things that she saw in the world.
This also involved emotional animations that would be added to her animation sets,
which helped make Liz seem like she was reacting to the world around her.
Finally, after we had shipped Infinite, it was time to look at DLC.
We wanted to deliver something that had been requested by fans of the franchise
and elaborate more on an alternate Rapture that had been explored in previous titles.
This meant converting the roles for our characters from Infinite
into something more fitting for Rapture.
Namely, creating a femme fatale version of Elizabeth that would be right at home
in movies and pulp fiction of that time.
In many ways, the DLC Elizabeth is a more compressed version of the lessons we learned in the core game
that you will see in the next few slides.
We completely started from scratch and had a healthy pre-production for a time for a project of that size.
Our concept artist, George Lacera, referenced a lot of fashion from the time period
and took stabs at different takes on a femme fatale for Bioshock.
bringing in narrative, animation, and modeling into the conversation.
We wanted to settle on something that was both readable as Elizabeth,
but also reused her rig and animations from the core game.
After deciding on a concept, we moved forward to creating a new version of Elizabeth.
Once we put her into the game, we realized that,
much like the younger version of Elizabeth, like from before,
she just wasn't looking right.
We took the idea of her being clean, dressed in white,
and taking lessons of makeup and lighting from that time a little too seriously.
After trying a few different tweaks, trying to polish the textures,
and pushing the model around, we just decided to start over.
Essentially, there were just too many small things that just built up into a complete rework.
It would have taken longer to rework the character to address all of the feedback,
rather than just recreating her costume from the ground up.
At this stage we kind of went rogue.
The concept artist, myself and Ken,
worked together at my desk to speed up iteration time
and to get all the features that Ken had requested
into the asset as well as addressing art-related bugs
that had been bothering us.
Things like how her hair was rendering and sorting,
we updated her eye textures to introduce
new parallax rendering, the cut of her dress,
how she deformed to her predefined rig,
and things like that.
We decided that it was quicker just to work at the modeling stage
and review it in game since we were basically trying just to hit that last 10%.
The concept of the character was correct, it was just a matter of execution.
This meant lots of color choices, lots of different takes on accessories,
and generally lots of iteration on smaller details in the model.
Lots and lots of iteration.
So many color choices ranging from Scarlet Elizabeth
and trying to reuse the color scheme from the core game
and attempts to make different accessories
to give her some kind of points of interest.
Here you can see what the final product is that we felt as a team.
Really nailed the feeling of a femme fatale Elizabeth.
It was a nice translation of a popular character from our core game
into a different time period
and different setting that was familiar to our fan base.
In this next session, I'll be covering how a massive change in our direction
caused us to rethink how our general population
uh... causes us to rethink our general population and how embracing a standardized
standardized system
allowed a very small team to develop assets
uh... quickly and consistently.
making better friends.
As our art direction evolved,
it required us to take a hard look at our general population
and how they were fitting into our changing world.
The result was a complete facelift,
bringing our heavily stylized characters
from an art nouveau setting
to a more relatable, period-appropriate look
that you can see in the final game.
Using examples that span over four years of development,
I will show how changes such as these gave us
more grounded characters in the world,
a more repeatable population,
and a more consistent art style.
First I'm gonna take a drink though, if you don't mind.
The main issue we faced when deciding to move from a darker, Victorian-style environment
to a brighter, turn-of-the-century setting
is that our characters no longer fit both the tone of the game
and overall visual fidelity.
Given how long the project was in development,
gradually over time it was very clear that assets
that were created at the beginning of the project
how they look compared to the ones created about a year or two after.
Changing our game's setting required a complete overhaul on our characters
to take them from a mutated appearance to something more relatable.
We needed to reinvent our characters to properly fit their new home
and not seem like they came from an entirely different world.
While it was always fun to make monsters
and we were happy with the work that we had originally created,
as a team we decided to start over and recreate every asset
to support the driving art direction on the environment side.
Originally, we followed a model similar to Bioshock 1,
where all civilians were actually aggressive characters
who would either attack you on sight
or just be doing crazy things like eating trash
and swatting at flies that didn't exist.
Artistically, they were very similar to splicers
and followed a much more stylized appearance
with exaggerated proportions and overly expressive faces.
With the change in direction, it was also decided and became pretty apparent that this world would have many repeated assets.
We were actually creating a population to live in the world, and using faces like these would have had obvious repetition.
It was very easy to pick out features on certain characters, as you can see up here, and that was a problem that we wanted to avoid.
Creating assets in this way also meant that
artists were free to model and texture however they wanted,
as long as the final results looked good.
The final result artistically was interesting
and it did look good,
but it meant that every asset was created uniquely,
which led to inconsistent poly counts, UV layouts,
and texturing everything from scratch.
With the workload ahead of us,
and really only having three team members,
we knew this was not sustainable.
These assets also had unnatural proportions
that was more fitting in our stylized world
than our more realistic one
that would eventually be Columbia.
Our textures were also authored in a much more painterly way
and the overall tailoring of our outfits
were both too damaged and not period-appropriate clothing.
We really wanted to move away
from our civilians looking crazy
and wanted them to appear like people
in the photos from that time.
Much like the problems that we experienced with our civilian heads, the bodies were also very inconsistent.
Dropping our assets into a crowd, the textures we created were so distinct
that it became very hard to repeat the characters.
The color choices, the patterns, and types of models were too obvious.
And even if they looked good on their own, had very obvious repetition.
This method of working also left us with no clean way of kit bashing assets.
Every asset was essentially created uniquely,
and it had become very difficult to reuse any amount of work from one character to another.
We started making baby steps in terms of quality to match the environments being built in-game.
This meant building higher detailed sculpts,
more photorealistic textures,
and bringing the proportions to a more realistic space.
These behavior setups were in the right direction, but we really needed to push it further.
This is an example of our general population at the time.
Generally, characters were still looking very distinct, they were still too stylized,
and it was very easy to pick out specific heads.
And quality-wise, we still had older assets that were just throwing off our overall look.
um, spawning characters in a test level during an art review
and having one incredibly mutated face show up every now and then
seem more like a bug than an artistic choice.
We're also suffering similar problems with our bodies.
Some characters were still wearing ill-fitting dirty clothes
and the costumes were very very easy to pick out in a crowd.
These also became distracting.
In Bioshock games the
environment is generally an explorable area that we wanted players to experience
and having characters stand out too much
just drew too much attention
rather than having them fade into the background.
So it was becoming a pretty big problem.
The solution to these problems was to create a universal system.
This meant creating a base character that all future characters would be derived from.
Our heads had shared topology, UVs, and facial rigs.
This allowed us to rig heads in more or less one click of a button,
share elements of textures easily,
and reuse elements of the models from one character to another.
By establishing these constants throughout the game,
it was easier to make swooping changes
and to control the overall quality of our assets in game.
This workflow had us working mostly in ZBrush.
By having a scope that we could pull from
that had our universal vert order and UV layout,
we could basically drop it down to the lowest subdivision level,
press a button,
and have it rigged asset ready to go in Unreal pretty quickly.
By having a shared asset that we pulled from,
it also allowed us to work much quicker
and also establish an expected final result
that was easy to compare new assets to.
Rather than taking a shot in the dark and trying to have assets match a loosely defined style,
we had a very strong foundation that served as a quality bar artistically and technically.
It set a standard.
By changing to this workflow, it also removed most of the tedious work from our day-to-day jobs.
By not needing to unwrap every head...
create every low-poly model, and create a unique facial rig for every head,
we could focus on making art and pushing the quality of our work.
By establishing rules, it actually gave us more freedom.
Defining restrictions, what we could and couldn't do,
it allowed us to focus on quality and keep what was under the hood consistent.
As the world expanded and certain scenes in the game were developed,
the need for larger crowds became stronger.
We needed cheap assets to fill up areas.
Our general population assets were correct and looking great,
but the amount of joints, verts, and loaded textures on screen were too much for consoles to handle.
The solution was to create cheaper versions of these assets that had limitations.
Essentially making much lower vertex counts, heads, and bodies baked down into just one material,
and a heavily reduced rig, and no artificial intelligence.
We took to calling these characters chumps.
A really dumbed down version of our main character assets.
These assets were surface transfers, and basically an LOD of our major assets.
Over time though, these characters were put more under the spotlight
and their quality just wasn't holding up at all.
And to give us one last push to reach a desired quality level, a strike team was formed.
to tackle a large chunk of our town center level and bring it to a final version.
This involved all disciplines and art working together on a specific area.
Character, concept, environment art banded together to set an exemplar
for what following assets would live up to.
In this area, our crowd assets, or our chomps,
were a big focus for the character department.
To improve the quality of our assets,
we developed sets of characters per level.
Rather than cramming a bunch of characters
onto a retrofitted texture sheet like before,
we created characters in a modular way
with the intention that they would be repeated
a lot throughout the game.
These assets became easier to manage as there were just fewer pieces to update
and generally cheaper because they were purposely made to share single assets
across at least four characters.
Another friendly character, or characters, that came up during development were the Lutece twins.
It's interesting to think that these characters started off as just a name,
just a brand, and something that you never actually saw,
but turned out to be one of the most popular characters in the game.
The original direction for these characters is that they were identical.
They were literally the same asset,
but one had a beard and the other one was in a dress.
Obviously, this is a horrible idea.
It was one of those ideas that seemed fine on paper,
but just looked bizarre in practice.
The information wasn't reading,
and instead just gave us two characters that looked...
off, basically.
With the importance of this character increasing,
and wanting to move this asset into the quality of our main characters,
we needed another pass.
We decided to contact Claire Hummel again, since she did such an amazing job on Elizabeth.
We wanted to apply the same lessons we learned there and apply it to these set of characters.
And it was a huge success. The new version took a more simplified costume,
made bolder choices with the tailoring, and had great similarities that implied these characters belong together.
And finally, to ensure that we delivered a game with the highest quality possible,
I booked at least a month of polish time
for my team to get one final pass on the characters in the game.
Over time, like I mentioned before, we developed techniques that improved our assets
and left some assets needing to be brought up to a desired quality level.
We had developed techniques for baking in subtle lighting information,
corrected topology, and weighting methods that gave us better deformations.
Having this time allowed us to make sure that every asset had this exact same treatment.
And now some pretty staggering before and after images of our characters.
Most of these are from our initial push to drop stylization
compared to the final asset.
So it's about a two-year difference.
Here you can see one of our Asian civilians that was part of our general population.
and this is one of our Caucasian civilians seen in Columbia.
Many of our civilians from the Finkton area,
which is shown in a teaser video,
were pushed almost too far
into looking comedically poor.
Eventually we pulled back and made this information more subtle.
This asset shows the process from beginning to end,
one of our dockworker assets.
Oddly enough, this is the first and last character
that I worked on in the project.
Having started with a burly,
start-up character that involved a more period-appropriate,
just repeatable dockworker that properly fit into Columbia.
And finally, an example of how one of our female civilians changed from a more fantastical, unrealistic outfit into something much more cleaner and period appropriate.
For a lot of our civilian outfits, we actually looked towards the 1920s for tailoring.
Even though it was out of our time period, the style of the 1920s were creeping into the late 1910s.
This meant that better fitting clothes and more interesting colors and patterns.
And here you can see us going from a completely made up outfit on the left
to something more Victorian and then something more Edwardian.
In this last section, we cover my favorite characters from Bioshock Infinite.
This is the Vox Populi and the Founders Combat AI.
At Irrational, we greatly improved the appearance of our combat AI characters,
from Bioshock 1 to Bioshock Infinite.
After collaborating with our designers, we were forced to rethink how we handle character art
and a combat scenario.
This often required new models, re-evaluating silhouette,
the importance of color between factions,
and a tiered armor system unique to Bioshock Infinite.
Initially, there were no factions.
Our characters were literally splicers in a Victorian setting.
They wore regular torn-up clothes.
They were heavily mutated.
The first concept, as you can see here,
is that everyone was against you.
So every character you met was trying to kill you.
As we populated the world with regular people,
and the story behind Columbia and its struggle developed,
we really needed to split who was trying to kill you
from who just wanted to talk.
This forced us to start thinking about
who enforced the rules of Columbia,
who was trying to stop you on your mission,
and how to break them away from the crowd.
The combat system in Bioshock Infinite
challenged our team in a way no other project before it had.
Though you still had plasmids and guns under the hood, it was a completely different game.
In Bioshock Infinite, we had actual roles within factions, and both needed to be defined.
You needed to be able to pick out the shotgun guy from the machine gun guy, and they needed
to stand out from civilians so that you could easily detect a threat.
Infinite also had huge draw distances that required us to create characters that were more noticeable from a distance,
and given how many different types of characters were on screen, required us to share assets and overall proportions.
Initially we followed the same system as Bioshock 1 had and tried to apply the mindset to these requirements for Bioshock Infinite.
We found that the idea of anyone being anyone is horribly flawed and just confusing.
If any character can pull out a gun and kill you, not only is it confusing, but you're constantly on edge and never really told when the combat begins or ends.
which really fought against the idea of us wanting you to explore the city of Columbia.
Technically, we also tried following the same path as Bioshock 1
by manually placing each and every character as a unique asset.
Placing these characters also became very tedious and hard to iterate on.
Essentially, every spawner needed to be manually placed.
Once that spawner was placed, an artist or designer would need to access its properties
and point it to the correct skeletal mesh.
While this may have worked on Bioshock 1, it quickly became too much to handle in Infinite.
It was nearly impossible to control what assets showed up where,
where assets were being referenced and left a ton of room for human error.
To make this process easier, we developed an override system.
The override was assigned per asset
and had a drop-down box that had a list of options.
These options were defined by artists that referenced the list of characters.
By doing this, designers could just select what kind of character they wanted it to be
and we, as artists, populated what the character would look like.
This means we only needed to update one asset,
and it updated throughout the game,
rather than making sure each spawner was referencing the correct asset.
This also made randomization automatic.
If there was more than one option in the list,
rather than having each spawner manually tweaked
to be different from the one next to it,
the problem that this exposed, though,
is that Unreal stores all of the model and texture information
into memory before choosing which one to render.
Meaning...
The base match that we were originally trying to replace,
or that we had on the spawner and would be replacing,
was stored into memory.
And then the one replacing it
and all of its alternative options
were also stored into memory.
Together, this made one combat character
cost nearly as much as a main character.
The solution to this problem.
was the wrong box.
Every base mesh in the game is a giant pink cube with a placeholder texture
that costs virtually nothing.
It shares the same rig as all of our base humans in order to bring in animations.
since that was a requirement for the actual override.
But other than that, it's practically free.
This meant that all we were ever paying for is the asset being referenced in the override.
If an override wasn't present,
the giant box would appear and let you know that something had gone horribly wrong
and that an override needed to be assigned.
Our combat characters weren't just bullet sponges.
They were also a big part in telling the story of Columbia.
This world wasn't just civilians with people who had a chip on their shoulder.
They needed a military force to protect them
and the ideals of Comstock, the city's leader.
Even though they shared the same rig as our civilians,
having a uniform that they wore as well as having a unique headset
that was only ever used on aggressive characters
really helped us define what a threat would look like in the game.
Another challenge we faced on Infinite that was completely new to our team
was the introduction of a second faction.
Early on, we had known that there would be someone else that you fight,
but had no idea what that would be exactly.
We asked ourselves who these characters were,
and the answer was a faction that rebels against the founders
and symbolizes the voice of the working class.
It was the Vox Populi.
Much like the founders, they had to stand out from the civilians in the area.
Rather than creating a uniform for them though,
we decked them out in military gear from the time
and used color as a visual language.
for the factions that you were fighting.
Blue generally symbolized the Founders' faction
and red symbolized the Vox Populi.
By using colors in this way and keeping them consistent,
it helped to inform the player who was a threat and who was not.
So, for example, a civilian would never be wearing a red shirt
and were generally kept away from those colors and left in a more neutral area.
During the completion of Infinite, we pushed really hard as a team to deliver the product that we wanted to.
In this push, we had lots of feedback from focus testing,
and decided that we really needed to push our combat characters further.
We needed to show progression more clearly, and to find tougher enemies from the weaker ones.
Working directly with my art director, we created new combat characters in a freeform way.
Time was definitely a factor at this point, so we just worked at the model level.
Looking at elements that worked on older passes...
on the models and also wanted to preserve ones from the higher level characters.
The result was to create three tiers per combat role per faction.
Due to how many of these characters are on screen
and given how pressed for time we were,
we ended up sharing a lot of elements between characters.
Using Unreal's attachment system,
we added fully rigged armor that was built over a base model
and unique head attachments per tier.
Since we were only ever adding attachments,
the major cost came from the base mesh,
and each armor set was added on top of that,
rather than loading in and rendering
three completely unique body assets.
Here you can see working examples of the system in place.
It's three completely unique assets
that heavily relied on kitbashing
and the sharing of assets to speed up workflow.
And here you can see the opposing faction using a similar process just in their own style.
After exploring the Vox Populi more, we were able to really have fun with their designs.
These characters were contrasted against the uniform, standardized nature of the founders,
and were able to create their own costumes,
using the idea that these characters fought their way up to the top
and purposely wanted to be scary and violent.
We covered them in red paint, gave them devil horns,
and more torn up elements to their outfits.
Not only did it just look cool, it also really helped show the difference between the two factions.
Another element to our combat system was the idea of heavy hitters.
These characters way back in the dark, cloudy Flapshire setting were originally just going to be flying big daddies.
While that is still a great idea, it fit more with what we wanted Songbird to be.
These characters needed to be obvious threats in the combat scenario.
Sometimes towering over a crowd and easy to identify.
These elements also had their own rule set and unique versions per faction, their own rigs and higher budgets.
They were more fantastical and were designed to purposely be action figures,
which made us ask if we would want this character sitting on our desk.
A lesson we learned during development was to take a step back
and look at every character we have in a line.
Does it show clear progression?
Can you easily identify one character from another?
This led us to create what we were calling a dinosaur chart.
It was a huge image that we actually had printed and posted in the office
right at my desk
that showed every enemy you would ever encounter in the game
and how they stacked up against one another.
This allowed us to really have a bird's eye view and not work in a bubble.
After having our heads down for so long,
it was easy to focus on characters in a specific area rather than seeing the big picture.
By doing this, it also helped us pick out problems across the board
and tweak assets until they all reach a consistent quality level.
In these next few shots you can see the end result of a lot of iteration on our characters.
Imagine how the game would have looked if we had stuck with our original plan.
You can see characters that fit properly into the world that we had created.
More relatable characters that seem like they had chosen to defend against you
rather than just being plain old crazy.
Clearly defined threats with specific roles in combat
and tier level of difficulty throughout the game.
and a second faction of enemies that were clearly different
from the characters you encountered earlier in the game.
It took iteration, multiple passes,
and a hard look at what we had in the game to make it right.
Sometimes tough, painful choices.
It meant throwing away work that we had done,
in some cases we're happy with and proud of
for the greater good of the project.
In the end, game development is a team sport.
It isn't about personal statements and what individual assets you can point to and say mine.
It's about delivering the best possible product as a whole.
Fulfilling the needs of the team with high quality work.
Even if that means changing the work that you personally loved.
I hope that these examples prove that we as artists cannot be married to our work
and the ability to adapt to change and drop any personal attachment
and embrace the organic growth of development over time
as a necessary step in creating the best product possible.
not only for a AAA development, but for indie developers, student projects, and personal work as well.
Be honest with yourself.
Look at how your work contributes to the game as a whole,
and put the needs of the project before your own personal preference.
After reviewing these examples, I want you to go back to work, back to your school projects,
personal projects or mods, if that's even still a thing, with these lessons in mind.
You will lose work, but you're not wasting your time.
Just because your own work ends up getting thrown away,
it doesn't mean that it was a complete failure.
Even the thrown away work is contributing
to a bigger, better end result.
Not every contribution needs to be in the shipping game,
and no one expects that all of your work will be perfect.
To be blunt, get used to it.
It happens to everyone, on every project, no matter what the size.
On Bioshock Infinite, the estimate is that we created around three games worth of content.
And that could sting, but the end result is something better because of it.
Also, making games is a team sport.
Never forget this.
This is possibly one of the most beautiful things
about our industry.
There are many moving parts with all sorts of disciplines.
Moving at the same time, racing to the final goal,
but we're doing it together.
Other departments rely on you
just as much as you rely on them,
and it is important to respect that level of communication
and expect back and forth between departments.
Account for change in quality over time.
Every project, from the smallest personal project to the largest AAA blockbuster, will have a range of quality in it.
At the beginning of the project, you're getting the feel for it. You want to see what works.
As you get better, and everything is moving around you, the art that you did months or years ago will look worse.
You can try to polish it as you see it, but by doing that, you'll either spin your wheels, or end up in the exact same situation months down the road.
Block out time for polish.
Give yourself and your team one last chance to send out their work out the door and be proud of it.
Finally, great ideas happen naturally.
During development...
It is very common for fun things to happen naturally through playtesting and experimentation.
Fun is what makes a great game.
It is our job as production artists to try and let those things happen.
We are in a creative industry.
It would be incredibly boring and tedious if you sat down five years ago and planned out every detail.
Be patient and be part of the upcoming changes.
Encourage your team to be creative.
Enable them to let awesome things happen.
So.
When the combat designer comes to you and says that the player will be ripping off heads with a giant hook,
you put in the extra time to make some meaty bits.
And...
I am...
done.
So, thank you.
So you guys can like line up for questions if you have them.
I actually have a few infinite Steam codes
for the first two people to ask me questions.
Willing to just hand them out, just come up to me after the talk.
And also...
having just won a visual arts award.
That's one of the points, each of the team that's responsible for it.
This would be all of our Twitter using art members from Bioshock Infinite.
So, be sure to hit them up and aggravate them for me.
So when you guys outsourced Claire was she just a concept or does she do the concept and the 3d?
For the new characters like Elizabeth and the twins. She just did the the concept art. She was like a remote artist that did
Combat designs and basically went through the whole process
With her so like starting with like thumbnail sketches, and then like the final like rendered things she actually went a little bit
Overboard with it and did like more breakdowns on how costumes from that time
worked and really helped our models.
But we did it all.
We did the modeling all in-house.
Okay, cool.
Cool, thank you.
Can you talk at all about any kind of iteration
in terms of shader and material stuff,
considering your original art style is so different
from the lighting situation that you ended up with?
Yeah, we actually originally started with just like an out of the box like Unreal Shader, Unreal 3.
And eventually converted into a physically based rendering setup.
So we actually like completely gutted our entire material breakdown.
And it's something that's more like the metalness setup that you've probably seen online.
But before that it was like a traditional, you know, spec diffused normal kind of thing.
And like moved over to like PBR about...
About like a year and a half before finishing.
So.
Yeah.
What would you do differently?
What's that?
What would you do differently if you had to do it over again?
Um to speed up the iteration.
The speed of iteration, I think I would have
put in the standardized system a lot earlier.
I think even with the heavily stylized setting,
we still could have done it and still had
that kind of look, but with just a more constant thing that you could predict.
I think we held on to unique assets a little bit too long
that caused problems that we could have avoided.
Did you notice there was a lot of burnout
because of all the iteration?
No. I mean, you know, we're all kind of on board for it. You know, like, redoing, like, main characters over and over again. It can get to you. But, you know, it's for the greater good. And we all, we were all, sorry I got like a light right in my face. But we were all like, we were all on board for it. And all of like the decisions were like communicated. And it made sense. And in the end, you know, it's like hard to argue with, right?
Right, yeah, absolutely.
Thank you.
Yep.
Given the themes and the time period of the game,
when you guys were approaching design
of some of the more racist or hateful imagery,
did you have to tone that back and keep control?
Or how did you approach that, knowing that you
had a broad audience?
Well, I mean, you know, like a lot of games were generally were made up of a group of people from different backgrounds and stuff like that.
So, you know, we all had it like internal feedback on whether or not it was a good idea to go forward or not.
We have, there were some things that we pulled back on that, you know, hasn't been revealed and things like that.
Like some original ideas that I'm not going to say here.
But, you know, there's some things that you just try it and just, you know, totally if it's working or not.
It's like, wow, that's too much.
you know, you kind of pull back.
I have examples, but I'm on camera,
so I'm not going to say that.
I'm not going to say that.
Thanks.
Oh, hey.
Hi, hello.
I was wondering, with all the iterations in the art you made,
when you were planning the project in time,
did you go over it, you know, like...
Wait, you were over... Sorry, my English is not that good.
No, it's fine.
And...
In the time schedule, with all the iterations, you were overtime?
Oh, well, we ended up doing, like, crunch towards the end of the project.
But I wouldn't say that it was because of iteration.
It's just more of a, you know, I mean, new characters came online that we had to push for,
and like, pushing for, like, overall quality, but not...
not through iteration. We generally scheduled for that.
So if you're making something, and it's like,
well, we've got to rework Liz,
it's like, I'm just going to block out like two weeks
to bang out another Liz, basically.
Okay. Thank you.
Okay.
So, with the shared facial rig,
did you find that you were limited creatively
in making different characters or...
Well, I mean, for us, generally, like, the shared facial rig was for all of, like, our human characters.
So there's only so far that you go, right?
And, like, everything was, um...
you know, like generally shared over like male and female kind of thing.
So we didn't really go too far, like too far out.
We probably could have had more constants.
So like our eye positions and stuff like that probably could have been,
you know, consistent throughout people and things like that.
But it wasn't like super limiting
just because of like our art style wasn't wasn't wild.
Like you didn't have a guy with like a giant, giant head versus like
super skinny head kind of thing and anything that required.
like I knew, like Liz basically had like her own facial rig and like Daisy had her own and stuff
like that so anything that required it we ended up breaking off but they were usually like anything
that was out of the system so anything that was like a hero character or like super special
got that treatment. So you think it was helpful?
that you had a limitation so you wouldn't go crazy stylized.
Yeah, I mean I think at first there might be some whining,
I guess, about having restrictions put on you.
But once you define those guidelines,
you actually have more freedom to work within them.
So you have an established budget,
established workflow.
final, you know, look to your art and stuff.
And within that you can just like focus on making art
versus like, I'm gonna try that.
Oh, that didn't work.
I just wasted time.
Now I'm working extra.
You know what I mean?
So it's kind of like freedom,
freedom through restriction, I suppose.
Cool.
All right, thank you.
Thank you.
All right.
All right, go for it.
So from what I understand, I wonder, in the presentation was that, I guess, while you were working on the characters, there were being changes made to the story, and I guess new important characters being added.
Did you find that that was like a real challenge, I guess?
Um, no, we generally like, we would have like script changes that, I mean, just the way that I would try to have like the team working is that they would be working on things that, like if the script changed, it would be weeks down the road.
So trying to avoid.
you know, having somebody working on something and then the day, like a day after it's cut or changed or something like that.
So, uh, trying to avoid that as much as possible and kind of having like a block in your schedule moving with, uh,
with writing. So it'd be like a cascading kind of, uh, kind of deal to prevent that pain.
Thanks.
So the technical solutions you come up with to overcome some of the production problems,
how do you start initiating for those changes?
Do you just like sit down with like a production person and say,
here's a problem and you start fixing it? How do you start?
Yeah, I mean, generally, um...
like the department heads like in our company would generally be communicating all the time.
So like me and like the like character TD like shader artists and things like that would be
like talking in the same room to make sure that we're all on board and we'd have like actual
production people to help us with scheduling to make sure that we weren't dreaming up something
that just wasn't feasible. So it was like a.
It was pretty organic.
I mean, it was pretty easy to get changes done,
just that we had to rely on communication a lot.
So, if I ended up wanting to change something,
I would talk to the character TD
and make sure that that was possible,
like adding bones or changing our universal weighting
and things like that.
Thanks.
Cool.
I think that's it.
All right, thank you.
Thank you.