What up, what up, what up everybody?
It's your boy, DJ Rockman.
One part of the Maverick Hunters with your boy MegaRan.
I'm just going to play a quick tune real quick.
We're going to just start it off just like this.
Get some Mario love in here.
I am DJ Rockman, but I'm going to go ahead and hand it off to my partner in crime.
Yo, yo, yo, I can't see you in the chat. I can't feel you in the chat, but
I want to make sure that we are making a connection beyond camera and space.
So if you could in the chat, give me whatever your favorite emoji is.
Yeah, didn't have to wear a tuxedo to touch people.
Never moved rock, wasn't trying to see Judge Ito.
If it don't fit, you must have quit it.
And if it do fit, you must have did it.
I wasn't with it.
Focused on my love for hip-hop.
Went and flip-flopped to get props.
Try to keep it fresh like a Ziploc.
Similar to the games of yesterday, I blow the dust away, they still fresh today.
Reminisce to the first time I set it up, way past bedtime.
Wouldn't stop playing till we leveled up.
Fingers blistered, suffering from fatigue, while teachers wonder why I got a bad attitude.
Headed to class like Hessman in 86, regrettably passed the freshmen that gave me fits.
See they all come back, glad I taught em, I support em, although they seem to fall like autumn.
Back in the 80s when it begun.
Recall in DC, rockin' the T to say,
Run, Jesse, run.
Galactus tactics require straight jackets
To skip the viruses, we installed the patches.
Took the scenic route to find the fundamentals.
Inc is my drink too, so this ain't coincidental.
K. Murdoch made the call to Magaran.
We veterans, goin' strong til forever, man.
Might not be real, who knows what's real.
But they will never know what keeps us together.
I know we're young, I know we're young.
But if we come this far, we'll be here forever.
Pause.
Oh yeah, let me continue, this game don't stop, another day, another venue.
And if they make it a game of everything I've been through, that joint'll probably be rated
M. I say again, first they drop you in the middle of the hood, no communication skills
so you couldn't be understood.
Only one life, no save slots, yeah, enemies and party members that live on the same block.
And your HP and MP are dang near empty, huh?
And you can't max out, no battery backup.
If you back out, gotta start it all over again fresh.
You'd probably be impressed how I managed to cheat death
and take it out the hood with no regrets.
But I gotta thank that little gray lights with the red lights
there right in front of you.
I spent every night.
Might not be real, who knows what's real?
But if we never know.
We'll be here forever.
I know we're young. I know we're young. But if we've come this far, we'll be here forever.
A little earthbound to start it off. Thank you very much. Oh, let me adjust the lights here.
All right. Remember, I can't see you, so I only got to feel you. That's what I need. I need to feel you.
and your energy and your presence.
So, my name is Mega Ran.
Thank you. Big shout out to DJ Rockman,
my Maverick Hunters partner.
We travel up and down these roads where we used to,
back when people did concerts, and we used to do our little
one-two-thang, rappin',
DJin', and providing entertainment.
And now, we come right to your living room.
We are busting through your TV on this Thursday night.
Hope you've enjoyed GDC for the summer.
I hope you learned something.
Hope you got some great entertainment.
My friend 88bit, who actually played on that song
that we just heard, he played yesterday.
So I really hope you enjoyed it.
So I'm gonna get all my, what they call,
fan service tracks out of the way.
Like the tracks that if you don't know them,
you know the game that they came from.
So I should start with this one
from a good friend of mine, Will Roche.
Let's go to some Mortal Kombat.
Test your might.
Test my might.
Are you ready for a fatality?
Give me a fire emoji in the chat.
And somebody scream, Mortal Kombat!
Mortal Kombat!
You ready for combat?
Are you ready for combat?
Ah!
I'm at the helm, never break and I never bend.
Netherrealm, give and take, never let them win.
Never ran, never will, this is in my skin.
In my blood for the love, this will never end.
Eleven years, lost peers, I can recommend.
When death's knocking at the door, never let them in.
Through the breaks, through the cruises, and through the cracks.
Do your worst, do your works, man I'm coming back!
Do you jerk universe bow when I spit a rap fatality on every track?
It's a rap anytime anyplace. They ready for any attack. You'll aspire to a back in a style
That's the fact I've been ready for war ready for this is the day I was born. I said it before
I never let a competitor score
Bring on the core cuz I'm gonna get mine you better get yours like never before you coming at me. You better be sure
This is Mortal Kombat, we take it to the limit and we go beyond that.
Man, thank you so much for that.
I, um, when I first heard that track, I was playing it and I was like, man,
that sounds like a rap beat. And then very many months later,
I get a phone call or an email phone calls, more dramatic.
So I'll pretend it's a phone call. I get a phone call and it's Will Roger.
He's like, Hey man, uh, do you know a rival? I'm like, yeah, I do.
He's a great guy. Uh, super square. Yeah. Great guy. Um,
well I want to have him in you rap.
on the Mortal Kombat ending theme and I was like wait Mortal Kombat you mean like that Mortal Kombat
you mean like the Mortal Kombat I've been playing ever since I was a little kid Mortal Kombat from
1992 blood code a b b a a c a c or a b a c yeah a yeah you know it I know it I was like yeah 1992
Heck yeah, I wanna do it.
And then, dream came true.
So, big shout out to WorldWallJ.
I hope you caught his panel.
This guy, genius.
I loved his music before I even knew what he did.
Because he did Medal of Honor Underground.
Y'all know nothing about that.
But if you do, I'm not gonna hate on you.
Anyway, let me continue my fan service portion of the set.
So,
bounty hunting.
A very, very intense profession.
So you get in and you get out.
And you don't play no games.
So I want you all to type, this is the way.
It's easy. Everybody type it.
This is the way.
In the guilt we follow the code.
I can bring you in warm or I can bring you in cold.
This is the way.
No revisions or edits, first we set it on the target, then we divvy the credits.
It's the way, 20 bars of best guard steel, new armor, respect our guild, chill.
This is the way, stop anyone who get in the way.
No escape, no getting away, cause this is the way.
Man, though, keep unlimited ammo.
Roll like a commando, the danger is ample.
Banished from the surface, we slip in the shadows, man.
I come again, so we sit on the mantle.
Hey!
Armor shining like the sun's on Tatooine.
Heart knows no fear, runs on gasoline.
I'm like the wind, no noise when I deploy, y'all poised.
Just don't team me with no droids,
cause I can't trust them involving with no plans.
I can't expect anything that could be programmed.
That's the cast of the guild if I close the deal.
So for real, only take a noble kill.
You.
You know the deal.
Hold the steel just to forge it.
Fortify like a fortress.
The drip is just gorgeous.
Techniques and swordiness.
Activated in audience.
New republicans onto us.
Thingam this like a scorpion.
Maybe it was my gaudiness and the will of a warrior.
The Mandalorian.
And this is the way.
And again we follow the code.
I can bring you in warm or I can bring you in cold.
Jump.
No revisions or edits. First we set it on the target, then we divvy the credits.
Hey! 20 bars of best guard steel, new armor, respect our guild.
Man, this is the way. I'll stop anyone who get in the way. No escape, get in the way. You know?
Five years after the fall of the empire, the most precious targets acquired that inspired
a chase across the galaxy for an interesting prize, like a 50-year-old adorable alien child
with special powers beyond our comprehension.
Telekinetic with sensory perception, so intense I smitten, something special suspected, unconventional
methods, the child must be protected.
Load up the weapons cause we got problems to solve
Stormtroopers and hunters get demolished and dissolved
It's all a part of the job
Snipers making me targets
Never taking the office
They be taking me hostage
Enemy of the state
For the chances that I take
Many think that you got me
You're planning for my escape
Back in shelters departing
Then bring the search party in
Forgive me for my tardiness
Like Red Thyrum going in
Never will my story end
You know who I am man
The Mandalorian
And yo, this is the way
And Nicky O, we follow the code.
I can bring you in warm or I can bring you in cold.
Yeah!
No revisions or edits.
First, we set it on the target.
Then we divvy the credits.
This is the way!
20 bars of best guard steel.
New armor.
Respect our guild.
Yeah, this is the way!
I'll stop anyone who get in the way.
No escape.
No getting away.
This is the way.
Right where you are, I want you to say it.
This is the way!
Act like you're a bounty hunter.
Everybody say, this is the way.
Everybody get your jet pack on and go crazy.
Go.
This is the way.
Act like you're holding a cute little 50 year old child in your hand and go, this is the way.
Hey, thank you.
Alright, y'all. So, a little bit about me. My name is MegaRan.
Yeah, you would imagine a name like MegaRan.
You can probably guess my favorite game of all time by my name being MegaRan.
It's very obvious.
Tetris, y'all. That's correct.
Tetris. That's my jam.
Second favorite, though, is probably this game called MegaMan.
Yeah, you heard of it. You heard of it.
So I want to play that jam for you.
This is a song about...
A doctor, an evil doctor, who always has a plan and always gets away, but he's pretty smart and he has great music.
This is Dr. Wily.
So like, imagine if I asked Dr. Wily and all his super geniusness to sit down and write a rap about why he keeps trying to get one over on Mega Man.
This is what he'd say.
They'll turn up the beats.
Dr. Light could never do this.
Mwahahahaha!
And that's how it goes.
Feel free to throw up a W, whoever you are.
Know what I mean?
They used to say it would sound for Westside, but today it sounds for Wally.
One of the smartest in the world.
Amazing advancements in the field of robotics.
And money was no object, but he never felt the need to make a profit with projects.
He had a best friend, Dr. Light.
They could've changed the world if they had stayed together.
But is it during a bit of rivalry but what day it changed forever?
Why they thought he done enough and no matter how giddy was he was always runner-up
He got sicker sicker place built like it was Wily's turn to start coming up
See the school had a contest the shit wall technology and shot our progress
While he and Light collaborated, but Light got all the accolades while pressed.
Like, yeah!
Then he had enough of that, he started acting up,
and then he packed his stuff, and though his act was tough,
we weren't buying it.
See, that's the beginning of a man's science,
that's who might win some, but he just lost one.
Light kept building, the Ward's got one.
A table for one, well that's no fun,
so he built a robot to call his son.
Rock, named for his love for music,
a lab assistant who fleshed his toolkit.
Teenage boy, clumsy, clueless, always amusing.
That was the blueprint.
Didn't want him to live all alone.
He put another robot named Roll.
Life was grand, but little did he know that Wally was coming back.
So, yo!
I was beat, I was played, I was lied to.
Unappreciated for all the good I do.
They told me chill and I tried to.
And I was bothered by survival, crushing my rivals.
I'm taking over, nothing can stop me.
Stop Wally, do not try me.
It's Doc Wiley, do not try this.
I was beat, I was played, I was lied to.
Unappreciated for all the good I do.
They told me chill and I tried to.
Not myself, I'm a survival, crush of a rival.
I'm taking over, nothing can stop me.
Doc Wiley.
Do not try me, it's not wily, do not try me.
All was well in the city of robots, peace and love, no shots, no cops.
Guess who comes back to the block and when danger comes it's likely that it won't knock.
In a lab like a repo man, left all his robots reprogrammed.
so
he puts on a blue suit and helmet and the arm cannon so he's not
They were not there to be doubted They were there to be so bad, so selfish
Destructus is only objective But if only we'd know he respected
Maybe he wouldn't act so reckless I guess his bro is just man respected
Can't let him win this fight Time to get equipped, minds get sliced
Rock has Wily in his sight, but he can't bring himself to end his life
Well he likes to dock in the caves where they think he'll spend the rest of his day
But I heard the other day he is doing Stosen chat saying doctor Wily
He was played, I was lied to
The Wiley
Dr. Wiley. Dr. Wiley, yeah. I'm taking over. Nothing can stop me. Dr. Wiley. Do not try me.
It's Dr. Wiley. Joe. Joe. I was beat. I was plead. I was lied to. Unappreciated for all
the good I do. They told me chill and I tried to. And that was all about survival, crushing
my rival. I'm taking over. Nothing can stop me. I'm taking over. Nothing can stop me.
Dr. Wiley. Do not try me. If you're at home, do this dance with me. Go.
uh slide uh just slide clap clap clap and then slide with it and then slide with it
and then throw some hips in it and on that last one gotta pause it like
Yeah, boy.
Thank you so much.
Yeah.
So let's get my name is Mega Ran and now you know why I'm a guy
who does Mega Man songs.
So a long time ago and again only because phone calls are
dramatic.
I got a phone call.
I made this album that had that song on it and 11 more bangers
about Mega Man.
Put it out on the internet.
This is back in the MySpace days.
None of you remember this.
This is a really dark time for the internet.
Put it on the line.
And then, uh, everybody liked it. People were like, man, this album is so great. So good.
Oh man, you're doing your thing, man. You make great music. And then, uh, one day, a bunch of
people were like, yo, I really liked this song. And then, um, Capcom heard it and I was like, oh shoot.
Capcom called me and was like, hey, are you MegaRan? And I was like, uh, who wants to know?
And they were like, it's Capcom. And I was like, yeah, he's not here.
But then I felt like, you know what? I can't lie.
So they were like, you know what, is this you? And I was like, yeah, it is.
And they were like, so we wanted to talk to you about this Mega Man album.
And I was like, what about it? And they were like, look,
I don't know if you knew,
but it's kind of illegal to do the thing you did where you just like sampled our
stuff and didn't tell us. And I was like, I didn't know you couldn't do that.
I, I, I kinda, I kinda knew, I knew, I had an idea.
That's not important. So I was like, Oh, I'm so sorry. I didn't know. And they were like, well,
we got some even, even crazier news for you. And I'm like, Oh God,
the lawyers are outside my door right now. He's like, no silly. We love it.
We love it so much that we'd love to have you work with us on some songs.
And I was like, what?
So that was my first experience in the gaming industry.
I got invited to San Diego Comic-Con.
I got invited to E3.
I got invited to Evo.
I got so many cool things I started going to, and it just opened my life.
And GDC was one of the places I went after that.
It was like my first year doing this full time.
So for that reason, GDC is super special to me.
So it's awesome to have come full circle almost 10 years later
and be now doing a show with GDC.
So this is cool.
I was supposed to do an after party during GDC.
Uh in way back when it was supposed to happen in March, um, I had like three after parties in San Francisco planned
And like i'm not an after party dj kind of guy but like I am when money's good
So what happened was the money was really good and I was like, absolutely. I want to do after parties
And so I started I was like i'm that kind of dj now and I was like yo
My schedule is packed with all these cool events
And then kovid was like
F your plants, F your life.
And here we are at home.
But you know what?
At home though, it's allowed me to watch a lot of good TV.
And here's a song I wrote about a good TV show.
Have you heard of the witcher?
His name, Geralt of Rivia.
I saw him one day,
and I have a crazy story to tell you about him.
Yeah.
I saw him with my own two eyes as he cut a monster down twice his size.
So let me tell you about what I've learned and paint you a picture of the witcher.
You ain't heard of Garoth or Rivia, let me in there.
Reason that monsters speak, living and fair.
You'd rather be scared than rather in here.
The fright got him turned to white like they rid of this air.
After last experiment, so plenty of years.
Death in the air. Evil, the lesser the pair.
The beef refused to lose, so the lesser the pair.
But the tavern, they give him a beer.
For you to understand.
If you have a scar on his heart that can never be paid.
Now that goes to his road to everywhere.
Yeah.
And I've become like a week that we put his chair.
I'm just a bar trying to make my rent.
But I've seen cats cross and get played like went by the butcher of Blaviken for the right
price.
Bring him a man party.
He'll drag a man.
Toss a coin to your witch.
A valley of plenty.
Oh, valley of plenty.
Toss a coin to your witcher,
Valley of plenty.
Do you have a coin you can toss?
Hee!
Thank you.
Ha!
So, if you ever want to toss a coin
to your friendly neighborhood rapper,
I have plenty of ways to do that.
I have songs that I put out every month on Patreon.
So this is the shameless plug section of the show.
I do two songs a month on Patreon, patreon.com slash mega ran.
I do band camp stuff all the time.
I've got a big sale coming tomorrow actually.
Once it hits midnight, something cool is going to pop up on my band camp.
That is random.bandcamp.com.
All right.
So anyway, let's continue on with the fan service.
Have you ever heard of this game called Final Fantasy VII?
I heard like it's gonna be a big deal one day.
Maybe. I don't know.
A couple people like it. A few of my friends.
I heard it sold like a hundred copies, man.
It's gonna be big.
Let me change my glasses.
We are now ready to go to war.
I need you all with me in the reactor. Let's go.
Don't be scared.
I'm Barrett Wallace.
Gang on Barrett Wallace!
Got money on the mind, no fear in my eyes.
Avalanche the squad, so it's time to rise.
I'm just going forward, no time for going backwards.
The mission, destroy the Mako reactors.
They brought it on themselves, so they gotta take them out.
All in, but we might not all make it out.
Ending the Shinra and closing the chapter. The mission, destroy the Mako reactors.
I never got their names, and I didn't really care to. I just want the money.
So the mission I adhere to is simple. Join some resistance clique. Blow up the reactor, then we split. That's it!
Well, they go on about saving the planet, all the precious resources we've been taking for granted.
But I'm doing me. It's not that I don't understand it, but I'm trying to carry the
job out just how we planned it. Well, in my line of work, there's no time for softies.
These treat huggers better wake up and smell the coffee. Been around the block now,
far from a beginner. I've been to reactors back when I worked for Shinra.
And they don't blame me, and I don't like them, and they don't trust me, and I ain't like them,
war they ain't built for it. Troubles like my wallet, I only find it when I'm never looking
for it. So as I hit the bomb, I start to get a premonition, some kind of feeling shouldn't be a
part of my mission, but I do it. Ten minutes remain before reactor one is going down in flames.
And so we out to the train to rest. Part one of the mission is a complete success,
but for now it seems that the good guys are winning.
This ain't the ending, it's only the beginning.
Got money on the mind, no fear in my eyes.
Avalanche to squazz, so it's time to rise.
I'm just going forward, no time for going backwards.
The mission, destroy the Mako reactors.
They brought it on themselves, so they gotta get them out.
All in, but we might not all make it out.
Ending the Shinra and closing the chapters.
The mission, destroy the Mako reactors.
Now you're coming with me or what?
Come on y'all.
I'm gonna tell you about this crew called avalanche that we
rolling with this one is the hypest song of my set.
So usually this is the time I get everybody to get up and
get hype.
So if you are sitting down wherever you sit and get up
get up because I'm gonna be moving around and I'm 300
pounds.
Hey, hey.
Hey, hey, come on. Hey, fist up one, two, three, we beat em!
Insurgents, not a bit nervous, encouraged, gotta be further to go.
By any means, getting rid of my enemies.
A-V-A-L-A-N-C-H-E-E, that's who we be.
Insurgents, not a bit nervous, no lip service.
You gotta get further to go through what we gotta get.
Who want that problem with AV?
A L A N C H E.
That's who we.
There's a metal company called Shinra.
I don't know exactly what they into, but they really gonna get trouble in my life stream.
And I just can't let that continue.
They don't care who they hurt, who they injured.
Gonna turn my whole planet against us.
So it's simple, you join the resistance or you wind up going against us.
My name is Barrett Wallace.
I'm known for paralyzing.
But the rising points into submission, not fantasizing.
Wish this world wasn't violent.
Get worse if we allow it.
Hot head with a kenny for an arm and a mind with a number of visions inside it.
Uh!
Avalanche man, I just don't have a check.
Watch them scatter man, we never barren.
Slayin' those battle planes.
My people beside me, team from behind me with a better voice of reason
There's bigs and wedges, just seeing anybody in my way, we're squeezing
Behind me, I'm Lee, and I'm the bomb in the region, it's gotta be the highest treason
We came too far to back down, and I'm not leaving till we even
Bigger to everyone, you can get equipped
Not a president, a shareholder's door fits
And it's hard when I can't get control of it
Okay, fists up, come on now, hey!
Hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, got a bit further to go.
By any means, getting rid of my enemies.
A-V-A-L-A-N-C-H-E.
One more time, y'all.
Hey, hey, not a bit nerved.
Hey, no lip service.
Hey, got a bit further to go.
Do what I gotta get.
Who want that problem with A-V-A-L-A-N-C-H-E?
Yep, that's who we be.
Thank you very much.
Because you know, that's who we be.
B-A-R-R-E-1-T, they gon' have to come get me if they want me.
I don't bend, I don't break, I don't care about much.
Just my daughter, Marlene, and my peoples being free.
See, you gotta understand, son, I don't have the answers.
I just keep the faith, and I always keep a handgun.
No, I mean it literally, cause I got a handgun.
I call that a gun arm, so I'm never.
You're unarmed!
Thank you. Yeah, I got this thing for you.
characters with gun arms.
But that's my song called Avalanche.
So on this album that I made about Final Fantasy VII,
it's called Black Materia.
I thought that was catchy,
because, you know, I'm black.
But anyway, enough about me for a second.
I want to bring in my Maverick Hunters partner,
tag team partner, the hawk to my animal,
the axe to my smash,
the Tully Blanchard to my Arne Anderson,
and several other wrestling references.
I'm gonna tag in DJ Rockman.
Hey, yeah, OK, that's how we do it right there.
I guess we don't just warm it up, then.
Let me warm it up with some video game remixes.
Let's go.
I am the host of Nerdcore Nights here in the lovely place of Texas.
But what we're going to do is we're going to go ahead and throw on some tunes.
So let me go ahead and just get y'all started.
See you.
Liked this transcript? Let us know in the comments!
Everybody sing this song.
Yes, sir.
Just waking up in the morning.
Gotta thank God.
I don't know, but today seems kind of odd.
No barking from the dog.
No small.
And Mama cooked the breakfast for Noah.
Finally got a call from a girl I want to dick out
Booked it up for later as I hit the dope
Thinking will I live another 24?
I gotta go cause I got me a drop top
And if I hit the switch I can make that
had to stop at a red light looking in my near
not a checker in sight and everything is all fright
I gotta be from Kim and she could do it all night
called up to homies and I'm askin' ya'll
which part are ya'll playing basketball
get me on the court and I'm troubled
last week messed around and got a triple-double
freakin' brother's every way like MJ
I can't believe today
I can't believe, I can't believe, I can't believe, I can't believe, I can't believe, I can't believe, I can't believe, I can't believe.
But yes, I do live streams throughout the week.
Twitch.tv slash DJ Rockman.
This one right here from Jet Set Radio.
Called Malpoish.
From my buddy Kazoo Beats.
Once again, I am DJ Rockman.
You can follow me on all social medias at DJrockman48.
For my Smash heads right here, Smash Bro fans.
I'm a Melee head though.
Hi-yah!
Haya! Haya!
Haya!
Thanks for watching!
So this right here is gonna be the last track for me.
You know, we bring it back to Mega Man once again.
But let's go!
Checkmate!
What do you want to do tonight?
The same thing we do every night, Pinky.
Try to take over the world.
This trailer shows how the game will function on the NES.
Okay now we're in the transitune of the final day of development, and we're gonna be doing
our final wrap up.
And one last thing that we're gonna be talking about today is the final premonition.
Yes sir, once again I am DJ Rockman.
One part of the awesome group of Maverick Hunters, me and MegaRan.
Love to tag team together.
Play some dope tracks.
Let y'all hear some new music that we like to call Nerdcore and some video game remixes.
But like I said, follow me on stream on Twitch.
Slash DJ Rockman.
All my other social media is DJRockMan48.
And also, if you do want to contribute, and I'm going to spoil a little bit of myself, too.
If you want to show some love, you can follow me on Vimeo.
That's DJRockMan.
Support a brother, you know, doing the same thing.
We just try to take care of one another.
But I'm going to hand it back off if he is ready.
Give it to the boy.
Hey, you're the partner in crime.
Hey, you know, you're the king of the master blaster.
Aha. Hey. Hey.
Yes sir.
Guess you gonna wait a second.
Do you want me to get one more track for you buddy?
I'm gonna play one more track while we're waiting for my buddy.
Yeah, yeah. Check, check. There we go. What's going on? Hope y'all enjoy DJ
Rockman. Thank you so much for holding it down. Thank you. Always.
Brother. You heard. Keep an eye out on the streams. We'll be
popping up doing some more stuff together very soon. But
now for this part of the set, I want to bring it somewhere down
but unfortunately to to a real place which is where we are
today. So, let's get started.
Every day I watch the news, it's like a rerun.
Land that are free, can't believe what it's become.
They say it's broken, but I say it's going fine.
But a system in effect that works the way it was designed.
Plans get devised, this land isn't mine.
We stand it, I pray we get the answers in time for the youth.
That's why we put our hands to the sky, tell the truth.
The way got a chance to survive.
So we shift the paradigm.
We heard the battle cry hit the front lines from Arizona to
Palestine.
I had no disguise.
No verdict.
No alibi.
I would rather galvanized and pacify cats apply reasoning.
I see the power weakening dedication.
We can win.
That's why I'm screaming BLM can't think you can't eat can't
breathe.
I do this for my family.
So that means there ain't no plan B.
Yeah, so.
I'm going to talk, I'm going to play a new song.
I have never played it before.
I'm excited.
This track's called Afraid of the Dark.
Hope you can hear the music.
Oh, oh, mm.
Super new, super new, fresh off the,
fresh off the brain, basically.
Hey.
Yeah.
I get scared when I'm driving and I hear sirens, which is strange, because my tags are up to
date.
I ain't quite afraid.
You ain't done nothing wrong.
You ain't got no reason to run.
You don't have a gun.
You ain't breaking any laws.
You ain't talking back.
You ain't giving no probable cause.
You won't step aside.
Why are you so petrified?
You ain't obstructing justice.
You ain't got nothing to hide, so why am I surprised when situations escalate and black
men die?
Seems like it happens every day.
Something goes awry.
I'm going to investigate, but they don't even try.
It's like our lives are second-rate, so I'm terrified.
But not as much as you are.
Worried that I'm gonna make a scene, maybe take it too far.
See me riding, playing music loud in my new car.
Disturbing the peace of your community when you work too hard.
Understand you got a house and I'm just rentin'.
Treating me like a menace, a gender relentless.
Man, I'ma let you finish, but calling the cops on black folks in 2020, it's like a death sentence.
So let's talk about it. Why are you so frightened? Why is my advancement threatening so many white
men? And when it comes to black matters, why are you so silent? I need to know the answers.
Can you provide them? Yeah. Is it my style? The way that I walk? Am I too proud? The way that I
talk? Why does my existence cause so much pain in your heart? Ask yourself, are you afraid of the
dark?
Do you want to see me broken with my head down?
Or maybe six feet under the ground?
Am I a threat to you?
I'm just out here playing my part.
Why are you afraid of the dark?
Man, is it my style?
The way that I walk?
Am I too proud?
The way that I talk?
Why does my existence cause so much pain in your heart?
Ask yourself, why you afraid of the dark?
Now do you want to see me broken with your head down?
Six feet under the ground?
Let me talk to you.
I'm just out here playing my part.
Ask yourself, why you afraid of the dark?
Yeah.
This is a track called Cry of the Planet.
It's Final Fantasy VII inspired but it definitely, to me,
means a lot more because it's coming from a place where
they have a really important message about saving the planet.
And we're getting our planet destroyed daily by so many other things.
Yeah, yeah.
Close your eyes.
Listen.
Yo, yo.
Sometimes I feel I died in 2016, and this is just a simulation.
Maybe that's just extreme, but as I'm sitting midstream,
hoping kids don't dox me or swap me because I'm stating what's obvious.
Every statement that's faulty, they using despair as the jet fuel
to drive racist practices.
This ain't checks and balances.
It's just creating balances.
You hear it.
Tax cuts, witch hunts, strong borders.
I hear fear-mongering and dividing and conquering.
We let a monster in.
And that's simple and plain. All we did was complain.
These tweetin' threats like this was the game.
Straight negligent. Inflating estimates.
Trade deficit. Mis-education.
Plus fear creates negligence.
Hate imminent. Now to misplace evidence.
As a planet, we all stand to the great detriment.
Jobs take benefits and make medicine unaffordable.
It's horrible.
I hear the lies in every sentence and I thought it through and though I still want to feel
resentment for everyone that believed in you and thought this dream was feasible and thought
that you were speaking to their problems but now I believe you're beatable and it seems
we got the bottom but it seems we got to blossom like linden jasmine we blossom standing stronger
united by our desire and defiance I've seen over the horizon my people are out of hiding
yeah and we refuse to go silent but now
Listen, you can hear the cries of the planet.
But for now,
listen, you can hear the cries of the planet.
You can hear the cries of the planet, even scientists can't understand it.
We all know the disadvantage, impossible to manage.
So-called experts, they calling us a hoax.
But it's time for the networks to try a new approach.
They talking greenhouse gases, natural disasters, unexplained phenomena.
Time to wake up out of the monstery.
But we can't change things, this world is changing.
How many times we gotta see the same things?
Hurricanes, earthquakes, volcanic eruptions.
Time to wake up out of the monstery.
We need more action and much less discussion and probably less corruption before we all go on us
Somebody inform us mother earth is trying to warn us what we worry about the trivial the superstars interviews millionaires drama people
What's gotten into you?
Temperature be rising like the co2 levels unsettled, but sooner or later. We'll see the true devil, but for now
Yeah, listen, you can hear the cries of the planet.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, uh-huh, but for now, yeah, yeah, yeah, you listen,
you can hear the cries of the planet. Yeah, yeah, I hear them, I see them, you know,
and I cry for the planet. Thank you.
Right, my name is MegaRan. I'm gonna try to end off this show with a little bit of hope.
I don't want to end it all doom and gloom. Big shout outs to DJ Rockman. Big shout outs to 88
Bit and Saint in the Rain. I appreciate GDC so much. Shout out to GDC for having music as a big
part of this because as my shirt says, video game music is music and to me it's not just music,
it's life. It saved my life.
So many times. So I just try to give back to it. So this is a little gem from a game that I love
called Little Nemo the Dream Master. So for this hook I'm just gonna say hey hey all right. Now if
you could post all right in the chat that'll be cool. Hey hey all right. Once upon a time before
beats and the rise and before there was ever any random there was a boy in the hood who always did
good so the bullies of the block couldn't stand him
And on Christmas and birthdays he got mad presents.
So many he didn't know what to play with.
He had Transformers, He-Man, Ninja Turtles, Star Wars.
But the G.I. Joe's were his favorite.
He was so creative.
That if they didn't make the toy, like he decided to create it.
He put Storm Shadow's legs on Snake Eye's body till it popped.
Then he duct taped it. He made spaceships.
Then the big kids hung out on the block playing hide and seek and riding bikes.
They used to try to get involved but they told them,
Get lost!
And that's when they started getting high at night.
And I heard he made a friend that was as nerdy as him.
When he had about all he could withstand, he collected comics, cards, studied.
Read the Star Wars script like the back of his hand.
And in school he made A's and B's.
Teachers complimented his amazing feats.
And all the while he wondered, if I'm so amazing, geez, how come nobody won't play with me?
He said, hey, hey, alright, hey, hey.
Hey, hey, alright, hey, hope you got it.
Somebody say hey, hey, GDC say hey, hey, alright, hey, hey, alright, hey.
So to say this kid looked funny in school, that would be a colossal understatement.
He had high water pants and Coke bottle frames and a mouth full of armadada gracious.
His first girlfriend was named Christina Perez.
He took her everywhere. Now the boy was so cool, but she dated him on a dare.
Left him standing there without a clue. Man, kids can be so cruel.
At the time when he couldn't love him any less, but at the same time sure he got an A and a S
Cause his mom felt this was the best way to keep him out of the street
Although they were penniless, only child didn't want an emptiness
And it's a healthier addiction than cigarettes, and so it began
How did he escape the scene? He sat in front of that screen and chased his dreams
He went, hey, hey, alright, hey, hey, alright, hey, hey
Hey, somebody say hey, hey, all right, hey, hey, all right, hey, hey, all right, hey.
Hey!
Fast forward a couple years, he gains a couple peers
and sucks up game like a vacuum.
Then he went off to college and sorts some knowledge
and develops the heart to make rap tunes.
Vowed to stay true and he dropped his debut.
And, yeah, he's got his little name up here.
There was money in the bank, but money drew a blank.
Every time his second LP came up.
He thought back to childhood and how he survived in such a wild hood.
Then he realized they didn't hate him.
And whatever didn't break him, that's what made him.
So, never knew he'd stand for this love for his games and rap.
Open his soul and let him in.
Then he chopped up some 8-bit sounds, put it down and ran them.
It's now Lotus Megarand.
And his name's all over that internet.
Girls who didn't care were kinda interested.
And the best part of the story comes at the end.
But that part hasn't been written yet.
Thank you so much. My name is Mega Ran. You guys have been
amazing. DJ Rockman on the ones and twos. Y'all are so cool.
So, we're gonna end it off church style. That's how we do
a church style. We go like this. We do the soul clap.
Thank you.
Always keep your Mega Buster charged because you just never know.
Peace and blessings.
Be safe out there.
Everyone wear your masks.
Be awesome to each other because we need you.
Thank you.
I'm Mega Ran.
Good night.
Thank you, GDC.