Okay, thank you all for coming.
It's final day of GDC.
I hope you all had a great week.
And before I start, I want to remind you
to turn off your cell phones and would very appreciate
if you can fill out the questionnaire after the talk.
So if you don't know how to pronounce my name,
you can just call me Johnson, it's close enough.
I am not a native English speaker,
so my English may be wrong sometimes,
but still I hope I can get most of the points across.
I'm actually a programmer, but in recent years
I run an indie dev meetup called IGD Share in Taiwan.
I also run IGD Taiwan chapter
and co-organize Taipei Game Developers Forum since 2012.
But more importantly regarding this talk,
I was on the translation team for the official
traditional Chinese subtitle for Indie Game Movie.
But Netflix recently messed up our work.
I will talk about this later.
So I also worked on some of the indie game localizations
such as Nova 111 and Tengami.
I help Global Game Jam as the Asia regional organizer and the traditional Chinese translation volunteer.
And I also roughly do the same translation volunteer thing for Indicate Festival.
So let's just start with this very famous image. I think you've all seen this before.
or your base belong to us.
Suffice to say, I'm trying to help stopping
the opposite case of this.
Because from my personal experience in the past,
at times I wish I could have helped people
fix their Chinese localization issues.
Gaming is a global community now and
Not just the players in the US will see crappy or funny localizations like this.
A lot of games now are being localized into fast-growing, non-English-speaking markets,
especially in Asia where China and Taiwan play a bigger factor.
So let's check out some of the questionable Chinese localizations here that we have been exposed to in the past.
So this example is the traditional Chinese version of Neverwinter Nights.
Just by looking at a screenshot here, even if you don't know Chinese, you can still tell there's something wrong.
The dialect options are obviously duplicated, and there are strange numbers between the sentences.
But the most iconic thing in this particular screenshot
is that the last part of the dialogue
reads like this in English originally.
So it's, I tried to grab her hand,
her being an old woman,
but she gave me a kick in the teeth.
So this kick in the teeth, as far as I know,
is an idiom meaning that treating you badly
when you are in need.
But the traditional Chinese version mistranslated that into
literally a woman that kicks your teeth.
So there are hundreds of things like this
in the traditional Chinese version of Neverwinter Nights,
and this being the most funny and notable one.
As a result, Tease-Kicking Old Woman
sort of became the nickname for Neverwinter Nights in Taiwan.
So you definitely don't want your localization
end up like that.
I'm going to show you some more background information
and the context of this talk, and then...
Lots of examples grouped by categories,
you know, general idea and also like
simplified vs traditional things,
naming and encoding, UI, phones,
and lastly a little bit political stuff.
And then finally some tips and conclusions
that you can take away.
So let's look at this from a practical point of view first.
China's market share is huge and growing fast.
And Taiwan, although small in land mass,
but still the number six on this chart.
And if you look at the chart carefully,
you also notice that China has only one color in the bar,
simply because the chart maker couldn't track down numbers
from Android-related markets in China.
And this is the year-over-year growth.
Both China and Taiwan is in top five,
although again, at a Google Play's part,
they couldn't track down number for China.
And in addition to that, Taiwan is also an important
soft launching region for a lot of developers,
if the game type is suitable.
It's similar to Australia or New Zealand for the US market.
So if you want to eventually go to Japan or China,
chances are that you might want to soft launch in Taiwan
and see your result and performance this year.
So these are probably the more convincing
and practical reasons why you want to treat
the Chinese localization more seriously.
Now after we've established some reasons
you might want to do this,
let's start to talk about different aspects
of Chinese localization.
I would assume you probably already know this
simplified VS traditional stuff.
But in Chinese, things are definitely vastly more different
than you would think.
So this table shows the National Language Service
description in Windows for the various Chinese systems.
As you can see, it's very confusing to say the least.
Not to mention the spoken language differences
such as Mandarin and Cantonese,
and you know, you still have to deal with all the UI
and phones and encoding and some other stuff.
So there's a very valid question you can ask yourself is,
is this just too much trouble?
From my point of view, it's perfectly understandable
if you choose only one Chinese language to localize,
if at all.
Also, I asked myself the very same question,
why is it worth talking about this
and spending time preparing all the materials?
Because it's hard for me to see
that some of my favorite games,
especially some of the indie games,
sort of struggle in this regard.
Also, I often feel like Chinese-speaking regions
are not that well understood by people when I travel abroad.
And it goes without saying that I was greatly inspired
by the Arabic crash course that Rami gave us in GDC 15.
Now let's just dive into some of the actual examples in games.
And for the first example, I want to pull up The Witness.
So actually for The Witness, I am
going to talk about three different issues
of different complexities in it.
The first example here actually is very, very straightforward.
You see five menu buttons in the traditional Chinese version
on a screenshot here.
The first button in English is load a game.
And then the traditional Chinese look like this one.
So if we take that button text in the traditional Chinese
version and translate it back into English for you to
understand, it then becomes download a game.
So if you play The Witness in traditional Chinese,
this really sticks out like a sore thumb.
The game was seven years in the making
and very deliberate and dedicated in all kinds of ways.
Yet the translation people make this kind of mistakes
and the original developer have no way to double check that.
It just feel like the movie Titanic's night sky
if you get the Neil Dickerson, Tyson and Jim Cameron joke.
Does anyone know that joke?
Okay.
Yeah, the star is wrong in the sky.
So another example I want to highlight in the game
is this one.
It's rather complicated and reflects a few issues.
And also, it's about one of the game's endings, so spoiler
alert.
In the main ending of The Witness, you step into this elevator thing and you launch it.
The game basically will play a sequence of scripted animation of this elevator flying you around the island.
And the game will also read you a part of Diamond Sutra in English.
And you can see there some traditional Chinese translated lines of the Diamond Sutra in English on screen there.
And so the line on this particular screenshot is a star at dawn,
then a bubble in a stream,
a flash of lightning in a summer cloud,
a flickering lamp,
a phantom,
and a dream.
So at the game's ending, at least for the first time,
you sort of leave the game and you wake up from the dream, so to speak.
But it's not as simple.
So actually the fourth paragraph of this Diamond Sutra
has another sentence in the beginning,
starting with, so you should view this fleeting world
as a star that had done a bubble in a stream, and so on.
And here I've extracted the corresponding
traditional Chinese counterparts from the screenshots,
which actually is a secondhand translation
directly from the English there.
And there are a few things I can say about this.
It's a little bit too literal and some mistranslation.
But the most important thing here should be,
this translation should remind the players
of Diamond Sutra in Chinese.
So let's look the Diamond Sutra as we know it in Chinese.
It's like totally different.
And I've got a color code thing here.
Even if you don't read Chinese at all,
you can still sort of understand what corresponds to what.
So things to note here is,
first, the in-game English version
already ignored the first sentence.
And that first sentence, which is grayed out,
actually sums up pretty nicely
for the first and the last Chinese sentence here.
So actually, the Chinese character
that corresponds to the in-game English version,
just those 10 characters in the middle.
Secondly, you also notice that the order of the color-coded words and sentences is actually different.
If you recall the screenshot that I just showed, each line of Diamond Sutra is timed to the animation sequence.
So you cannot just put the original Diamond Sutra in English into the game.
As I've mentioned, a good localization here is supposed to be making you think of Diamond Sutra in Chinese.
Because if you don't, then...
an important layer of the meaning of the game
would just be lost for people who play in Chinese.
And you would be a little bit confused
about why the ending is this mystical gibberish.
If you can understand the fact that
these lines are from Diamond Sutra,
so then you can understand what it's about,
it actually connects to a few important ideas
in the witness.
So when I reached the ending for the first time,
I didn't realize that.
Only after I saw the discussion on Reddit,
I had a much clearer idea about the endings
and several other smaller clues in the game.
So at least to me, this feels pretty important.
Otherwise, why would a developer randomly choose
those specific quotes for the ending sequence?
But as we have established,
either you have a translation
that's not gonna make people think of Diamond Sutra
in Chinese, or when translating,
you'd use Diamond Sutra in Chinese originally,
but the ending animation sequence would be out of sync.
If the translator could somehow know he or she was actually translating Diamond Sutra,
at least there is a chance there is a workable solution could be found.
Something like this.
So you see now, so I made this and you see now all the color coded words and the sentences are
in line with each other and even for the line that's actually not present in the Chinese version,
the sentence in white there, a flickering lamp,
that is actually nowhere to be found in the Chinese version.
I can still just add that line and not breaking the order
So if you're a Chinese speaking person
and you've heard of Diamond Sutra before
and then you see this version
it would just be a lot easier
for you to think of the source of the quotes
And it's also deliberately written in a poem-like format
although I wouldn't claim the poem quality is good
but I think that serves the purpose
So in The Witness we've discussed about
three different issues
First is a very trivial localization error,
download a game.
Sometimes things like this happen due to the translator
doesn't know their domain well,
or the developer provide insufficient context to work with.
Since a lot of times the translator
only get a simple script text file,
and there are no visual cues, no audio cues,
no explanations, and no references.
But of course, I honestly don't know
why people would get,
they were confused load with download.
And a second-hand translation issue,
which you definitely want to double-check
if your content originates from other cultures
or other countries.
Most other quotes from the audio log in the witness
actually already state their source in-game,
so the translator would have the basic context of the quote,
but unfortunately, the Diamond Sutra ending
doesn't have the source stated.
So supplying additional notes or references here
definitely will be very helpful for localization process.
Also, the important decisions you've already made during the development of your game,
such as how to make the ending sequence based on translated materials like Diamond Sutra,
this might come back to haunt you when you are going to localize the game in the end.
I would have no idea what other languages can do about it
if there isn't a version of Diamond Sutra in that particular language already.
So in the last few slides, things like,
the things that we talked about can actually happen
to all kinds of localization process in any language.
And now I'm going to be more focused
on some of the detailed examples
of a simplified and traditional Chinese differences.
The first question you would ask is maybe
why don't you just use a converter?
I will show you examples why converter is just not viable.
So we've just seen the term game in Chinese moments ago,
so I will just use that again.
Now let's break the two characters down.
The both traditional and simplified Chinese versions,
the vocabulary game has two Chinese characters.
The idea of the second character is easier,
which just means drama.
And it actually is a one-to-one mapping.
But for the first character, both play and swim characters
are used in traditional Chinese,
and they have different meanings.
But in simplified, the two characters become one.
And so the mapping is many to one in this case,
which is not viable if you want to do
simplified to traditional conversion.
Okay, now this is a bit more complicated here.
There are three Chinese characters here,
and we use all three of them in traditional.
They have the same pronunciation, the only difference being the last character's tone is different from the former two.
So what is the big deal among these three characters?
So now let's do that mapping again.
First of all, this three-stroke character is used both in traditional Chinese and simplified Chinese, meaning interfere or involve.
The next character, the first meaning is dry,
but in simplified it is then mapped into this three-stroke character like the one above.
And when this character forms compound terms
combined with other Chinese characters,
it forms terms like dried fish.
But when it is combined with a relative term,
such as sister, it means stepsister,
and also stepmother, stepfather, and so on.
Finally, let's talk about this third character.
It's pretty versatile in meanings already, as you can see.
But then the simplified Chinese version also simplified it
into the very same character like the ones above.
And not only that, now you can see it's really hard
not to consider the F word potential and implication here
when you see the very same character can also be used
to describe step relatives.
Yeah, so you see some of these funny internet pictures
about machine translated signs in simplified Chinese
that look like this.
And it probably means dried vegetable, right?
This particular F word confusion won't happen
to machine translated traditional Chinese,
but you know,
teeth kicking old woman is just as bad.
So just to recap some of the points
we've talked about simplified vs traditional.
It goes without saying that the writing
of a lot of characters in the simplified Chinese
is a lot simpler,
but also the meanings of the characters
are changed or funneled.
And it is not a one-to-one or many-to-one mapping.
It's rather a many-to-many mapping,
considering a lot of the daily vocabularies
are different in China, Hong Kong, and Taiwan,
making the conversion not really viable both ways.
You may also say that, okay,
I'm making a game without words and text,
so localization should not be a problem for me, right?
But that's not true,
unless your game doesn't even use text for the game title,
which is almost impossible.
And beware of this issue because it might affect discoverability and also people's perception of the game in the target regions.
So the first example is Jumblow's another famous title, Braid, which as far as I remember doesn't have any other official names other than the English one.
When it came out in Taiwan, we just called it as is.
But in China, I think some press or prominent players online started to call this four-character term.
That basically translates back to time and space fantasy
or something similar.
But anyway, it's an unofficial name that just caught on in China.
However, in Taiwan, if you convert that four-character name
into traditional Chinese,
that actually is the name for Tales of Phantasia
and the later Tales of series.
So if you dump that four-character into Google
and search that,
there will be two different famous games coming up,
which is rather confusing at times.
Now the second example, Pokemon.
This is going to be particularly interesting one,
and maybe start to get a little bit political.
So in early 2016, Pokemon company tried to unify the name
and the logo in the major Chinese speaking markets,
namely China, Taiwan, and Hong Kong.
And for their upcoming, their then upcoming game,
Pokemon Sun and Moon, which released last year.
Because this was also the first time they were going to do an official Chinese version of the Pokemon games,
so they thought they want to fix the name of the game in different regions once and for all.
So here's the problem. Taiwan and Hong Kong have totally different names for Pokemon in the past,
because back then in the mid 90s, Pokemon anime was introduced into both regions independently,
although roughly around the same time. And the local people have different localizations.
And it's not even about a game, it's just an animation.
And all the different Pokemons in the series,
they mostly have different names between Taiwan and Hong Kong.
And then the Pokemon company want to unify that last year.
So here you don't have to understand what all the Chinese characters mean.
Suffice to say, now in Chinese speaking worlds,
these three Chinese characters, Baokumon,
in the bottom, maps to Pokemon now.
And it's based on Mandarin pronunciation.
This is an important point.
So about this specific issue, China market didn't have much influence over it over time in the past because
it began with the localization of the anime and China lagged behind Taiwan and Hong Kong in this regard a bit back then
and when their market was eventually exposed to franchise in a big way, China more or less settled down with the naming from Taiwan
The reason is pretty obvious now because Hong Kong have been using Cantonese pronunciation to name the Pokemon
And Taiwan and China both mainly use Mandarin.
So the key here is, while people in Hong Kong and Taiwan
both use traditional Chinese as the writing system,
you can still end up with potentially,
you can end up still facing hugely different localizations
when trying to do the games localization.
And the Pokemon company's decision didn't fare well,
didn't fare too well for them in Hong Kong.
Some gamers are really baffled by it.
While it was supposed to be an unification on naming and lots of stuff in Pokemon,
Hong Kong players were facing the fact that more than half of their beloved Pokemon names,
which had been used for around 20 years, now being changed as a consequence.
China and Taiwan players were hardly affected by it.
So this was an actual photo for a real demonstration against Pokemon's new Chinese version in Hong Kong.
The slogan on the sign here basically is saying,
Give our Pokemon names back.
These are the kind of things you just cannot be too careful about.
You know, Japanese has always been very famous for their carefulness when doing business.
But this kind of thing still happens, and I doubt they knew this would invoke protests like this.
As an opposite example, some of you might be familiar with,
or at least heard of the mobile suit Gundam.
And you'll see Bandai has basically no problem with it.
Different regions have their own official translations.
So next example, I was on a team
that helped the official traditional Chinese
subtitle for Indie Game Movie.
And I mentioned that Netflix recently ruined it.
So the thing is, when we decided whether to translate the names or not,
the main factor for us was, is the translation used by the developer or publisher themselves?
If not, is there any local translation that could be verified by big and credible gaming press locally,
and even to a point that usage is customary or even historical, like a legacy name?
If not, we just use the origin name in English or whatever it's from.
But when Indie Game Movie was published on Netflix late 2016,
Netflix changed almost all the names in our subtitle to use the names they found on Chinese Wikipedia,
which is almost at all times not official names.
Disrespectful or not, the main issue here is going to be discoverability on a storefront.
Because if people watching Indie Game Movie in Chinese
and saw name of the game,
and couldn't find it on any platforms that it's on,
are you doing any good,
or maybe you're actually hindering
the discoverability of the game.
And there's more to it.
So let's see how bad the Wikipedia translated names can be,
using Super Meat Boy as the example.
So let's see what's going on with this
Super Meat Boy's Chinese name.
The first two characters are simple,
the last two characters are simple, Super and Boy.
But the middle two characters, that means Carnivorous.
If you watched Indiana movie
or seen Edmund talk about this character before,
you know that it's about a concept
of without skin and protection.
And saying Meat Boy is carnivorous
is almost the opposite of the point.
And in fact, when the game was published by Microsoft Studios
onto XBLA for the first time,
they actually did a good job
on traditional Chinese localization
and give Midboy a cute Chinese name.
To use the same character twice here
is usually a way to emphasize the cuteness,
or in this case, it can also mean chubby as well,
without sabotaging the actual title of the game.
So the points here are, if you don't decide on a localized name yourself, you are leaving this kind of opportunity to others.
You should work with your translators on this issue if possible.
Because, as I said, it hinders discoverability on the storefront and also the perception of the game in that particular region.
And unofficial translations on Wikipedia is actually a real issue here.
I have no concrete idea how to solve this because you actually have...
no way to control Wikipedia editing.
And the next example I'm going to bring up is Thumper.
So back in mid-2016, Mark from Drool
asked me about the possible Chinese name for Thumper.
He already knew something's up
with the Chinese-speaking region
since his lovely wife is actually from Hong Kong.
Now let's do a small challenge in your mind
just for a few seconds.
If you know a second language other than English,
how and what would you name Thumper in that language?
Do you translate it by pronunciation or by meaning?
Or a bit of both, or neither?
What is your reasoning behind that?
I hope you can agree with me
that this is actually pretty hard.
I don't know if it's possible for developers to do this,
but there will be names that are hard to translate
and there are names easy to translate.
Let's just hope that you can land on something
that's easier to translate
and still being cool and unique in a way.
So an opposite example to Thumper situation is this.
Let's take a look at the manifold garden.
So sort of at the same time, mid-2016,
during early July, I invited the developer, William,
back to...
Taiwan and give a talk at our conference, which is
Type A Game Developers Forum 2016, and he just casually mentioned this to me
Saying that his friend suggested to him that he go with the name
This four character name which means infinite garden in Chinese as you can see it's very close to manifold garden
So this serves as an example of easy to translate names.
And infinite garden in Chinese still sounds pretty cool and true to the theme as well.
So William said he probably will go with this name in Chinese.
Of course, sometimes there are very good reasons to leave some specific things in your game
untranslated on purpose.
And I don't mean just the title but also other specific terms you created for your game.
because gameplay or design or aesthetic reasons
or maybe your translators just couldn't find a good corresponding term in the target language
However, when it comes to China, let me briefly talk about China's new policy here since late 2016
Basically, they have a mobile game content regulation citing other language-related regulations in China.
And as far as I know, somehow it is not only enforced on mobile games,
but also on console platforms that have branches in China.
It's either that, or there are similar regulations or laws for console and PC games that I didn't dug up.
Like there are several other related laws regarding general publication, online publication, online games
which more or less have the same context in China.
So these are the actual title of the regulation if you want to check them out.
Of course there are no English versions for these documents.
I only write them down, I write those notes down so that English speakers can understand.
If there are friends here who know more about the specifics
of the approval process in China,
please correct me if I'm wrong.
As far as I understand, the reason why Thumper
needed a Chinese name is exactly because of those regulations.
When he asked me about it back then,
he was trying to get the deal sealed
with the approval process in China.
But in fact, Sony had already sent names to the process
without Mark realizing.
three of them were pre-approved.
So basically, the developer had to choose
one out of those pre-approved names.
There was no other options due to time constraints,
since it's extremely costly to resubmit.
The official statement is that the process
usually costs one month, but what I've been hearing
is that it's between three to six months in the worst case.
So in China, Thumper is translated to rampaging beetle.
This is sort of an okay name considering the circumstances
and the other two pre-approved names were even worse.
So another example I want to talk about is Deemo.
So this game is from a pretty successful game studio
in Taiwan called Rayark,
which is best known for their rhythm games.
Deemo was released on PS Vita some time ago,
and during last year,
they were also trying to get approved in China.
In order to get approved, they translated the game title,
and also they have to show it next to the original title.
Other indie games on PSN China had to do this as well,
including Thumper.
But for Deemo, there are other stuff,
further complicated things.
So you see, this is the result menu
after you finish a song in a game,
and it originally looked like this.
And the simplified Chinese version got changed to this.
One interesting thing is that they didn't translate the...
There is a yellow text there, Hard Level 8, which is the difficulty of the song
They didn't translate, instead they just changed it to the corresponding text, to L8
And because Hard Level 8 in simplified Chinese is just so much more cluttered visually
than the original Hard LV8 text
And the approval feedback said if the English text or letters don't have obvious meanings,
you can leave them as is, but you have to translate everything else.
So LV in this context obviously means level, so they said it had to be translated.
Then the approval feedback also demanded them to translate all song names.
But
Then again, it didn't look as good, and the song names' textures were custom made by artists originally.
It would be quite impossible to redesign them all in simplified Chinese,
not to mention that some of the song names don't sound as good after translation.
So their compromise was they would show the suggested translation
for the song names on top right corner of the screen.
At one point, they were even asked to translate the composer names that will be shown in another menu.
But the composer names...
A lot of composer names actually are invented words.
That is not...
even translatable. And even if they are translatable, a lot of times composer names serve as a unique
trademark for them and should be universally used. It would be a huge problem for rhythm games if
the translation is enforced. Fortunately, the approval people in China finally understood that
and dropped the topic for the composer names.
A few things here.
First, I think negotiations during the approval process
is almost unavoidable.
And also, the approval feedback
could still be reasonable in the end,
but you need to be prepared for several
back and forth discussions that take up a lot of time.
And you need to put effort into modifying stuff
other than the usual things you already have to do
when doing general localization.
Since every game is different, though there are guidelines you can check out,
it is still hard to tell if your specific case will be approved or not in advance.
And I'm not even talking about other parts of the regulations.
They are just so much more detailed but up to interpretation, not exhaustive stuff.
So all that is already out of scope of this talk,
so I'll just stop there.
In short, suffice to say,
if you want to release on mobile or console in China,
find a good publisher.
And in the case of Thumper and Deemo
that I just talked about,
basically it's Sony helping them
dealing with all this approval and feedback process.
Okay, so go back to easier stuff, encoding.
Now, nowadays this should not be a problem anymore.
because you should be able to just stick to UTF-8 at all times.
But just watch out for this byte order mark thing that only Windows has.
When I was helping Indy get a movie during the subtitle,
at some point during their text processing,
the encoding was somehow changed into UCS2 slash UTF-16.
And we didn't realize that and made a mess for a little while.
Another big issue turned out to be that when UTF-16 and the UCS2 texts were being integrated
into the Indie Gamer Movie Player on Steam, there was a forced replacement of all carriage
returns with line feeds.
And because of the fact that UTF-16 characters are multibyte fixed length encoding.
The 0Ds and 0As which were carriage returns and line feeds in ASCII
were also used by multibyte Chinese characters in UTF-16.
So the force replacement ruined a very small portion of the subtitle,
like what's being shown here.
And we didn't even notice that before it got released on Steam.
So we have to fix that afterwards very quickly.
So I think the takeaway is that always check every related options in all the editors you might touch during the development process.
Unless, I mean usually it's not just you, it's all the people on the team.
Some people may do text most programmatically, and some people may use different editors because of specific reasons.
And bad stuff can happen and hide within all the sorts of places you might not think of.
So basically UTF-8 all the way.
Now this is a big deal here, UI and phone issues.
Here's the menu of Skull of the Shogun in simplified Chinese version on Google Play.
Of course the game itself was great, but at first glance at this screenshot,
even if you don't read Chinese, you should still notice there are Sirif and Sense Sirif phones mixed up with each other.
Under no circumstances should you do that.
And it's just strange why this was published as is.
Of course, the original developer, 17bit,
was not responsible for this.
I think another studio ported the Android version for them.
But again, the point here is just
that even if you don't read Chinese,
you should still be able to see the problem.
The second problem is also pretty common
when you try to localize into Chinese.
You see the button text is already
quite small on the top left.
But let me just show you the Chinese version.
So, the buttons on top left corner are totally unreadable.
So two things here.
Chinese characters just have a higher stroke density.
It's a fact.
So when you use small fonts,
English versions may still be readable,
but there's going to be some chance
that the Chinese version will be unreadable,
just like this.
Moreover, maybe because of the scale of the font settings
or just different...
the phone settings just different between different phone files.
When you want to draw it using the API calls,
say I want the texture to be generated from this 24 point glyph,
the end result might not be the same using different phones.
So like in one phone the 24 point character is like bigger than the other one.
And another example here is from the game Fez.
This is from the English PC version.
You see all the pixel art characters
are very cool and sleek.
But now the traditional Chinese PC version,
just by changing it into a pretty standard
sensory phone there, you start to feel
that there's a conflict in style
with the escape button down there already.
And now let's see the original Xbox 360 version of Fez,
which was an earlier release.
They used a different Chinese phone back then.
And this particular phone was sort of an equivalence
of Comic Sans in Chinese, which although was kind of cute,
I just don't think they are a good fit
for Fez in my opinion.
It's also worth noting that the different phones
were chosen for different platform releases.
Of course there could be multiple reasons why they did this,
such as the phone license was exclusive for 360 version.
We don't know, but this is also a real problem
we are trying to localizing for multiple platforms
because you might need different,
under certain circumstances you might need
different phones on different platforms.
And also, you see this spacing between the punctuation marks
and other Chinese characters and also the line heights.
Everything is just so cluttered.
and making quite hard to read.
This can also happen to a lot of localization process
and it's quite technical because you need to understand
the effect and the details of typography information
from a true type phone and such.
And the different phones for different languages
can just throw you off in all kinds of ways.
So finally some general concerns
about Chinese phone themselves.
The biggest problem we face collectively
is that the pricing is just so steep.
I have an actual quote from a Taiwanese phone company.
So if you want to embed a phone into your distribution
for one phone, they were charging it for 10,000 US dollars
per product, per platform.
It's just crazy.
And also there's a lack of choice.
Most of the time, you are left only with two standard choice, which is a standard looking series font and a standard looking sans series font.
Because Chinese fonts are just fucking hard to make.
You know, like, ASCII, 128 characters, it's pretty easy, right?
You can have thousands of font choices, and also, you know, you can have things like windings.
But for a Chinese font to have general purpose usefulness...
it has to, say, at least have 5,000 different characters.
And the average design difficulty for each character
is also way higher.
And to keep a lower cost on this,
especially for indie developers,
usually you would have to rely on system phones,
you know, calling from OS-specific APIs.
And it can be very hard to unify the looks and the style across platform.
Although I have to say the default Sans Serif font nowadays on different platforms
actually look more and more like each other nowadays.
So if you only need a style-neutral Sans Serif font,
you may be able to get away with just using the always default fonts.
But if for any reason you need a free and embeddable Chinese phone for your game, for Serif,
you can try Hanazono Mincho, which is a Japanese academia produced phone,
originally intended for Buddhism research.
I think it also covers all Chinese, Japanese, and Korean characters.
And for Senserif style, I think the best one currently is the Google NotoSense CJK series.
CJK stands for Chinese, Japanese, and Korean.
It was a brilliant collaboration between Google and Adobe.
There's also an open source phone project
called the Wunchan-E in China.
And they started the project many, many years ago
and it's also quite popular.
But Wunchan-E is licensed under GPL,
so there may be GPL implications.
And just for the sake of being thorough,
when it comes to phones,
there are also phone glyph design differences.
So the phone glyphs here on the left side are designed in Taiwan and the ones on the right side are designed in China.
And this is not about simplified or traditional differences.
Basically what I'm saying is, there are phones more suitable for Taiwan and some phones more suitable for China.
But actually it probably won't affect your gaming in any way.
If you really are interested in knowing more about this stuff, you can try looking into...
There's a book called CJKV Information Processing.
It's published by O'Reilly.
And the last category of issues, it's political and going to be pretty fun.
Although we've already seen a bit of this from the Pokmon thing.
Back in early 2016 in Taiwan, this is actually pretty huge.
Street Fighter V came out back then,
and what can possibly be political about Street Fighter V?
But as you recall, Street Fighter V has been developed
and promoted as an eSport-focused video game,
and they were doing all kinds of official push
for Street Fighter V eSports
in a way that is never seen before in the series.
Now locked in players can choose their own nationality
to represent themselves or their country.
And of course, national flag system was also designed.
But when it comes to Taiwan.
If you ever watched the Olympics or some of the Baseball World Cup games before,
you might recognize this flag as Chinese Taipei flag,
which is a flag that Taiwan is forced to use in actual international sports events.
But even then, there is something off about this flag.
It's a mash-up by Capcom people using Chinese Taipei flag and their own trademark.
I mean, what the flying F is this, Capcom?
A very famous Taiwanese Street Fighter player, Gamer B,
and a lot of Taiwanese, other Taiwanese players
try to send complaints about this,
but Capcom just gave a sorry, not sorry answer.
This is fairly new too, Winning Eleven 17,
also came out last year.
Or as you note here, Pro Evolution Soccer.
Actually, they really put into some serious effort for Chinese-speaking regions.
The game has complete Mandarin and Cantonese voiceover,
which is actually pretty fun when you imagine anchormen shouting in Cantonese.
But they also did this.
If you choose Taiwan in the country options,
it will warn you about not being able to attend any international games.
You know, as a Taiwanese gamer, I can only say that this game's realism is impeccable.
So, lastly, this example just came out a few months ago.
Yakuza 6 has a Taiwanese hostess that you can meet up.
One particular dialogue is about her homeland,
and this was the line when Yakuza 6 came out originally.
What is your impression of the country of Taiwan?
There is no English version of Yakuza 6 now,
so that's just my translation.
As a result, a lot of Taiwanese gamers were very proud of Sega at the time,
but not long after the screenshot was posted online and began to circulate,
some of the prominent internet personalities in China started to raise this issue,
and basically Sega bailed out.
So about a week later, the line became, you know, like this.
And from a production point of view, let's just be neutral about it,
from a production point of view, if you make mistakes like this,
mistakes like this, this is not just text changes, you know,
you have also to change the voiceover as well in just in a few days.
However, fun fact, Yakuza 6 isn't even released in China yet.
There is no simplified Chinese version as of now.
And as a matter of fact, the whole Yakuza series has never been officially released in China, ever, in the past.
Somehow Sega had to employ self-censorship over this.
So I guess this is quite interesting.
This is the kind of things you might run into when doing localization in Chinese.
So now let me just quickly summarize a few tips and conclusions.
So I've noticed this on a few occasions in the past.
There is this one symptom you can easily recognize
if your Chinese localization is machine translated.
So what you see here is the option menu
from Skull of the Shogun in the simplified Chinese version
on Google Play.
The option being highlighted here
is the language setting option.
The last character in that three-character term is , meaning person
And the language option should not be something person
Another language choice, it's a four-character word
If you see that particular character at the end of a Chinese word
it either means off something
or it's an empty word following a verb or an adjective
And still, the language option should not be like that
So if your language choices have something similar to those,
you know it's almost certainly machine translated.
And by extension, other parts of your localization
may be machine translated as well,
so you better do something about it.
And just for your information, if you don't know yet,
the term simplified Chinese written in simplified Chinese
look like that, and the traditional Chinese
written in traditional Chinese look like that.
So this is what your language options should look like.
Also, I talked about the converter issues
between simplified and traditional Chinese.
You don't want your translator ever to be using converters.
Although, if you don't know Chinese,
you cannot check if they use the converters.
But actually, that's not true.
What I'm going to propose here
might sound a little bit stupid,
but actually, you can find your own converter online.
There are ones with English interfaces on the web.
You can find the converter online and use that yourself,
and try to compare a small portion of the text
from traditional and simplified Chinese versions of your game.
You know, better to test a few longer sentences.
It should be pretty obvious if they are auto-converted,
because they will look the same as your output
from the converter you just used.
And you can then decide if something needs to be done about it,
like find another localization service or something.
But if you just want to check if your traditional Chinese localization is converted from Simplify,
there is a very simple way to tell that.
So if your traditional Chinese menu has this term, which is restaurant menu,
then this is 100% guaranteed a direct conversion from Simplify Chinese,
because the term is simply used like that in China.
It's sort of a legacy term.
But both Taiwan and Hong Kong don't use that.
Of course, unless you are making a restaurant game.
So next you have to know who you are working with.
Be sure to ask your localization service translator
or publishers to make sure whether they are doing
simplified or traditional Chinese or both.
Best case scenario, they should have different people
dedicated to simplified and traditional separately.
And please do not say just, you know,
we have that in Chinese.
Simplified or traditional, you have to specify.
Otherwise, it's just confusing.
If I see a game saying, we support Chinese,
then when I started playing the game,
I will assume that I'm going to
see traditional Chinese myself.
But if it shows up in simplified Chinese,
that actually can be a little bit annoying.
And actually, it's vice versa.
If you are using mainly simplified Chinese
and you see a game saying we have it in Chinese,
when it comes up as traditional,
it will also feel a little bit disrespectful or annoying.
Also, as a general idea,
work with your localization service or translators.
Provide them with enough context and references to work with.
Get them hands on your game.
If you have watched the movie Arrival,
you would get idea what it means to be on the scene.
If you haven't watched the movie Arrival, go watch it.
A spreadsheet full of just in-game text
can sometimes be very hard to work with.
Provide explanations for invented terms or special usages.
Specify quote sources, joke sources,
specify when you can allow translators
to deviate from your original text
to better fit a target audience, things like that.
And fan translations. Not saying that you should solely rely on this, but it can actually happen.
For example, there's a fan translated traditional Chinese version of the manual
for the game Keep Talking and Nobody Explodes, which is like 20 or 30 pages of PDF.
And also, one friend of mine in Taiwan helped on Epic with all its traditional Chinese translation
60 years ago.
just because he loved Unepic so much and happened to be a very professional translator himself.
And again, in my opinion, political stuff a lot of times is not avoidable, as a few examples I've brought up today.
What I'm trying to do here is present the situation to you and put these issues up on the table.
I think at least this is beginning, this is a beginning for further communication.
I'm perfectly comfortable with the possibility that all of you decide that you don't want to deal with Chinese localization anymore,
or maybe you want to just give up on traditional Chinese and Taiwanese players in the future.
But at least now that's done a decision from insufficient information.
I just want people to really recognize and understand that. That's all.
Finally, we all know this is not easy at all.
And as a game developer, it's difficult not to have the sentiment of like,
if only all people speak the same language.
So as the final point I want to make today is that
different languages and different cultures lead to diversity and uniqueness.
And I think they are the crucial parts of innovation in games as art and games as media.
So we can have more and more exciting new games in the future.
Every time I come to GDC, I'm always so impressed with the
diversity and the inclusiveness here.
I hope this talk brought you more insights into Chinese
speaking regions and more understanding of our
situation.
A quick shout out to these friends who have been a great
help during the preparation of this talk.
And thank you.
Please feel free, if you want to ask any questions, you can
line up to the microphone there.
I think we're...
Hi.
So my question is regarding the recent legislation
for no foreign language in Chinese game.
So specifically regarding credits and license text,
sometimes there's legal license text for software,
like an Apache license that you include in your credits.
Is that generally just fine to have that verbatim in English as the original legal text was presented
that you're required or is there going to be usually problems with credits and then also like
English names and things like that?
So for I think for documents that is not actually in the final version of the game.
I think...
So this would be like credits that are displayed in the game, like when...
during credits and like the license text. It's in the game, it's not a part of the gameplay,
but it is in the game, so...
From my understanding,
there are some exceptions to this, like...
they will give exceptions to some of the technical...
like the license documents you talked about.
So from my friends' experiences before,
they said there are some exceptions you can maybe tackle,
but the problem is that you really have to just negotiate
and try to go through this whole feedback
and approval process.
Cool, thank you.
Hi, firstly, I'm here to say sorry about the Pro Evolution Soccer example,
because I'm from the Pro Evolution team, so...
Thank you.
Sorry I didn't let you in the international competition.
I remember there was a serious discussion going about the definition of international competition.
So, sorry, I don't think this is a national competition.
I think it's just I want to present this situation to you guys,
because I don't think a lot of people actually...
really know that.
You know.
Right.
Yeah.
So, okay, my question is about the approval process actually.
My basic understanding is that the government is checking if all the known Chinese contexts are translated into Chinese language.
Do they even check if all the terms in the game are equivalent to what's common in Chinese?
I mean, we are dealing with lots of football player names.
for example, and we don't know what the official translated Chinese name for each player.
So we are now struggling with that.
And my question is just, do they even check the Pokemon example?
Like, are those words different from what you use usually in your country?
I don't think they will check that.
Yeah.
Yeah, I don't think so.
Okay, so they basically check if the context is translated in Chinese, like all the context.
Yeah, so basically if you want to translate, I think they are like people's names or specific
terms that may be used in China already, things like that. I think either you can look up those
and I...
So I think if it's not...
Well, you got me there.
So, like, you know, official translation for the support player's name, things like that.
I don't think those will be enforced by the...
China government. It may be enforced by representatives of, or maybe it's not reinforced,
it can be just that if you have a name that is not a common one, people would not get it recognized.
Okay. But I don't think that will get you blocked during the approval process.
Okay. Yes.
Okay. Thank you very much.
Okay.
OK.
Sorry.
So if you have other questions, you can just come up front.
And thank you for your time today.
And hope you have a, yeah.
Thank you very much.