Right.
Hi.
Thanks for coming, everyone.
It's really nice to be back at GDC,
back in the coolest numbered room in this whole building.
And to be showing Tearaway again, I showed it last year.
That time, very much focusing on the paper construction
of the world.
This time, I'm going to take a slightly different angle
and show some of the stuff that subverts what you might
think the game was about.
If you'd seen it in screenshots and you see this kind of.
This world of bright, kind of youthful paper craft.
You might not have necessarily realized that all of this other stuff,
the way that we sort of tore the fourth wall off the game world
and did all sorts of strange things with the context of the game
and sort of thought about the wider thing of this is a handheld game,
there's a world outside of it.
I'm trying to focus on more of that kind of stuff.
I can never resist talking a bit about paper,
so there will be some in here for paper fans.
So the title of the talk, let's get this started, get that.
Disturbing image of me off the screen.
Is believable, make-believe, how we built our fantasy world.
And built that world around the player.
And bringing the player into the narrative and into the experience.
allowing them to collaborate with the story in ways that were more than just moving the narrative forward
to actually sort of play a role, play a part, and feel very engaged with what was happening in the game.
Now, what I'll be talking about will...
It's kind of like highly...
It's highly flavored with our kind of medium molecule special
sauce, you know, and it's pretty spicy.
So, you know, it might not be exactly what other people would
be able to take and suddenly, you know, make an FPS with
Your face appearing in the sun or something like that.
But I think there's some core things behind what we were trying to do with the game
that are maybe interesting to think about.
And just the way that we've been a little more overt really with what a game is.
I'm also, I've actually forgotten to say,
tearing the fourth wall off this talk,
I've forgotten to say all the stuff I was supposed to say
about turning phones off,
so you've had like a couple of minutes
of being able to make phone calls before I said that.
And also, I think you probably, you would have been sent a survey thing.
So if you could fill that in and tell everyone how amazingly professional I am at pressing
the left arrow on a laptop while making my lips move, that would be much appreciated.
So let's start digging in further now.
So we should probably put some hearts on just to...
There.
Perfect.
So just in case that you've not seen Tear Away,
has anyone played Tear Away?
Oh, nice.
I like this room.
I was just going to play a trailer just
to kind of refresh our memories of how the game looked
a couple of years ago when we first announced it at Gamescom
and kind of remember the context at that point.
And I mean, it did develop on since then,
but I think it's still a good representation of what
the game was all about.
You should have got a better bed, better for your head, better heads meet sharp ties.
You should have got a better bed, better head for all you feel,
And then the bad dads leave, promise it to me, promise me they'll see.
Keep going, keep going, keep going, keep going.
Ain't got no time to make it, I'm on my way.
He was also over the image quality of the game, so some of the most unresponsive comments didn't show up.
If you changed the graphics too, the enemy player would have been in big trouble.
There was also a warning sign that said that the enemy player wanted to die, but it still didn't show up.
As a result of putting death in the comments, the game's game was delays and unanswered.
So I made a correction, and it's a bit frustrating.
You
So there we go.
Now obviously, as I started saying, it would be very hard
to talk about Tearaway without mentioning this stuff, paper.
It was really the main way that we achieved a believable, make-believe world
through the simulation of a world made of paper.
And it enabled us to have a fantasy world, but one that was realistically constructed.
Because it was made from an everyday material, it's one that we all recognize, we all understand.
It's kind of our way in.
It was just really important to the game to really ground the fantasy.
It united and unified our ideas.
And it really meant that we could go much more,
well, far crazier with all of the stuff that we would later add to it.
And it made that fantasy very tactile, very tangible,
and something that you really felt
that you could hold it in your hands
and see how it reacted to your input in very dynamic ways.
And plus it looks cool. You know, it's great colors,
you know, interesting shapes.
I kind of feel that it feels a little bit like sort of polygons have sort of sneaked out of the
digital world and come into our world. You know, this sort of strange alien shape you
only really ever get to see in a game. You suddenly see it sort of sitting on a desk.
But I'm not going to really focus on paper today.
You can hopefully still access the talk I gave last year on the GDC Vault,
which was all about the paper world, the paper engine that we used to build it,
showed how we pieced together each piece of paper and glued it all together
in just the same way that you would if you were...
building a real paper world.
I'm going to focus on some of the design decisions
and the process that we went through in coming up
with lots of the other elements of the game,
especially those ones that were to do
with what was going on outside of the paper world,
the features that really connected with the player
and made them part of the game and brought them
into the game.
So we've got this sort of sketchy, rough timeline
of how the development, how it played out.
All the time, looking at just how we could center it
around the player.
So like with lots of projects, we started off
with some new hardware.
New hardware means new ideas.
And just having the Vita for the first time
and sort of exploring it and wondering
what we could do with it, it had all these kind
of new functions that.
It hadn't really been possible before.
So that instantly gave us a starting point, a spark.
From that, we then concentrated on building out a world,
creating a fantasy landscape, something
that we could interact with inside of the Vita,
working out what that wider context was.
And then we discovered that that world we'd been building was just a bit too generic.
It was quite dull, really.
There wasn't really enough...
It wasn't really true enough to the initial first ideas of, like, really focusing on the hardware.
So that's when we had a game jam, and we really sort of pulled apart what a game was,
and really thought about, like, new ways to...
but to interact with the content that was inside of this digital box that you've got in your hands.
And then we went through an editing process,
because the ideas that we'd come up with
were pretty left field.
And we really needed to figure out
what of those experimental elements
were going to be usable in a shippable game,
and which ones also we could even take further and go
even more bizarre with them, really
get into the core of what was good about those experiments.
And having done that, we also needed to establish a goal of the game.
What was the player trying to achieve?
What would be the end result?
What would they get out of playing the game?
And just make sure that with all of this sort of new, strange interactions,
that there was still always a clear goal to keep them very focused and motivated
with this journey that they'd be going on.
And then we did that minor stage of building the whole game.
And then after that, we needed to figure out
as well simultaneously how we were
going to be able to allow the, let the player have
a feeling of authorship on this story
so that it was.
It became more like their world.
It started off as our world and then kind of
transferred to themselves.
So just rewinding back to our timeline, I'll go through all
of these stages now in a bit more detail.
So back to our initial new piece of hardware and a weird
idea on how we could use it.
So here's what we started off with, PS Vita.
As you've played Tearaway,
you've probably seen one of those before.
It's kind of an intriguing box.
It's very shiny, covered in inputs
and new ways to kind of touch it
and get responses from it.
But also, it's got the classic controls on there as well.
So there's a huge amount of scope with what
we could do with it.
I mean, that's obviously a promo shot of how you're kind
of supposed to interact with the Vita.
But what I really wanted to do was something more like that,
where you could actually pick it up.
And by pushing on the bottom of the Vita actually tear your fingers up through the world and see them kind of
erupting up into the
into the the game world inside.
I mean, it was obviously something that we couldn't do on any other hardware, which made
it kind of compelling to try out this idea.
And it straightaway suggested that you were doing something, well, it was more connected
with the wider context of what was outside of the game console.
You know, as you're pushing your fingers in, you can see.
There's like a little hole and you would be able to see a little bit of video through there and see the floor and it sort of, you know, it starts to unite these two worlds together.
And the way that the player holds the device,
and it becomes very important.
It means that obviously their fingers
need to match with their hands.
So we needed to make sure that we got the skin color right,
and the size and shape so that it really
felt like their fingers.
And it really had this sort of strange feeling of, it makes you look at your fingers again,
like, you know, they're quite strange objects when you really stare at them.
Our technical artist, Stefan, is kind of haunted by staring at very close-up images of giant fingers.
Because...
Placing them in this new world makes them look both very alien,
but also kind of reassuring as well.
Just like the paper, it's a way of understanding
there's a bit of our world in this other completely different world.
And I think that's kind of a quite good way of summing up the game,
really, in some ways.
It's sort of like reassuring, but also kind of quite alien as well,
and the combination of the two.
So here's a very early video from this time of just how the
game could have started.
This is actually very similar, weirdly, to how the
game actually ended up, with the rift kind of being formed
between the real world and then the fantasy world inside it.
You actually get a little tiny glimpse of the finger popping up into the world, but it is a very tiny glimpse, so blink and you'll miss it.
The finger's actually dressed up as a lion as well, just to add an extra layer of bizarreness on top of it.
So here we go.
There we go. Short and sweet. The end.
So, yeah, I mean you can see there already, you know,
the world's sort of starting to come together.
But here's some very early piece of concept art,
which is quite abstract.
You know, started to see little things
like the video feed poking in through the background.
You can see the finger poking up in the foreground,
although it doesn't actually look anything like a finger.
It kind of looks like a brown egg.
It's not that understandable.
It's kind of quite hard to understand what's going on in the scene.
Although the one thing I really like is that the gophers there
actually ended up in the final game.
They're like the earliest piece of artwork that stayed all the way through the project.
But, you know, we were really trying to sort of pare this back and figure it out.
And we really needed to just take it back a bit more to what was in front of us, what was around us directly.
And, you know, here's what's directly in front of me at work, which is apparently a desk.
You know, it's just covered in paper and doodles.
And our whole studio is kind of quite a chaotic,
creative bundle of stuff.
And as we were doing these early stages,
we were sort of pulling together all these concept art,
like the image you just saw,
and we were printing them out.
And they were just building up around us, and that started to become a more interesting environment than the imagery that we were creating.
So, you know, that's where we really pushed the paperiness a lot further and really developed that as a...
It's just the over, the kind of unifying look for the whole game, so that we could actually be kind of more experimental with the content, and be more realistic with the way that it was constructed.
You know, it would...
It was sort of, well it would just make our fantasy world like very very believable
And and it was important that the world it wouldn't just it wouldn't just look different, but it would it would feel different
Whilst remaining very approachable and and very relevant as well
Because it was because it was so sort of realistically constructed we could then go we could go you know pretty out there with
what we were making with it.
So that's kind of...
I'm going to stop talking about paper now.
I've done my paper bit.
I'll move on with the rest of the game now.
There we go.
So this was the starting point in our design process,
this idea of pushing your fingers
into our papery world.
That was just this novel interaction.
And it really needed more of a game world around it.
The actual game was unclear for a while and went through a number of iterations,
transforming from an isometric dungeon crawler,
which you kind of controlled with your finger as the character,
all dressed up like a lion, as you saw just now.
And then we tried out a more sort of 3D RPG style,
because...
The change in that direction was so that we could,
we wanted to feel like we could explore
this paper world more, you know,
it's a very different type of experience.
So, you know, we really wanted to be able to
sort of look at it up close and see off
and see vistas of this sort of, of this material
and see what that meant to build a world
that looked like that.
So we started working on this, let's move this on.
We started working on a 3D paper world that you could travel through.
This was a little character that we created when we realized that controlling the game just with your fingers,
using the back touch all of the time, was quite a hard thing to expect of a player.
It wasn't, you know, ergonomically, it wasn't that comfortable really.
So, and we wanted to have a little character that was in the world, you know, someone that could sort of respond more to...
If you're pushing your fingers in, you know, it's kind of nice to have someone to actually react to this, rather than you just sort of looking at it, you know.
It's like the old, if a tree falls down and there's no one to hear it, does it really make a sound?
Where it's like, if a giant finger rips up through the floor and there's nobody to see it, was it really there?
Um... possibly not.
So, uh, this was, this was, uh, the, the 3D world that we were
building at this time. I can, there we go, at night as well.
Um, but it wasn't really, uh, showing, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh,
It wasn't really sort of involving the player that much.
You were essentially just pushing up on the stick.
It didn't really suggest how you could do novel things to this world,
how you could reach into it, how you could...
you know, started doing more dramatic or chaotic things,
didn't really have a good way to allow the pushing of your fingers into the world.
There didn't seem to be a particularly strong reason for that to happen
and it would only happen very few and far between.
And we needed the player to be...
to be much more sort of present outside of the game world, like all the time.
So it's really reinforced and it's not just, you know, it doesn't just happen occasionally.
So, to be honest, you know, we just wanted to go a little weirder.
So we kind of took a step back and went into a new phase, which was Game Jam.
Which, you know, we knew we had enough of the game to make a fairly sort of generic experience.
But we really wanted to challenge ourselves to do something a little bit better than that.
something a little more experimental and surprising.
And just generally do something that really supported
that oddness at the core of the starting idea, really.
And just build out from what we could
do with this hardware platform.
So in order for it to be a successful game jam,
we really needed to have a really good subject to jam on
so that we could actually go kind of wilder.
with our experiments and judge them.
So we jammed on this idea of it being
a world held in your hands.
You know a world that knows
Knows about the player outside of the game world
and and and sort of make something more of the way that the world like
Responds to them being outside of it the way that they're holding the Vita the way that they're they're looking at the Vita
You know because it felt that that there was a nice sort of truthfulness in that really you know games are often kind of trying to
simulate
Well, pretend they don't exist, almost.
You know, and I think tutorials are often hated
because they kind of remind you that it's a game, but
it felt like it would be really true to actually say,
yes, this is a world that you're holding,
and, you know, it's inside your game console.
The characters in there are looking up and seeing you.
And it felt like it made a much more interesting relationship.
And that truthful realism, that really chimed with me as well.
Because I'm particularly inspired as a child
and continue to be now by stories
that have got a fantasy that's really
based on some kind of realistic starting point.
So that the fantasy then felt more believable.
And I think what was great about those was
that then you could be more inspired
to create your own fan art and kind of,
you know, add your own stuff to it
and really expand out that fantasy
because it had a sort of, a fact underneath it
that was very truthful that you could understand
and build upon.
So I mean, I'll just rattle through a couple of quick examples, but
Where the Wild Things Are is a really big influence.
The kind of kid, like, you know, sort of escaping from the real world
into this more fantasy world where he can just have a great big wild rumpus
like lots of us did last night.
And also Time Bandits, another favorite of mine,
where the fourth wall kind of actually does get torn off.
And Labyrinth, another fantastic film.
Because they're all pieces of fantasy,
but they're based on a realistic core, and kind of quite
a mundane core, really.
Like, the center of Labyrinth is really Sarah's bedroom.
It's like her creative sanctuary.
It's filled with her personality and her creativity.
All these decorative elements around the room,
they all gradually form the basis of the fantasy world
that she's transported to later in the movie.
It's not really clear whether the items in the room
have influenced her to create this fantasy
or whether the fantasy is inspired
by the things in the room,
but it's just the way that the two are really intertwined.
So if I zoom in on a little bit of it, Blade Runner style.
There we go.
You know, you can see there the Escher drawing on the wall
and then you see later on,
there she is kind of in that environment.
I think it's the way that the, all the characters as well, you know, you can see them represented
in the stuffed toys that are scattered around on her floor.
It just makes it the surreal adventure from the everyday objects around her, you know,
it's very personal to her.
And that felt like a pretty interesting concept to have behind the game as well.
You know, this fantasy world seen through the eyes of like an everyday person.
But obviously we can't cast an actor to play the gamer, you know.
It's got to be the gamer themselves.
So we needed to like actually think a little bit about,
well, what can we say about our gamer?
You know, we can't have a Sarah.
We've got to have, it's got to be the person holding the Vita.
So, you know, we kind of...
This was, this needed to be the reality that we would base it off.
You know, the way that someone is holding it.
You know, we knew one fact about someone playing a video game,
and that's, you know, they're pretty likely to be playing a video game.
So, you know, and that became, you know, it's fairly obvious, really.
But, you know, it's kind of an important thing to bear in mind, really.
And when we started with this process, you know, we knew that it would be a handheld game.
So we knew that, you know, players would be holding it with their hands.
And we'd already made a thing of the fact that you could push your fingers in.
But we also knew they'll probably be looking at it with their face, so maybe we could do something with their face.
It's always going to be in pretty much the same place staring down on the game world.
And also, they're pretty likely to have items all around them,
you know, items that are important to them, you know,
the little pieces of everyday treasure that you have
around yourself, like it might be your wallet or a photo
of a loved one or, you know, a glass of orange juice.
And, you know, it felt that we could maybe, you know,
combine all of these elements and start sort
of building a fantasy out of them.
to draw the player more into this fantasy
because it would be all things that they recognize
and they know that it's been partly based on them.
So that was really the basis of our game jam,
to just think about, well, okay,
so someone is holding this world in their hands,
looking at it with their face.
What's the greatest context of the world around them?
What items do they have with them?
And through our timeline, we really got together as a whole team and did various experiments
to work on these ways of drawing the player in and making something of their existence
in the game world, to make it a world held in their hands.
So I've got a couple of videos from this period.
So this first one is Omar.
There's Omar down there.
Give us a wave, Omar.
Let's get him going.
I've been testing using the face detection to, when I roll my head.
So it's using the front camera?
Yeah, it's using the front camera and seeing my face and evaluating the roll of my face
and rotating the camera accordingly.
This very important door opens up when you smile.
It just freaks out.
Oh wow.
Hang on, your smile is doing that?
Yeah.
It's a bit dodgy.
It only recognizes Omar's smile though.
That's kind of the idea.
That's very cool.
There's a lot of issues, but it's kind of here to exhibit the design and technical issue
and see how we can design around that, maybe use that for something.
There's other parameters that the library gives us, such as we can have a glass door that only opens if you have glasses.
It could be a door, though.
It could be a girl door.
It can be a girl doll.
Only open if you're a girl.
No.
So that's, I guess, that's a bit,
I'm trying to get that in a state enough that it's kind of working in the game
without breaking the rest of the game.
It's very experimental but maybe you can find used to that.
Well, that's great. That's helpful.
Yeah. Cool. Great.
So it's something quite experimental.
It's also my desk there.
Whoops.
Let's move on.
And here's Matt.
He was also working on some experiments as well.
This is one using the microphone,
thinking about how we could use audio to draw the player
into the world as well.
So let's.
The first part of a megaphone.
I was trying to think how we could do the recording voices a good way.
I'm not sure I've got it in the right place.
So this is his megaphone object, and if you hold down this button, he holds it above his head,
which allows you to talk into it.
So you're like,
CABBAGES!
And then when you press this button,
It's powerful enough.
Can't do.
You can drop it as like a mine.
Bit silly.
Does it work with any vegetables?
With vegetables?
Carrots, doesn't work with lettuce.
So actually, I'm going to skip through that one.
Let's move on to, well, there's a little bit of paper,
just to keep me happy.
There we go.
So through this mixture of the whole team experimenting
with all these different things, I mean,
I had certain things I wanted to try, and Dave Smith,
he also wanted to try a bunch of stuff.
But everyone could really get involved
and try out their own ideas.
And we ended up with quite an overwhelming list.
So we had things like.
which you could tap the back of the Vita
and things would fly in the air.
We had allowing you to put fingerprints on the landscape
and sort of make it messy so that you really felt
like you were touching the land.
Flicking glue around, matching,
using the camera to match the color of the camera feed
with the things in the world.
Face detection so that we could angle the camera
depending on how you're looking at it, and the gravity
using the gyros the way you were tilting the world, having the Vita buttons actually inside of the world.
So it's like that's kind of a quite a mad thing.
As you saw or heard,
sound recording, bringing in the player's voice is a powerful force.
A really big one was actually bringing in this feeling of a pop-up book
and making the world fold and unfold
and how that really pushed the gameplay forward
as a 3D environment that you could traverse.
Record scratching,
beard doors,
that should probably be a bullet point on any game.
Augmented reality, like actually allowing the character to come out of the game and
start running around on your podium when you're trying to do a conference.
Using the front touch to unpeel things.
Using crafting so that you could actually cut out bits of paper and move them around.
I don't know what that last one is.
Growing.
It's going off screen.
Maybe it's growing a beard to open a door.
I don't know.
So having got all of that stuff, it's quite an overwhelming list.
So we really needed to edit it.
We really needed to think, what could we actually
have in the game that would?
that could guarantee a certain level of experience for all players.
And I think the big takeaway from this period was learning the things that would require...
require skill and timing, and should require skill and timing.
And then separating those from the things that are just there to make you laugh,
to make you feel, you know, an emotional reaction to the world, to make you, you know, just enjoy yourself.
And, you know, that was just a really core thing for us, you know.
We tried out this idea of having
I
mean
it has been written.
Maybe you haven't got like studio quality lighting in your house.
So, you know, it felt like we just...
It was much better to just allow players to go,
right, I want that bridge to be pink.
And, you know, they take a photo of a pink thing and they move on
rather than just being blocked all the time by having to solve,
you know, sort of hard problems with this kind of stuff.
Leave all of those...
Those activities for the more platforming things with the folding, unfolding world, the drums, you know, those kind of elements.
And the same went for Matt's sound recording experiment
that you just heard.
We tried it as this sonic weapon,
using the player's voice as a way of blasting the enemies
away and unfolding the papery landscape.
And while it was fun for a few seconds,
and it's kind of entertaining when you see it in a short
video, it didn't really hold up as a long-term experience
of going on this journey.
So let's just play it a couple of times, just to annoy Michelle.
So we paired it back, so it just became a character.
We wanted to get the most out of it,
which was seeing the way that the world was responding
to this bellowing voice.
So instead of having it happen all over the place,
we brought it down and made it more characterful
by turning it into a scarecrow.
So that, you know, the player would get a more memorable, less repetitive version
that felt more helpful to the world because you were actually helping a specific character.
And also probably, you know, it lowers the chance of players getting arrested for playing in a public place.
So, you know, that's always good.
And the face tracking tech for the beard doors,
well, that was just too glitchy.
We wouldn't have been able to ship a game with that.
But we really enjoyed the way that it made you smile,
made you sort of think about what you were doing with your face while you were playing.
You know, so it felt like there was something there,
but that wasn't the right implementation of it at that point.
So, you know, we knew by this stage that we had our paper world coming together.
We knew that we were going on a journey through the paper world, you know, with our little
messenger character.
But our goal was really to involve the player more directly than usual.
You know, we wanted to push it further and give the player, you know, an actual visual
identity in the game.
And it was trying to figure out how we could get that same feeling of pulling facial expressions
and that we saw in the beard doors, but not letting the technology get in the way of that
really.
So, you know, we knew that the character would be trying to progress through this world and get to a goal to reach on this adventure.
And it needed to be visual, you know, they needed something to walk towards.
And it needed to be something that they wouldn't need a, you know, crazy mini-map to find.
And so many folk tales have the sun as the core of their
as their stories, you know, that it's like the starting point for
you know a world's creation or often used as a climax for the world's end. So, you know, a sun is a very very recognizable
you know thing up in the sky, but just walking towards it as a goal of the game didn't seem very compelling.
But you know, maybe if it was broken
If it was torn open and it revealed the player looking through,
they would then be ever present in the game.
And it would start to be a story about reuniting the character with the player.
So that really established the goal of the game,
guiding the in-game character back to the player
so that they could be reunited.
And that kind of elevated the player's importance
in the story.
It made it a more meaningful relationship
between the two of them.
And it really, it meant that they were pulling faces
and they were doing all of the things that we were talking about,
you know, seeing that video just now,
but now they're just doing it for their own entertainment.
It meant that instead of, in a cut scene,
instead of pressing the skip button,
you know, they're actually just kind of getting involved with the drama
and kind of pulling their own faces and acting things out.
A bit like this little example,
you see the two of them looking at each other.
Quite cute.
And essentially, we got this sort of hyper-realistic main
character for free.
We didn't need 50 customization sliders to make
it look like the player, because it is the player.
So that's quite handy.
But it is a divisive feature and not everyone, you know, for some it's been their favorite part of the game,
other ones, you know, it's less so, but a few people have said, you know, it should be something that you can toggle on and off.
But, you know, I think...
I think that would be a huge shame.
It's not like you would turn off Ellie in Last of Us.
They're a core character in the game.
So I think they really need to be there.
I think it's really important sometimes in design
to make a big decision like that
and make something that, well, sort of divides people a little more
just so that you make something really memorable for some people.
Yeah, let's put some hearts on just to show that.
So moving on through our timeline,
we're getting towards the end now.
We were now in the process, we've done our game jam, we've edited it down, we've established the goal of the game.
And now we were building the world, the most intensive phase.
There's not quite so much to say about that, but something that was very important throughout the whole experience was making sure that...
The player was just having positive feedback all of the time to really draw them through this world
and make sure that everything was being rewarded.
Every footstep they took was just getting pleasant visual feedback as they progressed on through the world.
And, you know, the world is just celebrating the player's presence the whole time, you know,
just sort of spawning particles and hearts and, you know, just being really, really happy
about the fact that they're there.
You know, I think a key point, when I was talking about the sun earlier, is that
All of these characters are looking up at the sun and, you know, sort of like almost
worshipping it.
So, you know, that should, you know, hopefully feel like a nice experience for any player
like looking in.
And then as the game was forming,
we knew that we wanted it to be more than just our story.
We wanted the players to be able to add to it,
so that it would gradually transfer the ownership from us,
the people that started making it, to them.
I started the game with the line, this is not your world.
It's a world of stories.
The idea being that it's kind of like a folk tale
of that.
You know, it gets told and retold.
The basic structure is there, but the details change each time because this is this massive
wild card that gets introduced every time, which is the player themselves.
And the way that we did that was through lots of simple and almost instant customization,
lots of creativity, which all adds up.
Because that was kind of the most...
Well, the strongest way to really set the player at the heart of this world
was to make it their world as they progressed through it.
Yes, so we'd learned from LittleBigPlanet, you know, like what amazing, amazingly complex things people will make if you give them the tools.
But it's something that not everyone does.
So for Tearaway, we really wanted to make sure that it was very inclusive and everyone could create and add.
So, you know...
Like using cameras and things like that just made it very, very quick and easy to change
bits of the environment.
You see here with this elk, you know, you can almost instantly make him spotty.
Which just makes him very happy.
You know, and photography became a huge part of the game.
Because it's a very democratic form of creativity.
If you've got a beautiful world to photograph,
then obviously everyone can take beautiful photos as a sort of baseline, really.
But adding on top of that, we added filters and other things
so that players could go deeper and add their own elements to...
to that system.
You know, it became more like Instagram, really, where, you know, you can make something look
cool in the time that it just takes to press a button, essentially.
You can't fail that challenge.
And there wasn't any point in us creating, you know, sort of impossible algorithms to
try and figure out if someone had made something that looked good.
You know, it's kind of, it's up to them if they're happy with it.
And if they're happy with it, they'll probably want to share it out as well.
So, you know, we produced a system so that they could do that as well.
And then for many in LittleBigPlanet, choosing costumes was a way that they customized their
experience without delving into the level creation.
And for Tearaway, we didn't really want to go down the same route of having ready-made
sort of costume pieces.
But it felt that without having character customization,
it was much harder for the player
to feel the bond with this messenger
that they're going to be taking through the world.
So one of the engineers on the Tearaway team, Nathan,
he wanted to give the ability to cut out bits of paper
and create a similar feeling for character customization.
based entirely on what you could do with a cutting mat
and a pair of scissors and some bits of paper.
And when he first pitched it to me, I was a little bit concerned that it was quite easy
that it could be a huge amount of feature creep and it could really bloat out into something
huge.
So it was really important for us to really stick to that real world metaphor of the cutting
mat and the pieces of paper.
Just to make sure that it stayed very real and very well.
Like, if you actually did have a cutting mat and you met a squirrel with delusions of grandeur,
you know, you could quite easily sort him out with a crown.
Here's some images that I grabbed off our website, showing a lot of the creativity that
players have been doing.
None of them are particularly complex.
Most of them are quite similar.
But the important thing is that they're the personal creation of everyone that made them.
And we chose to make this Challenger crown because it's such an easy shape to describe.
But it's also one that you can add your own details onto, you know, if you want to collage
a load of gems or...
You know, extra details on them. That's all, it's all possible.
But ultimately, you know, they get to stick them on a cute character
that's being, you know, professionally animated, so that, you know,
they kind of feel like they've made the squirrel because, you know,
it's kind of unified, you know, their bit of the world and ours together.
And then that extends on into being able to do it for the main character as well.
And plus, also, you know, when you make a system like that,
you allow people to make all sorts of things as well,
which you might recognize.
But I'm not going to say what they are.
You know, I mean, I think it's, I would rather people make,
you know, their own imaginative characters,
but I think fan art's a really good way to start.
You know, it's a way to learn and experiment and work
within the parameters of...
of the other IPs that they're aiming at.
Developing this also really showed how we needed a selfie camera,
otherwise you'd never be able to see any of these images.
So then the final point I'd like to make
was that once we built this fantasy around the player
and let them, well, we wanted to allow them to sort of close
that loop, really, and just take all of this world out
of the game.
It wasn't just a world around them in a sort of digital way.
It actually was possible to bring that world kind of physically around them.
So that we could get more of this sort of feeling from Labyrinth again.
So, we all know about 3D printers and how they're the...
The future of turning digital things into physical things.
But for Tearaway, we went a little more old school.
We went for 2D printers.
They kind of sit around being all beige and unused
and unloved.
And they don't really get to have any fun with video games.
So we designed all the mechanisms, the reward systems
in the game so that the player could then print out
the things that they find.
You know, take them out and print out all of these things as like physical trophies.
With the aim of making these what would normally be a digital trophy, like, really make mean something.
Make it tangible and not only visible to other players of that particular game,
but make them visible to everyone, you know, out in the real world.
To make them real, not just a fantasy.
And obviously, you know, if players actually make that paper craft trophy themselves,
then it becomes theirs, it becomes unique to them.
You know, unlocking it in the game is like the initial challenge that everyone has,
but creating it in real life is when it really becomes their own object.
So, kind of a little summary.
Some of the examples of how we tried to merge the player's world with the world that they were playing with
to make something a little more interesting out of the mundane and really put the player at the heart of it.
We gave players a way to play in our fantasy world
through a material that they would recognize and understand.
We tried to then make it very relevant to their lives
by drawing in what was around them,
using the cameras and the microphone
to sort of treat their world
like a sort of photographic texture library, almost,
of how they could unite the two systems.
And making sure that they could easily add to it with challenges that were almost instantaneous,
but that were additive.
So they would, over time, they would really sort of change the world in ways that were
far beyond what they thought they were capable of themselves.
And then also we needed to figure out when to challenge the player,
but also when to just celebrate them and just let them, you know, have free reign and enjoy
the mechanics that we were supplying them with.
And then finally, just treating the game as a starting point
so that they could hopefully start building this world
outside of the game or actually get involved
and have some other creative experiences that don't actually
have anything to do with the game at all,
but just enjoy making.
And that is pretty much me done.
Thank you.
Do we have any questions?
I think that might be a no.
Oh, sorry.
So much light over there, I can't see you.
Hello.
Hi.
Great talk, thank you.
Thank you.
I was wondering how long it took to make the game
and how long the game jam was in relation to that, too.
So, how long was the game and how long was the game jam?
Well, the game in total development was about two and a half years, I guess.
And the game jam... I mean, we had a very concentrated period, which would have been...
I guess maybe a month or two.
But once we'd done that, then it became more sort of part
of the culture of Tearaway so that we would have mini ones
as we proceeded, which kind of got shorter
as we sort of figured out the mechanics more and more.
But yeah, so yeah, I guess.
It's obviously a smaller part of the overall development time,
but a very important one.
Great.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Thank you for remembering me how amazing the game was
in the first place.
The question is, I loved it so much.
There was only one thing that kind of annoyed me.
I was wondering if you guys had any problem with that
during designing and testing.
Some of the animations of the paper things
like really change every few frames, not on a smooth basis.
I understand where this comes from.
But on the other hand, the other animations,
like character animation, are very smooth.
So kind of my perception was this kind of disjoint
of this trying to simulate how we did a classic animation
with paper, changing like 10 times a second, not 30 or 60,
but the other part being smooth.
So did you have any thoughts about that?
So I'll try to summarize that.
Yeah, so the different frame rates of the paper.
I mean, to be honest, we designed it so that everything animated was not animated at full
frame rate.
So all of the characters are animated at like 15 frames a second, so that they do still
have that stop motion.
But you maybe don't see it quite so much because they're smaller on the screen.
But I mean, it was important to us to get that sort of aesthetic of feeling like the
paper was coming to life.
It was kind of self-conscious about the fact that it's moving.
But obviously, the game needed to run at full frame rate
in order for you to move around and have
kind of action-based gameplay.
So we weren't sure for a while whether we
would be able to unite the stop-motion style
with full-motion movement.
But I feel that we got a good balance there.
Thank you.
Okay, well, thank you very much.
I think I probably need to say about the form again,
so if you could do that, that'd be amazing.
Thank you for coming, and see you again.
Cheers.