Thank you, thank you, thank you all.
So, hi, my name is Jonas Turner and I am a sound designer and voice actor.
Today I'm going to be telling you my personal insights on how to make a game feel better with sounds,
or how you can enhance a game feel with sounds.
This is like a 20-hour massive talk compressed into 20 minutes.
So let's do this.
So my name's Janus Turner.
I work at E-Studio.
That's a sound studio back in Helsinki, Finland.
E-Studio has its roots in music production.
That is recording, mixing.
mastering, producing music and so on and so on.
And I was hired over there a few years back in 2012 to bring my video game sound design
stuff over there.
So woohoo!
I have my own room.
It's just like home with parents, I have my own room.
So here are some of the games I worked on.
I did sound design and voice acting for Nuclear Throne.
I did sound design for Badland.
I did mainly voice acting for Broforce.
I did some sound content too, like alien sound effects and stuff.
We had a small team in Environmental Station Alpha, and I was the lead sound designer on that.
We had a slightly bigger team on Angry Birds Transformers, I did the lead sound design on that too.
Sound design on Downwell, some additional sound content for TurboDisk Mount, and...
...reverb programming, and...
final mixed stage stuff for the swapper and the list goes on and on and on. If you want to know more, get me a beer and we'll talk.
Wow, we are recording this. So, you can still get me a beer though.
And I design games as a hobby, I've been doing that for quite some while.
Cool, enough about me, let's go on into the subject.
So, first off, things to think at the design phase.
First off, what's the game like? That's a basic question.
And what's the main focus of the player?
So, be sure to choose the focus.
So let's say if it's like a shooting game, you have to...
like battling, shooting, dodging, ducking for cover and stuff.
Keep that in mind and try to make the best out of it.
You can think about ambiences and stuff, but...
Put your main focus on what's the player doing, what's the core thing of the game.
Think about that. If it's like a football game, kicking the ball.
Start to think of things how to make that feel nice and like, just juice that.
Or car game, you're driving and steering the car or whatever, tired of screeching.
Put your thought into stuff like that.
Take a piece of paper, put like, okay, this is a card game.
Shuffling cards must feel good.
Stuff like that. Just basic. Start with that.
When you have that in your mindset,
you will already be like, hmm.
So, to make the game feel better,
I need to juice this stuff.
And it's in your subconscious already.
So when you start creating sounds, you're like,
is this good enough? Hmm.
So keep that in mind.
Think about cues to make people listen to the game,
or listen to the UI, and not to look at UI.
Like an action game.
Sorry, UI artists, by the way.
But think about an action game.
There's shooting happening.
Monsters coming from there.
Alien, oh no, underground worm attacking you.
You don't want the player to be looking at UI.
You're like, no, no, I have to be in the middle of the battle.
Then you're like, how many bullets have I got?
You don't want to do that in an action game, you don't want to give players like...
You want to give the players like action, not reading a book.
So think of like audio cues to make that happen.
Like let's say you're shooting, you're out of bullets,
you could have the player shout like,
oh, I'm out of bullets, or make like clang of metal like,
and you know, okay, I'm out of ammo, or about to be out of ammo.
So keep that in mind instead of like...
Come on, that's not action.
So think of stuff like that.
When people base actions on sounds, you know that's a good thing.
Think about music.
Sound effects and voiceovers blending together,
like potential frequency clashes.
If you have music going, boom, boom, crazy bass, horns,
like all the time, the sound effects are like, boom, boom,
and then the voiceover is like a mutant going, blah, blah, blah.
Like, all that together will make the game feel muddy, you're going to have crazy busyness happening on,
loss of focus, sometimes that's a desired effect, but throughout the game that's probably not what you want.
So, think about like...
Think about like, um...
Bringing the designer and composer together to work on the project.
Like, okay, composer, what do you want to do?
Oh, you want to do that? I want to do this.
How do we make these two work together?
So get your composer and sound designer together in the same room or Skype or something.
That's already going to make it way better.
You could have dynamic systems. I'm going to talk about those later.
Just make sure the feel of the game is number one.
And for you musicians, if you want to, like, release an official soundtrack
this is the best sounding thing I've ever done.
It doesn't need to be that in the game.
A soundtrack itself can be a separate entity for what's in the game.
Just make sure what's in the game complements everything.
And create something unique.
What I mean by this is make something that people think this game is unique.
that game. For instance, a language, creating a language for a game might be a good way
to do this. As an example, for Nuclear Throne, I wrote this language, created this language
called Trastalk that the mutants talk, and the enemies have a different dialect of that.
So that already gives like
world building. It already makes the world feel like a living world in a sense.
And what I have in the game is when the players enter a world it's like
stuff like that. So I have that happening. So that already feels I know I'm going to a new level,
new world, like when the monster shouts that. And the cool thing is sometimes you see players,
like I've seen players play another game and they go to a new level and they're like
flash and I'm like
that already gave them a nice memo of the game.
You could do success sounds like, doo-doo-doo-doo, you made it, like doo-doo-doo-doo, hey.
Stuff like that.
Just something that makes the game feel like the game it is.
Make the game feel unique.
One thing I would say try to avoid is you have this game doing the inception thing,
that game doing the inception thing, that too.
Wow, you all made the inception.
Good job.
So try to be...
a bit original.
That will already make the game feel like your game.
I have to go really fast through all this.
So let's jump into creation.
Plan on gear slash chain.
What I mean by this is, usually when I start a project, I decide what microphone and what
preamp.
I will use for all the action sounds.
So like jumping, opening doors, explosions, stuff like that.
I would always use the same pair, like same mic and same preamp for all of these sounds.
Like I would be really strict about it.
And let's say for voiceovers, I would use that microphone and that preamp.
And for the enemy voiceovers, I would use that microphone and that preamp.
Stuff like that.
And what this does is...
It kind of makes these sounds be in the same sonic space.
Like, they are already, like, all the action sounds will feel the same
because they are recorded with the same stuff.
All the voiceovers will feel the same because they are, you know, you know.
And that just makes the world feel more believable.
It's the same ears listening.
Like, it makes sense, right?
And what I mean with chain is, you know you have, like, Pro Tools,
Nuendo, Cubase, Ableton, like, whatever.
You have a software.
You have all the layers here.
OK, I have that for clothes, that for metal, clanking, whatever.
And all these make one sound.
And they go through the master chain.
So what I would do if this master chain is,
I would always have the same dynamics processing,
like same limiter.
a saturator, if I want to use that in the game, like give some distortion feel to the game,
I would always have the exact same effects processing in the master chain
for every sound I make for the game.
Because that makes everything, like these have their own, like, the action vocals and stuff,
they have their own, like, sonic spaces here, like they have different gear,
they are already different from each other.
Then I have the master chain that ties all these.
They feel different, but they still feel the same because they all go through the same filter, so to say.
And it just ties them together, it glues them together.
Just keep that in mind.
Oh, whoa, I jumped a point.
So one point about using the same mic and preamplifier stuff is,
for actions and vocals and stuff, it will make them pop out from the mix
without doing crazy tricks.
So I would have like...
battlefield scene happening and then the voiceovers are done with another setup.
That will make already the vocals pop out a bit more.
And enemies have a different setup.
You make them pop out from the player setup.
Just think of how the pairs stuff sonically.
And I don't mean the Sega game.
And that also makes a good drinking game.
Like, every time I say Sonic, I have a drink.
I know, I will.
So, so, so.
Now let's do some tips. Make your sounds shorter. So, with this I mean, well I actually play
a jump sound that I made. So you can hear that's a jump sound. And it takes that long
to complete. So the thing is, you have like long sounds like that, it will, it will make
In time, it will become repetitive.
It will give you gradual fatigue of always pressing a button and waiting for it to end.
It will become really annoying at some point.
You don't want to jump anymore.
You're like, it's taking so long, I don't want to do that.
Think about opening doors.
After the third door you're going to say, fuck doors,
I'm going to blast my way through.
So, oh, sorry.
I said the nice word.
So make some shorter to resist that.
Like, normal jump, shorter jump.
It already feels more like, I could listen to this way more
than to that, like in a game.
It just makes the sound feel more...
What would be the right word?
Like, I mean, no...
It just makes the sound feel nicer.
The game feel nicer.
Then, um...
Make the beginnings shorter of your sounds.
Think about the player pushing a button.
What I mean by this is...
When you...
Like this sound.
There's a small gradual build to it.
You jump.
If it's shorter...
It's instantaneous for the button press.
And why this is important is
You want the player to press the button, I mean usually you want the player to press a button
and be like, hey, I did that. I pressed the button, I jumped in the game. Instead of I pressed the
button and that creature jumped in the game or like whatever it is. Like you want it to be me,
extension of player, not like not you controlling another character. So like now I press jump,
it's you jumping. Now it's me jumping.
I don't know if you can hear it from this, but that will make the player feel like I
did it.
It will give them a feel of satisfaction.
It's instant response to their action.
And that's always a good thing.
But then again, having a delay might make things feel sluggish.
A good example of this is the Dark Souls games, for instance.
Woohoo, shout out for them.
like if you're over encumbered, you're equipping a goddamn house on you.
I'm so heavy.
And then you try to jump.
It's like, that already feels like, oh, it's so,
it's the most heaviest thing ever.
Instead of being, like, that doesn't feel heavy.
That just feels like you have crazy diarrhea or something.
So having like.
It's like, oh, that's heavy.
You're wearing a house with horns or something.
So think about that.
Ooh, checking my notes.
Cool.
OK, so going on.
My favorite bit, impact, or impacting with impact.
The thing with impact, what I do a lot in games
is I decide on a small audio file.
It would be like, I don't know, 5 to 20 milliseconds long
or something.
My professor's degree.
So you have this small, really really like p-p-p-p-p kind of sound,
and I would choose that, like a different sound per game,
just like, either like p-p-p-p or like k-k-k or something like that.
I would take a small sound like that and insert that to every sound asset I do to the game.
I don't necessarily like looping sounds, but like every single shot sound.
Because having that in front, like here's the whole file, I would have it like right at the beginning.
What I can do with this is.
I can adjust punch of the sound.
If I raise the volume of this sound, it will make the sound like instead of being like
you can like adjust the punch of the sound.
If you want it to be less punchier, put it quieter.
If you want it to be really punchy, put it really high.
And with this you can also...
like, emphasize bass, make bass feel more like, it sounds more bassier.
So instead of like having a shotgun sound,
I would just have, like, shotgun sound being like just boost the bass of that and it's like
bllbbbllbbbbbbbbbbbbbbbbbbbbbbbbbbb
I would have that small pppp sound have like tons of bass.
So that what that does is kind of fools us in a sense, and fools our speakers like subwoofers and stuff.
That the small thing only has like a pppp, pppp, really like pppp, pppp, a heavy bass, and then the rest can be normal.
Like this...
You can just leave the shotgun sound as normal and have a nice punchy tight bass.
And if you have like 20 shotguns shooting, the game doesn't go like...
Now the game would be like...
So, think about that. That was probably pretty weird.
You can emphasize the button press here.
Having that in every sound will make the button press feel like,
hey, I'm pressing buttons.
Especially if every action has that sound.
It just makes it feel like this is what I'm doing, and so on,
and so on.
You could have a different sound for maybe the enemies
or something.
I don't know.
You can experiment with that.
And a good example of having a button press
with that small impact is, let's say
you are pulling a lever.
Castle Bridge comes down.
If you don't have anything, it's like I press a button.
If you have a small punch sound, but even if it's like bare,
you can't even hear it proper.
It's just a feeling like a small bass over there.
It's just like, something like that.
And you have that in front.
It's like I press a button.
That small thing makes it feel like I did something.
I pressed a button.
So on and so on.
This makes it feel like I did something instead of me, again,
pressing button and that doing it.
So think about that.
Distortion ETC artifacts.
Let's move on.
With this, I mean, and now I'm going
to easily piss off some people, but you know.
Distortion ETC artifacts.
What I mean with this is kind of like technical flaws
in the game.
You can sometimes use these flaws to enhance it.
So let's say.
You have 20 knights with crazy halibers attacking you.
And the game master, the master channel of the game,
like the in-game audio engine, is like,
pffft, pffft, pffft, pffft, pffft.
There's millions of knights.
It's like, ah, my ears hurt.
Ah, ah, it feels so tense.
And then you slay them, and it's quiet.
And you're like, ah, my ears can breathe again.
That might be technically considered as, wow, wow, wow,
you were clipping.
It was not good, not good.
But if it felt good?
Why not? If it's not hurting anyone, it's not breaking anything,
fucking go for it.
Another thing, like if you have like master limiter going crazy,
like you're in underground level, all these sound files are base,
and it's like everything feels like,
so what's happening? Out of order, ah.
People would be like, hmm, that's a technical flaw, you're a master limiter and this so and so...
Fuck, um, that, no, like, if it felt good, go with it.
Ah, jeez.
So, let's move on, I still have a few minutes.
Sound systems.
Ducking.
I don't mean like, quack quack duck, no, it's a shitty joke.
So, um, ducking.
With this, you know, you have music playing on the radio, someone talks, the music goes down,
they stop talking, the music comes back up.
We use that in video games a lot for...
Like a character talking and the background dims down, right?
What if you would use that for actions, for UI,
and stuff like that?
I've been using that for some time
now in games to enhance something.
I'll just give you a quick example.
Here's a sound clip with no ducking.
It's just someone shooting this background.
What if I put ducking on the weapons?
Let's compare again.
No.
Ducking.
I don't know if you can hear it through here, but what happens here is.
The shooting became more prominent.
It was more clear.
There was more power.
It was like, hey, I'm doing something that affects the world.
It gives that feeling of power to the player.
It's really cool.
And what if you'd apply filtering to that as well?
And by filters, I mean, you know, boom, bomb explodes.
Stuff like that, right?
Maybe some ear ringing, whatever.
What if you'd apply that to the actions as well?
So let's do the clip with no ducking.
With ducking.
With filtering.
Or it feels like, like, grr.
Of course I'm like over-accenting right now.
Now it's like overly accented.
But if you do that slightly, it will bring so much power
and feeling for the actions.
And you could apply that to anything, like UI, or jumping,
or whatever.
It's just even having a slight amount makes it feel better.
It feels like I'm doing something.
Or if there's a powerful enemy, and it's like,
it's like, oh, this is the most powerful thing ever.
And.
And you could have like different stages of this.
You could have like loose weapons like...
You could have like a shotgun...
Or you could have like rocket launchers...
You could like bring feel before even affecting like mixed balances.
You would just like do ducking balances.
And that already does a cool thing.
So...
But with sound systems, give priority to what is important.
Like, don't just create a lot of sound systems and like,
everything's ducking, everything's doing that,
I have this cool reverb thing, occlusion, whatever.
So, you have all this cool stuff, but if it starts to make the game feel like
more like a technical demo than a game or something, like, if it doesn't...
feel good anymore, introduces like input lag or whatever, just take it out.
You don't need to join the fashion club of technical people, just do something that feels good.
Because nothing is as irritating as loosening the feel or breaking the illusion of the game that,
hey, I'm doing this.
Keep focus of the game always number one thing, and if you do that, the game will feel much better.
And thank you!
Follow me on Twitter if you want to talk to me about stuff related to this.
I'm here today, tomorrow maybe.
If I find accommodation, I might be here longer.
So, cool.
We have like three minutes for Q&A.
Any questions?
I told you it's really compressed.
Are you ready for questions?
I'm going to go straight into a slightly technical question.
You mentioned setting up your master chain in your DAW.
In Logic, when you want to export all the tracks as separate sounds,
and you hit that export all sounds as tracks,
it doesn't put them through the master chain.
It puts them all through their own insert thing.
So you end up doing loads of inserts, I think.
Or have you found that you can do that in Logic?
But you can do a workaround with this, that you create a track,
and you record all those layers in that track.
Done.
You put all... oh, you...
You route them to a track, and you record to that track,
and then you have, like, that sound file there.
Like, you would make a master aux, like auxiliary,
and you would route that, like, everything through that,
into an audio track.
Empty audio track.
And then you record that audio track.
But that will then put them all together on that audio track.
But when you're wanting to get all your sounds out of separate files...
Like, as in for a...
Let's say like Ys or Fm or something.
Yeah.
Do a master chain on that.
In FMOD.
Yeah, I know we're putting the sounds straight into Unity, so then you don't have the master chain.
So there isn't a way to put your master chain onto all the individual...
Oh, do it, all the individual ones as well.
Just put the same fucking chain at the end.
So you copy the chain onto every track?
Yeah, that's what I would do.
Oh, okay. Yeah, that's what I've been doing. Thanks.
Yes!
Do you have some example of that impact you've mentioned earlier?
Oh, didn't I play it? Okay.
Jump shorter.
Now we play small impact sound to emphasize button press.
I don't know, can you really hear it right now?
But if you have that same impact for, let's say, dodging as well, stuff like that,
it will make the dodging and jumping kind of feel...
like, make the button press feel similar.
I can give you more examples later on if you want.
Yeah.
I don't know who did that.
Hi.
Are there any virtual instruments that you
use that you can advertise?
Advertise?
I mean, that are good.
We are not supposed to advertise in GDC.
No one's paying me, so I'm not advertising anything.
Oh, no.
Ha, ha.
VSTs that I use, like instruments.
Yeah.
I use Pro Tools' own instruments.
They're pretty lame, but they work, so why not?
I don't really... I record most stuff myself, so I would use, like, real instruments.
Unless it's like an orchestra, I would use, I don't know, EastWest or something.
I don't know. I don't...
Maybe later, if you get me a drink, we can talk about this.
We do have time for one more.
One more. That guy's been holding his hand for a long time.
Thanks.
Um, alright.
You said that you want to make sounds shorter, right?
Uh, excuse me?
You said that you want to make sounds shorter.
Yeah.
Right. So I was wondering if repetitive, long sounds don't become earworms.
Like if you ever played Zelda, the Link's going like,
well, I can't do sounds.
Yeah.
You know what I mean.
Doesn't that help to make game feel better or something?
Yeah. Of course, when I say make sounds shorter,
It doesn't necessarily apply to everything, but like that link thing, that's the feel thing.
They're like, okay, having like a long attack, they're like, that feels good.
They were like, fuck it, it feels good, let's do it.
Swearing again.
So they're like, yeah, it feels good, like let's do it.
So if it feels good, like ignore, if anything feels better than this,
my own personal rule set, go for it.
If it feels good, it feels good.
So like.
What I do is I usually start by making sounds shorter,
unless a longer version feels better.
And it's like totally up to the occasion.
Yeah.
All right.
Thank you.
One more round of applause for Jonas Stirner.