All right, everybody.
Welcome to French 101.
We.
Actually, does anybody in here speak French?
OK, then I ordinarily start these off
with a really terrible joke.
And I'm not going to break the cycle at GDC.
Just some of you may not understand this one
because it's a bad French joke.
That there's two cats swimming across a river.
One of them is named one, two, three.
The other is named un, deux, trois.
Which one makes it to the other side?
You're right. 1, 2, 3 cat makes it because unfortunately 1, 2, 3 cat sank.
I'm already getting jeers from up here. They want me off the stage.
So it's day four, everybody, and I think this is probably an apt panel for day four.
Who's feeling just exhausted?
Okay, okay. Hold on. Keep your hands up. Keep your hands up.
Keep your hands up. Keep your hands up. Okay.
For those of you who are feeling exhausted,
keep your hands up if you've deliberately said no to things
like parties, interviews, et cetera.
Okay, most of you.
Okay, that's good, that's good.
All right, so what we're gonna do is we're gonna,
we have this fantastic panel of industry veterans,
and we're gonna talk about how they deal with stress,
particularly burnout stress,
and hopefully they're gonna have some really great tips
for you all to do the same thing.
But first let's talk about, well, who I am and who I'm here with.
My name is Dr. B. I am the clinical director of a mental health non-profit called Take
This.
Starting in 2012, we were actually the first mental health non-profit to serve the game
industry.
And our whole mission can be boiled down to it's OK to not be OK.
And it is a, you know, basically...
Mental health challenges are far more common than we realize,
regardless of whether they raise to the level of a full diagnosis or not.
And yet we're not talking about it.
One of the statistics we like to cite is from the Centers for Disease Control
here in the United States.
And it's roughly one in four people will be diagnosed in their lifetime.
Think about that.
And this is actually kind of a conservative number.
This number does not include substance abuse disorders.
This number does not include neurodevelopmental disorder
like Asperger's.
But it's still significant.
If you don't know someone who suffers
from a mental health diagnosis, yeah, you do.
Yeah, you do, and they're not talking about it,
which is part of the problem.
So take This Exists to help bring education
to studios, to attendees,
and we do a lot of talks like this.
and we wanna bring awareness to all of you.
And apparently you're all concerned about burnout, yeah?
Yeah.
Cause like this industry's hard or something.
Like, totally.
Who got into this industry with the dreams
of I'm gonna make amazing games?
I mean, obviously.
But, and it's gonna be great,
and I'm gonna do it in my spare time,
and I'm gonna leave it,
I'm already getting laughter as soon as I say spare time.
Yeah, we're going to talk about that.
But what is burnout?
Like, no, seriously, I'm asking you, what is burnout?
Somebody give me a guess.
Because we use the term all the time.
And I want to make sure we're all on the same page.
Yes, you in the back with the red sleeves.
It is when your blood completely, suddenly,
puts a stop that you can't stop.
So it's when your mind completely and suddenly stops
and you cannot think anymore.
Okay, who else?
Yes.
Deep depression.
Let's go over to, yes.
100% for too long to the point that you cannot go anymore.
Way back in the corner.
Cannot function.
Well, that just, that summarizes it all.
Yes.
Your work starts to become terrible.
So you can't think, okay, so.
I love that I'm getting such a great response on day four.
Unless you're all stretching and I just don't know it.
Cause I don't know, you know, got to keep that, nevermind.
All of you are correct, in part.
Burnout is all of these things.
It's not, first of all, it's kind of like impostor syndrome.
It's not a diagnosis.
All right, imposter syndrome isn't actually a syndrome.
But burnout is something that is a unique, long-term form
of stress that affects our cognition, our ability
to think, affects our mood.
So deep depression touches on that.
It affects our functioning.
And it also affects our career longevity.
And incidentally.
It has correlates with all of these things.
Now part of the reason this is going to be really important
for studios, if you are a manager at a studio,
big, small, somewhere in between, doesn't matter,
pay attention to this because turnover rates
are a substantive cost.
A statistic that we cited in a white paper
that TakeThis wrote for the IGDA in 2016
called Crunch Hertz, cited that the cost,
just the cost of retraining a new employee
is 20% of their annual salary.
That's not to even mention losses in productivity
due to retraining time.
In the United States alone,
productivity costs related to depression
were in the $44 billion range per year.
So we want to optimize our spaces.
And I believe it was the most recent
developer satisfaction survey that the IGDA put out
that roughly two out of three developers
and game industry employees dropped by their 10th year.
We don't have many veterans in this industry.
And we want that, because we want that expertise.
And so we need to eliminate this stuff.
But since I mentioned Crunch.
Okay, well again, since you all were in the mood for raising hands,
or stretching, I don't know, I'm not going to judge,
but what happens to burnout if we just work less hard?
Yes.
You're probably working less hard for around the same amount of time,
so you're probably just as stressed as you were instead of doing less.
So you're probably working just as hard for less amount of time,
and you feel just as stressed, if we just eliminate the work hours.
Okay, yes.
You start losing momentum if you back off.
Okay.
And what was that?
From audience, and benefits me, but my work fails.
Benefits you, but your work fails.
So when you're watching your numbers,
and you're looking at ratings and all of that,
and what happens then?
I mean, that's terrifying.
Yes.
You start to get stressed about what you don't have done.
Oh boy, if I had a nickel for every time I heard that one.
Yes.
You're less likely to ship.
You're less likely to ship if you don't work constantly.
You read our paper, seriously.
Actually, over studios who regularly use Crunch,
there is a correlation with lowered Metacritic scores.
Yeah.
Yes.
but everyone else is probably gonna stay longer
and people will start to be intelligent.
Okay, so there's fear.
There's fear of a lack of progress in your career
because your peers and your superiors
are going to be looking down on you if you work less hours.
Well, what happens to burnout?
Yes?
Guilt.
Guilt?
Like an exaggeration.
Oh boy.
We're opening up a whole can of worms.
Didn't know this was gonna turn into group therapy,
did ya?
Yes.
So you can still do harder and the fact that you're choosing not to to choose your health over your actual output,
does it make you feel guilty or self-pity?
So we hear negativity about self, negativity about work, guilt, fear. Yes.
I would say like it's kind of like an interesting trap, right?
Because if you get burned out, that's basically a form of depression in my opinion.
So you're doing that to counterbalance the fact that you've been working so hard.
But then if you feel bad that, you know, you haven't really been getting any work done.
So to summarize this, burnout's a form of depression,
and you work harder to beat the depression,
but then you get more depressed about working hard
and your work's not as good
because you can't think it straight and phew.
Okay, no one else has experienced that, right?
Okay, well let's talk about why it's not just
a simple matter of working less hours,
and you're all touching on this.
because burnout is not just a matter of exhaustion.
Sure, burnout, exhaustion is a part of it,
but it's not the only part, okay?
There's two other components based on a model
that's been in use for a couple of decades.
That it's exhaustion, it is cynicism.
So in other words, just I don't care.
I don't care about you, I don't care about this.
You know, who likes working around the person
who's always negative all the time?
God, I'm glad nobody raised their hand.
God, oh yeah, but it's a drain on you,
it's a drain on the team, it's a drain on,
oh, forgot I had that on.
They're so tiny, the lav mics.
But it becomes a trap of negativity.
But also, there's an interrelated idea
of a sense of ineffectiveness.
Do we feel like our work is producing anything?
Do we have a purpose?
And the solutions to burnout have to tap
into all of these things.
Like how discouraging is it when you're working
on a project so close to completion, canceled?
Anybody experience that?
Yeah, yeah.
I think some friends of mine, and I won't say which studio,
but they had one they were working on for five years.
And right before it was about to ship, boom, canceled.
How demoralizing is that?
How ineffective do you feel in your job,
where all the five years of work, nothing?
How negative are you going to feel
about your next experience?
And also how exhausted.
So this is all of the above coming into one.
And that's really what burnout is.
Now, a couple of things we want to talk about in this
is also self-doubt.
Self-doubt, unhealthy self-doubt.
I mean, if I, in my current physical state,
decide I want to go free climb El Capitan,
and there's a part of my brain that goes, no.
No.
Let's ignore my crippling phobia of heights for a moment.
and I just couldn't do it physically.
There are healthy forms of self-doubt,
but other forms of self-doubt are unrealistic,
and that produces a sense of inefficacy.
So all of this is interrelated.
All of the topics that are commonly talked about
in terms of the stressors of being in the game space
are interrelated and contribute.
We can't just focus on one to find solutions.
We need to focus on purpose.
We need to focus on investment in the product.
We need to focus on reasonable working hours
because your cognitive,
I know it feels weird.
I heard somebody say, I lose my motivation.
You feel like you lose your motivation?
Well, most of us.
I get weirdly amped after a while,
but even I have my limits.
Because of this, there's another thing called,
technical term is allostatic load.
Don't have to remember that.
But basically, think of a thermostat, okay?
Our bodies are remarkably adaptive.
Now, if you leave the door open in your house,
and it's New England in the winter,
your thermostat is gonna start to work overtime.
For those of you who may be from outside of the US,
New England is cold.
I'm from the other side of the country in Seattle,
so I never heard of this term winterizing your house,
but apparently it's a thing.
We have rain, they have blizzards.
And so your door is open, your heater is going to try
and maintain the temperature in your house.
So it's gonna kick into high gear,
and it's gonna do a good job for a while,
but it's gonna burn out.
Our bodies are no different.
And we need to regulate that a little bit better.
But once it gets used to it, it's hard to come back down.
So we need to have preventative measures as well.
And that's what these lovely folks here
are going to talk about, how they have maintained success
in this industry for as long as they have.
And I'm going to ask everybody to introduce themselves.
And unfortunately, one of our panelists
security at the airport, just unexpectedly long,
missed his flight and was unable to be here with us.
But he gave me some great written answers
that I may be cheating and reading off later.
But, who are you, what do you do,
how long you been doing it?
Okay, so I'm Kate Edwards.
I'm a geographer, and I've been in the industry for 26 years.
I do culturalization work, which means I help game developers
avoid political and cultural mistakes in their content
that gets them banned by governments
and has consumer uprisings and stuff like that.
I did that at Microsoft for 13 years,
and I've been self-employed ever since.
In my last 10 years or so in the industry,
I've gotten very involved in advocacy issues.
I ran the IGDA for five years.
As the executive director, I left in 2017.
And since then, I've been very active
in a lot of advocacy issues, including unionization
and creating a legal defense fund
and things of that nature.
You know, you can applaud.
This is already an audience participation panel.
If you feel free to applaud, you know,
spontaneously, you go for it.
I know where my hecklers are.
So I'm David Ettory.
I'm the CEO and co-founder of Spry Fox.
And we've made games like Triple Town, Alpha Bear,
Bushido Bear, Roman The Mad God, Steambirds.
Any of y'all have played any of those?
And yeah, happy to be here.
I'm Amir Rao. I'm the studio director and co-founder of Supergiant Games. We're an 18-person
independent game company here in San Francisco. We made Bastion, Transistor, Pyre, and we're
working on a game called Hades right now.
And missing is Tommy Rufenes, who is the CEO of Team Meat. They have some really cool stuff
for Meat Boy coming out very soon, I hear.
And I'm Dr. B, the clinical director of Take This.
I am not a developer.
I'm actually a doctor of clinical psychology.
And so for you all, so when have you experienced
any of the things we talked about
in terms of negativity, exhaustion,
a sense of inefficacy in your work,
and how do you deal with it?
You wanna start?
Oh.
Okay.
Ah.
So I guess for me, I view that form of exhaustion
as the potentially inevitable outcome
of a passionate point of view on your work.
So for me, when I have felt that way,
My own view on it, looking backwards now,
because most of this happened much earlier,
is that it was like me understanding
and learning what my limits were.
I had no other way of discovering them,
no matter if I come to this panel or not,
than to work the way I did to find out
what I was capable of and where I might break.
So in my experience, I worked a lot.
especially on something like Bastion,
I think we were living in a living room of a house,
we're working all the time.
But we were also like kind of young
and didn't have anywhere else to be.
So, I try to be kind to myself
in the retrospect of all that stuff.
I've definitely pushed myself too hard.
I've made mistakes that,
in understanding my own limits.
But that's a,
I think the hard thing about that stuff is it's a recurring lesson that you end up having
to sometimes relearn every time you might get...
I mean I think we all want to be...
I think a lot of us are drawn to this work because we are like passionately consumed
by it.
And we sometimes want a job that is so creatively fulfilling it does not fit inside 40 hours.
And I think that that sometimes leads to the types of things that you're talking about which is sad because
It started like from a place of of actual like joy and engagement
So you're talking about basically a constant readjustment of your expectations in in learning from your failures
Yeah, basically I'm trying to say is like I haven't fixed or solve this
like
This is like an ongoing part of you know our lives
You know we don't
We're not at a giant company.
There isn't someone who's bringing in tubs of food and
implying that we should all be working late.
It's not that kind of thing.
It's a small group of people who are passionately invested
in the work we're doing.
And how much of their life is a part of work is a constant
exchange based on what's going on in their life and what's
going on at work.
So I've experienced, I think, two very different forms of burnout, but both pretty nasty.
One of them was, like, way back in, I don't remember, it was 2011 or 2012 or something,
and we had, it was on Realm of the Mad God, actually, we had, for a fairly arbitrary set of reasons,
five weeks to make the game way better, or we were screwed.
And so I worked a hundred hours or more every week for five weeks.
And it was just like Amir was saying,
that at the end of that it was like,
oh, that's, I found my limit.
Like I ran all the way up to the edge of the cliff,
very nearly threw myself over it,
and then thankfully pulled back,
and was like, I'm never doing that again.
Like I was a broken shell of a human
at the end of that five week period.
And then the other kind of burnout is very different,
but just as nasty, and it's the,
when you work on something, even if you, you know,
you work on it for reasonable hours,
and not more than 40 hours a week,
and everything's hunky-dory,
but then you ship it and it fails,
and particularly if it fails for reasons
that you feel like were not in your control,
which is something that's gonna happen a lot in games.
You'll look at it and you'll be like,
I did my best, my game is good, it still didn't succeed,
which is a super common story,
every time that happens,
and thankfully it hasn't happened too many times,
but when it does, you just feel the life sucked out of you.
And there's a period of time where you're like,
why am I doing this?
And it happens to you even if you have made,
like I am very lucky,
and I use the word luck very intentionally.
Like yeah, I work hard and all that stuff,
but to have as many successful games as Firefox has had
requires a lot of luck,
in addition to skill and sweat and all that.
And it doesn't matter.
Like I have, even with all the number,
you know, I think we have like five games that have been played by several million people,
like, and it doesn't matter, when a game fails, you still take it super personally,
and it's like, and it makes you want to quit. So yeah, those are my two burnouts.
I think from my perspective, because my job has been a little different.
I mean, I have, I've been involved in crunch episodes with different teams,
because I'm more an advisory role to a lot of these teams.
I have a choice whether to crunch or not.
When I created my geopolitical team at Microsoft to handle this kind of work,
I made sure that my team never worked ridiculous hours,
even though at the time Microsoft was kind of insisting on pretty long hours
for different teams, especially if you're like a core programming team.
And I just said that we don't work that way here.
I'll take the heat for it, but my people, you go home.
But a lot of my burnout, well, let me ask this question.
How many people here consider themselves an introvert?
Of course, yeah, we're the game industry.
So I do, too.
I mean, I can take Myers-Briggs or whatever else,
and it always comes out an I something.
I can fake extroversion really well now.
But one of the biggest challenges
I always had in my career was people burnout.
It's dealing with people, and I'm not saying it's just because they're incompetent.
Not everyone's incompetent, but there's people who just have different visions,
or they pull you in a different direction, or they are incompetent.
There's those people too, let's face it.
And it's just having to deal with that kind of pressure of being in an organization.
So I guess part of it is what I face a lot is organizational burnout.
It's like being in this organization that might be dysfunctional.
Even though you love your function, you love what you do,
you love.
whatever job you're doing, but you just,
the organization you're in, just, ugh,
it's just you wish it could be better
in multiple attempts with management and all that,
just don't make it better.
And so I find, when I look back over my career,
that's usually all the inflection points I've had
where I've left a company or done something different,
made a major shift, was always because
of a interpersonal thing.
It was always because either the organization
burned me out, like Microsoft,
The work that I did at Microsoft, I love my work.
I've been doing it for 30 years now, and I still love it every day.
I got tired of doing it there for many reasons.
And so I'm just like, I have to get out of here.
I have to do something else, do it somewhere else.
And so that's often the case for me, is you just kind of reach this point where I can't do it here anymore.
You hit walls and everything.
You know, and along with that comes emotional burnout, too.
It's like when I created this geopolitical team, it took me seven months.
I wrote a proposal because we had this big incident happen in Korea, and it inspired me to create this team.
I had to shop it around to five different VPs before I finally got approval, and every one of those rejections was very difficult.
I'm like, why can't they understand?
This is a great idea.
Then finally, the last VP who approved it,
approved it in five minutes.
And that's because he was not from the US.
He was the only VP I talked to who was not from the US.
He's from South Africa.
And his first answer was, I thought
we're doing this already.
So he's like, yes, we need to do this.
So I think for me, I've had less of the physical burnout
episodes, but much more of the interpersonal.
organizational kind of burnout episodes that have been pretty trying at times.
Well, and it's interesting for me to think about all the different positions that you all have,
because one of the things that Tommy said when he answered this question via email
was that he's never really experienced burnout the way we described it in that model,
and I wonder how much of that has to do with literal ownership of the work.
You know, David and Amir, you're both in positions where...
The work truly is yours.
I mean, you're both speaking about passion to this.
And, you know, Kate, you're a consultant.
That is a very different position, where the people,
you can say all the amazing things you want,
but they could choose or not to listen,
kind of like the original Jurassic Park.
No, seriously, no, the technical consultant
on the original Jurassic Park, Dr. Jack Horner,
is a big proponent of the idea that the Tyrannosaurus Rex
is not a hunter, but a scavenger, largely
based on its anatomy.
That would have been a boring movie.
But you're in a position where they can take or leave your suggestions.
So all three of you are in very unique positions.
What would you say to those who don't have your positions about this?
Easy question, right?
Well, I think that, I mean, just my view is that that just doubles down on the stress.
I mean, if you have some level of agency in the work that you do, like in my case, it's
like I consult, and if they don't like what I said or they're not going to do what I say,
I'm just like, good luck.
You know, it's in writing that I told you so.
So when you do screw up, not when, but when you do, because I know you will, because you
didn't listen to me, you will get banned in this country.
You will have this huge uprising on Twitter.
You know, you can come back and just say, you know, we're sorry, we didn't listen to
you.
But it, but that's hard.
That's very hard.
Because I want them to succeed.
My whole job is to help them succeed.
And so that adds a lot of stress on me.
I get emotional stress from it.
I feel stressful for them.
And if that happens frequently, which it doesn't, but it can,
you know, we have multiple things like that happen,
that's burnout.
You're just like, maybe I should just go take
an easy job somewhere.
I could just be a program manager on Marvel,
so maybe I can meet Chris Hemsworth someday or something.
I don't know.
So I think this is, I'm going to give an answer to basically
two questions here.
One of the things that I've noticed that helps me tremendously with burnout is making sure
that I love the people who I work with.
It makes an enormous difference.
It doesn't matter how crappy the world is and how many things are going wrong.
If I trust and care about the people who I'm with, it's kind of like, well, we're all in
this together.
We'll make it work, right?
And even if we don't make it work, we care about each other.
We'll figure this out.
I realize, and so that's an inserted question you were going to ask later,
but I think that this is, I understand that I'm privileged,
like I literally get to pick who I work with because I'm the person who runs the company.
But I do feel like when I talk to my friends who are not in that position,
that they oftentimes underestimate their ability to get themselves out of situations
where they're working with people whom they aren't happy being around.
And that's actually something that I'd really strongly encourage you guys like it like you know many people are afraid
To even go to their manager for example and tell them like I'm not happy around this person like and there's so many reasons
You could be not happy. It's not like it could be that they're a terrible human being sure
And that happens.
And it could also be other things.
It could just be subtle things, like there's a major cultural mismatch,
like you're constantly feeling friction,
like you're not being able to settle it yourselves, you know, whatever.
Actually, sorry, I should take a step back.
If it is something like that, like talk to that person, try to work it out, right?
Like don't just be miserable.
Like that's like a first thing.
But like if you have tried that or feel like there's a good reason you can't,
like for example, that person is a harasser.
Then yeah, you go to your manager.
Like, don't just be silently miserable.
And if you feel like you can't go to your manager about something like that,
like, that's a very strong signal you are in the wrong place.
Like, you do not belong in a company where you cannot tell your manager that
there's another person who, for whatever the reason, makes you not want to go to
work.
You know what I mean?
And if you make an effort to make sure that you're only working with people who
you like and respect.
it will make such a huge difference.
It dampens burnout dramatically.
And if that means that you need to just be
more of a hustler and always be aware of like
where your next job might be
because the current one isn't the one
isn't working out for all the reasons
that I just described, then like so be it.
You know what I mean?
Like hopefully not, like hopefully eventually
you find a place.
Like I like to think that the people at SpriteFox
feel pretty good about being at SpriteFox.
We don't have a lot of turnover, you know?
These companies exist, you can find them.
Like you owe that to yourself.
If you're gonna work this hard,
let's face it, everyone in this room who's making games,
there's a very, very high chance you could double your salary
in any other industry.
Like, very high chance.
So if you're gonna work in this industry really hard,
like, making less than you could be making anywhere else,
possibly longer hours than you'd be working anywhere else,
like, you deserve to at least work with people that you like.
Thank you.
I'm trying to let that one sink in for a moment,
because, I mean, that touches on two of the three parts
of the burnout model.
You're talking about self-efficacy and attachment
to an outcome, as well as a lack of cynicism in your work
environment.
So you're touching on two out of three,
and it sounds remarkably protective.
That's awesome.
Amir, how about you?
Yeah, I mean, you know, a late night.
So we made Bash in the living room of my dad's house.
So like a late night there was not a burnout night.
It was like a sleepover that lasted for 20 months.
So.
It was a different feeling because I was there with the woman who would become my wife and
my best friends in the whole world working on a game together.
So that feels really different than if you're in a big team or a big company where I think
one of the things that's really interesting to me about Crunch stuff is
I think it's pretty rare that someone directly just says,
you know, push, push it.
Like, do more than you can do.
That's almost never the conversation, right?
It's usually a little bit more insidious,
which is you have way more work than time.
People are starting to stay late.
They're starting to bring in dinners.
These like small telltale signs,
leadership is getting anxious and nervous.
Well, and that's what we heard from everybody here.
Yeah, release date is coming up, these kinds of things.
It's all, and if you are in a situation
even where you love the people you work with,
you may feel like a lot of social pressure to deliver
because you don't want to let anyone down, right?
In those scenarios, it can be helpful
to think of the difference between
when you own the work and when you don't.
Because if someone is asking or implying
that you should do this,
If you're doing it for probably what we could categorize are healthy reasons, like you want
to be a part of something, you really believe in what's there, you think it's time limited
and it's not going to destroy your life, those are maybe some reasons that you can use to
convince yourself to put in a little more or whatever you want, but for the most part.
the people who are creating these environments
are like maybe the only ones who stand to benefit from this.
So a lot of people work really hard on things
that they later do not see the economic or positive
or brand or reputational benefits from that.
And that's really, really different.
So think about.
Think about who is going to benefit from your overwork.
Because it's a really different equation if it's you and your peers and the people you're connected
to and fans that you might love or a franchise that you might be really,
really attached to than like shareholders or like the executive staff of your corporation
who may not even know your name.
So it's a really, really, really different sort of setup between those two things.
Well, what do you all see?
You mentioned, David, you mentioned your privilege
in being able to pick your team,
and Kate had stories of, you know,
way back in the day at Microsoft
and the bureaucratic structure that it is.
Where do you all see managers,
especially like mid-level managers,
where is their responsibility in helping to curb the burnout?
Well, from my perspective, a manager is a leader,
but what to lead is to serve, in my view.
And if you are in a leadership position,
that means you are serving the needs of the people under you.
And if you don't see it that way,
then you should not be a leader.
You should not be a manager.
Basically, it's not a triangle with you at the top,
it's you at the bottom.
serving the needs of everyone in your organization.
So you work for them.
And that's really the perspective that you have to see it.
So on that level, you have a fundamental responsibility
not only to the job that they're working on
so that it's successful,
so you're obviously trying to work towards the production
and all that kind of stuff,
but that also means shepherding their needs.
and making sure that they're okay on an emotional level,
physical level, all these other dimensions
of what makes a successful project happen.
And to look just at numbers and just look at a timesheet
of what's due, the due dates and all that kind of stuff,
yeah, you gotta do that
because that's part of your responsibility.
But to me, that's the easy part.
The hard part is actually going around
and making sure you know the names of everyone on your team.
and making sure you know what their situation is,
and making sure you have some level of empathy
with the different situations that they're facing
because every single person's different.
And so that's one of the things I often really try
and encourage people in a leadership role.
It's like if you cannot see yourself as a servant
and as a shepherd, then you're definitely in the wrong job.
All right, apparently Kay just dropped the mic on that one.
Just don't drop the mic, they're expensive, okay.
You all talked about mistakes.
That mistakes are inevitable.
And in fact, Amir, you talked about your learning process
as a constant recalibration of mistakes
in a new environment.
What advice do you have for everybody on how to accept the fact that we will make mistakes?
And how do they build the resilience to get through them?
Yeah, so they're not mistakes.
That's the simple answer.
How could you have known?
There is no way for you to have known how it was going to affect your life and what
was going to happen to it until you did it.
So I would not necessarily view those chapters of your life
as a moment where you totally drop the ball on something
that everyone already knew.
Because everyone's limits are different.
Everyone's lives are different.
All those things are unique and personal to the individuals.
So if you've experienced some extreme emotional event
connected to work, or even like a persistent low level,
nagging emotional event sort of connected to those things, I would be kind to yourself
about that.
The reason I have to keep relearning is because it's popping up in different ways.
You know, if it was the exact same thing every time, I would be much more prepared.
But the way this kind of consumption creeps into your life is going to be different each
time and it's probably because it's coming from some place inside you.
that's either highly motivated or highly ambitious or highly loyal to the people you work with
or whatever those things are, it's probably coming from a place that isn't entirely negative,
that isn't just a lack of self-control, an inability to constrain yourself, a lack of
prioritization, like all the things that we can use to beat ourselves up with.
Yeah, I just, yeah, it's not a mistake. It's just how you have to learn.
So you're talking about reframing.
Yeah.
But it's, I mean, it's central to.
It is not a coincidence that many of the most successful creative companies,
including like the Pixar's and stuff of the world, like they are all very,
very good at trying to banish the word failure from their company cultures.
Like it's not failure.
It's just not failure.
It's, I mean, there are forms of failure, but
they're not the ones that most people think about.
Like if you hire someone.
and they are just unreliable and mean and whatever,
like, you know, bad person attributes for like,
I don't know what you would call that.
Like, yeah, those people are failing, as far as I'm concerned.
And we do everything we can to try to get rid of...
Unfortunately, we've actually... I don't think in the history of SpriteFox
we've ever hired someone that was quite that bad.
But like, when we hire someone who's even a little bit toxic,
like we make an effort to get rid of them quickly.
Because that's failure. That's bad.
Aside from that, like if it's a person who's like an intelligent human being
who really cares and is honestly trying their best,
and something goes wrong, it's never failure.
it's just they tried their best and it didn't work.
And we're super, super hardcore about that.
And we've started to entrench that
in other aspects of our culture.
Like for example, a little bit of quick background
that will help you understand.
Spry Fox is kind of weird.
Like we're only 18 people, but we'll have like four games
in concurrent development at any given time.
And we've been like that since the beginning
when we were even a lot less than 18 people.
And we do that in part because
we have this obsession with making highly creative games
and we know that we're probably,
like that's super risky and some of them are gonna fail.
Maybe even a lot of them are gonna fail.
And so as a result, you have to be making a lot of them,
so that at least one of them can succeed and cover
the cost of all the failures.
But when you do that, like I was saying earlier,
like you're pouring yourself into these original expressions
and then they fail, and it's a knife in the heart.
And so how do you deal with that?
And the way you deal with it is by not calling it failure,
like you celebrate all the things you learned
from making that thing.
And like we try to be really conscious about that.
where a game, at the end of it,
we'll spend a lot of time talking about
what are all the cool things that we did
and what did we learn from that?
And oh, were there any problems?
What did we learn from that?
And it's never failure, you know what I mean?
It's just growing as a person.
I think that's super central.
We also recently in our Slack channel.
added a pyre channel for a place where like if you're working on a prototype and the prototype
ends up not being fun, you like give it its end off there, right? Like, like, you know,
it was a good soldier, it died, hooray, on to the next one. And like, and it's just a
way of, like again, so that it's not, you didn't screw up. Like the fact that your prototype
wasn't fun is not a, is not on you. Like, that's what happens with prototypes. Let's
celebrate the fact that this one...
didn't work out and move on to the next one.
You know what I mean?
So I think that's actually pretty important.
I highly encourage you to try to completely reframe
your thinking that, and also again, quite frankly,
if you're in a place where that's not the way people think
and they're not willing to think that way,
no matter how much you encourage them to,
like maybe that's not a good place to be.
Like don't be at a place where you get browbeaten
for trying your best and it not working out.
Yeah.
So all of you have touched on this idea of studio culture
being important.
Like, what's your take home tip for people looking for a
good fit for studio culture?
Like, what do you look for?
Go for it.
It's always good when I ask a question like, ooh.
Yeah, well, so I mean, I can just talk about.
I'm gonna just answer a different question because yeah.
Well that's, you know what, that's okay.
Take the politician's way out.
Yeah, so yeah, I'll just answer the question
I wanna answer, which is like,
what do we do around things like this?
Like, what do we do to promote healthy working habits?
Because, so ultimately, it's Supergiant.
Here's the thing I'm most proud of at Supergiant.
We made really good games.
All the people who worked on Bastion still work there,
right, those are, that group is still there.
So.
For us, like, uh, sustainably creating, like, the games we make is, like, central to what we want to
accomplish. So, you know, hopefully we'll be like the Rolling Stones and be like super
fricking old, charge like $10,000 per game or something when we're like 70. Um, but, um, the
basic idea for us is we end up...
uh, doing things we like hesitated about because we came from EA, so it's like we shouldn't
have policies, but actually we need policies. Um, and we especially need policies, uh, to
save us, like, from ourselves. Um, so an example of stuff we do at Supergiant. Uh, we don't
send weekend emails. So like Friday at 5 to Monday at 5 AM, there's no emails or slack
messages or anything like that. If there's an emergency, you get a phone call and there are
emergencies. Um, and so you don't have to worry about checking, you know you can turn it
off, that's it. Uh, we...
used to have unlimited time off and then no one took time off. Um, so we have a mandatory
minimum 20 days off and you can take more. Um, so the idea is we have the kind of culture
where people need to be reminded to leave. Um, and so we made a policy around that. Um,
And then we have like really liberal kind of like work from home type of policies
because we want like work life balance is something that comes up a lot.
I, for some reason I chafe at that phrase cause it makes it sound like there is a
perfect state that you can achieve in which your work and life are like
perfectly just in it like together.
Um, for me, we, we try to talk about like work life integration.
How does work contour to your life?
Like how can it fit into your life?
And in any reasonable human company
that's trying to sustain itself,
that will change like almost every year.
So in terms of a culture, you know,
work contours to your life is a central part of our culture.
And we end up inventing all these small ways to promote healthy habits for ourselves as a result.
And the only reason we could make those is because we did the opposite and it didn't work.
So we had to learn it over time.
So we've done some similar stuff where, for example, we say you should not work weekends.
And sometimes, like you said, there's emergencies.
people will have to work weekends, but we explicitly say,
and by we I mean Daniel and I, the co-founders,
that if someone is working on a weekend,
there is a very high chance that that means
Daniel and I fucked up.
Like, we take that on ourselves.
And like, and we encourage everyone who works in SpriteFox to feel free to call us out on that too.
Like, if someone's like, I worked eight hours on Saturday, you suck Dave.
Like, like, like that's a good thing, right?
Because it increases the odds that I'm, I mean, it decreases the likelihood that I will then put them in that situation again in the future.
Because I don't like being told I suck.
So...
So there's that.
And we also have a challenge that Supergiant doesn't,
which is that we're spread all over the world.
So this has made it super hard to have boundaries
around work and life, because it's like.
I have people who are in South Africa.
They're messaging me at hours that I would rather not be
messaged.
But I don't want them to have to work crazy hours, so I will
accept those messages.
And it's a thing, and it's complicated.
And honestly, there's no good answer to that.
It's very messy.
So what we've tried to do to solve for that, aside from
like, please don't work on weekends, so at least I'm not
getting the insane 2 AM message on Saturday, is
please be respectful and ask folks how they feel about being
messaged at any given time.
We have people on the team who.
feel very, very, very strongly that they should not be bothered in Slack on a Saturday or Sunday
for any reason. And so I know who those people are. And like, we now have a culture in the studio
where like, if I'm like trying to like use their name, but I don't want to bother them, I'll like
Brent, like we'll write we'll do B dash rent in Slack so that he does not get a ping.
You know, and everyone in the studio knows this,
and you'll see, like, on the weekends,
when people are, like, the few people
who are bothering to write something on the weekends,
like, they're all dashing names.
And it's great, because it's like a conscious
and very clear cultural sign
that, like, we respect people's boundaries.
That's probably one of my favorite things
that has happened organically in our Slack channel.
So it's just a thing, like,
you just have the open conversations about it.
There are people in the group that like,
they actually, like, for them it's actually more important
to be able to take, like, Friday off.
Like, they actually want to spend a few hours on Saturday
and like, take all of Friday off.
And it's like, okay, you can do that,
but like, you're gonna do the hyphen thing
on the weekend when you are working.
Like, you're not bothering the rest of us.
Don't, like, don't ruin our lives with your choices.
And like, and it works, for the most part.
Like, it's messy.
Again, I'm not gonna pretend that this is like, perfect.
There are definitely times where like,
there's some friction, but it works okay.
Well, I know from the other side of the coin,
how many people here are freelance by choice?
OK, so there's some of us here.
Yeah, not a lot of us, but there's some of us.
So for those of us who are freelance or consultants
or in that role that we're not working in a company,
but we choose to work with different companies,
oftentimes we choose because we need to pay a rent or a mortgage
or whatever.
So a lot of times it's hard for us to turn down work,
because we want the work, obviously.
But there are times over my career where I have turned down.
jobs from certain clients because
either the project that is being brought to me is something that I don't want to
work on, it's just the content is something I don't want to associate with,
or the company just has a really bad reputation for how it treats its people.
And those are really hard decisions to make
because you're just like,
I really could use this contract,
but it's trying to take the high road
and kind of reinforce these are my values.
And the thing is, I do communicate that to them.
Now, maybe that burns a bridge with them,
but if that's the way they are,
I really don't give a shit.
So, maybe I don't want to work with them again.
So...
Um...
But...
I do think it's important to not only make that decision,
but to communicate why.
Why am I choosing not to take this work
that I desperately need?
Because you are doing this, and I know this, and this,
and this, and you can make all the excuses,
but I've talked to your employees or whoever,
and it's pretty clear that you've got a messy situation.
And so I don't want to reinforce that,
basically help make you successful on the back of people
who are being treated really unfairly.
But that's hard, I mean it's really hard in the consultant role or
the freelance role to turn away stuff like that.
But we have to be very conscious of it.
And the other part of that, oftentimes pretty much every freelancer I know,
we don't have someone in management giving us holidays.
We don't have anyone telling us to go home at night.
We don't have any of that,
because we're basically in our home office just heads down doing this.
And oftentimes we're doing it, of course, because we absolutely love what we do.
Hopefully we do, if we don't then we shouldn't be doing it.
But that's really hard.
And so I know for me, it's been really tough
over the last 14 years after I left Microsoft
to really discipline myself to stop working.
You know, actually, like a policy when I'm home,
I travel a lot to speak at events,
but when I am home in Seattle,
I, like Saturday is usually just my day.
I just, I don't do anything other than just go out,
you know, you know, get some air, you know, do whatever,
maybe, you know, clean the house a little bit.
just don't do work.
And so I try and do that kind of thing for myself.
But even that's been really hard to discipline.
So I think when you're in that role, it's tough.
And you really have to find that self-discipline.
And if you have to, get other people around you to hold you
accountable to it.
I do want to quickly, something occurred to me
belatedly that I do want to emphasize.
Everything that, in particular, that Amir and I
were talking about, everything that Amir and I were talking
about in particular is predicated on what I was
saying earlier, which is.
We like and trust the people we work with and vice versa.
Like, so much of what we've been talking about
would break down if we worked with assholes.
So I think that's something you,
I'm gonna repeat it because I think it's so important.
This is really something you have to take to heart.
Like you, you know, there's this mythos,
this mythology in Silicon Valley and in games of like,
well, there's that.
amazing programmer who's like ten times more
effective than any other programmer, but he's also an asshole, but it's okay
because he's ten times better than any other programmer, he's gonna make our game
amazing, and so like
you, yes, you want people like that.
I think that's bullshit. You don't want people like that. And that seems pretty consistent across the board, like
almost everybody I've ever spoken with has said universally, I will,
I would prefer
a middle-of-the-road employee
who's a delight to work with.
versus some diva who comes in and says,
yeah, I want my desk to be filled with
1,000 brown M&Ms every day as I go in.
And if there's one blue, I quit.
Yeah, I mean, think about it.
You can't have a policy where people are required
to take at least 20 days of vacation
unless you trust those people, right?
That they're not gonna abuse that,
that they're people worthy of that.
You can't have a situation where.
you know, where you expect everyone to do the hyphen thing in Slack and not bother each
other unless, like, they're people who actually care and would internalize something like
that.
Like, that just stops working otherwise.
Like, so, yeah.
Choose who you work with carefully.
And so that seems to be an ongoing theme here,
is that the team makes a difference,
and the team helps build the connection.
But on top of that, in terms of studio managers,
you, because of the amount of discipline it takes
to take time off when you're really passionate about this,
and it is, it does take a lot of discipline,
and it's really helpful to have people
who bug you to take time off.
I don't know this from personal experience at all.
I've literally been ordered to take a vacation
two weeks from now.
Um...
My boss is laughing at this because she's the one who made me do it.
But, um, but, um, you're talking about implementing studio policies
to make people realize that working less to a degree
makes them work more effectively and keeps your employees.
And one of the signals, Amir, you look for in things is turnover rate
in terms of a good studio environment.
So, lightning round, because I want to cut to questions for a few minutes.
Um, think about your questions now.
Begin them with a who, what, where, why.
Not story time.
What would you want to tell yourself,
your earlier career self,
about how to make your career last?
And Tommy replied with the very colorful,
only be loyal to those who are loyal to you
and lawyer the fuck up.
Wow.
Well, my answer would be very simple.
One of the things Mark Twain, he once expressed, it's been said in many ways, but he wrote
that comparison is the death of joy.
And if I could have told myself that, even when I was 10 years old or 15 or whatever,
that would have changed my life tremendously.
I am very thankful for where I am.
I have no regrets about all my different paths, but thinking about others and where they are
and how good they are or bad they are, any of that.
and around this issue of stress and burnout and everything,
I hear it all the time when I talk to developers.
The one huge massive layer of stress
is that they're looking on social media,
looking on Facebook and Twitter,
and they're going to this conference in Dubrovnik,
and they're going over here,
and here I am in my shithole still working,
and I'm depressed, and I'm angry,
and this game's not working,
and I can't get the build going,
all that kind of stuff,
and I think that layer of pressure
is just like you're at the bottom of the ocean.
And I just think you have to just stop comparing yourself
to what other people are doing around you
and just focus on what you do best, focus on your work.
Especially one of the things I see a lot
is when people say, I will never be as good as them.
I'll never be as good of an artist or programmer or whatever
and if you see people like that around you,
whether it's in your studio, at school or whatever,
guess what, you just found a mentor.
Go ask them to help you to get better at what you're doing.
But that.
That, I think, for me, would be a fundamental difference,
if I had just mined my own business
and focused on what I do best.
No comparisons.
Find a mentor.
Yes.
Awesome.
Woo!
Oh, Lord.
So I would say the stuff I look back on and
feel the worst about are the times when overwork
might have affected my relationship or my relationship.
So probably something like, you know,
tell Anna that you love her
and that you're grateful for her.
You know, we're married, everything's good.
But, you know, certainly that's the stuff I look back on
and it's like, man, she lived in the house with us.
She like was there the whole time.
She cooked for us, she did all sorts of things that lifted our spirits and made bashing possible.
So you know, I've said it a lot since then, but I should have said it more then.
So tell those you care about that you love them.
Okay.
I've been pretty lucky.
There's not a whole lot that I would have told myself to do differently 10 years ago aside from,
and you guys can guess this from the multiple things I've already said, like,
there's a handful of people I kind of wish I would have separated myself from sooner.
You know, people who were like, just not awesome people.
And by awesome, I don't necessarily don't mean they weren't the greatest artist or programmer ever.
I mean, they were just not nice people.
They were just very selfish or very this or very that.
And like, they made my life worse.
And as soon as they were out of my life, my life got 10x better.
Oh.
Yeah.
So we've got about three and a half minutes for questions.
And there are microphones right here.
But the good news is we will be hanging out
in one of the wrap up rooms afterwards
if you have more questions that don't get asked.
So come on up to the microphone,
give us your quick question,
and we'll see what we can answer.
Ian Schreiber, RIT. Many people here are students, faculty, or people who mentor them.
For at the student level, there are some people in higher ed that say, that take
the thing of we need to teach how to take care of yourself, how to work in a
safe and sane way. There are others that say, well, lots of parts of the industry
suck. A lot of these students are going to go to Carnte Studios. We need to
prepare them for it. How would you find the balance between those things?
So how do you teach students the balance between hard work
and sustainable work?
Well, how do you balance the fact that industry
is going to have some crunchy studios
that students will go to and you are,
and part of our role is to prepare students
for that eventuality versus, you know,
not burning our students out
before they even get to industry.
So how do you prepare students
for the reality of the industry as it is
while teaching them to try and be better?
Yes. Okay.
That's a great question.
And you all have answers to this concrete ones, right?
I mean, I've actually been involved in a lot of educational programs,
especially in Europe.
And one of the things that some of them have done is try and model,
you know, they basically model themselves after a studio, an ideal studio.
So they try and model that behavior to the students in the process of education so that
they can take that model and bring that expectation to their employer.
One of the things I've also been mentoring a lot of students about is that when you go
into a job interview, you must be asking those questions about what's the work life like,
do you crunch here, what's your diversity numbers, all of that kind of stuff.
You know, and not only ask the question, but be willing to walk away if the question is
not what you want to hear.
That is super tough and it takes courage to walk away from your first job, but I've heard
some students who've done it and they felt instantly empowered because now I have a choice.
I wasn't desperate.
And I think we have to encourage students to be able to do that and make that choice
for their own benefit.
So in other words, teach students to ask good questions.
Training programs need to model the ideal.
Yes.
Cool.
I'm going to add one thing to that, which is that because I
Like, I agree with that, and then at the same time, I know,
because it's just the reality of life, that there's going to
be a bunch of young people out there who are going to feel
like they only have one job offer, and they've spent the
last four years trying to get in the game industry.
You better believe they're going to take that job offer.
Even if they're going into a studio that they
know crunches 24-7.
So given that.
I guess what I'd say, and I realize this is hard,
because 90% of this room is introverts,
and I'm a secret introvert too, so I get it,
is you just have to always be networking.
You have to make an enormous effort
to make sure that you meet other people,
that you get your name out there,
that you have eventually other options,
because yeah, you might find yourself
feeling like you're being forced to take a job
at a place that has an unhealthy culture
in some way, shape, or form.
And I'm not gonna judge you for doing that.
Like, if you feel like you really have to do that to break in, so be it.
Like, do that.
I mean, I worked like a mule when I was in my 20s.
I mean, I'm not gonna criticize anyone for that.
But like, the reason I'm not still doing that is because I forced myself out of my box
and that worked more than I thought was physically possible.
Um, you know, because again, secret introvert.
So, yeah.
So, um, we just got the call for time.
Where is the Meetup room for further questions?
2-0-4, okay, we will be in room 2-0-4, but thank you all.