This presentation is being sponsored by the Writers Guild of America.
Our motto, if you have a plot, hire a professional.
If you don't, make a game.
Before we begin, we're going to be showing clips from Psychic Detective
that depict characters in extreme psychic torment.
If you are experiencing likewise because of hangover this morning,
don't sit by the speakers.
And a note about showing clips from a game
or an interactive movie.
Looking at clips instead of playing them
is a little like looking at a court transcript of a Robin
Williams monologue.
You're going to get the gist of it,
and you're going to appreciate a lot of it,
but you're going to be painfully aware that something
is missing for you.
And in this case, it's making decisions and making choices
and having the movie instantly react to you.
What I asked John to do was assemble what we refer to as the Psychic Detective Cliff Notes.
How many people have actually played Psychic Detective at least once from beginning to end?
Alright, for the many uninitiated, we're going to take you through a breakneck tour of what this is about,
and then talk a little bit about the pragmatic challenges of trying to create this kind of animal.
So, with no further ado, maybe a little further ado.
I was just gonna say that it's a title that we created with Electronic Arts.
It's published on the 3DO, PlayStation, and PC CD-ROM formats.
It's five hours worth of live action material which you are playing through 20 to 40 minutes at a time.
That's basically it.
Beautiful.
We refer to it as an interactive film that's 30 minutes long
and five hours wide.
But more to come.
Here's your basic high concept.
A little non-interactive intro, which
tells you something about the main character and the plot.
People think if you have psychic powers, the world is yours to control.
That's a load of crap.
If I could predict the future, there'd be a few less dead bodies.
Ladies and gentlemen, welcome to the Pika Lounge.
My name is Eric Fox, better known as the Psychic Flash.
There I was, doing what I do best.
The old freak of nature routine.
Called myself the Psychic Flash.
Hey, the old folks loved it.
Me, I got fast, easy cash, and the occasional voodoo groupie.
Your grandfather gave this to you on his deathbed.
Very moving for you.
Very boring for us.
Alright ladies and gentlemen,
anyone else out there have another...
Her name was Lena Pozak.
She looked like an angel,
but she sent me to hell.
With one shove,
she sent my whole world spinning.
She showed me how to transmit my psychic self into the consciousness of others.
To see through their eyes.
Hear through their ears.
The real mind pirate stuff.
Naturally, it was a price.
That's my sister Monica.
Cute.
plastic dress
maybe you can find out for me
and him?
I don't know
my father had a money student
he was hoping to come in first
so leave it
it doesn't waste much time
who's the toy boy?
where's Mr. Moulage?
meet him at the tea room at 10 o'clock
prompts appear that allow you to choose actions for the main character.
Those are going to appear in the upper right corner.
I overkill on the first date.
Come on.
Perhaps you are a man who enjoys...
We tell him to get lost.
You shouldn't sell stuff that isn't yours.
There are also objects that you can touch and receive retro-cognitive flashes.
The icons for those are going to appear on the bottom of the screen.
And when you touch one, you get a movie.
And these are clues and back story and information that you are going to have to in your head
assemble.
Nice logo.
Mini quick?
Maxi quick?
Mirage Quest is an institute for self esteem.
Maximum you, maximum me.
What about the screaming cat?
I have no idea what you're talking about.
The further along you go in the story, you will discover R. McGuffin in the plot, which
is called the Psychic Collector.
The Psychic Collector, when it is activated, as it's just about to be, will enhance your
powers and therefore double your interface.
All the characters are chasing after the four psychic collectors.
Three have been found, one is still missing.
Now you have the ability to jump into people's heads from a distance,
or in this case, read the psyche of a character who's with you.
Stop it!
What was that?
You also up...
You were reading me!
Invading my psyche.
You also have the ability to throw thoughts at other characters and make them do things.
These icons appear at the bottom here.
I'd like you to have this.
Thanks.
No later, no payback. Let's move.
Yes, it's a comedy.
Those can be very, very strategic.
Now, those are the sort of things that, as a player,
these are the choices that you're making on the fly.
What happens if you want to sit back and just watch the movie?
We allow you to do that as well.
Late in the game, yes?
Oh, I was just going to say that it may be obvious or not obvious, but every time you take advantage of something,
you're changing what's going to happen next.
Obviously, when we touched the object, Sylvia reacted to the fact, and we knew something a little bit more about Sylvia,
the blonde woman with the MirageQuest pin.
When we told Chad to get lost, we were active, and the objects that appeared afterwards would only appear if we had told Chad to get lost.
If we do things throughout the entire movie, we're going to change what is and is not available to us as we play through.
That's the idea of creating a narrative that works like a nervous system.
And you make one choice up here, and it's telling the entire story what you've done, and it's going to ripple all the way through.
Now, so what we want to demonstrate now is, late in the story, you come to Sylvia, you're
looking for notebook containing vital pieces of information.
If you sit back and do nothing, the scene might unfold like this.
You're in the wrong room.
Don't we ever get a scene together?
Hmm?
Know what Max is doing? I was just in his head, writing a little poem for the princess.
You're so far in the rebound, you haven't stopped bouncing.
Screw you!
One way of getting even, but I hit hard.
You can't compete with the trophy wife.
She's nothing!
Nothing? She's adorable.
What's any of you around for anyway?
Pest control.
I want this one back when he's properly cooked.
Let's look at it again, and in this case, John is going to activate the collector.
You're in the wrong room.
God is throwing submissions.
Oh, swear me with the blood from a kosher killing.
Oh, weird industrial fluids.
Oh, make me do unspeakable things with these little things.
Oh, super glue-up parrots in my body,
they'll be scratching and scratching,
bleeding through your paws.
Oh, oh, and I'm wearing a clown costume.
Oh!
Rick, you're gone.
I'm Lance!
Who ordered the gun?
I think we did.
Would you like me to fire it, and maybe clean it for you?
Just give it to me, you know, I could ram it, and load it.
Give me the god damn gun, Lance.
I want you to have it just like you pictured, okay?
The fact that Psychic Detective doesn't stop, uh, is really crucial.
to understanding a lot about the structure, a lot about the challenges that we had to tackle,
and what makes it different from other products that call themselves interactive movies.
The most popular entertainments out there that are interactive movies tend to work a certain way.
You get a bit of film, and then you have to solve a puzzle, and then you get some more movie,
and then you have to solve a puzzle, a little more movie,
a puzzle that could last 60 minutes before you get more film.
Those are very entertaining experiences, but what they lose is a sense of film time.
I mean, what we respond to in movies, what we think is great, is the relentless pace.
The fact is, films and even TV shows, they don't pause, with the possible exception of
Winky Dink, you know, which was the grandfather of all interactive movies.
We'll do a seminar on Winky Dink later.
We will.
But what happens is, if the movie is hurtling by, then
you've got to make your choices on the fly.
If you're wondering what's going to happen next, even as
it's happening next, and trying to decide, well, what's
the proper decision to do here?
You know, we think that becomes an interesting experience.
And it comes from the fact that we decided to tie all of the different prompts to the dramatic action.
Right. It also means that what we're doing is we are treating the film as the puzzle itself.
Because you are sitting there and deciding, whose head should I jump into, what object
should I touch, what thought should I throw, when should I use the collector, and by doing
that you're editing the movie on the fly.
Which is, to people from Hollywood, a very sacrilegious phrase to say.
It is honestly what goes on here.
It seemed like a good idea because if you set up a set of characters,
those characters are operating according to traits which you have communicated to the audience.
Those traits, for us, were themselves a set of rules.
That certain characters are going to do certain things,
and if we push the characters into different emotional arenas,
they're going to react in character.
according to the rules that we've set out for them.
And if we think about that challenge as being the beginning of the game,
then the puzzle aspect is threaded throughout the entire experience,
because we're asking you not to figure out whodunit,
but to figure out why everybody done it.
Why everybody's doing things.
John likes to call it a whodunit instead of a whydunit,
and I like that very much because...
An interactive story is horizontal by nature.
It's got to be wide.
There's got to be a lot of parallel possibilities
existing side by side.
There's got to be a lot of back story and a lot of subplots
that you can wander at will.
A whodunit is going to basically build to one plot point answer.
And once you know it,
end of story. A wide done it can be about the fact that A did this to B, later on C
did this to A, now A, B, and C are going to meet over here, unless of course D finds out
about it. That becomes a much wider map of story and there are a lot more possibilities
that you've got to uncover and connect. I mean films we think lend themselves to this
sort of
method because they're so fragmented to begin with.
It is a puzzle. A film is a puzzle that's been assembled for you.
You know, it begins at the writing stage where you're putting your scenes on index cards
and trying to decide what's the proper order.
You're breaking it down into the pieces that you're going to shoot most efficiently for production.
And then the editor and the director are sitting together,
and they're stitching together the most meaningful whole.
Now, what if you made a Rubik's cube of a film,
where there was more than one meaningful whole,
and where each different sequence and different order
that you might put together was going
to give you a different kind of experience?
That's what we're dealing with here.
One of the ways that you do that is to play with time and sequencing.
You set certain actions in stone, within the story, and you allow the player to come to
them at their own pace, in their own order.
Yeah, they're essentially dramatic modules that have different entrances and exits and
can be altered depending on previous action.
And if those dramatic modules are attached to a certain number of set-in-stone tent poles,
people can play through experiences in different time order,
with different emotional states and different sets of knowledge,
both in the player's mind and the character's minds,
when they approach those different modules.
So here are a few givens, and we'll show you how they play out.
The fourth collector is hidden over here.
There is a blackmail scheme, very dangerous, going on over here.
The old lady is waiting for us in the mansion here, and Sylvia is going to show up and try
and kill her.
And down the hall in the mansion is a hidden room, which you may or may not have found
out about.
At a certain part in our movie, our hero Eric Fox is going to return to the mansion to see
the old lady.
And the fact is, this can happen a number of different ways, depending upon what order
you've taken things.
He can show up and he can know absolutely nothing.
She says it has to be you all along.
I trust you behave yourself.
Drowning in the water, trying to swim and swim, but ripping your own throat with sharp
hooves.
I love that old world folklore.
Quiet!
You joke and fumble when you must face the killer himself.
Only two options appear because we know nothing.
Lexi, the best of the Black Diamond.
It's your next miracle.
Now, Amy, we went to the blackmail scheme, and we got psychically fried.
We're showing up a moron.
But we're able to save the old lady.
Lena, no!
Stop!
No!
Silence!
Can't you see? It's her.
He's a burnt marshmallow.
Think how you can train him.
Oh, you fool!
I love your blouse.
I'll tell you what.
You find the fourth collector, huh?
And then you let the village idiot make a special delivery.
And then maybe I'll give you back Little Sister.
Find it, boy!
I've always wanted a pet.
**laughter**
Very well.
Come back to us.
He only has three!
Otherwise you are gone forever!
The other hand you might have gotten the fourth collector and shown up in time to save Madame T
Which means you can use the fourth collector
Just for me Eric
Make a twist
Get another one
You can go weirder, cowboy.
Much weirder.
Are you with me?
Oh, you're the best.
Oh, I'm sick and lazy.
On the other hand...
Perhaps you got the collector, but too late.
You arrived later in time.
Go!
You cannot hide, you must fight him!
I'm not ready.
Only fear, find the scar, do not choose me!
If you were ten years older, and I was thirty years...
Let me try.
Another possibility is that you had found out about the hidden room.
So you go there first.
And there's lots of stuff to see in the hidden room.
More clues and backstory that will help you piece the whole mystery together.
But if you stay too long, there are obviously jeopardies involved in that.
But in this case, we left in time.
Yes, we left in time.
Tell Max he settles for three.
Tell him yourself.
You can't hide.
He can't make the black diamond.
Max gets what he needs.
He's already got the little girls.
I'll get you both.
Or you know where to find us.
Oh, and Max sends you lots of kisses.
And look at her try to talk to Mokey lately.
And of course another example is you could find the hidden room, you could go in, you could touch objects to your heart's delight, but what that means is you're going to probably show up and the old lady will be dead.
Now what this does is it gives you a sense that your choices really matter as
you're playing the film. From a production standpoint it allows us
to deal with a lot of possibilities in an efficient and budgetable manner.
I mean, was all of that...
It means we were locked in Madame T's bedroom for two full days.
In terms of the development of the movie, we've got six chapters.
The moment we just showed you is towards the end of the fifth chapter.
But the way the moments, the way the dramatic modules are played mean that...
You can arrive too late to save Madame T.
You can arrive early and she can still be in jeopardy.
We've tried to make something that has the flotation of these dramatic modules in time
and also something in which the variables are shifted
because of what you've done previously through the movie.
So we tried to track and estimate what you would know at that point
and what the hero would know.
From a production standpoint...
We did a very smart thing early on, and it's something we had done with Jim at Electronic Arts,
which is that we played the game on paper with a lot of different people,
not only to get their reaction to the tone, the kind of interaction, and the scale of what we were trying to attempt,
but it was a useful thing because we had a 500-page script which Michael wrote,
and for most productions, that seems impossible.
The limits of physical video production are that you need the cast and crew on site to be able to turn out
usually maybe five or six pages of dialogue a day if you're moving at a real clip in terms of making a motion picture.
With 500 pages, we had about 20 days to shoot, in fact exactly 20 days in which to shoot all the material,
which meant that we were covering a great deal more than five or six pages a day.
And in order to be able to do this and not go crazy, we did some things in production that made a lot of sense.
We lit a lot of the environments we were working in theatrically.
so that we could shoot more than one or two angles at a time.
In fact, in some instances, we could shoot an entire 360-degree number of setups,
looking at different actors from different angles because of our switch of POV,
or building the scene.
in traditional filmic style with wide shots, masters, and close-ups, twos, and singles.
The other thing that we did when we played the game beforehand
was we educated the cast and crew to understand why something that might seem abrupt...
and completely discontinuous, even though we were shooting out of continuity order,
would make a certain amount of game sense because of what we were intending.
So, after a while, even though the actors were porting around a shrunken copy of a 500-page script,
They were well-versed enough in knowing the threads of the drama to be able to know exactly why they were doing things.
For example, Sylvia's reactions to being pulled off Madame T.
There's seven, eight, nine different ways that she's stopped from killing the old lady.
She had to know each time what was going on in the plot so that she could react to it because
something that's subtle in her performance is what she does and doesn't know.
What the bad guy Max Mirage has been keeping from her.
and what's in the foreground. It's one of the things that you as Eric Fox can use to elucidate
stuff. You can use her jealousy of Monica to your advantage, but the performer has to be able to
communicate that to you in a subtle sort of way so you know what her state of mind is.
Which also means that we're setting you up for the throwing of thoughts at various characters
because if you throw aggression, submission, or affection at particular characters, you're
going to get different reactions depending on who they are at that moment.
We might get something we like from the bouncer by throwing affection.
If we ever try throwing affection at Sylvia in certain circumstances, she's really going
to take it the wrong way.
So from a production standpoint, we did a number of kind of interesting things.
In fact, we found that the actors after a while were a little bit more on the ball about
exactly where we were coming from and where we were going because we were concentrating
too much on the actual details of production.
So there was a great advantage to playing the game in advance with everybody.
Come back around now to the idea of the film as a puzzle.
We were looking at how you can play the movie in different
orders and how that's meaningful.
The other idea is that we're trying to get our audience to
connect the dots visually.
Our supposition is, any one of you sat on an airplane and watched the movie without headphones,
you'd know what happened in the story.
You could tell us the story without necessarily having listened to it,
or even paid extremely close attention to it.
When John talks about it being a why done it, we've taken a great deal of the backstory and of the subplot and literally chopped it up and scattered it around the movie.
We've sort of turned the film or the story into a landscape and we want the player to wander through and find different moments and slowly start to connect them.
What the hell is the screaming cat about?
You will eventually learn that if you happen to come back.
to the right place for it.
Doing things like having psychic memories, being able to read the history of people,
and having psychic flashes allows us to create these sort of sequences.
We're going to now take a look at reading the psyche of the arch-villain Max Mirage.
Everybody played that part perfectly.
This is how you do it.
All of those fragments, they mean something.
Yeah, along with being abstract.
Yes.
There are lots of moments throughout the piece
in which we are very, very explicit about what things mean.
So in a way what we wanted was we wanted the thoughts and ideas to percolate in everybody's head
through multiple viewings, and then when the apparentness of what things mean occurs to people
and they get to the right place at the right time, there is an explicit explanation of what they may have thought was going on.
In the process of putting together a story that works this way,
you are inevitably going to want to shuttle the player to certain areas.
You can call these areas funnels or bottlenecks,
but they are a pain in the ass,
because you know that they're going to see them a number of times,
or they're going to pass through this area a number of times.
although we figured out a way around this recently.
In the end, the true answer, I think,
is to have the player and the computer
construct those sequences almost on a shot-by-shot basis,
doing montages on the fly.
In Psyche Detective, we tried a couple of solutions.
We didn't necessarily cover all of our bases,
but a number of times we used.
Two methods. The first is to create a short scene that is really like the hub of a wheel.
It has a lot of different options coming out of it.
So even though you're going to hit it a number of times, you can go different places with it.
Right, and one of the things I think that you may have noticed about psychic is that
when you decide to take action, when you decide to either jump into somebody else's head,
touch an object, or respond to an action prompt,
you are cutting off the moment that you're in the middle of,
and you're jumping to another moment.
So we connect?
And this is a prime example of that.
You can touch your keychain.
Coach Monica, just a little more.
I do not trust this Mirage Quest.
You're going?
Stop her.
I have to.
Don't ask why.
You're just like your bracelet.
Just hate me if you must.
You can beg her for help.
You can follow her.
Or what John has chosen to do...
Go home, you idiot.
...is that you can jump in her head.
How come I never thought about going home?
You think I don't know.
I can't feel you.
Sliding around in the back of my head.
We spent a lot of time talking about the combination of reward and frustration.
What can we reward people with as they play through Psychic Detective?
And what level of frustration are people going to feel because they don't understand what's going on?
And we decided...
explicitly to throw people into the soup in the very beginning in the exact
position of our main character which is you've been led into a film noir world
you've been lied to and you've got to figure things out because your ass is on
the line we are anticipating that
People are going to bring their personalities to playing Psyche Detective.
Some people are going to simply sit back and let the movie play,
and the movie will talk to them and tell them a great deal of story.
Some people are going to jump in and touch everything that comes up first.
It's the first thing they're going to do, they're going to just grab anything that comes up.
There are rewards and frustrations for that.
We're going to mete out equal amounts of,
that was a good move,
and maybe that wasn't exactly the brightest thing.
So that people will adjust their rhythm
to the rhythms that we've put in front of them.
The rhythms of the characters,
the rhythms of the videos of the scenes,
and the rhythms of the available choices
that come up depending on what they've done.
Another way then to deal with funnel points is, of course, to have different variations of the scene.
In this particular case in time, where the little weasel named Mokey is picking you up after you come out of jail,
you may know different things.
The movie is going to track that, and the appropriate scenes are going to play.
I just want to use the damn thing.
You want a collector? We can get one on Brook Street.
Sure, sure. A genuine Rolex.
The fourth collector is in a pawn shop.
We know this. We're positive.
Oh, baby! Do you realize what we could do with two collectors?
Pick a country. Be an emperor.
We got Lexi by the balls.
Excuse me?
Ah, don't play dumb.
You think the Max Mirage comes out of nowhere?
New face, new rack. Same old slime dog.
Lexi Golitsyn.
Ah ha! That's my pills!
Maybe I just want to use the damn thing.
Kid, this is white hot.
We snag a collector.
We're big league, psychic mercenaries.
You with the brain, me with the rolodex.
That collector belongs to Lena.
The hell it does. I shelled out cash four years ago.
So you say.
Don't you get it?
Lexi never died.
A face job and a lounge act worse than yours.
Max Mirage?
No, Wayne Newton.
Come on dude, get with the beat!
So if you've actually gone with Moki to this drop,
it means that you did a handful of things earlier in the movie.
And we realize that at this point,
the vital piece of information you need to know
is that Max Mirage, our present day bad guy,
is actually a rather evil ex-Soviet spy named Lexi Golitsyn in disguise.
The best metaphor that I know for an interactive story or playing an interactive story is ironically
a feature film and that's Groundhog Day.
where the player is really Bill Murray. You are in a
universe that is full of rules with actions that are fixed in time.
You've got to decide how you're going to behave,
how you are going to deal with everything, and what you're ultimately trying to do is be in the right place at the right time and
be the best possible version of yourself to be able to advance and to break the cycle.
One of the things an interactive movie has to do
is let you know how you did.
Throughout the film.
we try and talk back to you and have characters let you know
not only how you're behaving, but what you've accomplished and what you might know.
But what all of this is ultimately building to
is something that is referred to throughout the movie, which is Black Diamond.
And Black Diamond is both a physical board game, but more importantly, a mind game,
a psychic battle that is going to take place.
It's unavoidable. It is sort of our high noon showdown.
And yet there are so many different ways that you can head into it.
Depending upon not only what you know, but who you've helped,
who may still be alive, who may be stronger,
because you've found secrets that could heal them.
All of those things are taken into account.
Does Jim want to say anything about...
I need to see it.
Okay, we'll take a look at it first.
You have your ugly thoughts.
That's the bad guy.
Your little demons.
I have mine.
And he's turning on all four collectors.
Which ones are stronger?
And he's sending us into a psychic battleground space, which is...
So, in the very beginning, you've got eight possible icons out of a total of 32.
They reflect how you've played through the movie and what we think you know.
You pick the first four, and Max will pick the other four.
You're trying to pick the four that you think are the strongest for you, that you understand.
Max gets the others.
I never move first.
It would be bad manners.
And then basically you're battling him.
You're playing what you think is a strong piece for you
against what you think is a weak piece for him.
Maximum max.
Maximum obedience.
Maximum fighting.
Silence!
A lot of characters like Lena and Madame T'Kunoff,
the old lady and our heroine,
did you really think you could be her knight in shining armor?
I wanted to help.
Too bad. You just damned her to hell.
Characters can be in different states by the time we get here.
In fact, at this point, Madame T is a very strong icon, and Lena was a very weak one.
Be careful, boys. She'll suck you dry. She needs you to keep herself strong.
The only thing she needs is your ass on a platter.
Hmm, that one was particularly tasty.
The damn thing is red!
Well, take note...
for some other lifetime.
Yes, in fact, back to the triumph.
Is that the best you can do?
Sacrifice yourself?
So we get one of 14 possible conclusions to the movie,
depending on how we play it.
I'm so full of blood.
Of the balls.
It's over, Mark!
If only I could die.
I win! I win!
Kiki, I win!
Kiki!
Kiki...
We've suffered pretty severe brain damage, as you can see.
And at the very end, the game will tell you which of the 14 conclusions you triggered.
and it will give you a little hint for your next play through
which is based on something you didn't see the first time.
Right.
We've been talking a lot about the puzzle and the movie being the same beast.
I thought it would be appropriate now to hear from Mr. Simmons, who in many ways was safeguarding
the agenda of the game itself and dealing with two people who had never made a game
before and were prepared to run wild.
I guess just to sort of finish up on the Black Diamond game part of it and what Michael had
said about needing to find a way for...
the game to talk back to the player.
You know, the conversational model that we talk about in interactive design a lot, you know,
the player thinks of something, says it into the game through the interface,
the computer analyzes that input, thinks about it,
formulates a response, and now something's different when we think about it.
During the course of an interactive drama, there's less of that than we're accustomed to
in a gaming experience where the conversational loop is really tight.
Other than the kinds of things like we do something and in the next scene we mention it to Moki
and Moki goes, oh, you know, what you don't know is, and then he gives us some stuff back.
So that the feedback loop is slower at that point.
But in order to...
to think of, if you want to think of I'm winning the game, I'm accomplishing some particular goal,
then what you're able to do in this very, very simple little board game of these eight icons
have values relative to each other and they may come and go depending on, if your brain's been
fried, the value of the pieces you're playing with are lessened because you just don't have the
powers.
So the feedback loop in terms of win-loss, if that's the way the player wants to come
you know, think about the experience for themselves, and some people think about it that way and
some people don't, is very long. It's 30 minutes long.
because the piece is only 20 to 40 minutes long,
people will sit down and in one sitting,
go through that loop two or three times
to see how they're doing and grow a lot from doing it.
One of the things that we...
had no idea if it was going to work or not, which is why we played it on paper so many times.
Michael playing the role of Mr. Memory and standing in front of somebody and just playing the game for
them all day long. I mean, we'd bring people in, lock them in this room, and they'd play the thing
for, you know, eight times. I'm having bad flashbacks. Yeah.
what I had to sit in there and referee because he would have this tendency to
want to help people out a little bit and so the way he would play the game is he
would describe the scene and all those little icons that are on the screens we
had three by five cards of and he would slide them forward and they were
available and Madame T walks out of the room and her icon disappears and
somebody would be oh no you can't have it and but he would want to go okay you can
have it back
So we play all the way through and we would get to the end and we'd pull out this board
and put it on the table and have all these little icons spread around and Michael would
figure out which icons had to go on and then some of them sort of, depending on how the
story goes, all eight may be dictated by the playthrough you've done.
Perhaps four are dictated and the four we go grab kind of at random.
bring one of the women in, let's bring a minor character in, you know, we haven't
used the skull in a time or two, let's bring that in. And we'd throw that on
there. And we didn't tell anybody anything about what they were supposed
to do, other than, you know, you can you can pick this piece up and move it. And
they try to go, you know, all the way around the board, say, no you can't move
it that far. Oh, okay. And so we do it and then we would...
take the two pieces and do the little kids game of like, and this one stays.
And then he would describe the movie that would play as a result of it.
I mean, the first time we did it, people were just totally baffled.
And they just thought, this is, you know, this makes no sense whatsoever.
And we go, yeah, okay, let's make a note of that.
Makes no sense whatsoever.
And then they'd play it a second time.
And they would see a correlation.
between what they had done before and what had happened the second time,
they would notice that, oh, these are different icons that came up this time
than came up the time before.
Oh, they noticed that. Okay, that's a good thing.
And after about the third time,
they would begin to formulate some firmly held opinions about what's going on here
and here's what I'm going to do the next time
and I'm going to go after this and I'm going to get that and I know.
And they were dead wrong.
But...
They had formulated an opinion, they had made a commitment, they were engaged.
And after about the fifth time, they had some firm opinions and some of them were right.
And they could see that they were right in that feedback mechanism.
If I've got the cigarette and such and such has happened and I see that skull and I do that,
I know every single time that that's what's going to happen.
So they start formulating.
a set of patterns which sometimes results in I've got to see a certain movie repeatedly,
but more often doesn't.
And they vectored toward improvement and getting things to happen the way they wanted them
to with very, very, with no instruction manual hints and help.
They put that together and that's when we realized, okay, it's going to work.
And that this feedback mechanism that we've structured at the end does allow them to put
the whole story together and know what's going on and why, and to feel like they have some
power over controlling it.
And having control in an interactive experience over what's going on instead of just feeling
at the mercy of arbitrary design decisions is a real challenge, and so we felt like we
did a pretty good job with that.
In many ways, our hope is that we find an audience for Psychic Detective that has a series of reactions to the material.
The first is the impulse to win, or to play it as well as possible.
The second is to know the whole world of the story.
find it and put it together and make for themselves a coherent narrative.
And the third is hopefully to find all the cool stuff.
I mean, John has stocked this project with brilliant and twisted and funny little movies.
If you get engaged, if you find a character that you really like,
hopefully you'll seek it all out.
In many ways...
As we got involved with Psyche Detective, I was reminded of an experience that I had when I was in high school
when I bought a comedy album by the Monty Python Group called Matching Tie and Handkerchief.
That had on one side a double set of grooves.
And I played that side eight times and I got the same comedy routines.
And the ninth time, the needle dropped in the second set of grooves, and there was 15 minutes I had never heard before.
And that was a moment where technology and comedy conspired to blow my little mind.
And it was a great experience. And it was a great sensation.
And my feeling is that CD-ROMs of this nature hold that potential.
That we can be making interactive stories, animated pieces, full motion video pieces,
where you pop it in, you don't know where you're going to begin.
You don't know where you're going to go, and you certainly don't know how it's going to end
We you know we started with looking at the puzzle aspect of putting all these pieces together
We with Jim's brilliant
Help and his original impulse about jumping into the minds of other people to be somewhere where your body shouldn't
We realized that we could take hurdles it interface hurdles away from people
and we could give them impulsive but instinctually correct material
with which they can drive the movie,
with which they can navigate through a realm of character-driven story possibilities.
It occurs to us now that we can up the ante on that quite considerably
by going deeper into the story, the world that the characters live in, and the characters,
because everybody connects with those elements
and everybody knows the language that we're speaking.
It's it's necessary to take the pieces and chop them up even smaller
And it is very necessary for the movie to know how many times you've played it
Listen before we wrap up. We'd be happy to take some questions
Yeah back there
The average user
800, 900 hours? No, no, no, no.
It's a really difficult question to answer.
If you want to see all 14 endings, you know, 20 or 30 hours.
If we're talking average intelligence, we might stretch that out a little bit more,
but the average gamer is a pretty smart customer.
10 to 20 is reasonable.
Back there?
confirmation results were made on paper before you wrote the code.
What did you change in your evaluation based on feedback?
One of the things that we tried to do was open up the funnels of the bottlenecks.
We realized that, hey, you know, we keep coming to the scene, and we're going to come to it
every time, and people are going to get pretty damn sick of it.
Let's try and open some of these up.
We also built a prototype of the first chapter with still images and voiceover, and just
voice only between different characters.
And it was more of, there was a lot more internal musing on the part of the main character,
which we realized we didn't need because the user, the player was going to be doing that
and was going to be filling in a lot of the blanks.
So actually we realized we could take out a great deal that we thought we were going
to have to give to people and that they could create their own jumps and leaps between things,
that they were the glue between the different puzzle pieces.
We also realized that there were some important clues that opened up having some abilities in the final Black Diamond game that we needed to make a little easier to find and some that we needed to obscure a little more.
We, the whole thing took a little over two years.
I think because we were in very undefined territory.
Three months of brainstorming and six months of writing and twenty days of production and then a year of editing and coding I think.
Yeah, we were working with a proprietary authoring environment that Electronic Arts created,
and the overlap of post-production and authoring was not quite as neatly dovetailed as we would
have liked.
Good job.
Obviously
my job. Well obviously there's no way to rough cut an interactive movie so we
have all the pieces made and then oddly enough I ended up authoring it but that
ended up being pretty cool because I could if I reached an authoring problem
movie wise I could quit the authoring environment go back into Adobe Premiere
recut the movie and bring it back into the authoring environment.
And that proved to be actually a fairly interesting way of being able to manipulate these elements.
Way up there in the back row.
Yes, you said, I think you addressed this partially, but you talked about finding a way around some of the funnels so that you didn't need to find them necessary.
I don't know if I meant that they were not necessary.
It was necessary so that the script did not explode into chaos or thousands of pages.
It was necessary at times to shuttle the main character and the player to certain areas.
The point is you can do that with one scene that will always be the same.
You can do that with an array of scenes and depending upon what that player has done,
different ones will play.
Or go for a really short scene with a lot of choices right up the bat.
But in more recent works that we have been developing, we've just looked at the overall
structure in a completely different frame of mind.
and looked at how to not only create the dramatic modules,
but how the different levels of interaction move them around
and actually change them, as Michael said before, on the fly.
And that's one of the things that we're investigating.
Thank you.
Are we stuck with the mystery genre?
I hope not, no. Comedy, thriller, horror, anything you want.
Thriller, horror still has history.
Comedy. We want to make comedy.
We think that actually interactive comedy is perfect because you change the setup, you change the joke.
I think that there is a presupposition right now that because you wanted to have one foot
at least planted in the game world, that there's got to be a quest involved or some goal.
And I think that often that will shuttle you towards some aspect of mystery.
To my mind, one of the main things to break is supernatural powers.
I think it's very, very easy to traverse this territory and have your choices be about powers.
I think it's a lot of fun.
But I think one of the great goals is to go beyond that and create an environment
where nobody's really questioning,
why am I making choices?
Why am I tweaking the narrative?
Why am I playing God?
They're just going ahead and they're doing it.
Right, because the drama demands those choices.
Actually, a mystery seems to hold a lot of promise for an interactive thing.
I'm trying to figure something out.
But one of the pitfalls of mystery is that in linear media,
we accept things that we don't understand in a mystery.
We enjoy the feeling out of touch and out of control
because it's meant to be.
an eerie feeling that we know will come to a resolution and will be fixed by the time
it is over, an interactive experience needs to have you a little bit more in touch with
I am on top of what is going on.
I mean you are vacillating all over the place, but it is kind of a delicate balance and if
people feel too out of touch, they are very unsatisfied with the experience.
Within, turning 20 days into 40 days,
what production things would you have done
differently in practice tonight?
I wouldn't have turned 20 days into 40 days.
That costs a lot of money.
He wouldn't let us.
We were warned very early on.
Production things.
It's interesting because we've been thinking
a lot recently about animation
and about different kinds of graphic environments
for this kind of piece,
or for this sort of storytelling advance.
And the advantage of live action for certain things is kind of interesting because there's a,
and I think we communicate it pretty well as you play through it,
there's a certain level of physicality that I think people want.
And episodic television, when you get into a TV series that you really love,
there are certain central issues that are always constant and things that change.
I would go further into that.
where you're taking characters, you know, into very weird situations.
We've got a comedy idea in mind in which
we're anticipating taking a host of characters into a number of very far out situations.
And that's production, you know, that's real production value.
We're out of here?
We got booted. Thank you very much for coming.