Thank you and welcome, everybody,
to our talk about the making of Tetris Effect.
As you hopefully know, Tetris Effect,
the new take on the classic puzzle game for PS4, PSVR.
If you don't know what Tetris Effect is,
if you know what Tetris is and you see this talk,
you're going to get the idea, I think, pretty quick.
So the format for the talk is going
to be roughly in the chronological order
that we took through development.
And then we're going to summarize
at the end with some key takeaways
that we each felt like we learned from the project.
But this is really Ishihara-san's talk.
the director of the project.
But we're gonna be playing musical chairs a bit
and switching back and forth to the podium.
So yeah, we wanted to just all introduce ourselves
at the top here.
I'll start.
My name is Mark McDonald.
My title is VP Biz Dev and Production at Enhance,
but we're a really small shop,
so we all do lots of other jobs.
I do some PR, marketing.
I'm gonna talk a lot about focus groups that we ran.
for Tetris Effect, that sort of stuff.
My background is in the media.
I started off on video game magazines,
so you can kind of get a rough idea how old I am.
Electronic Gaming Monthly, Official PlayStation Magazine.
I switched to online, ran the video side
of a site called 1up.com.
And then moved to Japan about 10 years ago and to the dev side of the industry where
I worked with some friends at a company called 8-4, which is a terrible company filled with
garbage people.
Stay away.
But one of them is up here on stage with us.
Graham Howard, thank you very much.
Graham is going to be doing interpretation for Ishihara-san.
So yeah, anyway, 8.4, I was lucky enough
to work on big titles for Nintendo, Capcom.
Imagine makeup artist, that sort of thing.
And that's where I first started working with Mizuguchi-san,
consulting on what would become ResInfinite.
That was about three years ago.
And eventually, when I left 8.4, I ended up at Enhance
and have been there ever since.
So with that, Isharu-san, I'll hand it over.
My name is Takashi Ishihara.
Good afternoon everyone, my name is Takashi Ishihara.
In the past, I've worked as a concept artist and art director on games that fuse music and visuals, such as Child of Eden, Luminous, and Rez Infinite.
I am the development director of Tetris Effect.
Thank you for having me.
pretty long years, since 1990.
So I joined SEGA in 1990,
and I produced SEGA Rally and arcade games, racing games,
and the Reds, Space Shuttle M5,
Child of Eden, Luminous, and so on.
And this title, Tetris Effect,
this is my 20th produced title.
So yeah, thank you for coming today.
So let me talk about the Tetris effect.
So the beginning of the story.
I met Hank Rogers long, long years ago, who is the CEO and chairman of that Tetris company.
And he's living in Big Island, Hawaii, in the United States.
And so I met him a few times in the big island and we watched the stars and you know,
watched the fires and the huge, you know, the big nature. He's living in a big, huge ranch and
so you know, the many horses and sheep and many animals. They have a nice little compound.
It's an amazing, crazy place.
And so we had a discussion like, hey, Gucci.
So he called me Gucci.
Some people call me Miz, and some people call me Gucci,
and whatever.
You can call me any.
So he said, hey, Gucci, why don't you
make a Tetris with the music?
So he played Rez and the Luminance.
And
So he asked me, you know, that kind of things.
So, and yeah, yeah.
But that is luminous, you know?
So he said, yeah, I know, but you know,
the Tetris is, you know, is a very special mechanism.
You know, it has.
Like he's talking about zone experience of Tetris.
You know, have you played Tetris?
Yeah.
I think it's the most famous game, you know, in the world.
And so you know about the zone experience, you know,
you concentrate, you play, you don't think, you know,
just feel, and then you can play without thinking.
So this is a very strong experience and a very special,
unique, the point of the Tetris.
So, and we had a discussion, you know,
the mixing, the music sounds and the visual
and new type of storytelling.
We may make a new type of game, and also with the new technology like VR.
So maybe we can make a totally new thing.
So this is just beginning, the kind of story we have.
Then I came back.
Oh, yeah, I got the keywords from Hank,
like Tetris music, feel good, and a few zen,
and a few in the zone.
That means flow.
So that kind of inspiration is getting bigger in my mind.
And then.
Coming back to Tokyo, and I met Ishihara.
So yeah, and I asked him, OK, please give me
some design and drawing, start to draw some inspirations.
And he gave me some really key great art like this.
This is very special.
The first.
the one of the art.
So you can see the sounds and the visual mixing.
You erase, disappear the line, and you get the sound effects
and some smoke, fire coming, and the moving with the music.
And if you can see this with VR, you can imagine what's
kind of happening.
And he gave me that kind of art.
It's very unique and you know, the feel, some story and emotional.
And like this, you know, feel the music, the feel, the atmosphere.
And this is really trippy, psychedelic, but moving with the music and
the sounds and watching this 3D.
So this is a spacey galaxy.
And then, so we usually we have a pretty long pre-production before we make the game.
Just only, you know, the play in my mind, your mind.
You know, to play and play and play and play,
and you listen to the sound, the sound, the sound of music,
and the music reacts with the visual particles and moving.
Yeah, this is the, you know, we need the imagination.
But we have that kind of a period.
By small people like me and Ishihara,
and sometimes the sound designer,
but we have this pretty long pre-production.
I think we had,
how long was it, two years, a year and a half?
Almost two years pre-production, just before we make the demo, before interactive demo.
So I think this is a very unique style for Enhance. And after all, if we want to move,
if we want to move, you know, okay, let's make the movie first. So this is the first movie we made.
And so we had the concept like this.
Okay, so this is a, okay, let's call the project Zen Tetris.
So this is a code name, but Zen Tetris,
and this is kind of an image.
So the mark made this image.
So I asked Ishihara-san to make this image.
And this, in kind of the movie, I think helped a lot.
getting everybody on the same page.
It also helped when we were pitching it to partners and stuff like that.
But to Mizugu-san's point, you know, we would not have had that
if we hadn't spent two years, if they hadn't spent two years.
I came on in the middle of it in pre-production.
And so that's one of the things that Enhance we really believe in.
And our studio structure allows us to do that.
where we can have just a couple people noodling on something for a couple years,
getting the art really right.
And so this was, yeah, we were going to kind of go this direction for marketing.
The name of the game we thought was going to be Zen Tetris.
We'll talk about that later. But.
One thing just to add before we now go to Isharasan was that the movie was great and everything that
Demis was talking about I was fully on board with, but the one thing that you know you didn't see in
that movie was any new kind of gameplay, right? It was all very stock standard Tetris, which
maybe that's okay. It certainly looked really cool, especially in VR. Maybe that would be enough, but
from very early on there was this question of well is it okay to not have some new kind of gameplay thing
and anyway that's that's kind of foreshadowing so with that why don't we switch over to
Ishihara-san. Okay so then okay I talk with him with Ishihara-kun
So, and me and Mark, so we had a discussion,
okay, let's ask to Ishihara as director.
This is his first director project.
So, yeah, I want to introduce him a little bit.
So he was high school student, high school kids,
when I was made a res.
first grads, 2001.
And after graduating the school, he chased me to Sega.
But I quit Sega, and I moved to Q Entertainment.
But he worked.
In Sega, maybe two, three years.
It was right after he got to Sega, Mizuguchi-san promptly left Sega.
And the whole reason that he came to Sega was to work with Mizuguchi-san.
But in Japan, you can't just pick up and leave, especially in Japan,
after you start working somewhere.
So he was stuck there for at least a couple of years.
Yeah.
I hope he's not a stalker.
But so he did a really good job in a project, Child of Eden.
So he drew the 3,000 art.
That was amazing.
And he also did the Resident Infinite art director.
And then, OK, it's a really good time now.
So Ishihara, go.
So OK, I want to introduce Ishihara-kun.
So after that, I went about preparing for development to start, all by myself, a little bit at a time.
This is a simple specification, but it is information on the layout required to build a VR space.
And what we have here is a fairly simple design document,
but it contains all the layout information necessary for structuring spaces in VR.
The face you see here is the player, and you can see a representation of two manta rays that are swinging before the player's eyes,
and you also have bubbles rising up from below.
This is a representation of a tetromino block.
When you delete a tetromino, beautiful water particles fly into space.
This is a design document for the dolphin stage.
This is the stage where you have windmills floating in the sky.
I had been imagining an experience where you could fly through the sky in VR.
And finally, we have a total of 30 different stages.
And eventually I had design documents for all of the 30-odd stages in the game.
At this time, things were quite busy at Enhance due to the ongoing planning and development of REZ Infinite,
so pre-production of Tetris continued behind the scenes for almost two whole years.
When thinking about the game's design, I was also considering how best to present sound as well.
I have to look at how the sound and visuals come together in the production to allow a sense of depth to the end product, to create an atmosphere for performance.
If you don't have an idea of how visuals and sound will come together in presentation at this point in time,
said presentation will ultimately lack depth, and it prevents a gameplay experience that truly feels great.
And so, as development of REZ Infinite came to a close at the end of 2016, so began the development of Tetris Effect.
We started the project 3 months ago, and created a demo of playing Tetris in the deep sea.
Here is the video.
Our starting point was a prototype that allowed the player to enjoy Tetris in a deep sea environment,
which we made within 3 months of starting the project.
We have a video of just that, so let's take a look.
Since the game is being created for VR, we made absolutely everything in 3D, from the blocks to the background.
The space is filled with schools of fish, manta rays, and whales, all of which swim around the environs.
We also made use of large amounts of particles and 3D sound as well, making it a very rich production overall.
However, we encountered two very big problems.
The first problem was that we couldn't feel the comfort of the most important point in enhancing the game.
Our first problem was that the game simply didn't feel good, which is something we at Enhance value above all else in our creative process.
On the contrary, we felt tired, sleepy, and unable to concentrate.
It was actually worse than just not feeling good. It actively induced feelings of drowsiness, fatigue, and caused people to have difficulty concentrating.
After lunchtime, when I was playing a test game,
I often fell asleep while wearing VR helmets.
There were often times where when sitting down for a test play after lunchtime,
I would wake up to find out I had passed out with the VR helmet on.
Since we were not able to express the feeling of the game,
we felt the need to enhance our Synastasia engine.
The game lacked the presentation and expressiveness necessary to inspire something that feels great in the player,
and I believed the answer was to improve our Synesthesia engine.
The Synesthesia engine is a proprietary system of ours that we use for creating sound and particles, and we used it for REZ Infinite as well.
The Synesthesia engine, by the way, is a proprietary system of ours that we use for creating sound and particles, and we used it for REZ Infinite as well.
The second problem was that the player's mental energy was largely dedicated to manipulating the tetromino blocks, to the point where the player was, when you get down to it, basically not taking in any of the visuals or sound at all.
This is not an overstatement.
There were many people who don't remember
the existence of fish, manta rays,
or even the sound of the song.
And I'm honestly not exaggerating here.
There were many people who could not recall
that there were fish and manta rays swimming around
or that there was even music playing at all.
This experience was nothing like any other Tetris experience.
and people were like, what, there was a space whale?
I totally didn't see the space whale.
So people were not getting it at all unless,
and sometimes it's kind of problem maybe 2.5 that we had,
which is if the manta ray,
people wouldn't notice the manta rays at all,
but if the manta ray dared to,
even for like a split second,
cross over the play field, the matrix,
it was the first thing when people took off the headset
was like,
Get that fucking manta ray out of this fucking game.
That thing is driving me crazy. It's terrible. I want it out.
Destroy them all.
So yeah, so there were a few problems right at the start.
Of the two problems that we had on our plate, I felt like the second one was what needed to be addressed first and foremost, so that's where I started.
I figured this phenomenon must be a result of how, when wearing a VR helmet, the human brain is deluded into believing that the VR space it sees is the real world.
The player seemed to be discarding all information they believed to be of no use to them, instead concentrating entirely on one single point, manipulating tetriminos.
It seemed to me that the player would discard all information they believed to be of no use to them, instead concentrating entirely on one single point, manipulating tetriminos.
I took on several challenges to solve the problem.
And so in an attempt to solve this issue, I tried a number of things.
I had experimented with ideas like making the presentation more over the top, or drastically
changing the angle at which the game is played, but we ended up going back and forth between
prioritizing presentation, which would get in the way of actually playing Tetris, and
prioritizing Tetris gameplay, which would cause the presentation to suffer.
Unable to completely swing either way, I had quite the dilemma on my hands.
I thought on this problem for the next few months, awake or asleep, I had tetrominoes floating around in my head non-stop.
I was confused, and I decided to review Tetris again.
I felt that I might have understood Tetris before.
After much soul-searching, I decided to take another look at how Tetris plays from the very beginning.
I did this because I felt like, at that point, I may have had this idea in my head that I already understood Tetris. ゲームを開始し、一粒のテトリミノが盤面に現れ、回転、移動、設置、消去を繰り返し、クリアするまでの流れを何度もプレイしました。
So I start the game, and a single tetromino appears in the matrix.
I played through the process from start to finish multiple times, rotating, moving, placing, and clearing tetrominos.
At this point, I focused on the emotions of the player as they change throughout the game.
So while doing this, I focused on one particular thing,
the emotions of the player and how they change as the game goes on.
And I was able to find a hint to solve the problem.
In doing so, I came across a certain something that served as a hint in solving my dilemma.
That certain something was the existence of moments when the player, in the midst of doing something that requires intense concentration, is given a moment where they can breathe.
It seemed to me like this play sensation was something similar to how people are when they're driving.
I usually look ahead, but when I pass a traffic jam or turn a corner, I feel a moment of relief.
When driving, you typically focus on a single point directly ahead of you,
but there is also a sensation of relief every time you find your way out of bad traffic or after completing a turn.
At this point, the driver may loosen up and look around,
talk to the passenger, or start playing music.
And at those times, the driver's nerves loosen for an instant,
and they unconsciously take a moment to take in the surrounding scenery,
talk to the person in the passenger seat, or fiddle with the radio.
Of course, this is within the safety driving range.
Are they still obeying the rules of the road, of course? Safety first.
I decided to go over how everything is presented in the game,
this time imagining what kind of experience a person has when they go out for a leisurely Sunday drive.
I took the elements that we use in the game's presentation, light, color, sound, and movement,
and condensed them into those moments where the player's emotional state is such that
they have room to breathe.
We also rearranged most of the composition near the play area,
so that players can feel the direction immediately.
This is an image of the last possible distance for the driver to move his eyes.
Also, we took most of the in-game objects and rethought their placement,
moving them close to the play area so that the player would immediately be able to register
what they're there to convey. The idea is that they would be placed such that you,
the driver in our metaphor, could effortlessly take it all in just by shifting your gaze.
In doing so, we were able to create a sensation that allowed players to both engage with the gameplay of Tetris,
while still unconsciously internalizing the surrounding objects and effects.
I think it's safe to say that this was made possible by grasping the exact point where the player's emotions are in a kind of a state of flux.
One thing to just to add to that from the user tests, we had an early sign that that he had a son was on to something here with his kind of driving model that if stuff was in your immediate kind of peripheral vision, you could still take it in.
Certain levels we had from the start where you were flying sort of into the screen.
In the final game there's like a dolphin level, the windmill level, Da Vinci, those levels.
From very early on, those were the levels where users were registering what was going on in the stage
and also they really liked them.
So those were some of the highest rating games and some of the ones users talked about afterwards
when we talked to them about which ones were their favorites.
So it was like an encouraging early sign that he was onto something.
With the focus issue solved, we then had a definitive link between the visuals and the design.
So we then got to work on focusing on the other problem we had, which was one of creating something that feels good.
So, what am I getting at when I'm talking about something feeling great?
And it's something that we put a lot of emphasis on when creating ResInfinite as well, which is one of Enhance's representative works.
We believe that the connection between gameplay, visuals, and sound is extremely important,
and we are committed to balancing these three elements one-to-one.
We place a great deal of importance on the linking of three elements,
gameplay, visuals, and sound.
And when balancing these elements, we strive to achieve a perfect ratio of one-to-one-to-one.
We try to make it so that no one aspect sticks out.
We're conscious of these three things as one larger whole, and we aim to create games
that bring out a sense of strong exhilaration that can be gained when they are functioning as one.
For Tetris, the gameplay was overwhelmingly strong,
so we needed to increase the visual and sound presence.
For Tetris Effect, the gameplay part was something that stood out as particularly overwhelming,
which made it necessary to raise the level of presence and expressiveness of the visuals and sound to match.
We extended the two functions, physics and morphing, to the CineStudio Engine.
So what I did was we had the Synesthesia engine expanded to include two new functions, physics and morphing.
First, by expanding our physics functionality, we were able to give both particle and object movement a tempo that attributed a sense of strength, and that added the element of reality to our toolbox of expressions.
This made it easier to internalize things such as atmosphere, temperature, how sound expands and feels,
and this made it easier for each and every effect to exude that feel-good sensation that we want.
Next is morphing.
By expanding the morphing function,
a fish is born from a particle and later turns into a manta or a whale.
And next is morphing.
By expanding morphing functionality,
we were then able to create a sense of progression
that emerges when a particle turns into a fish
and then transforms into a manta ray or a whale.
This allowed for emotions to be turned into stories.
And when these pleasant emotions start to pile up and bundle together,
it transforms into what we hope is a very moving experience.
You know, this is a like a chemistry, you know,
that the physics makes you feel like very emotional.
You know, the impact like, oh, oh, oh.
And into the move, moving.
It's not making like narrative, you know, it's like a storytelling.
So we tried to mix both.
Next, we added some new elements that would not have an impact on Tetris' core game design.
And next, we added some new elements that would not have an impact on Tetris' core game design.
First, we put some work into the level design.
In normal Tetris, as the player progresses, the speed gradually increases,
but in this game, the speed increases, slows down, and increases again.
In regular Tetris, it's normal for the speed to gradually get quicker as you progress,
but for Tetris Effect, we made it such that it could, for example, speed up, slow down, and then speed up again.
As we mentioned earlier, we lower the speed when we want the player to focus on the game.
When the game is slow, we increase the speed to get the player to focus on the game.
And this is done for a reason similar to what I mentioned previously.
We slow things down when we want the player to be conscious of the presentation.
And we speed things up so the player can focus on the game when there isn't really as much going on on the presentation side of things.
Of course, we discussed this a lot with the level designers,
and we managed to balance the fun of the game with the quality of the presentation.
And this is of course something the level designer and I discussed at great length,
so that we could strike a balance that both makes the gameplay engaging and serves the presentation.
And yeah, just to add to that, I think this is something that seems simple,
but actually took a long time, really right up until the end of the game to...
to really keep polishing and working on what felt right,
and what felt unfair, and what felt too crazy back and forth.
Along with it, too, there were a lot
of questions of, in a Tetris game that
has a quote, unquote, story mode,
what does failure look like?
Like, what are you risking by having to continue,
or can you continue?
And we'd had it for a really long time.
We did not want to make it something that,
we really wanted to keep it something
that everybody could enjoy.
So we had it where you could just continue
and your score would reset,
but the amount of lines you cleared stayed the same.
And it just felt like there were no consequences at all.
In fact, sometimes people would just.
get to a new stage and just go game over so they could kind of start fresh
because they just didn't care about the score. And so
that was one of the things that that came on at the end is this and also the
next slide is how do we divide up the game? How do we
balance the difficulty to make it where you know this is not
going to be a 40-hour game whatever we do but
how do we make it where it's a
It's a satisfying journey, so to speak, and you care when you get the game over screen,
and you also care when you're able to clear it without having to continue.
And so lastly, Tetris Effect is a game that takes a few hours to finish.
When driving, we used the concept of 7 areas as if we were driving in a parking area,
so that we could stop the game whenever we were tired.
But to again return things to my driving analogy,
we implemented this concept of the game being split into 7 areas,
along the lines of how you'll find rest stops along a highway.
This lets the player step back and take a break from the game whenever they feel tired.
This solved the player's fatigue and sleepiness.
Doing this got rid of the problems we had encountered with players getting fatigued or drowsy.
And so all of that is how we fused Tetris and a VR presentation into this one cohesive whole,
leading to the creation of what we hope you'll agree is a great feeling Tetris experience that
the first of its kind. So yeah, so the game was taking shape.
We were starting to feel pretty good about it overall.
We'd ask people playing the game.
They were starting to feel pretty good about it overall.
We were working really closely with our licensor
with the Tetris company.
They had good feedback.
They were helping us refine a lot of the particulars,
a lot of feedback in terms of this color on that color
is hard to see when this happens,
and that sort of thing.
They were really good about that sort of stuff.
But also, the very particular bits of the controls,
you would think.
Tetris is just Tetris.
You don't need to work at really fine-tuning those controls,
but actually you do.
That's something that took the whole length of the project.
But yeah, overall, they were also
really happy with how the game was shaping up.
So things were going great.
But there was still that concern from earlier on.
So it wasn't a new concern.
I had that little inner voice saying that the game still
needed some kind of original gameplay hook.
So.
Here we were reinventing how Tetris looked, how it sounded,
most of all how it felt. But what about how it plays?
Can't we do something to innovate in terms of gameplay,
you know, something that could add or even multiply
everything else that we're doing?
I just really felt the gameplay third of that graphics sound
gameplay was lacking a little bit.
And it wasn't just me.
When I would talk to other people about the game, explain
the game, they were into it.
You could tell they were interested and excited,
especially when they would play it.
But they were also kind of leaning in a little bit, kind
of, it seemed like, waiting for one more thing.
It's like, yeah, OK, yeah, and?
And then there was not that one other thing.
So we would talk about this every so often throughout the whole project.
It would kind of come up to the point it became kind of a running thing,
which is like, and what about that gameplay thing?
Like, what are we doing for that?
And Miz and Ishara-san were both, they did both generally agree.
that yeah, it would be really awesome to have some kind of new gameplay feature that fit the game and did everything we were hoping for.
But also it was kind of tempered with...
some concerns that maybe it wasn't strictly necessary.
You know, maybe that could be left to some of the other modes.
Maybe this game, the main mode stays this more pure Tetris experience
because, you know, it could in fact become a bad thing.
If we didn't hit it just right, it could get in the way.
It could screw up what people what we know people already love about Tetris.
And I think Ishihara-san had a really good point, which was there have been so many Tetris games over the years, you know, hundreds.
And how many new gameplay mechanics can you think of in that time that have stood the test of time, you know, that you can even remember?
Besides a few quality of life things like the preview piece and the next window and some of those kind of peripheral things,
but real gameplay features, and to be honest, none of us could think of any really,
that didn't come off as gimmicky or kind of interesting, but ultimately very forgettable.
And maybe we wouldn't come up with anything, but I did feel really strongly that we had to at least try.
At first, we tried to incorporate a rescue system such as slowing down the fall speed of the tetromino,
slowing down the time, and eliminating all the tetromino on the board at once,
but none of them matched the game design because they lacked the tension required for Tetris play.
At the beginning, we had tried implementing systems that were essentially get-out-of-jail-free cards.
You could do things like slow down the speed at which tetrominoes fall,
turn back time, or erase all the tetrominoes in the matrix.
But they didn't match well with the game design for one crucial reason.
They reduced the sense of nervous tension that is necessary to make Tetris fun.
And as that was going on, Nishimura-san, the main programmer on the team, came to us with an idea.
He said, wouldn't it be neat if the tetrominoes didn't disappear?
This is an idea that allows us to erase lines such as 8 and 16, which were previously only 4-digit.
His idea was, if you had a fixed period of time during which tetrominoes would accumulate
instead of disappearing when they form a line,
it would be possible to jump right past the four line clears that Tetris players have known up to this point,
allowing for players to clear eight or even sixteen lines at once.
The main programmer was a great programmer who had been in charge of the Tetris gameplay for two years.
He suggested that we try it out as a team.
And this main programmer had been in charge of the actual Tetris gameplay part of the game for all two years of its development.
And he's absolutely incredible at his craft.
So we decided that if this is something that he thought would work, then we should just go ahead and give it a shot.
And this here is what he made. Let's take a look.
This experience was a great fit for the game design of Tetris, and it created a wonderful sense of cohesion.
And the sensation it created was something that did a truly amazing job of expressing what it means to be in the Zone.
We decided to call this experience the Zone System, and it became a symbol of this game.
We called it the Zone System and it became an experience that is symbolic of the title as a whole.
Great. So awesome. We all agreed. We were all fully on board with the zone system.
It was basically had everything we were looking for. It was significant, but at the same time it didn't get in the way of the more pure Tetris gameplay.
It had benefits for beginner players and for experienced players. It looked cool. It fit the vibe of the game. Everything.
So it was awesome. We were feeling pretty awesome.
But again, there was something else nagging.
The little voice again was talking about the online
multiplayer mode that we had planned.
So from the very start of the game, we'd been thinking, OK,
we have to have some kind of
online is a Tetris game.
We have to have some kind of online multiplayer, probably
battle mode, right?
So we didn't have a great idea for it as the project started,
though, so we thought, OK, well, let's get into the
project, and it will kind of naturally come out of making
the game.
But about a year in, we still didn't really have that idea.
And we put out a call to the team,
like, okay, we really now have to start working on that,
so let's get all the ideas that you guys have.
Ideally, something that breaks the mold.
You know, we wanted something.
different, but also that still fit the mood of the game,
which is not a really easy task when the game is still
called Zen Tetris and you're trying to come up
with a battle mode.
So all that really came back after asking was a pretty
straightforward, fairly standard one-on-one battle
mode.
So the team just really didn't seem into it.
Like, they just weren't inspired.
And we didn't have, you know, like a Tetris 99 grade awesome
idea, which I think is brilliant for multiplayer.
And so it felt like, it really started feeling like we were
going to make this online battle mode because we had to
make an online battle mode.
But what if we didn't have to make an online battle mode?
So something occurred to me while I was explaining all
this to a friend.
and saying, well, we have an online battle mode
because we have to have an online battle mode.
After saying that a bunch of times,
one time it finally was like, wait a second, maybe we don't.
And I know some people probably here are saying,
yes, yes, you do, you really should have,
you guys are idiots.
But that became my pitch to Miz and Isha Hasan,
what if instead of doing that thing that
other games have done that you can get online and do for free right now in a pretty good, robust,
official version of with like Tetris Friends and that sort of thing. What if we took that money
and time and resources and instead doubled down on what was cool and unique and special about
our game specifically? You know, what would that look like? So...
Around this time, I was using a meditation app called Headspace.
It's pretty popular.
Some of you might have heard of it.
If you haven't, how that app is laid out is it's an app for meditating, and they
basically divide up and tailor these guided audio meditations to how you're
feeling or how you want to feel.
So if you can't sleep or you want to sleep, if you're anxious, if you want to get energized, etc.,
there's separate places to go for meditations that'll address each one of those.
And with Tetris Effect, we were already getting this feedback from people who were playing it
that they were responding basically the way that we were after, kind of emotionally.
You know, oh, it's soothing.
Or, oh, it was really intense.
Or certain levels just make them smile and laugh.
So again, what if we took our battle mode resources instead
and put them in a new mode designed to provoke more
of those kind of feelings?
And so that's where we came up with what's now effect modes.
These are different categories for a bunch of different game
modes that you could choose for when you wanted to relax,
or you wanted to really have a challenge.
or if you want to just play some old school classic Tetris,
there's a place to go for that.
So it wouldn't be a proper GDC speech
without showing you some stuff that I think
got left on the cutting room floor.
So when we set about to design those new modes,
we had certain ones that we knew would go in,
marathon, kind of the mainstay standby Tetris modes.
But as far as the new modes, again,
we threw it out to the team, everybody.
come up with your best, craziest, coolest, most fun
ideas that fit the theme, and let's talk about them.
And if it sounds good, let's prototype it.
And if it's fun, let's make it.
So other stuff that we ended up not going with.
So we always wanted a kind of cooperative online content.
We wanted people to still feel connected to each other
in with the theme of the game and not in a one-on-one kind
of battle scenario, but hey, we're all kind of in this
together working towards some kind of communal goal.
So what we ended up going with was a weekly ritual, which is
where players amass points in designated modes towards a
communal goal.
And if they reach that goal, they get a reward.
I'm kind of speeding up now because we do want to get a
couple questions in for QA.
So I'll kind of.
speed through the rest of this.
But our original idea was that those communal cleared Tetris
pieces were all going to gather into a sculpture.
And if you completed the sculpture,
then it would animate in some weird, hopefully fun,
surprising way.
The problem with this was we were going to run this weekly,
and we just couldn't think of 52 good things that
made sense in the game.
It's kind of like, wait, what's going on again now?
What game are we making?
Um, but it was kind of funny and sadly though, we had to kill our, our, our
dancing astronaut, um, sorry, dancing astronaut, um, game name.
Okay.
This part I'm going to really speed through.
The game was called Zen Tetris, uh, since forever.
We liked it.
It was different from other Tetris games.
Here's some of the logos.
But as you see, once we started making the logo,
it was like, wait a second.
Zen does mean relaxation,
but it also means kind of simple and austere
to a lot of people.
And our game is giant space whales
made out of particles exploding,
literally, into rainbows on the beat.
Like, is this the logo to that game?
I don't think so.
So yeah, other logo treatments.
It wasn't good.
And in Japanese, Zen, while it would have worked,
kind of has this old feeling to it as well, which
was what we were going for.
This, at least, we did stumble on
while we were doing this kind of thing,
because we ended up using this for the subtitle, which
was perfect for Tetris Effect.
But the point of this part is that,
for a different conversation in the marketing conversation
that I was having with another guy at Enhance, Yamada-san.
about the marketing of the game, we kept going back to this Tetris effect.
So the marketing for Zen Tetris was going to use the Tetris effect
because it was a very positive thing that the game had.
You know, the Tetris effect, if you don't know Tetris gets in your brain
and you can't you can't get rid of it.
And it actually has all these health benefits that have been scientifically
proven severe.
It can lessen the severity of PTSD, even one of the most recent studies.
But distract from cravings, increase the size of parts of the brain, et cetera.
We kept coming back to that Tetris effect.
Let's make a documentary about the Tetris effect.
Let's have an ad where it's like, ask your doctor if the
Tetris effect is right for you, like that kind of thing.
And Yamada-san is just like, wait, why aren't we calling
the game Tetris effect?
We keep talking about Tetris effect.
And it was kind of like, now it's like, duh, yeah, of course.
But we had been thinking of it for so long as Zen Tetris.
Also, we thought there might be legal reasons why we
couldn't do that.
But Miz got it immediately.
He loved it.
Shahar loved it.
Tetris Company was fully behind it.
So we changed that at the very last second and got a logo
that was much closer to kind of what we were going for.
So, oh boy, real quick, final thoughts.
So my final thoughts are basically listen to your inner voice by giving an outer voice.
So talk things over with the team if you're hearing something.
There's two voices in my experience, inner voices.
One is this intuitive, really smart, positive thing that knows better what's going on than you do.
The other is, you know, just doubt and fear and doubting everything.
And so my method of separating those two things is to talk it out with other people.
And sometimes, like I gave the example of the name, they'll have better ideas.
Other times, just in explaining it to somebody, you end up thinking of something.
And so definitely listen to that inner voice, but to kind of separate it, try talking it over with somebody else.
And Isha Hasan.
To close things out, on the VR side of things, creating a fusion of Tetris and VR required a great deal of work on the development side to fine-tune the presentation and a whole lot of compromise as well. The whole thing was quite the ordeal.
However, after finishing the game, I felt that it was a plus, not a minus.
This time, however, having finished making it, I feel like those difficulties were not minuses, but pluses.
Even in the existing 2D-based games,
we have found points that invite you to VR production and VR space,
and by creating such scenes in a new way,
I think we have hidden the possibility of changing them to attractive VR content.
I believe that even existing games built on 2D foundations have the potential to be transformed
into appealing VR content so long as you can find something that can be used to connect
it with a VR presentation or place it in a VR space.
Or if you have no entry point that seems to exist already, you can create one from scratch.
VR is capable of inspiring a whole new dimension of emotions that can't be experienced in 2D.
I feel like the game industry is still sorely lacking in VR titles.
And at the moment, I feel like the game industry is still sorely lacking in VR titles.
I would be very happy if what I shared today turned out to be a little bit of good know-how for all of you out there. Thank you very much.
It would be great if some of what I've shared today turned out to be a little bit of good know-how for all of you out there. Thank you very much.
Yeah, thank you very much.
This is a pretty long journey for us.
And yeah, so we had many things.
You know, we started from kind of a Zen feel,
feel good game, but we decided to mix the new elements.
And yeah, this is all the time, you know,
the game production is like that, isn't it?
Yeah.
So, and we learned a lot, you know, we tried to mix, I think the two elements, I'm talking about
the zone, you know, so we wanted to make a very relaxing fugal game and the other hand, you know,
it's kind of like excitement, you know, we needed to combine both.
And so I learned about the zone mechanism.
So zone mechanism, you are in a zone when you are in a zone.
So you are kind of the between relax and excitement.
So it's a very small, tiny zone.
But yeah, we learned a lot about that.
Oh wow, so we can make that kind of a feel,
the using the power of the visual and sounds,
and also, you know, tattoo skin mechanism.
So, yeah, I can say to you, you know,
we can have much more space to explore.
Using the technology, even if thinking about the VR, AR, MR, XR technology, this is a 3D experience, experiential we can create.
So this is a new era.
But, you know, we have a bunch of space, this is white snow, and this is a big journey and explore.
But, we need to go there.
you know, to make the new kind of experience.
So game has a 50 years history,
and the movie has a 130 years history,
but the first people, you know,
tried to make a new something.
So we are facing to the next era,
I mean, experiential era.
So, yeah, it's a really exciting thing.
And also I want to thank to my team, Monsters and Resonare.
So that was a really good team, you know.
Yeah, we had a long history.
You know, we made Resonate Infinite
and that kind of experience,
we can go, we could go to the next step.
And of course we want to go to the next step.
That's right.
The future.
From here.
Yeah, and yes, I want to thank to Tetris company. Yeah, so we want to prove, you know, even if the
old famous IP like Tetris, it's like a, you know, complete game, nothing add. But is it true?
You know, we wanted to prove that, you know, if we can.
Yeah.
Is it true that you can't add anything to it's already perfect?
There's nothing more that can really be done with it.
And I think hopefully us and also now Tetris 99 have proved like, yeah, it's
it's just a matter of imagination.
That's totally a new experience.
You know, we are making the new experience, right?
We are experienced designer, isn't it?
Yeah.
Thank you very much.