Good afternoon, everybody.
It's a great pleasure for me to introduce our speaker
for this afternoon's session, Jonathan Perry.
When he sent this proposal to the advisory board,
I thought, now I can finally find out
why I'm in love with Leilana.
So my goal for this entire presentation
is to figure out how he made me fall in love
with his characters and really care about them
and worry about them.
I've seen the presentation, and it's going to be fantastic.
This is his first presentation and his first one at GDC, of course, so I ask everyone to be really gentle and to give him amazingly high scores so that he comes back and does this again, because I think this is going to be a real treat.
All right, Jonathan, knock him dead. Good luck.
Thanks a lot.
Good afternoon everyone, thanks a lot for coming. So just a few reminders before I get started,
please if you could, silence your cell phones and keep an eye out for the email that they send to
give me a review. It'll probably end up in your spam folder so definitely check that out.
So let's get started.
My name's Jonathan Perry.
I'm a lead cinematic designer, or a cinematic lead at Bioware.
In my time at Bioware, I've worked on Mass Effect 1 and 2.
I've worked on all the Dragon Age titles as well,
including a lot of additional Dragon Age DLC.
So this talk is called Contrastive Juxtaposition.
And contrastive juxtaposition is really just a fancy term
for putting two things that are completely
different right next to each other
to create a dramatic effect.
And it's an effect that we use in our scenes
to create these.
powerful and emotional moments in our games. It involves a dramatic reversal or a rapid shift in the audio narrative or visual polarities.
So to give you an example of what I'm talking about,
I'd like to show you a scene from the very beginning of Mass Effect 2. And to set the scene,
the Normandy is under attack from a collector ship.
Most of the crew is either dead or has escaped and Joker is the only one left on board and Shepard's trying to get him
into an escape pod.
So, this scene was a really powerful and emotional moment for me in the game.
And part of it was because I had just lost a character that I had spent 40 or more hours
with in the previous game, saving the galaxy.
But it was also the manipulation of contrast and context in the scene that really made
it hit home for me.
The quick shift from being alive to dead was also supported by a dramatic shift in the
audio and the visuals as well.
So we'll talk about creating the timing and the content
for these types of moments.
We'll also take a closer look at contrast and context
and how they can be used as creative tools
throughout the development process
to make your scenes better.
So I'll start by talking about the role of story and cinematics
at BioWare, so a bit about the people
and the processes involved.
Then I'll talk about contrast and context,
why they're important and how they can be used to impact
the player experience.
From there, I'll discuss how contrast
can be used to create strong story themes
in a narrative possibility space,
how content teams can use contrast
to create content that supports those story themes,
and how context can be used to create a more meaningful
experience for the player.
So I'll be, spoiler alert, I'll be using a lot of great examples from Dragon Age and
Mass Effect, but I will be talking about Mass Effect 3 a little bit.
I've tried to keep this as spoiler light as possible.
If you've played the demo or you've seen the trailers, you've already seen a lot of what
I'm going to show.
But if you're one of those people who doesn't want to hear anything, doesn't want to see
anything, I'll give you a heads up before I spoil any plots for you.
Consider yourselves warned.
So as most of you already know, story is a huge part of Bioware games.
Our goal is to create the best story-driven and emotionally engaging games in the world.
And to that end, we have a lot of storytellers.
So if you look at the makeup of some of our design teams on Dragon Age 2 or Mass Effect
3, you see we've got a lot of combat designers, systems designers, but about half the team
is made up of storytellers.
So writers, editors, cinematic designers.
And when I talk about cinematics, I'm not just talking about the pre-rendered scenes
that you see in the game.
We do those too, but every single line of cutscene is a cinematic as well.
And BioWare is a bit different from most studios in that we have two cinematic teams.
We have cinematic animators and cinematic designers.
So the cinematic animation team is the one that most studios have or are familiar with.
They create the biggest and most complex moments in the game.
So scenes like the dragon fights in Dragon Age, the epic space battles in Mass Effect 3.
They also do a lot of the complex character interactions
or introductions to your possible companion characters,
as well as a lot of the highly choreographed combat scenes,
ambient kill scenes, those types of moments in the game.
Now, cinematic designers, on the other hand,
work on the interactive moments in the game,
the interactive conversations and cut scenes.
And we create these using a massive library of animations.
We also work very closely with the writers
throughout the development process
to develop the narrative flow of the game.
And we design the tools for generating and iterating
on massive amounts of high quality interactive content
very quickly.
So between the two teams, we end up
creating about 30 hours of cinematic content
for an average BioWare game.
And we try to use all these principles
I'll be talking about throughout the development process
on all of this content.
So here's a very basic model of how we create the story
in the cinematics for our game.
So the writers create the story.
The content teams then create the various assets
that we need to tell that story.
And then the cinematic teams put it all together
to create the cinematic experience.
So we'll refer back to this model a bit
as we go through the presentation.
But first, I want to take a closer look
at contrast and context, how they work,
why they're important, and how they're used to create meaning
and shape the player experience.
So I think the picture on the right is one of my favorite pieces of concept art from
the Dragon Age franchise.
And it's a great example of contrast.
Because in the same image you see light and dark, life and death, gentleness and brutality.
And it's beautiful, but it's sick.
And I love it.
It's great.
It feels important.
It feels meaningful.
There's a story here.
But why is it that this contrast gets our attention?
Because like it or not, from an evolutionary point of view, we are hardwired to notice contrast or change in our environment.
It's a survival instinct, really.
Seeing the orange line in the green field, or hearing the twigs snap in the dead of night,
Or the smell of smoke in the air can alert you to danger in the environment, and it can
often mean the difference between life and death noticing this contrast.
It's a good thing.
It's a built-in Spidey sense, and we use this attention to contrast all the time for survival.
But we have a hard time not noticing contrast, so it's great to use for advertising your
product, getting it to stand up off the shelf, getting somebody to pick it up and play it.
But in print media, this contrast occurs all at once, but when somebody's picked up the
game or is watching the movie, the rules of contrast change.
In a narrative, audiences like to see characters undergo transformative change or have a change
on the world around them over the course of the narrative.
We love seeing characters get thrown into these unfamiliar situations, struggle to adapt
and survive, and learn something in the process.
Now when talking about contrast or change in a narrative, I like to think of it in terms
of polarity.
It's still about the difference between two things, but it takes that difference and applies
it to a two-dimensional coordinate system.
So we have positive and negative polarities, and these could be anything.
Good versus evil is one we're all familiar with.
Light side versus dark side is one of my favorites.
But they don't have to fit the pattern of good and bad, or good and evil.
They just have to be different.
So up versus down, left versus right.
These would all work too.
Now visualizing contrast with a polarized system, it makes it easier to see the movement
over time.
Polarity creates conflict or struggle between two opposing forces, and it allows us to see
not just that a character is changing, but that they're changing in a direction.
So two are away from a certain state of being over the course of the narrative.
And if we want to track this, we can kind of change our model a little bit and track
this shifting between polarities over time.
So as players in a game, we like to be the ones that are driving that change in our character
or the world around us.
We want to choose how to play, what side to align ourselves with, who lives and who dies.
So we want to be the one that's driving that change.
So polarities or contrast is an important part of all narratives because it allows us
to create these characters with different personalities, beliefs, and values.
And it's that difference between these characters that creates conflict.
And that conflict motivates a need for change or action.
So everyone's familiar with this scene if you've played Mass Effect 1, but this struggle
between polar opposite forces creates suspense and drama.
We all want to know who's going to win, who's going to live, who's going to die, what happens
next.
So now let's take a closer look at context.
Now when somebody asks you what a word means, the usual response is, well, what's the context,
meaning what's around it?
Because what's around something can have a significant meaning on that experience or
on that thing, or an influence on that meaning.
So, the picture here on the right is an example of the Kuleshov effect.
And in this experiment, the Russian filmmaker, Lev Kuleshov, created a montage.
First, he showed a bowl of soup.
Then he cut to a reaction of a man's face.
He showed a child in a coffin.
And showed the man's face.
They showed a woman laying seductively on the couch and then he cut back to the man's face.
Now the audience who watched this experiment or this piece of film were asked to comment on the actor's performance.
And they loved it. They raved about it.
What a brilliant performance. Subtly magnificent.
You could see the hunger when he saw that bowl of soup.
Oh, his sadness, that sadness when he saw that child in the coffin.
And oh, that lust in his eyes when he saw that woman.
But really, it was the same expressionless face, the guy, every single time.
So this just shows us that the audience perception of the actor's performance
and what it meant was heavily influenced by the surrounding content.
So the Kuleshov experiment demonstrated that the context of an experience
can often hold more meaning than the content of an experience.
So it was a bit hard to see in the previous example,
so I'd like to show you a more modern example of this effect
as demonstrated by Alfred Hitchcock.
Now the third way is what one might call pure cinematics,
the assembly of film,
and how it can be changed to create a different idea.
Now have a close-up.
Then we'll share one of...
Let's assume he saw a woman holding a baby in her arms.
Now we cut back to his reaction to what he sees, and he smiles.
Now what is he as a character? He's a kind woman, he's sympathetic.
Now, let's take the middle piece of film away, the woman with the child,
but leave his two pieces of film as they were.
Now we'll put it...
a piece of film of a girl in a bikini.
He looks, girl in a bikini, he smiles.
What is he laughing at? A dirty old man.
He's no longer the benign gentleman who loves babies.
That's what's different. That's what's wrong.
Well, it seems like that was a little out of sync,
but you get the idea.
By changing one image in a sequence of shots,
you can change the meaning of that entire sequence.
In this case, he loves babies, or he's a dirty old man.
So we do this a lot in Bioware games,
and the image or the sequence that we kind of swap out
is influenced by your previous decisions,
creating a more meaningful and personal experience
for the player.
So we'll talk about some additional forms of context
in a bit, but the important thing to keep in mind here
is that we can manipulate the order.
or context of events to enhance meaning or create meaning that would not have been there
otherwise.
So now that we've covered some of the basics of contrast and context, I'd like to take
a look at how we can apply these ideas to improve our story and content in our games.
So contrast and context are used as creative tools when developing a strong narrative theme
for your game and to start to fill out that world with characters and missions that the
player can explore through choice.
So the first thing we try to do when working on a new game is to identify the theme of
the game.
So if your game is more than just a bunch of mechanics holding hands, what do you want
it to mean?
If your game has a story, what is the story you want to tell?
So this can be hard, but it's important to establish these themes very early because
they can inform design further down the line.
And this is hard.
The way I like to think of it at first is versus.
So something versus something.
Someone versus something.
In the case of Dragon Age, it would be Grey Wardens versus the Darkspawn.
Or in Mass Effect, Reapers versus humanity.
So once you've established the major players, think about what each side represents.
So if your game is about a conflict between two forces, what is it they're in disagreement
over?
What beliefs, ideals, or background does each side represent?
And these can be deeper or more abstract themes that don't necessarily have to fit into the
pattern of good versus evil, right versus wrong.
So for example, in Mass Effect 3...
Humanity represents innocence, free will, and a force of chaos in the world, whereas
the Reapers represent authority, determinism, and wanting to restore order.
And we started to explore these themes with content very early in the game, starting with
the first shot in Mass Effect 3, so let's take a look.
So we start with this boy playing with this toy ship, but it's more than that.
This is the only child we've ever seen in the Mass Effect universe.
He stands out by contrast, and that's a good thing.
He seems important, because we want this boy to represent something.
We want him to represent humanity.
He's young and innocent.
He's got his whole life ahead of him to make decisions, make choices, to shape his own
destiny.
And then we cut to Shepard watching.
So this is really similar to the Hitchcock clip
that we watched earlier.
We see a boy playing.
We cut to Shepard and she smiles.
So what does that say about her as a character?
It says that she loves humanity and she wants to protect it.
And we see this as we kind of go through
the opening of the game, the Reapers attack.
She tries to coax this boy out of a vent.
And then later she watches him board this shuttle
to get out of the city.
And by this point, you realize that this boy
represents everything that you're fighting for.
Everything you're gonna spend
the rest of the game fighting for.
So we explore similar themes in Dragon Age 2.
Themes like free will versus fate,
being an individual versus being part of a larger community,
and the balance between freedom and security.
So early on, look at your game,
think about what are the different sides,
what do they represent,
when establishing the major conflicts
and story themes of your game.
So we also use contrast and context
when starting to create the world
and flesh out the world of our games.
And when doing this, it's important to think of contrast or polarity as a meta pattern.
It exists on all these different levels in your game.
So think of all these levels when trying to build out your IP or build out your story.
And even if conflicts or struggles on certain levels aren't necessarily central to your game,
they can be really useful for creating context, explaining why things are the way they are,
why people behave the way they do.
And so going through this, you could have polarized states of reality.
In Mass Effect 3, Shepard's fighting a war against the Reapers in reality, but also explores
the world of her subconscious through her dreams.
At a galaxy level, the entire galaxy is engaged in a war with the Reapers, but within that
galaxy we have worlds and polarized conflicts between these worlds.
For example, between the Krogans and the Solarians.
Within every world, you have conflict between groups.
For example, the Mages versus the Templars in Dragon Age 2.
And within every group you have polarization within these smaller groups.
For example, the mages in Dragon Age 2 represent a larger group, but within that group you've
got circle mages, blood mages, apostate mages, all kind of doing their own thing, all having
their own goals and agendas.
There's also individuals that compose every group and they represent various polarities.
In our game, every companion character stands for or against something.
So there's different personalities represented in clashes and goals, beliefs, and character,
and inevitable. And this makes for some really great content. The banter between the different
character combinations in Dragon Age is hilarious because it draws so heavily on this contrastive
juxtaposition of characters at odds with each other for comedic effect.
There's also conflict within every individual.
So Fenris, for example, hates mages,
but he also hates slavery.
So what do you do when you see a bunch of mages being enslaved?
So within an individual, there can be a struggle between
revenge and forgiveness, love and hate,
trust and suspicion.
So think of all these different things.
This is also, there's polarities within the player.
Who does support or oppose?
Who lives and dies?
Are you going to play Paragon, or are you
going to play Renegade?
So we let the player influence the world around him
through these choices.
And as much as possible, we want these choices to be meaningful and to have a real impact
on the world or the people around you.
In previous Mass Effect games, the player usually had these paragon, neutral, or renegade
options in any situation.
We love giving players choices, but this neutral response is essentially the meh of the conversation
wheel.
It's, I don't care, what do you guys think?
I don't know, what do you want to do?
So it didn't do anything to shift the player towards one side of a polarized conflict or
the other.
It was more in the middle.
So in Mass Effect 3, one thing you'll notice that's different is in most cases this middle
option is gone.
In this game, there's a lot at stake, there's a lot of really big decisions to make, a lot
of really huge consequences.
So we're not just going to let you sit on the fence and let somebody else figure it
out for you.
And the interesting thing is that even with this middle option removed, it still feels
more like a role-playing game.
Choices are harder and have real consequence.
The choices are tough.
So while the player has control over the polar alignment of their own character,
it's interesting to see the effects that player's choice and action can have on the companion characters in the game.
So every one of these characters has a unique collection of attributes, behaviors, and values that define them as a character.
And while these don't change much over the course of time,
the choices you make as a player influence your relationship with these various characters.
In Dragon Age Origins, for example, your followers had very clear opinions on what was wrong
or right, and these didn't really change much over the course of the narrative.
When you were making a major decision, they'd let you know how they felt about it, what
they thought you should do, and based on how you responded, you would either get approval
or disapproval points from each follower.
High approval points improved the follower's combat performance in the game, would open
up the door to a possible romantic relationship with some characters, and people with a low
approval rating might leave your party.
So we use, uh, Mike this is for you buddy, uh, the player's relationship with Leleana.
My, my relationship with Leleana is a great example of how different things could be and
a great example of contrastive juxtaposition in the narrative.
So Lele and I, Leleana and I, we were in love.
Um, I gave her all these gifts, I had high approval rating through the roof, and I was
totally romancing her.
Uh, but.
One decision I made in the Temple of Sacred Ashes,
she really disagreed with so strongly that she came at me
and in a fight to the death, I had to kill her.
And this is great contrast of juxtaposition.
She went from my friend to my enemy,
and alive to dead in this that moment in the player of,
oh my God, what have I done?
I reloaded.
So.
back to the approval system as this polarized system, overall it was very clear and it worked
very well. So, disapproval is bad, approval is good, the system worked well, it was clear
and players understood it.
Some players felt like the system kind of limited the choices they could make.
Everybody wanted high approval ratings from their followers, so
sometimes they felt like they couldn't choose what they wanted to, they had to choose what the
followers that were with them wanted,
or that they could only take along the followers on the quest
that would agree with whatever decisions they wanted to play, the style they wanted to play in.
So we wanted players to feel free to make their own choices, so we tried to tweak this a little bit in Dragon Age 2.
So we created this friendship and rivalry system,
and the idea was similar.
Players or followers would move towards one side
or the other of this scale,
based on whether they agreed with your actions or not.
The difference here was that rivalry wasn't bad.
Achieving a high rivalry value with your follower character
triggered this dramatic conversation
where you'd hash out your differences,
agree to disagree, I don't like what you're doing
but I respect you type of thing,
and it would open up those combat perks,
open up the door to these romantic relationships.
your relationship with this player or character would improve as a result of this big argument.
So, high friendship and high rivalry were both good,
but players were used to the old system from Dragon Age Origins
and didn't really understand their rivalry wasn't bad.
And looking back at it, it's easy to understand why.
Because we presented it as this polarized system, except in this case...
Friendship and rivalry were both good, and OK, it's bad to be in the middle, but the
color scale on that, it kind of looks like the old Paragon Renegade system, and so we
can see how players got confused.
So the important thing here is when creating these polarized systems, or things that look
like polarized systems, make it clear to your player what the different sides are, what
they do, especially if the systems change from a previous iteration.
So we also use contrast when designing the missions or the quests in our games.
Now once you know the plot of a mission, or this could be applied to a conversation, an
act, the entire game, a great exercise is to map out the narrative beats.
So you can see these little ticks on the bottom of this image.
So pick one of your polarities and think about what side you want the player to be exposed
to at any point throughout the mission of the game, at each of these narrative beats.
So whether it's how you want them to feel, or what side of a conflict you want them to
identify with or to expose them to.
And then we can make sure we expose players to both sides of a polarized conflict before
letting them choose which side to align themselves with.
And we've been trying to get away from these good versus evil type of choices.
Really we want to give you a hard choice.
Shades of grey.
We want to make you pick between shades of grey.
There is no right or wrong, but you've got to choose anyway.
So this exercise is great for making sure that each of these different sides of a polarized
conflict gets the proper exposure.
And this back and forth between players also does a great job of keeping players engaged.
Alright, so this is the part if you want to close your ears or eyes, uh, don't listen
to this if you don't want to spoil for it.
It's really not that bad.
But, uh, so we're going to take a look at a mission from the middle of Mass Effect 3.
Now, if you've played the demo, uh, you'll know that, uh, one of the missions involved
helping Morden escort this female Krogan out of a Solarian facility because she represents
a possible cure for the genophage, which has been a huge issue since the beginning of Mass
Effect 1.
So in this later mission, you have to help Morden get this female Krogan to the Shroud
facility on Tachanka to release this cure into the atmosphere, curing the genophage
so that the Krogan will join you in the war against the Reapers.
But before setting off on this mission, you get a secret message.
letting you know that there's a secret way to sabotage this cure
in such a way that the Krogan will never know.
So the Krogan will think you helped him out, they'll help you in the war,
but the genophage will still be in place.
At this point, you don't have to decide, but you know you have two options.
You can sabotage the cure or assist the Krogans.
So to make it easy to chart this out over our narrative map,
we can put the action events that support sabotaging the cure on top,
and the events that support assisting the group on the bottom,
or on the top.
uh... these roughly correspond to uh... paragon a renegade options that will
track it like that
So, on the way, this Krogan leader who's kind of helping you out, he's all about getting
revenge on the Salarians. After today, the Krogan superiority will be obvious to everyone.
So he's already planning his revenge. You meet up with a bunch of other Krogans and
they start fighting amongst themselves, even though they should be working together towards
this common goal. You see how vicious and cruel these Krogans are to each other. So
at this point the player is thinking, maybe sabotaging the cure isn't such a bad idea.
But then this female Krogan comes out, she gets them to stop fighting.
The groups unite, you load up, you roll out, the music is inspiring, let's do this thing, right?
On the way there, she's telling Reeve,
we need a leader who's not focused on war.
We've spread war across the galaxy before, and the genophage was the result, so
we need to learn from the mistakes of our ancestors, or be doomed to repeat them.
Okay, awesome! Maybe all these Krogan need is a strong female Krogan, uh, keep them in line, keep them in order, unite them as a group.
So, I could see how this could work, maybe, uh, maybe helping them out's not such a bad idea after all.
But Reeve's not buying it, so he's still determined to get revenge.
You step outside and look around you and you see how destroyed the world is,
how the Krogans grew tired of a peaceful life and started nuclear wars with each other,
destroying their world long before the Solarians implemented the Genophage.
Uh, okay, hmm.
But then we also show the player that Krogan's were once a peaceful and advanced society.
They weren't always creatures of war.
And you can see this in their architecture.
And their art.
So there's a sense of wonder here, a sense of history, and you can imagine how things
were long ago and might be again.
So I'm going to stop spoiling this for you, but there's a lot more I won't spoil.
But you can see how we expose the player to both sides of a polarized issue before making
them choose.
how to align themselves. And these are tough choices.
Eventually you've got to make a decision. You've seen how vengeful and vicious these
Krogan can be, how they wage wars against each other, destroy their own world, but you've
also seen how hard they fought for their future, what they had been and could be again, and
how a strong female Krogan might just inspire them to a peaceful greatness once again.
And so now you have a narrative map
that you can use when working with the content teams.
So you can start thinking about how
you can use various content to support
the different sides of these polarized issues.
So moving on to creating the content.
Once you've established the high level story
theme and polarities, you want to create
content that supports them.
So this is all about creating the language with visuals
and audio to develop unique identities
for the different sides of the conflict.
for the various people and the places you'll encounter
over the course of the game.
And you also want to think about how the visual or audio design
can change over the course of the narrative.
And provide feedback to the player
about the state of the world and how it's reacting
to your choices as a player.
So now when I talk about content,
I'm talking about the VO, the characters, level, animation,
sound effects, music, visual effects, all this stuff.
There's a lot of content that goes
into creating the experience.
So at this point, good communication is essential.
This process can end up being a bit like a game of telephone,
where from the story side, things are pretty clear.
But once it goes out to the different content teams
and it goes through their various pipelines and workflows,
the message can get diluted or lost in translation.
And it's often the case that when it comes out on the other side and we combine it together
to create this experience, all these assets aren't telling the same story.
So it might be that the tone of the music or the VO isn't right for the scene or a character's
appearance doesn't accurately reflect their personality.
And when it doesn't work, it's really obvious.
Here's a great example from...
Dragon Age 2 Legacy DLC.
This character is Larius and he's an old Grey Warden commander who goes off to the deep
roads on his calling to die fighting Darkspawn.
Except he doesn't really die, he just gets corrupted enough that they leave him alone
so he's left to wander around slowly losing his mind.
Okay, okay, yeah, I got it, I got it.
So we go off and somebody records the animation for him,
somebody else records the VO for him,
and the character team is working on his character.
And it wasn't until we put it all together
that we realized how wrong we were,
how different our understanding of who this character was.
So he's hobbling around like this spry young monkey,
and he's talking like a weezy-geezer,
and he looks like this nuclear fallout victim,
and we put it all together and it was wrong,
it was all wrong.
So we ended up having to go and re-record the animations.
We had to get new mocap.
We had to go and re-record the VO.
We had to tweak his character.
And we ended up spending a lot of time and money
to fix this problem.
So what could we have done differently?
How could we have done this better?
Surely more documentation, right?
More documentation's always the answer.
wrong. So sometimes excessive documentation can be the problem. At Bioware, we are occasionally
guilty of writing narrative overviews like George R. R. Martin wrote a choose your own
adventure book. So I once made the mistake of printing these narrative overviews out.
I've got a little time to do a bit of light reading, right?
and the resulting stack of papers was absolutely overwhelming.
And it's now that I realize that,
maybe I have to read through this,
but a lot of the content developers and creators
aren't going to read through this massive stack of papers,
so they're going to remain unaware of the central themes of the game.
So instead, they'll kind of resort to creating content that's cool.
And cool content is cool, right?
But it doesn't necessarily support the theme of the game as well as it could.
Now we could have avoided this whole catastrophe if we just spent five minutes and used contrast
to talk about where the characters sat between these different polarities.
The process is really about communication and making sure that everyone understands
what something is and what something's not.
Now we want everything to support the story.
The teams responsible for telling the narrative, the audio, and the visuals, and the gameplay
elements should all be telling the same story with their work.
So communication is obviously key here and it's not just about communicating more information
but about boiling that giant stack of papers down to easy to understand ideas.
So the idea is to keep it simple, right?
When communicating the story vision with the content teams,
you want to be able to give them a clear idea
of the polarities that you want to explore,
and then let them decide how to support
those narrative polarities with polarities
within their own disciplines.
So artists can use visual polarities
to support the narrative themes.
And this goes back to the basics of visual design.
Does the villain dress in black?
Does the good guy wear a white hat?
So getting back to the basics, you
want to be able to see a character
and immediately know and have a good idea of what he represents,
who they are, and what do they want.
So familiarize yourself with the basic visual components.
visual design and how they can be used to tell a story or convey emotion.
So visual components like line, color, shape, space, movement, tone, rhythm.
Think about what each side represents and how they can support narrative polarities.
Now it's kind of meta here, but the opposite of contrast is affinity.
So sometimes it's not about making things look different, but making different groups
look like they belong together.
So for example, we used color, shape, and patterns
to make these different groups of Templars or Grey Wardens
kind of look like they belong together.
A great example is the Darkspawn in Dragon Age Origins.
They all looked really cool, but they were all very different.
They didn't really look like they belonged together.
And we wanted them to seem like they should be together,
like a family.
So we used tone and color to make these guys look like they belong in a group.
In Mass Effect 3, it's immediately clear who the bad guys are.
If you see these little glowy blue dots and it's running at you, start shooting and get the hell out of there.
Now, visual polarities are also great for showing character progression or for externalizing the interior qualities of a character.
This is a great example for Mass Effect.
So if Shepard plays as a thinking, sympathetic paragon,
he looks more human.
Whereas if he plays more renegade,
thinking or not thinking, more logical and unfeeling,
he starts to look more like a machine.
His skin starts to split,
revealing these cybernetics beneath.
And this is great because it reflects
that larger story theme of humanity versus reapers
or humanity versus technology.
And think about how color can tell a story.
For example, the red in this scene could represent danger.
Or think about how the polarities of light and dark can tell a story.
In this case, transition from life to death.
So the same thing with audio polarities.
Think about the basic audio components, whether it's volume, pitch, speed, rhythm.
So figure out what the polarities are and think about how they could be used to represent
the different sides of the story.
Things like, you know, all these.
And in Dragon Age 2, we use the polarities
of known versus unknown when doing the ambient sound design.
So for example, we wanted Kirkwall
to feel like your home.
It's a familiar place.
You spend a lot of time there.
We want you to feel safe there.
So the ambient sound design is full
of real and familiar sounds.
Kids playing, dogs barking, merchants shouting.
But by contrast, when you venture outside of Kirkwall,
the locations are full of unreal and otherworldly sounds.
It's strange and unfamiliar.
It creates this sense of danger in comparison.
Same thing with the music, using rhythm and tone in the music to represent the different
sides of a polarized conflict like the Templars versus the Mages in Dragon Age.
The music changes as the player completes quests for the different sides.
It has a mystical sound when pursuing these Mage-related quests and a more structured,
ordered, militant sound when pursuing Templar-related quests.
So I love working in cinematics because we get to take all this great, meaningful content
and put it together, and then we add our own layer of meaning on top.
The camera can tell a story too, and it's a powerful tool in creating an experience.
So things like the camera angle, lens, shot composition, camera movement, these all tell
a story.
So again, it's important to understand what the different cinematic components are and
how they can be used to create meaning or support the story that you're trying to tell.
For example, the camera angle can make a character look weak and vulnerable.
or powerful and oppressive. In this case, it again reflects the larger theme of humanity
versus the reapers. Just tilting the camera can make a world seem chaotic and out of balance.
A close-up is personal, while a long shot feels detached. And we can combine these elements
to create more complex shots, more complex emotions. In this case, a feeling of detachment
or distance from your character in this world that's out of balance.
So we can also use spatial context to add meaning through,
a lot of people call this environmental storytelling.
So in Dragon Age 2,
we wanted to give the followers their own space
that can further reflect their personalities.
For example, we've got Varric here
and he's got books behind him.
He's a storyteller and that reflects that.
Him sitting in this chair,
kind of mirrors him sitting in a chair,
telling more stories in an interrogation room
in the framing narrative.
And this is fun, this is a lot of fun.
It's a great example of working with your level artists to tell a story outside of dialogue.
So Thane, for example, is this badass lizard assassin, and so we stick him in this assassin's
aquarium with these fluorescent lights and guns everywhere.
And the environment around the player can serve to remind them of the things they've
done, the adventures and the quests that they've already gone through.
So now that you've used contrast and context to create your story, to create content that
supports that story in the narrative themes of your game, you can put them all together
and everything's telling the same story, right?
Well, when this works, it is absolutely amazing.
There's a dream sequence in Mass Effect 3, and it's very emotionally powerful and it
stuck with me for a long time after playing the game.
And in contrast to the real world, this dream world is desaturated and foggy.
Your movement is slow and heavy.
The sounds are strange and the music is haunting.
And it really stands out from the rest of the game because the narrative, the visuals,
the audio and the cinematography are all working together to create this experience for the player.
Now, we also use reflective context to further shape the player experience.
We want your current experience to be shaped by your previous choices and actions.
So this takes a player experience and makes it a personal experience.
And that's how you take players and turn them into fans.
So for example, your experience of the Genophage mission I described earlier,
it could be completely different if you didn't kill Rex in Mass Effect 1.
It's pretty hard not to kill Rex.
And so if he's still alive, it means that you've pursued this relationship with him,
you've got a strong relationship with him,
you understand how he thinks, how he feels, a bit more about the Krogan history,
and how he could potentially be a leader.
So it definitely has an impact on that experience of that mission.
So your previous actions also influence the choices that you have in future conversations.
We've got thousands of choices in our games, and every one that you make opens up or closes
off future choices.
So some people occasionally lament the lack of choices, but not realizing that the choices
available to them at any point in these Bioware games are based on how they've been playing
the game so far.
Now we want you also to see your choices reflected in the cinematics.
And this is something that...
we could have done a lot better in Dragon Age Origins.
If you've played it,
you might be familiar with the murder knife.
Now, this was this kind of weird, wooden handle, dinky kitchen knife.
And at various points throughout the game, you had this opportunity to kill various NPCs for whatever reason.
And when you did so, I always wanted to kill them with this giant two-sided axe with purple electricity and flame shooting out that I've been carrying around for like 20 levels.
But when I killed this guy, I kind of pulled this knife out from behind my back and you throw it or swing it or...
We had all sorts of these scenes and it was really a missed opportunity to do something
unique and show the player killing a guy in a way that was consistent with how he built
his character and how he'd been playing the game so far.
So for Dragon Age 2, this was really important to me to fix this and allow the player to
kill somebody with their weapon in a way that was consistent with their character, how they'd
been playing the game so far.
So just as an example, you can definitely
see the results in Dragon Age 2 and the Dragon Age 2 DLC.
This is a few examples of a cinematic kill scene
where you take out a boss in various ways,
depending on whether you're an archer, a rogue, or a mage.
So this creates a very personal experience
for the player, which is much, much, much more satisfying.
Now we also use temporal context to help
shape the player experience.
Now in BioWare games in particular,
you have a lot of freedom in where you go, what you do,
what order you do things in.
So when working on any conversation or cut scenes, we have to be aware of, well, what
has the player already done?
What does he still have left to do?
What does he know?
What does he not know at any point in the game?
And sometimes timing is important.
In Mass Effect 2, if you don't go save your crew fast enough after they get kidnapped
by the collectors, a lot of them die, including Kelly Chambers.
Who's going to feed your fish now?
So this is also important when creating the DLC for Dragon Age 2 because the player can
play this DLC at any point in time in the main game.
They can play in Act 1, Act 2, or Act 3 during the main playthrough.
And a lot of consideration had to be given to what was a player's previous experiences
and how could they shape the current experience.
So just as an example.
In the Dragon Age 2 DLC Legacy, Hawk learns a bit about the true nature of his father.
And it was really important to us that Hawk be able to have this discussion with his mother
to talk about what he had discovered.
But depending on when you played this DLC in relation to the main game, Hawk's mother
could be alive, missing, or dead.
So we had to figure out how to make this scene in all these different cases.
and make it meaningful. So in the case of Hawk's mother being dead, we set up the scene,
we use these cinematic polarities to create this effect where it's really Hawk having
this conversation with a memory of his mother. And this allows us to add more emotional weight
to the scene. Now, occasionally players are able to play through your content in a way
that you might not have expected.
In Dragon Age Origins, the party camp was this safe place where you could go and equip
your gear, chat with your followers, pursue romances, and it was a safe place.
You never got attacked in the party camp.
Except for that one time we thought it'd be cool to attack you in the player camp, right?
So you get attacked, you take out these bad guys, and you're covered head to toe in blood.
But you just kind of go back to business as usual, chatting with your followers, swapping
gear, pursuing romantic relationships.
And these romantic relationships, they take a lot of time.
to get to, so we wanted these to be sweet and sensual, there's nice romantic music playing,
but in this case, in this case you were covered in blood.
So what was supposed to be this sweet romantic scene ends up just being disturbingly bizarre
and hilarious.
because of what the player had done previously.
And this is not what we wanted.
This isn't what I wanted when I created this scene.
It was all wrong.
So the lesson here is that when you craft these key moments
in your game, just be aware of what the player might
be able to do before and how it could potentially
sabotage your efforts.
So back to contrastive juxtaposition.
So now that we've talked about contrast and context
when creating your story, your content, and your cinematics,
how do we use all these together to create
these powerful?
emotionally engaging scenes.
So, first I'd like to give you kind of a simple example
of contrastive juxtaposition in music.
Now, normally I wouldn't suggest this
when showing a clip from the show,
but pay close attention to the dialogue,
especially towards the end.
When you're in a fall
If you can't fly
I'd better start rocking or I'll really give him something to cry about.
Shut up, buddy. It's cool. Check it out. Check it out.
Here it comes.
Yes! Yes!
Rawr! Yes! Yes! Yes!
Rawr!
Rawr! Yes! Yes!
This is pretty cool.
Yes! Yes!
Yeah! Yeah!
What? What's going on?
It's true.
How come they don't just like play that cool part through the whole song?
Well, Beavis, if they didn't have like a part of the song that sucked, then it's like the other part wouldn't be as cool.
Really? You're pretty smart.
You're a tough one, Beavis.
Yes. Yes.
So it's a pretty silly example, but I think you get the point I was trying to make.
It demonstrates this basic concept of how the juxtaposition of these two contrasting elements,
in this case, the soft verse and the hard chorus, can have an emotional impact on the viewers.
And I love this idea that if they didn't have a part of the song that sucked,
then maybe the other part wouldn't be as cool.
Now, obviously, none of us want any part of our games to suck,
but it just speaks to the fact that you can't necessarily crank it up to 11 and leave it.
It's that back and forth between contrastive elements that grabs your attention and holds
your attention.
And sometimes you need that slow moment, that calm moment before the storm for your key
moment to really stand out.
So to do this, you have to first identify what those story moments are around that target
moment.
So the story moments in that example I showed at the very beginning is Shepard is helping
Joker into the escape pod.
She gets thrown back by an explosion, barely presses that eject button before another blast ... ... ...
shoots her right out of the Normandy, the Normandy explodes, and then she floats off
into space to die.
So if these are the kind of story beats of your scene, what is the moment that you want
to stand out?
What is the moment you really want to have that emotional impact on the player?
So in this case, it's Shepard floating away into space to die.
So if that's your key moment, how do you make it stand out?
And what you want to do is you want to make the lows lower
and the highs higher.
Create that strong contrast in the narrative, the audio,
and the visuals around it.
So in this case, we want to highlight this narrative shift
from alive to dead.
Then we do that by first showing this massive explosion,
the biggest explosion you could have,
and then immediately cutting to these tiny, tiny, tiny little
VFX in the background.
And you can kind of see how we might map out
that polarity shift.
Now, the music completely cuts out as soon as Shepard is outside of the Normandy, and
the music doesn't come back until the sad piano at the end, and sad piano will always
make you cry.
So the sound design in the scene goes from sounds of the world around Shepard to just
sounds of Shepard and her suit as she's gasping for air.
In a single shot we go from a close-up to this wide shot, creating this feeling of loss
of separation from your character.
And here's that transition.
And then in the final shot, we watch the sun set back behind the planet until the world
is dark.
And this visual clarity mirrors the narrative shift from life to death.
So now that we've kind of gone over this, let's take another look at that scene and
see how all these elements work together.
So I hope I've given you a better understanding
of these different shifts in polarity
and why contrast and context are important
and how we use them as creative tools
throughout the development process when creating the story,
the content, the cinematics, and the overall experience
for the player.
So some key takeaways here are identify your story themes
early so you can inform design further down the line.
Keep it really simple when communicating these ideas
to your content teams.
And remember that context can really
have a significant impact on the meaning of an experience.
If you're interested in learning more about narrative, visual,
and audio polarities, I'd highly recommend these books.
The Writer's Journey by Christopher Vogler,
The Visual Story by Bruce Block, and Sound Design
by David Sonenshine.
So that's the end of my talk.
I hope you have some time for questions.
If I don't get your question today,
please feel free to email me or follow me on Twitter.
And I'd definitely be interested in hearing your feedback.