Hi, my name is Jongwoo Kim. I'm from Kitfox Games,
and I'm here to talk about Cruel Fate,
Emergent Tragedies in the Shrouded Isle.
Just a quick note about our studio.
We're based out of Montreal,
and previously we released Moonhunters,
which is a co-op action RPG with procedurally generated world
and trait-based role-playing mechanics.
Last year, we had a highly successful Kickstarter campaign
for Boyfriend Dungeon, which is a dungeon crawler
crossed with dating sim.
But today we're going to talk about something very different.
Has anyone played The Shroud at all?
Some of you.
OK, I'm going to play the trailer anyway,
because I get to do that.
Let's see.
Here we go.
["SHROUD THEME"]
Oh, that was not intentional.
Oh, too much power tripping.
Sorry.
I'm just gonna drag back my notes here.
All right, so as you saw in the trailer,
the Shrouded Isle is a human sacrifice cult simulator.
You play as the high priest of this small island village
that worships a slumbering dark god.
And in preparation for his awakening,
you try to maintain the faith of your people,
maintain the loyalty of the five great houses
of the village, and make a human sacrifice
at the end of each season.
The project began as an entry for a game jam back in 2015.
We really loved the concept,
so we decided to fully develop the game.
So in August 2017, the full version of the Shrouded Isle
was released for PC and OSX.
Later that year, due to positive reception,
we released a free expansion pack called Sunken Sins.
And just recently, in January,
we released a switch port of the Shrouded Isle,
and in March, we released it for Japan region as well.
So what do I mean by emergent tragedies and what does that have to do with the Shrouded Isle?
It goes back to the game jam.
The theme was, you are the monster.
And instead of making a game about a physical monster, we wanted to explore why someone
makes monstrous choices.
Why does the leader of a community take actions that clearly harm members of that community?
And in tackling that theme, we wanted to maintain ludonarrative congruence,
which is to say that the narrative is told through the gameplay.
But you might be more familiar with the more common term,
ludonarrative dissonance, in which the narrative is undermined by the mechanics.
So our creative goals were difficult to achieve because we needed to depict this dystopian society of the cults.
But a lot of the design references we could find had this underlying utopian or heroic assumptions
and had the risk of undermining the tragic narrative that we wanted to tell.
To give a quick comparison, we wanted to depict a stagnant society that tries to control and constrain its people.
By contrast, utopian games tend to focus on growth through the empowerment of a protagonist or the expansion of a community.
We wanted to explore the divisions within the cult.
What political games are being played?
Who is seen as virtuous or sinful?
But most games we found depicted unity or assumed unity instead,
whether it's a band of adventurers or an army that's loyal to a greater cause.
Most importantly, though, we wanted the gameplay to depict failure.
Telling a story about a corrupt society in which the leaders do whatever it takes to
maintain their regime.
But the majority of examples we found had an underlying message of triumph.
Depicting victory over an evil foe or prosperity of a community.
So why make emergent tragedies?
Because it allows us to depict dystopias and moral grayness
while achieving ludonarrative congruence.
The narrative is told through the gameplay.
We can make more impactful experiences
than scripted content because the player becomes
an active participant and thereby causes
their own downfall, or in rare cases,
succeeds at an immense cost.
But doing this is very challenging,
because we have to find alternative gameplay elements
to replace key aspects of utopian design.
So this talk will be analyzing three gameplay elements
that were used in the Shrouded Isle
to create emergent tragedies.
So first we'll look at how physical resources
were replaced entirely with psychological resources.
Then we'll talk about the core gameplay,
examining how process-oriented mechanics
were replaced with character-oriented mechanics.
Finally, we'll talk about progression systems.
Spatial expansion or tech upgrades
were substituted with progression
through information gathering.
So let's first talk about resources.
In the Game Jam version, two of the town's resources
were physical, food and shelter.
This was a sensible need for the town,
but it was too easy for the player to stock up
and fill the bar and imply a state of prosperity
for the town.
And we could have balanced the resource management to make the state of prosperity difficult to achieve,
but there was a deeper problem in that directly managing food and shelter really felt irrelevant to a cult leader's interests.
So in the final release, we replaced all physical resources with psychological resources.
This way, the core economy of the game revolves around what a cult leader would care about, faith and politics.
So in the bottom row there, you see the five virtues of the cult.
Ignorance, fervor, discipline, penitence, and obedience.
These variables are affected by the actions and traits of the townspeople.
If characters behave virtuously, the bars go up.
If they behave sinfully, the bars go down.
If the bar slips below the threshold for too long,
the people lose faith in the cult and the game ends.
The upper row holds the political resources,
the opinions of the five great houses of the village.
So on the far left, you'll see that House Kegney
feels satisfied with the regime,
while neighboring House Iosefka in the second column
feels merely neutral.
When you bestow favor on a house
by using their members as advisors,
their opinions go up and their opinion goes down
when you exclude them or kill members of their family
for this seasonal sacrifice.
If any has his opinion drops too low for too long,
they revolt and the game ends.
So the big benefit of using psychological resources
is that the player embraces the values
of the cult implicitly.
Even if the player personally disagrees in the real world
that raising ignorance is a good thing,
they quickly learn that it is absolutely necessary
for their cult to survive in the game.
Furthermore, they are
The psychological resources are divorced from objective reality or survival of the townspeople.
So as a result, the player's narrative interests are dissociated from the villager's narrative
interests, which motivates the players to make rather Machiavellian decisions when difficult
situations arise.
There's a further benefit in that you can keep the game in a state of volatile stagnation.
As opposed to having an economy that just keeps growing and growing and growing over
the course of a playthrough, the overall size remains relatively stagnant or even in slight
decline.
So, at the same time, the individual resources have high volatility so that the crises in
the game emerge dynamically.
So let me give you a quick example.
I'm going to select Chessa on the very far left
of the advisors list as my lead advisor this season.
She belongs to House Kegney,
so she specializes in burning books.
If she succeeds, she'll raise ignorance
by a moderate amount this month.
She's also personally a sadist,
so she'll raise fervor significantly by her example.
This is really great because fervor
is dangerously low right now.
She is also rebellious, which is a major vice.
By using her as an advisor,
her example will reduce obedience of the town
below the critical threshold,
and therefore create an overall disobedience problem
for the village.
In terms of politics,
House Kegney will understandably be very happy
that you entrusted Chesa to lead the town,
and they become zealous supporters of your regime.
In exchange, every other house is somewhat insulted and envious and counterbalances the economy.
In the Epherson's case, it pushes them down just enough so that it breaks their camel's back, so to speak, and they will rebel next season.
So maybe choosing Chesa isn't the best option right now.
As we saw with the example, a simple choice of who should lead the town for a month was given a complex nuance because of the volatility of the individual variables.
Each gain is counterbalanced by a comparable loss in other variables.
So while having the high volatility for the individual variables, we avoid having a spiraling growth or collapse, which would unbalance the gameplay and also undermine the narrative.
And we theoretically could have done this with physical resources, but I find that psychological resources are far easier to justify as having this volatility that I needed.
Because it's easier to explain that Chessa is a fervent person who sometimes goes too far and tends to be disobedient and rebellious,
rather than trying to justify why gathering food would result in destruction of shelters or decay of shelters.
Reigns is a game that uses psychological resources to depict tragic outcomes.
The resources in the game simultaneously represent the physical amount of something as well as
the faction's strength.
So, for example, the sword represents the physical size of your army as well as their
relative political influence within your kingdom.
If the bar is empty, your kingdom can't defend itself and becomes conquered by an invader.
If the bar is too full, your general overthrows you in a coup d'etat.
This careful balancing act combined with the volatile outcomes creates cascading crises.
But at the same time, their economy is very fragile and strategic play is difficult without
memorizing the card outcomes.
So at some level, I do find that this undermines the player ownership of choices, but it works
fine for Reigns because it embraces death with a whimsical tone and has a dynastic meta
progression system.
So even if you die, you get something in the end.
Moving on, let's talk about character-oriented mechanics.
Utopian simulations tend to have process-oriented mechanics.
Critical actions or systems in the game
are abstracted industrial processes
or are done through an organization.
A residential zone is drawn.
Income is received every month.
A research project is chosen and just completes over time.
Even when characters are involved,
they are largely interchangeable and only matter
as far as how quickly they gather something or speed up
the process.
So going back to the Game Jam version for a second,
at the time we also had a very process-oriented game.
The player gave orders at the house level,
so like house Kegney would gather food
or house Josefka would build shelters and so forth.
And the results were calculated in aggregate
because it really didn't matter how each house
gathered a particular resource.
This felt dissatisfying because similar to what we were talking about with the psychological
resources earlier, it didn't seem like what a cult leader would want to do or care about.
We wanted the player to engage with individual characters, judging for themselves whether
a villager is virtuous or sinful.
We wanted the player to have a reason to want to sacrifice somebody.
So we changed the mechanic to be entirely character-oriented instead.
The goal was to dramatize resource management by having the player act through or act upon
characters whose behavior was fundamentally unpredictable.
While the player can order characters to do something, they can't fully control what they
do or what the outcome will be.
So let's go back to Chessa again.
So in this playthrough, I don't really know her very well, but I'm still going to select
her as a representative for House Keg.
I'm going to need her help desperately this season because ignorance is at a critical
level and members of House Kegney are responsible for raising it.
As I don't know her very well, it's going to be hard to predict how she will impact the town.
We know that because she's part of the Cagney family, she will most likely raise ignorance.
But we don't know how severe her vice is.
According to rumors, as you can see on the second tray under her name,
she is rumored to be disobedient.
So I'm just going to trust for now that it's not too serious.
Unfortunately, Chessa screws up.
She fails to find enough books to burn, and instead of raising ignorance, she actually reduces it instead.
Not only that, her vice might be severe.
We don't know exactly what she did, but she completely reduced the town's obedience.
This is an infuriating outcome, because not only did she fail at what I trusted her to do,
she turns out to be a terrible sinner who is misleading my people.
I trusted Chessa because as the player, I was engaged with her at every single step.
I personally appointed her, and then I personally ordered her to burn books.
Due to the stress, I had a certain expectation of her, which she did not fulfill.
I felt betrayed by her because...
She was an individual that did this,
and she was personally connected to me
as a result of my orders to her.
If an industrial process or an organization
resulted in this outcome,
I would only have myself to blame.
But due to having character-oriented mechanics,
we added dramatic context to what would otherwise
be a really banal resource acquisition action.
Another game that uses character-oriented mechanics to tell emergent narratives about
expectations and betrayal is, of course, Darkest Dungeon.
The player sends parties of adventurers down to these deadly crypts, and for the most part,
the characters will obey the player's orders.
However, as their stress rises from all the horrors that they encounter,
the party gains afflictions, which are negative traits that permanently change how the character behaves.
So, for example, being hopeless not only causes debuffs to the character,
it causes the character to ignore the player's orders.
Having one character with an affliction is manageable, but...
it snowballs very quickly and eventually unless you pull out,
the entire party will be full of afflictions.
One thing that Darkest Dungeon does well is counterbalancing this,
subverting this with the mechanic of virtues.
So.
There's a small chance that instead of gaining an affliction,
you gain a positive trait which boosts the party instead.
So for instance, being courageous
as opposed to being hopeless.
By doing so, the game subverts the player's
negative expectation in a positive way,
creating emergent narratives of heroism and turnabout.
Moving on, let's talk about progression systems.
We looked at two conventional approaches,
which would have been to go wide
and allow for spatial expansion
and go tall and allow for upgrades.
But thinking about it,
it felt incompatible with the narrative
because the island is isolated from the world
and has a dwindling population due to ritual sacrifices.
To have a progression system
without having the cult grow in any way,
we decided to use information.
The way it works is through the townspeople and their traits.
So let's take Bogdan here for an example.
At the start of the playthrough,
we might not know anything about Bogdan's behavior.
But as the cult leader, the player has the right
to investigate, excuse me,
investigate members of their village for their behavior.
So if we inquire about Bogdan's virtue,
at the next stage, we understand
that he's rumored to be obedient.
But we still don't know exactly how much he will affect the town's obedience until we
inquire about him again, and then it's revealed that he is timid, and we'll add five points
of obedience every season.
Through revealing traits, the player is given subjective rewards.
The characters themselves do not change at all.
They behave exactly the same, no matter how much their trait has been revealed.
Instead, the player's perception of that character changes.
Since the player can more accurately predict the character's impact,
they can make better decisions as they reveal more traits.
There's also a change in the villager's perception of that character in the final phase.
So if the player unveils the fullest extent of a character's virtue or vice,
it changes the bonuses and penalties in the sacrifice phase.
So let's go back to Chessa.
She drained the town's obedience because of her vice,
but we don't know exactly what that vice is yet.
When we inquire about it, we discover that she is rebellious.
This is a major vice.
At the end of the season, we have to choose one of the five advisors to sacrifice.
And I'm going to make an example out of Chessa.
Because I've exposed that she is rebellious,
I'm able to make her family grudgingly accept this final outcome.
Furthermore, her village, sorry,
her death will send a message to the village,
restoring some of the lost obedience.
With Chessa's death, justice is served
and the villagers have learned a lesson.
As you saw, the benefit of using information progression
is that it allows us to temporarily blind the player.
By giving access to incomplete information,
we can create scenarios in which players'
good intentions go terribly wrong.
It's in the player's best interest to gain information,
so therefore the player is motivated
to get to know the characters,
which adds support to the character-oriented mechanics
that we talked about in the previous section.
And granted, this approach can be frustrating
if the situation is completely opaque or unreadable,
but the gameplay remains fair
as long as the player is given some information
and has active means of acquiring more.
In fact, I would say that the player is rewarded for being prudent and having foresight as
long as they can make reasonable assumptions about the missing information.
Probably the single best example of information progression is Return of the Aubrey Dinn.
The player is trying to figure out the fate of the crew and passengers on the Aubrey Dinn
by using a magic pocket watch to go back to the moment of their death.
By carefully observing the snapshot flashbacks
for what the characters say, what they do,
and whom they associate with,
the player slowly pieces together faces with names
until the truth is revealed.
The game discourages guessing
by only confirming your answers in sets of three,
and directly warning the player
if not enough information has been found
to be able to actually identify the character.
All the same, an astute player is able
to make reasonable predictions about a character's identity
long before having enough evidence
based on their appearance, occupation,
and the language that they speak.
So to bring this all together,
emergent tragedies allow players
to create their own downfall.
We can tell narratives about dystopias and moral grayness,
not through scripted content, but through gameplay itself.
Psychological resources are the fundamental step in this,
and that it encourages players to embrace
alternative paradigms and discourage min-maxing.
Even if the player personally does not agree
with the values of the cult and the Shrouded Isle,
they must implicitly accept them within the game
as their survival and success depends on them.
Character-oriented mechanics then dramatize
this resource management.
By having most, if not all, mechanics in a game
revolve around characters, we can tell powerful narratives
about expectation and betrayal.
Finally, progression through information
allows players to improve over time
without direct empowerment.
Instead of gaining more resources through spatial expansion
or refining them through technological upgrades,
players effectively become more intelligent
through the course of a playthrough
by being able to better predict
the consequences of their actions.
This also creates opportunity
in the middle of the playthrough
for good intentions to go terribly, terribly wrong.
For our latest project,
we've taken principles from the Shrouded Isle
and adapted them for the mystery genre.
It's an experimental project that focuses on subjectivity of testimonies
and relies entirely on information progression.
If you're curious, we'll be showcasing a seven-minute demo
at the Experimental Gameplay Workshop on Friday.
That's it for the talk. Thank you very much.
I think we have time for questions.
The microphone is in the middle.
I'm just curious, you've got a game about dystopia and mechanics there, you know, about
managing psychological needs.
Did you ever have confusion when playtesters were playing to try to determine what constitutes
a win in your game?
Like, how do I make a decision that I know is, does the game think this is a good decision?
It seems like a bad decision?
Are you asking, were there cases in which the player was confused about the...
the purpose of a certain resource or the goal of the game?
More like the goal of the game.
Was the intention to leave players kind of wondering
whether or not they're progressing to what would be
defined as a win state, or is that kind of part of the
purpose of the game that the players are questioning?
Am I winning this game?
Clearly I get the bars below the threshold and I lose, but
what is the sum of the correct decisions that I've made and is that going to take me to
something that constitutes a win or at the end do I just feel like a bad person?
Okay so to summarize then the question is were there confusions by players about the
goal of the game and was that intentional as far as the experience is concerned?
I would say that at the start of development it was not intentional, but as we observed playtests and that we found that by the second playthrough players grokked it, or just the survival of the first season of the players grokked it, we just embraced that side of the game.
An interesting anecdote for me is that I often observe that the player tends to embrace their
inner tyrant by the second season.
So the first season of a game, people will try to be good, whatever that means, but then
they realize that, hey, being good in my sense doesn't actually help me be successful in
this game.
And then their mindsets shift, and it's a bit disconcerting.
Like a disconcerting to watch but I mean in some ways it's a success in other ways
I wish that there was a moral like a longer moral dilemma that happened that that would be the intended experience from my perspective
Thank you. Cheers
Hey, so sort of bouncing off that first, I love the game,
thank you for making it.
The game made me turn into a bad person,
which is normally hard in RPG games for me.
But something I noticed is that, yeah,
like around the second season,
I began to feel more apathetic
because I was embracing this like dictatorship role
in the community.
And it began to in some ways sort of conflict
with some of my gameplay behavior
because I was developing a kind of apathy.
to the characters, to the world, because I wanted to succeed so well.
So I was curious if you had any thoughts on how, you know, I think this awesome goal
of having people embrace this more darker side of leadership and playing with apathy
as a narrative construct can sometimes conflict or maybe in some ways enhance the apathy
that we can develop as a player and if that's something that is negative
or if that's something you think we can gain some cool experiences from.
Okay, so is the question, sorry I'm just trying to grok the full question.
Yeah.
So is the question something like, given that there's a certain apathy or distance that's
like inherent to the structure of the game, how do I feel about that as far as a design
choice?
Yes, and how does that conflict with, often times as game designers, we want the opposite
of that for gameplay.
Right? So how does that apathy that you get as being this protagonist conflict with the gameplay apathy?
And just if you have any thoughts about that.
Right. So the interesting thing about that is that I often find that the players have very
Let me rephrase, certain players have a certain desire to be empathetic with the characters.
So the generation of the characters are, it's very, very simple in the Stratodile compared to like a Roguelike, let's say,
or like a Dwarf, compared to something like Dwarf Fortress, like it doesn't hold a candle.
But there's a portrait, there's two traits, one positive, one negative.
And for many players, that's enough to perceive a personality within that.
And P players tend to get attached to...
those personalities.
And we also have a system where you can rename the character.
So in some cases, like, you've named this person
after your friend, are you really gonna, you know?
And so that sort of attachment, I feel,
there's just little things that adds up to
if you will, like certain threshold in which the players become attached to that character.
And so I didn't feel, for this project anyway, that the apathy that you developed would conflict
with my motivation. But if I were trying to make a game in which I wanted the player to deeply,
deeply care about the people in the town,
I would agree that the Machiavellian nature
of the project would have been a poor fit.
Yeah, totally.
OK, thank you.
Cool, thanks.
No other questions?
You mentioned randomness in the different heads of the houses and things like that.
And I was wondering if it, because I haven't played it myself, but it looks really cool.
If it is just completely random of like, you know, given the context of the world state
of the game and, you know, the resources, you could get something really good, you could
get something really bad, or have you guys considered or tried to put in like, you know,
any sort of AI that would kind of read the room and decide based off of what the player
is doing and what they have, what would be the most interesting, you know, traits to
give something.
Okay, so if I understand you right, is it like, how did you balance the randomness versus
like the intentionality of the project?
Like if it's just, you know, pure, is it a full-on slot machine of what you get or is
there a little bit of like crafted behind it?
I would say that initially I would have wanted the project to be as deterministic as possible
other than the initial starting conditions for the town.
But what I've observed over time is that the design space becomes very, very narrow and
the... .
Because the game is about failure, right?
Imagine if you're able to predict every op.
Let's say we play rock, paper, scissors, right?
And then I tell you,
hey, I'm gonna play rock next turn.
Are you ever gonna use scissors?
Other than for just for the fun of it, you know?
So in that way, to keep the feeling of being the leader
in a terrible situation, like as,
as relevant as long as possible for the experience.
Like some amount of randomness was added.
But for the most part, there is very little of it,
I would argue.
There's more of missing information.
If the player were able to have like all the towns
that characters traits from the get-go,
the lack of randomness in the Shrouded Isle
would be more apparent, I'd say.
Okay, thank you.
Cheers.
Since the Shrouded Isle deals a lot with using gameplay that works with systems and exploration,
had you guys at GitFox ever considered basing it on historically power structures or systems
or maybe using this kind of gameplay to explore more historically bent ideas?
So the question is, have we considered exploring historical situations and ideas with systemic
gameplay like this?
To tell you the truth, for the Shrouded Isle, we didn't have something specific in mind.
As I said, it came out of a game jam.
But what I find interesting is that after release, a lot of our colleagues kind of projected
like what the game was actually about, like whether it's at a workspace or like, you know,
like at a political party in particular or whatever.
I would want to, like, so I have a background in Soviet history and so I do
want to depict, you know, a single party structure, like, I think it would be a
good fit for the Shrouded Isle, but we haven't moved further, like, in pursuing
those projects yet, but it's something that I would be definitely interested in.
Hi there, thanks for the talk.
I was wondering, you said players took like a whole act
to really understand the game.
What do you think that kept the players interested in the game
before they truly understand it?
If I'm going to be blunt, the art.
So I mean, it's an interesting question.
So we thought that the,
so this, we showed the Shrouded Isle multiple times at PAXes
and we were always surprised at the,
the relative amount of attention that a game about bars
going up and down, frankly, gets at a convention.
And it's because of the striking art style
and just like the harsh, like, nature of the game,
the tickles, like, you know,
the right parts of brains, I guess.
It's really hard to say.
So honestly, I underestimated.
the level of interest in this project. I thought that it's too weird and too cruel of a project.
But overall, I'm really gratified that it's received the attention that it already has,
frankly. Does that answer the question? Cheers. Okay. That's it for the talk. Thank you very much.
Please fill out your evaluations. And, yeah.