Hi everyone, thank you for coming to my talk.
My name's Tyler and this is Dream Daddy,
how we created player inclusivity and you can too.
This is the first talk I've given in about 10 years.
So come on this journey with me.
Is anyone else really nervous?
OK, no.
So here's me.
I'm Tyler J. Hutchison.
I work for a company called Game Grumps.
You might know them.
And I was the director and lead developer of a video game
called Dream Daddy.
Hey, Dad Dating Simulator.
For those of you who aren't aware of what Dream Daddy is,
I feel like some of you might know since you came to this
talk and it's in front of the door.
But for those of you who don't know what Dream Daddy is,
it was a very successful game that came out
on Steam this summer.
In Dream Daddy, you play as a dad whose goal is to meet
and romance the dad of his dreams.
It's a gay dad dating simulator.
So this talk, how we created player inclusivity,
and you can too.
It's kind of important for a game that's
a dating simulator about men dating other men.
And you might expect the next slide
to answer a very important question for you.
This is an advocacy talk after all,
so you might expect me to say, why?
Why should you care about this talk?
Why should you care about player inclusivity?
Well, it's 2018.
I'm not going to answer this question for you.
It's kind of already been answered
by numerous other people.
I'm going to draw your attention to these talks, which you can watch on the GDC Vault.
Most of them are between 30 to 60 minutes.
So if you bring them up on your phone right now and watch it at 60 times speed, we can
all get done with them within about a minute.
OK, so I think we're probably all on the same page now.
We agree that player inclusivity is really important
to have in your games.
And it probably makes for better games.
And no, it definitely makes for better games.
Not probably.
What's wrong with me?
So you also might be coming to this talk
hoping and expecting me to be an expert to tell you
how to make your game diverse and what to strive for,
how to make a really excellent, diverse game.
You might even expect that this talk will be, oh, what?
Oh, no.
This killed my joke.
Comprehensive!
It's not.
Player inclusivity and diversity is a ginormous topic.
There's so much to cover, and I could not possibly
hope to cover it in a 30-minute talk.
If you want a longer version, and probably a better version
of this talk that's just all more encompassing
and expansive, I highly recommend
you check out this talk by Meg Giant,
10 Ways to Make Your Game More Diverse.
It's...
very broad and it is also very specific at the same time,
and it's just a great resource.
Please check it out.
Also, it features pictures of baby sloths and puppies.
And now my talk also features pictures
of baby sloths and puppies.
OK, so this isn't the be all, end all talk
on player inclusivity.
I'm not an expert.
In case you haven't noticed, I'm like a straight cis white dude.
I'm probably not the best person to be talking about this, but here I am.
So what is this talk about?
Well, Dream Daddy.
is a really cool game that had a lot of big dreams.
We knew we were kind of doing something really cool
and that had not been explored.
And we knew we wanted diversity and inclusivity
as a part of our game.
We felt it was pretty important.
But we had a short timeline to make the game
and we had a small budget.
So a lot of these big dreams and cool ideas we had
were.
Totally out of scope.
If we wanted to accomplish these things,
we had to find a way to make them work within our means.
So what we had to do was figure out a way
to add as much inclusivity and diversity and fun,
the primary thing we really want to make,
it's a fun game, with minimal scope increase.
If you're a developer, you are probably familiar
with the term scope, which is how much stuff
are you going to add to your game?
Or how much stuff are you going to add to a project?
We needed to find that balance of scope between budget and time.
So we needed minimal scope increases.
You could say we needed no scope increases.
Hi, I'm Tyler, did I mention I worked on a game
filled with dad jokes and bad puns.
I apologize for that.
The title of this talk, How We Created Player Inclusivity
and You Can Too, might better be summarized
as how we created player inclusivity while still being
mindful of our budget and our timeline.
And it made our game better, just overall.
Pretty cool.
So before we begin, there's a few exceptions
I would like to cover.
Your results may vary.
So, some exceptions.
Dream Daddy is not a perfect game.
I mean, like, I think we did a really great job on it,
but it's not the be-all, end-all for player inclusivity and diversity.
Again, these are really diverse topics,
and there's a lot of different ways you can approach this.
But I think we did some pretty cool stuff that's worth talking about.
Dream Daddy is a small game, which
allowed us to kind of experiment and do things that you might
not see in a very large game.
So as a result, some of the things we did
may not scale to a AAA game.
But I think they would work very well in any small budget,
or even a medium budget game that has a lot of heart.
Hopefully, though, the takeaway from this
is that you'll see some of the things we did,
and it might inspire you to come up with your own ideas
for larger projects and figure out
how to make things that scale and also don't eat
into your budget of your game.
Because if we can find a way to make our game inclusive
without spending millions of dollars,
Why wouldn't you, right?
So I think a lot of people seem to think that inclusivity
costs money or it's hard.
You need to have experts and stuff like that.
But you don't.
You just need to kind of be thoughtful
and take a step back sometimes.
OK.
The first way we did things.
Let's get to the obvious thing.
Sorry, this is zero indexed.
I'm a developer.
We told a story, Dream Daddy is a story that features a cast of hot dads who are gay or bisexual or, I don't know, sapiosexual maybe?
But one of the best ways to increase player inclusivity and diversity in your game is to feature characters who are diverse. I can't stress this enough.
Just do it. Tell diverse stories.
It improves the stories. It opens up new creative paths.
But I think everyone here probably knows this already.
If you're coming to a talk about how to increase player inclusivity,
you're probably like, yeah, let's tell stories about diverse characters.
So the next thing we added to Dream Daddy
that I think really helped increase player inclusivity
is a character creator.
A character creator is a fantastic way
to add diversity to your game, because players
are more diverse than I can predict, or you can predict,
or really anyone can predict.
So letting a player represent themselves instantly opens the experience up for them.
And providing players with plenty of options and choices
and how they represent themselves in a game is just fantastic.
The problem we ran into is dating sims and visual novels
normally don't have character creators,
so adding one into ours seemed a little like...
out of scope. Remember, we're on a budget. Adding a character creator to a visual novel,
that's totally out of scope. But we wanted one anyways. So we needed to figure out a
way to add one. We felt it was really important because obviously it helps players feel more
invested in the story. It allows players to be represented. Character creators are fun,
right? And also our character creator is going to be called Bill the Dad.
And it's for building dad sonas!
We gotta have that!
Except, character creators are usually expensive.
Assets, details, sliders.
On a small game like Dream Daddy,
we could never do something like this.
Or this.
Look at that.
Is it, say, jowl depth?
What is that?
Or this! This is an amazing character creator.
Like, really cool.
This one is a beautiful character creator from The Sims.
Look at all the choices of how you can make a pair of lips look
almost exactly the same to all these other pairs of lips.
This was really expensive, I bet.
But totally worth it for The Sims.
And this would have looked great in Dream Daddy.
Like, how cool would that be if your dads could look like that?
Here's a modified version of Skyrim's character creator.
Someone decided they didn't have enough sliders
and needed to add more sliders.
So people love character creators.
And the amount of effort and detail
that goes into building something like this,
it is really expensive.
And it's a lot of work.
But seriously, so awesome, guys.
Great job.
Please keep making character creators like this.
I love them.
I'm not here to tell you, don't make character creators.
So we wanted one of these.
So we had to do this.
K-I-S-S. If you know what this stands for,
it is keep it simple stupid.
We had to work within our means and come up with something
that we could manage.
So number one, things to building our buildadad,
no sliders.
Sliders are really complicated.
You have to create rules and boundaries for them.
None.
Sorry, Jerry O'Connell.
So we took a look at the original character
creator, Paper Dolls.
It's maybe not obvious that, hey, this
is a totally functional way to have a character creator.
And it's pretty simple.
You just slap things on top of each other.
Paper dolls are great, especially if you
have tons and tons of assets.
You can just start swapping images in and adding
all kinds of stuff.
But I can't stress how much money we did not
have to work with at all times.
So we needed to have some limited choices
in our character creator.
And we really wanted to make these choices count.
So to do that, we focused on big tonal shifts for assets
and options rather than subtle ones.
we can't afford to have a thousand pairs of lips
that all kind of look the same.
But we can afford to make big changes
and do things like create three body types
that are all varying in size and shape and are different.
So in Dream Daddy, you can play as this athletic guy,
a thick dad, and a slim daddy.
All of them are, I think,
pretty attractive.
They look great, and they're fun,
and they kind of encompass a wide range of body types.
The important thing is we didn't focus
on letting people adjust their shoulder to width to height
ratio, or their ulna size, or whatever, femur length.
Most people can identify with one of these body types
and say, hey, cool.
This represents me.
We also knew that once your dad Sona was built in the game,
you'd mostly be seeing him from the shoulders up.
So we focused on creating a lot of hair assets,
because this is one of the most distinguishing features
on a face, if you like.
looked at someone from 20 feet away,
you can't really focus on their eyes or nose shape,
but you can totally tell someone
who someone is just based on their hair.
So it's a really good way to get a lot of diversity.
So we focused on hair texture, color, silhouette,
all of these things that players use
to reflect a player's style, race, and gender identity.
We start off with a standard bald, but we also have a pompadour and a lot of hair colors
that are not just like white people, only hair.
So when you're making hair...
Oh, I forgot I added that in there.
This is an important hair option in all cases.
Make the effort to make as many hair options for your players
as possible, because hair is extremely diverse.
And we got a lot of bang for our buck just by adding lots
and lots of hair options.
created a pre-selected color palette.
And we did this for some specific reasons.
We did not add a full color gradient
so you could create any color skin
because we wanted to be representational
of skin colors specifically and not rainbows.
And if you give someone the ability
to pick one of 256 million colors,
it becomes really hard to find something
that actually you can kind of identify with.
So instead, we tried to just develop a nice range of skin colors.
And Leighton, here in the front, spent a long time going through
and just making sure we had a diverse rainbow of flesh tones.
This makes it really nice when you're actually building your character
to quickly identify, like, oh, here's some nice colors that I want to look at.
And I think Leighton went through and just kind of picked.
I think every color in Dream Daddy is a beautiful color,
and you can make a beautiful dad with it.
Overall, we aimed to focus on stylization over realism.
We didn't want our players to build an exact replica
of themselves.
We wanted them to build a cool dad Sona
that they could identify with.
Our goal was for people to self-identify and express
themselves.
So even though you can't tweak the focal distance
between eyeballs or jowl depth, you
can build a dad who looks cool.
And that, I think, is probably one of the most effective uses
of a character creator, saying, hey,
this is a cool version of myself or something
I aspire to be on screen.
That's fun.
Our next thing is fill in the blanks.
After announcing Dream Daddy online, before it came out,
there was a lot of excitement on the internet.
People talked about it all the time.
But there were also a few questions that came up.
Frequently, this was one.
I saw this a lot of.
on Twitter. How do all of these gay dads have kids? And I think the expectation of the person
asking this was usually to try and offer a counterpoint of like, this game's not possible
because gay dads can't have kids. And that's silly.
It's not 1999.
There's tons of avenues for gay couples to become parents.
And with Dream Daddy, we, of course,
wanted to cater to that.
If you've not played the game, Amanda
is your dad's son's daughter.
And one of the ways we wanted to answer this question
was to have the player answer it for themselves.
We're not in the business of telling you
exactly how you're going to play.
We want you to feel represented and included.
So of course, the first answer is Amanda could be adopted,
or she could be birthed by a surrogate,
or birthed by a partner, like a cis-female one.
Perhaps your dead sona is bisexual
or previously had a female partner.
Maybe it took them longer to come to terms
with their sexuality.
There's a lot of history and reasons why.
A gay man might have a child.
It could also be that your daughter was born by you
if you are a trans male, or born by a partner
who's a trans male.
There are a lot of ways that couples can have children.
And we wanted to cater to all of them.
Some of these, though, start to bring
in the question of a character, or your dad,
Sona's sexual orientation.
Because...
just because your dad is dating other dads,
that does not mean we should assume your dad, Sona, is gay.
But we also kind of want to know if your dad is gay, bi,
pansexual, sapiosexual, or heterosexual,
who is maybe coming to new realizations.
We wanted to make sure that, canonically, there
was a way for the player to represent
their diverse stories.
This was important to us.
Pretty quickly, when you start matching these up,
some of them are interlinked.
These options can turn into a complex decision tree
with lots of edge cases.
As I mentioned before, we had a small budget.
Poor.
This tree looks very expensive.
It would be nice to cater to and have specific stories
for every single case.
We couldn't do that.
So we had to ask ourselves, how do we
allow people to explore this without getting
into a crazy tree?
Or worse, doing something like this.
How many people have fun filling out one of these?
Okay, one person. Great.
Now, let me ask you this.
Can you imagine filling out one of these for sexual preferences?
I think it's already kind of awkward enough just for race,
but I imagine that getting into the nitty gritty of something like this
is even more awkward, and that's not necessarily an experience
we want our player to have.
this also can become technically complex.
And it doesn't make sense narratively
to all of a sudden have a questionnaire
at the end of your character creator of like,
hey, what's your sexual orientation?
How's your daughter here?
Fill us in.
And we obviously don't want to make people feel categorized.
The answer was narrative choices.
We realized that it doesn't actually,
we don't need to know your exact sexual orientation,
we don't need to know Amanda's exact status
of if she was born from surrogate or was adopted.
born by you, but by making our questions part of the narrative and making the questions
about Amanda and your relationship, we were able to, and keeping the questions simple,
it leaves the door open for a lot of scenarios, and it keeps you involved in your universe
of Dream Daddy.
So we don't.
deny a player's existence, we keep it open.
This allows us to acknowledge the player's preferences
without forcing them into a category.
So instead, we ask you, what was your ex-partner?
Did you call them father or mother?
Or did Amanda call them father or mother?
And we also ask you, you tell Amanda a story,
and if it was a story about when she was born
or when she was adopted.
We do this.
rather than in a questionnaire, in the actual game.
So we use a narrative where you are looking
through a series of old photographs,
and you go through and you basically tell Amanda
a series of stories about each photograph,
which helps us build your character's past.
I think this is ultimately more effective
in creating your dad's sona's canon.
than just filling out a questionnaire.
And also it lends to some, I think,
really beautiful and fun moments with Amanda,
where it kind of brings you to this area
of being a little sentimental
and going through some old photographs
with your daughter, who you love very much
and want to protect.
So,
next we have number three.
Enable your team with tools.
This is, I think, very important if you are like me and like a white guy who's non-diverse.
Something you can do is if you are in a position of leadership is make sure you're striving
as best as possible to make sure that everyone is heard and enable everyone on your team
to have access to creating and participating in the overall narrative and story of your
game.
With Dream Daddy, we had an evolving story
that was regularly changing.
And if we were building Dream Daddy using a node-based visual
novel tool like Twine or Yarn or Fungus,
we wouldn't necessarily have been
able to explore our character development
and make changes to the game simultaneously
with our teeny weeny budget.
Because the writers, Leighton and Vernon,
would write something, and then we'd
have to bring it into an engine and like,
translate things and then add scripting for characters sliding across and actions and changing their expressions.
Our writers would have been locked into time restraints with traditional dating sim tools,
and whatever they wrote would have required extra build time.
So this kind of sucks.
But I found this really cool tool called Ink.
I highly recommend it.
It's super easy to use, kind of.
I think Leighton sometimes has some,
she had some problems with it crashing once,
but that's fine, we figured it out.
For the most part, it's a great tool.
And it allowed our writers to have direct control of the game.
The only problem is it was geared
towards text-based games specifically,
and we were building a visual novel.
So, we created a tool called the DDML.
compiler. This is the Dream Daddy markup language compiler. It's based on an altered version
of Inc. syntax and it would allow us to generate every single scene in our game based on these
scripts. It was inspired by things like Ruby on Rails, which means you could just hand
it something and plop, there's everything in your scene. All of our animations, facial
expressions, eggplants, it would parse through this and figure everything out and build it
for you. Our entire Unity scene was just there. So look at that. Cool.
That got built not by me, but it was generated.
So our project became more agile.
We could iterate through concepts easier
than if we were building Dream Daddy
with the standard visual novel tools.
It allowed our story to keep changing
while still making progress on the rest of the games.
I stress that because diversity was something
we were conscientious of, and that
meant bringing in consultants with diverse points of view
and sexualities to look at our script.
So bring in experts and outside voices.
This is always a good idea.
We brought in lots of consultants,
and it helped Leighton and Vernon know
they were on the right track.
It helped them figure out parts that they maybe were not
happy with to have expert voices and identify things.
Consultants also may have increased our budget, I know.
But.
I don't think it changed our timeline,
and it was totally worth it, because it got us
to our final product faster.
By having outside consultants come in and give notes
on our scripts, we were able to get through things faster.
And having the DDML compiler made it easy for us
to listen to them and make changes
based on their suggestions.
Also, one of our consultants for the game happened to be this like kinda popular famous
musician.
He's a gay man who loves dads, if you follow his Twitter.
And he came in and checked out Dream Daddy.
And he really, really loved it.
And as a result of doing this, he went home
and he wrote the theme song for Dream Daddy
because he loved it so much.
And this would have never happened
if we had not brought him in as a consultant
to consult just on the script in general.
We weren't hiring him as a musician,
we were hiring him for his opinions.
But as like, just synergy, so.
Do it. It's great. Also pay people. We paid our consultants. Don't forget to pay your consultants.
It's important. Their voices are important.
It's going to make everything better. I promise.
Okay.
The devils and the details.
Dream Daddy had a problem.
It had gendered pronouns in a lot of places.
And we went through the game. We discovered that sometimes we were using gendered pronouns when we didn't need to.
We wanted to change this, but remember,
our game is on a budget, and doing something like this
is totally actually fine and in scope.
It was actually really easy.
If you're not doing this, please start doing it now.
It cost us nothing to be conscientious.
Vernon and Leighton just went through
and tried to remove a lot of gendered pronouns
when referring to groups.
So right now, if you want, you can go through your game
and find, for example,
any place where you use the phrase,
ladies and gentlemen, and try saying something else,
like, treasured guests, fellow humans,
good people of Earth.
or even esteemed buttheads.
Regardless, the important thing is this forced us
to think outside of a comfort zone
and think outside of the box.
And the results were that we ended having a lot more fun
and I think richer text
with the dialogue that Ferdinand Leighton wrote.
Like, there's some great stuff in there.
It got us to a better place than if we'd just left it.
Okay.
You'll probably make mistakes.
DreamDaddy's not perfect.
And if you're not constantly checking things,
even if you are constantly checking things,
things still might fly under the radar.
In the start of the game, here's a mistake we made.
In the start of the game, you have the option
of sleeping with Robert the first time you meet him.
If you do this, you unlock an achievement called Bad Dad.
And some players interpret this as us chastising them
for expressing their sexuality, when in reality,
we did not mean that at all.
We literally just meant this because Robert's the bad dad.
He's got a leather jacket.
And he likes knives.
So we did not even consider that.
You can't win them all.
And it's not going to be perfect, but please don't let this prevent you from trying.
And please don't let a fear of this prevent you from attempting to make inclusive games.
This might happen.
For instance, be careful with that old, unfinished, never meant to be published thing you might
have left lying around in your code.
It turns out if people really like your game,
they will find it.
And they will publish it on the internet.
And they will talk about it like it's canon.
And they will have a lot of opinions and thoughts
on something that maybe wasn't even
meant to see the light of day.
We were still figuring it out.
So take a deep breath.
There will be criticism, but this is a good thing.
It will either be something you can change now
or change in the future.
Listen to it.
Fear of imperfection should not prevent you from trying to be inclusive at all.
Just go for it.
If you get it right, for someone that normally doesn't get a slice of the pie, you've made
progress and I think on the whole, you've done a good thing.
So you may not be able to cater to every single person on earth, but if you manage to do it
for someone who's not normally being catered to, who doesn't normally get to see themselves
represented, A+.
Okay, here's the final thing.
This is an important takeaway.
Four hours of time invested.
And let me see if we can figure out if it was worth it or not.
We included an option in Dream Daddy to do this.
So what this is...
is it's a binder.
And we wanted to include a binder option
for player characters who wanted to play as a trans male.
And this is a way to do that without checking a box
or questioning someone.
But it does recognize like, hey.
you might be a man who wears a binder and we want to provide you with that
representation. It took us four hours investment to make this change to our
game. We had assets already. All we had to do was kind of change up some
appearances and like drop it in. We'd kind of already built everything so it
was really easy to do. We were able to do this because we kind of built things out
and all we needed to do was just be conscientious of it.
Let's find out if this was worth it or not.
What do you guys think?
All right.
So four hours of investment in time
garnered results like this, and this, and this, and this.
As a fat trans man, there's little representation
for me and my brothers in similar body types.
Thank you all so much for this rep.
When I saw you could just casually make a Transbinder wearing Dad, I kind of almost cried.
As a gay trans guy, the trans options in the game made me cry.
It was touched.
Thank you for representation, Dream Daddy.
I'm in tears.
Sorry, it was hard to go through and read all of these.
There's a lot.
Canon trans characters and options that make your Dad so into trans literally brought tears
to my eyes.
Literally in tears about Dream Daddy.
This one really means a lot of support that I've never gotten from a game before.
This one. I love this one.
I'm crying. My dad actually looks like me.
Thank you so much for having heavier and trans options.
He's a cool dad-ass.
Thank you all very much.
I may have run long.
I don't know if there's time for questions.
Nope, there's no time for questions.
So if you have questions, meet me over in the Overlook room
on the second floor.
Thank you all so much for coming and watching me.