Hello, I'm Scaff Elias.
I work at a company called Three Donkeys with Richard
Garfield.
You've probably heard of him and not me.
And I worked at Wizards of the Coast for a long time, for
many, many years.
About 10 years ago, we started this consulting business and
just sort of go around and help people with their games.
I was supposed to ask everyone to silence their cell phones.
Thanks.
Yeah, the one piece of advice the assistant gave me
was to not choke.
So I will attempt to not do that.
As recently as 24 hours ago, I thought
this was a 60-minute talk due primarily
to a lack of intelligence.
And so good luck, as the audience.
You're going to have to do your best Calvin Johnson
impersonations and catch what I am throwing.
So, luck and skill in games.
The talk's primarily about how luck and skill interact with each other.
And why do we care?
We care because a lot of times you'll hear complaints, there's too much luck in a game,
there's too much skill in a game, and it matters a lot to your audience, and it matters more
and more to your audience as time goes on, the longer they associate themselves with
your game.
Virtually every definition of game that you'll find
will state that some amount of indeterminacy is required.
And those definitions that don't state it explicitly imply it.
It is a necessary part of what it means to be a game.
And what creates indeterminacy, well, randomness does.
So we get to luck and skill, and we try to start defining these.
And we find that, first of all, they're
very difficult to define.
Colloquially, we have some understanding of these.
When we try to nail down very strict definitions,
it can often turn out that they lead
to counterintuitive results.
And I think that's a problem.
Exactly how to define it, we're not
going to be too careful with.
But how they interact with each other
is sort of what we'll be talking about.
So overt randomness in games.
This is actually easy to see.
It's easy to define.
It happens a lot.
You can have dice, cards, random number generators.
And that's clearly going to add a degree of randomness
to your game.
Some things that may be less clear
are game-theoretic randomness that
comes from, say, simultaneous decisions, other players,
politics.
There's a lot of other ways besides sort
of overt randomness.
And then, of course, there's physical and mental
limitations.
Your memory.
Your accuracy, throwing darts at a dartboard,
that's clearly random.
Again, it's not completely random,
but for all practical purposes, it's
random within a certain set of parameters.
Your speed, your strength, these are the sorts of things
that create randomness in games.
way to have randomness in a game is maybe you have a simple choice between two doors.
Door A leads to victory and door B leads to success.
Or, sorry, failure.
And so it's pretty clear, right?
The ogre's behind one door and the treasure's behind the other.
It's completely random.
But what if you had some information about the doors that maybe you don't even see at
first?
There's a very complex way that you could have figured out what was behind door A.
one door and what was behind the other.
And this choice that was random to you,
if you decide that you can't figure out these equations,
is it really random?
Is it really randomness in the game?
Or is it a matter of skill?
So oftentimes, when you ask people
to name a game that has no luck in it,
chess is the first thing that pops up.
Because there's no overt elements.
There's no hidden decisions.
And so it seems, it feels like, this
should be a game where it's a game of pure skill.
My business partner Richard has often said, oh, maybe one day
he'll play Garry Kasparov at chess.
And to sort of prove that there's randomness in chess,
he'll just play randomly.
and win. And it's clear that he can do this.
Garry Kasparov has not won every chess game he's ever played
and as long as there is some set of moves
that will lead to victory against him,
Richard can stumble upon it. Unfortunately,
his chances are better winning the New York State Lottery 15 times in a row.
So he shouldn't go betting a lot of money on
playing against Gary.
But the point is that there is randomness in this game,
unless, of course, Gary has the entire move tree memorized
in his head, and he has a response regardless
of what that random move is.
It feels for a game like chess that it should be pure skill.
And sometimes we forget that chess
is quantitatively different than tic-tac-toe.
It's not qualitatively different.
And tic-tac-toe is a game where you can observe people playing.
And it's very similar to the situation of the Concealed
Doors, where
You and I may not experience randomness when we play it,
but children do.
And it's very interesting.
There's been some reports done on this,
of watching children play.
And you can find that the results are mapped very
similarly.
in character to the results of chess players playing
against each other, where you'll have a set of people where it's
virtually purely random.
Some people are better.
They're able to see a little bit in the decision tree,
so they're making less mistakes.
And then some people have the game essentially solved.
We're probably too far behind that, but the past.
our memory of tic-tac-toe to remember when it seemed random,
when it seemed difficult. And we had to make a guess when we
didn't for sure know what the next best move was.
So the point to this is that the amount of luck in a game
is not a function of the game itself.
It's a function of the game and the player.
And that's something that's very important to understand.
Let's take another pure skill game, like chess.
It's not the most fun game, but it's still a game.
And you've got 30 seconds to compute the 50,347,200th digit
of pi.
Does anyone want to play?
And you take a guess.
It's obvious to us.
It may not be so obvious if we look at a game like chess,
that there is randomness in it.
But it is obvious that in this game, there is randomness in it
because this is impossible to compute in the amount of time.
However.
Again, without changing the character of the game,
we can say, what's the fourth digit of pi?
And now when we're playing this game,
this is inside the scope of the human mind
and with a little simple memorization.
Now all of a sudden, this game that was purely random
has no more randomness associated with it.
The point about this game is that.
It's not just about the game and not just about the players,
but it actually changes over time.
Even if you sort of understood the complexity
of the human brain to a much higher degree
than we'll ever understand, and even
if you understood exactly the calculations required
to play the previous game.
If when you play the fourth digit of pi game in 2000 BC,
it's purely random.
It's no different than when those people are guessing
the 50 millionth digit of pi.
And when you play it around 250 BC,
it all of a sudden becomes an incredibly skill testing game.
Archimedes around this time starts figuring out within,
his guess would be between three different digits.
And now, in 2000 AD.
or 2013, there's, again, no randomness left in the game.
And there's a very little bit of skill, but there is some.
And the interesting thing here is
that you can't determine by looking at the game,
or even the capabilities of the players,
you can't determine how much randomness
there is in the game.
It's something that varies over time.
So we think we have an idea of what these pure luck
things mean in a game.
But what does it mean to have skill at a game?
Well, the dictionary definitions of skill
are the ability to do something well.
Another way to say it is it's an intrinsic ability
to achieve a differential outcome in a game.
And note that all of these things, with the word well,
or, um,
trying to achieve one outcome over another,
hinge on the fact that skill is essentially a comparison.
And so the measurements of skill that we have,
like an ELO rating system or whatever,
are always comparisons.
That's the best way to get at what it means
to have skill in a game.
When you ask people,
Is this game more skill testing than another game?
Does game A have more skill than game B?
How do we measure that?
Is there a simple way that we can do that?
Well, when you ask, say, students in a class
or sit around and have a discussion about it,
some of the things that pop up are, what's
your maximum win percentage?
There's an intuitive thought for people that.
If a game is very skill testing, the best player,
a pro at that, should essentially always beat
the worst player at the game.
It's pretty clear if the best player in the world
has a 50% win chance against the worst player in the world,
let's say the game is cutting for high card,
there's no skill in the game.
And the higher that number goes, in some sense,
there is more skill in the game.
Another common way of defining how much skill there is in a game, and this is actually a very interesting and effective one because it leads to, say, social structures that might develop around the game or the metagame of the game, is how many different buckets can you put people into where bucket two has a 75% chance of beating the bucket from people one?
How long is that chain?
The longer that is, I think almost everybody would say
there's more skill in that game.
The ELO rating, which I think probably most people are
familiar with, it's the chess rating system.
Lots of video games use it.
It's been altered over time.
Actually can reconstruct, if the assumptions that ELO made
are true, can reconstruct that level of the chains of skill.
And what it does is it sort of assumes a random performance
on people's part.
And actually, he's pretty good at modeling
a lot of different games.
But the complete set of information
is actually a much, much, much more complicated thing.
If you really want to know how much skill there is a game,
you would need to know the true expected win
percentage of every single player versus every other
player over time.
This is not something you're going to be able to get.
This is virtually impossible.
And how the curves of player performance change
is actually very interesting, because it is not
easy to a simple linear parameterization
of the level of skill of people.
So you have to choose what you're
going to measure, because you're only going
to be able to take a slice.
And you have to choose wisely.
Let's take, for example, this game we'll call rando chess.
We like to use sample games because sometimes it actually
gets to the heart of the matter more than, say,
a real game does.
So you play a normal game of chess,
and then afterward you roll a die.
And then on a one, whoever lost the game,
they are declared the winner.
Well, rando chess clearly has more luck than chess does.
But does it have less skill?
When you think about it, any sort
of these reasonable definitions of skill
that you had beforehand in your intuition
are that really, actually, it doesn't have any less skill.
And what do I mean by that?
All of your previous skills are still useful.
Your player ranking of every single player in the world
has not changed at all.
you still have the same world champion.
You still have all of the chess books.
You still have all the opening moves.
You still have every little bit of effort
and every little bit of skill that you
would want to acquire to win chess.
That's all still existing in the game of rando chess.
And the point to that is that this skill versus luck
is actually a false dichotomy.
Really, you should think of it more as a graph where
you have a certain amount of skill in games
and a certain amount of luck in games.
And games can be sort of placed anywhere on that.
Go has a lot of skill, as does poker.
But poker has more luck.
So what did change in Rando Chess?
The game clearly changed.
Skill, by a reasonable definition of it, didn't change.
But what did change was, as luck went up,
skill became harder to measure.
In order to achieve that same ranking,
you would actually need more trials than before.
Another way to say that your skills is harder to measure
is that you get less payoff in terms of your victories
for the same amount of skill.
So when you add luck to a game and you make skill harder
to measure, what's happened?
Is that bad?
It may very well be bad, because maybe your players
expect a very high payoff for the amount of skill
that they've acquired at the game.
They have, after all, put a lot of effort into it.
And key to understanding this is understanding
what the value proposition of your game is for your players.
For instance, if you're playing a competitive game
and there's some payoff or skill.
As those players continue to play that game or that genre
of games over time, and they put more and more time and effort
into mastering that game, they may very well
expect a higher and higher payoff for their skill.
And that's how you get things like fighting games becoming
more and more skill testing over time.
If you're a dedicated customer of these sorts of things,
again, for a competitive game, where inherently in the setup
it's you versus the other person on an emotional level
as well as.
sort of a rules level.
It's not unlikely that you're going to be very upset
when your payoff for skill gets lowered.
So, should we remove all indeterminacy from games?
When you do that, you can run into trouble
if you make your game too skill testing.
You can play the game, who's taller?
And then when you do that, it's no longer a game
because you've removed the indeterminacy.
Really, it's more of a measurement.
And measurements are fun to play at most once.
When you look at games.
on our luck versus skill graph, you
can see things like a foot race.
There's really not that much randomness in a foot race.
People's times do vary, but they vary
by a relatively small amount.
And that's why, back to the measurement thing,
how many times is it fun to take a measurement,
you'll see grade school children will play foot race.
And they'll play it once or maybe twice.
And there's not a lot of people in high school or.
post-college or elderly people playing the game foot race.
And there's a strong reason for that.
And that's because it's not that fun to play time
after time after time.
Whereas you can have games that have more skill associated
with them.
And again, by more skill, you can
take a sort of empirical measurement
of the amount of training that people do to become
world-class sprinters.
as compared to world-class soccer players,
and see that it's less in order to achieve
the top of the profession.
But there's a lot more luck in these sorts of things.
And you can look at this chart and say, oh, I kind of
understand intuitively that I may not
want to reduce my indeterminacy by too much.
I don't want to skip over this too quickly,
but there are other benefits of luck and randomness in games
that we are not talking about.
There's a million benefits to randomness in games.
For instance, people are just enthralled
by unexpected outcomes.
Specifically, though, since we're talking about the luck
and skill interaction, that's a subject for another talk.
So when you add luck to a game, because you've
looked at this chart and you see, oh, well, look,
golf's sitting there.
A lot of people play golf more than play foot race.
And what are some of the benefits
of adding luck to a game?
Well, one of the benefits is that when you play
a game that has luck in it, we saw this a lot with Magic,
The Gathering.
People would tend to blame.
their success is on skill and they would blame their defeats
on luck. That's great. That's an amazing psychological crutch
for your players that makes people much happier playing the
game even though they're losing. Because there is an overt
randomness to it, it gives them something to very clearly fall
back on. The problem is over time, you sort of, the more and
more experienced players are, the less and less this illusion
will hold up.
and they understand that it really is their fault.
But the great benefit of this is that early on in a player's
career, they may get ego boosts when they're first
starting to play the game.
Another benefit of adding luck to the game is the amount of
people that you can have fun with, that is to say, play an
indeterminate game, goes up.
In a game with really low luck, you can have
Most games be too hard or too easy,
and they're not fun to play.
Again, it's closer to a measurement.
It's a very difficult problem to solve today.
With the internet and computers and matching systems,
you can find that just right person
if your audience is big enough.
And the problem is that even after you
find that exact right person who you're
going to have a fun game against.
You might find the right person in terms of skill,
but are they the right person?
Are they the friend that you want to play with?
Maybe you want to play with your family.
You want to sit around a living room.
So this ability of matching the internet and computers
to solve this problem doesn't help.
If I want to play with Timmy and my game is so skill testing
that it's not fun to play, then I
have to think that maybe I'm playing the wrong game.
As we mentioned before with the fighting games,
payoff for skill is something that players, especially
in games where reward for skill is extremely important,
say poker, over time they may expect to get
a higher and higher payoff.
But because luck can broaden audiences,
Phil is probably not so upset that.
poker has less payoff for the skill that he's put into it.
He would much rather be the prince of the set of all poker players, top 10 or 20,
than he would be the undisputed number one of an audience the size of, say, Go players.
The situation is a lot more complex than you can see from something like the ELOS system,
because a one-dimensional parameterization of the amount of skill that people have doesn't necessarily...
really tell you what's going on. However, and you can actually
see that. There's some sample things here you can see. For
instance, there might be an element of luck in the game
that's only accessed if you have high skill. Maybe when you go
really, really far into the game, you're an amazing, amazing
player, then you're able to access this bonus level. Once
you hit that bonus level, there's a random, you know, 99%
of your score gets access to that bonus level. What that sort
of thing will do is if you add that to your game.
You have reduced, you've increased the luck between top
players playing against each other and you haven't changed
it at all for your lower level players and you haven't
changed it at all for when your higher level players play
against your lower level players.
Same sort of thing can also happen because
Some elements of randomness can only
be accessed by playing poorly, like maybe a Shell and Mario
card or something like that.
So how your skill curve of each person
and how they interact with each other,
and how much skill there is, and how much randomness there
is in their interactions is actually
a very complicated situation.
We'll take this example.
Maybe you have a real-time strategy game.
you can have randomized prices or technologies in it.
Before randomization, maybe it's very clear
what the best strategy is.
The best strategy is to build a tank.
And you have three different players.
And their ratings are, you have two excellent players.
The game is primarily based upon, say,
hand-eye coordination, tactical skill, that sort of thing.
Your strategic choices aren't really that important.
But then you play, and the prices
have become randomized between all these objects.
So all of a sudden, maybe dragons
are a viable strategy now.
They were overpriced before, but now that's the way to go.
Well, you've clearly added skill to the game.
For the player to decide in the beginning
what the proper choice is is an area of skill and mastery.
So maybe player A can now beat player B more often.
That 100 point rating differential between them
might expand.
The levels in your skill chain might actually go up.
At the same time, maybe the best skilled player in the world
can only pick the right thing 90% of the time.
And player C.
picks the right thing 10% of the time.
Well, if the strategic choices outweigh all of the hand-eye
coordination and all of the tactical skill
that you could develop at that game, guess what?
The win differential, the expected win differential
between player A and player C will now go down,
even though it went up with player A versus player B.
So how do you use all this information?
Since basically what you.
sort of, the more you look at it, the more you realize how complicated the situation is.
Well, I would start by saying you have to know who your audience is.
You have to know what your intended audience is.
And what's your key value proposition to them?
Do they expect that it's a highly competitive game?
Do they expect a high reward payoff for their skill?
Is it going to be played around the family dinner table?
I mean, if it is, you better make sure
that you can have a highly indeterminate game among almost
any set of people that are there.
Is it going to be played over the internet?
Is it going to be played solo?
All of these things will tell you.
how much randomness you ideally would have in your game
in order to get a significantly consistent amount
of indeterminacy in each instance of that game.
Does your revenue model require replays?
This is a really important consideration.
Again, back to the foot race example.
If your revenue model says.
I want this person to come back and play again and again and
again and again. You want to stay as far away from that
measurement as possible unless perhaps you have a truly
enormous audience. So you know that you can always match that
person up perfectly against someone who is almost at exactly
their skill level. It's a very hard thing to do, but it is
possible. Another important consideration is do your IP and
marketing match your skill and luck interaction?
Mario and the dragon from RTS sample game number seven
are not the sorts of things which appeal
to the type of players that are going to want to play
a game like Go, which has an extremely, extremely,
extremely long skill chain, very high reward ratio
for the skill that you achieve at the game,
and it's extremely competitive.
And sorry that the talk was so short.
I had to skip over some things.
Richard and Robert and I wrote a book, Characteristics of Games.
A lot of this stuff's in there if you
want to read more about it.
Any questions?