Thank you all so much for coming.
My name is Abhi.
I'm the designer and writer of Venba.
And this is my talk.
I'm calling it Lore Don't Tell, a guide for telling culturally rooted stories.
So what is Venba?
Venba is a narrative cooking game where you play as a immigrant Indian mother who moves to Canada in the late 1980s with her family.
and her travel to Canada, her recipe book gets damaged.
So as a result, players have to cook various South Indian dishes to restore these lost recipes while also exploring this family story.
The game explores the relationships within a family and how it grows and changes over time, but it does that through the lens of food.
The problem I see a lot is that showcasing a culture in media can be very challenging, especially if it's a culture that an international audience isn't necessarily familiar with.
If it's a culture that's familiar, you can just focus on telling the story, but when it's not, you feel a need to tell not just a story, but also educate in the ways of the culture in addition to telling the story.
You almost want to set up the context so that players can understand the story you're telling.
But ironically, I find that this leads to worse storytelling.
The story and plot now serve two purposes.
Not only does it have to do justice to the characters, it also has to educate.
And anytime you could do that, you could be telling the story instead.
So the solution to this problem already exists.
It's what we call lore.
With Venba, I got a lot of praise for how it portrayed the culture in a very unassuming way.
Someone said Venba just exists.
It doesn't say or do what it is.
It just presents itself, right?
And people asked a lot of questions about how I wasn't worried about the specific, hyper-specific details that I showed, about players missing those details, et cetera, et cetera.
And when I was trying to explain why it felt right for me to tell the story in this way, and add these details in this way, I realized I was essentially describing what we all understand to be lore.
In most media, there's plot and there's lore, right?
Plot is told to the player, but lore exists for the player to discover.
In fantasy settings, we are often thrust into worlds and cultures that are drastically different from ours.
But in those settings, not everything is explained to the player.
Often things are left unsaid.
The author alone might know these details to flesh out the world, but they heavily leverage the lore to do it instead of using the plot.
So why should real-world cultures be any different?
Before I start going into specific examples, I want to address one thing.
I think when we try to tell culturally rooted stories, we put a lot of pressure on ourselves to make sure we capture all of it, right?
And I definitely understand this responsibility.
I think this also causes an insecurity in us because we know that to tell this culture is not something people might be familiar with.
But I think we need to let go of that insecurity.
My favorite Tamil movie director, Vetri Maran, would often say, the more local you are, the more international you become.
So to me, that means tell a very hyper-specific story, and somehow it feels more universal that way.
And the strength of the stories we tell is that it's different and unique, and we shouldn't dumb it down and risk losing that.
Let me start by going to specific examples.
So one thing I see is a lot of times we, in an eagerness to communicate to the player, we start treating the familiar as unfamiliar.
What I mean by that is that
If we want the players to engage with our world and the things in our world, and as if they are familiar cornerstones, we have to treat it as familiar first.
So when a player is thrust into the world of Venba, they may or may not be familiar with Tamil culture and Tamil cuisine, but Venba and Pavlin are experts, right?
And there's a dissonance here between the knowledge of the players and the knowledge of the characters.
But if I write the game in a way that the characters explain the different aspects of the culture, then these characters themselves are acting as if the culture is something that needs to be explained.
I never talk about idli or dosa in a way that, oh, it's a fermented rice batter.
I don't talk about it that way.
I just say idli and dosa, right?
Because I know what it is.
But if I try to account for players who don't, Venba and Pavlin are starting to act like they don't know what idli and dosa is.
So instead, I think it's better to lean into the dissonance instead.
Aggressively don't explain anything, and don't explain anything that these characters normally wouldn't.
If it's not a conversation that they would normally have, then don't bother.
And I think this actually creates a feeling that these characters aren't here for the player, or in service of the player.
They're here regardless, and the player is just here along for the journey.
There is one level in Venba where Venba cooks a variety of dishes, like a marathon.
And I don't tell the players what the name of these dishes are in English.
So a lot of times during playtesting, players are like, these dishes look so good.
I want to cook them.
What are they called, right?
And this is the most common feedback I got for this particular level.
The feeling I wanted to recreate in this level is Wenba creating dish after dish after dish, right?
So it's complete contrast to the other levels where there's only one dish you create.
So the way to address that feedback is, some people said, why don't you put a title at top of the dish when the final thing is presented so players know what they're cooking.
And this is a completely valid ask, and we almost considered it.
But then it struck me, how absurd would it be if I showed pizza and large letters showed up saying pizza, right?
So here, the game itself, from the UI itself, it's trying to acknowledge that
if I showed those titles that these dishes are not something you should be familiar with.
Instead, if you go the other way, yes, it leads to some player frustration, but it at least cements the fact that these are the bread and butter for Venva and Pavlin.
And just like how it's important to familiarize, keep familiar things familiar, you can do the opposite to reinforce what is unfamiliar for these characters.
So when Wenba speaks in Tamil, the default text color is white.
And throughout the game, that's how it remains.
But when a character speaks in English, the text color changes.
This treats speaking English as a special occurrence, which makes sense for these characters.
And it's not something normal to the players, right?
But by default, when one of the members was implementing the language tags, by default it would be English, and you'd have to tag it to make it dumber.
So that also led to the different colors, right?
But I had to reverse that very consciously.
Because it makes sense for all of us growing up here, the English does feel like the default, but you have to make sure that that doesn't bleed into the game itself.
The other thing I want to bring up is, where does all of this stem from?
I think it stems from an eagerness for the game to be a good representation, but often it leads into it trying to be representative.
talk.
And it's important to remember that we are a representation, we are not the representation.
But you might be seen as the representation by the players, but that's a problem of not enough pieces like Pinball or other games existing.
But if you do try to be representative, it leads to the game feeling more like a tour guide than a story that you're saying.
This line can actually get really, really blurry when you're in production.
So with Venba, I knew that a lot of the players were interested in it for the story.
But I also know that a lot more players were interested in it because it's about South Indian food, and they were really excited about it.
So a lot of the feature requests that we got were things like, can we understand what these dishes are?
Can we get trivia about them?
Can we get their recipes?
And all these things, right?
And these are very, very reasonable asks.
I felt the need to cater to them a bit, and catering to these things might seem innocent enough, and in fact it makes the game much more commercially viable if we say that, oh, play Wenba to learn how to cook.
But I specifically was very careful about avoiding this, and whenever people ask, can we play Wenba to learn how to cook, I would just say,
talk.
they can't walk away with a complete understanding of the dish itself.
And you have to be specifically careful about this when working with publishers or merchandising because these are the aspects that appeals to them and these are the things that they might push for.
But you're not creating a product, you're trying to tell a story.
So instead, what I did was, the thing is that I'm also very, very passionate about South Indian food.
And I do like to tell people, oh, Italy is made of three days rice fermented batter and things like that, right?
And similarly, Benba is also very passionate.
So I, I was able to find organic ways of Benba geeking out about food and treating that as a way to give the players more insight and more trivia about the recipe.
So there are ways to find it, it just has to be more subtle.
If you're not giving players these things, but what you can do is inspire them to seek more for themselves, especially when it's a real-world culture.
So for example, this is how every level in the game starts, by showing this calendar and there's a small proverb.
I never explain what these proverbs are called, what these collections of proverbs are called, why are they here.
I don't explain any of these things.
But the thing is, that proverb, it's actually called a venba.
And venba is named after these poems.
So there is a question of, is this game named after these poems or after the main character?
And even though it's so subtle like this, I saw so many people looking up these proverbs, trying to find out where they're from.
People found, like, dumber subreddits, and they were like, oh, can you translate this for me?
Where can I read more of this, right?
that's
This is important because these gaps are important for us to leave.
If I made a playlist, then it becomes much more authoritative, and it becomes the one source, right?
And if I make a guide for, go look at these things, it mutes that discussion.
But when players have questions, it actually generates more discussion.
So I think it's really, it's actually effective to leave these gaps.
I'm
and you can do that either with the framing, so with the food, like it was really important for me to make it look really delicious and sound really good and all of that because whenever I cook, I know which part of the recipe step I get excited about, right?
So visually, it was very easy to push for that.
And similarly, the characters in Venba are also deeply passionate about thermoculture.
So just seeing that passion is infectious and that's what leaves a lasting impression on the player.
So players might not always see lore, but they'll definitely feel it.
And I'll give you some examples of that.
Every level in Wenba also starts with this photo wall, right?
And on the left side, you'll see a photo frame of Wenba and her parents.
And on the right side, you see more modern day photos of her family in Canada.
So I really, really like that I did this because photos in India, especially back in the day, people just took them and they would cut them out of pictures.
They weren't really made to any standard sizes.
So it's very clear to me that Venba brought pictures of her family from India to Canada.
There's no frames that fit in, so she put two photos in and made a frame out of it.
And as the photos took in Canada, they come for a very specific frame size, right?
For a lot of Indian players, when they see this, they're like, yeah, I absolutely have a photo like this in my home.
They immediately catch that.
But players who are not necessarily from the same culture, they still get this same feeling.
I don't have to explain all of these things.
They're able to connect the gaps.
And this gives so much personality.
And if I shy away from showing something like that, because players wouldn't understand it, they wouldn't be thinking about it in this way.
And if I did explain it, it would be boring.
So I think this is a really nice line to walk.
So another thing I did that was very subtle is once again bringing back this example between English and Tamil is that something that really bothers me about diaspora media is when people write dialogues in English and there's a very first generation immigrant speaking.
I can tell when it was written by an assimilated person and not an assimilated person because sentence structures change when your language changes.
Your thoughts change when your language changes.
So if you write in English from the get-go, Venba is speaking English.
So to avoid that, I actually wrote all the Tamil dialogues in Tamil first, and then I translated them into English.
This might seem like a lot of effort, but language is thoughts, right?
Like sometimes I have to consciously switch in which language I'm thinking to flesh out that thought better.
So it was much easier to capture that authenticity if the dialogues were written in Tamil first.
And similarly for Thavin, who's more assimilated,
a lot
She was able to recognize that very consciously because she's summer, but I think every player still feels the same feeling They're like all these feelings add up right into fleshing out this world.
It might just not be that explicit
So if culture is lore, we should also make peace with the fact that lore is meant to be miscible.
A core essence of fleshing out a world is giving the players a feeling that they don't fully understand this world yet, and there's parts that they haven't seen yet.
There's a lot of details and subtext that I've crammed into Venpa, but that by definition means players won't see everything.
They'll miss some things, they won't connect things individually.
But this means more to the players that don't miss it, right?
Because they're able to connect it because they have had a certain similar experience or maybe they're from that culture.
But even for the players that do miss it, this gap actually creates a lot of depth.
So I'm really wary about filling the gap just because people miss it.
So in the spoilers, in the fifth level, Benba's husband Pavelin passes away.
And the way I communicate that is by a single shot of Pavelin's photo and his glasses and the book because he's a writer.
Culturally, this is a big difference between the West and South India, specifically.
We don't hang photos, or we don't use to hang photos of ourselves unless a person passes away.
And especially when it's framed this way, as a singular photo of him, people who saw that and it's black and white, they immediately got, if they're from Tamil Nadu, they immediately got that, oh, Pawan passed away.
But for a lot of other players, they didn't get that.
until maybe the level ended or maybe even after when they see Coven wearing Pavelin's glasses.
And this might seem like a issue to address and to make it more explicit, but it's not the worst thing if they don't connect the dots immediately, right?
If you let the question linger in their head, that actually creates a lot of interest.
Like if they're playing the game thinking, wait, what happened to that?
What happened to that?
and then they finally find out, they're more engaged also.
So it's not absolutely the worst thing.
And then they're like, okay, so that photo then retroactively they can make the connection.
And when you make connections like that, you really learn the culture, you really feel the culture.
We might all feel this when we go to different countries or different cultures.
We just observe certain things that are different and we're not quite sure why they're different and then we'll understand it slowly.
So playing Venva essentially gives that same experience.
There's also, okay, I know I said lore is meant to be miscible and all of that, but I'm just going to go through some details that I'm a little annoyed that not enough people noticed.
So this one is when they revealed the Puttu scene, and I really love it, but it's a direct reference
to this movie, and even though you didn't have to have seen this movie, like the comedy of the scene is captured here.
And similarly, the dad, Pavelin, has a very striking resemblance to one of my favorite actors, so much so that from the beginning that's been the reference.
And then here, Venba's cooking biryani, which is one of the most complicated recipes, but Venba is such a good cook, her confidence comes through just in the way the dishes and utensils come in, right?
She's excited to cook, and therefore the player is excited to cook.
And when she pours the oil, she's just, you know, shotgunning it, right?
talk.
This might be the most subtle one.
In one of the levels where you cook with ghee in Canada, the ghee is semi-solid, and you put it into the pan, and then it melts.
But when you cook with ghee in India, because the room temperature is higher, it's already melted to start with.
And when I asked my team, they're like, oh, we already have a ghee acid.
I'm like, no, it needs to be liquid.
They're like, no one's going to notice, but it's important for me.
So, a lot of these details might feel very self-indulgent, and it is.
All these movie references and everything is very, very self-indulgent for me, but it makes it so much more worth it when even one person notices.
And the main point is that even if other people don't notice it, they will feel it.
They will feel that when they're stacked with details and there's this world that they haven't quite discovered yet.
Every opportunity, every, I know indie developers sometimes groan at achievements, but for me, achievements are just so liberating, because they were just this window of places where I can cram even more references, even more details, and showcase what are the things I like about my culture.
Yeah, and that's pretty much it.
That's how I approached Venva.
And yeah, I think, I definitely understand that we all feel the need to
Make sure that players understand what's cool about our culture and make sure that we convey what we find interesting and do it properly.
But if we let go of that a bit and we make peace with the fact that some players might miss it, I think it does make for a better product.
Thank you so much.
We can do questions, if anybody wants to do questions.
If not, please remember to fill out your evaluation forms.
Hi, I'm Yu-Sun Chung from Electronic Arts.
I really enjoyed this talk.
Thank you so much.
And I really like the visual, and I really like the use of color.
And yeah, I think the food, I can't wait to go to the game and start making those myself.
Awesome.
Which platform is this game available also?
Canada was referred in the presentation.
Did you make it in Canada?
Yeah.
So I came to Canada when I was 12 and when I was inspired by a lot of the families I saw in Canada.
We're out on pretty much every platform.
PC, Switch, PS5, Xbox.
We're also on a massive sale right now.
Awesome, I'm buying it tonight.
Did you get any feedback from Indian audiences, whether in Canada or in India?
Yeah, so one thing I was super worried about is my friends back home will roast the shit out of diaspora media.
And I was like, oh no, I hope that doesn't happen with Venba.
But thankfully, I think I was really committed to keeping things very authentic and important.
So much so that in the biryani level, one of the things that most players struggle with, there's a livestream of one of the streamers, a Tamil streamer playing with his mom, and she didn't even look at the recipe.
She was just like, yeah, go do this, go do that.
And the fact that her instincts were right in the game, I think, is really good.
So they're all really happy with it.
And that's something I'm very grateful for.
Hi, I have been, I've played Vampire, actually, a while ago.
I've been following it for a few years now, actually, because I am, one of my research areas as a professor of game design is food in games.
So, very relevant.
And one of the questions that I had for you was, how did you approach the design of the cooking itself?
And then a follow-up to that would be, how did you balance the story elements with the cooking levels?
How did you figure out what was a good balance between those two?
Yeah.
So for me, that was a really, really hard problem to figure out because Indian recipes are very, very complicated.
Like the ingredient list itself is like,
like
And Idli has like these plates and these ways you rotate and place them.
And it felt like a physical turn the object around kind of game.
So that became much easier to start making.
So I started to find puzzles within the recipes themselves.
They were simpler, but I think they were more fun to solve.
Um, and I also try to keep in mind like which dishes doesn't make sense for the family to cook.
So in the 1980s, making something like biryani would be very expensive, uh, because those speciality spices are really hard to come by.
But in the 2006, the explosion of the immigration community in Toronto makes those things more possible, right?
So it nicely aligned with the recipes are getting more difficult and complex, but it's also because when we can now actually cook these, uh, dishes.
Thank you.
So yeah, hi Avi.
Thank you so much for the talk.
Yeah.
And as a Tamilian, big congratulations for the IGF awards yesterday.
Thank you.
I was screaming my lungs out.
May have heard me.
Thank you.
So my question is that around the world, there are a lot of local games made by local devs for local audiences.
But we see that these are not as popular in the West, especially like games from Iran, from India.
Whereas Venba is something that, as you mentioned, instantly kind of appealed to the global audience in a way that other games haven't.
So if you didn't try to do this consciously then, you know, why did it work?
What's your opinion on how it?
Yeah, I think a lot of it is in we were in the right place right time also being in Canada being in So close to a game dev scene comes with massive massive privileges So I don't think I think if I didn't make when but it's a matter of time before someone else did And yeah, I think right now
the India game I've seen is exploding.
And I can't wait till so many more cooking games come out that when Bob becomes irrelevant, I'll be able to breathe freely then.
I think it's just a matter of time.
Yeah.
Okay.
Thank you so much.
Hi, thank you so much for the talk.
It was so incredible.
I particularly loved how you had the two different assets for the ghee, the solid and the liquid.
I was wondering, how did you negotiate that with the extra asset for the temp team?
Yeah, my producer is sitting in the front row.
So yeah, I think what I really like about working with my team is that they will first understand what I'm going for.
If I am able to convey why it's important to me, they'll be like, OK, fine, we'll do it.
But it's just about finding the way to do it.
It's a lot of compromises, a lot of compromises for sure.
We can keep adding details, right?
But those kind of small details go a long way.
So it becomes a big compromise thing.
I'm really bad at scoping and all of those things.
So I'll keep putting ideas on the board.
And my team will ruthlessly cut it.
And sometimes we get into debates and stuff like that.
But I think that's how the game is made.
My follow-up is, is there anything that was cut for scope that you still wish could have made it?
Yeah, so initially I wanted way more levels to begin with.
So that cut down to seven.
And I think things like, I wanted the player to have the feel, like once you cook idli, it's stuck, especially if you use a cloth.
It's very satisfying when you peel that idli off the cloth.
Very, very satisfying.
And I wanted the player to be able to do that physically.
But I also suggested this idea after we had already passed certification and we had a month.
So yeah, there's so many things like that.
I made an entire document.
After we passed CERT, we're like, OK, we have three weeks for day one patch.
My lead programmer made, here's some bugs and polishes that we have to do.
My producer made an even smaller list.
I wrote entire features and story arcs that they ruthlessly shot down as they should.
Thank you so much, and congratulations again.
Thank you.
Hi, I'm wondering how you went about Canadian culture.
Was there anything you wanted to highlight from there or did you kind of want to undersell that to highlight the Indian culture?
Yeah, so I think this goes back to the original question of like, if Venba is about something, what is it not about, right?
So you're absolutely right, like that is something I struggled with also.
There's so much in Canada that I love and want to show
talk.
not show so much of Canada.
And the entire game happens inside the home for most of it.
And that was intentional so that when Wenba finally goes back to India, that's when we show that they're sitting out in the open in the terrace.
So to Wenba, immigration was very suffocating.
And that's exactly what we wanted to show.
Thank you.
Hey, good talk.
I do games that has a focus on the African diaspora.
So a lot of the creative challenges I very much understand.
One of the things that I've struggled with recently over the past couple years is sourcing, the wanting to, the things that you kind of mentioned, wanting to show and make sure people kind of get an understanding of certain aspects and details.
aspect of
would
when I started watching anime, I had no idea what was going on.
They were just so authentic and they didn't make it for us, they made it for themselves, right?
But we put up with that, right?
We would look up everything.
I would go to the wiki pages and like, what does that mean?
What does this mean?
So if they can do that, like for me, that's what I wanted to do with Venba, is like, if I read
talk.
to translate it themselves with Google Translate.
And they're like, oh, this dish, I'm going to go cook it.
I don't quite understand it, but I'm going to find the ingredients.
So they're doing that.
I'm really, really happy about that.
So I think your passion for whatever you want to show is organic.
You trying to make it accessible to them is inorganic.
And I think as long as we stay organic, it will shine through for the people who want to engage with it.
Appreciate it.
Thank you.
I think that's it.
Thank you so much for coming.