I am a researcher at the Squid Research Lab, where we study the mysterious forms of squid that transform into human form.
Hello, I am a member of Squid Research Lab, an institute that studies a mysterious type of transforming squid.
But I'm afraid speaking like this for a long time might grow tiresome, so I'll just do it like this.
I'm Nogami from Nintendo.
I joined Nintendo in 1994 and have been a member for 24 years.
I started as an artist in the development of SNES's Yoshi Island.
My first work was as an artist during the development of Yoshi's Island for the Super
Nintendo Entertainment System.
After that, I worked for over 10 years on development of the Animal Crossing series
as both a director and an artist.
Now, I work as the producer of both the Splatoon and Animal Crossing franchises.
Today, I'd like to talk about how both Splatoon and Splatoon 2 came to be.
We, the Nintendo development team,
what we were thinking about while making these games.
I hope this will be a meaningful time for you.
I want to delve into what we on the development team
were thinking about while making these games.
And I hope you'll get a lot out of this session.
At the beginning of 2013,
we gathered 10 members to create a new game
without being trapped in the framework of existing games.
In early 2013, we formed a team of 10 developers
with the goal of creating a new type of game
that wouldn't fit easily into pre-existing categories.
We discussed our ideas together every day,
until after half a year, we found ourselves
with over 70 different design proposals and a number
of software prototypes.
The idea that formed the basis for Splatoon emerged from this process.
Our initial prototype was fairly simplistic.
You would move a cube-shaped character around a flat map,
shooting out white or black ink.
We used cubes because they were easy to create,
and eventually ended up calling them blocks of tofu.
At this point, we were able to connect multiple Wii Us
and play Splatoon, where you would play as a team
and decide who won by the area of the ground you painted.
Of course you could also attack your opponent and beat them.
Linking together multiple Wii U consoles allowed us to have team battles in which we'd compete
to cover the most area with our own team's ink, and that became the core of Splatoon's
gameplay.
Of course, you can also attack and defeat your opponents.
And at this stage, we'd also come up with ways to make use of the Wii U GamePad.
Winning meant needing to ink the ground around you, but also that this would reveal your location to your opponents.
This put players in a bit of a catch-22, and we soon realized it would be one of the most interesting and game-like aspects of our prototype.
You might have seen it in this video, but the idea of hiding within your own ink as a way of concealing your position also emerged around this time.
We used the feature of the Wii U, the gyro function, to create a skeleton of play while searching for a playable expression and operation.
From there, we explored ways to leverage the Wii U's unique features like motion control
to come up with actions and inputs that felt good to perform,
and in so doing, build out the gameplay of our idea.
I think that a finished game is classified as a shooter,
and there are parts that use the word shooter.
But we didn't try to make a shooter from the start.
We used a technique that makes it look like a Nintendo-like action game.
the finished game would likely fall into the shooter category.
And parts of it make use of the language of shooters,
but this isn't to say that we'd set out to create a shooting game from the start.
Rather that the gameplay took this shape as a result of the methods we used
to make a Nintendo-style action game.
The team's ultimate goal was to create a new game,
but our initial goal was to create a new gaming experience.
While our end goal was to create a new game,
the first target we aimed for was creating a new type
of play experience.
We believe that the appearance of a game is important,
but we also believe that it is also important to make it
more appealing to the player.
Art does not have to represent the function and purpose of a game.
So the look of a game is certainly important,
but I think of it as something that
makes gameplay more compelling and amplifies its appeal.
A game's aesthetic and art must embody and complement
its functionality and purpose.
There were options to use existing IPs,
but I felt that a new world and new characters
were necessary to embody new gameplay.
We did consider the option of using existing IP,
but felt that new characters and a new world
would be the best embodiment of this new play experience.
By the way, Nintendo always has a tendency to create new things.
That's why ARMS and Nintendo Labo were born.
I should mention that there's a sort of ever-present desire at Nintendo to produce new things.
Projects such as ARMS and Nintendo Labo are examples of things born out of this atmosphere.
We don't abandon this desire to try new things even when working on established franchises,
for example, with The Legend of Zelda Breath of the Wild.
And on that note, I hope you'll look forward to my colleague, Mr. Yabuki's arms session,
which is at 2 p.m. today.
But let me backtrack a bit.
The characters of Splatoon are squids that can transform to become humanoids.
At first, we were surprised that the main character was a squid,
but there was a reason for the creation of this character,
and until it was born, there were many theories.
People are often surprised when they first hear that the main character for our game is a squid,
but there are reasons why things ended up this way,
and the road leading to the character's final design was not without its twists and turns.
As development progressed from prototyping to creating an actual product, the characters we first relied on were rabbits.
Rabbits have different colors, such as black and white, which are suitable for the Chinese character.
It is also said that rabbits have a strong sense of balance.
Rabbits can be both black and white, making them easy to separate into teams.
We also learned that rabbits are apparently very territorial creatures.
We wanted to use brightly colored inks and thought they would contrast well with the neutral color of the rabbits.
We were able to explain some of the reasons why we chose rabbits as characters.
These were all reasons we could use to explain why we'd gone with rabbits as characters.
But what would rabbits be doing shooting ink?
Why would rabbits be able to submerge themselves in the ink once they shot it?
These were the sorts of questions that came up when I showed our game to others in the company.
I think it was a lack of persuasion.
Something about the concept still didn't sit right.
I felt that this was not just a mistake in the way the characters were chosen,
but that there was a part of the game's idea that was not sufficiently integrated.
So I thought that the game's appearance and gameplay didn't match.
To solve this problem, Sakaguchi, the director,
organized the player's performance.
To help tackle this problem, one of Splatoon's directors, Mr. Sakaguchi,
organized and consolidated what the player's abilities would be.
When not submerged in ink, you would be able to attack.
While submerged in ink, you would lose that ability to attack,
but would recover health and could move more quickly.
We distributed player abilities across two different forms that the player could take,
each with their own pros and cons.
We had all sorts of different character design ideas.
And squids were actually one of the original candidates,
but we couldn't find a definitive reason
to choose one design over another.
But once we thought of this ability to move quickly
through ink as swimming, we discovered a strong reason
to go with squids as our characters.
And to further distinguish between these two ability states, we decided to have the character
take on a more humanoid appearance when not submerged in ink.
And so our characters were born, squids that can transform into people.
This also solidified another pillar of Splatoon's gameplay,
that battles would unfold with characters switching back and forth between these two forms.
We discovered that the act of solving problems in this way gave birth to new gameplay ideas.
This also solidified another pillar of Splatoon's gameplay,
that battles would unfold with characters switching back and forth between these two forms.
This is the trailer we used to show off Splatoon for the first time at E3 in 2014.
While it's a short 80-second video put together by Splatoon's other director, Mr. Amano,
the key elements of the game are all on display, from gameplay to sound to art style.
Based on what I've discussed up to this point,
it might look as if everything about this world had been planned out from the beginning.
The main character is a squid.
The setting is a little bit different from reality.
So far, we've decided on a limited number of members,
such as art directors and directors.
So the characters here are squids,
and it takes place in a modern world similar to our own,
though with some slight strange differences.
We'd gotten this far with the game's director,
an art director, and a small-scale development team.
But at this point, individual members of the team began contributing ideas about what they
thought would fit the world well, and other features they felt passionate about.
As more assets were created, the world of Splatoon began to take shape.
The design of the weapons, the fashion of the squid, and the graffiti in the city were all similar.
Sound staff suggested that the BGM should be played during the battle,
which is a popular thing among the young people of this world.
We also thought of a fictional band, and changed the musicality of each band as we composed.
I created content while imagining that it had nothing to do with the content of the game,
and I made it convincing to the world.
In this way, we propped up our world and made it more convincing
by imagining and creating content not directly linked to the game's core concepts.
For example, I made a big bowl that was firmly attached to the beginning,
and then I made the content inflate so that everyone could throw the ball in.
That was the way I made it.
So to give an analogy, it would be as if we started first by building a big container.
Then we tossed balls into this container, filling it up and expanding what the game's content would be.
You might think this process was unique to Splatoon,
but it's actually a methodology for creation that Nintendo has long relied on.
There were several issues when we sent Splatoon to the world as a product.
It was an unprecedented IP, so we didn't know how many people would download the game and play it.
We had to face a number of challenges in making Splatoon a product we could send out into the world.
As this would be a new IP with no established history,
we weren't sure how many people would pick up the game and play it.
As you're likely aware, creating and maintaining a player base is one problem that online multiplayer
games have to wrestle with.
If the population of players is too low, finding people to play against can take time.
If the problem gets bad enough, you won't be able to find opponents and the game becomes unplayable.
Also, because Splatoon featured this new mechanic of shooting ink onto the ground,
we felt that releasing all the weapons and stages we'd planned at once
would prevent players from discovering all their unique traits before moving on and forgetting them.
We also thought that balance adjustment was essential to allow players to play online games for a long time.
We also felt that balance adjustments
were key to keeping players engaged
with a competitive online multiplayer
game over the long term.
We decided to narrow down the number of game modes and content
to address these issues, and gradually increase
the number of content over the long term.
In order to address these issues, we decided to provide a focused amount of game modes and content at launch,
increasing the amount of content a bit at a time over a longer period.
We wanted to create an environment where players can continue to play with a fresh mind,
by adding weapons, stages, and rules to the game to help them get used to the game and to grow in the community.
By adding new weapons, stages, and modes as player familiarity with the game increased
and the game's community evolved, we hoped to keep the game fresh for players and create
an environment they'd want to stay engaged with for longer.
This is a graph showing Splatoon and Splatoon 2's daily active users
in the months following the release of each game.
The data is from players around the world.
The games were released two years apart but are shown together on this graph.
The blue line is Splatoon while the green line represents Splatoon 2.
Splatoon was released on May 28, 2015, while Splatoon 2 launched on July 21, 2017, so the
start of the graphs are a bit staggered.
The graph is growing every weekend.
There are many users who play on the weekend.
I think you can see pretty clearly that the daily active users for numbers for Splatoon 2 outpace those of Splatoon.
The repeating spikes in each graph represent weekends.
And this confirmed our suspicion that a lot of people play Splatoon at the end of the week.
Splatoon maintained a fairly stable rate of daily active users, with a bit of a jump coming in August of 2015.
This was around the time that we released a sizable update for the game, which included a new game mode.
And because the sales of the game increased during Christmas, the sales of the game increased as well.
I think that the increase in sales during Christmas is because we were able to maintain the user's activity and the environment where it was easy to play.
Unlike Splatoon, which had no franchise history to rely on, Splatoon 2 saw a sizable increase
in daily user rates immediately following release.
User rates remained particularly high on weekdays,
which we can at least partially credit to an overlap
with summer vacation in Japan.
From the second half of August onward,
our weekend daily active user rate was almost horizontal.
Then we saw another large jump during the holidays
and are now maintaining a user rate higher
than when the game launched.
YOSHIMASA ENJI, JR.:
Right here, you can see our daily user numbers
took a bit of a dip.
YOSHIMASA ENJI, JR.:
And this is actually the weekend when Super Mario Odyssey
was released.
It seems like everyone was busy playing Super Mario Odyssey when it came out, but after
that we released a fairly large update and our numbers recovered.
And there are some big changes in the weekend.
This is the weekend when the game's event is held, called FES.
You can also occasionally see spikes larger than the typical weekend increase.
These represent weekends when in-game events called Splatfests took place.
Which do you like better, ketchup or mayonnaise?
Halloween costume, vampire or wolf?
and other questions that are not relevant to our daily lives.
We will split the players according to the results of the vote.
And we will collect the results of all the matches that we played for 24 hours
and decide the winner.
This is an event involving all the Splatoon players.
Splatfests bring together the entire Splatoon community
and split them into teams based on their answers to some not-so-serious questions.
Which is the better condiment, ketchup or mayonnaise?
Who would you rather be for Halloween, a vampire or a werewolf?
Players then battle furiously for 24 hours, and a winner is determined based on the voting
breakdown and number of wins for each side.
I want to encourage people to play games, but I also want to encourage people who don't play to talk about it outside of the game.
When a Splatfest is going on, the entire game is wrapped up in a festive atmosphere,
and players fill the hub area with handwritten messages and drawings.
Splatfests are of course designed to give people a reason to play the game,
but we also hope they get those not actually playing involved in the conversation,
and in so doing make Splatoon something that's discussed beyond the bounds of the game itself.
I want you to seriously discuss which is more important, your family, friends, social media, ketchup or mayonnaise.
It's our hope that family members, friends and people using social media use these events to get in seriously silly debates about pressing topics like whether ketchup is a better condiment than mayonnaise.
The development of Splatoon 2 started during the previous update.
Development of Splatoon 2 began while we were still in the middle of updating the first game.
This was prior to the announcement of the Nintendo Switch,
but when I first heard about the concept for the new hardware, I thought it sounded like a good fit for Splatoon.
At home, we can use the TV to watch TV, and we can take the Nintendo Switch outside and use it to communicate with friends.
We can freely use these two play styles, and I felt that it was a new experience for Splatoon's multiplayer.
The ability to change freely between two styles of play,
so playing online on a TV while at home,
and then taking the Nintendo Switch on the go
to play via local wireless with friends,
fits Splatoon's multiplayer model well,
but also felt like a new experience.
On the other hand, there were several challenges
in creating Splatoon on a new platform.
One was...
the screen composition would change,
but we were able to overcome this by trial and error.
On the other hand, we had to face numerous challenges
in creating Splatoon for a new platform.
One of these was that the layout of the screen had changed,
but we were able to overcome this by trying a variety of solutions.
One of the big challenges was that
the player population would decrease
by the time the game was released.
At the time, we didn't know how much the Nintendo Switch would sell.
Another hurdle was knowing that until the Nintendo Switch became more established,
it was possible that our player base would shrink.
At the time, we had no idea how much the Nintendo Switch would sell.
We also wanted new players to have the same experience as those who had played the previous game.
We also wanted new players with no experience of the first game
and veteran players from the original Splatoon
to have the same sort of experience with Splatoon 2.
To accomplish this, we continued our strategy from the first game,
adding content in real time
to match the growth of player skill and the community itself.
and the experience of enjoying the process of content growth
is the value of Splatoon.
Our reasoning for this was that Splatoon's value as a game
came at least in part from the experience of enjoying and adapting
to a constantly evolving set of content.
The single player hero mode
was a practice game where players who were not confident in jumping into a battle
would get used to the controls and then try out the other modes.
The single player campaign, which we call Hero Mode, serves as a sort of training ground
for new players who might lack confidence with the controls before taking on other modes. 遊び進めていけば十分な手応えがありますし、世界を掘り下げ、キャラクターに愛着を持ってもらう役割もあります。
Playing through the campaign puts players through their paces, but also lets them delve into the world and builds their affection for the characters.
And as we anticipated Splatoon 2 would have many new players, we decided to give this mode the same purpose this time around.
We also wanted to create a new game that would be another highlight of Splatoon 2.
We chose Salmon Run as our theme.
But we also wanted to offer a new type of play that would be a big attraction for Splatoon 2.
This wound up being Salmon Run, a mode that focuses on cooperation.
Though relatively simple in structure, this mode challenges player proficiency with the game's core controls,
requires them to use a variety of weapons, and was designed to encourage replayability.
The three modes, War, Hero, and Salmon Run, are independent games,
but are designed to be connected as one game cycle.
While the three modes of multiplayer, single player, and salmon run each offer unique play experiences,
they were designed as pieces of a single game cycle.
Rewards earned during single player and salmon run can be used in multiplayer,
and the skills acquired in each mode will come in handy in each of the others.
年を越える若者が縄張りバトルに強じる傾き アルバイトに汗をかく そして人知れずヒーローとして世界を救う So the young squid who is the player's character, has come to the city to take part in turf war battles,
but also works a part-time job.
And unbeknownst to anyone, they're also the unsung hero tasked with saving the world. プレイヤーの体験としても、分身である一人のイカの若者を中心とした出来事に見えるように演出しています。
These experiences the player has are designed to make it feel
like the game world revolves around them and their inkling character.
Splatoon is not a game where you just play through all the content you have prepared for release.
It's a dynamic experience where you can grow and evolve through the content.
I think this is also a game's value.
Splatoon was envisioned not as a game that you simply play to completion after purchasing,
but as a dynamic experience with value that comes from its content's ability to grow and change over time.
We saw ourselves providing Splatoon as a set of experiences for the players,
as opposed to a static piece of software.
While the first game and Splatoon 2 split this single experience into two different
products, we hoped people would come to think of the two games as constituent parts of a
connected whole.
The world of Splatoon 2 is a world that has been around for two years,
the same time as the previous game.
We decided on the setting first,
and then we built up the city, the fashion, the music, etc.
so that you could feel the two years of transition.
Two years passed in our world between the releases of the two games,
and that same time has passed within the world of the game itself.
Having decided that from the beginning, we designed the look of Splatoon 2's Inkopolis Square,
as well as the fashion and music trends of our squid characters,
to reflect the changing trends over these two years.
This flow is also connected to the Octo Expansion, which was announced the other day.
And the Octo Expansion we announced recently is another example of this perspective.
In the Octo Expansion, we explore aspects of the world and characters we hadn't been able to completely flesh out in the main game.
And by merging the Octo with the new species, the Octo,
Splatoon 2 will be transformed into the next time.
With this expansion, a new type of character, the Octolings, will join Inkling society,
adding further to the changes that Splatoon 2's world experiences over time.
With the Octo Expansion, we wanted to explore ideas for using the variety of weapons and player abilities we'd created to enable players to get the most out of Splatoon 2.
And while this content is paid DLC, we designed it for the player who wants to explore the world of Splatoon 2 on an even deeper level.
Of course, we plan to continue offering free updates to the game's weapons, stages, and more,
to ensure that all players can participate in multiplayer on an even playing field.
We've also changed and re-created some of the characters to fit the fans' reactions.
These young ladies are the Squid Sisters.
characters that served as guides for the player in the first Splatoon.
In the world of the game, they are a successful pop duo,
but fans have latched onto them even more than we imagined that they would.
Fans have created all sorts of Squid Sister fan art,
with some people even imagining elaborate backstories for them.
In response to these requests, we released new songs and held live concerts in the real world.
This is a virtual live concert we held in Japan the other day.
This is a scene from the virtual concert we held in Japan just last month.
At this event, the Squid Sisters partnered with the new guide characters from Splatoon 2, Off the Hook.
About 5,000 people came out to this show and really raised the roof.
It might seem a bit strange to you, but as developers, nothing could make us happier
than to see the characters we've created mean this much to people.
For us, it was like watching kids we'd raised grow up and then go on to succeed in the world
on their own.
We are also monitoring the live content and the game content in detail.
By the way, this live was held in Japan and France, and next week it will be held at the Polymanga 2018 in Switzerland.
It has not yet been realized in the United States, so we are looking forward to a good offer from them.
So far, concerts like this have been held in Japan and France,
and next week, we'll have another one at an event called Polymanga 2018 in Switzerland.
There hasn't been a concert yet in the States,
but I can assure you the Squid Sisters are hoping an appealing offer comes along.
For the final Splatfest of the first Splatoon, we pitted the squid sisters against one another,
and the results carried over into the story for Splatoon 2.
We wanted fans to realize both of these things,
that time passing in the real world
passed in the world of Splatoon as well,
and that we absorbed feedback from players
and reflected it in the game.
In the Octo Expansion, we'll also be fleshing out
these characters from off the hook,
in part as a response to expectations
that we've seen from fans.
I think of events taking place in association with the game in the real world as a part of the game in their own right.
When I was a kid, I enjoyed playing games,
but I also remember having fun talking about games with my friends.
Of course, I'm someone who enjoyed playing games myself as a kid,
but some of my best memories are the excited discussions that I had with my friends about games.
I think drawing fan art and attending events
are still part of enjoying the world of games.
So in my mind, drawing fan art and going to game-related events
are part and parcel with enjoying the world of the game itself.
That's one of the reasons I enjoy games.
This is a video of the Splatoon Koshien tournament in Japan.
More than 870 teams and more than 3,500 people participated in the preliminary round,
which took place in nine venues all over Japan and online.
It was a very large-scale tournament.
The preliminary rounds were held at nine locations across Japan, as well as online,
involving more than 870 teams made up of over 3,500 people,
making for a truly large-scale competition.
While there were many core gamers among the participants,
we also saw lots of teams made up entirely of children or the members of a family.
We saw a team made up of four moms, and a team with members from three generations, including
a grandmother, her daughter, and her granddaughter.
I was really happy to see people from such a broad range of ages and social backgrounds
form teams and bring their A-game to play in the tournament.
In the U.S., Splatoon was used in the Nintendo World Championship.
And last year's E3 was a world tournament with representatives from the U.S., Europe, Australia, New Zealand, and Japan.
Splatoon has also appeared as a game in both recent Nintendo World Championships, and at
E3 last year, we held an international championship featuring teams from the US, Europe, Australia
and New Zealand, and Japan.
For the Splatoon European Championship, tournaments were held in nine different countries,
with the winners gathering soon to decide who will reign supreme.
And there are also many grassroots tournaments being organized by the community.
For me, as a developer, there is nothing more rewarding than watching players from around the world
having fun playing a game I helped create, regardless of age, gender, or nationality.
It is an honor for me to be evaluated as a highly competitive game by Splatoon and Splatoon 2.
I am sweating while watching a serious match between high-level players.
It's an honor for us to hear that people think Splatoon and Splatoon 2 have the potential for a really high level of competitive play.
My hands still sweat a bit whenever I see high level players engaged in such intense battles.
But our goal is for as many people as possible around the world to enjoy playing our game.
In Splatoon, competition allows these players to pursue the highest level of play that they're capable of.
I want to continue to support them so that they can have such opportunities.
I was brought up in the gaming culture.
I have many good memories from games and I am standing here as a developer.
I'm someone who has grown up surrounded by, and was in part raised by, the culture of video games.
Games have given me countless good memories and experiences,
and have made me the developer that I am today.
And that may include games that some of you have had a hand in creating, or will someday create.
I hope that people will feel that games are great and interesting,
and that they will continue to make games that will leave good memories,
not only in the game, but also outside of the game.
So it's my hope to continue this work of creating video games,
both the actual games themselves and the experiences that extend beyond them,
to give people their own lasting gaming memories,
and to show as many people as possible how great our medium can truly be.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.