Good morning everyone.
First, let me introduce myself.
I'm Tabata from Square Enix. Nice to meet you all.
Good morning everyone. Just let me introduce myself.
As most of you probably know me already,
but my name is Hajime Tabata.
I'm the director of Final Fantasy from Square Enix.
Hi, I'm your interpreter for today.
I'm Rui Kawada.
I'm the chief project manager of Final Fantasy XV.
Yes, but everyone is nervous because it's the first day, right?
It seems like everybody is kind of like a little bit nervous and very quiet because it's very early in the morning.
Okay, let's do a little bit of a Japanese lesson together.
A Japanese kind of morning kind of like, you know, greetings.
Yeah, just repeat after me.
Here we go.
Good morning.
Okay, very good.
Let's do that then.
Before starting my today's session, let's look at the trailer which we released after the launch of Final Fantasy XV.
Let's take a look.
I fear I have left too much unsaid.
Take care on the long road.
Wheresoever you should go,
the line of Lucis goes with you.
Octon, my son.
Thank you.
So you just saw the trailer and as you know we released Final Fantasy XV last year in November
and the GDC actually asked me to come here and share my development expertise based on the success of Final Fantasy XV.
I think that FFXV is currently a success in the business.
But if you ask me if it's a personal success, it's a little different.
It's not like I'm rich or anything. It's normal.
But mine isn't actually really a success story, and I don't have any magical expertise to speak of,
and I haven't suddenly become a millionaire either.
To be honest, for me, FFXV has more to offer than just a successful story.
It's a lot more about reflection and learning.
So instead of a lot of success stories, I have a lot of regret and learning from my experiences.
So what can you tell us about FFXV?
then what I can tell you today during my talk.
I took on the challenges I took on with my teammates
through the FFXV project.
My story is really simply about the challenges I took on with my teammates.
I can't tell you the success story,
but I thought I could tell you what I learned and what I saw through the challenge.
So I'm here today, I can surely tell you what I learned,
and so through this challenge.
It's not about the success story.
But today I'd like to share three lessons
we learned in particular.
It won't be your typical GDC talk, but it's about the very high level of design for a gigantic project called Final Fantasy XV.
I'll try to make it fun as much as possible, and it will be useful to you at some point, so I hope you'll bear with me.
By the way, friends and teams are always important to me from my childhood days.
So let me tell you a little bit about my story.
I used to ski competitively as a kid.
It's called slalom.
I was the fastest in my ski club.
So even with all the kids there, I entered a local tournament.
I made my parents promise to buy me a Game & Watch if I won.
My parents never bought me a game up to that point.
I kept thinking about whether I should get Donkey Kong or Mickey and Donald.
I lost the tournament in the preliminary.
I was convinced that there was someone stronger than me.
I just convinced myself there was a really strong guy there.
But it turned out the guy that beat me lost in the final.
And that guy who won the local tournament got beaten in the regionals.
I was back then, I was 11, but that's when I realized there will always be someone better than you.
I think that's because I'm more focused on team play than individual play.
Even if you can't win alone, but you can still play for the winning team.
That's what I learned from this experience.
Yes, that's the main point.
Back to the original topic.
The first lesson is about a goal.
This is what the father of Final Fantasy, Mr. Hironobu Sakaguchi, said.
So namely, what did making Final Fantasy a challenger again mean?
It meant approaching the project believing this was our last chance.
If we don't do it this time, there won't be a next time.
I heard from him that there's a lot of people who are really interested in this project.
That's where the final in Final Fantasy comes from originally.
Right after I was named director of Final Fantasy XV,
I talked to the regional sales head
and received the sales forecast from each region.
So right after I was named director of Final Fantasy XV,
I talked to the regional sales head
and received the sales forecast from each region.
The numbers were not solid, it was very severe, under 5 million worldwide.
Unlike the past, it was a turn-based battle, so we changed it to an action-based battle.
The reason for this was the change in the way we played and the brand of FF.
I set a sales goal of 1 million copies higher than the forecast, to 6 million.
So knowing we had to surpass that would bring us together and force us to take up the courage to push through whatever stood in our way.
So as a Final Fantasy, I've got a lot of history in the past, and as the latest installment of the Final Fantasy franchise, this is the goal that Final Fantasy XV should take.
So I approached it with a way how the original Final Fantasy 1 did, so that if it didn't
succeed, it would all be over.
So, look at this slide. If I compare this challenge to mountain climbing,
let's compare it to the previous titles I was involved with.
I used to work on handheld titles, as you know,
and compared the first two titles actually on portable devices.
If it were mountain climbing, this project would be like this.
If my previous titles I got involved was kind of like 3,000 meters kind of like the mountains,
Final Fantasy XV would be Mount McKinley, so 6,000 meters high.
The official name now is Denali, but I call it McKinley during my speech.
I had never climbed such a high mountain before, so I had no idea what equipment, route or plan I should use to climb it.
At first, I was quite confused about what to do.
Speaking Japanese
Yet by setting the goal high, I made a lot of true friends who offered to stand by me.
Yes, scaling that mountain wasn't my goal alone, it was our goal, all of us.
I now realize your true friends are the ones that stick with you to the end through good
times and bad.
And my friends and I built a studio to make Final Fantasy XV,
and that studio was called Business Division 2, BD2.
Yes.
Everyone, when you are working on something,
try to set a clear goal of making it happen.
So we took on development and marketing,
knowing there is no second chance,
and that became the mantra of our project.
And in any endeavor, try setting one clear goal that you realize at all cost, and when
it's abstract, make it concrete and an object goal that can be conveyed to others.
And the second lesson involves teamwork.
So we needed expertise and technology to conquer the 6,000-meter-tall peak at Mount McKinley.
So we decided to update all the 3,000-meter-tall mountains that we had as know-how.
So our experience, past experience in 3,000 meter climbs wouldn't apply.
So we needed a new knowledge base, new tech, and new tools.
We needed a new knowledge base, new tech, and new tools.
On top of that, we needed a team that could wield them and take us to the peak.
Conceptually, it will be a mass of mastery.
So first of all, they told me their strengths and what they wanted to do, and I asked them to do what they do best.
I didn't want to compete with my weak points.
I wanted to contribute to the project with my strengths.
I asked everyone to do that.
I created a team that could do that kind of design.
The roles are assigned by pairing strength and personality
to maximize performance at all times.
IMAGE is a strong and flexible organization like a pro sports team.
So it was a grand restructuring that
reset the existing hierarchy and assumed
the mode of a football team.
SPEAKER 1.
SPEAKER 2.
SPEAKER 3.
SPEAKER 4.
SPEAKER 5.
SPEAKER 6.
SPEAKER 7.
SPEAKER 8.
SPEAKER 9.
SPEAKER 10.
SPEAKER 11.
SPEAKER 12.
SPEAKER 13.
SPEAKER 14.
SPEAKER 15.
SPEAKER 16.
SPEAKER 17.
SPEAKER 18.
SPEAKER 19.
SPEAKER 20.
SPEAKER 21.
We were able to challenge many development milestones in different formations
and achieve many results.
As a result, we literally changed the formations
to optimize for each development milestone.
I think everyone is working now,
but do you tell your teammates and leaders what you want to do?
I'm sure all of you here today have got your professional work, but how many of you have
actually told your peers and bosses your strength and what it is you want to do?
If you are not satisfied with your performance, please try this method.
Communicate these things can really help bring out the best in yourself.
I highly recommend to those who need to design the team.
Maybe you are not the actual problem, it's the organization itself that is the problem.
So if this is the case for you, and once the team changes and learns how to utilize you,
you can deliver the best performance ever.
What I aimed for with FF15 was to create a team of 200 or 300 players,
which is the average number of players in American football.
On a team scale, it's like having a squad of 200 specialized American football players
instead of like normal 11 players.
As a result, the Final Fantasy XV amassed a great deal of energy once it got rolling.
Right after the development started, many people felt that there was a wall to the development of Open World, but thanks to this strong team, we were able to break through that wall.
So we managed to overcome our biggest technical hurdle,
which was to create an open world environment and game
system when we had no prior experience of this before.
YUSUKE USTUNOMIYA So the team worked nonstop up to March
2015 when we released a demo titled Episode Dusk Eye.
What this demo was like, I would like you to watch the video first.
What it was like is very important for the next part of the presentation.
So, some people probably don't know about this demo.
So, let's have a look at this trailer of what the demo was
and the status of the game back in early 2015.
And if you could watch the trailer as it leads to what I would like to talk about next.
["We Wish You a Merry Christmas"]
This was actually the trailer that was made two years before the actual launch of the game.
Making this demo was a proof of concept for us.
The core system of FFXV is a daily cycle.
We make sure that the cycle from day to night is the basic system of the game,
and we make sure that the various game designs around it work.
It gave us a clear idea of what else we needed for our final product and how much work it would take.
The base concept of Final Fantasy XV is the daily cycle, the day and night cycle.
To make sure that the basic cycle works, we needed to have a minimum number of locations.
We thought that we needed to have the minimum number of combat, camp, and character growth equipment.
We had a lot of feedback from the users about the character's likes and dislikes,
but our game design was mostly good.
So with this episode, Dusk Eye, towards the game design,
the user reaction was pretty much like what we expected,
but towards the characters, obviously up to the users,
who they like to play, who they really like.
However,
But actually, the development team faced a very, very severe problem at that point.
Yeah, like I said, obviously, by making this demo,
it was a kind of proof of concepts for us.
So it gave us kind of like the idea
of how much work still needs to be done.
Speaking Japanese
So we realized we were only at the third station
on our way up the mountain.
We were halfway done in terms of our development progress, but the peak was still in the distance, and the task was great.
it's the time we really had to confront the chaos that came at us with the teams.
We were moving well until then, but now we lost our will.
So obviously the volume we needed to get it done was big, so racked by chronic pressure and fatigue and insecurity.
So our team lost its muster and performance dropped off sharply.
So the summer 2015, summer to autumn 2015,
the performance of the team dropped really, really sharply.
So we couldn't kind of deliver what we really needed to do.
Yes.
So I found the answer to where is our home.
One day, when I was about to go out to work,
At the time, my 6 year old daughter came to me and hugged me.
She looked very lonely and asked me,
how long are you going to be busy?
I looked troubled and said,
I'm still busy for a while.
So without letting go, she asked me,
how much longer will you be busy?
And not knowing what to say, I told her,
well, it's still going to be a while.
So she said,
she was about to cry, but she held it in,
and made a smile,
and said, Dad, hang in there,
cheer up,
that's what she said.
And she brought me a picture of my smile,
and gave it to me as a present.
and on hearing that she held her tears back
so I wouldn't see and with a big smile said
chin up and keep up the good work daddy
then she back to her room and brought me a picture
a drawing of me working
it wasn't good drawing actually but I laughed a lot
I felt that she wanted me to be happy and smile all the time.
When I see her crying desperately, as a parent, I feel like I'm being crushed.
At the same time, I want to show my family
At the same time, I realized how much my family actually put up with.
So, in order to solve this problem, I had a meeting straight away with my team.
And we decided to organize our own Bring Your Family to Work Day.
The objective was to achieve a better work-life balance, to show appreciation to our families,
and to give them peace of mind.
So we paused for a moment and considered a way our families could learn about our work
and also our goals.
We spent quite a lot of time to prep for this actual family day, even though we were really
in a hurry and also we were really worried about the development milestones and schedule.
Back then, the BD2, Business Division 2, had around 250 staff.
So bringing their own families to the office was such a big project for us.
The staff had a lot of kids, so we customized the FFXV for kids to play with.
So what we did is we actually customized the Final Fantasy XV for the kids and set up some PCs for them.
The kids really enjoyed playing the FFXV for the whole day.
My daughter is in the picture right now, and she played the game.
And actually our staff and their kids spent all day playing Final Fantasy XV together.
And my daughter was there too. She's actually in that photo somewhere.
So our developers showed their husband and wives and parents,
kids, their work desks, and showed them what it is they do.
YOSHIMASA ENJI, JAPANESE INTERPRETER
So showing them what we actually do every day
gave us a kind of new appreciation for it.
YOSHIMASA ENJI, JAPANESE INTERPRETER
It was really important for each staff to show what they actually do for work to their families.
From there, the FFXV team regained their energy and went on to reach their goal.
By having this family day, we got our master back and set our sights on the goal again.
Compared to before,
The key to having a stronger team, it was very, very important to have the family members
behind you to support you.
And the third lesson was in the result of our challenge.
So let's take a look at this video.
This is actually a Japanese TVC which PlayStation Japan team actually made it for us.
FINAL FANTASY XV
Yeah, as you can see, the development of the game was kind of winding down towards the end of the development phase.
We conducted events all over the world to get our global audience excited for the release.
But actually, there was a big, big crisis actually waiting for us.
I'm not talking about our two months delay.
This actually happened after we'd mastered up and ready our day one patch.
I'm talking about spoilers from places that broke street date.
We never did simultaneous worldwide launch before, so we lacked the expertise to stop copies from getting out early.
If the early birds were enjoying it in silence, we could bear it.
Ta-da!
But that there are people actually actively trying to ruin the experience for those waiting
for the launch with campaigns on social media.
And I spoke to the relevant parties and heard a lot of people actually complaining about it.
I spoke to the relevant parties and heard a lot of people actually complaining about it.
And then I discussed internally and warned our fans about the threat,
and made it clear we wouldn't take ill, intentional behavior lightly.
So we lost a lot of the malicious spoilers,
but on the other hand, the criticism of Bokkojin and the game itself
heated up and had a negative impact on the promotion.
There were a lot of lessons learned from this.
But I learned a lot from this experience.
But if I find myself in a similar situation again, what should I do?
How are you going to face the situation?
Rather than relying on enforcement, I probably would come up with another solution.
For example, I'm thinking I'd like to use the spoiler makers to our advantage and create buzz
and come up with an idea to integrate them into promotion somehow.
Like the Family Day project,
when you're in a pinch, you need a bold idea to overcome it and turn it into an opportunity.
As with the Family Day episode, I believe it's critical to look at crisis as opportunities,
because there is always a drama.
Yeah, not only like a big project like Final Fantasy XV, but any other project you're working on,
there is always a drama and a crisis and some other big problems waiting for you.
What I really learned from my experience in the development of Final Fantasy is this slide.
So take crisis into opportunities.
We were finally able to complete FFXV and release it.
We were able to reach our goal of 6 million sales in a month.
As I said at the beginning,
if this doesn't hit, it's over.
There's no next time.
I'm hoping for the next one.
I'm sure you all understand now, but to me FFXV is not a success story.
So now you've already probably realized that my story about Final Fantasy XV is not a success story.
Yeah, so I don't have any magical expertise from this undertaking, but I know now that
the greatest goals can only be reached by taking big chances.
So now we know there are big chances waiting for us, so we'll continue to take on challenges for Final Fantasy XV and also as well as other new challenges.
and bring Final Fantasy back to the challengers.
I think this is another answer to the theme we have worked on.
It's almost time to wrap up, so I will say something a bit GDC-like.
So, towards the end of my talk, so let's end on a proper GDC note.
So, I brought a little video that my team has made and a little peek at where we are at.
Let's take a look.
Thank you.
Applause
Speaking Japanese
So we are currently working on three big points.
Procedural, AI and Distraction.
We are actually working together very closely with NVIDIA's Gameworks team.
Probably it was difficult because it was very quick, so it was difficult to actually see the actual scene, the monster scene.
That scene was actually showing the monster battle algorithm.
They actually kind of try to analyze the player's kind of like play pattern and then to make
the animal kind of battle pattern.
based on that player's battle pattern.
So we actually have our own goal already in sight.
It's a brand new challenge for us.
Are you actually challenging anything new?
Do you want to kind of work on a challenge with us?
So we are all open to any offers, like developers, technology, businesses.
We won't be doing Q&A today, but if you'd like to contact us, please do so.
We look forward to hearing from you if you'd like to challenge the future of games.
We are waiting to hear from anyone who wants to take these challenges with us.
Actually, there is a special present.
Our technical partner, NVIDIA, kindly prepared something.
NVIDIA's branded backpack.
I was thinking about who to give this to,
but I think I'll give it to someone whose birthday is today.
Yeah, I was kind of like thinking like how to give this away,
but maybe today's birthday lucky person in this room.
Is there anyone whose birthday is today?
Anyone whose birthday is today?
No one?
Nobody?
For real?
Zero.
Ah, here they are.
There are two.
Oh, yesterday!
Yesterday.
No, no, no.
Let's see.
After the session, please check the chair you are sitting on.
There is a mark where you can get a present.
If you have it, please come out to the front after the session.
Yeah, we actually put a little note under your chair.
So if anyone found it...
Not now, not now!
Do it later!
After this talk.
Yeah, if you found anyone a lucky ticket,
come and talk to us after that talk.
By the way, some of you may have noticed,
but this backpack has something inside.
Yeah, if anyone noticed actually,
this is not the only NVIDIA branded backpack.
It's something inside.
I'm sorry. This is the Nvidia Titan X.
Yeah, Nvidia Titan X. $1,200.
$1,200. If you're lucky enough to get this, please come to our talks later.
Yeah, any lucky person who found a ticket, please come and talk to us.
Okay, that's it for my session. Thank you all for joining us.
So now my session is over.
Thank you again so much for coming.