Hi everyone, my name is Ian Chen and I'm a Taiwanese-Canadian composer working in films,
TV and video games.
Today I will introduce you to a variety of traditional Chinese instruments.
And at the end, I will show you how these instruments may be used in the context of
Western orchestral music, taking examples from my soundtrack to indie game Fantastic
Creatures, which was nominated for Music of the Year at last year's Game Audio Network
Guild Awards.
Now before I start, I must mention that I am by no means a real expert or an ethnomusicologist on the subject matter.
My knowledge came mainly through discoveries I made along the way when arranging and writing for these instruments,
as well as from my time in college when I managed a small Chinese music ensemble in upstate New York.
In comparison, in China as well as Taiwan, traditional Chinese music has their own conservatory
systems separate from that of Western music.
And just like Western music, there are many branches, subgenres, and regional differences
within this overarching thing we call Chinese music.
And since China is geographically enormous, there can be astonishing differences between
the music of different regions.
And some of the most popular Chinese instruments today actually all came from different regions of China.
Today I will attempt to go through some of the most popular instruments
as well as some lessons on ones that are unique to the Chinese musical sound.
First, let's look at the different family groups.
Now, there are many ways to categorize Chinese instruments,
and traditionally, Chinese instruments are grouped
into these eight categories you see on the screen,
known as the Ba-In.
These are the metal on the left, stone, silk,
bamboo, gourd, clay, skin, or leather, and at the end, wood.
And for the purpose of today's discussion, I want to use the more modern way of categorizing them
and we'll broadly divide them into bold strings, plucked or struck strings, woodwinds, and percussions.
Now in the family of bold strings, the most famous one is probably
the erhu, which is also sometimes called the Chinese fiddle.
Even though the one we are most familiar with is really only a specific regional variant of the family of the Huqin from the southern part of China.
And I actually have one right here with me.
I want to use this to show you the construction.
As you can see on the face, there is a little bridge sitting on the python skin.
And this is actually, so when I brought this instrument into the US, I actually had to
declare it because of the Python skin here. And as you can see, the bow
actually sits in between the outer and the inner strings.
So when you play the inner strings, you kind of pull towards you.
And when you play the outer one, you push it out.
Anyway.
And with the samples, it sounds like this.
As you can hear, the Ohu is very expressive and melancholy
and is suitable for sentimental solo passages.
But even though it is in the bold family, bold string family, like a violin, I would advise against using Erhu in an ensemble setup the way violins, violas, and celli are used in Western orchestras.
I know there have been attempts in recent decades to reinvent Chinese music using the Western orchestra setup as a model.
And as such, many modern Chinese orchestras employ an ensemble of Erhuists to replicate the string section in a Western orchestra.
Here I have some example pictures to show.
This is the Nanyang Chinese Orchestra. As you can see on the left and the right,
there are groups of Erhu players. And then here's the Shanghai Chinese Orchestra. See the Erhu players.
And there have also been attempts to reinvent new instruments for this purpose.
For example, the gehu, which was invented in the 1950s to replace the cello in the modern Chinese orchestra.
It's kind of like, it's the size of a cello, but with a python skin and such.
Now my problem with this approach is that the sound of an uhu is, I think, fundamentally
different from the sound of a strings family in a western orchestra.
The uhu is really strong and piercing as a solo instrument, but in an ensemble setting,
the sound of each instrument doesn't really add up the same way violins do, for example.
And as a result, the sounds produced become kind of bland and non-expressive.
But this is my personal opinion, and of course, you should seek out recordings and judge for yourself.
Now, this leads me to the next instrument family group, the plugged or struck strings.
You can see at the back.
In a large ensemble setting, I think these will be the instruments I use to provide a strong foundation and harmonic structure to the music, similar to how strings are used in Western orchestras.
And in particular, the zong ruan, the da ruan, the pipa, liu qin, and yang qin are the most popular ensemble instruments used in this way.
And each of these instruments is also great for solo.
One of the most famous in this category is the pipa, which can be heard in the soundtracks for Zhang Yimou's 2004 film House of the Flying Dagger, as well as, for example, Stephen Chow's film Kung Fu from the same year.
Yeah, I have a very, I have, so I have the Liu Qin here, which is a smaller,
kind of like a smaller version of the pipa as well as the Zong Ran on the right.
I'll show you.
As you can see, it has four strings sitting on a
wooden body. It sounds like this.
Play with a pick.
And there's a technique often used called shake that sounds a little bit like this.
No, I'm not a liuqin player.
And then, of course, you can bend the strings.
And this is the zong ran or the medium lute and it sounds like this.
Now it's much louder because the body is bigger and it has a rich low tone.
And you can also do a shake.
Now if I remember correctly, these instruments come,
actually come from the western part of China.
Um, so,
and I'll show you what the samples sound like.
So this is the pipa.
Of course, you don't have to do this shake, you can do it.
And the next one, another popular instrument in this family is called the guzheng, which is a zither-like instrument and basically the ancestor of the Japanese koto.
And in an orchestral setting, it can be thought of as similar to a harp.
And here's a picture of a guzheng.
And it sounds like this.
Actually, hold on.
So as you pluck on one side, you can use the other hand to
push down on the string on the other side to raise the tone and to make this kind of...
And I mentioned how you can use like a harp when you play Glissando on it.
a very Chinese sounding thing.
And next we have the Wens family, which includes the Di Zi, the Sheng, Xiao, Suo Na, and Hu Lu Si,
just to name a few. The most famous one, I guess, to the Western Era is probably the Di Zi, which is
which is a flute made from bamboo with a membrane attached to create a kazoo-like timbre.
Sounds like this.
Please note that the Dizi is in itself a family of flutes of different sizes and tones,
and you would often pick the kind you want based on the music and the register of the passage,
kind of similar to how you might pick an English horn over an oboe or a piccolo over a flute.
A Dizi player often carries a bag of a variety of these instruments and
use them based on the key and characteristics of the music.
And speaking of which, it might be good to know that many Chinese instruments,
especially those in the woodwinds family, are key-specific, just like their Western counterparts.
The difference is that Chinese instruments are not fitted with keys to help with semitones,
since Chinese music is traditionally played in a seven-tone
yugotemperament rather than the Western system of totem.
And as such, you'll find that a Chinese Dizi player might switch between a C flute and a D flute depending on the music written, even though these are pretty close in register.
And I have some pictures, I think.
Hold on.
Ah, here we go.
As you can see, this is a picture I took of the Hulusi and Dizi player who came in to record for the soundtrack.
At the back you see a bunch of Dizi that he brought for different passages of the music.
And finally, don't forget that percussion instruments are some of the most important and widely used instruments in all sorts of Chinese ensembles, from small to large.
For example, in...
Beijing opera, the drum cymbals, woodblocks, and clave play some of the most critical role
in dictating the proceedings of the play, and often also signify important story events
in the opera.
Now percussion instruments can take center stage much more often than what happens in traditional
western orchestral music. Examples can be heard in films such as Ang Lee's Oscar-winning film
Crouching Tiger, Hidden Dragon. They're in a fight scene.
You only hear a few percussions playing, but it's kind of captivating and pushes the drama forward.
I also used a passage like that in my soundtrack.
Well, I'll just show you right now quickly.
This is really cool because you don't often hear this kind of passage in western percussion music.
And then later...
This is the peepaw.
Which we discussed earlier.
Yeah
Um, so that concludes the most
I guess in the most popular the more popular instruments that I was going to talk about, but there are also a few
uh lesser known instruments that I want to talk about which I incorporated in my into my soundtrack
Uh in the pluck instructions family, we have the yangqin
Which looks like this.
Oh, no, not that one. This one.
As you can see, it's basically a dulcimer.
And it's very useful in a supportive role,
doing things like trills, chords, and arpeggio runs.
Something like this.
And another interesting instrument in this category is the lesser-known zither called guqin,
which is one of the most ancient instruments and one with many romantic stories associated with it.
It is favored by scholars as an instrument of great subtlety and refinement,
and is often used to symbolize the concept of music as a whole in Chinese culture.
And that one looks like this.
And when you play, you move the thumb around.
So kind of like the remains of the the plucking sound can change notes as you go.
So it's kind of hard to sample.
I did use a little bit of it in the beginning of one of my tracks.
I don't can find it.
Anyway, it sounds like this.
It's a little hard to show because when you move the thumb around, it changes the tone.
Anyway, next we have the the Hulusi, which is the gourd category and is in the woodwinds family.
It's made from three bamboo pipes attached to a gourd, making a beautiful rounded and mellow sound.
I think I showed it earlier.
It's this thing sitting in the front and the whole thing looks like that.
It's originally used by just a few ethnic minorities in the Yunnan province
and later gained popularity throughout China.
Here's what it sounds like.
I did use it as a solo instrument in some of my passages.
Nope, not that one.
What's this here?
That's the hallucinogen.
So the passage is Hulusi on top of strings and at the end during this hit you actually
you can see this is a linux version of Hulusi.
So that's all there is to it.
I hope you found this video useful and if you did please like and subscribe and we'll
see you next time.
Take care.
Bye.
Bye, bye.
bye.
Bye.
the Chinese gong as well as... well I mimicked the Chinese gong with like metal balls as well as
an arpeggio on the yangqing as I demonstrated earlier.
Finally, we have the sung, which is a really cool instrument.
It's basically a mouth organ made with bamboo pipes of different lengths.
It has one of the most unique sounds not really heard in Western music.
It is also the grandfather of many instruments found throughout Asia and Southeast Asia,
such as the Japanese shÅ.
It looks like this, and when they play, they hold the instruments with both hands.
So it is also very expressive.
And I used in...
Actually, let me show you how it sounds.
So you can play multiple notes at once. And in the more modern Chinese orchestras,
there are more versions of this invented that are larger and it creates support for the music.
Let me see if I can... Oh, I also used it in a way to play off the brass section in an orchestra.
Let me see.
So there are a lot of different techniques in all the instruments that I briefly mentioned
today.
Sometimes it's difficult to know all the details of the instruments, but what's great about these folk instruments is that once you hire an instrumentalist in, they can provide articulations or ornaments that you didn't even think was possible.
And that really adds a lot to the music as well.
I want to briefly talk about how, um, well, let me just show you some passages and different
examples of the music.
So for Di Zi, I use as a solo.
It's very piercing, so it's really easy to cut through.
So that was a combination of Di Zi and the plucking family with the strings.
So that's more of a fusion sound, whereas here I'll show you a more traditional sound.
Again, percussions.
with the pipa. So small ensemble is more common in traditional Chinese music.
And then they do, I use the song.
I would go into a western sounding.
The strings ensemble with the pipa and the beats on the top.
And now the Erhu.
As I mentioned, I prefer to use the Erhu as a solo instrument.
And now, cello is also very useful, even though it's not a Chinese instrument.
Traditionally, I feel like if you use a traditional Chinese instrument, you kind
of lack that sort of low end string sound because it just didn't exist.
So in fact, a lot of modern Chinese orchestras just simply use the cello.
And just like a Western orchestral score, cello is also very useful in this context.
What else can I show you?
I've shown you this one already.
So this is the bao, which is a di zi-like instrument without the membrane.
So it sounds rounder.
And that's called a Bawu.
B-A-W-U.
And now before I go, I want to also briefly mention how when you hire an instrumentalist,
nowadays there are many who also read Western staff.
However, traditionally,
It's more of an oral tradition, and then later there's a new way invented to notate things,
which is called the gempu, which uses numbers instead of western stuff. And here's an example
of how that looks like. So, for example, in Amazing Grace, so one means the
For example, in the key of C, one would be C.
So this would sing like a...
So as you can see, it tells you on the top that it's in 3-4.
And then if you see one, it means the C, and then three is E, and so on and so forth.
And the dots means the octave.
So this is traditionally how...
recent traditionally how things are read and you can even see it in score form. As you can see,
this is like a large score with the woodwinds on the top, the strings here, and the percussions.
the pluggings, and so on and so forth.
And when I had the instrumentalist come in to record for my soundtrack, I had to handwrite
all the... to basically transcribe all the score into the Jampool form.
As you can see...
Oh, it's going to be hard to see. Oh, there we go.
Like that.
So for each instrument,
I had to make the
Jempu version of it.
Now I know I'm based in LA
and there are actually many artists
here who
or many instrumentalists here who also
read Western stuff.
I mean, they could be more expensive, and it is not the way that they probably learned
the instrument originally. So if possible, I would suggest to see if you could make a
Genpoo version of it for them, especially if the people you're hiring, for example, for me,
I hired them from the eastern region of LA where there's a lot of Chinese population and
And a lot of them don't actually read Western stuff.
So this is useful to know.
Of course, if you don't, if there's no way for you to translate it, then by all means
hire someone who knows how to read Western stuff.
But like I said, it is really important, I think, especially when you write for Chinese
instruments, to hire a Chinese instrumentalist to come in and they will add so much to the music.
All right. I think that concludes my talk today.
I hope it was useful and I'll see you next time. Thank you.