Hi everyone, I'm really excited to be here today.
Thanks for having me.
My name's Evan Jacover.
I'm the CTO of Jackbox Games.
And today we'll be talking about the Jackbox Party Pack,
the collection of five games we've made every year
for the last seven going on eight years.
And I'm really excited to talk to you about it.
So here we go.
So I'll definitely get into the Jackbox Party Pack franchise but first I think it's good to
start with a little history so if you'll indulge me we'll go back to the 90s and
if you won't indulge me you can fast forward I guess because it's a video.
So Jackbox Games used to be called Jellyvision, and Jellyvision started out with a hit trivia
game called You Don't Know Jack, which was released in 1995. As a side note, I started out
at Jellyvision as an intern after getting this game for Hanukkah and writing a fancy fanboy letter
to the company, and then, you know, I guess the rest is history. Been there 20-some years.
So You Don't Know Jack was known as a trivia game where high culture and pop culture collided.
So it had questions like this one. Which of the following household tasks can Superman not perform?
And the answer is erase a floppy disk with his magnetic force.
And as you can see this content becomes somewhat dated over time.
Not a lot of floppy disks floating around these days.
So after You Don't Know Jack, Jellyvision released You Don't Know Jack Sports, followed by You Don't Know Jack Vol. 2, You Don't Know Jack Movies, You Don't Know Jack TV, You Don't Know Jack Vol. 3, You Don't Know Jack Vol. 4, The Ride, You Don't Know Jack Headrush, You Don't Know Jack Offline, Louder, Faster, Funnier, You Don't Know Jack Fifth Dementia.
You don't know Jack Mach 2. You don't know Jack Abatz, which is the third German edition.
You don't know Jack Volume 6, The Lost Gold, which went off the rails a little bit, I guess,
if I'm being honest. A lot of you don't know Jacks.
And it's not like we didn't try to make some other games. Some even made it to market.
Who Wants to be a Millionaire, the PC CD-ROM game, Jellyvision made that one too.
But it was a struggle to break away from being the you-don't-know Jack company.
And then some new consoles came out, and the CD-ROM market kind of evaporated.
and sounds like the beginning of a behind the music story where we all descend into drugs and bankruptcy
and all of that, but it wasn't as dramatic as that.
Jellyvision did go dormant in 2002 and then around 2008 it was revived as Jellyvision Games.
And after some experimentation and research,
Jellyvision Games released its first game, which was
You Don't Know Jack, 2011.
Well, we couldn't quite escape it.
We tried branching out into mobile and social games,
but we struggled to make the freemium model work.
And, you know, not as many people played Lieswater or met Octoputz,
the Wordputz mascot up there, as we would have liked.
The thing is, so-called social games aren't actually all that social.
You play them alone in the bathroom or on the couch, not at a party with friends.
And that was kind of our thing.
We wanted games where you play at a party with friends and there's laughter and you
yuck it up and stuff.
And the whole freemium model was difficult for us.
But then a new device came along and we thought, OK, maybe this will help us break back into people's living rooms.
And that was the Ouya.
For those of you who don't remember, the Ouya was a Android console that was a big hit on Kickstarter.
made several million dollars on there. And we thought, oh, this might be a good opportunity
for us to get a new game out, you know, back into people's living rooms where people could
play on their couches with their friends. And so we released You Don't Know Jack on the OUYA.
So we were kind of scrambling at this point. Money was tight.
you know, we had this game, but we had an issue, like how many people are going to buy
four $50 controllers for a $99 console? You know, so we weren't convinced that many people would
be playing You Don't Know Jack with their friends if they didn't each have their own controller.
So we thought, well, if only there's some way, like some device.
that everyone had in their pockets already that they could use to interact with our games.
And that led us to make a mobile controller app that we called JackPad.
Jackpad was problematic for several reasons. For one, you had to install an app. And that's an
immediate roadblock for many users. Very frustrating. Also, everyone needed to be on
the same Wi-Fi network, which is also a pain in the butt. And then there's always that person
with a weird phone. At the time, there was Windows phones. We're not going to make a
Windows phone app. And so it was somewhat limiting in that way, too.
Well,
Much to our chagrin, OUYA didn't pan out as we had hoped and so we tried to regroup and figure it
out, figure out what we could do next. We had spent all this time writing content for games
like Lie Swatter that didn't really take off so we thought well maybe we could use that for
something else. Lie Swatter is a simple trivia game where you get statements like blondes have
more fungus problems or hot pink is the most popular selling duct tape color.
and you need to decide if they're true or false. It's really that simple. And we thought, well,
what about movie theaters? Yeah, there's all that time before movies start and there's a giant
screen and people have their phones out anyway. Plus, movie theaters are this evergreen business
that will always be popular, right? This was in 2013 when Netflix still only had one original series.
So we built a version of Lieswater for the big screen and took it to a midnight
showing of Christmas Vacation at the Music Box Theater in Chicago.
And unlike Jackpad, we just had people go to a website,
Togetherplay.tv, and they'd go there,
sign in and interact with the game.
No apps to install, no controllers.
And guess what? You know, it worked.
People took out their phones and played along.
It was really cool. I'll leave this as an exercise for the viewer, but you can decide if this is a real Kanye West tweet.
As soon as I'm off this jet, we bought a zoo on Redbox.
So every player would see that statement. They'd have to say if it's true or false.
There was a leaderboard. Lots of fun.
Unfortunately, it turns out movie theaters like using that time before movies start to sell ads and make money instead of paying game developers to entertain people.
So this business never took off, but there was something compelling going on.
Look at all these people happily playing on their phones.
And so it felt like something we wanted to pursue even more.
What came next was a new game called Fibbage.
Fibbage is a bluffing game where you make up answers to
obscure questions and try to tell the truth from the fiction.
So for example, a Swedish man who works as a dishwasher receives disability
benefits due to his unusual addiction to blank.
All of the players type in an answer that they think could plausibly be correct.
We show all of the player submitted answers along with the correct answer,
which in this case is heavy metal music.
And then everyone tries to guess which one is the correct answer.
And Fibbage did well when it was released.
It felt like we were onto something with this phones as controllers concept
and party games, and we wanted to build on that.
So enter the Jackbox Party Pack.
We often don't want to admit that things are about money, but honestly, the first
Jackbox Party Pack was to some extent about money and staying in business.
We were selling fibbage for about seven dollars and wanted to find a way to get a
product at a higher price point into the market.
and a pack of five games for $25 seems like a pretty good value proposition. Five games, five
bucks each, not bad. We just needed five games and we kind of wanted to do this pretty quickly.
Fibbage came out in the summer and we were going to try to release the party pack by the holiday
season, by November. So we were in a rush and we had to figure out what we could do. Well,
We had Fibbage already, so that's one game. So we made a couple more questions, called it Fibbage XL.
We still had that OUYA version of You Don't Know Jack, and so we repackaged that and called it
You Don't Know Jack 2015. So that's two games. Lie Swatter, we had all the content from the
mobile version, and you know we had done some work to make it work in a movie theater on a big screen.
So that's game number three.
Our editorial director Arnie Niekamp mentioned that
he thinks he figured out how to make the Lyswater host flow work
with only five or six new lines of audio recording.
That's how bare budget we were at this point.
Drawful is essentially fibbage with drawings and we didn't have a lot of time to make Drawful,
so we took advantage of the fibbage structure as much as we could, so much so that the sound
effects in Drawful 1 are mostly Andy Poland, our audio designer, using his voice to try to
make the exact same sound effects for each moment in fibbage.
And then there's WordSpud, which is kind of a long story.
But this is a game we had floating around
years and years ago.
We made it for the Jellyvision website in early 2000 and.
We thought that maybe that would be a thing.
Yeah, it was a four player game and
there's this opening song
that kind of explains how it works.
And I got a flash swift from 2005 working to put this in here.
So let's see how it goes.
When the world is passed to your name
Type a word or phrase
That will light your head
And then you hit return and the other players vote
And if they like what you say
Then you all feel so gay
And you'll just beat the world's spud
Hey!
World spud!
So that's Andy's son, uh...
Our sound designer, Andy Sun, who recorded that singing when he was about five and now he's in his 20s.
It's still a catchy tune though.
So yeah, WordSpud is a game where just a...
A word is passed to your name as he says and you have to type in anything that goes with it and
everyone votes and decides if it's acceptable or not. If it is, that new word that you typed in
is passed to someone else and it just continues on forever. It's a weird game if you even call
it a game. It's become a bit of a punchline at Jackbox Games but you know, hey, fifth game.
We need five games and there we are.
So we went on, you know, quite a journey here.
But each of these steps or missteps or dead ends
led us to making the party pack.
And and so.
it ended up all going someplace useful. You know, we realized we wanted to make party games. That
was what we liked doing. We were tired of making You Don't Know Jack, or maybe our audience was
tired of us making You Don't Know Jack, or maybe both. Freemium just wasn't for us. We
didn't have the skills or interest to find ways to monetize.
players. We just wanted to make a fun game and sell it, you know, and not have to worry about
everything else that goes into making freemium games.
Physical controllers are too expensive to expect a bunch of people to buy them for a casual game.
It's a pain in the butt to download apps. OUYA wasn't the answer. The movie theater market
wasn't interested. Consoles were starting to allow self-publishing by independent studios
at this time, which was an exciting idea for us.
We needed to get to a higher price point and you add all of this up and you have the Jackbox Party Pack.
So making a pack of five games may have initially been about making our business sustainable,
but it also turned out to be one of the best things we could have done creatively.
As we learned with You Don't Know Jack, it's very easy to fall into the trap of just catering to your audience and making more of the same thing.
We.
had something that had caught on with Fibbage and we could have just gone down
this road of Fibbage Sports and Fibbage 2 and Fibbage The Lost Gold whatever that
would be and eventually that franchise probably would have just petered out.
Now the Jackbox Party Pack 2, which came out the next year, did include Fibbage 2,
but it also included four brand new games, including Quiplash,
which ended up becoming probably
our most popular franchise
in the Party Pack era.
And before Party Pack 2 came out, we actually did a Kickstarter for Quiplash and released it as a standalone game.
We had just seen Exploding Kittens make like $8 million on Kickstarter, and so we had moderately high hopes.
And it did... eh.
mediocre, I guess. We probably lost money on it, all things considered.
But one takeaway of this is that it's really hard to get people to buy into
an entirely new game idea.
And, you know, people ask us all the time,
why don't you just release all these games individually?
And, you know, one of the reasons is it's just a lot of it's hard.
The Party Pack concept helps a lot with that.
Jackbox Party Pack 3 included Quiplash 2, which by then was a big draw,
and we thought, okay, that will be an anchor title that will draw people to buy Party Pack 3.
But it also had four other games, and all four of them would go on to become really big hits for us.
Trivia Murder Party 2, for example, went on to become the anchor title in the Jackbox Party Pack 6.
So, you know, we came up with a new anchor franchise through this Party Pack model,
and Trivia Murder Party, both of the Trivia Murder Party games are among our most played games.
You know, another way to think about it is if you have to spend $6.99 on a game like TKO in order to play it, you need to be convinced that it's worth it.
And we have to find a way to market that to people and explain what TKO is, which is a little complicated.
For those who don't know, TKO is a game where you draw pictures and make slogans and then combine those on a T-shirt and then the T-shirts battle each other until there's one ultimate winning T-shirt.
And yeah, it's a weird game to say the least.
But if you've already bought the Jackbox Party Pack 3
for Quiplash 2, you'll at least give TKO a try,
you know, to see if you like it.
It's just there in the menu waiting to be played.
You know, you already have your friends over,
just let's see what TKO is like.
And TKO has become a very popular game for us as a result.
without the leeway to push boundaries, knowing there's still a lot of value in the pack,
we probably wouldn't have made these more niche-y games, some of which
became big hits and some which didn't. But games like Monster Seeking Monster, where
monsters ask each other out on dates. Or a game like Bomb Corp, where office workers
and a robot and a talking dog need to fix a photocopier so it doesn't blow up.
or push the button. A spaceship where a spaceship crew has to identify aliens by playing little
mini games or a game like Devils in the Details where a family of devils needs to work together
to make dinner. And you might think well these games I'm listing here aren't that popular.
um you know niche games of these party packs which might be true um but what we found is people's
favorite games are all over the place there isn't really a consistent thread of like this game is
the best game and if you look at just the party pack seven reviews we see all you know things
like this.
Talking Points is my absolute favorite game in the bunch.
I found that Blather Round was probably my favorite.
Devils in the Details might have been the most fun game of the pack.
Champed Up is without a doubt the best game in Party Pack 7.
Quiplash 3 leads the pack of new party games.
So, you know, it's hard to say.
you know, what's what. Every game was declared the best and the worst by different reviewers.
And so, you know, you get a pack of games and it has two or three games that you love and,
you know, two or three that you don't. It's still a good value and everyone is
getting different games that they love and different games that they don't.
So without this game model, I don't think we ever would have built up such a vast portfolio of games
or like the creative engine to keep generating new ideas. And that's been such a boon to our
company that we've come a long way since this. Also, I just want to throw it out there. You
don't know Jack is great and I love it.
We brought it back in the Jackbox Party Pack 5 as You Don't Know Jack Full Stream,
and it's probably my favorite version of the game. It's just nice when you don't have all
your eggs in one basket for one game like that. One of the most difficult design challenges of
You Don't Know Jack Full Stream was reinventing question types.
like the Jack Attack or the Diss or Dat to be played with eight players. In previous Jack
Attacks, the first player to pick the matching answer correctly got the points for that question
and everyone else was locked out and didn't even get to answer or didn't even had no opportunity
to get it right. And in this new version, it keeps really the spirit of that alive,
but everyone can answer, everyone can get.
get the right answer and it still has that tension which I think was a really
impressive amount of impressive coup by the design team.
Also you don't know Jack was meant to be the tentpole game in Party Pack 5.
But we actually found that some new games like Madverse City and Patently Stupid were played more
and that's a good thing. I think, you know, we're always happy to have
new franchises take up the mantle and keep things new.
All right, now I'd like to go a little bit into our process for developing new games and getting
them into production.
And for starters, let's take a look at our timetable. We release games, a pack of games
every year, which really condenses the amount of time we have to work on these games.
In the fall, that's when we release our latest game, usually in October,
our pack of games, I should say.
We develop marketing assets, we do a post-mortem, we go on convention conference tours and promote the games,
and we also begin forming some small teams and playtesting new ideas.
In the winter, that's when we're really focused on playtesting,
ideating playtesting some more, identifying an anchor
title for the pack of games.
Did I mention playtesting?
We're still doing that.
And we start the greenlight process.
In the spring, we lock in games for the pack.
hopefully, and we get into pre-production and production, and then summer we're in full-on
production and development, sweating a lot, get into submission by the end of the summer.
So it's a year, but really, you know, when we're in production it's maybe six months
of production time for each game, depending how quickly we come up with ideas for the games.
A big part of our company culture is that anyone at Jackbox Games can pitch games.
We've had games pitched by writers, artists, producers, engineers, QA, you name it.
Good ideas can come from everywhere and anywhere. So if there are games,
game designing rats in our office with a game idea, and I'll be honest, there might be.
It's an old loft building. Yeah, let's hear them.
So it took us a few years to come up with a process that made sense.
So we've kind of been honing it since then.
But here are the basics to our Greenlight process, which is what we call the
process to get games into production.
We have a rotating Greenlight committee.
It used to be the same four people.
always on the committee that would hear pitches for games.
And last year was the first year we started rotating different people onto that,
which is great because we're getting some different perspectives.
And we'll probably get some different types of games greenlit,
have some different thoughts and ideas into what makes a good Jackbox Party Pack game.
Before pitching a game it's expected that whoever is going to do the pitch has run several internal
play test sessions. We want to get other people at the company to see the games, play them. We also
send out a survey to the whole company asking what everyone's thoughts are on a game and that
gets incorporated into the Greenlight Committee's assessment.
Games don't need to be digital to be pitched, and I'll go into this more in a little bit,
but we need to be able to play something. So it could be a bunch of index cards or post-its or
you know drawing on a piece of paper. We do that sort of thing all the time and we just want to
try to get a sense of...
of the game and at this point we're pretty good at seeing the course from a bunch of post-its to
a fully produced Jackbox Party Pack game. Pitch results for all the games are posted
for the whole company. We try to make this process as transparent as possible.
And I think that's something we've gotten better at every year.
So all of the explanations for why a game is going into production or not
is shared and the whole company can see all that stuff.
A lot of people ask what makes a good Jackbox games, even internally, you know, people who
are pitching games want to know like, well, what should I be doing to, you know, get my
game, you know, give it the best chance to get picked.
And there's not really a specific recipe.
And we kind of go out of our way to say like,
there's no criteria, but we did put some criteria together to help guide people.
And it's very possible that a game could meet none of these or all of these or some combination
and still be greenlit. So we love games that appeal to a wide audience.
The Jackbox Party Packs are bought.
by all ages, all different types of people. We love hearing stories of people playing
with their grandparents over Thanksgiving. So, you know, we want...
to cater to as many people as possible.
This is very vague, but fits the brand of Jackbox Games
and the Jackbox Party Pack.
Kind of let people interpret that as they will.
You know, we're probably not going to make a gritty, serious,
you know, war game.
Who knows, I guess.
has a lot of excitement and passion within the studio
and will be fun to work on.
We're big believers that if you like what you're making,
you'll make a better product.
So, you know, there might be a game
that seems like it would be a good fit,
but if no one's really excited about it,
we're probably not gonna make it.
is funny and makes people laugh. Our CEO notoriously has an office right next to the
conference room and if he hears a lot of boisterous laughter coming out of a play test that will
definitely make him curious about what game that was. Funny games and laughter
says that people are having fun and that's been our bread and butter.
for a while.
Encourages social interaction, gets people talking.
Even if a game works on your phone as a controller,
if you're spending the whole time just looking at your phone
and not interacting with anyone in the room,
that's less ideal.
Has a low barrier to entry, easy to understand,
pick up and play.
I think that's pretty self-explanatory.
We don't want our games to have a 20-page rule book
or explanatory video.
We want you to.
you know, maybe stumble through one play session, but after you've played the game once, you should
get it. Does something new within the Party Pack format? We're always looking for ways to
try something different. It was really exciting for Madverse City to push some boundaries and
do text-to-speech, for example, drawing, whatever a phone can do, taking pictures.
We're always looking for ways to push the medium further.
It doesn't work better as a card game or board game or mobile game.
We want a game that really fits our format
with having a big screen, a shared screen, and then a small
screen in your hand. It isn't too similar to another game we have made or are
making, especially a game in this pack. We
don't want to have a pack of five drawing games or five
trivia games. We like to have a broad range of
different game types.
And finally, engages the audience in a new and or meaningful way.
So when people pitch a game, there's a couple of different pitch results.
You could have a green light, which means the game is good to go on to the next stage.
And at that point, we'll staff a team on it and it will go into pre-production,
evaluate and assess production risks, identify the game core and define a creative brief.
that's all part of the pre-production process. Some games, some pitches have a yellow light,
which means it's a neat idea, but we need to revisit some assumptions. Sometimes
the game mechanics aren't quite there. Sometimes we're worried about certain risks,
and we want to make sure we can resolve those risks in the time frame before we put a game
into production. And usually at that point, we'll assign some additional people to
to the pitch team and they'll be expected to work on it for a while and then re-pitch the game.
And then there's Red Light, which isn't like, ugh, what a bad game. It's more like,
we're probably not gonna do this game right now, so let's put it away for now and we'll revisit
again maybe next year if there's still interest. And a lot of time there is interest and a lot of
these Red Lights do get revisited.
There are about five or six games pitched for every game that makes it into production,
and often those games that don't make it into production are revisited and refined year
over year.
I do hope someday we get to make poop cake.
One can dream.
Trivia Murder Party is a good example of a game that took a few years to get a green light
and how it benefited from having a bunch of other games pitched as well that, you know,
didn't make it into production. Trivia Murder Party, for those of you who don't know, is the
classic you've been kidnapped by a serial killer who asks you trivia questions to determine who
lives and dies trivia game. You know, what a trope. I mean, it kind of is, I guess.
So everyone who gets the trivia questions wrong goes to the killing floor and has to play a
minigame to determine if they live or die. So here's an example of a trivia question.
And that's kind of what took a long while to figure out. Like the trivia is fun,
the minigames are fun, but being dead or a ghost, you turn into a ghost,
and out of the game is not fun. Here's an example of a minigame.
you know, different people put poison into different cups and you have to guess which
cup doesn't have poison. If you drink poison, you die and turn into a ghost. If you don't,
you get to continue on and stay alive. And the game continues until there's only one person alive.
And then you go on to the final round.
So originally the idea was that you just want to be the last one to survive,
but then it's no fun being out of the game and feeling like, well, I can't win.
Then there was an idea where the last survivor faced off against the ghost with the highest score
at the end of the game, but that still left a lot of players uninvolved if only one ghost was able to
win the game or compete to win the game.
So this is from a game designer on the game, Mark Turowicz. He said,
making everyone feel dead but still involved was the missing ingredient.
I think the final round content came from a playtest for a different pitch called 66%
and we combined that with this dumb horse racing prototype. So what he's saying here is the final
round for the game basically took aspects from two other games that were pitched that we also
didn't make.
and some aspects of the of Trivia Murder Party that already existed.
If you want to know what the dumb horse racing game is, if you've ever been at a carnival and seen this game, you get the idea.
Although I guess this is camel racing.
I don't know where this picture came from.
Oh, Wikipedia.
Anyway, so we built a prototype for a game where you answer trivia questions and your horse moves forward based on how well you do on the trivia questions.
And we never made that game.
So the final round ended up looking like this, and taking elements from all those sources.
So the last surviving player, the one at the top, gets a head start, and everyone else is a ghost,
and based on your score, some of the ghosts get more of a head start as well.
and you need to identify which items fit in a category correctly to move forward.
So in this case, which of these three choices are African nations? Zimbabwe, Guam, Somalia.
And it ended up being a really like fun, exciting final round. If a ghost overtakes
the survivor, they steal the body and they become a corporal character again.
there in first place and then the first player to exit escapes and wins the game and it really
fits the theme really well. I think this final round ultimately is one of the main reasons this
game works so well.
I want to kind of finish up by just talking about where ideas come from and how they coalesce into a game at Jackbox Games.
So, as I mentioned with our timetable, once we wrap up a party pack, we immediately jump into coming up with ideas for the next pack.
Some games spring fully formed from the head of Zeus, or in the case of Joke Boat,
they spring fully formed from writer and director Brooke Bright. This game, she conceived
like of this game almost in its final form right down to the name and the cruise theme.
Some games take months to name but Joke Boat was immediately and forever Joke Boat.
Here's part of the pitch doc. All aboard toot toot!
You and your friends are passengers on a cruise ship where you're also the entertainment.
put up your best or worst jokes as players try to get the approval of their peers.
And if you play joke boat, that's pretty much what the game is.
Other games take longer, and Madverse City is a good example of that.
Madverse City started out as an experiment to see
if there was anything we could do with text to speech
and also technically if we could do text to speech in a game.
So I'm going to take you on a little journey here through playtests from 2017.
So the first one, this game was called Telefun back then. Telefun Tests were in September 27,
19, or 2017.
So players listened to an obscure VO voiceover file
and then wrote down what they thought was being said.
So there was an audio file that was distorted
so you could barely hear it.
And you had to take a guess at what it was.
The results, guessing the correct answer,
which no one ever did, not a good sign,
or hearing it revealed wasn't the fun.
The fun was hearing the guesses.
So about a week later, Richard did another test.
Brian Chard, one of our audio designers,
was the one who started this whole process.
Telephone test number two.
Similar to fibbage this time, where one player's response
to a prompt is distorted and others guess what it said,
all the responses are read via text-to-speech.
It was fun to hear the computer say what people wrote.
Biggest laughs were the word chode and a few comments about Ryan and Mark.
So we're learning that text-to-speech can be funny here, especially when it says what people wrote.
Later that week, each player was given a list of two to five parts of speech to provide,
adjective, etc. Those words fill in the blanks of the first line of four poems.
So now it's poetry.
The results of this test, figuring out a way to gamify it would help.
I like the idea of it being competitive instead of collaborative.
I'm interested in trying some sort of rap battle.
Now, about a week and a half later, couplets, now the game is called.
Players write parts of an entire couplet.
It's played back using a singing version of text-to-speech
with musical accompaniment.
The singing robot was hard slash impossible to understand.
Let's try this with the entire first line filled in
except for the last word.
Now if you've played Madverse City,
you know that that's how it ends up working.
Now we're finally calling it Rap Battle Beat Poetry, so we're getting closer.
Tested a Beat Poetry version and a Rap Battle version.
They'll both produce laughs. The Rap Battle felt more like a game.
And finally, Halloween, looks like. I told them up front that the Mad Libs
words would need to be rhymed, too, so they should take care not to set
themselves up for a tough writing task.
And the results this time, we're starting to get into kind of the more nitty gritty wonky game mechanic
honing in now of the game design. Scoring should maybe be a combo of voting by spectators mid-wrap,
but also by voting post-wrap. And that's pretty close to what the game ended up looking like
in Madverse City. You have two
two couplets. You're given the first line except for the last word of it, and then you write the
second line of each one. Players can vote during the reading of the rap, which is text-to-speech,
and then they also vote at the end on who did better. So it gives you a good sense of
how our games take form over the course of several play tests and tweaks.
Push the Button also took several years to find its footing.
We wanted to do a Mafia werewolf style game for a long time.
For over three years, we've probably produced over ten prototypes and pitches and variations.
And just looking through our docs, there are designs for all different variations on this, so we could go through some of those.
Warren Arnold, who's a game designer at Jackbox Games.
was particularly interested in this game. He started it off. And originally there was a pitch
called Push the Button. This is another example of the name of the game, making it all the way
through to the end. The first pitch was all a drawing game. And then there was Push the Button
with Guns, where a leader sends players on missions to fix a ship. And if people searching
a ship find bullets, the leader can shoot a crew member.
uh push the button oxygen version where you're on a ship running out of oxygen and you need to
complete a gauntlet of mini games before you suffocate push the button experts edition each
player has a hidden expertise and needs to convince others that they are the expert saboteurs lie
about their expertise and this goes on push the button word edition push the button escape pods
And finally, we're back to just calling it push the button again.
There's a rotating captain who can pick from a set of activities to challenge the others
and deduce who the aliens are. So some things that helped were letting a captain choose a task
and also choosing who will complete the task. So not everyone does every task
and there's some strategy in the choice of who's going to complete the task.
If you've played Push the Button, you know that a lot of these choices that you see here didn't
make it into the game. You can't airlock a player or lose three minutes, you know,
for no reason, or skip a captain.
There's obviously a lot of hidden identity games out there.
If you'll remember, one of the criteria that we look for is ideas that wouldn't work better
as a tabletop game.
And that's one of the things that made Push the Button compelling was that there was this
constantly ticking clock, this timer, and it puts pressure on players.
And that's something that would be really hard to do elegantly in a tabletop game.
In pre-pandemic times, almost all of our games start out as paper and pencil tests.
It's common in November to just see scraps of paper and post-its with weird stuff written
and drawn on them strewn about conference rooms. This is an early prototype of Champed Up here,
Mr. Pinch and Harold Handy. This is another game that never got made.
Not really sure what's going on with that baby's arms.
Here's another paper prototype of a game.
Spiders.
Yeah.
OK, one more.
I just like showing these because they're funny.
Bag of lint, head and torso, old fishing net.
This year, however, we had to rely
on a bunch of different tools.
For example.
complicated spreadsheets and Google Sheets was a tool we used to test games remotely
over video conference since we were all working from home. So this spreadsheet here is a test of
what would ultimately become Thriplash, the final round for Quiplash 3.
We also use Tabletop Simulator.
Roll20 is a tool that's used to run tabletop role-playing games
like D&D. So here's a playtest we did using that.
You can make what you will of this.
Here we are using Jamboard, which is
Google's whiteboarding tool.
This is a test of a game that will actually
be in Party Pack 8 that we haven't announced yet.
So feel free to study it and try to figure out
what's going on here.
with Mr. Fingers and Randy Blandy.
Here's another test of the same game.
In this game, weirdly, it uses a mechanic
that was first used in Poop Cake.
Remember Poop Cake from before?
Arnie Niekamp, who pitched Poop Cake,
actually demoed the paper and pencil version
on a charity Twitch stream because...
We figured, you know, normally we don't show games like that that we haven't released in case we want to release them later.
But we figured it's not like we're ever going to make poop cake.
Right. And little did we know, a core mechanic of poop cake would end up in a game in Party Pack 8.
I can't believe how many times I just said poop cake.
Anyway, after the paper and pencil testing or Jamboard or Google Sheets or whatever,
we often make a digital prototype. And this is a digital prototype of that same mystery game
I've been showing. More spiders in this version.
And here's another example of a digital version of a game. This is JobJob.
which we announced will be in the Jackbox Party Pack 8.
And this is what it looked like maybe a month ago.
And the team is hard at work making it look
not like this anymore. So we're really excited to get more games
out in the world. We love this process. It's been very fun for us.
And this is what we're working on now. We have five games in production for
the Jackbox Party Pack 8.
and I know the whole team at Jackbox Games can't wait for everyone to play them.
So thank you so much and I'm Evan Jakover from Jackbox Games. I hope this recorded
and I hope you have a great Game Developers Conference. Thank you again.