All right, it's probably right about time to get started.
So let's go ahead and do that.
How's everyone doing today?
So good, right?
Yeah, you made it, it's Friday, you're still alive,
you should be proud, right?
Hopefully we'll do you proud as well.
I'm Roger Altheiser, I'm moderating this panel
with actually talented people.
And we'll start with introductions going from my right.
Hi, my name is Rachel Leiker,
I am the UI UX lead at Hardsuit Labs.
Hey, I'm Chris, I'm a content designer
on the World of Warcraft team at Blizzard.
Hi, I'm Vivian Wong.
I'm a technical designer at AtWat, as I call it.
Andrew Witz.
I'm lead in multiplayer modes and systems
at 343 Industries.
You guys announced a game last night, didn't you, Rachel?
We did, Bloodlines 2.
Ooh, that's gonna be a pretty good game.
Thank you, everyone.
You know it's a good game when you get another one.
All right, so introductions.
Let's talk real quick about that.
So you all have these great jobs.
How did you get to be you?
Let's do a real short one on that.
My background is in marketing and sort of content design,
and really I just kind of got bored with that,
so I decided to look into UI UX.
I went to school.
I got my master's degree at the University of Utah Entertainment
Arts and Engineering Program.
And from there, I sort of stumbled into a few jobs,
indie programs, things like that,
and then landed my first real gig at BossKey Productions
via networking, and then moved to Seattle
and applied out of the blue for Hardsuit and landed that gig.
So.
I actually started off doing GamesPress early on for a couple different websites.
One of them was Destructoid many years ago for about a year.
And then I'd always wanted to get into game development.
the cards kind of aligned.
I went to DigiPen, got a bachelor's there,
did a couple internships, one at Blizzard on WoW
and one at BossKey as well.
I turned into like a full-time gig,
shipped LawBreakers, rest in peace.
And then now I'm back working on WoW at Blizzard.
Hey Chris, how'd you fall into those internships?
People always ask me.
So when I was in my junior year at DigiPen,
We were all sort of hustling to try to figure out how we were going to get real big boy game design jobs after we graduated.
So my team and I, we all just started kind of working together to put out as many applications as we could.
I also was attending GDC, tried to talk to as many people as I could.
I think it's helpful to try to sneak into parties if you can, and you don't know anyone,
just don't be afraid to make friends while you're standing in line, even though you know
you don't have the invite.
And that actually did work out for me.
But your mileage may vary, so be careful.
And then same thing for BossKey, I just kind of applied for the internship, got a design
test back.
I did everything I could to research the role I wanted to go for and it managed to work
out okay.
Sweet, sweet.
Yeah, so I went to UC Santa Cruz's program for game design and...
Nice.
That's a great program, right?
It's pretty good, it's very CS focused,
so that's kind of the background I come from.
I struggled a little bit to get a job in the industry.
I kept coming back to GDC though, as a volunteer.
And eventually I got a design test set of that
and kind of became a content designer,
and then a level designer, and then a tutorial designer,
and now I'm a technical designer.
That's a lot of designer roles.
Yeah.
For me, I pretty much was making games on my own.
I have a bachelor's in creative writing, which was great.
It helped me kind of think differently from UMass Amherst.
And I kind of was working in startup tech in Boston
and while making games on the side
and learning how to program a bit more.
And finally, I was a digital media specialist.
and uh... i just really wanted to make games professionally i just like really
want to make is my hope is that somehow i would end up making games
professionally through uh... being a digital media uh...
uh... employee uh... didn't really see that immediately i was so hungry to kind of make
my own games uh... and uh... get paid for them the dream uh... and uh...
i went to uh...
University of Utah at the EAE program and I was there for about a year and I was hired by Ubisoft
after a year and
That was just for that was the year of making five games
simultaneously and I ended up getting my first gig as an internship at Ubisoft Montreal and
Then joined the Rainbow six siege team when it was just starting up. Yeah, I've heard of this game
Awesome. So we also want to talk not just about breaking in,
but what it's like to have a successful early career.
So rather than talking about like how you built your portfolio and got a job,
I'd like to talk about how your portfolio is now and what it does for you. Uh,
Vivian, you want to lead us off on that?
I have a very minimalist portfolio.
I basically just have my website and it has the four most recent games I've worked on,
my role, what technologies I use to make those games, and a brief description of the game.
I usually try and fit in a video.
That's about it.
Oh, nice.
I like it, right?
Nice and small and light.
Yeah, it's very, I try to basically create as less,
the least amount of friction as possible,
so people can really just high level
get an idea of my skills and what games I've worked on.
No, I actually think it's great.
I am never happy with my portfolio.
I am never happy with it.
I feel as though even if I just nailed it and I'm like, yeah, this is me, I'm just always
like this is not at all me at the same time.
It's just, I don't know, I'm always struggled with assembling my work and showing it off
because especially design, showing off the different stages and different things, it's
kind of a really difficult thing to do because you end up talking about it.
And GDC ended up being a really great spot to do that.
We all travel here to, hey, how did you do this thing?
How did you make this experience?
How are you thinking about things?
And you want to do that in a portfolio across the board.
It's like, what is your process and stuff?
And I feel as though it's hard to do that in a snapshot for
me, so I struggle to make them.
And a best practice I do is just start from the finished
product and work my way back, which is different from how
you see things, where you go from your original idea and
see how you failed till you got that thing.
So it's kind of an inverse thing for me.
It kind of helps me.
I still struggle with them though.
I don't know if I'll ever kind of like be like,
yeah, I'm an expert at portfolios.
Right, yeah, fair enough.
I was kind of in the same boat a bit too.
And like we actually had an assignment in school.
It was just like, build a portfolio.
I'm like,
I don't know that I've ever seen really like what a design portfolio looks like.
Not sure how to structure that.
Started asking people like, hey, what do you look for in a design portfolio?
Got a lot of like, that's a good question.
What do we look like?
We'll look for in a design portfolio.
So like clearly like I was lost.
People that were like hiring for the roles were also like unclear on what advice to offer.
So I started thinking about like.
I don't even know what an interview is like for a design position.
Oh God, I'm out of my depth, what do I do?
So I structured my portfolio as how would I want to experience an interview?
If I can give someone content to basically have
questions to ask me that I've already thought answers through for,
then that's how I wanted to set my portfolio up.
So I just put all my digital analog.
games, writing whatever that I thought was relevant,
kind of set it up into different categories.
And I've never actually culled any of my work
from the portfolio, so I like to have my homepage
sort of set up as like a linear progression
of like, here's where I was like X amount of years ago
versus like my most recent shipped products
and I kind of try to include some stuff that,
problems I solved so that if I get asked about them,
like I'm not floundering to come up with things
to talk about.
I like flounder portfolios and social media.
Yeah, so social media can actually enhance your portfolio experience quite a bit because
you can shoot out your pieces in a very succinct manner and people typically can grab onto
those things a lot easier than your traditional portfolio website.
So if you have an Instagram, if you have a Facebook, if you're on Twitter.
Just throw your stuff out there and you can make some nice color commentary about the
piece, kind of what you learned, your process, things like that.
And that can be both invaluable to employers, but also to other people who are kind of in
the industry or looking to get into the industry.
They can learn a lot from things like that.
Andrew, what are you doing with social media these days?
Talking about wrestling.
Nice, nice.
Actually, it's important though, right, to talk about that personal stuff.
Yeah, I think so.
I think who you are is, I mean, if you're comfortable
with it, right, it's a big level of comfort
when you wanna talk about things that you think about
and your interests, I think that's really good.
It kind of helps develop, I think it helps build
soft skills with yourself, and so when you start
collaborating with other people, you can kind of know
how to start those conversations and get common ground
with people you work with, which I think is super important
for building that family aspect of a dev team.
And that's kind of how I've always worked,
is just kind of sitting down with people
and what are you interested in?
What do you do?
What games do you play?
It's all kind of the, it seems really easy.
This is like a very, like it's common advice,
but I feel as though it's really the best advice
is just, you know, talking to people
and then doing that for yourself,
of talk about things online that you're interested in
and really kind of elaborate on them and share those things.
I mean, that's why I kind of talk about wrestling a lot, is because I like it a lot and I think
about it a lot.
And it actually does help me in my game design.
But we'll talk about that later.
One thing to keep in mind with social media, though, is that when you do land your job
with a studio or a company, is to check their social media policies, because sometimes they
have rules about those kinds of things.
But also, it's good to kind of learn what the company's stance on certain things are.
so that you can either mirror those
or they can provide resources for you to talk about them
and that makes your job super easy.
Yeah, a lot of companies have policies about that
professional, personal, social media thing
that governs both sides of that, right?
They do, very much so.
You using social media at all?
I do, sort of.
On occasion?
On occasion.
I used to talk about Twitter Tuesday.
I used to be more active on Twitter
and I really just like retweet cool stuff
that I see other people tweeting about.
I kind of backed off of it a lot.
And again, it's one of those things
like your mileage may vary.
I think it's cool to build up your circle of people
that are doing things that inspire you
and try to connect with them in that way.
It makes breaking the ice if you wanna meet somebody
who you look up to at GDC a lot easier.
So that's kind of what I try to use it for now
more than anything else.
That's a perfect segue into our topic on networking.
Vivian, he set you up.
Do you wanna talk about networking and how you do it?
I, for the longest time, still actually have a terrible time networking.
The thing that was really a breakthrough for me though was realizing that networking is
a skill all in itself.
I used to think that you were either just good at networking or you're bad at networking.
just not true. So that's another thing that coming to GDC every year has been so helpful
because you just get in the practice of kind of making those connections, making those small talk
conversations happen and then once you know what games like you have in common and you've played
you can talk about like, hey did you see this like cool event they designed? How do you think
they did that? Why do you think they did that? And you can make a lot of friends that way.
Yeah, I actually, I was not always a, I don't even think I'm really a good networker now.
I mean, I think I just, I like to talk about games a lot, especially games that I'm playing.
Anywhere I've worked, I kind of always just walk around the studio kind of asking people
like if they're playing the new game that just released or any, or what are people talking
about.
and or is anything that someone is playing and then if I don't know what it is, I immediately
start playing it at home or something just to kind of talk about it.
I think that's a great way to start.
I think there's always ways to improve being a good networker and especially inside of
your own organization.
Collaboration is really easy when you kind of know people and you get to know people
and you have a shared connection.
Andrew, you got a personal story about that?
Yeah, yeah, sure.
So yeah.
I would say uh probably on Rainbow I was like number one moving to a new country. Canada is
not like super far away but Montreal uh being an English speaker as well. I'm not a good
French speaker at all. Uh and so it was at first I thought it was really daunting my first
year in the industry of you know this is my first uh triple A gig and also like I don't I'm
really worried about communication and I was kind of really nervous about that and um I was
uh really surprised at my dev my my my um.
team around me actually reached out to me really well and like you know really were talking to me
about hey what are you playing and I would say I don't play play new games lately because you know
I'm just starting I've been a student for a while but I am playing this mobile game and then all of
a sudden like my whole team was kind of playing the mobile game we were all playing it together
and then we started playing games a lot together as breaks you know like lunch breaks and stuff
and then like after work and like celebratory moments a lot of samurai gun was played by
rainbow six dev team a lot of samurai gun
That's awesome, that's awesome.
So this next topic could be like its own talk, right?
Applying, interviewing, and landing a job.
So we're gonna do like a little bit of a lightning round.
I want each of you to tell your best story
or worst story about applying for and landing a job.
Who's brave enough to go first?
I certainly will. So, uh, when I first interviewed at hard suit labs and they
told me what the project was, which was bloodlines too, I fangirled out really
hard, like to the point where I was convinced I was not going to get that
job because they were just like, we cannot trust this person. And, but Hey,
I got the job and it was fine because they were looking for passionate people.
So, so that's not just a bumper sticker. They would say, oh, we want
passionate people. Yes, they actually did. And so I'm, I'm actually kind of
glad that I didn't turn myself down during that interview.
Did you show them your fanfic?
I was unprepared to show it.
They know about it now, though.
Andrew, go for it.
I think the interview that was most awkward for me was it
was a lunch interview.
I landed a lunch interview, and I actually spent the
majority of the lunch interview eating and not talking.
And so it was a lot of just like.
It was just a really big waste of time for that person.
I felt really bad, but I ate a lot because I was a student
and I was really hungry.
I was really hungry that day.
So that's actually a really good pro tip.
I actually had a recruiter once tell me,
tell all of your students to order salads,
foods that you can eat and still talk.
I'm so tired of people drinking soup during meetings, right?
Never get the sandwich.
Never trust the sandwich.
Nothing that's gonna fill your mouth
and make you tell it real quick.
Evan, you got one for us?
My best interview was probably, I was hustling at GDC on the expo floor and this company
called Carbine was like, hey, we desperately need new content designers.
This was a Friday at GDC, I had been volunteering the whole week and I was deliriously tired.
So everything he said, I was just like, yes, absolutely, I can do that, whatever, it's
cool.
And I guess I was just so tired that I became confident.
exhausted into success.
He was so impressed.
He was like, I'm not even going to give you the design test.
I'm just going to like send you an offer later.
Wow.
All right.
So, so you CA your way into a job, huh?
You just work hard, get exhausted.
I, um.
I was trying to think of a story that would be in line with what you guys are talking
about, but I'll take it from a different angle.
So something, as I've done more interviews, I've started to realize that I didn't realize
early on in my career was...
Interview them as much as they're interviewing you and don't be afraid to do that when you're like starting out
And you're really like hungry about like I just really want to get this job. It's my first job. This would be awesome
You don't really think about all the things that might be important to you once you're doing that job
And like what could be deal-breakers for you and what may might make your life miserable and kind of rob you of
All that like passion. It's it's a hard job to get into so don't
don't discount yourself.
And so I had an interview where I got through the whole thing
and halfway through, I realized, hey, this job's not really
for me.
I don't want this role.
I don't think I would jive with the team.
I don't think I would be passionate about doing
the work.
And I still went through the interview.
I wanted to see how everything unfolded.
And at the end of it, my...
my initial suspicions were pretty much like confirmed when we talked later and it was it was cool because I didn't feel bad to get the
The like rejection letter it was just like nope this this all makes sense
and so that's something that I would um
Like strongly urge you to always keep in mind as you are dealing with interviewing is don't just um
Kind of grab the first thing that like comes back to you
Uh, really sort of think carefully about it before you dive into something that could be a multiple year endeavor. Um in your life
What's it like now?
So you're not first jobbers now, right?
You're all like seasoned and hardened
and like rough and tumble veterans, right?
So what's it like looking around now?
Like some of you have changed jobs, some of you haven't.
For those of you who have,
what's the difference in the process?
I think the, I think.
Going off of what Chris just said, that's something that I think thinking about how
you go in, particularly in an interview, but I think it goes with everything else, is that
think about what you want, but also be okay to ask questions.
I feel as though that's one of the best things that ended up in my maturity in this industry
was just wanting to ask questions.
Because it seems really scary, because asking a question in a lot of ways kind of...
it already tells somebody, or your brain kind of tells you that, oh, if you're asked a question,
then they know you don't know something. So that's why you're asking it. And so the premise
is really terrifying, right? Asking a question is immediately terrifying. If you normalize that,
and kind of, you know, just, you know, the terror is always going to be there,
but always be comfortable asking questions.
Because when you ask questions, that's when you learn,
and you learn a lot easier.
And always ask questions to your teammates,
in an interview, anytime.
Always ask questions if you want to know the answer to something,
if you don't know something.
Acknowledging you don't know something, I think,
is probably one of the most powerful things
in being more mature in this industry.
Whether it's with tools, or just you don't even
understand a new genre, a design, anything.
It just helps you learn a lot faster,
because the premise of the question is,
I want to learn this thing.
And you seek out that information.
What's a scary question you've had to ask like what's what's an example something like that?
I would say one of the scariest questions is, you know, when you don't know how to implement
something. I would say for a designer, like for me, I think the hardest question I had
was there was something that I was just like, I was assigned a feature and you're like,
and you kind of know what you want to do and you go, all right, I want to build this thing.
And then your next step is you kind of want to say, how do I, how do I build this? Yeah.
Right. Cause it's almost just like, all right, am I not the right person to build it? But
I'm excited about it and I want to do it, but it just kind of saying, I'm being comfortable
saying I don't know how to do this.
And saying that to your team is a very terrifying thing.
But when you say that, and you explain what you do know
about it, and you explain your design, that becomes a
collaboration, a collaborative moment
between you and your team.
And if you and your team are close, you'll find that
people want to support you because you're a team together.
that they will actually, you know, they'll work with you
and they'll work through that problem with you
and you'll educate each other on the way.
And so I think like, that's the most terrifying thing
for me is just saying, I have a great idea.
Great, what is it?
It's this, oh, that's a good idea.
Yeah, I have no idea how to do this.
That's awesome.
Yeah, I don't have an idea how to do most of the things I do.
All right.
So let's talk a little bit about surviving and thriving.
That was intended to trip me up, wasn't it?
So we, how's it go?
We live to work or we work to live, right?
That's the tension, right?
So you're doing this thing and you want to be happy, right?
What are some keys to being happy in this career?
Like specific ones, like not general advice.
Like what are things that you are doing so that you are happy in your job?
One thing that I like to do, and I also express this to my team, is be really explicit about
where you would like to be in the future, either at a company or just personally, professionally,
and articulate those things to your leadership.
Because a lot of the times, to them, it indicates that you are willing to stay on and that you
are comfortable here and you want to proceed.
And it also gives them a chance to help you develop your tool set, help you learn software,
help you with interpersonal skills, whatever your particular dream or progression wants
to be, they will be invested in you and that is a very important thing.
Yeah, your managers want to mentor you.
Yes.
They want to hear that you're hungry to grow.
Yes, very much so.
Well, how about the rest of you?
What's something you're doing right now to make this career something you enjoy doing
that you want to thrive in?
I would say...
It's easy if you dive in head first and you're kind of fresh
and you're not sure where you want to end up with your role.
If you're a designer, there's so many different ways
that you can go with that.
There are lots of sub-disciplines.
So it's helpful to kind of identify early,
not just maybe what work you need to do,
but also what work you really enjoy doing
that gets you fired up.
So if you're really, uh, uh, look at you fired up with an example that for you,
like, so, uh, so for me, like, I think, uh, solving really challenging problems,
uh, in systems and gameplay in particular, uh, is super cool.
I think, uh, that sort of stuff is what pushes our medium forward.
And so if you can.
like find an opportunity to grab onto something
that you're like, oh man, I really wanna work on that,
and you can express that to other people on your team
and find a way to collaborate on that thing,
you're gonna do some of your best possible work
if you can put yourself into that situation.
And you're gonna feel more confident in your skill set
after you've successfully completed that thing,
you're gonna have learned a lot,
and you're gonna have seen the end result of your action
in players' hands, and you're gonna be like,
oh.
okay, like I feel better as like a designer or programmer or whatever, um, now that I've
like completed this thing and that just continues to build upon itself like the longer that
you, uh, you're doing your job for. Awesome. We're going to do three minutes. We're going
to go to the next slide then we'll get to it. Okay. Unless you got a story, right? You
got a burning story?
I would just add to that is just learning how to give good feedback is a really big
thing on how to survive and thrive.
I would say learning how to give feedback really shows where you are.
Always assume people are coming from the best position and then asking them where are they
coming from and then when you give feedback you can kind of give that as a razor whether
or not that feature or thing is kind of at the bar that you want that they do expect
it to be.
So, that's one of the... it can be a whole talk, but like...
What's the secret sauce of you giving feedback real quick?
Like, you're really mean, like you kick them and give them feedback?
No, no, never, no, not that at all.
So, I would say that one of the...
the best thing is just have a conversation with somebody and ask somebody.
If you're playing something...
or if you're working a feature,
what do you think is the best scenario for this feature?
Because then you get educated about
where that feature's gonna go,
and then what are the goals for that feature?
Then when you give that feedback,
you can give it in alignment with that versus,
this is, I just don't like this.
This is just, why would I, why is this in the game?
Like, you know, that's kind of this feedback loop
that we call, as players, we all kind of wonder these things
and then go back to being a player and not as a dev, right?
It's really good to maintain that dev perspective.
And not lose the player perspective.
It's always good to say, I don't understand something.
Yeah, fair enough.
Vivian, I got one for you.
You ready?
Uh-oh.
Yeah.
It's the big one, right?
Plotting your career.
Looking at where you are and planning your future.
What do you do?
So I'm a notorious meanderer.
I didn't really know what I wanted to do, which might be obvious based on my career
trajectory.
I was kind of just happy to do whatever came across my plate.
And I think that's kind of the one thing that's changed recently in my career is I found technical
design and I think it's really clicked with me.
Especially when it like makes sense.
I used to do tech in theater and I love solving problems for people.
And I also used to make a lot of macros when I played WoW
so that I didn't have to press as many scary buttons.
So it kind of all...
Oh, and also, this is my favorite one.
When I played Dragon Age Origins,
and in combat you could program your allies
to do certain things at certain points in the battle.
I just didn't play combat anymore
because I just programmed my allies to be perfect.
Yeah, you're a technical term.
That sounds about right.
Awesome.
My place.
Who else has a ... So we've got like a minute left before we open it up to questions.
Who else has a tip on plotting your career, taking stock of where you are and planning
for the future?
I think I have one, and I'll be short.
One thing that I like to do with pretty much
every aspect of my life is learn as much as I can
about something that is not my discipline.
And I don't have to go into in-depths
about like AI planning or anything like that,
but just having base knowledge of those around you
really helps with pretty much everything.
So get involved.
Yeah, I couldn't agree.
We should always be learning,
but always learning on the job is, yeah,
it's pretty valuable.
All right, we want you to keep in touch with us.
We're gonna open up for questions.
We have like a couple minutes to answer some questions
so we don't run over.
But you can also reach out to any of us.
We are all happy to chat with you at any time.
This community is all about that networking
and so we are all about that as well.
If you would like to ask the panel a question,
please step up to the mic.
Bonus points if it is a question and not a speech.
Triple bonus points if it's a short question
and not a question that requires you
to give your resume before asking it.
All right, who's got the first one?
We're gonna go over here.
All right.
OK.
That's good distance.
So I'm a first year student, and I always hear this word
networking, networking, networking.
Can you give me an example of what a short, simple, hi, my
name is blank, and I'm trying to network with you, but not
be obvious about it?
Can you try and give me an example of that?
Oh man. Can you even answer it? Honestly, I would just be explicit about it. Like, I
think that networking shouldn't just be about like, hey, I really love 343. What jobs can
you offer me? Like, that's the only, in my opinion, that's the only wrong thing you could
do in networking. But if you just say like, hey, I'm trying to network, make connections
in the industry, I think people who are interested in making those connections with you are like
more than happy to keep talking.
It should be organic.
Like, don't like brute force networking, right?
I hate the term networking in and of itself,
because it just sounds bad.
Just go to game-related things and make friends with people.
And if you have a tough time doing that,
figure out what your social lubricant is.
People often suggest alcohol, but it does not
have to be that at all.
Don't think that it does.
I think that's probably not great advice.
So if it's like you're at like a Smash Bros tournament or something,
or you see somebody wearing a t-shirt that's a game that you like,
that's your in.
And then if the conversation isn't working out,
then learn how to gracefully exit it.
And if it does work out, then keep in touch,
and those relationships will build up over time.
And I think that's kind of like what a lot of us have experienced
as we worked at different studios as well.
Yeah, like, don't brute force it, dude.
I literally had a student land his first job by walking up to somebody and say,
I know I'm blowing this moment,
can you help me not blow the next one?
Any tips at all, you don't need to remember me,
and then they went to lunch.
So I think that trying is also a big part of it. It's a great question.
Thank you very much.
So, Chris, I'm in exactly the position that you were a few years ago when you described,
I'm a junior at DigiPen trying to finish and refine my portfolio, and I don't know what
people want on a design portfolio.
For all of you, what do they want to see on a design portfolio, more specifically a systems
design portfolio?
Oh man.
I would say, so, there's no great answer for this, obviously, but I would say what I look
for, you know, whenever I'm hiring designers or a system designer, is I usually like seeing
the, like, the most recent projects.
and a short description of the project,
and then exactly what you did,
and anything that can breadcrumb me
to kind of find out what that project is.
Because then there's some common ground
for me to ask some questions, right?
You kind of like, it's common ground for me to kind of go,
oh, this game's really cool,
okay, they've had a lot of experience in this kind of game,
or this kind of game,
they'd be great for this,
this seems like this is a strong suit.
Those are all opportunities for me to ask you questions
about what, am I right in this is kind of what you want to do,
the systems you want to design.
Are you an expert in this?
Do you want to be an expert in something else?
It's more of a call to action for me to ask questions to you about what you want.
And so if it's a great fit, then awesome.
And so I would say start there of like, of think about of breadcrumb there.
If you have a really great system that you've had or a really great prototype, having a
video or a playable or anything like that is definitely bonus points, like absolutely
bonus points.
I would also say that a lot of these things, it's sort of a great lie where people say
these are the tips to do the thing.
That's not how dev works either, right?
We iterate and we test and we iterate and we test.
So he's talked about system designers, so the best advice is actually
to pull out your phone and after this talk,
meet him across the hall and show him your portfolio
and have him tell you what's wrong with your portfolio
rather than saying this abstract principle
to this to my portfolio.
Show people and people are receptive to
what's wrong with my portfolio.
And they'll straight tell you.
We have one minute left.
If you have the world's quickest question, we can do it.
What can students and young developers do
while they're still growing their skills
to kind of plant the seeds for their career
when they actually have them?
Ship games.
Cool.
No, make them small.
The biggest mistake that students make is they make things too big.
The first games you should be making, you should be getting them done in a week, right?
And then you can grow to a month, and then you can grow to a year.
But get some things done.
Who else has stuff?
Yeah, I definitely agree with that.
My first game that I made collectively
was about a sentient piece of cheese
that ran around a railroad.
And we made that in a week, and it was a 2D game,
and it was ridiculous.
But that was really hard, and we made it,
and it was a playable, and we had like two levels.
The pains of making that game actually set me up for how I wanted to get better and learn more things.
Show off a really polished core mechanic or system or something that defines your game and makes it fun and just end it there.
Don't try to blow it out of the water on your first try.
so we don't get railroaded out of here.
Railroad, cheese, railroad, blah, blah, blah.
Yeah, it's a great song.
We're going to be across the hall,
and we're happy to answer any questions you might have.
Hey, thank you so much for coming.
We really appreciate it.
Remember to fill out the form and vote on those things.
It's radically important.
You're beautiful and awesome.
Bye.