Thank you.
This is a great opportunity for those of us who already do this full-time to also branch
out into consulting, freelance work.
I've been doing exactly that for the last few years.
And in the next 20 or so minutes, I'm going to kind of share with you some of the mistakes
I made, some of the pitfalls I found.
So maybe if you're interested in this as well, you can avoid those.
Who am I? I am the senior tech artist at StrayKite Studios.
I've been in the industry for about eight years now.
I've worked on things like those.
But more pertinent to this talk,
back at the tail end of 2019,
I started freelancing and consulting as Technically Games.
And in that time, I have worked on things like that.
But I'll get to that later.
So why would you even want to do this, right?
You're already doing it full-time during the day.
Why would you also want to fill your free time with tech art?
Well, for me, there's three main reasons.
One, like I said, the demand is absolutely booming right now.
In prep for this talk, I checked the job pages of EA, Ubisoft,
and Activision.
And between those three, there are
over 400 open tech art or tech art-related positions.
And if you've been in any sort of position
to hire a tech artist lately, you've
probably seen this shortage firsthand.
Two, it can be really lucrative.
Tech art is obviously a technical skill,
and you can charge like it.
Now, when you're doing this part time, like I'm doing,
you're probably not going to retire to the Caribbean.
You're probably not going to buy a yacht.
But you might be able to buy a car, or go on a vacation,
pay off some student loans.
And three, it can just be plain fun.
You get to work with people you would never be able to.
You get to work on really cool projects.
You get to expand your skill set into areas
that maybe your day job would never have you see.
So let me show you some of my numbers
so you kind of get a sense of what I'm talking about.
When I started this back at the tail end of 2019,
I had one contract that just kind of fell into my lap,
made a little over $500.
But it kind of broke me out of a creative rut, right?
I did a cool thing, it was fun.
I decided, hey, if something comes along,
I'll probably keep doing this.
Then 2022 came along and I went from commuting for an hour and a half every day to sitting in my office for 16 hours a day.
A few other contracts came along to at the beginning of the year, one at the end of the year, and made a little over three thousand dollars with that last contract, especially.
I really found that I was kind of getting into it. I really started to enjoy myself. I incorporated
as Technically Games and I decided that in 2021 I really wanted to hit the ground running.
Last year I took on 15 contracts between January and September,
made a little over $20,000.
I really started to get the hang of it.
I really started to learn how to work with clients.
I started to learn what I like to do, what I don't like to do,
how to find contracts, all of that kind of stuff.
I got really burnt out at the end of the year.
And I'll go over that later.
I actually took October through December completely off.
It was not great.
And like I said, because I'm only doing this part time,
it's not, I mean, I'm not going to retire off of that.
I'm not going to quit my day job.
But it did help me pay down some student loans
and for a down payment on a house.
So you're sitting there and you're like, okay, this sounds interesting, when do I start?
There's a first, a few things you really need to do before you start.
Number one, always check your non-compete with your employer.
A lot of studios and publishers don't allow moonlighting whatsoever.
Always check your employer agreement for this kind of stuff.
If you have any doubts about whether or not you can do this kind of stuff,
always talk to your lead or always talk to HR.
I've found that these employee agreements for the moonlighting clauses are always really vague and broad.
They say things like you can't compete with our business interests, but what does that really mean?
Does that mean you can't work on video games? You can't work in specific genres?
to specific demographics.
And if you work at a place like, say, EA,
who makes games for everybody in every genre
for every demographic, that can be really limiting.
So you really want to make sure.
The last thing you want to do, though, is be sneaky.
Don't try to find the gray areas.
Don't try to find where you can kind of slip
in between the cracks.
That can really put you in legal trouble,
but it can also really put your clients in legal trouble.
Think kind of John Carmack with Oculus, right?
And if you are looking at a new place of employment,
always include this in your negotiations.
Some places will be really strict
about their non-compete.
Some places you might be able to redline the non-compete
or better yet, go to a place that doesn't have one
in the first place.
So once you have that out of the way,
you know you can do this stuff,
you really need to lay some groundwork first.
The very first thing you need to do,
the very first thing I wish I would have done
is to form an LLC.
An LLC basically is just a corporate entity
that you work under that protects your private assets.
So if somebody decides to sue you,
they have to sue your business.
They don't sue you personally.
If they want to get to your money, your assets,
they have to go after the company's assets.
They can't go after your personal stuff.
Really important.
You're going to want to make a separate bank account.
You do not want your invoices from your clients
going where your W-2 income comes from.
That just muddies the water.
It can really introduce doubt if somebody decides to sue you.
So you really want to keep these things separate.
Additionally, that really helps with taxes,
makes taxes a lot easier when everything is in one place.
It really helps with expenses as well.
You know that basically everything that's coming out of
the account is probably an expense
because you need to get an accountant.
An accountant will help you with expenses.
I really wish I would have done this sooner.
I only did it about six months ago.
Tech art is already pretty stressful.
It's a really big subject.
You don't want to compound that by also
having to learn tax law.
And in the US, there's this thing
called estimated quarterly taxes.
And it doesn't make any sense.
So please hire somebody to do this for you whose job it
is to do this for you.
It's money well spent, I promise you.
You're also really going to want to figure out your payment
processing sooner rather than later.
This is kind of a really big subject, but for me,
I never accept PayPal anymore.
They're kind of shady, right?
And I also don't accept credit card payments anymore.
Basically, all of the payment processing websites
or whomever out there, they will charge a 3% to 5% fee
on all credit card transactions.
So when your contracts are a little smaller,
maybe that's not much.
But once your contracts get to a certain size, that's...
a car payment, right? So now I only take ECH or wire transfers. Usually there is also a
fee on this as well, but they're almost always capped at something like $5, so it's much
more manageable. Um, okay, so we have all the boring stuff out of the way. Now there's a
little bit less boring stuff, but still kind of boring stuff.
You want to make a list of things that you actually want to do.
Get it out on paper. Prioritize the list.
Do you want to do rigging? Do you want to do tools?
Do you want to do shader work?
Get it out on a list so you can see it whenever you're talking to a client.
And probably more importantly,
make a list of things you absolutely don't want to do.
Because when a client comes to you,
and they're waving a big paycheck in your face with something you don't want to do, you want
to have that list in front of you to remind you why you don't want to do it. For instance, I
don't do any contracts that involve unity anymore and I don't do shaders. I did a contract
that involved shaders, I'll kind of talk about that later. It wasn't good. I'm terrible at it,
I don't really enjoy it, it was bad.
Unfortunately, I think social media is kind of required, at least to start with.
Probably half of my clients have come from just seeing random Twitter posts.
It's unfortunate, but I feel like it's kind of necessary.
Design an invoice, make it professional, make it easy to read, and if you can, design a
logo or better yet, hire somebody to design a logo for you.
And going back to those expenses, logos are expensible, which is very nice.
Um, when you first start out, you really want to brush up your portfolio when you're real,
especially, I've found, as the more junior you are, you really want to have a rock solid
real. This gets a lot less important as time goes on, once your kind of word of mouth
starts to grow with your clients and among their networks. You don't have to pay so much
attention to this, but you know, it's probably always good to have. Okay, so all that's out of
the way, you're ready to do the thing. Before you start the thing.
Always charge for art tests.
I know this is a very controversial subject
for some people.
I think we should just do it as an industry.
If you're asking somebody to spend their time,
you should compensate them for it.
But especially more so in this case.
Remember that you are not a candidate for a job,
you are a company.
They are one of your clients, a potential client.
If they need you to do an art test,
you should charge them for it.
I usually charge a flat fee to make it a lot easier on everybody.
But still, you should do this.
And be really discerning about your clients.
Do your homework.
Check Glassdoor.
That can be a really good option.
Talk to people who currently work there that you trust.
Talk to people who don't work there anymore.
See why they left.
All that kind of stuff.
The way a company treats their internal employees
will be magnified with how they treat
their external contractors.
Bad clients are always worse than no clients.
Remember, you're doing this in your free time,
and yes, this is still a job,
it's not always gonna be awesome,
but you don't wanna compound that
by working with bad people.
So setting your rates could probably be a talk
all in and of itself, but just a few tips for doing this.
Charge like an engineer.
We were actually just talking about this at lunch.
Tech artists, a lot of times, kind of pigeonhole themselves
into, well, I'm just an artist, right?
No, you're doing a highly technical job.
You should charge like an engineer.
So my tip, whenever you're first starting
to get your rate in line, just add 50% to it.
Doesn't matter what it is, just add 50%.
If a client can't pay it, they'll tell you.
But a lot of clients will do it.
Your rate also doesn't need to be static.
You don't have to set a rate and then that's your rate
for the rest of the year or whatever.
You can probably charge a bigger studio or a publisher
your full rate because they can afford it.
But if you're working with some little indie outfit,
maybe a solo dev working on a passion project,
you know, don't undercut yourself,
but still be cognizant of their resources.
Set your rate accordingly.
There's three main variables I take into account whenever I'm setting my rate for a particular contract.
One, the enjoyment of the job, how much do I think I'm actually going to enjoy doing it?
Two, the time frame in which they need it done. Do they need it done in a month? Do they need it done in a week?
That's really important. And three, again, the client resources.
Is it some person in their basement or is it, you know, a multinational corporation?
But for me, what I always do,
I always prioritize enjoyment over the other two.
Again, you're doing this in your free time.
You wanna enjoy yourself.
If you have a bad client who's gonna pay you a lot of money
or a good client who's probably not gonna pay you
as much money, for me, I will always choose the latter
every single day of the week.
Life is way too short not to enjoy yourself.
And let's all be honest, we're in like 2020 part three, right?
You need to enjoy yourself, especially in your free time,
even if you're doing work.
Get to know your client in the kickoff.
You'll probably usually have a Discord meeting
or a Zoom meeting or something like that.
Just get to know who they are.
You don't have to be friends with them necessarily,
but you wanna know their idiosyncrasies.
Are they gregarious?
Are they a straight shooter?
All of that kind of stuff will really help you
when you're talking to them throughout the contract.
This isn't always applicable though.
If you're just working with like the outsource manager,
that's probably just gonna be a bunch of cold emails
back and forth.
Don't sweat it, it's not a big deal.
So I've only been doing this for a while,
that's why the question mark is there,
because these best practices are probably gonna change
as I keep doing this.
I do not have the definitive answers
of how best to do this.
I still make a lot of mistakes,
but these are some of the things that have really helped me.
You wanna really stretch yourself, right?
Tech art is huge.
If you ask 10 different tech artists what tech art is,
nine of them will give you a different answer,
and then that one guy is gonna try
to convert you to Blender.
Don't be that one guy.
You really want to stretch your abilities
and open up your wheelhouse.
Your day job is probably going to see you
do a certain set of things probably over and over.
This is your chance to really do that thing
you've always wanted to do but never had a chance to do.
You want to know your limitations, certainly.
You want to be honest with yourself about your limitations.
Also, don't be overconfident though, like I was. Um, so one of my first contracts was
doing a bunch of shader work, like I said earlier. Um, I thought, hey, this seems pretty
easy, there's a lot of resources out there that will really help jumpstart me into it. I
set my, uh, time range, my time frame based on what I thought it was going to take, instead
of actual real data.
Don't do that.
Always do your research before you accept the contract.
It turned out that I was not good at shaders,
not near as good as I thought I was.
And I ended up spending twice the hours,
but in the same amount of calendar days.
So I just crunched for a month.
It was brutal.
Don't ballpark your hours based on what
you think it's going to take.
Really get the data beforehand.
So working with multiple clients that all have different proprietary plugins and
modules can get really overwhelming. So to manage this, I always set up environments
for every single contract because the last thing you want is for, say, client X's
custom deformer module to get into client Y's scene file. That would be really bad
and especially bad if that stuff got into your employer's files.
that would be really bad. So what I do is actually pretty simple, I just create like a bat
file that just shuffles around all my modules and scripts and I just double click on it
before I start some client work. It removes everything, it brings everything in, so
there's no chance of that kind of intermingling. It doesn't have to be complex, this
doesn't have to be some like huge bat script, some of my bat scripts are literally like
three lines. Just don't overthink it.
Uh, Git Perforce, definitely always, I mean, I'm sure everybody in here knows this,
version control is absolutely crucial. And especially Perforce, I don't know, some people love Git,
um, just use Perforce, um,
It's, it's free for under five users and you are obviously under five users.
Super quick to set up a repo.
It's been invaluable for me, especially when you open that one file and Maya
corrupts it for like the 10th time in a week, you really want to be able to roll back.
So this one sounds like a huge no-brainer, right?
You just need to know your NDAs.
And it probably is a no-brainer, but I don't have common sense,
apparently.
About a year ago, I disclosed some confidential information
in a public setting.
I checked my own NDA first, and I was totally in the clear.
But.
Oops.
A few frantic messages later, I learned
that I had not broken my NDA with my client,
but I had broken my client's NDA with their client.
Can get really tricky.
Just because it's not in your NDA
doesn't mean you're free to talk about it,
especially if you are a subcontractor.
This can get really tricky
as that rabbit hole kind of goes deeper.
So now I just don't talk about anything.
Hence the slides at the beginning.
It can be kind of a bummer, right?
Because you're doing a lot of cool stuff
and you really want to talk about it.
Just don't talk about it.
If you have to in order to kind of land that next contract,
be really vague.
Say what you need to in order to prove that you
know what you're talking about.
But never go in as any sort of specifics.
Just, again, kind of common sense stuff.
Tech art can definitely be mentally exhausting at the best of times.
Once you start filling your free time with it, burnout is almost inevitable,
but there's a lot of things you can do to mitigate this.
Just always remember that this is your business.
It's not a grind. It's not a hustle.
You want longevity, so you really need to take care of your mental health here.
You need to set boundaries with your clients
and with yourself about the amount of time
you're gonna spend, and you need to be really firm about it.
For me, I limit it to 15 to 20 hours a week at max.
Excuse me.
If a client needs more of your time than that,
turn them away.
It can be brutal at times, especially when it's something you really want to work on,
but if they need you for 30 or 40 hours a week, don't do it.
It's not worth it.
There will always be more clients.
Like I said about the huge tech artist shortage right now,
everybody is looking for a tech artist.
I promise you there are more clients out there.
And document your hours for every contract, even if the contract is on a per-deliverable basis.
I'm going to go into this later.
But time estimates, a valid good time estimate
is so crucial.
And then on the back end,
always add 15% to all of your time estimates.
I call this my Maya crash padding.
I love Maya, I really do, but it crashes so much.
You can just never kind of expect
what's going to happen, right?
They're gonna want something in an older version of Unreal
and you have to download that
and you didn't think you were gonna have to.
A Maya file will not open for whatever reason.
You just need that extra padding.
Finally, keep your work life and your freelancer life separate.
And this is especially important now in this world of work from home,
when your work work and your freelance work is right in front of your face at all times of day.
Your employer is paying you for your 40 hours a week, so honor that.
Don't double dip. Don't do two things at once.
It's kind of unfair to your fellow workers.
You really want to set boundaries with your clients right out of the gate about communication
and how much they get of you.
For instance, I'll email during the day because it's usually pretty quick, but I will stay
away from Slack because it can be a huge time sink, and obviously I'll never get on meetings
like Zoom calls or something during the day because those can be a huge time sink.
There will come a time, there will absolutely come a time
when your client will expect and demand you to do work
throughout the day.
The correct answer to this is always no.
They'll push you, but you really need to stand firm on this.
It's really important.
If you can, try to create,
I know this isn't doable for everybody,
but try to create a different physical environment
for your day job and your freelancing work.
Maybe your office is during the day and then
the couch is at night with your laptop or something like that.
Or it can be even simpler than that.
Maybe move some potted plants around,
maybe change the color of the lights.
Just anything to further
that delineation between those two environments.
So looking long term, like I said,
I burned out really hard at the end of last year.
I took October, November, and December off.
I think some of the things I could have done to avoid that were to mix it up more, mix
up the work you're doing.
Remember that one of the reasons you're doing this is for fun, and that's not to say it's
always going to be fun, but going back to prioritizing enjoyment between contracts is
when you really can reassess this and do it.
Actively seek out clients that need something different than your last client
The first three contracts I took on all heavily involved skinning. I was also doing skinning in my day job
I got really burned out. So the next contract I decided to do shaders, which didn't turn out so well
But I think the thought was there
Really take your time finding the right client that's for you.
Again, there's always going to be more clients.
You don't have to take every single job that walks through the door.
If they need you for something that doesn't sound particularly interesting, look for another one.
Or if it's something that you just did, look for another one.
This is really a good time to reevaluate that list that you made at the beginning and kind
of shuffle it around.
Get a new number one, a new number two.
Really kind of reassess yourself after every contract.
Coming back to time estimates, I think this is probably the most important way to avoid
burnout.
you really need to keep track down to the minute if you can of how long different
things take you so your time estimates can be more and more accurate as time goes on.
Um, one of the, like once you have these numbers,
absolutely stick to them.
So what I did was actually just make a little Python tool
that I can just say like, I'm working on a biped
and I'm doing skinning and it'll keep my times
and it'll export all of that to an Excel file
and then I can filter that Excel file.
I can tell exactly how long.
Skinning a biped will take me.
I can tell exactly how long writing a new tool will take me.
And that just helps further along when you're going to that next client, really keeping
your time in track, and then add that 15%.
Aggregate this data from one client to the next as well.
Again, you're just trying to get to that convergence, right?
You're trying to get to a very specific number
of how long it'll take you.
That's not to say that every biped
will take you the same amount of time,
but it's an estimate and you need to get it better.
Annotate it, like I said, if you can.
It's going to take a different amount of time
to work on a biped skin than a quadruped skin.
So you just need that data again.
And finally, probably most importantly,
you really need to take time off.
Remember that this is your business,
and I know every business how-to book,
and just capitalism at large,
tells us that if you're not growing your business,
you're shrinking, but that's just not true in this case.
It can really feel good to make more money than last year.
It can really feel good to have more clients than last year,
but it's not the end-all be-all.
What I found this year is that when I was doing all this work,
I wasn't really enjoying the reward.
I was getting all these invoices in,
and I wasn't using it for anything.
I was just kind of sitting on it like a dragon.
I wasn't going on any vacations.
So what was the point?
You really need to take time off in order
to enjoy the fruits of your labor.
And I've said it plenty of times already, but there will be more clients.
If you need a break, this isn't your day job.
You're not dependent upon this to pay rent or anything like that.
If you need a break, take a break.
If you can feel yourself getting burned out, take a break.
Even if it's just a few weeks, even if it's a month, or in my case, if it was three months,
you have to look out for yourself if you want to do this long-term.
Life is really short, and time is really precious.
And I promise you, you are not going
to regret spending that extra time with your family
or your dog or doing that hobby you love instead of working
on that client project.
So hopefully, I kind of gave you a little bit of sense
of if you want to do this as well, kind of some
of the things you should avoid, some of the things
you should do right out of the gate that I didn't do.
Thanks.
And I think we have like two minutes for questions.
Yes, so I was wondering like.
You know, you talked about like NDAs.
How do you, like, starting out,
how do you build a portfolio to really show
that you can do these things for your clients?
Right.
Again, I think it just goes back to the reel.
You don't want to kind of advertise yourself
as doing something you're not good at.
So if you have a really good rigging reel
or something like that,
go after those contracts in particular.
But really, I think it also comes down
to just being on social media, unfortunately.
Especially to start out with.
That's where I found most of my starting clients.
Just write, they'll post something on Twitter and then you'll message them and then you'll talk for a little bit.
You just have to have that reel up to date so when something does come along, you can kind of jump on it.
Sweet, thank you.
Hi, great talk. I'm just wondering where you find the work. You mentioned social media is about half of your work.
So where do you find the work? And second question, what do you think of freelancer platforms?
I find most of that social media work on Twitter.
Game dev Twitter is bonkers, right?
Everybody is on Twitter in this industry.
That's kind of where I found all of that.
I've never used any sort of freelancer platforms
for anything like that.
I've been really fortunate in that the word of mouth
has been really good, so the other half of my clients
are all from word of mouth.
So I can't really answer that, I guess.
Perfect, thanks.
Hey Taylor. Hey. Um, okay. I had a quick question about when you take your breaks,
like in this case you took like a three month break.
I'm assuming you're going to jump back into it.
How do you make that transition from like not working on stuff,
not talking to clients to just jumping back into working with clients?
Um, I'll tell you when I find out. Um,
Most of this year as well has been on other things.
Just bought a house and all that kind of stuff.
So again, I've been really fortunate in that a lot
of my clients are still asking, like, hey,
whenever you're available, we have work for you.
But I think going forward, I can actually start to,
I've never really advertised myself before on Twitter
or any other forum.
I think that's something that I'll start to do,
actually actively look for clients.
Okay, thank you.
Hey dude, nice talk.
Could you tell us a little bit more
about the kinds of work that you're doing?
Is it like, hey, rig five characters,
skin five characters, make 10 materials
or something like that?
Or is it a more broad like,
hey, we need you to help out for a month?
Yeah, it's kind of both, honestly.
What I've found is that skinning in particular
Everybody needs somebody to do skins for them.
Nobody really wants to do it, right?
So quite a few of my contracts have just been,
hey, we have 12 characters and we need you to skin them
and turn them in when they're done.
But then there are others where it's like, hey,
we have this big project.
We need you for two months.
Just do whatever the art director says kind of deal,
which can be a double-edged sword because you can get
put on tasks that you don't particularly want to do
and maybe you're not even good at.
But again, that just goes back to the communication.
You need to get to know the client in that kickoff meeting
what they actually need.
try to discern what they actually need
instead of what they say they need
because those things are never the same.
But yeah, you just kind of have to work that out
as it goes along.
Cool, thanks.
Hi, thank you for the talk, by the way.
So how do you go about trying new things
or new skills to build up your skill set,
especially when you talk about shaders versus rigging?
Do you do it between clients
or even when you're working a day job and doing this,
how do you find the time to do that?
Usually it's between clients, yes.
Or again, if you've done something for a client
and that might be relevant to your next client,
talk about it but be really vague about what you worked on.
Maybe I worked on this particular system
but don't go into the specifics of it.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Good, thanks.