As those videos illustrated, your contributions to the industry have been phenomenal.
Every game that you've made is one of my personal favorites.
I noticed in the retrospective video that you said you have a love of wine.
Have you had a chance to try our California wine?
Yeah.
So, he's been drinking since he got on the plane.
My favorite.
California wine is great.
Okay, boy, let's get started.
RPGs have traditionally been much more fantastical in nature.
And when I first saw Shenmue, I noticed how real it was.
Everything looked just so real.
Some of the details that you've included in the game, I just couldn't believe it.
What do you think makes you so different from other game
developers?
And do you feel you represent a new kind of developer?
He does not necessarily think of himself as a new type of
game developer.
I've talked to a lot of different creators,
but no one has made games the same way I have.
The way they make games is different,
so the final product is also different.
And he thinks that watching movies or looking up at the sky or at the sunset, those kind
of stimulations are very important.
And I would like to keep making games this way.
Looking back at your older games,
Technology has advanced so much, yet it always seems as you've been creating your games that you've been on the edge of technology.
You're a true visionary.
I would be interested to know, what was the development process like when you first started developing games, and how has it changed?
So he started making games back in 1983.
Back then, he was a programmer.
So the team consisted of two programmers, one artist,
and one sound staff.
So a little room was enough for the team to develop the games.
So with Shenmue, by the end, at the very last stage,
there were over 300 people on the project.
I've put the video of the making of Shenmue together, so let's take a look at it.
He was on a journey to seek a vision of a new world.
In his mind, vaguely, an image of a new game was about to emerge.
The vast land and the long history was appealing something to him.
This is how the task of establishing the image of a new game began.
As you may all know, game development is a group work done by a large number of staffs.
In the very beginning, music was made.
And the purpose of this music was to have the staffs broaden their imagination freely,
and then to have them absorb all that inspires them.
No compositions, no pictures or photographs, only music to enhance their imagination.
Then, films.
were made to expand the visual image.
Creation of the main characters, which are the most important subjects in the game, was
far more difficult than what was expected.
Even with the ideal side views and the ideal front views, an ideal 3D model could not be
made.
Even after countless trials, a desirable image could not be achieved.
At the end, a real-sized sculpture was made to 3D scan, and an accurate ideal character
was generated.
Also, enormous number of image boards were made to visualize the world which surround
the characters.
This is how the development of the project, codenamed Barkley, was commenced.
End this pursuit of high quality and the challenge to embody the images they have in their minds.
There is no tolerance for anything less.
Every motion had to be endorsed accurate by actual human motion.
Based on the presumed emotion curves of the player, the story was enhanced with more depth.
Then, one question started to grow among the staffs.
Is this really a game?
Thank you.
That is so inspiring.
One of the things I noticed was the animation.
And coming from a sports game background,
we do so much in motion capturing with our animations.
And I was surprised by the tremendous animation
in Chenmue.
How did you actually do all of your animations?
I use animation a lot when I play sports.
The animation in this game is amazing.
How do you capture motion in Shenmue?
I'm sure you all know, but Greg,
Greg Kallai's American football and basketball are also beautifully animated.
I think you all are aware of the games Greg made,
and Yusan sees the animations in those games.
It's spectacular.
Thank you so much.
We've been using motion capturing since back when we were creating Virtua Fighter.
We are currently using various types of motion capture, such as magnetic and optical systems.
We use motion capture for the body, hand, and facial movements.
We use motion capture in many ways.
Unlike Virtua Fighter, we use motion capture systems for Shenmue to make small movements.
So in Shenmue, we are using a motion capture system which could capture more detailed, more smaller motions, more precise motions, not big motions.
YOSHIMASA ENJI, SPEAKING JAPANESE, INTERPRETER 2
We had to instruct the motion actors how to move for certain special martial arts.
And that's what we had to do before actually capturing motions.
And so we have a video which shows how motion was captured in Shenmue.
Let's take a look at it.
Yu-san will appear in it also.
Currently, he's giving instructions on how the motion actor should act.
And the timing...
As you can see, you can see the action scene or the motion capturing scene and also the
game scene. So you can see how the motions are applied in the actual game.
So there are currently in game development that there are so many works you have to do other than just programming.
So Yu-san, Shenmue is this huge success in Japan.
And I thank you very much for sending me a copy, by the way.
But I can't speak Japanese, and I don't understand exactly
what's going on in the game.
I've tried for hours and hours.
I really, really want to play it.
Will it be released in the US?
And could we maybe see a peek of it?
SPEAKER 1 IN JAPANESE
We are currently working hard on the localization.
The scenario is huge.
And the translations of the scenario has just been completed recently.
In Shenmue 1, there are 350 characters.
And we have decided on 200 voice actors so far.
Too many.
Too expensive.
Okay, so we brought with us a video with some English narrations and some English voiceovers.
So let's take a look.
For more information, please contact...
I...
I... Francis.
I... Francis. Who...
I... Francis. Who... dies...
I... Francis. Who... dies... in my arms.
I... Francis. Who... dies... in my arms. I'm sorry.
No way.
Nooooooo...
But in progress?
But okay!
Uh...
That way, right?
Constant improvements!
You know what...
I think you just need to retrace the flow of C.
Tylenol and pad, and you got it.
Remember to vote in the third box or the link in the description
if you're thinking about getting a game by  users in the future.
In the meantime, LETS...
SAVE
STEAL
NO, PLEASE!
DO NOT!
The Game inside will not open right now
I will be back later
It's the game itself
Welcome to The Origin of Decadence
I'm sorry.
Excuse me.
Oh, sensei Asougi's boy.
I'm going to use your instructions again.
Of course, provided it's something I am familiar with, this type of pressure stone is poorly found.
Well, all I can say is I, and I think everyone here,
is so happy to see that.
I think I'm going to have to try to convince you to get me
a GD or something.
Every time I see Shenmue, one of the things that just blows me
away is the direction.
And it looks like a Hollywood heavyweight made it.
And the story is just so amazing.
Can you tell us a bit about the storyline and your vision?
It's quite surprising.
It's like a masterpiece of Hollywood.
You use a lot of film-like approaches in the design.
Could you tell us about the story line and the vision of the game?
A man from China comes to meet...
not meet, but comes in front of Ryo Hazuki, the main character, who's living in Japan.
So one day, when Ryo comes home, he sees that man fighting with his father.
He sees his father being killed.
And right in front of Ryo's eyes, his father gets murdered.
And so the whole story is Ryo pursuing to solve the mystery behind his father's death,
which eventually goes over to China.
And so since it's a long story, in Shenmue 1,
it'll only take place in Japan.
And from Shenmue 2, the story will take over to China.
So the vast story will begin in Shenmue 2.
But today, I brought some footage from Shenmue 2.
Pull the encoder to unlock the laptop.
You opened it?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Go ahead, read it.
Can you read it?
Someone else read it, as well.
I'm Max Stephanie, and thank you for listening.
You know, the characters look so amazing, I can't believe it.
And you say there are 350 of them.
I mean, that's so many.
Too many.
How did you create them?
How did you go about really making them so real?
I'm surprised at how realistic and profound they are.
How were they achieved?
As I explained earlier,
we first made the main characters.
As we mentioned before, the main characters,
the sculptures were made of the main characters at the very beginning.
So this 3D scan, and then we 3D scan the sculptures.
But then that would end up having a 50,000 poly face.
And then we would need to reduce the polygons.
We're not making games for PlayStation 2.
And then we apply facial animation onto the models.
In Shenmue, we have a new technology called a mouth clip, which is a technology where
we can have the models automatically synchronize the voice.
So we have a Dreamcast with us.
We would like to do a demo.
So could we have Dreamcast 1 on the screen?
Let's start with this beautiful lady.
Please wait.
No, no.
This is real time.
Let's try moving it.
You can zoom in and zoom out.
The reflection of the eyes is beautiful.
And the hair, the softness and how it moves naturally.
So currently he's moving around the light, as you can see.
It's as if he was born with those wings.
Wow, Greg likes ears.
It seems that Greg likes ears.
The fairy tale is one bright...
I like details.
The details here are amazing.
...beginning.
Let's try a different character.
I may have made a mistake in the order, but...
We have an English speaking character, so let's try him.
His name is Mark Kimberly.
He's going to talk about the system of doing shopping in Chenmue.
So he's going to talk.
For you, son.
Oh, convenience stores aren't the only place to shop.
Candy stores are also a great place.
They have lots of stuff that will bring back childhood memories.
It's really fun.
So, as you can see, the facial animations are...
They're meant to move very much, very naturally.
I'll tell you about part-time jobs.
The mouth movements are recorded first, and then the computer automatically syncs them.
The 4-player operator is definitely it.
I'll teach you everything there is to know.
That's great.
That's...
Wow.
So, Yusan, Shenmue is such a huge game.
Yes.
Since you're the creator of the game, would you...
Could you take us maybe through parts of the game?
Could you show us some of the actual gameplay?
So last night he went through the trouble of setting the date of the Dreamcast to Christmas Eve.
So he would like to go in and make a demo.
Can we have Dreamcast 2?
This is Ryo's room.
He's going to walk around.
If you press the A button, the door opens.
So when you see an A icon of an A button, by pressing it, the door opens.
And so since this house is so big, he's just going to take a look at some rooms.
And this is the kitchen.
And that lady there is the housekeeper.
Now, he just obtained information from the housekeeper.
So, when Ryo obtains some information,
the signal shows that new information has been added into your memo book.
All the important information is written in the memo.
On the first page, you'll find her phone number.
If you call her, she'll answer.
And you can open drawers.
So since this is a kitchen, you see what you see in the kitchen.
So this is the fridge.
So you can actually buy stuff at the convenience store and store it in the fridge.
Let's take a look at a different room.
That's a Japanese living room.
Very small.
And there's a TV in the back.
So he's going to open the TV rack.
I'm excited to see what happens when I buy this.
Okay, so you gotta get Shimu to find out what you can do with this Saturn.
That was his allowance.
He got it from his father.
What should I do?
Let's go outside.
It's snowing.
I went to Dobuita, but I made a mistake.
In Shenmue, the weather changes constantly.
I'll try running.
He's gonna try running.
Trying to catch up to the scooter.
So at night you'll see many neon signs.
There are many bars around here.
So as you can see, the sound of the footstep changes depending on the surface of the road.
So when he's walking over snow, it sounds like he's walking over snow.
This is a pretty big town.
So that's the convenience store.
The name of the convenience store is Tomato March.
You got Shenmue potato chips.
So when you buy a Shenmue potato chips, it comes with a sort of like a raffle.
Welcome, Tazuki-kun.
This.
So, item get, right?
Then, draw a lottery ticket.
You lost.
I'm sorry, you bought it for me.
I don't know how many items he has right now.
He doesn't seem to have many right now.
Let's go to a different store.
There was someone blocking it from the door.
So he's going to try going into the arcade.
Game Center U.
It's called Game Center U.
There's a Hang On sign here.
Okay, there's Hang On.
And you have darts.
And you have old games.
Classics.
Space Harrier.
Oh, and there's Space Harrier.
100 yen per play.
That's like my all-time favorite.
I'll try it.
So he's gonna try playing it.
100 yen.
Back in him again.
Let's play a bit.
I'm getting serious.
Get ready.
One more time.
We don't have much time, so we'll stop.
Okay, so since we don't have that much time, we're going to stop here.
Ah.
That's it.
I seriously think I financed one of your first Ferraris with the quarters I put into Harrier.
You obviously have a really strong fighting game background.
Being the creator of Virtua Fighter, the all-time greatest fight game.
The sequences of fighting that I've seen in Shenmue are even more amazing.
Can you show us the approach that you use to get these sequences?
I'm a fighting game expert.
Could you tell us about the battle system?
In Shenmue, we have three big battle systems.
One is a battle system where you have to punch in the command, sort of like Virtua Fighter.
The next one is called, it's a new system, it's called QTE Battle.
It's a system where you can play by pressing only one button.
And the last one is called Move Instructions, where you get instructed of martial arts moves.
So in the game, you can meet people and have them instruct you of new moves.
And for the moves which you mastered, you can use in the free battle.
Okay, so we have a video showing the battle system, so let's take a look.
This is free battle.
It's where you have to punch in the commands.
So unlike Virtua Fighter, you can fight against multiple number of enemies.
It's made to be very simple.
This is called the QTE battle.
The control is easy, but you can get cinematic, dynamic action.
And this is the move instruction, and this old man here, he's going to instruct him, instruct Yoh a move.
He's going to give him instructions such as move right or move left.
Stand lower.
And this here, he has mastered a move.
So these are the three battle systems.
So I noticed in that prior demo that you said in Christmas
evening it was snowing.
And I'd read about something called Magic Weather, but I
haven't seen it.
Can you kind of discuss what it is and maybe
show us a bit of it?
YOSHIMASA ENJI, JR.:
Shemu is a full 3D interactive game.
But however, there are other such games, 3D real-time games, so we have added the element
of time into Shenmue.
As time changes, naturally the weather changes also.
So by adding the element of time, we had no choice but to change the weather in the game.
Okay, so we have a video with English narration on it of the Magic Weather and Time Control.
Let's take a look.
So this is spring, in spring you see cherry blossoms.
This is Dreamcast.
I will then be reviewing the transcript as it will be read aloud.
I'm going to be reviewing the transcript as it is read aloud.
It's a wonderful experience to be able to read.
I'm here to play a very famous game, the same event in the style of Gandori.
In another way, it was amazing and astonishing.
Players who don't know time in a question may learn at the next time a whole different planet.
This new system, which may be the high level of freedom and reality, is a magical weapon.
The point of time, and the change in weather, the change room is the explosive, the war time.
But certain cases may not always look the same.
So, at this time, first of all, I've been so lucky to be able to ask you questions.
I wanted to make sure that any of the members of the audience who wanted to ask questions,
if you would kind of pass your question cards to the side, someone can pick them up, I believe.
Okay, let me ask a couple more.
Let's talk more about the future.
How do you see games evolving in the future, and how do you see the creative process changing?
Network will be more and more important.
And also he sees that a new genre in games will be created.
I want to create a new market, a new genre.
I want to create a genre where movies and games are the same.
I would like to create a new genre that combines the reality of games with the interactivity of games.
Shenmue 1 was the first challenge towards that.
What challenges do you face when you're building the team?
I know it's such a large team, but what challenges do you face?
For the project team of Shenmue, only 30% were actual SEGA employees.
And others were people from other industries, such as movie directors or cameramen,
scenario writers,
professional architects.
And he had the chance to work with many people from other industries.
And he was able to build a nice network with people from other industries, and that was very valuable.
And he learned that the difficulty of managing a team
is proportionate to the size.
In thinking about future games, and of course that really
excites me, are there things that you develop very
differently, and the techniques that you've
pioneered in Shenmue?
are so different than what I'm used to.
Could these techniques be applied to any other genre?
He feels that the technology behind Shemoo, when used for like architecture or for presentation purposes, it'll be very effective.
And he sees that this technology can also be applied to arcade games, which he has been making.
He made the Ferrari game, which is the newest arcade game.
For the arcade game, the very recent title he released was a Ferrari game, F355 Challenge.
In the development of that game, at the very beginning stage, we actually made a concept movie which had a storyline.
So as long as there's a story to it, the technology of Shenmue can be applied.
And so we would like to take a look at the footage.
And can we have the volume a little bit higher?
Mallory, you know that game so well.
Here, have a cookie.
Here.
Thank you, Mallory!
I'm eating a cookie!
Enough, Mallory!
Thank you for watching.
The progress bar is at the top and you cannot clear it.
For more information on the MSPS, please visit the MSPS website.
This is not a nukeshot video.
It does not belong to a game design company.
This video is a fan worship.
I can't believe I could believe this.
I truly have no idea what I'm doing.
Wow.
That is totally amazing.
Okay, I've been told that we're out of time.
Usain, I want to thank you so much.
I'm so honored to have been a part of this,
and like I said, your creations are just amazing.
Thank you so much for being here.
Thank you.
So thank you for coming here today.
contained semi-normal,
semi-normal
She's the greatest
she's the greatest
banyak
biography
But she's an
English
rich
famous
vip
If you
want
to
want to
see
some
simplistic
Racional
Rinals
criminal
Mmm
Oh