Good morning, everyone.
Good afternoon, depending on where you are in the world.
Good evening to our developer friends
who are joining us in the lower left-hand corner of the screen.
My name is Brian Francis. Welcome to the GDC Twitch channel.
We are here today checking out a wonderful game.
I am obsessed with it. Hopefully you're obsessed with it, too.
It's called Loop Hero.
I'm so excited to have two wonderful guests
who are in the lower left-hand corner of the screen.
First off, we have Aleksandr Vatazerian, aka FlynnLol, and Aleksandr Gorslavac, aka Blinch,
since both of their first names are Aleksandr.
We're gonna call them FlynnLol and Blinch today.
They're the developers from 4QuarterTeam who brought us Loop Hero.
FlynnLol and Blinch, would you guys please introduce yourselves?
Hello.
You are on the camera, so you go first.
Okay, I'm Lynch, I'm a composer and sound designer and partly a game designer at Flute Hero.
Hello, I don't know what to say.
And I'm Alexander, I'm a programmer and like, I'm sorry, I'm a programmer and an artist.
This, some of that, and some of that.
It's so nice to have you guys on the channel.
As I said, before we started talking, I am so excited about this game.
It is so much fun.
I start playing it and then 90 minutes go by and I just don't remember how anything...
Like, I just don't remember how time works anymore.
You all might hear some noises from my machine. I'm switching between two machines, so it makes some Windows notification beeps.
Sorry about that. That's just trying to manage this whole system by myself. So, Loop Hero, as you can see, we're playing it right now.
Let me know in chat if there's any issues with audio or video.
This is a game where your adventurer just sort of goes on a loop,
and you build the environment in which they go with the loop on. That's a very poor way to explain it.
There's a lot of neat backstory game design going on.
It's to me. I find this game incredibly compelling. It's incredibly I don't like the word addicting, but it's the shortest word to explain what?
Addictions obviously a big serious thing, but it's so cool. It's a neat game. Um, so Finlow and Blinch
I'm gonna be asking you questions if you are watching in twitch chat
Please feel free to ask your own questions. I will grab them
I've got the whole monitor set up here so I can read chat and answer your questions
And yeah, whatever you've got for the devs. We want to hear it
So to get started, let's just lay some groundwork.
Let's go to the beginning of development for Loop Hero.
Where did the idea for Loop Hero come from, and how did it change from
prototyping the game to finishing the game?
It comes from pretty old conversation with our
main artist and main game designer Dmitri Karimov aka Desira.
And we were just talking with him about zero player game genre, where you not directly
control your hero and not actually control game itself.
But it's...
And yeah, it's come from this conversation that Dmitry just was talking about his idea
about little hero who walk in the...
a circle road and player must just build some tiles around the road and try to balance
this how it's difficult and how main hero getting stronger this monster and battles on this road.
So it was not for you know we did not jump in right after it we just okay interesting idea
and forgot about it.
Yeah, then we joined Ludum Dare 20... 45?
Yeah, I mean, it was October 20...
Yeah, sorry.
Yeah, 19, 2019, and it was Ludum Dare about Start With Nothing.
And we have not really good idea for this, but then we remember about...
that idea about the little hero who just walking in circles and we're like okay he it's pretty
much he start with nothing let's try something and yeah that's where it's come from but yeah
yeah it's just where it came from uh deceiver uh said always says that it was like a mental
training for him to come up with um
like mechanics that will allow zero player game to be engaging, because he just likes
to think about stuff like that and also he likes clickers.
It is, it does feel kind of like a clicker game.
What changed, just to sort of repeat the second half of my question, what changed in making
Looper from those first ideas?
What were some of the biggest changes the game went through as you worked on it and
finished it?
Our idea is pretty like it is right now.
It's about the same little hero who just walk in circle.
But yeah, but then we're making it complex and complex
and add a lot of things like game building, storytelling,
tiles, synergy, when it's transformed by each other.
The transformation of tiles.
Yeah, and the perk system and many others.
So our idea is not change too much,
but we are adding a lot of new things.
We can talk a little bit more, like you said,
this is a game where the player doesn't control the combat.
They don't control the hero.
So there's kind of this automatic combat system
that you can see on screen right now.
I was worried when I first saw it that it might, I don't know, like, you know, we think of games, we think of combat games, we think, oh, like, combat has to be fun, and the game playing itself for you doesn't automatically seem fun at first, when you first see it.
The idea might not be, I guess.
What do you think is fun about it? Because it's very strange to be sitting here, you know, we're watching the game right now.
And I'm looking back at what I was playing a few days ago, and it's still compelling to just watch the automatic little fights play out, you know, even though it's just kind of numbers.
I know in my head it's just numbers sort of firing off and I have no control over it, but it's there, it's compelling. What do you think works about that?
You don't control the button in the game, but...
You control everything else on the screen.
You set up your hero builds, inventory perks, some additional stuff from camp.
And it's like you set up this mechanism and just watching how it will work.
And it's pretty addictive thing.
And sometimes it works, sometimes it's not.
You can't say how your current action will affect in the long distance.
It's really interesting to see.
Will it work or not?
Maybe I can, you know, little tweak it, try something else next time.
And yeah, that is.
And as for why it works, like, it's kind of like watching a stream.
You cannot really control the streamer when you're watching him.
You still are rooting for them because
you want them to win and
when they fail, you get sad, and when they win, you get happy.
That's the kind of thing that goes on here.
It's like your little Tamagotchi.
Oh, I like that. It feels like Tamagotchi actually.
Like, or for me, God, it feels like the, there were these Digimon Tamagotchi.
I don't know if you, if you had Digimon in your, uh, or like in the 90s or like
there was little toys you could carry around and go on walks with and they
would battle automatically. It's actually very similar to that.
Um, okay, so our next question is going to be, um, we can talk about the environment card.
So if you're looking at the screen right now on the lower left-hand corner, if you know, loop here, you know, all this, but I'm explaining for the new folks.
If you're on the lower left-hand corner of the screen, there are environment cards.
Um, some of them you place on the side, as you can see with all those rocks in the mountain.
Other ones you place on the path that the hero walks on.
These spawn more monsters and combine in ways to increase the difficulty for the little guy making the loop.
How do you feel you've been able to encourage players to try and experiment with these cards, to try new things?
Because when you put a card down what you're essentially saying is, okay, I want more monsters and
I can see why someone might, like myself for instance, I was like, I don't know why I would make it harder for myself, I don't know why I would make more monsters.
And I sort of figured out why after a while, but I'm curious as developers, like, how did you make players want to try new cards and new experiments?
I guess it's just the core idea of the game is that you have to balance between making it too easy and too hard.
Uh-huh.
And...
Again, you didn't have...
You didn't know why you should place more monsters on the road, but then you tried not doing that and okay, yeah, that is not getting me
closer to winning, so I will try to place monsters and then you start to do it because
if you don't, you get bad loot from slimes
you cannot summon the boss and if you do, it's very late loop and you die.
So you have to basically.
Yeah, it's also part of learning about game because firstly you just walk around and
yeah, when you're just starting the game, you don't feel it's difficult because you know player, I mean hero just
fight
by his own, and it's not difficult.
So, okay, I will put these spiders, for example,
and it's still not difficult.
And the player just starting to place any tiles chaotically
because he don't understand how it affect
his run for long distance.
And then he dies, and he like, okay.
he recognized, he realized that it's not working.
Maybe I need to place little bit less monster,
or maybe I need to try put other monster instead this one.
And yeah, and it's only how it started.
And it's process during whole game,
like you're just trying to tweak it for your best.
um that strategy for game how it will be perfect balance for your hero and
i'll be and then and then you just unlock new classes and it's all not work for
them and you need started by a new cycle of this
balancing stuff
Um, just a fun anecdote I can share. So when I was playing my partner who's also playing this game and she's a few hours ahead of me
And she's seeing things I haven't seen yet
She walked over while I was playing not this specific run
But like a run essentially that where I was playing like this and she just said it screamed out loud
Like why have you put?
all that stuff together. Like, why have you made this so hard for yourself?"
And I was like, I don't know. And then we just started like, like, as soon as she said that,
something like one of the, the, oh yeah, it was, I layered the graveyards on top of each other,
and we had, um, uh, like, it was like, oh, a vampire died, and then there was a ghost,
and then there was a ghost of a ghost, and then the primal matter showed up, and she audibly
screamed like, what the hell is that? Like, I haven't seen that. She's, and I'm just like,
I don't know, I'm just...
I push button and loop hero go burr if you get that.
So that was a really fun, like our two different play styles collided right away.
And my more aggressive layering approach, which you can see right now, threw her off.
And it's always funny to see how people play differently.
You know, every people find out some own strategy and it's always interesting to see how they
will be, you know, set up their roles, which tiles they choose.
It's really interesting how many variations these people found.
Yeah, I, this isn't something we talked about, this isn't in the questions I sent you guys
before, but I kind of found as I was playing that, um, uh, uh, um.
What one thing I experienced was after a while like some cards just weren't fun for me
I guess like I might go. Oh, okay
Like I've had like the spiders for instance the spider card in my kit for a while
But now I've got some new things and I'm making decisions about trading them out and I'm after a while
I was like, I know this thing gives me rewards and there are specific rewards I can get out of this, but I
I just like, I just, the swamp is actually a much better example. The swamp, I picked it up because I'm like,
Oh, I see what this does. This makes my healing damage. So I need to be careful with this.
So I need to build a strategy that's less involved around healing.
And this early in the game, I finally hit a point where I was like,
Oh, but healing's like fun and not like, it was kind of like, I was like,
Wow, this kind of sucks to be in the middle of a swamp and in a longer fight.
And my health was just tanking. And I was just like,
Okay, well, I'll just turn off the swamp and try another environment.
And I was surprised at like,
I was surprised at just how it came how it all worked out
And you died at the swamp on the footage
Yeah, we get to see my past mistakes here
WL stride is w w1 wf stride
Has shown up in the chat wf stride. Thank you so much for watching
WF stride
Dut has a question for us, which is where did you get the idea for this type of looping game mechanic?
We kind of talked about where it came from before
So we don't want to totally retread that ground, but I will say WF stride wants to say great game by the way, so
That's one person in chat who's already written for y'all
So, I guess we can build on that question about where the looping came from, and more like, um...
It kind of feels like a programming loop, doesn't it?
Like, this game feels like, you know, like, uh, you set up a loop in, you know, when you're coding or whatever,
an if-then, and then the loop just kind of keeps running, um...
Where did the idea evolve from, you know, you talked about having a hero you don't control
And doing that game jam doing Ludum Dare. I think it was
When did you sort of have the idea to like have this kind of a almost like a programming loop come into play?
It was just an in the original idea that yeah
you build the road tile and you have to like leave with it now because it will stay there
and you will pass it multiple times. So you build something and then you will interact with this
many times on the loop so yeah it was original idea it's not something which will come later here.
Cool yeah. So it's like the very basic part it's like
When did you get the idea that in a shooter you shoot a gun?
Yeah, so Stride, if you didn't catch it, I totally recommend going back to the front of the
the top of the stream and seeing the full story they gave about the game's origin.
We've also got another question from Video Space Games. They wanted to say they also love this game.
They want to ask, was this game inspired by idle games at all?
It was, as I said before, we were just talking about idle games and about zero player games,
but it was not, you know, directly inspired by some specific game.
So it was like a conversation about genre itself, but pretty quick Loot Hero has grown
up from this genre.
and now it's something different.
But yeah, originally it was just our thoughts
about zero playing a game each other.
Right. What do you think idle games do so well that, you know, like we talked about earlier,
like the sort of the notion that every game must be as interactive as possible. And as,
but I know I love idle games. I'm playing one on my phone right now. That absolutely has like the
deepest grind. I'm not going to name it because I don't want to name and shame, but it's good.
Just got this really deep grind. And I'm like, oh, this is very hard, but I don't do much,
but I like this. Like, what do you guys think is so compelling about idle play?
If you're talking about Loop Hero, it's not actually an idle game.
Like, it's health, but it's a little bit part of Loop Hero.
It's an idle game if you're talking about hero control.
But, you know, after you're playing some time, you understand you need to do a lot of action in this game.
Yeah, it depends on your attention for the game.
So it's not really idle, but...
why idle games are so addictive.
I think people just like to see how numbers increase infinity and you just can a little
bit rest while playing them.
So maybe because...
Maybe Fennval can know more about idle games.
Yeah, yeah.
Maybe it's just basically you...
your brain gets happy when numbers go up and in idle games you don't really have to...
work for it, you can just meditate and see numbers go up and that's it.
Yeah, I do think you guys have done a really good job adapting that
and even with with more interactivity like we're seeing like almost every few
seconds you can see me in this footage like moving around
and clicking and it's some of it is numbers going up but like
you know there's the neatness of making that mountain in the lower left hand
corner there's
laying out combos on the path. I really think you guys have done a good job adapting
both that idle factor even while you increase the interactivity.
We're gonna go to our next question in chat from IllmadeCoder. This is a long one so
just give me a second to read if you have to read all of it. IllmadeCoder says that they
were playing around with remaking this game as a side project. Is that a kosher thing to
bring up in an interview? I don't know.
That they're trying to remake your game, but hey, I guess you inspired them
And I was they were they said they were playing around with the classes being within items
Rather than being something you choose
So instead you would try to have to form a build for the class via the equipment slots
Was that something that was ever thought of in design and do you think that would be tricky to pull off?
We actually were talking at some point about kind of system like that, but it's...
Like, it might be not promising anything, not saying it will, but there is a small chance that it will be implemented in the game, kind of system like that is...
your equipment making you more of the class, but don't know.
It was just one talk, one little talk, and that's it.
Blitz, is there anything you want to add?
Actually, no. We don't have any plans for it right now.
We talked about some...
Making class system more complex, but not something specific, but we can announce right now. So
That's that's totally fair. I'm honestly I'm super I'm
Appreciate you guys saying that it was an idea. So good. You're you might do it yourself. Um,
We discussed something like that at some point but
Not it's it's not in the game as you can see you just pick the class and that's it right
Um, yeah, so my next question, um, uh, IllmadeCoder wants to say,
add, uh, by the way, they're just remaking the game for fun and to learn not to try and compete.
Uh, yeah, IllmadeCoder, I can only say for myself, uh, I admire you trying to
retro-engineer this game, so I think that's super neat.
Um.
My next question is going to be
Were there any challenges when it came to like readability and have having players understand what was going on?
You've got this incredible pixel art aesthetic
I personally sometimes myself have trouble seeing exactly what is happening on screen
It hits harder in town like when I look if we get back to the town
Part of the game in a bit I can describe it more accurately but sometimes when I'm looking at you know right now
I can sort of clearly see okay. Those are the mountains. That's the grass and I can pick out
You know the swamp the field the vampire mansion the blood trees
There's no vampires out right now because I think I turn them off the goblin camp, but
You know, it's I don't I you understand that after hours of play, you know things become more familiar
But I'm curious when making this game
Did you have any challenges about you know, we're making sure players understood was going on just at a glance
It's DeSiva who drew all the styles and sometimes he redrew a few ones for more readability and
desert for example and rocks and mountains as I remember too. Road as well. So yeah it's
it was some challenge for it and maybe we still have a few problems. Maybe we want to for example
make something for you and notice your hero is more clearly on late loops when it's you know
too many enemies and you can't see where your hero going so yeah we're planning to
improve it so it was a lot of challenge but
Yeah, as I said, Deceiver is a cool artist and who made all the styles and it's definitely
a new task for him, so we just can't answer this for sure.
That's totally fair.
I think he did a good job overall, just, you know, it's, I think, as displays have gotten
bigger, pixel art, you know, pixel art was made for smaller screens, smaller computing
power, and sometimes as those two things have scaled up.
I've just noticed that it sometimes creates, you know, sometimes it's just as hard to read as, you know, mushy pixels in less good games from yesteryear might have been.
Not this game necessarily, just pixel art as a broad art.
Um, let's take kind of a programming tack.
Um, uh, obviously as...
As, um, this, this game, as loops in this game get more and more elaborate and complex,
um, you know, the game is trying to, you know, layer, uh, different, different systems and
remember, okay, you know, if there's a graveyard, then ghosts, you know, are supposed to spawn,
um, or enemies are supposed to become ghosts. If there's vampires...
They get regen in you and the stacking complexity gets gets very uh,
Uh, it grows and it scales in complexity
As and it may you know, this is still early in the game the footage we're looking at but i'm sure as it goes on
It gets even more and more complex. Um, were there any challenges when it came to?
kind of making sure the game and the game's core structure could handle all that information coming
in rapidly. You know, because sometimes when I've talked to game programmers, you know,
and they're working on less graphically complex games, obviously, you know, when you have a game
that has realistic lighting, when you have more realistic features, those are very complex to
render. But then, you know, strategy game developers have told me, like, man, like,
when you are trying to, like, make sure your game can store and run all this complex information,
like, that's actually its own challenge that's less visible to players. Did anything like that
come up in development not really I mean storing like an array or a like a
single variable it's very cheap like a computer from 2005 can handle it easily
and oh more than more than that like an enemy is just basically
a number of variables, maybe like a hundred, but a hundred variables is still
bytes or kilobytes of data. So
it's, it's not much.
Maybe in strategies, like if it's a global strategy with a
thousand of units and they're in 3d and they have vectors and they have like,
3D lightning with the...
with like the...
how do you call it?
The lion that goes from the...
from the thing.
The drace.
Yeah.
Then you will
need more memory, but
here, no.
It's very easy to store it all.
And for the complexity...
There were challenges because there are only two programmers and one day we are thinking what to do with like four...
There are four chapters in the game. I guess you can spoil it.
Yeah.
Yeah, maybe I shouldn't but it's too late already.
And we were thinking, okay, there are four chapters, how we make enemies more interesting.
So some of them have skills, maybe we just make that their skill can proc with more percentage with each chapter.
So like spiders can...
throw a web with 5% at first chapter, 10% at second, and so on.
But then we decided that, no, we can add a new skill for each enemy each chapter.
So there are like hundreds of skills.
There are more, actually.
Like...
Yeah, and...
Two guys had to code 100 skills, which was...
Yeah, it was...
It was hard, and then it turned out that some of the skills didn't work, some did break something, some...
messed with some other parts of the game and we had to test it a lot and people still found some skills really broken in certain circumstances,
despite all the testing, because we just couldn't test everything.
Yeah.
And there were rare occasions in which the game just soft-locked, basically, because one of the skills...
Um without but we we we are we are working on it honestly
Without teaching the audience how to softlock Loop Hero, is there a particular skill or skill interaction that surprised you?
Either something you guys found while you were developing the game, or is there something...
Any type of this interaction, it was some skill combination or skill itself, or even...
I don't know.
Any type of this skill activity can break the game.
We have really a lot of testing, trying to catch everyone.
But we still find out some skill broken or not working as they must.
So yeah, it was a pretty challenging part of the development.
Was there any skill interaction that was really funny that you didn't expect?
Because I already think there's a lot of funny ones that are by design, but what are the unintentional ones, I think?
I can remember, for example, last one, but it's not really funny and we have a lot of negative feedback because of it.
Harpies in the game have ability.
How many punches they get, then the armor is increased by every punch.
every hit I mean. So if you have an archer in a tower of archers from your camp,
so around your campfire, you have some additional support from them and they
strike pretty fast. So if you have four archers who strike with like, I don't remember, maybe
to hit in second. This harpies getting like citadel of armor pretty fast.
Yeah. And you can kill them like no chances.
And we have no combo. Basically you cannot damage them at all sometimes
because they can have vampirism or regen.
too high and like you did one damage then they heal five so just impossible to yeah and and many
people no it's maybe not many but some people get this softlock and some of them was too angry and
try to i don't know shut out for us you know because of this little bug but we've already fixed
um and
This sort of things sometimes appears and you can't predict everything.
For example, it's one of the latest enemies in the game.
It's Seeran and they have ability to summon jellyfish on the battle.
I'm not remember for sure, but it was some broken ability and they summon not...
like infinity jellyfish on the battle map and you can kill them and
uh oh no it was a combination of ability they have a second ability
um about if uh water type of the enemy on the
bottom around them they have more um
uh evasion yeah percent and its evasion percent was more than 100
And you can kill them, no chances to.
But it was before release of demo and we fixed it.
Yeah, it's basically when you kill a jellyfish, like...
The siren counted the dead jellyfish's evasion also.
Uh-huh, yeah.
Yeah, yeah, so it was like...
It never needs to have 20 evasion for each jellyfish that ever was on the battlefield.
Although it should always have plus 20 and that's it.
Even if there are like four jellyfishes at once, just plus 20.
There also was a funny bug with the skeletons cracking.
The skeletons can crack and not die immediately, and you have to find the cracked skeleton.
There was a bug in which a skeleton spawned a cracked skeleton every frame of the game,
and there was an infinite amount of them.
Oh no.
So yeah, and...
you attack and you have like 100 damage numbers appearing each uh each frame oh god it was it was
funny i i love it when um i love it when bugs in this game are combinations this is something that
already happens naturally which is that
the combinations of skills. Oh yeah, this is my first encounter with the boss. We get
to see me die to the boss for the first time. To the lich. I like it, I like how the combinations
of skills create interesting thematic...
Elements, you know like when the vampires give everyone regen. That's a basic example. I already like that
I like it when even more when the the bugs, you know create these thematic like it's thematic and it's
Existentially horrifying to consider, you know sirens that just have all the jellyfish and their corpses help them
I
Just sent my favorite bug from the development in the discord. Maybe you can show it somehow. Uh, just send it in chat
Did you type it?
No, it's just a gif in the discord.
Oh, it's a gif.
Uh, let me...
Okay, we're gonna pop out.
Uh, da da da da da...
I'm gonna get it on screen.
Okay, so...
Uh, I need to, uh, fullscreen this.
Come on.
Okay, so we're looking at...
If you look at the lower left-hand corner of the screen right now...
Uh, oh my god!
Oh my god! What happened?
What am I looking at? I'm seeing...
Oh no!
I forgot two breaks in code.
Basically, I'm going to, I'm going to try and fullscreen this.
Hang on.
I want to, I want everyone to see this.
Okay.
And every of them have their own.
So we're popping this out.
We're going to pop this out so that everyone gets a full screen view of this.
This is incredible.
So you've got two breaks in the code and what exactly am I looking at here?
Well, I don't want to spoil the mechanic of the...
of a few cards.
So, just...
You actually can. You actually can.
It's, you know, game developer conference.
Yeah. Well, let's assume...
Well, you know, we'll give a spoiler warning if you don't want to see the spoiler right now.
I just...
I just want to think about this gif as an abstract art.
I do too.
This is beautiful.
Basically, you have a card called Labyrinth.
It does nothing, absolutely.
It just fills up the boss's...
What do you call it?
Bar.
The boss's bar.
Like, I forgot to...
to make that the additional labyrinths didn't spawn their own labyrinths, so
you place one, it spawns 15, those 15 spawn even more,
and so on and so on, and they fill out the whole map.
And I also forgot to make it so
the card after labyrinth spawns ghouls,
the monster ghouls, when they're installed. And I forgot the break there, so
labyrinths is kind of...
asking the code what should I do when I'm installed, when I'm placed on a map, and it
says well do this and then there is no break so it goes to the next line and it says spawn
ghoul.
So yeah, that's it.
That's incredible.
I just keep staring at it because just like loop hero this loop of this gif is just, it's
hitting the target.
It's my favorite.
Oh my god, thank you. Thank you so much for sharing this with us. I
You know, it's it's games, you know
When you're selling games games seem to look as perfect and polished as possible and showing their rough messiness is sometimes
Risky actually actually we posted the tweet. Oh, yeah. Well, there you go
Hey buy our game. It once looked it once broke like this
This is this is art. It's like you said this is I agree with you. This is fine art. I'm gonna get
Shrink it and send it back, but if you want to if you too want to stare at this forever on Twitter
You should absolutely
Go to their Twitter account and just watch it
Stream over and again if you just give me a second. I'm just gonna resize the window here
That was beautiful. That was one of the best things that's ever happened on the switch channel is getting to put a bug like that
at full screen
Oh, uh, to look at chat, there's some WF stride is it that that was a bug from before released?
So it's not real you can encounter it
I just want to make that clear the bug that we just got to stare at over and over again
Will not happen to you
Probably I'm gonna put a disclaimer in there just in case those line breaks showed up again somewhere else
Okay, um
Looks like strut. Uh, it looks like NPKNT's question has been answered
You can download loop here on Steam if you want to check it out. It's not on any it's on a gog or anything
It's not any of the stores is it?
I think it's also on GOG and the epic store
Right, yeah, Loop Hero is also available on the Epic Store and GOG if you want to check it out.
I'm going to ask a couple more questions here for my part.
We might need to cut out early here because of something that's popped up at my end.
Um, uh, okay, so I want to ask a question.
This is one of my favorite things in the game.
This is when I realized, like, oh, there's something special here.
Like, just because...
There's a system where, in the game, you can see it right now,
when mountains and meadows are placed, those boost the player's health.
Um, and I think that is so cool and so interesting because it doesn't make a lick of fucking sense to me.
Like, it does not, I, I, there's a, like, the narrative of the game establishes that there's, you know, like, a link between, you know,
the objects of the world and, and the hero's conception of the world, and so when Morrowind is back, like, like, there's a, there is a thematic link.
But broadly the idea of, oh, I placed a mountain down.
I have more health now.
It just, I can't link it in my head,
but the fact that this game made me
totally accept that logic,
I think that's what something games are brilliant at,
is like helping players take abstract ideas and.
internalize them. Where did that idea come from? Like where did that system come from and how did
it sort of evolve to, you know, then it scales upward obviously, you know, because when mountains
combine together you get the big mountain that spawns the harpies, you know, where did that end
of the system come from to make those meadow and mountain placement integral to the player's health?
In the beginning we don't have, we only have three types of the tiles, you know,
one of them is on the road, then we'll...
just like okay let them spawn enemies or maybe get you some resources when you're walking.
Second type is by the road like like letter or time crystals or vampires. We decide okay
they can also spawn enemy but maybe they will add some additional effects.
And free type, it's out the road.
So we're just thinking if they will spawn many enemies too,
this will be too chaotic for control it.
So it's not working.
OK, what they also can do?
Maybe they can do some bigger additional effect
with bigger areas, like lightning temple or beacon.
but then we're thinking about hero has attributes and maybe they will affect of them because
you know in our game you don't have too many attributes and
variation of interaction with how hero can get him stronger or something like that so
yes that's where it's come from so it's what's like written in
decision in the beginning of development.
Gotcha.
And as for how they conflict the narrative, it's actually vice versa.
Its narrative doesn't explain the mountains because at first the game was completely mechanical,
it didn't have any narrative at all, and the narrative is here to explain the mechanics
and...
So the mountain gives you health because we had to come up with something that mountains do and we thought okay
you can pick a mountain and make like a build that is reliant on your health.
So yeah that's what mountains are for.
But then for the lore, so you already have this maximum HP but you know when your hero
creating something that beautiful as that mountain.
He was so happy and uncovered his power.
Or something.
Yeah, it's basically mountains inspire your hero to be healthy.
Yeah.
Yeah, they're really beautiful.
Maybe it's like an alpine air that gives you more health.
Yeah, and he was a life longer for just looking at them as long as possible.
Look, I'll just say that I relate. I live in Los Angeles, California.
I'm surrounded by mountains and on a clear day when I can go see those mountains, I do feel better.
It's, I think, I think you're onto something here.
It's work. It's work.
Yeah.
It's realistic.
I mean, I thought I was pointing to... Anyway, yeah, you know what? Okay, so there's a question in chat I want to get to before we sign off.
I'll get to that question from Steaks. If you also want to throw in a question in chat, you can totally do that.
There's one more question from my end that I wanted to ask. It's lore-related. I didn't want to spend too much time on lore and story today,
because I sort of think people should just play this game and check it out for themselves.
This is what, this is another thing that made me go, oh my god, this game is something special.
This game is a fantasy game, there are some conventional fantasy elements, you know, fantasy enemies, slimes, skeletons, monsters, vampires, name it, pick it.
And there's a lot of dialogue that goes into like, you know, all of these things are lost or in the void and you're bringing back the world by summoning them.
The first dialogue that you encounter with the vampires, which we're not seeing here because I've already by this point seen the vampire so many times,
the hero and the vampire have an interaction where the hero says, oh, vampires were landowners.
They, you know, they were nobles who saw to the land. They weren't, you know, they weren't just monsters. They...
And I thought, oh my god, that's so cool that like...
They're monsters, but they have a role in the world.
And the Harpies also have some dialogue like that.
Like, you know, there was a society and vampires,
and this little bit of something, like,
made me care more about the vampires
than if they had just shown up in, you know,
if, like, you could have totally presented to me,
I would have been hooked by the mechanics and the loop.
But that one little line, like,
it just made me conceptualize something different
about these vampires, even though it,
it sort of barely matters the rest of the game.
Blinch, I think that was more your role, you did more of the writing.
What was your thoughts behind that?
Where did that come from?
When did you sort of go, hey, we want players to care a little bit more about these monsters
than just making them things to kill?
Yeah, for first, main writer was DeSivir, and that brilliant dialogue is his work.
I, with Spindle, I'll make a little writing for Encyclopedia.
You can find some.
few more stories about vampires by my writing too.
So originally, in Loop Hero, your goal not to kill all monsters or revenge to some villain
or something.
You basically try to rebuild this world, try to remember it.
So it would be pretty strange if your hero
you know, try to...
His goal was kill all monsters
because you put this monster on his way by your own
so it's a little bit dissonance about it.
So his focus on the story was on rebuilding
and we tried to make some, you know, make more sense
why a hero must kill all these creatures.
just not because they evil maybe not all of them evil but just because they have no other choice and
they have some um um how to say right um some their own uh goals for its conflict with what
hero try to reach yeah
Um, we're gonna get one more we're gonna get this last question here before we go if if our audience here has any more questions
for the the four quarters team
Um, where should they ask them?
Where should they send you all like if and and you know
Where should they ask if they want to learn more about making the making of loop hero?
You could also just say, nowhere, don't have questions.
Live in ignorance.
We made you this game, stop talking to us.
Let us take a rest and let us fix the game
and make it better.
You can also, that's a totally valid answer.
You picked the option.
It's an option, we're gonna let it go.
You know what, you have questions,
you can only ask them here.
You can only ask them to me.
These guys are doing us a wonderful service
by making Loop Hero.
Don't go bug them with your questions.
Let them make the game.
But that's.
That said, Steex, I love you for asking the question you have brought, because it's a great question and it's the one I want to ask on.
But for my part, I will just say, if you want to learn more about Loop Hero, they do have a Twitter account.
FourQuarters does have a Twitter account. You can go look that up. I would suggest doing it.
And Devolver Digital is obviously the publisher, and you can check out their feed if you want more info on where you can buy it.
Is it going to be on sale? I don't know. It's on Steam. There's going to be a Steam sale for it. Those will pop up.
So, we're gonna end on Stix's question.
Did you two, did the Loop Hero team, ever do any experimenting with a more pure, roguelike version of Loop Hero?
One with less persistence and more permadeath, or was it always designed with upgrades and persistence in mind?
At first, there was no upgrades, it was completely permanent.
Then again, we made it on Dudum Dare, which...
in which the team was start with nothing.
And that was it.
You start with nothing and then you go kill some slimes,
get some cards, some items,
then you build some more cards.
And the goal was just to get a higher loop and that's it.
And then when, again,
we didn't plan on making it the full game right away.
If the formula didn't work, if it was boring, then okay, we made a game, we spent two weeks, let's go back to something else.
But when we saw that, yeah, okay, people like it, it actually can be interesting, we...
Thought what can we do and the Deceiver said yeah, okay
I have an idea that will turn this like half hour game into a thousand hour game
Let's add a camp which you can upgrade and you get resources from the expeditions
So here's your incentive to like live longer and make more loops
so
Originally it was completely completely
without any progression.
Yeah, but then we don't want to permadeath or something
like that, because we try to push a player for experiment
with your card deck, with your building on the camp,
with some various builds for your hero.
And if you try something new in Group Hero,
you're not lost anything.
you just will get new experience, take few resources in any way, even if it will fail.
So you not lost nothing. So yeah, we not try to increment that or something.
Uh, gotcha. Well, with that, we're going to wrap things up for today.
Uh, um, Blinch, Finlol, thank you so much for joining me. This is...
This has been Loop Hero. This game is great for our part. We are the GDC Twitch
channel. Um, we're also just GDC. Uh, if you want
to know more about this year's Game Developers Conference, it's going to be
in July. It's going to be all digital. Um, if you
checked out GDC Showcase last week, you got to see
um, how we do digital events. We also did this for GDC Summer last year.
And so you're gonna be able to register and watch talks and network all online this summer from all over the world
We're so excited for it. We're so excited to have developers talk to you about making their games
Just like we have today with the loop here developers. So I hope you join us
I you know, there's gonna be something for everyone for all for narrative folks artists coders
Producers, it's all there. It's all that's what game developers conferences and that's what we love bringing you
Blinch, Finlol, thank you so much again, and we're gonna wrap and we're just gonna go on home. Bye everyone!
Goodbye.