OK, so let's get started.
My name is Mike Chautau.
I'm from Playbrain.
We're a company out of Tokyo.
This talk is about frictionless media
and why community is the new marketing.
So a little bit about me to start with.
Yes, you can see I look very Japanese.
I'm an Australian living in Tokyo for 16 years now.
And 20 years in games and marketing.
So I've worked in a number of different capacities doing that.
Most recently, right now my company Playbrain is a company that we started two years ago.
But previous to that I was running a creative agency in Tokyo where we were doing a lot of very youth market focused work.
So we're working for clients such as Red Bull, Heineken, Beats by Dre, brands like this.
And this one, this has given me a very interesting perspective on marketing that I've brought to games.
But previous to that I was also very involved with games as well in Australia.
I worked for a gaming company for about four years before I moved to Japan.
Along the way I also built a social media analytics company called Lens, which later
on we actually absorbed into Ultrasupernew, which is the creative agency that I ran.
So just to give a bit of a broad background on what I've done.
At Playbrain we do a number of different things.
We run the LJL, which is the League of Legends eSports
Pro League for Japan.
We also develop Deki.com, which is a platform that game
companies can use to power their communities.
And so we run that for titles such as GWENT, Overwatch.
Hearthstone, et cetera.
And this is a service.
It's actually a more regional service,
but most of our clients and most of our users
are actually in Japan.
We support right now Japanese, Korean, traditional Chinese,
and English.
And we also do a lot of streaming production and video production for games companies as well.
So Playbrain itself, we're very focused on games industry only,
but we do a lot of the different things that we're going to be talking about today,
which is a little bit where my background comes from.
So, who here comes from a little bit of a marketing background?
Show of hands.
Okay, so we've got a bit of a marketing side and community side.
That's about 50-50, alright.
So I'm going to maybe sort of define some terms
so we know what we're talking about.
So marketing being the study and management
of exchange relationships.
Marketing is used to create, keep,
and satisfy the customer.
When we're talking about game marketing,
quite often we think about this acquisition.
It's like a lot of the perception of game marketing
right now.
And a lot of what we're talking about today
is well, maybe that perception needs to change.
And we need to be thinking more about those second two as well.
So the keeping that satisfies is an incredibly important part
of the marketing activities.
So more users in equals more players,
therefore the acquisition side is very much where the focus is.
But there is something missing.
So we're going to be talking here about frictionless media.
This is a concept that we use to describe the work that we do.
And this is very much powered by community.
And how is that bringing something very vital to today's games and why that's specifically
necessary in today's games.
And I'm also going to take you through the four truths of frictionless marketing as well,
which is the emotions that we're actually trying to stimulate.
So when we talk about community, we actually want to think about what the intention and
what the emotion is of our users to make sure that we're actually giving them something
that's valuable to them.
Okay, so current marketing model as we talked about.
We're actually, we have these measurement analytics
that we use, CPA, cost per acquisition,
DAU, daily active users, ARPU,
the average revenue per user,
all these sort of stats that we have,
there's a lot more too.
They're actually really good ways to start to measure
the way that our game is performing.
and how successful our activities in marketing are.
But when we're actually looking at the way
that this data is used, most of the actions
that we're taking are very acquisition-based.
And I think this is something that there is a bit of a trend starting to change right now,
but this is still within a marketing function of a company, still very acquisition-based, we need more users.
is the answer instead of let's make the users that we have more valuable as well as getting
more users.
So the most effective way of reaching a lot of eyeballs is focusing on mass visibility
and awareness, and we get a lot of that.
So let me take you through a few of what that means in today's market.
You know, 0.05 percent.
Anybody can hazard a guess at what that is?
This is the average click-through rate
that you get on a web banner, 0.05%.
And that's considered a good click-through rate.
So if you're doing display advertising,
You're getting an incredibly low response rate through that advertising.
And you're going to be paying cost per 1,000 impressions is going to be something between
$1 and $10.
It can be a lot more than that as well.
We see prices, depending on which media you go into in Japan, of up to $30 can be actually
a common thing as well.
Cost per acquisition puts it in the sort of that $2 to $20 mark generally, which is pretty
high if you don't have a high revenue churning game.
So all these things are very highly measurable, so generally marketers think this is a very
safe thing to work with.
We can look at those numbers and go, oh, okay, we're going to get about this back on it.
That's great.
But it's only part of the picture.
Here's a different type of advertising that we see a lot.
This is OOH.
This is a big billboard that sits in...
This is Shibuya Station, one of the most popular...
I think it's the number four busiest station in the world.
We have about 2.4 million people come through there every day.
One of the things there we've done,
this is a particular project we did
for Clash of Clans a few years back.
We were very proud of the creative work,
super happy with what we did there.
But if you notice something about this picture,
how many of those people are actually in our target market?
You have an answer?
One maybe, yeah.
So, you know.
In terms of that target market, we're actually,
even the girl at the left, at the bottom,
potentially could be, but generally,
for this particular game, we're actually
a very male-skewed audience.
Maybe that guy at the top, but he's actually
potentially older than our target market as well.
So, we'll give him a maybe.
But I did a quick on a napkin kind of analysis of this.
And we get to maybe 1 in 5,000 people
are really going to be interested in downloading
our game based on 5% are actually in that core target.
40% of those are maybe interested in mobile.
40% of those are interested in the genre.
And then about 2.5% will actually download the thing.
So that's about one in 5,000, and we're back to that 0.05% of actual people actually reacting to our advertising.
So, okay, we can see where we're heading down this trend.
So we can put a cost to that as well.
You know, if you want to do a takeover of Shibuya Station, you're probably looking at about $200,000 a day.
It's a big station.
There's a lot of different media that you can take over to do that.
So I mean, if you've got something that is a very mass market orientated product, taking
over Shibuya Station is probably a good investment for you.
You get a lot of impact.
But if you have something that has any kind of niche, not so effective.
So, you know, we could get a cost per acquisition of $4 if we do well, probably more.
But it also is a place with diminishing returns, because if you think about it, Shibuya Station,
same people travelling every day of the week.
Once they've seen it, once they've decided if they're interested or not, you know, you've
kind of wasted your marketing money on them.
OK, so let's jump to television commercials.
So this is another kind of advertising
that we see a lot, especially in Japan.
So if you're doing a game marketing in Japan,
we do look at television commercial advertising
quite a lot.
And I've actually chosen to take an example that's
a little bit more US-centric for this one.
So the Super Bowl, this has got about $0.40 per person.
that you're going to reach for a 30-second spot
during the Super Bowl.
So that's, again, pretty high cost
to pay for a very broad mass audience.
What's the clicks-through rate on a TV?
It's very hard to measure.
You can probably look at when that spot runs
and how many people download.
But you've got a bunch of people who
are watching a football game.
They're not necessarily interested in downloading
an app at that particular point in time.
And so we could probably say that visibility, great.
Actual action that comes off the back of that
may not be as successful.
And again, broad audience, so if you've got anything niche,
not so effective.
But changing the way we consume media and games
is also changing.
If we have a look, we are much more interested in the long-term player engagement than we used to be.
The two big changes that we've seen in the last five to ten years is a massive shift toward multiplayer,
and real-time multiplayer, and also a massive shift towards microtransaction in just the last few years.
And that is changing the way that we want our users to behave.
We used to just want them to pay for the game, and then we're done, right?
As many people pay for the game as possible, and then we're on to making the next game.
But now we actually care about having those users for...
maybe five to ten years. It could be that long that we're after.
You look at a game like League of Legends, it's been around about eight years now.
A lot of the top games in the Japanese app store,
like Monster Strike, they've been around
six, seven, eight years. We're looking at the long-term retention
as a much more important part of the way that we deal with game marketing these
days. And I think we have to, you know, bring up
community as a solution for that.
Let me take you through one more thing, which is about how we're ingesting media.
And so we talked about television commercials before, but actually if we look at trends,
we've got things like Netflix starting to shift people's attention to places where there
aren't even any ads.
So there's no way to reach those people on Netflix unless you actually produce a Netflix
program.
We look at the core game of target's actually barely watching TV.
You can see here that second column is probably one of our core game of target age range,
16 to 24, and probably with the secondary one at 25 to 34.
Those ones, the numbers of the amount of engagement they have with television is really reducing.
And here's another one.
If you're looking at online advertising, the rate of people running ad blockers is increasing
very, very fast.
People don't want advertising is pretty much what I'm getting at.
This is really, really important to understand because that is telling us something about
the way that we're communicating.
We're interrupting the way that people are wanting to enjoy the world.
Last one here, digital ads are actually getting more expensive and reaching fewer people as
a result of the previous.
So it's about time marketing teams started looking in different places to appeal to the
players.
And that's why I want to introduce frictionless media and the four truths.
We'll get to the four truths.
Let's start with frictionless media.
So frictionless media is media in the form of content the audience is seeking to engage with.
So as opposed to a television commercial
where you're trying to watch a football game, for example,
and we're gonna throw up an ad,
and that's actually getting in the way
of the thing that they wanted to do.
So if we wanna look at this as a very simple chart,
it looks like this.
That red circle is where they're actually trying to get to.
And that blue track is where we're trying to push them.
So we're trying to shift them to first of all, our marketing.
So we want to take them away from what they wanted to do
to our marketing.
And then we're trying to have them make a decision
to not go back to what they wanted to do,
but go to our game, our destination page, landing page,
whatever we're going to have there.
And that is the friction that we're talking about.
So my proposal is that we take an approach of frictionless.
So frictionful marketing is it gets
in the way of what you wanted to see to deliver a message.
Frictionless is a very straight line.
Let's keep it simple.
So we want to deliver marketing in a form that
is proposing what the user is wanting to engage with.
So very simple path, target user, what the user wants,
your game.
All right, so let's give you some examples.
So influencer marketing, so you probably, many of you
are familiar with this.
We're supporting influencers to create content.
Common formats, video on demand, streaming content,
social media, blog content.
There are many other forms as well that we could imagine,
but that's the common ones we're going to see.
And of course, your channels are things like YouTube and Twitch and etc, etc.
In Japan, we have a few domestic channels that are a little bit unique to the market.
In Korea, you also have ones that are unique to the market.
China, you have ones that are incredibly unique to the market.
But basically, the structure is the same.
Then what type of content are we looking at?
We're looking at asking influencers to play our game, right?
That's a pretty obvious one.
We're looking at asking influencers
to show build guides and advice on how to best play the game
in terms of structure, strategy.
We're looking on opinion pieces as well,
so giving an opinion about which games
are the best of this specific genre
or what is good or bad about this particular thing.
These are all different types of opinion marketing,
influencer marketing that we can leverage
to market our game.
Some of them we need to pay for, some of them we don't.
When we do pay for them, you know,
it can be pricey in some cases
or it can be incredibly cheap in others.
And it depends on what kind of influencer you're after
and what kind of relationship you build with them.
The job of a community manager can actually include maintaining those relationships as well.
So it's not that you're just going to an agency and booking whichever influencers you can get.
Build those relationships and actually you will find that you'll get much better performance out of the influencer marketing.
Next.
Content marketing is a different category.
Looks very similar to influence marketing.
So we're still VOD, streaming content, social media, blogs.
But now we're talking from you as a game developer's
perspective.
And again, we want game plays, demos, special release
content, et cetera, possibly how to play content as well.
Developer insights, things that only you can deliver.
Things that help players get closer to you, essentially.
And of course behind the scenes, etc.
It's going to be a really good approach as well.
Let them learn a little bit more about your titles
and what you can share about that.
And they will get much closer to your game
and much more appreciate your game.
OK, next one, events.
So events, these can be online.
They can be offline.
It can be conference festivals.
You can be part of something bigger.
You can be your own thing.
They can be very casual, or they can be
very formal and grand scale.
There's a lot of different scope for events.
And I've given a basic cost breakdown here
of anything between $5,000 and $100,000.
But it could be free, just your time.
Or it could be.
a million dollars. It could be any level that you actually want to justify in your marketing
plan and it really depends on how you want to engage. And so we will talk about a few
of those examples, but some of the things that you might want to do are tournaments.
So if you have a competitive game, tournaments are great. It could be game trial events.
So we've done a lot of things like caravans around the
around the country, so that we'll set up in each city
with a little bit of a trial event.
People can try out a game.
You can do meetups.
So invite users to come and talk to you as the developer.
And just each other as well.
There's a number of games we'll actually have.
The community drives their own events
with meetups and things like that, which is also great.
Encourage that, support that.
Game culture based events is another one as well.
So you can have things like cosplay,
can help people get into the culture of your event
without actually necessarily playing your game even.
But these are all positives for the visibility,
the engagement with the game.
And the fourth category here is tools.
So these are things that could be website tools or app tools,
for example, that help the player perform better,
understand better, all these things around the game.
So some of the things that we're talking about,
the obvious one is forums.
So provide forums so that people can ask questions
of you or each other.
but also strategy builders.
So you can facilitate people to actually build strategies
of their own design, propose them to other players
as ways to beat the game or perform well in the game.
You can have maps of the game.
You can have things that you can't deliver actually
in-game necessarily.
You can provide as external tools to support the game.
And you can also have game assist tools as well.
So that's things that maybe there are little calculators
that will help you understand how much damage
you're gonna deal per second
if you have such and such a combination
or this kind of thing that helps you actually
do a more in-depth performance
for the people who wanna get to another level in your game.
And all of these things are going to be specific to your game, which you'll choose,
but all of these things are possible ways to further engage your audience in a frictionless way.
So not one of these needs to interrupt another experience, they can all stand on their own.
They can all be a part of the experience that the user is actually after.
Okay, so let's get to the four truths of frictionless marketing.
And so in this, I'll give you each of the truths
and an example of one thing that actually does that.
So the first one is the human truth.
So we gain a positive feeling of connection
from realizing we are playing or watching real people
with faults and strengths.
This feeling helps us build emotional connection
with the game and its players.
Why is this emotional connection important?
Whenever we're engaging with anything like this,
we're wanting to feel like there's something
actually getting affected.
And we want to have this human connection.
This is actually a subconscious deep desire
with most of our players.
And understanding that I could do better than somebody else,
or I could collaborate with somebody else,
or I could feel like there's places to succeed and fail.
These are all human interactions that will help you
engage with the game,
help you develop a love for the game, actually.
So, let's call this humanized media,
something we're gonna produce off the back of this.
So an example we have here is for the LGL.
The LGL is the League of Legends Japan League.
And we did this piece for
as part of the social media promotion which is operated on Twitter.
Twitter is pretty popular, pretty powerful still in Japan.
and probably in terms of social media communication
is probably one of the strongest channels that we can use.
And so what we did is we built some content
interviewing some of the players and letting them,
some of the pro players, and letting them
just communicate a few things
that opened up their personality a little bit.
And so this is an example.
This is in Japanese, so I won't run it for a long time,
but I can talk you through it.
I don't know if we have any audio on that anyway.
that not got hooked up.
Ah, it's not coming through.
Basically, he's going through a number of 10 questions,
which is just mapping with the League of Legends ban pick
screen.
And the things like, which players
do you like playing against, or which players do you
interact with, what's a famous phrase that you like to say,
what character do you like?
It's coming out of here.
Yeah, it's all right, it's all right.
It's okay, it's in Japanese,
so people won't understand it anyway.
And so it's just things to get at his personality
a little bit.
and this did amazing things in terms of increasing the profile of each of the players
and making people feel closer to the league.
It was a really successful thing.
At the end here, and I'll let it run just until it gets there,
he actually is asked like a bonus question at the end
where he's asked to mimic one of the casters from the league.
He had great fun with this and the response on his performance on this was just huge.
The fan base really loved it.
And there's nothing particularly skillful about it from him,
but it was really, really impactful.
And so what did we see there?
What were the results of it?
We actually had an increase 400%
of the previous top retweet records.
So just by doing these,
we did them twice a week for five weeks during the season.
two different players every time.
And we were upping the previous retweet total by about 400%.
Just the engagement that came off the back of it was just incredible.
It was a huge increase in the awareness of the players as well,
so people started to identify each of the players a lot more.
And there was a personal fan increase for each of those pro players too.
And so in terms of goals for this...
It hit all of our goals, actually.
We achieved exactly what we needed to out of it.
So that's an example of just exposing some of the human side.
There was nothing perfect about what he did in front of the camera, and actually that
was part of the charm.
His speech wasn't natural, it wasn't media savvy, but it made just such a nice impact.
Some of the other things that you might want in terms of humanized media,
direct response from developers.
This is something that any of you can do without a massive investment.
So if you want to respond to people on social media,
tell them things that you're allowed to leak,
or explain why you made certain decisions within your games.
These sort of things are really, really valuable for a player base.
studio tours. We did a...
For EA we did a studio tour of the DICE studio a few years back for the Japanese audience.
And this was received really, really well as a piece of content that people could actually
feel a little bit closer to the development process that was behind, I think at the time it was Battlefield 4.
You can also do things like play a documentary, so you can actually interview, whether you've
got a competitive game or not, interviewing some of the community and proposing that as
content to be engaged with, to share on YouTube, etc.
All these things can be a great way to do humanised media.
Okay, second truth.
So the progress truth.
So when somebody feels like they can grow and learn.
within a game, they're more encouraged to play and keep playing
and to enjoy the game. So this one as
If any of you are involved with your game design teams,
this is something game designers know very well.
You need to manage challenges and things like this.
But as a community manager, you can actually
empower this a little bit as well.
So you can identify places where players get stuck
and do things for it.
So let's call this over-the-hump media, right?
So somebody's hit a challenge within the game,
they can't get past it, they're considering leaving the game,
let's do something to help them.
So the example we can talk about here is Battlefield Senpai.
So this is another EA example.
So we did this, it's actually started a bit earlier,
but the example in the screenshot here
is that's coming up is for Battlefield 1.
We set up a channel, a Twitter channel,
which people could ask questions to.
and we had strong players able to answer through that channel
and give people advice on how to approach different aspects of the game.
This is great to avoid the churn that I mentioned before.
and help that engagement with the game maintain.
And so, especially when you're getting into a game
where you do want to keep people for a long time,
you want to have them engaged
because your revenue streams actually are affected
by the long-term engagement,
this is a great way to do that.
Okay, and what was the result of that?
We had an increase in Twitter followers of about 200% for this.
We had a strengthening of regular player base.
We developed regular interaction with the player base that could then be leveraged for
campaigns and communicating around new releases as well.
So this was also a very successful campaign that we ran for quite a while actually.
Okay, so other examples of over-the-hump media,
community build guides.
So the Dekki.com that I mentioned earlier allows that.
So we do like deck builds for Hearthstone and Gwent,
for example.
This sort of thing can be a great way
for the community to then share ways
to keep progressing and succeeding in the game.
And of course, influencer gameplay videos
are a good example of that as well.
Next truth, aspirational truth.
When people see a higher level that
could be reached within the game,
they develop an aspirational attitude to the game,
driving passion and effort.
So another one that, especially with competitive games,
this is really, really important.
But it can be appropriate to any games.
If people can see the top performance,
they can be excited by that.
So reach for the stars media, let's call it that.
And one example we've got here for Gwent, which actually
hasn't even released 1.0 yet.
We started a game tournament last year,
and it's still going every month now,
called the White Wolf Tournament.
And we run it every month.
It's been pretty well attended, and we livestream it on Twitch.
Very, very successful for such a new game
that is still trying to create buzz.
And Japan has become one of the key markets for City Project Red in the process,
because we've been able to stimulate the audience.
So this is just some screenshots from the stream.
I won't play the video because it has to run off Twitch.
But we set up with casters, and we have...
Nice professional setup there, we run every month, run the tournament, we find a winner,
we got a little bit of prize money, we fly the top four players to Tokyo and we have
them compete.
We even had one of the top performers was from Taiwan, so we even got a little bit of
a regional impact from it.
He had to play the game in Japanese, though.
That was fun.
So the idea of creating something
that demonstrates top performance
excited other players to try to compete,
try to get into the next tournament,
and has done great for giving a nice baseline
to the community there.
What did we achieve? We established the community of Gwent in Japan and we also regularly get
into the top, we regularly top the rankings for Gwent on Twitch. Pretty much anytime we're
streaming we're top of the Twitch rankings.
Other examples might be pretty much anything eSports. There are more as well but that's
the one I'll throw out for now.
anything eSports is showing top-level play.
And the last truth, because I know I'm running short on time,
inclusion truth.
When people feel like they're part of the culture of a game,
they are more inclined to contribute and engage with activities and gameplay.
So comfy sofa media, we're going to call it.
And the example I've got here is Hearthstone World.
And so working with Blizzard, we set up a weekly Twitch stream
where we have two key influencers come on
and they bring on a community.
someone from the community to talk about the meta,
talk about good decks to play, talk about news that's happening,
talk about fun stuff.
And we go through a bunch of
gameplay that they can play against people who are watching
live on the stream as well, so they'll usually play a few games against
people watching to our show weekly. We've been running almost a year already for this.
We also have some international guests occasionally too.
Jackie Chan who's a famous Hearthstone player out of the UK.
Results? We actually have near 100% awareness amongst top influences in Japan,
top Hearthstone influences in Japan.
Pretty much anybody you speak to watches the show.
So if you go to a tournament or whatever, they're all...
very heavily engaged.
We developed a regular audience who will tune in every week
and we provide a platform for news information
to be distributed to the most passionate users.
And I'm out of time, so I'm going to very quickly jump to the end,
which is just a little bit of a summary.
Traditional media is losing its effectiveness.
Community can fill that gap.
Frictionless media is a community-focused marketing
solution that can become a part of a game's marketing plan.
And frictionless media equals be the destination, not
the speed bump.
And the four frictionless media truths, human truth, progress,
aspirational, and inclusion.
Thank you very much.