Hey everyone, welcome to the GDC Twitch channel. My name is Brian Francis. I am a contributing editor
at gamasutra.com. I am also the community manager for GDC. We are here today back on the GDC Twitch
channel playing a game you may have heard about called Bugsnax. What are Bugsnax? What adorable...
What happens when you eat them?
This is something that you will find out
when you watch the footage that is playing for us right here,
which unfortunately is pre-recorded.
Sadly, we are not playing live today.
But hey, if you like bug snacks, you're
going to see some bug snacks.
If you would prefer not to get any spoilers...
I would suggest tuning away because this is going to be spoilers for the first hour of the game.
But, we're not just here to play Bugsnax, we're here to talk with some of the folks who made Bugsnax.
That's why we are your friends, Kevin Kessler and John Murphy, who will be appearing in the lower left-hand corner of the screen.
Kevin and John, if you would please introduce yourselves.
Sure. Well, I'm Kevin. I'm a programmer at Young Horses, one of two of us.
I primarily worked on the PlayStation side of things, in addition to just my half of the rest of the gameplay logic.
I'm John, and I was a gameplay designer.
for Bugsnax, mostly, you know, designing the game mechanics, the sort of behaviors of Bugsnax,
and the tools and traps used to capture them in the game.
Right on. We're going to be talking a lot about tools and traps in just a minute while the intro to Bugsnax plays out before us.
If you're in the audience and you'd like to ask good design or development questions for the folks from Young Horses, feel free to do so.
I've got chat open in the window, and I will be asking them.
Kevin and John, if you wouldn't mind starting off, Bugsnax is a...
It's a weird game with an incredibly functional purpose and game logic that has just captured people's attention.
Where did this come from?
It's kind of like a multi-layered question because where did the idea for bug snacks, bugs which are snacks, come from?
Where did the idea of a systems-driven game where you interact with them come from?
Where did the idea of everyone is Grumpus Otter's thing come from?
There's so many layers to the question, where did this come from?
And I only hope you can answer some of them in the way I phrased this.
We as a team decided, hey let's try to do something new.
We've only done Octodad, that's been our lives.
Let's try to come up with some different ideas and prototype them and see where that gets us.
So, we had a number of prototypes.
After pitching a few dozen or more ideas that we ended up trying and making,
one of them, pitched by creative director Kevin Zoon,
was based on the idea of bugs as different real-life foods, such as...
You know, what we ended up with the game, like a crabapple.
And the idea was we would go on like a safari, sort of an on-rails, Pokemon Snap style adventure.
Where you are using different physics-based tools to sort of lure and capture them from your vehicle.
And we, over time, moved away from that when we decided,
uh, I'm not sure that on-rails is fun,
I'm not sure that Pokemon Snap is actually fun anymore.
Um, so from there we kind of ended up layering
a lot of other gameplay mechanics,
just even from our other pitches that we didn't go forward with.
Uh, and that's where we sort of brought in...
Like, oh, what if these characters are on this island?
What if they're reacting to eating different bug snacks?
What are their backstories? How does that change them?
It really snowballed completely away from the original pitch,
but into something that I think we all wanted to actively work on.
Yeah, and I guess there were sort of like three games that we actually prototyped that like we...
None of them really worked by themselves. There was a game that was like a sort of like spooky
narrative summer camp sort of idea that we abandoned and then slowly over time like the sort of like...
Being a small community and bringing people into that community and exploring outward from that main camp crept back into the game.
There is a pitch for a game about...
Where the name Grumpus came from was a pitch for a game called Gut City Grumpus
that was about changing the guts of these cute monsters that looked very similar to
to what Grumpuses ended up like and changing their behavior by feeding them things.
Some aspects of that ended up in there.
Yeah, um, and then the- when we were making the Pokemon Snap like on rails sort of thing, the
mechanics, we like basically were like, oh let's try to make something that's like
on rails like this, because this was- when we started making this it was like when like VR was
like really peaking as a thing, so that was like kind of in our minds that we could try to take
advantage of that, but then like
That didn't end up working in our ways of trying to make it not just a...
The snapping pictures, like straight up Pokemon Snap sort of thing, those mechanics that we started to develop,
like, didn't work with being on rails because it just like felt like you're being rushed all the
time. Like you can't like set up a trap like this because then it's like, oh wait, there's my, like,
the thing that I'm trying to do is like I'm, I'm constantly moving past it on this roller coaster
and that's stressful and bad. So eventually we were just like, let's take some of these like
observing and capturing.
mechanics and make a little bit more of a chill, slower, um...
Chill, Slow, and Observational. I actually really mean, we're in the tutorial right now, so you're sort of getting the guided version of what these mechanics all look like.
But, yeah, I like that description. Chill, Slow, and Observational. That feels like the best part of this experience is when you're in that mode, making connections in your own head before you actually get to play in real life.
Before my questioning continues, I will give shouts to folks in chat like Saggycoffee, who just said hey! Hey, back at you, Saggycoffee!
I
didn't recognize the pronunciation.
Anyway, yeah, so if you've got questions feel free I'll also pull up your people's stream comments.
It's a stream, it's interactive, we're here, like I'm just an in-between guy for y'all to chat.
Anyway, more about Bugs Next.
John, you said you introduced yourself with kind of a like, um...
Yeah, like, this game has a lot of, like, kind of if-then logic that it invites you to pick up on.
Like, the simple logic right here of, this animal is scared.
If it's nearby, you can't capture it.
Like, that's the most... one of the most basic principles.
And then, as you'll see, this escalates really quickly with sort of once we get past the 30-minute mark.
What, uh... what makes good if-then logic in a game like this, I guess?
Like, what guided you through the process of making all these complex interactions?
Uh, that's very, it's funny to me because like, so like, on Octodad it was very much
like very linear if then logic, uh, like the sort of stuff that I was doing and so like
I did not know what I was getting myself into starting to create these sort of like much
more modular, um...
I guess pieces of the game about the traps and the bug snacks and everything where they
interact with each other in ways that I can't always predict.
And the if-then logic of basically building rudimentary AI was not really a thing.
that I'd ever done before.
And it took a lot of back and forth and help.
And Kevin, both Kevin and Devin, our other programmer,
making a lot of customized tech.
stuff and features for our editor to allow me to do this sort of more like class-based
stuff instead of having everything just be like flat triggers in a level that are very simple
and straightforward. Gotcha. Kevin, is there anything you'd like to throw in about making
this kind of in-game logic work like that you think other developers might benefit from knowing?
Um...
I don't know, because we really had a lot of iteration on different layers of gameplay.
Like, some of the stuff didn't make the cut, but I would say once we hammered in some of
the little things, it was nice to be able to just broadly apply them to all of the bugs
as sort of behavior.
You know, like being able to run to a bush and hide.
Not necessarily restricting that to one single bug, but being able to allow a group of bugs to have that sort of behavior as part of their list of actions.
I guess my follow-up question about bug behavior would be,
the game is sort of working right now, as we can see in the footage,
to establish a logic for the player to understand about that behavior.
So this is obviously a tutorialization of it,
but down the line there are some very complex interactions that...
Um, that the player has to comprehend in order for them to be able to proceed.
Um, was there anything in this process where you sort of thought about,
okay, this is cool and fun, but can we make sure players actually understand it?
Um, I'm curious if you had any particular challenges about that,
about making sure that like your good ideas were communicated to the player.
Well, I think in a lot of those cases, we ended up trying to make sure,
are there multiple ways to solve this, even if they seem...
uh, you know, unintuitive.
Because people may not get
maybe the most straightforward way we were trying to to guide them with some of these behaviors, but they'll usually creatively think of
at least one alternate, and there's especially cases where, you know, maybe most of us on the team
wouldn't
think of that solution at all
and are pleasantly surprised when that shows up.
I know one for me that I guess was intentional.
There's just some bugs I didn't realize you could just hit with a slingshot out of the
air and they'll just go flying.
I don't think the game explicitly tells you to try to do that, but me discovering that
on my own in this game that I worked on was actually very nice.
John, is there anything you learned about trying to help players understand Bugsnax logic?
Um, let's see. Well, one thing in terms of understanding sort of like the...
giving an impression of like what the the bug snacks were like thinking was uh the addition
of the little emoji bubbles. I think that that that helps one with just like a little bit of
very minor character building and helps reinforce like of this thing.
Like, don't do this, this is making it afraid.
Or like, this Bugsnax is attracted to this other Bugsnax in this situation.
Another thing was, basically, we have like, not a huge set of behaviors.
There's like, Bugsnax can shoot things.
be on fire or be frosty so it's hard to catch them. They can be sort of quick-moving and evasive
and or they can be flying those sorts of things. There may be like 12 things like that.
And then kind of like hopefully be sort of like recombining those simple behavioral building
blocks.
would make it so that when a player comes across a new bug snack, they have enough experience
with other bug snacks that they can sort of piece together or quickly figure out by playing
around with it and using the snack scope to get some clues about it.
It's not entirely new every time.
Yeah, I guess the follow-up, like, what happens after players learn about Bugsnax, you know,
when they, like, they're also, you know, like, you're caught, like, we have a task right here,
you know, use ketchup to lure Burger Beetle, I forget the real name of it, sorry, Bunger,
Bunger, because they're on screen!
You know, then you have to create sort of puzzles for the player, I guess, on top of that.
So I guess, like, then the, um...
The, I, I, obviously, you know, making games is an iterative, multi-layered process.
Like, first, you know, you have to make logic, and then you're iterating on puzzles.
But I guess, like, from there, it was like, okay, now you have, like, a chain of logic.
And I guess along with, I mean we can talk about the narrative context later because the narrative context is delightful, but you know then
when you get down to it, we're gonna see some puzzles later where it's like find these bugs and deliver them to this person
becomes a structure for how things proceed and on some level that has to work and be understandable as well
even with the logic you've described. So I guess what were your thoughts about making objectives for players in that space?
So most of the quest design, our creative director Kevin Zoon did a lot of that, but we talked a lot about trying to make it so that it's essentially a series of fetch quests.
It's like the core loop of the bug catching and questing, but we tried to mix in some other...
non-bug catching things or other mechanics that are related to interacting with the bug
snacks.
For example a mini-game where you have to...
Use the buggy ball, your little hamster ball thing, to lead a bug snack through a maze.
Just like little things like that combined with, I mean, the storytelling and characters
do most of the work, I think, of breaking up all of that, but we also wanted to have some
mechanical variety in there while still having this sort of core loop.
Kevin, do you want to add anything?
Um...
I guess I'd just say or reiterate, well, this level that we're watching especially really just sets up sort of the sequence of how a lot of the rest of the game is, where it will give you a tool presented at its most basic to get you to understand that tool, but then give you an objective where you really have to
Combine it in sequence with another tool in order to accomplish a specific goal.
And I know this level in particular went through a lot of iteration,
making sure it was at the right difficulty and the right pacing,
which was kind of hard because we had...
a decently wide audience of people testing this level over and over
where you get some people who were just able to breeze through this and are like
this is too easy this is a very boring tutorial but then you have other people like
really struggling, uh, you know, either to get the puzzles or to, uh, grasp the, the sort of twitchiness
that the gameplay can sometimes require. Uh, and trying to figure out how to balance that, uh,
a lot of the work really went into this, you know, sequence of the game in particular.
But I think that's probably going to be true of us.
A lot of games, especially games that are trying to do something different with their mechanics,
they're going to spend a very large percentage of game development making sure this level or this sequence works.
Gotcha.
Like I said, this is the GDC Twitch channel.
Normally we are here talking about how games get made, like trying to crack them open and
discuss the internal logic.
Why do I bounce up right now when this bunker hits me?
But we're going to bring in a fun question from chat from Kinmoku87.
Kinmoku87 says, they love bug snacks.
Did you enjoy coming up with new snacks concepts?
And most importantly, who is your favorite snack and who is your favorite breakfast?
I guess I'll answer first.
Yeah, go for it.
I feel like Bilbo is my favorite character, but maybe that's because he's very inoffensive.
I just kind of like that, you know, no matter what, he's trying to push along both the player and...
uh, the other characters in the game to sorta come back together and
recover from the sorta split that has occurred.
Um, my favorite bug snack is probably
the Ribblepede, uh, which you really have to
watch it in action to see why it's such a good bug.
Um, even aside from that, the transforms, uh, that it gives, uh...
are a bit jarring, but incredibly well done.
Uh, Jon, what is your...
I need to know what your favorite Bugsnax is before we continue.
Also your favorite Grumble, but you know.
Yeah, so I'm gonna go...
So, the Ribble Pete is kind of centipede rib.
Uh, my favorite is the, um...
I'm gonna say it's the Sprinklepede, which is a donut millipede, mostly because of the animation and sound design on that one,
because when you scare it out of hiding, it runs around the whole level and it rolls around like a wheel.
makes like a car screeching like peel out sound if you get too close to it.
And it's just a it's a great looking design.
And my favorite grumpus is Chandlo. It's kind of like a a a kind.
Chill bro, which is what I aspire to someday be.
Oh man, I think we should all aspire for kind, chill brodom.
Okay, let's dive into...
There's a big...
Um...
There's a PlayStation-y part of all this that I think is worth bringing up.
Um, I played this game on PlayStation 5. It's also available on PlayStation 4.
It's a game that you can buy... you don't even have to buy it if you have a PlayStation, you know...
I forget, uh, a PlayStation subscription. It's on PS Plus.
God, I forget my name of the service. I use the service, so...
This is very bad hosting of me.
But, um, uh, this is a game that is launching with the PS5.
It has some interesting features that take advantage of the controller, the new haptics.
Um, it also, because it's launching on PS5, it means you guys were developing for new hardware
before a lot of other developers were.
What was kind of that experience?
Um, and, uh, Octodad was also kind of an early PS4 game too,
so it seems like Young Horses has gotten two opportunities to sort of be part of the indie launch.
for Sony's new consoles.
Is there anything you guys have learned about this experience that was particular...
I don't know, like what do you think other developers should know about making games for this console?
Well, pleasantly, working on PS5 was
kind of identical to working on PS4.
We had put together our own tech
in order to do Octodad, and...
Basically after that, we kind of went with the decision,
well, we already ported it to, you know, like 11 platforms or whatever,
let's try to get another game out,
you know, while this generation happens.
So me personally, I was anticipating we would release
this game before the next generation.
Which we, I guess, kind of made it.
Being a launch title for PS5 was pretty beneficial just because it gave us sort of like a talking point for when we announced our game.
Plus we still had the PlayStation 4 version.
that we had been working on this whole time.
As far as sort of the development differences,
I do think coming into this,
the controller was absolutely my favorite part to play with
in terms of development.
We ended up using FMOD for audio
and Seth, who did our
uh sounds and it ended up getting assigned doing all the the sort of haptic feedback and vibrations
for the game through that system and i'm not sure we really don't have any like
external game development experience. I can't say what games did before this, but a cool thing we
were able to do was with the audio, sort of just use that to feed into other systems. For instance,
the animations of the characters are all flapping jaw animations. It's just all driven by
amplitude coming out of FMOD. And now the controller vibrations are also just...
audio sent out from fmod. Seth can just hook up a sound and route it straight to the controller
as a vibration.
And on top of that, the work that went into the PS5 version,
wherever to put into the PS4 version,
where it may not have the cool rumble features,
but we can just track all that audio that was meant to be routed to the PlayStation controller,
and reroute it to just the controller rumble amplitude on other platforms.
So that was my...
favorite part uh the controller also had some cool stuff we did with the the triggers as well
just sort of trying to make those feel different uh in terms of like oh uh when you've got the
scope open uh one of the triggers feels more like a clicking a shutter button
and then
Because I was sort of enamored with the controller, we also threw in controller sounds.
So like capturing the bug, the controller then speaks the bug's name right after capture it.
I wish we could have captured that for the stream, but you can't. Unless I have my phone
recording it, you can't. Like I'm just sitting here capturing bugs and it's just like,
like, bonger! Like just pops out of my hand. I'm like, okay.
Yeah. No, that one, that one really gets people.
Yeah.
I liked that you brought up the controller because I'm playing a couple other PS5 games
and I agree.
This thing is just such a cool device.
There's weird little ways that even though you kind of don't think these things are essential
for a game, they certainly make things feel really cool.
The fact that there's these special vibrations and the pressure, the different haptic pressure
you can get on the triggers.
We've sort of heard, like, developers, you know, you guys launched this game first on PS5, you mentioned Octodad got ported, so you've worked with other consoles.
We have been wondering, from talking to some of the developers, about...
Like, should developers like put extra time and effort, how much extra time and effort does it take to make things for this controller?
Um, what are your kind of thoughts about like what the payoff is for developers who are making games for multiple platforms
to be paying attention to the controller and putting work into making it feel special?
Um, the controller specifically, I think, is absolutely worth the effort.
But I guess, in terms of like, platform specific features, it was one of the things that took the least amount of time.
Uh, because there were certainly other things that we had to learn to use or to rethink.
Uh, but, I don't know. I think...
I think the controller is certainly...
A thing that adds an extra layer to playing the game that really didn't take that much
time to do compared to a lot of other things we've put in.
Um, ooh, uh...
Me?
Oh, that's interesting.
Excel Kobayashi would like to know, and you may not have an answer to this, but it's worth asking.
Ask away, I guess.
Does the PS5-style rumble work with the PS5 controller on PC?
Uh, Excel Kobayashi, I can answer part of that before they do, which is Steam just announced that the controller is supported,
but the special haptic features aren't being supported right now.
They're coming down the line.
Uh, but I don't know. Have you guys worked with it on PC at all? Do you know if it's gonna be like, um, as functional there?
I-I don't know anything beyond what I just said.
No, I read the same thing as you, and I don't know...
how...
uh...
you know, that gets implemented across different games, but...
I will say I wish, uh, Windows had better controller support.
They basically, you know, support an Xbox controller.
Or you use direct input and you have a lot of different under-the-hood hacks if you want other features to work.
And I know Steam has been doing a very good job of gaining access to a lot of these controller features and just automatically supporting it on their platform.
I wish it wasn't just a Steam-driven thing, but it'll be interesting to see if they actually do get the PS5-style rumble working on PC, because that would be pretty...
Pretty nice.
Yeah.
John, before we move off the controller, is there anything you'd like to weigh in with
about working on the PS5, I don't know, either working on the PS5 or working on the specific
controller, the new DualShock, that you particularly enjoyed in this process?
I know like you said it was your sound guy doing a lot of it, but if there are any thoughts
you have, I'd love to hear them.
Uh, yeah.
Yeah, like, yeah.
Like, I, like, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I,
I didn't really have much direct input, but a post-release thing that players have noticed
that I think is worth mentioning is that the game help has been really nice for people,
having these little video hints about how to catch a particular bug snack.
Anyway, I'll be here if you need me.
We had a lot of help from Sony on actually generating all of that, but that is a thing
that I think, you know, I imagine in general that's a thing that developers are gonna have
to do if they want to support that, and I think that players are going to like it a lot, or like,
at least for games like ours, like, it's like, oh, okay, next time I want to keep in the back of my
head that, like, uh...
If, like, maybe we're going to have to do this and it's going to be a lot of work, but it might be worth it.
Um, to- to- will probably be worth it, or at least it'll be a new expectation from- from players that it's there.
Um.
Yeah, people liked it a lot.
For, like, Bugsnax, I've seen people say that it is a particularly good use of that feature.
Yeah, I guess does that, um...
We're all talking kind of abstract here, because it seems like...
I mean, it's so hard to predict how these things will play out before they do.
I know, like, it's not accurate for me to say this influenced how puzzles got made in this game,
because no one makes puzzles with the expectations of how the guides will be.
But does it kind of help you as a designer to go, okay, I can push the boundaries on a puzzle if I'm confident that players...
Some players will want to participate in that challenge, and others will have the ability to quickly and efficiently get a leg up, you know, and sort of without hurting the other player.
Like having that little bit of... like there is a crutch out there that players can rely on that's in the...
It's simple to understand, and to learn on mechanisms behind the molecular dissemination of snack-dev-ators.
This is the snack-de-vator. Feed me strabby. Poke snack-de-vator in foot. Foot turns into strabby. Understand?
I never really wanted really tough puzzles, I wanted a little bit of the expressive,
you've got different ways to do this, and sometimes it's tricky.
So for me it's more like, ah, this fills in the gaps in my bad design sometimes.
It feels like a safety net for me, so that's kind of similar to what you're talking about.
Yeah, if I was trying to make a hard puzzle game, yes, but in general that's not what I'm trying to do anyway.
I think the use case that I saw when we had started first implementing it was
this would be amazing for parents with children that...
Maybe can't get past a certain part and are stuck and are asking,
why won't this game do this?
Uh, and the parent then may come in and see,
well, I have no idea where you are.
I haven't been playing this game at all,
but they can jump into game help,
uh, and either, you know,
help them, uh, play through it or play through it for their child.
Um, and even aside from that type of relation,
I think players who haven't been playing the game in a while may want to return to any
sort of game and see, hey I've got these activities active, this is where I left off, but I have
no idea what I was supposed to be doing.
And while we try to give those instructions in the game, sometimes having that extra video
instruction can just sort of help them get the ball rolling again.
And I do think that's kind of what Sony was trying to go for with the activity cards in general,
was to keep players being able to move through a game and not just sort of languish on a specific
spot that they may have happened to get caught up on.
The activity cards though, I don't know if they're getting talked about as much as I think they ought to, but...
One thing I wish we had done, that I want to say that Spider-Man has done, is have specific activity cards that you can't access the content in the game otherwise.
You have to go through the activity card to do, you know, the singular activity.
And it's, you know...
completely unrelated to the rest of the main game story, but
for me, either continuing with Bugsnax or our next game, I'd love to do just weird non-canon
activities that you jump in where we don't have to worry about like does this flow with the game,
it's just sort of this, you know, limited thing to do and that's where I see
A lot of cool moments coming from the activities cards in the future.
A. You have made me now I have to go back in because I'm playing Miles Morales right now and I need to go check out those activity cards because I did not know that.
And B. I thought I read an article there's something about pigeons.
I did do a pigeon quest.
The first game had a pigeon's word big thing, but we can talk about Spider-Man and pigeons another time.
B, that's so... it's weird because it's the only PlayStation that's doing it, right?
I don't know, like we already have like content that's platform exclusive.
That is a thing that all, you know, developers shell out money for, but if it's gonna be
that way, like I do appreciate...
I'm excited by the idea of developers being able to make something special for people
who are paying attention, and only a few people see it, but it's the ones who like check the
activity cards and go, hey, wait a minute.
Like, that excites me because I like it, I feel like it makes relationships between...
players and developers like a little more concrete like you can sort of
subsection out a group of people who will go that far as opposed to the people who are like
oh this is like like you know like you can help to sort of categorize your fans
I guess. For my next bug snacky question. There's also we skip over it there's a
interview system in this game where after a character you successfully get
characters back to town.
Like you said, you mentioned earlier, you know, it's from another Summer Camp prototype,
this whole notion of getting a community back together, like helping people solve their problems.
There is kind of this neat, like, oh, like players acquiring facts and piecing together those facts to do information,
which it's delightful that this is a game where you're a journalist because as an alleged journalist,
it's nice to play a game where I'm the hero for once instead of the side character who gets punched, like in Mass Effect 2.
I gotta say, what were sort of your thoughts about making a game where instead of just having a story that...
And there is kind of a straightforward story to it, and there are dialogue trees which are more conventional,
but this kind of like interviewing people, like it's low-key interrogation,
like the information that you get from these interviews needs to be, you know...
Like, what were... how did that sort of... I know this is maybe more of a question for your creative director,
but I'm curious what thoughts you guys had about making a system like that in a game when you're
already bogged down with, like, so much Bugsnax logic to also have this interview system logic.
Well, as we were playtesting, we would continuously get feedback that...
It was unclear who the player was or like why they were,
what their motivation was and things like that.
So we like slowly layered in, you know, like the sort of like opening scene
with your with your editor and then
the the interviewing mechanic and.
Yeah, so I guess we just wanted that sort of narrative frame for.
for who the player is.
And I think Kevin could talk a bit more about the iteration on the interview mechanic,
because that was for a long time kind of tedious and not super...
It's like, okay, this is what we're trying to use to solve this problem of not knowing who the...
It's like the main reminder throughout the game that you are a journalist and why you're there.
But for a long time it was like, it took a while to get it right.
Yeah.
Kevin, do you wanna, do you have anything to throw in?
Heh.
Well I'll just say like, yeah the interview system I would say came in late.
And so a lot of things about our game were a bit scopey during development.
But I would say doing a 3D object journal...
Uh, imprinting the UI on that, uh, all while not having a, uh, a UI editor.
I had to code all the UI in this game.
Uh, yeah.
And not having a UI artist for years.
Yeah, I was about to say, uh, not having a few, sort of, key people that were, you know, kind of the driving force behind the interview system.
Like, uh...
We had Bryce come in about midway through the project, and then late in the project,
along with other people on the team, just sort of finally hammered out, like,
okay, we need to make this sequence actually look good.
It needs to be presented well, because otherwise, like,
the whole driving force of the story is that you're the journalist, so, like, if the interviews...
Just sort of act like the dialogue system, then, you know, what's the point?
But then of course we had...
We brought in Justine as a UI artist to help us
dress up all of the
the UI in addition to that to actually make
all this UI shine.
And then of course Seth's music and audio.
It helped make the sort of sequence kind of, you know, defining moments for the player
and sort of giving them a chance to, you know, narratively pick out, like, what is it that is driving these characters.
And, I don't know, it really helps create good moments and sort of sets the mood going forward for each of these characters.
I agree with that. I appreciate being in a game where being a journalist is just not an incentive for the main character to punch you.
Anyway, I also love Mass Effect 2 to be clear. It's one of my favorite games.
I'm not that hung up about it. It's just you guys, well the second you guys put out a trailer that showed you're a journalist, every game journalist I knew collectively went, oh no.
Like, not out of like fear, but just more out of like...
Oh no, it's us. Like, we're the hero. It's a specific thing.
For folks in chat, we only have a few more minutes to get questions in.
We would love to hear your questions if you have them, but if you also just want to hang out and admire the bugsnax, we're just happy to have you here.
I am going to go ahead and ask one of my final questions, which is...
I know this would be more of a creative director question, but I am curious as to what your guys' thoughts are.
Bugsnax has a really interesting tone, where it's cute and also horrifying.
Like, there's low-key, it's low-key like the people transforming is kind of body-horror-y.
But it's also adorable.
The plot is, on the one hand, like, it's cute and it's about an island with all these grumpuses and all these cute names.
On the other hand, I kind of get the vibe that there's something kind of serious going on.
I haven't seen the late game yet, so there's even other things that I have heard about but not seen for myself yet.
But I'm just kind of like...
Like this is such a specific intersection like this is sort of like it's not cutesy like a PBS show
It's not horror like David Lynch and yet so many people
I know when they saw this game were just like low-key like
What am I looking at like like this specific intersection of these two things that is perfectly natural and also like completely
What wrong like like how did you sort of feel as?
Creative people like working on a game that had this kind of tone
That is both of those things, like cute and maybe a little horrifying.
Well, I mean, I think it really just comes from like.
Like we are a very like collaborative team,
like we probably do a little bit too much of like everyone being
in everyone else's business, you know, like before the pandemic,
we were all in one room all the time and we all have like
there's a pretty.
Interesting range of tastes and influences on the team.
We all agreed that the intersection of what everyone likes is in the adventure time zone,
where there's serious real stuff, and it's also silly and it's also cute.
So it's good that we're doing this.
We're able to actually get all that in there, you know, and we, you know, we have
influences that range all the way from like, you know, cute Muppets and stuff like that,
to like, you know, a thing that I always was like, was in the back of my head was like,
like, Apocalypse Now, you know, like, like someone looking for this missing person and
like, slowly descending into this.
the new headlines, new voice.
That's the magic of voice.
Now my creative piece fails,
can't help but love you.
I know I'm flowing, I'm flowing.
Mmm-hmm.
Ooh-ooh-ooh-ooh!
Aa-a-a-ah!
La-la-la-la-la-la!
Ooh, ooh, ooh-ooh-ooh.
Yep.
I need you to turn it up, darling!
Yeah, would you like to throw anything in with that?
Kevin?
I don't know.
Certainly there were times where this game was brighter and there were definitely times
where this game was darker in terms of tone.
I think we were trying to find that kind of balance where it could still be for ages that
could sort of competently play our game to the end.
I know a lot of us go back and we'll sometimes re-watch, you know, the family films that
were actually quite dark and there's still even some now, it's not just what we grew
up with.
So being able to take those sort of messages and put them through narratively through the
characters because not everything's going well for them and you're trying to help them
through.
They're troubles.
But a lot of children's media doesn't shy away from that.
It's able to present it in a way that I think kids understand.
And, you know, I think older people sometimes look at kids and are like,
oh, they're going to be horrified by this.
Or, but I don't know.
I think kids probably see a lot more horrifying things.
that I don't think most of what happens in this game phases them.
Like if you turn a character into a giant apple or whatever,
it's not going to phase them as much as an adult who's like,
that looks weird.
Maybe it's just like, I feel like maybe it's like as adults, like there's just more...
Uh...
I...
I am scared of more things than as an adult.
Well, I don't know.
Like, when I was a kid, I was scared of tornadoes, but I thought tornadoes were like these grumpy
looking monsters that lived in the basement.
Uh...
Not the actual windstorms that plagued us when I lived in Minnesota for a year.
As an adult, I have a mild case of tryptophobia, where if you show me a thing with too many holes,
I'm bothered. As a kid, I would have been like, whatever, like, tryptophobia.
But like, I saw one tree when I was like 14 or something, and now that tree is with me for life.
Impossibly,
impossibly, that is definitely TMI, but...
I, uh, uh, Kevin and, and, and John, thank you so much for joining us today.
Thank you for bringing us the wonderful world of Bugsnax.
Uh, we're going to wrap things up here.
Uh, Blader Coyote, uh, I'll, I'll address you in a second.
Um.
For those of you who are new to the GDC Twitch channel, this is a place where we interview developers,
talk about the games they're making, give you a chance to answer questions about them.
And GDC in general is all about the art and business of making games.
It's not just programming, it's design. It's not just design, it's the UI art.
It's not just the UI art, it's how do you sell and market games.
And sometimes we're talking about that.
We try to here and on gamasutra.com, that is what we are talking about.
So if you want to stick around, we'd love it if you click the follow button.
If you're a game developer, Talks for GEC 2021, you can submit your talks now.
Head over to our website, which is down at the bottom.
Trying to point... There we go. That direction on your screen.
You can go and look up information about submitting a talk.
And Blader Coyote is going to ask the question that is most likely to get us all in trouble with Sony.
Can you guys confirm that the protagonist is Peter Parker on vacation?
Is the protagonist's name Grumpus Garp, I guess?
Huh.
Uh...
It seems like no. Seems like the answer is no.
Yeah, I guess that's a no.
No comment.
No comment? Okay, we're gonna take that.
Um, with that, we're gonna end a little early over here.
And thank you all so much for doing this. I hope you all are doing well.
It is a pandemic plague year of many scary things and I hope everyone just stays inside,
wears a mask, and continues to keep each other alive.
This is the first stream we've had where we didn't have time to talk about making games remotely
in 2020 and I would have loved to, you know, pick your guys' brains about it,
but we spent too much time admiring the adorable foxes,
which I don't think you can actually spend too much time doing.
With that, have a good day everyone. Bye!
Thank you.