Hello everybody, my name is Xinxiang Chong, I'm a designer at Respawn Entertainment.
Welcome to my talk, Standing on the Shoulders of Giants, also less pretentiously known as
Evolution of Rodeo in Titanfall.
So quick reminder, please turn off all your cell phones.
We got a lot of ground to cover and only 16 minutes to do so, so we're just going to get
right to it.
So, what is Rodeo in Titanfall?
Well, in case you've never played the games before,
but for some reason are still interested in this talk,
the Titanfall series of games are first-person shooters
featuring acrobatic, wall-running pilots
dueling massive armored titans on the battlefield.
One of the signature moments of the game is something we call Rodeo,
where crafty pilots can sneak up on an unsuspecting titan
and jump onto their back.
In Titanfall 1, pilots rip off an access panel
and they shoot the exposed circuitry to deal heavy damage.
In Titanfall 2, however, Rodeo becomes a cat and mouse game of the pilot stealing a Titan battery,
taking a chunk of the Titan's health, and then the Titan frantically hunting
down the pilot to get the battery back.
So, what I'll do during this talk is give a highlighted tour of the history of Rodeo.
It won't be an exhaustive list of everything we tried with Rodeo, although I should be
here all day, but we'll cover the major milestones along the way.
I'll provide some insight about the unique design challenges for Rodeo.
Not many other games feature classes as distinct as Pilot and Titan, and making Rodeo be a
satisfying mechanic for both has actually some surprisingly difficult constraints, which
we'll go further into.
And lastly, we'll go into what we think went well,
as well as what we think went poorly with Rodeo.
Specifically, we'll talk about some of the rationale
behind the huge changes we made for Rodeo
between Titanfall 1 and 2,
and why we think it makes for better gameplay.
Incidentally, what this talk will not go into
is any in-depth details
of the technical implementation of Rodeo,
so if you're hoping to get details for that,
I'm sorry to disappoint.
But in the beginning, so back in August 2012,
what was eventually going to be Titanfall
was slowly but surely taking shape.
After spending years prototyping several concepts,
we decided to focus on two classes
for our multiplayer-only game,
wall-running, double-jumping, super-acrobatic pilots,
and giant mechanized weapons of destruction called Titans.
And the idea was that players would start the game
in a Titan, and then when it got really hurt,
they could eject away and get a second life as a pilot.
An early idea we had was, what if a pilot could jump onto the back of a Titan and do heavy damage to it?
And we called the idea Rodeo.
Rodeo was supposed to give pilot players another meaningful way to interact with enemy Titans,
other than just shooting at them from afar like a typical FPS.
And the picture you see here was painted by one of our designers, Jeff Smith,
early on to give an idea as to what this David vs. Goliath moment could look like.
So that was our first design goal for Rodeo, give a way for pilots to meaningfully interact
with titans, potentially doing heavy damage to them.
Of course, we didn't have the entirety of Titanfall designed back when we first started
implementing Rodeo.
As work on the game increased, so did our understanding of what it was we were making,
and our understanding for what other goals needed to be hit for Rodeo.
I'll come back to these goals as I show you the various iterations of Rodeo we had, and
how we were trying to do different things.
So, the very first major iteration for Rodeo had pilots immediately pop into place on the
back of a titan when they jumped near the titan.
After a short amount of time, an explosive would be planted on the titan, which would
blow the titan up.
So as you can see, this iteration is super barebones and simple, but even then it quickly
revealed a ton of issues that Rodeo had to contend with that weren't immediately obvious.
And the first and most glaring issue was that of communication.
How do you tell the Titan player what's happening?
So it's a first-person game, and the Titan player literally can't see that a pilot player
is jumping on your back and what they're doing once they got there.
As a pilot player, the problem is less apparent since Rodeo is pilot-initiated,
and the animations that it affects should convey what's going on,
but since Rodeo is a fairly unique element to Titanfall,
there's still quite a bit of a learning curve involved.
Next, once they understand what's going on, what should both sides do once Rodeo starts?
Clearly, it would be ideal if the Titan player could somehow react to what was going on,
and meaningful choices could be made on both the pilot and the Titan that would affect the outcome.
Lastly, how long should an entire sequence take?
Too long and it would distract from the main combat of the game,
but too short and you wouldn't be able to give the beats it deserved as a cinematic moment.
Of course, these aren't the only problems with Rodeo,
but these are issues at the heart of Rodeo that all versions of Rodeo have to contend with and solve.
So with that in mind, let's take a look at how the first iteration of Rodeo looked like from the perspective of the Titan.
So, as mentioned, this first major iteration of Rodeo
was implemented without us fully understanding
the issues involved, but it's useful for us
to take a look at how it addressed those issues
as a baseline we can use for future Rodeo attempts.
Firstly, communication.
Since this first major iteration of Rodeo,
we've handled this problem primarily
through HUD elements and sound.
These are the first and most obvious things to try.
And while they're not perfect, they kinda do the job.
When the pilot climbs on,
the tank gets HUD elements on screen saying,
you are being Rodeoed.
This is true even in the final shipped versions
of Titanfall and Titanfall 2.
second choice.
So for the pilot, once Rodeo starts,
the input, sorry, the sequence completes
without any further input.
However, the pilot can also choose at any time
to cancel the process by manually jumping off.
For the Titan, they needed to find some way
of removing the pilot before rodeo was completed,
and otherwise they'd die.
Other than having a teammate shoot off the pilot for them,
the two main ways the Titan could remove the pilot
were to disembark from the Titan
and shoot the pilot off manually,
or use electric smoke.
And a quick sidebar, in case you didn't already know,
electric smoke was a Titan ability that,
as the name suggests,
deploys a cloud of lightning around the Titan
that zaps anyone in its immediate vicinity.
You can see how this would be useful for a Titan
to get the rodeo pilot off his back.
At this stage of the game, however, it was kind of like a super move from Street Fighter,
so you had to charge up a bar before you could deploy it.
So the ability to kill rodeo pilots with it was somewhat limited.
length. Uh, so this iteration of Rodeo lasted about a total of 6 seconds and our playtest
revealed that this was probably a bit on the short end as it gave little time for the Titan
to react to what was going on before they died. But that said, from the playtest we
were also pretty confident it shouldn't take 30 seconds or so to complete either. So that
gave us a range of maybe about 10 to 20 seconds or so as probably an ideal window as to how
long the process should take.
So, even though this version of Rodeo clearly had lots of things to improve on, it's important
to focus and see if it did what it set out to do.
Did it give a way for pilots to meaningfully interact with Titans, potentially doing heavy
damage to them?
And I think that yes, we could agree that we did indeed hit this design goal.
Pilots can now jump up onto Titans and blow them up with an explosive.
However, having rodeo be a binary outcome where the titan was either totally destroyed
or totally undamaged was kind of unsatisfying.
When the titan won, the pilot could feel like all his hard work in getting up close accomplished
absolutely nothing.
When the pilot won, the titan was instantly destroyed, and this was counter to the idea
that players could feel safer in a giant armored titan.
And on top of that, there was a desire
for more player choice in the sequence.
Having it just be a canned animation sequence
for the pilot wasn't quite ideal,
and Titan players wanted more ways
to get the pilots off their backs.
So that led us to the next major design goal for Rodeo.
Make Rodeo be a process of a more dynamic range
of outcomes affected by player choices and skill.
And the next iteration of Rodeo had you holding down a trigger to do a steadily increasing
amount of damage to the Titan.
The idea was that pilots would have a special Rodeo drill weapon that you could take out
during Rodeo, and holding down the trigger would activate it.
So, note that while the presentation for this is really rough, it's actually not too far
mechanics-wise from the final version of Rodeo that we shipped with in 10.4.1.
You can also see the inspiration from the original piece of concept art that I showed
earlier.
And this is how it looked like from the Titan's perspective.
So, how did this version compare to the previous one?
With regards to communication, once again,
primarily through hot elements and sound
that we tell Titan pilot what's going on.
Since the drill process was a continuous process
as opposed to the previous discrete process,
that gave more time for effects and sound,
et cetera, to be played,
which helped the communication process for the Titan.
For choice, this time around the pilot had to choose
to fire the weapon instead of being locked
into a fully animated sequence.
Now in this iteration, we only started giving the Titan
the warning that they were getting loaded
when the pilot started firing the weapon.
So there was an element of when the pilot
should start firing the weapon for maximum effect.
Ideally, you'd start firing when the Titan
was already distracted fighting other players.
For Titans, not much changed.
The two main choices remain to disembark
and shoot the pilot off or to use electric smoke.
Length. This iteration of Rodeo had a variable length, but to take a Titan from full health to 0 lasted a bit longer than before, about 10 seconds or so,
although this was more easily tweakable than before by adjusting the amount of damage that the drill weapon did.
Now, did we hit the design goals of this iteration of Rodeo?
First goal was still preserved, so we'll check that off.
For the second goal, having the damage to the titan be applied over time made for a
vastly increased dynamic range of outcomes for rodeo.
Let titan players who are good at getting rodeo pilots off escape with minimal damage,
while letting rodeo pilots who failed to kill the titan still feel like they did something.
So yeah, we'll call that a success.
And while this version of Rodeo Play tested fairly well, the presentation needed a lot of work.
It also didn't help that we were technically unable to do the next step of putting an actual gun into the pilot's hands while rodeoing.
The code features we needed to really sell this feature just weren't quite there yet.
At this point in development time, however,
we were running very close to an internal milestone.
We needed to be able to present the game
at an internal EA marketing event,
and the current form of Rodeo
was way too far from being showable.
This was especially pressing
because we were trying to sell the concept
of a cinematic multiplayer for Titanfall.
So that led us to the next major design goal for Rodeo.
Make Rodeo be visually compelling.
This next major iteration of Rodeo we tried involved planting shaped charges that we called
cabers on the back of the titan after you had jumped on.
It would take multiple cabers to finish off a full health titan.
The Rodeo pilot would have to aim at specific spots to plant the charges, and the spots
would be semi-randomized.
And the titan player could also affect the aim of the Rodeo pilot by dashing around.
And this is how it looked like from the Titan's perspective.
So once again, we'll take a look at how this version
of Rodeo addressed issues before.
Communication, primarily through sound.
In this version, we had actually removed the big flashing,
you are being Rodeo'd, warnings,
as part of a conscious response to feedback
that there was always too many things on screen
in our crazy, chaotic game.
You could hear a thunk as each caber was planted,
but that was about it.
Playtesting did show, however, that we really did need
some kind of visual element on the screen
to tell you that Rodeo was being done to you,
so we eventually brought it back.
Choice. From the pilot's perspective, this was kind of like a mix between iterations 1 and 2.
Instead of a single planted explosive, the pilot chose to plant as many as they wanted before
jumping off and detonating them all. If the player died before jumping off, however, all the cabers
would just disappear. Not much change with regards to the Titan. They could still use electric smoke
or disembark and shoot off the pilot. Lastly, length. This iteration of Rodeo was definitely
slower than the previous iterations. It took about 15 seconds or so to plant enough cabers that a
Titan would die from them.
Same thing as before, let's look to see if we hit the design goals.
The first and the second design goals were still intact, so we'll check those off.
This version of Rodeo definitely looked more polished than the previous one,
and we successfully demoed it at the EA marketing event.
So yeah, we'll say we hit that goal.
However, internally, playtest feedback suggested that
this version of Rodeo was kind of too much like a minigame.
planting the cavers at random spots had to be taught.
And as a multiplayer only game
without a single player campaign,
mechanics that needed to be taught
were kind of already at the limit.
And that led us to Nick's major design goal for Rodeo,
make Rodeo be accessible.
So given the feedback from iteration three,
we decided to revisit iteration two
and actually do the technical work needed to finish it up.
We put in code features to properly handle
putting a weapon in a player's hands
while they were attached to the Titan.
And the player then needed to shoot his weapon
at a weak spot on Titan.
Bring it down.
Okay, you're time to start the launch. Call it when ready.
So we were still harboring the idea that when the Titan player knew that he was being rodeoed,
he could throw off the aim of the pilot on his back by dashing around, smashing themselves
into walls, etc.
So we made the weak point a relatively small area on the Titan.
We had art make us a little hatch panel that we attached to the Titan, and then we had
animation and damage effects for ripping it off and shooting into it.
And our initial playtests were pretty positive.
It felt like we had finally struck the right balance between it being fun, easy to understand,
accessible, and it being cinematic.
There were a few annoying lingering issues with the view of the Titan,
strongly affecting the view of the rodeo pilot.
So when the Titan dashed around and when he turned rapidly,
the pilot's view would kind of lurch right along with a sudden jolt of motion.
And it sometimes made rodeo maybe somewhat nauseating,
but generally we thought, this is it, this is what rodeo is going to be like.
Unfortunately, fixing the view issues took some time,
and we were running really close to our ship date,
so we decided to shelve any attempt to try and have the Titan stashing around,
throw off the aim of the rodeo pilot.
This is the perspective of the Titan.
Oops.
So once again, we'll run through the list of issues.
Since iteration four is pretty much a more polished
version of iteration two, you can expect that this part
is gonna be pretty similar.
Communication, primarily through HUD elements and sound.
However, with the addition of a hatch panel
on the brains of the Titan, we made Rodeo more grounded.
There was an actual physical thing
that pilots ripped out and shot at.
This helped sell the concept of what was going on to the pilot a lot better.
It also gave us the gameplay benefit of the first rodeo attempt on a Titan,
taking longer to start up, as the panel had to be ripped out first,
but subsequent attempts would let the pilot start shooting immediately.
Choice.
So with regards to the pilot, this was very similar to Edition 2.
However, the hatch panel having to be removed before the pilot could fire the weapon
was an additional prerequisite to be fulfilled.
For the Titan, we enhanced their existing choices.
First, by this time, electric smoke had become
a regular Titan ability that could be used on cooldown,
so it became much more effective of a counter for rodeo.
Secondly, to help players disembark and shoot the pilot off,
we made the player's auto-Titan kneel down
if it was being rodeoed.
So, this is a video that shows that.
So before we added this functionality, however,
when rodeoed, the player's Auto Titan would keep trying
to face the pilot on its back, shooting it.
So, you know, it kind of had about as much effect
as a dog chasing its own tail.
Since the Auto Titan now kneeled,
it was much easier to shoot the pilot off.
And it also gave us a way to visually communicate from afar
that the Auto Titan was getting rodeoed.
length. So this iteration already had a variable length, but to take a Titan from full health to
zero lasted about 15 to 20 seconds, which is the longest of all the iterations we had so far.
As mentioned before, this is about long enough for Titans to react to what's going on and for us to
sell the cinematic experience of it, but not too long where it starts to drag on like a separate
mini-game.
Did we hit the design goals?
First goal is definitely intact.
In fact, at this point, since we had added the concept
of shields to the Titan,
we made rodeo damage bypass the shield
and that increased the strategic value of doing rodeo
as opposed to just firing an anti-Titan weapon normally.
The second goal is intact as well,
just by the nature of letting how much damage
a pilot does be dependent on how long he stays on the Titan,
which can be affected by both pilot and Titan choices.
And we hit the third design go-to by doing a bunch more presentation work.
Having the technical feature to have a player hold on to a gun while rotoing,
having a hatch panel that reacted to being shot,
it all helped to sell the experience.
Lastly, accessibility.
We think that Rodeo in Titanfall 1
is actually pretty accessible to new players.
The only inputs involved with Rodeo as a pilot
are one, jump towards a titan,
and two, shoot your gun at a weak point.
These are actions we ask the player to do
in the rest of the game,
and as such, it's actually very feasible
that a player with no information whatsoever
can stumble upon Rodeo during the course of normal gameplay
and understand instantly how to play it.
It's admittedly less accessible from the Titan's perspective, but we've done things like make the Titan OS call out when you're getting rodeoed,
and even advise you to disembark and remove the pilot from your hull.
Overall, I think the accessibility of rodeo is a big win.
At this point in time, we've arrived at how Rodeo shipped in Titanfall 1.
I think it's appropriate to take a step back and reflect a bit deeper on some of the things
we thought went well with Rodeo and not so well.
Firstly, and most importantly, Rodeo proved to be popular with players in Titanfall.
Far and away the most important thing when you're developing a new mechanic is if players
enjoy it or not.
While internal playtest feedback is often a good barometer for success, nothing beats
actual player feedback.
There's plenty of YouTube videos of epic Rodeo moments, and sentiment on Rodeo is generally
positive, so we'll treat that as a win.
Balance. A general sentiment in the community is that Rodeo is fairly well balanced. Even
among high-level competitive players, there is a bit of a divide between whether pilots
or titans have the upper hand when it comes to Rodeo, with some really powerful tactics
available to both pilot and titan players in a 1v1 situation. For example, titans can
use the cluster missile and crouch looking upwards to pin the Rodeo pilot with their
backs against the wall and kill them from the explosion, at the cost of heavy damage
to themselves.
Pilots can jump on, and instead of just shooting their weapon into the weak spot,
they can attempt to call down a Warpfall Titan on their opponent,
eliminating both Titan and Pilot in one quick move.
So we'll take the fact that Rodeo is deep enough to support multiple advanced tactics as a win, too.
Returning back to what went well for Titanfall 1's version of Rodeo.
A fantasy fulfillment aspect.
David versus Goliath is always a popular trope,
and Rodeo evokes that imagery very well.
Another thing that went well with Rodeo,
organic interactions with the Titan Eject system.
Ejecting from your doomed Titan
onto the back of a Titan who was shooting you
is a very satisfying highlight in our game
that happens as a natural result
of both systems working as intended.
So this is a short clip from our E3 reveal trailer
showcasing the moment from ejecting
from your Titan into a Rodeo.
The other interaction that comes with eject is when you eject from your Titan and when
an enemy player is rotoing you.
Both you and the roto player are thrust high into the air when you can have an epic duel
while falling down.
This is a lot more deliberate than the first interaction and had plenty of bugs, but we
think the end result was very much worth it.
This is a clip from YouTube that showcases that moment.
So lastly, since we allow players in the same team
to rodeo their teammates, or as we like to call it,
brodeo, there's a number of interesting interactions
that result.
First of all, since only one person
can be rodeoing a tent at a time,
brodeoing blocks enemy rodeo attempts from happening.
Secondly, Brodewing is a great way for a Titan to quickly ferry pilots to destinations.
For example in CTF, since Titans can't carry flags, a popular tactic is to have your pilot
teammate pick up the flag, have him jump on a Titan teammate, and have the Titan carry
the pilot quickly to the flag cap base.
And so here I picked a video from YouTube showing the Brodew flag cap and how excited
the players are to pull this off.
Oh my god, this is amazing. This is so good. Oh my god. Oh, I did not think of this
I did not think of this. I did not. Oh, that's brilliant. I love it. Titans are made for this game, lads
Come on, go go go go right in the window
Oh get in there get in
All right, come back do it again do it again
Oh
So to encourage this teamwork element of Rodeo,
we even added a feature where as long as the Titan
carrying the pilot has shields,
any damage that the pilot passenger would take
is passed on first to the shields.
And these small things add a very much needed
amount of teamwork in the game.
So now that we've patted ourselves on the back a bit,
it's time to be a bit more harsh
and look at what we think went poorly for Rodeo.
First, the back and forth between the Titan and the pilot could be improved.
Note that even though we previously said that Rodeo supported a wide range of high level
tactics, there's generally a lack of meaningful things that the Titan player can do as a Titan.
Electric Smoke as an option is the loadout choice, but when activated, it really doesn't
offer much in the way of interesting gameplay beyond activate it and wait for the pilot
to die or jump off.
The cluster missile yourself in the corner tactic is kind of awkward, and it's a sign
that there isn't really a better option for Titans to do.
Getting out from your Titan to shoot the pilot is a valid option, but having to disembark feels like a bit of a concession that you don't really have an option as a Titan.
In addition to that, in our in-office playtest, once the Titan player hears the kutunk from the rodeo pilot climbing on,
the Titan player often disembarks immediately and tries to shoot him off.
The rodeo pilot then tries to jump off and take out the newly disembarked player, or he hides somewhere.
And this can lead to a very frustrating game of get out, get in, get out, hide and seek for the Titan player.
And this YouTube video shows this loop of the player getting out of the Titan, getting back in, repeat.
So he gets out, there's a dude on him, he jumps off, he's like, okay, I guess I'm getting back in my Titan.
Gets back in, he notices the guy is still on his back, and he's like, alright, fine, I'm getting out.
He tries to shoot him, and the rodeo pilot jumps again.
This time he fakes going back in before actually shooting the pilot off.
So, another thing that went poorly for rodeo, aiming during a rodeo.
We talked about Brodeal having useful applications, but actually staying on top of a friendly
titan and trying to shoot a target can be an exercise in frustration.
Titans move at a really fast clip and a lot of the screen of the Brodeal player is taken
up by the model of the titan, which makes it very hard to shoot anything accurately.
Last of all, readability.
As mentioned before, Titans can move really quickly
and only one person can rodeo a Titan at a time.
Sometimes when you turn the corner
and see an enemy Titan close by,
you just jump out in reaction.
It's hard to see sometimes though
if the Titan already has somebody rodeoing him,
and if it does, it often ends in the pilot's untimely death
as he gets squished by the walking Titan.
This is a constant source of frustration.
All right, so that was how rodeo was developed
in Titanfall 1.
We're about halfway into the talk.
How's everybody doing?
Alright, alright, so hold on tight because now we're going to go into the story of how and why we did Rodeo in 10.4.2.
So even though we clearly understood that Rodeo in 10.4.1 wasn't perfect and could be improved,
that still doesn't quite explain why we decided to totally change Rodeo drastically from 10.4.1 to 10.4.2.
As a reminder, we went from this... ...
... ...to this.
And this is the view from the Titan's perspective.
So to give some context as to why we changed Ruri
the way we did, we first need to get some history
in an experiment we did to Titan health.
In an effort to have a better sense of pacing
during Titan fights, we tried a system where,
instead of having shields, Titans had a series
of health chiclets.
These health chiclets would regenerate over time,
much like shields did in Titanfall 1,
but once a chiclet was gone, that portion of health
was lost permanently.
The idea was that it would give players a sense
of when they could play aggressively,
when a chiclet was full, and when they should play
defensively, when the chiclet is low.
When the player lost the chicklet, the tank would get a short period of invincibility, similar to getting knocked down in fighting games like in Street Fighter.
It would allow the victim some time to breathe, recover, and plan what to do next.
If you look at the top of the screen, you'll notice that the blue health bar is divided into three sections, or the chicklets as we call them.
You can also see that the enemy health bar in yellow is similarly divided into three.
So notice that as we fire on an enemy Titan,
as long as we don't do enough damage
to cross the Chiclet threshold,
you will be able to regen all the health you lost.
But once you cross the Chiclet threshold,
the enemy becomes temporarily invulnerable
and he has a shield to protect him.
Once the invulnerability fades,
that first health Chiclet,
you can damage the Titan again,
but that first Chiclet of health is now permanently lost.
And he only regens up to the second Chiclet.
So, unfortunately, the health chiclet system did not play very well with Rodeo at all.
Since you could regen all the damage you took until you lost a chiclet, it became a very
common occurrence that Rodeo wouldn't do enough damage to finish off a chiclet, which meant
the pilot player didn't do any lasting damage at all.
This was made worse by the fact that under the chiclet system, Titans didn't have a concept
of a normal shield anymore, which meant that the Rodeo damage, which bypassed the shield,
wasn't as advantageous anymore as compared to regular damage.
The invulnerability period also played havoc with the pacing of Rodeo.
The early iterations of the health checklist system gave the Titan a dome shield for a
few seconds, and that's the red shield that protects the Titan during Titanfall that also
does damage to enemies inside it.
It also forcibly threw the Rodeo pilot off the Titan to avoid the pilot getting killed
by the dome shield we gave the Titan.
Eventually, for other reasons, we stopped giving the Titan a dome shield, but we still
gave the Titan a period of invulnerability, which meant that rodeo shots during that time
just did no damage at all, so a pilot had to stop firing for a while.
The health checklist experiments lasted for a while, so it became pressing for us to see
if we could make rodeo work with it, instead of having rodeo be in an essentially broken
state for too long.
Once we agreed that something needed to be done for Rodeo, the design actually came together fairly quickly.
Since we wanted to keep the pacing of health chicklets, it was pretty intuitive that we made Rodeo just do a single chicklet's worth of damage.
This made it so that when the chicklet threshold would always be triggered when you Rodeoed,
and a Titan would have that moment of being able to catch their breath and reorientate themselves after getting Rodeoed.
The idea of batteries was also being floated around in design discussions when we were
talking about potential systems to limit how long Titans stayed on the battlefield.
So for example, maybe each Titan only had a minute worth of power, but players could
pick up batteries to extend this time.
This seemed like a great fit for Rodeo and health chiclets.
We could make chiclets be visually represented on the health bar as batteries, and Rodeo
be the act of removing one of these batteries.
It made the act of Rodeo doing one chiclet of damage a lot more understandable, and the
whole concept came together pretty well.
So if Rodeo was the act of removing a battery, it was a natural step for Brodeo to be the
reverse of inserting a battery and restoring a chiclet.
It's a simple idea but it actually has pretty far-reaching implications.
Nothing else in the game allows you to help your teammates in such a direct fashion.
Suddenly there's a whole new vector for players to contribute to winning the match instead
of just killing the opponent.
Titanfall had a kind of reputation as being a game that favoured a very lone wolf type
of style of playing the game, but now that your allies could heal you, there was suddenly
a lot more coordination, more communication.
We'd hear feedback from playtests that players would think they were going to lose the fight
against an enemy titan, but out of nowhere a teammate steals a battery from the attacker
and plunges it into the bag, allowing them to turn the tables on the fight.
And more than anything else, the positive vibes
that resulted from this interaction
was what convinced us that this iteration of Rodeo
was something we should commit to shipping.
In fact, we thought this version of battery-style Rodeo
was strong enough that we decided to ship it,
even though in the end, the inspiration,
the health checklists didn't ship.
So here we'll see gameplay footage
of a player in the battery medic role.
It's the last time in a standing match.
He's trying to keep the last hand on his team alive
by feeding him batteries.
As you see, he's able to turn the tide of the battle
by effectively being a healer for his teammate.
You're the last titan.
I'm getting you a battery.
I'm trying to get you a battery.
I'm getting this battery too!
You can make it!
Good job!
So another seemingly small but important change
that resulted from this was the duration of Rodeo.
Since we only wanted pilots to do a chiclet's worth
of damage when sealing a battery,
and we wanted them to take that battery
to insert into a friendly Titan,
it seemed obvious that we kicked the pilot off automatically
after the sealing battery sequence was complete.
And with this change, Rodeo shifted away
from being a long process that happened
over a period of time,
to a short event that is follow-up gameplay.
For the pilot, the gameplay is to get away
with the precious stolen battery
and deliver it to a teammate.
For the Titan, the gameplay is to now chase down the pilot
and take back the battery.
This new cat and mouse element of post-Rodeo gameplay
reinforced some of the broader gameplay themes
we had with Titanfall.
It also confirmed some of the suspicions I had previously
about Titanfall 1's Rodeo, that the actual worst part of it
is the pilot shooting the Titan's hatch panel.
From the pilot's perspective,
shooting a basically stationary target,
reloading and repeating until the Titan is dead
is not very interesting, mechanically speaking.
From the Titans perspective a general lack of tools other than electric smoke to get the pilot shooting you off your back was kind of frustrating
But now that the gameplay part of Rodeo lies
in what happens after the battery is stolen,
the weapons, the kits, the mechanics,
and the rest of the game all play a part
in whether or not the pilot can get away,
which makes for a richer gameplay experience.
For example, the pilots can use the grappling hook
to speed away quickly.
They can use cloak or phase shift
to disorientate the Titans to where they actually are.
They can use wall running to quickly scamper up buildings
and onto rooftops.
Titans can use their dash to quickly catch up
with the escaping pilot,
and use their assorted weapons to kill the pilot
and retrieve the battery.
And with that, the base design for Rodeo in Titanfall 2 was complete.
The first major iteration of this battery-style Rodeo was complete in early July 2015, and
even though we added more features to support it, the overall design didn't change very
much since then.
Some examples of things that we added to help the experience are the ability to use the
battery on the player's own Titan by embarking into the Titan with it.
So this weakens the incentive to help a teammate with the battery somewhat, but it does reduce
the frustration when you manage to steal a battery, but you have no teammates to give
the battery to.
overhead indicator for the battery for the Titan.
So with the speed at which pilots can move in our game,
it's very easy to visually lose track of the pilot,
which hurt the cat and mouse gameplay
we were trying to support.
The indicator, as of release,
lasts for about 10 seconds before fading out,
which we thought was a good balance.
It's long enough for the Titan
to not have to drop everything immediately
and chase after the pilot,
but short enough that the pilot
doesn't feel punished forever
for not being able to quickly get rid of the battery.
an ability for the pilot to call out to friendly Titans
that they have a battery.
In an ideal world, this would already be handled
through verbal communications over a microphone,
but this allows even pickup groups to communicate
and coordinate to some extent.
This was in response to feedback that was very frustrating
to chase after a friendly Titan
when you were trying to give them a battery,
but the Titan would be oblivious of you trying to help.
And since we were committing to the battery being a physical object that the pilot would carry around,
it made sense to limit pilots to only be able to carry around a single battery.
Initially, we tried to just flat out disallow players from rotating if they already carried a battery,
but this fought too much against feedback that players wanted to keep rotating the enemy Titan.
So to satisfy this repeated request for pilots to keep rotating,
we made a different version of Rodeo for players who were already carrying a battery.
Instead of stealing more batteries, the pilot would chuck a grenade down the port of the Titan.
Since we wanted to encourage this hide-and-seek gameplay of stealing a battery and running
away with it, we tried to discourage grenade rodeo by making it do half as much damage
as the regular rodeo.
So for completeness sake, we'll run through the list of issues again and see how it stacks
up to the previous attempts.
Communication, same as before, we rely mainly on HUD elements and sound to sell the experience
to the player.
Admittedly, this aspect is probably a bit weaker than Titanfall 1's version of Rodeo
since the concept of a battery and having to steal it and insert it into friendlies
is much more abstract than just shooting into the weak point of an enemy titan.
On the plus side, however, since Sandfall 2 has a full single-player campaign, we were able to rely on the campaign to teach some of the mechanics for batteries.
Indeed, the first thing that BT, the single-player campaign's titan, asks you to do is to bring him some batteries so he can recover from a depowered state.
Choice. As mentioned before, much of the choice for Rodeo is now shifted to the part after the pilot steals the battery.
From there, pilots have access to their full suite of mobility options, scrappling hooks, dim, etc.
Similarly, Titans have access to all their loadout
to be able to kill the escaping pilot.
We did bring back electric smoke from Titanfall 1
as a universal tool that all Titans have access to
once they hit a 20% charge in their Titan core meter.
Length, so it takes about five seconds or so
to steal the battery and from there,
it's variable as to whether or not
the battery is recovered.
Similarly, although for Titanfall 2
we didn't initially set out to solve explicit design goals
when iterating on Rodeo,
it's useful to re-examine the goals we had before
to see if they're still met.
So the first goal is still intact. Arguably, the aspect of doing heavy damage is weakened since each rodeo does at most one chunk of damage,
as opposed to the unlimited amount of potential damage that Titanfall 1 rodeo had.
However, the ability to give batteries to friendlies as well as the cat-and-mouse aspect of Titanfall 2's rodeo makes this goal overwhelmingly accomplished in Titanfall 2's favour.
The second goal is intact as well.
Pilots need to leverage their skills at traversal to get away from the Titan, and Titans need
to use their skill in hunting pilots to get the most out of the rodeo experience.
We think the third goal is also accomplished, although one could probably argue the visual
presentation for Titanfall 1's rodeo is stronger and more compelling.
Shooting at the brains of a Titan feels more compelling in a more abstract, stealing a
battery sequence.
The grenade version of the rodeo does help with this, however.
And the last goal is arguably where we gave up the most compared to the previous version of Rodeo.
A battery is an abstract concept, despite the lengths we go to make it more grounded.
It does help that we have a single-player campaign to slowly teach the player the concepts,
so we'll call this a mixed success.
Lastly, it's also instructive for us to re-examine what went well for Rodeo in Titanfall 1,
and see if those are still applicable to Titanfall 2,
and to see if anything new was added to the list.
At this point in time, it's maybe a bit too premature to comment about whether it's popular or well-balanced.
There is some feedback, even internally as well, about people who missed the feel of 10-4-1 style rodeo,
and that's certainly to be expected when you make a big change to a prominent mechanic.
But my hope is that over time, people will prefer this new style of rodeo.
Fantasy Fulfillment.
Admittedly, the concept of you pulling out a battery is weaker from a fantasy fulfillment aspect
compared to shooting the brains of a titan, so it's kind of unfortunate we took a step back in that regard.
The organic interactions of the Titan eject system
were preserved from Titanfall 1, so that's a win for us.
In fact, more parts of the game started
to have richer interactions with Rodeo's chase component.
So we think this was a big improvement overall.
Rodeo also felt much more improved and richer
since the pilot now has a strong supporting role.
Previously, it was mainly the Titan supporting the pilot
by ferrying the pilot to a hard point, et cetera.
Going down the list, let's see if we improved
what went poorly last time around.
The back and forth between the Titan and the pilot feels better this time around.
For the most part, we got rid of the Titan player feeling like they had to disembark
to shoot the pilot off. I think that's an improvement, especially from the fantasy
fulfillment aspect of David vs Goliath. The chase component of Rodeo is mechanically richer and
offers more room for counterplay than the old version of Rodeo. Since the amount of time the
pilot is on the back of the Titan is minimized, there's less pressure for us to create tools
for the Titan to get the pilot off their back.
Aiming during Brodeo. This is generally improved because the position in which the pilot climbs on for Brodeo is
higher than Titanfall 1, which makes it slightly easier to aim.
It's still not easy and there'll probably always be limits as to how good we can make it, but overall
I think there's a noticeable improvement.
So these two pictures just show the improvement we're talking about. The picture on the left is Titanfall 1 and the picture on the right
is Titanfall 2. Notice how much more of the screen's real estate is taken up by the Titan's body in the left screenshot.
Lastly, the problem of being able to tell at a glance whether you can rodeo a titan is still there,
but the situation is less of a problem than before since rodeo normally only has the enemy pilot on the back of the titan for about 5 seconds or so.
Admittedly, a titan with a buddy on him can still be hard to tell at a glance, but other changes that we made,
for example the enemy highlighting system, should hopefully help with this as well.
So one interesting development about Rodeo that we had for Titanfall 2
was the need to have different behaviors for the single-player campaign versus the multiplayer.
This was somewhat regrettable, but ultimately necessary to best serve the needs of the game type.
In multiplayer, only pilots can pick up a battery.
To apply a battery to the Titan, it either has to be done via Rodeo,
or by a pilot climbing to his own Titan.
In SP, though, we allow you to pick up one as a Titan by simply walking over it.
There are 3 main reasons for adding this extra limitation in multiplayer.
First, it doesn't encourage teamwork a bit more between pilots and Titans on the same team.
If the Titan could just walk over a battery,
there's less reason for you to need to depend on your teammates.
The second reason is to give an element of counterplay and risk-win reward.
If there are no friendly pilots around, the Titan player has to disembark to pick up a battery,
and then re-embark to apply that battery. This is a process that takes time and makes
the disembarking pilot more vulnerable. It also makes mid-combat pickups of batteries less likely,
which helps make the fights between Titans be a bit more controlled.
Lastly, there was a general desire on the MP team to make Titans last
just a bit shorter on the battlefield compared to Titanfall 1.
and making it a bit less convenient to pick up the batteries a step in that direction.
These reasons though aren't really applicable in SP, so we just made Tens able to pick up
batteries by walking over them.
There are some other subtle differences, like the amount of health and shield that the battery
application gives you, but those are relatively minor.
So we've gone on a journey of how Rodeo was conceived,
its various implementations through to Titanfall 1,
and why we made the changes we did for Titanfall 2.
Before we end the talk, however,
there's a few other bits and pieces
I'd like to talk about for the design of Rodeo
that didn't quite fit the mainly chronological nature
for the rest of the talk.
The first of these things I'd like to talk about is the trigger condition for Rodeo,
and by that I mean how does the player initiate Rodeo.
The very first iteration of Rodeo had pilots automatically magnetized onto Titans when
jumping near them. There's no extra button input needed. In part, this was done out of simplicity
to get the simplest thing possible to playtest the idea of Rodeo. This automatic activation
had a divided response. Some players enjoyed the ease of which it happened, but others hated how
sometimes it happened even though they wanted to jump away from the Titan instead.
I was very resistant, maybe unreasonably so, to the idea of having rodeo trigger only when
the use button was held down since I thought it was an unnecessary barrier of execution.
This is especially so for consoles where you'd be asking the players who had their thumbs on
the lookstick to move it to the jump button and then to use the hold button. This just feels clunky.
We did eventually try out a jetpack assist ability
for pilots which involved them using the use button
and being propelled towards the Titan they were looking at.
At this stage of development,
Titans were a little too fast at getting around the map
and this was done in part to help make rodeo
a little easier and to respond to suggestions
that having rodeo be triggered by a button press
would make it more interactive and more immersive.
In the final shipping game for Titanfall 1, however, the trigger conditions for Rodeo
remained very similar to how it was initially implemented, with it happening automatically
when you're jumping near a Titan.
I feel like this is one of the reasons why Rodeo is so successful, because it's easily
done and even naturally discoverable and learnable.
You could conceivably stumble upon it without anybody telling you what Rodeo was, and it
would, hopefully, make immediate sense to you.
In Titanfall 2, this is largely unchanged,
although we did adjust the angles and the height
required to get frontal Rodeo to start.
The idea behind this is that it's often frustrating
from the Titan's perspective that you see a pilot
in front of you, they jump, you try to punch them,
et cetera, instead of the pilot exploding
in a glorious pile of jibs,
they disappear and start Rodeo instead.
And some of this is caused by latency
and it's kind of hard to solve,
so we just made Rodeo not trigger for the pilot
when he's jumping straight on towards the Titan.
Personally, I kind of dislike this since Titans can actually turn very quickly, especially on PC.
So what started out as a pilot trying to jump onto a Titan's back,
can quickly turn into a Titan facing the pilot directly,
and the pilot getting stomped at a Titan's feet.
That said though, we're going to be monitoring players' feedback on that
to see if they prefer that frontal rodeo is harder.
Another thing I wanted to talk about was some of the counterplay options we tried in the development of Rodeo,
i.e. what options did the Titan have to get the pilot off their back?
As I went through the various iterations of Rodeo in Titanfall 1,
you may have noticed there didn't really seem to be any new ways we added for the Titan to remove the pilots off their back.
It was always just disembark or electric smoke.
And to be honest, this isn't because we didn't try, it's just that all the things we did try left something to be desired.
Here I'll talk about some of the few interesting things in this category that we tried that didn't ship.
So wall smashing. The inspiration for this came from this fight scene in the Princess Bride.
I'll be wearing them in the future.
I just feared what you'd give me so much trouble.
Why is that?
So, we had an idea that the Titan player could use their dash ability to ram themselves into a wall,
doing damage to the pilot and shaking him off.
So, it took multiple dashes to shake off a full health pilot,
which meant that the ogre with the smallest amount of dashes
had the hardest time getting rid of a roadie player.
We tried versions where the pilot player just got shook off
and took damage without dying,
but that meant that he could just jump back on again.
But then when we made it fatal,
it became frustrating for the pilot player
because it was hard for him to tell
that the Titan player was going to be running into a wall
at a high enough speed to throw him off.
All in all, it was just kind of clumsy as a mechanic.
Here, we'll see what it looks like
from the pilot's perspective
as the Titan tries to shake him off.
So you can see it's not very easy to follow along with what's happening.
Wired Hood.
This was a kit that could be equipped.
The idea was that the panel of the Titan was booby trapped, so opening it would cause the
pilot to be shocked and thrown away.
So the problem with this was that Rodeo pilots had no way of knowing beforehand that the Titan had equipped the wired hood,
so it led to players just assuming that every Titan had the wired hood on,
and Rodeo just happening a lot less as a result.
Astute observers among you would probably notice that the electric smoke that we shipped in the final game has
a lot of the same problems that you can't tell the Titan has it before it's used, but
since electric smoke had other uses and wasn't specifically designed only for Rodeo, we kept electric smoke in.
So before we brought back Electric Smoke for Titanfall 2, we tried implementing an Active
Reload style minigame for Rodeo.
The idea was that if the Titan managed to get the timing down perfectly, it'd be able
to push the pilot off without having its battery stolen.
So in here you see the bars coming up, the Titan hits it correctly at the green part,
and then the pilot is successfully thrown off without stealing a battery.
We also tried a version where the pilot had to do the minigame correctly to be able to
steal the battery.
Titan players definitely liked the idea of being able to push off the pilot without them
stealing the battery, but it proved really hard to communicate to the pilot what was
going on.
The pilot didn't know they were getting pushed off because the Titan succeeded in the minigame.
And even if we displayed the bars for both Titan and Pilot to both players, it proved
really confusing.
There's latency and there's prediction issues, which made it hard for us to show accurately
if the other player managed to do the minigame correctly.
And on the higher level, it kind of felt like a bit of a step back in that it literally was a minigame
that temporarily changed part of the controls for Titan and Pilot.
The response to this was not positive enough to outweigh the negatives, and so we eventually cut it.
One last thing I wanted to show was the idea of having multiple spots for Rodeo.
We actually tried this idea multiple times at different points in the project, but I'll
just show you footage of the latest prototype of it.
So remember that one of the largest persistent frustrations of Rodeo is that there's only
one spot available on the back of a Titan, and sometimes you can't tell there's already
another pilot on it when you're trying to do your own Rodeo.
An obvious thing to try to fix this is to allow multiple players to be able to jump
onto a Titan.
So we tried making Titans have multiple climbing spots.
Instead of pilots always climbing automatically to Titan's back, we let them climb to the
spot nearest to where they jumped on.
So here's a video of how a multiple spot rodeo worked.
So note that the player can climb around freely
on different parts of the Titan.
And that he can insert the battery
once he gets the correct spot in the bag.
So the ability to climb to different spots was important because we only allowed the battery to be stolen on the back of the titan
and there's a few reasons why we did this.
It let us give a subtle reward to players who were doing rodeo correctly by jumping from the back
since they wouldn't have to spend time to do the climbing animations to get to the back.
It also let us prevent rodeo from being instant death to a titan when there's four enemies jumping on at the same time.
And lastly, it really wasn't practical for us to design the titans with multiple battery ports all over the titan either.
One awesome moment that this gave us was for
rodeo pilots to shoot off enemy rodeo pilots.
So, unfortunately, although there were definitely cool moments, the complexity cost for having
multiple spots for rodeo was just too high to justify keeping it.
The extra cool moments you get by shooting off an enemy rodeo attempt, or multiple people
being ferried by a single titan, they just happen too infrequently for us to justify
having to make the players learn the extra complexity of having to understand which rodeo
spot you're on, to have to remember to look for other people rodeoing the same titan,
etc.
In Titanfall 1, when we were just introducing the idea of Rodeo,
which is a mechanic most games don't really have an equivalent for,
you can't afford for the mechanic to be too complicated.
For Titanfall 2, if we didn't make the changes to the battery system,
it might have been okay to add the multiple-spot Rodeo,
since we could depend on people having played Titanfall 1,
and we could leverage the single-player campaign to introduce extra complexity,
but you can't really do both the battery system
and the multiple-spot system together,
as it would confuse even players in the first game.
So we're nearly at the end of the talk now,
but before I leave, here's some lessons we learned
from working on Rodeo.
Some of this is pretty common sense,
but I think there's still worth explicitly stating,
especially for any budding designers out there
that are just starting out.
First, start fast and start simple.
The very first prototype of Rodeo I showed you
was really simple about its baseline implementation
you can get for the purposes of testing out a new idea.
But from that simple idea, you can already identify
the central issues of Rodeo that would plague the mechanic
all the way up to launch and beyond.
Also note that we didn't over-plan the idea before starting to implement it.
Don't write a 10-page document detailing every single sub-case and problem you can think
of before trying to implement it.
Instead, just try out the simplest version you can that contains the essential components
of the idea.
You find out so much so quickly from actual playtesting.
You'll be able to identify the things you actually need to fix and improve on, as opposed
to just potential problems.
Also note that when you're trying to sell a new mechanic or concept to others,
it's much easier if they can see a rough version of the concept in-game,
as opposed to a multi-page document that nobody really wants to read.
Second point, add as little as you can to make the idea work.
So there's a favorite quote of mine from Antoine de Saint-Exupry,
the author of The Little Prince, that goes like this,
perfection is achieved not when there's nothing more to add,
but when there's nothing left to take away.
As you can see from the talk, we tried a lot of things with Rodeo that eventually didn't
end up shipping.
Rodeo wouldn't actually have been better if we ended up shipping all those failed ideas.
It would have been too confusing, too weird, and too unfocused.
When you're working on a new mechanic, making sure that players understand what's going
on and that they have fun doing it is probably a higher priority than making it a mechanic
that is super deep and balanced.
Ideally, of course, it's going to be both, but don't hesitate to make sure it's fun and
understandable first before you're trying to make it deep and balanced.
Third point, advocate for both sides.
This is kind of only really applicable for multiplayer games,
but when you're designing mechanics,
it's important to make sure you're advocating
for both the player using the mechanic
and the player it's being used upon.
It would have been very easy for us to fall into the trap of making
rodeo mechanic focused only on the pilot,
one where the pilot could just straight up destroy the Titan.
But instead, by making sure that both the Titan and the pilot
have their own defined role in the mechanic,
that both have choices and counter-choices,
we made rodeo mechanic that is deeper and more fun for both.
And this isn't to say that you can't have mechanics
that are easier for one side or another,
but in theory, rodeo should probably be at least a bit in favor of the pilot
since they have to get up close to the Titan to do it.
It just means that you want to give the Titan at least some feeling of hope that they can
influence the outcome if they play well, instead of just being handed a death sentence.
Last point, don't be afraid to make big changes.
As I mentioned, Rodeo was pretty popular in 10.4.1,
and when we first started making changes to 10.4.2,
the battery-style Rodeo, there was definitely some feedback
that they preferred the old-style Rodeo from 10.4.1.
It's important to not flat-out ignore the feedback,
of course, but it's just as important
to not let all your decision-making
be ruled only by reactions to feedback.
Take a step back, calmly analyze what it is you're trying to do, and see if it's actually
achieving it.
In Rodeo's case, it was initially driven by a need to make Rodeo work within the confines
of the health checklist system, but once we started playing with it, we realized just
how huge an impact being able to give batteries to your allies was.
Having a chase component to Rodeo also made so many more abilities and weapons play into
Rodeo in a much more interesting fashion.
So although I was responsible for a lot of the design
and implementation of Rodeo across both Titanfall
and Titanfall 2, it would be remiss for me to not point out
that Rodeo was clearly not the work of just one person.
It takes an entire team of dedicated professionals
to bring game mechanics to life,
so let me just take some time out now
to thank all the folks back at Respawn
for their help on Rodeo and for this talk.
Special thanks in particular go to designers,
Mackie McAnlish, Brent McLeod, Carlos Pineda.
Programmers, Stephen Wong, Joel Gompert.
and animators, Paul Nesely, Mark Grigsby, Bruce Ferriz,
and Laura Tiff.
A special thanks also go out to our awesome community,
in particular the YouTube channels
from whom I lifted videos for this talk from.
Volin, Cog Incorporated, Average Willis,
Joseph Hanready, 11 Bravo Gaming,
Colin Vesper, and OX SoulFireXO.
Last but definitely not least,
all the fans and players out there,
all of us at Respawn are incredibly lucky
to have so many people care about our games,
and I hope our games bring you some joy and happiness.
And with that we'll come to end of the talk.
Thank you all for listening, my name is Chin-Hsiang Chong
and you can reach me at chin at respond.com.
I have some time for questions now,
if anybody's interested.
Thank you.
Thank you, thank you.
Hello, great game and great speech.
Thank you.
So first question was about how long
would your iterations take for the major iterations?
And secondly, how would you collect feedback?
Did you do surveys or just around as a group and so on?
iteration state and feedback.
So our company tends to do weekly playtests,
like a, sorry, let me rephrase that.
Design department internally playtests all the time,
like basically every day we play the game.
And then every Friday we have what we call
Friday night fights, which is design,
like basically bringing a more polished,
stable version of the game onto the entire company.
And we tell people, hey, these are the new things
that we added, and these are,
we would like feedback on these systems,
tell us what you like, or didn't like about them.
We get emails, we talk in person about them,
and you generally get a sense of that, yeah.
Cool.
Alright, since you guys said that the Ogre in the initial game had maybe a weakness to Rodeo since they had less dashes,
were there any considerations in this Titanfall 2 that Rodeo was going to affect each type of Titan differently?
So it does actually affect each, sorry the question is does Rodeo in Titanfall 2 affect each Titan differently,
and it actually does because in Titanfall 2, even though we got rid of the health checklist specifically,
like each person, each Titan still has like a...
chunk, like they divide the bars into like five sections.
For example, for the, yeah, the ogre has five sections
and rodeo only does one section of damage.
So the ogre is more resilient to rodeo in that fashion.
It takes more rodeos to actually bring him down
to like, zero health.
All right, thanks.
Is there anything that you can share
about your dev process on iterations
that helped increase the speed
at which you could go through those iterations?
I'm sorry, the question is about the iterations?
Yeah, so was there anything that you
could share about your dev process that
helped you get through those iterations faster
and understand quickly whether this idea was going to work
or not?
Tips for generally increasing iteration speed.
I guess making sure you know exactly what you're testing for.
And it's very common to just be like,
hey, I put this new thing in,
tell me what you guys think, guys.
But it's better to have more targeted feedback,
especially from players you trust.
Like for designers in particular, we ask,
so what do you think about this mechanic?
Does it increase the teamwork element of this?
What do you think it has on this other mechanic that we have in the game?
Like what do you think of the spillover effects?
And you ask people, people that you trust, that aren't just, you know,
like randomly going to say what they feel without really thinking about it.
But also people, you know, who aren't going to be
afraid to tell you things you don't want to hear.
If they tell you it sucks, you should listen to them and try to fix that.
Yeah. Cool. Thanks.
Hi.
I was just wondering, looking at all those different iterations of Rodeo,
I was just wondering, is there a favorite version that you had to cut that you have?
A favorite version of Rodeo I had to cut?
At the end of Titanfall 1, I was actually pretty happy
with what we shipped for Rodeo in Titanfall 1.
Like I said, I think it was a nice balance
between being cinematic, easy, fun, and accessible.
I am kind of sad we didn't keep the wall smashing thing,
but it was kind of clumsy.
Like, if you saw the video,
it's hard to tell what's going on
when you're being shook around.
So maybe if we had somehow managed
to find a more graceful solution to that,
that would have been good, but yeah.
Thank you.
And I guess that's it.
So two things.
Please remember to fill out your feedback forms, one.
And second, my very talented coworker, Carlos,
who's in the audience, he's gonna be giving a follow-up
talk about tank combat in this room right next.
So stick around for that if you're interested.
Thank you.