Hi everyone. Today I'll be talking to you about cuteness and why it's important.
So let's start off with myself. My name is Jenny and I also go by Qdork on Twitter.
I recently graduated from the NYU Game Center with a BFA in game design
and I've been making games for around three years at this point.
So here are some of the cute games I've made.
Slam City Oracles is a commissioned game
that I worked on with Jane Friedhoff
for No Quarter in 2014.
It's a game where you and a friend
slam around and tear down this colorful world
filled with all these weird and silly objects.
It's inspired by a mix of punk rock,
Riot Grrl, and bouncy physics.
So try to create as much chaos as possible
and have fun with that.
I also helped make this game called Stellar Smooch with AP Thompson who also helped me
a lot with this talk so make sure to go follow them on Twitter at Bad Tenders.
Stellar Smooch is a game about kissing and loneliness and it got into the IGF in 2014.
We also made a cool alt control version which we showed at the Wild Rumpus that year as
well.
You and a friend have to simultaneously squeeze this big red yoga ball at the correct time
to get the space probes to collide with each other.
The year after, AP and I teamed up again,
and we went on to create BeGlitched.
BeGlitched is a game about insecurity
in our computers and ourselves.
And though it may look cute and silly,
it's actually much more difficult than it seems.
It's currently out on Steam
and about to get an iOS release.
So if you're interested in checking it out,
definitely go buy it and give us our money.
So while I was working on BeGlitched,
I also took this prototyping class taught by Bennett Foddy
where I made a game a week based on a specific prompt.
So here are some of the prototypes
that came out of that class.
The theme for this one was 10 seconds.
So Morning Makeup Madness is a game
where you have 10 seconds to do your makeup.
It's a personal game and it's drawn from my own experience
of waking up super late
and not having enough time to get ready.
Wobble Yoga is another prototype I made in that class.
The theme for this one was shape shift.
It was actually a Ludum Dare theme.
And I decided to make this QWOP-like game
where you have to contort this noodly-limbed avatar
through this series of really challenging yoga poses.
And this game is also based
off of my own personal experience.
So anyway, I'm currently working on a personal game
about dieting called Consume Me,
and it's focused on this specific time period in my life
where I just wasn't super happy
with the way I looked and with my body.
Even though the subject matter is quite dark,
I intentionally decided to use this cute
and silly aesthetic for the game,
which I'll go into more detail later.
So I just told you about the games I worked on.
Here are some cute games that I like to play.
So Animal Crossing is a game where you go fishing,
catch bugs, and pay off your loans
in order to acquire more debt from Tom Nook,
the cute and adorable raccoon in the game.
Neko Atsume is another cute game on my list.
Leave out food for these cats and they'll give you sardines
which you can use to buy additional food
and toys for them later on.
It's a game with pretty limited interaction,
but I kept playing this one
because I just wanted to collect all the cute cats.
Threes is another one that I really like.
It's this tiny puzzle game about matching numbers.
And the design is really minimal but brilliant.
And I think the cute faces on the tiles
are just really charming and kind of add a lot
to the look and feel of the entire game.
P.O.Mori is a game where you want to stack as many baby chicks onto this plate of food
and make sure they don't topple over.
You just want to try to make the biggest structure possible.
And finally, Survive Mola Mola is this game that you can get on your phone.
You're raising this sunfish and it's your job to make this Mola Mola grow as big as
possible.
But it's actually a game that's kind of dark because you have to kill your Mola Mola in
order to make progress in the game.
So you have to unlock every single death method,
ranging from choking on every single type of food
to dying on every adventure that your mola mola goes on.
Anyway, so those are just some of the cute games I love to play, but the thing is, in
general, we have a tendency to dismiss cuteness.
We associate cuteness with being childish and immature.
But today, I want to present a case for cuteness.
So using my work as primary examples, I will show you how cuteness can attract, disarm,
and engage.
And you're basically making a mistake when you underestimate it.
So my first point is cuteness grabs our attention.
Many of the cute games I showed to you earlier are all
really quite charming.
And there's something about them that makes them feel
really friendly and approachable.
So I want to use Stellar Smooch as my main example to
show you how cuteness is attention grabbing.
So the way you play this game is.
So you tap the screen to release and make the space probes smooch each other.
And the game is short, it's roughly 24 levels, and there's this lovely poem which AP wrote
that acts as part of the level select.
So before the game looked like this, it looked like this.
Actually it really looked like this.
This is the prototype that AP made in a week with their Pixar art.
But, so anyway, this is the version,
the first iteration of art after I joined the project,
and we kept this visual style in for a really long time.
And even though there was nothing inherently wrong
with the art, I felt like there was something missing
about it.
You know, the art didn't look terrible,
but it also didn't feel really special.
Maybe boring is the right word to describe it.
And even though I swapped out the pixel art with this new visual style,
it fundamentally didn't change the tone of the game.
So the game still retained this very serious tone.
And I mean, just look at the title.
This is the original title of Stealth or Smooch.
Dents in metal are just memories of an embrace,
which is like a line from the poem.
And the game just lacked any sort of humor.
So when I was staring, so like I was staring at this particular screen for a really long time
and just trying to figure out how to make the art better than it currently was, which is challenging
because you know how do you take something that isn't really all that bad in the first place
and make it better?
And so I just drew faces over the planets.
And I know that sounds kind of like a silly answer,
but once I added faces to them,
there is something that felt right about the decision.
By the way, I think it kind of relates
to these images on the screen.
So I don't know if anyone has heard of the term pareidolia,
but examples of this phenomenon
include perceiving a face within an,
inanimate objects.
So we see ourselves in everything,
and this is just one of the ways
that cuteness can grab our attention.
So with that in mind,
I basically started from scratch all over again.
I began developing a new color palette for the game,
and then I went on to add these little faces
to the blobs of color,
which would later become the faces of the planets.
And I just kept iterating on it
and trying out different expressions.
I wanted to give the planets their own personalities.
And finally, I ended up with these five planets.
I experimented with adding detail to them,
but decided against that decision in the end
because I felt like embracing a more minimal look
made the game more elegant.
So I took away the excess detail,
limited the color palette to only six colors,
and ended up with these five planets
that are the current ones in the game.
And something I realized in hindsight
is that by adding faces to the planets,
I took these elements that were originally
part of the environment of the game
and made them into characters.
By incorporating emotional states to the planets,
the impact of winning or losing a level
felt much more significant.
And the game actually responded to your actions.
It allowed for more expressive and interesting solutions
to other design problems we had.
For example, this is just one of the problems
that we were challenged with.
Adding faces to the planets helped resolve this one issue
where basically in the old version,
this piece of ugly UI text would drop down
from the top of the screen whenever you lost.
and it would give you the option of trying the level again
or going back to the main menu.
And I really disliked this because I felt like
it looked incredibly jarring and was like very clunky
as a solution to this problem.
So now when you lose, the planets will start crying
and then like a restart button will fade
into the corner of the screen.
Oops.
However, when you win, the planets, whoops, okay.
Yeah, so when you win, the planets will smooch along
and it's just like very clear to indicate
whether or not you won or lost.
And I just felt like this ultimately
was just like a much more intuitive and elegant solution
because it just reduced all these elements
that previously had been on the screen
and really focused on the parts of the game that mattered.
Yeah, so, you know, the game shifted from being something
completely serious and kind of boring and lacking any sort
of humor to something cuter and more simple
and with like a lot more character.
And I just want to quickly talk about this process
from Understanding Comics, which is this book
by Scott McCloud.
It's...
Basically, I'd like to say the process that took place here
is a form of amplification through simplification.
And basically what it is, is like here's an illustration.
So, you know, to your left,
you see like a very realistic photograph of a man,
but then like with each depiction,
as you're moving towards the right,
it gets more simple and the image becomes more abstract.
And it's like, interesting to question,
you know, this image of like two dots, a line and a circle,
still resembles a face.
And it's just like, as acceptable to us
as the image of like the very realistically drawn man.
So, when we abstract an image through this process of cartooning, you know, we're illuminating
a lot of details and we're just focusing on the ones that really do matter.
It's like basically taking the meaning that we want to get across and amplifying it.
So in Cellar Smooch, by adding these faces to the planets
and making them cuter, it just allowed me to focus
my attention to the most important parts of the game.
And as a result, it gave me the opportunity
to just remove a lot of this unnecessary detail
left over from the previous art style.
So don't underestimate the importance
of adding a face to something and making it cuter.
So, however, the thing is, cuteness isn't always about
being friendly and approachable.
It can also act as a mask to hide darker motives.
So in Animal Crossing, one of the first things you do
is take a loan out from Tom Nook
because you need to have a house in the game.
And you need the loan to pay for it.
So the game starts off by putting you into debt
to this cute little guy.
But the thing is, even after you pay off this loan,
Tom Nook will always continue
to take your money away from you,
and he will always continue to put you into debt
and acquire more and more property.
He's kind of a little sinister in that sort of way,
like underneath this cute, cuddly face lurks
this more darker intent.
And another example, maybe like a more clear example,
is of cuteness acting as a mask for something
far more sinister is Flowey from Undertale.
You know, he's one of the first major characters
that you meet in the game,
and he appears to be super friendly and cute and charming.
However, it's quickly revealed
that Flowey is actually incredibly evil.
He provides an introduction to the mechanics of encounters
by sharing these friendliness pellets,
which are actually harmful bullets.
So, you know, Flowey's just another character that operates under this facade of friendliness.
Whenever he drops the skies of cuteness, he often calls the protagonist an idiot.
Which brings me to the main example at this point.
In BeGlitched, cuteness acts as a mask
and disarms people's initial expectations of the game,
specifically in terms of the game's mechanics.
Many people take one look at the game
and underestimate the difficulty of it.
They think it might be easy PC to play it.
Little do they know, it's actually a lot more harder
than its pastel exterior might suggest.
The cute aesthetic also masks the insecurity that the enemy hackers each possess.
So each of these enemies have their own insecurities
which cause them to lash out at the glitch witch.
So examples of this include the squid being worried
about his skills becoming irrelevant and becoming washed up.
The ape feeling frustrated at his inability to copy
or ape the techniques of the glitch witch.
And the bear trying to compensate for his lack
of hacking skills by purchasing
the most powerful technology.
However, cuteness does not necessarily have to hide dark and evil motives.
It isn't always just about masking insecurity.
Cuteness can be a form of rise
and rebellion by subverting people's expectations.
So the rise of cuteness in Japan emerged
in the 1970s as part of this new writing style.
Many teenage girls began to write laterally with mechanical pencils.
And these girls would write in big,
rounded characters and add these little pictures to their writings,
such as hearts, stars, emoticon faces.
These pictures would be randomly inserted and make it really difficult to read. So in many of
these cases, their teachers could no longer read their students' handwriting and the handwriting
style was banned in many schools. However, during the 1980s, this new cute writing style was adopted
by magazines and comics and even put onto packaging and advertising. This form of cute
handwriting, which once was banned in schools, has kind of led to this rise of cuteness in Japanese
culture.
And speaking of cuteness in Japanese culture,
is anyone familiar with the latest Sanrio character?
So her name is Aggretsuko,
and she's a 25 year old red panda
working as an office associate in the accounting department
of a highly respected trading company.
However, she's constantly taken advantage of
and bothered by her boss and coworkers.
She has to deal with getting much of the grunt work
shoveled onto her.
And there's this darker side to this seemingly cute character.
So when Aggretsuko gets fed up of everything, she goes and screams death metal karaoke after work.
So that was kind of my final example
for cuteness acting as a mask
for something much more darker and more sinister.
Aggretsuko lets us,
or has added dimension to her personality.
You know, she's not only cute, but she's also tough.
And it definitely lets us see how cuteness is flexible
because it lets us look at how we can use
this initial appearance of friendliness and charm
to take people's expectations
and subvert them in regards
to what's lying beneath the surface.
Even with BeGlitched, it's a game that's telling you not to underestimate it based off its looks, and I think that's pretty cool.
So my third point is, cuteness gives us room to experiment.
So BeGlitched didn't always look this way.
Even though it's a game about hacking,
it doesn't really share the same aesthetic
as most games that are traditionally cyberpunk.
When you think of cyberpunk,
maybe the first thing that pops into your mind
are green, dark dystopias and ultra evil villains.
which is what the original art of the game looked like.
Yeah, so here's the original prototype that AP made.
It was dark, green, and kind of serious.
And that tone also reflected in the gameplay as well.
When I joined the project, I kept this secret Tumblr,
which I would use to later help develop
my aesthetic for BeGlitched.
I'd reblog images that I found attractive and cute,
and it kind of embodied a certain sort of mood
that I was going for.
And at the same time, I was also really drawn
to these pastel color palettes and this girly pink look.
I also found these super cute versions of old computer UI.
I loved how people created these really girly and cute interfaces.
Something about the playfulness of this sort of imagery spoke to my inner 10-year-old who
loves Hello Kitty and Tamagotchi.
It wasn't just cute, it felt nostalgic in a way to me that green cyberpunk dystopias
did not.
However, this cute aesthetic doesn't really work for actual computer interfaces.
Like think about click-clippy.
It's kind of annoying and intrusive and gets in the way of what you're actually trying
to do.
So I think this cute aesthetic really only works for games because games are their own
aesthetic universes.
Having to compete in a space where everything else is at once is where you really want to
assert this actual visual difference.
So that's how I started iterating on the game.
One of the first things I did was swap out all the colors
and develop a new color palette.
By the way, I didn't really know how to do pixel art
before joining the project,
so it didn't look very good at first.
But I continued to iterate more and more,
and I just redid the thing over and over again.
And eventually the assets began to look better,
and the visual style began to be more cohesive
and clear to me.
And yeah, it just like took a lot of trial and effort.
I remember staring at the same colors
and feeling like I was going crazy looking at this.
Some days I wanted to rip my eyeballs out,
but eventually after about a million iterations,
I finally arrived with something that we both liked.
And I'm really proud of the end result.
Sure, I felt like this process took a lot of hard work
and dedication and being critical about my own art,
but being able to do something experimental
in the first place and carry it out through completion
is just like this incredibly invaluable experience to me.
And in a way, being able to experiment like this,
not being afraid to make mistakes and try out weird stuff
has bled into my other work as well.
So here are just some of the prototypes with my design
that has been really driven visually.
Morning Makeup Madness started out as something I doodled in Photoshop,
and then I found out that incorporating this drawing mechanic
that players could do creative stuff with
is a really cool way to let players be expressive with their work.
So after I made all these assets, I just brought them into Unity
and then added some constraints with code,
like a countdown and some colliders that would generate a score.
Wobble Yoga is another visually driven game.
So I wanted to learn about hinges that week,
and joints, and unity.
So I kind of made this little floppy toy,
and then I added some more constraints,
like very simple ones,
like adding a meter to the bottom of the screen,
and having poses that you needed to match.
Here's a two-player game where one player is the octopus
and the other player is the hand with the fork.
And it later evolved into this prototype,
which is a single-player game.
Basically, the player controls my hand
and depending on the food that you're holding,
my head will react differently to it.
So I'll chase unhealthy foods and avoid healthy foods.
Yeah, so I'm not really the first person to do this.
There are so many games out there that approach design
with visuals first, or at least place an equal,
if not more important, emphasis on the visual aesthetic.
So Ho Ho Gum by Ricky Haggett and Richard Hogg is one example.
Monument Valley by us too.
Wrestling with Emotions by Team Laserbeam.
Nog by Co-op Mode.
And Anything Made by Sock Pub.
So we mentioned how cuteness grabs our attention and how it can act as a mask to disarm our expectations
and how it gives us room to experiment.
Now I want to bring you to my final point.
Cuteness connects us. It's inherently relatable.
I want to quickly talk to you about Sanrio again.
So I don't know if anyone else is familiar with this character, but his name is Gudetama
and he's a lazy egg, always with this face of despair and kind of lacking in spunk.
And Gudetama is hard to motivate and has this extremely negative and defeatist attitude.
On his official Twitter account, he writes,
I don't really feel like tweeting every day.
It's such a bother.
I'll do it because the higher-ups tell me to do it,
but I know I'm gonna be eaten in the end.
But here's the thing, Gudetama is super relatable.
Everyone loves him despite his lazy demeanor
and his negative outlook on life.
I want to quickly bring your attention to a couple of games that share similarities
to Gudetama's appeal.
There are more and more creators right now creating weird and personal and really intimate
stuff, but I'm just going to mention two creators that have personally inspired my
work a lot.
So the first one is Nina Freeman,
who is a huge role model for me.
She's maybe the reason why I started making personal games
in the first place, because I saw and played her work,
and it opened my eyes to the possibility
of making really deeply personal and vulnerable stuff.
She recently released Kimmy for Humble Bundle,
and I think the Steam release is gonna come soon,
so definitely check it out when it comes out.
You may also know her other game, Sybil,
which she released like over a year ago.
And Sybil is an autobiographical game
where you play as 19 year old,
you play as a 19 year old girl
who has met this guy online
and falls in love with him basically.
And her relationship with him is revealed
through this MMO that they play together.
And I think this game does a great job of tying in this cute and relatable aesthetic
to deliver this super personal narrative and help players situate themselves in Nina's
point of view.
Another one of her games that I think really showcases this point of cute being relatable
and personable is How Do You Do It?
You're this little girl whose mom steps out of the house and you're curious about sex.
So you try to get an idea of what that's like by playing with dolls.
And I think so many of us have done that as children.
And I really like this game because I think it puts,
it celebrates teenage girls and their sexual agency.
And it's finally this game which gives women
a sense of autonomy without having to relate
their self-worth to what a man thinks of them.
I think it does a really great job
using this cute visual aesthetic
and these goofy, playful mechanics
that just help get the point across.
And this aesthetic just really resonated with me,
both as a designer and as a player.
Another developer who I really like a lot
is Lea Schoenfelder.
You might have heard this game she made with Peter Liu
for the Kinect called Perfect Woman.
And the main mechanic here is body bending.
So you start as a fetus in your mother's womb,
and you perform in front of a Kinect
to mimic various poses that appear on screen.
to act out this character.
It also uses these super goofy and bright visuals
to poke fun and lighten this more serious subject matter,
allowing us to engage and maybe think about
what it means to be a woman in this society.
Leia also made this game called Oot.
The goal is simple, you have to have sex with as many men
before you get married.
And the structure has a lot to say about
the sexual constraints that women find themselves in.
You know, it does such a great job intertwining
gay mechanics and narrative.
And the cuteness comes across here with this sense of humor,
which effectively allows us to deliver
these more serious topics.
All these games that I just mentioned are games that use this cute aesthetic to get
across these deeply personal and intimate subjects. Anyway, let's talk about Consume Me.
Like I mentioned before, it's a personal game about my experience with dieting.
It's still currently a work in progress and mostly made up of prototypes that
demonstrate the kinds of mechanics I'd like to incorporate into the game.
In some of these prototypes, the player must fit pieces of food Tetris-style on a plate
to hit a calorie target count.
Or put the avatar through strenuous workout routines.
And show the protagonist's distress as she tries on a crop top.
By making you feel obsessed with calories,
looking at food strangely and mechanically,
and fret over losing weight,
Consume Me puts the player into the mind of the dieter.
These prototypes explore a three-way dynamic
between the player, the character in the game,
and the fact that the character is based off of me,
the author.
What does it mean to push and prod the character
into certain eating behaviors
when the player doesn't get full control
of the character's thoughts and internal state?
I know the game looks really cute and silly,
especially for such a dark subject matter.
However, the game didn't always have
this goofy looking aesthetic.
It actually started out a lot more serious.
Okay, so the next couple of things I'm gonna show here
may be triggering to some people
with body image issues and eating disorders.
So I'd suggest looking away or prepare yourself.
So this is actually, I guess, like the basis for my game.
Back in high school, I was really not happy
with the way I looked.
So I decided to go on a diet.
I found myself obsessively fixating
on calorie counts and exercising.
So here are pages from my notebook
where I did these things.
Little by little, I began to see progress,
but it wasn't enough for me
because I was doing these incredibly unhealthy habits,
you know, these behaviors
that eventually slowed down my weight loss.
So I just kept on increasing my efforts
to doing something more drastic.
I started like going on these really weird
and extreme diets, like the 2, 4, 6, 8 diet,
where I would end up cycling 200, 400, 600, 800 calories.
And I definitely couldn't keep this up
because it wasn't sustainable.
So in order for me to reach my goal,
or this is how I thought I could reach my goal,
I started developing this set of rules
for myself to strictly follow.
I would make myself write everything down that I ate.
I would never allow myself to eat
more than a thousand calories a day.
Some of these rules were really kind of messed up
and ridiculous, like never eat anything
you don't know the calorie count of,
or wait at least three hours
before sleeping in your last meal.
I didn't know, but I guess I felt like I could control my destiny with these rules.
I wanted to meet my weight goals so badly that I would do anything, even create, you
know, like these ridiculous constraints up in my head, which, you know, kind of sounds
like a game.
And at my worst point, I would end up looking at these like very dark and depressing images
that I would use as motivation to help me lose weight.
And this is actually this aesthetic that I was considering about, considering using for
my game.
So here were some mock-up...
Here were some images I mocked up before I started prototyping, like as concept art.
And yeah, I was really thinking of exploring this darker tone and mood.
However...
I think what prevented me from actually choosing this visual style is that I think there's
a lot more nuance to dieting than just this depressing aspect which took place in my life.
Dieting is awkward and strange.
It's empowering sometimes, horrible sometimes, and we need a conversation with nuance and
honesty about it.
So I want to place the powerful feelings of self-consciousness and anxiety front and center
with this discomforting undercurrent of humor.
Is it okay to play or have fun with someone else's pain?
By giving you permission to poke fun at my own suffering, these mechanics attempt to
bring humor and vulnerability to this serious and uncomfortable subject matter.
So yeah, I hope I've, in these past 30 minutes, I've shown you how to make a
I've shown you that you're making a mistake when you undervalue what cuteness can do.
Which brings me to the end of my talk.
And just to quickly sum everything up, you know, cuteness can be sometimes dismissed
as childish and not really taken super seriously.
But, you know, it grabs our attention.
It can act as a mask to hide darker motives.
It gives us room to experiment and it connects us
because it's relatable and personable.
Which leads me to say that
cuteness is actually pretty valuable.
Anyway, I hope I've convinced you that cuteness is, in fact,
incredibly powerful and not something we should overlook
or undervalue.
There's a lot of potential to exploring design
which embraces cuteness, whether it be through mechanics
or through the visual style of a game.
Adopting cuteness not only allows
us to be attention-grabbing and disarming,
but also encourages us to empathize, relate, and care.
Thank you.
It's gonna be...
I don't know, should I do questions?
Does anyone have any questions?
I can't, yeah?
Hi, on your big list of your, like your teenage list,
you had one, I think like five from the top that said,
It was like, record everything you eat, stay motivated, and don't tell.
What is not telling?
Wait, sorry, could you repeat that question one more time?
Like one of the lists said, stay motivated and don't tell.
Right.
And what does that mean?
Well, because I never actually, you know, lost enough weight to be like qualified as like anorexic,
I never felt like I was qualified as being sick.
And I felt like I was just, it was like a really shameful thing to be obsessed with and care.
So that's why I was like, I don't want to tell anyone about it.
That's what my mind told me.
Do you have any examples of games that you think could have done a lot better if they
had a cute aesthetic and missed out?
Um...
Hmm.
I don't want to like say horrible things about other games like non-cute aesthetics, I guess.
I don't know.
I can't...
I don't know, I feel like I can't answer that right now.
Yeah.
You seem to be really natural
at finding and expressing cuteness.
Do you have any suggestions for those of us
who might not be so well-inclined?
I think you should definitely just consume cuteness
and look at it around you.
And I would definitely recommend having a Tumblr
and just reblogging stuff that you like
and keeping a folder on your desktop
that you just add images to.
That's what I do a lot to help develop my aesthetic.
And I think that anyone can do that.
Thanks.
Yeah.
Hi, I'm really a fan of your work.
Do you have any advice for people that
are not necessarily represented within the games industry that don't have a lot of access
to like games education for like tools that they could use to tell more about themselves
personal games, like to make personal games?
I would definitely suggest using Twine, first of all,
because I think that's a great tool,
especially if we don't have a lot of
background knowledge in programming.
I think my advice when it comes to this stuff is
go to game jams and meet people and collaborate with them,
and also be sure to finish small projects.
So don't make something that's really huge and ambitious.
Just start small and like,
finish the game and just keep doing that over and over again.
And, you know, uh, be weird about it and don't be afraid to like talk about
vulnerable stuff. Yeah.
Hi, thank you for your presentation.
I was really curious about the relationship
between visual aesthetics and mechanics.
And I wanted to ask if you thought there was such a thing
as a cute mechanic.
A what mechanic?
A cute game mechanic.
I feel like some of the games that I talked about
like Perfect Woman and How Do You Do It
have these goofy, silly mechanics,
which I personally find cute.
So I would say.
Yeah, like games that I guess emphasize like physics maybe,
like looseness, wobbliness,
I find really cute and charming
and that can be developed using visuals first.
And I think the other aspect of that
is there's a physicality about that sort of like messiness
in those game mechanics, which is interesting as well
because that seems to be common
across the games you were citing.
Great, thank you.
Hi. Thank you for your talk. It was very adorable.
Thank you.
I wanted to ask you, someone said outside that you have like
a YouTube channel? Or did I mishear that? Oh, like you do a
show? Is that true?
I really wanted to do YouTube for a long time, so there's probably a channel out there that I uploaded videos to
But I don't really have an official one right now
Yeah, it'd be possible for you to reshare your contact information if you did that did you do that?
I missed the beginning because there's yeah, I can definitely do that really
fast. Okay and then my last thing was would it be okay if I answered somebody
else's question the person who asked about how to emphasize how if they
don't feel inclined on cuteness? Sure. Okay my other suggestion for that would
be find somebody who really likes cuteness. Hi I really like cuteness.
That's a good yeah that's a good suggestion. If you really want more
cuteness in your game find somebody who emphasizes it and ask them for help. So
thank you. Yeah of course.
I really like your talk.
I mean, people keep saying that, so I have to say it now.
Wow.
It's also true.
OK.
Where do you personally, I guess,
cute and charming kind of go hand in hand?
But where do you kind of draw the line between them?
Because there are games that are charming, but aren't cute.
And there's games that are cute, but are not charming.
I think the way I'd like to, like,
I'd like to draw the line.
with like cute having this aspect of silliness
and goofiness and doing something kind of like dumb maybe
and being able to laugh at that.
So yeah.
So it's kind of like self,
like finding the humor in yourself.
Yeah, yeah, I think that definitely ties into it.
Cool, thank you.
Yeah.
I think, oh.
Hey.
So I kind of interpret what you're saying is
cuteness is something that allows us to address ourselves
without neglecting ourselves.
And I was wondering how you think that this kind of like
personal game making that you seem to be going forward
with some of your recent projects fits into the scope of
what people like in Anthropy saying about like
stepping in people's shoes and the likes of that.
Is your question like, how does my game making,
or the games that I've made fit into this like overall,
I guess like, all these games that are being made
about personal and intimate subjects like that?
Yeah, I mean, I think that like people need to create,
like keep making them, and I know it's a hard thing to do
because they're not like really,
marketable or it's like really hard for that to happen and I mean I guess like my personal feeling about that is like
like we just need to keep making more of this and not be afraid to like charge for our work and like
Asked to be paid for this hard work that we do
You know, but I think, like, at the same time, it's like, equally challenging because, like, when you, you know,
charge for a game, then, like, significantly fewer people are going to play it and buy it.
And I guess, like, the way I'm approaching this right now is, like, I...
I don't know, right now I just kind of see myself
like making these really short, cute things
that draw people's attention and can be played very quickly.
And I think that's like a good way of like
sharing your personal experience
by making it like very like visually focused.
So people like YouTubers and you know, streamers can play it.
But yeah, those are my thoughts on that.
Thanks everyone for all your questions,
but unfortunately we have to move on to the next speaker.
So thank you everyone.
Thanks Jenny.
Thank you.