All right.
My name is Itai Karen.
I made a game called Mushroom 11,
released a couple of years ago.
It's a game with very peculiar and weird mechanics,
and even weirder bosses.
I also made a research a couple of years ago on 2D cameras,
and I decided to combine my two passions
and try to create this retrospective of game bosses
and what we can learn from.
using references from older to more modern games.
So, what is a game boss?
A standard definition would look a little bit like this.
A significant computer-controlled enemy who must be defeated to achieve a goal or continue progress.
But we all know that the bosses that we remember and we like
usually have one or more of these items as an exception to this rule.
From what I noticed, it is closer to just an epic
confrontation that serves as a microcosm of your game
while temporarily breaking its rules.
So the boss battle is definitely part of your game.
It needs to feel as part of the unit, which is your game.
But it's uniquely qualified to break any and all of the rules.
Why do you need a boss?
I basically look at it as four different sections.
Reward.
Take a break from normal gameplay and reward players'
persistence with a new experience and a chance
at a major triumph.
Dazzle, surprise the player with an unexpected play experience.
Engage, use the battle to advance the story
or create an emotional attachment.
And challenge, of course, that test and acquire skill,
introduce new skills in preparation for what's next.
And we're going to talk about all these.
So shock and awe.
How we can dazzle the players with unexpected confrontation
while creating a lasting first impression.
And you're probably going to notice
that I haven't really put too much effort into the images
because that's boring.
All right, so what's the most important element,
even going back to 1975,
this is what's considered possibly the first boss battle.
It's basically just an enemy.
uh... with a unexpected strengths it is way more powerful than the player
expected
uh... it's also very unlikely for you to win against
uh... the dragon in
uh... the dungeon
uh... and it feels like a david and goliath it's uh...
kind of a
thread
that goes across pretty much all boss battles
an easy way to create
or like the standard way of creating
A boss that feels invincible is using the size.
This is Mothership from Phoenix from 1980, what I consider probably the first modern
boss.
The size is so large it also feels like it's almost impossible to defeat.
This is possibly one of the best boss battles in the whole time, I'm going to talk about
it a lot.
And this is a great example of how we can use technology in order to create the illusion of size and how tech can serve the design.
In this case, it was running on the NES.
The NES has a limitation of 64 foreground sprites.
Each one of them is 8x8 or 8x16, which means that they had to create a boss mostly on the background,
and every time a piece needed to move from one side to the next.
They moved it to the foreground, animated it, and then put it back in their background.
A few decades later, another game used incredible technology for the time.
This is Shadow of the Colossus. We're going to talk about that game a lot.
They created a physics system that's based on partially dynamic, huge objects
that influence the protagonist with its own inverse kinematics.
Moving forward through the years, God of War is a franchise that has some epic bosses,
huge bosses, and when we're trying to continuously surprise the player, they end up increasing
the size of the boss continuously.
The bosses in God of War allow you to change the rules during play.
In this case, the second phase of the boss is a level in itself, where you need to battle
the boss from the inside.
And all the way to the comically large, this is Gongan Weizen from Asura's Wrath, the last
phase of this boss is larger than the planet.
And of course, at some point it becomes, it's not the same battle obviously, so it allows
you to completely change the rules.
We're going to talk about surprising the player and that is probably one of the best examples of how you would be able to surprise the player in pretty much every aspect.
This is Sinistar from 1982 from Noah Falstein and team.
They were able to create a game, a space game, that completely was different from the space games of the time in both in terms of visuals.
The presentation, the theme, even the mechanics was much more complicated
and it's mostly known for its crazy digitized voice.
Again, to surprise the players you can use all sorts of methods.
Scare the hell out of the players, as you've seen in many of the bosses in the Silent Hill franchise.
And of course this memorable boss, the great Mighty Pooh from Conker's Bed Fur Day, using
humor and the presentation was something that I think everybody who played this game really
remembers it well.
And of course there are bosses in games that you wouldn't expect to have bosses.
This is Mario Kart DS, surprisingly has bosses as well.
We're going to talk about various different types of surprises throughout this talk.
This is just a quick presentation.
Alright, moving on.
Engage.
We can use the pause in gameplay to tell a story, build anticipation towards the battle, and revel in its outcome.
So the stories back in the early days of video games were mostly the traditional story frame.
A boy saves a girl. You probably remember that there's a thread in Miyamoto's work.
And even moving on, this is Karateka, more or less from the same time period,
used the same damsel in distress cliche, but in this case they used
A lot of cutscenes to create narrative progression and apply some foreshadowing, which in turn
create anticipation and engagement towards the final battle with Akuma.
And now the bosses are perfectly capable now to present a story in a way deeper method.
This is Joker from the Arkham Knight, and the Arkham series is one of the most amazingly
powerful.
And I'll see you next time.
Bye.
It has the most amazing bosses and great storytelling.
In this case, the Joker is already dead, but is trying to battle its own...
being forgotten.
And the first part of that battle is you playing as the Joker,
which is an amazing way of telling a story.
And creates this epic intro towards the battle.
And if we're talking about epic intros...
I still have shivers down my spine remembering this moment, the first boss in Shadow of the Colossus,
creating the silence before the storm in preparation for the first epic battle.
Another fantastic boss is Bob Barbas from DMC.
This Bill O'Reilly slash Max Headroom, just the presentation for this fight, creates this rage and again builds anticipation towards the battle.
Going back to the Arkham series, the intros for the battles in this series really allow you to throw the players off.
And in this case, this is kind of a glitch that they put into the intro to this battle.
When the player sees this thing, they are immediately kind of thrown off their element,
which makes the anticipation for the battle even heightened.
And if we're talking about breaking the fourth wall, we all remember
Psycho Mantis from Metal Gear Solid.
Um, this battle begins with...
Psycho Man is reading your save files and telling you what games you like, forcing you
to unplug your controller in order to proceed with the battle.
That really challenges the boundaries of what the game can do, and I believe that the boss
battle can really allow you, if you're uniquely qualified, to do just that.
And after the battle is complete, having some...
Some outlet and a short break allowing you to relish and gloat in the results of the battle
and of course advance the story. This is a particularly grotesque ending to the Poseidon
battle in God of War 3. And this might be the first true outro, also quite grotesque.
This is Hitler from Wolfenstein 3D with its famous death cam TM.
As a quick anecdote, I had to look up Death Cam TM and realize that it was indeed a trademark by PUBG,
Player Unknown Battleground, which is funny because Kill Cam is owned by Activision, so I think that tells the story.
Anyway, moving on to battle setup.
We can fit the boss to its environment and vice versa, figure out the timing and post-battle results, and boss sequencing and interconnection.
Another early boss battle can be found in Kung Fu Master.
This is the true level boss.
It literally is a boss at the end of every level and also creates an anticipation using
the enemy health bar that is visible throughout the level.
There's the ending boss, which I played Bubble Bobble multiple times.
I never reached level 100 and I didn't even know it had a boss.
But there are a few games in history that had a single boss.
But there's also the intro boss.
This is Fury from 2016, which is, I think, a perfect way of introducing the game
by starting with a bang, really.
So instead of having some endless cutscene telling you what to do,
you can start with a boss that teaches you everything that you need to know.
This is Nemesis from all throughout Resident Evil 3.
You battle Nemesis multiple times and in completely unexpected timing every time, so it creates
this lingering anticipation and this long engagement.
This choice of timing, as we've seen in Bioshock, you choose when to engage your first Big Daddy
and it has some meaningful results for later.
Chrono Trigger from 95 had a particular interesting way of giving you a choice of timing.
The timeline in which you engage with Lavos really changes the outcome and there are 13
different endings based on the timeline.
Going back to Psycho Mantis, again there's so many things to analyze in this battle.
One of the small details that I really enjoy is the fact that how they connect the boss
to its environment.
So the boss, even using telekinesis, it attacks you with picture frames and phases, which
I think it's a great idea.
Once again, the Great Mighty Pooh, well connected to its environment, attacks you with poop,
and you retaliate by throwing an oversized ball.
Alright, so connecting the boss with the minions, that's pretty obvious.
We keep creating this unified approach.
We remember even from Super Mario Brothers that Bowser is actually the king of the turtles
and visually looks connected to the minions, to some of them.
Although, another anecdote is that originally it was designed by Miyamoto as an ox, only
to be challenged and changed later.
Looking again at Super Mario Bros., the connection between the boss battles, basically you're
battling Bowser every time with slightly increasing difficulty, and every time you're sent to
a different castle.
But some games really make a point in creating this elaborate story and interconnection between the different bosses.
This is Undertale.
And every boss has a connection both narratively, thematically, even in terms of UI.
to the previous bosses and uses everything that you've learned from previous bosses
and eventually challenges everything.
So every boss feels like it breaks some rule that was established previously.
This is the Spider from Limbo.
I definitely believe it's a legitimate boss.
You battle it multiple times in the first part of the game.
And again, there are plenty of cases where a single boss can be a challenge multiple times.
And every challenge presents a different skill, and we're going to talk about skills in a moment.
Personally, my second boss in Mushroom 11 was a direct tribute to the spider boss in Limbo,
including the part where you use the spider's body to move over the acid pit.
Which is a quick point that I wanted to make.
In Mushroom 11, after you defeat the boss,
there's always an additional challenge
that you need to cross.
You need to physically cross over to the next world.
Which I thought was pretty interesting and clever.
But to be honest, this is not something I would do again.
Because.
When the player believes that, or they see that triumph,
they believe that they can proceed to the next level.
Instead, we're challenging them and immediately throwing them
back into a new challenge, kind of watering down
this excitement and satisfaction.
Wouldn't hurt to just continue automatically,
or find a different way to present this challenge.
All right, skill, mastery, and teaching.
So we're going to talk about the skills, how
we can design a challenge.
to test a specific skill and how to increase the difficulty and combine multiple skills
and of course the undivided attention that we have to teach new skills.
This is the first boss from Shinobi, a game that I really like.
That boss is pretty much a test for jump and shoot.
And it's basically a skill gate for that specific skill.
If you don't know how to jump and shoot, you wouldn't survive a minute in the next level.
So making sure that you're ready for what's next.
This is Father Gascoigne from Bloodborne, another game with fantastic bosses.
So Father Gascoigne is essentially a skill gate for parrying,
and allows you to test the basics before increasing the difficulty.
Of course, it's not always physical skills. This is an Athene from the Vault of Glass.
This is essentially the ultimate test of communication skills and collaboration between raid members.
One of my favorite things is when bosses actually teach you new...
This is King Bom-Om from Super Mario 64.
We are using this undivided attention and no distractions around the boss to teach you something new,
which is something that is very important when you're teaching to not have distractions.
And we introduced a new skill.
This skill is grab and throw.
We're basically providing a reason for you to utilize that new skill.
This boss particularly does a very clever psychological trick of priming.
Because if you don't know what you need to do, you can just sit back and see the boss
doing the same thing, and that primes you to think about grabbing it for a moment.
Once again, this is the chain from Fury, the intro boss.
I think bosses are perfectly capable.
of introducing the basic mechanics.
In this case, this boss is the first thing that you see
and teaches you all the basic mechanics and buttons and skills.
This is a very memorable boss, the first boss from R-Type,
one of my favorite bosses,
and it uses a great way of implicitly teaching you a new technique.
In this case, the force pod that you send to infiltrate, it has this curvature there
that keeps the force pod in the center right in front of the weak point.
And by seeing the effect, using hindsight bias, you retain the observed result.
That way, it reinforces the teaching of using the force pod.
This is Ruby Weapon from Final Fantasy VII.
It uses a great way of introducing a modified skill, in this case a handicap.
This is the Whirlsend. It's an attack that takes party members off the game.
And really changes the way you interact with the boss.
Another interesting handicap is the last boss in Shadow of the Colossus.
Following the tragic loss of your horse, Tagro,
you don't have the speed and capabilities that the boss allows you to do,
so you have to use evasion and stealth in the first phase of the battle.
Increased risk. This is the last boss in Sonic 2.
In this case, the entire level does not have any rings, which creates this illusion of
risk and the boss feels much harder, which is a different way of playing the game.
This is Berserker.
In a game with a first person shooter, or a third person shooter, where all you need to do is hunt down enemies.
In this case you can't do that, you have to lure the enemy to follow you around into the light to be hunted down by the Hammer of Dawn Death Ray.
And this is Ray from Uncharted 4.
And a lot of bosses use playable cutscenes basically.
open up infinite opportunities, introduce different skills.
This is not exactly expected, but this battle has, it's basically a glorified sword fight
using two buttons.
This is GLaDOS, the only boss in Portal, which introduces a new constraint.
This is the time constraint, or at least the explicit time constraint that was not available before.
Also, Colossus allows you to use multi-skill, combining multi-skill into one epic battle.
This is Wheatley from 4.0.2, which forces you to use all the different things that you learn throughout the game.
Going back to Shadow of the Colossus, this is a phased set of skills.
Every phase has a different, unique skill that it tests.
The first part forces you to shoot down the sacks.
The first part is making this sand dragon drop down.
The second part is all about timing and speed.
The third part is holding on to the body of the dragon.
Mr. Freeze is one of my favorite bosses, again, from the Arkham series.
This one also tests different particular skills, but gives you the choice of how to introduce them.
You choose when to try out every different skill.
The boss tells you that you cannot use that anymore.
He's going to be protected from that.
Which is, I believe, a great way of testing out different skills.
And of course, the side skills.
In a game that's all about space battles, in this case, the skill is to get a triple 7.
In space.
In Metroid Prime, which is a 3D action-adventure game, you get kind of a glimpse to a different game.
Spider Guardian is basically a 2D puzzle game, which is again something that only a boss battle can do, if you think about it.
One of my favorites, this is The Bride from Miss Explosion Man.
This is a side skill that's a tribute to Hat-Tip.
If you will, to another game.
This is basically a tribute to Punch-Out!!
And this is from last year, Dr. Robotnik's Mindy Machine from Sonic Mania.
Which is another glimpse to a different game.
A game with the same name, which is essentially a session of Puyo Puyo.
Alright, let's move on to the actual confrontation.
Alright, so...
We will be talking about how to design attack patterns around the tested skill that we just established
and how to encourage interaction between the boss and the player.
Dracula from Castlevania is a boss that basically tests jumping and hitting from very close range.
In order to support that skill, the attack pattern is designed to be very precise.
uses the negative space that is left by that skill and forces the player to get very close
to the boss and jump over it. So if you think about it, we are using and complementing the
skill that we've established. Cuphead from last year did a fantastic job in pretty much every boss
in establishing a skill, a specific skill, and then creating a negative space that forces you
to interact in a certain way.
Bosses, bullet hells like Don and Pachi, that Krattsu...
is a great example of the idea of negative space.
Because if you think about it, and as we can see,
the boss can kill you whenever they want.
If the designers wished to kill you, they would just shoot an endless amount of bullets
or end the boss with an infinite speed.
But in this case, we are actually trying to not kill the player.
We're planning how to keep them alive.
And you can see that even within the bullet hell, there are paths.
that are allowed for the player to use.
So that's what we're planning. We're planning the paths.
Another great example is from Contra.
Pretty much a lot of the bosses there create the idea of the counter-attack.
So you are attacking the boss as they attack you.
And that creates kind of a poetic justice, of course.
But also there's a...
There's an element here that's very useful for designing a boss, which is creating this
short time window and a limited space, which forces us to have this confrontation and this
cycle of evading and attacking.
We saw the King Kupama from N64.
This is the DS version, which is pretty much exactly the same idea.
It teaches you how to grab and throw.
but it uses a completely different way.
It throws a bomb at you, which again is kind of a cliche of bosses,
but it...
it...
this deflection that it requires puts the player in the line of fire
and forces this interaction between the boss and the player.
One of my favorite bosses, at least from the Zelda series, is Drinrova,
which again creates... forces this interaction between you...
And the bosses, in this case, you deflect the attack of one sister against the other.
One of my favorite bosses, Eusticia from Bayonetta, in another game with fantastic bosses.
In this case, it's another type of counterattack.
It creates a path...
By attacking you, it creates a path for its own destruction.
Another version of that can be found in Dingo Dial from Crash Bandicoot Warped.
You lure Dingo Dial to shoot at you, thus creating a path that you can use to destroy him.
And you can see also that the arena, in this case, was perfectly tailored for this specific battle,
which leads us to the arena layout.
Again, we're trying to create an arena that complements the battle and is based on that specific fight.
This is Cyberdemon from Doom from 2016.
In both phases of the battle, the arena is very small, open, no place to hide,
kind of reminiscent of olden times as well, and it increases the confrontation.
And further, so during the second phase, it uses this temporary layout change
that even creates this lane that restricts your motion.
and makes the confrontation even more obvious.
But the idea is that the arena is always designed and tailored to that specific boss battle.
This is a boss that moves extremely fast and is partially invisible.
You don't know where the...
By looking where the attacks come from, you know where the boss would be.
And also they made a lot of fences and...
There are also a bunch of different hubs for interaction.
Lighting can also be used as a great way of introducing a layout.
In this case, the Specter Knight boss in Shovel Knight uses the shadows to hide.
And if you haven't noticed how it moves in the first phase of the fight, you wouldn't even know how to interact with it.
So it kind of teaches and then tests your ability.
And one of the most important points in boss battles is the attack space.
And I'm referring to the idea that you can employ multiple approaches or strategies against the boss.
I think a good boss can be beaten in multiple ways, or at least different players can interact with it in different ways.
In this case, this is Ornstein and Smough from Dark Souls.
A fantastic boss that is particularly remembered because of the two bosses really.
One of them is quick and weak and the other one is very powerful and slow.
And you choose how to interact with that boss and you form your own strategy.
I'm not a huge RPG player but this is also a memorable.
It's a boss battle, this Archimon from Dark Dragon Age Origins.
It's also known for its various different strategies that can be used in order to beat the boss.
Once again, Big Daddy.
It's one of the first games that allows you to have these different approaches and mobs and emerging behaviors.
You can beat Big Daddy by using shotguns, electricity...
telekinetically moving booby traps, and even hypnotizing one Big Daddy against another.
Alright, moving on to clarity. We need to make sure that we avoid unpredictability,
obscurity, and randomness by setting clear goals, progression in hits, and predictable attacks.
So, the idea of a clear target is very obvious. We all know that we've kind of gotten used to the idea of a glowing target.
a weak spot which creates a clear vulnerability and a call to action.
There's even a funny article from The Onion exactly on that.
Creating a clear call to action is extremely important.
This is an example from Shadow of the Colossus.
Particularly when you have a large boss with multiple weak points, the sigils,
it forces us as designers to create some sort of guidance as needed.
In this case, the sword that lights up the next target.
In some cases, guidance is not needed. This is Dark Link.
You don't need to know its particular weak spots because it is you. You know its strengths and weaknesses.
This reminded me of Mirror Prince from Prince of Persia.
The first phase, the first part of the game, you create this Mirror Prince by going through a mirror.
The second part, you have to battle it.
And in this case, the challenge is a logical challenge,
figuring out how to beat it by lowering your sword and moving into him.
And this is the puzzle battle, and I really enjoy bosses that employ logic.
And figuring out the goal is the challenge in this case.
And one thing that's very, very important, and I can talk a lot about this,
and I don't want to spend too much time on it,
the idea is that...
You either employ logic or skill, but try to avoid doing both at the same exact time.
The reason is what I call the delta of chance, and I'm going to talk about that later.
Delta of chance is that when you believe that you've succeeded and then immediately fail
because there's an additional challenge and vice versa. That creates a very unsatisfying moment.
Clear progression.
We talked about the glowing red point, which creates a focal call to action.
We can also see that this particular game, and most games of the time, have a clear hit.
You can see a couple of frames that change the color.
And also, of course, the health bar, which we've all grown accustomed to in many bosses.
Not every boss has...
Health bars, in some cases, you don't really need it, as long as you have a clear understanding of how far you've gotten.
This is the first phase of Hive Mind in Dead Space.
There are a couple of pods that you... five pods that you need to destroy,
and by seeing how many you have left, you have a clear understanding of the progression.
Early... in the early games, this is a space harrier.
They used a kind of a weird trick of changing the color.
of the boss as they lose health.
But that trick has been long gone.
It limits your visual design abilities.
An interesting way of presenting your progression is done in Cuphead.
So instead of showing you the progression during the battle,
they do it when you die.
Which, if you think about it, is actually quite clever because
you...
potentially lose players just before a potential rage quit.
They can see how far they've gotten.
So that's a very interesting prospect.
It also shows you the phase which gives you even further indication of where you are.
Talking about Cuphead,
it's incredibly important to have a predictable attack
because predictability is control
and when you know how the bullets,
you can have many different bullets or attack types.
Go in the next frame you have control over the battle and as long as you have information and time to react
You can beat any boss
Some bosses kind of put you in a position where you don't have enough time. This is again the first boss in
Shinobi which is notorious for its
Randomness in the attacks. I think in this case. They actually wanted to create this panic
in order to force the player to use the magic.
But generally, randomness is very risky.
Going back to Space Harrier,
another interesting point is that
while in 2D it's very clear to see an attack coming,
it's very clear to extrapolate its position,
In 3D it's not that easy.
I think we've evolved in a way that a change in scale is not that visible.
Some 3D games do it better.
So, going back to Cyberdemon,
as long as it's visible enough that something is going directly at you,
then you should be fine.
In this case, the flare behind the rocket
gives you just enough information to know if an attack is coming directly at you.
Another cool trick from the Barbas fight,
it always attacks you sideways and then clamping towards you,
again giving you just enough information and time to react.
But you don't always have enough information or time to react,
You have to compensate with enough information.
The preemptive shadow, as I call it here, is highlighting where the hit is going to land.
This is both the fireballs and the bombs as well.
If you think about it, it kind of compensates for the lack of information that we, as spectators, have.
If Mario can look up and see the bombs falling, we don't have that luxury, so by providing
that guidance, it gives us just enough information to attack.
This is Hellblade.
In Hellblade, of course, and in many other games, they use preemptive animation.
It gives you well enough time to see when and where the next attack is coming by having
this animation of the enemy.
Also, here's another cool trick to introduce this telegraphy by actually literally saying
that attacks are coming behind you using the voices in Senua's head, which I thought was
brilliant.
This is Elantrador from Rayman Legends.
It uses multiple telegraphing methods.
You have the shadow that gives you information on the position,
or the location of the attack,
and the animation for the timing.
So with the timing and the position,
you have just enough information to respond.
Another cool telegraphing method used in the Master Hand in Super Smash Bros. throughout the series.
These kind of implicit hand gestures give you enough information to know when the next attack is coming.
Once again, Wraith and other battles in the franchise, if you notice just before the hit lands,
it slows it down just enough to give you time to react.
Which is some sort of telegraphing, but kind of changing reality slightly.
This should be fun.
So, the first battles in Punch-Out!!
They start pretty slowly, they have a lot of pre-emptive animations,
giving you just enough time to respond.
But as the battles progress...
and it gets harder and harder, you have less and less time to react.
In fact, the Mike Tyson battle doesn't really give you enough time to respond to any attack.
And the only way you would know what to do is by observing the previous attacks and timing them
and memorize them and basically anticipate in order to survive,
because the previous waves telegraph the next waves.
And that's what you see also in Cuphead many, many times.
The first attack, like in this case the egg,
is extremely risky, you don't even know what it does, and in fact if you're in the wrong place, you would die the first time you see it.
But once you see it once, you know how to react the next time.
And this happens constantly in this game, it works very well for a game that has a lot of these interactions, a lot of deaths.
This is a less common example, this is Lillerhorn from Super Meat Boy.
This entire boss is built on memorization.
It has 13 different stages that you need to memorize each one of them in order to survive.
Which works very well for this game because this game is all about dying multiple times.
All right, let's move on to difficulty.
All right, we're going to talk about Delta of Chance, which I mentioned before, and the
fact that we are here to reward and not to punish.
So the delta of chance.
If you look at any phase or any even attack type in a boss
or any kind of interaction with an enemy,
you usually see, or you better see,
a challenging peak followed by a foreseeable end.
You can actually see where it's going to end.
And a noticeable easing between them.
And the idea of delta of chance is that, well,
a positive delta of chance.
puts you in a position where you see an anticipated failure and
heightened risk followed by an anticipated triumph not immediate triumph, but anticipated triumph and
that translates
directly into the behavior of
Dopamine now. I'm not a chemist a biochemist, but
from it's pretty recent that they
studied this neurotransmitter and realized that its behavior
really rewards and encourages behavior that leads to a positive change in your behavior.
And there's always kind of a low dosage of dopamine that changes, peaks when you have
this positive delta of chance and completely stops when you have the negative delta of
chance kind of in an evolutionary way of teaching you how to work and advance in the world.
In our world, you can kind of imagine that if you think about playing a game of Tetris,
where you can see that you're almost going to fail, and then you see that the next piece is a long piece.
Sometimes you would want to kind of wait and extend that amazing moment that you know that you've just survived.
And that feeling is what I believe is one of the most important and one of the biggest takeaways I think you should have from this talk.
And this is something that I also learned kind of recently, because I made a game that is extremely difficult. You probably know that.
The idea of making sure that there's a challenging peak followed by a kind of anticipated triumph is extremely important.
And I can see this in pretty much all the good bosses that I surveyed.
And this is one of the reasons why this boss is so wonderful.
Because every attack wave has a...
a very challenging peak right in the middle of that attack.
You are attacked by multiple different pieces,
you are forced in this very narrow space,
and once you survive this,
you start seeing less and less pieces coming towards you,
and they get more anticipated,
you see where they're coming,
because those are the only ones left.
And there's a good one second
where you know that you've survived a very difficult challenge.
And that second is extremely addicting and satisfying.
And I think this is what we're looking for.
A great example is from Intruder, from Gradius II.
The first part is one single fire snake, and then you hit it and it splits into three.
That moment becomes extremely difficult.
But once you hit one snake and then the second one, you know that you survived it.
The last part, the last few seconds are just very, very easy.
So you have a few seconds of this wonderful satisfaction.
Another great way, going back to Hivemind, the first phase of the battle,
after you destroyed the third pod, you're picked up always by the tentacle.
And at that point, it seems like it gets a little harder because you're airborne, it's
harder to aim.
But really, there's no risk anymore because you're not subject to the attacks of the tentacles.
So subconsciously, you know that you've beat the first phase.
And those few seconds of you aiming are very satisfying.
Now this is not exactly a boss, but somehow it keeps coming back over and over again in discussions on the favorite bosses.
This is a song from Intargo 3, and I started looking at it and tried to figure out why people like it so much and mention it as a boss.
It had the same traits and qualities of a good boss.
It has attack waves that heighten towards a very challenging, crazy peak.
And once you reach that peak and cross it, it starts slowing down towards this satisfying moment
where you can just kind of rest, you know you succeeded until the next one.
And it's also very memorizable because it's a song, you know how to do this.
All right, let's quickly talk about multi-phases.
Now, there's a notion of creating phases just in order to extend.
the gameplay and this is something that I really don't enjoy.
I don't think that creating a long boss battle is something that's extremely important.
It's not a way for you to extend how long people play your game.
You are here to reward the player and provide some, in this case, break before increasing
the difficulty slightly or change the battle or change it to a different skill.
I also suggest taking into consideration the delta of chance, so make the break more anticipated
and apply some easing towards it.
Some great examples for phasing, as we've seen with the Sand Dragon, where each phase
introduces a different challenge.
This is a great boss battle from NieR Automata from last year.
The first phase you have this force field that protects the boss.
You can't attack it, but you can learn how it moves.
The second part where they turn off the power, you can actually attack it, but you don't really see very well.
So those two phases really complement each other very well.
Last example from the Arkham series, this is Russell Gould, where each one of the phases
changes the rules completely, the oversized boss, then gravity or multiple instances.
So I think the idea is that every phase can break the rules in a different way.
Now let's talk a little bit about the difficulty level and pacifism.
A lot of games introduce multiple difficulty levels throughout the game.
You can change it, you can just, the entire game becomes easier.
Cuphead actually allows you to change the difficulty level per boss.
There are other bosses that give you the idea of a non-fighting option, or maybe this is
the basic option.
In any case, whether or not you fight the boss, the challenge is still maintained.
It's a different challenge.
If you have the fire flower and you hit the boss, if you don't have it, you're using timing instead.
And again, the idea that non-fighting options can still maintain some challenge can be seen in Master from Fallout.
In certain circumstances, and if you go through a specific branch of the dialogue, you can actually convince Master.
to self-destruct and avoid a very, very difficult battle.
And if you think about it, it's not that you skipped the battle.
You just create a different challenge for yourself.
It's more a logical challenge than a physical one.
And a great example is through Undertale.
There are many types of confrontations, and confrontations can end without a fight.
In fact, there's a...
a true pacifist route that is also considered, I think,
as the true ending for the game, that you can just
avoid fighting all the bosses.
And the challenge is still there.
It's a slightly different challenge.
There are other games that allow you to skip bosses.
Because again, the boss is a reward.
If the player so chooses, they can just avoid the battle.
And this is Spire of the Dragon, where
we can use collectibles to progress and go
through the balloonists.
You can just avoid the battle if you have enough of the thing that you're collecting.
And it's all about... If the player just enjoys collecting but they don't enjoy fighting,
then that's their choice.
And finally, in Monster Hunter World, the whole point is that you choose the battles.
You take on quests and it's all for your own personal advancement.
The battle is a reward, it's part of the game, it's not a punishment that you have to endure
in order to get to the next world.
So, a couple of words on skipping.
So, you need to ask yourself when you design a boss,
is this boss essential to the progression?
Does it teach you something that you have to learn?
Does it make sure that you're not going to be hurt later?
And if not, then...
Are you really excluding unable players that you considered as non-deserving?
You remember that the battle must be rewarding, but players can enjoy different types of challenges.
So I urge you to consider easy mode or alternate challenges.
For example, I can definitely see start designing bosses that can be either challenged physically
or logically, and both ways are completely acceptable.
And of course, even skipping the boss,
because it's the player's choice.
If you want, you can always award the main path
with special items or access to different parts of the map
if you so choose, or even different endings,
as we've seen with some other games.
And if you think about it, it actually increases your replay
value, because if you let the players go all the way
to the ending.
They would enjoy and probably want to return to the bosses again, play them in like the
original main path.
It also exposes more people to your art.
And this is a personal thing for me because I spent around two months working on an ending
for Mushroom 11 that only less than 10% of the players actually reached because the bosses,
for example, and other challenges were extremely difficult.
And most importantly, this allows us to really work
towards true inclusiveness, while not
skipping on the actual challenge.
So in summary, I'm just going to call this out real quick.
These are the rules.
Reward, tell a story, locally source, skill test and intro,
do not try to kill, keep everything clear,
allow player expression during the battle,
phase wisely.
Mind the difficulty curve in the Delta of Chance,
and of course most importantly in boss battles,
rules are meant to be broken.
Thank you very much.
If you have any questions, you can line up in front of the mics
if we have time.
Yeah, three minutes.
Go ahead.
Hey, so you went over a lot of, obviously,
what the best bosses in games are.
But what are the worst tropes that you would consider?
So I had a bunch of those.
And just as respect to my fellow designers,
I try to avoid showing too many bad examples.
I touched on a couple of things that I found.
not as useful. I showed, I think some of the bosses in Shinobi, for example,
kind of implemented some things that I would not necessarily implement in my own games.
And again, I didn't want to talk about this too much, but
some of the bosses and challenges in my own game
were extremely difficult and this is, this
all has been a personal learning for me,
figuring out how.
And what makes a good boss battle, so I think I would definitely say my own game has some flaws
So you mentioned having an easy mode for skipping really or some ways skipping really hard bosses
But easy mode has a little bit of a stigma
With a lot of players is there a different way that that could be presented than just saying
easy mode for bosses
So actually, one of the things that I try to kind of mention in my final slide there
is that we actually need to battle the stigma.
Sure, I mean, we can figure out other ways of introducing easy mode,
and I do agree that I don't like using UI to tell you what you're playing.
This kind of puts you in the mindset, this primes you into thinking
that you're actually not as good as you are by just saying the word easy.
So that's a really important point, and I do agree with you.
However, the idea that we need to care about what some people
say because they don't feel that other players deserve
to play the hard mode is something
that we as designers need to challenge.
I think this one.
Oh, hey.
Great talk.
So, Breath of the Wild, my experience with that was I played as much of the game as possible
before getting to the final boss, and the final boss was super short because I was way
overpowered and I felt like I sort of missed the intended experience, or at least I felt
as if it wasn't as satisfying for me.
Have you thought about this and what are your thoughts?
I hated that fight.
We were very, me and Julia, we played it together and we got to the boss.
with a lot of power.
And I actually didn't like that battle too much.
I thought it was, I don't know, laid out in a way that was kind of extended too much.
I actually like most of, a lot of the boss battles that Nintendo has
that kind of have everything laid out very well,
where every phase has a different challenge.
And I think maybe part of the thing, and to be fair,
one of the amazing things that I love so much about Breath of the Wild is that
you can have multiple approaches to every single thing.
But the problem is that you can't balance everything to the maximum.
So in some cases, there are some strategies that are just better.
And you probably found those.
And I didn't. And I'll ask you what he did later.
But honestly, I think this...
really allows this elaborate expression space for the players.
So in some sense, I think maybe you played it very well,
and you missed some of the things.
That's part of the challenge for designing it.
So in a game that's focused around boss battles,
like Shadow of the Colossus, how would these rules change?
How do you continue to teach or connect to the minions
when there aren't minions, there are just bosses?
That's actually a great example.
I was trying to not go over too many things because already I had 115 slides.
Basically, the idea of Boss Rush and games that
only have bosses. I think Monster Hunter is a great example of kind of the non-linear way of
giving you the choice of when to challenge a certain boss. But in this case, the way I see
Shadow of the Colossus is that really, if you think about it, every boss or every colossus
is
is a level.
And that level usually has multiple different challenges throughout that level.
And usually, towards the end of the level, for example, the head of that monster, that's
the boss, if you think about it.
But each one of them, and that's something that I enjoyed tremendously in that game,
is that each one of those bosses introduces something else.
So I thought it worked out for that game.
I hope that answers your question.
First of all, thank you kindly for giving this highly insightful speech.
Now, earlier during the talk, actually at the very beginning, you did mention Silent Hill Homecoming.
And that got me thinking, how exactly do you try to get boss fights right in a survival horror game,
which emphasizes tension through tight resource management and also feelings of...
Occasional helplessness and powerful powerlessness.
Oh, that's a great question.
And to be fair, I only played a few.
So what I what I felt is that in terms
in terms of the boss battles in Silent Hill, really
what I saw, this is a great example
how the theme.
really worked out with the mechanic.
In this case, as you said, this anxiousness,
this pressure that you feel while playing it,
really gets complemented by the visuals in some way.
It could have been, by the way, just as useful,
if you think about it, if this would be a kind of a happy,
smiley face.
But the idea of creating this.
this perfectly unified set of behaviors and mechanics that technology supports,
the mechanics that support the visuals. I think that worked out very well. I'm not
sure if I answered your question though. No, I think you answered it pretty well. Thank you.
Thanks again as well, and you put a lot of work into that which is fantastic.
We went through a whole lot of examples.
The majority of those examples were single-player boss battles.
Do your rules change? Does your focus change when we're looking at multiplayer
and particularly more than just two people attacking a boss?
I think this is a great example, but if you think about it,
it actually answers the same question, because you need to ask yourself
what are the skills that you're trying to challenge.
So...
I don't think I would be able to play Atheon very well.
I know I wouldn't.
So this is one of those things that as I'm seeing other people play it, I can see how
they created a set of challenges that are particularly there and not in other bosses
necessarily to challenge the collaboration.
For example, in a lot of bosses in Destiny.
You can see where other players are.
So they created this time poll so you couldn't see that.
So for every different skill, you create a challenge,
kind of a negative space.
So it's easy to talk about negative space in 2D games or
3D games, where I want you to jump, so I'm going to shoot a
couple of times to make sure that you jump
as high as possible.
But also, if I want to challenge your collaboration,
then I'm going to put the players in a position that
they can't see each other.
Hey, so how would you handle having multiple, like, a boss battle in a game that has, is like a hero-based shooter or something like that?
So, for example, if Overwatch had a boss battle and you could choose any of their 24 characters,
like, assuming that the design philosophy is not to limit player choice in which characters they can bring into that battle.
Um, sorry, I, I, can you, can you...
Repeat that question.
I think I...
Sure, yeah.
Just, it's a pretty vague question, but like, what are some ideas on how you would handle
a boss battle that...
Like where the player basically has too many options available and how they could approach the battle.
I think that's a great point because I was talking about the player expression space is something that is underutilized right now.
There are a lot of bosses that
the expression space is limited to, you know, am I going to jump over two bullets or one bullet at a time?
And they showed
Ornstein and Smough from Dark Souls, which gives you this idea of like, okay, I'm gonna go through.
I'll go through this one first.
When you have too much choice, you have choice paralysis.
So in some way, I think that's also the art of designing.
And to be fair, I think that's why I led my talk here,
to talk first about the skill set
that you would like to challenge.
Once you establish a skill set, or a multiple skill set,
But there has to be some sort of clarity in what you're choosing,
what you're presenting, what you're challenging the player with.
I think that just presenting too many different things
kind of puts you in a point where the player would be helpless, in a sense.
So I think, again, that's part of my point.
There's no...
perfect way to tell you how to design a boss.
Like, how do you place the bullets?
What kind of, you know, how it moves from side to side?
How do you, you know, you attack towards the player
or towards where they're going?
All these things are, you know,
eventually it's the art of designing.
But in a sense, just having the clear view
of what you're challenging,
I think that's extremely important.
And that needs to be limited, but not singular.
I think we're out of time, so thank you very much.