It was known from the beginning that the main character, she's a kind of ballerina and modern dancer at the same time.
But the story I got to know when I arrived here just before we started working and also the story is a bit touching to myself
it's about the
woman who wants to go on with her life and solve her family issues with her parents her father left the family
And now she has to decide if she wants to see him or she wants to continue
Be with her mother or other way around so I have it myself my
My parents unfortunately are separated as well.
Inner fight is quite close to me.
I'm also in that age when I'm trying to make decisions.
Whose fault was that and what should I do with it?
I think it's nice also that the people who's gonna play
the game, they would have them to make your own decision
because it's a big decision.
In the beginning, I had a chance to see myself put into the skin of the character.
It's very funny to see something else moving like you.
It's a bit abstract, I would say.
But at the same time, we have a very similar body.
She moves as I move, so I make it.
It's gonna be looking really cool.