All right.
Hey, everyone.
Glad you made it to my talk.
My name is Mo.
I'm the lead designer at Mimimi.
I'm not 12 years old, as you might think.
I'm 31, actually, to get that out of the way quickly.
I hope there is going to be two key takeaways you have from this post-mortem for Shadow
Tactics.
It's a design-focused post-mortem, so maybe you learned something about game design or
our approach or what not to do.
And you will definitely learn that I'm a horrible artist because I drew through the whole thing
because I like doodles.
But you'll have to sit through that now, I guess.
All right, so let's jump straight ahead to the release day of Shadow Tactics.
This was the team on our release day, which coincidentally was the same day that the German developer awards were held and we were nominated
for many of them and we won many of them and we got very drunk and
It was like going up the stage getting an award coming down checking the steam sales being like yes
And going up again and getting very very drunk and everybody was very happy and supposed to be very very happy
But there was a big dark cloud hanging above us
Because we knew that
likely the studio would not exist anymore in one month of time and that was because
during the development as there were multiple reasons for this the the time of development
for shadow tactics was scheduled to be 18 months and we realized that we would need more time like
three more months was what we needed and so sometime during development that became clear and
We had to put our own money into that.
And those were the savings we had to sort of survive
until the next project would roll in after Shadow Tactics.
And we had multiple projects lined up for that,
and they one by one kept breaking away,
as things can happen.
And so we stood there and we made the decision
as the whole team, saying, okay,
do we put those three months into the game
and go out with a very nice game, maybe?
Or do we not do that and feel bad about it
for the rest of our lives, maybe?
So.
We made the hard decision to say, okay, this might be the last game we're making,
but we're going to make it the best game we can,
and put all our money into it.
And so most people on that picture were basically terminated at that time.
We knew that we would not be able to work together if things went wrong,
except for everybody who was involved in the console ports.
they would have to stay.
And hopefully would have made a new project in that time,
but it was a very bad feeling, of course.
Luckily, our CEO worked his ass off during that time,
and he came through and made a very good deal,
a follow-up deal, and of course,
publishers always wait a little bit.
And they had released a new game to see how it's doing,
and Shadow Tactics did well, so we managed to get a deal.
And on 23rd of December, he wrote us the email
when everybody was at home with their families
that things are fine.
We're going to be alive.
And this was in January, where we met in the center of Munich.
We're from Munich, Germany, and burned all the paperwork
and, again, got very, very drunk.
So this is all I'm going to say about the business, whatever side.
The rest is going to be design.
I hope that you know shadow tactics.
If you don't, this might be a very, see, I'm not a very good artist.
Um, if you do not know shadow tactics, I'm going to quickly explain it, but this
talk might be a little boring for you.
Um, so.
In Shadow Tactics it's a stealth game from a top-down, isometric, whatever perspective.
And you're playing as a gang of five characters.
It's playing in Edo, Japan.
And basically there are huge maps filled with hundreds of enemies
and you have to combine the skills of your characters to sort of get through there
and take out all the enemies.
Or ghost your way through, which is a lot harder.
The main mechanic we use for that is sort of a view vision cone thing,
where you have a bright area and a dark area, and in the bright area you always get detected,
and in the dark area you can crouch through it and feel stealthy like a ninja.
And this is familiar for anyone, this of course is all ripped from Commandos,
which is our big inspiration, the Commandos series and the Desperados series.
This is a quick disclaimer now.
I love those games, and if I'm gonna say anything bad
about the old games, it's purely analytical.
I'm not trying to make them look bad, okay?
So, except for some of them.
They were not that good.
So, this is Commandos 1.
It's the add-on for Commandos 1.
It's our favorite game of the whole genre,
and the genre died about 10 or 15 years ago,
and we sort of had to find out why
before we made another entry in the genre,
because maybe people just didn't wanna play this anymore,
right, we had to find out.
So.
We played the games and we dug into feedback and all that,
and it pretty quickly became clear that the height of the genre basically was
after Commandos 1 was released, there was Commandos 2 and Desperados 1,
which are very good games, and this was sort of the best moment for real-time tactics.
And then everything started to go downhill.
For each of the series, it was something different.
For the Commando series, it was that they wanted
to go more cinematic, and they always had
an affinity for movies.
The Commando 2 is full of movie missions.
They're sort of like movies.
And in Commando 3, they pushed that quite a lot.
things like parachute troops coming in and things surprising you and everything being cinematic and scripted.
But that's not really what you want in a tactical game, right?
You want to be able to not be surprised, to sort of deduct everything that's going on,
know what's going on, especially in a genre like this.
And they sort of lost that by going very cinematic.
And the Desperados series went into some weird things where you could go into first person and start shooting people,
and that just went very horribly.
And for
The nail in the coffin basically then was Commando Strike Force,
which was a shooter game.
I never played it.
I actually don't know if it's bad or good.
But people were very angry about the game
because it wasn't what they wanted to have anymore.
And so we realized the genre didn't
die because people don't want to play it anymore.
It was because there was nothing for them to play.
And that's when our idea of shadow tactics
became a lot more real.
And we knew what we had to make.
And we also knew that we had to make the game like Commando's
one, two, and Desperados one, and not the other games.
So, let's get into shadow tactics.
These are the characters we have in the game.
I'm gonna give you a quick rundown of them.
On the left you have Mugen,
he's sort of the big, brutish samurai guy
who can take out multiple enemies at once.
Next to him is Aiko, she's a kunoichi.
She's a female ninja, she can disguise
and then walk freely amongst guards,
which is very powerful.
And Aiko and Mugen sort of have a thing going.
Then in the center we have Hayato,
he's the generic.
archetype ninja dude with a shuriken.
And he's very versatile and agile.
Next to him is the fan favorite, I guess.
Her name is Yuki, and she lost her parents in the war
and grew up on the streets, and she's a little bit crazy,
but in a funny way, so that's why people like her, I guess.
And then we have Takuma, who's sort of,
from a mechanical standpoint, the oddball.
I'm gonna talk about that in a little bit.
And on his head, it's Kuma.
That's the pet tanuki he has, it's his distraction.
So I think that characters are the area where we most succeeded in the game.
They are the most important part of the game, and
the decisions we made really worked out.
And so I'm gonna talk about those a little bit.
When we looked at the old games,
we identified two problems they had with their character design.
The first one is this guy.
This is the driver from Commandos 1.
And anyone who played Commandos 1
might know what I'm getting at.
The driver was used for one thing only,
and that's driving vehicles.
So, and you don't drive many vehicles in Commandos.
So what would happen is you would take your cool characters
like the Green Beret, clear the whole map,
feel awesome with the Green Beret,
everybody's dead, and then there's a car,
and then you're like, ah, the driver.
And you pull the driver, the whole map up,
and it just gets in the car and drives off.
And so he's like a key, right?
He's not.
mechanically interesting character and not someone you use very much. He's just a key.
So this sort of became a design term for us, like characters shouldn't be drivery or the driver.
He's the epitome of failure for us in character design in these games.
And the next one I'm going to teach you a German word today, one that is very German.
There you go. It's Eier legende Wollmilchsau. It's a typical German thing.
I'm going to translate that literally for you. It means egg laying wool milk pig.
This is my interpretation of an egg-laying woolmilk pig.
It's an animal that does it all, right?
And in the Commando series, there's usually one character
in every game that does it all, the Green Beret.
He can carry bodies, he can use his knife to kill guards,
he has a great distraction.
And we thought, that's pretty cool.
We want all our characters to be Eierlegende Wollmilchsäue.
So that's what we did, basically.
We developed a system where every character
would have a certain type of skill,
and it was important that each of them had one.
The main first thing of course is the melee kill.
Each character has one and you can already see that Takuma sort of is the oddball because
he has a grenade, which is not very stealthy as a melee kill, but whatever.
I'm going to talk about that in a bit.
And they are all basically the same but we changed the balancing so that for example
Yuki who's not very...
good at this sort of thing, has a very messy kill animation, it takes a very long time,
so you have to use her differently.
But it's important that they all can do it, right?
Maybe someone is better in a certain situation, but they all can do the melee kill.
The next skill is very important.
It's the special, as we call it.
And this is sort of the skill that
describes what the character is.
And if you talk about the character
when I described them to you previously,
this is what you talk, right?
If you tell a friend, this is the type of skill
you're gonna talk about.
For Hayato, it's the shuriken.
For Yuki, her trap that she can lure people in.
Mugen, the sword wind attack,
where he just obliterates everyone around him.
It's not limited to three, what people think you can kill all the guards on the map with it.
Then we have Aiko, she has a distraction as that skill which is rather special, it's the disguise ability,
and the snipe ability of Tsukuma.
And while people might think that this is the most important skill for a character, it's actually not.
It's the most important one for the vision of a character.
But for gameplay the most important skill is the distraction, by far.
Because the distraction is the skill that you use to interact with the system of the game, right?
The kill is just a kill, it's very binary.
But with a distraction, you can sort of break up the enemy setups
and draw guards away and sort of...
I had to say a bad word there, sorry.
..can mess with the setups that we build.
And it was very important that the distractions felt different
because they really define how you play a character.
This is the most important skill a character has.
Just to give you a simple example,
if I use Yuki's whistle to whistle a character away,
it doesn't really matter if I kill him with a shuriken,
if I stab him, if there's a trap, if there's...
Mugen doing his sword thing, it doesn't matter, right?
The important part was that I could draw him out
with the whistle.
So, they are actually the most important skill in the game.
Each character has a gun.
And I'm gonna quickly talk about the role of guns
in the game.
Many games, and also the old ones,
the Desperados and Commandos, did something
where they had infinite ammo,
and you could basically start shooting at any time,
and just draw all the guards on the map to your,
and just...
kill them. And we didn't like that and we also realized that we would never be able
to create good gun gameplay mechanics and good stealth mechanics at the same time. So
what we decided was that we will just not do shooting and shootouts in a big way so
our guns are more like stealth guns. They have a very small range of audio or noise
so people don't hear them as much but you have a very limited amount of ammunition.
And the role is basically that if you're stuck in some sort of setup and you don't know what
to do and you just
You can't figure it out, you just use your guns,
shoot everyone in that one setup,
and then you can move along.
So it's basically a joker or a small cheat that you have.
And they all have a health pack, but whatever.
So the important part about this was that we made a system
where every character has each type of skill.
And the one that is most driver-like, I guess,
would be Takuma because he can't carry bodies,
he cannot climb, he cannot kill anyone,
but he's extremely powerful aside from that.
All of his skills are very strong.
The tanuki is the strongest distraction in the game.
The grenade, the normal one is not as good,
but you can switch it to a stun grenade,
which is completely overpowered.
Yeah, the snipe is just strong.
Alright, so that's enough for characters.
I'm going to do sort of a deep dive into one game design topic
between each of these broader topics.
It's supposed to be a warp vortex,
but it looks more like a snake.
A snail, I'm sorry.
Alright, for this one I'm going to talk about shadow mode,
which is a prominent feature in the game.
Something that's very important to us is that you're playing a team, right?
This was one of the pillars we had.
You shouldn't feel like there's individuals running around.
It should be like a team that is working together,
because this sort of is different from any stealth games where you're just by yourself usually.
And so what we thought of in the beginning is that we make team actions,
which would be like two characters working together and creating this new skill.
And this would be true for every character.
Every character combination would have their own team action.
Desperados did that in one of their sequels.
It did not work out for them, and I know why now,
because we tried it as well.
The problem with this is that team actions.
add a lot of complexity to the game.
It's hard enough already, I mean,
every character has two skills you have to learn, right?
The distraction and the special.
And that is hard enough for people already.
It would take them a long time to really get the hang
of how to use a character.
Now imagine if we add five to 10 skills on top of that
that are just very situational,
you can't even use them all the time.
and you have to try to learn those and really use them,
that was not gonna work.
And the second one was that we had a couple of good examples
for team action.
For example, we had the idea that Aiko could use Mugen
sort of as act like he's her husband
and sort of shuttle him through enemy vision
because they wouldn't think he's suspicious
or Mugen could bunk up other characters
and help them climb like a ladder.
But it sort of stopped after that
and we would have needed 10 or more.
So yeah, we scrapped that.
And we did the planning mode thing.
That also existed in Desperados.
It was a little hard to use
because the controls were not as tight,
and they are for us as well.
But the idea behind the planning mode,
if you don't know it, is that you can plan one action
for each character you have,
and then have them executed at a later time,
together or separate.
This is very important for gamepad controls.
We knew from the beginning that we're gonna do
a console version, so we worked on gamepad controls
from the beginning.
And it is very different because you control
the character directly, right?
It's very immersive in that case.
So on a computer you could simply just send
a character somewhere and do something else
with another character, but on a gamepad you can't
because you have to control the character yourself.
So shadow mode becomes very important
if you're playing with a gamepad.
And...
And what it turned out to be is sort of a do-it-yourself team action.
And it was brilliant because we didn't have to teach you any new skills.
You could basically use the skills that you already knew, combine them, make the game
feel like a team game, and voila, everything worked out well.
And I think this is also some of the most powerful moments in the game are when you
pull off a successful shadow mode.
So that worked out well.
And something that often comes up is the question why we only have one action that you can save.
And why not infinite actions?
It would be so much cooler.
We actually had that during development and it had a couple of problems.
It was pretty awesome, I have to admit it.
Like if you saw people just doing these insane things
where they would make insane queues and chains of
I throw a shuriken there, I walk over there, I use my stone,
the shuriken, I pick it up again, the cooldown,
and they would do insane things and basically clear parts of the whole map
just in shadow mode.
And that was fun, but that's not how we want you to play our game.
In our game a very important aspect is the real-time aspect.
And it's the aspect of execution.
You cannot just plan like in a turn-based game,
but you have to execute as well.
And if Shadow Mode is that powerful,
you don't have to execute anymore.
You just plan it and you look and see what happens.
And the other one was that the more complexity
the feature had, the more tools players wanted
to work with it.
So they wanted timelines where they could rearrange
the actions they had set,
or they wanted a pause function where they say,
you walk there and then you wait three seconds
and then you do this action.
And that would have been a nightmare from all sort of standpoints.
So we didn't do it.
And the lesson we learned is that less is more.
Wow, big lesson.
I guess nobody heard that before.
But.
The big part that was new for us was the fact
that what we actually had was fun, right?
It was not something where you just have
this huge pile of features, but a lot of stuff is added on
and somebody's coming, yeah, you should do less,
that would be better.
It was fun, it was a very good thing,
and there's games who have this planning mode thing
as their main mechanic, but it just wasn't our game,
so we had to cut it out, and the game's better for it.
Let's talk about level design.
I could talk a lot about that.
It's going to be rather short, though,
because there's a lot going on in this talk.
This is the mission eight of the game.
And as you can see, the map is very big.
You are this big.
If you can't see it, this is you.
So what is very important if you have a mission where people spend one to four hours on,
is that the mission is cool.
As soon as the mission is bad or boring, they're probably going to stop playing your game
because they know they have to spend a couple of hours on that mission.
And they also have to be very unique.
And this is sort of the first big thing that we wanted to do.
And this is something that Commandos 2 does the best, I guess.
They have very unique settings and great maps.
So we took that inspiration.
And the idea is basically that if you and a friend have played the game,
this is sort of a test you can make to see if your maps are unique,
if you can describe to them a mission with one or two words
and they know which one you're talking about instantly,
then it's probably unique enough.
And the important thing about this is that we did also not want you to...
get into a new map and realized it's the same thing again.
And you know you have to play that for two hours now.
So that was very important that things look differently.
I'm gonna talk about that a little bit more later
when I talk about pacing.
Another big thing was the emotional state
that you want you to be in if you play a mission.
This is very high level, but it's important to know that
like if you wanna be consistent.
So if you open up the mission, you're very very happy. Everything is new. It's looking gorgeous. You're scrolling over the whole map
You're like, oh wow, this is beautiful. Look at that landmark. Look at this nice building
Look at this and then it sort of dawns to you that you have to actually play all of this and you see things
Like oh my god, there's some Samurai over there. There's a huge patrol of guys. How am I ever going to?
and you want to quit, but then you're like,
okay, no, I can do this.
I've had certain missions before, I can do this one as well,
and then you enter in the emotional core loop of our game,
which is basically utter despair into happiness,
into I can do this, and many quick saves,
and maybe rage quits in between.
And in the end, you feel like a god.
You're in a purple cloud of puffiness,
and you're very happy, and the big thing is
that you can scroll over the whole map
that you have actually just completed,
and see everything that you've done.
This is important, and this is very, very good.
And we want that.
We could have done more in that department, I think.
We could have added to the stats screen
some sort of replay function
where you can just see what actually happened,
and you did this there, and you did that.
That's something we're probably gonna do for our next game.
Yeah, but this is very, very important,
and giving you that feeling of satisfaction in the end.
So basically, every mission is the same
as doing a small setup, right?
And I want to talk about openness a little bit.
One of our key pillars in the game,
the level design, was that you should
be able to play it your way.
Everybody should have the chance to play different
things, and every puzzle had to play different
approaches. And this doesn't only
apply to the small enemy setups, but also
to the whole map. This is Mission 5.
It's the first mission that we built.
It was sort of a vertical slice.
And I think it's one of the best, which is
awkward, because we didn't learn much,
I guess.
But...
In the beginning it's very linear, you get up to this gate and then the mission basically opens up.
And you can go left or you can go right.
And the briefing tells you this, right? It tells you there's two paths.
And something that's very important if you're designing for openness
is that you actually show players the paths.
If you have 20 paths but they're all obfuscated and you're like,
yeah, the player has to be clever and find them,
then they won't look and they won't find them
and they won't realize that this is an open game and they will think it's linear.
So what we always try to do is something like this T-shape,
where we say, OK, you can go left, you can go right.
And also be aware of the fact that you are not
losing content if they are not playing the other part.
The choice is only meaningful because they
don't get to play the part, right?
If they would end up in the same thing anyway,
there wouldn't be a choice, and the game
wouldn't feel open or good at all.
Plus, you can always have replayability.
If the player chooses to play this mission again,
they will choose the other path and have
a completely different experience.
And there also are obfuscated paths in this mission.
You can just go straight ahead and climb up the building,
but most people don't find that.
But it's cool, because if you replay it, you might find that.
You might feel clever.
We don't tell it to you in a briefing,
and we do that sort of stuff a lot.
I want to talk about bottlenecks, because if everything was very open and you didn't
have any bottlenecks, then the game would be very boring, especially ours, because people
could just sneak through everything and leave everything behind.
So how do we do bottlenecks and how do we make them still fun and not feel frustrating?
So the first thing that we do is basically bottlenecks always revolve around Takuma or
Mugen who cannot climb or swim, so you always have to drag them through, sort of.
In this case, this is the bottleneck.
You have to get Takuma to this sniper tower on the left,
but he cannot swim, so he has to go over that thing.
And what's important here is that while it is a bottleneck
to get Takuma there, you have infinite possibilities
with your other characters on how to solve that thing.
You can swim around the whole island,
you can get out anywhere you want to,
and approach the setup in a very, very open way,
and there are multiple solutions to it.
So it doesn't really feel like a bad bottleneck
where you're like, I have to do this now.
It still feels open, and you can be creative.
So, yeah, that's enough for level design.
Let's do another deep dive thingy.
Something that we learned, which is also pretty obvious, I guess,
for many people, but it's about how people approach
problem solving in your game.
So we have a player, and the player faces a problem.
In our case, usually a setup of some guards.
And there is this assumption players have on how they are approaching a problem in our game,
because it's called Shadow Tactics, it's a tactical game, right?
You have strategy, you're in this view, in this RTS view where you can see everything.
So people think that they're actually approaching problems very holistically,
and checking everything out, and then narrowing it down, and then starting to work,
but that is not what they're doing.
In reality, they do this. They see a guard, and this is the circle, sort of the tactical horizon,
things they actually see.
And they just go in and kill the guard,
and then they get seen and they quick load.
And they see, okay, this guy is in there,
so they add that guy to their horizon, sort of.
And they keep doing that over and over
until they have actually understood how the setup works.
And it is very important to understand that,
because they might tell you
that they are playing very strategically,
but they are usually not.
I'm sure that many people are, but many weren't.
And what this meant for our level design was,
that we had to make sure that things are not too far away
from the center of attention that you're actually playing in.
For example, we don't have large patrols
that are going like many minutes around the map
because that would just be bad.
You would play the game and then suddenly they would come in
and screw everything up for you.
And we try to have guards close to each other.
And this doesn't work all the time, but we tried doing that.
Another thing we did here was that we cleared off the areas very clear.
So you cannot see from one area into the other.
You can always rely on the fact that if you are in one area,
guards from another area will not disturb you, at least most of the time.
So the lesson we learned here is that what people tell you
about how they approach problems in the game is not really true.
And we thought about why this is the case in our game,
and it's very clear we could have seen that from the beginning
because shadow tactics is very iterative, right?
We teach you to quick save all the time,
so there's basically no punishment for failure.
The game screams that at you.
It's like, just try things out.
The quick load time is very low, just keep going.
And of course they don't think holistically
and watch everything because they don't have to, right?
And it's in our core mechanics,
and we could have seen that earlier.
Story.
I'm gonna drink something real quick.
So, the most important rule.
we had for our story was that the plot is not important,
but the characters are important.
And the plot had to work with many, many restrictions
from a game design and level design standpoint.
I'm gonna talk about that in a bit.
So it's structured very simple
and it had to facilitate certain things.
It's basically the Shogun is fighting Kagesama,
who's this ominous bad guy.
You don't know who he is.
And the important part here is that
The Shogun can send you anywhere because we have these missions where you're on a mountaintop,
it's winter, oh, you're at a lake, it's summer, and it's impossible to tell a story that feels
like a journey very much if you have a structure like that.
That's what I talked about with the different settings before, that we want every map to
feel fresh and new.
This is a big hit for the story, right?
You cannot do certain things then.
And that's why we...
And also the characters that you have in a mission
are not defined by the story.
They are very much defined by the pacing,
so the writer can't just say,
yeah, I want this character to be here
because he will not be there.
So we did this mostly in cut scenes, the plot thing.
Between the missions you get a cut scene and that's that.
But the more important part of storytelling that we had
is about our characters and how we talk about them.
The first thing we do is we have something like we call context dialogues,
sort of a dialogue that either triggers if you walk into a volume with the player character,
or if you do an action, you kill a guard, whatever, then these banter things trigger.
And they are very weird because we're in Edo, Japan, this is very early,
and they sort of have Skype, they can just talk to each other over the whole map.
And some people are offended by that and they don't like it, but...
Realize that people want your characters to talk to each other,
so they will have a lot higher suspension of disbelief
if something like this happens, if you do it right.
And we had certain things that we had to change
and had to work into the game that would make this less awkward.
For example, when a character walks into a trigger volume
and one of these dialogues triggers,
it's always that correct character that starts talking.
So every dialogue is written in a way
that there's a beginning line for each character
in the mission, and then the dialogue will go on.
And this way it feels less awkward
because sort of you are initiating the dialogue
and it's not someone screaming at you from 400 meters away.
And this worked out really well, I think,
and we got a lot of character things across
with that and the personalities.
And the other one is...
We call them player barks.
Barks are many things, so you might not
call them that in your studio.
But it's when you select the character, what they say
when you use a shuriken or whatever.
This work, work, yes, my lord stuff from Warcraft 3
would be an example of that.
And we try to use that for storytelling in something
I haven't seen as much, and I wonder why,
because it's the best way to do it.
Something very bad happens at some point in your story.
After that, for two missions, we sort of completely
swapped the dialogue lines your characters say
if you use them and make them walk around or use skills,
because they are depressed.
Because it would be very awkward if you have depressed dialogue
where he's like, oh my god, I'm so sad.
This is so bad.
And then you select them.
He's like, yes, sir, I'm going to do that.
It doesn't feel right.
And I think we could have done a lot more with that, used that.
changing this stuff up a little more.
Well, we did it a little bit with,
there's a snow map, they might say things like,
there's snow in my armor, but I think
from an emotional standpoint, this is a very underused tool
in RTS-like games that you can do very much with.
Pacing.
I'm realizing I'm talking very fast,
so I might slow down a bit.
I don't see much about pacing,
so this might be very, very basic,
and you might get bored now, but,
It's an important thing to me and also for our game,
so I wanted to talk about it.
And if anybody of you is into that stuff,
like pacing of the whole game, talk to me,
I wanna learn, I want new things.
So Shadow Tactics is about 25 hours long.
And the biggest fear I had all the time
was that people would get bored halfway through,
because there is not very much in the game, actually.
We have three enemy types, right?
They are basically all the same, they just react differently.
But they don't have different weapons or huge different behaviors.
In the beginning, we had concepts of guards like that would maybe.
gun around with torches and sort of burn the bushes you're hiding in,
and ninja characters that hide in bushes, and we cut all of that,
nothing of that made it into the game.
So it's very simple, and we only have three guard types,
so it's not much variety coming from that, right?
Then we have five characters, but we introduced them in the first third of the game,
and they do not change at all.
There is no progression, there is no leveling up,
there is no skills that you can choose.
It's just the same character from start to finish.
So how are we going to keep the player interested for 25 hours or more?
And the first big thing we did is that we invented sort of, well we didn't invent them,
we stole them from Commandos and so on, but, and we had these
high impact features that completely change the gameplay,
the core gameplay.
And one of them is the night time,
where the lights become very important,
the shadows become important,
which is something that is irrelevant on most maps,
on day maps, I mean.
And then you have the footprint mechanic,
where snow is lying and guards can see your footprints
and they will follow you up.
And this really changes how you play a mission a lot.
And we had these two things.
We thought about others,
like adding fog of war maybe to some missions,
which sadly never made it.
It's something I want to try, but.
There's technical limitations with that.
And it's difficult with the fog of war and a view cone,
right, because the guard, you cannot see the guard,
but he can see you.
So that would have been very bad.
So we did this thing, and we paste these out very carefully.
I'm going to show you that in a minute.
And we try to not overuse them.
And then we have some sort of story high points in a mission.
Usually, mechanically, the missions
where we have these big assassinations,
like you kill.
Koto, you kill Iyabu or Kagesama in the end.
There is not much going on from a mechanical standpoint.
We don't introduce new features there.
We don't introduce new characters.
They're just, like you learn stuff,
now use it and kill this guy.
But you have an emotional high point there
because story-wise it's pretty cool.
So this is important for pacing as well.
Especially balancing these two things against each other.
We have these graphs that.
I sadly didn't bring because I thought I would be a lot slower and didn't have time for it.
So basically the idea was that we have these high impact features like this or introducing
a character and we would assign a value to that, right?
And then we would see in every mission how many high impact features are there, how many
medium impact features are there.
For example.
puddles that you can go into that make a noise.
They don't change the game completely,
but they change it up a bit.
And so we get this value,
and then we can make a graph out of that
and see how much is going on from a mechanic standpoint
in every mission.
It's good for tutorial stuff,
and also just to see how the pacing turns out.
And then you base that against how the excitement
of the player is when he just opens the mission,
or if the story does something crazy.
So you balance these out with each other,
and then you get a nice pacing.
So this is the Excel file we used.
It's actually pretty simple.
There's not much going on.
But I still wanna just go over it.
Probably you guys have much more complex stuff,
but we'll see.
This is the setting stuff I talked about earlier.
As you can see, we tried to paste them out.
There is a bunch of village settings in the middle,
but they are very, very different.
One of them is very snowy, it's raining,
it's a very bad mood.
One of them is the fifth mission I showed you before.
And they are sort of, yeah, they're different,
so don't get fooled by that.
You can see there's the moon down there,
which I might show you at the end.
Yeah, we tried to be very careful with the settings
to paste them out in a way that it always felt fresh
and you didn't play in the same area
or the same visual style for too long
and never one mission after the other.
This is the night and the snow gameplay.
You can see we don't use it that often
and we usually paste it at a point
where you don't get a new character or anything else.
If there's not much going on,
then we introduce something like snow
or we introduce something like...
the night gameplay in the Lake Village.
And we do this once, twice, and then once and twice again,
and then we have a mission with both, and that's it.
We don't try to push it, we don't try to overuse it,
because then the feature would get old and boring.
And this is the most important thing we had for pacing.
It's the characters that you have in a mission.
People always want to choose their own characters for a mission.
They want to be like, yeah, I want to, this will add so much depth, right?
I could choose the game and play the game in very different ways.
But what would actually happen is that normal players would just stick to what
they know.
They would just choose the character they like the most and
then the game would get boring very quickly.
So it's very important that we have the power to sort of,
we have higher to two missions and you get used to a skill set and boom,
we take them away and you have to sort of deal with that.
And that is the most important tool of pacing we have.
If you can find something like that in your game where you sort of can control how the game plays extremely well like this and then use that feature, it's the best thing you have.
And what you can see is that we have only two missions that actually have the same character setup.
So, well, you can't really see it because it's very confusing.
I had to count that like five times myself to not lie to you.
But it's only these two missions.
Next to that you can see the mission objectives,
we tried to balance those out as well,
that you don't have like three assassinations missions
in a row, and while they mostly are the same,
that you always have to get to some point and do something,
it's still important that the vision and the feeling
the player has is very different in each mission.
And on the right you can see some play time,
we also put, like, the thing is a lot bigger,
I just cut it down, and this is the first playthrough
and the second playthrough from the team,
whatever, it's not really relevant.
So, the last deep dive I have right now, it's about one of the most important features in the game, which is the quicksave.
We were very, very afraid regarding the quicksave, because we thought that it's a very old school type of thing, it's very retro, and we didn't know how, especially reviewers would react to it, right?
What they think it's a...
It's bad design that we didn't really do our job properly
because you don't do that anymore, right?
The safe scumming thing.
And we got afraid and we sort of thought about features
that we could implement that would sort of.
remove the quick save.
We knew we would have it, but we tried
to make it less important for a long time during development.
And an example for this is the biggest story
of design failure we have in the game.
It's called Freeze Mode.
It never shipped, obviously.
And we worked on that for about a year, I think.
And we had so many iterations.
The basic idea was this.
Once you get seen, we don't want you to quick load.
We want to give you a second chance.
maybe just keep playing, we don't want the game to end,
because especially Commandos 1 was very, very brutal
in that regard, and it's not that much fun for many players.
There's some who like that, but they can play on hardcore.
And the idea was that once you get seen,
the game freezes, freeze mode,
and you can choose that you can teleport somewhere.
The idea was sort of that the ninja
is using his smoke grenade and just disappears
into thin air, which is a pretty cool move.
It had multiple problems.
The first one is that if players get seen in our game,
they usually get very excited and they start clicking
really fast and try to get away or something.
And this is not when you want to freeze the game
and force them to do a controlled input,
because they will not.
They will just click through it and then they teleported
somewhere and they don't know what happened
and they were very frustrated.
We could have fixed that, I guess, through input stuff,
but the basic principle of if someone is agitated,
you force them to make a...
controlled input that just doesn't work. So we had that problem for all the iterations of the feature and
the second big problem was
I have to mention by the way that
Many of you might think well
Why didn't you just put a rewind time feature in the game that would solve all the problems?
We talked about that and then we realized we cannot do that because it's very
hardcore from a technical standpoint and would take a lot of our budget and also
we didn't want a rewind time mechanic just to facilitate the quick save thing
right would have needed a lot more mechanics to work into that and make it
a game about rewinding time like the games about rewinding time are yeah but
back to the problems with the freeze mode so the first problem was that as I
said before people just click through it
And the second problem was that it added just a lot
of complexity and possibilities to abuse,
because people would get seen in it,
and then they would try to teleport somewhere
advantageous for them.
So they would sort of skip part of our gameplay
and get seen on purpose,
which is definitely not what you want.
So we had to fix that in a way,
and we made many iterations of that.
At some point, you could only teleport back on a line
where you would have been walking before,
and just sort of go back.
But none of it worked,
and it always had the same problems.
And so we ended up just,
yeah.
cutting the whole thing, well, we didn't cut the whole thing.
We were going down this rabbit hole of adding new stuff,
changing stuff.
We didn't really see what was going on anymore.
And at some point, our creative director came by
and he was like, guys, we should fix this.
And so we sat down in a room.
And we walked out of that room with a simple realization
that we had just put a slow motion there.
Because the slow motion does everything we want, right?
It gives the player time to think.
When they get seen, it doesn't really everything up.
screw everything up completely so they can still think and react.
But it also isn't making it so they feel like this was a sort of fail-safe,
because there was a problem with the previous systems as well.
Players would, they were not bulletproof, right?
There were situations where you would get seen and
there was no space where you could teleport to safely.
And if you put a system in your game that screams at the player,
well, I'm going to save you.
but sometimes I don't, then that's not a good idea.
And the slow motion doesn't do that.
The slow motion just says, okay, you have some more time
before you get detected, so use that time.
And it worked very well, I guess.
So, back to the quick save.
This was sort of the point where we realized that we should maybe embrace the idea that this is a game about quicksave and not try to obfuscate it.
So we added things like the quicksave timer. This is a timer that pops up after one minute of gameplay and sort of screams at you and says like, one minute, right?
We want you to save often. And screams at you and says, save the game! And after two minutes it gets orange and screams even louder and just gets...
You can turn that off if stuff like that annoys you.
But we could have done that a lot more...
Hardcore, I think.
Many people just don't see it anyway.
But we did sort of stuff like this, right?
We went into that route of embracing the quicksave.
And if you play the tutorial of the game,
you just walk around and there's some quicksave,
quicksave tutorials popping up all the way.
I think there are six in the first five minutes
of the game or something.
Because we realized it's important.
And the lesson that we learned from this was basically.
If this is part of the core of your game, you just embrace it.
Don't try to push it away, because this will always fail.
You cannot remove it from the core of your game.
It's the core.
So embrace it, and then people will love it more,
because you're being honest about what your game is.
And that quicksave reminder thing
got a lot of positive feedback from press and from players.
They were like, this is so cool.
I've never seen this before.
And it's such a simple thing.
We only did it because we at some point
realized that this is our game, and we have to do that.
So.
I am going to, like, in the beginning I was thinking about showing you something or making
questions, but because I talked so fast, I can do both.
So first, thank you.
You can reach me through these channels to chat or whatever.
I'm going to first show you something, and then if you have questions, we can do that.
This is gonna take some loading time,
but I hope it's worth it,
because I brought the old prototypes of Shadow Tactics.
So you're gonna see the moon.
No, no, no, this is gonna take a while,
so I'm just gonna talk.
So during development, we had three prototypes that,
oh, that's wrong, three prototypes that we made
that we sadly had to cut because, as I told you,
we couldn't barely finish the main game.
Oh, by the way, the performance is gonna be horrible
because my laptop isn't good, but it's not a problem.
Yeah, we had to sadly cut those DLCs.
This was the first idea that we had
for how you should enter the game
and everything would be on this map in a planning mode.
It's very ugly, of course, because this is alpha, right?
This is our alpha milestone.
Okay, let's see the moon. We had three DLCs, one of them was a ship DLC, whatever, then we had a
story DLC which was pretty awesome. The idea was that the characters get together in a tavern
and they drink and get drunk and they talk about stories of of missions they had and you sort of
have it a little bit like Bastion where you get back in time and you play and they talk over it.
And the twist idea behind that was that Mugen is talking about the easiest mission he ever had.
Where you play as Mugen all the time.
Wow, beautiful UI, right?
You play as Mugen all the time, but all the other characters sort of worked around him
and cleared that up, and you get to play both of those.
But this is the bigger DLC we had. It's the moon.
So the pitch behind the DLC was that...
Let's see... Yeah, there we go.
that space shogun is trying to sort of carve his face into the moon so you can always see
his face at night because he was very egocentric I guess.
And our characters didn't like that so they decided to take a spaceship and kick his ass
basically.
The big, like, we wanted the DLC from a business standpoint
to explain what the hell is going on here.
And we wanted a DLC that could make press.
Like, that was very crazy and where people were like,
oh, wow, like, if you release it a couple of months
after the game, they were like,
oh, I'm going to get back into Shadow Tactics.
They have the moon, right?
That was sort of the idea behind it.
And you can see it's very janky with the performance.
Then we had some ideas like what can you do in space?
We reversed gravity so you can only jump upwards
and have to take ladders to go down.
This was very bad.
We cut that from the, like we made two versions of this map
and we cut that in the second one
because it just wasn't intuitive
and it felt completely stupid.
And then we have like drones flying around.
You can see here making light.
So there was some cool stuff going on.
This is by the way, we had all the assets built for this,
they just weren't textured.
There's a lot of game designer, level designer art in this.
So in the center we have this huge shield
and there's this crane thing that they're using
to sort of laser the face of the Shogun.
You're basically in one of his eyeballs.
This is the huge crater that you're in.
You could kill him in two ways.
Either you could kill him by sort of luring him
beneath this laser and killing him there,
or you could go over there and kill him using drop pods
that you could call down,
and the alarm guards would come and drop pods.
There's a lot of cool stuff.
You can see I'm a bit sad that we didn't get to do this.
Yeah, just wanted to show you that
because I guess it's fun.
It never saw the day of light,
so maybe in the next game we'll do a moon DLC.
All right, thank you.
So if you have any questions, then you can ask me.
Hi, thanks.
Great talk.
I love the game.
So sort of a bonus question first.
As a big fan of the genre, are we
going to see a sequel maybe in a different setting,
like World War something?
But the main question is sadly about the business part a little bit, as a gamer who was waiting for the revival of the genre.
Because it seemed to me, I was aware of the game since its announcement, because I was hoping for it.
It seemed like initially the game got very little visibility, maybe from the publisher as well,
and sort of after a while became this cult hit that people knew was very good,
that it started selling, that's what at least the Steam Spy data seemed to suggest.
The community kind of exploded, people started talking about it,
so if you can share anything about that part, that would be interesting.
Sure. So regarding the first part, we actually, it's a small anecdote but we have time,
we went to Barcelona to visit Pyro, or at least Gonzo, who was sort of the director of the first
Commandos games, and he played Shadow Tactics and he loved it very much and that was very important
to us and we were very happy about it. But the Commandos IP is a very difficult IP to get,
so that is most likely not going to happen. And regarding the second question, so yeah,
We don't really, we're not good at marketing,
and marketing is hard, and you need a lot of money
or clever ideas, I guess, to do that.
And we knew that the game was very good,
and for some reason it didn't get traction very much.
We had a very early trailer, but it wasn't very good.
So that didn't do much.
And I think the biggest marketing asset that we
actually had was the demo.
Like we said, there's a free demo of the game.
And we released that one or two weeks before the game.
And that's when it sort of started to kick in.
But then it's a game that takes a while to play, takes a
while to get into.
So press would also, they didn't really release reviews
on the first day because we didn't send it to them early
enough, I guess.
Plus, there was things like The Last Guardian coming out
that some people might have been waiting for, or Final
Fantasy XV.
Small games.
They don't.
directly fight with our game, but still.
And so I guess that word to mouth was basically
the main thing that helped us then.
The game was good and then people talked about it.
You could always tell your friend that,
hey, there's a free demo, right?
You just, you don't have to buy it just because I tell you.
You can always get the demo and you can start playing.
And I think this is the biggest, best thing we did
for marketing that probably helped elevate the game
in the second and in the long run,
because they could just play it and you can try it.
One tip regarding demos.
If you're doing a demo for PS4,
be sure that it's a demo and not a trial.
They have this weird thing where if you make your game
and you can basically upgrade the game to the full version,
which we thought was pretty cool,
then you don't have to download it again or whatever.
It's a trial and it will not be visible in the demo section.
It will actually not be visible anywhere.
So don't do that.
Make it a demo, which might suck, but yeah.
Thanks.
So I lived in Japan for over 15 years and because of that I tend to be a little bit allergic to things, media, that portrays Japan from in the West, right?
And I've been really impressed with the game including like the voiceovers and all that and so I'm wondering how is it you got it so right?
I mean do you have somebody from Japan on the team or how did you do that?
Yeah, that was a big, big process.
We did not have anyone from Japan on the team,
but we had someone who studies Japanese culture from Munich.
We had him come over and check out the game
and give us mostly feedback on stuff
like the way they talk to each other or visual stuff,
like how much stone did they use
when they built their houses.
And we did a lot of research into that.
And it's not that easy because like it's way back
and then it's also Japan.
So you don't find as much here,
but we try to do a lot there.
One of the biggest.
topics of discussion we had for a long, long time was if wagons had two or four wheels
back then and how that was an ongoing thing.
Yeah, this is the level of detail you get down to at some point.
Yeah, it was tough and I'm glad that you say that we did it well,
because you never really know.
Because if you ask a Japanese person, they will tell you yes, but maybe not.
Because they're very polite.
And we are actually releasing it in Japan as well now,
so we're hoping to get some more feedback there regarding that topic.
So, great game, I think I'll finish it one day since it's pretty big, but hypothetically,
if you were to do a sequel, how would you handle the number of characters?
Because right now it seems that the number of characters is quite good for the challenges
that you have, and it seems that if you added new characters, you would have to add specific
challenges just for that new character to the formula.
So...
In what way would you look into expanding the features of the game,
like where it would be environment, enemy focused, or actually character focused?
So, we like the number of five characters,
so we will be sticking to five characters for our next game as well.
We are actually developing a game that is like Shadow Tactics right now,
so this is not a secret yet, but it's not Shadow Tactics 2 though.
It is a very difficult topic for us to see how we want to change the thing up and how we want to keep it that way
because we don't want to take away too much from what made the game great.
We also don't want it to feel like a simple copy-paste thing, and that is very hard to do.
So our current approach is that we have characters that are similar to the Shadow Tactics characters
and we have characters that are completely new, but it's still five characters.
So we had to take some of the stuff out that we had in Shadow Tactics.
We also try to do stuff with the environment, as you said.
This is, I can't really talk about the feature yet,
but it's pretty cool.
It's about how you navigate environment
and make the maps feel more real, like real places.
This was a big thing that we're trying to focus on
in the next one.
Hope it works.
Yeah.
Anyone else?
Yes.
Awesome talk, thanks.
Thanks.
Oh, that sounded weird.
I have two questions if that's cool.
One, so swimming seems extremely powerful.
Like, what are the sort of conversations
that led to it being that way?
Well, we had in the beginning, we had systems
where you could hold your breath
only for a certain amount of time.
And then we realized that this was very complicated
and weird because we had to make behavior
for the guards shooting into the water
and what they would do if they see you in the water
because they can't really react to that.
And then we decided, well, we just use the small things,
the straw things to bamboo for the ninjas
to breathe underwater.
It's very ninja and very cool, and just have infinite thing.
And the water is powerful, but we
try to use it clever and level design.
So we know that you can always get away through the water,
but it's balanced in a way that you will usually
take one hit from a guard before you get into the water.
So this was sort of a way of balancing that.
And secondly, what were the triggers
determine when the music changes?
Well, it's just rather simple environment triggers that we place in the environment
or level events when we say, okay, you have killed two of the four guards you have to
kill and we are adding new layers to the system.
We actually have some pretty cool audio stuff going on in the game.
For example, if you perform an action, like the tracks are very basic, but if you perform
an action with one of the characters, each of them has an instrument attached to them.
And if you sort of do something with Moogan,
you will have these Kodo drums playing something.
Whatever it is, if you do something with Hayato,
I don't know what his instrument is.
Yuki is a flute, obviously.
So you sort of, nobody realizes that it's in the game,
but you're sort of building the soundtrack
by playing the game through these stingers that we have.
And yeah, the audio guy, Philippu,
he's, shout out to Philippu, he's great.
And he did a great job on it, I think.
Thanks.
Thank you.
Okay.
Any more?
No.
Cool.
then thanks so much for coming out and think of doing the rating thing. This is my first
talk at GDC. I would be very happy if you guys rated. Thank you.