Hello.
Hello, everyone.
Welcome to the little dab of spice, of African spice,
to this whole conference.
It's only available here.
So good job on coming.
We, hello, I'm Ben, as he mentioned.
I do game design and marketing at Nyamakop,
a South African-based independent game studio,
which I co-founded with the very lovely and handsome man over here.
Hi, I'm Sugar.
I'm the business and technical side of Nyamakop.
Some say the one with more swag, but it's debatable.
It's hurtful.
We released our debut game, Semblance, in July 2018.
Sugar and I founded the studio straight out of university
with no real-world work experience.
in games or otherwise.
It's a puzzle platformer where the world is made of Play-Doh,
as you can see, and when we're feeling bold,
which is often, we call it the first true platformer.
Because you can move the platforms.
We have a very long linguistic spiel joke.
Lots of journalists have heard it.
I'm not going to enact that on you.
So this talk kind of centers around the idea
of breaking into indie games in 2019.
When we started making Semblance, it was, I guess, our goal to break in, right?
At the beginning, we had assumptions and internalized ideas about what it was like to make games.
And this was drawn mainly from public perception and cultures surrounding independent games.
Those assumptions were often wrong, and following them blindly would have left us in a...
a very bad place and probably wouldn't be able to do this talk right now.
So we wanted to give this talk, sharing our journey into indie games from South Africa
and how we made decisions to be able to make more than one game, pretty much.
And hopefully this talk can be used by first-time creators to get insight into what it's like
to try to break into indie games in 2019 and also help fellow African creators trying to
do the same.
So here are some of the assumptions we had when we started making Semblance.
We were going to build this huge fan base.
We were going to get great preview coverage,
get selected for awards and exhibitions,
get a publisher, get big YouTubers playing our game,
and just sit back.
And then our amazing work be found.
And on release, amazing reviews, tons of money,
and recoup in the first month or week.
It was going to be great.
It was going to be beautiful.
Let's look at how we did.
So we had
copious and high quality preview coverage from media outlets
during development, including all these ones
and various others.
The game was selected for one to two dozen exhibitions
all over the world during development,
including places like South by Southwest, The Maze,
and PAX East.
We won some awards, the Excellence in Game Design
Award at BitSummit, and were nominated
for various others over the years.
Also when we accepted awards, people
stared at Sugar's biceps.
He's wearing long sleeves today.
Thank you for your sacrifice, Sugar.
Thank you.
We also signed with a lovely publisher,
Good Shepherd Entertainment.
They helped us go from this tiny mini booth
at PAX East 2017 on the left
to this giant branded semblance booth
with branded stress balls and beanbags at PAX East 2018.
Generally, they just helped the quality production
go up a lot.
And then our game got featured by Nintendo twice
and upon launch, we became the first African-developed IP
to ever release on Nintendo platform.
So that was cool.
When we shipped, this is a live stream of our tweet deck
during the launch hours.
It was a lot of activity.
And reviews, our reviews were pretty good.
We're currently ranked as the 68th best PC game
of 2018 on Metacritic.
and I have no idea how they worked this out,
but the 32nd most shared Switch game of 2018.
We had a million social media impressions
during our launch month.
We were new and trending in Steam.
We had about 14 million impressions up until now
on our Steam page and a few hundred thousand visits.
We had no Nintendo launch feature though.
And games as a service really sucks.
We announced four weeks before we were gonna launch.
This is when we're launching.
And a week before, this game, No Man's Sky, was like, yo,
we're coming back.
And the big update that changed that game's legacy
launched the same day, same time as us.
And also some small indie games you probably haven't heard
of, Fortnite and GTA 5 Online, they updated their game
as well, that was pretty minor.
And now the sales, how did Semblance do sales-wise?
Wow, listen to that silence in the room.
Everyone's having flashbacks.
Indie games are dead.
So PC, a few thousand users on Steam.
After all that, on Switch, it's better.
Not a whole lot better, a multiple better.
And we did not get rich.
We have not yet recouped.
It's very sad.
And in case you're not familiar with published models, no
recoup means no semblance of sales money has come to us
yet.
We don't see Semblance is dead, though.
It's less than a year since the game has been released.
We have a couple tens of thousands wishlists on Steam
still, and we're working with our publisher
to look at other deals and avenues for the game
to recoup in the future.
But, I mean, obviously, the game didn't sell.
Like, how are we still alive?
How is it possible?
And we're still here working on projects.
And like, Semblance could have been a game that
could have been better in a swathe of ways.
You can look back at any game you launch and like,
ah, could have been better this way.
It was so better if we did this,
all those sort of things, right?
It's like hard to retrospectively do that.
But what you can definitely do
is try and leverage your development time
in perhaps lateral ways to ensure
you can continue making games,
which is what we want to talk about today.
And we say lateral because these goals and decisions
might not necessarily help your debut game perform better.
Sometimes you might even conflict with that.
it might enable you to make another game.
And sometimes those actual goals will help you
with your current game.
I always like to say, quite cynically,
the best creative integrity is being
able to make another game.
For more experienced folks, some of this process
will be old hat.
But for debut creators like us, we
have to learn a lot of it and actively decide to pursue it.
So we think it's crucial for.
particularly new creators looking to make their first commercial indie game to understand some of this stuff.
And really, like I mentioned earlier, we came across this because the writing's on the wall.
It's hard to avoid all this news and social media stuff about games.
Great ones not always selling well.
And we also saw from researching and talking to people
that debut games, newcomer debut games, rarely do well.
And by newcomer we mean here people
who have no real world experience, work experience.
Debut games by people from other industries
who come into games perform better.
But if you look at games that have come out
and done well from debut, it's like one a year,
maybe two a year.
Your Diane Wells in 2015, Events Zero in 2016,
The Haunted Island, Frog Detective Game in 2018,
and Sardau Valley.
which kind of destroys this whole metaphor.
But it's fine.
Yeah.
But it is very rare that debut games do well.
It's just how it is.
And so what we want to do is look at the lateral pillars
of breaking in.
And these are what they are.
You've got to be ready to succeed, prepared to fail.
You've got to redefine your metrics of success.
You have to have a long-term vision.
You have to be visible, be reputable.
You have to learn and apply it rapidly.
And you have to carve a contextual.
And now, Sugar, will take you through the timeline
of Semblance development and how we implemented
those lateral pillars.
Yeah.
So like Ben said, we had a few lateral pillars
that we used throughout development
to kind of guide the way we were making decisions
and how we were going to break into the industry.
Semnus really started in 2015, and it started as a university
project that quickly turned into a commercial
entity and company.
And at the time, the game looked like this.
The date in the GIF is wrong.
But the game looked like this at the time.
And when we were presenting the game at university, one of
our external examiners, after the presentation, turns to us
and says, hey.
The game looks kind of interesting.
Why don't you guys make it into a commercial project?
And at that time, that external examiner
was an ex-Naughty Dog developer, Judd Samanthoff,
who worked on some of the titles like The Last of Us.
So we thought it was a pretty good sign
to just go ahead and work on this thing as a real thing.
It was always our dreams to be indie developers as well.
So we put the project on ice, took it out of university,
and kind of finished doing university through 2015.
And even as early as then, we knew
one of the first things we needed to do
was to learn about the industry, learn about how
to make commercial games.
We read everything we could find on Gamasutra,
watched YouTube videos from GDC, and tried
to apply those learnings as quickly as possible.
And later through the development, we also wanted to be,
we got access into sharing communities
like the Indie Megabooth mailing list
and part of the Indie Games residency program, Stoogan.
And so learning was always a very important part
of our journey.
come in 2016 and now we got, we finished university
and we're ready to jump into the project,
really hit the road running.
But we were trying to build a game,
form a team with no dollar, no cash money.
And the way it kind of looks from our perspective in South
Africa is that we can't even look at things like Kickstarter.
We can't run a Kickstarter because you
have to have a bank account that's not from South Africa.
So that's off the table.
The government, not quite sure what
video games are at the moment.
At that time, though, they know it makes a lot of money,
but yeah, it's whatever.
In fact, to submit your game for ratings by South Africa,
you have to turn it in by VHS.
because it's under movies.
So it's a bit, it's a tricky situation there.
And local investors into the game space,
a few and far between.
So that was always a tricky thing.
And because of no money to fund the team,
and you know, as kids growing up,
we couldn't really, there were in.
mismatch of commitment levels within the team,
and that caused the game to not really develop that much
haphazardly throughout 2016.
But we kept going forward,
and in mid of 2016,
we found the deformation mechanic.
And this was kind of what was making the game interesting,
because up until then,
it was about a character changing shape and size.
And so we continued developing, the art style got a bit better,
but the funding situation was still keeping us back.
So towards the end of 2016, we decided,
hey, let's scrounge up a few pennies from under the couch
and fund an artist to help us create
the visual style of the game.
that it is sort of today.
And the idea was so that we could
use that little bit of money and then pitch it to a publisher,
and all our problems would be solved.
But at that time, since all the publishers
we could get a hold of, everyone was like.
Yeah, the mechanic's cool, but it's just not there yet.
In fact, one of the publishers even came back to us and said,
this looks like art of a student project.
That's ironic, because we had just paid an artist
to work on the game.
But we kept working on it.
made a little plan and we found one of those rare local investors to give us a bit of money
to make this game.
And at the time it was still small dreams to just release on itch, but we kept working
on it with a bit more money and got an artist on board full time.
And so like with these lateral pillars as well, we try to use them in a way to inform
production and design decisions as well.
like semblance that are forming terrain mechanic is very deep.
There's like a lot you can do with it.
But we decided to like rather than make like,
you know, a five-year project very in vogue with indie games,
we decided to cut a lot of features
like this beautiful jiggly pink platform.
I miss it so much. It's so bouncy.
Like and a lot of games do this, right?
But we were very aggressive about the scope,
like cutting features and ideas
and really making it as small as we possibly could.
And this helped also with funding, because two inexperienced kids from Africa, it seems
like a Nigerian hack email being like, please give us this money.
It's ridiculous.
But with the cost of living in South Africa being way cheaper than other parts of the
world and us having a very small-scoped game, it was way easier for a publisher or investor
to be like, OK, the risk-reward is quite good here.
And then we spent a lot of time making sure the game just
like stood out really well.
And this was active in terms of the long-term vision.
We literally looked through Steam and all these places
and were like, what colors aren't people using?
There was a lot of brown.
Triple A games do like brown.
Yeah. So we were like, let's do pink and purple.
Yeah. It sounds banal, but it was a real decision we made.
And it helps it stand out.
And then like Sugar said, like finding
that interesting mechanic of the deforming terrain.
Here's another one.
And then in 2017, there's two parts to 2017.
The first is when we're still self-publishing.
At this point, our goal was to go everywhere
and gain international exposure.
We paid ourselves in exposure, it's true.
And this pillar and this part was be visible
and be reputable.
In terms of the African perspective,
the market is quite big.
Like, people in Africa spend money on video games,
but the amount that goes to local creators is...
like so small. So it's very hard to survive selling directly to the African
market at the moment. So as a result, you have to sell to the West, which means
you have to travel to find that market. You have to make sure to meet journalists
and publishers and funders and platform holders and other developers in the West
because very few of them have representatives on like the continent.
It's almost a billion people, but they're like, it's fine.
You don't. That's not important.
And it's not easy to travel because of visas, how long it takes, money.
Travel is far and eats into development time.
And for us, we still made that decision to be seen and to be known.
Doing talks like right now, being at events, being on Twitter, just
taking up a little bit of mind share so that people knew about us.
Submitting to like exhibitions and awards all the time.
We actively try to make people know about us.
And a lot of this was, you know, gaining a reputation and prestige so that we could.
point to stuff in future to prove you weren't just two inexperienced African kids out of
university you should give money to, which you still are.
But instead, we can now say we're also award-winning game developers of the top 100 Metacritic
video game.
And those things might not necessarily have made the game sell better, but they helped
us in future with the reputation.
And so as part of this, thanks to Train Jam's scholarship, we went to our first GDC in 2017,
which is where we pitched Nintendo in the corner of a park.
with the sun out, I'd use my body to shield it.
I don't think you can even see the video,
he was like, yeah, it's fine.
And then right after this, we went to PAX, met Xbox,
and this was really the first time
we'd ever really been able to meet platform holders
because there was no other way to meet them.
And at PAX East, we met Press, got covered,
and met a bunch of publishers as well.
And what this really comes down to
in terms of being visible and reputable
is shooting your shots.
You just gotta take the opportunities
and make things happen.
When you're traveling from Saigon, it takes 24 hours on a plane to get to San Francisco
or Los Angeles, so you're not just going to sit back and hope for the best.
You're going to go out and get it.
This is really typified, I think, by this GIF.
This is me at E3 2018, an official Devolver Digital marketing material about to almost
kiss Nigel Lurie, one of the important people at Devolver Digital.
We were in the middle of a meeting pitching Semblance, and it was like, okay, this is
But it really, like this is what you have to do.
Like, it's really hard to get press at events, right?
Because you just, some like no name.
I probably shouldn't have just let this loop,
but I have nothing else to show you on the slide, I'm sorry.
Like, if you're going to, you can't book press at events
because no one's ever heard of you.
So you see that like blaring yellow marker on their badge
saying press, you just walk up to them
and try to get them to come play your game.
And you send those emails that might never get responses.
You just walk up to people.
And what we did as well is just submit
to everything we could find.
Like every Google form we could find, we submitted.
I have some beautiful rejection letters.
I just store them all.
There's like dozens of them.
It's lovely.
And then stuff like.
the first true platformer as well, it's like so ridiculous,
but no one's ever going to forget the time someone told them
they were making the first true platformer.
And it was quite intense.
We did 25 cities in five continents in 18 months,
and at one point we did four continents in four weeks.
Like, this is really the scale of how aggressively we chased this idea.
And, you know, stuff that's people have spoken about before,
like sharing development.
on Twitter. And for us, this was actually about reaching developers and press and platforms,
not even necessarily players, because you could talk to them and be like, oh yeah, I
saw this game on Twitter. This is like a really ugly gif of the game, but got an interesting
mechanic and I got a few hundred retweets. And it's also just like interacting people
with a personal level on Twitter. I had this like really ridiculous semi-viral tweet about
me looking in pain, looking at someone play our game. And I booked, we booked press off
this tweet. Like someone from GamesRadar quote tweeted and I was like.
I've always wondered if game developers did this.
And then he ended up covering the game at PAX East,
and at launch he wrote this really long thing,
all because I tweeted this random thing
and interacted with him.
And part two is the publisher, which is Sugar's.
So.
At this point in the production, we
knew that we had something special on our hands.
And we continued to keep traveling.
But now this time, we were trying to actively get
a publisher on board.
We traveled to places, Gamescom, E3, went back to studio.
And all this time while we were making this game,
because we were half running out of money,
half trying to get a publisher.
The game was ready to ship like every six months.
We were always demo ready.
That's why we could submit to many festivals and exhibitions.
And that is how we ended up with a game starting
to look like this.
It's a lot prettier.
And some of those publishers that
said no to us in the beginning were like, hey, what's up?
Game's looking good.
So we started actively looking and discussing
with several publishers about what it would mean
for them to jump on board.
And for us, this was important because it
was one of our pillars is we wanted to have the publisher
so we were ready to succeed.
But as we knew the writing on the wall,
we were also preparing in that unfortunate eventuality
that we may fail.
And that was the way we went about doing that was we got ourselves a publisher,
and because we had the publisher and the visibility, we were now at a position
where we could talk to the government in South Africa and help us get a grant.
And that was going to help us, tide us through, if anything happened.
And then we went as far as even just saying that we were going to pay ourselves a lot
lower so that just in case things don't go well, we were in a position where we could
still be working on things going forward.
And this was just one of the ways that we were making sure we were thinking about development
that we were going to be able to keep going.
Another thing was to make sure that we carved ourselves
a contextual path in this indie game market.
And you get a lot of.
Knowledge from GDC and all these places, but we felt that a lot of that knowledge is from a Western perspective
So we wanted to take it in turn and make it a way
We looked at it from South Africa one of the biggest things that you might hear is that
All going to shows going to things like Pax is may not be the greatest thing to do
But for us even with it being a large much
bigger investment, we felt that was important because that gave us that access to people
that we would have never been able to.
And I think things like that is what happens when you become more visible and you go out
there.
And that even helped for people to know more about South Africa and we were able to hold
something like Africa Games Week last year and then keep bringing more people to know
about the ecosystem in South Africa so that we're also building the local industry that
will in turn help us going forward.
And 2018 launch year, we're excited, we've got the publisher and things are going well.
And we launched, we were getting ready to launch Semblance, but we're still always dealing
with uniquely South African issues.
I know for you, you know that we launched on Nintendo Switch and
For going through consoles, you need to go through certification.
And certification will take a long time sometimes.
But you also need to submit the game as early as possible.
And I know we were kind of leaving it to the last minute,
but the day I was meant to be uploading the game to Nintendo,
power disappears.
And then this is something that's common,
it's even happening right now, it's called load shedding,
where they turn off the power for a select number of hours
until you get power again.
So I had to explain to our publishers,
yeah, I can't really do anything, there's just no power.
So those are kind of those issues that we kind of deal with,
but we eventually got it on Nintendo and got it certified.
And so one of the big things also is while we were making the game,
we wanted to have a different way of thinking about success.
So we didn't want it to be purely about sales and whether you made money.
And for us, we redefined those metrics of success by
Can we make a name for ourselves for our debut title?
Can we make sure that we're not just trying to make one game,
we're trying to make lots of games?
And that's what made some of the decisions.
Like, the most important thing was to ship a game
so that we could get to the next one.
And that's kind of how we were able to say that Semblance
was a successful launch for us.
And that's how we felt that it was going to be going forward.
And one of the next pillars is having a long-term vision.
And we felt that.
We're not just building one game.
We're going to build the next game, and the next game,
and the next game.
So everything was about a long-term vision.
And how we looked about making decisions today
were going to be in turn to help us tomorrow.
And those were things like making sure
that the game was well-received, and so
that when we went back to publishers for a second time
with a new game, we could always point back to being like, hey,
we managed to ship a game.
And so that was what kept us going with a long-term vision.
And even now, that's how we keep thinking about making
games and how we can keep making the next game.
So as we come to a slow end.
As a result.
Yeah, thank you.
As a result of this.
In spite of those sales, we have broken in now and primed to break out.
And what we mean by that is, you know, we've made a game, we've finished, people can tell
we're doing that, and we've set ourselves up for success in future.
And that's a result of Semblance not making any profit yet, right?
So while our and perhaps many other first-time creators' similar assumptions might have been
met with the launch of Semblance, our investment in this lateral process and goals has enabled
us to continue making games.
and our own studio.
And just like details like that,
me and Shugo have still been fully employed
since July 2018 with like a bunch of money
to use for prototypes and contractors.
We're pitching a new project here at GDC,
and it's been easier to get meetings,
and we're also looking at other funding avenues.
And like I said, we're primed for the future.
We're more informed, more connected,
and more reputable as well.
And someone let us do a solo GDC talk.
This process is still ongoing though, so ask us in six months if it all worked.
Hopefully it will.
And so just to summarize those processes is, you know, be ready to succeed but also prepared
to fail in case, sadly, it might happen.
Redefine your metrics of success.
Don't necessarily just think it's always about, like, sales.
Have that long-term vision.
Best creative integrity is being able to make another game.
Be visible, be reputable so that you can have something to point to and people know of you for the future.
Learn a lot and make decisions so you can apply that learning quickly.
You can't apply things you learnt on the first game if your first game takes 5 to 10 years.
And also just carve that contextual path.
And part of that is just remembering all advice is bad, including this.
And the reason it's bad is because it's not...
It's not contextual.
It doesn't apply to your context, right?
And because of that, you need to go out and get as much
advice as possible so that you can decide
which advice is good.
You can fail with it, experiment, and see what
really works for you.
And so thank you for listening to us talk.
So we've got like five minutes for questions.
Are you fine with questions?
Yeah, I think I'm good.
OK, cool.
Does anyone have any questions?
I think there's a mic somewhere.
Oh, thank god.
It's always awkward when you're like, does anyone have any questions?
And you wait like two minutes and then no one asks anything.
So I'm curious from when you guys decided to move into a commercial build,
how much longer it took than what you initially estimated?
And then how much of that was just inherent to the development process that you hadn't
learned about and how much of it was things you wish you could have done differently if
you did it again.
Well, I think, in fact, when we started the project,
we were like, yeah, we're going to just do,
it was always going to be our starter project,
like, oh, we'll do six to eight months,
you know, and get it on itch,
and then we'll get to the real game.
So when we started, we had a bit of ups and downs.
And so some of it was based on things
like we just didn't know about making video games,
like things take extra long.
But another thing that made it longer
was because we were doing things like trying to get a publisher,
going to events.
Sometimes no one would be working
on the game for two weeks.
And so development wasn't as straight cut as possible.
We still think the game was built technically in 18 months.
But even though the lifespan was three years,
because there were years with barely any work on them.
I don't know if that answers the question.
Hi.
Could you guys maybe paint me a quick picture of what the
game development scene is like in South Africa?
Because I have no idea.
It's super curious to me.
I think the total number of workers is around
700 at the moment.
So it's a very small scene, but we've had some very big
successes.
The most American game ever made, Broforce, is from South
Africa, also a penis sports game.
which was nominated for a narrative award this year at the IGF,
Jennifer Jousling. I didn't make the rules.
Stuff like Viscera Cleanup Detail,
which is a game about cleaning up after sci-fi massacres.
So we have a bunch of successful games for a very tiny community.
You might know of Amaze Berlin, which is this big independent
games festival in Berlin.
And for the last five, six years, we've had a Johannesburg
version, which has helped us connect to the international
community quite a lot.
So it's quite small, but for the impact it has, it's quite
cool.
I can send you blogs and articles.
It's a lot.
Are you leaving?
Hi.
So one thing you guys mentioned is that when you first
launched, you were kind of going up against a lot of
AAA games, a lot of really big games.
So I guess my question is, what can we do as consumers to
kind of support developers like you guys more?
It shows lots of things, but yeah.
Yeah, I don't know, man.
It's hard.
I mean, you kind of saw all the metrics we had.
We had a million social media impressions at launch.
We had a lot of metrics which, on paper,
showed that the game could sell and would sell.
So I don't know.
As a consumer, I don't know.
Stop playing Fortnite.
You and all the streamers.
It's just like, they only play Fortnite.
So yeah, I don't know.
It's just the whole ecosystem.
It's systemic, I think.
I wish I knew so I could tell you to do it and force you and follow up every six months
to make sure you're doing it.
But I don't.
Yeah.
Sorry.
No problem.
Thanks.
Hey fellas, great work. Question, how much money has been spent up to this point?
Is there a crazy number?
On the game?
Yeah, it's been a few years now.
I think we might be on the NDA with our publisher deals.
Oh really?
Exact amount, yeah.
Is that curated?
It's like a few hundred thousand.
A few hundred thousand?
Yeah.
But it's really hard to tell as well because of...
The way it was developed, like Sugar said,
like it's 18 months was the real realistic full time
development, and that happened over like three years.
So it's also like real amount, like if we paid ourselves
fully, how much would it have cost?
It's really hard.
Yeah, like the first year we were both living
with our parents.
So there was no cost then technically,
but there was like time that you spent in it.
So if you were to calculate that, yeah,
it's definitely hundreds.
Cool, no more questions.
Cool, all right.
Thanks for coming.