Hi everyone, my name is Vladimir and I'm here to give you my talk called Aesthetic Driven Development
or basically how we started making an art before we made a game,
how it worked out for us and how you can do the same.
So before we actually proceed, I wanted to give you some background information on who I am,
or rather who we are.
I run a studio of two people called Cold Wild Games.
It is located in Riga, Latvia, and my partner Helen, she does art and writing.
and I do pretty much everything else.
Occasionally we hire freelancers to do the music for us.
We've been making games since 2016
and we also own a pair of cockatiels
or weerobirds for our Australian friends.
The cage is a metaphor for us working from home
even though they leave it much more often than we do.
And all further images and tweets in this presentation
were made by...
Helen, that's her Twitter handle there below.
Anyway, so to give a bit more background, before 2019s the game development processes
for us was rather straightforward.
We would build a prototype that we enjoyed playing, then we would start figuring out
the graphics, essentially it turned out into the game.
We've made three more or less serious games up to this point.
they had a very moderate success. For what it's worth our most successful game called Lazy Galaxy
has achieved 6 000 sales over two years and I suppose some of you who might be watching this
presentation they might cry over those numbers and that's all right actually. I still think
it's not it would not be enough to maintain the studio, sustain the studio by itself. So
the move was to change the approach.
And one of the things that we did in 2019,
rather than start building a prototype
with gameplay in mind,
we focused on aesthetics and art first
and found out what our audience liked.
And to fast forward a bit, the game has sold around 10,000 copies in 7 months, so the real
bankruptcy that is threatening us is the moral bankruptcy probably, and the only one so far.
So I actually believe this happened because we focused on creating the attractive art
first, before we actually began making the game.
And in this talk, I'll try to outline the process and approach of how we did it and how you can systematically try to do the same.
Right, so first of all, in 2018, while I was porting the game, our previous game, to consoles, Helen did not have much to do.
And I just essentially told her to draw in the...
Octobit trend which started in October which basically involved environment as a subject and
each daily image would require an artist to draw a
painting using
more colors than before. So there was a color limit, there was also a time constraint on one day
to make an evening, to make a posting and for most days she tried to post it on one time,
at one similar time, it was in the evenings, so that both European and American audiences would
see it. But since I treat the games as an art more than a business, but at the same time
I don't want to dry of hunger, I decided to approach this whole thing as an experiment
to see where it leads to us.
The idea is to make something that everybody likes, us and people who would play our games,
and then to see if the game can materialize.
Right.
So after this, if we treat it as an experiment, we need some sort of a criteria to evaluate
the results.
I think we've created, well I've created, four different things that I want to evaluate the games, the art with.
First of all, I think we both of us need to like something that has been created, because as a studio of two people, it makes sense that both of us would like working on something together.
and I think for the smaller indie studios it's much easier to come to an agreement and to find
something that everyone in team is passionate about. Afterwards we would look at the response
on Twitter. How has the image been perceived? At every slide I will try to give the amount of likes,
retweets and comments about user reaction and how they would like the image or not.
Overall...
the ease of creation also matters,
because if you think about it, we're a two people team,
so we would need a way to make hundreds of assets together,
either to establish a soulless asset production container,
or just to include our limitation
to create the quality games.
Pick whichever you like out of these two.
So we really wanted to have a chance to create the art that looks decent but would not take
so much effort that we'd never publish a game. Afterwards we would also consider the game design
constraints because even if the image is created it kind of implies the style of the game that you
can come up with and not images are equally appropriate for different game types. And we
don't like all the genres so...
We have those four things, but what are the baselines?
I think it's hard to measure liking or disliking images by themselves, so...
To take it as a baseline, our usual game-related tweets had maybe under 20 likes, 1 or 2 comments,
mostly from our friends, thank you, and 1 to 5 retweets.
And I wish I'd say I was cherry-picking those ones here, but to be honest, this is what
the usual tweets look like.
I kind of like them, but I'm the biased guy here.
So the idea is we would look for everything that is better than that at the time.
Helen had roughly 500 followers at the start of the experiment and close to 1000 or a bit
more at the end of it.
So how did it go?
I'll try to give some descriptions of the images that turned out and why they did or
did not work out.
And for example, let's start with this one.
I call this the forest hut.
Let me move myself here.
So this is the forest hut, and I think both of us
like this one.
The response was also pretty good,
with 72 likes and 12 retweets.
But if you think about it, it's not easy
to create something like this.
First of all, this is an isometric perspective,
and pixel art is kind of harder with isometric perspective.
And plus the amount of details here is a bit,
well, that's a lot of detail, to be honest.
So even though we could imagine it being a part of some tactical RPG game,
it's ultimately a pass for us because we would not be able to afford to create a game like this.
Everyone's situation is different, but this is how I would evaluate it.
Then we had a stork and personally I'm a huge fan of the birds. I think Helen likes birds too.
And the stork had a good amount of likes and retweets, but again this color palette was...
it was kind of tricky to make it right.
But even then, the resolution is lower than the previous images, but what kind of game do you imagine with this asset?
Maybe it would be a decent puzzle game, but it's not really our genre and who makes non-erotic puzzle games in 2020, so that's an all.
Next, the market.
So, we liked it and I personally really liked the vibrant colors and overall it just seemed
aesthetically pleasing to look at, plus it was not very hard to make, but what killed
this one was the amount of attention, because only 33 likes and 1 retweet comparing to what
we've been getting before was clearly not enough for us to actually consider it as a
possible game art, even though both of us liked it.
Next are the ruins and I personally did not like it that much, so opinions were different,
but it had a lot of attention, but then again on the other side I don't think it would be easy
to create this because of the higher resolution and the amount of detail. So that's a pass.
In the end of the experiment we had a few images that would fit as the game sprites
and I wanted to go through some of those concepts just to show the way how I think.
First of all, two of them are isometric, which as you might have guessed from before is a
point of skepticism for me, but I'm not against isometric images per se.
If we look at the windmill on the left,
or is it watermill?
Yeah, this is the watermill.
If we look at the watermill on the left,
it still looks kind of generic, despite the good reply,
and you would probably not remember looking at it.
The waterfall is a bit more appealing,
but again, it's hard to imagine the type of game
that I would put it into.
On the other hand...
Why we like the temple? There are a few reasons for that.
First of all, the temple offers the unique style and for the artists who only start to do something like this,
for us, we are really struggling with the style for our games because
sometimes you feel like you can draw but it's not really memorable enough or distinguishable enough and...
Finding the right style for the artist is the real struggle.
And we still haven't figured it out in the end,
but it felt like the right step in the right direction.
Plus, if you think about it,
the temple consists of small, replicable geometric shapes
that you can use for other types of buildings or the world.
So ultimately, I think in this case,
the temple was a goal for these reasons.
So, we liked the floating temple and what do we do next?
For me, I don't feel comfortable diving
into the project right away.
And I think it makes sense to do some more
experimentations without huge commitment.
And for us, the logical step would be to take idea further.
And Helen spent a few hours to just draw
how the trees of this world would look like.
And she put it on Twitter again with more relevant tags like pixelart and gamedev at that point
and it still got a pretty decent response, very decent for us, 105 likes. That kind of validated
the idea and served as a positive sign to show us that we may need to pursue the idea further.
The next and somewhat a final step before creating the actual prototype for us
is to commit even more of our time and resources into this.
Helen drew ships and some more potential islands, how they would look in the game.
We combined them into small sequences of presumably gameplay gifs or concept art.
Let me move myself.
And every one of them.
had quite a bit of attention.
I mostly made those GIFs on my Saturdays and Sundays
and posted them on Screenshot Saturday
just to see how people responded,
and response was quite well.
In total, we spent roughly two months
for this whole process.
It was 25 workdays before,
between drawing and choosing,
then roughly 15 part-time days
to validating our idea further with those GIFs.
And,
I think overall those 40 days is a bit more than 25% of the time that we spent on the
project together before the Early Access launch.
I think I treated it as an investment and you should too if you do something like this
because it allowed us to find the audience for the project before we actually started
to work on it.
In the end, it just allows us to work on something that both we and audiences want.
Of course, if you can afford it, expanding this window of finding art is definitely worth it, I think.
Because this can be beneficial and open more options to you.
Of course, you still need some constraints to stay focused, because, for example, I don't
think I would do it more than 3 months in advance, because there should be like this
stop sign and point where you decide, I like this art and we should give it a go.
Anyway, so we have the art and it becomes clear that audience really likes this style and want more.
So, what actually happens with the game?
And I think at this point you really need to acknowledge the potential art style effects on the gameplay right from the start.
Because in our case, like you see this horizontal building overlay and display.
I was maybe thinking of something like Kingdom at the start, but I wanted to make a more complex building chains
And it becomes clear that you cannot have a lot of those buildings on screen at the same time
so
you cannot put a very complex production chain into the game
with limited screen space because then player would need to scroll around the
screen a lot
and it definitely affects the gameplay experience and user experience and
I was against it. If you think about, we also wanted to create it
as a non-violent game, just our preference, but if you
consider the...
combat based game prototype, then 2D combat, even if it is a strategic game, can become quite limited.
So, overall, I think hitting the right notes with art might seem like a treasure, but
if you can find the gameplay ideas with it, if we would not be able to find the fun gameplay ideas with it, we would not continue it.
But, limiting the amount of buildings to 6 or 7 per screen
did wonders for us because that allowed us to look for other options.
So the constraint is what game would you make if you had six or seven buildings
on the screen or on the level at the same time?
And I think it contributed to the next step for us.
So we can't have many islands, those small isles on one screen,
and but we still want some sort of a management game.
What do we do?
In our case we added this map as a sort of a glue to connect the islands together and
it really added this exploration aspect into the game which made the map exploration and
trading way more fun because players would be able to find different spots on the map
with different prices on the goods and then sell them or buy them in a profitable manner.
The map with free movement also allows us to add more quests or just more memorable
islands that would not serve a lot of the gameplay purpose but more of an experience
purpose because we want players to experience the game.
So overall I think this glue worked because of the constraints that we've set first from
the art style and then from our own artificial constraints based on this island amount per screen
and I realize that if you look at this presentation you might think wow this has been easy like
You can figure those things out and maybe you are right, but for us it was a real struggle to come up with something that is both pretty and playable,
because I don't want to take away the fun from the gameplay, but it sometimes is still very hard to come up with something potentially fun for other players.
Anyway, so you have something that people like and what happens next?
For us, since it became clear that audience likes what we are doing, we've tried to
capitalize on those pretty graphics and we've created the Steam page, I think, two or...
two and a half months after we started actively developing the game.
At this stage we just made a simple 30-second trailer from all of the features that we had
in the game at that point, rather in the prototype, and there were five screenshots.
The point was to start gathering wishlists.
So we published the Steam page and as soon as we had something new, we would post it
on Twitter and update the Steam page with screenshots.
Thus, it would lead people to wishlist the game or just get us more attention of the
game.
Another vital point for me was the remake of trailers.
The first trailer was really very simple, but then, as time progressed, I was updating
the trailers, re-uploading them, re-announcing them and it also gave us a bit more media
If I can say the word media, mostly it's people were retweeting it or just looking
at on YouTube.
So I think the innovations were a good thing.
On the downside, I think we had some of the complaints that on game launch was that people
have seen everything on our Twitter before they've launched the game.
But it was the minority and actually that's a valid argument and we've tried to be more
secretive about our development later on.
So we have a Steam page with directed audiences from Twitter, from Screenshot Saturday, from Pixelart tags to our game.
And also the Weather Factory studio helped quite a lot with their Twitter exposure.
So in the end when the game was nearing its launch, we had roughly 5,000 wishlists in 5 months and we launched the game in Early Access.
What happens then? The results were quite good because we had close to 6,000 sales in the first two months.
It hit 10,000 sales by January 2020.
So we also got covered by some bigger youtubers, which I've never dreamed to be covered by and
our community has doubled in size, which sounds way cooler than it is. It was
150 more people who we all like.
And
I didn't run any paid marketing, maybe...
No, I've run some ads on Facebook and on Reddit.
Overall it was under $20 total.
So I mostly relied on organic marketing.
I think having a pretty style allowed for this
because otherwise it never worked for us before
in the same manner.
So you might be thinking about it
and feeling like we've shot in the dark.
hoping that we would hit something.
And you might be true.
So these are not tested suggestions or improvements
how I would try to adjust the process if I do it again,
when I do it again, rather.
So.
First of all, I think setting art constraints would make more sense, for example, if you
ask your artist to only draw RTS units, or if you're talking about pixel art, you might
also set the resolution, maybe don't make sprites more than 64x64, and I'm still stretching
it, that's too much actually, but yeah, it's really up to you.
Also as I mentioned before, the longer experimentation would probably mean a bigger pool of potentially
successful results, but it also implies higher costs for you.
The other thing that was mentioned by me in the beginning,
I think it was the Kickstarter, just to validate your idea, but now if you ask me,
I never had a chance to run a Kickstarter from Latvia, but if you ask me, I think Kickstarter
should be launched together with the Steam page, together with Lists, so Kickstarter is still the
next step, a bit further after you've validated your idea.
Maybe if you want to have a cleaner result, avoid tagging popular accounts like Pixel
Dailies, because every tweet by them would mean a netflux of likes, but it would also skew your
data and statistics in not so favorable manner. So you would not be able to make a good decision.
Also, the last slide is viewer discretion.
I was thinking maybe I should put it on the first one,
but I think it makes sense if I talk about it in the end,
when you know all the context.
So after I posted something similar on Reddit,
there was a comment that I'm the manager type
who don't know much, and then I complained to my friend,
and then my friend said that it makes sense.
And I actually agree with it now,
because essentially what I'm trying to present to you
is the sample size of one, which worked for us,
and the.
What is the guarantee that it's going to work again?
Nonetheless, here are some of my arguments
which I would use to counter this argument.
First of all, we've made a few games before
that did not use this process
and it did not work out as well for us.
This is somewhat different than just drawing concept art
because...
With concept art you know what you are drawing, essentially.
You know the ideas that you are going to have in your game.
Here you just draw something and hoping that it would fit the game.
But it's not necessarily a bad thing.
At least not for us, if you want to approach it in a more artistic way.
Also I think David Wheel, I hope I pronounced your surname correctly, but in GDC 2019 he
had a good presentation where he also focused on marketing using visual aesthetics of the
game and I think it really worked for him.
So if you want to do something like that, do your research and be careful, that's all
I wanted to say.
Overall, I think this will be it for me.
Thank you very much.
I know you cannot ask the questions directly during this time, or maybe you will be able to,
but if you have anything, try to leave them in the video comments and I'll try to answer them.
There's this artist's Twitter handle if you have any questions for her or just want to follow her.
Plus my email is... yeah.
That's my email, if you want to know something, try to write it.
I usually answer within 2 weeks if I'm not super burned out.
Overall, I want to thank you for watching this, your comments or critiques are welcome
and I hope you have a nice year ahead of you and a nice life.
Vladimir is out.
Bye!