So my name is Will Robinson, and today I'm
going to talk about Web3 games.
For me, that means games that use NFTs, blockchains,
decentralized ledgers, smart contracts,
cryptocurrencies, et cetera.
I've designed this talk for people
who have heard about these things
but haven't been behind the curtains, so to speak,
who haven't seen what the industry is like
and would maybe want to know why people are motivated by it
and why they're not.
where things are going.
It turns out that most people in this space
are interested in lying about it.
So I'm hoping I can give you some truths at least.
Before we begin, I'd like to make it clear
that despite me working in crypto for four years,
I have empirical data to say that at least 97%
of Web3 projects are misguided, malicious, or broken.
And the ratio is even worse for games in Web3.
So just want to make sure that I'm not here to red pill you.
In fact, hopefully I'll convince you not to make a Web3 game
because it's either too early, too dangerous, too expensive,
too criminal, or too evil to bother.
Instead, I'm going to give you some mental models
to think critically about what's going on
and let you know what I think people in the industry
would rather keep secret.
At the same time, I want to highlight
towards the end of my talk how there
are some interesting potentials that Web3 has offered
at least one game community, which
has done some beautiful things.
That's fully open source.
It has no token.
It has no venture capital.
It has no carbon footprint.
And it values the labors of its community
in really interesting ways.
And it uses blockchains to actually dig deep
into the affordances of the medium.
And so I'll be happy to talk about that later.
Me? So in 2017, I completed my doctoral thesis in game studies. I focused on how rules incentivize
people to enact stories. I worked on feminist, Marxist, post-colonial critiques of games,
in-game items, and mods and modders. If you want to follow me on Twitter, I'm DangerWillRobin.
If you want to check out the website and the project I'm working on now, it's called Alliance.xyz.
Before even graduating, actually, my dissertation,
I had already decided to leave academia.
I was building a career as a forensic crypto auditor,
which is a pretty strange thing.
I was actually doing it in an accounting firm.
And you might think this is a radical shift,
but for me, I was still chasing the same rush
that game designers chase,
which is that I'm addicted to twist endings.
I know this is cringe, but ever since watching Richard Kelly's Donnie Darko at age 16, I've
been obsessed with twist endings and I've been setting myself up for surprise by the
media I consume ever since.
Almost anyone who's ever designed a game knows that they are especially suited at bewildering
even their makers.
So games are almost like players in themselves.
They lead players down garden paths,
they have players evolve dominant strategies
that are new and unexpected and unforeseen.
And we usually call these second or third order effects.
These higher order effects are table stakes
for people who think about systems
and for systems designers,
trying to get your initial conditions,
your incentives just right
so that your system reaches some interesting experience.
Well, that's a maddening ordeal.
And so Bitcoin.
is totally along that track.
And I know you've heard of it,
but maybe you don't have a good mental model,
so here's one that I like to have.
It's a spreadsheet, that's all it is.
It's a spreadsheet, you can reduce the number in your cell
to increase the number in someone else's cell.
You're not allowed to reduce anybody else's numbers,
and nobody can increase numbers
unless they decrease their own.
That's the game.
It's like soccer. If everybody plays by these rules, something fun emerges.
And what was interesting is that these numbers were of course meaningless at the beginning, like points in soccer.
But because the sheet runs, regardless of what you do to it,
it can't be stopped. It can't be stopped by governments or by corporations.
It has an intrinsic value to have a number on the sheet.
And so you'll pay to have someone reduce their number to increase yours.
And it turns out that Satoshi Nakamoto's intellectual contribution was that this is only possible if you waste energy.
And if everybody agrees to take the ledger that provably wastes the most energy,
well then you get a censorship-resistant currency.
We'll talk about why you might want that later.
But the problem being solved here in a cryptographic framework is called Byzantine Fault Tolerance.
If you want to Google it later, the Wikipedia articles are very interesting.
But if you do waste this thing, and if at least less than 50%,
like if any owner owns less than 50% of the wasted energy,
then you have a credible, neutral system
on which you can rely that it will behave the way
the code says it will.
And you'll want to remember that for later,
because that'll be helpful for thinking about games.
And so
Because it was making this funny money,
it was a pyramid scheme.
It was just people, computer playing in their basements,
coders, pariahs, people who were made fools of
for thinking Bitcoin was real.
It was faking it until it made it, basically.
And I think of Bitcoin as like an entity, like another player, like a game that plays itself.
It has its own personality, its own agency.
And not just a player, but I think of it as a devil.
Like you can sell your soul to it, and it will empower you with wealth and riches, like Dr. Faust.
And I actually think of it more than a devil,
I think of it as a Lovecraftian elder god.
Something that like cultists in the 1920s in New England
are like throwing shit in the reagents
into like a cauldron to summon something terrible
that might give them power, might enslave them, who knows.
And the reason is because it creates value, Bitcoin, for people,
captures that value and redistributes it.
It pays its followers, right?
And those followers then proselytize.
They go on and they say more and more and more Bitcoin everywhere.
And it works. It's a self-perpetuating philosophical object.
And you'll want to remember that too.
If a bunch of people hold the same asset,
they will coordinate to increase its value.
That'll be helpful for Web3 games later.
Here you can see that Bitcoin did exactly what it was supposed to do.
A censorship-resistant money allowed foreign powers to fund an internal terrorist organization
or revolution in Canada, depending on your side of the argument.
And we won't debate that here.
But essentially, this is like the native, beautiful possibility that the Bitcoiners see.
So at the moment when 2008 happens, the crash occurs,
and the governments, instead of punishing the banks,
prints more money to bail them out.
Basically taxes everybody who's holding dollars
by saying your dollars are now worth less,
so I can give some money to the banks
to make the banking system not collapse
instead of doing something else.
Satoshi Nakamoto gets very angry.
He says, this isn't a very good thing to do.
I'm gonna create Bitcoin.
But more than that, imagine if things got really bad.
your government became despotic, all-powerful,
could check your credit cards, could freeze them.
As soon as you want to resist that government,
which has now massive surveillance
because it's the future and surveillance is easy and free,
well, how are you gonna resist this super government?
And so for the cypherpunks who are building Bitcoin,
they're trying to come up with a money
outside of normal regulations.
And so we make Bitcoin to resist government,
to be illegal, to be a criminal object.
by design, it is meant to be criminal.
And criminal is not always a bad thing, right?
Like in a terrible government,
criminal is like actually the good guys.
And so that's how they see it.
And so Bitcoin becomes this like reliable code
that anybody can depend on just like TCP IP,
like the internet protocol, right?
It's a standard, we can follow it.
And this is one more thing to remember for Web 3 games.
You're building something that's reliable, right?
A layer of protocol that everybody can build on
and expect to behave the way it was set out to.
No one will have the power to change it.
Okay, just as a side note, these cypherpunks,
although they had these like noble ambitions
to like, you know, stop despotic governments,
they do come from a pretty creepy place
of like anti-Semitic gold bug world.
And if you want to read more about it,
I recommend David Golumbia's book.
But the same with the Lovecraftian cultists,
just because they had intentions and ideologies and politics
doesn't mean that the thing they eventually summoned
had those same politics and ideas, right?
The games you design don't do what you want the games
that you designed to do.
They have a life of their own.
Okay.
At the same time that the banks are unfairly supported by government central powers, Vitalik
Buterin is upset because World of Warcraft has nerfed his Warlock.
The Warlock had a Drain Life spell and a Siphon Life it was called, and it was removed.
And his entire build was ruined.
And I think he jokingly said, though it's not clear if it's a joke with Vitalik, that
Blizzard had way too much control over his game.
and then set on a long course journey just like Satoshi did to neuter government,
to neuter game developers, to make them subservient to their games, so to speak.
It takes years.
He eventually comes up with a new cryptocurrency
called Ethereum, and instead of being just a ledger
with plus and minus numbers, it's a global computer.
Every cell can be a program now.
And a bad computer, like a really bad computer.
Like imagine the whole world sharing one Palm Pilot.
Bad computer.
That's what we're after, because it's hard
to get the whole world to agree to one computer state.
If anybody tells you you can get the whole world to agree on a very large state, you can probably say they're lying.
Like, they're part of the camp of liars, or they misunderstand their own technology.
You can't get a decentralized view of a large state right now with our technology.
Okay, so, in this sense, you could imagine putting the rules of World of Warcraft on the computer,
not run World of Warcraft on this computer, and then sign off on them as, like,
these are the rules, nobody changed them.
Now, any game designer will tell you that's untenable.
We need to evolve and adapt our game.
Heck, even chess has patch notes every 400 years, right?
So, you know, to think that it would make sense
to keep a game stable wouldn't be ideal,
but instead think how would we get a community
to govern those rules,
to decentralize that ownership of the game.
And that's where
Ethereum is going to sort of try and propose this benefit.
So all these cells, like we said before,
computer programs can be anywhere.
The owner can be the program.
It can own its own programs.
The programs can own money.
This is a novel shift.
for most people.
Programs owning money is weird, right?
Imagine a self-driving car that charges you
and then it takes its money and it goes
and it pays for gas from a self, you know,
gas filling terminal and then just is a virus, right?
The car makes enough money, it makes an order itself
to a factory to make a new car
and that car shows up on a boat
and it starts making its own money.
You know, you could conceivably think of protocols
living on their own in this way.
And so the first major use case for this supercomputer machine was just to create mini bitcoins.
Every cell became its own ledger, a program for another split up of tokens.
And that enabled this ICO, the initial coin offering boom of 2017, where we could once
again...
do criminal activity with crypto.
In this case, the criminal activity though,
wasn't subverting governments in revolution,
it was subverting the SEC.
So the Securities and Exchange Commission, right,
has clear rules on like,
how you can like tokenize your company.
Usually it is through stocks and through regulations.
I was an auditor, I can tell you the list of regulations
is very long, it's very expensive to make a stock.
and to get people to buy your stocks.
But what Ethereum did was permissionlessly
let you buy stocks.
You could just say, these are my stocks,
and you can buy them here,
and if my company goes up in value,
these tokens will go up in value,
which is very dangerous.
A lot of people got sued by the SEC.
I don't recommend anybody do it.
And the thing is, people aren't used to
having that kind of financial access.
We weren't growing up.
in schools that trained us to buy stocks directly
from the source companies.
We have brokers who make sure that we're not drunk
when we buy our stocks very often.
Or even Robin Hood gets in trouble
when it puts fireworks after you buy your stocks.
But here, we can gamify the heck out of stocks.
We can do whatever we want with stocks.
No one can stop us, except when eventually you find out
who you really are as a real person,
and then you go to jail.
So people lost their shirts and more.
Contracts broke, contracts were lying, et cetera, et cetera,
but a tiny percentage of the ICO boom
produced what we call today decentralized finance.
We invented how to swap tokens,
how to get loans and leverage,
and basically rebuild the financial sector.
In crypto, here are the top five as of yesterday.
And you can see Maker did the first thing we needed to do,
which was a stable coin, put USD on.
the chain. Ave, lending that lets you basically borrow against that USD so you can leverage up
or short positions. These are just sort of fundamental pieces, building blocks
of any financial system. Those were built.
And you know by 2019 we have this great financial system.
The fees are way lower.
Like if you're trading on Coinbase it's 10 times more expensive to make a same trade.
But we can only have seven trades per second for the whole world to share.
That's the Palm Pilot again.
Seven trades.
Visa does 40,000 transactions a second.
Oh it might be 15 trades but it's really bad.
And so that was the good news, no more brokers,
no more middlemen.
The bad news is we could now have like drunk 12 year olds
with an internet connection taking leveraged long positions
on pictures of cats, right?
That's the financial system that ended up being built,
a crazy casino.
right? And the knee-jerk reaction here is like, well, we got to regulate this, but it's unregulatable.
That was the point. We created this elder god that gets to enslave us now. It cannot be censored.
The sort of
I would say is it's kind of like discovering
peer-to-peer sex, right?
So we had brokers, these priests, you know,
you'd go to them, they'd let you have sex with,
you know, one other person,
only if that person was like a different gender than you,
et cetera, et cetera.
And then we found out we can peer-to-peer sex,
and we did a lot of it, and it was messy.
We had lots of sexually transmitted diseases.
We had unwanted sex.
We had, you know, sexual assault.
We had unwanted pregnancies, et cetera,
because we didn't teach anybody
about how to have peer-to-peer sex.
We haven't taught anybody how to do peer-to-peer finance,
and so people are getting all kinds of scams,
money's lost, et cetera, et cetera,
not knowing what they're buying.
And so that's the situation we're in.
Probably can't stop peer-to-peer sex.
You probably can't really stop this either.
You'll only get to maybe educate people out of this problem.
Okay.
Then...
At the same time, we're creating NFTs.
So this is where we get to the sort of game side.
The model is different.
This is like one cell in that Ethereum.
sheet from before. So a single one of these cells here, one of these programs, looks like
this. And an NFT is very simple. It's an array of numbers. So, and it's not even an array
of numbers, it's just an array of slots. So one, two, three, four, and the person who
owns that slot. Alice owns slot one, maybe Bob owns slot two, and then they can trade.
All you're allowed to do is say, I own this slot and I no longer own this slot, I give
it to someone else. That's the rules.
In that smart contract, you usually have one website link.
It points to a service that'll hold a JPEG.
And if you own slot three, that means you own JPEG three.
If you own slot five, you own JPEG five.
That's an NFT.
That's all there is to it.
There's a way to hash that file
that's on the other server
so you know that it doesn't change.
And then all of a sudden you have
the capacity to move objects.
We tried to in 2017 as a crypto community to make a game on chain,
and we ran into that seven transactions per second problem.
You can't crash Ethereum basically with this thing called CryptoKitties,
which was just a way to like breed cats on chain that looked like they wore
sailor suits or different fun cute things.
But
These objects inherited this art status.
Some of the early ones today maintain Veblen status,
like a way of showing your wealth.
They also avoid a lot of SEC regulation
because they're artworks for personal use a lot of the time
and I'm not your lawyer and I'm not your financial advisor
and everything I say you can't take me to court about.
But basically, a lot of very wealthy people
moved their capital out of DeFi
when regulations started getting hairy and into NFTs.
It was a place to do more regulatory arbitrage.
This time it was less criminal
but only because no one had ever thought
to regulate this kind of thing.
And so NFTs became this stand-in, this new shelling point, a place to store value.
And the OG ones, like the CryptoPunks here, they're worth hundreds of thousands of dollars each.
And you think, well why? It's just a JPEG. But it's more than a JPEG, it's a coordination tool.
in the same way that Bitcoin is just a number on a spreadsheet,
this is the first NFT.
So it is the obvious place to store value
and acts as a social coordinating mechanism.
People can then, look,
if you're starting a new venture capital firm,
Or you're an old venture capital firm and you want to like raise money and then invest in crypto projects
There's no way they'll take you seriously
But if you buy one of these things and make it your profile picture
All of a sudden you show your commitment to this industry and to this idea
You're ready to put your money where your mouth is and so they act as a kind of social signal
Social signaling is so valuable.
And they're $100,000, but they're resellable.
So it's not like you lost $100,000,
you just lost the time value of that $100,000
and then took on exposure to the price change.
OK, so NFTs come out.
They're very exciting.
People are very interested in growing them.
We have this model of many people owning one collection.
And we talked back about Bitcoin.
When people own a lot of one asset,
they can coordinate to grow its value.
They all become shillers, shilling each other's bags,
coordinating around them.
Today, or only a couple of days ago,
I believe there was like a $450 million
deal for an NFT collection.
company to basically come into existence and compete with brands like Hermes, because the
community owns the brand in a decentralized way, in a way that's totally new and novel,
and evades regulation in interesting ways. Okay, so now we've got NFTs, they're exciting,
Axie Infinity.
The NFT's start to become useful.
They're being played with in games.
And again, the game is not on the blockchain.
What happens is I connect my wallet to an account,
and that account looks at the blockchain
and sees that I own something.
I own something, it sees my crypto address at slot three.
It looks up what slot three is.
It's that, not CryptoKitty, but Axie.
It's an axolotl on the left,
and it populates it for me in game.
It's a database lookup.
No logic is put on game.
I win some games, a centralized company called Sky Mavis then goes and prints some tokens
to my account, right?
And it does that printing on chain.
That's the model of the Web3 game that's super successful.
Axie Infinity here had a valuation recently at like $60 billion.
It's a, it's like a mobile game, right?
It looks nothing like...
any $60 billion game you've ever seen.
It doesn't play as well.
Its community is very different from most.
It's almost entirely based in the Philippines
and the global south.
Because when you play this game, you get those tokens.
And those tokens have values.
And that value can be higher than what
you can do working in one context or another.
And people here misunderstand why this game is valuable.
They think it's valuable because it's somehow
revolutionized.
play to earn. You can now play games and earn money and we've solved capitalism.
Absolutely not. People who believe that fell prey to a very terrible
pyramid scheme and the value of Axies, the value of this company,
have all plummeted since the curves of growth have not mapped on to the
the flood of inflation in this game. But what this game did do is millions of
players with no banks all of a sudden using Axie as the front end to DeFi.
Using Axie is the front end to the blockchain.
Axie isn't on Ethereum, it's on its own chain called Ronin.
And the people who own Ronin are the people who made Axie.
And Ronin has its own currency exchange called Katana,
and the people who made Katana are the people who made Axie.
And when Katana takes a fee, Axie's taking a fee.
And so what you have here is a $40 billion game project,
but it's a loss leader to a neobank.
It's a new way of banking people who've never had access to banks.
The promise of Bitcoin was to bank the unbanked.
It turns out we're going to do it through, you know, cute axolotls on a mobile phone app.
You can't even get this app on the App Store.
You have to, like, download the APK.
It's like, there's a lot of friction.
But the sense here is that games right now in Web3 are acting as...
loss leaders. Games on Web3 are strictly less fun, and they are strictly more expensive
to make, and they have more friction for their players. There should be no reason a Web3
game, standing on its own merits, would be better than a Web2 game. What they offer is
a new way to monetize players.
through banking. And the problem is there's a lot of regulatory uncertainty here. So doing
it is very dangerous. You have to be comfortable with a lot of risk. But if it works, you can
disrupt much more than any game industry. Okay. So mental model check here.
These aren't really games.
They're front ends.
They're marketing.
They're user acquisition for players
to then have wallets who have access to all of Web 3
and all the fancy regulatory bank business.
Now, Web 2 companies, like Ubisoft,
have tried to capitalize on this NFT movement.
There's a lot of.
excitement around owning the objects you have.
But I mean, I technically own the objects
I have in my Steam marketplace.
I bought a Dazzle skin recently.
I main Dazzle on Dota 2.
And that Dazzle skin, it's available via API.
It's an open API.
Anybody can read that I have it.
You can display it anywhere you want.
It's basically as good as being on a blockchain.
And I can sell it on the store.
And the fee for selling it is two pennies.
The fee for, there's no crypto fee lower than two pennies.
So the benefits people will say is true ownership,
but like, I don't know what that really means.
And other than saying tomorrow Steam could turn around
and turn off its services,
it could kill the Steam store,
and if your blockchain items were in a smart contract.
Theoretically, that could be possible
that it wouldn't be turnoffable.
And theoretically, there is value capture there.
So I would say that this is like really a stepping stone.
It's a way to also get players to start connecting
their wallets to companies so they can have your ID
and your on-chain identity
and your on-chain like financialization.
There's a benefit there for sure long-term.
On the ESG side, because I know we talked about how you have to waste energy for Bitcoin,
I just want to be clear, this was on Tezos.
That's a different blockchain. It doesn't use proof-of-work.
It uses a totally different consensus model.
This did not cause any carbon footprint.
It was really annoying to see that that being the major critique against Ubisoft.
Also, the majority of blockchains today don't have proof of work.
It's too expensive for them to get proof of work.
Instead they use things like proof of stake.
Instead of wasting energy, because you have to waste something for your blockchain to
work, instead of wasting energy they waste the time value of money.
You lock up your money.
its time value is now in jeopardy.
That's what we're wasting, not energy anymore.
And Ethereum, which is proof of work,
will be merging to a non-proof of work system
very, very, very soon.
So I think that worrying about ESG
when there's all this other terrible shit going on
in Web3 would not worry about that.
And ESG is about the environment side, just to be clear.
So yeah, Celo, Algorand, Cosmos, Polkadot, Solana.
Don't worry about ESG, worry about other things.
Okay, so I promised I'd get to like why Web3 games are cool,
what I like about them,
and where there's some possibility for salvation.
This is a screenshot from my favorite Web3 game.
In fact, I started an entire decentralized,
autonomous organization to play it.
It's called Dark Forest.
And it's an open source game.
And what I think is possible is that you can make open source a
profitable endeavor for all the people who want to contribute to the same code base, no matter who they are, where they are,
by paying them using Web3. And by making that copy of open source valuable. So in the same way that
Web3 made NFTs, JPEGs, not copy-pastable, created scarcity,
in a visual object, you can create scarcity
in a piece of code.
And that can let that piece of code get owned
by the people who contributed and built it
without having any need for venture funding or studios,
just hobbyists building together.
And that's what's happening in Dark Forest.
And you likely haven't heard of it
because it is just hobbyists building it together, right?
They don't have a marketing budget.
The only people who hear about it are, you know,
crypto nerds who get nerd sniped by this thing.
and who hear about other nerds, they respect getting nerds night by this thing.
So, unlike games like, and this is what I was studying in university, Skyrim or Little
Big Planet, which depend on suckering players into building levels so that the value of
the game can grow and then capturing that value and not redistributing it to the players
but to investors in the core dev team.
So it's not like that, right?
It's not an exploitation of playbirth.
Here we can have a game protocol
that depends on the players building it,
but where the proceeds can go back to those players.
That's an interesting switch, right?
Because we all love user-generated content.
We just wish the generators of that content
could get fairly compensated for it.
And it does happen.
Again, Dota, I'm a big fan.
The pros who play the international,
I pay $15 for a battle pass,
I get to watch them play professionally,
they get some amount of that $15,
the developers get some amount of that $15,
they're laborers, those pros.
And they labor for Dota.
They make the game more valuable by playing it.
And in the same way, Dark Force takes on that kind of role.
To give you a sense just before we go on a little bit more of what Dark Forest is,
it's basically Galcon, if you've ever played that.
Like, take over a planet, planet makes energy, send that energy to another planet,
now you've got two planets making energy.
Send those two planets to one bigger one, capture three planets,
exponential growth of just like moving across the map.
What's cool about Dark Forest, though, is it's played in zero knowledge.
What that means is every move you make in this giant world
is provably true in how you craft it
and present it to the blockchain,
but no one knows what you did.
It's like playing chess in the dark.
Only once you shine your light
on the spot where that move happened
can you see what happened there for real.
That's an interesting feature, right?
Because there's no central server to handle fog of war.
It's a decentralized on-chain game.
No one owns the protocol, so there's
no database where I can look up, hey,
what's under this fog of war?
You have to create fog of war in totally new ways, which
is very interesting to see cryptographic primitives do
that.
And what that means is because there's no central database,
there's no core team with superior powers over the game
like any other competitive video game where devs can have like a back-end access and knowledge,
winning in this game is fair. It's provably fair, right? You just followed the protocol's rules.
And so what the game community does is it awards prizes to the winners.
And those prizes are just like NFTs, just like commemorative badges, and they're commemorative NFTs on no syschain.
So again, no environmental impact on this chain.
And it gets into the top 63.
We've never seen a level five, six, or seven planet,
which are the biggest ones, get sold.
But they sell for about $15,000 to $40,000, the smaller ones.
I think a big one would sell for a million today,
because they're really hard to win at this game.
This is an enormous amount of engineering power
to come first.
You need to have a good team working
around the clock for weeks.
And it's sort of like a nerd competition.
It's a little like a math Olympiad winning this game.
which I think is kind of cool.
Provable credentials for the team that wins.
They're able to solve a bunch of cryptographic problems
and think deeply about it.
At the same time, it's still very playable
for any novice who wants to just struggle
through a bit of crypto learning.
Okay, so.
In addition to these players winning planets for winning the game,
they'll also get rewarded planets for revealing their strategies for how they won.
Because often players do crazy things.
The winner in round one rewrote the client of the game.
So the whole front end, like they took the open source code
and then found the places where there were awaits in move making
and instead of serializing the moves, just parallelized them
and was able to just...
make more moves faster in changing the code.
In round two, the team that won, we don't know what they did.
But in round one, four having revealed the new client,
they won an additional planet.
And that's really cool because now you're paying your players to share their improvements on the game with everyone else as a community.
So in round three we made like a marketplace so that in-game you could trade your like strategic weapons.
There was no marketplace in the game before.
The community made the marketplace, the people who made the community, they got a commemorative NFT.
NFTs have no value, right?
They're freely given, but the community ascribes them value
through their cachet.
Like if you have one of these planets,
it's because you were pretty cool
and did something pretty cool at some point.
And I would like to buy it from you,
not only because I think it's a valuable planet,
but I know I'm funding someone who's building in web three
at the cutting edge, right?
I feel good about what I'm buying
because the people making this game
are like only working on donations.
right? They're like A, 16, Z will come up to them at dinner with like a $10 million check at any
valuation they want. And there's like, no, like this is, this belongs to the community. And that's
a very different approach, right? In thinking about this. Um, okay. So.
Where does this take us, right?
What is the point of Web3 games from this angle?
Because it's hard to make money with it,
it's hard to build a new community,
there's no way you can scale this, right?
Like these players, these players here,
like you can only handle about 1,000 players at a time,
maybe 2,000 at best.
And then you'd have to work on new blockchains.
And when this game does play, the entire blockchain shuts
down.
There's no way to use it.
You have to pay huge fees to get past the game in order
to get your transactions through.
And that's one of the fundamental problems
with Web3 games.
So it won't be a retail sensation.
It'll be a niche community of super engineers
who maybe are building up their CVs in the way
that people build their CVs with GitHub repos.
So not thoroughly exciting in that way.
If they're gonna be valuable, these kinds of games,
they're gonna do different things
than what normal games do.
They're gonna stress test new blockchains.
They're going to be training grounds for new engineers.
They're going to be credentials for CVs.
They're not going to be these new fun times
that reach 40 million players.
It's just like not possible to put on-chain games
to 40 million players.
which is sad. It's like a sad truth, like really a big bummer. I'm sad about it every day, actually.
Instead, we're going to see a lot more of this, right? A lot more games that rely on some
centralized organization, running a normal web2 game, and then pushing some data to the
chain to get some financialization of players.
That's the that's the fundamental premise here
this is just way more popular we get way more of it and
these games are
Serving as user acquisition to their underlying blockchains
So what's good for Axie is they own the blockchain they're acquiring users to
But when I go downstairs and look at all the booths of all the people who are making games
on someone else's blockchain, I get really worried.
Because I don't know how you're going to capture the value.
Maybe through a wallet that will start taking fees at the wallet level.
But certainly the people who are going to capture the value are the blockchains that
are under that level, right?
And so if you are making one of these games, make sure you talk to that blockchain and
you ask for a lot of money because you're doing them a huge service.
And well, that's something that I do for the companies I help, right?
So this is me again.
What I do in real life is I run an accelerator for Web3 games.
I help game companies stop making games on Web3
or help Web2 companies start making games in Web3,
depending on the use cases and what they need.
So the
You know, it's so hard to get it through in one chat,
but basically we have guilds
who are managing thousands of players now
because those players are playing to earn
in these sort of pyramid schemes
and they're able to take wealth out.
Those guilds help connect them to players,
and sorry, to game makers.
I maintain a large collection of those.
Also the studios that are in charge of game making.
or the entities in Metro Engagemaking at all the layer ones,
so like Solana, Celo, Algorand, whatever,
the whole list, Terra, maintain relations with those,
trying to get people who are in this space to safely
and not scammily, hopefully, as best as we can,
try and make things like this.
That's the sort of state of the industry for now.
Look, I want to leave a lot of room for questions.
The sort of possibility space of where this talk can go
will be very long, and I'll give really long-winded answers
to your questions, hopefully.
So if you do have any, please feel free to ask.
Yeah, that's my talk.
Thanks.
Test, test, all right, hey.
Thanks, this was a really insightful talk.
It helped me a lot.
One of the things that I've been trying
to wrap my head around is...
whether blockchain offers something that databases don't,
like a standard database doesn't offer,
to a company like Microsoft or a major game publisher.
Why would they choose, for example,
to try to, I don't know, put the Arbiter's Sword
in the hands of a Call of Duty player
using blockchain as opposed to a database of some sort?
It doesn't seem to me like it makes any sense.
Like, why would you do that?
But anyway, that's my question.
That's an excellent question.
And the reason it doesn't make sense
is because it doesn't make sense for the most part.
So there've been a lot of attempts
to make centralized blockchains
over the last seven or eight years.
Enterprise blockchains, we call them.
It's sort of ridiculous
because the point of a blockchain, right,
was to make a uncensorable
Right? Like, government fighting machine.
And as soon as you centralize it,
then the government can just lean on the company that's centralizedly owning it
and say, stop. And it's over.
So as soon as you centralize a blockchain, there's every benefit that it could have had from, you know, allowing people to, you know, guarantee certain things about their NFTs not moving or changing.
Gone, out the window.
So there's literally zero reason for a centralized blockchain, like none.
If Microsoft can somehow get a decentralized consortium of people that's so decentralized that a government couldn't stop it,
Then you enable regulation circumvention.
You enable things like what we call regulatory arbitrage,
finding opportunities against Web 2.0 companies
because they have to follow the rules that Web 3.0 companies don't.
But the thing is, Microsoft is a publicly traded company.
If it starts to break any kind of rules,
it's going to be in deep trouble and it has a lot of money to pay fines.
And so it's a good target to go after.
So I would be very nervous.
about seeing as something like that. I do think that the disruptors in this industry will not be
like classic web 2 companies. They'll be companies that can take a lot more regulatory risk,
at least for the near foreseeable future. And then, so then a normal database is great.
Take that sword from this dragon game and put it in this gun game. Like, that's cool.
And make your database publicly available and open API
and let people come in and use it
and have other people use that item
and build a marketplace in web two.
Like you can build all these normal things.
So the only other real reason is that it might be cheaper.
Like there's so much free work being done in web three,
so much open source code available.
you can just use that infrastructure,
even though it's like fundamentally worse
and wasn't made for this purpose,
as a sort of leapfrog cheat
and not have to build anything yourself.
I can see sometimes like a really operational reason
like that be there.
Hey. Yes, I'm honestly still kind of confused on the value of like some of these NFTs. Just
taking the example up here. Oh yeah. So you own these characters on that particular blockchain,
which sounds like the blockchain itself is owned by a company.
Yeah.
Even if the blockchain survives, if the game were to shut down, right, where does the value
come from?
The fact that you own these characters, but the game itself is gone.
Sure, sure, sure.
So my argument is that the company has value, not these assets.
These assets actually have gone down in value dramatically.
I bought these with company dollars, sorry, company, for $2,000, I think.
I think they're worth like $300 today.
These objects are loss leaders to getting more players onto a platform that can do all of this.
If you get players to use your app as the front end to finance,
especially when those players come from a world where they don't have access to
banking, lending, trading, swapping, leveraging, shorting,
you get to be the owner of all the fees they're going to pay.
The lifetime value of your players is huge.
And so the company that made this game owns those players,
owns the front end those players have to this unregulated financial sector,
and those players don't live in the USA.
where there's an enormous amount of regulation.
They live in places where you can actually get around a lot of these problems.
And so that's why there's a lot of value that can be captured.
Right?
When people valued these...
at $2,000. The reason was really weird. So you'll have to bear with me as I do with my hands.
So imagine a world where there's three Axies only. That's what you need to field a team.
Okay, but we'll call those three Axies one Axie for the sake of my model. There's one Axie. And
this Axie makes SLP, smooth love potions. That's the currency in the game. If it plays the single
player campaign, it gets some smooth love potions. If you want to make another Axie,
you'll need a certain amount of smooth love potions and breed your Axie.
If I want my friend to play, I need to give them smooth love potions or breed them an exe.
They're scarce. They're a limited number. The protocol sort of limits the number.
So that smooth love potion scarcity leads to an increase in value of smooth love potion.
And my friend doesn't want to play that badly. Maybe he'll buy it for $2.
But someone hears, wait a second, you played this game for a day and made two bucks, right, playing?
That's crazy, I want an Axie too.
But now, okay, two or three people want to do this, the price has gone up.
Because demand has gone up and the supply of Axies is still really constrained.
So now there's, you know, three dollars for an Axie.
Some new people here, $3 a day, that's 50% better.
10 people want to play now.
Because there's 10, demand spikes,
value of an axie spikes in the market.
And what happens is this crazy funnel problem
happens where these things spike to hundreds or thousands
of dollars as there was not enough supply to meet demand.
And because they were so expensive,
demand grew because people thought you could
make more money with them.
But like a pyramid scheme, eventually you reach a point where the number of axes is growing exponentially,
because each one you make can make more.
And the number of players coming in isn't growing as exponentially.
There's a sort of stop where we have huge amounts of inflation of axes,
and then the price just goes as close to zero as it can.
over time. So they don't have value.
Right. They have a limited value through people who miscalculate
where they are in the pyramid. Right. That's and that's very
dangerous. Right. And you want to protect players and kids
from like huge mistakes in their financial decision making.
So yeah, no value in owning the front end.
In the same way that Facebook is like the internet
for many people, right?
Where the Facebook app is their interface to the internet,
Facebook owns those people, owns their marketplace,
or the way WeChat in China owns all the marketplaces
of the people using it, Axie will be a super app.
It'll be your social media network,
it'll be your bank, et cetera.
And so this is a loss leader Ponzi scheme
that attracts lots of players.
I think that's the way to have the mental model.
Does that make sense?
Yep.
Great.
Hey, over here.
Sorry, I just wanted to clarify what you said earlier.
So you're saying that the value of these NFTs or these tokens in general are basically they
don't exist.
And the only value is to the company who initially started it and fronted the whole thing because
they got the profit immediately.
And then it.
eventually all of this. Oh, no. Yeah, sorry. I'll clarify that. So the company actually made no
money off these NFTs almost. These NFTs, when you make the SLP and create the Axie and sell it,
you get 95% of the profits for what you sold it for. And the players were the ones creating them.
That's what created the economic flywheel and the incentive to play in the first place. They
just took a 5% cut of the sale. Sure. OK. So then my follow up would be like, so then what is...
I guess the overall purpose of adding these in the first place is just like artificially,
essentially generating like a small amount of income before it disseminates again
and there was no point in the first place.
Sorry, I didn't understand the question. Can you repeat it again?
So the way it sounded like was, and maybe I misunderstood, was
the value you're getting from these tokens that you made
are like very small and then
it's only given to like, you know, set amount of players at the beginning or something
and then slowly over time, you know, even these don't have value anymore.
So then what was the purpose of like adding this extra, like a lot of effort actually, to like
integrating this into your game?
Right. So the reason was it was like a multi-level marketing scheme.
So it's a go to market user acquisition strategy.
So if I tell you you can play this game and make $100 a day,
you will download this app and you will play it for $100 a day.
Almost like a huge number of people or $300 a month.
I think that's what it was at its maximum.
And so people actually weren't buying the Axies, it turns out,
because they couldn't afford them.
They were too expensive.
So these organizations called guilds went out,
bought the Axies, and then lent them to players
to play for money, and took a cut of that money
and gave the rest to the players.
And the players just made money playing,
money that was brought in from new players coming in
wanting to play.
But.
At a certain point, they weren't new players,
they were just new businesses.
Like taxi cab medallions.
Like I'm a company that owns medallions,
I lend the medallions out to my drivers
who go and drive for money, and then I take a cut.
Now, those guilds ended up holding a lot of Axies
that dropped a lot in value, especially the later ones.
They sort of got, you know, cleaned out.
But what happened is those guilds were like,
oh my god, this is profitable.
Like I buy an Axie, I get a player to play this game,
and now I make money and that player makes money.
And all of a sudden you have a company that didn't have a marketing team,
didn't need a marketing team to acquire new players, right?
Cottage industries emerged to acquire new players for them.
So they went from having like 200,000 players
to like 5 million players in the span of a month.
on this kind of model. So why user acquisition? That's the why.
Because the pyramid entices people to come join thinking they're going to make money. And the same reason why do people join
normal pyramid schemes? They think they're going to make money. And in this case
they did because the people who lost the money weren't the players for the most part. They were these guilds. I did it.
I hope that makes sense.
Over here, and we'll go over here.
A few of the things I've been hearing over this week as the benefits of building on a
blockchain are the interoperability and the ownership components.
I was just wondering how you factor interoperability into your mental model, thinking about these
as funneling users to DeFi.
Sure, that's a great question. So just to clarify, interoperability is this powerful concept, right?
Because this ledger is open, right, anybody can read what you're holding as assets, right?
And, you know, the Steam Marketplace is interoperable. For a while, you could even,
like, gamble with your, like, CSGO skins on, like, gambling websites
because the API was so interoperable and powerful.
So the improbability isn't novel to crypto.
We can have it anywhere we want.
It's default in crypto, so that's one thing.
The other thing is interoperability is also a promise
that keeps getting unfulfilled.
So if I'm a game developer that makes money selling NFTs,
and now I've made that money,
it's strange to think there'll be another game developer
who will use the NFTs I made the money on, right?
Like, they make them passes to their game.
The answer could be they wanna siphon off my players, right?
Say, hey, if you hold this NFT,
Here's a cool perk in this other game.
And so it can be a way to user acquire.
Say people who own this asset,
come to me, I'll give you a reward.
That might be why.
The other cool thing though, beyond interoperability,
and this is a big part of DeFi, is composability.
So I like to think of interoperability as
you can read data,
but composability is you can activate logic.
So when you use Aave to borrow Maker,
what you're doing is actually asking one program
to activate the code in another program.
And when programs start not just interoperating
by reading their data,
but using their logic across themselves,
you might get an explosion of value.
And that is what's happening in Dark Forest, right?
The composability here, as with,
like for instance in round,
Four, we made a smart contract player in our guild.
The player was just a piece of code.
It couldn't really play the game,
but what it could do is if you gave it a planet,
it would cash out its points and give the planet back.
And we had like 54 strangers, I think,
like give this planet, this smart contract, their planets.
It cashed out their points,
then kept track of how many points they each gave it.
And then when it came 33rd on its own,
with the help of these other players,
it could then like give that NFT to them pro rata
for the points they gave, right?
So that's really powerful, composability.
Interoperability.
is less interesting and also more possible.
Whereas composability is really hard in Web 2.0.
Like, it's hard to use the logic of Dota in another game.
Like, I don't know how you would get past the walled garden,
if that makes sense.
Yeah, thank you.
Over here.
Yeah, thank you for the great talk.
So it sounds like you've described this life cycle
of those games like Axie, where everything's great
at the beginning, more and people start joining, joining,
and eventually it collapses, right?
Do you think that's just like forever what's gonna be,
or do you think there's a way out of this cycle?
Great question.
There's a way to make your pyramid longer
so it explodes later.
You can tweak the economics that way.
It means giving up less money earlier.
There are ways to...
Look, here's what it is.
Axie was paying players to play alone in their basements.
That makes no sense.
Because you're not creating value when you play alone in your basement.
or outside.
You create value when you bring new players in.
You create value when you Twitch stream.
You create new value when you run an e-sports tournament
and people pay to watch it.
You create value when you build a mod
and people like to play with it.
And if you create value, Web3 can capture it
and redistribute it.
That's a powerful feature of Web3.
In the case of Axie, by giving out value for things that weren't creating, it's an unsustainable model.
It's like Uber paying you every time you take a cab ride.
Doesn't make sense, but Uber did pay you when you brought a new user onto the platform.
That does make sense.
So as long as you can make sure that the value coming in is greater than the value going out,
then you can maybe guess that it's a sustainable model.
I think that's a fair way to think about it.
Thanks.
But, just real quick, but eventually you're going to run out of users, right?
What?
Eventually you're going to run out of new users, right?
Yeah, yeah, you eventually run out of new users, so what you need is those users to
start paying money, right?
Like I pay $15 to Dota to watch the International, right?
Dota isn't paying me, it's paying the pros, right?
So they keep getting paid money as long as new players are bringing in money.
You have to capture value eventually.
What's interesting about Axie is it can start capturing value
in the financial instrument side and funnel that to the game
side.
The game could be the loss leader
that you keep funding through other ways of capturing value
because it's part of a rich ecosystem that
boggles the mind of a normal game maker, right?
Because you're never a game maker and a bank.
And then all of a sudden, that's what we're expecting you to be.
Awesome.
Thank you so much.
Hey, my pleasure.
Hello.
Hi.
In terms of the con, the overall con that you're describing that, you know, these are
games are UA to be on these blockchains and then you essentially people that don't have banks have
banks. So the overall con about you building Web3 games that I understood from your talk,
isn't that how technology in general is in terms of the business? For example, Facebook,
they provide this value to users.
But they want your data, that's how they make their money.
They're not expecting you to pay and get you to make money.
Amazon, you can buy things really easily from them.
and it's convenient and so you use them primarily for how you consume and make your shops.
But they're not making money from the products you're purchasing, they're gathering your
data and then using that data to feed all of the side businesses that they create.
It just seems that it's expected that blockchains will have this secondary value which is the
primary value for them by having games being, well, using their blockchain.
Right. So, and so that's, that's, that's exactly what I'm saying.
Okay.
Like, I think, I think you've got it. So if you're just making the game part, that's like just making
the social media platform without any of the ads part, right? Like, you'll, that's unsustainable.
you need to have a second source of revenue.
Otherwise, there's no reason to make it on-chain anyway in the first place.
Like, you should just make a Web2 game and create value just through fun.
What's happening here is Axie's creating value by doing user acquisition.
So it's not about data here, it's about, it could eventually be about data, but it's really
about this huge friction barrier of getting people into Web3.
Because once you get a Web3 user, they're worth so much money.
So yeah, I think it's expected when you think critically, but people aren't thinking critically
about this.
People really thought, like you could read these articles, they really thought Axie had
solved the problem.
Universal basic income like the entire global south was just gonna play video games and make a living for the rest of their lives
I seriously like non-stop could hear this and I was just like this
Why do you believe this the laws of physics can't allow for this and yet like that's so that's that's what I'm iterating here
I guess
Yeah, I think Axie is one of the examples in the space.
And, you know, I think there is a difference when you have game designers
who are experienced in building game economies, that they could find a way
to make it where the financial play of it is just another aspect of fun and not.
I don't think everyone believe that play to earn is just a thing
and you can live off making games.
I think there's a percentage that believe that.
I don't know.
Do you think that everyone's just expected to?
During the hype phase it was pretty intense and then it went from play to earn to play and earn and like people are on
You know changing the message as they learn it and figure out what works. But yeah, like
There are games where the economy is the fun
for sure, like EVE Online. Yeah, exactly. Yeah, I was thinking that.
Yeah. And there's a great book, by the way, called Virtual Economies by Vili Ladanvirta.
It's so good. And he talks about this, right, and that often game makers are going to give
a little bit of currency to their players.
just so they can see the economic engine that's there and how enticing it is.
So certainly there are blockchain games doing that.
And as long as the loop is closed and there's no value bleeding out,
like that can keep happening.
But what's happening is these blockchain games, because they're on-chain
and they're interoperable and composable with all of DeFi,
the tokens in that game are sellable.
And if people are selling tokens, that means someone else is buying.
And if they're buying because they want to make more money,
in the way that I buy milkshakes from the milkshake person above me in the pyramid,
so I can sell more milkshakes to the people below me, that will collapse.
And so, yes, there's definitely a way to make a more sustainable economy.
And hopefully we'll see them soon.
But when you do, those sustainable economies are less viral.
So they don't satisfy that purpose of loss leader for user acquisition.
Thank you.
Thank you so much for your questions.
Hi.
I want to ask if blockchain games could be a good solution to have people play PVP for
money basically.
So let's suppose Clash Royale, you go in and you bet $1 before the match and the winner
takes $1.9.
Yeah, that is a good use case.
Because the game isn't unchained.
The thing is, that's...
Gambling.
So there's a lot of laws you got to worry about.
Even if it's like an entirely skill-based game,
there are probably laws you have to worry about.
Also, there's KYC problems.
So you're not used to it.
But you don't want to fund terrorism
through this channel of moving money.
So you become like a virtual asset service provider
or a money service business.
So it is doable.
It's just.
you have to figure out what you're gaining over just a dollar, right?
Like, why not just put a dollar in the account and move the dollar over?
And if what you think you're gaining is regulatory arbitrage,
the answer is probably no.
You're probably not gaining much because you're exposing yourself.
So to regulatory scrutiny.
Right, because I was thinking of building that in our PvP game, adding the ability to play.
entering the room with tokens, then the winner takes like 90% of the tokens. The other 10%
goes to fund eSports tournaments and also the dev team and the expenses. But you say it's going to
be a regulatory problem. Yeah, I would say you're going to have a lot of regulatory problems.
What about skills? What? Skills is basically doing the cash-based tournaments.
Yeah, look, I mean, I'm not your lawyer.
I can't tell you, but I'd be worried.
I would just like, it raises,
I think it's cool to explore it.
I think it might be more efficient,
especially if you want that gambling to use in-game tokens
that are usable in your own economy,
and a more smooth thing,
but particularly more efficient
if that's gonna be your way of onboarding users
to financializing them.
If on top of letting them gamble,
you also let them swap assets,
and then take fees on that, make more money that way.
Okay.
Yeah. Thank you. Okay. That's all we got for today, everybody. Thank you so much for attending.