Hello, my name is Soha. I'm a manager of diversity inclusion programs at Riot and
thank you for coming to see me talk this early in the morning. At some point
during my talk GDC is going to be sending you a survey to just ask you how
I did and this is really the first time that I'm speaking in an external way
about what we're doing at Riot so I would love to hear some feedback if
there's anything we can do to make it better for next time.
Or if you never want to see me speak again,
that's totally understandable.
I get it.
And then at some point, I'm going
to do my best to make room at the end for talks.
We do have a mic in the middle of the room.
But if we run out of time, we have a wrap-up area
that we can go to.
And our lovely friends will help us get to it safely and soundly.
So yeah, thanks for coming.
A heads up that I'll be shortening the words diversity and inclusion to D&I just because
I'm going to keep repeating the words over and over and over and driving myself and probably
you up the wall.
So keep in mind, D&I means diversity and inclusion.
So some of the things that what I want to talk about today are some of the things that
I've learned as I'm journeying through different spaces of diversity inclusion leading up to
Riot and also during my time at Riot.
And the mouse isn't working.
Sweet.
Got it.
So when I say making it work, I don't
mean to suggest that there's a finite list of proven ways
to solve D&I. It's not like here's
a list of 10 things to do, and then bam,
you've got diversity and another five things,
and boom, you've got inclusion.
And there's also not one solution
that fits every single organization.
So you might find that things are different where
you work or the organizations that you're a part of.
It's not really an end result.
It's not like you do stuff and then you get diversity.
It's really more about ongoing actions
that shift and evolve and mature over time.
And really in the title of diversity and inclusion,
there's an implication that it's about learning
and embracing different perspectives.
And being someone who is willing to be a manager
in that space, that means being someone
who's willing to be challenged and question
your own assumptions and your own values
coming into the space.
It's really about a combination of.
building bridges to create deep connections with people,
and also to embolden ourselves with a growth mindset.
And these are two things that I will get more into later on.
I wanna add something to the conversation about D&I
that I believe is missing from a lot of mainstream,
mainstream conversations.
It feels like this,
this subject kind of just exploded at some point
and now everybody's talking about it.
And it's great, but we're also missing a few valuable
pieces of the puzzle that I believe are foundational.
You'll also hear me say like,
hey, this isn't about programs or training sessions
or courses or initiatives or policies.
And it's not to bash any of those things.
It's not to say those things don't work.
It's not to say that those things aren't valuable.
It's to say that before we get into that,
we really have to understand why we are choosing these things
why we're choosing a program or a course
or whatever sort of output comes out of that.
You can't really tack on products about improving DNI
unless you really understand the space that you're
working within, and on just a deep, fundamental, valuable
level in the organization that you're a part of.
So to step back, I'm going to do a deep dive
into my background leading up to Riot.
I get this question asked a lot, like, what do you do?
And it's mostly from people who are also interested in coming
into the space.
And I kind of have, like, a very wonky.
route getting into the role that I'm in today.
So I just wanted to talk about that a little bit.
And I feel like to, my philosophy on diversity
and inclusion has evolved in a way, hopefully,
and has matured alongside sort of my interest
coming into it.
So I've been a gamer my whole life.
My two earliest memories were actually in Saudi Arabia
and they were,
Michael Jackson's Moonwalker on Sega,
and the Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles game on NES.
And when I was seven, my family had just immigrated
to Canada for about a couple years,
and I'm the youngest of a really big family.
So I was kind of left alone.
while they were teaching themselves English,
I was kind of left alone because like,
it's when you're five,
it's pretty easy to pick up another language.
So I had all these floppy disks that were like,
vocabulary games and math games in addition,
but then I found another floppy disk that had Doom 2.
And that's kind of when I became a gamer for,
and I knew that this is something that I wanted to do
for the rest of my life.
But when it came to like an academic and professional life,
I didn't get into games right away.
So at first I studied political science and criminology.
And I say it's because I wanted to be a human rights lawyer,
but I think I just wanted a sexy, crime-fighting forensics
job.
And fortunately, that dream dissipated.
But unfortunately, I took into film studies and philosophy,
so I wanted to be unemployed for the rest of my life.
But this is really the point where
I started looking at media and like representation in media
and race relations in media
and how powerful of a tool it can be.
I specialize specifically in black exploitation cinema
and Palestinian cinema.
And this is where a lot of my interests
in terms of like, okay, the media that we have
is not just entertainment,
it could be something really meaningful and valuable.
And not just because we see diverse characters in something,
but they're actually,
the
Films in black exploitation in Palestinian cinema
are made by those people.
So it's very much an introspective externalization.
So I then moved to Toronto.
I pursued my master's in, again, nothing game related.
It was film and photographic preservation.
And strangely, this is actually
where my career in games began.
So Toronto has an awesome indie game scene.
And it was there that I stumbled upon
Dane's making games and they're like all here,
like dispersed throughout.
So if you see them, you should say hello to them
and find out what they're working on.
They're a great initiative.
It's a non-profit to support women and non-binary folks
to make games and provide them with mentorship
and accessible tools, particularly open source tools.
And this blew my mind because up until this point,
I hadn't really seen people make games
when they didn't have technical backgrounds.
one of the sort of myths about the tech industry
is that you have to be a programmer
or you have to be a computer scientist to make it big
and that's not true.
And this is where DMG really started to shape a lot
of how I felt about game making.
And really up until this point in my life,
I never really like played indie games.
It was mostly AAA games and the indie games
were ones that were on console.
It's not kind of like.
how today there's a lot of, you know,
there are marketplaces on consoles
where there's tons of indie games.
This was before that was happening.
So this was a really cool experience.
I volunteered with them for a couple of years
and then shortly after that,
I sat on their board of directors.
And this is where I seriously started thinking about
accessible game making and how many stories
that aren't represented in blockbuster games
that can be mobilized in, like, through indie game making.
One of my favorite highlights was Indigicaid.
And it's a collaboration between DMG
and the Indigenous Routes Collective
to teach a group of six indigenous girls and women
between the age of 13 to 24
on how to make their first video game from scratch.
And this was really eye-opening for me.
It was eye-opening to watch this group
give voice to their experiences and imaginations
in a way that is entirely new to them.
They were artists in different ways,
but this is the first time
that they're using game-making tools.
And like, game making is really intimidating.
Even when you know what you're doing,
it's an overwhelming career choice to get into.
And so mentoring just one of the women
to help her create her story,
that gave me a lot of hope for the future
of girls and women of color in games.
So at this point in my career,
I considered dropping out of grad school.
And I didn't, and there's like one reason
I feel like that I didn't drop out of grad school.
My master's thesis was so not what photo historians wanted to talk about or deal with that they
buddied me up with a game studies professor.
So we just spent most of our time talking about Resident Evil and he was just like,
yeah, submit it whenever you're ready.
Sweet.
So one point.
But the changes really started in terms of the changes in how I thought about diverse
communities and indie game making.
it really started to foster when I worked
in community management for a mobile game studio
called Yukon.
And I was also lecturing about DIY game making on the side.
So I had the pleasure to speak at Brandeis at NYU.
I got to Skype into Birzeit University in Ramallah
in the West Bank, which is awesome.
I'm half Palestinian, so that was a really huge moment
for me.
And at the same time running workshops
on text adventures game, text, that,
text adventure games, there we go.
at OCAD, York, and Ryerson University.
So at this point, I was particularly interested
in understanding marginalized communities and their voices.
And by that, I mean groups that are often not included
as part of the status quo.
They've been othered in society,
either implicitly or explicitly,
due to differences in race, gender, sexuality,
disability, socioeconomic status, and religion, and so forth.
And I wanted to be part of including and appreciating
different voices outside of non-profits.
Like, non-profits, when you're already
a community of activists, it's quite easy
to kind of do a grassroots collaboration
and get started on D&I initiatives.
What I wanted to do was actually work at an organization.
Because really, I wanted to normalize D&I.
I wanted to have it be something that we all can talk about
and that we all feel pretty comfortable talking about.
At first it was mostly about boosting marginalized voices,
but to also raise the quality bar
of teams in creative spaces.
So when Riot was looking for a manager of D&I programs,
I thought, this is the kind of role
I've been working towards.
You know, like despite the twists and turns in my life,
like a common thread is that I'm a pretty political person.
It's really difficult for me to view the world
in a way that's not influenced by my gender or my race.
That's always kind of a prevalent lens.
And this didn't change when I talked about games
or worked within them or mentored folks.
So in case this is a relatively new topic
for some of you in the audience,
I wanna just touch on the conversations
about diversity and inclusion in the games
and the tech world and kind of circle back
into sort of how my philosophy has grown
leading up to my role.
So diversity is on a lot of people's minds.
with something like Facebook, Google, Apple.
They're releasing their demographic data every year,
and they're recognizing that, hey,
we have an overwhelming status quo.
We want to be better at representing under,
at including underrepresented groups to have better balance
and to have, you know, better outcomes.
Because there's a lot of evidence
to support the benefits of the DNI.
When a group of people is trying to solve a complex problem,
progress often results.
from when diverse perspectives are brought in.
So it's not just about how smart or capable you are,
but how much you're willing to look at a problem
through a multitude of different ways
and then you land a breakthrough.
So when a group of intelligent individuals
are trying to solve a problem,
the diversity of those individuals
has just as much if not more potential
than just their ability or their education alone.
And there's also evidence that implicit biases
and stereotypes break down trust
and productivity and morale in teams.
So our implicit biases refer to attitudes
or stereotypes that affect our decisions.
They also affect our understanding and our actions
in an unintended or unconscious way.
So they're pervasive.
They usually favor our own in-group
and they actually don't always align
with what our declared beliefs are.
So we can.
say one thing but our implicit biases actually that affect our actions indicate maybe sometimes
the opposite or just a different route.
So these sorts of biases create echo chambers or groupthink, and that's detrimental to teams
and individuals in them.
They impact how we communicate, which can also dominate what
sort of direction you're going through on a project, or if you are in a meeting about
maybe compensation or performance management. That's a lot of areas where our biases can
trickle in. So it sounds pretty obvious that, you know, we'd want to be working on these
spaces. If diversity of thought coming from a diversity of people and a diversity of experiences
is a good thing, then let's fix it. But it's difficult. Getting it right is complicated.
And one of the first reasons, honestly,
is that it's really overwhelming.
Diversity and inclusion,
some of the most common sorts of concerns that I hear
is that it focuses on one group over other.
Like, you have to include everybody in this,
and that can be overwhelming,
and you have to start somewhere,
and where do you start,
and why do you start with that group, et cetera, et cetera.
And on top of understanding,
different experiences and different perspectives,
it takes a lot of introspection
to break down implicit biases,
and that doesn't always feel great.
Like, whether we like it or not, we all have biases.
It's neurologically impossible to not have them.
And it can be really uncomfortable
to try and unlearn our socializations,
the things that we grew up thinking,
like, this has always been like this,
it's always been this way,
these jokes have always been funny.
That's hard to undo.
So, for example, if any of you have ever had
to address your own privilege,
you'll know that it's a very uncomfortable thing
to do at first.
Privilege seems like a very dirty, very loaded word.
And really, it's more about, it's a study
of how we all have blind spots due to our lived experiences.
And there's no way that you are going
to understand every lived experiences
just because you haven't actually experienced them.
That's all that it really means.
It's that recognition that, okay, this doesn't affect me,
but I also have never had that experience.
So I understand that you also haven't had my experiences
and so forth.
But the thing is, like every one of us,
we wanna believe that the reason we're successful in life
is due to a constant hard work.
When the revelation is made that, hey,
we actually all face different obstacles,
and sometimes that means that you are further ahead
than others by things that you can't control,
like gender or race or wealth or physical ability.
it can feel like a punch to the gut.
And it's especially complicated
when identities are made up of balancing intersections
of their advantages and disadvantages
from majority and minority groups.
So for example, I'm a woman, I'm a woman of color,
I face sexism, I face racism,
but I also have high education, I have a good job.
There's all of these things that sort of make up like,
hey, these are places I don't struggle,
but these are places that I have struggled.
And it's important to see ourselves
as a sum of many parts and that they're not necessarily
opposites, right?
They're not like battling with each other.
They're more of just tensions and frictions
that we just have to understand on a deeper level.
Another reason diversity initiatives
are difficult to get right comes from a belief
that people should be rewarded based
on their merit, which is based on their ability and effort.
This is what's known as a meritocracy.
So meritocracy is like the best ideas rise to the top
based on whether or not they're actually the best ideas.
And that's a theoretically super sound,
fair, clean cut approach.
But in reality, there's evidence showing
that unchecked meritocracies can lead
to a higher likelihood of bias.
And that's because there's kind of this pursuit
of objectivity that's not really possible.
None of us can actually be truly objective.
And especially when we're working in creative spaces,
that's.
that's even harder to become objective
because it's all about emotion and passion
and gut feelings.
So, does that mean, fuck meritocracy,
let's never talk about it again,
let's do something different?
I would actually say not really.
I still think there's a benefit to it
if we're willing to actually make it work.
And using it as an aspiration,
that can actually help us identify
the behaviors that would stifle it.
So,
The sort of famous research that came out about,
it's called the Paradox of Meritocracy,
was made by Emilio J. Castilla.
And he's a professor at MIT's Sloan School of Management.
He's written extensively and researched extensively
about these issues.
And at a Stanford conference,
he was addressing the sort of like,
well, if it's a paradox, should we even try and pursue it?
And he says, it doesn't mean the pursuit is futile.
My research provides a cautionary lesson
that practices implemented to increase fairness and equity
need to be carefully addressed,
need to be carefully thought through, sorry,
so that potential opportunities for biases are addressed.
And the thing is, it's a prevalent thing
in the tech industry, which we're a part of.
So meritocracy is a core belief at Riot,
and we recently had a roundtable internally
to talk about specifically the intersection
of meritocracy and diversity.
What influences it, what doesn't influence it?
Like we actually have to address this problem
instead of sort of being too afraid to say like,
hey, there's a problem with meritocracy.
I don't wanna, you know, I don't wanna start any trouble.
It's like, no, let's talk about it.
Let's see how we can actually make this work.
We also have teams that are dedicated to building models
for solving this kind of issue.
Like.
How do you define fairness?
And how do you know that somebody is being fairly rewarded
or fairly recognized?
The more aware of where we can all make mistakes as humans
as part of the process,
the more likely that something as sort of idealistic
as meritocracy could actually be closer to be a reality.
And honestly, my philosophy
is that diversity and meritocracy,
they're not opposing ends of a spectrum.
It's not one or the other.
they're really working together in a symbiotic relationship.
Like, how do you know that you have the best ideas rising
to the top if everybody on the team
has very like-minded thoughts?
Like, if you're all in an echo chamber
and it's all groupthink, you're not actually
getting the best ideas.
You're getting what you think is the best idea.
If more diverse perspectives are included,
will the best ideas that rise to the top
actually end up looking different from each other?
And there's so much.
creativity bursting from marginalized communities in video games.
So if I could find a way to be part of including and inspiring and empowering
different voices and therefore help teams be more successful,
that's a future that I wanted to be a part of.
So fast forward,
I'm a D and I manager and my hope is that like I'm going to change the world.
I'm going to make it a better place and I'm going to do it my first 90 days
preferably. Um, but you know,
no big deal if I need to wait a couple of months before making this like amazing
breakthrough in the world.
I just wanted to make an impact really,
and I knew it wasn't going to be easy,
but I figured the first baby steps would be pretty clear.
Like, okay, let's partner with diversity initiatives, easy.
And hey, if implicit biases are a problem,
let's develop courses and training
and programs to tackle them.
So cool, plan is all laid out.
And none of it happens.
And.
There's really no shortage of support.
It wasn't like anybody stopped me
from pursuing the plans that I had laid out.
It really wasn't about that.
It was that for all the nuance involved in this space
and how overwhelming and intimidating it can be,
people are actually very curious
about making diversity and inclusion work.
want to get involved.
There's really no one stopping me.
But I was just missing a vital piece of the information,
which is really that if you want to make something work,
you have to understand why you're doing it
on a very foundational, fundamental, philosophical level.
The problem is that I spent a lot of time
trying to tack on solutions
to an existing organizational culture
without deeply understanding
how they'll interact with each other.
I was essentially undoing my own work
and doing myself a huge disservice.
So what I really needed to do was step back
and reassess my own assumptions coming into this place,
coming into this line of work.
So two months into my role,
Harvard Business Review published an article titled,
Diversity Policies Rarely Make Companies Fairer
and They Feel Threatening to White Men,
which is a brutal, which is a brutal headline.
And to summarize what, and it's always the case
where it's like the headline is super brutal,
but like the content is actually like pretty chill.
Like it's not like crazy.
But to summarize, it found that companies
that were using the existence of a diversity policy,
they use it as a logical or legal defense
to sort of discount claims of unfair treatment.
And white men who were the status quo in these examples,
they perceived women and minorities
as being treated differently,
so they perceived it as they were then
being treated unfairly.
They were the ones being treated differently too,
but in a negative way.
It's hard for me to not panic at first reading this,
because it's like, I just got hired to do this.
But it actually makes sense.
And I was like the first person to sort of,
that Riot hired to tackle these issues, sorry, head on.
People had been thinking and talking about diversity.
They were super involved in it,
especially since in the games and tech industry specifically
it was kind of exploding all of a sudden.
Everybody wanted to talk about it.
But this is the first time somebody who's me
was like hired to work on this full time
and actually develop a solution.
So, small panic attack over after reading that article,
I realized that these reactions make complete sense.
These reactions to policies and trainings
and sort of like sensitivity training sessions,
they make sense.
And the reason I feel it's because
people don't change because of company policy.
I feel like
There are some folks in here who work in HR
can probably attest to that, where it's like,
yeah, if you put up a policy,
it's not like everybody's going to be suddenly inspired
to change all of the behaviors
that are included with that policy.
focusing on policies doesn't actually address
the root cause of exclusionary behavior.
And diversity policies especially,
they can create an illusion that's not real.
They can create an illusion that different people
are treated, that they're unfairly rewarded
or unfairly treated or that they're
too fairly treated and rewarded.
And that causes a lot of tension and resentment internally.
So we're pretty quick to think of tactics like policies
or trainings to solve D&I issues.
But without understanding what it is that we're aiming for
or trying to learn or trying to change,
a lot of damage can be unintentionally done
because of distrust or misperceptions.
So there are a couple of key values
that I wanted to share today
that I found particularly helpful for my own growth
as a diversity inclusion manager.
And my hypothesis is that hopefully what I share
can help programs be successful and meaningful
and have lasting effect.
So it's not about not having programs.
It's not about not having policies.
It's about understanding why you're doing them.
So as a D&I manager, I'm obviously, I'm for the people.
And that probably sounds super obvious,
but it's all people.
Everybody wants to talk to the diversity inclusion manager
because we all have different experiences
that we believe are valuable to our teams.
But there was this light bulb moment
that where I had to pivot how I engaged with everyone,
not just everybody at my work,
but also in the industry as well.
This is the part of the larger sort of D&I discourse
that I feel like a lot of professionals don't stress
and it can be really easy to take for granted.
Because I came in thinking like, all right, I'm an advocate.
I'm going to find all the underrepresented groups.
I'm going to peer them out.
And I'm going to create programs and initiatives
based on what they need.
And that sounds like a great thing to do.
Because it's not a bad thing to do.
That's not a negative solution.
But without taking the time to understand the majority groups
that these underrepresented groups are collaborating
with on a daily basis and working with on a daily basis.
Programs and trainings and so forth that are targeting the majority groups will probably feel a little bit like this
Gentle persuasion
So especially with the current political climate
Building bridges to each other now is more crucial than ever
So NPR published an article
about how after the American election,
there was this new version of us versus them,
and where professional peacemakers,
who would be diversity managers,
share some of the immediate challenges
of a deeply divided country,
like addressing the concerns of people
usually thought of as privileged,
or having to navigate a language minefield
where the wrong word can ignite conflict.
And speaking of my own personal experiences after the election,
it was just like all of a sudden everybody on Facebook had an opinion
and everybody wanted to tell you it.
And there was just like threads of drama and blocking and freak outs.
And it makes, like, there's a lot of anxiety right now.
There is a lot of tension.
And there's an uptick that, you know,
I don't think a lot of people were expecting to see in 2017.
We're seeing more division and resentment.
It's leading to isolation.
It's resorting to groupthink.
and we're starting to fear the unknown.
And there's a restlessness and a whirlwind of breaking news.
Like every day, something new is happening and it's awful.
And it's like moving leaders and managers
to sort of have to realize,
how do I keep the calm internally?
And how do I like call for everybody to unite?
And there's also growing research on how social media
is disrupting the way that we communicate with each other
about specifically political issues.
And I've been seeing a lot of parallels personally
with how that's been specifically
affecting the D&I conversation.
And if we don't address the sort of disconnect
that's happening between how people look at each other
politically and how people look at each other,
how people communicate to each other on social media,
I feel like we're ignoring a vital piece of the puzzle.
And it's most recently played an unprecedented role
in the American election and in the current administration.
Like in January, we saw press secretary Sean Spicer,
the Spice Man, hold up a printed tweet
to address it at an actual press conference.
Like at the rate that we're going,
we're gonna see political tweets in textbooks.
It's gonna be part of language.
And like, listen, like as a millennial,
I hate when people blame shit on social media,
even though that's like low key
what I'm trying to do right now.
Because obviously like majority and minority tensions,
like tensions between majority and minority groups,
that's been around forever.
But it's impossible to kind of ignore the growing impact
of how online spaces directly frame
and affect the conversations that we have in person
as colleagues and as teammates.
And we in the games industry especially,
we have a lexicon that's built almost entirely
on how we speak on the internet.
Like we engage and care about an audience
that knows the ins and outs of Reddit.
They call us out for misusing memes
and make sure to know that we're embarrassing ourselves.
And they can easily out shit post all of us combined.
In terms of social media affecting D&I in games,
a number of initiatives and movements began as hashtags,
and they sparked into something bigger.
So this point and example,
it began as hashtag one reason why,
where a designer asked on Twitter
why there are so few women creating games,
and hundreds of women responded
with anecdotes of sexism in the industry.
And that evolved into hashtag one reason to be.
And this was started,
again on Twitter in response by narrative designer Rihanna Pratchett
as to the positive reasons of why women are in games and why
they should stay in games and why they should pursue their career
in games. And this evolved into a series of GDC panels where women
and minorities empower each other and inspire creators to make the industry
more inclusive and to make us a better place.
We also can't deny how
social media field groups like GamerGate or the alt-right,
and that have hugely impacted the conversations
that we have every day about D&I.
So what we're seeing is kind of like this wild evolution
of not only media and how media is changing,
but also our language with each other.
Because on the one hand, you have free, accessible tools
that are potential platforms and opportunities,
which is a key part of mobilizing groups and ideas.
And on the other hand,
you have free accessible tools that are potential platforms
and opportunities, which is a key part of mobilizing groups
and ideas.
So you have this potential for greater good
and incredible change and this other potential
of just raging dumpster fires.
But really what I've noticed the most within this new lexicon
is that we have a tendency to group people
and shorthand them with labels
that are loaded with assumptions.
I've seen far too many conversations and I've like,
I've had to catch myself from being part
of those conversations where we devolve
into a reductive dismissal of the other person
and those reductive dismissals like appear
on social media first.
So like, you're a Bernie bro or you're a Feminazi
or like you're a triggered snowflake.
Like that all happens online but we actually use
that sort of thinking too in person.
And it's this quick clumping of.
people to an online identity, it bleeds into the way that we talk to each other in real
life.
And even if we're more politically or philosophically aligned than not, I can't say that I'm entirely
surprised.
There are years of shorthanding and labeling and grouping that we've socially assigned
each other that up until this point we're a very divided country.
We're reducing each other to identities and affiliations and not considering much else.
There is a great talk by Howard J. Ross,
who he spoke about managing fear,
managing bias in a time of fear.
And it was all specifically about this kind of work,
where it's like, how do you,
people feel a lot of anxiety,
where it's like, there the rise of sort of like,
Black Lives Matter, and then people feeling like,
do you mean like only Black Lives Matter,
or like Black Lives Matter too?
And then it kind of grows and grows,
and especially with the election, you have,
people reducing to each other to like,
what do you believe in and what do you believe in
versus anything else.
We've lost a lot of nuance.
So as a D&I manager, if I'm working for the people,
I have to understand what makes them tick,
what gives them pause, or else nothing that I give them
is gonna address the root sort of cause
of intolerance or exclusion.
That means engaging with people I vehemently disagree with.
And mind you, I'm not talking about trolls.
I'm talking about people that you're working with,
people in your industry, your peer group.
If we believe that games are such a profound,
core part of our lives,
then we have to be working together on this.
And it's not easy.
Coming from, oops, sorry,
just like brushed up against my mic,
that probably didn't sound great.
Coming from a non-profit that's rooted in social activism
and moving directly into the industry
where this is a conversation people are having
for the first time, that made me have to stop
and sort of refamiliarize myself with how I got into.
this space and the sort of ways that I've stumbled along the way.
And that can be super humbling and grounding and a reminder that we all have to start somewhere.
So when we focus on building relationships, we're making an effort to find where bridges
can connect, not watch them burn in the rearview mirror.
And that's just one part of my hypothesis.
You know, I'm not only invested in working with people
who are heavily affected by diversity concerns,
but also the skeptics and especially the people
who are indifferent, the people who can kind of take it
or leave it or never really had an opinion either way.
And again, that might sound really painfully obvious,
but like it's super blindsiding when that is not part
of the core conversations that we have in D&I as a peer group.
And another core part in navigating the space
in a way that feels more authentic
and is more meaningful to me
is by fostering an organizational mindset
that embraces diversity.
And that means digging deep into a company culture
and embedding values and frameworks of thought
when it comes to diversity seamlessly into it.
Diversity is more like a model that matures over time
and taking shortcuts in order to increase head counts
or improve quotas.
aren't addressing the real problem of what might actually be alienating people, which
could very well be your company culture.
So knowing the core values of a company is when D&I programs become more of a rational
choice.
Like obviously we would go for something like this instead of giving way to sort of a righteous
moral stance or paying lip service to what's seen as a hot topic issue.
Again, investing in this is not just a theoretically good thing to do.
It's something that gives companies competitive edge
and makes them more innovative.
So let's say, for example, as a company,
you value teamwork and creativity,
and that's kind of seen what's upholding the company vision.
What you can do is that maybe instead of adding training
that's like high-level implicit biases,
hey, here are all the different biases that you can have,
a solution would be to actually put together
like a team-building workshop.
to address biases and behaviors that exclude other people who
are trying to collaborate with each other.
And this is obviously where diversity heavily overlaps
into biases and how they can break down team morale.
It's this alignment of, hey, well, if we care about teams,
then on the positive side, this is
what a healthy team looks like and the results that they get.
And on a negative side, this is how toxicity can form.
That could be a better starting point
to actually start initiating changes.
to address actual root causes, to get people to look more deeply into themselves and to
be more introspective.
So embedding diversity of thought as like a core tenet of a company's mental model,
that's really helped me understand how to connect with my peers in a deeper way regardless
of our political or philosophical differences.
Because now we have a value that binds us,
and it's the value, it's why we come to work every day.
It's our common ground.
A mindset that encourages diversity, in my opinion,
is psychologist Carol Dweck's growth mindset principle,
which I mentioned at the beginning of my talk.
So to summarize, Dweck makes a distinction
between two mindsets.
The first is a fixed mindset,
and this is when people believe qualities
like intelligence or talent
are predetermined or unchangeable traits.
and that influences how they grow.
So students, Dweck found that students
that have a fixed mindset are more likely to learn slower,
they're more likely to give up on challenges,
and they're more likely to avoid taking risks.
A growth mindset is when people believe
that qualities can be developed
through dedication and hard work.
It's like building a muscle.
So she found that students who embrace growth mindsets
were more likely to learn quickly.
and view challenges and failures as opportunities to improve rather than confirmations that,
well, I was never good at this to begin with, so why should I even do it?
Applying that framework to an organizational mindset is so important.
Like when a company embraces a growth mindset,
the kinds of people that thrive are the ones who aren't afraid of being wrong.
They're the ones that are not afraid of making mistakes.
They see conflicts and tensions as learning opportunities.
And they see different perspectives that test their own
as ultimately positive and educational.
And really up until this point,
I had been so hyper-focused on delivering DNI as a product.
Like, here it is, diversity and inclusion, we did it.
And like leaders in that, like, sorry, totally jumped ahead.
The thing is that no one solves it.
Even as researchers uncover more data
about the inclusion of underrepresented groups,
we're still finding more problems.
So as companies are including more people,
they're finding that they're actually
maybe including more white women.
There's more diversity of white women.
And black indigenous people of color
are still being underrepresented.
And there's a lot of sociological layers
kind of mixed in that you have to be aware of.
And when you're thinking of a global mindset,
if it's a global company,
you have to understand that the problems
that affect North America
are not the problems that affect Brazil.
They're not the problems that affect Turkey.
You have to really.
think deeply and when you embrace a growth mindset,
that means that as more data is uncovered
about how diversity can keep diversifying,
leaders in the space can develop alongside those changes.
And one of the examples is the way
that hiring managers think about candidates.
Like if you're prioritizing people who wanna hire,
if you're prioritizing learners,
not people who are self-proclaimed geniuses or rock stars,
you're creating a possibility for growth.
Learners, they know they don't have all the solutions,
but they will do whatever it takes to get them.
And they'll see failure as part of the process.
and not as a setback or a reason to give up.
And this tactic is actually specifically to target
women who either opt out of applying to jobs
that say like, hey, we want rock stars,
hey, we want geniuses,
because they're less likely to see themselves as such,
but if they do go through the process,
they're more likely to be stereotyped against
as not being geniuses and not being rock stars.
So a fixed mindset will probably tell you
that this is a risky thing to do.
But I do want to add that yes,
it's risky to hire people based on their potential
versus here is proof that I have done
all the rockstar awesome genius things in my life.
But keep in mind that our industry is almost entirely based on taking risks.
From crowd-sourced indie-developed games
to the ambitious of new studios or first-timers,
the chances of failure are extremely high all the time.
And a growth mindset can extend outside the hiring process, too.
So there's an awesome podcast, it's called Code Switch.
I talk about it all the time, so of course I'm going to shoehorn it here.
It's called Code Switch.
It's by journalists Shireen Marisol Maragi and Jeanne Demby.
And one episode featured Professor Catherine Orr,
who teaches courses on whiteness
as part of critical identity studies at Beloit College.
So she framed the teaching of race relations
specifically with regards to white privilege
as an intellectual habit.
And that means that her class would ask themselves
questions that have to do with understanding
who they are in the room.
How or why did they get to where they are?
And then allowing those questions
to begin informing their situations outside the classroom.
So teaching complex, nuanced topics related to diversity
as if it was an intellectual habit,
that would have all of us stop and ask ourselves,
why do I prefer living in this neighborhood?
Why do I not feel great when a friend of mine
who looks different than me has this controversial view
on my favorite hobby?
Why did I feel really great about that candidate?
The concept of a growth mindset where D&I concepts
and experiences that we have about D&I
That is what ultimately, if we're thinking about things as an intellectual habit,
that can fundamentally shift the conversations that we have.
And ultimately, that will be the thing that affects programs and trainings and initiatives.
So where do I go from here?
I've been thinking about this problem space
for just over a year now.
And for starters, D&I at Riot,
it originally sat as a pod of just me.
Like I'm the diversity and inclusion person team right here.
And it sat within talent,
which is our human resources discipline.
And I was mostly thinking about like,
okay, how do I affect?
learning and development. How do I affect our rewards and perks? How do we make that
more inclusive? How do we make things more diverse? But this year we're actually building
an initiative in the company that works directly on defining, strengthening, and expanding
the foundations of our organizational culture.
So our team is now dedicated to keeping a pulse on culture,
which means codifying the values that we find crucial
and how we work together and communicate with each other
and ensuring that those values are baked into projects
and programs across Riot.
And that affects things like manager development
or performance management, leadership development, and...
That, like we, and all levels of sort of decision making
across the company.
So we're ensuring that we're thoughtful
and that we're consistent in how our values manifest
from the inside out.
So that means thinking about how do we work together?
How do we collaborate?
How do we make decisions?
How do we communicate and share stories with each other
and also with our players and also with our peers?
We take culture extremely seriously.
And we believe that being deliberate about who we are,
that will help us grow and evolve in the right way.
And we want to hold all rioters accountable
to upholding our culture.
And the fact that D&I is now a part of that team,
that's a significant shift forward.
Because it doesn't actually change about whether or not I consider programs and
trainings and policies, et cetera, as potential outputs.
These are things that can still happen.
But we're actually thinking about it not as a pocket that influences part of
the organization, but as something that is deeply embedded in our values,
which fuels our passion.
At the end of the day, diversity is everyone's problem.
It's not just talents, it's not legals,
it's not just PRs or marketings or philanthropies.
It's part of everyday life and public discourse.
And when it becomes integral to your organization's success,
people start to buy in on their own.
You don't have to convince them.
Because now everyone knows that they have a stake in it,
that they have a stake in improving it,
and they have a stake in making the company stronger.
So I hope that what I shared today about learning to build bridges to all types of people and
having a belief system that welcomes growth and flourishes under challenges is helpful.
Keep in mind, it is a very hard thing to do.
You're not going to wake up one day and just have all of these things sort of clear and
cut.
It takes patience, it takes time, and constant action.
And it'll be messy, and it will be awkward,
and it will be frustrating.
But my bet is that if we learn to do this,
if we learn to unite and work together,
not only as a company, but as part of an industry,
we can make diversity and inclusion work.
So I wanna thank you for listening and GDC for having me.
And just a reminder, you will get a...
survey to say like, how'd she do?
And you can be like, oh God, finally, she's terrible.
And there will be a, we have 10 minutes for questions
and there will be a wrap up room that we can move over
if we're going over time.
There is a mic in the middle of the room.
So if you can please speak clearly into the mic,
I would deeply appreciate that.
Great talk, thank you so much.
Thank you.
A few months ago I came across Dr. Robin D'Angelo's
work on white fragility.
You familiar with that?
I am.
Okay, so very briefly, I'm sure you are,
for very briefly for those who aren't,
like I wasn't just a few months ago,
the way I remember it all is people like me
often think of racism specifically as a binary issue
and an individual issue.
So I or somebody else is either racist or not,
and it's good and bad.
And what a lot of people like me don't understand
is how systemic it is and how much gray there is in between.
So that was, woo, light bulb for me, super helpful.
Question is, do you find that helpful
in the work you do around racism?
And is there equal fragility?
Does that framework work for other inclusion issues?
Yeah, I found...
Honestly, taking the time to explain to people in a very sort of soft and gentle way how
these things are, how these things can affect you on a daily basis where it's like, hey,
it's not that you're racist, it's that you've just grown up only knowing this thing and
only believing this thing is right.
That has a much, I feel like that's super useful.
And really, like part of me hates that we sometimes have to sterilize a lot of the
real pain and real anger from underrepresented groups and marginalized communities to sort
of make other people feel better. But again, as like NPR calls it, diversity managers are
professional peacemakers. You have to sort of work within that framework. So yeah, I
have found it really helpful. And also what I found working really well, surprisingly,
is teaching people about intersectionality, is teaching people that you're not just one
thing or the other, that you are a person who's had many experiences and maybe
you have sort of invisible disadvantages
that other people don't see,
but they will make assumptions that you're super advantaged
when they look at you.
That has been a very helpful approach
in just calling out the nuance
and sort of reducing this binary thinking that you mentioned.
Yeah, thank you.
Hi.
Hey there.
Great talk.
I'm Shrek.
I'm from New Zealand.
Hi.
I'm glad you brought up the topic of nuance. And so I would like to introduce one of those
nuances and get your thoughts on it. And that's that say
myself as an Indian dude from south India, growing up for instance, one of the anecdotes I
like to bring up is that when I was around 12 years old, I won a violin award. Sounds like a
great thing, right? I have this creative side. And you would think that my community would
reward that. But the sort of response to that was actually that my parents would grill me that I
didn't actually get an academic award, right?
And now I work in games, right?
So, you know, but what it took for there to be this sort of acceptance in my family that this was okay
was this sort of 10-year struggle of constant conversation and constant criticism of my own community, right?
So when we talk about diversity and conclusion, I often see
that there's this onus on the majority to welcome us in.
And I completely agree.
That's totally valid.
But what I see missing from the conversation is active
criticism of minority communities, because it helps
the leaders in those communities, right?
It helps us to challenge our own communities
so that they can grow.
I mean, don't get me started on if I was a woman.
I mean, I'd probably be right now married with two kids,
right?
What I just want to throw out there,
and I'd like to get your thoughts on it,
is where does the role of criticism come in, right?
And as a majority towards a minority,
and I'll let you take it from there.
I think it depends on the goal of the conversation.
Like, are you criticizing,
like, when people criticize each other,
criticism is a good thing.
But if it is,
if it's not to get a deeper understanding,
that's when I feel like it's a problem.
So right now, with all the Islamophobia,
it's kind of like how I feel.
I grew up in a, I'm non-practicing,
but I grew up in a Muslim family,
and it kind of always feels like I have to explain
on behalf of the billions of,
billion of Muslims across the world
of this is why we might think this way,
or this is why this thing might have happened.
So it really depends on what is being asked.
I think healthy criticism is crucial,
but if it's kind of like a.
If it further, if you're trying to go for nuance,
but you're actually furthering, reducing the problem
and making it more binary,
that's where I think it's like,
you need to step back and just understand
what you're trying to achieve.
Cool.
Do you think there's a place in an organization
to criticize minority communities?
That depends.
Can you give me an example of what you mean by that?
I just meant that the focus is entirely, seems to be to be inclusive, but to also go and
challenge individuals and grow their leadership skills and things like that.
I kind of meant, yeah.
Let me, you know what, I think my answer will probably take a bit longer.
Let me think about that and I'll meet you in the wrap-up room.
I'll see you there.
Thank you.
Hi.
I work in Japan in a Japanese company and 97% are Japanese.
In that kind of a context, I can tell you that this kind of slow and steady approach isn't going to work in my situation to create diversity.
I've been sent here as a foreigner to try and bring diversity back to the Japanese company.
Do you have any kind of more specific tactical ideas?
Maybe you could share with me later for how to...
try and change the situation there.
The company is about 40 years old.
It's a gaming company.
Well, they have a gaming division,
but they're not really committed to gaming.
The culture is messed up.
And this is a company, sorry if I
might have misheard you, in Japan?
Yeah, it's a Japanese company in Japan.
I think you have to sort of like short answer,
and then we can talk more,
is you have to understand what diversity
they're looking for.
They don't know.
They don't know, okay.
Well, this is like, this is sort of, thank you,
this is sort of like the time for assessment.
I feel like my, one of the most crucial things
that D&I managers.
might not do right away is actually do a full assessment
of what is the pockets that are missing?
What is the story that's missing?
Do you think that manager should be Japanese or foreign?
I don't really have an answer for that.
Yeah.
We can talk later.
Thanks.
Hi.
I like to talk.
I have these diversity discussions sometimes.
I wondered, do you have any advice
on how to keep your cool when you're talking with someone
about an issue that deeply affects you
but doesn't affect them and they don't believe
it's actually harmful to you or that kind of thing?
Meditation has really helped me.
To kind of go back to the second question,
That was answered.
This idea of what is the goal, right?
Sometimes I have to set very clear parameters of listen,
I can try and help you understand
why people would feel a certain way,
but I'm not gonna sit here and justify why I'm upset.
You just need to accept that I'm upset about this thing.
And I find that that kind of sets the tone
of the conversation that not only helps them understand
that they don't have to like.
you know, be sort of a devil's advocate.
They don't have to play that position.
But it also helps me look at, kind of distance myself
and be a bit more anthropological
when trying to talk about my problems.
And that's kind of what I've, like, being very intentional
and setting a tone from the very beginning
is pretty crucial.
Like, I've seen conversations,
so we actually have like an internal Slack group
for diversity.
And there I've seen people use pretty great tactics of like,
I can't get into why I'm upset right now,
but like short points,
like this is how I feel about this thing.
Happy to talk about it more later,
but sort of short version.
And I feel like that has only been met
with like understanding and respect and compassion
because of people understand like,
okay, you're actually trying to open up to me
and this is a difficult thing to talk about.
That's helped.
Okay, thank you so much.
Yeah, thank you.
We have two minutes.
Okay, I think this might be a quick one.
Thank you for the talk, it was lovely.
In your work at Riot, would you say that most
of your attention and I guess your job,
your energy is going toward potential or new hires?
Or would it be more of like changing the internal,
like who's already there and being more inclusive
to the people that maybe already exist there?
Or both, I guess.
Yeah, so.
For me, it's actually been more so of the latter,
so that when new people are introduced and brought in,
they actually feel included,
and they actually feel like they're part of the culture.
I feel like when you're,
part of the problem that I personally have
with sort of headcounts
and trying to increase quotas of people,
is that if you're not understanding
why maybe you do have those underrepresented groups
to begin with,
bringing them in might not.
be the most obvious solution.
But I also don't think that those things
have to be one or the other, right?
I think that these two things can happen in parallel
and they can work together.
Thank you very much.
Yeah, thank you.
It's maybe less of a two minute question, so I apologize.
But you mentioned in your presentation
like fostering relationships with people who are not affected by DNI.
And I was curious if you could elaborate a little bit on that,
because I, too, am a little bit tired of for my entire life
being the one Arab Muslim that you know and being the good one and all that.
So.
it gets a little bit exhausting, particularly in this current climate.
So my gut instinct is, why do we need to seek those people out every single time?
I mean, is that not what we've been doing pretty much all the time?
So if you could just...
I think it's because people have an understanding or an assumption that
when you're talking about islamophobia or you're talking about racism,
you're talking about KKK or something so incredibly obvious and straightforward
that without addressing the daily ways that you can...
you know, undermine somebody or disengage somebody from a conversation because they
don't feel safe having that conversation.
That's where I feel like most of our problems are at.
We're actually just out of time.
So I would love to talk to you more about that, especially Arab Muslim.
I feel you.
Thank you so much.