New Orleans, a modern city with traditional southern values.
I'm asking me how far he was going to go.
What he was willing to do.
This is the city that survived the war in 1812.
The Civil War and God knows how many hurricanes.
But when Lincoln declared one after the war, he inflicted more damage than all wars and hurricanes combined.
Good morning, everyone. Welcome. Thank you for coming along.
My name is Matt Bauer. I'm the audio director for Hangar 13.
We are a studio within 2K Games,
head by Hayden Blackman.
Our audio team consists of myself,
two junior sound designers, two senior sound designers.
Our engineering needs kind of fluctuated up and down a little bit,
from one person part-time to three people,
and some really great external contractors that we worked with.
If you're not familiar with the game Mafia 3, I'll just walk you through it very briefly.
It's an open world third person cover shooter.
It's set in the town of New Bordeaux.
That's our fictionalized version of New Orleans in 1968.
It's the story of Lincoln Clay.
He is a man of mixed race.
He's an orphan.
He's a Vietnam vet.
And he's returned home from the war to find that his surrogate family, the black mob,
are deeply indebted to the Italian mob.
And throughout a period of time, his family is basically slaughtered by the Italian mob
and he goes on this sort of quest for revenge.
It's important to note that even though this is an established franchise for 2K, Mafia
1 and 2 were built by our studio in the Czech Republic.
This is the first project that Hangar 13 dev team took on.
So we were building a brand new team, a brand new engine, and an open world game all at
the same time.
If you're not familiar with the game, I'm going to show you a quick clip that encapsulates
a little bit of the story of what's going on.
Everybody alright?
That was the craziest fucking thing I've ever saw!
Why don't you give us something off the top?
We need to celebrate!
I gotta tell you guys...
Scoot me up, man. Scoot me up.
You know something, Lincoln?
You're possibly the baddest motherfucker I ever laid my eyes on.
You shouldn't have said no.
Where the fuck do you think you're going?
Where the fuck did you go you goddamned moron?
Motherfucker!
I forgot to mention it's a violent game, there's a little bit of language in there.
So, what to expect over the next hour.
I'm going to walk you through how we attempted to deliver period authentic vehicle audio
in a large open world environment.
Some of the things we learned along the way.
I'm going to do a pretty deep dive into the recording techniques we did for cars, trucks,
boats and tires and touch on some of the implementation methods that we chose.
Simple stats about the game.
I'll just run through this really quick.
There were 90-plus vehicles, 40-plus weapons, about 10 districts, 10 full suburbs we had
to build, a little over four hours of cinematic material.
We had a licensed soundtrack of about 106 songs, original composed score, three full
radio stations, complete with commercials, news, all that kind of stuff.
We were about half a million lines of dialogue once localized.
We used WI's inside of our own proprietary engine.
We mixed in 7.1 and our audio budget kind of peaked out at around 75% of one core and
around 206 meg.
On average we were a little bit less than that, but that's kind of where we peaked.
So really early in development, what we knew was that the time period was going to be 1968
and I needed to find cars from 68 and about 30 years earlier than that.
And I knew I needed classic American and European cars, I needed trucks, boats and we had to
service about 90 fictional vehicles in the game.
Our goals were...
to deliver authenticity.
Actually these first two goals really came from kind of studio pillars.
One was to always remind the player that they were in New Orleans in 1968.
So we wanted to always convey a sense of time and place and authenticity.
But then at the same time we had this other goal which was to deliver this Hollywood action
driving which basically meant excitement versus simulation.
So immediately there's a contradiction between being authentic and being over the top and
we had to kind of draw a line there.
We always wanted to immerse the player into the car and we did that through radio stations,
the vehicle interacting with the environment, all sorts of environmental changes when you're
in the vehicle and we knew we wanted to provide a big variety.
All the cars in our game were fictional makes and models so we had a little bit of freedom
there.
Our recording goals were really simple.
You know, safety first, don't be stupid, try not to break shit.
Capture great sound and then if we had time, take some photos and video while we were there.
And I'll show you a few of those recording sessions throughout the next hour.
So how do we find these cars?
We started by trying to plug into the local community, so we started going to classic
car shows and we ended up partnering with a car club who wasn't really tied to one
particular brand.
It wasn't like the Corvette Club or the Mustang Club, it was just this local club of about
650 members.
And they had everything from old cars to new cars, fast cars, slow cars, and they ended
up being kind of an agent that would help us find all the different cars we wanted.
We had friends make suggestions, we ended up working with a truck service centre just
north of here in Greenbrae, a marine service centre in Sausalito and we also went to a
supercharger factory down in Southern California.
So some of the challenges of scale.
We knew it was going to be time and cost prohibitive to record 90 unique vehicles.
So we decided to just find the most diverse group of engines that we possibly could.
We needed a mixture of some regular cars and some high performance cars.
And we had to figure out how and where we were going to do this.
And you know, I had these really early...
goals of, you know, I love racing games and I wanted to be as detailed and as amazing
as some of these really great racing games that I love to play.
And really quickly reality set in that, you know, this is just one slice of a much bigger
pie.
You know, it's an open world game, it's not purely a racing game.
And you know, we had to think about our allocation of resources, not just memory and CPU, but
how much time we could devote to this, and of course the cost.
So you know, even though...
It was a smaller part of a much bigger game.
Our goal was always to try and reach to be as good as possible or as close to these really
amazing racing games that I love to play.
Our final count ended in 30 recording sessions, which was 20 cars, two trucks, seven boats,
one electric car, and now we're actively recording new cars for our DLC packs.
When it comes to recording a car or any type of engine, there's a whole number of different
ways you can go.
And I'm not going to claim that our method was better or worse than anyone else's.
I'm just going to walk you through some of those different methods you can choose from.
You can go out on an open track or an open road.
You can use a roller dynamometer or you can use a hydraulic dynamometer, which I'll go
into a little more detail.
And each one of those has unique challenges and advantages and disadvantages.
And there's probably other methods out there.
These are just the four that I was really familiar with.
What we chose to do was use a dynapack for our cars.
We took our tyres to a racetrack, we did our trucks out on the open road, and then boats
we recorded both in water and on dry land.
And I'll go into more detail on that in a moment.
If you're not familiar, what's a dyno?
A dyno is basically a treadmill that lets you put your car on it and drive the car at
any speed you want while it's not moving.
It's something that allows a mechanic to tune the car, measure the performance of the car
and basically change the performance of a car at all different speeds while it's stationary.
So why choose a dyno?
It would be so much more fun to get out on a racetrack and thrash around in these cars.
Why do this method?
For us, it was a few things.
It was really a matter of safety.
We're dealing with old cars that are 45 to 75 years old.
I don't know how reliable they are.
I don't know if the brakes work.
I don't know if the steering works.
I don't really want to put my team members in these cars and send them off at high speed
down a racetrack.
But it also provides a really controlled recording environment.
We minimize the risk of damage to these cars and we have this hands-off miking approach.
When I started speaking to some of the vehicle owners, they got really concerned.
They imagined us driving around a racetrack with all sorts of stuff clamped and taped
to the side of their cars.
And these are old show cars with beautiful paint jobs and they take them to displays
but they don't really want to push them that hard.
So when we started suggesting this as a method to record, we earned their trust much more
easily and they were willing to work with us because it was a much more hands-off approach,
much more controlled environment.
The downside of recording with a dyno is that it can be kind of too clinical.
Sometimes you lose some of that great character of an engine.
And you also have a lot of overheating risks.
When you're in a controlled room like that, you have to put really large fans in the front
of the engine to bring airflow in and exhaust fans at the back to pull the exhaust out.
And we don't want that for recording, so we would record with the fans off, which meant
we had to be really, really careful to not overheat the cars.
Here's a picture of the dyno we used with a 1940s Plymouth.
So there's two different types of dynos that at least I'm aware of.
There's a traditional roller dyno which is really quick, it's really easy, you just drive
the car straight on, it works with almost any type of car and it's really common, easy
to find.
The downside is that the rollers themselves produce so much noise that it kind of makes
it impractical for recording.
There's also a slight safety risk in that there's a lot of inertia involved in the car
and it can break and launch forward into the wall.
But really the biggest downside for us is the noise, it just ruins the recording.
So if you use a DynaPak, which is a brand developed in New Zealand, it's basically a hydraulic
brake.
You take the wheels off the car, you bolt this machine directly onto the wheels, and
it's a computer-controlled brake that dials up the resistance and the load on the engine.
The big bonus is that it's practically silent.
It makes no noise at all.
It's really accurate, because we're working with old cars where the gauges probably aren't
really that accurate.
And it's really safe.
There's no inertia.
There's no chance the car can brake and launch forward.
The downside to it is that they're really rare, they're hard to find, and you usually
have to work with a high performance workshop that's really expensive.
It takes a lot longer to put the car on and off the dyno, you have to basically jack it
up and take the wheels off, so there's more time invested.
And one of the other downsides is that there's certain cars it just won't work with.
You know, if you have side exhaust pipes or really wide fenders or non-standard wheel
types, chances are you can't put the car on the dyno.
And the little side story about this car on the lower left here, this is a...
Late 1960s McLaren race car, when all said and done, it's about $800,000.
The thing had just been rebuilt from head to toe and the owner agreed to let us record
it.
But we had a 48-hour window that we had to record it before he was going to ship it off
to a race.
So we found a machine shop that basically built us custom adapters within two days so
that we could stick this machine on the dyno and capture it.
It was an 8 liter, 800 horsepower.
V8, it's the loudest car I've ever heard.
If you can imagine a lion right here kind of roaring at you, that's what this thing
sounded like.
So there's a picture of that car on the dyno with the body removed, and you can kind of
see where we had custom adapters to fit it in.
That was one of those cars where your ears ring for three days even with hearing protection.
So typical schedule.
Through a little trial and error we worked out we could record about three cars in one
day.
It was a pretty long day, but it basically took us an hour to set up, 30 minutes to pack
up.
It's really important to note that before we turn the key on any car, myself, the vehicle
owner and the dyno technician would have a quick conversation and we'd talk about the
limitations of the car, the RPM ranges that they're comfortable with, the temperature
ranges that they're comfortable with, and basically just let them know that we were
going to respect their property and we weren't going to be irresponsible with it.
And then the owner was really comfortable in letting us do what we wanted to do.
It took up to an hour to mount the car and up to half an hour to dismount the car.
The recording itself was quite easy.
It took us less than an hour per car.
And then we'd do a foley session with each car afterwards.
So some of the limitations we ran into was that we're dealing with old cars that have
various levels of reliability.
Their cooling systems are nowhere near as efficient as modern cars.
Some of them just can't do what you want them to do.
We had one car that couldn't rev more than about 2,500 RPM.
This car that's in the picture here, this is a 1930s American Bantam.
For anyone who's familiar with engines, it's a 2.8 litre V8 with a flat head, supercharger
and dual webbers.
And it's a really inefficient cooling type car.
So this car, we could record for 12 seconds and then it would overheat and we'd have to
stop for 10 minutes.
And then we could record for 12 seconds and then stop for 10 minutes.
But it sounded so amazing it was worth it.
At the other end of the spectrum we had a European car whose name I'm not allowed to
mention.
mention, but they're Italian and they like red.
And the owner of that car basically said, you know, you
can do whatever this thing lets you do.
Push it to 8,500 RPM if you want.
And we did.
And it sounded fantastic.
One of the things we learned, that regular cars just sound kind of boring.
We had this idea of not everyone in the city owns a hot rod, so we have to have this mixture
of regular and high performance cars.
And the regular cars just sounded more boring than we thought they would.
So I think for future, we will always go with slightly modified and heavily modified cars.
And then the really obvious one was that anything with a rear engine was going to be really
difficult to get a separation of engine and exhaust.
So specifically some of the things that went wrong, we had some cars with starter motor
issues, one car had a carburettor issue, two overheated, we had some cars that didn't show
up on brief, they had different wheels and different exhaust pipes, we even had some
car owners who they had these really beautiful show cars and they wouldn't drive them if
it was a wet road the day after raining.
So the key there is really to have backups planned before your recording session.
So now we know what we're going to record, where we're going to record and how we're
going to record.
But now we get down to the meat and potatoes of what we're actually going to capture.
We decided to do engine start, stop, false start, idle, rev blips.
We do ramp runs, which is basically getting the car from idle all the way to maximum RPM,
and we would do that fast and slow.
And that was mainly as a reference, so we could hear what the car should sound like
as it's accelerating and decelerating.
We decided to record loops of about six seconds, which we didn't need that much, but it was
just enough for us to work with.
And we would put a really high load on the engine,
and we'd do a really fine level of loops,
you know, 200 RPM increments all the way up to 2,000,
and then 500 RPM increments up to redline.
And then we'd repeat that whole process under a low load.
Our goal was to get three perspectives.
We wanted the engine, the exhaust, and the interior.
And then afterwards, when one car was finished,
we'd take it to another location and do a Foley session
of everything that opened and closed
and clinked and clunked
while we started preparing the next car.
The gear we used, I won't run through this in high detail, but basically it was an 8
channel sound devices unit.
If I could only choose one microphone for vehicle recordings it would be the DPA 4060s.
They were reliable in every single situation and really versatile and if I could choose
one mic that would be it.
I guess the other one to note is the AKG D112s, which are really designed for kick drums,
but we used them on exhausts to get that really low rumble of the exhaust.
And then over time as we did these sessions, you know, we expanded our kit.
We were recording directly into Pro Tools through an interface at one point.
We added a Zoom F8 so that we could slave the two together and get 16 channels.
So over time we kind of expanded our kit.
Just really simple extra common sense stuff to bring to a recording session.
Bring cameras, bring first aid kits, spare cables and batteries of every kind.
And probably the most important thing to note there is sandbags.
The last thing I want to do is hang a boom over a $150,000 Porsche and have the mic stand
fall over and dent the car.
So it's really important to get some really cheap sandbags and weight everything down.
Some really common sense tips when you're recording cars.
Confirm everything the day before.
It's not as important to them to show up to your session as it is to you.
Plan plenty of backup cars in case if you can.
Be flexible.
Some of these cars don't do what you want.
So it's really important to adjust your priorities.
And if a car is overheating, you may have to kind of decide what are the most important
things that I need to record now and kind of change your plan around a little bit.
And then just use whatever method is the easiest.
It's really impractical to be typing into an iPad when you're moving on a boat at 90
miles an hour.
So use pen and paper, use laminated sheets, use whatever is really simple and just easy.
And then the biggest takeaway here is investigate what your legal issues and permits and insurance
needs are really far in advance.
For our Tire session, which I'll show you in a moment, we started working with our legal
team maybe three months before the recording session.
And their rules were really simple.
Don't break the law, be safe and responsible.
And everything from that they were willing to support us with.
But sometimes that can take a really long time to prepare.
We had to prepare nearly three months in advance for that recording session.
So, where to place the mic?
Well, this is as open a question as any.
It's all down to choice.
For an eight mic setup, we chose to put three in the engine bay, four on the exhaust for
a dual exhaust system, and one on the interior.
Over time, we expanded to a 16 mic setup.
And that wasn't really because we needed more coverage of the car.
It was just because we were getting different tonalities from different mics.
And on some of those really expensive rare cars, we just wanted to have backup channels
as well.
But specifically we would put the DPA labs inside the engine bay and usually we would
put one close to the intake to get that kind of sucking air sound and then we'd look for
something else that was unique and different inside the engine.
And sometimes that was down at the back firewall, sometimes it was underneath the engine near
the exhaust manifold.
It was basically just looking for something that was different and unique about that engine.
And then we would have one mic a few feet back from the engine to just get an overall
picture.
And we would put two shotguns at the back of the exhaust and then the two AKG D112s
to get the low rumble of the exhaust.
And then usually just one mic on the interior down where the passenger's feet would go.
And I'll show you a video of the cars towards the end.
When it comes to trucks, it's an entirely different beast.
The challenges we had was being able to record them in isolation.
We couldn't find a dyno for trucks.
So we ended up recording them out on the open road.
We did one day per truck just by myself.
And the most important thing is a highly skilled driver is more important than the truck itself.
And I'll get into that in a moment.
Trucks are really hot engines.
And I was really worried about these really thin mic cables just melting in five minutes.
So what I ended up doing was going to a hardware store and buying dishwasher hose.
It was really cheap.
It was a way to run all the mic cables through and insulate them and we were able to do these
sessions without damaging anything.
The truck itself is a big clunky machine, so you try and use the body of the truck to
build natural windbreaks, and I'll show you a picture of that.
Here you can see kind of towards the back of the truck, we used the frame to position
our mics and we wrapped them in foam and tried to use the cabin of the truck to protect us
from the wind.
The real challenge was recording steady states.
So, what we did, we had this really skilled driver who went all up through the hills of
Marin Headlands and he knew exactly which road to be on to be the right gradient of
hill with the right amount of load on the engine and the right gear so that he could
hold the truck really steady under load and let us get a usable loop.
And then we did the whole process again by adding weight to the truck and he added the
trailer.
With a truck, the one characteristic that I really wanted to capture is called the jake
brake.
It's an exhaust system.
I don't know if you hear trucks go downhill and they kind of make that ba-ba-ba-ba-ba
sound that some people don't like.
That's a valve that uses the truck's pressure to help slow it down.
And that was something we really wanted to capture and use in the game.
I'd like to play you just a really quick sample of how our final results of our trucks ended
up in the game.
This runs for about a minute, a minute and a half.
Thanks for watching.
So, when it came to boats, again, that was an entirely different process.
We did a three day recording session to capture seven different boat engines.
And again, early on in the process, we didn't know exactly what the final art models would
be, but we knew we had to provide small fishing boats, medium boats, some sort of high speed
drug smuggling boat, some sort of large police patrol or coast guard boat, and then the kind
of bayou swamp fan boat.
What we found was that the really small, less than 10 horsepower engines, it's really easy
to record them in a tank.
We found that being out on the water wasn't so difficult for us to maintain steady RPM
states.
If you can go out on a smooth, calm, nice weather day, that really helps compared to
choppy weather.
And one thing we learned was that the exhaust of most boats is submerged under the water,
so it really offers you nothing to record other than that slight kind of glug, glug,
glug sound when you're at idle.
So what we decided to do was record a second pass of each boat on dry land.
And what you can do is connect, you know, the boats need water for cooling, but you
can connect the hose to the engine and then you can record a second pass to get that exhaust
and get that really aggressive bite that we wanted from the boats.
And then we blended those recordings together.
What we decided to do was take the engine covers off, put the DPAs under the engine.
We knew that the blimps and shotgun mics were going to, at some level, they were going to
work for low speeds and then at higher speeds they were going to become useless.
So having those DPA mics under the engine covers, we had a natural windbreak and it
didn't matter what speed, what RPM we were at, we knew we would get some clean, reliable
recordings from them.
I had this growing concern that...
You know, salt water and microphones don't mix.
And we could have very easily just destroyed all our gear in one day.
And we knew everything was going to get really wet.
So I decided to go to one of those fabric stores where they sell sewing material.
And I said, do you guys sell anything, any kind of waterproof fabric that I could buy?
And they said, yeah, sure.
This is our baby diaper section.
You can have camouflage or you can have this.
And I thought about it for a while.
We went with the camouflage, but we basically bought this fabric, wrapped up the mics, sprayed
them with that Scotchgard stuff that's great for your shoes, and made sure we kind of pointed
the back of the mic into the wind.
And you know, these things got soaked every single day, but we were able to protect, you
know, for maybe $30 worth of extra materials, we were able to protect all our gear and not
break anything.
So, that was really worthwhile.
And then we used a contact mic on the hull of the boat to get all the thumps and bumps.
What I would like to show you is a quick video of the recording session and one more quick
video of how those boats ended up in game.
Thanks for watching!
That was a really, really fun day.
Here's a little quick sample of how some of those sounds got used in game.
What you'll hear is more of the water spray, more of the thumps and bumps and some of the
different things we did.
On the fan boat, you'll hear that we added vibrations for rudder control and all that
kind of stuff.
So here's an example of how our final boat audio ended up in game.
Don't forget to subscribe!
Some of the additional pieces that we added to the engine, our designers wanted to add
forced induction, superchargers and turbochargers, and the difficult part about recording a supercharger
is that the engine that is underneath it, of course, is going to be loud.
So we contacted a factory that makes superchargers down in Southern California, and by total
luck, they have a completely soundproof room in their factory where they spool these up
on electric motors and test them and make sure that they're working properly before
they package them off to their customers.
I couldn't have been more lucky with the conditions.
And they agreed to let us in there, so we recorded that way.
The turbo was a little more difficult.
We couldn't find a similar situation, so it became a combination of real turbos,
sound design and foley.
We used ball-bearing keychains, compressed air, hospital defibrillators
and all sorts of different things to make our turbo sounds.
With the police sirens, we also had a real hard time finding a car with a 1960s siren.
It was early 60s where they started experimenting with electronic sirens and went away from
the old rotating impeller type sirens.
So we ended up going to eBay and just buying a siren and that's how we managed to capture
that.
We also found that a lot of the sounds from a 1960s police siren is due to the police
officers messing with the buttons and kind of moving the siren halfway between two different
positions and kind of messing with it that way.
So that's...
That was something we really wanted to capture and recreate.
Brings me to tires. This was also one of the most fun parts of the whole project for us.
Our goals were to capture a clean set of tire sounds in isolation from an engine.
We wanted to capture multiple different surfaces, including a wet road,
and then share that same recording across all vehicles in the game.
The challenge really was preparation.
You know, we looked at a whole bunch of different options of how to do this.
We knew that by using an electric car that would provide us a quiet engine and there
was only really one model of electric car that had enough horsepower to do what we wanted.
We looked at private racetracks, runways, commercial racetracks, and for all different
reasons it wasn't really a great option for us.
Some people declined to record with us.
There was a commercial racetrack really close to our office, but they have a go-kart track
and a drag racing strip, and we really couldn't get a private, quiet place to record.
We could, but it would have been really expensive to rent out the entire facility.
So what we settled on was Laguna Seca Mazda Raceway down in Monterrey.
That's about two hours south of here.
The reason for Laguna Seca was it was really reasonably priced.
If I want the racetrack, it's about $15,000 a day, but the skid pad area is only $1,000
per day.
It's a really safe place.
It's really away from any kind of main roads.
It's not accessible to the public.
And the skid pad area is enclosed and locked.
And again, speaking with our legal team, their rules were don't break the law, be safe and
responsible.
So that was kind of the mandate that I took when I was looking for this recording session.
Where we really lucked out is that Laguna Seca is on county owned land and they have
a noise ordinance where they're not allowed to reach a certain average noise level.
So the way they counter that is they actually close a couple days per month and do no racing
and that brings their average noise level down for the month.
So to our luck they let us record on one of those no race days and we actually got the
entire facility to ourself for $1,000.
It was really terrific.
We hired their lead driving instructor to be our driver.
We had one technician to basically swap wheels on and off of the car.
We rented this car from a private owner and we bought our own tires and wheels so that
we weren't destroying his tires out on the track.
We had an ambulance on standby, which is really an inexpensive thing to do.
And we had myself and one other sound designer and one producer.
The whole session only ran one day.
It was a really simple mic set up.
We put four labs underneath each wheel.
Basically right at the very base there where you can kind of see the corner just before
the wheels where we put our mics.
And then we used these camera tripods called a cam tree gripper which is basically this
really flexible industrial suction mount system to hang a couple of Sennheiser shotguns above
the wheels.
And then we would have the driver in the car, one person in the car, and then walkie-talkie
communication to just let everyone know if everything's okay.
What we decided to record was really steady driving in a straight line.
The kind of boring stuff was driving at five miles an hour, but we got this really nice
grit from the tires.
All the way up to about 70.
We did light braking but not actually skidding.
We did braking where we were skidding.
We drove around in circles and did light, medium and heavy sideways drifting.
And then we got to do the really fun stuff which was pouring clouds of smoke off the
car and getting the burnout sounds.
Two things that we learnt in our research prior, we had to look at what type of tyres
to purchase and we spoke to some drifting professionals who told us that basically if
we went with the cheaper Korean tyres we were going to get the best sound out of them.
So that was great because it was cheap and it was what we wanted.
And we also learnt that the temperature of a tyre completely changes how it sounds.
And this was something we didn't realise until we were on the track and the driver was explaining it to us.
That squealing sound that you get from a tyre is actually when the rubber is cold and it's still making some grip
and it's kind of losing its grip and making grip.
And that's what produces that squealing sound.
When a tyre gets so hot that it's starting to melt and turn soft,
that sound disappears entirely and you get this really cool whizzing sound.
And we were kind of fascinated by this, so we recorded it, and I went back to our designers
and said, is there any chance that you are simulating temperature?
And he's like, yeah, of course.
So we put that into the game.
And in our game, as you're doing burnouts, over time that sound will change based on
the temperature that's simulated of the tire.
And then we repeated the entire process.
We went down the road, did everything all over again, did it on dirt and gravel and
a grass-leaf combination.
The two big challenges that we faced during this was as we started to get into the really
high speed whipping around doing burnouts, I was concerned that those suction mounts
were going to fall off and with the mic cable connected the thing was going to swing around
like a wrecking ball and destroy this.
$140,000 car.
So I made a decision at some point to take those mics off and just go with the labs under
the wheels.
And I was a little disappointed because they really were the two best mics we had, but
in the nature of protecting and respecting this person's property, we decided to not
do that.
The other big challenge we had is traction control.
This is a modern computer controlled electric car.
Even when you turn the traction control off, it still has a number of systems involved
that are trying to save your life.
And so if you are sliding out of control, it shuts the power down to the engine and
it was really restricting our driver from doing what he wanted to do.
We knew about this early on, and luckily I had a friend that works at this company, and
he told me which fuses and relays to pull out and rearrange to fool the car into doing
what we wanted it to do.
So we kind of lucked out there.
But again, this came down to preparation.
We planned this session three months in advance, so I had maybe 50 conversations with this
engineer about everything I could learn about this car, about what it would do, what it
wouldn't do, and what my limitations were going to be.
I'll show you a real quick video of how some of those recording sessions went.
I'm going to play this back just a little quieter just to kind of protect everyone's ears
by the nature of this, how obnoxious this type of sound can be.
It was a really fun day, we were really happy with the results.
Everything turned out exactly as we'd planned.
What I'd like to do is show you a really quick sample of how that sounds in game, with everything
that we did after the fact.
What you're going to hear in this video is just the road sounds.
Everything else has been disabled, it's just purely the tires.
And I forgot to mention, if the surrounds are working in here, what you're hearing in
the quad speakers right now is a representation of each wheel in the game.
Each wheel on your car.
I don't know if you guys noticed the whizzing sound that kind of comes in and out at different
times and the way we did the driving on the rims, I actually took a jack stand and just
connected a contact mic to it and then pointed one other shotgun mic at it and just rubbed
it on the concrete and I was able to kind of create the loops that I wanted of different
intensities and different speeds and kind of jiggled it on concrete and that was a way
to come up with that sound.
When it came time to implementation, we were at this real crossroads.
Do we go with a loop-based system?
Granular synthesis is a really popular method that a lot of people are choosing.
We evaluated granular synthesis and there was an off-the-shelf product we could buy
and there were some things we liked about it and some things we didn't like about it.
I didn't have the engineering resources to go and create our own brand new granular synthesis
system so we ended up deciding to go with a very fine detailed loop based system for
this game.
That doesn't mean we won't evaluate that method again in future, and we are evaluating that
for future, but for this game we decided to go with a really fine detailed loop.
Again we were doing 200 RPM increments from idle to 2000 and then 500 RPM increments up
to redline.
Then we built everything we needed inside of Wyze with switches and blend containers
and RTPCs.
We ended up mixing everything down to a stereo engine, a stereo exhaust and it turned out
the interior perspective camera angle was going to be cut from the game but at the time
of recording we didn't know that so we captured it anyway.
We decided to keep the player's car completely 2D.
Even though it's a third-person game and the car is kind of out there in front of you,
you know, the camera moves around a lot, the car's spinning around a lot.
Our camera had this really kind of chasing Dutch tilt kind of system going on
and it was really kind of distracting for the player to hear their engine moving around so much.
So we decided to keep everything in 2D and then completely change the mix state
based on the camera angle that the player chose.
3D cars of course were, sorry NPC cars were of course 3D and we had the original goal
of keeping them just as high fidelity as everything else and again reality set in that we couldn't
do that so we ended up having to optimise them and ship them with a mono single engine
exhaust combination.
We had some performance concerns and it was really more important to me to hear more cars
at once on the road in a traffic situation than to just have two or three cars sound
as high as fidelity as possible.
So that was one of our limitations.
With tires, we shared those recordings, we did a slight pitch shift based on the size
of the car.
So trucks, we would pitch down and get a deeper howl and we'd pitch up for small cars.
Each wheel was tracked independently in the game, so each wheel plays the appropriate
surface that you're on.
And then for NPCs, we optimized by playing just the one wheel closest to you.
And that was plenty.
We were really lucky in that our design and engineering team made this really amazing
physics-based driving model that was built upon from Mafia 2.
And so we had access to a huge wealth of information.
You know, I won't go through every single one in detail, but the couple that I'll call
out was we were able to do the jake brake on the truck by knowing the engine load, the
clutch position, and the angle if the truck was only pointing its nose downhill.
And so that allowed us to do everything we wanted to inside of Wwise.
was spinning at a slower rotational speed relative to what it should be going for the
vehicle speed, then we knew we were skidding to a halt.
If it was running at a higher rotational speed, we knew we were doing a burnout.
And of course, if it was drifting sideways, we had that information as well.
So what you can see there is a series of blend containers nested inside of other blend containers.
And using some RTPCs, we were able to build all of our drifting and burnouts and tire
temperature simulation all inside of Wwise.
And then in closing, I'd like to show you just a really quick clip of kind of everything
culminated together.
This is kind of the best driving experience that we strived for and what we thought we
could deliver in Mafia III, so I hope you enjoy this.
However, Google has recognized that MAGIC is not the only way out of this hell.
Without further ado,
May the
purple
reap
the
Koh-i-Toon.
This is what the actual engine sound would look like.
So, thank you all for coming.
I really appreciate you taking the time to get up here.
early on a Friday morning.
I hope you enjoyed that.
I hope you kind of learned something about the process of recording cars.
We have a little bit of time left, so if anyone would like to ask questions, feel free to
come up to the microphone up in front.
Hi.
I'm a fan of the cars, so I'm going to ask a question.
Do you know what a car is?
Yes.
I've heard about it.
I'm not sure how many people have heard about it, but I don't think it's very well-known.
I think it's a car that is typically driven by a man or a woman.
And I think it's a car that is driven by a man or a woman.
Hi, great talk. I was just curious about the tire recording session, what was the tape
for around the tires? It appeared to be tape.
There was two purposes. One was to tape the mic cables down and the other was just a stone
protection. The technician we worked with
But particularly it's blue painter's tape which doesn't leave any kind of glue residue
behind because we were conscious of not damaging the paint.
But he basically said, you know, if we tape up certain areas of the car, this is where
all the stone chips are going to come from, this is where all the dirt's going to get
kicked up.
So particularly when we recorded on the gravel road, that was something we wanted to do to
just protect the car.
But it also served as taping down mic cables.
Awesome.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Thanks.
When recording these cars on a DynaPak for instance, did you have to have hub adapters
made for some of the cars for like the bolt patterns to get them to match up?
So the workshop had standard four and five bolt patterns and those adapters are adjustable
for certain widths.
We did have a special Volkswagen adapter made but it turned out we weren't permitted to
use Volkswagen recordings so we had to throw that away.
There are some brands out there that trademark their sound.
So we learned over time there were certain cars we couldn't use.
And then it was really just that McLaren that we had the special adapter made.
But everything else we searched for cars that fit that particular bolt pattern.
And then sometimes we would unfortunately have to turn down cars if they weren't going to fit.
Sorry, I have a question as well.
Hi.
Um, so you said that you recorded 30 different vehicles, but you used 90 in the game.
Were you like mixing and matching sounds from different recordings?
A little bit, a little bit. Mostly it was just we just shared those recordings across the 90.
So you just had like 30 like archetypes for vehicles and then...
Pretty much, yeah. And then we would choose what we thought sounded the best or most appropriate based on...
You know, the designers were tweaking what the performance of that car was going to...
what the virtual performance of that car was going to be,
so we would choose what we thought sounded the best.
Cool, thank you.
Thanks.
During the recording session out on the track um...
What did you use in terms of multi-track and like 64 gigabyte cards?
Did you just press record and just record all day long?
For the tires?
Yeah.
We had a sound device, 788T, and we had one person sitting in the passenger seat recording.
So we would use radio communication to talk back to our producer and tell her this is
what maneuvers we're about to do next.
And then she would note.
Note that and we'd talk time code back and forth across the radio and if we were forgetting
something she would say, look, on your list you've got these three more things you haven't
done yet.
And so we were just communicating over radio that way.
The radio was really mainly meant to be a safety feature, you know, if something caught
on fire or fell off we would have someone tell us.
But it also served as a way to kind of prompt us of what to do for whoever was sitting in
the car itself.
Cool, well thank you everyone for coming.
Enjoy the rest of your GDC.
Really appreciate you taking the time to be here.