So my name is Matthew Vione. I'm a founder at SomaSim Games.
And I'd like...
First, how many people saw me at FlashForward? I'm just curious.
Okay, a few.
So I just want to start with a hypothetical.
Let's say that you just put your job.
You cashed out some savings,
got rid of a 401k,
convinced your spouse or significant other that
one mortgage is good, but two is even better.
and you're gonna use that money to do a crazy or maybe stupid thing which is
make your first indie game
uh... so from that very first moment you're now on the clock
you gotta get that game done
out there and making money before your money
goes away
uh... there's a lot of other stuff that you have to do and do well in that first
year that first
while you're making that first game
and that's what I'm gonna talk about today
is all that other stuff that you need to do to make sure that your first indie game
isn't your last indie game
So we made our first indie game called 1849.
We released it in May of 2014.
It is a city builder, sort of in the classic Caesar, Sierra
impressions, late 90s, early 2000s genre of game, like
where city builder and tycoon games sort of run
into one another.
And we've been planning to do this for a while.
We really wanted to make our own game and make our own
studio focused on making simulation games.
So we planned.
We talked to friends.
We got all the information we possibly could, saved money,
and really got ready to release our first indie game.
And then in April of 2013, we quit our jobs.
Yay!
And our first question was, how much time do we have?
We have the savings realistically how much time do we have before that money
runs out and we have to unfortunately go get real jobs again.
And then how do we make this our first Indie game and not our only Indie game?
Like I said, we really wanted to focus on building a studio based on making these
kinds of simulation games that we really like.
So today I'm, this is basically what I'm going to talk about real fast, is the preparation,
the self-marketing and the self-publishing that we did while we were making our game
and while we were releasing it.
And I'm going to have some help from some people who
from the time when my country decided to go into the British Empire.
So, Ben is right here.
If you want to arrive at a given point, at a given time,
you have to plan your journey very carefully.
If you don't do that, you're going to get lost and wander around in the woods.
So we had quit and we were talking about our big game design dreams.
And we had four or five games that we wanted to make, and we very quickly realized
that they were just beyond the scope of a year.
We talked about them and we just couldn't make them work to our vision in that year.
So then we decided, let's flip that around.
So we have about a year to make a game.
What game can we make that we want to make that will inspire us can we make in one year?
And we did pretty good.
We planned for a year.
We made it in about 14 months.
The first thing I want to talk about is how we got to that
plan on that one side of the slide.
We used something called SWAG scheduling, which I think we
took from some friends at Microsoft.
And SWAG stands for Stupid Wild Ass Guess.
The first step of making a stupid, wild-ass guest schedule
is you just cut up items into a week or larger.
And again, it's stupid, wild-ass guests.
Just go with your gut.
Approximate. Like, I thought,
I think it's going to take about a month
to write the scenarios for the game.
So I said, it's going to take a month
And annotate with costs as well,
with benefits as well as costs.
Like, we were making a campaign-based game,
so that month on the scenarios was really important.
So it took a lot longer than other things, but
crucial to the game.
And make sure you multiply for relative risk.
If you look at each other and say, you know how to do that?
No.
Do you?
Uh-uh.
It's going to take longer than you think.
So give yourself more time for the, I don't know how to do
that, part of the plan process.
So then we broke everything up into these little chunks,
and we put them on Post-its, and then put them on a bigger Post-it.
Unfortunately, there weren't bigger Post-its,
otherwise we would have probably done that too.
And then we sort of ran a meta little sum function on all of this.
And lo and behold, we came up with
about 16 months to make a game.
That's longer than a year.
Swag scheduling has a tool for that, and it is called Butchery.
this is the unpleasant part of swag scheduling this is where you take the
design you've lovingly crafted and needed and honed and then hack out big
chunks of it
that big pile of post-its in the bottom there
over there, that sort of messy looking pile
that's our multiplayer system
we looked at it and said that's four months of work
sixteen minus four is twelve so unfortunately
our beautiful multiplayer system
And do this early, because taking out a multiplayer system
in a game and changing it to a pure single player,
that's a big design decision.
If we had done that six months in,
we could have had a lot of stuff built in multiplayer
that never see the light of day.
So butcher early, butcher often.
And again, if you have a tight schedule, reduce risk.
For us, that meant tech.
We knew how to use Flash with our eyes closed,
blindfolded, in the dark.
Not the sexiest tech in the world, and it wasn't Unity, which was the new hotness at the time.
So, we just decided, let's not worry about learning a whole new engine.
Let's do what we know.
And that let us take some risks in some other places.
Because we already knew the tech we were going to use.
And you're probably going to have to have contract work done.
Make sure that you hire carefully.
Hire friends. Hire friends of friends.
If your gut tells you,
that guy's a little cray-cray.
Go with your gut. You don't have time for cray-cray
when you only have a year.
and there's a lot of documentation to keep up with contractors from tax forms to time sheets
and checks, because contractors, they like money.
And managing contractors is a lot different than working with a co-worker.
If a co-worker goes off on a tangent, yeah, it's problematic, but it's not fatal.
If you only have a year and a contractor's off doing some crazy stuff,
that's your money and your year. So make sure that you stay on top of contractors.
I support incorporate right away. They let you sign documents
as a corporation not as yourself.
You can sign distribution agreements and all that other stuff as a corporation
not as yourself
and get an accountant. Tax laws in every country are designed to just
annoy and frustrate and these are people that specialize in annoyance and frustration.
So then we went and made a game.
About nine months later, we were in beta or alpha.
And I'm going to skip all of that.
The ins and outs, trials and tribulations
of making an indie simulation game were another talk.
So, nine months later,
and it's about time to start self-marketing and self-promoting.
Tom Payne here is correct.
Publicity is sort of voodoo black magic,
and the black magic gets stronger all the time.
Before that sort of nine month in three months from release window,
we started doing things like building community from scratch.
And we started on social media.
Facebook is useless when you want to build a community.
Unless you're willing to pay Facebook money,
you're not going to get anywhere.
There's no virality on Facebook anymore.
Twitter isn't right above Facebook for one big reason,
and that is journalists.
Love Twitter.
They spend all their time on Twitter.
Some of them even have some compensation based on what
they tweet and how they tweet.
So that's a great place to find people who are covering
your game, your genre, and your people in the media.
Reddit can be dangerous.
One day we decided, ooh, a new subreddit that looks like
it's great for our game.
Here's a screenshot and some stuff about the game.
10 minutes later, it was gone.
seems to fit, why didn't it go away?
So we asked the Redditor, what's up?
And he said, not now.
So then we asked, oh, well, can you tell us some pointers?
Like, what could we do to fit in more with the community?
And he said, not now.
So make sure you get to know the Reddit you're posting in.
Even post there, get to know that community before you do.
Otherwise, you could get not now.
We also started a dev log, and we began showing that on TIG
Source, cross-posting on Reddit.
It was a really good way of getting our screenshots out
there, information about our game out there
to a wider community.
Doing email and having a mailing list is really
important, because these are people who came to your site,
found your sign-up form, put in their name, put in their
email address.
They want to hear from you.
So use your email list sparingly and communicate
efficiently, and it's a really great tool of getting your
game out there.
Screenshot Saturday was also a fantastic way of getting things in front of people.
If you don't know about Screenshot Saturday, you should know about Screenshot Saturday.
And it also starts on Friday, not Saturday.
Every time we had new art that came in, we put it up.
Every time we had a new game feature, we talked about it.
Probably a couple of times a month seemed to us to be about the right time,
the right amount of time to share on Screenshot Saturday.
And then it comes to doing press outreach and PR.
In a past life, I was a director of communications.
And I know what it takes to do PR.
It's a full-time job.
And I'm a new developer now.
So I have like five of those.
So we found a really good contractor to
handle some of our PR.
But that still means that there's a lot of work that
you have to do on your end.
The first thing to do is come up with a really tight elevator pitch.
Um, these few words took about two months of work,
repeating them to ourselves in the mirror in the shower,
to friends, to like, they were like,
yeah, I know what your game is, already stop talking to me.
Um, and 1849 is a city management game
set in the California gold rush.
It's quick, it's concise, and it's modifiable.
So if we're talking to the mobile press,
we can say 1849 is a city management game
for tablets set in the California gold rush.
One thing that I would avoid is mentioning other games in your elevator pitch.
At this conference, about five people have come to me to tell me about their game,
mentioning other games that I have never heard of.
So I have no idea what their game is now.
And you're also running a risk, like, what if I hate one of those games?
So, just be clear on your pitch.
And game media, this is where you should start.
These are the trendsetters, tastemakers in our medium.
Get to know who covers your genre.
Talk to them.
Follow them on Twitter.
We were greenlit about four days after we got featured on
Raw Paper Shotgun.
I don't think that's a coincidence.
YouTubers, as anybody who's been at this conference probably knows,
are a big and increasingly important way of getting your game out there.
I'm not going to talk about the ins and outs of YouTubers,
but one of the things that is really nice about YouTube
is that it advertises your game in a way that screenshots can't.
People can see the motion of your game.
They can see what things do.
They can see how the UI works.
And that really gets them into your game in a way that a screenshot or text just can't.
One other thing is we used some YouTube, we reached out to some YouTubers during early access
and for us it was really valuable to see
our game being played by other people in early access. We got to see them do things that we
had never seen any playtesters do. We're like,
why are they clicking over there? Why are they building it like that?
It was a really educational process during early access.
And then there's the non-game media.
And I think reaching out to the non-gaming media gets
ignored in our industry to our own peril.
Our game is set in 20 real cities in California and six
real cities in Nevada.
So we reached out to the media, radio stations,
newspapers, TV stations, in every market where our game
has said it in every city or game is set
and we did things like hey we made a game that has stopped in it isn't that
cool and the starting record said
and it's really cool and we got our game above the masthead and
stocking record and then a full parade spread inside so we talked people from
the Sacramento Beach Nevada magazine to
the Marysville Mountain Gazette which was big hit
um and it was actually a lot of fun to talk to these
non-game media reporters
So find out, like, what is a hook in your game
that the media might be interested in
and pitch it to them.
You get a lot more coverage that way.
We also did early access and Greenlight at the same time.
So, obviously, we weren't in early access on Steam.
We did it on a site called Indie Game Stand.
And we had a lot of success doing early access this way.
We got to really work with that community that they have there.
We would, we basically had a game that was system complete,
but we still had a lot of scenarios to author and content to write.
So we would put out chunks of content and say,
fun, broken, just plain sucks.
And they got back to us and then we released more content.
And we actually really enjoyed building our game
with this smaller community like that.
And even next time when we do early access,
we are probably going to start with this community
and not with the Steam community.
The Steam community has high expectations of polish and
refinement in your game, and so we're going to try to get that right in early access elsewhere,
and then maybe do a short period of early access on Steam.
shows and expo's are great if your game has a controller
if it's multiplayer, if it has VR
if you have a simulation game with a tutorial that takes 8 minutes if you're the designer and don't have to read it
and really about half an hour to get into the meat of the game
shows and expo's might not be the best place for you to show off your game
We did a few of them, and they were great experiences,
but not really right for our game.
So if they're not right for your game, don't feel like
because everybody goes to PAX East, you have to be on the
plane to PAX East.
So we did all of that.
PR, all of our marketing, and then it came time to see if it was all worth it and gonna work.
It came time for us to release our game, and
we did a multi-platform,
a cross-platform,
multi-platform release simultaneously.
We sent out a media story that said,
we made a simulation game that you can play on your tablet and on your PC.
Isn't that awesome?
And the PC players, a vocal small minority of them,
said, no, it's a mobile port.
Gross.
And the mobile audience, like, cool PC game.
We're like, we don't care if it's a cool PC game.
Is it a cool mobile game?
And lesson learned from this is that
if you're doing a cross-platform launch,
make sure you have two distinct game stories,
one for the PC audience, one for the mobile audience.
We're gonna spend a lot more time customizing our UI, UX.
for mobile and for PC to make sure that we're really
speaking to the strengths and the expectations
of both audiences.
That sort of leads into picking a price point.
When you're on PC, on Steam,
you have the luxury of really being able to charge
what you think your game is worth.
You can go hunt about and see other similar games
in your genre.
Um, you can...
really price appropriately.
Mobile pricing sucks nuts.
You can charge $6.99 for your game
if you're a Minecraft or Final Fantasy
Final Fantasy game.
I mean, what kind of universe do we live in
when a Final Fantasy game costs $8?
I mean, it's a crazy time.
But we all know that most of these games
are.
99 cents, the huge variety of those 500 games that are coming out every day on mobile
are free or incredibly cheap.
I don't know about you guys, but I can't run a studio on games that cost 99 cents.
This is all a lead-in to what I call the Kobayashi Maru.
It's the no-win scenario of cross-platform pricing.
You can pick a price point on mobile that's close to your price point on PC
if you're interested in something no games at all.
Or you can
really reduce the price of your PC game,
but then that's not what your PC game is worth.
You did that price analysis on Steam and determined it's worth $15.
So why would you not charge $15 for it?
I don't really have a good answer for how you can do a cross-platform pricing.
Um, except that...
justify your PC price.
Give the PC player something that the mobile players don't have.
Or break out your content for mobile such that,
eventually, to get all the content that they would get on PC,
they are paying somewhere near that price.
Um...
Cross-platform pricing is just sort of an unpleasant situation.
And it's important to go on really all the stores that you can.
These are our revenue sources for 2014.
We made about 60% of our revenue on PC
and about 40% on mobile.
And really, that 40% on mobile,
if we hadn't have done a cross-platform release,
is probably the difference between us making our second game
and not making our second game.
So it was important for us to be on both platforms.
I think the best practice now is PC first.
Use that to build up some audience for your mobile game.
And then release on mobile later,
after you've had the time to really work out the kinks
for a mobile release.
They're a lot more complicated than a PC release
a lot of the time.
Just a little further breakdown.
Um...
About 40%-45% of our, uh, PC revenue
came straight from Steam.
Um...
Android and...
was 10% and then iOS was 30%.
This year, we're seeing the Android
come a lot closer to, um, the iOS,
and my guess is that those start to converge
and get closer as time goes on.
And also, if you look at that Indie Game Stand number,
um, Indie Game Stand is a smaller, uh, small,
it's a fairly small store and community,
but you really see the impact that our community building
and our work with their community
had on our sales on Indie Game Stand.
They're still even, what,
eight, nine months from release,
a big chunk of our revenues.
We got featured.
Yay!
Both Apple and Android.
Um, but we're a $4 title.
$5 title.
Um, I know how much my game is, really.
Um, and so that meant we got released,
and we were up there for the period of our featuring.
And because we were a more expensive title,
we didn't have the momentum,
the buzz that Apple looks for to repeat the featuring.
So it was really great in getting our, um...
first spike of sales up there while we were new and spreading some word of mouth, but
it wasn't like raining money because we got featured, unfortunately.
And getting featured isn't like black magic. Apple and Google have business, biz dev guys
who go out and work for games that really showcase their platform.
So we just found a biz dev guy that knows their biz dev guys. We said, can you talk
about our game to them? And they said, sure. And we got featured.
There are a few annoying things.
You just have to make sure that you follow all the
platform rules.
Like for us, that meant the annoying back button on
Android was a lot of work to get to do what Google thinks
the back button on Android should do.
So just be warned for little pitfalls like that.
So then you release your game.
And this is really, you know, it's the hockey stick.
It's what you hope for and dread at the same time.
So you, yay, release the Kraken.
Game's out there.
Then over the first few weeks, over the first week or so, you see it go like this as you fall off the front pages as
the buzz dies down. And now it is your job, unfortunately, to flog the tail forever and ever and ever.
Those little bumps are the regular sails that you see go on.
Just make sure that you're in them. They're not automatic, you have to opt in.
And they're a natural way of getting your game out there and increasing the tail.
That little bump right there was our DLC launch.
And it was a nice little bump in sales.
But really, I think the impact of the DLC
was if you look at the level of the tail after the DLC,
like that sort of base level.
And then before, you'll see how it's come up.
So the DLC really helped to get just to raise the tide.
And that one actually just happened.
And this was cool.
This was our first out-of-band sale.
Like, there was nothing else on sale.
And it's February.
And, like, it's a slow month.
And there's sort of a reservoir of wish lists
and recommendations that people build up in their queue.
And then you go on sale when there's not a lot going on.
And all of a sudden, you have your best month since launch.
So, you know, just be aware that that can be powerful.
And don't schedule it during Christmas.
Another part of flogging the tail can be ads.
We did some ads when there was nothing going on.
We had nothing to announce, nothing to say, other than
play our game.
And those didn't really do so great.
We found that when we treated ads as a communication device,
when we had something to say, when we had some kind of
urgency, they really started to work better.
So on sale, 40% off, new game, play now.
This one performed pretty well because it had an urgency and
it had a message to communicate.
And also, ads are you talking.
Yeah, you're paying for it, but there are you talking to
a community of people.
So make sure that your ads are consistent with your voice.
And for us, that meant bad puns.
The game writer, me, really liked these kind of terrible
puns like these.
um, ready for a minor distraction or loads of fun.
We found that the more that we went,
oh god, that's bad, while we were writing them,
the better they performed. So, like,
the ready for minor distraction ad did great.
We also had fully loaded simulation
and a whole bunch of other bad load puns.
And then really it's...
Just keep at it.
Reviews and ratings are important.
You can't really respond to player reviews, but just try
to keep on top of them.
If you see that you're at that cusp between mixed and mostly
positive, see what you can do to get it into mostly positive.
It helps your sales a great deal.
We had some people on our Steam forums and community say,
can we have trading cards?
Sure, you can have trading cards.
I don't know if I can quantify that it bumped sales any,
but I know it helped the community.
We had a lot of people, ooh, trading cards, cool, thank you.
We also noticed that we were selling a lot of games
in Germany, but our game was only in English.
So we did a German localization, and Germany
went from being sort of three or four in sales
to being a really strong number two behind the United States.
We sell more games in Germany than we do anywhere except
the US.
And then we also noticed that.
People in France weren't playing our game very much.
France is a big country with a big economy
and a lot of people and a lot of gamers.
So we said, let's try localizing our game in French
and see how that does.
And that just came out on February 13th,
so we don't have a lot of solid data,
but so far, anecdotally, it looks like we're doing
very well in France and French-speaking countries.
So we are indeed making game number two.
We sort of did all these things,
and we are making our second indie game.
You can go check it out.
It's very early in the prototype phase,
and we hope to be talking about it next GDC.
Um, so that's about all I have today.
I have some Steam keys for 1849 up here
if anybody wants one afterwards.
Um, so yeah, if anybody has any questions,
come to the center, and I'll try my best to answer.
Hi.
Yes.
You mentioned that going to expos wasn't a great way to get
test plays on your simulation games.
Did you find a venue to find test players for a sim game
that's more appropriate?
Yeah.
Early access, like I said, was a great help because.
people played our game a lot there. We also bothered a lot of our friends and family
that are also into simulation games.
The email list helped too. People came to us and said,
cool game, how can I help? How can I be involved?
We said, you want to playtest a broken game?
That was a really good way of doing it.
Oh great, thanks.
if I can go back to your anecdote in the beginning, the imagine you just quit your job scenario
did you guys spend any time looking for investors to help fund your game in the beginning or was it totally self-funded?
no it was all bootstrapped
okay
we really wanted to make our first game really our game and
if you go to investors you might end up making their game
gotcha, thanks
Hi, this was very helpful, thank you.
I hope this isn't a breach, but I'm a composer,
so if anyone is looking for music for their game,
I'm staying in this room for the next talk,
so come see me, thanks.
I have a question about getting outreach.
When you say you went out to
things like Rock, Paper, Shotgun, Polygon,
Was this all online? You're barraging them with emails, hitting them up on Twitter, or are you meeting them in person?
or maybe all of the above, you know, do everything you can.
Yeah, really all of the above.
When we were making this game, we still lived in San Francisco,
so it was possible for us to talk to some of the press more directly.
But it was a lot of emails, a lot of traditional PR,
where we would do announcements and press releases
that they would then follow up on with us and our consultant.
But yeah, everything.
If you find out a game journalist, just talk about your game,
talk about what they like, too.
So make it a conversation.
All right.
So I noticed this talk was obviously that you did a game in a year.
You're now making your second game. Have you changed that scope to be a larger amount of time
so you can have things like your multiplayer features now that you're not starving artists or
so to speak a little bit better off than you were before?
Definitely. One of the, our second game that we're making is one of the games that we
put aside. Like we don't have time to make that in a year.
So that's one of the games we're building next. It's probably going to take about
two years, hopefully.
But we're keeping the same sort of urgency.
It's important to say, we have two years to make this game.
And really, we kind of view it as we're starting over every
time when it comes to our game.
We're not counting on that first game to keep us going.
The second game needs to keep us going now.
So just keep urgent.
Hopefully this isn't too personal, but I'm interested in when you first set out, were you venture-backed, or how did you put food on the table for a year while you were keeping this going? You mentioned savings.
Yeah, I remember that like after years of planning, like this is something that we sort of, I think four or five years ago said that we wanted to do, and it was saving and working and keeping like that long-term goal in view. And that's really why we only had a year, because you can only save so much money.
Thanks.
Okay, I'm getting the... so I can do one more quick.
Okay. What kind of work did you contract out and then how did you go about finding those contractors?
It was art and art.
You don't want to see any of the stuff that we draw.
And really, it was like our own personal network.
Like, the artists that we worked with for the first game
and we're still working with, we found it through, actually,
her Twitter feed.
And we just said, we love your stuff.
Would you be interested in working with us?
And we got lucky, essentially.
and all the other artists was a friend from a from an old job who wasn't looking for work. So yeah, we mind our networks.
Thank you, everybody.