Super excited to be here everybody, but yeah.
So first off, we're going to talk about The Last of Us Part II, and specifically about
designing the museum level.
We're going to cover its process from concept to composition through to production.
First off, who the heck am I?
My name's Evan Hill, I've been a level designer
for about 10 plus years.
Obviously, I recently worked at Naughty Dog
on The Last of Us Part II.
Currently, I'm at Obsidian working on Outer Worlds II.
Also worked on a couple of other things,
but main focus for today, obviously,
is gonna stay firmly on The Last of Us Part II.
So.
It has a reputation for being a pretty brutal game,
really focused on its combat, on its stealth,
all these other really hardcore elements.
But I'm also really happy with how well we were able
to display narrative and very human moments
throughout the game.
This is gonna be focused on one of the levels that,
I think, let us push that the furthest.
You know, for example, shout out to Gene Park.
This was his reaction after playing this level.
I don't apologize for possibly ruining his shirt,
but yeah, yeah, this level connected with people
particularly well.
We got a lot of fan art, tattoos, and the like,
and hopefully with this talk, we can kind of dig into
some of the elements that really drove
this connection with people.
So yeah, that's what we're gonna be covering today.
This level that we designed.
What's it about?
So let's just start with the concept.
This level takes place three years
before the main events of the game
at the height of Ellie and Joel's relationship.
It's Ellie's birthday.
Joel is teasing her with this surprise,
just constantly just dangling it over her.
She tries to guess,
and it's focused on the interplay between the two of them,
on him delivering this amazing birthday surprise.
And I'm gonna lead you through how we developed
these specific sequences,
taking you from this super positive element
of the relationship all the way to where
it starts to unravel, where they start to fall apart,
and then we see where the rest of the game goes from there.
So yeah, that's just the concept layer though.
The real meat of this talk is going to be on two parts,
side A and side B.
We're gonna cover composition, which is
how we conceptualized all of these different elements,
how we actually thought about making this game,
and how we kept evaluating it
as it was continuing to be made.
The real design heavy stuff.
But that's only gonna be part of the talk.
The other part is production.
How did we take this from idea to a shippable product?
And specifically from the lens of me as a level designer,
kind of being in the thick of it all.
We're not gonna necessarily focus on
hard technical details, but just the actual.
motions of production.
So composition is gonna be about two thirds of this talk,
and production's gonna be the last third.
Got an hour, hopefully I'm gonna be able
to fit all of this in.
We're gonna try, but let's jump right into it.
So first off, side A, composition.
We're gonna start with the first track,
which is this really hot take of mine
that is everything is story.
Everything.
And the reason for this is because.
Every game is experienced one second after another.
I don't care what you're talking about.
You still live through the moments that you play a game,
and as a result, you see a plot.
You build one with yourself,
even if there's not an explicit one.
Playing a game is a narrative experience.
Even without a set plot, something like Guilty Gear
can give you narrative fulfillment, be it.
in the structure of a match,
where you're just making it through
by the skin of your teeth,
to longer term goals and longer term experiences,
like improving with a character.
I see these things as deeply narrative,
and they're emerging from their systems.
But the same thing can be applied to something like Valorant,
that same story that you're experiencing
through the matches,
the story of progression that you're telling yourself.
This also applies to systemic games like Rimworld,
Crusader Kings, Dwarf Fortress.
The main thing to understand with this is,
it's not about what games do,
it's how we as humans, as a species, deal with time.
So stories themselves are these structured
reliances of experiences.
And we normally think of things like movies and books,
but just look around us.
We have SportsCenter.
We have the same kind of thing I was just talking about,
but for athletic events, we have history.
So.
It's a cool idea, but how does that help us?
So, the main thing that this lets us do is three things.
Interesting moments, share the same anatomy,
so we're able to analyze any type of thing
that's not traditionally story using the same frameworks
and kind of push them around.
For games, this is really essential
because we're so multimedia, we're so all over the place
in terms of the ways that we engage players
and the ways that we push things towards them.
It also centers the player's experience.
Again, we're not talking about what my goal was,
what the team's goal was, what the meta commentary is.
It's entirely focused on the individual or the group
that is experiencing your story, your medium, your content.
They're the center of it, and it lets us focus on that.
And the third thing is this benefits immensely
from iteration.
Like, stories themselves are these kind of
whittling down affairs when you're making them.
And...
You know, it's how we got to make things like Last of Us
as good as they are.
Just trying and trying again, layering and layering again.
So really quickly, let's kind of break down
what I mean by all of that.
All interesting moments share an anatomy.
So I actually did a talk on this
a little more thoroughly yesterday.
You guys can check it out on the vault.
But the basic way I like to look at it
is using this methodology called Kishoten Kets.
Gonna go really fast through this.
You basically have a setup, you have a development,
you have a twist.
and you have a payoff.
This is how jokes work.
This is how most story beats work.
Again, how a football game can even work.
It's just a analysis of what makes things interesting.
You set expectations, you twist them,
and then you pay off the consequences.
The Mario games use this quite a bit right now.
Mark Brown has done an amazing video
just breaking down key shot tenkets for about 15 minutes.
We're not gonna cover that here, but really recommend it.
And yeah, centers the player's experience.
They're the center of this universe.
Everything we do is to affect their subjective
moment to moment experience in this.
Benefits from direct iteration.
Story is writing.
Good writing is rewriting.
It lets us kind of break ourselves out of this idea
that there's a right way to do things
or a perfect version of stuff.
We're just layering and layering and layering.
So for some good resources on this, by the way,
I'm gonna cover this in each section.
I would recommend Manga and Theory in Practice
by Hirohiko Araki, Robert McKee's story,
and the Visual Story by Bruce Block.
Don't worry, these will be back at the end.
Cool, that was a good idea, at least I think.
That's why I talked about it.
But what about the level itself?
So goals and acts.
These are the roots of the composition.
So we're...
trying to do this thing, we're trying to make a story,
how do we actually make sure it accomplishes
everything else that we need this to do?
What are we even trying to experientially accomplish?
So we kind of started with this at a high level
before anything else, before a pixel was pushed,
a vert was placed, or a sentence written.
We knew we wanted to show the high point
of Ellie and Joel's relationship.
We wanted the outcome of that
to reinforce the conflict between them.
We wanted to create compelling gameplay without combat.
We want to have emotional impact,
and we also want to teach the player how to swim.
But the next step is that we have to find moments
to meet our goals.
What's this rough evaluation that we're then finding
to accomplish all of this?
So what's the story is really what we're asking.
What sequence of events can do all of this
and still be interesting?
We're not just doing a checklist.
We broke this into three different acts
at a pretty early stage,
using the same kind of framework I just covered.
Setup, development, twist, payoff.
Three really simple acts,
break down the story as quickly as we can.
First was hike to the surprise.
We'd come in three years earlier.
Joel's teasing Ellie about whatever the surprise is.
She gets annoying.
He shoves her into a river.
And we suddenly teach the player how to swim.
So again.
We set it up, we developed it, big twist, you're in a river.
Oh, Ellie can swim, great.
I've taught you, we're now able to move on.
They move further, she shoves him into the river,
gets him back, and as they're continuing on,
you know, this tension keeps building and building
until the big reveal.
He's taken her to a natural history museum,
blows her tiny mind.
You've, you even as the player,
you've mostly just been focused on that back and forth
between the two of them.
You forgot pretty much about the surprise itself.
But then we get to the meat of it, exploring the museum.
We enter into this new space, this seemingly impossible
thing, just out in the middle of the woods as far as we knew.
And they bond.
They get to have this, frankly, magical moment where
everything else melts away.
They just get to be.
They go to the space area.
Joel doubles down, shows that his surprise wasn't even
done yet.
He's recorded a recording of the Apollo missions,
which again, internet's gone.
Nobody's ever heard about this for a while,
or at least been able to hear it.
Ellie's ecstatic.
This moment itself, like you can look at it
as that high point, as that moment
where they're at their best, and then they move on.
Ellie's curiosity to keep the good times rolling,
her drive to see everything,
gets them to check out this other building
that Joel hasn't explored.
Of course, they get separated.
She gets lost, winds up in a dark, spooky place,
and as you and her are starting to get eked out,
gets attacked by a boar.
Not actually any real threat, just really shaking.
But in the midst of this, she also finds
a piece of graffiti that really catches her attention.
Joel busts in, see if everything's okay.
You know, no threat, no infected,
but something that reminds them
of the other problems that they have.
That the events of the first game still happened,
and that...
Joel is still lying to her.
She doesn't know about what,
but she knows he's hiding something.
And this then leads to their unraveling.
So yeah, pretty straightforward.
Just a recap of the story,
but hopefully you can see how we kind of stack these
on top of each other to create that rhythm,
to create that pulse,
to accomplish everything we tried to do and deliver it.
It's delicious, it's great.
Good storytelling.
Nothing crazy.
That's cool.
But how did we actually find and develop these moments?
Like, I just gave you a list.
I didn't tell you how I got there.
So let's go into that.
Track three, characters.
The main thing to understand
about our style of storytelling at Naughty Dog,
and mine personally,
is we try to work from this premise
that characters drive the story's beats.
Everything we just described
was due to an action of these characters.
Joel is the one giving the surprise.
Ellie is the one reacting.
Ellie pushes forward into the annex.
All of these things, it's pretty basic,
but they're driven by what these characters want
and who they are.
So we understand that characters drive the story's beats,
but what drives them?
We need to understand the people coming along with us
into the story.
And how do we do that?
Break it down.
First, we do things like look at their character history.
Who are they and what have they been through?
This is Ellie and Joel.
They have been through an entire The Last of Us together.
All of that, their trauma, their grief,
got resolved in the end of that.
They are thinking that they are living
their happily ever after.
Game's done, Ellie was saved, no cure,
bit of a loss, but.
They're trying to move forward.
They're both looking to the future.
Since we understand these contexts,
and this covers everything else with them,
their personality, their history,
Joel's from Austin, Ellie's grew up mostly in Boston,
different vibes, but the main thing
that this character history gives us
is it helps us understand what these characters want.
And then we are able to take those wants
and drive them into actions.
So, quick breakdown.
Joel's main want in this scene, in this flashback,
is he wants to live the life he had
before he lost Sarah with Ellie.
And he's getting to do that.
He's a dad again.
He's got the daughter, shaped hole in his heart, filled.
Ellie wants to see the world progress again.
She grew up really, really harshly,
and now has experienced what she sees
as the only bit of stability.
She's very much on the pro like,
oh hey, the world can actually be good though.
Imagine that.
And you know, her love of space and science,
always looking ahead, kind of reflect this.
But then we take the next layer,
which is this is what these people want on the surface.
This is their most primary drive.
But they also have secret wants.
Joel's pretty simple.
wants to keep hiding the truth about the fireflies.
That man does not want anybody to know what he did.
Does not want Ellie to know what he did.
Ellie still secretly wants to know what happened.
You know, they have these two aligning superficial goals
that let them bond, let them really
just become a family unit,
but that core tension underneath
that we get to tug out at the end
shows how they unravel.
How they go from there to here.
So yeah, the secret wants come forward,
unravel both of them, Joel starts to lose Ellie.
Ellie fears she misses her chance to matter.
She's starting to kind of question and worry.
It's like, wait, what part was he lying about?
And yeah, the best way to think about this too
is that story isn't picking words.
It's finding the actions that bring characters to life.
So how do we go about doing that?
We're not trying to sit down necessarily
and type out a script or just bunker up.
One of the things that I really liked
with our process at Naughty Dog
is it was very kind of focused on acting in improv.
So we would just brainstorm, feel it out,
play as the characters, use all of this knowledge
and history to just come up with dumb moments.
Like it turns out, a lot of Naughty Dog is ex-theater kids.
And if you were to just like pop into the office,
somebody would probably be rolling on the ground,
other people would be using voices,
they'd be having fake shouting arguments,
but you know, can't really show that here.
But yeah, it honestly though, like that approach
is what I think got us some of these
like very lively feeling moments.
We didn't pre-plan a script,
we just worked from the characters,
tried to actually imagine what they would do
in these situations.
So yeah, if you guys want some more resources on characters
and how we kind of built all of this out,
we've got the Art of Dramatic Writing by Lagross Angry,
Creating Character Arcs by K.M. Weiland,
and of course, Robert McKee's story.
So that's cool.
But what about the player?
Let's talk about gameplay.
So I've mostly just talked about what happens,
who these characters are.
This is a game, there's a player,
there's somebody that is in the room with us
that isn't there until the game ships.
So how do we bring them into this experience?
How do we involve them in this thing that we're doing?
This is acting, this is improv.
Simplest way that I've been able to articulate this
is we approached it as if the player is an actor
that we cast as Ellie.
That means that this person, this performer,
collaborating with Ashley Johnson basically,
has the agency to drive her actions.
They might not be able to branch
and decide what those actions are,
they're still the impulse.
They are still the one doing this.
They are acting from a script basically.
That's how acting works.
You don't go on stage and
do a choose your own adventure play, you do your part.
They are the impulse.
They get to decide though still, some decisions,
the timing and the tone of those decisions.
They get to decide the what, the when, the why,
and it takes us to the next part.
We also want to ensure that these decisions,
these choices we're giving the player,
provide emotional expression.
They are either letting them,
facilitate or express an emotion that they think Ellie should have.
So they also get to let her explore her different reactions.
So I can press a button going like, oh, I wonder what Ellie's going to do with this,
and then get surprised, get this feedback that it's like, oh, she's going to make a
stupid joke.
She's going to get on Joel's nerves.
I want to see that.
I align myself with that.
I'm exploring this character interactively in a way that, you know, it's not quite acting,
but it's, I think, something.
enriching nonetheless.
And then the final part is feedback.
So we have agency, expression,
but the next part is yes-anding,
is like taking what the player's trying to do
and saying, oh, that's cool.
Also, developing it, throwing it back.
Again, kind of going back to this improv framework
that we're working from.
It also then drives the next expression.
It drives the next decision for the player.
You're actually having a back and forth
instead of, I don't know, filling out a spreadsheet
or going on a hike.
And some examples of this that we can kind of cover are,
you are the real person to press the button
to shove Joel into the water.
It isn't a cut scene.
It's not perfectly timed or canned.
It's whatever you feel like it.
Whenever you, honestly, as the player,
I think he's expecting it the least.
That way you get that bit of extra satisfaction.
Same thing with the swimming.
Really simple, but just this exploration of a new mechanic.
Up until this point, you've not been able to swim
in this game, we're at about like eight hours in,
you get a new expressive way to navigate the environment,
learning things like diving underwater.
You can also find some secret stuff,
like climbing on the dinosaur,
just being this reckless kid,
clambering up the nearest cool thing
that she finds when she's excited,
and getting to, again, like emotionally express that,
getting to just align with the performance
She's just jazzed to be there.
She's actually also kind of happy
that she's screwing with Joel.
Or her finding a hat, messing around,
going into the back rooms, cracking jokes.
These are all optional.
These aren't essential to her performance,
but they're things that you as a player
get to own having added to the performance.
You're the one who has decided that,
like, yeah, this is Ellie.
This is who she is.
You're collaborating with us.
You're adding to the scene
rather than just...
doing it by rote.
And yeah, that's just how we approached
a lot of these small sections,
putting hats on the dinosaurs, putting the hats on Joel,
even going back to emotional expression,
literally letting you just go into a mirror
and make stupid faces.
Can't get any more direct than that.
Choosing your hats, deciding how long you want to examine
this gift that Joel's given you,
you're the one to jump off, move forward.
And then when things start taking a turn.
There's nothing at all in the game
asking you to turn on your flashlight or crouch,
pretend that it's, you know, you're in danger.
You're the one doing that as the player.
You're embodying these emotions.
By this point, we've gotten you so deep in
that you're not really consciously doing this,
but all the same, you're providing the performance.
You're providing the emotional alignment
that Ellie is then acting out in the game.
So yeah, that's how we approach this gameplay.
The player is an actor cast as Ellie.
If you want more resources on this,
I would recommend Directing Actors by Judas Wetson,
Manga and Theory in Practice by Hirohiko Araki,
and of course, Story by Robert McKee.
I told you they'd be back.
But again, that's cool.
But how does the player know all of this?
We have all this elaborate plan for them.
We've tried to convince them to be an actor
in our weird digital stage play,
but we didn't send them a script.
We didn't let them know that this was going on.
How does this work?
The simple answer is level design.
So the way we try to use level design in this scene
is that space informs the player of direction and mood.
It lets them perform without that script.
It lets them actually just kinda take it by vibes.
Just do what feels natural.
And all of a sudden, hey, you're playing by the script.
Of course, any game you can just stand perfectly still,
spin around in a circle for three hours,
or walk in the opposite direction and turn it off.
But that simple bit of collaboration
really breeds that rhythm, that momentum
where all of a sudden you as a player are.
buying into the script, taking the stage directions,
you're performing, you're the person we need you to be.
So how do we do this?
Main things we need are clear information.
This is much more than just paint the path forward yellow.
That's all really, really useful.
You know, as you guys have seen those examples
where we'll just have a piece of caution tape
fluttering in the wind to let you know where to progress.
It's also about what types of things to expect,
whether you're driving navigation or not,
whether you're in danger or not.
All of these other subtle cues
really come into this idea of clear information.
And that you need to look at this
as like this informing of the player
is much more than just where to go.
And also, it's a difficult balancing act
because too much information can be bad.
I mean, we look at over cluttered UI,
we look at levels where the noise and the balance
is just not really there.
Even if I might tactically be able to understand
where I'm going, it's not giving me a mood.
Second thing we need is variety.
Aesthetics, verticality, traversal and interaction.
All of these different things that just provide contrast.
It's cool, but the real thing that it's useful for
is it also increases the memorability of information.
It lets you navigate better, it lets you segment,
it lets you kinda get everything from palette cleansers
to new directions, emotional shifts.
Again, you're directing this player here.
And the third thing is mood and impact.
Impression, immersion, and anything else
that's emotionally focused.
You know, we're giving you the mechanical process
of what to do, where to go.
We need to focus too on what these emotions are.
What should you be feeling?
And I think it's so important
that it's like I've separated this out.
We really need to get people to embody into the space,
to buy into the emotions,
and we signal a lot of that
with all the techniques and level design.
That's why we're here.
So everything from bright sunny days,
Joel leading you around
as you're being teased about this thing.
As you go in, an example here is,
Joel's leading you this whole way, and then he stops.
He just chills out and says,
I'm not gonna tell you anything else.
And this is when we actually provide the reveal.
If we go back here, there's actually multiple different ways
you can approach this thing.
We made sure this did perfectly each and every path.
But the key thing, going back to everything
we've been talking about,
suddenly the player's in a situation
where they don't know what's gonna happen next.
They know what to do.
They understand the emotional context of what's happening.
And the moment that happens afterwards,
despite it being exactly to the script
that we wanted to make,
gets to feel like their contribution to the story.
Just running through some other things.
We do this with letting the dinosaurs
be these interaction points for the player.
We show one-off, and then we show that,
oh, the player has dozens of options.
All these different ways that they can keep
adding to this performance.
We shift gears, we change aesthetics,
we make things claustrophobic or big.
We provide really clear framing on where to go here.
Like, if you pay attention, you can probably figure out,
like, oh, hey, let's head through that window,
jump down these bars.
And then, even more importantly, when we get to the annex,
I just fuck with people.
I put down collectibles.
I put down crafting objects.
All of the cover here is valid combat cover,
even without enemies.
Using all of these subconscious cues
to just signal to the player like, hey, watch out.
And unsurprisingly, players do.
They follow along.
They really kind of shift into the mood
that I'm asking them to.
I'm not manipulating them.
I'm directing.
I'm asking.
I'm like, hey, shift into this mode.
Shift into this perspective.
And that way, when we end up surprising the player,
shoving them down by the boar,
they get to experience that emotion in a much more valid way
than if it was just rope.
And as you're still reeling from all of that adrenaline,
we take you through that last beat,
that last point of separation.
But yeah, again, space.
It lets the player perform without a script.
Plenty of resources on this one.
I'd really recommend framed ink.
an architectural approach to level design,
architecture, form, space, and order, and the visual story.
So, neat.
But, what about, you know, things we haven't covered,
like timing?
Let's talk about pacing and process.
So we have all of this stuff.
We have the space, the gameplay, the characters,
all of the elements that we need.
How do we actually ensure that
It's digestible that someone would actually sit through
from beginning to end without falling asleep
or turning the game off.
How do we find the right rhythm?
Honestly, we kind of cheated in this case.
I just let the player do it.
I made it more like running and just pacing yourself
than like trying to accomplish some kind of graph match.
In fact, I could do an entire talk on pacing design.
And I did.
It was yesterday though, sorry.
So this is just gonna be the short version.
The main things we need to know are
when we were building this level,
we wanted to reward people who wanted to linger,
enable people who wanted to rush,
give the player clear options,
and eventually surprise them with a follow through.
These weird little moments
like being able to put a hat on Joel,
having Joel buy into these stupid ideas
that Ellie's been throwing out.
But yeah, really recommend it.
It's gonna be on the vault.
I wish I could cover it more in depth,
but we need to move on specifically
to the actual act of getting all of this done.
How did we keep looking at this?
How did we go from concept to completion?
We really tried to make it a living process.
Remember, talked a lot about how iteration drives story.
So we've talked about the player's experience.
We've talked about how,
we've involved and put them at the center
of this aesthetic universe that we have.
But what about us?
Simple truth is, you move forward,
you expect to get it wrong, you reflect,
and keep trying anyway.
Most of your ideas will end up in here.
Just get used to it, bask in the warmth.
It's never not gonna be painful, trust me.
The amount of iterations I had to do on this
and most of the other levels was,
Intensive, but also, I wasn't surprised by it.
We just kept using all of these lenses,
all of these perspectives to try and make it better
a little bit every single time.
That's cool, but like, the other honest question
we need to ask ourselves is,
how do you deal with that struggle?
How do you keep getting back up?
You know, I'm not just gonna sit here and say like,
oh, get good, get harder, get less sensitive
to throwing away work, which is just one
of the hardest things a creative can do.
In the process of making this level though,
I feel like I found a pretty reasonable answer,
which is keep looking for inspiration.
And specifically, I wanna talk about Naoko Yamada.
This person is my favorite film director,
and I'm gonna spend about two minutes
just completely derailing this entire talk
because it's mine and you need to know about her.
So about halfway through making this level,
we were just.
kind of lost, like we knew what we wanted to do,
I didn't know how we were actually gonna do it.
And then I found this movie called Liz and the Bluebird.
She is like made by this lady right here, by this studio.
She is of the same caliber as Miyazaki to me,
quite frankly.
And I just wanna do some quick points
on why I think that is.
So let's jump into that.
First, she is a master of character and body language.
This is the biggest takeaway.
If you watch her movies for anything,
this is the reason.
She is able to imbue her characters with a sense of life
and cognition and rhythm that is spellbinding.
And like, I don't even have to make a comment here.
Just look at it.
Like every single character has their internal lives
just on full display.
She finds strange little quirks and moments
to just pull out of characters.
In fact, she's so good at this,
she's actually notorious for just shooting people
from the knees down in a scene
and fully being able to articulate their emotions from that.
I mean, look, she's doing it right now.
She makes the mundane spectacular.
She's just able to take any normal world.
She doesn't use fantastical elements like Miyazaki.
Every single one of her films are real world,
real problems, simple people,
struggling with emotions and love,
and then she'll take all of that and emotionally destroy you.
Like, I have trouble staying hydrated in most of her films.
Like, I just sob.
Like, it's great.
I mean, look at this shit.
You're going to feel this way.
It's bleak and it's beautiful.
I think all of this happens because as a leader, I also find her as an inspiration.
She brings out the best in other great artists.
This guy right here is called Kensuke Ushio.
He is a phenomenal composer, but most strikingly, his music sounds totally different when he's
working on her projects.
He's normally doing like...
dark, grungy, insane, almost metal-like music for things like Devilman Crybaby.
For Liz and the Bluebird, he literally scattered paint onto the bars and then composed off of that
after seeing an animation technique she was using. She has a masterful studio that really backs her
up. And then, in the most selfish part of this talk, the other reason I like her is her favorite
director is my other favorite director. This guy...
who looks like a Dark Souls boss,
is Jodorowsky.
He's this weird Argentinian
where you don't have time to get into him.
The main thing is, his stuff's wild.
It's surreal, it's poetic,
and I think you'd regret missing it.
So two minutes are up.
Just wanted to do that aside.
I could do an entire hour on this director and her work,
and I might, but if I could just sum it up in one word,
it would be grace.
Her work is graceful.
And if you like anything I've done,
this is the template for a lot of what I pursue
as a creative.
This is the template that I'm like striving for now
after seeing this.
Like it changed the trajectory of my creative ambitions.
It was just that important to me.
But enough about that.
Let's get into the next stage, which is production.
The how do.
How do we actually take all of these compositional things
and make it happen.
So let's take a quick look.
So we had teams and timelines.
My role on this project officially was level design.
Basically, I was the first designer on the ground,
I created the layouts, some of the prototypes,
and then coordinated the teams at each stage.
I was basically the person who, quote unquote,
owned the level.
Doesn't mean I did everything
or was the main person in charge.
I was just the person responsible
for making sure everybody was talking to each other.
So at the start, it was just me.
The way we just generally do it is like,
we start with a level designer and a lead
kind of working together to incubate it.
We move it up to a four person strike team
until it's kind of cooking a little bit better.
And then as we move into alpha and play testing,
we slowly ramp up to more and more people,
more and more people, until at full production,
it's all hands on deck.
The maximum amount of people working on it,
all departments are involved,
everything is just firing in all cylinders.
Also, I didn't work on this level beginning to end
in one big chunk.
Each of us had about three to five levels
that we accomplished and wove together
for over about two years.
So I wanna talk about this process a little bit.
The first step to me,
how I'd like to describe Naughty Dog's goals
is to create a playable storyboard.
Step one of this is actually breaking the story.
We sit down with the writers, we read the pitch,
we grab the lead into a meeting and we just talk about it.
We figure out in a brainstorm,
what we're trying to accomplish,
what are interesting things that we can do,
using all of these things that we've talked about before.
We literally went to a seminar hosted by Robert McKee
early when I started there,
just to have a shared language
that we could start chewing on this,
start breaking this down into manageable parts
and make it happen.
After that meeting,
level designer would break off with the lead
and just plan a first pass.
We would try to get all of this done
in like less than two days.
It's a very, very concise but focused start to all of this.
The next step though is what I like to call
3D first design.
We would just jump straight into Maya.
No top-down maps, maybe just a rough outline,
maybe a few scribbles, nothing substantial
beyond actually getting a mesh done
that I can walk around in.
We get the block mesh in engine
and we try to actually move the character
in the camera around to see if it starts working.
The reason I think this is one of the best ways to do it
is it's the fastest way to test an idea.
You can see if this even makes sense,
if this feels too big or too small,
if the camera doesn't make any sense,
if you can even accomplish something like
revealing a dinosaur to somebody
by wandering through a forest.
You can say all of those things,
but it doesn't matter unless you can prove
that it actually works in engine.
And it's also important to do it so fast
because it lets you assume that things will be thrown away.
Going back to that living process and that iteration.
you were intentionally making this to die.
Like, don't care about it,
don't feel as little pain to shove it out and try again.
But yeah, what also do we mean
when we're talking about storyboards?
What do we mean playable storyboard?
So I think for extra context on what I was just saying,
a lot of storyboards are like this.
Like this is from Knives Out.
The image on the right is their initial concept
for this shot.
Just soak it in.
You don't need to be a master illustrator
to convey your ideas.
And now I'm gonna show you what we dealt with
in the early stages of development.
This was the first version of the dinosaur.
This is how we tested it.
This is how we saw if like, hey, can this even work?
And once we realized it did work,
we took it to the final version.
Unfortunately, due to a hiccup with the WiFi,
I was gonna show some.
videos of early playtest levels,
but they're all on my website, ehilldesign.com.
Basically just showing a bit of the block mesh process,
the kinds of things that we do to walk the player through
and have that playable prototype.
But just as another example, looking at this,
look at this mess, look at this scribble.
This is an early storyboard for JoJo's Bizarre Adventure.
The person behind this is like
one of the best draftsmen alive.
This guy's been in the Louvre.
This is what he normally draws like in a finished product,
but again.
He starts with this.
Starts with something that can be thrown away
just to see if the idea works.
So yeah, once we have this thing,
once we have this playable storyboard,
we walk through the block mesh with the leads.
We actually sit down face to face and just talk through it.
We fill in the gaps of animation and art
and dialogue with our performance.
Like I mentioned, we were all ex-theater kids.
Or not all, but.
We all acted like we were ex-theater kids.
We just lived in the scene with each other.
We tried to figure it out.
We would just wildly gesture and say,
like, oh, it'll look like this, it'll be great, you know?
And it led to a lot of great moments.
The first time I showed this off to the leads,
one of them, right out of their mouth,
can I climb the dinosaur?
Like, the grin on their face was phenomenal.
When we said, yeah, sure, we could totally do that.
And then we did.
Same thing with the hats.
It was just a dumb joke I made.
just totally off the cuff and it wound up being a feature
that a lot of people really like.
So yeah, we would talk about what sucked and what worked.
We would use all of that compositional stuff
we covered in the first part of this talk
to analyze what was good to move forward with
and what we needed to cut or redo.
And we just literally throw it all out again and redo.
It's the power of iteration.
You rework it until it clicks.
Normally we would spend about several weeks iterating,
like four to 12, depending on the complexity.
That's total, mind you, not per iteration.
Four to 12 weeks of figuring out this block mesh,
this playable storyboard.
Again, like including starting from scratch.
Like we tried to keep this as limited
and light as possible.
This is the part where the level designer
was the only person working on it.
But yeah, it lets it grow and breathe
as we get a feel for it.
We don't really even know at this point.
how long the final level is going to be.
You could add a third, double it, cut it, shift it around,
try radical different flows and beats of the elements.
Like the dinosaur kind of came in early,
but for example, the space capsule, that whole entire scene,
that wasn't until like the last quarter
of this like ideation process,
before the graffiti was just gonna be right after
the main part of the museum and on the space capsule itself.
But in going through this process,
me and the leads like wanted more.
We figured out what to add,
and then I just went back into Maya and added more.
But yeah, once we have this rough sketch done,
this playable storyboard, that's great,
but that's not enough.
The next stage is getting into alphas and playtesting.
We try to build a playable prototype.
That's where the first stage
is we're taking it to other designers.
We're trying to limit our gesturing, our manic energy,
convey the story and just let it speak more
and more for itself.
That's when we also start adding in more developers.
It's like I said, the four to six person strike team
that supports the level designer to actually finish
and develop features.
And then work towards that first playable.
First playable means the first time you can just shut up
and let someone play it on their own.
No guides, no role presentation.
I hand it to you, I leave the room, does it work or not?
Again, I would have some video for you,
but unfortunately not, all on my website.
And then once we hit that stage,
once I can actually hand it to you and leave,
we grab some outside people, hand it to them and leave.
So every few weeks we would have outside people come in,
they'd have really detailed feedback,
and we do this about a cadence of every two to three weeks
as we're shifting through production.
So this would be a studio-wide event.
And trust me, when you start play testing,
thoroughly like this or not,
you will see how bad your layout really is.
Everything that was duct taped over
with good intentions and slick presentations
just falls away.
You will watch people get lost,
not care about your story, complain,
and worst of all, be right about all of it.
Just rip it apart.
Also because of this cycle, this like tempo
where every two to three weeks,
we knew we were gonna be bringing in new people.
We knew that, oh, I fucked up.
That level sucked.
What can I do in the next three weeks to make it better?
What can I do to ensure that I don't break this
and it's still playable in three weeks too?
Yeah, so all the changes need to be playable.
We had so much data to work with though.
It was massively helpful.
And another level with it too, it was studio-wide tempo.
It wasn't just playtesting your level,
it was playtesting all the levels at once.
Then we would go back to iteration,
and then playtest all the levels at once.
It really helped facilitate just a cohesion.
Everybody knew what was on the schedule.
Everybody knew what needed to get done.
We were able to focus on tighter milestones.
But from there, we would also take all of that data
and try to dial things in.
That's when the more formal reviews
with studio leadership would tend to happen.
We'd refine features and scripting
and prove out any ideas that we have
with playtest feedback rather than just wildly gesturing,
hey guys, I think this is a really good idea.
Instead, we can go like, hey, this part,
objectively people like it, they keep talking about it.
Let's improve this or fix this.
Again, it's just all about trying
to facilitate effective iteration.
But even at this stage,
You know, we tried to cut things early,
throw things out fast,
but there's still gonna be a lot of rework.
Cuts, revisions, additions.
We use the entire team for input at this point.
Starting from scratch is almost limited
to specific sections, but it's still fairly common.
We call it back to layout,
where a chunk of the level might just be kind of
sawed out and redone.
Honest example of this was that space section.
We were pretty confident in the rest of the layout
and the rest of the area, but.
There were a few times where we just looked
at that upper area, that second floor,
and we had art done for it, we had some features in,
and it just wasn't right.
And we kind of pulled the trigger on redoing it again.
And yeah, just going back to that iteration,
that living process, you just keep trying to make it work.
You keep redoing and redoing and redoing.
But what happens when it does work?
Like YouTube just burnt all of this effort,
like desperately trying to make this thing work.
And now it does.
And now what?
That's when you lock the layout.
The level is moved from prototype to alpha.
Now the rest of the team can be brought in
to actually make this thing shippable.
Which brings us to full production.
This is the part where everything gets ramped up.
We bring off, hand off to the other departments.
This isn't a comprehensive list,
but you know, an example is like audio, VFX,
mocap, dialogue, character art, AI, foreground,
technical art, environment art, animation,
cinematics, QA, and on and on and on and on.
This is when we take it from just,
oh, the designers are working on this cool thing
with a small group of people to everyone needs to know
about every detail all of the time.
It also really helps collaboration.
We then start really focusing on feedback and direction,
more as level designers, more than anything else.
This is when it goes hands off.
Like, I should not be in Maya,
I should not be in editor,
messing with things other than gameplay scripting.
So yeah, it's like I shift time
to other levels at this point.
Like maybe I start the whole process over
on another section, or start scripting gameplay
for the scene.
A big part of this, at least in the Naughty Dog process
and in making this up for me,
was coordinating the team as well.
I was the one scheduling meetings, relaying information,
managing task loads and deadlines,
and also facilitating the review process.
I really liked what we did on this project,
where we would have large recorded meetings,
where we would just play through the level
and note down every single thing that was wrong.
And this would be like maybe eight people at some times,
just pausing, commenting, pausing, commenting.
So a 20-minute level might be three hours
of commentary video.
But we also had this annotation software
where you could take the recording and just make a note,
turn that note into a Jira ticket,
hand it all to the level designer,
hand off all the Jira tickets to the people
that need to get it done.
But yeah, this is mostly focused, specific feedback.
Very rarely would this turn into a full rework,
a back to layout kick.
But yeah, how did I do this?
What kind of fancy tools were there?
Nothing really important.
Face-to-face communication, legal pads.
Skype for business, email, JIRA, no silly proprietary
scrim board or anything else, just actual paper,
a few tags, and it kind of looks something like this.
For clarity, this is not at all for anything Naughty Dog,
this is just some personal projects that I kind of work with
but no, I would just kind of run around the office
like it was an Aaron Sorkin movie,
just talking to each department about every single thing
on my giant list I'd need done for the day.
I would break it down into sections with tabs,
and yeah, it was facilitating iteration.
And then the hard part comes, which is lock and polish.
So before when we said we handed things off,
it was kind of a lie, there were still reworks,
but this was the hard point where we would shift into,
we have deadlines, we're getting this done,
no major changes, push it from this janky prototype mess
to this thing that is naughty dog quality.
So in this polish stage, everything matters.
The review and the playtesting cycle I mentioned before
is continuing through this entire process, this entire span.
And the notes are picking up.
They're getting more and more.
It turns into a flood.
Every single department has tiny tweaks and everything,
but through all of this, it starts to finally take shape
into something that's gonna ship.
And yeah, a lot of this time,
even though there's no layouts to be done,
us in the level design department are running around,
doing additional scripting, fixing things.
We're just responsible to get things done.
I was basically a messenger boy on some days,
and it was hectic as heck,
because that's the real takeaway on this part of production.
The team does it.
All of these other developers that I worked with
are some of the most talented people
I probably will ever have the privilege to work with,
and they're just great.
They were on top of everything to the point that,
yeah, I was relegated to just running around,
conveying information in notes,
because, yeah, this.
that type of work isn't focused on somebody like me
or the leads.
It does take an entire massive organization to deliver.
And the result is honestly still just one of the things
I'm most proud to have helped on.
Like I, yeah, this was a joy to work on
and thanks for letting me do this talk.
So yeah, that's it.
We've covered composition and production,
hopefully giving you a bit of an insight into.
what it takes to make a Naughty Dog level,
specifically a weird one like this.
But yeah, final housekeeping,
let's cover some of the takeaways.
You wanna find a useful framework.
For us, it was story.
For you, it can be something else,
competitive integrity, counterplay, whatever it is,
you use them to guide iteration.
Start it rough as fast as you can, you fail,
you pick yourself up, often by finding some inspiration,
you iterate more, fail more,
try not to stop until it's great.
and you rely on your team.
That's it.
Hope you guys can follow me.
This is my Twitter.
I'm gonna be working on some secret podcast stuff
that'll hopefully come out soon.
And then the main thing is,
I'll be contributing to Outer Worlds 2.
And here's a list of resources.
Also go watch Liz and the Bluebird,
and A Silent Voice, and The Hickey Story.
I'm not kidding, they're really, really good.
And we have time for questions.
Hi, great talk.
Question about the playtesting every two, three weeks
that you mentioned, especially early on in the process.
What does that look like in terms of the questions
that you're asking the playtesters?
Is it very directed to a specific thing
that you're trying to accomplish?
Do you start out general?
How does that work?
I can't get too, too specific
because Sony really has been refining
their process constantly.
But in general, it's a lot of data,
big questionnaires, group feedbacks, focus tests.
So yeah, just literally anything
that we thought would help, we would throw at it.
There wasn't like a framework that we really worked from.
We're just like, what would we like to know
and what would they like to tell us?
Hi, thanks for the talk.
I was kind of on the same page as him,
asking about feedback from outside players.
How do you kind of handle that?
And how do you know what's good feedback
versus bad feedback?
I mean, you're the level designer, you know best.
How do you know what to listen to?
No, that's a really great question.
So in case it wasn't picked up,
how do you know it's good feedback?
How do you know it's bad feedback?
How do you turn them into notes?
A good rule of thumb I've always liked
is that the player is.
usually right that something is wrong,
but usually wrong about what specifically
is causing the problem.
The classic example was there was a first person shooter
where the two sides had identically,
statistically damaging guns.
Same fire rate, everything else like that.
But the sound effects on one
sounded more aggressive and more intense than the other.
And as a result, the players kept giving feedback,
like oh, this gun's more powerful than this one,
this gun's more powerful than this one,
you need to nerf this.
You're able to analyze that it's statistically identical.
The only difference was actually the sound effect.
They boosted the gain on it, the note went away.
Again, players are telling you something's wrong
because there's usually something wrong.
But they will always, the other thing to understand
is they'll always reach to the most obvious answer,
the most proximate answer,
the thing that's the most in their perception
because they feel it, they see it,
they give you the feedback, but yeah.
One more playtesting question.
How much do you have the same group of humans come in
to see if your new iteration works differently
versus try to vary them to make sure
that you're not just designing for that group of people?
Oh, we would try to get fresh feedback as much as possible.
Very rarely, I've forgotten if we ever brought
entire groups back or entire individuals back,
but in general with outside playtesting,
the idea is fresh first player experience.
And then that kind of,
Longitudinal iteration would just be mostly design team,
the people who are also the other developers.
The people who are making the game would kind of provide
that like, oh, where were we six months ago
and where are we now type analysis.
Thank you.
Quick question about the, I guess,
the proportion of time that you spent on the blockouts
versus the polish stage.
What was that like?
It was pretty variable.
I can't give you a hard time on it
because it was all just very fluid, very focused,
and the directors were the ones
kind of setting the final deadlines.
But again, I would wanna say an eighth of the time
or less was that initial ideation process,
and then it was probably somewhat close
to a quarter, a quarter, and then two quarters on polish.
That final stage of taking it from beta to.
ship, Naughty Dog is a bit longer than most other studios.
So I would say, yeah, that's the main balance.
I can't be like, oh, we spent three months on this,
three months on that,
because it was spaced over five levels over two years.
We had a lot of shifts in production and the like,
but in general, just providing more time
for that last step, that last team-focused step,
I think is another really important thing
that Naughty Dog does that's not necessarily associated
with our composition or our level design.
So as a designer, there's always a moment like you have to iterate until you get it perfect,
but there's also this expression where an art project is never done, only abandoned.
I'm wondering when do you know to abandon it? Like especially for that one thing that you
cut out entirely, because in my mind you could just try to polish a turd as much as you can.
Yeah, that's where leadership I think is really effective. So kind of by separating that
decision-making from the person making the ideas.
and the person deciding this is what gets made
and that's what doesn't.
So to me, a good lead is always a good editor.
They're the people who get to be a step removed
from the process of making the thing
and can kind of say, this is done,
this is good enough, this isn't.
And yeah, so it's like a structural thing.
It's not, don't do it alone.
I guess that's the best way I can do it.
I was surprised to hear you all used Maya to block out stuff.
So in my career, I've mostly used brushwork or primitives
or stuff to block out those rough shapes pretty quickly.
What did you find the advantages or disadvantages
were using Maya to block out stuff instead of, say,
in-editor tools or other things like that?
Yes, the main reason is just that Naughty Dog
has its own personalized tech stack.
There's no, like we're not using Unity or Unreal
or anything else like that.
So there was a lot of integration with Maya,
but overall the main benefit to it in my mind
is just that 3D first design,
being able to focus on bespoke sections.
So I wouldn't recommend this for all games,
like working on Outer Worlds 2,
we're obviously working from more of a kit structure,
but.
in a narrative-focused single-player game like The Last of Us,
being able to just custom make every piece of GO
in this storyboarding process,
I think we found that pretty effective.
We all worked.
fast enough, we were all capable enough
at this particular mode that we're able
to get things standing and done fast enough.
We also didn't have a lot of complicated physics objects
or the like in our gameplay loop,
so we were then able to mostly rely
on just mood, structure, sight lines, and pacing,
and then just go from Maya to Engine.
Hey there. So under the production schedule you detailed, other disciplines and teams
are rolling on pretty far into that design process. And under those conditions, how do
you maintain alignment and get all the other disciplines on board and engaged with the
original vision you had as the LD? Also, what sorts of steps do you take to find potential
compromises, mitigate wake, and more as the design owner once it reaches their hands?
I'm sorry, I'm having trouble hearing you.
Can you start the question over again?
I'll just reiterate the first part of the question.
So other disciplines and teams are rolling on pretty far
into the design process.
Under those conditions, how do you maintain alignment
and get all the other disciplines on board
and engaged with the original vision that you had as the LD?
Yes, so the main question is, how do you keep everybody
on the same page?
Correct?
Yes, so communication.
It's real.
Real dead simple, we would meet regularly,
we would talk about it.
And in the same kind of mindset
where I'm trying to involve the player
in the act of playing the game,
I'm always open to good ideas.
And the more good ideas that my team members bring to me,
the less work I have to do.
So I'm just really pro getting suggestions from everybody
on how the game should be designed.
And it has the secondary benefit of that extra buy-in
helps not only just people commit to it,
but then all of a sudden they're evangelizing their ideas.
They're talking about the cool things they add.
And then you get this group perspective on how things work.
So yeah, like communication, direction.
At Naughty Dog, it was a bit easier
because we didn't have dedicated producers,
so that extra communication had to be picked up by everybody.
So that's part of the benefit.
I don't know if I would necessarily recommend that
as a universal fix, though.
The second thing I wanted to ask is,
if you're reaching concept and geolock
that early into the process,
what sorts of steps are you taking
to find potential compromises with teams
that can't deliver on the original intention,
mitigating wake, et cetera?
So the main way we kind of approached that
was just trying to avoid that as much as possible
with that communication early on.
Trying to set expectations and the like.
There were very, you know, there were a lot of
reworks kind of taken from the top,
but rarely was it ever like, oh,
this team was so particularly behind schedule,
we had to cut things.
Again, that isn't anything with my certain process.
I think it's just the people involved
have been truly excellent at it for a long time.
Gotcha, thanks so much for the awesome talk.
Thank you.
Hi, thank you.
You were talking about in the blockout,
your main goals are to communicate the points
and beats you're trying to express in the level.
Are there any other basic interactions and systems
that you use as part of that blockout phase?
So the earliest, earliest version,
honestly, we would just get by
if we could walk around the level.
And like I said, the rest is just oral presentation,
riffing, just kind of.
pitching it in person.
It's not really a game, it's just a 3D storyboard
that you're puppeting around at that point.
When we shift into getting things towards first playable,
that's when we kind of shift out.
But yeah, we just ran out of time.
Hope that answered your question sufficiently.
We'll be in the wrap-out room just next door
if you guys wanna ask me any other questions.
I'll be here for a while.
And thanks again for this talk.
I'm really glad to be able to talk to you.
You