Alright, thanks for coming. Before we begin, let's do a few reminders. Number one, please
silence your phones and or noise makers. Just be polite for everyone. And number two, please
don't forget to fill out the surveys in your email. Don't forget to check your spam folder
because sometimes it goes there.
and yeah, I guess we'll begin. Alright, good morning everyone and thanks for coming. Welcome
to Solving Titan-Sized Problems, Evolving Titan Combat in Titanfall 2. My name is Carlos and
I'm a game designer at Respawn Entertainment. Before that I was at Infinity Ward and before
that I was at a company called Shell Games.
Click. Click. Here are some of the past projects I worked on.
Most notably of course Titanfall 2, which the game we'll be
talking about today. Couple more things before we begin. First as
you all know, video game development is a messy process.
And while this talk may make it seem like we just figured
everything out, you know, just like that.
This is really, the reality is a lot of these lessons are a
result of trial and error and we're only really able to
organize them in this manner after all the dust has settled
and we can go take a look at what we've done.
Second, making games is a team effort and while I'm the guy
standing in front of you giving this talk, a lot of what is in
this talk represents the hard work of the different teams that
put their work into the game. So with that, let's get started.
Button.
So what's this talk going to be about?
In this talk, I'll be discussing how we evolved
Titan Combat in Titanfall 2, and how we tackled
the problem of combat in a high time to kill shooter.
We're going to be breaking down the talk
into three major sections.
The first section is the introduction to the problem,
where we'll talk about kind of trying to insert
a high time to kill game, or trying to insert
low time to kill shooter sensibilities
into a high time to kill game.
and what problems can crop up with that.
The second part, we'll go into the solutions
that worked for us in Titanfall 2,
and we'll start with how we attacked this problem
in multiplayer, and then move on
to how this affected single player.
Finally, we'll discuss some pitfalls that we came across,
or problems that we might not have completely figured out.
real quick let's talk about titanfall 2. What is titanfall
2? For those who don't know, titanfall 2 is a first person
shooter set in the far future in which players play as pilots. Oh
god.
Agile soldiers that can wall run and double jump around the battlefield.
And during the course of a match, pilots can call down titans, huge war machines designed
for destruction, and manually control them on the battlefield.
So titanfall is really a mix of both low time to kill gameplay in the form of pilots and
high time to kill gameplay in the form of titans.
and a funny story, just for the purposes of this talk, I
realized when I talk about high time to kill, most people will
think about games like Halo and Overwatch. So just for the
purposes of this talk, when I actually say high time to kill,
I'm talking more of a 20 second or greater time to kill as
opposed to something, a game like Overwatch or Halo or Team
Fortress which lives in a more like 5 to 10 second time to
kill. So I guess in the real world...
we would call something like Titan combat extreme high time
to kill if we were to stick with high time to kill for team
fortress and overwatch. But you know, like I said, I realized
that a little late so just for this talk, that's what high time
to kill means. Okay, so now that that's out of the way, let's
begin by talking about what exactly the problem is we're
dealing with.
At the beginning of Titanfall 2, Titans were identified as an area in which the game could
greatly expand.
With mobility no longer being unique to the franchise, Titans were seen as a greater key
differentiator that could really set us apart.
The problem was that internally, Titan gameplay was largely seen as boring or lacking depth.
people would usually throw out the word mushy as a way to
describe titan combat. And references to rockemstock and
robots were often, I hate you, you're not playing my jif.
Rockemstock and robots was often brought up as a point of
reference for titan fights.
So if we were really to push Titan gameplay,
these would be the biggest problems to solve.
So we started asking ourselves, why?
Why does Titan gameplay feel so mushy?
Why does it lack depth?
So it seemed to have all the pieces,
guns that felt good, and rockets, and dashing,
and the Titans even moved quickly in an agile manner,
so it felt better to drive around in a Titan.
So we got back to basics and really started asking ourselves
some hard questions.
Questions like, where does shooter depth come from?
And we know that gameplay depth can come from having
interesting decisions.
So where would the interesting decisions
come from in a shooter?
So the model we came up with.
and most of you in one way or another might be already
familiar with this, is that shooters tend to give players
different layers of decisions that they're making.
And these are broken down by the amount of time players
have to make those decisions.
So we've identified three key layers that most of the
decisions can fall into.
There's the atomic layer, which lives in the sub-second
space, the, oh, I hate you so much.
the tactical layer which lives in the ten second space and the
strategic layer which lives in the five to ten minute space.
So we'll look at each one of these layers real quick. Atomic
decisions live, again, these live in the sub second decision
making space and they involve the player identifying a target
on screen and then deciding how to move their cursor over the
target which means deciding how they're going to move their
thumb on the thumb stick.
and then deciding when to pull that trigger,
hopefully killing the target.
And these types of decisions are happening
at a split second interval,
so you're not really always conscious
that you're making these decisions,
but they are there.
And these types of decisions have to do
with what we call twitch skill, or hand-eye coordination.
So you get better by practicing and building muscle memory.
tactical decisions happen at around 10 second intervals. And usually these happen when
players have just spawned in or maybe when you just finish clearing an area in a team
deathmatch setting. And these decisions will often involve the player assessing the current
state of the map, where am I?
where are the enemies or where do I think the enemies are,
and then deciding on his engagement approach.
Okay, so if I'm over here,
and the enemies are up in that tower,
and there's two ways to get to that tower,
they're probably looking at the main road
because there's a window over there,
so I'm gonna take this other road,
and hopefully catch them by surprise.
And these types of decisions often have to do
with what people often refer to as map knowledge.
So the more you know about the map,
the better you can be at making these decisions.
Mmm
Finally strategic decisions happen over a much longer
timeline. Sometimes over once per match, but sometimes also
in the middle of the match. And these decisions often involve
things like load out selection or team composition. So like I
said, normally you're familiar with these, you'd select them
at the beginning of the match. But for example in a team death
match scenario, it can happen in the middle of the match, say
when I go on a bad losing streak or bad death streak, I might
have to...
reassess my load out and then go change it and change my
strategy. So really another good way to think about all these
layers is like the atomic layer will revolve around thinking
about this next bullet that I'm going to fire and the tactical
decisions are thinking about what's the next fight I'm going
to have and the strategic decisions are thinking about
like what's next 3, 4, 5, 6, 7 fights I'm going to have. So
what we really have is this kind of.
food pyramid of interesting decisions. So you know that the atomic scale decisions are all
the way at the bottom for shooters specifically because these are the decisions you're making a
lot of these decisions at a time or per game. So for every five atomic decisions you're making
you're maybe making only one tactical decision. Made up numbers but you kind of get the idea.
There's way more at the bottom than there is at the top.
When we apply these layers to thinking about Titan combat,
the most apparent problem is that high time to kill,
or high TTK, it really works against
the atomic layer decisions.
And to illustrate.
Imagine we have our low time to kill shooter. I'm playing this game. There's my cursor. I find a
guy that I want to kill. So now I'm deciding in my brain, my brain is fully engaged in moving my
thumb stick to try to get this cursor over the guy. And I'm moving it and now I'm trying to
figure out when I'm going to pull this trigger. And I pull the trigger and then he's dead.
which means I can move on to my next decision. Or if I fail,
then it's more likely that I'm dead and I can move on to my
next decision anyway. Contrasting that with something
like a high time to kill game, the same thing that happens, I
move my cursor over the guy, there he is, I make a decision
to pull the trigger and then nothing happens. So I guess I'll
just keep this trigger held.
And now I'm not really making any interesting decisions,
I'm just retaining the last decision that I make,
and nothing's prompting me to make a subsequent decision.
And that can lead to boredom and frustration,
and this is what people commonly refer to
as the bullet sponge problem,
aka why bullet sponges are boring to fight.
And in Titanfall, this is exacerbated even more by the
fact that titans take up a huge amount of screen space. So even
putting your cursor over them is a lot less interesting than
putting your cursor over a pilot which takes up less screen
space. And so this is really the problem that a lot of high
tactical shooters will rub up against. More people will, oh,
sorry, I already said that. So we really need to solve this
problem if we were to make titans more important for
Titanfall 2.
Real quick, these are some other not as crucial problems that
came up during assessment. So looking at the tactical layer,
it seemed that...
Titan combat overall, it's got some good tactical depth because our map designers build our
standard three lane maps for titans and that makes it so that it's fairly easy to predict
where titans going to be and you can have kind of your standard traditional shooter tactical
depth can be drawn from that. The only difference is that titans can't jump or climb anything
so they're all really playing on a single plane so you lose a little bit of depth with that
but overall it's not the end of the world.
on the strategic front, we noticed that players would
often default to what we called dual purpose weapons, like the
XO-16 chain gun, which is a rapid fire hit scan weapon. And
the reason for this is that
In Titanfall, you're never really sure whether you're going
to come up against a Titan or a pilot. So it turned out to be
more advantageous for you to bring a weapon that could just
handle both types of enemies. So it turned out to be safer. So
most people ended up picking that weapon and so that was kind
of our weapon meta for Titanfall 1. So we'll be touching on these
along the way but the real problem to solve with regards to
high T2K has to do with the atomic layer.
OK, so now that we have a greater understanding of the
problem, we can start figuring out how
we're going to solve it.
So first we'll talk about how we went about solving this in
multiplayer.
We decided it would be better to start solving the problem in
multiplayer because it's much easier to apply multiplayer
depth to single player rather than the other way around.
Single player tends to use AI logic as somewhat of a crutch,
forcing AI to do certain things so that it helps the player or
challenges the player in certain ways. But it's almost impossible
to force players to do what an AI is doing, whereas it's much
simpler to make an AI pretend to be a bad player.
So first I want to talk about specific things that we brought
back from Titanfall 1. It wasn't all bad. So here's some
things that we looked back and we decided we wanted to keep.
The first is the concept of weak spots, which is basically our
equivalent of head shots for titans. So similar to the
head shot concept, this creates a high risk, high reward zone
that the player can aim for, which helps him with the atomic
layer. It helps him give like a higher skill, way to express a
higher skill over other players. That gives him higher risk.
The problem with weak spots in Titanfall 1 was that they were
only present when a titan's shield was lowered. So most of
the time you encounter a titan, the weak spots wouldn't even be
showing and you have to take down their shield. So you have
this portion of gameplay where the weak spots don't exist and
then they exist. So that was a problem for Titanfall 1 which by
removing shields in Titanfall 2 we were able to expose the weak
spots more often.
The second thing we carried over from Timefall 1 was the
concept of dashing and blocking as a form of damage
mitigation. So this video isn't playing. Wait, are you
serious? Oh there you go. Oh my god. So these skills we were
able to add on to the atomic layer but they were not viable
due to the presence of hit scan weapons like the XO-16 which
made it impossible to dash. But we'll talk more on that later.
Okay. So moving on to Titanfall 2, the first thing we did was we tried to figure out if any
other multiplayer shooters have solved the high time to kill problem. And we came up fairly
empty handed so if anyone has any ideas, I'd love to talk about it after the talk. So instead
we looked at other genres like street fighter.
and MOBUS and we said, hey, these games, you know, they have high time to kill and they have
good depth so maybe we can learn something from these games. So trying to find the
commonality between the two, you know, it being pretty obvious that these, both of these types
of genres have the idea of preset characters or classes. And once we kind of unlocked that
discovery, it became really clear that having titans be preset characters was going to be a
really good fit.
because for high time to kill, it takes advantage of the
increased face time between players. And not only that, but
the problem we were having of titans taking up a lot of screen
space is now also somewhat of a strength since you have that
much more screen space to visualize them. And so this is
how that turned out.
So obviously the nice thing with having Titan classes too is now we can kind of give players
these common mech fantasies that are pretty popular. So we have the fire Titan, we have the
Titan with a sword, we have a laser Titan, we have a Titan that can fly. So in a way it also
helped us kind of achieve fantasy fulfillment for the players. But the real win with Titan
classes was that high time to kill.
means you have more time to assess who an enemy is and think about what tactics he might
employ. And a lot of games like team fortress 2, they'll talk about the necessity of this
snap read, which is that players need to be able to identify their enemies in a split
second.
thereby increasing the importance of distinct silhouettes
for them. And for us specifically, our fights lasted so
long that the snap read wasn't even like 100% essential. I
mean, we still strive for good silhouettes at the end of the
day, but during dev testing, all we had to do was put the
names over the guy's head and it was, you know, good enough.
It was readable enough for kind of internal testing and it
helped us kind of develop really quickly.
In addition, high time to kill also means now that players now actually have plenty of time to think about how they can combo their abilities.
And as a good example, one of the titans, Scorch, has an ability called the Incendiary Trap, which he can throw out and ignite.
And this on its own doesn't do anything, it just sits there, but it requires Scorch to light it up with his main weapon.
And this is the type of ability that you would never ship in a low time to kill shooter, because it's really inefficient.
Like you're just better off pointing your gun at the enemy and shooting him.
Having fixed loadouts also meant that abilities didn't have to
directly compete with each other for players loadout selection.
So in an Alucard system, what would normally be on your right
bumper, if you had four selections, four weapons there,
normally you would want to balance all of them in such a
way that their power level was pretty similar. Because
otherwise players would just pick the best one all the time.
but in a fixed load out system, my right bumper ability could
be weaker than someone else's right bumper ability because
you could technically transfer that power somewhere else. So
someone could have a weaker right bumper but then a stronger
primary or stronger defensive ability and so on and so forth.
It also allowed us to create more niche abilities that
weren't necessarily useful in every single situation.
since we're going down the road of fixed loadouts, we wanted
each titan's abilities to synergize with each other. This
creates depth by allowing players to discover the
different ways that they can use a titan's abilities. So we
wanted to make sure that all titans were thematically
matched, but also that all their abilities kind of, you would be
able to think about how you could use one or two or three
abilities together. But,
We still need to address the atomic layer problem directly.
And to do this, we found that staying away from rapid fire
weapons actually benefited that layer.
Low frequency, high damage attacks create spikes in the
flow of the fight where players can have small moments of
success and failure.
So this also mimics kind of the low time to kill dynamic
since the acquire aim fire loop is completed after each
shot is made, since the lack of rapid fire capabilities
means that the player needs to reacquire the target after
each shot.
So this also allows for better rhythm in the fight
since it creates pauses between the shots.
So players can have time to assess the situation
between each of his enemy's shots.
So let's take a look real quick.
First, we're going to take a look at two videos real quick.
The first video is the XO-16 chain gun,
the infamous XO-16 chain gun.
Kind of the only thing that comes out of that.
So in that video you'll see the guy with the exo-16, he's just running around pointing
the gun at his enemy and there's really no new decision points.
that he's triggering. Other than the fact that maybe A, when he
reloads, he might think about taking cover then because he
can't DPS at that point. Or B, when his enemy pulls up a
shield, because then he might think about, well that enemy can
damage me but I can't damage him so maybe I should break away.
But as far as his aiming and shooting, it's fairly
uninteresting. You can see he's just pointing and then just
casually turning and nothing's really changing.
Now let's contrast that with the next video which is our more
low frequency attacks.
So in this one you can see after each shot he's having to reassess what he's doing,
reacquire his target which makes for a more interesting kind of play pattern for his
primary weapon.
But that doesn't mean that we don't have rapid fire weapons.
Because the good thing about rapid fire weapons is that
they're really good for new players.
They're really easy to use.
So it provides a way for new players to get into your game
and immediately start having fun.
So we didn't want to completely give up that
accessibility.
but what we did was we made sure that the titans that had rapid fire weapons would have
something else in their loadout that could compensate and create depth. So a good example is
the titan ion. His primary weapon is a rapid fire rifle but his right shoulder, sorry let me do
it again. His primary weapon is a rapid fire rifle but it's really weak.
And his secondary, which is a shoulder laser,
is a one-time, kind of high-impact skill shot
that deals a lot of damage.
So that's, so, as an Ion player,
you're gonna, you're really,
you're really using your splitter rifle
to just kind of throw jabs at your opponent,
but what you really want to do
is hit him with your strong laser.
And so here's what that looks like.
So in this video in particular, you'll see the first laser shot
was missed and that was pretty crucial. If he would have hit
that laser shot, this Titan would have been doomed and he
could have gone in for the execution. As mentioned
blocking and dashing was something we carried over from
Titanfall 1 but we realized that this only really works when
everyone's weapons are projectile based. Projectile
weapons have travel time and that time is essential for
players to be able to respond to it. So combining projectile
weapons with slow fire weapon designs, damage mitigation
becomes a much more viable concept in Titanfall 2. Next.
But projectile weapons tend to be really difficult to use,
especially combined with the fact that many of our weapons
were not rapid fire. So to help with this, we have tech called
fat projectiles that we can apply. And what this does is it
gives our projectiles width, making it easier to hit targets
with them. The nice thing with this tech was that it was also
used for pilot weapons and it allowed us to create non-hit
scan weapons for pilots that could go toe to toe with the
assault rifle.
But hitscan can still exist.
And a good example of this is one of the Titans Legion
who has a minigun.
But his minigun has a built in spin up time.
So that compensates for the lack of travel time
in his projectiles.
And we do a lot of work to change his silhouette
depending on his weapon state.
So players can easily read whether or not
he's ready to fire.
In addition.
This also makes positioning way more important for a Legion player, so we kind of accept that he'll
have less engaging atomic decisions. That's okay since we've traded it for an increased dependence
on his tactical decisions. Video.
Another thing that we did was design abilities that created permanents on the battlefield.
Scorch's loadout in particular features abilities that linger for some amount of time,
so it forces his opponent to constantly kind of rethink his position, or it pushes his opponent out of position.
And something we realized...
was that abilities, sorry, rather, something we realized
was that titan fights would often last a long time and
titans would often play in the same space. So having something
that can change the meaning of that space would help keep those
fights fresh. Some other examples of this, of permanence
that we made were the cluster missile, particle wall, the
scorches incendiary trap, or the laser trip mines for ion. So
But static permanents are good, but we found that permanents
that move in a slow, predictable path are even better.
So the slow moving part is important because you want
these permanents to last a good amount of time
on the battlefield, or enough time that players can react
to them in a meaningful way.
So if they move too quickly, they'll end up hitting a wall
or flying by your opponent, and then they're basically
gone at that point.
And we came upon this discovery when we made this ability
called the Arc Ball.
which oddly enough didn't ship as a titan weapon. The arc ball or the thunderbolt, that's the
pilot version of this weapon but this specifically is the arc ball. This is an ability that
launches a slow moving projectile. Can you see my pen? No you can't see my pen. Can you see my
cursor? So this is our slow moving projectile as you can see. And you can see this
projectile kind of zaps the opponent that's within range of it.
So when we play tested this, we found that it really added an
extra kind of, an extra layer that would really change the
dynamic of the fight, but only for a certain amount of time.
So here's what that looks like in practice.
If this video would play.
Maybe if I click.
So you can see in that video there's multiple ways to kind of use the arc ball not just to
damage your opponent but to force him into certain bad situations that you can take advantage of.
And this kind of mimics hopefully this GIF will play.
Oh, I hate you so much.
Yes, so this mimics what in Street Fighter people,
the slow fireball in Street Fighter,
which players can use to,
I think they call it fireball zoning.
So what it does is it forces their opponents
to react to the fireball
and possibly put themselves in a bad position.
Finally, the last element that we worked on was improving our
Titan's core abilities. In Titanfall 1, core, sorry, in
Titanfall core abilities are essentially supers or alts. They
are ultra low frequency moves that can have a high impact on a
battle. Titanfall 1 had core abilities, but they were mostly
things like double damage or increased health, which were
okay, but they didn't really create the spikes in gameplay
that you would want from an ultra low frequency attack.
For Titanfall 2, we had to rethink our core abilities to be more attack-like,
with the goal of having them create opportunities to tip stalemates or create reversals.
One thing that we wanted to make sure when designing these abilities, though,
was that they weren't instant win buttons.
We still wanted the notion of allowing players to express skill when using these core abilities.
So there's the idea of being able to use a core ability poorly and being able to use it well.
The best example of this is Ion's laser core which has wind-up time to warn the opponent
that it's going to happen and when it activates the attacker has slowed movement and he has
disabled dash and a slowed turn speed. So a player has to make a judgment on whether or
not it's a good time to use that ability. This also opens up a new type of gameplay.
which is commit and punish, which is something that you find in fighting games a lot.
So when, in fighting games, when someone does a specific move, a character will commit to a
certain movement and could possibly expose himself that can, and that the enemy can exploit.
So here's what that looks like for us, if the video would play.
Ion laser core activated.
We're not ahead by much. Let's pick up-
Just a snack.
So what we're really doing here with all these changes is we're
trying to create new decisions for the player to make outside
the atomic layer. So we kind of just made this new layer, which
for now I'm calling the technique layer. And the
technique layer is this loop of decisions that occur in roughly
two second windows. And they have to do with assessing the
current board state, so not the whole map, but just this fight
in front of you.
and thinking about what abilities you have,
what abilities the enemies have,
and then executing your next move.
Somewhere in there, you're also thinking about
your cool downs and trying to figure out
whether or not your next available ability
is something that you can possibly combo
your current abilities with.
And this layer is sort of present in low time to kill shooters, although it's very underplayed,
and it's present in the form of grenades as a pre-engagement attack.
So in a low time to kill shooter, if I know that there's an enemy in the next room,
I could throw a grenade in there and increase my chances of winning that fight
by pushing the enemy out of position prematurely,
and then going in knowing that he would be out of position when I walk in.
Okay, so now that we've built our combat depth in multiplayer, we can fairly easily, or, you
know, we can apply this depth to single player. So, when we started working on Titan Combat in
single player, our first instinct was just to assume everything would work great. We spawn a
bunch of Titans, we, you know, lay out combat the way we normally do, no problem. However,
ran into the problem of combat fatigue where players would
often get pretty tired after a titan fight. So to solve that,
we experimented with what we called weak titans. And that's
a concept where presumably we would say that auto titans would
be easier to kill than say piloted titans. And you know,
when we implemented it,
At first it felt great. I go play a fight and I kill a bunch of weak titans and then
eventually once in a while I'll fight a non-weak titan. So people were reporting that they
were having fun.
But we let it sit for a couple months and after further
inspection we realized that being able to move through a
bunch of titans in a row, it really made titans feel weak.
Like they weren't special anymore and they're too
disposable. In addition we had all these cool behaviors from
multiplayer that weren't being showcased because the titans
would die so easily.
So we scrapped that idea and instead split the difference. We
increased the health back to the original values and then pushed
the differences in health. So that's our empty health and this
is what the health values look like in single player. So the
light chassis has around half the health of its multiplayer
counterpart and the medium chassis has around 80% health.
Now, a 50% light chassis health, it's still a decent amount,
so they can definitely still have some time
to use their abilities.
At 50% health, I believe fighting a Ronin on average
still takes the player around 15 or 12 seconds.
So this allowed, but, pah.
This also allowed designers to tune fights a little bit better.
So if you wanted an easier fight,
you would drop a couple of light titans,
like a Ronin or a North Star.
And we found that good fights usually
were comprised of maybe one heavy titan with a couple
of light titans backing him up.
But in general we still found that fights were pretty tiring.
So we needed to break up titan fights even further
with kind of infantry sections or reaper sections.
So if you don't know what a reaper is,
he's kind of like a half titan.
He's got like one chunk of this health
and he's half the height of a titan.
So he can die pretty quickly to a titan.
So these kind of infantry sections prove to be good not
just to break up the fights but to sell the scale of titans as
well. Because if I'm a titan and all I come across are big
titans, I don't really get the sense that I'm this giant robot.
I just, everything is my size so whatever.
So since we ended up with high-ish health titans, we
generally tried to have titans fights be like 1v1 or 1v2, 1v3.
And this allows players to focus on the enemy titans more,
since we also found that players had a lot more face time
with enemy titans than in low time to kill games. So this
increased face time means that we had all this time to play
with, so we used it to give enemy titans more personality.
it was a good opportunity to kind of build a relationship
between the player and the enemy he would be fighting. And to do
that we wrote a system called the VEU system that would detect
player actions and make enemy titans respond accordingly. The
idea was that when you were fighting an enemy titan, that
titan's pilot would have an open communications line with you and
he would taunt you and stuff. So it would do things like when the
player damages an enemy a certain amount he would respond
by saying, oh, how dare you.
or if the player used his core ability, the enemy would say something about that too.
Stronger than I thought, not by much though.
It's been fun, pilot.
Salvo core away.
So real quick.
Let's talk a little more about our Titan AI. Again, since players are now spending more time
with each enemy, they have a lot more time to notice AI behaviors. So it became worthwhile to
invest in a more robust AI system. In designing our AI Titans, we decided to go the route of
Street Fighter bot fights. So we like that when you fight against a bot in Street Fighter, all
normal thought processes that you would go through when fighting a player still applied.
More or less to fighting a bot. So our titan AI generally tries to act like a player and
they follow the same rules as a player. They'll only block or dash once you've fired and
having projectile weapons again here will help because they can take advantage of that
travel time to make that decision.
They also follow the same cool down rules for their abilities
so it's also possible to bait certain abilities out of an
enemy and then counter with your own attack. Nice thing is these
titans are used both in multiplayer and single player but
single player just adds a layer of characterization on top of
the multiplayer AI.
The last thing I want to talk about is our AI boss battles. In
Titanfall 2, spoilers, players will fight a number of boss
characters which are the different mercs that Blisk has
hired to help him. Due to time constraints, we didn't have
enough time to hand strip each boss battle like how we would
usually think of a traditional boss fight. Instead, we
Our bosses just use the same system as our other titans, but they're just more aggressive about using their abilities.
And what I mean by that is that our normal titans will usually wait a little bit after their ability is ready before they actually use it.
But our boss titans will try to use their abilities as soon as they're available.
But, we still wanted to make our boss battles feel more special, and there are a few things we did for that.
So one...
is all our bosses have these cool intro cutscenes
that showcase their personality,
and with the exception of a few special cases,
this is the only time we actually see
cutscenes in Titanfall 2.
Two, bosses have regenerating shields just like the player.
Not only does this make them harder to fight or deal damage
to, but it also enables them to act just a little bit smarter
than other titans, since they'll also
try to preserve their shield.
So a boss titan will try to retreat behind cover
to try to get his shield back.
Bosses also have doom state which is an extra layer of health that puts a titan in kind of an
executable state. And we removed this for our normal titans because again it extended their
health too much. But it seemed appropriate for bosses to have. The nice thing is this also
makes it so that bosses are the only ones, only titans that can get executed. And each boss
actually has a special execution animation tied to him.
Finally, boss titans have extra video call outs that they can
use and they have a special pool of just taunt dialogue that
they can say if they haven't said anything in a while. So
they'll call out, in addition they'll also call out if they're
being aggressive or defensive so they seem just a little bit
smarter. So let's see what that looks like. You were not invited
to Kane's party and that's why you're dead.
Well, well, another runaway hero with an SRS Vanguard class Titan.
Now we're talking!
Let's get this party started, Scrub.
Walk away, Scrub, just walk away.
Only a matter of time before I rip you out of that cockpit anyway.
Target hit, Fox 8.
Nice try, love, but I'm no pushover.
Die, Clannah-Mother!
Alright, I'm ready for more.
Goodbye, you little bastard.
Dodge this.
He's using the core. So predictable.
You should not have done that, pilot.
And it's got core break hard shit, too.
Destroyed by some pitiful excuse for a pilot.
No! No!
No!
Micro One lost control. I'm losing control. Going down. Mayday, Mayday. Going down.
End of break.
Overall, I think given the circumstances, it worked out pretty well. I think the fact that the
bosses actually use normal AI makes our boss fights feel kind of less scripted and more real
than the traditional ones.
I do think there's a lot of improvement though,
and I think there may be a middle ground
where we can have our boss titans use their AI,
but designers can script in special events
to sell the spectacle.
And you get a little bit of a glimpse of that
in the Viper fight in our game.
So the Viper fight is one that was more special scripted
because the designer for that really wanted to do it,
and he's the one that flies around
and does a special core ability
that doesn't appear in multiplayer.
So I think in the future,
I would try to push more in that direction.
Finally, let's talk about the unexpected problems that we ran
into during development and some of these problems we haven't
even really figured out the solution for but these are just
things to watch out for. The biggest pitfall in the direction
we took was that all these different loadouts really
increased the complexity of Titan combat.
By introducing the skill of ability combos
and enemy recognition, we created a potentially greater
skill gap between players that played the game a lot
and know all the characters and the players that don't.
And this can be partially solved by good matchmaking,
so we don't ever put two players of different skill levels
in a match together, but matchmaking can only really
go so far, so I think more work needs to get put into that.
Other league games such as league or street fighter, they
do a lot of work both inside and outside the game to give players
access to information about their characters. We did a
little bit of this with intro videos for the titans but I
think there's still a lot more we can do. Something like a
training room or a certification course would be ideal so that
players have a safe space to practice using their loadout.
Another thing that added to this was that when we started
working on titans...
we primarily focused on making sure players were having good 1v1 fights. And this was all well
and good, you know, we built kind of a 1v1 map and we would play test there and just have like
really fun 1v1 fights, or even 2v2 fights. So it was all well and good, but it became really
disastrous when we actually played a real match of attrition, a 6v6 match of attrition, since
players were having to deal with not just more titans, but the potential of pilots sneaking up
on them as well.
So this means that we actually had to tone down
some of the more obtrusive effects
that were again working in a 1v1 context,
but were pretty bad in kind of a 6v6 context
where anything could happen.
And a good example of that is North Star's plasma railgun
used to apply a really huge knockback effect
whenever you would get hit.
And this was great in 1v1 since it really helped him
force his opponent into his ideal range.
you can imagine when playing a 6v6 match you can get tagged by
a north star rail gun out of nowhere and all of a sudden
you're shifted like 36 units or 3,000 units to the left and you
don't really know why. So we had to take things like that out.
The other problem that presented itself, sorry.
The other problem this presented was that we also tuned health values to be, again, to be
interesting in a 1v1 context. Our intention was to make sure the titan fights had enough time to
feel like a real fight. Again, looking at street fighter fights as reference. In practice,
however, we found that whenever two titans would get into a fight in a real match, they would
effectively kind of end up going into their own little corner.
and play out their fight that took forever and they would effectively ignore the match.
And we had this one, I remember in particular this one event, there was this hard point
match and I was, I got in my titan and we were running around, I tried, and I found another
titan and we started to fight.
And it was, the match had already finished,
like the victory screen went up,
and we were still fighting,
and the evac happened, and everyone left,
and we were still fighting.
And like, we basically just ignored half that match.
And so that was, we determined that
that was not a good thing.
This problem of complexity is exacerbated by the fact that
you're in a titan for about only really 30 percent of the time in
titanfall. So this means that even if you wanted to practice
using a certain titan, you would have to play this pilot game for
a while and wait until the next one is available, which is not
really ideal. So right now if you really wanted to practice
using a titan, the best place to do it...
Let's do that again.
The best, so you really wanted to practice using a Titan,
the best place to do that is in Last Titan Standing,
which is a game mode that always starts you in a Titan.
But even that game mode, it's an elimination game mode,
so you gotta wait after you die
before you can do it again.
In single player, this is the main reason
why we switched to the on the fly loadout switching for BT.
Initially, players would pick up a new loadout from enemy titans, but we ran into the problem
that they might pick out a loadout that they didn't like, or they weren't good with, and
then they'd basically be stuck with that loadout.
And since it takes a long time to learn a loadout, it really disincentivizes players
to seek out new loadouts.
They would just stick with the ones they're comfortable with.
With the Mega Man style loadout system, players could kind of...
kind of try a loadout without the fear that they might not
like it, because then they can always switch back to
something they're comfortable with.
So at any point in time, they can just kind of dip their
toes in and then possibly be better.
Also in single player this pushed us to create a dynamic
hint system. So what our hint system does is it tries to
kind of detects what you're doing in a fight and kind of
takes a lot of data. It tries to figure out how long you've
been in a fight and if you're only using your primary weapon
in that fight it will signal you to use your other abilities.
Unfortunately the system isn't super duper smart yet so
sometimes when you're taking damage it will just tell you to
use electric smoke. Really the intention is it tells you to use
an electric smoke and then go to cover but people didn't really
know that all the time so there's a little bit more
improvement we can do for that in single player. Oh and also we
should port that to multiplayer.
Another specific thing to high time to kill is the problem that it's difficult to communicate to
players where they made a mistake. For low time to kill gameplay we have a feature called kill
replay which will show the players their final moments before they died. This 8 second window is
usually enough to be able to show players exactly how they died so they can do better next time.
But high time to kill fights could last for a minute and showing the final 10 seconds of
someone's life may not reveal anything valuable.
In addition, players will often eject out of their Titan instead of dying,
so they aren't even in a mindset to absorb that lesson,
since they're still busy trying to run around shooting other Titans.
So this one, we're still unsure of how to solve this,
and some ideas have been brought up, like showing a feed of major damage sources,
but I think more research needs to be put in regards to how we can present this information.
As I mentioned the single player, when we started designing combat encounters with these
titans, our first instinct was to lay out one fight after another similar to other shooters
we've worked on. But we found that even after just one fight, players got pretty tired since
titan fights are a lot more involved than pilot fights. So we had to make a conscious effort
to space out titan fights more and insert infantry combat in between just as a pilot
cleanser. The only exception
is levels like trial by fire and full weapon which is this. So
this is trial by fire. And in this level you're fighting a
bunch of titans in a row but we have additional mechanic. We
have friendlies in this level so they can help kind of take,
tank the damage from other titan enemies and they can also deal
damage to enemies so it helps you kind of just push through
that level.
And in this level, this is the last level, the Fold Weapon,
and in this one you also fight a bunch of Titans,
but in this level we have a mechanic with ship bombardment,
and that'll bombard all the enemy Titans
and basically turn them into weak Titans,
because now they're all damaged,
and you can go mow through
all those weak Titans pretty quickly.
This is generally less of a problem for a multiplayer since
there are less titans on the field overall due to the whole
pilot titan pilot thing. And in last titan standing we have
natural breaks that are the round transitions so those are
also good cool down moments. But I imagine if you were to make a
multiplayer game that's like high time to kill all the time,
team death match, you would probably run up against this
problem as well.
Finally, the last problem is more of a Titanfall
specific problem and it has to do with regen health.
So regen health is great because it makes type,
you know, it'll force players into this position
where they have to retreat, get behind cover,
stop, think about what their next thing is gonna be.
for Titanfall it was bad because we needed the Titans to cycle out. In Titanfall we were
dealing with this problem called Voltron. And Voltron happens when one team gets four or
five Titans together and they just
gang up on one titan and they obliterate all the other team's
titans. And now the other team has zero hope of winning the
match because every time they bring their titan in they just
get stomped. And in titanfall 1 this was a huge problem because
of regenerating shields it was very difficult for the enemy
team to even damage the titans. So removing any sort of health
regeneration kind of helped the other team kind of bring other
titans down.
But again, in single player, we kept regenerating health
because that wasn't really a concern.
So this is the end of the talk,
and then we'll just recap real quick.
So high time to kill negates depth at the atomic level.
So try to push designs that embrace high time to kill.
For us, fixed loadouts fit really well
with high time to kill.
They push enemy recognition and ability combos,
and that type of stuff fits really well
with kind of the increased face time.
Think about how to add more interesting decisions
within and outside that layer.
Again, for us, low frequency attacks and permanence
were a good first step, but there could be more out there.
Be ready to handle increased complexity
and watch out for combat fatigue.
Finally, I just want to point out
that when we started this project,
High Time to Kill was kind of seen
as a little bit of a problem child,
and there was definitely a lot of temptation
to lower Titan health values.
But I'm really glad that we really embraced
the High Time to Kill nature of Titans,
as it made us, it really pushed us
to create something that I feel is really unique.
in terms of shooters and it kind of opened up this new design
space for shooters where ability design can really flourish and
you can have more room to create more weird and kind of cool
abilities. And I'm pretty excited for what the future
holds for that.
So, that's the end of the talk.
I want to call out, just special shout out
to these people up here.
They, these people in particular,
a lot of their work is also represented in this talk.
So, Mac McCandlish, who's the lead designer.
Stephen DeRose, who is the other guy that worked on Titans.
He really helped push Titans to be, you know,
super polished and shippable.
And then, Ji Sang was the AI programmer
who worked on Titans as well.
And that's all. I don't know, we have like four minutes for questions. Also Respawn is hiring.
Hey, how's it going? I'm wondering if you experimented with damaged regions to offer more
choices at the atomic level. So like I shoot off a titan's arm and it can't use a gun, I shoot
off its chassis and it can't use its core. And if you did experiment with that, why did you not
take that? I don't know if we experimented. We didn't experiment with that in Titanfall 2. We
experimented with damaged regions dealing different amounts of damage but not like losing
your arm because then.
you basically would just be walking and then you couldn't play anymore.
You would lose a segment of gameplay that would normally be important to you.
With regards to different damage values,
something interesting that I didn't actually put in this talk was
in Titanfall 2 we reduced the amount of damage buffs that the crit point gave you
because we found that we were able to put depth in other places.
variance in the amount of damage you can deal was bad for the guy receiving damage. He also
needed to predict how much damage he was going to receive and he can't really control where the
guy is going to hit him. So reducing the amount of variance just kind of helped improve the
predictability of that. Thank you for the talk.
With the balancing of all these six abilities in Titan classes,
I was wondering if you experienced any particular challenging areas,
and if you have any comments on any stuff you've seen shake out from the players
life-testing it for you.
Sorry, would you mind being more specific?
I don't think I fully understand your question.
Okay, I was just curious how the...
what your experience was like balancing these six different
like Titan classes.
Oh, so the question that was about just in general
balancing kind of the six classes?
Yeah.
So I didn't, I wasn't actually the guy balancing it,
just, you know, to put that out there.
But overall when I think when we were making these
Titan abilities, it was kind of a weird,
it was, especially in its infancy,
it was difficult to figure out.
how many abilities a titan should have and which, there's one point in time where we
experimented with sharing, kind of maybe they should have one slot which had shared
abilities. But it turned out it was just much better if everyone had their own unique
thing. And then balancing them, you just play test and then if a specific thing was too
strong you would pull it back or if it was too weak you would.
Buffet, you know, it's all you're just getting feedback from different players and you know as if you've been in chin stock
Both the multiplayer team play tests every day and then every week we have Friday night fight
so we got a decent amount of feedback from
from our dev team. And then from the live game, we look at the
reddit, obviously that's kind of a slice of our community, trying
to figure out if any metas has emerged and then figuring out
what we want. We balance the live game as well. We'll change
some numbers depending on what players activities are.
Thanks for a great talk. I was wondering in single player if you had any tricks for scaling
difficulty without falling into some of those same traps of bullet sponges on one end or
titans not feeling special on the other end? Specifically, well, I think once you increase
the health, so basically what I found is you can
once you start increasing health to bullet sponge levels,
wait, is that your question?
Sorry.
Is your question, if I increase the health
to bullet sponge levels, what should I do,
or what can I do to not increase bullet sponge levels?
I was more curious if you had any more creative ideas
than just scaling the health, since you pointed out
that sort of leads to bullet sponges
or titans not feeling special at the other end.
Well, there's, what did we do?
We did.
kind of shield usage which is a little bit of help but also it's just a little bit of extra
help that they can regenerate so it also makes them feel smarter. You can play with how often
they dash or avoid damage or block. We had one version of Titan AI when they weren't really
tuned.
where they would use the vortex shield and they were so good at using the vortex shield,
they would vortex your bullets and it fired it back at you and then you would catch it
because you saw them use it. But then you fired it back at them and they would catch it right
away and then fire it back at you right away. So you could try to make them just be more
aggressive with how they use their abilities too. I guess things like that. Hopefully that
answers your question. Thank you.
There's a wrap up room over there if anyone wants to talk
some more. But I think people need this room. Thanks for
coming.