Hello everybody, my name is Nino Sapina.
I am a CEO and co-founder of Reelcast.
Our company develops immersive experience in extended reality using different kind of
technologies with virtual reality, mixed reality or method reality.
In the last four years, we have developed many different experiences for cultural locations
to present to the visitors of the Museum of Heritage Locations.
My company was created four years ago with my co-founder Diego Fernandez Bravo.
He's a technical director and I am a producer.
We worked together for more than 15 years in the video games industry.
Notably, we developed at Ubisoft very famous games like Just Dance and The Raving Rabbits.
So very mainstream games using motion gaming with the controllers, with the Kinect cameras.
So we were always interested to see how interactive innovation can bring new kind
of experience to the gamers or to the visitors. When we built this company, we wanted to see
how this new immersive technology works with the general public. The public who is not technical,
who doesn't know how headsets work, and who doesn't know even how the games work.
Because in museums obviously you have people from all the ages, all the technical and non-technical
knowledge. Some people are even don't like technical devices. So we wanted to test this
technology with this kind of project.
building right now. So I will show you the experience that calls Insurrection 1944
that speaks about the Second World War and the end of the war in Paris. Let me
present you the location. So this is a view of Museum of the Liberation of
Paris. It's built on the place D'enfer-Rochereau.
which is a famous place for people who already visited Paris.
They probably visited catacombs.
The catacombs are just across the boulevard, on the other side of the boulevard.
And the particular thing about this museum is that it's built upon a very historical location,
which is the underground shelter that was built between two wars
for the population of Paris in case of a chemical attack.
That never happened, but this place was built.
for that time and then the resistance during the Second World War have identified this place as an
ideal place to go there and to act, organize the resurrection and the resistance in Paris region.
On this slide you can see the stairs that are leading to this place,
which is quite deep underground, there are 200 steps.
It's a long descent to the location.
And in the second photo, you can see corridors.
There, they are completely empty,
which means that for the museum direction,
they really had a hard time to find a solution
how to present what happened in this location
without any physical artifacts or things to show inside.
They are small.
small armories, you can see some elements but very few because most of the things were taken away.
So all corridors are different, the same sorry, and the rooms as well. So the solution of
virtual and mixed reality was really ideal to populate this place, to give the life to this
place so the visitors can be like...
in the time of 1944 and to meet the resistance and the people who was working there for two weeks at the end of the war.
So I will show you the video without sound that I will comment that shows the museum and the experience itself.
Please note that the video cannot transcript the real immersive experience.
So you can only see these 2D images but.
The only and the best way to realize is to go there and to have experience. So I warmly invite
you to come to Paris when you can. This exhibit is permanent, so it will be there anytime and
so you can have a real experience. So this is the museum and the Don Perrot show place and we have
been using.
archive video that was filmed at the end of the war, where they filmed the resistance still
in this location. And this helped us to reconstruct the characters, the objects,
and the different activities that happened in this location. It was, for example,
Central, Telephone Central.
and of course different characters like this soldier who is your guide and Colin Rourke who
was the leader who was the chief of the resistance, a very famous historical character and thanks to
this experience you will be able to meet him. You can see here the picture, the photo of Colin Rourke
that was taken the same location as
As we were building the experience, we have recreated the colonel role in three dimensions
using the human actors. And we did the same scene, the phone scene, where he was phoning
to the network of resistance to find, to resolve some very urgent situation during
the liberation of Paris. The particularity of this place is that it's 100% humidity.
So very particular and difficult constraints for technical materials, so it means that we should
not leave any headsets or other devices in this place for a long time. Obviously the depth and
difficulty to access, there was no Wi-Fi at all, that was also the constraint from the museum,
so we had to build.
the system for HoloLens that uses spatial anchoring but only locally embarked in the headset
with no possibility to have a communication between the headset and remote
calculations for example that could help in a spatial anchoring.
And as I said, we had very few elements, mostly photos,
and this only movie that was captured at the end of the war.
So the choice of the technology of Collins
was really, I would say, the one or few that
fit the needs of the museum and their will
to show what happened in this place
without any physical objects.
So we won this, it was public appeal to win the project and then we it was a very big rush
because we had only seven months to build the whole experience which is quite short regarding
the all the creative elements that have to be built and also technical hurdles that should
be resolved in this short period of time. It's a little bit about the
about how it works. So here you can see the notebook of the visitor, because visitors play
the role of the journalist in the time of Second World War, and his role was to interview all the
resistance and to understand what is going on during the war and during their action,
and to make article for the press.
for the Parisian population to know how to insurrect and how to liberate from the occupants,
from the Nazis, before the Allied troops arrived, because Allied troops were arriving in two weeks
and the Resistance was there to make a communication between the
Resistance in Paris, in the Paris suburbs, and obviously with the Allied troops that were arriving.
So here you can see the initial works inside of the museum before the installation. Here's the
director of the museum showing us the plans. This is a big door, the entrance of this place,
and this is the famous indication where is the office of the Colonel Raul that dates from this
moment and that is part of all the elements of the storytelling.
The challenge was how to make a life in this place without any objects.
So, as I said, we built a whole set of characters and the objects and the storyline to lead
you through this space in a very natural way without need to any human assistance.
So it's visual, it's audio.
Audio is very important.
And we succeeded to build this experience to lead the visitors in a very simple manner,
but behind that was a very complex technical solution.
So this is the plan of the location. So you can see there are multiple corridors and multiple
rooms with different activities. So was like entrance. So entrance was the first
I would say contact with the mixed reality for the visitors.
So they just got the headset on the head and then they see the door that opens.
So they have to press the ring button with their finger because it works with the hand tracking.
And then the doors open and then they see the virtual character inviting them to the experience.
and then the character leads them to different rooms.
So one of the things that was very important is that
this place is quite, I would say, the corridors are not very large,
so we wanted that the visitors can go in different rooms,
but not all together at the same time.
So we built several paths through this location.
So every time when another visitor...
it would take another path and do the experience in different ways.
So that was the solution to use the place, the whole place, as much as possible
without having people walking in the same direction at the same time.
So the best comfort and the best quality of the experience.
We were using for this the mechanics of video games that we worked for many years.
which means that everything is interactive. Each room you can meet a character that speaks to you,
that asks you to do some very simple gesture. It's not a video game, it should be more accessible
because the experience is shorter than the game, but still it was very important for the immersive
part that visitor can do things in each of the room and feel like they were part of the story.
So for example here in the room of
Cartier Général in headquarters, they were like building a
barricade in a reduced model. In the phone central, they were
reading the articles to the operator. In the secretary room,
they were finding the movement of the troops to be shown on the
map that was on the wall. And in the colonel role room, they were
giving
a pen to the corral so he can show them what's going on there and after they were following the
soldier through the experience. So here you can see the, I would say without a wall,
the whole different characters and the settings. So it's in fact it's a quite huge scene
but obviously separated in smaller chunks of each experience.
So you can have seven characters that are in this experience that are getting activated
when you come close to them and they talk to you.
The character approach is very much related to the
I would say the movie storytelling because they're alive, they're looking at you at the eyes,
and they are really following what you are doing. And if you, for example, you get lost or you wait
in the corridor, but they will stop. They will wait for you. They will ask you, do you want to
continue? If you do something wrong, for example, you don't understand what you have to do, they
will try to help you. And then at some point, they will just lead you to the next step.
So it's really intelligent and adaptive interaction towards the visitors so they
they feel like they're really handled by the real humans even if it's only virtual characters.
Here you can see the excerpt of the movie and also the archives. So we use the scan
of the journals from the time and perform them in 3D models and then make them interactive so
visitors would choose the article that the secretary will read and then make an action
to show what's going on in the field and to show them where are the troops coming.
We built the scenario with the specialists and experts from the history that was
provided by the museum.
And so we did a lot of work for the research
to be really very accurate in terms of history
and to choose the most crucial part of the history
and in the same time to make a choice,
not to do too much because the experience is 25 minutes,
which is quite long for this kind of experience, but still.
At the end, time goes by very quickly, and it's important for the visitor to remember the key elements of the history.
And then after, he can go upstairs in the museum and go much more in-depth about each of the elements and find information about every moment of the liberation of Paris.
Here we can see the...
the equipment and the habits of the soldiers that we used to scan in three dimensions.
So our approach was really to use the actors, the real actors, that we did like a casting and we
choose the actors that were the closest to the looks of some historical character, for example
role.
And also we work with all the, I would say, creative crew from the movies, like costumes, like
mannequins, for the lookalike of the face to make them as real as possible before to do the scan.
This is the session of capture of photogrammetry.
So each actor went to this session and was captured multiple times to have the best quality model
of his body with the habits of the time. And so there was a scan of the body and there was
more detailed scan of the face. You can see our developer working on the integration of different
assets, 3D assets, animations.
elipsing dialogues into the same character that became alive.
And this is also very close to the video game industry where
you build the characters, they have a full set of motion, capacity to walk, to talk,
to interrupt their movements regarding what you are doing.
Here you will see the session of motion capture, which is also a way to, after the 3D scan,
we did motion capture to capture all the movement that have been decided to be used in this
experience.
And this is a soldier, Roch, he's opened the first door and inviting the visitors to come
and to enter the experience.
So we spent several days to capture all these movements.
You can see the sound studio with a recording of voices.
The funny thing is that the main character,
Colonel Rolk, who is obviously French,
and when we decided to make an English version
of the experience, we decided to keep him speaking English
with his very strong French accent.
And it was a really great choice.
And all the visitors from England for the United States,
they find that very normal and have no problem understanding
and make this experience even more,
I would say, immersive and lifelike.
The last image is about facial capture,
where we captured all the expressions of each.
actor and after recreated facial expression that was added to the model and then enable each actor
to talk different languages with very accurate lip syncs. So there are two languages available,
French and English. Here is the manual to use.
The important part of the experience is also to have a person who is taking care about
how the experience is managed outside of the experience.
Means receiving the visitors, explaining what they will do, not in terms of content,
but in terms of just handling and start and the end of the experience.
The idea is that the visitor doesn't have to touch headset at all.
Everything is installed by this mediator and he is taking the headset at the end of the experience
and the people should just forget about technology and go through the experience themselves
and they'll go completely immersed into the experience. So these are the indications.
So this is for HoloLens 1 because we started with HoloLens 1 in August 2019.
So the first version was HoloLens 1, so there was all instructions how to handle charging,
installation, and different adjustments for the mediators, not for the users.
We did a lot of play tests before deployment, which means that we passed at least one month's
testing with different personnel of the museum to find the best adjustments for the experience.
And then even after the deployment, we use one month more to see how the experience was working with the users.
And thanks to the mediator who was there watching the experience, get the feedbacks and improve the experience during the integration of this last month.
And that was very important.
The Microsoft was also a great partner because they were present.
They even sent some people from the Redmond R&D to help us with the spatial anchoring,
which was a very big challenge for this project.
We didn't have any loss of material, any breaks.
So this is really thanks to this system of a mediator who is taking care,
completely care about the headsets and not leaving the user to manipulate.
because it's not needed.
And as you will see at the end,
the returns of the public are really very, very positive.
And that was really a big plus for this kind of experience
where normally one part of the visitors are reluctant
to this kind of technical solution.
So this is a Hollens 2 and six months after the installation of the experience,
we were one of the first companies and teams to deploy a Hollens 2 experience.
This museum was also the first client to have the Hollens 2.
So it was a very big project and exciting for us to get hands on this new device.
Since then, we have more than 10,000 visitors.
Even though COVID removed a big part, still this experience is permanent and it's bringing the visitors every day.
Obviously, this kind of experience brings young audience to the museums, which is the purpose.
But it works very well with also people for any age.
And this was also a big discovery for us to see that even the people for plus 60 to 70
can do the experience and appreciate the new technologies and to see and participate in this
kind of experience. So the team was really very much involved and did huge efforts to make this
happen.
And fortunately we get a lot of feedback from the press, from the media after the release.
So we had a huge coverage coming even from the United States.
We collaborated with Microsoft, and they've sent some journalists, some influencers to make
different articles. It was really this experience still today, it's a reference, I would say,
in use of mixed reality in cultural locations. Finally, we won two awards,
SATIS 360. It was an award given by the movie makers.
famous movie makers, like the movie maker from Taxi, which was a very famous movie in France,
because they discovered this kind of storytelling that they didn't know.
And we also won the ORIA award in Germany, which is a very famous award since two years now,
and we was like a winner in 2020. In fact, the award is 2019, but it happened in January 2020.
And obviously, we are very happy to participate to GDC with one year of delay, but still,
we believe that's a great opportunity to share this experience with you.
So, a little bit more about visitors' feedbacks. So, as we said, the museum and us, we really
taking account, we try to take into account a lot about the opinions of the visitors,
especially the first visitors, and to see how they are using the experience,
what are the hurdles, maybe obstacles, what makes them, what makes the experience maybe
people who don't want to finish or who don't like the technical solution.
But frankly, we were very surprised, but very, very positive feedback.
from all over the museum.
So I can show you some sentences.
There is like a book of remarks from the visitors
and the museum, Paris Museum,
who is handling 40 museums in Paris.
So they have really a lot of different museums
and have different kind of digital solution
for these museums.
They say that this is the first one
There's such a big positive feedback from the audience.
It's almost unanimous.
So people are really very, very happy and very impressed
about what's possible with this kind of experience.
So we...
Yeah, we are happy to and we believe that there is a big future for this kind of experience
in a different location. We also now, especially with the COVID, are also proposing
to the location to build in-situ experience but also virtual experience that use the same assets
so that can enable people who are at distance to participate to this experience together.
So I let you leave these words and then I will finish my presentation on this slide.
And please feel free to ask any question you have after the session. Thank you.