Thank you all for coming.
There's a lot of people in here and I'm really nervous.
So thank you.
All right, so I've been at Riot Games for several years now.
And we are the makers of League of Legends,
a free-to-play multiplayer online battle arena that's
not working.
No.
Sorry.
Here we go.
One second.
There we go.
All right.
We are a no, free to play multiplayer battle,
online battle arena.
And I can remember about five years ago
when Brian Thompson first joined the team as an intern.
We put him on.
Gatekeeper Galio.
And when we saw his work on Gatekeeper Galio,
this shit fucking blew our minds.
This was really good.
And it was better than anything that any of us
had produced up until then.
He was using colors in a way that was much more interesting
than we had ever done before.
His shapes were more stylized and graphic.
There's actually some semblance of visual hierarchy
where none existed before.
And it was communicating gameplay really well
without detracting from the aesthetics.
It was amazing work and we all reacted really poorly to it.
We were all mid to senior level artists at the time.
And up until then, we were all thinking,
you know, we're doing pretty awesomely.
And here comes Brian, this intern,
who like blows our shit out of the water,
raises the bar completely,
and also has no ego about it,
doesn't even realize how amazing he is.
So, you know, we all started to feel kind of jealous of him,
and it made us question our own capabilities as artists.
We're like, fuck, what are we even doing here?
And so rather than recognize that we had this gold mine to learn off of who could teach us and you know
Help us get better in our skills
instead we distanced ourselves and
We put up these walls. We were trying to you know a mask how fragile our little egos were and
We kept ourselves. We kept trying to find ways to one-up each other
This was the landscape of the team, not because Brian came in.
Because Brian came in and was awesome,
it just exacerbated what was already there.
So we were trying to find ways to differentiate ourselves from each other,
prove to one another that we're better than everybody else,
and I was definitely guilty of this.
We had a small little side project spinning up,
and it was staffed with a superstar animator
and a superstar producer,
both of which were really well known in the studio.
And they needed some VFX help,
and they reached out to me only
because they happened to know somebody on the team.
And so I snatched that opportunity for myself immediately
without doing the right thing,
which would have been to understand the needs of the project.
and take it back to the team and figure out
who would be the right resource for that project
because it probably would have been Brian.
You saw how amazing his work was in the last slide.
And it also would have been a really good opportunity
for him as a junior artist by then
to completely own his own project.
A great opportunity for him to learn,
but I took it away from him
because I wasn't thinking about any of that.
I was just thinking about how...
this project was going to make me feel more special and above everybody else.
And that is how I felt.
And it, you know, continued to exacerbate that competitiveness
and underlying animosity on the team.
Another thing that we were really good at
was we would blame failures on individuals
rather than look at failures like they're team failures.
So when we were working on Lucian,
which by the way, it shipped like three years ago,
so this toxicity on the team persisted for two years,
maybe more than that.
When we were working on Lucian,
we would have our regular feedback sessions,
but we had a very weak feedback culture.
So people weren't asking for specific feedback,
and we didn't take the time
to give actionable, quality feedback to others.
And on top of which, the artist who was working on Lucian
just had sort of like a standoffish vibe to him,
so we didn't try to break through it.
And he didn't ask for feedback, we didn't give it to him.
Eventually he ships Lucian, more eyes get on it,
and we realize that it's not hitting the quality bar.
And instead of saying, like, this was a team failure,
you know, we all had eyes on it,
but we didn't do anything to help him,
give him the feedback, help him grow.
Instead, we pointed the finger and said,
you know, that's the artist that worked on Lucian,
it's his fault, not ours.
So this is only three stories, but we do have two years worth
of stories that are all of the same vein.
And we had become one of the most unhealthy and least liked
teams in the entire studio.
And working from the inside, you know, that toxicity and unhealthiness,
it was really difficult to work in every day.
It was starting to get really hard to be a part of it.
So something needed to change.
And, you know, frankly, I think each one of us had gotten to a point where we were
ready for a change.
But even though we were ready for a change,
that change was still going to take a lot of time
and hard work.
So at this time, the tension on the team was really high.
Toxicity and that inability to work well with each other
was at its peak.
And that's when Chris joins our team.
And coming from an outside perspective,
Chris can immediately see just how toxic the team is.
But rather than first take time to build relationships with us so we could get to know him, understand where he's coming from,
he immediately, you know, starts pulling us each aside and says,
this is the thing you're fucking up on, this is the thing that you suck at, this is what you need to change.
And we didn't know who he was,
we didn't understand what his intentions were,
so it really rubbed us all the wrong way.
We were thinking, who the fuck is this guy?
So he immediately lost trust and rapport with each one of us.
So feeling at a loss, he turned to a mentor,
and this mentor recommended something called Campfire.
Campfire is something where everybody kind of sits around,
there's no real agenda for the meeting,
and the purpose is to just talk.
The goal being that by talking,
you start to get to know each other,
eventually build relationships,
maybe you start to actually trust each other enough
to air out your differences,
actually talk through your grievances
and get out the other side better for it.
But the caveat being don't you dare try to attempt to do campfire
Unless you are ready to take in all the shit that someone might have to say about you and possibly die in that fire if necessary
So Chris recommended that we do Campfire,
and we all begrudgingly did it.
And the reason why we were so reluctant
was because even though deep down we were ready for a change,
you know, when we looked at everybody else in the room,
our perceptions of everybody was,
you know, they're kind of egotistical,
they're difficult to work with, I don't really like them.
So the last thing, you know, I wanted to do
was sit in a room for an hour with these people.
But, you know, it's kind of the only option on the table,
so we did it.
And that first meeting came along, an hour passed,
nothing happened, sat in silence, super awkward.
So the next week happened and we tried it again.
So another hour passes, sat in silence,
nothing happened, super awkward.
And then the next week comes
and finally somebody breaks ground.
And this person said,
I don't think that anybody in this room respects me.
which is a really hard thing to say
to a room full of people who you don't think respect you.
So that moment of vulnerability really snapped us out of it
and we immediately started jumping in to explain to him
how wrong he was and that we really did respect him.
But somebody else said,
you know, the reason why I don't talk to you
is because your work is so intimidating,
you make me feel like a shitty artist
and so I just avoid you altogether.
And one by one, we each just started to word vomit on each other and reveal how we really felt.
And it turns out that what we thought was a problem, you know, we originally thought that everybody was egotistical,
they're kind of full of themselves, they're not very nice people.
It turns out that that wasn't the problem at all.
The real problem was that we were each dealing with so much insecurities,
and we didn't have the tools to understand how to navigate through those insecurities.
So the way in which we each reacted was by throwing up walls,
putting up this false sense of ego so that we can pretend like we have confidence
when we're really just masking how frail we are inside.
and to also try to feel like a peer amongst all these other artists who we massively respected.
And so it turns out that we were all dealing with a bunch of insecurities.
We were coming from the same place.
And so when we were finally able to find some common ground,
we could finally take a step forward.
which was a huge deal for us because we had never,
ever been able to find common ground before.
And who knew that we all suffered from the same problems.
And so, you know, at this point,
we're starting to build relationships with each other.
Those relationships turn into trust.
And eventually, we're actually feeling open
to be vulnerable and share our weaknesses
in craft with each other.
Something that could have never happened
in the past old culture.
And at this point in our history,
we're also trying to shift the style.
So where we were using photorealistic textures,
we're moving into hand-painted textures,
where we were, you know, our effects had a lot of high detail,
we're moving into large graphic shapes.
And also emphasizing the importance of a visual hierarchy
where before our effects, you know,
the elements in our effects would be fighting against itself.
So for one of our artists, Troy, who was an original artist on the team,
and he originated the old style, we were essentially asking him to take everything
that he's ever known, everything that he's ever done, and just throw it out the window,
and try to do something that's completely out of his depth, that's just so foreign to him,
which is a very scary proposition for any of us.
And we actually did ask him to do this back in the old culture back when it was still toxic and you know a scary
environment where we could you know be vulnerable and
When we asked him then he completely rejected the idea and he was really defensive about his work
But now that we had started to build relationships and trust
and it was OK to be vulnerable, this time when we asked him,
he came to the table.
And he was really honest with how he felt and said,
I don't know if I'm ever going to be
able to hit this new style because this is something
that I've never done before.
And it freaks me out.
I don't know if I can get there, but I'll do everything
that I can to try.
Which was such an awesome change of attitude.
It was really humbling and it inspired us.
So the rest of us rallied around him
and we supported him as best as we could.
And that support was really motivating to him.
And Troy took the initiative and reached out to Brian
and Jin, who I'll talk about later,
both who were junior artists at the time.
him being a senior, he didn't care,
he was just really excited to learn off of them.
And they were really honored to be able
to teach him their skills.
And soon enough.
Much to especially Troy's surprise.
You know, Troy didn't know if he was ever going
to move away from this style.
To him, this was what he had been doing forever.
He felt like he was an old dog with old tricks.
He didn't know if he could do anything more than this.
But incrementally, he was able to slowly move
closer to the new style.
And the thing that freaked Troy out the most
was whether he would be able to hand paint his textures.
And he wasn't sure if he'd be able to do it,
and he didn't want to feel stupid,
you know, making a texture and if it failed.
But now in this new culture
where we were becoming more supportive
and we were okay with failures,
you know, Troy felt comfortable
to try hand painting textures,
and then, you know, fail at it,
and then learn from those failures and try again.
Again, something that could have never happened
in the old style, or in the old culture.
So at this point, learning becomes a really big part of our culture.
We care a lot about learning.
Learning from anybody.
It doesn't matter if you're learning from an intern or a junior.
Everybody has something that they can teach someone else.
That's really the thing that we started to focus on.
And so at this point.
Jin joins the team as a junior artist.
And pretty immediately, we throw him out into the deep
end and have him working on new champions.
And for those of you unfamiliar, we frequently
patch new content to the game.
And sometimes that new content is a new champion, which is
unique to the game.
And so the artist who works on that new champion is
responsible for creating a whole new suite of effects
that's completely unique to that champion to the game.
And some would argue, and some did argue,
that that kind of work requires a level of autonomy
and creativity that should only be reserved
for a senior artist, and that a junior like Jin
should work in that senior's shadow
so that they can learn incrementally and slowly.
But that's something that I call bullshit on
because I truly believe in trial by fire.
that everybody deserves the chance to own something really huge and demonstrate to the
rest of us that they actually do have the capabilities to get there.
And of course we would support him along the way, we wouldn't just throw him in the deep
end without a life preserver or some swimming lessons, but the point is giving him the opportunity
to really own it and demonstrate that he can get there.
So we stocked up our guns and we kept them there.
And Jin worked on Atrox.
This was his first champion ever.
This was probably the worst new champion any junior artist
could work on because Atrox is a darkened character.
And up until this moment, there was no such thing in our
universe that is darkened.
In fact, I don't think there is darkened that exists
outside of Atrox.
And you know, had we started Jhin on an Ionian champion,
Jhin could have at least looked at the other Ionian champions,
pulled references and used those as resources.
But for Aatrox, all he knew was
it can't look like anything else in the game.
Which is a pretty broad spectrum.
And...
In my opinion, I think that he really knocked it out of the park.
I know Jin's sitting right there, he's cringing at this slide and he probably
is really mad that I keep staying on this.
But to me, a junior artist, you know, working on such an ambiguous problem,
I think he did a really great job. He was really bold with his color, his use of color.
You know, he was creative with his meshes. The gameplay reads really well.
And so we were impressed with Jin's work,
and we kept him on New Champions,
and we kept challenging him with big challenges.
So, you know, as time progresses,
champions become more challenging,
the gameplay becomes more complicated and sophisticated.
And Jin continues to step up to the plate.
Because Jin is who he is, he continues to try and challenge
himself to do better than his previous champions.
So his use of color becomes more deep, more interesting.
His meshes also become more creative, more interesting.
He's constantly leveling himself up one
champion at a time.
And in just one year, Jin went from a junior to a senior.
And now as our principal artist on League,
Jin uses the same method of mentorship
in which he challenges others
with seemingly larger than life challenges.
He trusts in their capabilities
more so than they trust in themselves.
He supports their development along the way,
but he really allows them to own the big challenge
so that they can own the big win.
And in fact, Jin believes in this way of mentorship so much so that he takes it to the next level.
Because Jin truly believes that every single person, no matter what level you're at, intern,
junior, doesn't matter, that everybody possesses some strength that's unique to them that they
can teach to others.
And so Jin doesn't even call it mentorship, he calls it a knowledge swap.
And whoever he does mentor is challenged with having to teach him back something else.
Not to be facetious, but because he truly believes that they can make him better.
And so now, at this point, our culture has totally shifted.
We're all about learning and learning through feedback.
You know, we continue to cultivate our relationships.
We continue to value vulnerability.
And so now these parts of our culture are starting to creep into everything else that
we do.
So when Jason applies for Riot,
Jason applied for a motion graphics position
because he was a 2D flash animator at the time.
And even though he wasn't right for that role,
the motion graphics lead came and showed me
Jason's application because we were just nerding out
on his flash work, it was really awesome.
So I decided to give Jason a call.
He hadn't applied for the real-time VFX position,
but honestly, I just wanted to meet another artist
and tell him that I really admired his work.
So I gave him a call,
and that conversation was really awesome.
He asked me lots of great questions.
We ended up talking about real-time VFX,
and he was intrigued by it,
and it was something that he wanted to try
and challenge himself and learn more.
But he was really honest about his capabilities as an artist
and also honest about his reservations of, you know,
sinking time into something that seems pretty
out of his league, at least at the time.
And his honesty, his vulnerability,
also his commitment to challenging himself
really resonated with me.
So I also wanted to give him a shot.
So we left that conversation with an understanding
that Jason was going to teach himself real-time VFX,
and I gave him our test so that he would have something
to shoot towards.
And throughout this time, we were corresponding.
He would ask me some questions.
I would send him any tutorials that I could find.
And eventually, he sends in his first test, the first
iteration of the test, in 3D, along with the 2D flash
animated version, so that I could see what
he was trying to do.
Now clearly the 3D version still needs a lot of work.
You know, the timing's kind of linear.
The colors are all the same.
The shapes are very obvious.
But I was really impressed that he even got this far.
He taught himself to do this in a short amount of time.
And I was also impressed with his vulnerability
with even being able to show me this.
Because the 2D version is so fucking awesome.
And then he was, so I know he has taste as an artist.
And he was willing to show me this other version,
which clearly isn't quite the same.
So all of those things, again, his vulnerability,
his commitment to his own growth and development,
his openness to feedback, all of these things
really resonated with the whole team.
And so we gave him feedback, told him what was
and wasn't working, how he might be able
to technically achieve in 3D what he was doing in 2D,
and he went back at it.
And the next iteration was much better, and each iteration just kept on getting better.
So we learned enough about Jason to really understand who he is, his motivations, and
most importantly, his potential, and that he would be worth bringing in to teach from
the ground up.
But that decision was met with opposition
because the question was, why would we bring someone in
and sink time and resources into
when we could use that amount of time
to go and find some other artist like a senior artist
and that person can come in and hit the ground running?
But based on our history, we knew that craft wasn't the most
important thing to us.
We knew how difficult it was for us to cultivate this
culture of being open to feedback, vulnerability,
commitment to your own growth and development.
And we saw all of those things in Jason immediately,
something that was really hard for us
to cultivate on the team.
And so because of the testing process and we learned all of
these things about Jason, it was very easy to dig our heels
in and fight for him.
And some of you may know that we ended up hiring Jason.
And in just three years, he went from an artist
who knew nearly nothing about real-time VFX
into one who actively mentors nearly every VFX artist
in the studio, and also mentors students
and artists in the industry.
And had we been in our old culture,
we would have never hired Jason.
We would have looked at, you know,
that first version of the test,
and we would have thought, not good enough, fuck him.
And in fact, when I think about that,
I think about all the other amazing artists
with massive potential that we passed up on
because back then we weren't in a place
where we realized that attributes,
other things that artists bring to the table
are just important as craft.
And so I can really attribute the growth and evolution
of the style and our work to the growth
and evolution of our culture.
In fact, at this point when we were working on A-RAM,
that was the first real inflection point
in the change of our style.
And that's actually when we had started doing campfires.
And from there, we were building trust, relationships,
building a supportive learning environment.
And from then on, we've been able to grow and level up
our work and our style ever since.
And so now this is the new status quo
of the culture of the team.
This is who we are.
We very much value relationships, trust,
vulnerability, and learning.
In fact, learning is such a big part of our culture
now that it's a responsibility.
It's like an expectation of your job.
So artists like Chris, Jin, Jason, Brian,
they are all expected to give back and teach what they know.
all while continuing to cultivate this environment of support,
that it's safe to be vulnerable about your weaknesses.
And I know that I'm painting a really rosy picture of how everything is so awesome,
but it wasn't an easy one, two, three step for us.
It was a long, arduous, and emotional journey,
and one that we continue to work at every day.
In fact, three years later, we still do campfires.
It's something that we've been doing every week since.
Because we know what a pivotal moment this was for us
and how important it is for us to continue to cultivate
relationships and trust and vulnerability with each other.
And now that actually our team is scaled,
and it's a pretty large team, so we're
sprinkled across the entire studio.
We don't sit next to each other anymore.
We sit next to, we are separated by buildings.
And then because of the projects we work on,
There are barriers between some of us, between projects as well.
In this new landscape, it is even more critically important to continue to bring the artists
back in and continue to cultivate our culture through relationships and trust building.
And we are now using campfires to share knowledge,
teach each other.
At times we share our challenges with each other,
and even if nobody else in the room
is experiencing the same challenge,
we get together as a group,
we help that artist brainstorm,
and we help them find a solution to their challenge.
And by doing so, we are able to demonstrate
just how important relationships, trust,
vulnerability learning is to the health
and culture of the team.
And so, even though this is something that we work at every day,
that in a nutshell is how we were able to turn our toxic team environment
into what it is today.
Thank you.
Thanks, guys.
I know that I had a lot of time and I sort of blew through it.
Or there's still a lot of time left.
So if anybody has questions, that'd be awesome.
If nobody has questions, that's also awesome.
Super happy to get off the stage as well.
Yes, hi.
Sorry, I'm gonna keep you there.
So you mentioned that the team has now grown
and it's spread out,
and I'm assuming there are new people coming on.
You know, you kind of ramp up.
How do you deal with new people coming into this culture
of say, dealing with campfires
or getting comfortable with that?
And have you had people that are resistant to it?
And how would you deal with that?
Yeah, so because we have such a long history of sort of building this really fortified
membrane of our culture, we very much know what we're looking for in artists.
And we have a pretty rigorous hiring process.
And so those attributes are actually attributes that we look for when we're hiring.
In fact, we have panels specifically targeting those attributes.
And so, first off, coming into the door,
we already know that they should feel more open
to wanting to build relationships.
And then secondly, because when people are new,
the first thing that they wanna do is make relationships
and friends in their new office.
And so we're very on top of, you know,
making sure whenever new artists come in,
we grab them and put them into campfire.
And our campfires are once, are every Monday.
And so that's kind of where we start to, you know,
they get to at least meet other people in the studio.
And so far we really haven't had a problem
getting people into the culture
because we have a really rigorous hiring process.
And then we, you know, make sure to grab them
and start to get them into the culture immediately.
So.
Thank you.
Yeah, sure.
Hi.
Hi there.
Thanks for the great presentation, love it.
My question would be, how were you able
or have the other art departments sort of liaison with you
to try to spread this sort of, you know,
great group cohesion and exercises
to their other art departments?
Yeah, we have actually.
So the tech art group within Riot
also was suffering sort of through the same things
as we were.
They were sort of a disjointed group
because tech artists,
they all have really different kinds of skills.
And so it was difficult for them
to sort of find that common ground.
And we did the same thing.
We recommended that they do campfire
and we also offered to facilitate for them.
But actually, campfire, those kinds of meetings
are most powerful when it's only the people
in the room who matter.
Like, having a facilitator just sort of makes it feel
like you've got a therapist in the room.
And so, yeah, they started doing campfires as well.
And they've actually also been able
to turn over their culture.
So it's a pretty powerful tool, guys.
Would really recommend that you try it.
So yes, we have shared, and we've really shared this
with anybody who wants to know about it.
Okay, awesome, thanks.
Yeah.
Hi, that was a really cool talk, Ansela.
Thank you.
My question is, having hired people
that haven't come from a background
doing real-time VFX, just the process of optimization,
to be able to get that stuff running properly,
how hard is it to teach that kind of thing
to someone that comes from a completely different background?
You mean like teaching them the technical skills,
like knowing when to optimize and how to optimize?
Yeah, exactly.
That kind of stuff?
I think if you guys were here earlier for Keith's talk,
Keith and Drew, there's always going to be
some kind of ramp up.
You know, like every studio uses different tools.
Every studio has different parameters
for optimization as well.
So there is kind of this like two month ramp up time
for everybody.
But as long as a person is open to learning
and they understand that it's going to be different
at every studio, they do understand
that it's important to optimize,
we found that it's not difficult
to actually teach those things.
They're just like technical tools.
But as long as you have the frame of mind
of you know that you need to optimize your work,
then how you do it isn't so hard to teach,
if that makes sense.
Cool, thank you.
Thank you.
Hi, so you were talking about there are certain attributes that you look for during your hiring
process and there are certain attributes that you saw in Jason that made him appealing to
be hired for that kind of thing.
I guess with that understanding, are there...
Are there tangible or certain things that you do
to try to look for those attributes, if that makes sense?
Or is it just kind of like a gut feeling,
like, oh, this feels right as far as,
basically, how do you get those attributes
to be something tangible that you can kind of communicate
to other people and be like, this person's a good fit
because of this, this, and this?
Yeah, I would say that it's really,
it takes time to learn how to dig into attributes,
especially when you're interviewing somebody
for like an hour.
You know, somebody can put their best foot forward
for an hour or even for like a whole day of interviews.
It's pretty easy to mask who you really are.
And so for the testing process, I really recommend finding a way to define your attributes that
you're looking for and find a way to test for that.
So for us, the way that we're able to dig into that is by doing rounds of feedback.
Because through those rounds, you understand, can this person take feedback?
Do they have an ego about their work?
Do they know how to apply feedback?
Can they ask questions back to me?
Can they even challenge me on my feedback?
Which is like that part if a person isn't challenges
It's not like a test
But my point being by being able to find a way to just spend a little bit more time with that person to understand
Who they really are I think that is the most powerful way for us to try and dig into attributes rather than just
Trying to interview somebody for an hour
Okay, great. Thank you. Yeah, you're welcome
I'm just wondering the hierarchy in your office like the way that the structure is at riot. Did they allow
For this kind of thing to happen or did you guys kind of have to fight to make this happen?
Like there's I worked in the game industry and there's just there's with the way we had it set up
It was like this would be very hard to do although totally needed
but be very hard to do because the the eye of Sauron's always
Yeah, I can definitely relate to that,
because I've worked at other studios as well.
We are very lucky at Riot in that
we're pretty empowered to do as we want to with our time.
Because we have a rigorous hiring process,
we trust everybody that comes into the door.
It's like, we know that you are the kind of person
that we can empower with however it is
that you want to spend your time,
because we know that you'll get to the end point,
however it is that you get there.
So we're really lucky that we can work in this way.
And so, that's how we've been able to do
a lot of experimentation, I guess.
have meetings where they're not about craft,
spend the time to actually mentor each other.
We have wheelie desks, so we kind of like wheel
to each other's workstations.
You know, if somebody needs to level up,
we'll have a mentor sit next to a mentee.
So we're really lucky in that way.
But I think, you know, for those studios where, you know, there is an eye of Sauron, I think
that, you know, if there's a need on your team and if there's enough, you know, like
where we were, we were kind of ready for a change.
So if you can't do it within work, you know, there's opportunities where you can go out
for lunch and try to talk, maybe go out for beers and try to talk, but limit the amount
of alcohol because it might get a little too hairy.
But there are creative ways that you can try to work around it,
if it is something that you really need to work on.
But I do understand. So we are pretty lucky at Riot.
Thanks. Anybody? No?
Cool. Well, thank you very much for coming.