All right, hi, everybody.
My name is Bennett Foddy.
I'm a philosopher at Oxford University,
and I also make games at Foddy.net and on iOS.
And I'm going to be talking a little bit
about the relationship between games and real sports.
Video games are played in a simulated world
with arbitrary rules for imaginary points.
Players aren't harmed when they die.
And for the most part, they don't have any money on the line.
So I think the most fundamental of all design challenges
is to make the events in the video game world matter to the player.
In particular, the player needs to care about how they play the game.
If there's no need to play the game well,
the player's actions become lazy and then routine.
And at some point, the only thing that's keeping them playing
is a story that they're passively consuming,
or the art, or the Xbox achievement points.
A game where player performance doesn't matter
might still be enjoyable,
but it's ultimately disposable.
You know, it's a simulation of a simulation.
It's like a movie where you have to wiggle a thumbstick
in order to keep the projector running.
This is what players do to get the frequent flyer achievement
in Superman Returns.
They're so disengaged that they're not even looking at the screen,
not even touching the controller anymore.
I think as designers, if we can get players to care about the outcome of our games,
they'll be more engaged, more focused, and the games will ultimately be more meaningful to them.
But it's a pretty hard problem, since the events in a video game are ultimately,
they don't matter at all in any kind of practical sense.
So what I want to talk about is how this problem is addressed
in the world of real non-digital sports.
Now real world competitive sports, you have to say, I mean, first of all, they're not
designed usually in the same way that video games are.
They evolve as a set of shared social or cultural practices.
So American football, we think, evolved from the ancient Greek game Episkeros, which is
pictured here, which in turn surely evolved from an even more ancient game, probably involving
throwing rocks at other people in order to hurt them.
But if you were designing a new sport, like when Frisbee golf was designed,
you'd face the same basic design challenges that we face when we make video games.
Like games, sports are basically enjoyable or fun activities,
but the outcomes in any sporting activity are fundamentally pretty pointless and arbitrary.
You might play a sport for enjoyment,
but there's no inherent reason why you should care about who wins, who loses,
and how people played the game.
Despite that, sports have been far more successful at video games at making their performances
and their results matter, both to the players and the spectators.
Football and basketball stadiums routinely filled to capacity.
More than a billion people watch the Olympics every four years.
Athletes are prepared to sacrifice everything to attain the highest possible performance.
They train day in, day out, suffering painful and even disfiguring stress injuries.
They collapse at the finish line, crying or fainted.
They take life-threatening doses of performance-enhancing drugs,
even in sports where the financial rewards are tiny, like in the Olympic racewalk.
Think of Liu Xiang and his crippled hop to the finish line in last year's Olympic hurdles.
Now that kind of commitment would be ridiculous in a video game player,
even though video games basically are no more silly, no more pointless than real sports.
Of course, part of the reason why athletes care so much about their sports is that there's a huge amount of money and fame on the line, you know.
And part of it is that sports, of course, are just older than video games.
I guess if we play Street Fighter continuously for over a hundred years,
and give people a million dollars when they win at Evo, people probably care about it a lot more. That's true.
But those can't be the only reasons why people care more about sports.
You know, basketball was shown at the Olympics just 13 years after it was invented.
The Street Fighter, for comparison, is now 20 years old.
Even in sports with relatively small audiences and no prize money, like Little League Baseball,
people care much more about the outcome than they do in the case of video games.
You almost never hear of people taking a game as seriously as this,
even though sports are fundamentally just as inessential and arbitrary as video games.
No competitive video game fills a big stadium or is televised on a major network.
There's no bans of violent Starcraft hooligans, no Halo player trading cards.
There's no back page column in the local paper.
This is how Evo looks, the biggest tournament for Street Fighter.
Note that pretty much everyone in the audience here is also a competitor and not just a fan.
And that's how the Super Bowl looks.
So clearly, real world sports are doing something right
that video games aren't managing to do.
And I think as designers, we can take a lot of inspiration
from what sports are doing.
So that's what this talk's about.
I'm going to talk about a few of the things that we can do.
I should acknowledge up front that we already have things that we call eSports, I think,
legitimately.
I take it that a genuine eSport really only differs from a non-digital sport in that it
involves a computer.
It has a lot going right for it.
So what makes sports, or eSports, different from games?
I think that part of the answer is that all sports, including eSports, are heavily steeped
in performance.
Two senses of the word.
In sports, there's a big difference between knowing what to do and being able to do it.
You have to perform your moves in a way that's not trivial to do.
It's not easy to reproduce the same movements twice in a row.
And that's one of the things that makes Street Fighter a viable sport,
while a game like chess isn't.
You know, performance in the sense of high performance, or performance enhancement.
But the second dimension of performance is that sports, unlike many games, are performative.
Your actions within a sport convey meaning to the audience.
Sometimes they convey some of your character, your personality, or your feelings to the
people who are watching you.
And the presence of the audience, in turn, imparts meaning on your sporting performance
and it makes it matter more, both to you and to the audience.
Here's a simple way of looking at it.
Usain Bolt probably broke the world record for the 100 meter sprint dozens of times in
training, even in competition against his friends and his teammates on the Jamaican
track team.
But it doesn't count, and it doesn't matter, and in some sense it's not even really a sport
until the grandstand is full.
That's when it goes from being training to being a sport.
When you play FIFA over an internet connection with nobody watching except you and your opponent,
it's nothing like a sport. So it's not as though only sports-themed games automatically
get to be eSports. You have to directly support it in your design. Here's one that does. I
think Counter-Strike is more like a sport because even though you play it alone in your
bedroom over the internet, it's set up so that the people who lose when you die
You form part of a peanut gallery that's forced to watch the surviving players compete for the win.
Right, so the win matters more in Counter-Strike
because your teammates and your vanquished enemies are watching and cheering and booing.
But, you know, I think they could make it matter even more if they altered it
so that the players could see or hear the cheers and boos of the ghosts looking on.
And not many people know about this, but in I Want to Be the Guy Gaiden,
which is a single-player game,
the developer, Michael O'Reilly, has the ability to
visit your game, drop in without you knowing at first, give you hints,
even manipulate variables to make it harder or easier for you to kind of
mess with you.
Right, so the point I'm trying to make here is this.
If you make sure your game has a physical performance aspect,
like Street Fighter, even if only in the thumbs,
and if you make it so that it's played in front of some kind of audience,
then you can pretty much guarantee that the outcome of the match
will matter more to the players and to the onlookers.
And that's part of what I think it means for something to be a sport,
to perform in front of others,
to be watched, cheered, booed.
Human rituals in general, whether you think of weddings, funerals, executions or football matches,
don't mean much unless you have participants and witnesses.
And the same is true of video games.
You can make your game matter just by designing it to be performed
in front of a simulated crowd, if you like, in front of a single human being, as in this case.
Or you can build your game out from the ground up
so that it's designed to be watched by a crowd, played at a party.
Design your game so that it gives the spectator something to watch for, right?
So you also have to be aware that anything that happens between the player's thumb and the gamepad
is probably invisible to anybody watching.
So this is why joust works well.
All of the motions are out there for everybody to see.
Some of the ways that sports make themselves matter to the players
come out of that public performative aspect.
So for example, one crucial aspect that is basically missing from games next to sports is drama, right?
This focus on human suffering, frustration, striving, that's absolutely core to the spectatorship experience in sport.
Sports are dramatic because the stakes are higher.
And of course you get higher stakes for free when there's spectators, right?
Spectators make you embarrassed if you play badly, or proud if you play well.
But sports are also often explicitly designed to bring out emotional and physical suffering
to the maximum allowable degree, right?
So in the race walk at the Olympics or in the Tour de France, it pushes the human body
to the absolute limits of physical endurance.
is structured in such a way that it puts one solitary awayside batter
in the path of nine guys who oppose him
and tens of thousands of local fans in the bleachers
who hate him and want him to die.
And I think there's a kind of pressure that comes out of that.
Something really interesting can happen under that kind of pressure.
Athletes puke, athletes cry, athletes spit the dummy.
And it generates feelings of drama and emotional investment
in the players and in the fans and in the press,
making sports matter in a way that video games usually don't.
And video games do their best to undermine
the sense of occasion and the sense of drama
that's present in every big sporting performance.
You quick load, you make a little bit of progress,
and then you quick save.
The player erases every mistake and they keep every lucky break.
And I think this is one of the worst and most pervasive failures of game design.
Even in games where there's no quick save, we design them systematically so that they avoid,
that we avoid the chance that someone will be frustrated or humiliated,
and thereby we also avoid the chance that someone will feel really seriously proud or accomplished.
But we can easily reverse that. We raise the pressure on players by drawing inspiration
from things that lend drama to real-world sports, right?
So one example is, it's embarrassing to screw up in a real sport because the crowd is watching
your every move, right? And parlor games, like pool, especially those
that aren't played with an audience, are more like video games than sports in this sense,
right? Because the audience is very small or non-existent.
But with parlor games, we've found some ways to compensate
for the lack of the audience, the lack of public shaming.
In Australia, the tradition is that if you lose a game of pool
without getting a single ball in a pocket,
you have to pull your pants down and go once around the table.
Go, dude!
With that on the line, I think then your performance matters a lot, right?
In a video game, you could roll out a ready-made crowd using Twitter
by auto-tweeting the poor performance of the player to publicly embarrass them.
You can design your games with controls that are designed to be physically exhausting,
like our game MegaGurp.
In this case, you have to play efficiently or else you'll get, like, a very painful leg cramp.
But maybe the most effective way to raise the stakes in a video game is to take the most basic thing
that makes the results of sporting events matter, right?
There is no do-overs in competitive sport.
You can create a sense of occasion by designing levels that can only be played once, or only once a day.
Or you could let the players play any time, but only challenge for the leaderboard once every four years, like in the Olympics.
Maybe that all sounds a little bit too radical.
I want to say that you can also raise the stakes of a game in more subtle, metaphorical ways.
In competitive sports, especially boxing, we've developed this kind of complex language
around challenging, winning and losing that includes trash talk, or shit talking, the
other players.
So that language is used to invoke deeper social concepts
like honor and pride in sporting results.
And I think it increases the stakes, both metaphorically
and in reality.
We increase the stakes of a sport metaphorically
by saying things like, I'm going to bury you, right?
Or I crushed you.
Even the basic term, I beat you, is a violent term.
We borrow the language of deadly combat and violent crime
in order to make losing sound a lot worse and more important
than it really is.
Now, obviously, you can get all the trash talk that you want
if you play an online multiplayer shooter.
But I think you can also use it in single player designs,
where we face the toughest challenge to make
players' performance matter.
An example would be, Devil May Cry.
Shit talks to you if you do poorly.
Tells you that easy mode is unlocked.
I did this more explicitly in my game Klop has this antagonist called Sherrod who literally
insults you every time you lose.
There's no real life audience in this case, but in this case there is this NPC character
who forms a kind of a peanut gallery, observing and reacting and criticizing your performance.
It doesn't really matter what Sherrod thinks of your running style, but it kind of starts
to feel like it does.
And more often in games, we use a visual metaphor for high stakes
instead of a verbal one.
So if you think about it, this is the reason why so many games
use the player avatar's death as the failure state.
In fact, I think that's the best or most legitimate reason,
justifying reason, for the amount of violence
that we have in single-player games.
And that's why there's something so unsatisfying about games that bend over backwards to avoid a death state.
If the player is invulnerable, there's no metaphor for high stakes.
And the outcome of the game starts to feel predestined and meaningless.
You think of L.A. Noire, where they made it almost impossible to run over pedestrians.
If there's no danger of a penalty, the stakes are lowered.
The outcome matters less, and the player stops trying to drive well.
Of course in sports, in real sports, apart from martial arts I guess, the penalty for
failure isn't injury or death, it's just humiliation, frustration and shame.
But that's deliberately designed into sport as well, again making heavy use of metaphors.
For example, sports make heavy use of the concept of nationalism by forming teams around
countries.
So there's this idea in the player's head, if you're playing for your country, you know
everyone in the country is watching you and depending on you.
And I think the Trackmania guys realized that when they made nations,
where you can compete to push your country higher up in the ladder,
again like in the Olympics.
Now, it's not a real way of raising the stakes.
You know, there's no actual benefit to your country to be higher in Trackmania nations.
But it's a metaphor for something that matters, just like trash talk.
All right, so one final point.
In real world sports, there's this strong ethic of player integrity, which I think is
an essential part of what makes the outcome of a sporting match matter to the players
and the fans.
We spend billions of dollars every year testing athletes for this long list of illegal drugs,
right?
We have an international panic when Tiger Woods cheats on his wife or when Lance Armstrong
turns out to have been doping the whole time.
And sporting organizations have sided incredibly heavily against things like match fixing,
especially in soccer and boxing.
In the sporting world, the reason we object to fixed games or performance enhancing drugs
is that they violate an ethic of integrity in sport.
So integrity is important because it's part of what gives the result of a game legitimacy and importance.
If you win because the other team wasn't trying, or because you paid for an unfair advantage,
then the results of the match aren't interesting.
So integrity is part, it's like an important part of what makes the outcome of any sporting
event matter.
It's really difficult to give single-player video games the same legitimacy when there's
no spectators, no human referees, and no one will ever know if you've used a trainer or
a cheat code.
But I think certain reward structures that we put in our games undermine the ethic of
integrity even more.
even if you're not cheating.
Pay to win, I think, is the video game equivalent
of match fixing or doping.
If you can pay to improve your performance by purchasing
upgrades or unlocks, then it doesn't matter anymore how well you're playing.
Even when it's sanctioned by the developer, even when it's provided by the
developer,
buying progress undermines the player's integrity.
I'd also argue that any game that lets you just exchange progress for time, time for
progress without really trying is essentially suffering from the same problem.
So grinding is just paying to win with a different currency, time.
If you're grinding, it doesn't matter how well you're playing at all.
I mean, you can obviously speed up the grind by playing well, but you can get more efficiency
by playing eight copies of the same game at once.
Now, it's true, I mean, one of the things that may jump to mind is that in sport you have to do something that's a bit grind-like, which is training.
You have to train in order to play well. It's not just a matter of showing up on match day and focusing hard.
But training also has to be done skillfully. You know, you can't just exchange time for victory in any sport.
And people always tell me that they beat QWOP. They're really proud and they're really happy they come and they say that they beat QWOP.
And then I inquire a bit further,
and it turns out that they did it this way,
by kind of tapping the keys as fast as they can
and scooting along on one knee.
Now, I would feel pretty ashamed to admit
that I was playing a game with so little dignity.
But I'm in the minority there, right?
That's the minority view, because we
don't have a norm of integrity in video games.
So as designers, what can you do to foster that norm
of integrity in your game?
Well, if you approach a game in the same way as you approach a real-life sport,
the first thing that you do is you do your best to maintain a canonical record
of the player's performance, especially in single-player.
Right, so that might mean
doing your best to make sure that the scoreboards are secure or that
high scores are validated.
It might mean doing your best to make sure that updates to the game rules
don't invalidate previous scores.
It might mean making sure that players can't pay for better equipment,
or grind mindlessly to achieve better stats,
or progress through the game.
But if our games don't explicitly reward and support integrity in the players,
then I think that they're basically doomed to be disposable entertainment
rather than something more.
All right, so in this talk, I've argued that the biggest
challenge that we face as designers is to make the events
in our games matter to players.
And I've argued that we can meet that challenge in a
number of ways, taking inspiration from real sports.
If we're making a multiplayer game, we can give it
performativity by placing it in front of live spectators,
either online or in live performance spaces.
And you can raise the stakes of the game by running one-off tournaments where the player
only gets one chance to do well.
In the event gaming scene, at Baby Castles, Wild Rumpus, Wagos Rancheros, Prince of Arcade
and so on, we've been doing these things as much as we can.
And I think in single player it's harder, but there are still things that you can do.
You can utilize social networks or NPCs to build real or simulated audience.
You can enforce permanent consequences to bad player performance.
You can have one-off game events to build a sense of occasion.
And you can even jump in and shit-talk the player, either automatically or as in, I want
to be the guy guiding by hacking their game.
And you can make sure that they can't win unless they're trying their hardest.
I think it's super rare to see single player games or even private multiplayer games that
do all those things at once.
But games that do will be engaging and they'll be memorable.
And I think they'll matter a lot more to the players and to the spectators, just like real
single player sports.
Thanks very much.
We've got a question from Chris.
Do you, uh...
Just, can you talk about the cultivating integrity
and the norm of integrity versus, like,
hacking as kind of a metagame thing for games?
Like, you know, figuring out a solution to co-op
that doesn't require you to play the way you want it.
Can you talk a little bit about the conflict between those?
All right, so, okay, so the question is,
you know, is there a tension between, uh...
cultivating a norm of integrity and allowing players, I guess,
so I guess in QWOP, I didn't do anything to stop players from
from scooting along on one knee. And even after I realized that they were all doing that,
I could have, I could have, I mean I published it on my website. I could
easily have just gone in and made some kind of rule
that stopped people from doing that.
And actually...
One of the things about this is that I think that if you enforce too hard...
If you try too hard to force players to play with integrity,
there's a risk that it no longer is integrity, right?
They're not making a choice to play with dignity,
that maybe there is less dignity after all.
And I've been trying it both ways.
I actually think that it's better in QWOP
that I didn't enforce it too much.
But what I've been trying to do as a developer is going around.
and ridiculing players who do that,
I'm trying to publicly shame them.
That's my way as a developer
of trying to foster that norm of integrity.
Look, I do believe that games
shouldn't be too strict with their rules.
So, but, you know, hopefully,
hopefully if I put up enough of these slides,
people will feel bad about playing that way.
All right, next.
Hi, my name's...
My name's Roy, and I'm developing right now a strictly local multiplayer competitive game.
And we had an event at a local bar back in Vermont in the States
where we had people off the streets play the game, and we had a tournament.
And largely, it was pretty successful, but there were still some people in the crowd
who were like, oh, why is there a video game here?
So, my question to you...
Sorry.
Is how large of a role do you think the decreasing,
yet prevalent, stigma against video games
plays a part in the popularity of video games versus sports?
Yeah.
It's a real problem, right?
I mean, we were at the Sony event at IndyCade last year.
And they rented out the bar.
But at some point, it was no longer completely private.
And regular people started coming in.
And they were mad at us because we were sitting playing Samurai Gun in a big group.
Everyone's having a good time. You know, they're ordering drinks.
It's not like we're not, you know, doing that.
And then, you know, waitresses start to shut us down.
And we've got, like, these kind of guys in suits and ties
who've come from the picture studios, like, making fun of us
for playing video games in a bar.
I can sort of understand it in a way.
We've got a whole bunch of cultural norms about those spaces,
about what people are doing.
And I guess video games are constructed as not being part of that, right?
And that's something that's going to take some time to change.
We need games that are designed for those spaces.
I mean, part of the problem is, you know, we're sitting around with this laptop.
It's like 15-inch screen.
It's four of us huddled around it.
There's really, it's very difficult to kind of get the
spectatorship aspect going, because nobody can see it
except for the people who are playing it, right?
And nobody actually knows what we're doing, because we're
sitting here with these controllers and our thumbs are
just sort of barely moving.
And so to somebody who doesn't know about video games and who
doesn't want to get up really close to us, there's nothing
in it for them except that we're sort of taking up space
and kind of killing their vibe.
But when we run Doug Wilson's game, Johann Sebastian Joust,
in the same sorts of spaces, people don't seem to object.
Suddenly, that's something everybody wants to get involved in.
So it is possible, I think.
We've got two jobs to do.
One is to design games that can be played within the kind of context
of the existing spaces.
And then the other one is that we have to try to support the
establishment of new spaces.
You know, like I was supporting LA Games Space, and I've been
contributed to Baby Castles for many years, Silent Barn.
So there are emerging some spaces where we can start to
kind of create our own culture in those spaces and not be
kind of like harshing the vibe of these millionaires who've
come down from the picture studios trying to have a
regular bar experience.
Hey, it was totally fascinating.
I really like the idea of what sports can bring to games.
I was wondering what you thought about what games
can bring to sports design.
I'm thinking a lot about current debates happening
about rugby rules that are kind of broken,
and soccer rules that are kind of broken,
and what the video game world can bring to sports.
Yeah, it's an interesting question.
So when you have like the electronic linesman in tennis
or in soccer, it decides whether the ball has
gone over the line.
There is definitely a blurring of the lines between video
games and real sports, right?
I'm all for that.
I think that video games, the reason I'm interested in video
games rather than just playing or making sports is that I
think that there is something special about video games.
that you can't get with tabletop games, with parlor games, or with real sports, right?
I think there is this kind of tight pairing between a system that can react instantaneously
and a human brain and human body that allows you to have experiences and to produce engagement
that sports can't.
At least as they're currently envisaged.
So I think there is absolutely a lot of room to bring
the kind of benefits of video game technology
to real sport and maybe we can have like a best of both worlds.
That would be fantastic.
So a lot of what you're talking about is certainly relevant to competitive games and multiplayer games and
talking about raising the challenge and raising the stakes and stuff.
Those kind of things certainly appeal to people that are really into those sort of competitive games.
But I wonder, to what extent do you feel like that some of these prescriptions that you're offering
would apply outside of those types of games?
Because obviously, a lot of the reason why a lot of games are getting easier or less punishing
are to, in the interest of, you know, widening the potential audience.
Do you see that potentially working in a mass market?
Or would it always have to be kind of that niche, competitive kind of...
Yeah, OK.
So the answer to that is that it's really easy to explain
in a kind of multiplayer competitive scheme
how to make it more like a sport,
because sports are kind of often like that.
But I think that there are kind of lessons
that you can take from sports, even if you're making single
player games that are not even designed
to have that kind of adversarial, difficult,
competitive thing, right?
So if you think about a game like Proteus, which
doesn't even have goals.
Proteus by Ed Key.
So it's a game where you basically just walk around
a beautiful landscape and you experience
some sounds and you see some things, right?
That's the sort of description of the game. It's amazing.
Now that's the kind of game which is nothing like a real-world sport.
But we've had very good results showing it in public
to large groups of people, because there
is a kind of performance aspect using
the music and the visuals.
And so it's possible to bring out that kind of experience
performance, even without the competitive thing,
even without the multiplayer thing.
If you're thinking about how this will be perceived.
As a performance, even if it's not in a big public space
with a huge audience, even if it's
just the people in your household who
are watching you play over your shoulder
while you're playing on the couch, you can design for that.
So I think that it's harder in the case of single player
games, especially single player games that are not
sort of super competitive.
But it's still possible to think creatively about this.
And I think still you can take some inspiration
from real sports, for sure.
OK.
We're out of time, so thanks very much, everybody.