Hi, I'm Jeff Hester. I'm an artist at Harmonix.
And welcome to the talk, Maximizing Critique,
Improving Communication for Everyone Involved
in Critical Feedback.
Conversations that involve critical feedback
are part of our everyday lives as video game developers.
This talk is in the art track, and I'm an artist,
and most examples we'll be using are art.
But the top things I'll be covering are
relevant across all disciplines
and in between all disciplines.
The conversations that we have that involve
giving each other feedback happen all over
and everyone in all of our companies.
One thing we can do as artists is,
we often have come from a background in art school
where these kinds of conversations have been
a really integral part of our education.
And I hope that the talk today is gonna give some,
even for artists, some fresh insight
on some strategies we can do to improve
the ways we give and receive critical feedback,
or at least articulate what we already
might be doing intuitively,
having come through art school.
But one thing we can also do, those of us who are artists
who have this background, is we can really use
that background to be leaders in our own companies
and helping to change company culture
and improve this kind of dialogue across
and in between all disciplines.
So hopefully I'll be giving you some fuel
and some strategies you can do to do that.
When conversations that involve critical feedback go well,
our products get better, we increase efficiency,
we increase team cohesion,
but when those conversations go poorly.
then they result in wasted work,
adrift in creative vision,
and just really bad team morale.
And by badly, I don't mean what we normally think of
as just bad.
You know, I don't mean somebody saying,
you know, that sucks.
We know that's bad feedback.
But I mean, there's often a lot of times
that feedback is just okay,
or it's neutral,
and it's not being as effective and actionable as it can be.
And we're gonna talk about that a lot today.
How do we take feedback that's all right
and make it awesome?
So my background interest in this goes pretty far back.
Before I worked in video games.
I taught for a long time, for more than 10 years, in China and in the Rhode Island School
of Design and at the New York Academy.
I've also taught a lot of workshops at places like the Metropolitan Museum, Fisher-Price,
Turbine and Harmonics.
During this time of teaching I became really interested in the idea of critical feedback
and group critiques and how it is that we give feedback, when is it effective and when
is it not.
A lot of that came out of...
my own challenges to do it well, and when it went bad,
when it went well, and trying to take those moments
and find out what it was about them that was either good or bad.
And about seven years ago, I was fortunate enough
to start working at Harmonix,
which is an awesome company.
I can't say enough great things about it.
And one of the great things about Harmonics
is it has an amazing culture of critical feedback,
especially in the art department.
And I found that the work and thoughts
that I'd done as an artist and as a teacher before that
really fit in really well and it was great
to experience that at Harmonics.
While there I've worked on Rock Band 3,
I've been on lots of research and development teams,
especially leading up to Fantasia
where I was the lead environment artist.
And most recently, I'm now currently working on the Harmonix Music Visualizer, Harmonix Music VR.
So, while I was teaching, one of the things I would often talk about with students is this word, crit.
What the hell does that mean?
And I would say to them, especially when they're freshmen, we say, okay, we're going to have a crit today.
We talk about that, but what is that? And the freshmen often didn't know.
They often didn't know, does it mean criticize, or does it mean critique?
And there's a big difference between those two things.
And we start to talk about it. What is the difference?
What is the difference between criticize and critique?
Criticize.
is much more superficial.
It's your initial response.
It's the first response, you might say.
It often tends to be more about personal preference.
It often tends to be very judgmental.
It's not.
It's just what happens to come out.
And it's much more on the surface.
Whereas critique is about taking something apart,
analyzing it, looking at it from all levels,
looking inside of it, understanding how it works.
And that might lead to judgment,
it might lead to assessment,
in terms of is it working well or is it not working well.
But that assessment is not the main part of critique.
The main part of critique is the analysis.
So critique is more objective.
It's analytical, it's reflective, it's deeper.
It's going into the surface of something,
understanding what it is.
And often, when feedback is not as helpful
or as actionable as it can be,
it's because it's living on that realm
of just being something that someone is just criticizing.
But when it becomes much more actionable,
it's heading into being more critique.
One of the unique things about this talk today
is I'm not going to just focus on how we are more effective
in giving feedback, but I'm also going to talk
about a lot of strategies for how we can receive
feedback more effectively.
You know, often, any bit of feedback you get,
it might be this nasty old lump of coal,
but you don't have to leave it that way.
Just because it came that way,
there are ways you can take that nasty lump of coal
and turn it into a diamond.
And I'm going to try to give you some strategies
to help start thinking about ways to do that.
Often when we think about feedback, we think about it being a one-way street.
The giver going right to the receiver.
And one thing that's really problematic with this
is often people think that I don't need to think about the person who's receiving this feedback.
It's their fault if they can't understand it.
They need to have a tough skin.
And you know what? That's bullshit.
You know, because feedback is, these feedback loops
are moments when we can really have a deep conversation
and build community in our companies.
And if we're not thinking about it as a two-way street,
if we're thinking about it just as a one-way loop
and we're not really caring about the person
who's receiving it, then we're missing a huge opportunity
to build relationships in the company
and build our whole,
creative environment.
But when we start to think of it as a two-way street,
you're going to start to think about it empathically.
If you're giving feedback, how are you
thinking about how it's going to be received
from the person receiving it?
If you're receiving feedback, how
are you thinking about it from the person who's giving it?
Are you going to assume it's the best intentions?
Or are you not going to assume it's the best intentions?
So we need to have empathy on both ends of this
and see it as a two-way dialogue that we're really working
together toward a common good.
Before I get to a few strategies,
goals are one of the most important things
we can think about when we're giving critical feedback.
If you remember nothing else I talked about today,
none of the specific strategies I'm gonna go over,
just remember this, if you have a goal,
if you articulated your goal,
when you're about to start giving
or receiving critical feedback,
right away you're gonna start heading more
into a form of critique, rather than just criticizing.
Because having that goal is gonna help you
be dugging under the surface of what you're doing.
I'm gonna give you a few examples of the kinds of goals
that I was keeping in mind when I'm designing
the strategies we'll talk about today.
The first one is align your work with the art direction.
This is a great default goal to have.
You know, if you're not sure what goal to have,
just think about this one,
because right away you're gonna start giving a context.
You're gonna be contextualizing the feedback you give,
and giving it some sort of larger reason for being
is gonna help it be much more relevant
and much more actionable.
Leave room for creative problem solving.
This is a great goal for helping that two-way dialogue.
If you're leaving room for the person you're giving feedback
to solve the problem creatively,
then you're already inviting them into the problem.
You're thinking of it more as a dialogue
rather than a one-way street.
Encourage team spirit and cohesion.
Keep that in mind with critical feedback,
and things will really be helping
to make sure your feedback is being effectively received.
And developing a desire for feedback.
This is true of both receiving and giving feedback.
It helps us to embrace it as a wonderful act,
not this moment we have to fear.
pillows at RISD that people would sit on, it was like, you know,
crit happens. It was just, just, just furthering this culture that crit was bad.
Oh, crit, it happens. And no, crit doesn't, yeah, yeah,
crit happens. It's awesome. It's this wonderful moment of
of working together, sharing. It's a great time, not something
to be avoided or, or not look forward to.
and becoming a valuable team member.
Going in with that kind of goal also
will really help to right away
get, you'll start to find your own strategies.
Your own strategies will intuitively rise up
if you're keeping some of these goals in mind
or if you're just having a goal in general
that you have in mind.
So let's get down to it.
Let's start talking about some strategies.
Some first, some strategies for giving feedback.
I'll talk about two of them today.
The first one is define problems before solving them, right?
That's very often the first thing we say is we start to presenting a solution.
Make that red or move that over there.
Those are solutions and it becomes they're not as actionable as they could be if you define the problems.
Let's look at an example of that in action.
Let's look at the development of the early Rock Band 1 head style.
This Rock Band 1 head style went through a major course correction or change in its style.
If we look at the earlier version, we can think about or imagine some of the less effective solution-based feedback that could have been said about this.
For example, it might be said, the head should be more anatomically correct.
What's wrong with that?
That's not going to hurt anybody's feelings.
Is that bad feedback?
It's not effective feedback.
It's not effective feedback because it's presenting the solution to the problem,
not presenting the problem itself.
As an artist, what are you going to do with this?
Well, I can make it anatomically correct.
But how? In what way?
There are a lot of ways to make something anatomically correct.
I don't know because I don't know what the goal is.
I don't know what problem I'm really trying to solve.
Another example, add more hard edges.
Yeah, OK.
I could do that.
I could start slapping in some RDA, but I don't know why.
I don't know what problem I'm trying to solve.
So these are solutions being presented.
What's the problem?
What's a good way of rephrasing this as more problem-focused feedback?
We need to create heads that are more anatomically correct,
but still united by a common, iconic style that fits the rock band world.
How can we do that?
Now, let's make a couple comments about this.
One, it's longer.
Yeah, it's longer.
Though, so you might...
I gotta...
It's a lot more efficient for me to say the other stuff.
You know, the other stuff is shorter.
I want to be right to the point.
I want to be direct.
You know what?
Yeah, you'll be efficient.
You'll be direct right now.
But then,
you might be not as efficient when the artist doesn't really have a clear goal
and you have to go through a lot more iterations
and it's a lot unclear.
So sometimes, effective feedback is longer.
It's just...
Just part of it comes with it.
But the overall process becomes much more efficient
and much more, it works better.
We is a great word to use.
You know, want to incorporate the things,
make people brought into a common problem,
relating it to the art style as it's done here,
bringing it to the common rock band world,
and ending with this question, how can we do that?
An invitation to come in and solve this together.
This is something we're all working on.
It really helps to improve that feedback.
And in this case those kinds of dialogues really produced this wonderful wonderful head that became this great icon
For rock band itself and really helped the whole brand
Another strategy, describe reasoning behind the judgments.
Often we just present, in the same way we often just present a solution to the problem,
rather than describing the problem,
it's often common for us to just tell, say our judgment,
you know, I don't like that, that's too red, that's too hot, that's too...
Instead of spending some time asking ourselves what is underneath that judgment,
and that might be reasons, it might be by describing the experience that's underneath it.
And let's look at some examples to get at this.
We'll look at a few different iterations
of the Rock Band 4 main menu screen.
This is one of the first early iterations of this.
And let's look at some examples
of judgment-focused feedback.
So, feedback is focusing on judgment.
So, someone might say, composition sucks.
Well, we can all agree that's bad feedback, right?
Obviously, that's not going to be effective at making someone work.
It's going to be really effective at pissing somebody off
and really messing the whole, you know,
communication up and messing your relationship up.
It's not going to be effective.
However, look at this.
The composition is weak.
Well, that's not so bad, right?
That's not really maybe going to hurt my feelings.
It might hurt my feelings a little bit.
I don't fully, if so, feel attacked.
But you know what?
It might not be so bad, but it's still not effective.
It's still not effective because it's being presented as a judgment.
The underlying experience or reasons behind that judgment
aren't being expressed.
Why did you compose the band that way?
This is a great example of focusing on the artist rather than the art.
Right?
Every once in a while we need to do this.
Every once in a while you have to ask, you know,
why did you do this? What's going on here?
But be really careful about that.
If it can be rephrased in a way that's not focusing on the artist,
but focusing on the art,
it's probably going to be more helpful.
The other thing about this, in addition to focusing on the artist,
is it's also a judgment.
It's kind of a veiled judgment.
You know, you really...
You really fucked this up. You screwed this up.
You know, what's wrong with you?
This is a judgment. Not only a judgment about the art, but now it's a judgment about the artist.
You know, and that's not gonna, it's not as effective as it could be.
So, all of these bits of feedback are various levels.
Some are more benign, some are really more harsh.
But what they all share in common is that they're all judgment being presented in different ways.
So how can that become much more effective?
How can it become much more actionable?
The same kinds of ideas.
Well, one thing you could do is you
could describe the experience that led to that judgment.
So for example, I might look at this and say,
gosh, my eyes just wander all around this thing.
I have no sense of primary or secondary focal point.
And then my eyes just get locked on that white light
shape on his shirt.
It's like a prison.
It's locked.
And my eyes can't get away from that.
And what's happening there is
I'm describing my experience.
I'm describing my experience that led to the judgment.
There's a little bit of an irony here, right?
On one hand, we want to be more objective and good feedback,
but here I'm using subjectivity.
I'm using my experience.
But I'm doing it very differently.
I'm not using my personal preference
in terms of subjectivity.
I'm just saying, I like chocolate.
I don't like vanilla.
Not that kind of subjectivity.
I'm using my experience to help get at an objective issue
in the work.
I'm describing my experience.
And by describing my experience, we
start to get at things.
Another thing starts to come out here.
You can start to see now there's some criteria
that the artist can hold on to, right?
primary and secondary focal points.
That just is kind of bubbled up by describing experience, right?
Because now we have something now the artist can hold on to.
It's, oh, I see, now I understand the kind of experience I need to create
by working on this composition.
And so now, as I go back into it to improve it,
now I'm excited, because now, not only do I see the problem
because I understand it, but I understand that the real thing I want to do
is create an experience.
and I understand what kind of experience I want to create,
I'm going to dive back into it,
and oh, I'm really excited to get to work.
And here's the next iteration,
you can see now we've got some nice primary,
secondary focal points,
I can see the guitar player,
then leading back into,
my eyes are really led around,
from the red to back into the blue,
starting to get some of that,
but we can also do another round now,
of iteration,
and another round of judgment-focused feedback.
So let's see, what was another judgment we can place now,
on this, you could say,
that's a poor use of camera angle.
Another example of judgment,
not really bad, it's not going to really hurt my feelings that you said that.
So this isn't about necessarily hurting feelings, it's not about critique
that is often obviously bad, but it's about often critical feedback that's not
as effective and actionable as it could be. Because how is this actionable?
Well, I guess I could change the camera angle.
But I'm not really—what do you mean by camera angle?
I'm not sure what—I could start playing around with it,
randomly putting camera angles in,
but I'm not sure because I don't know what the problem is you're trying to solve.
Right? And I don't know—
I don't know exactly where this judgment came from.
So, maybe we could rephrase that
and make it some more effective reason-focused feedback.
So, instead of focusing, in this case,
on the experience that led to the judgment,
you could focus on the reasons that led to that judgment.
So maybe you want to say,
you know, the composition as a whole
should feel more as energetic as the characters.
Adding tilt to the camera might help.
What are some other ideas?
Let's dissect that a little bit.
So it begins with the reason behind the judgment, right?
And it takes something internal to it.
Now we have a criteria we can use
as the artist goes into it.
They have this criteria.
They want to make things energetic, right?
It does present a solution here, right?
Which is something I suggested earlier not to do.
Adding some kilt to the camera might help.
But the difference here now is this being,
the solution is being presented as an option,
as an example.
You know, adding some kilt to the camera might help,
or some others.
Incorporate people, bring them into this discussion, right?
Well, we can't always do that.
We can't always do this, right?
There's oftentimes in the production pipeline,
we just don't have time for group discussions.
We're really busy, we gotta get this done,
this is due tomorrow, it has to happen.
I'm the art director, I know what this needs to happen,
I've been working on this for years,
here's what needs to happen to solve this.
What do you do in that case?
Do you just tell them?
You need to tilt the camera angle, do it that way?
That's an option.
Another option, which is kind of in the middle,
which is I think much more effective and actionable,
is to offer reasoned, focused feedback
that still
has the reasons behind it.
So the composition as a whole needs to feel more energetic.
Adding some tilt to the camera will help.
So, don't just say add tilt to the camera,
but why does that camera need to be there?
What's the reason behind that?
So that way the artist has that criteria
that they'll know when they're fixing it,
when it's going to be good.
What are they trying to achieve by doing this?
So they have the sense of it,
and they can feel empowered then,
even if they're not empowered to...
to come up with their own solution,
they're at least empowered to understand
whether the solution they're doing is right or not,
because they understand the criteria that's underneath it.
And in this case, we ended up with this awesome composition
on the Rock Band 4 main menu screen.
So those are a couple strategies for giving feedback.
Defining problems rather than solving them.
Describing reasons rather than just the judgments,
or also giving the experience behind the judgments.
And they're fairly simple, they're fairly basic.
But if these things are so basic and simple,
Why do I always screw this up?
I've been thinking about this a lot as a teacher,
as an artist for a number of years, a video game company.
I'm engaged in critical feedback every day.
I still, to this day, often judgments come out,
solutions come out.
Why is this so hard?
Why is this deceptively simple and actually fairly difficult
to do?
It's because it actually involves two steps.
First, we have to recognize where our first response is,
as our intuitive gut response, and stop it.
or catch stuff that's coming out of our mouth and add on to it.
So first we have to recognize our first response,
and then we have to reflect and rephrase.
So we have to catch what that is, and we have to think about it,
and we have to rephrase it to become more effective.
That makes it really difficult.
It's also the case...
when we're receiving feedback.
When we're receiving feedback,
we'll go into some strategies for that now,
we also have to often stop ourselves
from our initial response,
which is tending to be pretty defensive.
Oh, oh, I already thought about that.
Oh, being defensive.
And putting that first response down
and then going into the receiving of the feedback.
Here's some strategies that can help us do that.
The first is to ask questions that encourage critics
to define the problems or describe the reasons.
So basically, this is the same strategy
as I talked about before, but in this case,
you're on the receiving end of it.
So when the person giving you feedback
isn't phrasing their feedback as defining problems,
or they're not phrasing it as describing the reasons,
then what you can do is take that feedback,
that raw lump of coal, and you can start asking questions
to turn it into the diamond that's hidden inside of it.
So look at an example of that.
This is a monkey.
I love this monkey.
This is a monkey from Disney Fantasia,
Music Evolved, from one of our scenes.
It was awesome concept art by Gianna Ruggiero.
And I loved it.
I loved this monkey, and Gianna loved it,
and we were really happy with it.
But unfortunately, it wasn't fitting in
to some larger narrative and art direction issues,
and so it needed to be changed.
And that was a little bit unclear for a while.
And there was some poorly phrased solution-focused feedback,
such as, make the monkey older.
Now if we all imagine ourselves as Gianna,
we get that, we make the monkey older.
So, oh, yeah.
Okay.
I can make the monkey older.
But what, what, how?
How old?
I don't know.
Why?
What's going on?
You know, it's unclear.
Right?
So how could that be?
What could you do if you're in Gianna's position?
We could start to ask questions to reveal the problem
underneath that solution.
What, what are the, what are we?
How would an older monkey fit into this scene more successfully?
What is it about age that's important here?
Why an older monkey?
Or just simply,
what problem are you trying to solve with that solution?
Just ask it, right?
Let's look at an example of some poorly phrased judgment-focused feedback
that could have also been about the same
awesome monkey.
The monkey's too goofy.
Yeah.
Monkeys are goofy.
What's wrong with that?
So, you know, okay, that's my first response,
if I hear that, if I'm Gianna, I hear,
yeah, I'm a monkey, so, ooh, I'm gonna stop that.
That's not helpful, right?
So obviously this bit of poorly-faced feedback
has some, it's as lump as coal,
what's the diamond inside?
How can I get that out?
I can start asking some questions.
You know, okay, so let's ask some questions
to reveal what's behind the judgment.
What feelings do you think the monkey should evoke?
What kind of feelings should people have when they're looking at this monkey?
If they don't want to make him feel goofy, what kind of feelings should be there?
So we asked these kinds of questions, we got to the issue,
and the real issue turned out to be...
We asked these questions, the poorly phrased feedback was transformed
through our asking of questions, and finding out that really we need a monkey
that fits into a narrative based on sadness, isolation, and an attempt to connect.
Oh, okay.
Now we can start to think, now I understand why those issues are,
now we understand there are problems trying to be solved.
Okay, so we've taken that poorly phrased feedback,
we've asked some questions, and we've transformed it
into something that's really helpful, and now we can dive into it,
and we end up with this awesome, awesome monkey
that has this amazing sense of empathy,
that you're lost in space, you can't get to this monkey,
you're trying to help the monkey.
It was... I love this monkey.
I love both versions of the monkey, but the second version of the monkey was obviously
the most relevant one because it was appropriate for what we needed.
Another strategy for receiving feedback is frame the critique.
Let's look at an example of the development of a scene, also from Disney, from Fantasia
Music Evolved, called The Haven.
In this case, the art lead David Barilena and Don Rivers, the cinematographer and lighting
designer, knew that we had to make this scene to be much more iconic.
We needed to make it different from all the other scenes.
We had to find a way to give it its own identity,
and we had to do this really late in the production process.
Everything had already been made.
We couldn't change any assets.
So they did a great job of framing that critique
when they brought it to the group,
so they'd get the feedback that wouldn't be off base,
wouldn't be feedback that was taken away from those things.
So it's just by framing the critique.
you know, the things I just mentioned.
We need to give this scene an iconic look
using the elements that already exist.
So right away, you're not going to start getting feedback of,
oh, change the trees, let's get some new trees.
That's not an option, so let's not waste our time
getting that kind of feedback.
Let's frame the critique to get the feedback
that's most effective.
And it ends up with this awesome,
really iconic looking, beautiful, beautiful scene.
Third strategy for receiving feedback,
look for themes in the feedback.
So this is a great one if you can't ask questions.
Maybe somebody walked by your desk
and dropped a bomb on you and walked away.
You can ask them some questions.
Or maybe it came from the client or whoever.
But for some reason, you're not in the position
where you can ask questions.
You're not in the position where you can frame the feedback
before it happens.
So this is a great strategy in those situations.
And so we'll look at another scene from Disney Fantasia,
Music Evolved, the nation scene.
This scene, I'll go back one.
This was a beautiful work of concept art.
But once we got it into the roughed out, grey boxy version of itself,
we realized there were some problems.
And unfortunately we realized those problems after
the animation of the dragon coming from this mountain was already there.
So the mountain was locked in place, which was a problem.
So we started getting all this feedback,
when it was like, move the volcano back,
the area between the city and the mountains is boring,
make the background trees smaller.
add some flying creatures in the forest.
And you know, we tried some of these things, some we couldn't do.
We couldn't move the mountain because we didn't have time to redo the animation on the dragon.
And we tried some of these others. We were playing with these details.
But finally what we realized we needed to do
was we needed to take all that feedback and put it in a bucket
and look at it, across it,
and say, what is common with all of this?
What are we being told in all these bits of feedback?
And what we were being told in all of those was the common theme.
And the common theme was the space feels shallow, it lacks excitement.
And so we started thinking, well, what can we do? How can we change that?
We came up with the idea, we can't change depth because we can't move that mountain,
but we can't change it in Z, but we can change it in Y.
Let's just drop the floor, and suddenly we can have this big, vast space that feels vast,
you can see through it now, so it feels like it's deeper,
even though it's not deeper, you can see back through there.
And also now we can put the dragon on this ledge
that feels floating in space,
we don't really understand its depth anymore.
So it solved a lot of bunch of problems.
But we didn't get there until we looked at the themes
running across all that critique
and started to deal with them as a group
rather than trying to deal with each bit of feedback
one on one, one on one on its own.
So, let's just kind of recap the strategies I've talked about over the last 20 minutes.
First, were strategies for giving feedback and describing the problem rather than solving it,
and describing reasons or experience that lead to judgments.
and also strategies for receiving feedback.
Asking questions, focusing the critique,
looking for themes.
One other thing I'll add to one of these
is when you describe reasons or experience,
or when you ask people to describe
the reasons or experience,
it also helps to reveal sometimes
if something someone has said is purely personal.
Let me give a quick example of that.
Say you've got a horror game,
and so feedback somebody gives you is,
you know, I really don't like that character.
Or, that character's really not good.
And you say, well, that character makes me feel bad.
And you say, well, tell me about the experience
you're having with that character that led to that judgment.
Oh, gosh, every time I see her, she scares the hell out of me.
Well, so obviously it's a case where, that's good!
You want that character to scale the hell out of you, right?
And this is just an obvious and simple example
of what often can happen, which is sometimes
someone gives you a piece of judgment,
or they give you something,
and they think it might be criticism,
but once you start to dig underneath it,
you find actually it's not, it might be awesome.
And it's a great example of times
where when you're receiving feedback,
don't immediately react to it.
dig underneath it to find out what's really there because it might actually be awesome.
It might be that it's great.
Same thing too, when somebody says something really nice to you,
oh, I love that red you've used.
In that case, my initial feedback is, my initial response is to go,
oh, thank you. That's great.
But instead, that's still a lump of coal.
Because I can't do it, it's not actionable yet.
So you say, I love that red you use.
Oh, what is it about the red that you love?
How is it functioning?
You ask some questions, dig underneath both the good feedback
and the difficult feedback to really get
the stuff underneath it, and it becomes much more actionable.
Takeaways that I think would be helpful for today,
the things I would hope that you could take away from this brief
chat about critique.
First, clearly define your goals.
If you understand what you're doing, it will really help to make what you're saying deeper and not just so much on the surface.
Focus on critique and not just criticizing.
So take things apart, examine them, don't just have comments that go on the surface.
Remember that all criticism is potential critique.
The examples I was just giving.
Even if someone says a nice thing to you, it makes you feel good.
Even if somebody... it all can be potentially good.
And you want to try to find the information underneath it and make it actionable.
and then recognize, reflect, and rephrase.
Try to stop yourself from saying what initially you might say,
think about how it's going to be effective,
and think about how rephrasing it in some effective ways.
And remember that our first reactions are often really
poorly phrased and not as helpful as they could be.
So those are some of my ideas for critique.
And I've been thinking about this a long time,
and I love thinking about this kind of stuff.
I still struggle with it.
And I am mostly interested in the conversation itself.
And I just, as an invitation, please,
if any of you are also interested in thinking about this,
shoot me some emails, hang out afterwards,
I would love to hear your stories,
I'd love to hear your strategies.
You know, these are some strategies I've come up with,
there's lots of others.
And we'll have a few minutes for questions,
but also afterwards, if you don't feel like
doing questions, you just want to have a chat,
I'll be in the wrap-up room,
because I'd really like this to be the beginning
of a larger conversation about this.
I think it's something that is really important
for our industry to really focus on,
and many of us do it great,
but it'd be great if all of us could do it even better,
and especially across disciplines.
I think finding ways to make this interdisciplinary
would be really awesome.
Thank you all very much.
Applause
So, how do you deal with a lead or an art director that says the dreaded three words,
I don't know, to any of your questions?
First of all, that's an awesome art director.
As an aside, it is, because they're not going to lie.
Right?
As an aside, I've had a doctor for many, many years.
One of the things I love about my doctor, Dr. Stephen Scott,
if anybody happens to live in Providence, Rhode Island
and wants to find a physician.
The thing I love about Stephen Scott
is that he will always say,
I don't know, gosh, I'm going to look into that.
Instead of...
making some bullshit up.
So that's the first thing.
I don't know the context, but in general,
someone saying I don't know is often a great thing,
that they're willing to say that.
What's the context you're thinking of in particular
when someone said I don't know?
Like if you have, if they give you feedback
and you ask a leading question as to,
oh, why do you feel that way?
And they say, I don't know, full stop.
Like there's no constructive feedback whatsoever
beyond the, you know, that's it.
Maybe ask another question.
I mean, obviously, it's not going to be.
Also, another way you can say is,
you know, it's really good just to say,
well, I don't know your relationship with the art director,
but somebody say, gosh, you know,
that's, it's not really helpful for me.
One thing that would be really helpful for me
is if I could understand some of the stuff underneath this.
Or, you know, just kind of finding ways
to kind of keep that conversation going.
Is that helpful?
A little bit.
Yeah, but yeah, I think the other thing you can do
is find the other strategies.
You can start to dissect it yourself.
So if they gave you something,
and you ask them what made you feel that way,
and they just say, I don't know,
you can take that feedback
and try to put yourself in that position.
It's like, okay, if this is the case,
you know, like looking at one of the examples I said,
if the camera angle needs to change,
start saying, well, what is it about it
that might make that camera need to change?
You try to get inside of it,
and you can try to imagine what the underlying reasons are.
Okay, cool, thanks.
Yeah.
Hi.
Do you have any tips for stimulating a team to give more critique?
Because I have a team that...
they're all friends and
they have good relationships
they're not very comfortable critiquing each other
yes, I do
yeah, and there's an essay I wrote that was in a book that almost got published
I'm going to try to find a way to self-publish it
there's a whole
bunch about how to do group critiques in ways, but I'll give you one thing that can be really helpful
and that is often people go into a critique and they think they have to judge
and that's not true.
In fact, judgment, we know this from playtesting, right?
Playtesters give us their experience
and that's what helps us understand
whether the game is working.
And you can think of critique as the same way.
Think of critique as a time to be playtesting
the artwork or whatever it is.
So you can put people in front and say,
let's all just talk about how we experience this work.
So if it's a bunch of people, instead of them feeling like they have to judge each other,
take that out of the equation, right? This isn't about judging, it's about describing.
So we sit in front of a worker of art and say, okay, where are your eyes looking when you look
at this? Or, that's a leading question, or you can start to say, let's go around and everyone
starts to just describe an experience they're having when they play through this level.
What's an experience you had?
And then people start to describe their experiences.
And by describing experiences then, you can start to say,
oh, that was the experience we wanted to have,
or that wasn't the experience we wanted to have.
And then you can start to find out what the problems are.
So you kind of bubble it up from organic experience,
rather than thinking you have to judge.
And that's one thing I, when I taught,
that's how I always did all my critiques.
I would just say, okay.
We're not going to judge at all.
And students are like, what?
Thank God.
But then they think that it wasn't going to be real critique.
But that's what real critique is, actually.
Real critique is the taking apart and analyzing.
Is that helpful?
Yeah, I love it.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Yeah, actually, I tend to find that a lot of the ways
to really break loose on the critiquing
is to create a third party separate thing
that you're doing first.
So for example, if we're approaching a project,
to look at other people's versions of the projects,
and where all of you are able to feel
like you're safe to talk to each other
because it's not somebody who's in the room,
you're already getting the language going.
So as the language gets going and then you ultimately come back around to work that you're doing or you're a little bit later in the project
People tend to feel a little more comfortable critiquing each other because they feel like they've been in the presence of hearing critiquing
That is a great point. Yeah, establishing a culture and which and this one thing that harmonics does so well
I just love working at this company because harmonics also has this great culture of giving critique and and we all have the dialogue for
It we all are used to talking about each other's work
And if you're in a situation where that may not exist,
this may relate to the previous question too,
then part of what you can do, this is a great example,
is find ways to instill dialogues about critique
about something that's different.
Bring in some other games,
have a discussion about another game.
Bring in anything that you can start having,
just practicing the muscles of critical feedback.
It really does seem to be a factor,
is the more that people are just kind of used to
feeling like they can start talking to each other
with negative language that...
at least they would think would be negative,
and actually be something that just spurs further
conversation, I tend to find it's very effective.
That's wonderful.
Thank you for sharing that.
So my question relates to some issues I've seen.
Within our company, we do a lot of feedbacks on game designs.
A lot of times we're doing this, well, we still
don't have prototypes that you can play with.
So we're just talking about, do you
think this would be fun?
Do you think it would be fun?
Good point, yes.
In those kind of situations, we had a number of times run into a lot of problems.
One of them is, you know, if you're just coming to a meeting and you get presented with it,
I've noticed some people, they don't like to give critique because they're like,
I'm still thinking about it, I don't know, I've got to really think.
And so sometimes we'll say, okay, well, we sent out the material ahead of time.
But when we did that, what we noticed is,
just the speed at which you can think through and iterate
through stuff, for better or worse,
just slows down a little bit.
A second issue we ran into is, at least in situations
like these, invariably, there's something
that is subjective, right?
I just think this game play is fun.
I just think that game play is not fun.
And so, you know, it's like how do you address these kind of things where fundamentally it is a subjective?
Yeah, I think those are both great points.
I'll start with the second one first, and the second one is that in this case, it's someone who just doesn't have practice
explaining their subjectivity. And because that's just not the, when you say, I don't, I just don't like it,
there's always some sort of experience underneath there that's leading to that.
subjective reaction, right?
And some people just aren't good and don't
have a lot of practice at explaining
what that is underneath there.
And that's where it just takes someone
who's got a talented facilitator to start to say, OK,
what is it about that you don't like?
What experience?
Describe.
You can just pull it back and say, well,
describe the experience that you're having of it for me,
or finding ways to ask questions that start to get at that.
So I think there always are ways.
This idea of I just don't like it.
there's always something underneath it.
There's a reason you don't like it.
You just may not be able to articulate it yet.
You may need some help articulating it.
And that's just a skill building exercise
and good facilitators can kind of help with that.
Your other point about giving things ahead or people not being ready, I think it's always
helpful if somebody isn't ready to give feedback, not to force it, because then that's a recipe
for bullshit.
Because that's when, and I would always say this to my students, if you don't know what
you're going to say, slapping words on it because you feel like you have to say something
is the worst thing you can do.
Because that's the definition, the definition of bullshit.
Language that is not connected to reality.
Just language for the sake of language.
And so that ability to say, I'm having some feelings
about this here and I can't articulate them yet.
Give me some time.
So if you have to articulate the meaning,
that's when a good facilitator also can help.
OK, let me help you articulate it and start asking questions
to try to get at what that is.
And so those are a couple thoughts.
Was that helpful?
Did I address your...
Yeah.
Yes.
The strategies that you posted, do you feel they have to be tailored based on the experience
level of an individual if you're providing feedback to a junior artist or a senior artist,
or do you think it's abstract enough that it could work for anyone's experience level?
I think they're abstract enough to be universal.
This idea of simply, you know...
presenting the problem rather than just giving someone
a solution, that works across all levels.
And when I was a teacher, I was fortunate enough
to teach all levels.
I taught freshmen all the way up to graduate students.
And I did the same stuff with everybody.
And there are different levels of depth of discussion
we could have at different levels,
but the strategies underneath that were the same.
Was that helpful?
Yeah.
Ryan Locke from Abertay University in Scotland.
I'd be really interested in some advice from yourself based on the discussion we just had.
I'm really fascinated by this area in particular because I work in computer arts mostly
and I deal with students across multiple disciplines, whether it's concept design, 3D graphics or design, illustration.
There are quite a lot of things going on there.
And one of my main objectives with my third year group
in particular, so this is the year
before they do their final year, is
to develop a community of critique,
because it's me versus a lot of students.
Often I'm the single point for critique or feedback,
and I'm not always available or I'm busy.
There's probably a lot of other issues
there in terms of other classes and how busy they are,
blah, blah, blah, blah.
But that idea of fostering a community or preparing students for industry or even outside,
well it doesn't have to be industry, but do you have any advice in terms of your experience
in education and how you might help foster a better community of critique in students?
Yeah, I think part of it has to do with getting out of this idea that critique is bad.
It's something to be avoided.
It's so ironic.
Some place like RISD values itself on the fact that it's a great place to learn critique,
and it is.
I mean, RISD is an amazing school for learning critical thought.
It's the core of what they do.
But then they'll go and do weird things,
like they'll have this Crit Happens pillow that you sit on,
like making like, oh, there's mixed messages there, right?
Sending like, oh, it's this bad thing we should avoid,
you know, but then we're seeing,
and so that part of that is just distilling that culture
that this is a wonderful moment for us
to be together and work together.
It's about being a community
and working toward a common goal.
So getting the culture right is really helpful.
And then also making it so that you teach people the process rather than just giving
it to them.
So you're not in a situation where the teachers need it.
In an ideal world, you want to be teaching these students so they can go off in small
individual groups and do it themselves.
And when I was a teacher, that's what I would always focus on doing.
And so I would give them these strategies, and I would never run critiques where it was
me and them.
I would never run critiques.
We're like, okay, I'm gonna teach you how to critique
by showing you how to do it.
Because that's baloney, right?
That you just can't do, because that,
then you gotta learn by doing, right?
It's like virtual reality.
You gotta be in it to get it, right?
So coming up with strategies of ways of,
this essay I wrote has a lot of these in it too.
I'll try to find a way to make.
Yeah, I'll try to find a way to get this out and and but but the one of the strategies was you know going around
Is having everyone first describe?
Objective thing about what they saw you know it's red. It's plaster. It's you know it's big. It's five inches tall
It's that you know just something objective, so we start talking
No judgment, no deep thought.
We're just getting words to come out of our mouth.
We're kind of getting warmed up.
And then doing some rounds where you start to now describe your experience.
Oh gosh, it feels like it's going to fall to me.
Oh, it makes me scared.
Whatever.
Now you describe your experience.
It's just going around and just starting people...
So you come up with a formula.
First you do this, then you do this.
And now we go around and everyone starts to describe
a way in which they think it's not living up to its potential.
Or something.
So there's a strategy.
and then say, okay guys, now you know steps one, two, three
of this process, now use a small group,
go over and do it there,
and use a small group to do it over there.
So, okay.
Is that 5 or is we're done.
And so.
Was that somewhat helpful?
Yeah, no, I was fine.
I do some things already,
but like you've given me a lot of great ideas,
which is so important.
And I was wondering if I could maybe just grab 2 minutes with you after you can grab as many minutes with me as you'd like.
I'll be in the wrap up room afterwards.
I would love to talk with you more than anyone else that would like to have more talking.
Yeah, that would be wonderful so much.
Sure.
Hi.
I'm a 3D artist that is on a team of predominantly 2D artists.
And trying to get really good constructive feedback can be rather difficult.
I often find myself kind of talking about my process and going through what I'm doing and how I'm doing it.
I often don't find that feedback that I kind of need coming back my way.
So I guess in terms of your experience, how would you facilitate that conversation when...
that there's that kind of disconnect between like what you're trying to, the problems you're trying to solve and like
people's experience like that process. That's rough. Yeah, I think just really thinking through the strategy of like framing the critique
and really kind of starting to think through like what are the experiences that you can try to frame?
You know, just asking people how they're experiencing something or what they have, but you can kind of
you find a way to kind of frame it.
So you're not just putting it in front of them,
because they're going to be looking at it
from their point of view,
but you need to kind of get them to look at it
from your point of view, right?
And so you can start to, you know,
think of yourself as a teacher.
Like, you're going to be a 3D design teacher.
What are the principles of 3D design
that are important here?
and if they don't understand them, kind of helping them understand what they are
and then asking them if they're relevant to what's there.
But the underlying strategy there is trying to find some ways to kind of frame the critique.
That's kind of what I would go about it, but you're in a rough position.
Yeah, I often do that, but I find that it's often one-sided.
And I feel like I'm kind of just leading the critique
and it doesn't feel quite as back and forth as I would like.
Yeah, well, framing it is getting it going, but once it's framed well enough,
then hopefully they can start coming out.
But yeah, you're in a rough position with that.
Sorry, I may think of some other ideas.
Well, I appreciate it.
Thank you.
I'm a 3D artist, too, so I understand.
So if you're not thinking three-dimensionally
and you don't have the ability, it's
hard to be in that mindset if you don't.
But creating some mock-ups or creating some prototypes
that get at the three-dimensionality
and having them experience that might be helpful.
I don't know.
I'm just trying to throw some stuff out.
Awesome.
Thank you.
I think this will be the last question.
Hi, Aleem. I'm an effects artist.
I was wondering on your insight or your thoughts in the process of cross-disciplinary critiquing
with, like, say, designers or programmers or whoever,
in regards to assets that aren't quite done,
I feel like in our industry we have a lot of, like,
to show an asset for critique is almost to take it to final.
uh... and what challenges that brings to the
the emotional critiquing state
uh... and if you've ever
run into that or actually solve that in any way or have insight
yeah that's a really rough one too because you have people who aren't artists
they're looking at what's there and when people are artists are looking beyond it
they know
okay this is an unfinished asset
i know where it's going i can imagine it being done but someone who's not an artist
is gonna see what's there
and i think that's where framing can be really helpful too
if you kind of maybe have an image along with it okay
here's what this will look like in the end
And here's what it looks like now.
And so we're not really looking for feedback
about the materials, because the materials will get to there.
We're not looking for feedback about these specific aspects
of the effects, because they will get there.
But we are looking for feedback about x, y, and z.
So if you have some image that allows
them to get in their mind what it will look like,
that they can superimpose onto it,
then that might help to frame it.
Is that helpful?
OK, great.
Thank you all so much.
I'll be here for a few minutes, and then over there.
Thank you.