I'm like, I made Secret Hitler along with,
I co-designed it with Tommy Meranges,
and then we produced it with Max Temkin,
and then Max Schubert did our art,
so I'm not the only guy.
So Secret Hitler.
How many of you, raise your hands if you know the basic
idea of Secret Hitler, how it works.
OK, a lot of you.
And then keep your hand up if you know Avalon also.
Just raise your hand if you've also played Avalon, because I
referenced that a lot.
OK, so I'll just give you a real background real quick.
Secret Hitler is a social deduction game.
You can put your hand down.
No, thanks.
Secret Hitler is a social deduction game.
It's a hidden role game.
So you start the game.
Everyone gets a role.
You get to see it, you can't show it to anybody else.
And then on In Secret Hitler, there's two teams.
There's liberals and fascists.
It's 1930s Germany.
The liberals don't get to have any extra information,
but at the start of the game during the night phase,
the fascists open their eyes, they identify each other,
so they know who the bad guys are,
they know who the good guys are.
Hitler doesn't get to open his eyes in the bigger games,
but he puts his thumb up so his buddies know who he is.
And the liberals don't know shit.
Just like real life.
I'm a liberal.
No, anyway, so the way the game works,
every round there's a two-player government.
There's a president and chancellor.
President placard moves around the table clockwise
and then they nominate a chancellor.
So they're like a president, vice president,
running mate a little bit.
And then they get to enact a policy.
And that policy is either fascist or liberal.
There's a policy deck of 11 fascist cards,
six liberal cards, president draws three cards,
discards one face down, passes the other to the chancellor,
chancellor also discards one face down,
and then the last one gets played face up.
And that's the card that everyone else gets to see,
that's the card that gets enacted.
So the president gets the most information,
chancellor gets some information,
and everyone else only knows the card that comes out.
And then they judge the 2 based on whatever happened.
So the liberals won't pass 5 liberal policies to win the game.
The fascists want to pass 6 fascist policies to win the game.
And every time you pass a fascist policy,
president gets to do crazy shit
because fascism is all about like getting power for the government.
So as fascism goes along, it increases in danger.
And once the first 3 fascist policies have been played,
if you ever elect Hitler chancellor after that point,
the game immediately ends in a fascist victory
because Hitler kills the president,
burns down the Reichstag and becomes fear for life.
So that's the historically accurate way for fascists to win.
And then those two bullets, though, are the liberal antidote to Hitler.
If you pass a fascist policy on that bullet, you get to shoot somebody.
And if you shoot Hitler, fascists die with him.
Once those three fascist policies are out, it creates a really tense moment
where Hitler is trying to not die, but also trying to get into power.
So, okay, that's SecretHailer, that's how it works.
Now everyone knows how to play.
Great.
So, social justice games.
I'm not actually a board game guy.
It's funny, I've been coming to GDC for 10 years
making video games, and I finally make a board game,
and that's when they invite me to come talk.
And I don't, I'm not super into board games.
And so when I moved to Chicago a few years ago
and started hanging out with Cards Against Humanity guys,
and they got me into board games in a big way,
just hanging out with them, they're immersed in the culture.
And I got into Avalon.
I had played Werewolf before that,
so I knew kind of what social deduction was about,
but I hated Werewolf, Werewolf's a bad game.
But Avalon is beautiful and an amazing game.
And it really got me into the role-playing aspect of it,
which I thought was really, really cool.
I played D&D when I was a kid, but when you're playing D&D and you're trying to act like a dwarf with a beard and a huge axe and doing a weird voice and everyone else is just looking at you like you're an asshole, it's not a fun role-playing challenge for me.
But with Avalon...
you you're roleplaying is very very constrained if you're a bad player
anyway if you're a good player you're not roleplaying you're just trying to suss out who's good and who's bad
but the acting challenge of playing a bad character is so fun
uh... because it's so tightly constrained your actions are
are just throw this guy under the bus or claim that you didn't play that bad card
and it was really fun for me to try to get into that acting challenge
because i'm actually really like pretty introverted dude
and i don't uh...
lie to people or throw people under the bus in real life,
but when you're playing this game,
you can mess around with really negative social actions
and it's okay and you're still friends
at the end of the game.
So that's, I really fell in love with Avalon
and actually Tommy and I were playing Avalon.
for about a month and we kind of agree that it was mostly a perfect game
because it's so simple, there's so few moving parts that
but it creates this rich experience of everyone kind of arguing and you really get into deep
conversations with people and you really, you know, kind of get to know people really well through this game.
We thought it was kind of perfect and couldn't be improved on
and so as a challenge we were like, hey let's make a better one.
And we tried and you get to judge if we did or not.
So our early inspiration was really based on taking Avalon
and then expanding on the things that we thought were
cool about it, and maybe taking away the things that we
didn't like.
But the really initial early builds of it, the ideas that
we were tossing around were really pretty dry.
It was all really focused on mechanics.
And it wasn't until I watched Band of Brothers in like a
couple of years.
one sitting after we had given up on mechanics based approach that I started researching Hitler because Hitler is super interesting
Germany was relatively liberal country and he used the Democratic
system to turn it into a despotism, essentially, a totalitarian country.
I thought that was a really compelling, interesting, fertile ground for social deduction.
Using the democratic system against itself seemed like a compelling setting.
A lot of historical-based mechanics came directly out of that initial research.
Like the president-chancellor relationship, where the chancellor can betray the president.
that comes directly out of Hitler and Hindenburg,
and also the road to fascism,
the government getting more powerful
as more fascist policies came out of that historical,
slight Wikipedia research.
So the idea definitely came
from the historical setting of it.
So our design focus, and this is like me post-mortem
deciding what our design focus was a little bit,
but it was definitely focused on individual experiences
rather than creating a game that was like super balanced
or really accurate portrayal of history.
We wanted players who were playing the game
to be having really intense moments,
really personal moments and interactions with other players.
We wanted the drama to stay high throughout the whole game
and keep accelerating until the end of the game.
We didn't want it to slow down.
If one team got too far ahead and it just turned into kind of
a snowball, we didn't want the other players to feel like it
was kind of a foregone conclusion.
We wanted everyone to always feel like it was kind of on a
knife's edge.
And we wanted them to tell a really fun story every time
they played the game.
And it would come out a little bit differently each time.
And I didn't realize this until I was doing this talk,
but the game, when you're playing it, creates the
typical plot structure of rising action to the climax.
And the climax, this is the version for Secret Hitler.
but the whole game is the rising action.
Every time a fascist policy comes out, it gets more intense.
People get more suspicious and worried about what's going to happen to the government
until one side wins or the other side wins.
And in the end of the game, after it's over, everyone sticks around.
No one really leaves the table.
They keep drinking, they keep shouting about who was right, who was wrong.
And usually it's me, because I always am right.
And no one ever trusts me, even though I'm very good at this game.
So our path was definitely focused on two facets,
kind of the one-on-one drama of interpersonal interactions.
So we wanted to give a lot of moments
where people could betray each other.
And we also wanted to have the Hitler mechanic
be a personal decision.
So when you're president, you have,
and Hitler's active and can win the game.
you have to pick not Hitler and that's a very dramatic moment when especially
when you have no confirmed not Hitler's to pick from.
You have to pick out of this field of people, one of them is definitely Hitler
and will lose the game if you pick the wrong guy.
So it's a really tense moment for that person to go through.
But then we also want to focus on the dramatic tension throughout the whole game.
So Hitler is like this antagonist, shit I keep hitting the mic, Hitler is like this antagonist, he's like Jaws, he's kind of lurking in the darkness and he's always there, and as the game goes he gets more and more important to the story and it creates, it's a fun moment to try to, I don't know, shit.
The policy that we use if you're familiar with the game the policy that plays an important role
in shifting the balance of power between one team and the other team
and we also extend the climax. So I'm going to get to all those points later.
So the personal betrayal moments is the core of the game and that's the main thing that we took from Avalon.
I started playing Avalon and I really like the first mission, which is just a two-player mission.
So if you played Avalon, as you go, each mission gets larger in size and shrinks a little bit,
so the bad guys can kind of hide in the numbers.
But in that first mission, it's just you and one other person.
And when I started playing the game, the meta for our player group
had already resolved that, oh, the first mission is safe.
Like, you can't fail the first mission.
No one's ever going to fail that,
because it outs them immediately to the good player.
If you have a spy and a good player on that team,
you're never going to reveal yourself that quickly.
And so as kind of a dick, I wanted
to fail that initially, just to mess with their meta.
But also, I knew that if I went into that,
it would be a fun acting challenge for me.
I knew that I would have the rest of the game,
I would be fighting with this other person.
And when I did that the first time,
it was the best experience I had playing board games.
Because I knew what was happening,
and I knew that I had to act my ass off
for the rest of the game.
And it was way more intense and way more fun than just kind of like slowly playing and
biding my time. I really had to start, I started a conflict immediately and it was really engaging.
And I think it was fun for the other player too because she knew immediately that I had
betrayed her and that we were now in a fight and she had to fight for her life and profess
innocence for the rest of the game. So I thought that was really fun and I know it extended
that out to the entire game for Seeker Hitler. So every single round is that, has a potential
for that kind of interaction.
There's always going to be more for that direct betrayal which I think is really
fun and really is a part of why Secret Hiddler is great.
It also helps the Liberals
a little bit because every time you have a moment like that
where two players disagree, like in this diagram you have maybe A and B are in a
disagreement currently
and they're fighting over what they saw
and you've seen D and C have worked with A before and E and F have worked with B.
Now you get a lot of information to what the puzzle is.
And liberals need, they don't necessarily know who is right on that side,
but if they get another couple of interactions like that,
they sort of figure out the web of alliances that work in the game.
And so these direct one-on-one interactions create more information for the puzzle,
but you only get a few of them throughout the game.
Usually people just claim they drew three fascist cards when they do bad stuff.
But it's really fun to piece together the puzzle as a liberal.
So the other big thing that we wanted to take from Avalon,
but repurpose, because we thought it was strong but not necessarily perfect,
was the Avalon mechanic.
So in Resistance Avalon, Merlin is a character
who knows who all the bad guys are. He's on the good team,
but if he overplays his hand, he can get shot at the end of the game
and lose it for the good team.
We really like that he was a strong power for the for the good guys, but also
a vulnerability. But we didn't like that his death came at the end of the game.
So we wanted to invert that a little bit because it felt a little cheap. If you
only had like 3 players on your team, there's actually a good statistical
chance that he'll just get shot at random. And it feels a little cheap and
not very earned. So for Hitler, we inverted the concept and we took away
all this information.
And we also made him vulnerable throughout the whole game so that he can change the tide at any moment and it
Really ramped up the tension in the second half once he becomes active and he can die or get elected and win the game
for either team
It makes it more tense while the game still going on rather than kind of pulling the rug out of
under the good team after they've won.
And it also changes the dynamics of who you can trust.
It makes the game into kind of a two-act structure,
where in the first act, liberals and fascists
are just trying to get on the board,
trying to do some stuff, get some policies out,
and in the second half, liberals are locking it down,
and they have to figure out who is Hitler.
And if you've done too many liberal policies,
you actually look worse,
because you've been set up by the fascist team
to look like a good guy who's gonna get elected.
So, okay, those were the initial ideas
that we brought to the prototypes.
We took Avalon, we basically just took Avalon
and added that shit, and it was already really fun.
And how do we know it was fun?
So we were playtesting in the Cards Against Humanity office
and these guys were doing board games all day
and then we invited them to the conference room
and we bribed them with pizza
because every prototype is terrible.
and they would come and play for like another 2 hours and so they wouldn't
leave the office for like 10 hours and after the game is over they would stick
around and keep telling stories of what happened throughout the game and they
would love to regale you know fascist would talk about the close calls where
they almost got caught liberals would love to admit mistakes and there's
always one liberal who knew who all the bad guys were and that was me and no
one trust me.
But we had to figure out why it was working and Tommy and I took some time to
focus
down what our design was really doing well.
and we thought that it was focusing on personal conflicts and ramping up tension.
We weren't focusing on creating a really balanced game
or one that definitely was synchronized in actions.
We wanted one where everyone had options
and it felt like it was a story that was kind of going back and forth
and ended in a reasonable, interesting conclusion for everybody.
And the main way that we kept it interesting as we went was through the policy deck.
The policy deck was originally going to be just a way for fascists to hide bad actions
because in Avalon you have the increasing team size,
but we wanted to create that really fun two-player dynamic of president and chancellor throughout the whole game.
So in order for fascists to have a way to hide,
we needed to have them be able to blame it on a random deck.
And we were initially just going to have a static draw chance.
and we would replenish the deck after every round so it was only like a 30% chance or whatever to draw a liberal policy.
But what we found was that if you let it deplete itself,
and let, like, if one team gets ahead,
their cards come out of the deck too much,
it sets up a really interesting dramatic tension.
And so, like, you can have a board that looks like this,
where the liberals are way ahead,
and a newbie might be like,
oh, well, we only need one policy, this is gonna be easy.
You go back to the same values we trust,
and we'll get this last one out.
But in reality, the deck looks terrible,
and you're going to have a full liberal team
draw three fascist policies,
and that inevitably completely upsets the trust balance.
So this creates a really, really interesting
rubber banding a little bit
that lets both teams always feel like they have a chance.
So fascists won't see this and be like,
well, I guess the game's over, I'm just going to quit.
They will have that lie ready.
So when that fascist policy comes up,
they can jump on it and be like,
you guys did it, I know you had to play that fascist
and just create an upset balance
because fascists win when chaos takes over.
And so the deck is actually like the hardest thing we had to balance.
We started with 6 liberal cards and 10 fascist cards
and we were just like throwing numbers at the wall.
We didn't know what we were doing.
We knew we wanted 6 liberal policies
so that you could miss one policy and still win the game.
But as far as the number of fascist policies,
we had no idea what we were doing.
10 seemed reasonable and it was fun at the time.
But then we added 2 more policies just to make the numbers round
because that seemed like a good thing to do.
And we played a game, a playtest at the Red Line, which is a pub in Chicago.
And it was a terrible night. I played, I got liberal, I got liberal three times in a row.
And I had no idea what was going on. It was madness.
We lost every game. I don't even think it was close.
And I was so despondent by it that on the ride home...
after the game I thought that Secret Hitler might be just completely broken
or the policy deck was a bad idea in general
because I know that randomness has the potential to create bad streaks
and I thought that maybe it was inevitable
that people were going to have a terrible experience playing Secret Hitler.
But then we changed it to 6 to 11 and it was fine.
So I don't know why 6-11 is the good balance.
But sometimes, I mean, that's the value of playtest is you
try it out and you see what works.
And my brain wants to add that last fascist policy to make it
a nice, even square.
But this one works.
And it's just magic, and I'm not going
to question it anymore.
And it has all sorts of interesting issues.
Like once you've played the first five cards, there's two
left that you can never see, and you have
to reshuffle them.
Just a lot of weird, natural issues that make card counting
difficult and make the game more interesting.
So I have no idea why this works, but
it works really well.
So Hitler is the bad guy of our game. He's a very bad man. We don't want him to win.
And Hitler as an active threat is the most important part of the second act of the game.
The game really works in two acts.
As the action is slowly rising after each fascist policy, all of a sudden Hitler becomes active
and everyone locks down and has to figure out who's good and who's bad
because if you put the wrong guy in government you lose the game instantly.
And that's the main way that fascists win is by electing Hitler.
So maintaining that threat of Hitler as the bad guy
was a very important part of keeping the second half of the game interesting.
because liberals will do everything to try to circumvent
Hitler's power and and lockdown power within a small number of trusted players
and so we had to do a few things to keep that keep them reaching out to new
players
and always trying different new chancellors because that moment where you
elect someone chancellor
and at the table has to ask them are you Hitler and you wait for them to say yes
or no
is the most tense part of the game and we wanted them to have to do that a few times
because it's just it's fun to have to
have them shout in your face yes or say no in a relieving way.
So the ways we did that were presidential succession works as a natural way of like
eventually one of your confirmed not-Hitler chancellors will have to play as a president
and then you have to find someone else.
We also have the term limits which were put in place specifically to keep people from
going back to the well of trusted liberals each time.
So if you're the president or chancellor on the last round you can't be elected the next
round so you have to keep reaching out to new players.
And also the fascists usually have the assassination power because you have to play fascist policy
to be able to do it.
and they will often kill confirmed not-Hitlers in order to gain,
get another chance at putting Hitler on the chancellorship ticket.
So the final thing that we did to make sure, oh shit, I'm going so fast.
The final thing that we did to make sure that the game stayed interesting
up until the end of the game was to extend the runway.
with the veto power. So the veto power is really interesting
in that it gives liberals a last chance once the fifth
fascist policy has been played, they get an opportunity to throw away a triple
fascist draw.
Which is great for the liberals because if you get a full liberal team
it's like, oh dope, we can get rid of these cards, we don't have to lose.
keep going because we don't ever want the deck to win the game for the fascists.
We want the fascists to get in there.
But the problem is that now they have to pick a new team.
Those two players who are clearly liberal,
who just played or just got rid of three fascist cards,
they're unavailable now thanks to term limits.
So you have to once again go out into the wilderness and find new players
because we... and then you're almost always going to pick at least one fascist for that team.
And because that's way more fun to have a fascist actually screw over a player.
Because when you have, our dream game was that you get to the last possible veto
and you have a liberal president and a fascist chancellor and the president's like,
hey we can veto and the chancellor's like, no man, I'm going to win the game.
And we dreamt about that for like a month before we finally actually got to play it
because it's pretty rare but it's a lot of fun.
So we always wanted the game to focus on giving fascists a
chance to actually betray people.
We didn't want it to be a natural loss for liberals, and
we didn't want the liberals to just trip over themselves.
We want the fascists to get in the game and actually screw
people over.
That's the graph of the tension, once people realize
they can veto.
Okay, so the general takeaway that I want you to come from
with this talk is that I don't think that you can actually be
good at Secret Hitler.
We had a lot of people early on at BoardGameGeek telling us
that Avalon was way better because it's more
deterministic and the randomness of Secret Hitler
makes it impossible to win.
And I at first disagreed and was angry,
but now I actually kind of agree because I don't think
that you can be good because the game is so random
and there's so much self-balancing going on.
that if you get too far ahead you're eventually going to get rubber banded
back
uh... and that almost every time you play the game it conforms to this
plot structure which i just think is more interesting though and that's that's
the real take away is that i don't think being good at secret hitler is important
uh... i think as long as people play the game and they have fun and they have a
really engaging experience and they come away with this
interesting story of twists and turns and betrayals
all that that's all that matters is the experience whether or not you have a
good win ratio is not interesting we thought about how could you do it
secret or tournament and I don't think it's possible one because of the teams
are in balance but to it's just
we focus on creating interesting experiences for you go through
I'm not necessarily a chess like deterministic game
and that's why I think it's good
a secret and that's all I got
We have a lot of time for questions, because I totally
ran through that.
So if anybody has any, I'm happy to answer.
So I'm curious, since you guys obviously built the game and
worked on the rules, if you encountered this in play
testing, but we've seen a lot, especially with new players.
the person explaining the rules always definitely organically seems to be like
the most trustworthy even though they're often not yeah, and is that something
that you felt was a problem with the matter or something you just was like
this is kind of cool let's run with it not try to fix it.
I I think it's inevitable I do think that okay, I actually had that it
covered in the talk a little bit, but I do think you can be good at secret
Hitler in that you know the probabilities a little bit you know how
the game works and I played at Pax when we were initially prototyping it.
and I play like 30 games and I only lost one because it was just playing with new
players. So that's definitely true and it's definitely an issue and it's
especially true for me like I know that better than everyone else because I can
just pull out the I made this game
excuse.
But I don't know if it's a problem or not. I don't know if that's solvable.
I didn't try to solve it.
we just tried to make the rules as clear as possible.
And we have the video explaining the rules,
so we're hoping that people get it to speed quickly.
And I think after two or three games,
people kind of glom onto the idea well enough
that they know what kind of lies they can make
and what kind of lies they can't make.
Yeah, that kind of fades when you have a group
that plays together for a little bit.
It seems like with new players,
it's always the case that people gravitate
towards trusting the guy that explains.
And we were playing at the Cards office,
so we had tons of board game interested people to play with.
And so we definitely got tunnel vision.
We were focusing on experience level.
play, first and foremost, the people at the office
have played hundreds of times, so I definitely
didn't think too much about the new player experience.
Cool, thanks.
Hi, thanks for all the fun.
Thanks.
I read an article that you sent a copy of the game
to the US senators.
Yeah.
Is it true, and have you heard back?
No, Max is kinda tied in with the Democratic,
he worked for Obama's campaign,
so he has been hearing some stuff.
I've just been reading on Slack while at GDC,
because we put that out on Thursday,
so they haven't gotten the packages yet as far as I know.
But yeah, we'll see, I don't know.
Great, thank you.
It's been crazy, thanks.
So I actually really like the idea that you cannot be really good at Secret Hiddler so that the experience is more...
It's nice for my ego too, like I feel very good saying that.
But what I'm wondering about is that you mentioned that the game self-balances and so on and so forth.
Is there a relatively equal win ratio for...
It is, yeah. Actually we put out the print and play during the Kickstarter
and we asked for people to reply back.
telling us who won, how often they won,
how often they played, and who won.
And we found out that early games,
Hitler gets killed sometimes,
but then after really early on,
Hitler never gets killed again,
after you've played like two times,
because Hitler figures out he should shut the hell up.
And then...
And then we also found that it's a really even balance.
But I do think that some groups will swing fascist
or liberal depending on what the individual skills are.
So I think overall, like worldwide, it's pretty balanced,
but that might not be true for your specific game group.
But I don't really know.
And we also don't care.
Like if you're having fun, I don't really care who wins.
I clearly want the liberals to win, but.
Okay, thanks.
Thanks.
Hey, so this is completely hypothetical, but you mentioned you've done a lot of game design in the computer or, you know, electronic space.
Yeah.
Thinking about games with secret or hidden roles, it feels like a critical component of that is the in-person interaction.
Totally.
If you wanted to translate that experience into a computer game sort of, you know, remote interaction multiplayer situation,
what do you think are the critical things you would need to think about to make that work?
Well, it's really, really tough.
Honestly, there are like three different versions of Seeker Hitler that you can play online.
One is on Tabletop Simulator.
It's like the most popular thing on Tabletop Simulator right now.
And it's annoying because it's terrible to play without facial recognition.
Like, reading another player is a huge part of social deduction.
I think that you can get away with other forms of information in Seeker Hitler,
but like, I don't even know why you play that.
So we don't like support that or want to do that.
And I guess there's VR, the eye tracking stuff that's coming
out, maybe some facial recognition stuff.
But without that face, I don't want to play it.
I'm thinking less about translating Secret Hitler into
a video game and more about designing a game specifically
to support that kind of hidden role stuff.
Sure.
Yeah, well you've got to get away on a lot of voice stuff.
You could definitely design a game around it, I'm sure.
Like there are plenty of games that are about hidden
identities online.
But I haven't played a whole lot.
Thanks.
Sorry.
Hi, this is a question about matching theme to mechanics.
Sure.
So imagine it's April 2016
and you're making a game called Secret Trump.
and there are six Republican nominees,
but no one knows which one is the Donald Trump.
I think we all knew who the Donald Trump was,
and everybody knew who Hitler was.
So what's your justification for doing a hidden,
nasty person in a political intrigue context?
So the metaphor is that like you...
People right now are saying,
well, don't say Trump is like Hitler.
Hitler put people in concentration camps
and Trump hasn't done that yet.
Well, clearly we would like to identify Hitler
before he puts people in concentration camps
is what I feel like.
So clearly you're not gonna know Hitler
because he's named Adolf Hitler.
Like the next one's not gonna be named Adolf Hitler.
So the metaphor is like.
supposed to be a little more fluid than that.
In that this game is really more about identifying liars
and figuring out who is bullshitting you
and just trying to tell you what you want to hear.
And that's what we hope people get from it,
is to be a little more skeptical
about the political process.
Like at the highest level,
that's what I want people to take.
And I don't expect us to change the world or anything.
cool so that was an awesome talk thank you very much
uh... i remember when secret hitler came out it just exploded onto the scene and
everybody who's playing board games is like
you've absolutely got to play this game
was any kind of deliberate marketing
strategy that you used to get it out
uh... cars against humanity
facebook page
that we've got if you don't know Max Temkin is a co-creator country's
humanity and he's a friend of mine and he wanted to help me make the game.
And so he used his might and like the senator, the sending games to senators
like that's we've got a ton of press in the past week from that.
And that's all Max is a genius.
Like he put
Super Bowl ad was just a potato that said advertisement on it. So like he's crazy and comes up with insane ideas and stunts
So that's I don't have it. Nobody. I can't reproduce Max Temkin for everyone else. Can I ask one quick follow-up?
Yeah, she's the print and play. Do you think that helped because yeah
I thought there was lots of print and play then people like I've got to buy this game
Yeah, I think it's just good for spread.
Like, it's a terrible way to play,
and the components for the full game are so nice
that I feel like it's an obvious upsell.
Like, you get real wooden placards.
They're so fun to throw around at people.
So I think it lets the game spread,
and like, Cards Against Humanity did that too,
and they're hugely successful,
so I don't think it cuts into our sales at all.
I think it just spreads the word.
Cool, cheers. Thanks.
Yeah, thanks for sharing.
It's really cool to see what went on behind the scenes.
The process of making this game, you say it's the first board game you've made?
Yeah.
I'm curious about what did you discover about yourself and in the process of this game,
and what are you going to do next?
It was real natural.
the game design concepts were
I just use the same process I use in video games, but
the turnaround was just a day instead of
like a week or a month to try something out, like
we would play test it, people would tell us what the shit
and we're using a ton of, like, Cards Against Mania
has published a bunch of games, so we would just
steal games from the shelf and like
repurpose their components for our components.
And so like the turnaround on changing an idea was so quick.
It was very similar to developing a video game in process,
but it was just so much faster
that we got it done really, really quickly.
Like it was a month and we had a really solid game.
So yeah, I don't know if I wanna make another board game.
I haven't had any good ideas.
So that's kind of the key for me.
I'm messing with VR now, we'll see.
So there was a question earlier about what the senators did,
and Max had tweeted about it just like literally minutes
before you started your talk.
Yeah, I saw that.
Yeah, it was like,
a pitted staffers against one another
on both sides of the aisle
over who would get to keep their copy.
Yeah, I don't know if that means
they got the packages already,
because a lot of people were telling us
they don't even open their packages,
and so we'll probably just get them all back,
which is like, that's fine with me.
We've got a ton of press,
and we get our gains back.
That's free press, right?
But yeah, it seems like he has connections on the hill,
so he'll actually know before anybody else.
Yeah, really well done.
The production quality is incredible.
Thank you.
Yeah, we're really happy with it.
Hello.
Thank you for your talk.
It was very interesting.
Thank you.
We both agree that I think the fun is the most important factor.
So did you maybe spend more time on balancing fun
instead of balancing the game?
Yeah.
I probably ran through this in the talk too quickly,
but our focus was, Tommy and I sat down,
we were like, what are we gonna focus on?
And it's clearly high tension moments,
like creating moments where you have to make
a really difficult decision,
and you have a little bit of information on each side,
but you don't know which way to go.
Yeah, I mean, because I think for me personally,
I think playing the,
fascist that is maybe more interesting because you can create all the chaos.
I think it's more interesting for new players because lying is just immediately fun,
but I think it's really satisfying to play as a liberal too,
just because the puzzle is kind of solvable.
Like it's almost, you almost have enough information to put it together
and I feel really good when I do that.
Thank you very much.
Thanks.
Cool.
Alright, that seems like it's it.
Thanks everybody.