And I suffer from obsessive compulsive disorder as well as depression.
Now, I don't know how many people identified as OCD.
Sometimes people say,
Oh, I just got the Pokemon game and I gotta get all the Pokemons
or I'm not gonna be happy or something.
That's not really OCD.
It's not just being anal retentive. It's a dark and troubling illness and
It's been a real struggle for me. I have a clinical diagnosis for both
I've seen a therapist and have been for over 10 years and
In all my therapy, I've discovered. I don't think there's a cure. I'm never gonna be
fixed. But therapy helps with gaining tools to deal with my illness. And I was dealing
with it pretty well before I started 24 karat games, and not so much during the development
of retrograde.
So, a little bit about Retrograde.
We released last August on PlayStation 3.
We spent about four years on the PlayStation 3 version.
We just released a PC port on Steam last week,
and I did that basically by myself,
part-time for six months.
The team was roughly three.
I did the game design and gameplay programming.
Justin Wilder did the engine, special effects, and tools.
We worked with art contractors for the project.
But we had trouble finding a good match
until about the latter half of the project,
when we started working with Joe Grabowski.
And then we contracted him full time
for the remainder of the project.
On average, I worked about 80 hours a week
for the four years of the PlayStation 3 version.
The game has about three quarters of a million lines of code.
Let me just let that sink in.
Three quarters of a million lines of code, and there's two programmers.
That's insane.
According to the Game Developer Magazine,
the post-mortem of LittleBigPlanet,
they said they had about half a million lines of code
and 37 developers.
So lines of code is difficult to measure,
and it's hard to compare.
And it depends on the standards used.
We used Code Analyzer.
And the actual number is not really important.
I'm not trying to say I'm better than you.
I have so many lines of code.
In fact, it's been a bit of a curse.
The thing that's significant about it is that we had a huge project.
Why did we have so many lines of code?
I wish I knew.
But no, we tried to create a reusable engine that
would be modular and support different projects.
And all this adds complexity.
So 46% of the code was the engine in quotation fingers.
Because really, it's just a game, right?
What is the engine?
It's not like we're selling it, you know, Unreal,
retrograde, whatever, no.
38% is the game-specific code, at least in our minds,
and 16% was the tools,
but they shared a lot of engine components.
We had a good amount of tools.
There are several different features
that had quite a bit of lines of code
when we were trying to do procedural art.
We had these animated signs for the menus,
the Octaboard boss, which I'll talk more about later,
and this procedural city background.
And each of those things
had 5,000 lines of code by themselves.
So when we first started 24K Games, we didn't plan on
self-funding a project.
We just started working on a demo.
The idea was we were going to pitch ourselves to publishers.
Unfortunately for us, the economy soon crashed,
right after we started 24Karat,
and game projects were getting canceled left and right,
so it seemed unlikely we could get a gig.
We decided to start self-funding a small project
targeting Xbox Live and PlayStation Network,
and we thought we could do it in 6 to 12 months.
Seems like a reoccurring theme in the other IGS talks.
But we figured that our project might not be a big money winner,
but we can make a name for ourselves as a company,
as a quality developer.
So the concept of Retrograde is that you're playing a game backwards
to the beat of the music.
So it looks like a side-scrolling shooter,
but it's actually a rhythm game.
We were doing our own indie project,
so we wanted to do something interesting and fun that would stand out.
The Xbox Live and PlayStation Network space way back in 2008
was really not as competitive as it was now.
We thought that even with a simple design,
we were in good shape relative to the other games
on the market at that time.
We saw our main competition as Boom Boom Rocket.
And I'm not sure if anyone even remembers Boom Boom Rocket.
But I mean, it was an enjoyable rhythm game,
but it was very small in scope.
So after about a month and a half of work on Retrograde,
we submitted our demo to IGF in October,
and we were very fortunate to be nominated
for excellence in design and excellence in audio.
We lost our artist co-founder at the beginning of 2009
since he couldn't afford to self-fund the game.
At the IGF, it was really nice, because Sony came around,
and they were interested in getting us on PlayStation Network,
which we were really excited about,
because we wanted to make a console game.
But at this point, the bar for console indie games
had really been raised by Braid and Castle Crashers,
which came out after we started 24Karat.
We scrapped our schedule completely
and wanted to try something more ambitious.
Big mistake.
We originally designed the game's graphics so we could
scale down to mobile, but now we're on PlayStation 3, so we
wanted to redo our art style to take advantage of its
graphical horsepower.
So by October of 2009, we finished the gameplay pattern
for all 10 levels.
The art wasn't really where we wanted it, and we were having
trouble finding a good contractor.
We decided to do another pass completely on the music
and make it better and design it,
the music in conjunction with the gameplay patterns.
And we were adding more complicated bosses,
a new player and enemy fire types.
So Retrograde became like a spoiled child
and I couldn't say no to it.
Things changed in 2009 when I met my wife, Joanne.
It was during a lull in the project.
So I was only working 60 hours a week.
Unfortunately, after a few months, I felt the pressure on retrograde again,
and I resumed working 80 hours a week and spending less time with Joanne.
In 2010, we spent a lot of time on procedural art generation,
since Justin and I, the founders, lacked artistic talent,
and we had difficulty finding good contractors.
We had a pseudo-realistic art style, which really makes procedural generation
difficult.
It's a lot harder than something abstract.
We had an obsessive attention to detail, which really hurt us.
At this point, we were already in perpetual crunch.
We wanted to get the game out as soon as possible,
since we were burning through our savings.
But we never looked for ways to simplify the game
or shorten development time,
which, obviously, would have been a good idea.
So this is a video of our procedural cityscape, which I talked about before.
The buildings have little lights on the windows, and they go on and off based on time of day.
So during night there's more windows on, and see now most of the windows are off,
and then we have the lens flare and the sunrise.
Oops, wrong button.
So, in 2010, I knew I wanted to marry Joanne.
When she was visiting her family in the Philippines,
I made a co-op video game to propose to her.
I basically placed the wedding ring
in a battery pack of the controller,
and then I sort of tricked her into playing it,
because I'm like, oh, I'm playing this IGF game,
and it's co-ops, I really need your help playing it.
And then at the end of the game, I put in a fake message
saying like, hey, you know, player two out of batteries.
Luckily, she didn't know what the Xbox battery icon
looked like, so I just had some.
in there. Anyway, I got down on one knee to fiddle with the USB cable and I told
her to look at the batteries and so she popped it out and found the ring. So
fortunately she said yes, although I did program in a response for no. It's
pretty cool.
There's actually, I invented a pixel particle system, so there's just like tears streaming down,
but it's all pixels aligned to the grid, so...
I recorded her reaction too with a webcam, and I put it up on YouTube, and you can find it,
and I think it's pretty cool, I don't know, and I think I put up the losing crying as well.
But the bad part is because of my financial investment
in retrograde, I couldn't afford a nice wedding.
Joann was very understanding, and we
decided to just get married right away without a ceremony
and delay our church wedding until I finished retrograde.
Or at least that was the plan.
So in 2011, my motto was release or die trying.
I spent a lot of time on detailed animations
for the bosses and complicated attacks and behavior.
So this is the Octoborg boss I mentioned earlier
that's 5,000 lines of code.
He has all sorts of procedural attacks and animations
and complications.
We also redesigned our entire pipeline at this point,
so the artist could animate the backgrounds as a Maya scene,
and then we export all the keyframes for the objects.
And so this video is also a good example of that.
You can see all the crazy animated stuff.
As the year progressed, I felt like we could finish by the end of the year,
but we'd be in the holiday season, which is a bad time to release for an indie game,
so we might as well spend extra time on it.
Of course, this is after three years, over three years of development.
I was really terrified to release the game for fear of failure.
I felt like the more I worked on it, the better the game was,
which would increase our chances for success.
However, the longer development meant it was a bigger risk,
which made me even more terrified to release.
In the back of our minds, I think we really knew
the game would never be profitable for the amount of time we put into it,
but we never changed the way we developed, despite that.
So Joanne wanted our church wedding in fall of 2011.
And even earlier in the year, I was beginning
to think that I might not finish retrograde before then,
which of course makes things very difficult.
I managed to pick up some work on the side to help make ends meet and pay for a church
wedding, but I didn't put retrograde on hold, so I doubled my workload, which of course
meant even less time with my wife.
For our wedding celebration, I only took off Friday, Saturday, and Sunday, and I think
I actually worked a half day on that Friday.
I made so many personal sacrifices for Retrograde, I felt like I had to make the game amazing
to justify those, which really compelled me to keep working hard on it, even if it was
my swan song.
So at the beginning of 2012, I was really depressed.
It didn't feel like the end would ever be in sight.
I felt like I'd be working on it forever, and I wanted to quit game development completely.
The only reason I kept working on Retrograde was because I felt an obligation to the fans
who played the game at PAX, IGF, and IndieCade, and who were really looking forward to its
release.
Even still, we refused to make compromises to get the game out of the door earlier.
For example, we ran out of memory, and instead of downsampling textures or having loading
screens, we redesigned the engine to support streaming.
We also had unnecessary polish.
We created the challenge mode map, which you saw at the beginning of the video,
which is like Super Mario World and has secret passages.
We added alternate ships with characters from other indie games,
like Octodance, Super Meat Boy.
And we have a DJ deck-based music player, which on PlayStation 3
is actually controllable with the DJ Hero controllers.
And then we have.
unlockable concept art, cheats, and more than I can even list.
So for my wife's 2012 spring break,
she wanted to go on a trip with me.
She works for the LA school system,
so she likes to do something fun when she's off.
And so her original plan was a night at a bed and breakfast.
Of course, one evening at a bed and breakfast doesn't seem like a big deal,
but it was right before PAX East,
and we were nearing release, at least in my mind,
so I was really noncommittal.
She ended up settling for an entire day out,
and eating out, and going to museums,
and these are just things we always wanted to do,
but never got a chance to because of my work schedule.
At the end of the day, she was so happy,
and she thanked me for such an amazing day.
At that point, I realized, what have I become?
I was not the person I wanted to be.
I never imagined that I'd be the type
of husband who would ignore his wife to work all the time.
It's definitely not how I pictured my married life.
So we finally felt like we did everything we could to make the game successful,
and submitted it at the end of June.
The reviews were good.
We had an average of 80% on gamerankings.com.
The main complaint in the reviews were that there's only 10 songs, which
honestly is one of the better complaints you can have.
I want more.
But given the obsessive level of detail we had, there was no way we could afford to do any more content in a reasonable time frame, nor could we afford to keep funding development.
So this is the final feature list of Retrograde.
We did 1080p, 60 frames a second with antialias,
and someone at Sony thought that was a PlayStation 3 first.
We had dynamic lighting and shadows,
potential visibility set generator for object culling,
background streaming for all data, blah, blah, and so on,
and so on, and so on, and so on.
Now, with all that applause, you'd think that that was actually an accomplishment,
but none of that actually helped sales.
I think, actually, we may have sold less copies of the game
than there are people in this room here.
I'm kidding, but not by much.
So, the game went on sale August 21st, and, as I said,
the sales fell dramatically short of our relatively modest expectations.
I'm honestly too embarrassed to show the y-axis on the graph,
but trust me that even those peaks are low.
So the initial sales trade off quickly, and we did two sales.
This is just the PlayStation Network data we launched last week on Steam,
so I don't have fancy graphs for that.
But, I mean, the sales were at a larger discount,
and they moved more units than launch, but didn't make as much money.
But why didn't the game sell?
I wish I knew.
Any business endeavor is a risk, and of course they don't all pay off.
I mean, certainly the Kickstarter, 30%, only 30% get their funding.
I mean, for Retrograde, we didn't get a huge amount of press.
I'm surprised you people are here.
No one's even heard of the game.
But anyway, given our awards and showing off the game at PAX year after year, I thought
we would do much better.
So what did I learn?
It's really tough to come up with things
because it still hurts to think about.
When I do think about it, I have obsessive thoughts
about how I'm a failure and a bad game developer
and everything is my fault.
And honestly, those thoughts really ring true,
which makes them very difficult to block out.
However, there are several lessons that are fairly apparent.
Don't compete where you can't.
We spent a huge amount of time on our 3D rendering tech
and all those bullet points and graphical polish,
but we can't compete with AAA games and big studios
on 3D graphics quality, so it was really a bad idea to try.
We spent so much time on graphics,
both from the content side and the tech side.
Will this feature increase sales?
When creating something out of love, it's a bad question to ask.
It doesn't feel right.
However, if you have to make money off a project
to maintain the life you want to live,
it's something you should think about.
I'm not recommending that you compromise your vision
based on what you think will sell.
I think that's a terrible idea.
But I think asking yourself that question
gives you an important perspective.
At the very least, you can ask for feature X.
What is the net impact on the player's experience?
These questions are a good sanity check for how you should be spending your development
time.
We lost sight of this earlier in development because we wanted to make the game we never
got a chance to at other studios because we always had these really tight deadlines.
So this is our in-game concept art viewer, which has fancy pixel shader transition effects
and streaming JPEG decompression.
probably a poor use of our time.
Focusing our efforts on creating gameplay content instead of the visuals would have
allowed us to release sooner and been a better game overall.
Although I did the game design and gameplay programming, I spent much more time on graphics
and procedural animation and effects.
So this is an image from our Skydome system.
And so how it works is it projects frustums
on the sky sphere and then generates clipped geometry.
The idea is then the clipped geometry
is rendered with decals tied into the environment map.
And then it's composited in the shape pixel shader
with multi-texturing because we wanted to reduce fill rate.
Because then we basically only have to draw the sky sphere once,
and we don't have to draw separate geometry for the cards.
I spent about a month on it.
Really, we should have just gotten an artist to make more cube maps,
or been content with less details.
I mean, I don't know if you noticed the sky domes in the previous videos,
but I'm betting not.
I really should have been making more content, more songs for the actual game, making the
game.
Live the life you want to live.
Even if Retrograde were successful, I'm not sure all the sacrifices I made would have
been worth it.
The development of the game was quite frankly miserable,
and it put a huge strain on my marriage right as it was beginning.
I'm now trying to work 40 hours a week,
and I quite honestly feel like I'm getting to know my wife for the first time,
which is pathetic and sad.
I feel immensely guilty for putting her through the development of Retrograde,
and while she was very supportive and patient,
that wasn't something she should have had to put up with.
So, this is more of the Mobius proposal, and I did all the art, programming, music, and
everything, and that worked pretty well.
It's not the best looking game, as you can tell, but I managed to come up with an art
style that I could deliver on with my limited 3D modeling skills.
Unfortunately, in Retrograde, we didn't get the people we needed, or designed for the
people we had.
We lost our artist early on and had little success
finding a contractor that could create the content we wanted.
We should have switched the art style to be more abstract
and then committed to procedural graphics.
We ended up building the tech to do completely artist-driven content,
but it was after we already wasted a lot of time
trying to do these pseudo-realistic graphics procedurally.
Well, duh.
I'm sure you're all saying these mistakes seem obvious.
Why is that guy even up here?
He doesn't know what he's talking about.
Well, the real question is, why did we fall down this path?
And I have a few ideas.
I don't think AAA development methodologies adapt well
on the small scale.
I worked on a number of projects at supposed AAA studios,
you know, doing the big budget titles.
And I thought, oh man, I'm going to kick ass as an indie
because I have all this experience.
But like.
I don't think the mindset was right.
So this is a directory map of our insane code base.
We built out all these systems and modules to create this engine
that was supposed to be used for future games,
but honestly we probably won't use the engine again
because the game was unsuccessful,
and really I'm trying to focus now on creating games
that are easier to make content for.
So all of this effort was a waste.
We really should have focused on the minimum effort to get this project done.
If we succeeded, then we should have started worrying about the next one.
It sounds silly to say don't plan for the long term,
but if you don't know if there is a long term, it makes a lot of sense.
So polish matters.
I think most successful games deliver a really polished experience.
And we recognize the importance of polish, but we went way overboard.
So this is a video of the final boss.
The iris on his eye is hinged like a proper mechanical iris.
But of course you can't tell because it's like 10 pixels, even at 1080p.
He makes a number of expressions throughout the boss battle.
I thought they gave the boss some personality, but no one has ever mentioned these animations
in any review or fan tweets.
I'm really betting no one ever noticed.
Why did we go so overboard?
I think partially because it was our baby, partially because we completely lost sight
of the business aspect, and we really felt like making a great game was the key to success,
but that isn't enough anymore.
We never re-evaluated our decisions.
When we started going down an avenue,
that was how we saw the game.
We never took a step back to try and figure out
what we could achieve the same gameplay in an easier way.
In hindsight, I wish we would have made the game in 2D.
I think it would have looked better
and finished way earlier.
We began building 3D tech because...
We felt like we had a lot of computer graphic skills,
and we could differentiate ourselves from other indies.
But once we decided on Retrograde,
we never stopped and said, hey, the game's in 2D.
Why don't we make it in 2D?
Instead, we decided to do 1080p, 60 frames a second
with anti-aliasing instead of 720p like everyone else.
It required a ton of optimization and engine work
to pull off.
It contributed to our enormous code base, which, of course,
makes porting more daunting.
We get a lot of requests for a Vita port, but like, bringing the game to any new platform
is very difficult because of the immense code base and its complexity.
So what's next?
Justin Wilder, the other remaining founder of 24K Games, left and got a full-time gig.
I'm still trying to find balance in my life.
I don't want to neglect my responsibilities to my family.
I want to work reasonable hours and spend time with my wife.
And realistically, I need to start getting paid for work.
I'm hoping to do another indie game and apply the lessons I've learned,
but I'm not sure I can afford to.
Retrograde has not been profitable, and perhaps there's hope on PC, but...
I've kind of lost my confidence.
And, you know, certainly getting money for a project
at the beginning is tricky, and I took lots of notes
at the Kickstarter presentation, but hopefully I'll be able
to continue living my dream of being an indie developer.
But I, it may not be possible to balance my life
and have the career I want, which.
is unfortunate, but that just may be in the cards for me.
So hopefully that's not.
Fingers crossed.
So thank you for listening.
I really appreciate your time.
I hope you found this helpful.
Does anyone have any questions?
I have time.
So.
Does that work?
Sorry.
Sorry to interrupt, but I have an announcement to make.
It will be short.
When you started the conference, most people didn't
leave the room.
So if you could please let us scan your badges on your way
out, so you can receive the survey and fill it up.
It's important to us and to the speaker, too.
So please, there will be three exits, and you will be asked
to have your badges scanned.
So that's it.
Now you can go back to the questions.
So we can do questions or no?
Okay, cool, questions, go for it.
First off, thank you so much.
That was really raw and intense and I don't know about everybody else, but that was, I
really appreciate you being that honest and frank about that.
I, uh, my Steam login doesn't work for some reason.
I was just about to buy the game right now, but I assure you when I get home I'll be buying
the game on Steam, because there's no question.
I played it at all the different PAXs and things.
I really appreciated when you guys did the shirt promo.
I still have mine.
But I guess what I want to say, I just interviewed Andy Schatz, who's been working on Monaco now for three and a half years,
and he had a lot of similar things, a lot of, this should have been simpler, I should, but he wanted a lot of ownership,
and I think what you're talking about is not isolated, I think a lot of developers in the indie space want to own the code,
want to, had AAA experience and moved on, so...
I guess I just appreciate your specific insight and just want to let you know at the very least someone else I talked to
Had a very similar raw experience of dealing with the new marriage while making a game and all that sort of stuff
You're not alone out there. Keep it up
I hope that the next project you have is that perfect balance of your creativity and getting paid. Thanks again
Well, thank you very much
Thanks a third time
So that gigantic code base that you're probably never going to use, is that headed to the
graveyard or would you consider sharing?
Honestly, I don't think I would wish it on anyone because, like, it's, I mean, we did
some really unique technical stuff that's very applicable to retrograde.
So if you want to make a game exactly like retrograde...
then, well, it's still incredibly complicated,
but it'll do retrograde really well.
But, like, anything else, I mean, like,
I don't think it's really helpful to anyone, unfortunately.
Hey, the game looked really great.
I've played before and it was really awesome.
And I know you took it to PAX and you got feedback on it.
I was just wondering at any point,
did you consider bringing a producer on?
Like, you know, maintaining control and everything yourself,
but I know you got play testing
and you would have gotten feedback from that
as to what people wanted.
I was wondering if you'd ever consider,
or if you consider in the future bringing...
bringing an external producer on or someone you knew
or some friend to just sanity check the sort of stuff
that I just know I find it really handy in my stuff
to get other people to come and tell me
that I really shouldn't be spending ages on this feature
that no one's gonna see.
Well, I mean, it's tough because we wanted
to make the game for ourselves.
We wanted to do everything the way we wanted
because at studios, I don't know how many people,
has anyone worked at like a AAA studio
or worked for someone else?
Show of hands.
How many people worked there, had a bad decision,
forced down their throats, and there was nothing
they could do about it?
So I would have expected a few more hands,
but you guys are lucky.
But I mean, it's a lot of times, you know,
people say this is the way we're doing it.
their reasoning may not make sense to you,
it may not make sense at all,
but you just have to deal with it.
And so with retrograde, we're like, yes,
we're free of the bonds, we're free of the shackles,
but then we wasted our freedom on.
obsessing on all these details. So, no, it never entered into our heads that we should
bring anyone else on, that we should consult people. It was just like, this is our baby,
this is what we have to do. We need to finish it, and we need to finish it our way. Which
is stupid, if you didn't catch the gist of the talk.
Uh, hi, I wanted to say thanks, uh, for sharing and for, uh, to provide some context, I, uh, also suffer from severe OCD, and I have that regular struggle when I'm making a game that I'll, I'll know I'm spending way too much time on a feature that no one else is gonna care about or even notice.
And so it's great to just know that someone else is out there who struggles with that same thing.
And as far as the question goes, I wonder, moving forward, since it is a continuing struggle,
how you feel you are going to learn from that experience and approach finding that balance in a new way,
now that you have that behind you?
Well, I mean, certainly...
I mean, it's tough. It's a struggle. I, I think everything in life is a struggle, right?
It's not just me with obsessive compulsive disorder. It's not just certain people with
problems. Everyone struggles with development. Game development is hard. And certainly, if
you listen to any talks today, I think you would get that message. But I think with all
your experience and every time you do it, you know, you.
take something from it, and certainly I've taken a lot from it, like, you know, I have to be
hypervigilant that I'm not wasting time. And, you know, it's really tough, because polish matters.
You know, sometimes those details really make the difference between, you know, a 90 or an 80, and
I can't say I have a formula, but certainly I at least have some perspective that doing
things that no one will ever notice is probably not a good usage of time.
So I hope that answers your question.
I wish I had better answers than that.
Thanks.
Okay, last question, but I'll be out in the hall if anyone wants to ask more.
Quick question.
What happened to your hat?
Well, so, the story behind that is one of the things with 24KaratGames is I tried to do branding.
So I tried to dress crazy. I had like a gold miners hat with a light on it.
And then, you know, I would do all these events in this gold miner persona.
But like...
Part of the problem is 24 karat games is sort of dead, because it's just me.
So like, I mean, even moving forward, I don't know if I can create games as 24 karat games
because I don't have 100% ownership in the company.
So I may have to retire the poor miner.
But also, I mean, besides getting the right color shirt for the video recording, which
they're very specific about, I wanted to give this talk as myself, if that makes any sense.
I don't know.
I mean, certainly when I did the minor thing, I tried to have this very positive, you know,
buyer game, it's great, I'm a salesman, which takes a lot of energy.
I don't know, maybe it's just me, but like, oh my gosh, like, PAX and doing that salesman
thing.
Killer!
I'm just so drained, like, every day.
Like, oh my gosh.
So this is me, the regular me.
Hopefully, hopefully I can still put on a good show.
Thank you so much for your time.
And I'll be...
Regular you is awesome.
That's what you're about.
Thank you.