You
Ladies and gentlemen, the IGF and Choice Awards will begin in a few moments.
We ask that you please take your seats.
Bye.
Stay super.
Bye!
Ladies and gentlemen, tonight's program is about to begin.
Please take your seats as we will be starting momentarily.
Also at this time, if you would turn off your cell phone
and other electronic devices, it would be greatly appreciated.
Please welcome the chairperson of the Independent Games Festival, Kelly Wallach.
Hello everyone, and welcome to the 20th Annual Independent Games Festival Awards.
It's an honor to be here tonight and congratulations to the finalists and honorable mentions and to all the folks who submitted their games,
the members of the community who helped judge our pool of nearly 600 applicants, and to all the jury members who dedicated their time and expertise to having countless discussions on this year's award categories.
It's an incredible amount of work and is only made possible by the contributions of hundreds of dedicated members of the community.
I'm constantly humbled by the efforts and I feel incredibly grateful to be a part of
it.
Also, a big thank you to our sponsors.
So the IGF Platinum sponsor, ID at Xbox.
And the IGF platform sponsor, Steam.
As technology continues to move to the forefront of our lives,
games are going to continue to become an integral way
to connect, explore, and learn about the world around us.
Games can also be a stepping stone
to learning the language and skills necessary to exist
in this changing world and to build and create
the tools of the future.
It's imperative that we give this opportunity and language
to as many people as possible.
If the same content is made by the same people with the same experiences over and over,
we're going to turn off not only fans, but new creators as well.
If you don't see yourself reflected in the world around you, it limits your possibilities.
It limits what's possible for all of us.
If you look at a movie like Black Panther, not only is this a touchstone, but it's vibrant,
it's new, and it's exciting.
And one of the reasons that it's so captivating is that every inch and every second of the
film exists in a world that explores a rich history and culture long uncharted by mainstream
blockbuster storytelling.
Audiences are hungry for new experiences, for new content, and new worlds.
You see this exploration growing in games as well,
with roots in the indie community.
Games like Arian, Azura, and Malacca,
that integrate storytelling of vast cultural worlds
from all corners of the globe.
We see this reflected in hundreds of submissions
we receive from all over the world for IGF.
And indie showcases popping up in Johannesburg,
to Saudi Arabia, to China, to everywhere in between.
The ability to share and create your stories,
and experience the stories of others,
is what makes games so powerful.
As independent developers, you have the creative freedom,
an entire universe of possibilities at your fingertips,
a kind of virtual world, if you will,
that can express billions of stories
experienced by each player in wholly unique ways.
This year's nominees prove that there's wonderful work
already being done.
The next step is to open the doors to more communities,
to create more opportunities for more diversity,
and not just of gender or race,
but of economic backgrounds, religion, sexuality,
and diversity of thought.
This is accomplished through mentorship, access to funding,
room for failure, and cushioning of risk
by fostering individuals and supporting content that might
not appeal to conventional wisdom.
The narrative is that there isn't an audience for this work.
Well, maybe there's no audience because there's no content.
It's time to prove that we can do it.
So thanks again to everyone in this room for inspiring those around you,
for creating possibilities, and building new and wonderful worlds for us to explore.
And now, I'm very happy to introduce the chair of the FreePlay Independent Games Festival,
co-founder of League of Geeks, and one of Australia's finest exports since Tim Tams,
Trent Custers.
Thanks Kelly. Wow. Australia's finest export. Cop that, Thor. Okay. G'day everyone. There
you are. That's literally the only Australian joke you're going to get. So, alright. Twenty
years. Twenty years of celebrating indie games. Independent games. I mean I think that deserves
another round of applause.
And you know what, I think that's actually a great note
to start the show on, that it's the 20th annual IGF Awards.
As you know, we've been supporting the IGFs
with updates, new content, bug fixes,
for what, I think 20 years now since launch?
And well, with the rising costs of award show development,
you all know how it is,
we're gonna be changing things up a bit this year.
This year, instead of giving out IGF Awards
just the old-fashioned way,
Every finalist will receive a special IGF chest.
No, true story.
Inside that chest is your chance, finalists, to win your IGF award for your category.
I mean, hey, seriously, I mean, it's a good deal.
And I mean, don't fret.
If you come up empty, you can always purchase additional chests from the in-show store.
It's totally fine.
There are a few, I can see, yeah, alright, I can see a few faces in the audience.
Look, I know what you're thinking. The IGFs, pay to win now.
Not the case. Nope, not the case.
In fact, if you are the type of show attendee who doesn't want to spend any money purchasing additional chests,
you can always purchase additional chests.
you can actually earn them in-game.
True, it's true.
Game development, that is.
Just another
three to five years slaving away with your
team and who knows, maybe we'll give you another one.
Alright, welcome to the 20th
annual IGF Awards.
Let's get this show on the road.
Thank you.
I just tried to introduce myself over your applause, which I don't think is probably
going to work out for me.
I'm Trent Custers of League of Geeks, and I'll be your host for this evening.
And of course, don't worry, the IJF Awards are going to be the same as always, rigged
by the Indie Illuminati!
Yeah, that's it. Those people who cheered are the Illuminati, so you know, just keep your eyes out.
Seriously though, you may not believe me, what with an Aussie host up here and all,
but this award show is a real deal. It's some serious business. I mean, look at the line-up tonight, folks.
What an absolutely fabulous array of games we have for you this evening.
Yeah, that's definitely... Yeah, reason for applause.
Barber is You is up for four awards tonight.
Four awards.
Yeah.
Absolutely phenomenal effort for a student game.
And of course a terrifying reminder of the slow
but certain march of time for the rest of us.
Getting over it with Bennett Foddy,
up for three awards tonight.
Give it up for Bennett everybody.
Yeah.
I'll tell you what.
By a fellow Australian too, but he's now living in New York.
I mean, you'd have to leave Australia to get away with putting your fucking name in the title.
Am I right, Bennett?
No, not many people know this, but Bennett was actually the bassist in the huge Grammy-nominated electronic band Cut Copy.
And then, yeah, and then went on to be a professor or something at Oxford.
So, rock star, academic luminary, world famous game designer.
I don't know about you, but it's pretty hard
seeing people achieve your dreams
without watching them nail it in reverse.
We're all stuck in 2018 and Bennett's out here
Mario Kart mirror-moding life.
On you Bennett, well done.
Where the Water Tastes Like Wine,
another incredible game, right?
Yeah? Fantastic.
Now, I'm not sure if any of you have seen it or played it,
but if you have, you will have no doubt known and noticed
that Sting actually does VO in the game.
That's right, the Sting.
Someone convinced Sting to do VO in a video game,
which tells us one thing.
Sting has no idea what video games are.
Cuphead, beautiful game, absolutely fantastic,
flawless, beautiful.
Well, but, I mean, that's not to say that any of the other excellence in visual arts or finalists should be concerned.
I mean, you're all, you're all absolutely excellent. You look fantastic.
And besides, you've, let's be realistic, you've got bigger things to worry about this year.
A game with Stick Art is up for grand prize.
West of Loathing, everybody.
It's true.
Stick Art.
Up there, Seamus McNally.
And it's another thing that I noticed this year when I was going through the awards,
it's great to see a bunch of follow-up finalists who've been here before.
They've been finalists in years previous.
It's fantastic.
Tacoma from Fulbright, who's... Yeah, yeah, yeah. Fantastic, right?
**Applause**
Tacoma's level designer, Nina Freeman, actually was the IGF awards host last year.
So pretty stoked to find out I'll be a finalist next year.
**Laughter**
SubZep Games, into the breach.
Back Again, or Space Crack 2 as it's known to the DEA, and of course Tooth and Tail from
Pocket Watch Games, which we all know is the second best furry game ever made.
True story, true story.
Seriously though, it's great to have you all back.
All the finalists that have returned this year,
nominated again.
I mean, it's incredibly important to us Indies
to know that success can be repeated.
And that if we're successful enough,
we can stop making games altogether.
Like Rami.
Aw.
Congratulations, Rami.
All right, all right, let's get this show on the road.
Who am I?
I'm horrendously overscoped.
Three out of four of my team members did absolutely nothing.
I've missed more deadlines than Spy Party.
Well I can tell you that it's none of these titles because these are the finalists for
Best Student Game.
Ben Calkins.
Sam Sweet.
Don't Make Love, developed by Majese, Dario Dambra,
Nina Keel, Giorgio Carlino.
Penny Blue Finds a Clue.
Developed by Cactus Curse Games of DigiPen.
Lauren Stutzstream.
Jesse Hibbs.
Leonardo Saikali.
Garrett Huxtable.
We Were Here.
Developed by Total Mayhem Games.
The Total Mayhem Games Team.
Baba is You, developed by Hemphuli.
Arvi Thekari.
Guardian of the Gears, developed by DigiPen Team Studio 76.
Cameron Craig.
Eduardo Gorenstein.
Julie Gregg.
Kaiden Nugent.
Pretty decent.
All right, and the winner of the IGF Award
for Best Student Game is...
Bubba is you.
Do I have a joke here?
Thank you.
It's pretty cool to be here.
Well, I guess I have a couple of minutes to thank some people for getting here with Baba ISU.
There are a lot of people to thank and I have a tendency of talking a bit too much, so I'll try to keep it short.
There are four entities I'd like to thank specifically.
First of them is Anni Leskela, my girlfriend, for supporting me throughout the development of Baba ISU.
Thank you, Anni.
The second one is Lucas Miller, who is actually at GDC this year, for teaching me how to use Lua,
which has been super important in making Babes U.
They are a programming genius in other ways as well, so thank you for that.
Then there's Niklas Niflas Nygren, who is actually a finalist this year in IGF as well.
for teaching me how to use some programs
and how to keep working when it's very hard to stay motivated.
And finally, I'd like to thank the Nordic Game Jam community
for creating amazing events, without which
Babaisju wouldn't be here.
So I guess it's a good time to start making those like,
bye-bye, Swin jokes.
Let's keep doing that throughout the night.
I don't know, whatever.
Thank you.
A sure sign of the maturation of the indie games community is no doubt the level of quality
and polish that the presentation of our games now exhibit.
In fact, indie games are beginning to look so good that it's not uncommon to see comments
like, fuck you EA, on the Steam reviews of indie games.
I mean, what's better than some internet slug mistaking you for an army of publisher-financed
artists, am I right?
I think we've made it, folks.
And so with that, the finalists for Excellence in Visual Art are…
Excellence in Visual Art.
Night in the Woods.
Developed by Infinite Fob.
Scott Benson.
Charles Putner.
Adam Saltzman.
Sven Ruttnar.
Cuphead, developed by Studio MDHR.
Chad Moldenhauer.
Jared Moldenhauer.
Maya Moldenhauer.
Echo, developed by Ultra Ultra.
Martin Amborg.
Joker Heckstrom.
Soren Beck.
Morten Hedegren.
Luna, developed by Phenomena.
Robin Hunnecke.
Glenn Hernandez.
Alina Hale.
Elise Miller.
The Gardens Between, developed by the Voxel Agents.
Jonathan Swanson.
Josh Bradbury.
Henrik Pedersen.
Matthew Clark.
Chuchill, developed by Amanita Design.
Yaromir Plaki.
All right, some pretty games, okay.
And the winner for the IGF Award
for Excellence in Visual Art is
Chuchill.
This is crazy.
Unbelievable.
Wow.
I think we should thank
mostly...
Everyone.
Thank you. But mostly to
our colleague Jara Plachy,
who is the main creator of this game,
who designed it,
made all the animations
and art.
And the game design as well.
who can't be here tonight with us because he's with his wife and their newborn son.
Thanks to him. Thank you. Thank you so much.
So back at Log HQ in Melbourne, our studio,
we've got things pretty much on lockdown.
We run a tight ship.
But our producer, Woody, has a post-it note,
very important post-it note, stuck to his desk.
And that post-it note reads, don't forget audio.
The following games are from developers
who did the literal opposite of forgetting about audio.
Our nominees for excellence in audio are
Excellence in audio.
Tormentor X Punisher.
Developed by E-Studio.
Eunice Turner.
Bo Blythe.
Tuka Stephenson.
Nilo Takalainen.
Cuphead.
Developed by Studio MDHR.
Christopher Madigan, Luke Hatton, Chris Sweetman,
Samuel Justice, Vignette, developed by Skeleton Business,
David Kanaga.
Rain World, developed by Video Cult.
James Therrien.
Lydia Esrig.
Earnog Earn Limited, developed by Nifflis Games.
Nicholas Nigren.
Hari Damert.
Bjorn Malmros.
Hot Dog.
Celeste, developed by the Celeste team.
Lena Raine, Power Up Audio.
And the award for Excellence in Audio goes to...
Ernog Unlimited.
Oh, so neither of us are Nicholas.
Uh, so, uh, actually he couldn't make it.
He wanted me to tell everyone that he's really sorry.
Uh, but he has a very strong fear of flying.
So we are coming up to accept this for him.
And I'm shaking like crazy because this is the most nervous I think
I've been in like 20 years.
Uh, but, uh, he wanted me to thank all the people that they just mentioned,
but I want to say who is hot dog.
The mystery of Hot Dog.
The mystery of the Urnog.
Hot Dog is Nicholas's dog,
who does all the voices for the dogs in the game.
That's the voice actor of Urnog.
Yeah, but thank you everyone.
Thank you for everybody who's in this industry,
who's doing these indie games, who's taking risks.
Ah, I wanna cry right now.
I'm just so, like everybody here is so amazing.
It's like, you know.
Yeah, everybody should be on the stage.
Everybody should be getting an award.
So, sorry, I'm getting emotional.
Thank you.
You may remember him from his legendary mountain ascent in 2017's Getting Over It with Bennett Foddy.
But where is he now?
We sent a reporter to get the answers.
Over to you, Lindsay. On the scene with the story. Mimosas at lunch.
Can't wait.
Yeah, ever since I got over it with Bennett Foddy, things have been great.
I get recognized on the street.
But, you know, I'm still just a normal guy.
I put my cauldron on one leg at a time, just like everyone else.
I live in a really nice neighborhood, you know, Seymour loves it, my dog.
I try to stay busy, you know, I got some hobbies.
I like to bake and I'm getting really good at badminton, if I do say so myself.
And yeah, I just recently got into painting, which has been really good for me.
Yeah, it's been really positive.
So we've heard there have been some changes in your life.
Would you like to talk about that?
Yeah.
Yeah, my wife left a couple months ago.
Um, you know, it's been hard, but I'm trying to stay positive.
I just, uh, recently made a Tinder profile.
So, you know, I'm getting out there.
Ladies and gents, your man's available.
Oh, is that from your time on the mountain?
Yeah, yeah, I'm kind of nostalgic, you know, so I like to have that one on there.
Oh, oh, Connor.
I'm sorry, uh, I have to go after we get that. Sorry.
Hey.
Hey, I called twice. Where were you?
Sorry, I had my phone on silent. We were doing an interview thing.
Did you forget you have Connor this weekend?
No, I didn't forget. Okay.
Well, he hasn't eaten lunch, so you'll need to feed him.
Okay.
Here is his inhaler and his allergy list.
I already have the allergy list on the fridge, Beth.
Are you hungry, little buddy? Are you hungry?
Yeah, you're hungry.
Uh, I love being a dad, you know.
He's so great. He's my little man.
Aren't you my little man? Are you ready?
You ready for the airplane?
So you're a single dad. You're currently unemployed.
But you seem happy.
I mean, once I got over it with Bennett Foddy,
I kind of felt like I could get over anything.
Woah! Is he okay?
He'll get over it.
Riveting stuff. Thanks, Lens.
Next up, Cuphead and Wife welcome their first child, but rumor has it he may be more mug than cup.
Whoopsie!
Ha ha ha ha ha ha.
Totally not his kid, though.
Yeah, now it looks like a complete mug.
Family's destroyed.
Bloodline's tainted.
It's over. 🎵
🎵 Please welcome to the stage, Alt-Control GDC co-founder, John Polson.
Hey everyone, good evening.
The Alternative Controller Exhibit, Alt-Control GDC,
has hit its first major anniversary,
now five years and going strong
with over 100 amazing submissions this year.
I'm so fortunate to get to organize Alt-Control GDC
and see it grow every year.
I'm happy to also see all the cardboard, hardwired, and otherwise DIY controller experiments pop
up inside and outside of the pavilion on the GDC show floor, evidence that the game industry
is excited to change the way we play.
Only at Alt Control GDC can you experience true claustrophobia
in a game played in a grave, interact as either audience
or performer in a puppet show,
or embrace your inner rainbow unicorn and strap
on a horn while surviving a mundane office job.
2018's unique award will shine in its own way,
handcrafted by Jerry Bellick,
a multi-year Alt Control GDC alum.
Give it up for Jerry.
That is the award.
Jerry who, yes, as you guys may know is also the creator of the Chusatron.
Among the 20 awesome creations you can play at GDC this year, here are the finalists.
Unicornelia by Courtney Snavely, Jane Mitchell, Vivian T. Lee, Dylan Negri.
Puppet Pandemonium by the Puppet Pandemonium team.
Wobblegarden by Robin Baumgarten.
Too Many Captains and Not Enough Wire by Avi Romanov,
Giada Sun, Mark Wars by the Mark Wars team.
So please join me in congratulating
the winner of the Alt Control GDC Award, Puppet Pandemonium.
Thank you.
This is amazing.
I've made a little list just in case so I don't forget anyone.
Okay.
Thank you.
Thank you to my team.
Thank you GDC and the all control judges obviously and IGF.
This is amazing.
Thank you to my mom for helping me learn how to sew through Skype, which is cool.
Thank you to my boss for letting us put this thing together in his garage.
That was really nice.
Let's see, John, thank you as well.
And all the other fantastic, inspiring pieces that make us all play these games and stuff.
And all the performers who played, because that was really scary.
Do you want to say anything?
I would like to thank Terrence for dragging us all together from some VR hackathon and
a Halloween party to just make this crazy idea real.
Yeah.
Keep making...
Thank you very much.
Game design is too often the most illustrious and celebrated role in game development.
It's true.
It's very true.
I'm a game designer, I can say that.
Just like a great soundtrack, great game design,
you don't notice.
Great game design takes a step into the background
and permits the player to become immersed
in the experiences we craft.
Great game designers, whether sole visionaries
or dedicated teams, are masters of the unseen,
mavens of illusion.
But most importantly, game designers
are the advocate of the player.
And here are the nominees for Excellence in Design.
Excellence in Design.
Into the Breach.
Developed by Subset Games.
Matthew Davis.
Justin Ma.
Shenzhen IO, developed by Zaktronics.
Zach Barth.
Keith Holman.
Matthew Sagey Burns.
Kyle Steed.
Wilmot's Warehouse, developed by Hollow Ponds.
Richard Hogg.
Ricky Haggett.
Ellie Rainsbury.
Baba is You, developed by Hemphooli.
Arvi Teikari.
Earnog Earn Limited, developed by Nifflis Games.
Nicholas Nygren.
Corinne Catalin.
Hot dog.
Getting Over It with Bennett Foddy, developed by Bennett Foddy.
All right, and the Excellence in Design award goes to...
I've been trying to open these extra slow by the way.
Baba is you.
I kind of used everything I had to say in the first talk, so let's keep this short.
Thanks again.
I'm very surprised, and yeah.
Thanks.
I remember one of the first things that stuck with me when I entered the industry was a
GDC talk that Clint Hocking had done in 2007 or something, where he talked about something
a colleague said to him in response to some outlandish feature request he'd no doubt come
up with.
And that person said, dude, it's code.
We can do anything.
The Nuovo Award is a category reserved for a very special type of developers
who take that notion far too literally.
What a brilliant, brilliant celebration of the vast landscape of our medium
and an honour to celebrate these games and developers.
Here are the finalists for the Nuovo Award.
Nuovo Award
Getting Over It with Bennett Foddy
Developed by Bennett Foddy.
Tarotika Voodoo.
Developed by TPM Co. Softworks.
Ikushi Togo.
Max Preston.
10 Mississippi.
Developed by Karina Popp. ♪♪
Amortition's Tale.
Developed by Laundry Bear Games.
Gabby Darienzo.
Kaitlyn Trombley.
Jennifer Costa.
Helena Herron.
Cosmic Top Secret.
Developed by Kloss Film and Those Eyes.
Trini Layer.
Lisa Saxtrup.
Bjorn Sweene.
Christian Torgard.
Everything is going to be okay.
Developed by Natalie Lawhead.
Baba is You.
Developed by Hemphuli.
Arvi Thekari.
Kids.
Developed by Playables.
Michael Frey.
Mario VanRickenbach.
I love it, you're all fucking awesome.
That's awesome.
Alright, and the winner for the Nuova Award is...
Getting Over It with Bennett Foddy.
My wife's going to say, that's living in your office.
Walking around the conference, I've
just been struck by how many people
I see who have really helped me a lot in the last 12 years.
Just encouragement, critique, writing tools that I used,
creating online spaces that I needed.
I think without Derek Yu's website,
I just honestly would never have gotten started.
Yeah.
And, you know, I think that's, like, that's the only thing that makes indie games possible,
is that we're all helping each other all the time.
And that's what I'm going to think about every time I look at this somewhere in my office.
Trust the Australian to try and walk off the front of the stage, of course.
Alright, now we so often talk about story in games,
but narrative is the very framework of a game's storytelling potential.
Narrative is the architecture of the story,
the systems that communicate story,
the delivery method for connecting with the minds and hearts of our players.
It is perhaps one of the most specific
and exclusive elements that our medium
can offer above any other.
And so it's with great pleasure
that I present to you this year's finalists
for Excellence in Narrative.
Excellence in Narrative.
Tacoma, developed by Fulbright.
The Fulbright team.
Attentat 1942, developed by Charles University and Czech Academy of Sciences.
Vít Šíslar, Jakub Guemrat, Rikard Alexander, Marie Černa.
Where the Water Tastes Like Wine, developed by Dim Bulb Games and Serenity Forge.
The Where the Water Tastes Like Wine writing team.
Night in the Woods, developed by Infinite Fall.
Bethany Hockenberry.
Scott Benson.
Alec Holoka.
Butterfly Soup, developed by Brianna Lay.
Tooth and Tail, developed by Pocket Watch Games.
Andy Schatz, Alex Kane, Dexter Friedman, Andy Nguyen.
And the Excellence in Narrative Award goes to
Night in the Woods.
Hold on, I'm going to tweet about this real quick.
No.
Thank you.
I don't think, I wasn't expecting this.
I just told every single person I met,
I'm like, we're not going to win this.
This, oh no, man, we're just going to watch someone else
walk up there, but thank you.
This was the first game we ever worked on.
Thanks to Alec for saying, hey, you guys
should just go with the story that you want
to go with on trusting us.
with that. It was obviously a group effort but that was just a huge vote of confidence in
faith so thank you. This goes out to everyone who doesn't get to tell their stories in games
that end up on big screens here.
Like, five years ago or four years ago, just the thought of us ever being able to tell
the kind of story that we wanted to tell in a video game, let alone win an award for it,
is insane.
So just thank you.
Thanks a lot.
That's it.
Do you want to say something?
Thank you.
Ash, what's playing?
Bye bye, Jean. ♪
Oh. ♪
Ahhh. ♪ ♪ ♪
What the fuck?
Wife?
I'm bored.
you
Woo! Free sale!
Okay.
Please give a warm welcome to Chris Charla,
Director of ID at Xbox, and Sarah Bond,
General Manager, Xbox Third-Party Publishing,
who will be presenting the ID at Xbox Gaming
for Everyone Award.
Hey everyone.
Hey everybody.
So one of the raddest things about the independent development community is just the diversity
in games that folks are working on.
So we always like to take a little time during the IGF to put a spotlight on a group that's
helping bringing gaming to everyone.
But that's not just about the games that you guys make.
It's also about making sure that everyone can play.
There are multiple great groups focusing on this
in different ways, and they're all super cool.
Tonight, we want to showcase one of them,
our friends at Special Effect.
Before we visited Special Effects, we've always been a huge gaming family and gaming is something I wanted all my children to be able to have the opportunity to do.
Chase has got a severe form of cerebral palsy and he has dystonia which means he can't fully control his body very well.
Even trying to get Chase to push a button is really difficult to do because he just doesn't have the fine motor skills to do it.
But he really loved gaming and you could see that he wanted to do more.
So we went up to the gaming room in Oxford and throughout the day we tried lots of different pieces of equipment, lots of different games until we found out what worked best for Chase.
As a parent it's made so much difference for Chase being able to access video games.
I was really sad that I thought he was never really going to be able to join in and do those things on his own.
Particularly to disabled people, I think games are really important because, you know,
somebody who's able-bodied can go out, they can play golf, they can go and drive a car,
they can do almost anything in real life.
Tristan's going to have those same opportunities.
So being able to sit down and put on a game means that it creates a level playing field.
He can do an activity that he probably wouldn't be able to do in normal day-to-day life.
But even better, with gaming, he can play alongside someone who's able-bodied
and it gives a real boost to his self-confidence, I think.
That was good.
Look at that.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Thanks, guys.
And please give a warm round of applause to Mick Donagan, the CEO of Special Effects.
Yeah, thank you. Yeah, hi, I'm Mick Donegan, founder and CEO of SpecialEffect.
As you can see, a charity that helps people with severe physical disabilities to play video games.
Our base is in the UK, but we don't think of ourselves as just being UK-based.
We're world-based.
With video games, there are no borders or boundaries to the countries in which they're played.
The only boundaries are those within the games themselves, for those people who are unable
to play them because of their disabilities.
Special effect technicians, software designers, therapy staff work as a team to help severely
disabled individuals on a face-to-face basis in order to unlock those barriers and provide
them with a customized setup that enables them to play the games they want to play at
the highest possible level they can.
As a result of our help, many of them can compete with and beat non-disabled gamers,
sometimes even the professionals.
The difference that this specialist's one-to-one support can make is literally life-transforming.
One user, a guy who hadn't been able to play his favourite game for 15 years, simply
said,
Thank you for giving me my life back.
However, our one-to-one solutions don't just benefit individuals.
The insight and detailed knowledge we gain from the one-to-one, lifelong assessment and
support we provide puts us in a perfect position to share what we learn with both hardware
and software developers worldwide, so that they have an opportunity to incorporate our
ideas.
Put simply, by implementing a feature that's worked successfully for just one individual,
literally tens of thousands of disabled people with similar needs across the world can benefit too.
I'm absolutely delighted and shocked to be honest to receive this award on behalf of SpecialEffect.
However, I'd also like to take this opportunity to acknowledge and celebrate the work of all
the individuals, organizations, and developers all over the world, not least here in the
U.S., who so clearly understand the inclusivity and sheer joy that only access to video games
can bring, and are working increasingly successfully to share this joy with as many disabled people
as possible, whoever they are.
wherever they are and whatever their disabilities.
It's a real privilege for myself and my special effect colleagues
to be members of what I firmly believe is a global movement
to give a life of gaming to everyone.
Thank you very much indeed.
As developers, we showcase games all over the world,
standing on convention booths for sometimes days on end,
shaky shaky hands all the time,
talking to fans, colleagues, hugging.
We definitely hug too much.
Yeah.
And just like the rabid, unkillable viruses
that sweep through game development studios
the week after a convention's closed,
this following game has swept through society
and into our hearts.
It gives me great pleasure to announce this year's recipient of the IGF Audience Award.
Who talks? We weren't expecting this at all.
This is amazing. Wow. I wrote something for the audio award actually, but because we weren't expecting to win this at all.
Thank you so much. Holy shit.
Celeste released just a few months ago, but in that time we've received such an overwhelmingly positive wave of feedback and love from fans
that have resonated with the game, its themes and
Celeste is a game that so closely ties all those themes together through design, through
writing, through characters and audio.
It provides an optimistic approach to tackling its challenges.
It says that it's okay to fail on your way to success.
I relate to that a lot and I think it also shows in its reception.
In these few months, I've personally received hundreds of emails from people that have identified
with its depictions and attitude towards depression and anxiety.
I've had someone reach out to tell me that they decided to live because of the encouragement
the game gave them.
And that's no small thing.
I just wanted to share that with all of you.
Thank you so much for recognizing this whole game that was built from a lot of love, from
a lot of people.
Thanks to Matt, to Noel, Amora, Pedro, Kevin, Gabby, Sven, all of your contributions to
something that I think is really, truly special.
Please give a warm IGF welcome to the winner of last year's Seamus McNally Grand Prize
Award, Brendan Chung.
Whenever I play a game and it doesn't crash, it feels like a little miracle.
How is this game running and not immediately getting crushed under the sheer weight of itself?
How did you make this interesting, funny, beautiful thing with such little time and resources and support?
Well, we all know how it feels to be small.
And we all know how it feels to be vulnerable.
And that is our strength.
And that is what makes our work we do so special.
Here are the nominees for the Seamus McNally Grand Prize.
Seamus McNally Grand Prize.
Getting Over It with Bennett Foddy.
Developed by Bennett Foddy.
To live is to suffer.
To survive is to find some meaning in the suffering.
Night in the Woods.
Developed by Infinite Fall.
Alec Holoka.
Bethany Hockenberry.
Scott Benson.
M. Halberstadt.
West of Loathing.
Developed by Asymmetric.
Zach Johnson.
Victor Thompson.
Wes Cleveland.
Kevin Simmons.
Into the Breach.
Developed by Subset Games.
Matthew Davis.
Justin Ma.
Heat Signature, developed by Suspicious Developments.
Tom Francis.
John Roberts.
John Winder.
Baba Is You, developed by Hemphooli.
Arvi Thekari.
And the IGF Seamus McNally Grand Prize winner is...
Night in the Woods.
I promise I'm not tweeting, I'm just checking my notes.
Wow, this is weird.
I was here, I think, 11 years ago for Aquaria, so this is very unusual.
I just want to say a couple things.
Thanks to the amazingly talented and incredibly self-motivated team.
I was super lucky to get a chance to work with such incredibly funny and awesome and caring people.
And thank you to everyone in my life who believed that I wasn't a completely irredeemable piece of garbage.
That especially includes my family, Greg and Debra, Eileen and Ian, and shout out to Bob Fenton,
my therapist, a cerbic British man who, you know, called me on my bullshit, so thank you very much.
Hey.
So I'm Becca Saltzman and I'm part of Finji, who sort of has like helped shepherd this.
I have a few thank yous, sort of like as a studio,
that I need to send out.
One is to our team at Sony, who, God bless them,
stayed up all night before launch night.
John, Elisa, and Matt, thank you very much.
Also, our dev teams who helped us launch on Xbox and Switch.
I managed to do this trash on my own
with our porting studio in 22nd Century in Austin.
That's, yeah.
Joe, Tony, and Taylor, wow, thank you so much.
A couple of shoutouts actually to Xbox and Nintendo.
God bless you Wally.
I don't know who you are, I'll meet you someday.
Yep, there we go.
And also Sarah and the assortment of people
who answer third party panicked emails over at Nintendo.
Also a little shoutout to our gremlins,
our babies at home who made, yep.
And also to Iko the cat, thank you very much for that Wednesday before launch.
Well that was unexpected.
Thanks, this is Alcalocas second Seamus McNally by the way.
He won another one 25 years ago.
So, congrats to Alec.
Thank you for all the people that we've...
All the people who have supported us over the years. This is a weird game
We're still shocked that people that have found an audience and people were into it
Um, there's too many people to thank for me personally. I just wanted to thank my friend Charles who's not here right now. He was
He's just a good guy and he's been there and like my corner the entire time
Also our friend Carla who's over there with the rest of the team of Fulbright
Very much helped us through some pretty hard times and
Yeah, thanks to Bethany and thanks to Alec and everyone else on the stage.
Thank you.
Yes, a dinner to all the things.
Um, I don't know.
I was just thinking about this and it's just kind of weird that I grew up in like
Mifflin County, PA.
Um, and it's just cool that a lot of people really enjoyed a lot of the
stories that were things that I grew up with and family history and it seemed to
hit a court with people.
So thank you.
Thanks everyone.
Night in the Woods, everyone.
How about that?
Alright.
Yeah, Night in the Woods.
Come on, come on, come on.
Round it up.
Alright, so we're nearing the end of the show, so there's a few people that I want to thank.
Of course, our incredible sponsors.
IGF Platinum sponsor, iD at Xbox.
Thank you so much.
The IGF Platform sponsor, Steam.
I see him over there.
I'd also like to thank all of the incredible finalists here tonight.
If you're a finalist, stand up.
Get on your feet.
Come on, let's see you all.
Get up, let's see your faces if you're a finalist.
Come on!
Alright, here they are.
Well done.
So thank you, all of you, for your incredible, absolutely mind-blowing contributions to our
medium. Thank you so much.
All right, so honorable mentions as well.
I mean, some of those folks don't even get to come here
to San Francisco to GDC.
They may not even be at the show.
They may not have a GDC pass,
but they're an honorable mention in a show
that has over 500, over 400 entries.
I mean, that's still an incredible achievement.
So please put your hands together
for all of the honorable mentions this year of the IGFs.
Yeah.
This year's judges and juries, thank you.
I hope we didn't rattle too many friendships
with all those debates and arguments that no doubt went down.
And of course, all the crew behind the scenes tonight
making the magic happen.
I mean, I forced them all to do three dress rehearsals,
so thank you so much for that.
That includes Callie, Sandesh, Simon,
and of course, GDC's brand new GM, Katie Stern.
Everyone, please give her a warm welcome.
Alright, so that brings us to the end of the indie show, but I mean, don't get up, don't
get out of your seats, stay right where you are, because coming up next is the 18th annual
Legend of Zelda Awards.
Get ready everybody, get ready.
Obviously it's the 18th Game Developer Choice Awards with all of our favourite awards like
Best Money, Most Tigers at a GDC Party and of course the PUBG of the Year Award.
Some seriously incredible talent on display tonight, folks.
Some phenomenal games and very deserving developers.
So don't go anywhere as Robin Haneke,
who is indie as fuck, is about to get on stage
and absolutely slay at the 18th Annual
Game Developers Choice Awards.
I'm Trent Custers, I've been your host this evening.
Have a wonderful night.
Ladies and gentlemen, we are pleased to begin the second half of our evening and welcome you to the 18th annual Game Developers Choice Awards.
Please welcome the host of the evening, Robin Hunneke.
Hello.
Indies fuck, yeah that's right.
Hello, welcome everyone to the 18th Annual Game Developers Choice Awards.
Let's give it a round of applause because it's badass.
Woo!
Rent the runway cannot touch that closet, babe.
Before we begin, I would like to personally congratulate all of tonight's nominees across
all categories.
Getting nominated here is a sign that your peers across the crafts of game development
truly cherish and value your work.
Whether it's narrative, design, art, sound, or technology,
your fellow developers know just what
you went through to get here.
And they choo, choo, choo's you.
It is also very likely that you're making actual money
for your publisher, so please pick up the check
for the rest of us this week.
Thank you.
But seriously, y'all, if you are nominated and you can still stand, you're not too drunk,
please do.
Now's your chance.
All nominees, stand up for a round of applause.
It doesn't matter if you win.
Fake it till you make it.
Okay, now sit down and laugh at my jokes.
Who are these magical, mysterious developers?
There will be a lot of high production value videos to explain that about each of tonight's nominees,
and I don't want to spoil it for any of you who are just here for the chiptunes.
So, I will say this. Many of this year's games took decades of developer time to build,
years of player time to enjoy, and mere seconds to become scapegoats for the NRA.
Seriously though, 2018, as Kelly Wallach pointed out in her IGF chairperson remarks,
presents us with opportunities to innovate, to be inclusive, and celebrate
the stories of a much broader range of creatives. As a developer, a CEO, and a
feminist, and an advocate for these values throughout my own career, it is so
fucking nice to be able to stand up here and say that out loud.
I for one am thrilled to be standing up here giving dudes awards, especially now that we
are finally all in agreement about the fact that harass is one word.
So let's get on with it, shall we?
You never forget your first.
I imagine almost everyone in this room fondly remembers their own debut game, a game that,
despite many flaws, you could not help but be insanely proud of.
Proud because against all odds, you managed to get it done.
Sure, it would have been better to ship a slightly smaller version of your game, perhaps
a year earlier on a platform that would actually fucking monetize, but you had a vision, and
you saw it through to the bitter and bankrupt end.
S'il vous plaît!
A wise developer once told me that Mefford's first law of game development read thus.
The worst thing that can happen to a young developer is for their game to be successful,
as they might be tricked into thinking that they had something to do with it.
So don't be jealous of these Best Debut nominees, pity them for they are destined to be fucked.
Just spend the profits from this game on the next one which will do about half as well.
The nominees are...
Best Debut
Team Cherry
Nominated for Hollow Knight
Ari Gibson.
William Pellen.
David Kazi.
Christopher Larkin.
Sidebar Games, nominated for Golf Story.
Andrew Newey.
Studio MDHR, nominated for Cuphead.
Chad Moldenhauer.
Jared Moldenhauer.
Infinite Fall, nominated for Night in the Woods.
Alec Holoka.
Bethany Hockenberry.
Scott Benson.
M Halberstadt.
Buried Signal, nominated for Gorogoa.
Jason Roberts.
I just love that last one, it's just him.
It's a beautiful game.
And the winner is...
Cuphead.
I can't believe you took the wrong steps.
I was here the whole time, and as I moved forward I heard front steps.
But still my heart led me in a direction in the same way of approaching this game, which
was go with what I'm feeling, go with what I know, and some of it pans out, such as this,
and some of it lets you do whatever I did.
We have to thank our whole team, which unfortunately not everyone is here, but this is a team effort for this game.
And our families, everybody for putting up with us, Microsoft, all of our fans, just super exciting to win this award. Thank you so much.
Such a good game.
Tonight's first nominee for Game of the Year...
Nier Automata.
Developed by Platinum Games.
Published by Square Enix.
Yoko Taro.
Yosuke Saito.
Takahisa Tarua.
destroyed? Not quite.
Anyone with parents over 40, or who
is one, is painfully familiar with the argument that smartphones
are the leading purveyors of social, political, and personal apathy.
Why do something productive when you can just thumb through your Instagram?
Why get to know that person sitting next to you?
We can text your cousin and ask about the Warrior score.
Why download music illegally when you can rent shitty copies of it that barely stream
to your handheld computer?
The truth is, there's no reason to do anything.
Control is an illusion.
The past is gone and the future is fucking unknowable.
So, you might as well download these nominees
for Best Mobile Game and decide if you agree on the winner,
especially if they're free.
The nominees are.
Best Mobile Game.
Reigns, Her Majesty, developed by Nereal, published by Devolver Digital, the Nereal team.
Hidden Folks, developed by Adrienne de Young and Sylvain de Groot.
Adrienne de Young.
Sylvain de Groot.
Martin Cavalli.
Monument Valley 2, developed by Us2 Games.
Adrian Law.
Manesh Mistry.
David Fernandez Huerta.
Jonathan Topf.
Gorogoa, developed by Buried Signal.
Published by Annapurna Interactive.
Jason Roberts.
Bury Me My Love, developed by The Pixel Hunt, FIGS, and Arte France.
Published by Pladius.
Florane Moran.
Lorane Herbet.
I hate opening these envelopes.
The winner is Gorogoa.
Well, thanks everybody.
I think when I was up here back in 2014, I said that I started this, the journey of making this game alone,
but now I feel like I'm part of a big family, and that's especially true now.
I got my sound designer beside me. Thanks, Ed.
Thanks to Joel Korlitz, composer on the game.
Thanks to everybody at Annapurna Interactive,
without whom I think the game literally would never have been finished.
Yeah. You want to say anything, Ed?
Just thank you to Jason for letting me be part of this journey.
You're welcome. Thank you, Ed.
That's it. Thank you, guys.
The second nominee for Game of the Year,
Super Mario Odyssey,
developed by Nintendo EPD.
Published by Nintendo.
The Nintendo EPD Team.
Narrative in games have come a long way in a short time.
It wasn't that long ago that most antagonists in games
were two-dimensional caricatures of villains
devoid of motivation for all their wrongdoings.
Developers didn't need a reason to have a player shoot
thousands of rounds of ammo, chewing
through hundreds of digital enemies in their games.
But look at us now.
Now, games can tell moving stories.
deeply personal stories before sending the player off to kill their way through hours
of entertainment.
As our nominees in this category illustrate, some developers are willing to do much, much
more.
They are willing to take risks and weave tales that make us laugh, make us think, and make
us ask why.
Let's all press F to pay respect to these nominees.
Developed by Infinite Fall.
Published by Finji.
Bethany Hockenberry.
Scott Benson.
Alec Holoka.
Hellblade, Senua's Sacrifice.
Developed by Ninja Theory.
Tamim Antoniades.
The Northmen say the world will come to an end.
What Remains of Edith Finch, developed by Giant Sparrow,
published by Annapurna Interactive.
The Giant Sparrow Team.
Maybe we believed so much in a family curse, we made it real.
Horizon Zero Dawn, developed by Guerrilla Games,
published by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
The Guerrilla Team.
Wolfenstein II, the New Colossus,
developed by Machine Games, published by Bethesda Softworks.
Jens Mappes, Joerg Gustafsson, Tommy Tordtsen-Bjork.
And the Best Narrative Award goes
to What Remains of Edith Bitsch.
Thank you. There's so many good, sound reasons why this game should not have been started, or funded, or completed.
But thank you so much to the team, and all of our friends at Sony and Annapurna for your tireless patience and enthusiasm in being sure that it does exist. Thank you.
Yeah.
Chelsea?
I just...
After being a part of this community for so long and seeing so many amazing things created
by so many amazing people, just being here is such an honor and I'm so grateful for everybody
who made it possible, Annapurna, Sony, and thank you.
Hey everyone.
Yeah, this was a labor of love.
It took everything to get this done.
We went through a big road of trials.
Special thanks to my brother who's sitting right here,
who was a big help on the game.
My girlfriend, my parents, all our families.
Everyone put, like, way more than themselves into this,
and it's fucking amazing.
I love you guys.
Here tonight to present the Ambassador of the Year Award is Poria Torkin.
Good evening.
I was born in Iran.
My family fled to the Netherlands when I was six years old.
But I was lucky.
Growing up Dutch provided me with incredible opportunities that many children like me never had.
I was incredibly fortunate to spend several years working and growing at the Peerless Guerrilla Games in Amsterdam.
Hermen, Angie, thank you for all the opportunities you gave me. Thank you so much.
And later...
When I applied to a studio I've wanted to work at ever since I first played Halo,
Bungie brought me to the United States.
I am lucky, and today, standing in front of a room filled with my peers,
I am honored to introduce my dear friend Rami.
Because not everyone has been as lucky as I have been.
It is easy to forget that there are hundreds of thousands of people across the globe
who would drop everything to have an internationally acclaimed game studio nearby their homes.
And there are hundreds of thousands of people who share the dream of standing on this stage,
or even simply being in this room, but who do not have the opportunities that we were granted.
They didn't have access to the knowledge, the jobs, the network, the press, and the visas
that we, and definitely I, benefited from.
all for reasons entirely out of their control.
It is because of and for these people that we are honoring Rami tonight.
He is not just receiving this award for his passion for independent development, his love
of games and the power they have to change us, or his formidable beard.
He is receiving this award for his accomplishments and work,
focused on providing people with opportunities and access
that each and any of us deserve, but not all of us are granted.
His studio, Flumbeer, has diverted significant resources
towards helping fellow and aspiring game developers.
From creating DoPressKit, a free tool which
is used by thousands of independent and mid-sized
developers around the world.
to working with young initiatives like Train Jam, Indie Mega Boots, or Playground.
From supporting and advising platforms and events with their indie offerings,
to organizing One Reason to Be,
he consistently uses his reach to raise awareness and urgency
on things he recognizes as unjust or underrepresented.
He spends a significant portion of his time traveling to emerging territories to speak
to students, local developers and investors, governments and accelerators, museums, universities
and media.
All with the goal to help cultivate game development communities and guide opportunities for developers
with potential.
And perhaps most notable of all, he introduced his mother to Final Fantasy and shared that
experience with all of us on Twitter.
Please join me in welcoming my friend, the man with as many names as initiatives, Rami
Ibrahim Mahmoud Hanafi Ismail.
Assalamu alaikum. My name is Rami Ismail, one half of Dutch Independent Studio of Lambeer,
and I'm thankful. I am thankful to my parents, who have each in their own way inspired me
to be driven, humble, and curious. Their presence here tonight means the world to me.
I'm thankful for my siblings who have instilled in me a sense of playfulness, of responsibility
and a kindness towards others.
I'm thankful towards my family and friends who, despite not many understanding what it
is I do, have always supported me in following my passions.
I am thankful for those who created and worked in this medium and industry long before I
was part of it.
For creating a medium that I fell in love with decades ago.
for nurturing a culture of sharing and self-improvement,
and for working on improving this industry,
tiny step by tiny step.
I will try to uphold those values,
and I will try to improve upon that
which you would not or could not.
I'm thankful to everyone who took a chance on me, and there are many of you from my early
childhood until just today.
I'm very aware that I'm far from perfect and that many of you have worked hard to support
me, teach me, correct me, work around or with my idiosyncrasies, and help me do what I do.
I'm thankful to my co-founder, JW, who despite our well-documented differences...
who despite our well documented differences has always been a person I'm thankful to work with
and who has, without exception or reservation, supported me using Flamberg's time, brand and resources to help other developers
and pushes me to stand up for what I believe is right.
I'm thankful to my wife, Adriaan.
Who I met through games, who proposed to me through games,
and who has, through support and example,
shown to me what it means to be a gracious, considerate,
and inspiring human first, and a hardworking, generous,
and responsible creator second.
Her generosity and thoughtfulness
are a daily inspiration.
I'm thankful to the passionate players around the world, those that support this medium
with their passion, their kindness, their constructive criticism, their curiosity, and
their love for this medium and its creators.
Your enthusiasm is an inspiration, a goal to work towards, and a reward all at once.
I'm thankful for the designers, the programmers, the artists, the musicians, the actors, sound
designers, writers, QA, localizers, platforms, publishers, press, critics, content creators,
marketeers, investors, producers, and other people that touched games on their way from
the tiniest concept to the curious input and hearts of a player.
You are all part of what allows this medium to flourish, and this medium is better for
having you be part of it.
I am thankful for the event organizers, community organizers, teachers and professors, government
employees, archivists, activists, researchers, and other passionate people sacrificing part
of their life towards helping this industry and community connect and grow.
Without your passion and efforts, I would not be able to visit your communities, to
learn from your cities, your cultures, and your country's unique stories, challenges,
and opportunities.
I am thankful for those that work and fight to democratize this medium, to stand against
injustice and toxicity, despite the hatred, anger, and so often lack of support they face.
Your belief that this medium can be more makes this medium safer.
more representative, more accessible, and more inclusive to those of any sex, race,
gender, sexuality, ideology, heritage, history, language, country, culture, disability, socio-economic
reality, age, or situation.
I am thankful to those of you who participate in this medium despite feeling or being treated
as different or out of place.
I am thankful to those of you who participate in this medium and would want to be here,
in this room, but could not be here due to their financial, geographical or political
realities.
adds perspective to our medium and your work will continue to make our medium stronger,
richer and more representative. I'm thankful for those of you who are now taking their first step
into our medium or who dream of one day being part of it.
As a medium, as an industry, as a people, we have our challenges and problems, we have
our disagreements and controversies, but throughout all of human history, people have created
ways to be playful, ways to be curious, and ways to learn.
And you well might choose to take that torch forward into the future.
And if you do, I hope that you will try to improve.
upon that which we here today will not or cannot.
Being an ambassador of something can only be a point of pride if you believe that that
which you represent is valuable.
Throughout my life, I've seen games give people joy, wonder, curiosity, a means of
expression, education, friendship, and love through both play and creation.
So the overwhelming pride I feel in receiving this award
comes not from the award itself or from the title implied in it.
The pride I feel comes from the idea
that I could be an ambassador for you, the work that you do,
and the value it adds to life's current, past, and future.
So I'm thankful for those who support you.
for those who encourage you, and for those who believe in you.
Because I am thankful for you.
All of you, you are why I am proud right now.
And that pride, I feel, can only exist because I am proud of you.
Make aims.
Tonight's third nominee for Game of the Year, The Legend of Zelda Breath of the Wild.
Developed by Nintendo EPD.
Published by Nintendo.
The Nintendo EPD Team.
Hello everybody. Still here. Alright.
I think we can all agree that technology makes our lives so much better.
From untraceable currency primarily used in illegal transactions
to social media platforms that bring unsolicited dick pics right into your DMs.
There's pretty much no such thing as bad technology.
And our industry is certainly no exception.
Think of all the ways we innovate even when we make the same game over and over and over again.
Really, the only thing more amazing than the engineering work that is gluing together the interactive experiences showcased here tonight is the fact that I didn't have to say blockchain even once.
The nominees are.
Best technology.
Destiny 2, developed by Bungie, published by Activision, the Bungie engineering team.
Hellblade, Senua's sacrifice, developed by Ninja Theory, the Ninja Theory team.
Assassin's Creed Origins, developed by Ubisoft Montreal.
Published by Ubisoft.
Sylvain Tratière.
Julien Desaigneur.
Alexandra Begnachflor.
Horizon Zero Dawn.
Developed by Guerrilla Games.
Published by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
The Guerrilla Team.
The Legend of Zelda Breath of the Wild.
Developed by Nintendo EPD.
Published by Nintendo.
The Nintendo EPD team.
And the award for best technology goes to Horizon Zero Dawn.
So yeah, let's make a open world RPG in our first person engine, sure.
Oh, and we want to have giant fucking robots as well, too.
Robot dinosaurs, please, yes, no problem.
You can imagine those design meetings we had back then, it was fun.
But holy shit, we pulled it off, and I'm super proud of this achievement.
First of all, I'd like to thank our amazing fans for their feedback, the GIFs that we got, the videos, the screenshots.
It's super awesome to see all that stuff.
I'd like to thank our family for being very, very, very patient with us.
I'd like to thank Sony WWS for sticking with us in this crazy plan that we had.
And of course, I'd like to thank all the people at Guerrilla, including the people we did not bring.
There's a few of them.
And I'd like to thank all of you for this amazing award.
Super proud.
Thank you.
Thank you, Thank you.
Thank you please.
Thank you.
Thank you, Thank you.
Thank you thank you.
Thank you.
Uh... what are you?
I'm a human. What are you?
I uh... I uh...
Don't... know.
Once, I knew who I was.
It was a me.
A Mario.
But now, I know nothing.
You don't understand!
I am not a human! I am not a toad!
You're a... Mario!
What is a Mario?
You're my husband!
That's not enough!
Whoever fights monsters should see to it he does not become a monster himself.
And if you gaze long enough into an abyss,
the abyss will gaze back into you.
And he will become a monster.
You're tearing this family apart!
Shut the fuck up, Luigi!
Brings himself of a being, a man.
Ha ha ha ha ha!
Who am I?
Amen.
It's me.
One of the things unique to audio and video games
that is often done with a very small team.
Unlike, say, graphics, which can employ many, many artists
and programmers working to achieve a desired visual
effect, audio often comes down to the craftsmanship
of just a few people.
Sometimes it's just one slightly weird dedicated person
working hard to achieve their vision.
In this way, audio developers impact a game on a much more personal level than almost
any other discipline, which is pretty fucking cool.
This is the part where I describe how these special privileges make audio people really
difficult to deal with at times, like especially around deadlines.
But honestly, I actually really believe that audio folks are the truly unsung heroes of game development.
So I'm just going to let these nominees roll with mucho gratitude.
Best Audio
Cuphead
Developed by Studio MDHR
Christopher Madigan
Luke Hatton
Chris Sweetman
Samuel Justice
Nier Automata, developed by Platinum Games, published by Square Enix.
Kaichi Okabe.
Yoko Taro.
Yosuke Saito.
Hellblade, Senua's Sacrifice, developed by Ninja Theory.
David Garcia Diaz.
The Legend of Zelda Breath of the Wild.
Developed by Nintendo EPD.
Published by Nintendo.
The Nintendo EPD team.
Horizon Zero Dawn.
Developed by Guerrilla Games.
Published by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
The Guerrilla team.
And the Best Audio Award goes to...
The Legend of Zelda.
Awesome. Hi everyone, and thank you so much for this award.
My name is Cindy. I work at Nintendo, and it is my honor, my privilege, to accept this award tonight
on behalf of the Zelda team and also on behalf of
Nintendo guy who couldn't be here tonight.
We like him, he's a keeper.
Now, Hajime Wakai is not only a really cool name to say,
Hajime Wakai and his team of talents are responsible for the amazing sounds in Zelda,
and often theatrical sounds.
You know, so whether it's the, for me, the sound of the wind blowing through that grassy plain
or the buzz of the insects that you hear when you're standing on a mountain at sunrise,
Hyrule really feels alive in this game and that has everything to do with sound design.
So on behalf of Mr. Wakai and his team, thank you so much.
Tonight's fourth nominee for Game of the Year,
PlayerUnknown's Battlegrounds,
developed by PUBG Corporation.
Chang Han Kim, Brendan Green, Tae Seok Jang, Chang Ho Lee.
Let's give it up for Nintendo Girl.
No, seriously, he's really cool.
Art direction is a miracle.
The ability to pluck ideas from one's brain
and bring them to life on screen is truly amazing.
That this happens in the crucible of game development,
where a team's vision is often at odds with the game engine,
schedule, budget.
the producer, your mom, means that when everything does come together, it is a sight to behold.
Who can forget the first time they saw games like Inside, Firewatch, or The Witness?
Truly beautiful games whose visuals serve to complement or even amplify all the other
elements of the gameplay experience inside them.
This year's batch of nominees for Best Visual Art are no different.
Here are the nominees.
Best Visual Art.
Persona 5, developed by P Studio, published by Atlas.
Katsura Hashino, Shigenori Soejima, Naoto Hiraoka.
Cuphead, developed by Studio MDHR.
Chad Moldenhauer, Jared Moldenhauer, Maya Moldenhauer.
Horizon Zero Dawn, developed by Guerrilla Games, published
by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
The Guerrilla Team.
The Legend of Zelda Breath of the Wild.
Developed by Nintendo EPD.
Published by Nintendo.
The Nintendo EPD team.
Night in the Woods.
Developed by Infinite Fall.
Published by Finji, Scott Benson,
Charles Putner, Adam Salsman,
Sven Ruttnar.
There should really be five envelopes here,
so I'm only gonna open the one,
but it's a really tough category.
Winner for best visual art goes to Cuphead.
Thanks to everybody that believed in our crazy little game and supported us, because of course,
without you buying it, Chad and Jared would now be in crippling debt forever.
I'd like to give a shout out to all the other artists that couldn't make it to the stage
today.
Tina Novrocki.
Joseph Coleman, Caitlin Russell, Ali Morby, Maya Moldenhauer,
and of course, Chad Moldenhauer,
who single-handedly animated and designed
the very first trailer that caught the eyes
and imaginations of so many of you.
Thank you all.
Sweetheart, boobie, you wanna invest in the future of video games, take it from me, okay?
Nobody's gonna wanna spend $300 on a home console when they could put a couple of quarters in at the arcade, am I right?
Just one second, daddy needs a bump.
Pwa ha ha ha ha ha!
What the fuck?
You wanna waste your time with a playing card company?
Nintendo?
More like Nintendon't waste my money, am I right?
Look, this is what you wanna invest in, okay?
I just got a box of mint-kindish copies
of E.T. for the Atari 2600.
That's right, the Spielberg picture.
So how many can I put you down for?
One second, let me pop these ludes.
So, are we in business?
Say what?
Look, just roll with me on this one, okay?
The only way to tell stories in games is through cutscenes, alright?
I bet my life on it.
Shit.
Okay, look.
I know I haven't always been right, okay?
But what I know for sure is that gamers love good graphics and a linear story, okay?
Take your shit and get out!
I'm keeping the house.
Baby, wait, please, baby, just give me a second.
Just, I'll, look, do not invest in mobile games,
whatever you do.
Shh, baby, listen to me, listen to me, okay?
You cannot do free to play.
You have to charge at least 50 bucks up front
if you want to snowball's chance in hell
of making your money back, okay?
Don Giovanni sends his regards.
No, no, no, please, I'll get you the money!
Consoles need cutting-edge hardware!
It's all anybody cares about!
All right, everyone, come get your Wii's.
Whoa!
That's all here for all that great advice.
Designers are often seen as the rock stars of our industry.
The designer is the creative force of a project that does
most of the press and gets to make all sorts of glamorous
decisions on the features and the feel and the tone that go
into the video games that we love to play.
I look around this room.
I see a lot of designers I know and trust.
I've got a couple of questions for you.
Number one, if your game had only one button in it,
would you make that button R3?
Have you ever, and I mean ever, considered the possibility
of putting a headphone jack into a child's chest?
Number three, do you like anime?
If you answered yes to all these questions,
then you're actually Kojima and your leather pants are on fire.
For everyone else, thanks for working so hard to make games
better one failure at a time.
The Best Design Award nominees are Best Design.
Super Mario Odyssey, developed by Nintendo EPD,
published by Nintendo.
The Nintendo EPD team.
Horizon Zero Dawn, developed by Gorilla Games,
published by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
The Gorilla team.
Player Unknown's Battlegrounds, developed by PUBG Corporation.
Chang Han Kim.
Brendan Green,
Taesuk Jang,
Changho Lee.
The Legend of Zelda Breath of the Wild.
Developed by Nintendo EPD.
Published by Nintendo.
The Nintendo EPD Team.
NieR Automata.
Developed by Platinum Games.
Published by Square Enix.
Yoko Taro, Yosuke Saito, Takahisa Tarua.
And the Best Design Award goes to...
The Legend of Zelda.
I'm a Nintendo girl.
I wish I had worn higher heels said no one ever.
So many aspects of this game's design were remarkable.
From the massive world that the developers built to the open-air game structure that
literally tore down Zelda standards and gave players absolute freedom.
And all of it really comes down to a singular vision and
we are beyond happy that it connected with so so many people.
Thank you so much on behalf of Mr. Aonuma
and Mr. Fujibayashi and the entire Zelda team.
And now our fifth and final nominee for Game of the Year,
Horizon Zero Dawn.
Developed by Guerrilla Games.
Published by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
Praying won't save us.
The Guerrilla Team.
So you will have to leave the sacred land.
Where the trail leads, I will go.
To be totally honest with y'all, it's pretty hard for me to stand up here and give an award
away for VR.
Because most early titles on new platforms are glorified tech demos plus shooting, which
I kind of fucking detest.
At the same time, I just self-published an artsy-fartsy VR fairy tale about a little
bird who swallows the last piece of the waning moon, so...
You clearly should not come to me for advice about what will sell.
But all joking aside, I do truly think that someday there will be VR games that expand
the way that people see our medium, which is an art form.
And that's why I'm truly hoping that people actually fucking buy VR hardware this holiday season.
Tonight's VR nominees are...
Best VR AR game.
Superhot VR, developed by the Superhot team.
Tomasz Kaszmarszczyk, Piotr Iwanicki.
Star Trek Bridge Crew, developed by Red Storm Entertainment, published by Ubisoft.
David Botipka, Robbie Edwards, Clark Gibson.
Lone Echo, developed by Ready at Dawn, published by Oculus Studios.
The Ready at Dawn team.
Resident Evil 7 Biohazard, developed by Capcom.
Jun Takeuchi, Koshi Nakanishi, Masachika Kawata.
The Elder Scrolls V Skyrim VR,
developed by Bethesda Game Studios,
published by Bethesda Softworks.
Todd Howard, Andrew Scharf, Jesse Flanagan.
This year's winner for VR AR game is...
Superhot.
Wow.
Well, that was unexpected.
Did you see the other nominees?
It's actual big brand names this time.
So I guess, Robin, there's actually hope for VR.
Somebody's yanked by the headset.
So well, it's been.
It's been a pretty wild year for us in terms of VR,
and I would like to thank pretty much everybody.
But I will also allow a couple of words
to our game director, who's currently down with a cold
at our crummy indie Airbnb.
At least we think it's cold.
It's either cold or a typhoid fever from what we've seen.
So Piotr, say hi to everybody.
Bye everybody. Thank you.
The crowd is amazing, Piotr.
Wish you could see it.
And I wish that all of the guys back at home in Poland
will see it as well.
The creative team is extremely smart.
And there's, I think, about three dozen of us right now.
And we hope to stay in the industry.
And we hope to build more VR stuff in the future.
So all the Bethesdas and the Ubisofts of the world,
please keep up the good work.
We need your customers to buy our games as well.
Thank you guys.
And now, to present this year's Lifetime Achievement Award, please welcome to the stage, the producer
of the Game Awards, Jeff Keighley.
Hello everyone, surprise. How you doing?
Alright, well this is a really special moment for me.
Because back in 2007, Shigeru Miyamoto won the GDC Lifetime Achievement Award.
And he told Time Magazine that the obvious objective of video games is to entertain people by surprising them with new experiences.
Tim Schafer is a guy who specializes in the new.
Tim of Legend!
I have been playing Tim's games for so long, since I was a little kid.
And he specializes in the new.
He bursts new worlds, brainstorms new characters and architects new experiences, time and time again.
Tim is one of our gaming industry's most original and creative thinkers.
He's also, of course, one of the funniest.
Now, at a time when the breadth and depth of content made by this industry can be misrepresented,
Tim's fun, colorful, and comedic games are more important than ever.
Now, I first came across Tim's work when I was very young, about 12 years old, because
between schoolwork, I'd play LucasArts Adventure Games home in Canada, where Tim got his start
with a $27,000 a year salary, working on some of the earliest adventure games.
And of course, there was The Secret of Monkey Island, where he learned about game design
from the legendary Ron Gilbert.
Let's hear it for Monkey Island.
And one of my favorites, Day of the Tentacle, which he designed alongside Dave Grossman.
I will still always remember the CD-ROM talkie version of Dot,
and my quest to power up the Chrono-John.
These are memories from many years ago, but they still stick with me.
Now, as I played those games, I couldn't quite believe this rich, interactive storybook
that I could shape with the click of a mouse.
And, you know, I remember me and my brother playing through those games,
trying to figure out the puzzles, the inventory items,
and often resorting to CompuServe to get hints to figure out how to get through
these incredible games that Tim built many decades ago.
Now, as Tim's career progressed at LucasArts,
he started designing his own games like Full Throttle.
Yes.
And Grim Fandango, which is celebrating an anniversary this year.
Now, these seminal games help cement Tim's signature style,
rich, quirky worlds with funny talking characters
and challenging puzzles.
Now, one of the things that I most admire about Tim
is how over a 30 year career,
he's never built games based on what genre
is trending in the market.
He builds what's in his heart.
And we love you for it, Tim.
And Tim has put everything on the line time and again in pursuit of his art.
Today he runs his own independent studio, Double Fine, right here in San Francisco.
Home town boy.
It hasn't been an easy 18 years for Double Fine, but together with his fans and his team,
they've found a way to fund and support their own games like Psychonauts,
Psychonauts 2 in production now, and Broken Age,
and even pay it forward by helping other smaller developers through Double Fine Presents.
Tonight it is my great honor to present GDC's Lifetime Achievement Award to a friend who's
built some of this industry's most memorable and new experiences, and on a personal level
has helped inspire me to devote my career to celebrating games and the people who make
them.
Ladies and gentlemen, please welcome to the stage Tim of Legend.
Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you, buddy.
Thanks so much. I should.
Thanks. I got this.
I got this.
Under control.
This is where I feel most comfortable.
I've hosted these awards many times,
and I thought I'm super, I'm the master of my domain here,
this is cool, I got this.
And then Jeff makes me feel like a blubbering idiot
with his little, yeah, but yeah, and all of you.
Thank you so much, thanks, thanks Jeff.
Thank you.
Thank you, everybody.
Thanks, everybody, here.
Thanks, everyone, at GDC.
Thanks to Simon and Katie and the spooky ghost of Megan Scavio.
Thanks, everyone, at Table 8.
Yeah, Table 8.
Everybody in the back, thank you.
Thank you so much.
This is a tremendous honor, and I'm incredibly humbled
and happy to be getting this award tonight.
So thank you.
I know what a lot of you are thinking.
How can I give this award to this guy?
He's so young.
But I'll have you know, the truth is, I've been, as Jeff spoiled, you know, in this industry almost 30 years.
To set that time in a particular place, when I started in the games industry in 1989, the Berlin Wall was still standing.
And then I started making games, and then the Berlin Wall fell.
Yeah. Great. Yes.
So you're welcome.
I'm not saying I did it all by myself, and I've got to thank a few people for that.
Much like my time at games, I've been incredibly lucky a lot of times, and I realized as I
was writing this, it's like a list of times when I should have died, and I didn't.
And I've got to thank all the people who helped me with that.
I've been so lucky in the just amazing people I've crossed paths with along the way.
I started my career in the industry at a company then called Lucasfilm Games, and David Fox
had no reason to hire me, especially after in my interview I totally accidentally confessed
to pirating Ballblazer.
But he did, and I'm so grateful for everything that happened after.
And I want to thank Noah Faustine for giving me a crash course in programming AI
so that I could write the ship combat in Monkey Island.
And I want to thank Ron Gilbert for cutting the ship combat in Monkey Island.
Yep.
Thank you.
I assume because it was so good that he couldn't beat it.
I'm really grateful for Ron for picking me and Dave Grossman to work on Monkey Island,
Secret of Monkey Island, my first gig in games.
I learned a lot from Ron, and I especially had to stop worrying and stop censoring my
own ideas.
I wrote a joke.
really quickly about a three-headed monkey.
And Ron came out to see it and I was like,
don't worry, that's temporary dialogue,
I'm gonna take out the three-headed monkey joke.
And Ron's like, no, we're keeping it.
And in fact, we're gonna have Steve Russell
draw a three-headed monkey, it's gonna be great.
And I was like, what?
And then it really is like a profound moment for me
to realize that...
Me, like everybody is so creative and one of our biggest problems is just how much we censor ourselves.
How much we like, that's too silly, that's too ridiculous, I can't share that with people.
And that experience made me realize that I should just let it out.
And that's formed the tone of everything I've made ever since.
So thanks Ron for that.
Thanks also to Dave Grossman for pushing me to be a better writer just by sitting next
to me and writing such amazing dialogue in the next desk.
I want to thank, how lucky was I to work down the hallway from Hal Barwood, the director
of Corvette Summer, right?
Right down the hallway, who taught me when I was whining about how I had to cut the dialogue
down by half and he was like, just do it.
And he taught me how to edit my own dialogue and not worry about it, and it's the greatest
lesson I ever learned.
Be ruthless when editing your own dialogue.
Oh my God.
I want to thank all the great people and smart people in LucasArts upper management, Lucy Bradshaw, and...
Well, that's it.
Sorry, team.
I have been lucky enough to work with the best artists in the industry, Peter Chan, Larry Ahern, Peter Sakel, Scott Campbell, Lee Petty, and others!
See? I've met amazing composers, Michael Lang, Kumpa Jekian, and sitting over here at table 8,
the man who's scored almost every game I've ever made, Peter McConnell, right there.
Special thanks to you, Peter.
I want to thank all the amazing people who make all my dialogue sound so much better
than it is.
The amazing actors I've worked with, and the amazing producers and directors and casting
agents back at LucasArts, Cameron Nealio, Dara Farrow, and especially Chris Brown, who's
also sitting right here.
Chris Brown, thank you so much.
I've worked with Chris since like 1992 or like 1850, I don't remember.
She can like cast, direct, and edit and somehow convince movie stars to work for indie game
rates and it's amazing and I owe her so much.
Thank you, Chris.
I want to thank everybody, but I'm sorry, I'm running out of time.
Thanks to the amazing animators.
I love animators.
Thank the amazing programmers and the testers and the producers I've worked with.
Thank heaven help all the producers who have to keep me on schedule.
By the way, we're hiring producers right now, so forget I said that.
It's great to work with me as a producer.
Thanks to all the publishers we work with.
And we work with just about all of them.
But I want to call out one in particular.
When Psychonauts was canceled, we took it around to get it re-signed,
and everybody passed on it.
Everybody.
Not that I'm bitter.
That's what this is about.
We're going to settle some scores.
No, I'm kidding.
I want to call out one in particular.
We would have gone out of business in 2004 if it wasn't
for a little family operation in Jersey called Majesco.
So I want to thank the Sutton family
for helping us out with that.
Jesse and Joey and all the Suttons.
Also thanking us through that really trying time
with Seamus Blackley and all his cohorts at CAA.
It was really great to have someone
on our side during a horrible experience like that.
And I want to thank...
Okay, wait, now, I have to tell a story now.
I asked for permission to tell a story and I didn't get permission, but then that bartender
over there served me four shots of tequila, so.
In between getting canceled and getting signed by Majesco,
there was a long period we didn't have any money,
and we ran out of money.
And I had to make a talk to the whole company
and tell them that the next payroll was not coming,
and there were 30 people who were like,
we've been crunching on a game for four years,
and now it's gonna disappear,
and no one will ever know that this company ever existed.
Which is hilarious if you've ever been in that position,
it's really fun.
So I thought, hey, I was really desperate, and there was one lifeline I could call.
I had a friend who had sold his company to EA, and I thought he might be able to make
that kind of loan.
I hated to do it, but I called him and I said, I hate to ask you, but if you lend me that
money, I'll give you like 10% of my company.
Oh my God, please help us out.
And he said, I'll think about it.
I'll go talk to our lawyers, and I'll see if I can do that.
And I sat there at my desk and it was just, I chewed off all my fingernails and then he called back and he's like,
my lawyer's telling me I can't take stock in another game company.
So, I'm just gonna give you the money.
And I lent you the money and it was amazing.
It was just, it had such an effect on me.
It's just that I was...
I was so embarrassed and desperate to make that call and just to be met with that kind of generosity
um
Anyway, anyway, um, it struck me and so to this day
Thank you
And so Tuesday, if you play one of my games, you'll see special thanks to Will Wright.
And I want to thank Will.
It's nice.
Thanks, Will.
I hope it's okay if I told that story, but no one else got to ask him for money, I swear.
Don't do it.
It really struck me and it motivates me to do whenever I try to, I really want to help
people as best as I can because I remember how that felt to be in that position.
Anyway, we didn't go out of business and we're still here 18 years later.
There are a lot of double finers here in the audience tonight.
They're the loud ones in the back.
Double fine!
Hey, there they are.
I want to thank everybody at Double Fine, all the beautiful people at Double Fine.
A special shout out to the veterans who worked at the company for 16 or 17 years.
Ray Crook, Dave Russell, Jeff Solis, Kee Chee, Anna Kipnis, Nathan Stapley, and the rest
of you.
I want to thank all the new employees too for injecting so much new blood into the company.
Oh, I broke the trophy.
I'm so sorry.
Anyway.
Thank you, everybody.
I want to thank also Justin Bailey for boldly going into
Entrata waters with Fig and taking us and other crowdfunding
entities on a crazy journey with him.
And I want to thank a man who, if not the tallest person in
the games industry, he's the tallest in my heart.
I want to thank Greg Rice for all the work he does.
And keep being.
Not just in keeping Double Fine afloat,
but also in helping out other indies
with Double Fine Presents and Day of the Devs.
Thank you.
And I want to thank my wife, Rachel,
who's sitting right there.
Rachel.
Yeah, I met Rachel in 2003,
right before we went into Psychonauts Crunch Mode.
And I was like, I'm a big time game person,
it's gonna be great.
Everything's going to be easy.
And she has stuck with me through that and through everything that's came after.
So thank you.
And I didn't trip on the little hologram stairs, by the way.
So credit for that.
And finally, I want to thank all the backers and all the players everywhere
for not just playing our games, but reaching out to us and letting us know
that they matter to you, because that has made all the difference.
And so that's it.
I want to tell you, even though you gave me this Lifetime Achievement Award
that I broke, I'm not going to stop making games.
Because.
Right?
Because, uh, because I can't afford to.
But there's so many memories came up when I was making this list.
It's easy to look back on all the games and all the ups and downs
and the roller coaster and the troubles and everything.
But what I realized when I was making this list is this crazy collection of human beings
that really makes this experience so meaningful and made it possible and so rewarding.
So I want to thank everybody.
That's really what keeps me making games is all these people.
So I want to thank you again for all your help over the years.
And I want to thank you again for this generous, generous reward.
Thank you everybody.
Cheers to Tim Schafer!
And Will fucking Wright.
All right, a little emotional here.
If we've learned anything over the past few years,
It's that the collective wisdom of the voting populace
is an error-free, finely-tuned, victory machine.
Collectively, we are simply incapable of making a bad choice.
The board doesn't have shit on us.
And with that in mind, we turn our eyes to the Audience Award, wherein the same people
that voted a research submarine, Bodie McBoatface, decide what their favorite game was last year.
I for one can't wait to find out what we all picked.
Alright, here we go motherfuckers.
The audience award goes to Nira Otamada!
Good choice!
Thank you.
Yeah.
So I didn't think that I'll be able to win an award. So we
really rushed up here.
Thank you everyone for giving us a vote.
Thank you.
Man, this job just keeps getting better and better.
All right, it says here on this envelope, Choice Innovation Award.
While games is a growing business, the community of developers is fairly tight-knit.
That means that many of you will recognize folks running in tonight's memoriam reel.
Let's take a moment to note their passing and recognize their contributions.
What is innovation?
What's the sound?
One hand clapping.
This category is often the place where we put games
that probably won't sell, but look really fucking cool.
And also, games about difficult subjects,
like love, sex, collaboration, and compromise.
In the end, there's never one clear definition of what pushes the boundaries of our craft.
However, there can only be one chicken dinner.
Tonight's nominees for innovation are...
Gorogoa, developed by Buried Signal.
Published by Annapurna Interactive.
Jason Roberts.
The Legend of Zelda, Breath of the Wild,
developed by Nintendo EPD.
Published by Nintendo.
The Nintendo EPD team.
What Remains of Edith Finch.
Developed by Giant Sparrow.
Published by Anna Purna Interactive.
The Giant Sparrow Team.
Everything.
Developed by David O'Reilly.
Published by Double Fine Productions.
The Everything Team.
Player Unknown's Battlegrounds, developed by PUBG Corporation.
Chang Han Kim, Brendan Green, Taesuk Jang, Chang Ho Lee.
The Innovation Award goes to Gora Goa.
Well, I left my sensible career path in my late 30s and I'm over 40 now and my knees
hurt.
So I guess it's never too late to innovate.
I just want to say that I'm in an extremely lucky position to have contributed to three games in this category.
So I want to thank David O'Reilly for letting me make sounds to the universe
and introducing me to the words of Alan Watts, which are life-changing.
And to Giant Sparrow for also letting me contribute
to their beautiful narrative experience.
And Jason, thank you again.
Alright, thank you.
Thanks.
Thank you.
Jake also helps me run SF Indies.
Shout out to all SF developers in the room.
He keeps us from never meeting because I'm always so fucking busy.
Anyway.
As someone whose team won this award years ago, I have to keep saying that because it's
the only reason that a publisher would ever give me any money.
I can say that there is no better feeling than to have been chosen as the Game of the
Year by all you motherfuckers.
Yes, the industry is callous and cold-hearted at times.
Yes, we tend to privilege games with huge budgets and huge sales numbers.
Yes, we still have a real shortage of games with strong black protagonists.
But, we're working on that shit.
I'm looking at you, Campo Santo.
When all is said and done, what matters the most is that we keep focusing on new designs,
new technologies, and new stories that open our field to new players who will one day
grace this stage as developers themselves.
Every one of us started as a kid playing games.
And every one of us will start as a kid playing games.
Let's hear it for all the kids out on the internet right now.
Internet teens who are playing games!
Applause
Once again, here's the recap of all of tonight's Game of the Year nominees.
Game of the Year.
PlayerUnknown's Battlegrounds.
Nier Automata.
The Legend of Zelda Breath of the Wild.
Horizon Zero Dawn. ♪♪
Super Mario Odyssey. ♪♪
You all touched so many hearts this year.
Thank you for all the hard work your teams did.
You all deserve a round of applause before I open this envelope.
Come on!
Alright, ladies and gentlemen, the 2018 winner of the Game Developers Choice Awards Game of the Year is The Legend of Zelda.
Come on, Nintendo girl, get up here!
Wow. Thank you so much. Just beyond a great, really great big thank you, the only other
thing I really want to say is that this particular Game of the Year award is especially meaningful
and especially humbling for our developers because they're voted on by their fellow developers.
So thank you for that.
Speaking of those guys, I couldn't possibly do this award acceptance justice without their help.
So let me turn it over now to Mr. Ayanuma and Mr. Fujibayashi. Thank you.
Hello GDC and gamers everywhere.
Thank you to all the developers who voted for the Legend of Zelda and Breath of the Wild for Game of the Year.
It is an honor.
I would also like to take this opportunity to thank all the games nominated for this award.
In the Legend of Zelda series, discovery and exploration are two major themes.
This time, the production of Legend of Zelda, which is different from the previous series, was a journey of discovery and exploration for us.
We are deeply grateful for the enthusiasm and support we have received from many people for our challenge.
The Legend of Zelda series has warm fans who have supported us for over 30 years.
I think that the fact that you have come on this great adventure together with us is a sign of love for the Zelda series.
The positive reactions we've received so far will continue to give fans new surprises.
On behalf of the Zelda team and Nintendo,
Thank you!
Seriously, how many hours of this game have you all played?
Let's just really seriously, how many hours of Zelda have we all played?
This is amazing.
It's a great franchise.
All right.
That is all, folks.
Award shows are never short enough, and there are never enough trophies to go around.
And everyone here deserves at least two more drinks than they got while sitting here listening to me talk.
Once again, it is a huge honor to have been up here and give away these awards to people
that I know personally have struggled to make this art, to make this industry open and diverse
and amazing.
And I want you to just all give a huge round of applause to all of tonight's nominees.
And since I'm the queen of the universe right in this very moment, I'm gonna ask you all to make great games in 2018
and for the love of God fucking vote!
See you all next year.
You