Hi guys, thank you for coming today.
My name is Weori.
I'm a game developer from Osaka, Japan.
I would like to send my gratitude to you guys here.
I have important information for this panel.
I will touch about all of the stories of the mission today.
So it means I will talk about big spoiler.
Yeah, please notice that.
And one more, you might not able to a lot of laugh
as like my panel at Indie Softbox,
because I would like to show my serious side for you guys today.
Okay, let's start.
Okay, let's move. I will talk in Japanese because I have a great translator for today. She's Kyoko-san.
Please listen to the translation of my weird, bizarre talk.
Yeah.
Ja, sumimasen. Nihongo de hajimemasu.
Alright, let's get started.
The missing no kihon johou iimasu.
So then, what is the missing?
Ichiban, mizukara no karada wo kizuzukete susumu puzzle platformer de aru.
The puzzle platformer de aru.
So we're going to start off with the basics.
It's a puzzle platformer where you need to damage or hurt your own body in order to proceed.
Secondly, this is our debut title for the studio, White Owls Inc.
There are a lot of awards, including the Navigator Award.
And this title received many nominations and won some awards, including the Navigator Awards.
The categories we won are Best Original Adventure and Original Song.
Two categories, very important categories.
Two, which is the same amount or number of categories that Red Dead Redemption 2 won in.
Yes.
Yeah.
How about that?
Thank you.
Yeah, but God of War is in volume 16.
But then again, okay, God of War won in 16, so...
Yeah.
The most unique feature of the game system is that it's a system where it creates a cycle of self-mutilation and regeneration through the puzzles.
Where you serve your arm and throw it to knock down something that's high up.
Cut your body in half to balance a seesaw.
Or you light your body on fire and use it to navigate through the darkness.
And you would also slam yourself into a wrecking ball to break your bones and solve a gravity puzzle.
And here I'd like to give a quick summary of the story.
The first half of the story is about a hero who visits a island called Tuiokutou with his best friend,
and he suddenly loses his best friend on a stormy night and goes to look for him.
So for the first half, the main character visits Memoria Island
with her best friend, who goes missing during a storm.
And then the main character heads deep into the island
in order to find her.
Speaking Japanese
A sudden strike of lightning gives the main character the power of immortality,
which allows her to survive through repeated suffering and regeneration,
all in order to find her friend.
And as the story approaches the second half, we're led to the clock tower,
which shouldn't really be there.
So, the player discovers that the main character had actually died, and this is the afterlife.
And so, the main character is on the brink of death, teetering on the thin line between life and death with her immortal body,
and the world of the island represents the world inside her mind.
And then at the ending, or after the ending, the player realizes that this painful adventure wasn't a search for the best friend,
but a story of regeneration, where the character found herself again in order to be reborn. That's the storyline.
So next, I'd like to talk a little bit about how the gameplay is fused with the game design.
So in The Missing, what I call there are two axes of suffering and rebirth.
So on the game system side, you have physical pain through self-mutilation and the power to revive infinitely. ストーリーの方では徐々に明らかになっていく心の痛みとそれを打ち破るという再生の物語
On the story side, you have mental pain that gradually becomes clear and a story about a rebirth that overcomes it.
At the start of the game, most of you here too, probably, the players will likely just get a very superficial impression of,
hmm, this looks like a unique puzzle game or a mysterious world with a charming girl.
However, through repeated suffering and rebirth come together as one sensation over the course of the game,
the player ends up sharing the pain, giving them the same experience as the main character.
In other words, the game play of self-determination and the pain of the protagonist's temporary experience are synchronized.
We aimed to make the player accept the conflict in the ending.
So in other words, the pain you put yourself through in The Missing is synchronized with the main character's mental anguish as they waver on the brink of death.
After finishing the ending, the player is able to accept all their contradictory actions.
By the way, I have maybe 30 more slides.
So, you're probably wondering which one came first, the chicken or the egg?
First, I made a hypothesis.
The more the game's story is strongly connected to the gameplay experience,
the more the player will be moved.
And by the chicken and the egg, I meant the story or the game design, obviously.
So I started by putting together a hypothesis.
The more a game story is strongly fused with its gameplay,
the more it will move its players.
I was also convinced that this was something
that could not be achieved in other media besides games.
And I knew at that time, I was so sure that this was a method of story writing that cannot
be achieved by any media other than games.
So, to prove that hypothesis, I decided not to write the scenario ahead of time.
And based on that hypothesis, I decided not to write the scenario ahead of time.
Specifically, I decided to make the story based on gameplay,
and not create a stage for the story, but a story on top of the game.
And specifically what I mean by this is that I adopted the method of making all the story beats rely on gameplay.
So the gameplay is not created for the story, but rather placing the story beats on top of gameplay.
And then I also decided to keep the very strange and sort of bizarre hooks
separate from all the story beats.
They only exist as parts of the performance within the cut scenes.
And I decided on locations beforehand that would ensure that the story flowed together,
even though I hadn't started writing it.
And I picked locations that would make sense and work that way.
So for example, forest, waterfall, fields, a waste plant, diner, factories.
These could be placed in any order,
and they wouldn't break the mood or the atmosphere and wouldn't affect the storyline.
I'll explain it in a more simple flow.
So let's put the process into simpler terms.
It would look something like this.
First, we'll decide the basic system of the game.
So first of all, the story decision process, basic game system decisions.
Those are the decisions we make.
And next we have the synopsis.
And then next it says death methods, but what kind of puzzles would we implement?
And we talked about those and made the decisions.
Location details and the order.
And then the various level design details, what kind of puzzles.
And lastly, only after all the above, the main story writing began.
It actually ended up being a little bit more complicated.
So this is what it really looked like.
I won't read this, so please take a picture quickly.
Yeah, so this is now your chance to take a picture,
because I won't go into detail.
OK. 5, 4, 3, 2, 1.
Go.
Next, I will talk about the relationship between the game system and the main character.
In order to make the game experience the two-axis play and the two-axis play,
the first thing you need to do is to make a strong connection with the game system.
So in order to make the mechanics of suffering and rebirth
into a game experience, the first thing
that needs to be put together is a game system
that is strongly fused with the story and the main character.
So here's a question.
Why is the main character a girl
rather than an undead creature or a dark hero?
How did I decide on this?
It depends on what the player wants to experience.
So how do you think I decided on this?
What sort of story is it? What sort of main character would be best?
We needed to decide on what we want the player to experience
before we decided on that.
For example, in the case of gun shooting,
So here's an example if we're talking about a game with a gun combat. 基本のゲームは銃を撃って敵を殺すということにしましょう。
Okay, so let's say the basic system of our game involves shooting a gun to take down targets. Very simple.
I'll give you three examples of what kind of feeling you want to give the player.
It can be a sense of excitement, mission, or accomplishment.
Or it can be a sense of determination or reality.
It all depends on that.
So then, what is the sensation you want to give the player?
This is very crucial in determining the main thrust of the story of the protagonist.
So let me give you a few examples.
The sensation of exhilaration, a sense of duty.
or accomplishment, is it urgency or is it reality?
So, seen here, there are certain kinds of stories that would be fitting for each sensation.
If you had a game where an ex-Special Forces character who became a cook or a chef
goes around shooting up zombies, it would be difficult to express something other than exhilaration.
I think the sense that the player gives is the most important part to decide the story and the character.
So this is the area highlighted in the yellow box.
This is the most important sort of aspect to look at when determining the factors.
So then let's talk about or apply that to the missing.
So our basic system, as I've been saying,
is one in which you solve puzzles using self-mutilation and regeneration.
And using that, the sensations I wanted the player to experience were pain and salvation.
Which, as you can see here, naturally led to my decisions regarding the story and main characters.
And then, you need to feed back the main character and the story.
However, you're not done there.
Because once the story and main protagonist are decided,
you then proceed to feed that back into the game design.
You need to feed back on how the girl is destroyed
and how the story is created.
So for example, how would a young girl go about self-mutilation? How would she regenerate?
So moving on, in order to make it so people can sort of empathize with the story,
there are a variety of techniques I use this time around, which I will like to explain here.
The first thing is, the initial hook to the story should be as simple as possible.
So for The Missing, it's very simple.
You fall asleep with your best friend, only to await to discover that they are gone.
That's really it.
And if you want to present something strange or unusual,
have it acted out on screen in a very minimal manner as possible,
but don't stretch that out into a large act.
It might be difficult to do it one by one,
but we'll do it in a way that doesn't affect the stage,
where the beautiful starry sky suddenly turns into rain and there's lightning.
And what I mean by this is that a quick example is that in this scene,
it was a beautiful starry sky just moments before.
Now some light rain is falling, the wind is blowing, and lightning is crashing down.
The sequence of events can be set in a very minimalistic manner.
But I also made it so that once you push things along,
the story's depth is supported by three parallel axes.
YUSUKE USTUNOMIYA So those three are first, present,
second, past, and third, a future that
begins from the past and present events overlapping.
So in the present, you proceed along set stages,
but since the past is comprised of events that already happened,
there is no impact on how we went about creating the stages.
Sorry, I already covered that past.
And since the future is only related to the last boss and ending,
the way we went about making the missing allowed us to work in some depth.
OK, we're at halfway point now.
And then we made the decision to make it a platformer.
So doing so makes it so that the player doesn't need to be told where to go.
All you're doing is just go to the right. Anyone can understand that.
What that meant is it made it possible to cut down on the amount of events and text
dedicated to instructing the player.
And I think this was the biggest sort of invention or discovery for us,
is that discussions from the past, which I mentioned previously,
can now be viewed here as a log on the smartphone.
So what we do here is we depicted JJ's relationships with the people around
as an indirect way of showing who she really is.
Okay, so we're going to speed it up a little bit here.
Okay.
Next, I was thinking that I wanted this game, The Missing,
to be played by the young people, the younger generation players and gamers.
And so writing the story, there are a few things that I kept in mind.
First is I made the main character's problem something life-sized and very personal.
Next point is that there is no need for any of the story to be about saving the world.
And I did a very thorough sort of surveying and discussion
and really almost like interviewing the younger
generation folks.
And what I learned from that is that there
was a desire for recognition and self-actualization.
And so I really wanted to hone in and focus on those topics.
I don't know if I can say it in English, but I'm using my university life as a second writer to express the blueness that I can't express to an old man.
Next, I actually hired a graduate student as a secondary writer
to bring out the youthfulness that I may not have anymore
because I am a ojisan, an old man.
Yeah, me.
And so that was very helpful.
And also, to make it easier for people to read the text,
I used a tool that young people usually use to read the story.
And then I used text messages on a smartphone, a very common everyday,
we're on it all the time.
And it felt very much more like a daily thing that you're already used to doing.
So, now we're going to talk about some of the scenario creation rules
that I applied for The Missing.
So I showed this to the younger graduate student that I just mentioned.
I'll just say that you shouldn't look at the wiki and write.
Okay, well, one that I want to mention is that don't look it up on the wiki and then write.
Can I move forward?
Yes, okay.
I wanted to create a work that never pauses,
just like a movie that never has a scene cut, like Gravity Zero.
So I'm going to try to put this in a way that hopefully sounds pretty cool.
I wanted to create a work that never pauses,
just like a movie that never has a scene cut, like Gravity Zero.
It's not that you shouldn't do it because it's indie,
but it's important to know how much the game will reach the real world
beyond the screen,
and how much it will attract players from outside the game.
If you don't think with enthusiasm,
you won't be able to impress people.
And I spent a lot of time thinking about how to make that possible as an indie developer.
How do I make the game world such that it bleeds out of the screen,
extends into the real world,
or what can be done to bring the player into the world within the screen?
This is something that I believe always needed to be kept in mind.
Next, I will talk about the main character, JJ McFeild.
Okay, so now we're going to do a deep dive into our main character, JJ McFeild.
I thought long and hard about how to go about making a very appealing main character.
And I questioned myself. I really want to find a character who I've never seen before.
In order to make her character loveable,
I thought it was essential to have admiration and empathy.
So I decided to create a portrait of her.
And to get people to love this character,
I hypothesized that there were two essential elements,
admiration and sympathy.
And I started from there.
To realize these two,
I decided that it would be best to depict
the person I see and feel from the inside
that everyone has.
And that's how I made JJ.
So try to bring these to life.
I determined that the best choice would be to depict
the two sides that any person possesses.
The you that other people see
and the you that exists within yourself.
That and how to go about depicting it
brought me to my next problem.
I was sure I could accomplish my goal of making players feel a sense of admiration for JJ
through her regenerative abilities and her mission to save her best friend,
but I spent a great deal of time thinking about how to inspire sympathy for the character.
But at some point, I realized that I had to face prejudice
in order to gain people's sympathy.
Then one day I realized that in order to inspire a sense of sympathy
that transcends boundaries such as gender, race, language, and ideology,
I concluded that it was necessary to come face to face
with the reality that is prejudiced.
So I am of the opinion that all people in some way are simultaneously both in the majority and also in the minority.
Since I am Japanese, I am a minority, but if I go back to Japan, I am an overwhelming majority.
So here today, as I stand in front of you, I'm a Japanese, so I'm in the minority.
But when I fly back to Japan, of course, that's my home country, I'm in the majority.
And with those thoughts in mind, upon reaching the ending,
I was hoping that players would have realized the same truth on their own.
Bless you.
Okay, so here's the flow of the fusion between admiration and sympathy that I aim for with
The Missing.
Here's the flow of the fusion between admiration and sympathy that I aim for with
So at the very beginning of the game,
players start playing under the assumption
that as a human, they're in the majority.
And then synchronization with the main characters
begin naturally as you start controlling the character.
But in this game, from the beginning to the middle,
you can see that you are a minority in this world.
You can see that in the gameplay,
and the story is a mysterious story.
It's all ingrained in the game.
However, from the beginning to the middle part,
the game suddenly imprints the idea that in the world of this,
the missing, you're a minority, from both monsters or enemies
appearing or from the storyline.
It does this from both gameplay and story perspectives.
And doing so completes the first stage of empathy.
This includes the bond the player feels towards Emily,
who is a fellow member of the minority.
As the story progresses, the game becomes more and more difficult.
The protagonist actually took the blame for being a minority and died.
Knowing that this is the story, the player's pain reaches its peak.
And upon reaching the second half of the game,
you learn that the protagonist ended her own life
due to her suffering as a minority,
and the game's difficulty increases in kind,
which brings the suffering of the player
to kind of a peak at that point.
However, upon reaching the ending, we expected that the players would be both proud of JJ
and themselves for overcoming their suffering, and feel like this was a story about themselves.
And then having experiences as both the majority and the minority,
and also having lived through that suffering,
I thought people might become aware of more diverse points of view and perspective.
This time, I was able to dig into JJ's character and discover another big discovery.
And then, digging into the character of JJ, I found a way to articulate something I had discovered.
The status of gender and LGBTQ is not a character's individuality.
You should not misunderstand it as individuality.
So, and this was something that I was already cognizant of, but was never able to state clearly.
The LGBTQ status should not be misunderstood as a character trait.
This is because, just like American or Japanese characters, LGBTQ is only a trait.
What's important is the person's personality, and what should be expressed is the only part of the character.
And quite often you will have works where characters' entire background will stop,
and start and stop with them being gay or lesbian.
This is the same as saying,
this character is a man or a woman, or American or non-American,
which isn't a character trait.
If you don't draw the character's personality, life, and thoughts
as more important than their status,
the character won't be attractive.
And from my own personal experience, and I hope you too, you are the same way too,
if you spend time with these people, they are clearly far more defined
by their individual personalities, ideals, and the lives that they've led.
And those are the things that you remember.
In my previous development experience, I would react to such biases and ignorance with
discussed and would reject them just outright without really explaining why.
But in the process of explicitly detailing my thoughts, I learned how to explain why this is wrong.
The one wonderful thing about discovering or realizing this is how it can be applied to
any character or how any character is shaped.
And as just stated in this slide, it could be an antithesis for, let's say,
for an easy female character or female protagonist idea, which you can then explain
and correct as needed, and the same goes for deciding what race to make a character.
You know, like, okay, we're talking about a Japanese character.
Okay, Japanese people are samurais.
Chinese people are chefs or kung fu masters or making Americans as soldiers.
I think you get the point.
Next, I'd like to talk about the characters that surround the main character.
OK, so I think we'll be able to fit all of my content in, so I'm gonna go through the next point,
which is the importance of characters who surround the main character.
I've summarized the elements to define the character's personality.
Okay, so I put together some elements that are used for defining personality when deciding on characters. これまでの人生
Life up to this point. 趣味・趣向と技能
Likes, hobbies, and skills. 興味の対象とその熟練度
Proficiency as an object of interest. 両親や友人、近親者の環境
parents, a friend, and family environment,
the objective assessment from a family or family member,
the surface level acquaintances and their objective assessment.
And your own self-image.
So these seven points I listed here, I actually, during my presentation in 2011 here at GDC,
I mentioned these in building a character resume.
This is necessary to determine the personality of the story,
not simulation or learning.
So, let's see what it's like in JJ's case.
So, you see the additional red phrases here.
Now, these elements were needed to give personality fitted to the story,
so they're not real life.
simulation based on science or theories or anything like that,
but more recipes for entertainment.
And so for The Missing, I really sort of emphasize on points 5 and 6.
5 and 6.
The people around JJ are the ones who are expressing 5 and 6.
So those in 5 and 6 are people who surround or around JJ.
Actually, the characters other than Emily don't appear in the 3D model.
But they play a very important role in understanding JJ's personality.
So Emily is actually the only one side character in this game who appears with a 3D model,
but she is crucial to understanding JJ's personality.
So if you're wondering why that is, it's because side characters in this game don't fulfill defined roles.
In other words, that character will always act in a way that seems natural and realistic for them, and the same goes for their speech.
Essentially, it's precisely because they do not exist for the purpose of pushing the story forward.
And here we have one of the most important points,
is the character, the fourth wall breaker character.
Breaking the fourth wall is something supernatural,
just as the metaphor suggests, and it's very important. 文字通り壁越えですよね。 壁越えする登場人物は、
自由に壁のこちら側と向こう側を行き来できる必要がある。 And characters who break the fourth wall
need to always be able to freely travel between both sides.
This time, FK, the stuffed animal, is playing the role.
He is... Is it okay to say he?
He has given depth to the world by crossing the boundaries of the water island and the real world.
So in this game, the wall breaker character is FK.
Is it a he? I think it's okay. Is this he?
A stuffed animal who can travel between the real world and Memorial Island.
And characters such as these, such as FK, are extremely important.
I believe how forcefully and sort of keenly a wall breaker like this could be used as
tremendous impact on the quality of the final story and work.
And to close things out, I would like to talk about something that was added at the very, very end of development.
So this message that you see here, this game was made with the belief that nobody is wrong for being what they are.
This message originally was not displayed at the beginning.
However, after speaking with my advisor for this game, I decided that it was necessary.
to put this at the beginning of the game.
So despite holding this belief from the beginning,
it never occurred to me that it should be displayed.
We had several meetings where we had discussed
whether or not to include a message along the lines of,
this work was created by people of various races,
faiths, and genders.
But looking back at it now, all I can think about
is how distasteful it would have been,
and almost sounds like an excuse.
It was like an excuse.
But the advisor told me what I wanted to say.
So I decided to just say it.
And so, yeah, sounding like an excuse, the advisor...
And I spoke to other friends who happened to be my...
The friend who happened to be my advisor, she said,
well, isn't this what you really want to say, Swery?
At the end of development, we were about to finish bug checking,
but the programmer was so angry that he said,
even if the producer is angry, just put it on.
So we did our best.
And this was really basically at the end of development.
The work had finished, we were doing our bug checking.
The programmer was not happy to get this message.
The producer was not happy to get this message either.
But we were able to somehow get it into the beginning of the game.
What I want to say is...
Do what you have to do, don't get caught up in development.
And after all that, what I'm really trying to say here is,
don't become a prisoner of your own development schedule.
Do what you need to do.
If you make this decision,
the project may end on schedule,
but you may lose the time and passion you put into it.
Please remember that.
if you make the wrong call on this front,
your game may release on schedule,
which seems like a good thing,
but it might not become something that reflects
all the time and effort you put in creating it.
So this is advice and guidance for you all
from my own experience.
De.
Eh.
Arigato.
Arigato gozaimasu.
The Missing is currently on sale.
It's 33% off on Switch, Xbox, PS4, and Steam.
But I don't know why, but the PlayStation Store for the US, for the North American users,
somehow it's not on sale. Don't blame me, it's not my fault, but sorry.
Please include the bit about the sale in the article.
This is part of my talk today, so anyone who's reporting and writing an article about today's talk,
please include the bit about the sale.
In bold, font, highlight, please.
Yeah, that's all. Thank you.
We have time for Q&A, but I had a pleasant surprise delivery of an audio message from a good friend of mine.
Would you like to hear that?
Does it work?
Oh, does it?
What?
Not tonight.
Audio is on?
It is?
One more time.
Hey, Zack, did you enjoy Swery's talk?
No, don't tell me.
I don't need your opinion.
By the way, congratulations on the success of The Missing.
It's great.
That's all.
Sorry, I got this message, so I played it.
Hello, Sueri.
Hi.
I can't see you.
It's okay.
So if Japanese characters are samurais, Americans are soldiers, what are the French?
Chef.
Any other countries?
Difficult.
I don't know.
You.
Hi.
Thank you for the talk.
I have not played the game.
I'm excited to get it on sale.
Spoiler alert!
Yeah, I know.
You should have guessed.
It's okay.
In the beginning, you talk about the kind of starting with the basic system of self-mutilation
and regeneration as a way to inform the sensations you hope the player to feel and then find
the character.
I'm curious if you ever tried reversing that and starting with the sensation you wanted
the player to feel as a way to inform the puzzle design.
So for example, a puzzle that tells the story or makes the player feel separation anxiety.
In today's conversation, you talked about the flow of the game,
where you had to feel the joy of replaying and self-destruction.
Have you ever thought about the design in the opposite direction?
In terms of the story?
There are quite a few cases when you just make a normal story, but in a previous game…
Sorry, I wanted to understand wants you can feel directly from this.
This time, I don't think we developed it that way.
The reason is...
I heard people say that Swelly's games are interesting.
So I wanted to make an interesting game, and that's why I started with that approach.
So for this game, not that we didn't think about it,
but we definitely went the way that we explained today.
And the reason for that is because I think I know enough
about the reputation of my own games,
how the players have responded.
And it's two things.
One is story is great, it's fun, it's entertaining,
but the game sometimes a little like so-so.
That's how I felt. So for this time, for The Missing, I knew that the game had to really shine and to really stand on its own feet.
So I had a mission or a must do for me was to make a great game.
Cool. Thank you.
Thank you for your great talk.
And I have a question about making characters.
And I agree that it is very ridiculous, superficial,
that making a character with some nouns, like Americans,
male, female, sister, or French maid, or have cat ear,
that is very, uh,
Maybe it is efficient, but superficial and ridiculous.
But in the larger team, about 100 people,
some people cannot understand very long trait like yours.
And in my position, I must make about 100 or 120 characters.
and must make understand all of my steps.
So I have some difficulty with this,
so is there any good idea with Raja team?
With larger team.
Larger team.
In my case, when I create a character with a 100 characters, I get a lot of feedback.
So when I create or select characters for a big production team,
it's a very difficult task.
I have some advice for you.
I understand that it's difficult to create a good character for a big team.
The answer is...
I think we should go out for a drink.
All of us.
Buy alcohol.
Thank you so much.
I just want to make sure there's no one standing there, right?
Oh, thank you for the talk.
It was just as great as your drinking one.
Great to have two Swery talks and one GDC.
You're one of the only, I guess, prolific,
one of the many prolific developers who
usually have their name attached to their game as Swery.
Sorry, can you speak up?
There's a crowd in the back.
like you know a Swirly65 game, and I think deservedly so. A lot of times people have commented
about your games being very unique and having like you know a distinct style whether it's
surrealist you know scenarios or you know dark subject matters and what have you. My question is
how would you sort of define like what actually makes up a Swirly65 game and I guess what kind of
expectation or emotion do you want a player to feel when they purchase one of your games?
Can I make sure that I understand the question?
My question is
how would you personally define like what is a
Swery 65 game and what emotion or expectation do you want players to feel when they buy your game?
What do you think about the game?
It's a difficult question.
What do I think about my game?
Basically, the most important thing is
Experience.
I want to make a game that is as experiencing as going on a trip, watching a movie, or playing with friends.
That's the Swelly game I'm thinking of.
So if I were to define what is a sweary game
with my own words, the most important thing
is that you earn or you get to experience something.
Very similar to when you go travel
or when you watch a film
or you're just hanging out with your friends.
Those are very important experiences.
So similar to that, I would want you to feel that
and go through that experience when you play my game.
That would be a sweary game.
The games that users will feel the swelling of are coffee, donuts, and deer.
Deer.
So from a user perspective,
how I think they view it is coffee, and donuts, and deer.
That's it.
Thank you.
Hello.
First of all, thank you very much for your talk.
Very enlightening, very educational.
So, I think that the game's message
that everyone has the right to be who they are
is a very beautiful message.
But while you were planning out the game
and throughout the development cycle,
did you have any concerns about the reception
due to the themes?
Considering that, I mean, of course,
I mean, just to clarify,
I am a supporter of the LGBTQ community.
However, to many on an international scale,
it is a debated topic.
Did you consider or worry about the reception this game would receive both within Japan and on an international scale?
I am a big supporter of the LGBTQ community,
and I think this is one of the themes of the game.
I was also concerned and worried about the reactions in Japan or globally.
I didn't have to worry about the reaction.
Basically, I just had to push forward what I wanted to express.
But I still had to adjust a lot with the publisher.
what the reaction was going to be,
because it was the ultimate sort of conclusion
of after having all these thoughts and planning things out,
that was the kind of answer.
that was there, so I marched on with that.
But working with a publisher and having a relationship with an external partner,
there were certain sort of discussions and maybe adjustments
that were brought up onto the table.
That, in fact, did happen, but I, myself, was not concerned at all.
The publisher understood what we were saying,
The problem I'm talking about is that
after the game is released,
we can tell the media and the community
that there is no problem.
That's what I'm talking about.
And throughout these discussions,
we had these discussions, they were brought up,
but what happened was,
once the game came out and we saw the reaction
or whatever article or reviews or commentary,
within the community and the media,
we were able to say that these were really of high concern.
So that was the result of, they were concerned,
but we were able to sort of prove
that they weren't as sort of as critical
as maybe they thought it was going to be.
Thank you, and a quick question.
What's your favorite liquor?
And whiskey.
Do you have one for him?
I'm sorry.
Anybody, anybody?
Anybody, yeah.
Accepting.
Kidding.
Okay, maybe we have one more.
One and okay.
Yeah, two more.
Do you want to go first?
You first?
OK.
I was wondering if during the development of the game
you had any concerns that players would take away
or make light of self-mutilation as opposed
to the actual message that you wanted to deliver
or you wanted them to drive by the end about self-acceptance
and restoration.
And what length did you go to ensure that they
derived the correct message?
When we were developing the game,
their message was that we should value our own existence.
It was a big message for us.
We were thinking about whether we could convey that message to the players,
and how we could incorporate it.
I think it was a very difficult thing to do.
As I said on Twitter,
JJ's experience and story
is not only because she has the characteristics of an LGBTQ person.
But I think that everyone around the world has the experience of being bullied
or being a part of the bullying.
I could tell that the story would be my own and
if I could visualize that by using the experiment
I felt like I had full confidence that everyone would raffle off and be right.
Yes, so I've commented from time to time maybe over Twitter, so maybe you've seen bits and
pieces of my sort of feelings and thoughts around that.
But in the case of JJ, it's really based on her experience and story.
Yes, she is a member of the LGBTQ community, so there's already that kind of setting.
that you can sort of start believing in and engaging in.
But in real life, I think we've all, to a certain level,
experienced something similar, or you were bullied,
or you were actually on the side that you bullied someone.
And so from your own personal experiences,
I had a very sure feeling
that we had gone through experiences ourself
that would be either brought up as you played the game,
or that,
you were there at one time. So I sort of assured myself that we would all lead to the realization
at the ending of the story that you would feel the manner that we explained in the slide. So
I kind of had that really gut feeling assurance from the very beginning. Okay, thank you.
Hi, firstly I want to say thank you. I've appreciated this talk. I really like the part of the character design of the embassy and the LGBTQ is not that important, but they're
identity, not an identity but their personality. That part I really like it.
And secondly, that is not a question, but I want to say thank you for following us
back on Twitter. You're so kind in this industry and I hope your game will sell well.
First of all, I really liked the presentation of creating characters.
Not only the visual, but also the community,
and how you accept yourself.
It was beautifully expressed.
Second, I don't want to ask a question.
I'm really grateful for your comments and follow-ups on Twitter.
Thank you.
No, thank you. I really enjoy talking about something with you guys. It's true. Thank you.
Thank you so much.