Woo! Got some traffic now that just came through.
Hello everyone! Welcome to the GDC Twitch channel.
My name is Bryant Francis.
I am a contributing editor at GunwithFuture.com.
I am the community manager for GDC.
I am here today playing a game that I have been having a lot of fun with.
The game is called The Outer Worlds.
It comes to us from Obsidian Entertainment and our friends at Private Division.
This is a, not quite an open world RPG, but just kind of a, you know, it's an action RPG
brought to you from a very talented studio down in Southern California, who are two members
of whom, two directors of whom are in the lower left hand corner of the screen.
Before I introduce them, I need to introduce Alex, who I need to get his face back on camera
a little.
Alex, how you doing?
You don't really need to. Hey, I'm Alex. I'm an editor for gamasutra.com and GDC.
But I'm not that important. Who is important is our two special guests. Special guests,
will you please tell everyone who you are and what you do?
Go ahead, Tim.
I'm Tim Cain. I was the co-director on Outer Worlds.
I'm Leonard Bojarski. I was the other co-director.
Right on.
Nice.
You guys have been doing RPGs for a while now, right? What number RPG is this?
Are we counting Diablo as an action RPG or not?
Sure. I count it. Yeah.
Do you want to count MMORPGs?
Absolutely.
Stonekeep is an RPG, right?
Tabletop also counts. 8. 7.
Stonekeep. Oh, God.
A lot. I don't know. I've made like 7 or 8 games. I lost count.
And that, that, does that include Stonekeep?
Yeah, well, it's been a long day.
It's been already.
You know, I just see a lot of candy, a lot of them.
The next 25 years worth or so.
Yeah, I got to say real quick, happy holidays to everyone who marks
Halloween as a special occasion.
We are taking questions from chat today about game design, development
and this game specifically.
So if you have questions for a letter, Tim, please throw them in chat
and we will get them relayed with all haste.
I just kind of wonder how you guys are feeling.
The game just came out.
You're coming off a launch.
How's everything going in the studio?
Good.
I'm feeling really good.
It's nice to have people out there playing the game
and enjoying it.
You know, we've gotten a lot of great reviews,
so that's always wonderful.
You're never quite sure how people are gonna react
to what you're doing.
You get so close to it while you're developing it.
They're laughing at the right time.
They're not laughing at the wrong things.
Right.
They seem to like the story and the characters
and Moon Man, so check, check, check.
All right.
It's all green from here. Tell us a bit about how this project came to be and how you came to work together.
This time,
um, a few years ago, the founders asked if I was interested in making an IP and they had already talked about an idea for it. What I told them to pull it off. I would really need to have Leonard.
I would not be able to do the story and in any way the characters without
his abilities. So they said, okay, and he was over at a little no name studio,
Lizard, working on a project you've never heard of called Diablo. And he said, okay.
Yes, it was such a great pitch. No, I, you know, the opportunity to make another IP from scratch
with Tim and, you know, return to my single player RPG roots was just too good to pass up.
Tim and I have a lot of fun when we're making stuff and it was just great to return to that.
They literally put us in a room for three months. I think all we did is...
Yeah, they wouldn't let us out. They just shoved the food in.
So it was really fun to do that though. We hadn't done that in 10 years.
Yeah, more than 10 years.
Yeah, I kind of want to, you know, as Brian guides us through here,
I kind of want to get your thoughts on where...
RPG design development have gone in the past decade or plus like
You know folks who don't know I mean if you can trace your work back
You know through Diablo and all kinds of other stuff back to Troika back to Arcanum back to also under something all the way back to
You know stuff beyond that so I mean you've been doing this for well over a decade maybe two
Like easily right because fallout was the 90s. So tell me like
Sum it up succinctly the entire progression of last two decades of RPG design and development. How have you
How have you seen it change? How are you feeling about it these days?
Uh, there's this game that just came out called the outer worlds that we think is is a great representation of where rpg design is
No, seriously. I mean, I think that it's fantastic. You know when we first started making rpgs
um way back in our play rpgs were still a viable thing in people's minds and then
over the next decade or two people really weren't as interested in RPGs in the mainstream. I mean,
there's always, you know, the people who loved RPGs, but the mainstream of games seem to have
moved away from that. And then, you know, you get like your massively multiplayer RPGs, which
whether they're actual RPGs or not is open to debate, but I think that some of that and then,
you know, games like Diablo really kind of...
sparked a
Resurgence of that and then you have you know your mass effects
Which are very interesting. I mean, I thought that what they did with mass effect was really cool
I think the witcher is really cool
But we just felt like there was a lack of games where you had the blank slate character. That was really
Generated from scratch by the player
We felt like that hadn't really moved forward
As much as all the other aspects of RPGs had you know
We never except for vampires about to say we never got the opportunity to do first-person RPG
We did that with vampire wasn't as successful as we would have liked at the time
People seem to like it now, but I think that was one of the biggest things was having actual RPGs in first-person
But then it seems to it seems like you know the stuff that we love to do the blank slate characters
the really focusing on player role-playing of however they want to role-play
and the reaction to their choices seemed to be the things that people weren't
focusing as much on as that we wanted to focus on.
I think too that RPGs used to be heavily influenced by tabletop
and I think computer RPGs are finally moving, becoming their own thing.
You don't have to be a D&D RPG to get a lot of people interested in your game.
or GURPS or any of the other Pathfinder, I mean those make great RPGs too, great CRPGs,
but I think RPGs, computer RPGs are now becoming like their own thing.
Yeah, I wonder if-
Go ahead, please.
I was just going to say, in the fact that people are excited about this,
this type of RPG and are reacting so well to the, you know,
the stuff that we've always loved to do is just really nice
because there was a time where, you know, you go to a publisher
and try to pitch them on making a game that had a lot of, you know, depth
and story and choices.
And they just kind of give you a blank look and try to steer
more towards multiplayer or more towards an action game.
Yeah, I am.
It seems like people, anecdotally, people seem much more excited and passionate.
I mean this in the best way.
They mean much more excited and passionate about this game than they are about something like
tyranny or something, which I also really, really enjoyed
and felt like it could have gotten a lot more attention.
I'm curious, why do you think a game like this seems to be hitting so well now,
as opposed to some of other, I'd not say Obsidian stuff hasn't done well,
but there is it feels like the outer world has broken through
into a larger audience than Obsidian games typically do.
I wonder if that matches up with your own.
observations from inside the studio and if so why I
Think well the reason I think that's happened is one. There's not really anything out like this right now, and so I think
We kind of
Hit a good time to
Product something like this and also one of the very one of our early pillars that we decided on was we wanted to make this
Game easy to get
a lot of RPGs and our RPGs in the past had this. The very first thing you were
hit with is a ton of numbers, a ton of stuff you had to read in order to get in the game.
And this one we said let's try to move as much of character creation out of
character creation. Let them spend skill points later. Let them, you know, let perks
come later.
and dive into the game so you can start playing.
And I think that just appeals,
I think that gets more casual players,
but I think that still appeals to hardcore players.
They have their depth, it just comes later.
And I also think it has to do with the first person view.
You know, I think people look at a isometric game
and just really, you know, if you're not into RPGs,
I think people kind of like just back off immediately.
Whether or not it's true,
they assume there's just so much.
complexity and depth that they just don't want to have to deal with up front which again goes to how we want to kind of
ease people into
Making more and more choices about their character as opposed to trying to figure out, you know
um, I always use this example because
Because we didn't fall you know
If I put points into this energy weapon, am I going to be able to find?
You know energy weapons before you know halfway through the game and in fall the answer was no
So, you know with the categories that Tim and Charlie our lead designer came up with
I thought that was a fantastic solution where I don't have to decide I'm being a range character
I put points into the category and I think people really responded well to that because it's
By the time you have to start making your specialization choices, you understand what the game is and you kind of understand what you would want to get into more.
That's why I liked having worked with Leonard for so long, because we could literally have a conversation where I'd start,
Hey, you know that stupid thing we did in one of our games? Let's not do it in this game.
That was our to do list. Don't do our stupid things we've done before.
Yeah, well, let's let's focus in for a second and talk specifically about that leveling system.
I don't know how hands on either of you were with this, but for folks who haven't played it yet.
It's a RPG-loving system where people can put points into skill groups up to a certain point.
And after a certain point, those points will go across all skills in the group.
So you'll get one point in all three, up to 50, and then you have to put in points on a one-to-one basis.
I'm curious, I've never seen that, as minor a change as it is.
I've never seen anything like that in a PC game before.
So tell me, how did that process, how did that system get designed?
How did you come up with it?
Well, I'd already had the categories in the game.
where you had, and it always started with you just tag two,
because I'm like, you don't really,
I don't want them to have to think too much
at the beginning about what they want to do.
I'm just interested in this and this.
And I think it was our creative director, Josh Sawyer,
said, hey, that's gonna really make people
want to specialize.
It's kind of penalizing to generalists.
And so I redesigned it so that the points
you put in the categories.
spread out to all the skills in that category at the beginning and suddenly what we had was a game where I don't have to
Think about anything other than I like using
Guns it doesn't matter whether I like using handguns or rifles or heavy weapons
I just like guns and that's all you have to think about for anywhere from five to ten levels
And then later on you know what's cool about that is that you try all the guns that appear in the game
And we don't have to drop all the guns immediately because no matter what gun we drop, you're going to be pretty good at it.
And then you can play with different guns for a few levels and on different maps and different creatures and go,
I really like machine guns.
And then so by the time you realize that, you can start putting points directly into heavy weapons.
And that applied to all the skill categories.
You could play with different dialogue skills and say,
I really feel bad when I lie to people, but I love intimidating them.
Boom. Put all your points into intimidation.
for the character building side as opposed to the people who just want interesting choices to make.
I'm going to pause for a minute and give a quick shout out to chat and apologies for some mild
technical difficulties I've been trying to solve at my end. For you folks out there in chat we have
folks like Big Crazy Wolf who are so happy, they want to say thank you guys for this game,
they absolutely love it. I've been asked by VRaptor64
To just do the secret people request the stream. So it's what I'm gonna work on
Disclosure the Raptor is friend of the show Carly who is apparently watching me over there
But yeah, other than that, we are taking your questions
We would like the questions to be focused on game development if you could
I'm dealing with some mild controller issues that were not happening earlier. So I will work on fixing those
Alex do you have any questions for our guest? I have so many you guys. Thank you so much for
Giving us a full hour.
Yeah, so I really feel that this game does some interesting work
to sort of, and as you just said, to sort of streamline
the process of getting into it and sort of make
the ramp into the mid-game very gentle.
I'm curious to know, is there anything
you felt like you had to sacrifice or give up on,
either specifically to sort of design
this sort of opening couple of hours,
or just in general that you sort of regret?
Not I don't think in the way you're you're thinking about we did have to make there's two rounds of cuts
We had to make in the game for content
For scope so that we could finish the game and make sure it was as polished as it is. So that was very tough
But that was that was just content
I don't I don't believe I don't feel like we made compromises or cuts at the very beginning to get players into it
You know as Tim was saying, you know Josh
Sawyer's the design director at the company and he worked on
New Vegas, along with a lot of other people on our team.
And what they had done was to make sure that in the very first area of the game,
they had a lot of skill checks all over the place.
So he was mentioning that to us, and we were like,
you know, that's a really good thing to keep in mind.
So we just really wanted to give players a lot of feedback early on
that all of their choices were mattering.
And also, you know, just having people like him or other people who have worked on games but aren't working on this game currently, or weren't working on this game currently, around,
it's fantastic to have RPG developers that you can have play your game who aren't as close to it as you are.
Because you get so close to this stuff, you're not quite sure if it's landing or not.
I mean, I've been telling other people, before we shipped, I finished this game 16 times.
With wildly different characters.
I was still finding new stuff in the last playthrough.
And then after we shipped...
Was watching a streamer play and he found something in Edgewater. I'd never found before and like other than this that was that
There's a grave that's all by itself
Oh that one way to the beach and it's because we changed that area several times and I got back after the final change
But still the fact that I'd never I knew there was a POI down there
Right
I really want to get into writing about all this too. But before we do that's a great point
I want to jump into how did you?
How does the studio set up a production workflow so that you can produce?
Sure, how do you like I'm going to fix this controller problem?
No worries. There's a ton of stuff in this game. It's big. It's open, you know, it's a sizable
endeavor. How does the studio effectively produce the assets for a game like this? Because it sounds
hard. It is really hard. Yeah.
Um, like coordination?
Yeah, I think there's a lot of planning involved. There's a lot of coordination.
You wouldn't believe how many things slip through the cracks and we're scrambling.
Like, how did we miss that?
It's a lot less organized than it probably should be or than people would expect it to be.
We had amazing QA, which is not a bar. We don't have a lot of bugs.
But they tested this game so many different ways.
And just a lot of very talented developers, you know, keeping track of things.
I mean, we make very detailed design docs.
We try to keep them living to be living documents so they don't just sit there.
But after a while, it's, you know, it's it's almost as much work
to keep up the docs as it is to just develop the game.
So we really rely on people who are working on their areas
to take ownership of that and make sure they're getting what they need
and that the docs are if the docs aren't up to date,
that they're communicating with the other departments.
And then of course our producers, you know, I don't think the producers get enough of enough credit on a game like this
We had a fantastic production team and they were they were doing a lot of the work of keeping track of everything
Everybody needed and making sure it was being worked on when it needed to be worked on. Yeah
That occurs me you meant you shouted out QA which is fantastic. I gotta say, you know, I put
you know, maybe 10, 20 hours in this game and it's, uh, it's very,
it's very stable. It's very, uh, it's bulletproof as far as I can tell. Um,
and there has been times in the past when obsidian has gotten a lot of like,
uh, like critical lampooning for perhaps launching with buggy games. Um,
I don't know how much of that is due to a number of causes, whether it's, uh,
you know,
just the scope of the games or the production process or the time involved or
whatever. Um, but I'm curious, like, uh,
How has the studio's approach to QA and how has your observation of the studio's approach to QA changed over the last couple of years?
And was there anything new put into place on this game that maybe was done to make it just extra bulletproof?
One thing I tried to do early, as early as I could, was I wrote up all the playthrough paths that I wanted supported.
And on a game like this, I didn't try to do every single one because that's hard, but I tried to do major ones like
make a character that fights mainly with guns, do one with melee.
Make a character that uses all the science weapons.
Make a character that tinkers everything.
One of them was a dumb character.
One of them I said, make a character that kills everybody.
Everybody you run across, kill them, hopefully before they even talk to you.
And of course, I'm sure QA had a lot of fun with that one.
But that actually tested a lot of things in the game about...
can quests continue without a quest giver?
What happens when people make particular weapons way outside the level range we're expecting for Xenon?
What happens when people go in with wildly different skill sets
and yet they still have to be able to finish a particular quest?
And we got a lot of feedback from QA and that helped us fix a lot of quests
and other content in the game to make it viable for every different kind of character.
I think the biggest thing overall that we did differently was...
In the past, we wouldn't make those choices until we had to, to make cuts.
I mean, and we were pretty much at a place where we had to in this one,
but we just realized it a lot sooner or faced up to the fact a lot sooner.
Because before we're just like, no, we want this content in there for the players.
The game is going to suffer without this, without this content in there.
We have to make sure it's in there.
So that means you're, you're, you're developing the game.
way further into the beta than you should be.
You know, you shouldn't be developing really seriously past alpha.
You know, we always end up pushing that, but you know, you want a really good
beta period where the game is playable from beginning to end,
all the content's in there, and you know...
A lot of times we were just so passionate about what we were doing in the past that we wouldn't
make those cuts and this time we forced ourselves to make those tough choices earlier than we had
before and that enabled Tim to play the game 17 times instead of developing the game.
There's other things we decided early like putting a dumb
dumb character lines in was something we said right from the beginning.
So it's like every time a writer came on board we're like you have to support dumb
player characters. You know, don't resist, just give in now and write those lines. And I think
they wrote some great stuff. Sure. I want to jump in a chat here and not let everybody go
unnoticed. Big Crazy Wolf asked the question, basically has the response to the game been what
you hoped for? Better or worse?
It's it's definitely what we hope for I mean, it's it's a lot better
Than than we were expecting because you always see the flaws you always see you're so close to the game
You see the game that you wanted to make
of when you started it, and you only see the places...
I mean, there was a lot of stuff to be proud of, don't get me wrong, I was very happy with the game,
but all I could see was, you know, the bigger game that I had originally envisioned,
and, you know, having to make the smaller game, having to, you know, make some of those tough cuts,
not having some of the depth that I was hoping was going to be there originally,
was a little bit hard to see past.
And, you know, when we...
We got people playing the game earlier, you know, we had a
E3 we had a very successful E3 and they if there's a judges day where the judges played it and they were all really enthusiastic
About it
It's kind of like at least I was a little bit in denial like every time I heard somebody had fun
I'm like, oh they must not have gotten to this part or this other part, you know
It wasn't until I saw you know, all the great feedback that I finally go. Okay. Yeah
I'm being a little bit too hard on some of the stuff and start accepting that people are having a great time
Right on. Did it exceed your expectations?
Yeah, one thing I love is when I'm reading reviews, especially when I watch streamers or watch video reviews,
there's so many details in the game. I'm so glad that people are finding
like fun ways of interacting with NPCs or side quests that they didn't know existed or even...
I love it when people think, I'm going to do this really weird thing to solve this quest.
And then they discover, we thought of that, the NPC has a response to what you just did.
And I love that they're finding these things because it's like,
we wanted to make this world that we described as wide.
People always talk about, how long is the game?
I'm like, let's talk again about how wide it is.
Because it's a very wide game.
Yeah, it's um, let's talk about the writing. Let's dig right into I know there was uh,
There's a full writing team, but uh, you guys certainly had your hand in it and I want to talk about
um
sort of like the general thrust of of what you were trying to accomplish with the writing in this game and the narratives
and um sort of just like uh, how do you write
How do you write a funny game? Honestly, because like I have found that many funny games
that purport to be amusing are actually really tricky to get into and
Especially the opening of this game the comedic timing and the writing it like really lands for me
And I don't see that in games very often. So like how how did you approach structuring and writing that kind of stuff?
well, the humor was was
the same kind of humor me and Tim always like to put in our games.
It's a combination of my dark worldview and Tim's silly worldview.
So that part, at least knowing what we wanted it to be, was I think half the battle.
And we already had done that several times before.
So I think that started us out a little bit ahead of the game.
But I think for me, when I was, you know, instructing the writers on what we wanted,
Yeah, we wanted humor. We wanted to make sure that there was, you know, enough humor in it.
But at the same time, it always had to come from situations that had to come from characterization.
It had to come from the absurdity of the world, like people trying to live their lives and
and justify to themselves how they could, you know, how they could live and make the choices
they were in this absurd situation, as opposed to just trying to find funny jokes. If you create...
absurdity in the situations and depth in the characters,
just them reacting to it in an honest way is going to create a lot of that for you.
And just, you know, that's not to say we don't have, you know,
awesomely talented writers, because we do,
but once those things are all in place, I think it's easier for them to kind of...
get the humor in there. Because Tim would play an area and say, oh this area is too dry,
and the writers would make another pass on it, and it wasn't like a torturous process or anything.
The raw material was already there for them to kind of exploit to make more humorous.
But as Leonard pointed out, Leonard's the reason this game isn't goofy,
and I'm the reason it's not depressing.
I like pointing out that it's not depressing, because there's sort of a way that like,
especially for a total of this game, which it harkens back to Fallout, it harkens back to,
you know, a cynical outlook about what will happen in the future.
That's me.
It's still, I've seen some really interesting takes from people who've played the game,
especially about the first major choice you have to make, which, we're pretty deep in
the game, but I won't go shouting spoilers in case anyone's new.
For the pair of you I'd like to know, it was really cool, I got to see Kari Patel give
a GDC talk last year about working with the dialogue tools that your company works with.
Obsidian has been working with a really similar tool set for several years now.
Even as it's been making different kinds of games.
It's been making Infinity Engine, Tribute RPGs, it's been making, you know, The Stick of Truth, the South Park game.
And now it's come out and made something that's kind of a modern Fallout-like, I guess?
You guys worked on Obsidian Produced New Vegas, so it's fair to say that.
Um, uh, how has it been, obviously as game directors, like sort of keeping up your toolset
to make very similar games, even though you had to change, like, major, major genre changes several
times? Well, this is the first game I've
worked on at Obsidian, so I don't have a lot of history,
except for the history I had with the people
back when we were all at Interplay.
And when we were at Troika, we used Excel.
So it really wouldn't be hard to clear that bar
for a dialogue tool.
But I just have to say that the dialogue tool and the quest tool and the different tools that they've developed over the years here at obsidian are just fantastic.
You know, the dialogue and quest tool are big visual flow charts, so you can see how the conversation flows, which is, you know.
an enormous help with the kind of complexity that we're putting into this these kind of games.
But you know they've been developing it I'm assuming since since they started as a company.
Oh yeah 16 years in development on those tools.
And it shows it's it's it's a fantastic dialogue tool.
Yeah I've been here for eight years and we use the same tools on South Park.
and Pillars of Eternity and Tyranny and Outer Worlds.
And because of that, people can move from project to project
and you're already familiar with those tools.
They just get improved every cycle.
So we hit the ground running with those.
Nice.
Real quick, just for my own edification,
what engine is this game built in?
I don't think I've ever actually looked at it.
Is this...
What tools is this built in?
This is a real four.
OK, yeah. All right.
Cool. That's I was just curious.
So let's talk a bit about
how you build games that reward player choice, right?
Because like this game seems so much about giving players many options.
You know, it's very wide.
How do you think about the way you structure choices?
Like I have to assume it's not just always.
Every zone has good, bad, you know, and then third option.
Is there a structure or any kind of like process you go through to build these
out? These narrow structures,
we're all just kind of writers rooms and realizing a little bit from a very high
level. There's two things. Number one,
it should never feel like a good and bad choice.
It should always feel like you're making a difficult choice between.
Maybe on the surface it seems very simple, but as soon as you dig into it at all, it gets a lot more complex and
Again, you know not only the character stuff
I talked about earlier, but the character stuff on the side of the player letting the players
develop I mean a
make any kind of character they want and play any character they want in any way they want
is like one of our most important things in the game. We love our story, we love our characters,
but at the end of the day, we always are asking ourselves what are players going to
want to do when presented with this choice.
And when we're playing through, you know, when we get feedback,
whether it's from people on the team or people off the team,
they're like, why couldn't I do this here?
And we're like, there has to be a really good reason in game that you can't do that there.
Or we have to give you that option.
Or we have to make it structured in a way that that option doesn't come up.
So we're always looking at how can we pay the,
how can we not only let the player play how they want, but reward them for playing that way.
Um that that is always at the forefront of our mind with with creating this these kind of this kind of content
Yeah, it uh, it seems uh challenging to create um, lots of different opportunities for players to express themselves within the limited opportunities you have
Uh given the scope of the game like, uh, do you go into it with like character player archetypes, you know explorers killers
Whatever or is there is there a different process for trying to suss out?
Um where players might want to go
Yeah, we had 13 archetypes.
Yeah, the one that Tim came up with for QA.
At the very basic level, it's the one we...
the choices we came up with way back in Fallout are still at the heart of everything.
It's you need to be able to talk your way, fight your way, or stealth your way through the game.
We added leadership, which depends on companions.
And of course there's all the different ways, combinations, whether you're, you know,
whether you're killing people, not trying to kill people,
whether you're playing melee, ranged.
you know, all those different facets to it.
But really, you know, when we're developing these kind of things,
it really always does come down to how can we really emphasize the player's choice.
And, you know, one of the things I like to do with the riders is,
you know, using Edgewater as an example, at the surface it might seem very simple.
Oh, here's the group of people that are kind of bad.
Here's the group of people who are kind of good.
So, you know, I always want the riders to add.
depth to the characters and having the character that might on the surface seem like the evil choice or the bad choice
Is actually a very noble character who's who might be completely misguided
But is doing this for the right reasons and people who are doing the right thing might be doing the right thing for the wrong
reasons so there's all these different ways that you can
Come up with a basic choice and then layer all these different things into it to give it a bunch of different flavor
That makes a lot of sense. There's a really good question here in chat that's very relevant.
Sam P. asks, how do you deal with narrative disconnect?
When do you address it and when do you just let game systems happen?
I assume this is the sort of thing where you complete a quest and just blow somebody away right afterwards.
We don't. Some of that we try to deal with.
I mean, a great example where.
We could have pushed it further and we didn't is, you know, with Parvati, you pick her up in the first town,
if you killed the people who were in the room with her when you pick her up, she's very upset about that,
you know, but then you can go into town and just start blowing people away and she doesn't seem to notice.
You know, that's the kind of thing that I was talking about earlier,
where I would have loved to have, you know, made sure that we handled that,
like you killing people who were obviously your friends and not just the first people you were with when you got her.
So sometimes we don't have the opportunity to do as much of that as we would like.
So I think where it's important to us is that
While you're doing the quest or these people are active in the world in terms of the questing and storyline,
that's really important.
If in a lot of ways it's after they've played their part and they're really kind of become, you know,
don't really have a lot more to do in the game and the player starts killing them,
except for the systemic reactivity,
we don't really put a lot of effort into making the whole game react to that.
And that's kind of the trade-off we make.
Where in the past I think we would put more effort into those kind of things and have a much less polished game.
For sure. Man, I had no idea Felix had a dropkick.
That's so crazy.
Seriously.
Good.
That's his move.
I gotta get more of that.
I'll tell you about it if you want.
Yeah, no doubt.
So I want to jump back real quick. I mean, again, chat, you're killing it with questions.
Keep throwing them out there. We'll keep going.
But real quick about the humor and stuff.
Something that I realized really works for me in this game that hasn't always worked in the past is...
The animation and none of its motion capture just incredibly good animation work on part of the team
But the like a little stuff with the professor and you know little physical gags
I almost never see really good physical gags in a video game
This might be one of the best I've seen especially in the beginning
It was any special work or shout outs you want to give on already like advice for fellow devs on how to like get that
Stuff working or was just a product of a really good animation team
Both I think are you talking about the intro cinematic or just when yeah, I mean, yeah
Well, because the reason I ask that is because in-game is different from how we do the cinematics.
The cinematics, I mean even in-game we did a lot of motion capture, but there was a lot of hand animation,
there was a lot of hand editing of those.
In the cinematics, the intro cinematics specifically, there was a lot more motion capture involved.
And some of it was even done out of house with us directing them.
on the things we wanted to see and how that would be accomplished.
All the in-game stuff was done in-house, or most of it was done in-house,
and that was a totally different process.
We had to come up with some basic gestures that all different characters could use
and try to mix and match those.
Well, they're both great, and they killed it.
Thank you. I think our animation team did a spectacular job on that stuff.
Yeah, I'm not sure which is because I'm so used to games of this perspective being tying back to stuff
You know from the fallout lineage and stuff
Maybe there's been enough advancement since then in technology that it just feels more real
But it just really works in this game in a way. I haven't seen before
Yeah, right you're doing incredibly well
I wonder
I want to get into the business and sort of how you guys launched it and stuff, but before I do, I mean, you're both,
we tried to use this term sparingly, but you're both game industry veterans and I'm curious, like,
you've worked on a number of titles in your careers and I wonder if there's any specific
ones that really influenced the way you approach this game, whether it's Arcanum or
Fallout or Diablo or anything else.
Well, I know when we started this, I took our lead designer, Charlie Staples, aside and said,
look,
Because I remember I said we started with, I did a lot of stupid things that I won't do again.
I told Charlie, when I made Arcanum, if I had an idea, it went in.
So Arcanum is like chock full of every idea I had at the time.
Some of them did not belong together.
So I told him to edit me.
And so we had a lot of really cool things planned for this game.
And Charlie really helped edit it down to like,
these are like the features at the heart of what you're trying to do.
And also, if you like combat, that was all Charlie.
So I think part of what we did was,
Leonard and I have worked so long and so well together,
and we trust each other.
And we kind of extended that.
We had a really good lead team that we also trusted.
And I think that, in turn, helped
us make really good core mechanics that were in the game.
Like you mentioned, you love Felix dropkick?
I think that may have.
From the animation department all we said was Felix
Loves toss ball and carries a toss ball stick to hit people and I think they came back
They said hey, how about it first special attack? He actually the flying leap through the air and I'm like great
It is great, it's fantastic
Yeah, that makes a lot of sense
I uh, there's been a lot of questions here in chat to sort of like what you expect the new game
They want to know when patches are coming when updates are coming
I kind of wanted to hit all that and ask you guys like
In 2019 now that so many games are live games and like the process of releasing games seems to stretch three to nine months at least
Like how are you? How are you? How are you looking at this game and its launch?
Are you sort of keeping an eye on it and hoping to keep it updated and fresh?
Are you sort of putting it out there and giving you some time to sit before you come back to it?
Like how do you feel about supporting this game? And how is that different from the way you used to work on games?
Well, at least now, the big thing for me is,
so we launched the game,
and I could immediately watch people playing it on screens.
Right.
So you can see what people do,
which sometimes isn't what they report.
Like, they'll report a bug or two,
but we're watching it going,
that shouldn't happen.
We should probably fix that.
There are things they aren't necessarily complaining about.
But, not to toot our horn,
but I want to toot it,
we haven't had a whole lot of bugs,
so it's not like our hotfix list was...
full of things on fire that we had to fix.
Yes, there was like a really rare crash
and there was some other things we wanted to fix
that we saw should be happening.
But for the most part, what we've been looking at
is we're looking at what we call friction.
Like people are playing and they're just having,
they're hitting friction points on the UI
or parts of the game that something
isn't being messaged very well.
And we're trying to get that done
in a fix that will happen very, very soon.
And then we'll keep watching how people play
for a longer term patch a few months down the road.
Right on. So let's talk about business.
I would, you know, I mean, obviously everyone wants to know how well it's doing.
I expect you probably can't talk about that kind of stuff.
But the platforms it's on are really interesting to me.
I mean, you've got Windows consoles and then you're coming to Switch,
I think next year is the plan.
So like was that challenging at all, that like multi-platform rollout?
And I'm curious, like.
Yes. OK, we'll start there.
That.
Was there anything new or challenging in that?
Any advice you'd give other developers
who are doing similar things,
especially targeting the Switch, which seems challenging?
Well, we're having the Switch developed out of house
because three different platforms was enough for us.
Yeah, so we found people who had done it before
and had experience with it.
It was really hard.
Have you made cross-platform games before?
Because you've worked on South Park.
I'd never made... I mean, when I worked on Diablo,
I worked on the PC SKU,
and then they made the console SKU in-house,
but it was a separate team.
So this was the first time I worked on a multi-platform.
game. However, being that I'm more involved in the conceptual side of the art and the writing,
the technical side of the art changes from platform to platform, but conceptually it doesn't
change. And the writing is exactly the same. So I don't have to worry about any of that.
Tim, on the other hand, has to stress on all of that.
Yeah, we had, I mean, the UI, there were differences in UI, especially input.
Trying to get all the stuff we wanted on a keyboard mapped onto a controller in a way that made sense.
We went through several different iterations of how to control things.
We actually ended up dropping some features just because there was no way to map it onto a controller.
I think what was really important though was we kept all three platforms, the PC, PS4 and Xbox, kind of in parity.
We built a new build every day, so every day we got it we had a brand new build.
Whatever new went in was there.
I got in really early and a few of the testers got in really early, and we had it tested usually before the rest of the team got in.
We knew whether the build seemed stable and then everybody else could jump on the team could jump onto the new build
And we test all three right away in the morning and pretty much the biggest difference. I guess was UI and
Input, but I yeah, I think the really important point about that at least for me was from the very beginning. We both said
We want to design an interface that's obviously the more interfaces we could design that are going to work on all three the better
However, we don't want to compromise one of the skews
To make it easier to make another one or vice versa. We wanted each one to feel really good
PC shouldn't feel like a console port. Yes
None of them should feel like a port of the other basically they should all feel good
Our our pcui should feel like a pcui our console ui should feel like a console ui
Yeah, I um, there's questions in chat about the font size
I know that must be tricky to work out on tvs for consoles versus pc
I mean you could be like 10 feet away versus like a foot away. So I imagine that's wild. Um,
you know
Real quick as long as we're talking about font size and text. Um,
How did you settle on the name the outer worlds and have you played the outer wilds yet?
Yes, I played outer wilds and it was really good. Yeah
We we had a few different names, but we really liked outer worlds
and
Didn't we even talk with them about Outer Wilds?
Yeah, we couldn't come up with any other name we liked.
And we hadn't heard, at least I don't think Tim or I had,
heard of the Outer Wilds when we proposed Outer Worlds.
And then we found out about it fairly quickly afterwards.
And we're like, isn't this a concern?
Should we keep looking?
And I think everybody was just kind of tired
of trying to find a name at that point.
Because we had come up with like actually one or two
that we liked, I don't even remember what they were now,
but.
had already had games or books or something else
using that name.
So I think it was a combination of fatigue
and the fact that Outer Wilds was supposed to be out
like six months before us or something like that.
You know, we're figuring, well, that's not a problem
because, you know, game dev never slips.
Well, plus we have the perfect solution for gamers by both.
Exactly.
They're both good by both.
Absolutely.
I cannot agree more.
Most positive answer to have that question.
Brian, how you doing in there?
I'm doing okay.
What was that?
I didn't hear what he said.
Oh, sorry, I was mumbling.
I should have spoken up clearer.
I was saying that's the most positive answer I've ever heard to that kind of question.
Yeah, I haven't played it, but I hear it's a fantastic game.
I got to get it.
And they're both sci-fi.
Yeah.
Both fantastic. I can't believe we only have about 15 minutes left
But we only have about 15 minutes left folks and chat if you want to get your questions in we would love to have your
design and development focus questions
We think you have been asking some wonderful stuff. Thank you all for joining us
I'm acting like I'm ending the stream, but I'm not um. I just ducked back to my ship for a minute to do a
Repair repair and ammo ammo figure figure out my ammo situation cuz I was running out out there um
Tim and Leonard, my question for you, um, one of the things I've observed about this game, like the big challenge of making games like this compared to say Fallout New Vegas, is um, how you space out things in the world.
Um, my complaints about Fallout New Vegas was, um, every faction area...
which was a lot of areas in the game, felt a little odd because every faction had to be ready to turn into a combat zone at a second's notice if you shot someone.
So they didn't have some of the explorery things they liked because they were also loot zones, like combat loot zones, as opposed to carefully crafted dungeons.
In this game...
I have the opposite problem, which is every faction zone feels great and alive and populated,
and that area we were just wandering through, I noticed, is a little more empty than other
games of its type, which I'm not trying to rag on Outer Worlds here, this is just an observation I
had. How have you sort of dealt with the concept of filling out spaces and making sure they feel
like a living world, even when you have the budget to only produce like a tiny aquarium-sized world?
Um...
Very carefully, we tried to fill out the areas as much as possible.
In terms of faction areas versus non-faction areas,
that was something that kind of just happened a little bit naturally.
I don't think we were really considering that because, you know,
you could turn any of our areas into a combat areas as well,
even if it didn't have anything to do with factions.
But I feel like, you know, I kind of agree.
I think I feel like we should have had a little bit more.
content for you to explore and find on Monarch, but that's some of that stuff is
kind of where we we made choices of like okay we're gonna we're gonna really
polish this stuff. We also tried to always use like I used to call it the
roller coaster model of design where
There's space to do some exploring, and there's space to do some combat, and there's space to talk to people, and that should vary up as you play.
There's no area in the game where there's like two hours of solid talking, or nothing, you don't do anything but fight for two hours, or you don't do anything but explore.
Because it's fun to have that broken up by other things you can do, and you kind of get all the different skills.
Like early on we had a few levels where I'm like,
I'm doing an awful lot of fighting in here
and there's nobody to talk to.
So we actively tried to break that up.
Right on.
There's a question here in chat that I like
because it's just so bold.
Daza wants to know, do you plan on improving
simulation elements such as NPC scheduling in the sequel?
And what do you think about integrating
quests with simulation systems?
So yeah, apparently yeah, I'm making a sequel.
I didn't know that.
I would have been right on that sequel.
Yeah.
There's a lot of things about NPCs that would be fun to do.
About the scheduling though, we actually talked about that early on.
I actually always got a little annoyed when it's like,
oh, I want to go sell myself to the shopkeeper.
Oh, it's closed.
And then it's like, do I break in and get them out of bed?
I just like this.
Our shopkeepers are always there.
Our vending machines are always on.
We have day-night cycles, but we kind of steered away from making the player have to watch a clock.
In fact, you'll notice there isn't even a clock in our game.
Because we had no timed quests and we had no scheduled quests that could only be done at a particular time of day or after a particular wait.
Right.
Yeah, right on. I just thought there was no time in space.
Or a statue.
Maybe we can dig into a little bit. We only got about 10 minutes left here
But I definitely want to get more into the companions as well
So I mean they're a big part of this game and their charm sort of pulls you through
Beaconfield wants to know where do the ideas for Parvati and Ellie come from are any of the companions based on real people?
Not that I know of
Parvati came from Chris Latois, one of our writers.
He started the character, Kate Dollarhide finished her.
So that was basically a combination of both of them.
We had some very basic ideas
of what she needed to do in the game,
but her personality and who she was
was very much their creation.
For Ellie, it was a little bit of a different path.
She was also worked on by two different writers,
Dan McPhee and Carrie Patel.
And Felix is kind of in the same category as Ellie.
We were making our vertical slice,
and we just had to come up with two companions
to start proving out systems.
So we came up with Felix and Ellie,
and there really wasn't a whole lot of discussion
put into what their place in the game was
and what they were supposed to represent thematically.
It was just like, let's make some characters
who would be interesting to have banter with each other
and to interject into conversations.
So that really came out of those writers just...
Natai Podara wrote Felix, and Dan McPhee at the time was writing Ellie,
and they just wrote these characters and came up with some interesting things about them.
Felix just kept getting revised and iterated on by Natai as we went through the whole game,
and then at a certain point, Carrie took over Ellie and kind of revamped some of her.
But that was really interesting because every other NPC in the game kind of came about to fit a certain spot in your party or to fit a certain story kind of style or theme.
And those two really just started out as like, we need two characters, two companions to follow the player around.
Let's just jump in and make some interesting characters.
And then we kind of like figured out where they fit in the world after that.
It's interesting to note, Roseway was our first like zone that we made.
that had all the quests in it and NPCs and all that.
And Ellie and Felix were the two characters
that just, they were already,
when you started up that zone,
they were just already attached to you.
So I probably played Roseway with Ellie and Felix
at least five or six dozen times.
And it's funny now to play it with them
because it just reminds me of two years ago.
We had a lot of that banter stuff working even back then.
Right on.
I wonder, I assume every writer brings their own inspirations and influences to whatever
they touch, but I imagine you guys had a lot of control given your lead role in the project.
Was there any specific influences or inspirations that shaped the tone of this game?
I get a lot of stuff like Firefly and Red Dwarf, but is there anything else?
Yeah, besides just our senses of humor.
We yeah, Firefly, we talk a lot about the Simpsons and Futurama.
We were huge for the writers.
Specifically, I really
talked to them a lot about Brazil, the movie Brazil.
Yeah. Some Wes Anderson movies, some of the darker Coen Brothers movies.
early Kurt Vonnegut.
So we just kind of like really talked a lot
about a bunch of different influences like that
and how and what type of things we wanted them
to look at from each.
A great example of that with Wes Anderson for instance
is I think the Grand Budapest Hotel
has some really sweet, endearing characters
and also some very, very broad characters
with a lot of, and there's a lot of kind of
sorrow and depth and darkness there with a very kind of like silly overtone to it
so I thought that was like a really good touchstone for for people who weren't as
familiar with some of the games we made in the past but I love how writers ran
with it because like Sam
Sam was my idea, but all I said was,
I want a robot in the game.
He's a cleaning robot.
He's not sentient at all.
And all he does, everything he says,
is something about cleaning or him being a robot.
And Megan Stark just went overboard.
The stuff she did was so good.
Because sometimes you'll be in a situation
and Sam will say something
that's just what you'd expect to pop out of a robot,
but it's kind of a meta commentary on what's going on.
And it's very funny.
I think she nailed that character.
Yeah, totally.
We got about five minutes left.
So any last pressing questions, please get them in.
Brian, do you have any of your own?
What?
We kind of glided past it, even though I've
been spending so much of this encounter in combat.
What do you think makes good combat?
Like, why is this game sort of not just
like me talking to everyone?
Like, what was your guiding light for making
this gunfire feel good?
Or melee?
Wow, we just barely pulled Charlie in.
I wanted it to be impactful, especially melee.
We had a lot of talks about, hey, we
have a lot of guns in our game, but melee has to hold its own.
So all of our melee weapons have a really strong hit impact.
They all do area of effect. They basically all hit anything that they sweep through.
People aren't mentioning this, but melees are automatic hits.
If you're standing near someone and you swing your weapon, it always hits.
The amount of damage you do varies, but you always hit with a melee weapon.
And they often do lots of damage against swarms, like Mantis swarms.
So we had a lot of interesting rules like that,
to just make sure that combat always felt really good,
no matter what weapon you were holding.
Like, all the weapons are different.
We had the plasma charge up in really early,
and that's a totally different way of using a weapon
than, say, spray and pray with a machine gun.
But they all work.
You put points into them, they get better,
no matter what style you like.
That's something I really like in this very RPG-esque.
No matter what gun you like in this game,
you can find, or gun style, you can find a gun like it.
put points into that skill and just have fun with it.
Although you tend to run out of ammo if you like machinima.
As you can see from the stream, I am unfortunately dealing with some ammo loss challenges.
Happen to me all the time.
There you go. Alright, buddy. Stay down.
Wow, we are coming to the end of the stream.
Thank you everyone so much for watching. Thank you Tim and Leonard for joining us today.
Thank you. Thanks for having us.
Alex, unless there's anything you want to get in right now, I'm going to start wrapping things up, but that's okay.
No, this game's great. This game's fantastic.
Thank you.
More games.
So cool. I could literally spend the next five minutes just complimenting the game,
but I have endings or moves to complete. Thank you so much to Tim and Leonard for joining us
here on the GDC Twitch channel. Thank you to all for watching. If you are a fan of games and how
they get made, we'd encourage you to hit that follow button because if you do, you will get
notifications on when we get live. And when we go live, we will always be talking to interesting
developers or doing something that is...
We're big believers in the process of making games,
tells us so much about why we enjoy the games we enjoy,
we think it's valuable for people who like games,
for people who just play games, so that's why we do what we do.
If you are a developer yourself,
we'd love to have you at GDC next year.
There are so many really interesting things to do at GDC,
interesting ways to learn about making games.
You can scroll down on this page and click on the bypass
to learn more about our passes for GDC.
And I guess it's, I'd do best to say that this time of year, while we're still in the early pricing period,
it's also the time to get the best price on your pass.
For everyone else, I hope you have a good day, I hope you have a good time in the colonies,
and I guess the board wishes you well.
Although I don't like the board. I'm not going to do anything for the board.
Oh, I guess I'll ask this question. We've had a lot of great questions in chat about support, about other factors that we didn't want to quite throw in because we wanted to keep things dead focused.
If they want to ask those questions, where should they ask them for? Where can they reach you guys?
Support at obsidian.net. We also have obsidian forums.
Yes, we have forums. They're welcome to reach us out.
So that'll be forums at obsidian.net.
Yeah.
I just want to say real quick.
We have a page on Facebook.
Oh, perfect.
Facebook as well.
Before we sign off, there's a bunch of great talks.
I know I'm a company man, but there's
a bunch of great talks on the GDC YouTube channel
that are totally free to watch, including some, I think,
dating back to other Obsidian games,
some from these folks as well.
I think Tim, one of your Fallout postmortems is on there,
and it's incredible.
So go watch those.
They're good, and they're free.
And there are more great content like this.
Alright everyone, have a good day. Bye!
You too, bye!