Welcome. Welcome to our three micro-sessions about indie arcades and events.
My name is Yon. I have Zurida and Marie.
Zurida's going to kick off by giving a short history or overview of playful culture and events.
Marie will talk about her activities in The Wild Rumpus,
and I'm going to round it off with some of my experience in building arcades and going to these events.
Thanks, Sion. My name is Sarayda Buter. I have my own company called Zoe,
and I am co-founder of Playful Arts Festival in the Netherlands,
and I'm a worldwide co-director of the Global Game Jam.
One of the things that I've been doing in the past few years is organizing events to bring
people together, to connect them and give them a sense of community for different kinds of purposes.
For example, in 2010 I set up in the Netherlands Indigo Showcase, which is a showcase for game developers,
Dutch game developers, to show their games to each other, but also to
do a different audience,
audience that normally never go to game events, and show them what kind of games are made in the Netherlands.
We did that by using these
Arcade cabinets that give a more of an exhibit feel than a messy
different kinds of PCs and stuff like that that you normally or which you usually saw but with
game exhibits. So we tried to use these and you can actually see them as well in
at GDC or at Gamescom this this week at the Holland Pavilion and booth number B030.
Another event I started last year was the Playful Arts Festival,
which is a festival where we try to connect people from different kinds of audiences together
and have them play together.
So join us, come together with us,
spectacle games, bring you toe-to-toe and head-to-head with your friends,
collaborate, play, sneak, team up.
We tried to get people together and play with each other so they could mix and mingle and experience new things.
Like you can see here that you have Hit.Me!, which is more of a physical game,
and then other games like MegaGurrp or Hocrum.
We also brought the Play for Arts Festival to an art fair in the Netherlands in Rotterdam,
where we try to give new audiences new experiences like this game and put them in an art fair,
which is a different place than what games would normally be experienced in the Netherlands, at least.
And then last year I organized Day in the Park in the Netherlands.
And it was actually meant to take place in the park, but it was pouring down.
So we decided to do it inside and get people together and play more folk games
and games that you used to do on the playground.
And you can see how this makes people smile in this setting
and get them a little bit closer together than what they normally would do.
And you can see here a little bit of lemon-yousting going on in the middle of the Dutch game garden.
So Eric Zimmerman said in the introduction to game design,
the 21st century will be a century of play.
Game designers will be the architects, the storytellers,
and the party hosts of this playful new world.
So how is this done?
I think play is...
A couple of things are part of play and playful culture, according to me,
which is there's a certain sense of participation.
People have to participate to make things happen.
There's a sort of performance going on and spectatorship,
which helps this performance.
And then encounter.
And encounter can be getting together,
but also experience and encounter new games and be curious about it.
So this happens around the world in different kinds of places
through game makers, people that make games,
events that happen worldwide, public space,
in public space or in a certain space,
and collectors that make stuff like this.
For example, games.
And games can be folk games like this,
or local multiplayer games, which you can see here,
or performative games like Hit Me from Kao Abe.
Ramiro Cobeta is a game designer and he was asked what he's doing and he said,
I focus a lot on making games that bring people together.
So he's interested in social behavior and interactions between different people.
And a whole bunch of people and events and collectives do this in the world.
And it started, well it didn't start, but you can see here an overview of a couple of events and collectors that were starting this, like Cocoromi in 2006.
And then, well these are kind of events and collectors that are doing this.
throughout the world. And what's interesting about this is that they're all inspired by each other.
So when I asked in a mailing list, why did you start doing this, then they were
answering with things like
Cocoromian baby causes were happening and we wanted to have something like this as well.
And this can be in the UK, but also in Argentina and in Sweden and in Australia.
So Baby Causes is mentioned a lot.
Baby Causes is this underground collective in New York,
and they had a mission of bringing things to a larger audience.
As you can see here, either through do-it-yourself arcades
or getting them together and showcase these arcades
and get people to play, which normally wouldn't maybe not do,
but they were just pulled into the whole playing experience,
sometimes literally by having these things surrounding them.
Douglas Wilson, creator of Johann Sebastian Jaust, says that there is a lot of ground to be explored
between the intersection between games and more experience-based creative traditions.
And you can see what he did, for example, with Johann Sebastian Jaust.
As we are now in Europe, I was looking to see what kind of stuff is happening in Europe.
And there's a whole bunch of them out there, like the Indie Games Arcade at Eurogamer brings games to...
Indie games to an audience, a AAA audience normally.
Game City in the UK, for example, who tries to experiment with new kinds of events.
Like this, for example.
A maze in Berlin where they try to have an indie connect, where they put things up like this and try to have gravity on the wall.
But also, this is a little bit an example of the exhibition.
And also, a pop-up event like this, like the Nifflas dance was happening there.
And we brought it also to Croatia, for example, Beach Game Jams,
what Rumpus and Marie are going to talk about,
and the Wood Festival in Copenhagen is happening,
and then where these kind of people, you see the joy in their faces,
and it's a new festival that's going to take place next year again.
And then it's not only game events, but also in the theater,
stuff like this is happening.
What Kony is doing, they try to have people experience new adventures in the theater and outside the theater
and use these theater aspects of it.
So there's a lot of stuff happening out there.
We try to engage, Chad Toperk and me try to engage
new, all these curators and collectives
in conversation with each other.
So we have the new game salon, which is a hangout,
bi-weekly hangout, which we started recently.
And if you want to know more of these things
that are happening everywhere, I set up a Tumblr
where I collect all these videos for playful culture.
which you can see, have a look here.
So this was my talk for now. Thank you so much.
Applause
They asked us to take the questions at the end, outside, because we're short on time.
There we go. Hi everybody. My name's Maria Zoe, just sort of mentioned I work as, or I run, help run the World Rumpus, self-titled Queen Ruffhauser.
I guess sort of I refer to myself as Queen Ruffhauser because the work that we do, or the work that I do running it is sort of very wide and varied, so there's a lot of tasks involved.
The World Rumpus is within itself I guess sort of.
I have arcade, indie games club nights, and I really hate referring to it as a club night
because there's something sort of inherently sort of 90s and kitsch about that.
I can't really think of a better way to phrase events which bring together indie games and
alcohol and late night events.
And so we've run seven events to date, and we predominantly run these in London, but
we've also run events as far afield as San Francisco in partnership with Venus Patrol
and One Life Left, and we've run events as well on a fucking boat.
So, generally this sort of stuff that we curate at these events,
so the selection of games that we present is stuff that we curate.
So, it tends to be, we started off with a very strict rule of saying,
right, it's going to be local multiplayer games only.
And then we accidentally broke that rule by showcasing games such as Super Hexagon,
which were sort of, okay, well actually no, it's competitive single player as well.
At our GDC event, sort of two years ago, we then hosted or presented Proteus, which is
the furthest away that you could probably get from local multiplayer and sort of competitive
single player games.
So when it comes to talking about the games and the events, the games that we show at
our events, it's kind of, I guess with the logic of, we kind of know it when we see it,
but...
But yeah, so we've also been branching out
sort of in the past year.
So this past year at GDC, we also ran the World Rumpus
Rumpus Royale, which was an indie games world tournament.
And we've also worked alongside Venus Patrol and Keita
Takahashi's company, Yuvula, to create the game Tenuonya Teams,
which we presented at our event or a party last year.
So who are the World Rumpus?
So it's not just myself.
I work alongside.
This rag-tag bunch of people who are Dick Hogg and Ricky Haggett,
who work to...
They work creating the games Ho-Ho-Kum and Fro-Wish-a-Says,
and George Buckingham, who you can probably not believe
was retrospectively photoshopped into that picture afterwards.
He was probably best known for creating the game Punch the Custard.
So, why do we do the events that we do?
And I think for me it's that...
I look around at sort of the events and things that were happening within London at the time
when we started World Rampus, and there were a lot of events which were for sort of indie
developers to showcase their work to other indie developers.
And there was also a lot of events which were showcasing indie games within larger game
expos and established spaces.
I don't want to use the word gamer, but as it's only a seven-minute talk, I've got to
paraphrase.
So I'm going to use that term.
But neither of these spaces were actually places that I felt welcome or I felt that
I was really supposed to be in.
But as someone who wasn't really a game developer or someone who wasn't really that involved
with playing that many sort of AAA games.
We're sort of thinking, well, where do people like me go who are sort of creatively curious
about these sort of games to run these events?
And exactly as Zoe just sort of mentioned in that talk, that I feel like a cliche that
we were inspired by looking at these photographs of events that were happening elsewhere.
So the events that Gamma were putting, or Cocoromi were putting on, and the Gamma events
which you can see here, and the events that Babycastles were running in New York.
I looked at these spaces and I looked at these events and the people that were at them and I could see myself in those places and it felt like a space where I would be welcomed in this sort of event that I was passionate about recreating and running this sort of event.
So we sort of took inspiration from those and started setting up our own events.
And it's kind of interesting listening to sort of Kelly Wallach talking this morning about the reason why they don't look at or when questioned why they don't bring.
Why they bring the indie mega-books to PAX and they don't look at creating.
a separate showcase is specifically for those games.
Because if they thought that they'd be putting a filter
onto the audience that you'd be bringing in.
And I guess the point that I'd argue
is that it's completely correct that you
would be creating a filter.
But by running those events at PAX as well,
there's still already a filter in place.
And it's not a filter that someone like myself
passes through quite comfortably.
But also, these events like the stuff
that Baby Castles were doing and that Kokoromi
were doing as well.
They weren't just necessarily about sort of creating these sort of neutral spaces.
They were spaces which were born out of the creativity and passion of the games that they were showcasing.
For me, when I look at a game like Johann Sebastian Joust,
which if I have to hold up one game as being
the real sort of inspiration for running the events that we do,
it is this one.
And it's a game that just for me does not
equal being showcased necessarily
in a convention center like you can play there.
But for me, playing Johann Sebastian Joust
is about being in the hull of an ex-Cold War fishing
ship in the middle of night with sort of this audience
of people passionately around, the people playing sort
of bane for blood as they're watching the players.
without these games.
So it's about creating spaces which aren't just
neutral spaces for people that are outside
of our established games-led audience,
but it's about creating spaces which
are boring and sympathetic to the games and work
that they're showcasing.
And so I've just put up here a few of the details of the events
that we've run to date.
Our first event was back in 2011, and that was an event that we ran for...
Attendance for that was free.
And I looked at our budget the other day, and it actually made me laugh,
because it was about five lines long, and it came to about 400 euros
or something for the amount that we spent on it.
And the attendance for that was 300.
So it was great that we managed to keep costs down by borrowing a lot
of equipment, which does make a lot of extra work for yourself.
But there are ways of doing these events and creating and setting these things
up and running them at sort of low...
low cost and none of these costs that are up on the screen as well either take into
account the time that we work or that we do to run these events.
We're doing all of this as a labor of love and we don't pay ourselves to run these, but
you can then see that we've progressed up to GDC, which is a bit of an anomaly because
we've kind of got a captive audience out at GDC when we run the parties because there's
already a really big, enthusiastic indie games audience there.
But then coming to the most recent event that we did in London,
which was, as I say, it was on a fucking boat.
And that was the first event in the UK
where we charged entry for.
Because as this audience grows and as we manage
to reach these bigger creative audiences that
sit outside this sort of games literate sort of audience,
that of course, the costs.
And we need a bigger boat.
We need a bigger venue.
We need bigger spaces.
And because of that, that costs money.
And we want to put on these bigger exhibitions and larger
showcases.
But to do that, it costs more money.
And so we had to put a ticket price on the event.
And it was great that our attendance was sort of double
what it was for the first event.
But what we did find retrospectively was sort of
being at that event is that you could see by the audience
who had attended that it wasn't quite the same balance
that we'd had for the first event.
Instead, we were kind of missing the people that we'd
seen at our first event, which was for free, which
We were kind of missing the people that weren't perhaps already in that indie games or games
literate space.
So I think it's something that retrospectively I want to look back at what ways we can work
to potentially still make sure that we're building these events up and we're able to
grow with the demand.
But also making sure that we remain sort of open, neutral spaces that do welcome people
from outside of this space to come and realize that, okay, so that they don't, you don't
feel that you necessarily like games or you don't classify yourself as a gamer.
But there are things here that you can get passionate about.
And we need to create events and build this sense of culture
and community around these things.
And one of my favorite quotes that we had for events
was from The Guardian, which was this one which I've highlighted
in blue at the bottom, which I'll leave on,
which was that our events are a glorious mashup of music, play,
and alcohol.
Seriously, if you've never caught one of these things,
come along and bring lots of people
who don't usually play games because their lives are
about to change.
And that's what we want to do at Cyc.
We want to introduce more people to this stuff
and run more fun and interesting events.
So if you want to find out more, you
can visit theworldrunperstock.co.uk,
or you can find me on Twitter at CycIsHungry.
Thank you.
Hi, I'll try to make this real quick.
I think I have seven minutes.
My computer starts.
So hi, my name is Yon.
Um, I made a little weird presentation.
It's an experiment.
Please bear with me.
Uh, welcome.
Um,
Please, please hold your claps.
I'm going to be saying we a lot probably.
It's because I have a company that's called GlitchNap.
We're starting up a collective in Antwerp called the House of Indie, probably.
I'm affiliated with the ITU of Copenhagen, where I'm doing, where I have started a student organization that's doing events.
And with the Copenhagen Game Collective.
Let me tell you the story of the last year of my life,
because that's kind of really related to all of this.
It all started when we made this game called Laser Knights,
which was a four-player locomotive-player game we made
because we didn't want to write an AI or do level design.
We were lazy.
So it ended up like this, where four people,
because obviously you can't play four players on a keyboard
because of physical space and hardware limitations,
it ended up four people crouching in front of a computer,
having a blast, kicking the floor, you know, jumping in the air.
But...
Yeah, that's not really something you can sell.
But the interesting thing that happened here...
This is a tilted thing. This is annoying.
I'm just going to use a touchpad.
Bear with me.
So really quickly, we realized that this creates a space around your game,
like a sort of almost physical area that you're now playing in with people.
But it's really confining to, like, stand bent over and look at a laptop.
So...
What we did was we put the game in an old arcade machine, you know, like one of those old fridges,
and we were able to, when we set it up in a public space, attract a lot of people
because of the familiar shape of a fridge that plays video games.
And then we were invited to the Nordic Game Indie Night
as a nominee on the one condition, unofficially,
the one condition that we would actually bring the arcade machine,
which was a problem because we didn't actually own that one,
we borrowed it from someone.
So we decided to build our own, which led to this.
With no money and no carpentry skills,
we ended up buying two IKEA coffee tables,
the cheapest ones you can get,
and putting them together, putting a screen in there,
and popping out four controllers, which resulted in this.
This is my favorite picture.
This guy is obviously having a blast.
at playing LaserNate.
We ended up actually winning that award,
which I think no small part to bringing this arcade
because we just dominated the space.
Every game had its own booth.
They all looked identical.
Ours was really special because we built this physical thing.
And it kind of went on from there.
The problem with this one was the IKEA wood is actually cardboard,
so the wheels we put on there kept on breaking.
So we decided we need a new one, and let's make mobility our priority
so we can take it everywhere.
So we made the Babycade, which looks kind of like this.
Again, there's a young person having a blast.
Yeah, that's it. We couldn't get a shopping cart, so we ended up just buying the cheapest
vintage baby stroller we could get. This has been showcased several places, and we're hoping
to bring it to parks and just drive it around downtown with both our indie games and your
indie games and whatever.
A bit later, I went to Global Game Jam in Antwerp, which is my hometown, although I live in Copenhagen.
I decided to bring part of this culture that I'm engaged with back home.
So again, I had no money, so I bought the cheapest vintage coffee table I could find.
I put a screen in it, and I brought it and played some of the games that I play so often in Copenhagen.
That ended up, I ended up meeting exactly the right person who wanted to help me with this, took it forward,
and we ended up making it into The Press X, which is a platform where we curate indie games and bring them to events.
We've exhibited Proteus and Super Hexagon, Tengami, and other games at places that have never seen those types of games before,
which is really awesome, and this was made in January, we finished it in February, March,
and it's been to like ten different events, and it's gonna be hopefully more and more.
This is a beautiful, it turned into this beautiful thing with like, we put like gold, gold plate on there that says press X and it has like gold hooks for your Xbox controllers. Really nice.
And in this one, actually, I got invited to showcase a game at Wild Rumpus.
And I arrived a day early, and that's a bit of a right conference.
And I arrived a day early and I decided, well, I don't really want to see London.
I'll just build an arcade.
So I got somebody... I spent the whole day making phone calls.
Again, I had no money.
So I, um...
I got somebody to lug these pallets through downtown London with me on foot, like a kilometer
or two, and ended up at the venue and just cut a hole in the top, put a screen in there,
and again, I made this thing with very little effort that just completely dominated the
space at the Bit of Alright conference and at Wild Rumpus.
So, to sum up, what I'm trying to say is,
build arcades, it works out, it's great,
it's great fun and it's really rewarding.
Use whatever you can find, bring them wherever you go,
and organize meetings for them.
Basically, if you build them, if you build it, they will come.
So I wish I could tell you that I have some master plan where a year ago I decided to become a game installation artist.
I wish I could tell you it was super easy getting these projects funded and finding materials, etc. etc.
I wish I could tell you there's never been any hammering or gluing or sawing mistakes.
I can't, but I can guarantee that these machines are a really good way to get your game to
actually be played by people you otherwise have a difficult time reaching, because they
don't necessarily understand computers, but they understand the shape of whatever it is
you have there, or they understand that this is something interesting that they should
pay attention to.
It can also get you invited to a lot of cool parties, like GDC Europe.
In our case, it won us our first award.
I got here to come to GDC Europe and sort of host a panel.
I really recommend it.
The thing we started in Antwerp, I put a screen in a coffee table
and since then we've curated two entire exhibitions
and we've brought it to ten other events.
So, to round us all off, I have no idea how I am on time.
Why I think this matters from a sort of higher point of view,
these devices are the only gateway, or every device is a gateway
to the digital world inside.
If you want any game to be played by humans,
you have to make an interface to the physical world,
which means you're giving it a physical shape.
You don't do this consciously when you make a computer game
because the computer is your shape, but you totally have the power
to put it in any other shape, and every shape is different.
Using shapes that we're familiar with has really interesting consequences.
The three crates, pallets I put on top of each other were so sturdy,
people were standing on them and dancing and sitting,
and it was so makeshift, I was just going to trash it, I wasn't going to bring it back home.
I handed out markers and duct tape for people to tag it and make it, you know, this sort
of old, you know, here today, gone tomorrow thing.
The Press X, on the other hand, became this beautiful ornament, like we ended up lacking
it so it's shiny and it's beautiful and people just want to go in there and be enthralled
in whatever magical, beautiful indie game we put on there.
So and to connect it to the other things, events and showcases is where these installations
come to fruition.
The importance of local multiplayer games has been argued quite a lot in last year's, you know,
Dispatch Friends, Kickstarter, and stuff like that.
These events, they can provide the critical mass that those games need to make sense,
both for players and spectators.
Games like that often don't make any sense when you just play them like a four-player game
with only three people and there's no spectators.
That's not the same.
To me, they are to games what movie nights are to movies, or concerts are to music.
It's a place where you come and you enjoy the games that are being curated or that you
brought yourself with your friends.
Then also at these events, interesting things happen where these
concerts or movie nights overlap.
This is Chipsle playing at the Wild Rampus party in front of Super
Hexagon, which is a super interesting combination of two forms of media.
Same thing happened to the game I made Go Nuts, and DJ's wearing
robot masks while we're trying to play it on his body.
And that's all I have to say.
I hope you are inspired to start doing the same thing I have so I can bring my arcades
to your parties.
Thanks a lot for listening, thanks for coming.
This has been a great turn up, great opportunity.
These are all the people I would like to thank and mention, etc.
Thank you Marie and Zoraida, and see you later.
Questions?
We'll meet us outside.
There's one last thing.
I almost forgot.
So when I got invited to come to GDC,
I thought it would be so cool if we could bring,
or we thought it would be so cool
if we could bring an arcade, but what's possible?
So I booked my Air Berlin Fair,
and they said you can bring one luggage.
And I was like, I don't need a luggage.
I can just put some t-shirts in my hand luggage.
Then I decided, why not build an arcade inside a suitcase?
So we came up with the Lugatron, which you can see right here.
And I'm going to be playing on it until they kick us out of this room.
But more interestingly, it'll be in the Expo Hall next to SOS's amazing
Achtung Arcade, which actually has a place in the Expo Hall until tomorrow
afternoon.
So please stop by, come play it, talk to me, or find me on the internet.
That's where I live.
So thank you.