started. Um, my name is Nick Van Vught and I'm the uh, community lead at Yukon Games. Uh,
today I'm going to be talking to everyone here about overcoming community negativity. Um, and
as the title suggests, it can be a bit of an exercise in sanity. Um, I've been asked to let
everyone know to please silence your noise makers. Um, that'd be fantastic.
So very quickly to give some background information,
Yukon Games is a Toronto based mobile game studio.
At Yukon we currently have 13 titles available for download
which vary across different demographics.
Our oldest games on the top row
have been around since 2009.
We use the term U Wars to refer to all of them at once.
These titles are built in HTML5.
They're text-based games that center heavily
around community interaction
and befriending people in the game.
These are also effectively re-skinned versions
of the exact same game, each with their own theme.
Because of this, the audience for these games
are very similar.
Skewing more heavily to the male demographic
between the ages of 18 to 49,
these players also tend to be some of the more volatile
that we deal with.
In this presentation I'm going to be using a lot of case
studies from these games as the majority of the struggles that
we've encountered in our day to day engagement come from these
seven titles. U-Wars is also a unique case study because it is
100 percent controlled and operated by our community team
in a live ops fashion and has been for the past three years.
So once active development stopped in our games,
our position within the community team
was to continue to engage with our players
and bring them new content while running weekly events.
With no dev knowledge on our small team,
this focused on easy to use tools
that allowed us to keep players as happy as we could.
However, the lack of development over the past few years
have only made player frustrations even more evident.
We've had a lot of members of our community who have had their accounts for upwards of
eight years and have become discouraged with the state of the game and the lack of updates.
These are some of our most passionate players who flock to the forums and to social media
to express their concerns about these titles.
As I mentioned, my talk today is going to be about tackling and overcoming community negativity.
And as I'm sure everyone read in the course description,
as community managers, we assume that we have this topic handled.
It's easy to think that because you've dealt with negativity and lack of enthusiasm in the past,
you're going to be able to address these concerns.
In reality, it's an ever-changing landscape and something that we honestly don't do enough
and should always be working on improving.
As a quick warning, I'll be showing some player feedback
and comments in this presentation that are a bit colorful,
to say the least.
I hope that no one takes any offense to this,
but really I wanted everyone to get a better idea
of what we deal with on a daily basis.
I know it's stuff that we all worry about on a day-to-day
and keeping this presentation as honest as possible
is the only way to get the most out of it that we can.
Also, as you can tell, I'm using really bad stock images
from the web, from like the internet,
because those are the best.
Maintaining player enthusiasm is a tough job for community teams, as I'm sure most of you
know.
Decisions are frequently made outside your control, and the responsibility of interacting
with and mitigating the expectations of your community falls on your shoulders.
It can often be difficult to conduct yourself in a way that is both representative of your
gaming studio, while also empathizing with the frustrations of your community.
But these aren't necessarily contradictory positions.
Enthusiasm is also hard to maintain.
Some days are extremely rewarding and you feel as though
you've cracked the code on player engagement,
and other days you feel like you're beating your head
against the wall repeatedly over and over and over again.
And that's why figuring out little tips and tricks
on how to overcome these type of things
can be very rewarding and helpful.
Most importantly, I believe that maintaining enthusiasm
is draining on both your staff and the gaming community.
It can be easy to brush off some pointed attacks or player criticisms,
but often keeping your community happy and engaged in your product
can be detrimental to the well-being of your team and the community.
The biggest problem we face is that giving players what they want
isn't necessarily a top priority for your product team.
It can often come at the cost of long nights spent dealing with player concerns
or dreading going into the forums day after day.
At the worst, these expectations can cause anxiety or depression, and the problem with
that is that maintaining player enthusiasm is our responsibility.
Because this is our responsibility, you have to work with your community on improving player
sentiment.
It can lead to increased sales, improved team morale, and a better community to interact
with.
It can just be tough some days to dive in head first, understanding the negativity that
you may face.
So to give a bit of context in this presentation,
as I mentioned, I took somewhere in the ballpark
of maybe over 100, closer to 200 screenshots
of extremely negative comments that we've received
in my five years at Yukon,
but in an effort to keep the presentation
moving along very smoothly, here are just a few of them.
So here we have a user calling us dumb and lazy, saying that we're creating an unfriendly
atmosphere and saying that we don't deserve to be in the gaming industry. This user has
also chosen to use one of my most disliked nicknames in our company history. Pukin.
this charming player has also used the term Pukin uh and told us to stop running
tournaments that cause lag. So for some added context about Pukin, it became so
popular that we actually added it to our language filter blacklist.
And this one's super fun as well.
A user saying that the new feature we implemented
was a joke, calling us a merry band of morons
and telling us to take our heads out of each other's asses
and wake up.
He then goes on to say that his five year old
could have designed a better system
and that we're gonna lose players due to this feature.
For some clarification, this comment came following
a request to update the feature the player's
complaining about, asking us to make it more interactive,
which we did and was met with extreme negativity.
This player called us dishonest, which in itself isn't too bad, but he just piles it on
afterwards saying that we're a joke, that our community laughs in our face and that they
fail to believe in us. Another player saying that we don't care about our community and that
we only care when our players call us names. In an effort to exemplify this, he then calls us
wankers and clowns. And here's another fun nickname, F-Ukin, which a player renamed
themselves to and then said that they were the CEO.
He then encouraged the community to go to the app store, providing them with a handy
link where, like I said, it's HTML5 games, and then called for a boycott of the game
and also called to arms to write negative reviews in with the Better Business Bureau,
which I stayed up writing responses to.
And this is a good case study too. Lots of fun, this one. Um, here's a case where we tried to do
something fun for our users. It was the holidays and we wanted to give back to our players by
giving them a bunch of free items, running cool events, um, and just giving them stuff just for
logging in. Most of them seemed to revolt saying that the gifts weren't generous enough. This
player remarked that our two admins were too busy engaging in intercourse to respond to
their concerns.
And another player mad about the free holiday gift,
saying that instead of plowing them in the butt,
we should have given them something better.
Like I said, free gifts, just for signing on.
They didn't like it.
In our attempts to help players out
and create a more engaging product,
we were met with even more frustration.
We ran a survey to better understand
what players wanted from the direction of the game.
The intent was to give a voice to all players
and to genuinely gauge player sentiment and frustrations.
The survey received some eloquent and thoughtful abuse,
which I've highlighted here.
Here's a player saying that our results were dog shit
and insulting, saying that we're unable
to successfully run a game.
He goes on to tell us that we're inept
and unable to do our jobs.
In the rest of the message, he even provided me a copy and paste template for me to send
to my CEO about what a bad job I was doing.
And here's one of the many players, many players, that agreed with the previous post, saying
that the survey was a massive waste of time and inferring that we were bribing them into
answering it and that it reeked of desperation for a dying game.
So, that's funny, what can you do when you're faced by this
toxicity day in and day out, every single day,
it's just awful.
And you can, managing these varying degrees of negativity
across a dozen active titles means that you have to learn
to and adapt to the different communities that surface
in your games.
Treating every case as though they were the same
can be catastrophic and detrimental to managing
your community.
And keep in mind that there are no catchalls
when it comes to handling these concerns.
Regardless of the level of negativity or prior experience,
there are underlying principles
that every community manager can do
that help inspire, build, and maintain player loyalty.
So here are some tried and true approaches
that we've used at Ukin to help mitigate player concerns
and to keep players engaged.
Champion those in your community
who are passionate about your game or product.
Constantly try new things, given the tools that you have.
Admit your failures and faults both for the company and personally as a community manager.
And finally, be honest and relatable. And these are going to be the pillars that I'm
going to be discussing in my talk today. So let's start with the first point.
Making champions out of those who are passionate creates players who will fight by your side and
who will dilute negativity wherever they see it, be it in the forums, on social media,
and even through email. Forces of War is our real-world war-themed U-Wars title. At its peak,
it had nearly 400,000 monthly active users. One of those players was named Barry Chen.
Although Barry had only ever spent a few dollars in the game and had long since stopped spending,
he was very, very close to many influential and high-spending players.
Our community managers arranged a tournament that Barry would run completely by himself. We
only needed to set up the modifiers and schedule the tournament. Something our community
managers could do without bugging a developer. Barry would organize the players,
calculate the scores for us and encourage players to sign up. We on the community team
would only need to cross reference those numbers, which only took a few minutes, and
supply some free items and minimal free currency for the winning players. It was so
successful that players still talk about it to this day. So here are a few comments that
better illustrate this. These are happy comments.
Thanks, Barry, even though I'm not participating,
it's a lot of work, it shows dedication.
Thanks to Yukon for chipping in some prizes.
Everyone knows Barry is a boss.
He's selfless and organized.
Cheers, Barry.
Barry's the god of forces of war.
He's bringing war back to this great war game.
War's a theme.
Grandmaster Chen, when he walks in the room,
everyone bows.
Seriously, the initiative and selfless spirit
really creates a new perspective for so many, Barry.
Thank you, Yukon, for working with and green-lighting this player-run tournament.
Hope you can upgrade your servers to deal with the next one.
And that's fine, I'll take a little bit of, you know, a little bit of harassing
if it is followed by such a positive comment.
So, what did all this praise get us?
The tournament was a resounding success.
We had a 200% increase in revenue over the period of the tournament,
which was more significant than some of our more successful staff-designed tournaments at the time.
We created a limited item that players could purchase
called the Chen, named after Barry.
It had great stats and was sought after by the community
who wanted an advantage over other players.
We also gave Barry one of his own items for free,
which kicked off player personalized items within the game.
We now hold Hall of Fame contests and regularly create
and name items after our passionate players
to give back to them and to also generate excitement
and buzz around participating in events.
Creating these items is both low friction and low cost,
and it encourages players who are passionate
to engage more often in the community,
and also to generate positive sentiment, which can't hurt.
Finally, this event was the initiative needed
to start player-run and organized tournaments,
which we still support to this day nearly five years later.
In conjunction with these player run tournaments is the idea of trying something new and is a key
component in all of our games. We always take feedback into consideration for development, but
actually acting on it shows players that you're willing to listen to them and act on their
ideas. Trying out a new modifier in a tournament or running an event outside of scheduled
rotations can show players that you're willing to work with them instead of against them.
By listening to the feedback and suggestions of your community, you show them that their
opinions are valued. It's not just about listening, though. You have to act on it. And
don't make false promises telling them that you're going to do something that you're unsure
of, but promise them that you can look into it and make sure that you report back.
Sometimes getting these changes up and running quickly can be difficult, but keeping communication
channels open with players helps considerably.
Through community suggestions, we've run numerous tournaments and events in our games outside
of regulated times and have seen a three or four times increase in sales and a lot of
positive sentiment for such a small change.
As a case study, let's take the Centaurians event that we held in one of our games, Age
of Legends, our fantasy-themed war game.
In addition to battling, competing in clans, and completing missions, crafting has always
been an important mechanic within our games.
Players liked upgrading their items to make them even more powerful, but were limited
by the number of items they could carry.
So this presented a unique opportunity to give players exactly what they wanted, stronger
items they could use in battle, along with a more interactive event that had been requested
for months.
The premise was a bit complicated, but ultimately it allowed players to focus on acquiring items
that they could craft into a stronger item.
This image was shared on our Facebook and Twitter pages, not only to give players a
better visual opportunity to understand what needed to be done, but also to grow those
pages out.
And again, we were met with resistance from the community.
Although they had been asking for something like this numerous times, there was a fear
that they would miss out on obtaining these limited items.
players with low level accounts were frustrated that they may not get the high level items
without having to pay for it. And as soon as the event started, many called for boycotts
and others called us useless and insulted our developers before even trying out the event.
But following these complaints, we still had plenty of positive comments in the forums as
well. People giving us credit for trying something new.
One of our players congratulated us for doing something
different, saying that they would still get great items
just for participating, and that some events are just
intended to be difficult.
And thankfully, this player said that with the release of
the event, we managed to make the game interesting again.
Finally, a post by a player who goes out of their way
to help the community better understand the benefits
of participating in the event,
even if they aren't entirely happy with it.
He addressed the concerns of the low-level players
and even gave them some stretch goals to shoot for
to benefit themselves from the tournament.
This post alone encouraged the vast majority
of the community to actually try out the tournament
and increase the amount of positive sentiment
for trying something new.
Explaining the worth of something like this is very difficult. And on the surface, knowing
that players simply participated isn't quite enough to justify the amount of work that went
into it. In a worst case scenario, we would have created a tournament that had flooded our
economy with really strong weapons and it could have caused a collapse in our game's balance.
Which brings up a more measurable question. What did our metrics look like?
So we had a few thousand players participate in the
weekend event.
80% reached the first tier.
So right away, if you just played along and you hit the
first tier, you'd get some free premium currency.
65% of participants received free items.
And those were worth much more than the free premium currency
that we gave them.
And only 1% actually obtained and managed to assemble the
ultimate item, which isn't necessarily a bad thing.
It promotes the limited nature of the item and the prestige
of actually being able to obtain one.
And our metrics showed the company that investing in new ideas like this is actually a good
thing.
Month over month, our revenue in the game grew by 47%.
And even had a tail that extended into April, which was usually one of our slower months
in the year.
Next is admitting when you're wrong or admitting when something isn't working correctly.
And it's imperative in combating negativity.
It's also a trait that all community managers need to embrace.
There's a need to protect your integrity or stand strong against accusations, but telling
players when you know something sucks can help a lot.
In our game Crime Inc., we have items called underbosses. They can be purchased using
premium or soft currency and give stat boosts to player accounts. They have great art and
allow players to collect a council of criminals to help attack others. Following a lengthy
investigation, we had found that one of our premium underbosses, so ones that you actually
had to spend real money to obtain, uh, needed to be rebalanced. And the item was initially
designed without a long term plan in mind. We had
we had to make a really difficult decision.
We had to reduce the benefit that the item was giving,
even though players had spent real money on it.
Her name was Meryl Newsome.
And with the right items equipped,
Meryl could provide players with nearly unlimited
recharges to their health and stats.
So it effectively let players play for free
for as long as they wanted.
And for a free-to-play title like Crime Inc.,
this was very, very dangerous.
And obviously this blew up in the forums with players calling us greedy bastards, saying
that we're bending the laws, committing fraud and saying that the decision to make the change
was highway robbery. Players were urging others to contact third party services for full
payment refunds, resetting their accounts and many were contacting us with some of the
more belligerent and abusive behavior that we've encountered in the company. And this
comment isn't even the tip of the iceberg. So how do you deal with something like this
without popping a vein in your head?
In our experience, admitting exactly what happened
and why it had to happen means that you have to admit
that the initial design was ill-informed
and that the fault lies in the hands of the company
and relieves the players of blame.
Although players are drastically affected
in rebalancing cases like this,
finding loopholes is understandable.
In order to keep the game fair and balanced for all players,
it's important for the community to not only understand
why the decision was made,
but then to give them a platform to voice their concerns.
We spent an exhausting afternoon in the forums,
responding directly to player concerns and feedback.
No question was off the table.
We spent a considerable amount of time doing our best
to quell the concerns of our community,
and honestly, it helped.
We had numerous players praising us
for taking the time to talk to them
and for trying to find a compromise for their concerns.
Sure, there were still plenty of upset users,
but knowing that we took the time to address the concerns
took a lot of the pressure off.
In summary, we found that players are substantially
less likely to directly attack you if you put up your hands
and you say, my bad.
And that goes for bugs too.
Tell players what's going on.
Are you working on a fix?
What's the status of the fix?
It shows players that you're trying to manage
their expectations the best that you can.
And my final point, it's important to not come at players
from on high.
Representing your company is critical,
but also being able to talk to your players on their level
is necessary in improving communication.
Saying that you understand your player's frustration isn't always helpful.
It can come across as dismissive if you don't genuinely try to connect it with your player's
concerns.
Show them that you know why they're frustrated, reiterate their concerns, and speak to their
issues in a way that shows them that you're more than just a talking head.
Anticipate how players will react to your comments.
If you can anticipate their response,
it makes it significantly easier
to mitigate your expectations.
If you write a response and think,
this will probably make things worse,
chances are it will.
Show of hands real quick,
who has written up a response in HitSend
when they knew that it was gonna make the situation worse?
Me too.
It, don't do it.
You're gonna keep doing it.
I'm gonna keep doing it,
but it never makes things easier.
If you can recognize it before you HitSend,
you have time.
and bite your tongue, seriously.
You may feel inclined to respond to the contrary
and to prove the player wrong,
but never allow yourself to respond while in this headspace.
In some cases, honesty means telling a player
that they're incorrect,
but it never means that you should do so in a way
that devalues their contribution to the community.
As a side note, did you know that there's like
a million photos of women biting laptops on Google?
I hate it so much.
So being honest and relatable gains you a lot of credit
in the community and players are always thrilled
that you took the time to talk to them on their level.
In one of the threads I mentioned earlier
where we conducted the community survey,
we received a considerable number of complaints
from players who felt as though regardless
of the intention of the survey,
it was too late for us to redeem ourselves.
Our response was as follows, and I'm paraphrasing
as you can see a very long admin post.
It's difficult to help a community that's so negative.
The purpose of the survey was to give a voice to players who feel uncomfortable posting in the
forums, because of the negativity, and being mean doesn't open dialogue for proactive solutions.
Even following that initial post, players continued to harass us, saying that we didn't
care about our community and that the requests for new features had gone unnoticed for quite
some time. Aha! This provided an opportunity for us to be more transparent to our user base.
We went on to describe a bit more about the way new features are worked on and how they
get through a suggestion pipeline and eventually deployed by our devs.
It also gave us a chance to explain to players that the voice of so few in the forum doesn't
always represent the best interest of the entire community.
I think that was noted in the first talk this morning for the community summit, which it's
roughly 1 in 1,000 that actually respond in the forums, so it's such a small, small number
of players, but they can also be some of the worst players.
And after a bit of explanation,
players received the response very positively.
This player is thanking us for taking the time
to address their concerns,
and admitted that they had lost faith in our ability
to provide customer service,
simply because we weren't being as honest
as we should have been.
This player's feedback was actually very well put,
saying that despite their comments,
they were only interested in engaging in a dialogue,
and didn't realize that we would have taken it
as seriously as we did.
Another player saying that our intent interactions in the forums turned them from the grumpiest
player to the most content. And a player telling us that we just provided them with the best
in-game customer service and feedback that they've ever received. This player is noting
that baby steps helped the situation and actually provided useful information, encouraging us
to be as honest as possible.
and probably the most relevant comment
and the one we receive the most often,
thanking us for taking the time to listen and to get abused.
And this screenshot goes a long way
in illustrating just how frustrating it can be
to be a community manager.
Players assault you with abuse and harassment
and expect you to wait around for praise
once you've managed to push through to a breakthrough.
It's exhausting and draining,
and yet we encounter it every single day.
So what does this adoration mean?
In this first graph, the bump that you see here in August is a 67% increase in revenue
week over week following our interactions we had with our villains players in the forums
in regards to the community survey.
The long draining afternoon of abuse actually provided worthwhile results.
The second graph I have here is following
the Merrill Newsom incident in Crime Inc.
Getting into the forums and spending an afternoon
quelling player concerns resulted in a 54% increase
in week over week revenue.
It seems hard to believe, and trust me, it was,
but we weren't running any new sales or interesting events
or anything like that during these spikes.
The conclusion to tie to this is that spending the time
to actually connect to your players
means that you might be making your company more money.
If there was ever a reason to bring to your company
how important having a community team is, this is it.
So let's recap.
What can you do to maintain player enthusiasm
and help mitigate frustrations?
Champion those who are passionate,
so have players on your side to fight for you
and to rally the troops.
Try something new once in a while.
Get players out of their routine
and keep them engaged with your product
and your company's direction.
Admit your failures and faults.
Do your best to explain to your players
why things happen the way that they did.
And finally, be honest and relatable.
Be a spokesperson for your community
and give them a reason to root for you.
So what does the future bring?
Well, first and foremost,
the company is moving towards casual titles
like Kings of Pool, Bingo Pop,
and coming soon Jeopardy World Tour.
These present their own challenges
with different demographics,
but ultimately the themes I've talked about today
remain the same and will help carry our community team
into these releases.
And it's important to always remember
your vocal community is only a small representation
of the people who enjoy and play your games.
Don't let it get you down,
and just remember that it's something
that we're all learning with how to cope.
In the interest of time, I'll just take some questions of the wrap up area.
Thanks for having me and please remember to fill out your survey.
Thank you.