Good afternoon, everybody.
Welcome to We Demand Games.
The GDC people have asked me to remind you to please silence
your cell phones for takeoff, and also to remind you please
to rate the talk afterwards.
I'm Owen Gottlieb, assistant professor of interactive games and media at Rochester Institute
of Technology, and I'm also there at the MAGIC Center.
So I teach in the School of Interactive Games and Media, and the MAGIC Center is our game
studio and also a laboratory where we do all kinds of research.
There, I'm the founder and the principal researcher at the Initiative in Religion,
Culture, and Policy at the MAGIC Center.
This is our new campus, our new building, which is opening in the fall.
A brand new building where we're moving from a beautiful building to a very special new
building so maybe you'll have a chance to come and visit.
At the initiative, which we call RCP, we do original design and research on literacy
and comparative religion, exploring what anthropologists call the acquisition of cultural practices,
basically how people hand down aspects of their cultural practices and create new practices
within a cultural group.
And all this is targeted to policy impact, either in education or in governmental policy.
And we're faculty at RIT.
We're faculty at about seven other institutions, and that's growing.
And many fantastic graduate students and undergraduate students.
We have an alum here, Ruben, today, who is a part of what we have created, and Ian Schreiber
as well.
We've recently released two tabletop games in the Lost and Found series, and we also
have a digital prototype that we delivered for the mobile phone for our strategy game
for the National Endowment for the Humanities.
So our games are released via GameCrafter, which is one of the places that I'm going
to speak about today and do some targeted case studies about our work there.
They're for sale to the public using print-on-demand.
And these games happen to be about teaching religious legal systems.
So the games are set in Fustat, Old Cairo, in the 12th century.
And the first two games address a Jewish legal code by Moses Maimonides called the Mishneh
Torah.
And we're currently in development on an Islamic law expansion module.
We hear a lot these days about negative perceptions and fears around religious legal systems,
but we hear very little about what evolutionary anthropologists call the pro-social aspects
of religion.
And these law systems were a primary form of governance, promoting community sustainability,
collaboration and cooperation.
You can see this in the game play.
And we're working to expand that discourse around religious legal systems in their historical
and geographic contexts.
So print-on-demand comes into play in many different aspects of my work and the work
of the team members, both in the design studio and also in research in the field as we take
our games out to be played and watch what happens when people play them and different
iterations of them.
And then also teaching game design in the classroom, so when I'm teaching game design
and development,
Using these systems to help students learn about what it means to ship and that whole process.
And it's really centered around getting something on sale and in the hands of players.
So I teach my students about backwards planning, planning and visioning and the importance
of having a picture in mind of your goal and have your team bought into that goal as a
North Star with which to navigate and to inspire and aspire.
And so this was kind of the vision that had started it off.
These are the finished games in shrink wrap that we had received back.
And the idea was, could we get a box game in our hands and have it?
And so this was our North Star.
We actually had one game in mind, and we ended up with two games,
which I'm very excited about.
So I start here with this realized vision of games in my hands,
and then we'll work backwards.
So this is me turning around the box.
I can't believe after the years of work we put into it,
I'm holding the game.
It's going to go on the shelf.
This is the strategy game, and here's the party game.
So how did I formulate the vision that we would eventually together realize?
Well, I had my previous game, Jewish Time Jump New York,
is a mobile GPS augmented reality game for teaching history on location
in Washington Square Park in New York City.
And the game was built on Eris, an open source platform,
and so the game is free for players.
I'm very proud of the game, and I learned a great deal about getting games
into the hands of players and on the market with that project.
Now, Jewish Time Jump, while it was a critical success,
and it's a success from our players' perspective,
keeping it up to date required tremendous and consistent
effort every time the software updated.
So every time the Ares platform updated,
or every time iOS was updated, and we
had to rescale everything for the screen size.
And entering this new game series,
I wanted a game that wouldn't require constant updating,
and nor would it require the kind of raising of funds
that I need to do to support that kind of updating.
Meanwhile, at the same time, my research is shifting, so I've been shifting focus from
place-based games for teaching history into looking at and analyzing the parallels between
medieval legal codes and game systems.
Both are rule-based systems, and I had moved kind of the law project to the forefront.
So we were looking at genres of tabletop games that would fit with law codes regarding, in
particular, lost and found objects.
We were thinking about things like resource management.
And I'm committed to the intersection of the embodied and the digital, just like you see
with the GPS game out in Washington Square Park.
And so we turned to a card-to-mobile approach, with games like, think about Agricola or
Settlers of Catan, that you have a tabletop game and they also have a mobile version of
it.
So I was determined to have a game that we'd have a version that could sit on the shelf
for decades without the need for digital update or for emulators to run it, because I always
get sad when I have to go, oh, I have to somehow find an emulator for this game.
And leaving behind also the freeware model of Jewish time jump, because I was going to
prove that I could generate revenue, even if small, that could
Turn back in to support the research and the kind of work that we're doing about games and learning.
So I spent a great deal of time researching what it would mean to publish an analog game,
talking to friends and colleagues who had published tabletop games
and gone through all the trials and tribulations of that process.
And eventually I landed on print-on-demand as the only viable option,
given my needs and constraints.
So we settled on the Game Crafter, and I'll speak briefly about some other options.
Over the course of about three years, I worked closely with students, including Matthew Fassman,
Ryan Muscoff, a number of other students, exploring all the affordances and limits of
print-on-demand, and then we learned about those firsthand in the hard way.
And I hope that the takeaways today, when you make your decisions going into print-on-demand,
You'll take those with you, and we'll have gone ahead and forged the bridge for you a bit.
So this is the GameCrafter storefront.
You also may be familiar with print and play from AdMagic, the people who make cards against humanity.
And this site has advanced since we were making our decisions.
It wasn't the right fit for us then. It could be now.
We kind of scouted this, whether to determine it was a good fit.
They now have a storefront as well.
And I have students in my class now, in game design and development,
who are also using Shapeways to sell straight-to-market game pieces
that are 3D printed.
Another kind of model to keep in mind.
So we landed on print-on-demand, and this is the Shapeways site.
We landed on print-on-demand, and so I want to discuss
what could print-on-demand afford us?
So here's a quick sense of what it was going to mean for us.
That we could release a game that didn't require expensive and regular updates,
that we could move forward to commercialization,
right, our games are on the market in the hands of paying customers now,
with an extremely low budget.
We could pilot a game that way and get it to market
without having to already have high sales figures.
We could print prototypes with our art and put them in the hands of players in volume
quantities and lower costs than actually having to print each one at our university print
shop, for example.
And we could develop a game for research with a shelf-worthy look and feel, that kind of
sense of what I was holding in my hands.
And maybe even more importantly from a pro perspective, I could avoid these things I
really wanted to avoid.
So I wanted to avoid laying out thousands of dollars to make a print run prior to sales,
so low budget entry to market.
I didn't have to run a Kickstarter campaign and raise funds and do community management
for Kickstarter or do supply chain logistics for making sure that things get shipped out
to all the people who contribute.
I was very hesitant to go the Kickstarter route, especially on this project, but in
general I see the tremendous effort that people who do Kickstarters have to do.
I wanted to try to spend more time in the design studio if possible.
And when I talk about supply chain logistics, some of the things I'm talking about are,
for example, warehousing.
If you're going to order a thousand games, you've got to usually pay rent and store them
somewhere, especially if you're in a city and you don't happen to have a safe space
to store cardboard.
Other aspects of the supply chain logistics have to do with the distribution.
Am I going to have to walk to the post office, you know, four or five times a week
with bundles in my hand in order to get there and ship them out?
And then I had spent some time doing some work in supply chain logistics
when I was a management consultant and knew about aspects of the system like RMAs,
so return merchandise authorizations, and I did not want to get involved with that.
I wanted to concentrate on game design, development, and looking at how people learn with games.
In addition, the storefront would give us merchandising so I wouldn't have to fight
for shelf space anywhere, so that was important.
And then thinking about working with a printer.
One of my friends had said to me, listen, when you're working on getting your analog
game printed, you need to go to China and you need to meet in person with your printer
because you need to have a relationship with that printer or things are going to go sideways.
And I really didn't want to have to build a relationship and go to China and I had really
no way of going to China.
It's someday I want to go to China, but not for working, you know, with working on a printer
in that regard.
So these are all things that I could avoid.
Now on the con side, because I want you to know about some of the issues that are right
up front that we're dealing with, you have an increase in printing cost when you don't
go bulk.
So if you haven't gone bulk, you're going to be paying a great deal for printing costs
on an individual game or even maybe 10 or 15 or 20, the price is going to go up.
We're going to talk at greater length when I do the case studies about not having product
safety testing.
And ways that there are workarounds for dealing with that.
We still needed product liability insurance, and I'm going to tie that back to the issue
of safety testing.
We weren't directly working with a printer, so I couldn't pick up the phone and talk to
the printer and say, listen, this is an issue.
So that's a downside of not having a relationship with a printer.
So we have higher prices and then lower margins.
We're talking about very, very low margins because of the cost of printing in a print
on demand service that you're not doing bulk with.
So I want to take you inside some of the case studies of working inside of the GameCrafter
in particular, so that you can avoid some of these pitfalls that we've had.
And we're going to start at the very end of production, and I like to call this one the
Case of the Greedy Grabber.
For those of you who haven't been inside on the GameCrafter, this is the inside.
You can see these patterned card backs, and I'll show you in more detail.
All of the art in the game is based on architecture of Fustat Cairo in the 12th century.
And so this is where you kind of put up all of your individual cards.
This is, I have the students in my class have to have everything ready on GameCrafter.
They're not forced to actually take it to market, but they have to understand the production
process to get it so they could take it to market.
This is another card back working on architectural patterns.
We're going to talk about playmats and cards.
So one of the things, these are playmats from the game.
So it's largely a card game.
This is also important to think about because the cost of,
say, a meeple is going to be much larger than the cost of a
card, and so many of the designers I've been talking to
have been saying, OK, we're going to go all card.
And you can take mechanics that are based on things that
would be more expensive.
We're going to make them a card mechanic and be able to ship a game that's much more affordable.
So we went the card route from the beginning with the exception of our instruction booklet and these play mats.
So there's play mats that each player has and then there's a communal play mat where communal play takes place.
This is what the communal playmat looks like so that people are placing their cards.
It's a game about balancing your communal responsibilities with your family responsibilities,
collaboration, cooperation, competition, mixing, and then the trade-off decisions that players
start having to make in doing that.
And this is the cow herd roll card.
So that's the playmat that the cow herd plays.
And we have both male and female characters for each of the...
for each of the roles in the game.
Now, this is about QA.
So there's markings on here that are not the actual cards,
they're QA markings.
We went through about 19 QA cycles
on the last version of this.
And I wanted to show specifically ways
that we approached QA.
So I'm gonna close in on the money purse in the river.
And, right, this is so if we have about seven,
eight people doing rounds of QA,
because all the details, right, have to be.
We did about 19 rounds of QA on the version that goes to the printer.
We did a few early print rounds to test things out, but now we're talking about the one we
took to market.
We did that and then I ordered proof copies of the game so I could pull the game out,
I could look at it, I could go through every aspect, check all the printing, check the
card ends, everything, went through the whole thing and it looked gorgeous.
We were like so excited.
So the teams gathered around, we're looking at this, okay, we can go to ship.
So we had shipped one of each game.
We then order 10 of each.
Now these are games in the $35 range,
and you pay shipping, and you pay shipping insurance.
So we get the boxes back, open it up,
and we start spot checking.
And this is one of the play mats.
Now you'll notice on the bottom that there's cutoff.
So completed communal responsibility
is partially cut off.
And on the cow herd, you can see that beyond the law pile
at the bottom right is cut off,
and the T of transgression is cut off.
We're going like, how is this possible?
Like we have a proof in our hand.
But this didn't happen, and yet this is happening.
So we can't imagine what it is.
And we start to do investigation.
And I reach out, and I'm writing to the game crafter.
And we went back to the designer, who followed the
specs very closely.
And eventually we found out that if you pull a template
and you look at the margins on the template, that you have to
follow the margin on the template.
exactly and that the stats on the left won't work to get you there.
And from there we got into, I talked to a printer friend of mine at the university,
and he took me back to my old days when I was working in print and said,
oh well you know there's bleed and no bleed printing by the way,
and so when you are going to...
print in bulk, it's actually going to change the way apparently the game crafter is going to do this.
So there's a page actually in Help that they talk about in detail that we found months later.
This might not even have been up when we first looked.
They talk about the registration settings and all this, but we had no idea even to look.
for
this kind of thing.
And now the game is out, and this is fixed,
and we fixed the 10 copies we got back.
But for anyone who's going to look at this,
you want to get into the details of how
to work with things like the difference
between getting a proof copy, which is not a proof copy,
and how that can change in scale,
and in particular, into some of these printing aspects.
So a proof copy will not clue you in.
Plan for the greedy grabber.
That's case study one.
This is the case of don't eat this game.
And so I'm not an attorney.
This is not legal advice.
If you want that, you need to seek out an attorney.
This is a story about what I researched
and then decided to do.
And I hope that it's informing for you
when you're working in print on demand.
So this is part of the page
of Lost and Found the Strategy Game.
And if you go into the text a little deeper,
you'll see we have a line that says,
may contain inks that should not be ingested,
not suitable for children younger than 14 years.
Is anyone familiar with this issue of testing?
A couple people.
Great.
So 14 years is our text.
And then you'll actually see a button from the Game Crafter
that says 12 plus.
So what are we talking, what is this all about?
Well, it has to do with the hazards to children and players
such that anything from a small sharp piece
to an untested ink in the card,
imagine you have a printer overseas or even here.
Well, if you don't test the inks
with an independent laboratory,
they could have lead in them, for example.
And if an overzealous player or child decides
to chew on a card, right, you're in trouble,
you get the picture.
So we started to look at
We dug into this working with Ryan Muskoff and working with Matthew Fassman,
started to dig into the Consumer Product Safety Commission regarding third-party testing,
and they're saying, well, you don't have to test if it's children 12 and under.
But actually, we further researched to look at our responsibility and liability potential,
and we talked to other game designers.
And our target audience is high school and up, including undergraduates.
We wanted games that were sophisticated enough to have undergraduates engaged in play, but
for it to be accessible to high school students.
The regulations are actually complex and ambiguous,
and in some ways, we decided to err on the side of caution
by including an age restriction in the marketing and merchandising of the game.
So we're not going to read all that, but we went through this with a fine-tooth comb.
And the Game Crafter actually says they don't do lab testing.
If you go do pricing for lab testing, it's maybe in the $3,000, $5,000 range,
maybe in the $1,000, depending on the lab or the kinds of tests that you're going to...
And the game crafter says, we don't do it, we don't make games for kids.
And then their definition is 12 and under.
And so I spent a lot of time talking to labs.
Now the actual standard actually makes reference to 14 years of age in addition to mandatory
testing for 12-year-olds.
And so we picked 14 as the age cutoff.
14 is, for us, the most relevant standard for our product.
And GameCrafter only offers badges for 12+, because of their reading of the regulation,
and 18+, for mature games, I guess.
But our boxed text and our actual boxes, they're marked for 14 and over.
So what I decided for myself, we also got product liability insurance, and we work with
Magic Spell Studios to do that, and I had one designer say, you must get product liability
insurance.
So we went ahead and got that, and I would say know the limits of the print-on-demand
up front and plan for them, and check the relevant regulations, and confer with other
people who've done it before, and just plan accordingly for this.
And there are hundreds and hundreds of games available on print-on-demand, and I think
many of them don't take this into account.
But because we dug into it for so long, I wanted to share that with you and kind of
the thoughts about how to take this, I think, you know, more safely to market.
This is called the curious case of the sand timer that grew.
We, in the party game, we have this,
you can dial down or dial up the time
for how long people are gonna have to tell their story with.
And so we said, man, it would be great
if we could put a timer in the box.
So we said, all right, well, the timer,
they have all these amazing pieces
that you can put into your games,
and it's about $2.30.
So we said, all right, let's do that.
And then the cascading decisions start to come.
As we know with coding, also the case with print on demand.
So we had a medium-sized box, and then we actually have to,
yeah, got to count the cards and figure out how many cards
can fit in the box, and could we fit the timer in the box?
And so we're sitting there, you know, stacking cards
and counting cards and figuring out the dimensions
and doing all this, and we eventually figure out
that if we get the timer, we're going to actually have
to go up and box size.
And if we go up and box size, you're going to have
to buy the bottom box and the top box
and a wrap for the images on it.
And the process kind of expands with that timer.
And so the timer increase to produce the game
went from $2.30 for the timer, an additional $3
in increase in box cost, and then we
were going to have to redesign all of our box layouts.
And so we decided people could use their watch.
Because for a game in the $30 to $35 range,
I'm not adding $6 to the purchase price for a timer.
So that's the case of the timer that grew.
So the cascading decisions that happen when you're trying
to make small changes, because they're going to have all
these physical effects as well.
So using print on demand in the design studio and in
research for the field allows us to do things that we
wouldn't normally be able to do.
and testing games with people with artwork
and being able to print some of the prose that we went over earlier.
Now, in the game design classroom, I use it for things like,
okay, you're a producer, what are your milestones?
What are your deliverables?
And how are you going to backwards plan to get there?
So you've got to budget your pieces and you have to know
are you going to put a timer in that box or not?
And my colleague, Ian Schreiber,
they usually get a price that they need to hit
and it's a pretty low price and then they can usually barter.
They can usually pitch to us as producers to say,
do they get a couple more bucks on their budget?
So they're budgeting as well.
So I find it particularly helpful when thinking about
what does it mean to get something into the hands of a player
and that process of backwards planning and producing.
So there are benefits to doing it that way.
So some takeaways, and I also want to open it up to questions.
Plan ahead, learn the details of the print-on-demand system.
Weigh that decision of are you going to go digital, analog, print-on-demand, mix?
Keep an eye on the differences in single proofing versus volume,
with the case of the greedy grabber regarding printer differences.
Realize that small shifts and changes will have ripples
in terms of formatting and cost.
And please, don't eat the game.
That would be my probably number one request.
Thank you very much.
That's the formal piece.
And so I'd love to entertain questions about print on demand because I could talk about
this for a very long time.
But I wanted to make an opportunity to converse with you.
If you can come to the center and speak to the mic, that's the best way to get your question.
And then I'll repeat the question.
So yeah, Kevin O'Gorman, I teach at the Art Institute of Dallas and Richland College, also in Dallas.
And just to back your play here, I've been doing this for a year, and just to commiserate with the Game Crafter.
Another cautionary tale, I had worked on a tabletop game for two years design-wise and
getting, buying myself the prototypes as we iterated along and had it down to the final
stretch and it was a tile-based game so I was using the literally you know like drink coaster
thick tiles and stuff.
Right when GameCrafter switched from the die cut method to the laser cut for the giant
slugs for those.
And so up until then, they would die cut and bag the tiles.
And right when I was ready to design the box and go for it, they switched to laser cut,
which meant they left them unpunched in the slugs.
And so my game no longer fit in the small box because I had sheets.
And so I actually did call them and begged and pleaded.
What's their phone number?
Well, I shot him an email and then ran into them at a board game conference and stuff.
So I, you know, harassed them.
And they said there was really nothing they could do about it.
And so I actually had to switch from the, like, coaster style tiles to card thickness,
square cards, to replace the tiles just to maintain my footprint in the box.
Yeah.
So that does happen.
So I was going to say, you know, there's the great benefit.
You know, I couldn't do this without GameCrafter,
and so I have tremendous, you know, love for their product
and their service and what they do.
And because of what they're doing, right,
we have to deal with some of these things.
And it's probably through our community
where we're sharing these things and trying to plan ahead
and trying to test things that we'll get there.
So...
I think using a service like this has benefits and drawbacks, but I'm much happier with the benefits than I am, you know, upset about the drawbacks.
But they're tough.
Yeah, and the whole idea of, I do the same thing, my students, their classwork has to be GameCrafter ready, like you were saying, but I don't require them.
But I've had two students, you know, publish their stuff on the GameCrafter, so it does work.
I'm getting a minute warning, I'm trying to see it in the back.
Yes, thank you very much.
I'm going to be around afterwards in the after area and I'm happy to talk to people out there.
Yes, hi.
Hi, I just got one question.
I'm working myself for a board game publisher in Poland and run game jams and this kind
of courses with the universities.
Is there a big problem for you to reach out for professional publisher help?
All these problems, it's my first lesson that I teach on my course for board game development process.
So this could, I could also help you in some kind. Is there a very big
big distance between publishing business and education?
In Europe, yeah, like in Europe, we don't have this. What's this difficulty in the US?
Well, we probably have millions of people trying to go to,
my guess is millions of people trying to go to individual publishers,
so kind of like trying to break into Hollywood studios.
And so I think my perception is until you have very high sales,
like for example, The Captain is Dead has thousands and thousands of sales
and they were then, they pitched to I think Eon Games.
But I think the difference between making a game
and showing that it's viable in the market
is probably part of what is the distance between a publisher
that'll say, well, take your game
versus the hundreds and hundreds of other people
who are trying to pitch their games.
That's my guess.
You're guessing, yeah?
Because, for example, the game that was launched on My Game Jam two years ago
now hit the market.
And meanwhile, we had games that, for example, Nemesis Campaign reached $4 million on Kickstarter.
So we can...
Those are proven financially. They've made $4 million.
Yes, but also we have space after launching that successful campaign to collaborate with
universities just to teach our future employees that we can start out while cooperating with
educational business.
It would be great to potentially collaborate.
This is mutually beneficial, so reach out for these professionals.
Not everyone is as open as me coming here.
You don't leave after this.
Give me your car.
We'll collaborate.
But I think this is what happens at GDC, is the chance
to collaborate and maybe break through what seems to be a
barrier that doesn't need to be.
So I look forward to talking to you.
Thank you for bringing that.
I've got, I think, three minutes left on the clock.
Other questions about any aspect of this?
I'd love to entertain a couple more questions.
Yes, I have a question. Jose Zagal, University of Utah. So in academia, we're also tied to
semesters or quarters and there's sort of timeliness factors. So I was wondering if you
could comment on how this print on demand and doing all these cycles, how you made that
work in the context of semesters or the academic year?
Yes, thank you.
So, and we're starting to, a couple people have started to talk about it, about not saying
you have to take this to market, but that you go through the process of budgeting and
then getting stuff ready to print.
And I do a couple things.
I did, there was a talk, my material was in a couple years ago here, about doing non-binding
agreements on teams.
around IP, so at RIT all the students own their IP.
So I have them do a non-binding agreement about how they would carry it forward past
the class.
I have them scope down so that they're going to actually produce the game in about four
to five weeks, very short, and get it ready to print.
And then I say, okay, and then continue your playtesting.
Maybe you take it to Protospiel, which my colleague Ian Schreiber turned us on to.
Continue playtesting, continue working, but do you know at a certain point you could hit
the button and put it to market.
So it's chunked that way.
And also I talk to them about scope,
about what type of game are you doing?
If you're doing a sprawling dungeon crawler
and it takes two and a half hours to play,
it could be harder to get playtests in in time.
So I try to get them to scope for that.
I'm sorry, it says one minute, I think.
So I try to get them to scope.
So I'd say scope, they don't have to print then,
they have to think about and plan for
what it would mean to print the next term
to give them the path to access that.
And the hope is that.
Some of them are going to go forward and it'll become their portfolio piece, or they might
then pitch a publisher with it.
I usually have them list what are the three publishers you want to reach out to with this
game and go pitch to that publisher now that you've got a prototype, that kind of thing.
Cool.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Do we have time for one more or are we done?
I think he said one more.
Okay, great.
And so my question was, I saw you mentioned doing like playtesting with the print on demand.
What's sort of the cutoff point when you go from hand-making your playtesting materials
and when do you go to printing them?
That's a tough question.
I would say we probably did from printing from spreadsheet to cards and PowerPoint.
In the Lost and Found games, maybe 60, 70 of those before,
we were parallel working with the artist team
at the same time and then said, all right,
now let's, we feel like we've gotten the showstoppers gone,
now let's try.
So it was kind of feeling for the play
and that the play tests were at the point
where players were responding in the realm we wanted them to
and we wanted to get the artwork together.
We were also forced because we were on a budget.
So our budget was gonna say, look,
you have that much time to get it done.
So the budget pushed us.
Ian always says, you know, the game is never done, it's done when you stop.
So a combination of the financial pressure of a budget and time like a semester
and how the playtests are going was how we made that decision.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Alright, thank you very much everybody.
I'll be outside and happy to talk more about this with you.