Hi and welcome to the Art of Thunderbolts The Dragon's Trap.
Thanks for coming. My name is Ben Fiquet.
I'm the art director of the game and co-founder of Lizard Cube,
a studio we started in 2015 with Omar, the developer behind this project.
I was also the only artist on the game,
so it's easy to talk about the artistic process behind it.
As you may know, this is originally a game from 1989, created by Westone and directed by Ryūichi Nishizawa.
Omar and I were Sega kids and we loved that game.
So 25 years later, we decided to remaster that lost game
in HD, both thing and drone, art and animation,
a rearranged soundtrack made with live musician.
And on top of that, you can swap from the original game
at any time at the press of a button.
For those who might not know what it's about,
here's a video.
To be continued...
If you have more than one ninja at home, you'll become stronger,
Don't rush!
Yeah!!
So there has been many Wonder Boy games,
starting from a young caveman on a skateboard
to slowly shifting towards a fantasy action
adventure platformer.
This was a big license at the time,
giving birth to numerous games on various platforms.
But what mattered to us was Wonder Boy 3,
the Dragon's Trap, also known as Monster World 2 in Japan,
Dragon's Curse for the PC Engine,
and Turma da Monica in Brazil.
It's considered one of the best games of the platform and also a personal favorite for us.
So when Omar said to me he wanted to try to do a remake of the game,
I almost immediately started to draw.
But how do you start? How do you transform nostalgia into something artistically relevant?
Let's start by talking about inspiration.
Quick note about me, I'm a French artist who's been working video games and... sorry.
and animation, comics, for about 12 years,
and I've been training fine arts
and to do the animation at Goblin School.
I'm not specifically a game artist, to be honest.
I don't have the knowledge
of many talented individuals here in GDC,
but I really wanted to reimagine that great game
at the best of my abilities.
Even if I had to do a lot of interpretation,
I really tried to nail the original inspirations
that were projected into the game at the time.
So for a start, Akihito Yama,
I think he's a major inspiration in 80s Japan.
Not only is he definitely one of my favorite artists,
but I think the developers were really influenced
by his style at the time.
And on top of Dragon Ball,
his work on the fantasy genre is absolutely wonderful.
European comics, which is a style people outside of Europe might not be used to,
but this is a big part of every French kid's culture.
It obviously is a huge influence in my work.
The beauty of Hiroshi Yoshida, which I find particularly beautiful.
And many others. I'm trying to show a wide range of things I like.
All of them have in common to leave a big place for line art and subtle colors.
And this is why I believe in a style that has never been properly explored in video games.
And at that point, even before starting,
I knew I wanted to make a beautiful hand-drawn game.
And crafted 2D in video games is beautiful.
And in my opinion, it can give so much life
to characters and environments.
But the amazing thing with 2D is that basically the only
constraint is your imagination.
You get what you see is what you get.
And mainly the thing is we started
with a grand total of two people, Omar, who's
been doing the programming, and I.
and we couldn't afford other team members.
So we had to rely on our own strength.
And I'm not a 3D or cut-out animation guy,
but I can easily draw and animate in traditional animation.
Artistic development. This is something I really like to do,
looking to find the right art style for a particular project.
In this day and age where there is less and less constraints
in terms of visuals, it should definitely not be overstated that you
need a proper amount of artistic development.
I'm not saying the visuals are everything in the game, but good art
will help you
not to have your game overlooked and ultimately bring more sales.
And first I'd like to praise the beauty of the original game.
It might not look like much for many of you, but there are really beautiful choices.
that were made with all the constraints of the master system, palette limitation.
The sky, for example, is rarely blue,
and this indicates a deliberate taste and work of color theory.
The style is simple, but everything is rich and vibrant.
So, when I started, I really didn't know what shape the project would take,
so the obvious thing to do was to make mock-ups for visualizing what I had in mind.
At first, I tried to be very loose,
experimenting far from the actual image and design of the original game.
I tried flat colors, uneven ground, background actions,
but as the project took shape, I tried to get closer and closer to the original.
Eventually adding effects, water, color style, but limited to the original shapes.
This was the first image we were really happy with.
An image that will drive the art in the right direction.
I also like to test out in video form and ended up making a test in After Effects
just to see if Parallax would work.
Here's another mockup I did following that art direction.
You can see a very early version of the UI.
It's also very important and took many iterations
to get right, but we won't have time during this presentation.
At that point I started to implement characters into the background.
One important thing I tried to do was having a sense of unity between characters and background.
This is why the lines are equally thick in the background and in the characters.
You want to feel that you created a scenery, not just gameplay assets layered on top of each other.
Here is an evolution of the introduction of the game,
which I started by doing a color test.
And then I did details.
In this image, I wanted to show all the locations you
might encounter in the game.
But it could prove quite distracting.
So here's the final image.
And with the final image, I also tested out animation,
because I wanted to have that in the game.
But it was.
a bit too much work to have proper animation for cutscenes, so we decided to scrap it out.
Characters! It was time to really focus on characters, and the characters were
kind of tough, really, because...
it has been very difficult to pinpoint exactly what they look like.
As we've seen, the games are all very different in terms of design,
and even in the same game, things might not be rock solid.
These are the official artworks, for example,
but these are the sprites you see in game that's
not even the same colors for the hero of the air.
What would be considered the right choice?
And we met with original creator Nishizawa-san.
And I asked him if they had any concept art
on the characters on paper.
He told me that at the time,
they didn't really do those kind of things,
mainly because they didn't have the time.
They drew every pixel art straight away into the game.
And so the mindset I was in for this project
was to sublime my childhood,
to make it look as I saw when I was a kid.
So I decided that the Master System sprites
were the right.
starting point.
Like with the Mocatta, I started really loose. At the time, we didn't know if we could
acquire the official license, and I started to scribble different kind of characters.
That's when Wonder Girl emerged. She eventually found her way into the game, as we thought
it would be a nice addition to the game.
The Nurse and the Shop Owner.
Sorry, what?
Slowly, the first characters we were really happy with started to appear.
Some were easier to apprehend, and some took many iterations.
And on a side note...
I'd like to say that a good concept art doesn't necessarily require tons of drawings.
You often see art directors priding themselves in having millions of drawings before deciding
on a specific one.
But I'd like to say this is not mandatory.
If something good comes at you right away, be smart and seize it.
If you're absolutely convinced it's good, I don't know, go for it.
It can save frustration, time, and eventually money.
I also had to respect the boundaries of the original sprite for collision,
but as you can see, this is when I started to take some liberties.
One of the good things with doing a remake is that you already have the full scope of assets you need.
In this case, which kind and how many enemies I had to draw.
You can say the same about all the locations and even the length of the animations.
I only have two advice for character design. The shapes with...
The variety of the shapes gives a rhythm to your drawings.
You might want to have a big head and small feet,
so a large body and big hands.
This is important for adding character,
and having a good silhouette is also very important.
And contrast.
On top of the rhythm you give with the shapes,
it can also be a huge boost if you vary colors
and contrast inside a character.
So animation, this is something I really like.
Actually very important for me as part of video games.
A good art direction in my mind should have in mind
how the characters will move.
It can convey more emotions or impact
if you place some attention on it.
And this is my personal references.
I grew up in the 90s, and there was
a wave of beautifully animated games
initiated by Daft Perry using the technique they call Digicel.
These were the games I loved, and it feels to me
they were so alive.
Like this one, I mean, it's beautiful.
So, the pros and cons of traditional animation, it obviously is beautiful, it's easy to start,
I think, that's what I think, you just have to draw a succession of drawings instead of
a huge setup of rig, texturing, etc.
But you won't have a lot of room for iteration, since you would have to redraw your frames
every time you make a change.
and you need a capable team of artists.
And sometimes it can be tricky to have.
You can change the character's appearance during the game
because you would, again, have to redraw all the frames.
And the texture management can be tricky.
So these are the first test I did for the animations.
is crucial to plan things in advance,
especially with solution and mission.
And before really starting to make the game,
I started experimenting with different design and software.
The first vision was mainly to try animating in Flash,
which doesn't quite work for me.
I've been struggling with Flash my whole life.
And the second one was here to refine the technique.
and also to pass on to Omar to try to implement it in the prototype.
I wasn't quite happy with the design, and the animation felt a bit dull,
so finally the third version, more bouncy, better design, the technique is almost there.
Another set of animation tests, you can see for example that the lion's sword
was not easily readable at first glance.
I decided then to convey its use for gameplay, which
is one heavy weapon able to crush above and below him.
So heavy, in fact, that he has to drag it behind him.
And the thing is, I love we kept it.
But sometimes, as far as collisions are involved,
you can see the sword overlapping the background
with no real sense at all.
This animation is Wonder Boy at the beginning of the game.
This is what I wanted to do.
Because at the beginning of the game,
you're supposed to be at the end of the second game, Wonder Boy 2.
And you're all powerful.
You have the legendary gear.
And I wanted him to move a bit cocky and show off himself.
Eventually, we scrapped that because, again, too much work.
And at some point I wanted to try to have town portals,
but instead of a magic door, I thought
it would be funnier to have that dragon mouse
holding you and beating you back in town.
Now everything this animation are doing is just improving the look and feel of your movement.
We didn't change the physics behind it because you can still play the original game,
but even then just adding scratch and stretch, anticipation or pacing can give a whole different appreciation for controlling your character on screen.
And in my opinion, even if the control stays a bit stiff, you now have a better sense of your character and the enemies.
So here's a process video. As you can see, I started by taking references from the original animation frames.
Thanks to the community for that, because I grabbed it from the internet.
And first, the rough animation. You can see the sword swing is a bit different than in-game.
I'll explain later why.
And then after that you have the cleanup part, where you have to retrace everything you did.
And finally, color.
And on top of the colors, I like to add a dark gradient,
which helps anchoring the character to the ground.
Here's an example of constraint I had to deal with.
You can see the sword swing of the original,
which was quite linear.
I wanted to add more of an impact,
and it's implied to have a longer pause at the beginning
and a swift slash of the sword,
but we decided to follow the collision of the original game.
You can see the collision here in green.
And it was animated at 30 FPS.
That's why you can see the sword is a little bit late
at the beginning compared to the collision,
but catches up afterward.
It's not really perceptible, but it eventually drives the work in certain ways.
Here's the way I cheated with 2D animation. I added a turn animation,
particularly for smoothing the transition when switching direction.
But how to have a right-handed character suddenly become left-handed?
The original game did an amazing thing by having another sprite when you turned,
so your character would always have his word in his right hand,
but they add a total of 7 frames of animation per character.
and I have 10 times more, so
even if I really wanted to have that feature,
it was simply an absurd amount of work.
So here's a trick.
I drew the animation as to the shield and the sword
flow a smooth curve and end up in the same place
when facing the opposite direction.
And with the magic of animation,
you don't see nothing in real time.
Backgrounds, another challenge because due to the technical limitation of the master system,
the original game could feel quite empty in some areas, so I had a lot of interpretation to do.
Here's the mummy room, for example. There's basically nothing because technically,
the master system was considering the boss as the background, so they couldn't have anything else.
And here's what I've done with the place,
overlooking the changing graphics.
In these kind of areas, I added visual storytelling
by placing various elements in the background.
Here's another example.
The forest outside the village was just trees
next to each other, repeating for two levels.
And I experimented very different things
before having something interesting.
And the main thing that was missing
was the gameplay readability,
because...
In this level, you have a little cloud throwing you fireballs and it was not really obvious.
So I stripped down the most I could and gave space for the cloud, but doing so, that same
background was becoming quite empty.
So I added that statue.
It doesn't particularly make sense.
Some players have been asking what it represents.
Even if I know it's mainly for filling a void,
it is also a world-building item.
It might be the statue of a lost hero,
a place where heroes die, who knows?
It gives you something to look at and wonder,
instead of, you know, void.
And here's the game.
You can see I added a lot of parallax to give perspective.
It's always eye candy.
And on the statue, please note that we added a slight 3D
deformation.
It's not really obvious.
And we used it for pillars and big sprites.
But it feels more natural that way.
Eventually, I tried to spark interest in every screen,
adding details and a bit of narrative.
And here you're going to see three different levels of the desert area.
In each of them I try to have something changing.
You start at the base of the pyramids and then pass in front of the old temple.
And finally end up in sort of an oasis, always mainly the same assets but
rearranged to feel you change scenery.
And here you go.
When you have every asset separated,
you start to implement it.
Omar managed to create a splendid engine where I could
put everything I needed, all of it running in real time
on top of the original game, allowing
me to know exactly where to put my new assets
and eventually making something pretty.
And if you feel like a tinkerer, you
can access that tool in the Steam version of the game.
Just have to edit.
You can find the explanation on the website.
And here we are.
I feel incredibly grateful being here,
presenting what started as kind of a fun project.
Not only we got to work on the Dear Childhood Memory,
but we managed to do it the way we wanted it.
And it resonated with players.
I'd like to thank, obviously, Ryuichi Nishizawa and his team
for making that wonderful game.
Not only is he a really nice guy,
but he has been only but supportive of our work
from the beginning.
And of course, all the projects behind it,
Omar, whose love and passion were
the true engine of the project, and the team at LaserCube,
and our publisher, Dotemu, who first believed in us.
Side note, I'd like to show you a bonus
that I've been playing with.
Some of you might remember the game,
which is called Kid Chameleon.
And this is what I've done with it.
It could be awesome, but it's not a real project,
because really, I don't have the time for it at the moment.
But anyway, it could be cool.
Thank you very much.
We might have time for a few questions.
I'm a huge fan of the game. I played through it all.
It's fantastic.
I fell in love with it when I saw the original...
like, the initial promotional art.
I'm curious, what's next for...
What's next for Lizard Cube and what's next for Wonder Boy?
Are you guys going to do a new version of anything or...
Actually, I can't talk about it.
It's not Kit Kamien, obviously,
but it's a big project and I'm very happy to be part of it.
But it's going to be traditional animation. No worries.
Awesome. Thanks.
Hi, thank you for the presentation.
Amazing art all the way.
So my question is for the large object that you were
describing on the background that had a 3D effect, was that
a normal map thingy, or is that like 3D model?
No, it's actually just a simple cylinder
that Omar added the option.
When I wanted a sprite to behave like a 3D object,
it's just behaving like a cylinder based on the camera.
So there's no normal map, no modeling.
If you look closely, it's not very...
very well made.
But it does a trick.
And if you look at the pillars, it works better
because it's very cylinder.
OK, awesome.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Here we go, another question.
Thank you very much.