Hello, everyone.
Thanks everyone for attending.
My name is Piers Harding-Rolls and I work as a games industry analyst at Ampere Analysis.
So the topic for today's talk is the games content subscription market, and I'll be examining
the market opportunity.
competitive catalog landscape and delving into some of the characteristics of the subscription
gamer.
So I think first off I think it's worthwhile just setting the scene of where I think we
are as a kind of industry in terms of its development and the kind of disruptive wave
that we're going through at the moment. It's a kind of long development cycle I would say.
We started off with various stages through which have been developed through the connectivity of
different device categories and they've allowed different business models to emerge. And we're
now in this I think final stage, the sort of culmination of all this development heading
towards what I would describe as a kind of on-demand consumption model.
And I guess the definition of that is giving players access
to content across all device categories
when and where they want it.
And the idea is to deliver content or games
to the broadest audience in the most efficient way.
And if we think about that kind of consumption,
we're thinking about a form of consumption
which fits well within the subscription monetization
model.
And I think that's driven the idea, this sort of catchphrase of the Netflix of games.
So it's been bandied around for quite a few years now.
And I think when people use it, it sort of immediately conjures up comparisons
with other entertainment sectors.
At its most basic, it suggests access to a catalogue of content, of course.
And that's, you know, fairly straightforward in the context of some of the games
description services.
obviously Xbox Game Pass, PlayStation Now.
But it also indicates the kind of shift
that we've seen in other entertainment sectors.
So the way we've seen the video and the music sectors
develop a much more significant shift towards subscription
as the main monetization model for the industry.
And I think that, in turn, stokes a bit of fear
in the games studios and the developers
that.
you know, potentially under that sort of model,
they will be progressively more squeezed,
and the rules of monetization and engagement
start to shift from what we are used to now.
But actually, I think it's a pretty misleading analogy.
There are some similarities between the games sector
and these other entertainment sectors,
but the games sector is fundamentally different
in many ways.
As many of you sure know, most of the spending on games
is on in-game monetization,
primarily in free-to-play titles.
So 79% of the total market opportunity in 2021
in terms of consumer spending
was based on in-game monetization.
That means I think it's very unlikely that we're going to see a wholesale shift to subscription
monetization.
Also in the context of subscription services, there is this ability to have hybrid monetization,
so in-game monetization combined with subscriptions, which means that the commercial framework
for these services is very different from the framework for other entertainment subscription
services.
And it's not just a case of replacing, say, the premium sales with subscription sales.
You know, you have this ability to monetize those subscription users in other ways as well.
And that means a potentially higher ARPU in terms of, you know, higher ARPU ceiling in
terms of the overall opportunity potentially compared to these other sectors.
The other difference is that there's not much exclusive content
which is available just for subscription services.
I mean, there's a few examples, I think, in Apple Arcade,
but generally you can't, if you want to get access to a game
that was in a subscription service,
you can do that through other forms of monetization.
So all the games in Game Pass, for example,
you can buy premium games outside of that.
And that means the commercial framework is different
game subscription services also means that drivers for content inclusion within the services
vary within the game space compared to the entertainment sector. And I think that is
reflected in the sort of deals that can be done. So the actual acquisition of content
into those services from both the service provider side and from the devs, there is
a good deal of flexibility in the types of deals that can be done, I think.
So if we look at the key drivers for adding games
to subscription services,
obviously we have the direct revenue.
And I think there's, you know,
a lot could be said about the different deals
that can be done with different platforms and services.
There's a lot of variation there.
It depends on, you know,
what the service provider is trying to get out of it.
and the extent of the willingness to provide exclusivity from the content owner, for example,
and other factors such as, you know, whether it's a new launch or a new release. Obviously those,
I guess, more comprehensive deals offer a bigger revenue opportunity.
But for many game devs, I think that's a really tough decision to make.
So, you know, the decision of putting your game, day and date,
into a subscription service for an exclusive period of time,
it's tough to make a decision around that.
Is that a good commercially, for me, at this point in time?
And I think as a result, many of the deals that are done
are really for older titles, catalog titles.
They tend to be the deals that have been done.
The other drivers for adding content
to these subscription services include,
you know, reestablishing a franchise.
If you're bringing a new game in a particular franchise out.
and putting an older title into a subscription service to raise the profile.
There's the ability to reach a wider, a broader audience
and potentially getting exposure to highly engaged gamers.
So some of the stats that Microsoft has come out again with today,
you know, talking about.
gamers, subscription gamers, Xbox game pass gamers
who are much more willing to spend on content, et cetera.
There's also this ability to boost visibility
and do co-marketing with the service providers, essentially.
And there's also a network effect to consider.
If you bring in a significant amount of users,
the network effects potentially on other platforms
where your content is available
and the opportunity in terms of additional premium sales
might be boosted because of that.
So I talked a little bit about why you would put your content
into these services and how games is different
from other entertainment subscription services.
I also think it's worth just looking at the opportunities.
So we've got it in perspective to understand, you know,
how impactful it could be on the market.
So this is the North America and European.
gains market total with the chunk that is relevant
to games content subscription services.
It's only 4% of the market currently.
So I don't think we should, I guess,
overblow the idea of the Netflix of games
in the context of the entire game sector.
And if we look at the forecast.
It's growing and it's going to continue to expand.
But I also don't see that there's going
to be this very dramatic shift
across to subscription monetization.
Because of those points I made earlier talking about the,
you know, the strength of in-game monetization,
for example, which takes a massive majority of the share
of spending across the sector.
So this is.
our estimates for market share for the leading services.
Again, this is across Western spend,
across games content subscription services for Q4 2021.
And it's clear that Xbox Game Pass is in a dominant position.
And Microsoft has, you know,
been very active in terms of its acquisitions, and that is driving a kind of
concerned that its pipeline will be substantially boosted,
its first party pipeline, and what
are the implications for third party companies
that are putting their content into that particular service?
And this kind of dominant position
obviously exacerbates that situation.
I think there will be some implications, potentially.
So the more first party content, the bigger.
franchises that it brings into the service, obviously I think squeezes those smaller titles
potentially, and if there's this significant shift towards games as a service titles, then again
I think there's a potential for it to undermine the engagement available for smaller titles in
those services. I think we have to take it into context though, this is
an impact which could be contained around the console opportunity, so the Xbox console
opportunity, and potentially have a knock-on impact on PlayStation to some degree.
At the moment, I think it's less relevant to the PC space and obviously the mobile space.
In terms of the wider opportunity, I don't think this is a significant amount of concern.
So the success of Xbox Game Pass has been driven primarily
by the inclusion of newer releases compared
to other services.
Obviously, the sort of watershed moment was the introduction
of their own.
first party releases directly into the service, but there is a very strong correlation between
the performance of Xbox Game Pass in terms of the number of subscribers it's picked up
in the second half of last year and the number of day one titles that have come into that
service, a sort of mixture of, so in blue here that's third party titles and orange
is first party titles.
And it's very hard to see other services competing
on this level of willingness to financially back the service
to bring in certainly first party titles.
So Sony's upcoming kind of reformat
of its subscription services,
I don't see them changing their policy
for first party content,
but potentially they may start to boost it
in the context of third party new releases.
But this is why Xbox Game Pass has been particularly successful.
So this is just to reinforce that idea.
This is PlayStation Now Age of Catalog
and Xbox Game Pass Age of Catalog compared.
And you can see that Xbox Game Pass is...
much younger in terms of its catalog, it's got a lot more fresher content and newer content
compared to PlayStation Now. Obviously the positioning is vastly different. The success
of both of those platforms I think reflects the quality and the age of content that's in those
different services.
And if we're thinking about how the Game Pass catalog is going to evolve,
I've talked about that kind of watershed moment
where first party games were placed into that service.
And then progressively we've seen third party content,
which is high profile, basically catalog content,
which older titles, but high profile titles.
And we're in this stage now where.
third party games, day one release, are going into the service and the next stage is seeing
bigger franchises of those new releases going directly into the service. So that should
be, you know, we've already seen some interesting additions this year. I think it's just inevitable
that we will see some big franchises going in.
And I think the end game is this idea of cloud native games,
and that's when we get some sort of exclusivity, I think,
for the Game Pass proposition, obviously distributed
through xCloud within Game Pass Ultimate.
And I think that's the end game.
It might not come this year, might not come next year,
but it's certainly something that's
with the announcements today, for example,
with the idea of Azure and other factors.
This is definitely the kind of roadmap
which they're developing towards.
So we talked about the sort of main players in the market
and the usual suspects, but are there opportunities
for content owners outside of those?
So at the moment, there's a lot of activity
of cloud gaming service providers in the telco space.
who are served by white label aggregators and cloud gaming
technology companies.
And there's an opportunity there, I think,
to license content into those services.
Although it's not going to be a huge opportunity.
It's a sort of incremental opportunity.
And I think there's a window of opportunity
to do these kind of deals now, because the interest is really
high.
There's a lot of services that come to market.
There's a lot of competition between services.
and they are wanting content, they're competing for content.
So there is an opportunity there. And then obviously we have other new entrants coming
into the market. Netflix is the obvious big name which has announced its move into the market.
it's now securing content. I think it wants to secure, you know, a good batch of third-party
content so it can build up the portfolio. Whether it can do that under the current terms that it's
offering I think is perhaps questionable. I think it may need to revisit those terms to become more
competitive with the existing players. So it's something to consider for them. But this, you
know, Netflix's move might prompt other SVOD players to move into the market as well.
So there are opportunities to pursue,
but I think it's also worth looking at how competitive
the kind of catalog situation is
across the subscription services.
First up, you know, this is just a basic number.
This is the amount of distinct titles,
I think from December 2021,
number of distinct titles across all the services that we track.
And actually, it's not most services are.
Pretty small, you know, there's less than 300 titles,
many are less than 200 titles.
PlayStation now has a lot of legacy classic games in there
that bulks out the catalog, but they are a kind of exception
at 900 titles.
And Xbox Game Pass Ultimate is around 500.
Xbox Game Pass PC is less.
Xbox Game Pass console is, again, less.
But I think...
you have to sort of realize that actually there's not that much
uh... content in these services at the moment there's not a huge amount
and
I think you know competition to get your games into those services depending on
what they
the service providers want in terms of the level of,
you know, maximum catalog that they hope to have.
I think that's something that, you know,
obviously impacts the ability for you
to get your content into those services.
And if we think about, you know,
if they are expanding that much,
this is the Xbox Game Pass ultimate volume
of distinct titles, if we sort of define it,
across the whole year.
And.
Aside from the sort of uplift from EA Play PC being bundled into the service, it's not
actually that much different from March's 500 titles, December 2021 is 515, a very small
percentage, you know, a few percent increase in total volume.
Possibly because they're thinking, well, do we, can we actually, is it commercially viable
to have more?
Is it going to become a discovery issue?
All these kind of factors that come into that decision making.
There is some rotation in and out of those services, obviously.
So overall, there were 686 distinct titles in Game Pass in 2021.
But still not a massive number.
And a lot of those are kind of, you know, legacy titles
or titles that won't come out of the service.
There's, you know, the slots are taken, in effect.
If we look at the activity of publishers,
this is another way we slice the catalogue data,
is to look at the company activity.
You can see that there is around 700 companies
across these services active.
Many of them with one or two titles,
but there are a few which have built a more progressive amount of titles
that are going into the services.
And...
It does suggest that there's already a certain level
of quite significant competition to get access to those catalogs
in terms of the activity of different companies.
But also, you know, it shows that there's a willingness
to experiment and, you know, identify if there's a,
you know, opportunity there, a worthwhile,
incremental opportunity that's worthwhile.
This is a slide which looks at the Xbox Game Pass.
distinct games by actual publisher from December 2021.
You can see the Microsoft and EA titles,
obviously, take the most volume,
big chunk of the share of those titles.
But there is a, you know,
a wide range of different publishers that are active
and some, in effect, direct publishers,
you know, devs that are directly publishing into...
this particular service, and I've highlighted the ones
which I think are relevant to the kind of indie space.
And it shows that there is a kind of small
but relatively important role for the indie titles
across those different indie publishers.
This is obviously not all the publishers
that are active in that particular service,
but they are the biggest, you know, in terms of ones
that have got multiple titles in that service.
You know, the thing we have to consider is if Microsoft does
add a lot of first party content, which it inevitably will
do with the acquisitions that it's done, and it's looking
to acquire more higher profile sort of franchises
from third parties that go into these services,
whether those smaller titles, less distinct titles
or less well-known titles are increasingly squeezed in terms
of the kind of discovery loop.
And this slide just takes a little look at the,
you know, one of the strategies in terms of publishing
for Devolver Digital, looking at which services
they're putting their games into.
I think what this shows is there's been a kind of
diversification of its strategy in the context of,
it's taken some of its products out of Xbox Game Pass
or it doesn't, it's reduced its exposure
to Xbox Game Pass and its willingness to...
diversify across other subscription services.
So it's showing a fair amount of sophistication, I would say,
and that's what we're observing in terms of the strategies
of different companies in this space
that they are slowly growing,
kind of more sophisticated strategies.
Another thing that's worth looking at is the kind
of complexity of the market environment.
So of the services that we track...
Some of those are what we describe as local telco-based services,
but they all have catalogues which are relevant
and can be tracked in the context of seeing
if they are overlaps with, say, the international players.
This visualisation is a tree map from our data tool,
which looks at the different catalogues of services within Italy.
So it's looking at some of the local services versus the global services and looking at
the overlaps between different services.
And it shows already a good deal of complexity, sort of understanding where your, if you're
a service company, you know, where your exclusives lie and how much content is really unique
in terms of your service.
Also, this kind of information I think gives content owners
the ability to negotiate better deals to kind of take advantage
of that complexity to understand the landscape
and see where the gaps exist within particular portfolios
and where you can have the maximum impact
in terms of your particular products
if you're looking to put those into subscription services.
So, I'm going to finish up. We talked a bit there about catalog.
I'm going to finish up with some slides.
around consumer research basically that we do to look at some of the characteristics of subscription
gamers. And generally you know they are much more active than your average gamer so
here it shows they spend 23 percent more time on a weekly basis playing games.
substantially more engaged.
If we look at the average number of subscriptions per gamer,
I think it's interesting, obviously US is the heaviest
there, the other markets that we do our survey work in,
you can see that there's a kind of downward trend.
I guess there's some thinking there in terms of your,
if you're thinking of your content strategy, will, you know,
if you're looking to engage an audience
in specific territories, then.
You know, whether you're putting your gains into subscription services or not,
you know, there's a decision to make there if you feel that it's under sort
of represented in certain markets, for example.
It also illustrates that there is significant growth potential, I think,
for subscription services in these other markets where in the US it's, I wouldn't say it's mature,
but it's obviously more advanced, but it gives you an idea of the kind of ceiling
that could be achieved in some other Western territories, for example.
We also ask consumers how they discover games.
And there's some significant differences
between what game content subscribers do
to find their games versus your average gamer.
So subscribers look to social media, online video sites,
and games.
Platform online stores as their kind of sources for discovering content. It's quite interesting that games platform online stores
So high for a subscription service
It kind of reiterates the idea that actually they're much more engaged and they're willing to spend across all kind of different content areas
For the average game a word-of-mouth is actually much is at the top
So there's a significant difference in the way they discover that you know might be very
interesting to you in terms of reaching different audiences
and that would be relevant across those kind
of discovery channels, I guess.
This is looking at Game Pass subscribers, and it's looking
at just some of the basic demographics.
So this is the age range, and you can see
that the age of Game Pass.
So this is a comparison of Game Pass.
Xbox players with Game Pass subscribers versus Xbox console gamers with no Game Pass.
And you can see that it skews a bit older in terms of the subscribers.
And I think that's because, and also they have, you know, more likely to be living with children
at home. It's more sort of family oriented. In terms of the...
Devices that they play on vary devices, so multiple devices and quite high penetration
of obviously console as you'd expect but also smartphone for example, which
goes with the idea that Game Pass is progressively multi-screen in terms of its strategy. You can
see how that fits into the types of consumer that are using Game Pass.
And this looks at the spend across different categories
of, again, Game Pass subscribers versus Xbox console gamers
without Game Pass.
And you can see that across all categories,
they tend to spend more.
This is not as, I guess, dramatic spend uptick
as some of the data that Microsoft has released itself.
It released some more data today, actually,
looking at the spend.
But it does kind of correlate and I guess,
you know, from an independent source,
this reiterates the idea that they are willing to be,
they are more engaged and they're also spending
more content, more on content across different forms
of monetization.
So getting access to that audience
is actually quite beneficial in that context.
And this slide looks at the genre taste
of the game genre taste of Game Pass.
subscribers versus a game, Xbox console gamers without Game Pass.
And I guess some of the key differences is that there seems to be a willingness
to have a more sort of varied genre taste versus, you know, the average Xbox console user who is
looking at, you know, is heavily into shooters, etc. There's less...
interest in that. There's more interest in more casual games and a sort of broader
appeal I think of different games. And I think that reflects the family type experience,
the family environment that Game Pass subscribers are playing games in.
So just to wrap up.
This is a few sort of takeaways of the session.
I don't believe that subscriptions will become the dominant monetization model for the game sector,
as it has done progressively within the video and music sectors.
The fact that in-game monetization is worth such a significant chunk of overall spending
means I think it's very unlikely that that's going to shift,
it's going to be so significant for that to happen.
There are multiple reasons to add games to subscription services.
We touched on quite a few of them.
It's not just about direct revenue,
but there's opportunities for marketing your product into services,
using it as a marketing platform, engaging a broader audience,
a more varied audience, an engaged audience
that might be interested in a broader collection of content.
The Game Pass domination of the market at the moment,
I think it does potentially have some implications,
but we've got to think about where those implications are
going to play out.
And I think that, you know, if we're
thinking of the broader market, if you're just
focused on Xbox as a platform, for example, console-based,
then I think you would think about it more seriously.
But the implications are more focused
where Game Pass is dominant.
There are additional sales opportunities to take advantage of,
which I think there's a window of opportunity to take advantage
of those sales or those commercial deals that are taking place
within the gaming space with telcos and local providers.
But that is.
window of opportunity, I'm not sure how long it's going to be open for.
There's a lot of interest at the moment because of the rollout of 5G and full fiber solutions.
So it's something to consider, I think, short term.
We investigated the idea of indie content and the role it plays within the different services
and the importance of it.
The question is whether in certain services, as they become more high profile,
the scale of those services grows, and we get to a point where, you know, bigger franchises
are considering going into those services and there's first party content, whether,
you know, those smaller games get increasingly squeezed and the terms of acquiring those
or putting those games into those services starts to deteriorate in some way.
And we investigate the subscribers.
to these content subscription services
and how they are different to the average gamer.
In fact, they're more engaged, they play more,
they spend more, and they have more varied gaming tastes
means they are an interesting and certainly worthwhile
group of consumers to get access to.
Thank you very much.
So I'm happy to answer a couple of questions if anyone's got.
Hello Simon.
Hello.
Yeah, I had a question about the, say, the indie publishers, and I know that Devolver
put in some of its risks when it went public on AIM, that they were concerned that the
upside from, you know, single player indie games that don't have IAP might be diminished
over time with Game Pass.
Can you talk to whether you think that will be an issue?
I think that's one of the, you know, one of the question marks.
I don't think anyone really knows, but I think...
that it's more less about probably kind of service-based games and more about the kind
of franchise-based, you know, higher profile titles and that's taking a lot of the, you know,
engagement and eyeballs. The first party releases thing, I think that's one of the more pressing
immediate impacts that could be felt. And whether that's...
you know, it has an impact because of the awareness of certain titles and their coming
into the service, then that takes a lot of engagement. I think if you combine that with
service-based games, then you're getting a bit of a sort of perfect storm in terms of
taking a lot of the engagement away. So I think there is some concern over that, but
then we've got to think, well...
Now, where is this taking place?
In the broader market, there's a much bigger,
broader market out there, but this is relatively contained
to this particular area of the market
within progressively the Xbox platform.
But, you know, in terms of it could impact, you know,
the thinking around Sony's upcoming changes
to its subscription services and things.
So it could kind of bleed over
into other competitive console platforms.
I don't think it's going to have such an impact in the PC space, although Microsoft is committed
to doing more PC games for Game Pass.
So it's a little bit of an unknown, but I would say that there is some concern, but
we have to put it into perspective in the context of the market.
Hey there.
Hello.
To what extent have you seen that the subscription service is actually driving the behavior of
being more engaged and spending more versus the people who are more likely to spend and
be engaged are also those who would sign up for a subscription service?
It's a bit of a chicken and egg question, isn't it?
I think there is probably a bit of both.
So the most engaged people are happy to try out,
be the first early adopters or whatever.
But we're now at a phase, if you're looking at Game Pass,
they've got 25 million subscriptions.
There's no doubt that those people that
may have signed up to that, even in a family setting,
they're willing to try more content
and try varied content and try games that they
wouldn't have tried before.
So.
It's probably a little bit of a mixture of both, but I would say that it's legitimate on both of those kind of characteristics.
Got you. Thank you.
No problem.
As a game developer, what's the right way
to weigh the financial opportunity
of doing an exclusive with a game subscription service
as opposed to traditional publishing?
That's a good question.
I think that's a very hard decision to make
because obviously it depends on what you feel
you can do as a company for your particular product
and the terms that you're being offered.
And I think the terms are, realistically,
they're probably gonna become for,
well, certainly smaller developers,
they're gonna come under pressure.
I mean, there's.
within specific services, I think.
And it's down to what the service provider's
trying to achieve as well.
My assumption is that the financial incentives will
be less, but the exposure greater.
Is that the right way to view it?
Sorry, can you repeat that?
That the exposure is going to be wider,
but the financial return is probably
going to be lower for that specific game?
Well, I think if you take.
You know, Xbox Game Pass, an example, they have their own, you know, their own content,
a significantly expanding pipeline.
I think that strategy is to rely less on paying huge sums to get third-party content into there.
So I think it's inevitable that there will not be as...
the terms won't be as good and the deals will be...
you know, will probably reduce to an extent, but maybe not in the sort of near to, maybe
not over the next 12, 24 months, because they're still relying on that third party content.
And also there's this push, you know, I think Microsoft's doing a push into the PC space.
So it depends on what they're trying to achieve and what platforms they're trying to achieve
it on.
And so there's lots of variables, I would say, in it.
The thing is, it's not.
The risk is it's not standardized, I would say.
It's not standardized across different services.
It can change over time.
So that's where one of the significant risks is.
And if you're developing a thing with the idea, OK.
I'm going to push it into the one of these service that's the terms that you negotiate,
you know, they may be different in sort of 12, 18 months time from when you thought,
you know, you heard what the terms were previously, you know.
So I think there's some risk involved there.
Any other queries?
Just one quick question. I'm curious your thoughts about how the emergence of game streaming is going to impact the growth of subscriptions over the next several years.
Game streaming is a kind of incremental distribution opportunity I would say.
It depends a lot on...
So the biggest services are those services which use both download and streaming to an extent.
So those services are majority download at the moment.
Obviously the expansion strategy is to use streaming to reach audiences they haven't reached before.
But that depends on the type of product offering they put together and the sort of price points and stuff.
And certainly in mobile first markets, for example, and interesting opportunities, say, for example, in India, I don't know.
Latin America or other Asian, Southeast Asia, you know, where there's a kind of mobile first
opportunity, you have to think about whether there's going to be a sort of commercially viable
strategy for packaging together something at a lower price point that's only specifically
for mobile platforms, for example, for Game Pass. Great, thanks. No problem.
I think we're sort of running out of time, anyway, I think that was possibly the last
question, but I'm happy to chat with anyone who wants to chat, and thank you very much
indeed for coming.