Okay, hello everyone, I'm Caitlin Brunel.
I have been in the industry about seven years.
Right now I'm at Naughty Dog,
although the ideas for this talk were developed
while I was still at CCP.
So before I start, a quick spoiler warning.
I will be spoiling a couple of plot moments.
Chances are you've already heard of most of these,
even if you haven't played these games, but fair warning.
So, before I launch into the meat of this talk, let me give a quick review of the major terms.
Autonomy, competence, and relatedness are psychological terms used for increasing
intrinsic motivation to play your game. And, well, why am I focusing on these three?
There's actually quite a few statistics about how effective these three together
are at increasing player retention. For instance, these stats from Immersive
claimed that MMO retention was much higher in games that provided these three psychological needs.
In their study, 46% of players who had spent one month playing an MMO with autonomy,
competence, and relatedness were still playing that MMO nine months later. By contrast,
18% of players who had spent a month playing an MMO that they self-described as fun
were still playing that MMO nine months later.
Autonomy, competence, and relatedness have strong statistical results.
And they work in more than just games.
They've proven effective in education, in sports, in the workplace.
So what are they?
Autonomy is feeling like you have options, like you're in control,
feeling like you're responsible for the results of your own actions.
For instance, why is Grand Theft Auto so popular?
It's not because any one piece of the game is totally flawless, it's that you can do anything
you want. Want to drive a firetruck? Okay, go drive a firetruck. Similarly, everyone likes
making silly pictures in Photoshop because you can create anything, and part of Lego's appeal is just
how open-ended it is. Competence. Competence is feeling like you're up to the task.
Like the thing you're trying to make the character do is what the character actually does on screen.
It's also associated with a feeling of mastery.
The player feeling like they know the strategies and they're good at the game now.
For instance, people who never played a console game before will play Wii Sports
because they feel like they're up to the task of swinging a Wii Mote.
On the flip side, people hate Microsoft Word's autocorrect
because they think they intend to type is not what actually appears on the screen.
The controls don't do what they intend. So Microsoft Word is a badly designed game.
Now there's actually a bit of a special case with competence where,
statistically speaking, it has no effect without autonomy.
Let's say I hand you a piece of chalk and tell you to write on the chalkboard.
Probably all of you feel like, yeah, I have the skills to do this. But are you motivated?
If I tell you to write the same line over and over, probably not. If I tell you to put
anything you want on the chalkboard, yeah, now you've probably got some good ideas.
For betterness
long, that you're part of something bigger, that you have peers who will look out for you, and that
you're also responsible for their well-being. And despite relatedness being all about people,
ironically, NPC interactions are more consistently effective at giving positive relatedness. Unlike
other players who might just yell at you for being a noob, NPCs can every single time have a reaction
of, wow, you're that guy who saved the whole town! I can't believe I'm meeting you!
So to give a quick shorthand for these terms,
autonomy is having options,
competence is feeling up to the task,
and relatedness is connecting with people.
So you might be asking,
why wouldn't we just want to max out
autonomy, competence, and relatedness?
After all, you get a huge spike
in player retention if you do,
and some games do go this route.
Take Farmville, for instance.
You can plant crops in any pattern you want, giving you autonomy.
The only skill is clicking, so no one feels a lack of competence.
And your friends are relying on you to play and benefit from you playing,
giving you relatedness. So does that make Farmville the pinnacle of game design?
Now, don't get me wrong, it is very efficient at what it does,
but let me make a case for deliberately denying the player
autonomy, competence, and relatedness.
I'm going to compare two different scenes where autonomy is taken away.
In Portal, there's a scene where you have to destroy an inanimate box.
And quite a few people, not everyone, but quite a few, form a sort of emotional connection
with this box, and so destroying the box is something they really don't want to do.
In Portal 2, there is a scene where in order to advance the plot, you have to put the villain back into power.
And a lot of people don't want to do this because they're angry with the villain, breaking the player's autonomy.
Now, here's the interesting thing.
People love Portal's scene and hate Portal's previous scene.
In both of these scenes, you have your autonomy taken away.
the villain is making you do this heinous act,
and in the other, the game designer is making you do it.
Which means, in one case,
the player is angry with the villain,
and in the other case,
the player is angry with the game designer.
Or, alternatively, they might just end up feeling
like they can't relate to the main character.
Either way, you probably don't want the player
hating your game design or hating your main character.
That's usually a writing success.
Now, some of you are probably saying,
whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa, hold on.
Were we talking about autonomy?
How did we end up talking about villains?
In other words, how do we go from talking about
a purely game mechanical concept
to a purely narrative concept?
So here's what's happening.
You start with a piece of game design,
in this case, one that takes away the player autonomy.
This causes a powerful emotion in the player.
Anger at having their autonomy taken away.
And then we use trickery to get the player
to associate that emotion with a narrative and not
the game design that caused the emotion in the first place.
This is a big deal.
This is an emotional storytelling tool
that exists only in games.
But is this the only way to produce the emotions we want through game design?
I mean, do we have to break autonomy?
Because autonomy is something we really don't want to break.
I mean, it triples our subscriber numbers.
Could we maybe modify the scene a bit so that it doesn't actually break autonomy?
What if there was some super secret way to save the Cuban portal?
would this be better? Well, there's a couple of problems with that. The first is newbies.
Newbies aren't going to know there's a secret and therefore they're still going to feel the
autonomy loss. The second is that eventually when the newbies go online and talk about this scene,
they're going to hear no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, you did it wrong. You're supposed to save the cube.
And now all of a sudden they feel incompetent.
So now we're breaking two rules instead of just one.
So okay, wow, that didn't work.
Do we really just have to break autonomy?
Well, hold on.
What if we just let people keep the cube?
No secrets?
Now, nobody loses autonomy or competence.
But now you've completely changed the emotional tone of the scene,
why be angry at the villain anymore?
Why be sad at the scene now?
In short, if we want our game design to produce negative emotions
to be harnessed in our narrative, then we need to break rules.
So now that we know what makes Portal's scene effective,
let's try to fix Portal 2's scene.
The problem with Portal 2's scene is, why does the main character agree to the plans?
Who's forcing her to do so?
I mean, the main character gets ordered around by a potato.
Why does she obey the potato?
Why doesn't she just make her own plans?
To fix this, what you need is a stronger authority figure.
Someone who can give the main character orders she can't refuse.
Let's come back to Portal 1 now.
Given that we already have our formula,
villain that takes away your autonomy,
how can we improve the impact of this scene?
Now, the funny thing about this scene
is that it has no real impact
on a certain percentage of the audience.
Some people, when they play Portal, react,
it's just an inanimate object.
Sure, I'll incinerate it, no problem.
It would be a very different story
if the cube was instead...
a cute robot with personality and seeming intelligence.
Now, the walls in Portal are covered in graffiti from past test subjects, leaving
poems and tributes to the cube. What would happen if you let people write their own graffiti?
What would happen if there were flowers in the scene that they can move around?
Basically, give the players a small piece of autonomy.
you're still breaking their autonomy, the player still has no control over the big things,
they still have to kill the cube, but they do have a small some autonomy over what kind of
send-off they give the cube and how much respect they pay, which theoretically will make them more
engaged with the scene. So enough analysis about Portal, let's take a step back and look at the
Some of you might be wondering, could we use the emotion in Bug produced by our game design
to enhance something other than narrative? And the answer is yes, it could be used to emphasize
a moral. Brenda Brathwaite, for instance, has games where you experience various historical
atrocities, such as the slave trade from Africa to America.
These games give you a history lesson. They probably get you closer to understanding what
people were really feeling than any history textbook ever could, because you feel your
human rights being taken away through gameplay. Alternatively, instead of narrative or morals,
you could give people strong feelings about an abstract concept. This is most commonly seen
in flash games that try to argue against a certain kind of game design. Let me give you an example.
This is a screenshot from Super Press Space to Win.
Now, the only controls of this game are the space bar.
The game never gives you a choice about anything.
It's press space to buy a potion,
and press space to walk, and choose a stat to upgrade
when you only have one stat.
A lot of people playing this game would say,
oh, of course, this is a critique of linearity in RPGs.
Although, actually, I think the message is a little ambiguous.
I think another group of people would walk away
concluding that linear RPGs actually
do give them a lot of freedom, a lot of autonomy.
And they just didn't notice it until you
took that autonomy away.
But I would argue that impacting narrative, impacting morals,
and impacting an abstract thesis are all pretty similar.
You're trying to convey a message and you're using game design to make the player feel
exactly the way you want them to feel.
So yes, you could manipulate player emotion around any external idea,
but the tricks are basically the same.
So you might ask, what about not going external at all?
Could we map a negative emotion from one piece of gameplay to another piece of gameplay?
And the answer is yes.
you can make people dislike a well-made part of your gameplay, if you wanted to.
For instance, this is a fairy from Zelda who yells at you to stop what you're doing and
listen to her, and nobody likes to be told to stop what they're doing, so most players
hate her, and yet she's just a hint system.
That's usually good game design.
Why would you want people to hate a well-made part of your gameplay?
And by the way, I'm not just being rhetorical here.
In narrative, there are villains that audiences love to hate.
Will there ever come a point in games where there are game mechanics that audiences love to hate?
Video games are a young, evolving medium.
Maybe someday audiences will clamor for villain game mechanics.
Who knows?
All right.
So far we've only really done a dozen variations on one example,
and it produces one emotion. Let's expand our repertoire of emotions.
Specifically, so far we've only been messing with people's autonomy.
We can get different emotions by messing with their competence and their relatedness.
For comparison purposes, breaking autonomy makes people feel controlled,
makes them feel like a pawn, like they're being forced to do something against their will,
which in turn makes them angry against authority,
and all of these feelings together naturally make people want to start a rebellion.
Breaking competence has a very different effect.
Instead of making people want to start a revolution, it makes them want to feel helpless,
makes them want to admit defeat.
makes them want to ask for help.
Relatedness is a bit less one-dimensional.
Psychologically speaking, relatedness
is the opposite of loneliness.
However, when someone is in a state of relatedness
and you take that away, depending
on how you remove relatedness, they
might feel grief or loss or homesickness.
So let's talk about breaking relatedness
through game mechanics.
There are several ways to break up an existing relationship.
You can use death killing a character the player cared about.
You can use physical distance. Have the player go on a long journey far away
from friends and family. You could have the player's friends and
peers reject the player. Of course, rejection can go both ways.
You can make the player want to reject their friends and peers because it
turns out their friends and peers are horrible, like maybe they're Nazis or something.
And a couple of games use exactly that plot twist.
You know, your friends are secretly Nazis.
But the vast majority of games just go for murder.
And it's easy to criticize this and say
that games should broaden their writing horizons.
And they probably should.
But is there a psychological reason why
murder might be more effective?
To answer this question, let me first
go on a tangent about a psychological experiment.
In this experiment.
people were given electric shocks by someone in another room.
And like any good scientific experiment,
it was a double-blind test with two groups.
One group is told that people in the other room
were acting maliciously,
that they know pressing the button will cause pain.
The other group is told that
there's someone in another room pressing a button,
but they're totally innocent.
They don't know they're hurting anyone.
Now, it turns out malicious shocks really hurt.
Innocent shocks don't.
Well, the first one does, but the pain quickly drops off.
So why murder?
Because it's malicious.
The malicious act is going to cause more pain.
So if we are going to use a murder scene,
how do we make sure we get the most emotional impact out of it?
One of the more important points is making sure people care about the victim.
And how do we do that?
We use gameplay.
We create a game mechanical relationship between the player and the victim.
But don't skip narrative either.
Remember how not everyone cared about the cube from Portal
because to some people it was just an inanimate box.
So how do we create game mechanical relatedness?
in all the same way that relationships are built between humans.
You want to create trust and respect between the NPC and the player.
Enough trust that the player will happily do the character a favor
because they know that character will return that favor.
You want them to rely on each other. Maybe your main character can't fly and
so relies on someone who can, and she in turn
relies on the main character for brute force.
You want them to feel like a peer to the player,
like they are working together towards something bigger.
So let's take a look at Daederas.
Now, okay, like her or hate her,
she's gotten more attention than any other video game death.
Maybe there are game mechanical reasons for this.
Let's analyze.
She gives things to the player,
lore explaining how to defeat the bad guy,
goals that the player can do.
At the same time, she needs your help, and she will often fight by your side, helping you.
And finally, she dies halfway through the game, not in the ending credits,
after the game ends, after the game mechanical contract is over.
All the characters could die at the end of the game, and at some level the player would not care.
But no, Eris dies in the middle of the game, when she's still needed for more lore,
more missions, and more gameplay.
So we've been talking about how to make people care about a character. So far we've used relatedness.
But what about using autonomy and competence? After all, autonomy and competence are good
techniques to get people to care about pretty much anything. So how do we increase player
carrying through autonomy?
One way is to use user-created characters, like with The Sims, where players create lives and
relationships for their characters. If you tell someone to dream up a set of characters and invent
stories and relationships about them, they're going to be upset if you next tell them,
okay, one of your characters is now dead. How do we increase player caring through competence?
make them feel like they rely on this character to be competent.
Like they're more competent at the game
when they're using this character.
And actually, Eris does a little bit of this.
She is your healer.
And when she dies, you lose all of her equipment
and any experience you invested in leveling her up.
So, so far, all of the examples I've used
have been strictly linear.
Let's take a moment to talk about how to extend these to nonlinear storylines.
Remember, all we're doing when using this technique is that we take a gameplay moment
that produces a negative emotion in the player and fool the player into feeling that emotion
about the narrative. All you need for this is a small piece of gameplay and a small piece
of narrative that you can freely place anywhere in a nonlinear setting.
And you don't even have to pair the same piece of gameplay
with the same piece of narrative.
You can mix and match.
Just make sure that you have one of each.
What you don't ever want is intentionally bad gameplay
that's not serving a purpose by driving narrative emotion.
Let's go into some specific examples.
How might we do murder in a non-linear setting?
Find the character that the player seems to care about the most.
the character that they're coming to rely on for help, for whom they're doing the most favors.
And then you kill that character. A few games actually use exactly this trick already. I
believe Far Cry 2 does, for instance. What about coercion, like in Portal,
where the villain forces you to incinerate the cube? When you think about this...
You're taking away player autonomy and forcing them to do things.
How can this ever, ever be nonlinear?
The answer is to make the entire scene optional.
Like, maybe it's something that happens only if you're captured.
Once you're captured, you're on rails for a bit,
but you don't need to be captured in the first place.
So every example I've given so far can be reduced to a single dramatic moment where
something happens in gameplay and is immediately linked to a piece of narrative.
What about an emotion that takes time to build up? For example,
the loneliness that you get in games where there's just nobody around that you can talk to.
Now, first things first, before asking how to extend this to nonlinear narratives, we need to
tie the game mechanical loneliness into a narrative. Portal, once again, gives us a fairly good example
where not only are you lonely, you know who to blame. There is this robot running tests on you
like a lab rat who won't let you leave. Not only that, it's malicious. The robot knows you want to
leave and won't let you.
In order to pull off this kind of loneliness in a non-linear setting,
you have to make an isolated section of the game that's all going to obey the same rules.
You have to decide from the moment you set foot on this island, you lose all radio contact with
your allies. And sure, maybe you don't need to set foot on the island at all.
Maybe there's multiple routes you can go once you get to the island, but...
You need a section of your game where the game mechanics reinforce emotion consistently,
regardless of player path.
There's also potential for going the other way around in a non-linear story,
of dynamically detecting a loss of autonomy, competence, or relatedness,
and then harnessing that emotion. For instance, noticing the player is frustrated.
Maybe they can't beat a boss and...
turning that frustration into a plot moment.
Now we get to actually give an example of breaking competence.
Breaking competence actually has several pitfalls.
The first is a psychological result that people just don't care about competence
unless it's a situation where they have autonomy as well.
If you force a player into doing something, they're not going to care that
much if they fail.
Next, feeling like you're terrible at a game makes people want to give up and quit.
And if they quit, they never see your wonderful plot moment.
Finally, skill levels vary. Be extremely careful when you create an impossible task
that people are meant to fail, and make sure that people actually do fail it.
Let's dive into an example and look at some techniques for solving these issues.
This is an image of a board game that Brenda Brathwaite made for her daughter to teach her
daughter about what really happened in the slave trade from Africa to America.
The middle passage. Her daughter had to sail a boat of slaves across the ocean. Now, each turn
she rolled a die to see how much food was used on their trip, and she was rolling really high,
and she said, Mommy, we're not going to make it. What are we going to do? And her mother replies.
well we can keep going and hope that people don't die or we can put some people in the water.
And this had a powerful effect. Suddenly her daughter had a much deeper understanding of
the historical event. I started asking all kinds of great questions like did that really happen
so I could come home one day and you'd be gone and would we get together again on the other side?
All right, let's break down this game design and analyze how it gets around the major pitfalls associated with breaking competence.
How does Brenda's game make sure that the player retains autonomy?
She gives the player choices during failure.
Her daughter has two terrible options, drowning or starvation, but she has autonomy.
In fact, this is the most autonomy she's had since they loaded up the boats.
And this is really noteworthy. Most games, when you're not going to make it, do the exact opposite.
They take away player autonomy. Your buttons don't even do anything. Your screen fades to grey.
Taking away autonomy makes sure you don't care about failing. And these games don't want you
to care about failing. This is exactly the opposite of Brenda's game. Brenda wants her
daughter to care about failing.
How does Brenda's Game deal with players of higher skill level?
Luck.
Brenda's Game is not a game where you can sail through every time without problems.
Eventually, if you play this game enough,
you're going to run into a crisis situation where you have run out of food
and you will have to make some hard decisions.
How does Brenda's Game deal with people who want to give up and quit?
Brenda's game has a GM who can respond at the perfect time, right before the player quits the game out of frustration.
Now, okay, obviously that's not an option for most of us making electronic games.
In electronic games, we basically need to do the same thing we've been doing for years.
Guess what the player is feeling?
It also helps to just drag the seat out.
make sure that the player can see their impending game mechanical doom coming a mile away while they
struggle against it. So how could we modify Brenda's game? Now don't get me wrong, I happen
to think Brenda's game design here is quite brilliant, but not everyone is making a game
about historical atrocities. Let's say we wanted to modify the scene to have a more positive spin.
How would we go about doing that? You could get rescued by another captain.
Now, think back to every rescue scene you've come across in a game.
Chances are you barely remember them. You feel like you didn't need rescuing and could have
fought those enemies off on your own. Take away player competence first, however, and then players
tend to feel gratitude.
We've made the player feel helpless,
which means they really want and appreciate help.
So, okay, maybe you're thinking of using one or two of these scenes
and are now wondering how many of these scenes to use,
at what point in the game to use them.
Psychology has a few more hints for us.
First, don't overuse these techniques.
The way human emotions work is that a corresponding chemical is released in the brain.
If the brain runs out of that chemical, then you actually can't feel that emotion anymore.
This is why people always talk about creating highs and lows in game design,
because the human brain literally cannot maintain a constant high state of emotion.
And yes, eventually the human brain can refill its chemical supply,
but this takes time and isn't something you can rely on your player doing.
Another interesting psychological result is that human memory is actually very easily overwritten.
Instead of remembering what someone's face looked like every day for the past five years,
you just remember the most recent version. And older versions of the memory literally get
overwritten.
And this is already known in cinema, where if people like the final scene of a movie,
they usually say they like the entire movie.
So when sticking in a scene with negative emotions, you usually won't want this to be
the final scene of your game.
Unless, of course, your goal is to have a sad ending.
And actually, there are games that do finish on a sad ending, and a few of them use some
of these techniques.
Next note, psychological studies generally point to the presence of autonomy having a larger impact
than the presence of either of the other two. So this most likely means that losing autonomy
will have the strongest emotional impact of three.
Okay, enough psychological tricks. Let's review the process from start to finish.
First, you're going to want to choose a part of the narrative.
Next, of all the possible emotions you could use,
decide which emotion you want to add to the scene.
Once you've decided, this emotion
will dictate what kind of game design rule
you're going to break, be it autonomy, competence,
or relatedness.
And then you use the emotion created by gameplay
to enhance the emotional impact of your narrative.
And that summarizes the strategy.
At this point, I'd like to open things up for questions.
Oh, also, I've been asked to mention that, yes, we
are hiring.
OK, let's go to questions.
So how do you explain all of these ideas to your publisher?
I mean, if your publisher is pushing you towards having autonomy, competence, relatedness,
I mean, if they're not, then you just say, oh, hey, we're going to have a scene with a death
in it, and those are really good movies, right? So they'll be great in games, right?
You're talking about an idea that's possibly alienating for your player base and therefore alienating your revenue.
And that's definitely something that they're going to look at.
Of course.
I mean, is movies probably one of your strongest things that you can use as a common ground to go,
look, we've had these tragedies and we've had these upsets.
You can also point to other games that do similar things.
Like you can point to Portal and look at how much...
You know, the way to companion cube became like an internet meme, right?
Yeah
Okay, so you were talking about player death and saving them kind of at the end and how
they might be thankful.
In the 2008 version of Prince of Persia, Elika would always save the player before they died
and people ended up finding it as something not useful and something they didn't like.
In the end, they felt it was too easy and there was never really any sort of punishment
for falling.
What do you think of that?
Right.
Well, I mean...
I don't know.
I think it's a pretty good joke.
It's very appropriate.
It's a very good joke.
I like it though.
Well, okay.
I'm going to go kill some people.
Okay, bye!
Bye!
All right, well, that's the end of the story.
I hope you enjoyed it!
If you did, please be sure to like and subscribe!
I'll see you next time!
Bye!
it starts to become expected after a while, right? The feeling of gratitude, part of it is like,
the unexpected part is important. It's not like, okay, I know this is going to happen. It's like,
I feel helpless, right? You don't feel helpless if you know that you are going to be saved no
matter what, right? So you think it would have improved it if sometimes she saved you and
sometimes she didn't? Um...
Possibly, I mean, I don't actually, I haven't actually played the game in question, so...
I mean, I think it's, these are things best used sparingly as opposed to
your player expects you to always do this, so...
Yeah.
Thanks.
Do you have more examples of taking away confidence from existing games?
Yeah, I mean, like, specifically for the rescue thing, like...
uh... megaman x has a scene in the very at the very start where you have this
enemy that you basically can't beat
uh...
and then you like you know you get rescued by zero and then you know
similarly i mean i i sort of alluded to it in the picture but uh... let's go back
here
far enough but uh... super metroid has you being rescued by a metroid
uh...
So and then there's also like, oh gosh.
I mean, Brenda Brathwaite has done, well,
I mean Brenda Brathwaite's games are just good examples of like,
they're full of this kind of stuff.
But I mean.
One Falls for Each of Us was a game where she's talking about the Trail of Tears.
And you have to, you know, it's a situation where 50,000 Native Americans were moved,
displaced from their homes, right? And she actually has 50,000 game pieces. And, you know,
the first reaction is like, you want me to move 50,000 game pieces? Are you crazy? And then it's
like, oh my god, they had to move 50,000 people. That's crazy, right? So, yeah.
Yeah, I should have just kept a note of like, I mean, I went into this with like 50 examples and I paired it down to like three, so.
Go ahead.
In terms of taking an atom, an atom.
Autonomy. Autonomy, thank you.
But, taking away from the player, is it, do you think there's a key difference between
Taking it away so much that it you know
It's a cutscene versus literally make buying off all their options that it's the only thing that they can do
But they still have to do it. Yeah, absolutely
I think there's a huge difference between that like forcing the player to inseminate the Cuban portal
Would be it would be an extremely different scene if that was an FMV where it's just like oh
Why is it the main character doing that that's not what I would have done right like
Although sometimes it can be just as effective, I can think of one game.
So maybe for your next speech, would you kindly mention Bioshock in it?
Yeah, no, there's tons of games I could mention, of course, but yes.
I just wanted to mention that you were talking about confidence in games and people wanting
an example.
A great example is...
heavy rain when you have the option of killing the drug dealer.
If you kill the drug dealer, you are in his child's room,
and therefore, if you kill him, you are incompetent as a parent and human being,
as a moral human being.
However, if you let him go, you do not get the information that you need
in order to save your own son.
So, no matter what, you make a decision in which you are not competent.
Huh.
Yeah.
Go ahead.
One thing I had a question about was the type of scene where you're in an unwinnable situation
is sort of a convention you see a lot in, say, JRPGs.
Very frequently you'll find there's a boss fight somewhere that you have to lose to move
the plot forward, and quite often the player actually knows they have to lose.
It's usually really obvious that the level gap is just so disparate, and does that take
away from...
the ability to evoke emotion when you know, like,
I better not waste my potions, because this is one I have to lose.
Yeah, when you know it's just a scripted sequence, then yeah, I mean, absolutely, that takes away from emotion.
Or, like, even just in JRPGs, if you're, like, I mean, half the time when you play them, you're suspicious.
Like, is this fight a plot fight, or is it not? Right?
So, I mean, it's more effective than when, yeah, like, you legitimately feel like,
I should be winning this, why am I not winning this? Like, yeah.
But then you run the risk that players quit because they think,
oh, I must have done something wrong.
Right, yeah.
I mean, you have to be careful to save them at the right time
or cut off the scene at the right time, right?
Cool.
Thank you.
Hey, you probably knew I was coming to the mic.
Yes, I knew you were coming to the mic.
So Scott Rugby from Immersive.
Since one of our guidelines is autonomy,
I love the fact that there's a talk on breaking the guidelines
because that's all about it.
You know, to the question about, I thought there were a lot of interesting points, two
things I wanted to mention.
One is that autonomy is technically not just about choice, but volition.
And so one thing that we find, and we found this, I think I mentioned this to you yesterday
in Uncharted 2, that, because you do a lot of things where like people are betraying
each other and a lot of nasty stuff.
One of the things is that emotional stuff.
gets people really engaged in the story.
And so even though, so they volitionally,
they feel very volitional about moving forward,
even if their choice is taken away.
And so actually, the autonomy scores are maintained
by that sense of volition.
Right.
But another thing I wanted to mention,
just as an example, is Left 4 Dead,
where you really talk about getting your competence
taken away and your autonomy is when you're incapacitated.
Those are some of the most terrifying moments I've ever had.
That's why I didn't play for very long.
It's too scary.
But when that NPC comes along and saves you,
we actually have done measurements
where you see this real surge in relatedness.
Right, of course.
Because you matter.
So there's actually this, it's almost
like there's one need being traded off for another.
Yeah, no, I think a lot of these cases,
like at least the positive ones, maybe not Brenda Brathwaite's
board games, but the positive ones, you generally,
like maybe you're losing in one area,
but you're gaining in somewhere else.
Yeah, absolutely.
Okay, well thank you everyone, and don't forget to fill out your reviews that will be sent
to you through email.
Thank you.
And have a great day.
Bye.