Hello.
Hi everyone.
My name's Andy Nguyen, and this is gonna be a talk
about building community within open development,
but more specifically, how you can use community
as an additional tool to help you with your development.
So, as a quick overview for the layout of the talk, I will talk about what I mean by
community development as opposed to community management.
Community management, I believe, is something more about maintaining what you already have,
and community development is more about integrating the community into your development process.
I'll talk about how it began, our most important tool that we're currently using for community
development, which is Discord, and then how you can get started with it.
So who am I?
My name's Andy Nguyen.
I work at Pocket Watch Games as a producer and a designer.
And we're most known for having released Monaco
back in 2013, for which I was the level designer.
And my most important role right now
for our current project is that of a business
and community developer.
So our current project is Tooth and Tail.
It's a real-time strategy game.
It's not out yet.
And the goal of this game is we wanted
to make a real-time strategy game with simplified controls
that was playable on a controller.
And the idea here is that real-time strategy games are
sort of notorious for having overly complex controls
or a high barrier to entry.
And we wanted to see if we could make a real-time strategy game
that was just as engaging.
though without that aspect of having to learn to play well in order to enjoy the game.
So here's a quick picture of what it looks like.
It's, you know, player versus player.
You can play 1v1 or 2v2, etc.
But more importantly, it's story time.
So about six months ago, I was in Korea.
I flew out there for an event called BICFest, or Busan Indie Connect Festival,
and it was in Busan, South Korea.
And I was having a great time, because it was one of the first times I've ever flown
out of the country.
Though I was setting up shop by myself, and I found it really challenging to sort of communicate
how to play the game with new players.
Even if we had sort of streamlined gameplay, it was not easy to talk to somebody who didn't
know English and explain how to play the game, how to explain the controls, etc.
So I'm kind of freaking out, and I'm trying to come up with my own way of describing how to play the game.
And I know it's Korea, so the closest thing I ever got to communicating with them was I could point to the game and say StarCraft,
and they're like, oh, StarCraft, StarCraft. I'm like, okay, great. I'm like, let's one step closer.
And I could point to a work, and I'm like, SEV, and they're like, yeah, SEV.
Wow, I know like Korean words now.
But that's the closest thing I ever got
to actually teaching them how to play the game.
And so about 30 minutes in,
and I had to do this for like the whole weekend,
this individual comes up and he places his laptop
in between the monitors.
and there's an image of the controller.
And then he starts telling people how to play the game.
He's really enthusiastic.
He's cheering on one side, he's cheering on the other side.
He's telling them what to do.
He's like, go attack him here, go do this here.
And then when he wins, he's like, GG.
And I was like, whoa, what is this?
He goes and takes a selfie with me.
He's extremely nervous and extremely shy.
And he pulls up his phone, and through Google Translate,
he says, hi, I'm from the community,
and I've traveled two hours here to help you.
This was one of the most amazing things I ever had happen
to me as a developer, because it saved me in that moment.
But it wasn't the first time something like this happened.
Six months prior, back at PAX East,
there was a Boston local named Chris, and he contacted us.
And he said, hey, I'm in Boston, and I
was wondering if you wouldn't mind if I
could help out at your booth.
So we let him, and it was a very simple volunteer job
where he got us water, got us food,
but he loved the game so much,
and he was one of our best players at the time,
that having that extra pair of hands at a trade show
is incredibly valuable, and anyone here
who's demoed at a trade show will know how exhausting it is.
So to have somebody just help meant so much.
And the thing that is still kind of unbelievable to us is next week is PAX East and we have
12 volunteers from our community coming to help us.
We actually expanded the size of our booth to accommodate them.
I honestly don't know what to do about that.
But it made me feel like there was something special.
And I feel like everyone here can achieve something special too.
So the community within Tooth and Tail is a closed alpha,
meaning that we don't let everybody in.
And we've only been running it for about a year.
We've had 3,500 applications for this alpha.
And among those, there are 2,500 members who are part of
the community, of which 500 are online daily.
So these are very small numbers when I think about.
You know, some developers have Twitter followers in the tens of thousands or Facebook likes
in the hundreds of thousands.
But I think a lot can come out of these small numbers.
So here are a few community examples.
Clash of Comrades is an organization
that is entirely community-driven.
In the beginning, we used to schedule our own tournaments,
but now they schedule their own tournaments themselves.
I think there's actually one going on right now.
They used to run these monthly,
but now they run these weekly.
They coordinate the applications,
they schedule all the times,
they stream it, they shoutcast it,
they create VODs and highlights,
they even produce their own prizes
and mail them out to people.
They even informed us of other services so they
helped us with discovery by showing us a service called Splice.gg which promotes eSports games.
We never intended for Tooth and Tail to be an eSports game because it's kind of silly
to think that an indie game could be something as big as, you know, the MOBAs of today.
And I'm not saying that we are.
That was never our intention.
But the fact that the community wanted to take this into their own hands and make it
something like that, I think, is quite amazing to us.
They take these matches that are played across multiple different patches and then they compile
data and they send this data to us so then as the balance designer my life is made a
lot easier because I have data to work off of in terms of what's being played and what's
not being played or what's the success rate and what's not the success rate.
And I can just do my job and not have to worry about if I'm doing it right or not because
I'm constantly getting this feedback.
They've even gone so far as to help us with the troubleshooting process, because obviously nobody likes bugs, but rather than getting mad because the game crashes, they supply the information necessary to solve the crash.
And then before the crash is resolved, they even go to inform other community members about what the symptoms and causes of the crash are, so that they can be avoided or resolved on their own.
This is a product of having a community dialogue.
And it also has the benefit of basically
having community troubleshooting.
So we don't have an FAQ because our FAQ is organic.
When people have questions,
they're answered by the community.
They even go ahead and make like strange memes of us
and they like to spam it with the channel and stuff.
So what is community development?
And I think this is the key point here
versus community management.
So for in our experience, what community development is,
is it's business development.
For example, this competitive scene
that was made organically,
which goes on to produce content, marketing content,
that we could spend time on our own
as a small development team making,
but we don't have to because they make it on their own.
It's game design because they're playtesting the game
constantly and giving us this feedback.
And it's also a quality assurance because the moment
something happens across different platforms,
Mac, Linux, PC, or different types of hardware specs,
they let us know immediately.
And not only do they let us know,
they help us diagnose the problem
because the worst thing is when someone tells you a bug,
game crashed, and that's all you get.
You don't have any idea what to do about that.
So this is all supplied by the community
and I like to think that...
as developers you can leverage the community as an additional tool to your development team.
So our goals when we started out making Tooth and Tail
was we wanted to build a marketing machine.
Essentially we wanted to achieve
the point of self-automation.
And more specifically, the goal here is to get to the point
where we can just focus on game development
because other aspects of development
are handled by the community.
This was inspired by a talk that I attended back in Steam Dev Days in 2014,
where Tom Bui at Valve says,
the community will make games better because they can experiment and iterate at a much faster rate than you and I ever could.
For example, we're a small team of three core members
at Pocketwatch.
We're literally capped in the sense that
even if we work 24 hours a day,
there's only so much we can output.
And we can think about how to output more than that.
However, if you consider that the community
is an additional part of your team
and that community will continue to grow,
then that's exponential growth,
as long as you encourage your community
to develop alongside you.
You can see this through the blood of all of Valve's things.
They produce hats, the community produces hats,
skins for League of Legends, skins for Counter-Strike guns,
and the community even votes upon what kind of materials
they want to have inside of the game itself.
So Valve doesn't have to produce that content.
They even go so far as to price use the laws of economics to price these materials for them
So they don't have to have somebody whose job it is to assign arbitrary price values to these new assets that are coming in
It's a machine that's automatically
Sort of it's automated by the laws of economics and by the community based off supply and demand
There was a time back in college when I used to love watching these tf2 skits
But they would only come out once every six months or so and so valve
with this philosophy said, well, it'd be a lot easier
if we gave the tools to the community
so that they can make the skits for us.
And now you have the Saxxy Awards
and there's an infinite number of TF2 marketing cartoons
rather than once every few years.
Other developers do this too.
So when World of Warcraft came out, you could mod the UI.
And I think at the time their intention was
to allow players to customize the visuals of it.
But the most downloaded mod by magnitudes
was something called Quest Helper.
And what Quest Helper allowed players to do,
or what they enabled them to do,
is sort of quest in a way where they could understand
where to go and what the objectives of the quest.
And so that was an indication of the game design for WoW.
So in the Cataclysm expansion,
they actually just implemented it into the game.
So the results of this sort of process is you now have fans developing content for you,
you now have fans developing marketing for you, which makes a better game than you and
I could ever make, and it builds a bigger team than you and I could ever be.
So why did we take this approach?
Well, Tooth & Tail is a multiplayer game, and for indies, multiplayer games are sort
of infamous for having this...
chicken and egg problem where if nobody's playing your game,
no one's going to buy your game
because you can't play against anybody.
But if nobody buys your game,
then no one's playing the game.
And so we knew we needed to see the community
in the first place.
We knew we would require a constant iteration on the game
because if AAA companies are even struggling
with the balance of the game,
how could a small indie team with limited resources
consider balancing the game?
And we felt like this was going to be
a challenging game design for us
because we wanted to take all the core philosophies,
concepts, and experiences of a real-time strategy game
that you know and love, like Command and Conquer
or StarCraft or Age of Empires,
and then boil it down into something
that was really accessible but felt the same.
And so as a result of this approach, what we did was we created a suite of automated tools for community development.
And this is how we began that process. So for comparison, Monaco took the avenue of traditional press.
We got some IGF awards. We did a bunch of interviews. We went through the traditional press outlets like IGN or blogs like Kotaku or Joystick at the time, etc.
So for comparison, what we did was before we made Tooth & Tail,
one of the reasons we made Tooth & Tail was we wanted to make a game that was streamable,
or in other words, as fun to watch as it is to play.
Because we knew that back in 2013, it was sort of the verge of Twitch becoming the phenomenon that it is today,
and YouTubers were getting more...
talking directly to consumers better than the traditional blogs were.
So we wanted to make a game that encouraged this kind of content,
and it, in essence, encouraged community development.
Another reason why we chose this method was back during Monaco days, we felt like something
that was sort of essential to the sort of indie marketing that a lot of us indies do
is Twitter.
And we were not very successful in achieving the amount of followers or the amount of virality
or retweets that other developers were getting with their games.
And so we felt like maybe Twitter wasn't something that was in our company's blood.
We weren't good at tweeting.
But what we were good at is we were good at engaging
the consumer directly.
And with Monaco, we did this to some success,
but not to the scale that it is today.
With Monaco, we were good at getting fans to talk with us
and love developing the game alongside us
and essentially become evangelists for the game,
ambassadors for the game that promote,
go out there and they talk about the game for you.
And that goal is very small.
That goal is very achievable.
It's not hundreds of thousands of followers.
It's like 10.
And that's all you need, which is great.
So when we took this approach,
we decided our marketing outlets would be Twitch
and Discord, or at the time it was MIRC or IRC,
which is basically developer chat.
So Twitch, the way it began was at the time in 2013,
streaming development was sort of something
that was becoming very popular
and a lot of developers still do it today, we still do it,
but it was very much a traditional dev stream.
Andy Schatz would be on a computer and you'd be coding,
you're talking about the game,
this is a very early, ugly prototype of the game.
But what happened organically,
was as the game became more fun,
we played the game on stream
in a way that was very competitive.
And we were sort of role-playing this idea
that even though the game was an ugly, ugly prototype,
we were imagining the game as it was in its completed state.
And it set a culture of competitive play.
We were shoutcasting the game.
We were doing highlights.
We were talking high-level strategy.
We were getting excited over the back and forth
of the competitive match,
even though it was just a simple prototype.
And as people watched that, they participated with us.
And this is part of our open development style.
So it's like, you can talk to us as developers
as we're sort of engaging in this back and forth.
And we acquired alpha members through that method.
So essentially what I'm talking about here
is establishing a culture
of the kind of community members that you want
by acting as the community members you want.
than engaging with those community members directly.
And so when you acquire them into your community,
they are now sort of replications of you.
Then the second avenue for which we have done community building is through
the community chat itself, the direct line to the community members.
And we've made sure that all of our marketing avenues focused to this point.
So the Steam forums, the tweets that we do do, our Tumblr, etc.,
they all tell the consumer to go to the community chat.
It started with IRC, and IRC was fine.
But IRC is like 1,000 years old, and
a lot of people don't really.
want to, it's not like a user-friendly interface.
But then Discord came out back in I think October of 2016.
And this thing, this application changed the face
of how we approach community entirely.
So Discord, what it is, it's a free community chat tool.
Everyone can use it.
I'm sure you've all heard of Slack.
And I'm sure many of you have heard of Discord
as it's rising in popularity.
It's essentially Slack.
for the consumer, it's a consumer facing product.
Trying to replace the days of like Ventrilo or TeamSpeak
or all those things like when you used to get
into your clan chat and talk with your clan
or talk with your guild before you did a raid, et cetera.
So about three or four months ago, I was invited to be the first ever guest blog or non-Discord member to write articles on their official blog.
And the way this happened was I was talking to one of the developers for Discord about how we were using their platform to do development rather than actually just gaming community building.
and how we used the tools that they provided
that were intended for community building
and how we leveraged those tools
to assist in the development of the game.
And he was fascinated by all the Cypress of doodads
and whatnot that we had done,
so I ended up writing a blog about it.
And I'll go over some of that with you today.
So here's how we enhanced our community chat.
First off, our permission tools.
So with the permission tools, what essentially it comes down to is you can assign roles or
status or different privileges to different members in your community.
Now the typical interaction of this, or the typical way this surfaces in community is
you have moderators.
So this is something that's very typical in forums.
You have moderators that delete bad, you know, troll comments on forums or whatnot.
But what we've done here...
that I think sets it apart is we've thought about expanding the scope of what permissions
mean.
And so in Discord, we've separated them out by color and by priority, and we've identified
the individuals who serve as ambassadors for the company and the individuals who are superfans,
et cetera.
This is a 100% voluntary job.
And it's driven, it allows the community to basically help itself.
So we select these members out of the community who we believe
represent us and represent the company in a positive way.
And we explain to them what they mean to the company.
Then we assign them this unique role.
Essentially, I think the reason why we chose to do this is because
If you're very passionate about your community,
having the responsibility to help grow your community
is something that's very intrinsically rewarding.
So we've gone beyond just making moderators.
We have guides.
Guides, their role is to convert a new player
into a non-new player by informing them
of all of the thick questions they have about the game.
They're essentially living FAQs.
We even have superstars in which we recognize members who do positive things for the community.
We mark them as a superstar because they did fan art or they did a custom song for the
game or something or whatnot.
You can make tools with Discord.
So one of the tools that we did is we have a completely
hands off alpha onboarding process.
Traditionally what happened in the past was we would have
like a form and individuals would sign up for the form
and then we would basically email keys out.
But this took time off of our hands as developers
and we don't want to distribute keys manually every morning.
So we decided to make the onboarding process for the alpha
be something that was community driven.
So after having selected the select few of moderate,
select handful of moderators who we felt represented
the company in a positive way,
we instructed them that they now had the power
and the responsibility to key members of the community.
So as tons of community members come into the chat,
the moderators now identify the ones who they think
represent the culture that we want,
the culture of positivity or of inclusivity.
And then they proceed to vote on that individual.
And if enough moderators vote on that individual,
a bot automatically private messages them a key.
And this is how we make sure that we weed out individuals
who may be toxic or too salty when they play,
and encourage that there's a positive growth
in our community.
This is done via a bot, but more importantly,
it's done via the community.
The bot itself is actually programmed
by the community as well.
So we also wanted to make sure that we created retention
with this method.
So the tip, like I said before, the typical format
was to have a sign up form and then to give out keys.
But I think in the past, we didn't have a lot of success
with that because once we gave out the key,
we had no means of making sure that they played the game
or provided us with the feedback necessary.
So instead, our current format is that players now have
to earn their keys by contributing to the community.
This means engaging in, watching the stream,
engaging in conversation, asking questions,
providing answers, becoming familiar with the game.
And by earning a key through proving
that they're passionate about the community,
it means that the community itself is ultimately
full of just passionate people.
And less individuals who are just looking for a free key.
This really does promote retention.
We've also used the tools within Discord to help us make the game.
So, Tooth & Tail is an online game and it doesn't have matchmaking.
You can play online.
There's a lobby system and you can make a lobby and play against each other.
But there's no way to mark yourself as looking for a game.
However, because everyone is in the chat,
using the bot that was programmed by the community, you can type ready.
And it'll now mark you green, so your name turns green.
It also marks you as a permission or a role as looking for a game.
So you can ping looking for a game.
And this is what it kind of looks like.
On the right hand side where there's user list, you can now look and
say, hey, that's every single person looking to play the game.
They're green, when they chat their name's green and
I can see them on the side so
I can private message them and tell them if they wanna play the game.
This is great because now it just gets more people to play the game.
So, getting started, these are some simple stuff that you can do today.
Pick your hub.
You can, for us it's Discord and we're having a great time with it, but you can pick any
hub if it's like a chat hub or a blog or what not.
Set up your roles or define your roles more specifically.
And this is something that I feel like
has worked out really well for us.
We defined our role as a developer.
We've defined our superstars as moderators
or guides or featured members.
Define what those roles, privileges, and entitlements mean
because it establishes various levels of importance
within your community.
Create a singular landing page so that people can go to this one spot and
get all the information they need to know.
Because your community is not just a hub with a bunch of people in it.
It's now an ecosystem.
It's now, it's got its own rules and its own metrics and it lives and
moves on its own.
They're gonna have questions.
They're gonna wanna participate in it as if it's a game in and of itself.
Announce your updates.
So.
It's important for you not to go dark because your community is eagerly waiting for the next bit of news.
So constantly talk about the little things that you're doing so that your community can have something to engage in.
You can do this either Discord or Twitter,
whatever hub you have, and then invite them to engage.
So you take your invite or however you want
to ask your community to join this one spot
and funnel them all into one place.
In the beginning, we tried funneling them
all into a newsletter, but ultimately,
we worked into just funneling them all into this chatroom.
Whatever it is, just make sure that they know every single step of the way,
whatever it is that you're talking through, where to go.
So whenever we tweet, we Facebook, whenever we make a blog on Tumblr or
a Steam forum post, it all tells them to go to this one spot,
that one landing page that I talked about earlier.
And hopefully, if you build your community up enough,
then you can have people for some reason meme out about you.
That's not Photoshop, that's Andy Schatz's face at the Boston Major.
So this is some of our moderators.
I'd like to give a big shout out to them.
Here's some resources that I used for this talk.
And thank you.
And that's our Discord page and my Twitter and our, oops,
that's, I should say Tumblr or blog or whatnot.
But yeah, I encourage you to check out our Discord
because it's got a lot of really cool,
fun things you can do in there.
So thanks so much.
Oh, okay. Questions, anyone?
Hi, so really great talk first of all.
Okay, thanks.
So I have a question.
Your game obviously is multiplayer,
which is the kind of game that already
sort of encourages people to seek out a community.
Yeah.
So they have someone to play with.
How viable would you say all of these things are
sort of for a single player game
that is generally more of a solitary experience?
Well, yeah, I've thought about this as well.
I think the key isn't necessarily single player versus multiplayer,
but something that can be iterated on or have perpetual engagement.
So a game like Darkest Dungeon, which has added content constantly,
or like Don't Starve or whatnot, can easily foster this sort of community.
A game that would probably not work well in this, like the most extreme case,
would be something like a narrative game that's...
like a short narrative game that's prone to spoilers.
Because once the consumer finishes it,
there's not much they can do beyond that.
But if you have something that's like a systemic game
that is procedurally generated
or continues to build upon itself,
there's lots of reasons for the player to come back
and give you feedback.
Thank you.
Hello.
Hi.
I have a question.
So when you're on Twitch streaming the development, how
do you decide when you're going to be streaming?
Oh, because if you don't want to give away a certain part
of a game, you want that part secret.
Or what makes you decide, OK, we're going to stream this,
but not this?
Right.
So the question is, how do you decide what to stream and what
not to stream?
We also have portions of the game
that we haven't streamed at all yet.
They're the ones, for us, it's what we've chosen
to be the most prone to spoilers.
So we haven't streamed any of the single player
or anything like that.
What we typically, the high level goal of streaming for us
is to set a cultural example for the community.
So we stream in the way we hope
other viewers stream themselves.
And it's worked out because by running tournaments
for something as small and as simple as this alpha.
we've encouraged other people to do the exact same thing.
And it works.
So find whatever it is in your game
that you think you can imagine other people doing for you,
and then stream that way.
Because people, you know, you lead and they follow.
Okay, thanks.
Thank you.
So.
So I think two of the biggest concerns in generating an open development community is
One the creation of clicks or kind of a sense of elitism or entitlement within privileged users
And then also being held accountable for the actions of those
Individuals and occasionally having to apologize on their behalf, right? How do you?
for one thing, incentivize a community,
a type of community engagement
that doesn't stratify your player base.
And also, how do you hold people accountable
without letting it get so far
that you're stuck making an apology
that you never should have been forced to make
in the first place.
So just to go over your question again, the first one is elitism, right?
Yes, I guess the first one is how to prevent clicks among privileged players.
And then the second one would be how to make those privileged players self-accountable
so that you're not having to shepherd them around.
Right, so these situations have already come to us.
there have been complaints from other members
who are not moderators,
who felt like the moderators themselves were too click-like.
The question, sorry,
the question is that how do you prevent clicks
and how do you hold players accountable
for if they're in a position of power and they abuse it
or something along those lines, right?
So both have happened to us.
As far as clicks are concerned,
I've never done anything to actively prevent them
in the sense that,
I don't say, the moderators themselves do have a private channel for which they talk
about moderation.
And that in and of itself is a click.
And they talk about their own things in private.
I don't feel that this is destructive to the community.
And I think a big part of that is a lot of what has gone into selecting the moderators
themselves is to make sure that even though they have their own subsection of which they're
essentially the elites.
they're vetted so that they're not elitists.
They do talk directly to everyone else as individuals,
and I've established a rule page for the moderators
to know that they should not talk to individuals
as if they are inferior to them.
Now, in the event that this does happen,
and it has happened, we've...
The developers are the highest tier of elites,
essentially, in development, and they have to step in,
which takes time off on our hands.
It has happened a few times over the year,
where we have to step in and talk to a moderator directly,
and then guide them.
But this particular correction process
allows it, sort of,
serves as a way of showing the moderators how to behave.
It is sort of going to happen, I think.
Yeah, thanks.
Hi there, I'm Paulo from Brazil, thanks for the talk.
Your company has already made a name for itself with Monaco.
Yeah.
I'd like to ask if you have any tips or hints for companies
that still haven't made a name for themselves to start up,
to kickstart these communities.
Oh, sure.
Well, to be fair, while we do have a name or a reputation for having made Monaco,
when we opened the alpha initially, it wasn't like a flood of people applied.
Because there are new and interesting games happening all the time.
And we felt like, while we had a small advantage, in the form of about four people off of our Monaco forums.
The first four people who ever joined the alpha were four off the Monaco forums.
That was kind of the initial bump.
And it took a while.
The first, like I mentioned in the talk,
we were IRC before we went to Discord.
The first year was less than 30 individuals in our IRC.
So it took a while.
But those 30 individuals are also the same 30
that are on every day to this day.
And many of them are moderators now.
So the goal here is not to have a huge community.
The goal here is to find the few that really, really
will stay with you the whole time, for years.
And I think that's a very achievable goal,
even if you start from zero,
as long as you tell people where to go
to connect with you.
Because if they don't know where to go,
then they're not going to be able to show you
that they care about your work.
Thank you.
Okay, thanks.
There are some in the open room.
Okay, sure.
Thanks everyone.