Hi, my name is Richard Atlas, and I'm one of the co-founders of Clever Endeavor Games.
We make a game called Ultimate Chicken Horse, which has sold well across many platforms,
garnered over 260 million views on YouTube, got nominated for an IGF award,
won a PlayStation award, and has generally been very well received.
I've been gathering a huge list of questions designed to challenge you and convince you
that we can be better leaders.
This talk is a little different.
It's not a story of success and it's not a story of failure.
It's not going to teach you a specific technical skill.
Rather, it's going to encourage you to look at your situation and force you to answer
some uncomfortable questions about your practices as a leader.
Together, we're going to admit our flaws, think critically about our practices, and
talk to each other about our situations.
We can be better leaders.
So join me on this journey at GDC 2019.