and welcome to our talk about our game subscription
on Patreon.
We're a sockpop collective.
We're a video game collective slash game dev boy band.
We are four game makers based in Utrecht in the Netherlands.
And pictured from left to right, we're
Ruben, who's sitting over there, Diamond, who's standing next
to me, me, who's standing over here,
and Tom, who's sitting over there.
We make a lot of small games.
In fact, last year, we released 26 games in total.
We release these as part of our subscription service on Patreon.
What that means is that people can subscribe to get a new game made by us every two weeks.
We started this Patreon to make money with releasing cool small games so that we can
become sustainable in the long run.
In this talk, we'll explain how we got started,
how we managed to release a new game every two weeks,
how we combine it with working on other projects,
and how our Patreon grew.
To quickly give you an idea what the 26 games are like,
we'll show them to you quickly in this video.
Okay, gotta snipe to start, though.
Okay, there we go.
Suck butt.
We gotta go a little bit fast because there's less minutes in this log than the games we made last year.
Oh, oh no.
Alright, next.
Alright, so now for some Patreon background.
So for the Patreon, you get one game every two weeks
for $3 a month.
However, the games are also available
on our favorite website, itch.io, for $3 each as well.
The Patreon roughly works similar
to a magazine subscription, where if you subscribe,
you only get the new games and the current games,
so you wouldn't get our entire backlog.
of 30 games.
Most of the games are designed to be finished within a single play through, taking roughly
about 50 minutes to one hour to complete.
Right now we have about a thousand patrons, totaling for almost $4,000 a month.
However, this is not our only source of income.
We also do some freelance work and some commission work,
as well as releasing some bigger games that are not
released for the Patreon.
We spend about half our time on the Patreon.
Right, so this should provide some context around the Patreon.
And now we'll discuss how Sockpop was formed.
Yeah.
Yeah, so we met each other roughly around 2014 as young game jammers through mutual
friends and Twitter.
And we often would do game jams at each other's places, especially the Lunumdari one.
And that's basically how we got to really know each other, like the four of us.
And at the end of 2015, we wanted to take things more seriously and spend more time making games, basically go pro, right?
So, there was one big obstacle in the way, which was that we saw that it was getting increasingly harder for game makers and games to stand out from the crowd, as a lot of you must be familiar with.
So we decided to band together under the Sockpop name as a collective.
So not like a traditional studio.
What we would do, we would basically function without being two hands involved
with each other's games, and we'd use our combined forces to be more visible.
And yeah, like that we basically started making a bunch of small, mostly jam games
and releasing them under the Sockpop name.
Yeah, and by making all these small games and posting GIFs of it on Twitter,
we quickly gained a following on there.
Tweets like this one.
And this one.
And Twitter became very important for us.
For a long time, it was basically our main way to communicate and be visible
to the people that liked our work.
And over time, we actually started influencing each other as well
and developed a similar style, I think,
with lots of procedural animations,
cute physics,
and funny interactions.
So yeah, after doing this sock pop thing quite casually
for a couple of years, mostly just running a Twitter account
and sometimes doing showcases,
we were getting to a critical point.
We needed money.
Maybe some of you recognize this problem.
So in order to cope with this problem,
we noticed we had two things.
We had a dedicated, albeit a small, following.
And we were good at making small games fast.
But we had no real idea how to turn that
into cold, hard cash.
Yeah, so we tried to figure out
what maybe could work for us.
The first thing we thought about was maybe turning
our small projects into game dev tutorials,
because that's something a lot of people asked us.
But yeah, we really quickly found out
we don't really want to make tutorials,
we want to make games.
So we decided not to try this.
Then another idea was to make remixed versions of existing games.
So we would basically make them sockpup versions,
but nobody really wanted to give us their source code,
so that didn't really work out.
Yeah, it's too bad.
Then we decided maybe we can try making an album,
like a music album, but instead of sound and music,
there is small games instead.
And we actually tried that.
We released Bamboo Ippie, which is a collection of small bamboo-themed games.
And it really didn't work out too well.
It didn't really sell enough to try something like that.
That was our first time really experimenting with selling a commercial game.
Yeah.
Well, and then someone said to us, well, you're making all these games.
Why don't you just sell them?
And while we thought the games were a bit too small and generally they were unfinished as well,
to even consider selling them, I guess we could see how we could just finish up some rough edges
and maybe try to release them some way or another. And then we found out about Patreon.
So, for those of you who don't know what Patreon is, it's a platform where you can support artists
on a monthly basis.
And when we saw this, we realized that we could use this to create a subscription model
by simply giving those supporters games as a monthly thank you gift.
So we decided, let's try out this Patreon thing.
Yeah, let's just do it.
And at this point we thought, let's just set up a page really quickly,
and you know, get started.
But we kind of underestimated all the work that goes into setting it all up.
In the end, it took us about half a year of part-time work.
And here's a short list of things that we needed to do.
We needed to set up an entire subscription page.
This has nothing in it, so that was still pretty easy.
Then we needed to make a nice banner,
a cool introduction video.
A cool piece of introduction text.
Goals for us all to achieve together,
those are in the bottom left.
And tiers, so you can get the game for $3,
but for example, you can also pay $10
and then you also get the source code,
so you can make a remake version of our games.
Yeah.
We added Discord integration,
which became an important tool for us
to stay in touch with our community.
And then there was a bunch of different thank you texts,
FAQs, help files.
And finally, we built an integration
between itch.io and Patreon,
so that all the Patreons could actually download
the keys they are eligible for.
Yeah.
So that's a short recap of the stuff that we needed to do.
Right.
So another thing we realized is,
in order to make this work,
we kinda had to shift our focus from Twitter.
to Patreon.
Yeah, and this was a hard decision for us to do because at
this point we became somewhat addicted to retweets
and getting followers.
Yeah, someone mentioned that we were a bit of a gif factory
at this point instead of a game studio.
Yeah.
Yeah, but in order to really do this, we kind of had to guide
everyone to the Patreon instead.
So we did this by becoming sellouts.
and putting links and tweets,
and there's a big bubble on our website.
And in more tweets, so when something really blew up,
here's our Patreon.
Yeah.
Yeah, and then the final thing we did,
like the final, final thing,
was the only thing we were actually good at,
which was make a bunch of games.
So we made eight games as a buffer,
in case anything would happen
where we couldn't make a game for the Patreon,
we would have these lined up.
Yeah, so everything was pretty much lined up.
And then the plan was that everyone makes one game
every two months.
We work on it for around two weeks.
So it's like taking a jam game, then polishing that up.
And then we have six weeks left to work on other stuff,
like bigger projects, freelance work, et cetera.
And it seemed like a great plan, so we decided, let's go.
Good plan.
So yeah, we launched on January the 17th with two games.
Bambini, which is a game about bees,
and Yit, a game about trash.
And the launch was quite important for us
because we think it can really set a tone.
So yeah, we decided to give everyone these two games
instead of one as a starter bonus
and started to look more like a real deal.
And based on how other patrons were doing,
we expected to reach about $100 by the end of the month.
which was exceeded to, yeah, it was $500, which was nice.
Yeah, it was really nice, so we decided,
let's start releasing more games.
Yeah, let's do that.
So, Diamond made Dr. Oomgaboom's School of Life.
I made New Colony.
Yeah.
Diamond made another game called King of the Sandcastle,
where basically for the first time we found out
how fun it is to let our patrons fight each other.
Yeah.
Then Tom made Muras.
And we even made the app we named Dino Games.
Yeah, there are dinosaurs in there.
Yeah.
All right, so then it was already April,
because time really kind of flies when you release
a new game every two weeks.
And we noticed a couple things.
The first thing being that we saw that the growth started
plateauing.
We had $500 in the first month, then $650, then $900,
and then a little bit less than $900.
So the first patrons started leaving.
And we were a bit worried that maybe the patron became
old news.
And then it also turned out making the games didn't really take two weeks.
It took more like four weeks.
It wasn't just polishing up a jam game.
So things weren't looking too great at this point, but we weren't going to stop.
So yeah, let's make some more games.
Yeah, just make some more games.
Right.
So Aaron made Driftwood and I made Hoko Poko.
And then someone made TomScape, which is an homage to RuneScape.
And then it's May and all of a sudden,
there is a Polygon video made by Brian Gilbert,
is that person?
And the video really blew up for us.
Yeah, what happened is it basically doubled
our patrons and income.
As you can see in this graph,
yeah, this is kind of what happened.
And we thought that growth halted because our Patreon became old news.
Nobody talked about it anymore.
It's a few months in.
And but in reality, there were still tons of people that haven't even heard about it
and just needed a way to find out about us.
And next to that, we think a lot of people were kind of skeptical.
Like, can they keep up with this breakneck schedule?
Yeah, we're five months in now.
And I think we kind of proved that this was working.
And people started trusting that they would get a new game
every two weeks.
Yeah.
So that was really cool and very motivating.
So hey, we went back to making games.
Yeah.
All right, so Ruben made Kammer.
I made Huts.
Diamond made Zoo Packs.
Tom made Botanique.
And then Ruben made Spider Pawns.
And then I made a game called Llama Villa,
which the tagline was,
it's literally The Sims, but with llamas.
Yeah.
Yeah, you laugh now, but it was kind of annoying
because from this point forward,
patrons kept asking about everything, but with llamas.
And we said no, and then they took the source code
and just replaced sprites with llamas.
Right. So then there was quite an important game for us and it was a game made by Time
and called Simulant. It's a card-based God game where you fulfill mankind's wishes,
like blessing them with fish or spreading the plague.
Simulant, like we said, we also sell the game separately on itch.io and Simulant sold quite
a lot.
Here's a graph.
The red one is a bad Patreon game and it's still separately on itch.io, so it's about $50.
Then green is like $1,000.
That's a good game.
And then I guess Simulant Purple makes it 10 really good games.
Yeah, so it made about 10k in one month, US dollars,
which is pretty good for a game made in four weeks.
So we were really happy.
So let's talk a bit about our rules within Sockwap
about splitting our income,
because that became very relevant at this point.
Yeah.
So for the Patreon games,
what we do is we just split the Patreon
and HAL income equally.
So everybody gets 25% after we spend it on office rent.
This is not our office, by the way.
Ours has more plans.
And then for non-Patreon games, the rules are different.
There, at least 5% goes to Sockbobs.
You can choose not to spend more of your own percentage,
and we use that to spend on events like this,
and submission costs for events, and nice hats and caps.
So yeah, that's our rules regarding splitting income.
Let's make some more games.
Let's do it.
Tom made Hoppa.
And then Ruben made Soco Loco, which is a train simulator.
And then in September, at this point,
we looked back at some statistics,
and we found out that less than 50% of the patrons
were actually downloading the games,
which is kind of weird.
Yeah.
So we were looking up why is this happening.
We found out there are two reasons.
One of them is people were downloading the games in bursts.
So since the games were so short,
what a lot of the people were doing
is just download a few of them
and play all of them in one evening.
And the other reason is maybe a bit more interesting.
We found out that a lot of them didn't support us
for the games, but also for us and who we are.
And I think with the amazing amount of games
that come out nowadays, people start realizing
that video games are being made by humans and not robots.
And maybe how people will follow their favorite musicians.
they will also start following their favorite game designers.
Found out if they have a nice dog or cat.
So inspired by that, we started making videos with us in it
so people could get to know us a little bit better.
And yeah, we talked about why we made the game,
what was our inspiration, yeah, et cetera.
Oh, and another thing that happened
is we reached our halfway goal, which
made us very happy, as you might be able to see.
We did a little live stream.
Yeah, and then came infamous game number 20,
the game we don't talk about.
It's Oh Crap.
It was more like, oh crap, we have no more games to release.
So we ran out the buffer we talked about at the start.
So we had the eight games.
But because sometimes we restarted,
or sometimes making the games longer,
we basically had no games lying around.
And we had no time to make a new one,
because we were busy with other projects.
So.
So this was the first time where we needed to figure out a solution, really.
And we had this old game lying around called O'Crab,
which we made together in 2017, and we decided,
well, we basically have to release this because we have nothing else.
And we thought, oh no, the Patreons are going to be really mad,
and it turned out, oh, it's not too bad.
They understood that we didn't sleep for eight months, so it was okay.
It was actually a really interesting moment, because we realized...
Yeah, the next time this would happen.
we were screwed.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah.
But we were basically forced to finish
every game we started now,
which put a little bit more pressure on us,
but it's also nice because that would really make sure
that we don't spend too much time making these Patreon games.
And we also realized, well, maybe a bad idea
always has something good.
Like if you make a Patreon game and about halfway through,
you're like, I'm not sure what to do with this.
And there's always something you can zoom in on
that will make it fun.
And even in the case that people really didn't like one of the games, they would realize,
well I paid about $1.50 for this, and yeah, I'll get a brand new different thing in two
weeks, which will probably not be O'Crab.
Probably not.
And they weren't.
This is Fisser, made by Aram, and then I made Döller.
Tom made Frog Struggles.
And then Aaron made Skidlock, which is a game about cycling.
Very fast, very city. Don't get hit.
And then it's already December and the year's almost gone by.
Goes really fast.
And at this point, some of the small games
started to become big.
So what we did is a few of the patron games
that we and or the people who played it especially liked,
we started developing them into bigger versions
and basically doing full releases of them.
And I think this is an interesting workflow
since the patron games are actually
minimum viable products, or we call them small versions.
And with this, we create some basic income while doing this.
And we can test the game design of the game, but also
the commercial viability.
So for example, with Similand, I legit thought that the game
sucked, I didn't like it at all.
But then the people who played it loved it, and especially
YouTubers did, which generated a lot of visibility for it.
So I knew that if I would make a bigger version.
Yeah, it would definitely do at least something.
So there wasn't a big leap of faith anymore
for me to do this project.
Yeah.
And while we were working on bigger versions,
of course we released some more games.
So.
Newman made Kraken Scourge,
and then the final game of the year I made,
it's called Clutchball.
And yeah, that's all. Before you know it, we released 26 games in one year.
Yeah.
And I think our biggest accomplishment was not getting burned out.
We were really scared this would happen, as releasing a game every two weeks creates a lot of pressure.
But we tried to take our rest in the evenings and weekends as much as we could.
And we helped each other really out by working in the same space and talking about the games a lot.
We have a weekly meeting where we try to be really professional about everything,
but it's 9 out of 10 times it's just us chilling in the sun.
And I think that's really nice.
Like, we really helped each other a lot that way.
And then we also tried to stick to our own rules.
Like the first rule we had was, like,
make the game in two weeks.
Well, it turned out that really didn't work.
But once we had the four-weeks rule,
we really kept to that and make sure
that you're not constantly in this sort of high-pressure mode
of working.
And then you have these four weeks to work a little bit more
chill on your big project.
So that was basically that.
Now for some future and some challenges
that we're still facing with the Patreon.
Yeah, so this is our graph at the moment.
So for the last couple of months,
we had a quite steady increase of about $200 a month.
But I'm not sure if you can see this, but every time there's this little spike, it starts
declining after, and right before that happens, there's another spike.
And I tried to draw it, but I don't think you can read it that well.
But every time it has a big reason why that spike was there.
And every spike has a totally different event to it.
So we are not sure if these events will keep popping up
or we're basically out of control.
Yeah, a lot of these events always seemed like
they were out of our control and we,
they just popped up out of nowhere.
Yeah, just random.
Yeah, and then we want to reach the purple line, which is $5,000 a month, which will really
cover almost all expenses that we have now at the moment.
Yeah, and then another thing we do is we release some bigger projects, hopefully.
Yeah, so separately from the Patreon, Tom is working on Burnband, I'm working on a bigger
version of Skidlocked, and Ruben is working on a bigger version of SocoLoco. And the question is,
will these games do well, especially the Patreon games? Because if they do, that would really
establish this workflow for us where we have this sort of minimum viable product and then work on
it more and then sell that. So I think that would be really cool to see. And then, yeah,
I think that's going to be nice.
Yeah, at this point, we've already released 32 games.
This is our latest one called Card Kids.
Yeah, we hope we've given you some insights about how
we've run our Patreon.
And maybe you'll even consider doing your own small game
subscription.
I think we'd love to see more people do it.
Yeah, if you have any other questions,
feel free to reach out to us on Twitter or via email
or in real life.
Thank you for your attention.
Appreciate it.
Thank you.
Thank you, Aaron and Taimin.
We actually have time for one or two questions.
There's mics over there.
So if you have any questions
for Taimin or Aaron right now, you can go up, yeah.
Hi, thanks, guys, great talk.
Do you have any advice for keeping small games like this
narrowly scoped and not sort of getting lost?
Even if you have a month, I imagine that you could have an
opportunity to really dig into mechanics or art or
something deeper.
How do you maintain a consistent level of polish
without going overboard?
So the question was, how do we keep our scopes small so that
the games don't become too big to make in four weeks?
Yeah, well, in our case, since we're this collective,
say you were having too big of a scope
and we do this weekly meeting outside in the sun,
the other three of us will get angry at you and be like,
no, don't do that.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think that's how we do it.
Kind of how it goes and also.
We try to start with the base first and then just keep adding stuff that would make sense.
Yeah, at some point we're like, alright, so you have one week left, try to wrap up at least the full game loop.
And then, well, you can always polish some things in the end, in your final week.
Hey, I'm Tana, I really enjoyed the talk, it was cool.
One thing I wanted to ask is that you guys mentioned
not having burnout, and you also mentioned
your four-week cycles.
Is that based on like a 40-hour work week,
or do you just kind of work until stuff gets done?
Right, so the question was that,
if we work a 48-hour work, a 40-hour work week, basically.
Yeah, like pretty much, I'd say most of us
are at the office from.
10 to 6, but not all the time is spent working.
So yeah, I think that's based on that.
Sometimes more, sometimes less.
Yeah, thanks.
Hi, Averro, it was a great talk, by the way.
Oh, sorry.
We'll do both.
Yes.
Cool.
I was just wondering, if you guys set that guideline for once
you come up with an idea and you start working on it,
you have to finish it, how do you
avoid getting stuck on those games
and feeling kind of burnt out over them?
So how do we avoid getting stuck on the games when you have these guidelines?
I think actually it happens sometimes where with a game you're like after three weeks
of working on it then you're like well I'm kind of done with it but at this point we
basically don't have really any other option so we just have to finish it and then...
I think a lot of those cases where it happened, then afterwards we were still pretty happy with those games.
Yeah.
So like maybe at that point, for example this game, when you said a couple of weeks ago, I was like...
This one?
Yeah, this one.
Yeah.
So I was like, not sure if it's any good, but now I'm like, that's pretty fun, people liked it.
Well, I think what we do is we playtest it a lot with friends.
And then you'll notice, alright, so this thing is what they like.
This thing is fun, and then the other thing, which I thought was gonna be fun,
is stupid. So I'll just kick it out.
The four of you mentioned that all four of your styles kind of converged into the sock pop style.
Did each one of you bring something different? Like someone had the animation,
someone had the physics, or was it kind of like one person had it?
So if our style was like the, the question is if this, our style is the combined forces of us four.
Combined efforts.
Yeah. I don't know, I think Tom really, Tom has always had super cool colors and that's kind of really inspired me.
Yeah, I think we, when you really look at it closely, we all do have our own strengths.
But yeah, there are so many things that we've learned from each other.
And I think at some point, Ruben and Tom were talking about how you do knees on legs.
On procedural animation.
Yeah.
And I did that at the same point as well.
We were like, yeah, knees.
They're great.
Yeah, knees.
Thank you.
It's the bees' knees.
All right.
Last two questions.
Yeah, I'm curious how much of your guys' time is spent on the boilerplate of the game development and the distribution and stuff in the four weeks that you spend on a game.
Right. So the question is, how much time do we spend in that four-week cycle on promoting and marketing materials, etc.?
Yeah, yeah. And just on some of the...
parts of preparing a game to be launched and stuff,
rather than developing the game.
Yeah, I think the answer to that is quite simple.
It just takes one full day.
Yeah, it's like roughly one full day.
Yeah, so the video takes like an afternoon and then.
making a video, doing...
There's actually a long list in our Trello board
that explains everything you have to do.
Yeah, that's like a full day of work.
But it's not very fun to talk about.
It's like, oh, make a Mac build, make sure that this setting is...
Don't think about it.
All right, one more question.
Hey.
One of the things I love about your guys' games is that you have this style that you have as a group.
And I'm curious how much of a reusable code base and tool sets and assets that you use...
from game to game. I'm assuming because you have this consistent style now, you probably have some stuff that you can start with and not have to build literally everything from scratch every time.
So how much of our assets are shared between different projects?
Yeah, and just in general, how much you reuse them from project to project.
I think it's less than you would think it would be.
Normally what I do is I think about which game
had a certain thing and then try to find the script.
It doesn't really work well.
I don't know how you do it.
Yeah, sometimes I share code with Ruben, I think.
Yeah.
I think it's mostly code because sometimes
Ruben takes ballots from other games, right?
Okay, no, no, it's what he said.
But no, it's a lot less than.
Yeah, to some degree, yeah, obviously.
And then there's a lot of stuff we do over and over again.
Yeah, it's mostly about, I think,
the techniques that we reuse,
and then the techniques itself are not that much code,
or it's always a little bit different.
But the legs, we always do the legs from scratch,
because you get the unique walk cycle.
Yeah, exactly.
Right. I think that's it.