Okay, hi everybody.
I'm thrilled to be here.
I, uh, actually, I'm kind of honored to be here
because I'm totally honored to be here.
I never in a million years would have expected,
uh, that 20 years ago when we made Myst,
um, anybody would be interested in it 20 years later.
So this is pretty incredible.
Um, so, um, I get started.
Thank you all for coming.
It makes me feel old.
Postmortem.
This is what a name.
I want to go back to a little earlier than NIST.
Um...
In 1984, when...
1984 was just a little bit after the Mac was created.
So it was four years later.
and Rand and I were in different places.
Rand was in Texas, my brother,
and I should say that Rand Miller,
my brother, and I'm Robin Miller,
and we were the guys who made Myst,
just in case anybody was here.
Wow.
I just like had this feeling inside me of just
utter confidence.
Wow.
I want to bring you home with me now.
In 1988, Rand was in Texas, I was in Washington State,
and he called me and said,
I've got this idea for this interactive storybook.
I, like, wasn't interested really in this,
but he was really into computers,
I kind of wasn't.
I didn't have a computer, in fact.
He wanted to send me this thing called HyperCard,
which he did.
And I went into my parents' basement.
They had a computer in their basement.
And I started working on, I started drawing a manhole cover.
That was like part, the first part of the story.
I don't know why I drew a manhole cover.
And I continued drawing a linear story.
I drew the manhole cover open.
And I just like continued drawing sequentially
this storybook.
But I got to this vine growing out of the manhole.
And I didn't know what I wanted to do at that point.
I didn't know if I wanted to go up the vine or down into the manhole.
And from there, it just, the medium itself became non-linear.
And it's as if the medium was calling out to be non-linear.
It was not, it was not something that we really invented.
at that point in time, or really were trying to do,
it was just...
it just happened on its own.
So that was the manhole in 1988.
And then we continued making these games
that had all the same qualities, one after the other.
And you saw that last... those screens before,
they were black and white.
Totally, totally simple.
There were a lot of kids' games, and they...
Point and click, first person point of view.
And the player as the main character.
You didn't have an avatar or anything like that.
You just sort of were in the world,
and you were the person in that world wandering around.
You also had this quality of everything being explorable.
In the manhole, not so much.
But then later on,
we kind of realized as we would watch people play...
that people would see a door and they would definitely want to go through that door.
But if people saw something like a forest in the distance, well, they wanted to go to that forest.
If people saw, no matter what it was, a drawer, anything,
they wanted to be able to explore the entire world.
They didn't want any boundaries to that world.
And so we attempted as much as possible to create no boundaries.
Now...
Nowadays, almost every game is, they're just mammoth.
They pretty much have no boundaries.
Back then, it was a little different.
We got to a point around 1990 where we had this idea that,
hey, let's make one of these worlds for grown-ups,
for an older audience.
And we wanted to add something a little bit more like a story,
a non-linear story.
And we wanted to make the player like a protagonist.
We wanted believable characters.
And we wanted the player as the protagonist
to make some sort of ethical choice
between right and wrong.
We thought that would really create
an interesting story of some sort.
There'd be an emotional provocation.
So we created the Grey Summons.
we created the idea of the Grey Summons and we proposed it to Activision
and uh... Activision
told us to stick to children's games
which really uh...
was
disheartening
we were not doing very well at that point in time
uh...
and so I mean and we were really not doing very well we were eating and I'm
not exaggerating
We were eating rice and beans and government cheese, and that's like, that was our diet.
We were probably very healthy.
A lot more healthy than I am today.
But this was, I mean, this was the end of, potentially the end of our career in gaming.
And I think, though, as a matter of fact, I know, we had learned so much, we had gleaned
so much from what we had done up to that point.
everything we had done in those earlier products,
we took and we folded into what became Myst,
which I'll talk about in just a little bit.
It was almost at that exact point,
or a little afterwards, that Sunsoft of Japan
came to us and said,
hey, we've got this great idea.
We would like you to make a game for an older audience.
Just like, you know, you've been doing, except not for kids, okay?
Because we don't want you to do that anymore.
We want you to make something, but for, you know, like, everybody else.
And so, it was, it blew our minds, and we were on board totally.
We just had no idea, you know, what to do in terms of that.
It was 1991. I'm just, like, giving you a sense of what time this was, okay?
This guy was around. This was, like, the, one of the most popular movies of the year.
These were cell phones, and we couldn't afford them.
And this was the internet, and we couldn't afford it.
So we didn't know at all what to do in terms of our game.
But we knew what we, we kind of knew what we wanted it to be.
At that point was a nonlinear story again.
believable characters.
We wanted advanced graphics.
Much more advanced graphics than we had been doing.
We didn't know what that meant at all.
Um...
In fact, we thought we would probably be
hand-drawing the graphics.
So Myst, for a while at that point,
was gonna be all hand-drawn.
Um...
And it was intimidating to, like, think.
OK, we're gonna make this game.
It's gonna be really advanced graphics,
but we're gonna have to draw it all.
In, you know, how, what would that mean?
And some sort of puzzles.
We didn't, what would the puzzles be?
And then again, some sort of ethical choice.
That was really intimidating.
What would this ethical choice be?
Mystery. We knew, OK, yeah.
It's gonna be a mystery.
just to go through some inspirations that were behind Myst,
D&D.
Growing up, our brother, not Rand, not me,
but our other brother played a lot of D&D.
And so we were kind of surrounded by that a bit.
He would get all of his friends together at least once a week.
they would sit and play it. And so, Ran and I were able to observe, when there's a really
good dungeon master, you get this thing where it's like, you know, a great story can happen.
It's creative. It's fun. It can be a blast. And maybe not so much with a bad dungeon master,
but, you know, it can be a really cool and adventuresome and exploratory, you know,
cool thing. In fact, Rand created his own dungeon at one point in time. He wanted to
do that. And what he threw out was rolling to create your characters and rolling for
your dexterity, rolling for your strength, rolling for these other aspects of your character.
And he said, okay, you guys are going to play this and you're just going to be yourselves.
Use your own intelligence and just observe within this universe.
And in fact, he never used dice at all.
He just told people what they saw within that universe.
If you look, there's one drawing over here.
And it's Ran's dungeon.
A drawing from Ran's dungeon.
When we were creating Myst,
we got to the very last age we were designing.
It was the Mechanical Age.
And if you notice a similarity...
It's, we used this as a part of the design.
We kind of like, what are we going to do for this last age?
Oh, let's get out that old dungeon you designed, Rand.
Zork.
We, we had played Zork.
Rand had played both the Zorks.
There was, there was all kinds of other video games before Myst, obviously, but...
We hadn't had a lot of experience with those other video games.
We had played those Zork games.
And I had played like half of Zork 2.
It was incredibly cool.
Rand had played both of them.
And they were definitely an inspiration for us.
Because they were these non-linear worlds.
So...
I'm just going to quickly go through, you know,
Star Wars, of course.
The world there.
from a very early time, it was the myth behind that universe
was deeply inspirational.
Portals to other universes,
we took almost directly from the Chronic Zinarnia.
And then Jules Verne, the idea of an island.
we took from Mysterious Island and then just old books.
You know, we kind of stole that idea.
You know, we stole a lot of things, in a way.
I don't know if all creativity is kind of stealing in a sense.
Okay, pre-production.
I don't know where we got the idea for Two Brothers.
It had to be subconscious on some sense, on some level.
Um...
But we went with two brothers.
Oh, this is interesting.
Oh, when Sunsoft came to us, they said, look,
what we're going with is game machines.
That's what we want, guys.
You take everything else.
We don't want all the PC stuff.
That's not valuable.
What we think is valuable is game machines.
So it's like, great.
We got all the PC stuff.
And they went with game machines.
But game machines, at that time, had no hard drive buffer.
and very small memory buffer.
So we had to design around that for Mist.
That was an interesting design restriction.
So how do we design around that?
We had to load different pieces of Mist.
We had to compartmentalize Mist,
which we did by making creating ages.
This works really well for design.
Probably a lot of game makers have discovered this along the way.
A lot of designers have discovered this along the way as well.
Just to fit pieces of a thing in your mind,
to know there's one central place.
If you think of wandering around Disneyland,
you always know there's that central location.
And then you go out to all these different areas
and you always feel like, yeah, OK.
I can always, no matter what, if I get lost...
I can always go back to that central location.
In fact, we had on an earlier product
that we had done,
done the same exact thing.
We'd had this ship, went around to all these planets.
You can always very easily get back to that central ship.
So we were kind of used to that idea.
But I'm not...
I don't know if we would have done that on Myst
had there not been that memory restriction.
It was something that we did,
and it worked out really well.
Puzzles. I actually hadn't put this part into my presentation
until last night. I was in an interview and somebody asked me,
oh, how'd you come up with puzzles? Completely forgot about it.
We had an idea when we created Myst that most people don't like puzzles.
Gamers love puzzles. But we weren't creating Myst for gamers.
We were creating the game for, essentially, non-gamers.
And non-gamers don't like puzzles.
So a good puzzle shouldn't feel like a puzzle.
It should feel very familiar and not arbitrary.
It should have a sense that it's just a part of the world
and that it's just something you're just figuring out
because it's, you know, it's like a throne breaker in your house.
You know, what happens when the electricity goes out?
Well, you go and...
you know, you switch the breaker back on.
And so we kind of did that as much as possible in Myst.
Now, we created some bad puzzles in Myst,
but we also made some good ones.
And so to a certain extent,
I think Myst works because of that.
In fact, we made some really bad puzzles in Myst.
There's one or two that just are, that suck.
But there's some that are pretty good.
So you solve a good puzzle.
You're able to solve a good puzzle
with just observation and basic common sense.
So here's an arbitrary puzzle that we did in Myst.
Not good.
This one is not arbitrary at all.
And if you remembered, if you played Myst...
It was just the windmill that pumps water up from the sea,
and you've got this container full of water,
and then there's the water pressure that powers everything on the island.
It's really just...
Maybe it doesn't feel like a puzzle at all.
It just feels like you're trying to power stuff on the island.
And then you've got this puzzle where you're just trying to...
You've got a chest at the bottom of this lighthouse,
and it's stuck down there.
It's got something in it.
You've got to bring the water up inside the lighthouse.
It's definitely a surreal environment.
But the puzzle itself doesn't necessarily feel so arbitrary.
OK.
While we were designing, this was so great for us.
We had no fans.
We had no demographic.
No sales projections.
No outside expectations of any sort.
So it's like we just had a ton of fun.
We didn't have to second guess any of our choices.
We just got to explore the world as we were designing,
which was fantastic.
It was really, really...
I think it was a rare experience.
I don't know how often people get to really do that.
We literally were just...
We were creating this world for ourselves, and...
I think...
That was one of the reasons Mist did well, is because we made it for ourselves.
And that all really took place during the design. A lot of it took place during the design.
You know, just having fun with it. We got to have a lot of fun with it.
So much so, and this is an example of that in just even the name. I don't know, it's like a
30-second phone call, where it's just like, hey, what should we name it? How about Mist? Okay, good.
You know.
Whereas, like, Riven, I don't know.
The Riven, it took months to name Riven.
So, because there was multiple people involved,
multiple companies involved.
It's just the difference.
This is, once we had totally designed it,
we came up with a proposal.
These are pages from the proposal.
Kind of interesting.
Brought it back to Sunsoft.
They said, great, we love it, let's go with it.
That's the original budget for Myst.
We came up with the amount we thought it would cost.
We doubled it, added some more.
Ha.
Um...
Then we got together.
We had hired a couple people,
and we play-tested it in a D&D fashion.
And we did that because we wanted to find
any big problems with the game.
So it's like, okay, you're standing on a dock.
This is off to your right. This is in front of you.
And we found issues with the game at that point.
It really worked incredibly well.
So I recommend that.
It was excellent for us.
Worked well.
Production.
There's some things in this production
that aren't really production.
I don't know.
There's kind of little of both production
and pre-production, but...
We had a lot of questions
about how do we resolve certain things
in production.
like our advanced graphics,
our protagonist who makes this so-called ethical choice,
our believable characters, and this non-linear plot.
Our advanced graphics, like I said,
we were gonna hand-draw the whole thing,
and I did spend some time toward the beginning
just like in Photoshop.
I was drawing things, and I got really scared,
thinking, oh my God, what have we gotten ourselves into?
There's no way. I can't draw all this stuff.
This is, like, this is gonna look crappy.
And so, um, and then...
I got out Stratavision,
and I started drawing, um...
basically gray scale, you know, extrusion maps.
You don't know what an extrusion map is.
It isn't important.
It was this kind of thing that kind of looked like this.
And color maps.
And I made something that looked like Myst Island.
And I was able to create an island.
That's all that's important.
Once I created an island, a single island,
then we knew, okay, we can make a 3D world.
And it was like, from that point on...
We were home free and we knew the world was gonna look very, very different.
And cinematic. And we were thrilled.
And then we went to town, you know, creating these worlds.
Now right there, that screen you see is 920x1080. I've stretched it. I've made it very big.
The actual size of Myst was more like that size.
That was the gameplay size. So it was a very tiny resolution.
We were able to do that. The shots took between 2 to 14 hours to render each shot.
So the more complex shots, and we had to like do things like hide everything on the island except exactly what you were looking at.
The protagonist of Coerce is whoever's playing the game.
And they got this whole...
ethical decision thing. It was just, for us, it was as simple as choosing one of the brothers.
It was one was good and one was evil. And at that point, we hadn't added this other
choice.
As far as believable characters, we had some real problems there. Because there was this
issue of one-way communication. When you're playing this, the other characters, any characters
you meet, they communicate to you.
They communicate to you, and you don't get to communicate to them.
Yes!
Bless you.
And you're in a non-linear world.
At any point in time, while this person is talking to you, you can just walk away.
It totally breaks the spell of believability.
As well, we had no method of displaying video at that point in time.
When we began the game, when we began production, QuickTime did not exist.
So there were some ways.
to display something like video,
they just weren't really that...
they didn't do it very well.
So, we thought we needed to design around these limits.
And in terms of a one-way communication,
you know, with whatever characters you come across,
them speaking.
in this sort of monologue style,
we tried to feature it as much as possible
with a one-way device of some sort.
In terms of a nonlinear world,
again, we tried to feature that problem.
And we'd say that all the time.
Randall and I would always say,
don't fix it as much as feature it.
But we tried to feature that nonlinear world
with some sort of location-based device, you know.
And both of those issues we featured
with the books that they were in.
So you had to go there
and you had to be in that location,
and they were in these little books.
QuickTime came along halfway through development,
which was...
Oh my God, when it came along, we were so thrilled.
We needed it.
So with them, in these books, it was almost like a barrier existed naturally between you
and the book.
these characters. It was okay for you to walk away from them
because there was almost a screen or plate of glass between you and them
and they were fading in and out all the time and if you had come across them in the real
world it would be okay to walk away from them.
That's kind of it. It felt more believable in that respect.
So we wanted to make something that felt as believable as possible.
It feels really not very believable when a character's standing there talking to you
and you turn around and walk away.
Or when a character's standing there talking to you
and you can't say anything back to them.
In this sort of scenario, they didn't expect you to talk to them
because they couldn't have heard you anyway.
Plot.
Okay.
Our plot was set up in, basically like the islands were set up.
Very simple style of plot.
If I were to outline it, this is basically what it would have looked like in the beginning
when we had first designed the game.
It was something that anybody, or at least us designing the game, could have fit in our
heads, that we could, that we did fit in our minds very easily.
So...
It made us happy.
Um...
I'm just going to compare it
against the flowchart
for Riven's plot.
There was...
It was so complex,
we never could keep it straight.
Um...and, um...
I think, um...
As the developers of Riven,
it made it frustrating to work on, for one thing.
It also wasn't contained,
and you couldn't just sit there and imagine the story
from beginning to end as you had experienced it.
Like, what is this contained plot?
So...
Whereas Myst, you could think, oh, okay, this was the story.
This was bum, bum, bum, A plus B, B, you know, this is,
and it was, so it was, it was, it was, again,
looking back in hindsight, I think it was another reason
why, why Myst was successful.
Climactic ending, this was something that came later
after our initial design.
Ta-da!
That's my effect, it's not an audio presentation.
Atrus.
We realized at a certain point in time that we needed
this other sort of character at the ending.
Because people just choosing between the two brothers was not enough.
They needed something more toward the ending.
And so we realized that this father would make that choice more complex.
And...
And so we added Atrus.
And so it just changed the ending
to something that looked a little bit more like this.
And in terms of this whole ethical decision...
aspect of the game and an emotional provocation,
you know, I think it had that.
I'm not sure if we really succeeded so much,
as much as we wanted to.
You know, I know there's games today that...
that really emotionally provoke,
we attempted it,
and...
and we did our best
to emotionally provoke people.
And I think instead, it was a fun game.
But it was an effort.
Technical limitations.
This is kind of interesting.
A single-speed CD-ROM,
it was slow.
A single-speed CD-ROM is really, really slow.
And so we were dealing...
with slow enough speeds
that we had to carefully lay out the island
or the islands on by hand
onto the disk.
So, you know, Mist Island,
and this is kind of an exaggeration.
I mean, it's totally an exaggeration,
but, uh, Mist Island would go here,
for example, Stone Ship Age,
and then so on.
But even more than that, you know,
we would say you've got all the shots
and animations along this path.
They would all go together in one place.
Or likewise, the shots in this location.
So if we hadn't have done that, you know,
the speed of the CD-ROM just wouldn't have...
we wouldn't have been able to...
from the drive fast enough for anybody to play this game.
Okay, distribution.
I think this is kind of interesting,
just for us, just as a memory.
We did show it to a couple of people,
but we were working with Broderbund at the time.
And, you know, we had all these images of the first island,
and this was what we showed to Broderbund
when we first sat down with them.
when we finally sat down with them, and they were like,
they loved it.
And that's who we went with for Myst.
And they said to us,
and I think it was soon after that,
they said to us, look,
why don't you try music with this?
And we were not real keen on that idea.
There weren't a lot of video games out with music.
At that point, I don't remember exactly what video games
had music in them.
What we liked was diegetic music,
and that was something we had been doing in our previous games.
So, you know, for example, you walk into a radio station,
you go in there, you pull some tapes into...
You program the radio station,
and then you go to another place where there's a radio,
and you hear the music that you've programmed.
So we felt like if you had soundtrack...
It would seem false.
It would just pull you out of the environment.
Um, because, you know, music doesn't play in the real world,
and so why would it play in this place
that we're trying to make it be so believable and so real?
Um, and so we said,
okay, well, we're gonna write some music,
and we're gonna put it in Mist,
and we're gonna show you how wrong you are.
And so we did that.
We wrote some music, and we put it in Mist,
and instead, like, it really worked well.
And so...
So it's like, great, okay, well now we need to write a soundtrack.
And so we did that.
And, um...
In terms of post-production...
Oh, okay, this was, this is good.
Um...
We did pretty extensive game testing.
Where we would put two people in front of the game,
and we put, we always did it with two people,
because two people, um...
would talk to one another.
Whenever we would sit one person in front of the game,
they would just like play, play, play,
you know, find a mistake or whatever.
But we would sit two people
so they could talk to one another
and then we could hear whatever they didn't like or did like.
And which, like, you know, we would sit back there.
And when I say we would sit back there behind them
or stand back there behind them,
it was Rand and I standing behind them
writing notes, extensive notes.
And whatever, you know, whatever they would talk about.
whatever they didn't like, or, you know. And, and then we were able to change things on
the fly. So, like, if they're here, and they clicked here to go to the planetarium, it's
like, OK, great, we didn't make that work because this is the button to go to the planetarium.
We could just step in immediately and we could fix that. And so this was, like, vitally,
vitally important.
Because we made... we wanted the game to be accessible
by everyone.
And if they clicked on something and it didn't work,
well, that was something... that was our problem.
That was, like, you know, that was something we had done wrong.
And so we spent a lot of time doing this kind of testing.
We wanted the interface of the game
to be totally, totally invisible
and... and playable by...
not necessarily by gamers.
We didn't make the game for gamers.
We wanted it to be playable by non-gamers.
And so we played it with a lot of non-gamers.
And so that, I can't stress how much that helped us.
It also showed us that there were problems
with the story and setting up the game.
We...
Like, we didn't have what I guess we call an inciting incident.
Like, we put this note.
We put this note in the beginning of the game.
Um, it hadn't had it previous to this,
so we added it.
And it introduced people
to this new thing we added,
a door right by the dock.
And a message from our main...
character now, this person Atrus.
And Atrus now gives the player a message
and sends them on their quest.
So people, you know, before this was added,
people didn't know what to do.
It was something like this playtesting,
this kind of playtesting,
where Rand and I were directly involved
for long, long periods of time,
really gave us a lot of vital information.
Here's our new flowchart with the floor chamber.
OK, last thing I'm going to quickly touch on here is we did this focus group testing.
And this is something Broderbund did, and we just thought, what?
Focus group testing?
I just think it's kind of funny and interesting, and they brought this one group in, and we
were like, what?
Oh, no, they hated the game.
The first group hated the game.
And, oh, man.
It was really discouraging.
And they brought Group 2 in, and man, this group just,
they loved it.
And I think that was the first time Rand and I got this sense
that, wow, this might sell like 100,000 copies.
You know, maybe we'll make our money back,
or maybe we can do another game after this.
We were so happy.
There was a guy there, Bruce Fredericks.
I don't know, I don't know what he's doing now.
He showed slogans.
And so he showed a bunch of slogans to these guys
at the focus group testing.
He showed, one of the slogans he showed.
And I, oh god, I hated that.
No.
So it's such a sale.
And you know, over the years, I've just like.
become your world.
So.
OK, well that's it.
You know?
I don't have.
Thank you.
Thanks.
So questions?
So, I was curious, so you mentioned a figure of $265,000.
And you were saying that you asked for an amount and then you doubled it,
or they gave you double what you asked for, or something.
What was the first number you asked for and then got?
Okay, great question.
We came up with an amount, we doubled it, then added some more,
and that end figure was $265,000.
Oh, yeah, well, we actually spent more than that.
But, you know, if only it had occurred to us that,
hey, you can go back to the people who are paying it
and ask for more.
Oh, you know, it never occurred to us.
So we were, like, really thinly stretched
during the development of the thing.
And, yeah.
I don't... the answer to your question is,
I don't remember what it actually cost.
Right.
Were you, so it looks like you used HyperCard to make this.
Did you have to totally hack it like crazy,
or was it like out of the box HyperCard?
Yeah.
The question was, did we have to hack HyperCard like crazy?
Because we used HyperCard to create this game.
We didn't have to hack it like crazy,
but we did have a couple of x commands.
And one of the x commands we used was to have,
the main x command we used was to do color in HyperCard.
But mostly, no, it was pretty straightforward.
I mean...
It, I mean, we were able to.
I would kind of say that if HyperCard hadn't have existed,
I don't know how we would have ever made Myst
because, or any of our previous products.
It was so...
It allowed us to do things so quickly.
Even like the play testing I mentioned.
where we could just stay there and watch people.
If they clicked on something, we could just, boom, pop in,
change something instantaneously.
HyperCard was amazing.
Kind of funny, when I was putting together
this little presentation, I was using Apple Keynote.
It reminded me so much of using HyperCard.
Not quite the same thing, but yeah, HyperCard was.
An amazing tool, you know, I wish something like that still existed,
except that you could, like, put things up online with,
but it was just an amazing tool for us.
Could you please briefly discuss the design process behind the bathysphere?
What?
The bathysphere. ...
Really hard.
Oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh.
Okay, yeah.
That was our worst puzzle.
Yes, it was.
You know, okay, the design process on that,
originally, you walked through it.
So all the drawings we have are, like, pathways,
and then, um, like, little...
pagoda things that you get to.
And you, you, so it was like this huge,
almost labyrinthian maze.
Um, and it looked really cool in our heads.
Um, but then when we got to the production,
we realized, oh, my, how will we possibly create it?
In fact, we, we started, Chuck Carter was the one
who, who, who made all that.
And we, he started actually...
making it and then we realized, oh, this is going to be this massively huge thing. How
are we going to do this? And it's going to be cumbersome to play. Because you're going
to be walking forever and, but, but you know, you actually find your way through it with
sounds. We failed on that one totally. That's the answer. So, that's one of those arbitrary
things we made. That's the worst puzzle in the game.
Oh, um...
I just wanted to say I played Myst in the fourth grade
in the computer lab, and it literally has changed my life.
It's probably why I'm actually here
instead of, I don't know, being a lawyer or something stupid.
Um...
So thank you for that.
Um, my question, did you go into the production
knowing Stratavision, or did you have to learn it
sort of as you went?
Um, before in some of our previous products,
um, kind of, you know,
There was something we did called Spelunx, and we had in little pieces, little bits here and there, I had used it.
We got to know it really well in NIST.
So...
And it was simple. It was a very simple program as well.
Very easy to learn.
Take one from the backseat mics way back here.
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, you got two sets.
Back there.
Hi, Robin.
I'm Ryan from Untold Entertainment.
I build adventure games.
Thanks so much for making Myst.
It was an inspiration for sure.
Thank you.
Speaking of inspiration, it was really fascinating to me that you listed...
Is there a weird echo on this thing or what?
It was interesting that you listed D&D as an inspiration, but you never mentioned the
third...
person graphic adventure games with a lot of inventory manipulation.
Were those not even on your radar?
Like, did you guys ever play them?
Third person...
Sierra stuff, LucasArts stuff?
Not really on the radar.
Wow.
We just, we didn't play them.
Um...
Yeah.
I had never played any of them.
Now, maybe Rand had played some of those,
or, you know, some of those,
but I hadn't played any of those.
Yeah, I think the only game I ever played,
previous to Myst, was probably Zork 2.
Um...
And, and then I just, you know,
and that wasn't really my interest.
Games, I didn't like, I didn't like games.
I didn't play games.
Now, I play a lot more games.
That's wild.
So, yeah.
Um, how about way in the back over there?
man in audience 1 Hi. First, thank you very much. Beautiful game. It sounded like you
had some really creative approaches to game testing, and we just kind of scratched the
surface with you. And I specifically thought it was really interesting when you said you
watched, not just watch to see what people would click on, but how kind of you would
react to that. And I wondered if you had more to say about that, like what your expectations
were going in.
and kind of how those shaped your design process
for the puzzles.
Um...yeah, I mean, not...
just that, you know, we really wanted this to be a game
that, you know, um...
We didn't have a target audience,
and we just really wanted it to be a game
that a very wide group of people
could play and enjoy.
And the interface, in terms of the interface,
the interface was extremely important to us.
That it kind of feel like it not have an interface.
So we just tested that again and again and again.
So...
That was, you know, we...
that testing was extremely, extremely important to us to make sure.
You know, the game feels like there is an interface,
and we wanted it to feel cinematic in a sense,
with no computerized elements.
Computerized.
And, um...
And so we designed around that.
You know, there's...
You know, whenever Rand and I, during design, were tempted to...
to give it the cinematic feel as much as possible.
Because we know there's an audience out there.
We knew at the time there was an audience out there
that is kind of...
So, and then the testing, I don't know.
I don't know what I'm saying.
I don't know if that answers your question.
Ha ha ha!
Okay. I was just curious, you mentioned when you started, when your brother contacted you with the idea,
you were living in Washington and he was in Texas.
So I was just curious how you guys managed the project and what was the division of labor like in general between you and your brother?
Okay, yeah, well, you know, that went on for like, we lived separately until one of our kids' games.
And then during, by the time Myst came along, we were in the same place.
And so that was in Spokane, Washington.
And so it was really easy at that point.
And was it like, were you both doing everything,
both doing art, both doing story, or did you kind of?
Yeah, well, we were both designing.
So during the design process, we were totally doing,
we were together in the same room,
working on all of that together.
And then I would go off and do the art.
working with, like I said, Chuck Carter on Myst,
and then Rand did all the programming.
Yeah, scripting and etc.
Thank you.
All right.
Hi, I love the games,
and I decided to pick up the Myst novels a couple years ago,
just like two years ago, and I really enjoyed them,
and I enjoyed all the story that they filled in,
but I guess I was kind of surprised by the scale of death and destruction in them.
It's kind of different from the games,
and I was wondering if you could comment on, like,
What made you want to develop the backstory?
Was it the fans or was it, you know, was it the head?
Sure, yeah.
We wanted to...
At the point we were...
We wanted...
We knew we were going to make another game.
And I don't remember at what point that was.
Probably after people's...
They thought, oh, okay, well, we know we're going to...
We knew there was more to the story.
And then we thought, well, we wanted to tie those two things together,
Myst and this next game we were going to make.
And we came up with this idea of tying the two together with this book,
this novel.
And we kind of liked the idea, OK, it's a book, this is a world about books.
So that made sense to us.
I don't know, does that answer your question?
How long did it take for you guys to actually create a game?
And you said that you were running low on funds.
So how did you manage that, and what did your publisher say
when you talked with them about your planning
that didn't work out so well?
It took two years.
And what was the second part?
What did your publisher say?
Did you meet your schedules,
regardless of the money running out?
Well, we, you know, we worked hard to meet our schedules.
Sometimes we met them.
Sometimes we didn't.
But we always got close enough, you know.
And then we had two publishers,
because we had Sunsoft,
and then we also would have Broderbund.
And so we were kind of...
we were at different places with both of them.
And so, you know, I think we kept up pretty well.
Took two years, though, totally,
to create the game from start to finish.
Thanks.
I have no idea what time it is.
And if I'm anywhere near...
Okay, good. Okay.
So thanks again for Myst also.
It was also inspirational to me as I was growing up.
So when I played it, it took me about five days,
about an age day.
I had friends that finished it in like one sitting one day.
When you were developing it,
did you have any kind of time in mind,
like, oh, you were kind of aiming for, you know,
six, seven, ten, twelve hours of gameplay,
or was it just get through it how you get through it?
You know, I don't think so at all, no. I mean, we, like I said earlier, we were creating this world for ourselves.
There wasn't a lot of games, or none that we had experienced that set a precedent for hours of gameplay.
So, if there had, I'm sure we would have felt like, okay, well we need to give people this many hours of gameplay.
But, so, we were just creating this world that we thought would be really cool and interesting
and fun and it was a fun place for us to experience as we were creating it.
We were living in that world.
That's all we'd ever done was live in the worlds we were creating and, and enjoy them
as we created them and then go on to the next world.
And we never, we never for, just even for a little bit thought about like, oh, it's
going to take this many hours.
to experience this.
Now, we watched people play it, then, in our testing.
And so we could see, oh, this takes a while.
This is good. This is... they're enjoying it.
People are hooked for this amount of time.
People enjoy the place.
And they don't get bored. That was the main thing, you know.
So, yeah, but we never intended from the beginning
for it to take a certain amount of hours.
Thank you.
Way in the back.
What are you and your brother doing now?
Um...
The Immortal Augustus Gladstone.
It's about a guy who...
It's a fictional film.
About a guy who believes he's a vampire.
He believes he's immortal.
It's kind of filmed in a documentary style.
And...
And so this crew follows him around.
He lives in a vacant hotel.
And he's out to find a relative.
It's not necessarily a comedy, believe it or not.
But yeah, so we're going to be, it's probably this summer,
I think, that we'll be coming out.
So look for it.
Thank you.
Thanks for asking.
Hi, Phil Fish, you followed me back on Twitter a couple days ago and that made my week.
I just wanted to say I grew up obsessing on your games for years and years and years.
I beat Riven without looking up any information anywhere. It took me a full year.
The first video games I ever made were Myst clones in black and white HyperCard,
and then I spent years and years and years writing my own age books
and really getting into world building.
And, you know, that's kind of what I do for a living now.
And my question is, will you please sign my copy of the Book of Atrus?
Yeah, OK.
Yeah, very nice meeting you, very nice meeting you.
It's... I've been so obsessed with your work my entire life.
All right.
This is the one talk I see at GDC this year that's yours.
You want it too?
Yeah, to me.
Alright, there you go.
It's great to meet you. I love your game by the way. I love it.
Oh yeah, oh yeah, it's beautiful.
Alright, um...
Oh, way in the back.
Hello.
I just have a quick question about the protagonist, the person playing the game.
I was always curious if you had in your mind a backstory for how this person acquired the book.
Absolutely not, no.
We were really, we really strongly felt like that the protagonist in the game, or you,
was just whoever was playing the game.
And so, that was, that was really important to us.
Now,
You know, it's funny because I know other stories have evolved.
Like, it's, this people have said the stranger or something.
But it was, and I don't even know what that means now.
But it's, but yeah, we always felt like, you know, it needs to be
just whoever's playing the game with their...
They need to really feel like they're in this place themselves,
and that it's them in this world,
rather than playing the part of some other person.
In Myst, that was really important to us.
Cool, thank you.
Yes, you.
Okay, hi.
I just have two comments that I'd like to make.
One is that the whole metaphor of writing books
and then going to the worlds that you write
is such a incredible story idea that it holds up so well.
I just wish more people would take that idea
and do something with it because it's such a cool idea.
And second is, you and I have never met,
but we have spoken on the phone.
My name's Jack Wall and I wrote the music for the sequels,
Myst 3 and 4.
And it gives me great pleasure to give you a huge debt of gratitude
that I owe you right now.
Thank you, sir.
Nice to meet you.
What about you?
Okay, in the back.
Hi. Yeah, I recently dug out my old copy of Mist
and went through the journal that I had
with all the notes of solving the puzzles,
and it was amazing to go through those memories again.
And so I'm curious, whose idea was it
to include that in the package, the journal?
I don't remember whose idea it was
to include it in the package,
so I'll just say Broderbund's.
But I know one of the things we felt strongly about, and it was the idea to not have instruction, an instruction manual.
And I don't know if newer versions of the game have an instruction manual.
I know one of the original Mists didn't, because we really felt like, you know, people shouldn't have much instruction when they start playing it.
And they didn't, and we felt like they didn't need it.
So...
But I don't know is the answer.
Well, it was fantastic, and thank you.
You've said that your drive for making the game
was that you wanted to make worlds
that you would want to do, like, for yourself.
And you've also said that you didn't care
how long the game was,
and you almost forgot about puzzles
when preparing this talk, so I guess my question is,
why was it so essential
if there'd be puzzles filling the game?
Oh, it's not essential at all.
Um...
But they slow people down,
and then they get to experience the world
a little bit more slowly.
But yeah, I mean, for me, I just love being in the world.
I do like the story.
Puzzles, I think, tend to strengthen, they can tend to
strengthen that story a little bit more.
If there could be a game, and I'm sure there could be a game
with no puzzles, and where you could have story somehow, I'm
sure that could work.
I know there can be a game with no.
puzzles and no story and it could work.
You know, Minecraft does that amazingly well.
So, yeah.
I guess.
I guess we're, I think we're over.
As timer now?
I'm afraid this room is on a very rapid turnaround.
We're going to have to cut here.
All right. Cool.
Thanks so much for coming.