Hi everyone, my name is Guillaume Coron.
I am a senior graphic programmer at Contic Dream.
Contic Dream is a studio which creates games
with strong visual and story.
And we have our own in-house engine.
This talk is an overview of various rendering techniques
used in our two previous games and in the current one.
It mainly focuses on lighting and shading.
My co-worker Thibaut is credited here for his help
on this presentation, but he's not with us today.
OK.
The first part will focus on our need to be physically best
and the path we choose from Heavy Rain to Detroit
Become Human.
I will discuss why we are using photometric units
and the need to have material calibration
and validation tools.
Then I will explain the direct lighting and shadow techniques
you will use in your game.
And I will make a brief talk about our volumetric lighting
solution.
And I will finish with our indirect lighting
implementation.
But let's start with a quick trailer of Detroit
Become Human.
I'm the android sent by Cyberlight.
You have to accept the world as it is, or fight.
My name is Connor.
My name is Marcus.
This is our story.
For the players.
OK, get back a little bit in the past
and talk about our previous game.
Every run was the PS3 game based on forward rendering engine.
All the shading and lighting was done in gamma space,
and the BLDF was derived from BlinFoam.
It's pretty classic.
On Beyond Tosu, we converted our rendering engine
to a different one.
All material evolution remained in gamma space,
but lighting and shading are done in linear space.
We use a more refined BRDF based on micro-facet theory
with some approximation to fit the PS3 capability.
For Detroit Become Human,
we get back to cluster forward shading
to have more flexibility on all materials.
All our rendering pipeline is now in linear space
and we use micro-facet BRDF mainly based on GJX distribution
with support of anisotropy.
The diffuse part still use a vanilla Lambertian diffuse term,
and we do partial energy conservation
between diffuse and specular.
Photometric units are used for all intensity
on both analytical light and emissive surfaces.
All our material are built by our artists
with the help of a shading tree.
This is very powerful and can be hard to control performances
and global coherency.
Some materials can have multiple specular lobes,
like the skin shader, the car paint,
or even the lid shader in some cases.
To handle this kind of materials,
we have implemented something we call a BRDF layer stack.
We split our BRDF in multiple layers and stack them.
Material can have two specular lobes, plus one diffuse
and one subsurface or backscattering one.
For example, the lead shader have only one specular lobe
by default, but it can be possible to add a second
for metallic materials with render effect on them.
Energy conservation between layers is required, and each layer computes its reflected and transmitted energy.
The remaining energy is reused to compute the next layer.
To have a perfect energy conservation, we will need to pre-compute energy transfer over the entire BRDF,
taking into account multiple scattering, Fresnel, and absorption.
This approach was not retained by the fear of the costs introduced by multiple lookups needed to achieve this.
And unfortunately, we just take into account
the Fresnel interface to achieve energy conservation
between layers.
But a recent talk by Christopher Kula and Alejandro Conti
at last year's Seagraph on this subject
gave us some hope to use such a technique in our next project.
OK, now you have an overview of how our shading is processed.
And I can talk about the issue we
faced in the production cycle.
Before Detroit become human, each artist build their own level and add their own habit.
Lighting from one scene to another could be very different, even under identical light condition.
Materials was not spared by this issue.
In this case, it was really hard to reuse props
in different scenes and understand who is the culprit.
Is it the material or the lighting?
For all this reason, we decided to move
to photometric units to fix a part of the problem.
When we started to this development,
light coherency was our main goal.
With photometric units, it was easier to compare
sunlighting to real-life references,
and artists can use real-life measured value.
It gives guidelines for artists to correctly
lead their scene, and by the same way,
it presents them from unconsciously back
lighting information in their albedo.
For example, when they do darker albedo for night scene.
And finally, intensity range between bright and dark area
of the scene are more plausible.
For more information about photometric units,
you can refer to a great presentation
by Sebastien Lagarde and Charles de Roussier
called Moving Frostbite to Physically Based Rendering.
Let's do a quick reminder about photometric units.
You have the luminous power that can be expressed in lumen.
was the total light amount energy emitted by light.
The luminous intensity that was expressed in candela
is the luminous power per solid angle direction of a light.
The illuminance that can be expressed in lux,
that was the light amount falling on the surface.
And the luminance that can be expressed in candela
per square meter.
And it's per unit area of candela in specific direction.
Directional light can be expressed in lux,
because as seen previously, lux is the light amount
falling on a surface.
Other lights can be expressed in lumen,
or in candela per square meter if area lights are used.
You can see some luminous power references provided
by Sebastien Lagarde in this presentation of the subject.
And as you can see, the range between values
can be really high.
Quadratic attenuation are mandatory for punctual light
sources to compute correct illuminance
at the surface of object.
And illuminance can be really high near the punctual light
sources.
For emissive surfaces, we add an emissive intensity parameter
on all materials in combination with a traditional emissive
color.
Emissive intensity is expressed in exposure value, heavy
or stop in photography.
But why are we using heavy and not candela per square meter,
which might be a more logical unit
to use for emissive surfaces?
Candela per square meter is a linear scale,
but is not perceived as such by the human eye.
But EV is perceptually linear scale for the human vision,
and adding one unit in EV
double the perceived light intensity.
To work with such high range,
we need to correctly expose our scene
even in our level editor.
Using an auto exposure is not recommended.
It can easily break your landmark.
To keep real life comparison,
we use measured exposure for triple light condition.
And fortunately, all level are split
in volume called scene zone.
This scene zone are used for visibility
in combination of portals,
and usually match a room in a house.
We add to them our exposure information.
In this case, our director of photography
provide exposure references for set artists.
The scene exposure are fixed,
are fixed value for the scene zone,
and there is no camera transition.
We instantly apply exposure
when the camera enter in the scene zone.
Scene exposure is expressed in EV100.
It represents a combination of camera shutter speed
and f-number for ISO100 sensor sensibility.
Scene exposure is a great tool to ensure
that our lighting was in coherent ranges
for asset production.
And it is really useful to pre-expose
our accumulation buffer.
But it's not enough for in-game exposure.
where we need more control.
And that's why we introduced camera exposure.
Camera exposure is an exposure composition
over the scene exposure.
And it gives more control to dynamically change the exposure.
Artists are able to choose between four different camera
exposure types, depending on their need.
Auto exposure are mainly used in gameplay phases,
and manual exposure on cut scenes.
Okay, the first one, we call it manual exposure.
The exposure value is in EV100
and can be controlled by animated curve.
The second one is called camera.
It computes exposure from physical camera setting,
like the half stop, the ISO, and shutter speed.
We have an auto average that computes
the exposure from the log average luminance of the scene.
That's pretty classic.
And the last one is called auto UV zone.
It's a little bit special.
It computes the exposure from the value provided
in the scene zone in addition to decals, exposure decals
manually placed in the scene.
This screen capture represents our camera auto EV debug view.
As you maybe can see on the scale on the right,
All the pixels in the room have neutral exposure compensation.
This is because the camera is currently
in the scene zone of the room.
All the pixels outside of the house
are in a different scene zone, which
is approximately three steps above the current scene zone.
This is the right pixel.
It's the red pixel, sorry.
And the dark pixel near the entrance
was EV decal manually placed by artist to control exposure.
This decal was approximately half a stop
below the current scene exposure.
And now let's see it in action.
You can see the box of the decal near the door.
And when the camera sees all the pixels in this zone,
the exposure, the total exposure is down.
And as you can see, when the camera goes out,
the same exposures change.
But the camera exposure do compensation
to have a smooth transition.
OK.
To work with photometric units, we developed a lot of debug tools.
Here is some examples.
The first one is virtual spot meters
that give us pixel absolute luminance
in candela per square meter and EV100.
It also gives us RGB value of our accumulation buffer.
It's really useful to tweak emissive surfaces
and debug high value in specular reflection.
And the second one is a fast color debug screen
that helps us to check if a scene is well exposed.
It highlights range for correct exposed middle gray,
skin tone, and ranges for creased black and burnt white.
This debug screen is really useful
for our director of photography
to check if the scene was correctly exposed.
Now, with all the work done on the photometric units and exposure,
we have a good framework for lighting with real light references and consistent value.
But if we don't want to break all the work done on the lighting,
material needs the same treatment.
Our first idea was to scan a huge quantity of material to use them on our game,
but it was not possible for us to do it. We don't have the workforce for it.
Even if we are not able to scan all materials,
we really want to capture some objects
and material references.
To do this, we needed to build a controlled environment
that was easy to reproduce in our engine.
We built a black room with three incandescent bulbs
and captured reference material and objects.
All this process also gave us possibility
to validate the work done on photometric units
and capture our first full-range image baselight.
Around this, we built a tool called the HighSync tool
that provides calibrated environment
and easy access to material properties.
It is really important to use full range image baseline
to have a result as close as possible to the reality.
You could find some interesting information on this subject
on a presentation by Sébastien Lagarde
called An Artist-Friendly Workflow for Panoramic HDRI.
Artists can easily check their props in this tool
and check if the materials are correct.
Screenshot of this tool.
Let's see the screenshot.
The panel of the left give easy access
to display material properties.
And the props and character of the game
can be verified in this tool.
It's pretty useful to detect wrong material setup.
In addition to the icing tool, we provide some debug options to highlight values with out of range material properties.
Wrong base color is highlighted in red, wrong Fresnel value for glass shader in blue, and material with wrong metallic setup in yellow.
It's really useful to quickly understand what's wrong with your material.
Let's see some example.
This allows us to identify that the base color
of the snow are often too high,
and the glass shader often have too high reflectance value.
And in some cases, we could find some strange setup,
like for the sofa, that have metallic property on it.
Now let's talk about our lighting and shadowing solution.
Okay, we use photometric units
and have calibration material.
But what about analytical light?
All of our analytical light were punctual sources.
We have a direction light, a point light, and spotlight,
and a projector light that is a directional light
constrained in a box with attenuation.
Pretty simple.
Attenuation is quadratic by default,
but artists can tweak the value from zero to two.
It is useful to fake bigger light
by decreasing the attenuation.
The quadratic attenuation is combined
with an attenuation radius that try to preserve energy
as much as possible, but energy loss is unavoidable
at the end of the radius.
But punctual light sources.
But with punctual sources, some really high intensity peak
can appear in the specular reflection.
This issue is mostly present in materials
with mid and low roughness.
To fix this issue, we have implemented area light
using closest point techniques.
But forward rendering mean all lights
need to be an area light.
This introduces additional cost to lighting,
and artists should have to re-lit
all the scene already lit.
And unfortunately, it was too late in the production cycle
to integrate them in the current game.
Finally, we slightly biased the material roughness
to prevent the issue.
Okay.
With light, with different shading,
we were able to use custom geometry easily.
It's up to constrain light in an arbitrary geometry
to prevent them to leak from wall or even without shadow.
But because we have a forward engine,
it was not trivial to use custom light geometry
like we've done before.
To handle a part of the problem,
we have added an orientable near-clip plane
on all of our light.
It's very useful and cheap to add light positioning
without custom light geometry.
We also had some visibility flag on our lights
that give us the possibility to reject light
per cluster and per pixel.
A light can lit all the scene zone of a level
or just the scene zone where the light is in
or all the scene zone visible by the light,
the first term of the light.
It prevents leaking from light with a shadow and it's great for performances.
By example, in a house, a light on the second floor won't lit the pixel of the first floor with this flag on it.
Okay, now let's introduce our close-up lighting system.
Our game are story-driven with many close-up camera shots.
We want to be able to lit our close-up shot
like on a movie set.
And we pay special attention to the lighting.
With our tool, we are able to edit the lighting of all
camera shots on a post-production phase.
Artists can choose for each camera track
what object will receive our close-up light
and can also add some exposure track on them.
On the engine side, the close-up lighting is a set of light used to replace the regular lighting.
Artists choose objects that will be lit by the close-up light set.
They can also affect the indirect contribution with GEI and IBL color multiplier.
They can flag a regular light in the scene as additional close-up light.
And close-up light always use our close-up shadow system
that we'll explain later.
And it have its own light cluster
fitted to the bounding box of the close-up selection.
And the size of this additional cluster is 11 by 11 by 4.
OK, let's see a screenshot with our close-up lighting on
and another with the close-up lighting off.
It's pretty useful in this case.
Now that the subject of direct lighting has been approached, I can talk about our choices,
the choices we made on the shadow part.
We use classic shadow mapping techniques, but our percentage cross-filtering is done
with 8 samples and temporal super-sampling.
All the samples are jittering using blue noise, and the temporal anti-aliasing softens the
result for us.
The default blur radius is three pixel wide
and can go up to 15 pixels.
Shadow bias is automatically computed
from the geometry normal
and artists do not need to worry about it.
We also implement soft shadow in the form of PCSS,
but it's turned out to be not feasible for us
because of the too high register pressure in your shadow.
But PCSS is still used on all tooth shaders.
Shadow was stored on an atlas of 8192 square pixel texture
at 16 bit precision.
Artists are able to choose between three different sizes for their shadow
and all are multiple of 256 pixels.
Shadows are resized depending on their distance to the camera.
The resolution can be halved at max.
We decrease resolution in four steps to prevent pixel quarrying
and repack them in the atlas when reaching a multiple of 256 pixels.
The shadow atlas was lazily updated,
only if a light move in,
or if something move in their frustum.
Point light faces can be individually excluded,
and we also have a tweakable near clip plane
to help with numerical precision and light positioning.
This clip plane can be correlated or not
with the light near clip plane itself,
but this one is not, don't support rotation.
For the directional light, we use cascaded shadow map
with the same filtering than on the other lights.
I sample with temporary supersampling.
With most transition between shadow split
by using jittering and temporal anti-aliasing,
our cascade have four split at max,
but majority of our scene only have two or three split.
And split distribution is automatically handled.
No artist input needed except for the far distance
of the last split.
We handle a static shadow too.
We try to have a shadow on all lights.
And to do this, we have a static shadow system.
The shadow of a light switch to a static shadow
depending on the camera distance.
They contain only static geometry,
and we do only one sample with bilinear comparison.
It's pretty fast.
All the static shadow are stored on an atlas
of 2,048 square pixels,
and shadow itself are 16 full square pixels.
We are able to have up to 1,024 static shadow in a scene.
Static shadow for the directional light
is handled by a huge texture storing
all the static geometry.
It's a pretty huge texture.
Okay, close-up shadow.
Like for our close-up light system,
we want to have high-quality shadow on our close-up shot.
We are able to have two additional shadow
for our close-up light system,
and the system is always on,
even if we are not in a close-up shot.
All the shadow can be promoted to a close-up one.
Close-up shadow are used to add precision
and contact and self-shadowing.
Artists select a relevant object in the scene
that receive close-up shadow.
By example, all the characters are close-up shadow receiver.
And only this object receive the close-up shadow.
Okay, how it work?
First of all, we compute a bounding volume
of all visible close-up shadows receiver
on the radius of 10 meter around the camera.
The bounding volume of skinned object
are computed from a point cloud
to be able to fit to only the visible part
of the character or the skin object.
Then we fit the first term.
to the binding volume of all the visible close-up receiver.
An object between the light position
and the near plane of the fitted frustum
are projected on this near plane.
In this case, we render only the object in the bonding volume
and all the object between the bonding volume and the light.
Okay, a screenshot with close-up shadow on
and another without the close-up shadow.
It's really help with light leaking and self-shadowing.
Okay, our shadow memory budget.
We have a big chunk of memory dedicated to shadows,
which is about 280 megabytes.
Close-up shadows are stored on the main shadow atlas.
We are able to have between 10 to 1,020
for shadow at a time,
depending on the resolution of the shadow.
By example, in the case of point lights
with six face casting shadow,
At 1024 pixels each, the atlas is filled up
with only 10 lights.
And trust me, this case appears more than once
in the production.
Okay.
Now, a video that displays the shadow atlas.
You can see some close-up shadow
that constantly fit on the character.
you have two close-up shadows.
And on the lower left and lower right,
you can see shadows that resize depending on the distance
with the light source and the camera.
And when the close-up lighting is enabled,
the number of close-up shadows is proportional
to the light count used for the close-up light shot.
OK, shadow performances.
We have 15 to 20 shadow updates on average per frame,
but there is no limit quantity.
It can get wide in some cases.
And on the previous video, the shadow cost
is between 1.5 milliseconds and 3.5 milliseconds.
Majority of OSN don't go over 5 milliseconds for shadow,
the most of the time.
The cost for the close-up shadow are really scene-dependent
and it can be really fast if few objects are reprojected
on the near plane, but it can be really slow
in the case of a tree covering all the first term
of the light because of huge alpha test coverage.
Okay, let's talk about volumetric lighting.
For volumetric lighting, we use an unified volumetric lighting solution
popularized by Bart Wonsky in 2014 and Sébastien Hilaire in 2015.
The technique consists of storing all the medium property and the lighting
to a volumetric texture fitted on the first sum of the light.
It's a kind of deferred shading done on a volumetric buffer.
For more information, I advise you to read the previous paper on this subject.
In our case, we render our volumetric buffer with checkerboard rendering.
The native resolution of our volumetric buffer are 192x108x64 on the base PS4,
and we slightly increase the resolution on the Pro.
The temporal component of the effect
use blue noise jittering on the depth slicing,
and all the features are supported,
all lighting features are supported,
like click plane on the light and shadow,
as well as our indirect lighting.
Fog contribution is supported in our JBaking,
and it gives us an approximation
of multiple scattering in the fog.
Okay, volumetric light can leak through surfaces with this technique
when the light is in the same depth slice than the surface of an opaque object.
As you can see, the light can leak some sample in the cell
and when we compute moving average of all the sample,
the light contribution can be stronger than expected.
For us, it is really important to fix this issue
because we have a lot of small volumetric light
attached to objects.
To fix this issue, we store min-max depth per tile
in two dimension.
We use max depth to clamp voxel thickness
at light evaluation.
And we apply a ZBIAS when sampling the volumetric texture.
that was storing the light catering
when the type variance is above a certain threshold.
That don't fix all the issue,
but it can be really effective in some cases.
OK, let's see a screenshot with the volumetric lighting off,
and another with the volumetric lighting on,
with some color setting.
It's prettier in the game.
In the majority of our scene, the performance has around 2ms and can go up to 3ms
in scene with huge amount of moving light.
We use some technique to reproject and prevent ghosting on moving light
and this is why in this case we have more cost when huge amount of light are moving in the scene.
but we don't go over 3ms all the time.
Okay, just a little video because I love this effect.
It's quick.
Okay, now we can talk about our indirect lighting solution.
If we go back in the past with Beyond to Soul,
at that time we were using Half-Life 2 AmbientCube,
stored per vertex for static geometry
and with LightProbe for dynamic geometry.
The indirect specular were the mix of various technique.
We have planar reflection,
and also with vertical blur pyramid to fake roughness
and cube map.
a capture without BureauDev integration
and manually used in the shading tree.
It was pretty ugly at this time
and all the artists need to do
the capture and integrate
the high BL in their shading herself.
And what we want is to have an unified solution
for static and dynamic object.
We start to work on a probe-based solution for everything.
Our solution is typical this day.
We use image-based light for specular component
with ggx-ndf integration.
Filtered importance sampling is used to prevent firefly,
and we have influence and parallax box.
For the diffuse part, we begin to use diffuse probe grid.
But as we choose to use diffuse probe grid,
some technical flow appears to us.
Light leaking was one big issue introduced by some...
introduced by PropGrid, and it's an ongoing research
around with some interesting solution proposed last year.
Interpolation irregularity are not often addressed,
but was considered as problematic for us.
By example, if we try to fix light leaking
by rejecting probes based on occlusion,
it often leads to interpolation artifact.
We ended up to never discarding any probe.
We store our probe in an adaptive sparse octree
automatically built with RTSQ.
They can provide density zone to out the automatic voxelization.
And the scene voxelization help us to automatically adjust
the resolution of the octree around the object
and the wall of the scene.
Okay, in our case, one octree cell contain eight probes
on one per corner of the cell.
A pointy space is always surrounded by eight probes,
and we never discard any probe,
but virtually offset them at the baking time instead.
Thanks to this, artists can use a probe attractor.
This attractor are closed mesh
that attract all the probe in the volume.
This attractor can be fit to a room or just on a certain object.
And they are really cute, and they are...
There, sorry.
And they are useful.
And they are usually close to all volume zones already used for visibility.
Artists can also use mesh repulsor to offset probes outside of the geometry
On the left, note how probes inside the single-faceted cube receive light information
and introduce light leaking
On the right, probes are offsetted outside of the cube and create a more natural occlusion
Also note the interpolation error on the right side of the cube
Okay, offsetting probes help us to solve majority
of light leaking cases.
As previously said, we virtually offset all probes
during capture or baking time.
But the evaluation of the GI
is always based on the original grid position.
The offset is only done at baking time.
Probe inside the wall is undefined.
because the wall usually uses backfascaling,
and the probe was in a state that we don't know.
We use a repulsor to virtually offset
the probe position outside of the wall.
In this case, this probe that was moved
on the outside of the wall,
takes some bright red color.
We fix one side, but this creates some leaking
on the other side of the wall that's,
that was way dimmer than the first one.
Here the leaking was always present and irrelevant.
We subdivide the arg tree around the object, if possible,
and it will fix the issue.
If it is not possible to subdivide because we reach the maximum octree depth,
we favor minimum indirect light error.
Weak indirect is always less noticeable than bright indirect.
Okay, in the cases we can properly handle,
we also provide some probe color modifier
with smooth quadratic transition for manual modification.
This color modifier are post-applied on the JBEQ
computation and provide really fast iteration.
To prevent filtering discontinuity between octree,
between octree level when using hardware filtering,
we first color continuity at baking time
by interpolating probes that are not,
that are on the border of the octree depth size difference,
like on T-junction.
In this case, blue probes are never computed,
but interpolated instead.
It's helped to prevent irregularity
and this allow us to use hardware filtering.
Okay, let's talk about how we store data in Perlsock tree.
Only leaves have content and we only need to store leaves.
And remember, I previously mentioned,
we have eight probe per leaf
for the eight corner of the tree.
Leaves are stored in a volume texture atlas.
We pack the eight probe of each leaf
into a two by two by two block of the volume texture atlas.
Probe are shared on corner of the YOG3
but need to be duplicated to support adaptive
difference in the cell depth of the oak tree.
And it gives us a lot of redundancy.
To prevent this issue, we do not store the oak tree leaves,
but its first parent cell instead.
We pack leaves first parent into tree by tree by tree block
of the volume texture atlas.
Storing parent cell is way better.
We still have some redundancy, but it's good enough for us.
The irradiance is stored in each probe by using second-order spherical harmonics
with geometric reconstruction for better quality,
which means we need to store four coefficients by probes.
In this case, we have three RGBA volume textures
at 16-bit precision for our volume texture atlas.
By example, 24,000 probes can be stored on 100 by 100
by three volume texture, which gives us around 3 megabytes
for all these probes.
In the game, we are closer to 100,000 probes
for each scene zone.
This gives us approximately 15 megabytes by scene zone.
Okay, how do we display our GI?
We never discard any probe that allow us
to directly sample volumetric texture
by using hardware filtering.
But for each probe, we need to store a hash key
and to reconstruct atlas texture coordinates.
We use one hash per octrelive.
The hash code is formed from a 3D position
thanks to Morton Key algorithm.
It's a constant time algorithm
to transform multidimensional data to one dimension.
And the hash code is restricted to 32 bits,
which limits the octrelive to 10.
And finally,
The hashcodes are used to compute textual coordinates
to fetch the atlas volume.
The bonuses provided with such technique
is that we can easily blend between different,
between multiple G-set with a compute shutter.
It lets us to easily switch our GI when a light is switched on or off.
And it can be useful to make GI global illumination transition for daytime
or, by example, when opening or closing a curtain, like on this video.
Because we use scene zone with portal,
we want to avoid add transition between scene zone.
Artists can set up transition distance around portal.
All dynamic object passing through
sample both global emission.
The sample global emission of the both scene zone.
Transition is based on distance to portal and normal direction.
A screenshot here with the transition off
and one other with the transition on.
This helps us to have a really smooth transition.
One character go to a room to another
with really different lighting condition.
OK, for static object, we also use global elimination
transition for objects.
Most of the objects are in a unique scene zone,
like interior wall versus exterior wall.
But what about door, window, and window frame?
These objects are assigned to a scene zone,
but are also visible from others.
In this case, we flag object to sample both GI Atlas,
and it solves the issue.
On the left, the door and the window
only sample the interior GI,
and on the right, they sample both.
Okay, now it's time to conclude this talk.
First of all, the road to physically based rendering
never ends.
We need better energy conservation
for light and materials.
Materials are not physically accurate enough.
And being physically based is good,
but don't forget artist's visions and needs.
It's really important.
And remember that photometric units
can provide a good framework to ensure
coherent asset production.
And always use referent environment
to validate your materials.
OK, what's next for us?
We want to have area light and soft shadow everywhere.
It's one of our big subject.
We need to work on energy conservation
and improve our BRDF layer stack.
Adding more dynamic components in our global animation system
is also really, really important for us.
We haven't had the time to add pseudo-dynamic global animation,
like adding spherical harmonic light injection
and virtual point light or inject color modifier on the fly.
For volumetric lighting, we want to add more flexibility
on fog density volume and add volumetric shadow too.
And that's it.
I want to thank all the rendering team at Country Dream
for their fantastic work.
And I want to thank Julien Merceron for this advice
on my presentation.
OK, it's time for a question maybe.
Did you experiment with BC6H compression?
For your indirect lighting.
For the global emulation?
Yeah.
Yes, we...
All our...
All volumetric texture...
Sorry, I'm...
don't do this, we don't experiment with compression, I think.
The size was really small for us and we don't,
we won't have enough precision
to our global dimension.
Sorry.
Thank you.
Hey, how did you guys handle the interpolation errors
at the edge of the blocks that are stored in the
pre-texture?
We have some redundancy in your global elimination atlas.
And we don't have to involve the different interpolation,
because we have all the probes surrounding the position
in space that was on the block.
And when we have different level in the oak tree.
We don't compute, can I go,
we don't compute all the,
the probe, but instead we interpolate,
we do some interpolation between the two different probe.
Oh, sorry.
Oh, no.
OK, the blue probes are interpolated
and using the probe from the upper level.
And in this case, we don't have a discontinuity
when we use, when we fetch.
OK, but like in the next slide, when you go,
when you have the texture like, sorry, keep going.
The one past this one.
in the texture that stores the leaves,
like when that two by two block is next
to another two by two block,
you guys said you were using like trilinear filtering
on the texture to get the value.
Like what happens if you sample near the edge of the block
where it connects to the other one?
We offered that to don't go over the half pixel.
Okay.
To just get on the,
Okay, cool, thanks.
On the block.
Thank you.
Another question?
OK, I think we can conclude here.
Thank you.