When you have trouble making art for video games, where do you want to go?
Home.
Who do you feel like seeing?
No one.
How much time do you spend in the office?
Too much.
Bad art pipelines hurt in so many ways.
Sadness.
A loss of interest.
Anxiety.
TechArt Bootcamp can help.
TechArt Bootcamp is an all-day event at GDC 2019 that treats known symptoms of poor art pipelines.
If you've experienced poor distance field vision, saggy or unrealistic cloth, underperforming shaders, a buildup of tool cruft, confusion about production constraints, an inability to scale your tool's deployment, or have trouble keeping track of your data, then it may be time to come to the Technical Artist Boot Camp on Tuesday, March 19th, 2019.
Severe liver problems, never fatal, were reported. Signs include abdominal pain, dry mouth, and waking up in your hotel room not knowing how you got there.
Talk to your tech artists if you have too many scripts, or if it takes 16 hours to make
a build, as it may be a sign of a serious or deadline-threatening condition.
Side effects may include nausea, constipation, and drinking coffee later than you know you
should.
Tell your tech artists right away if your pipeline worsens, if your tools exhibit unusual
behavior, or you experience sudden bouts of rage against your machine.
Ask your recruiters about hiring tech artists.
Game development is tough.
TechArt Bootcamp can help.