Hi everyone. I'm Elisabetta Sealy and I'm a game designer at Naughty Dog. And I'm going to say a
few things about me to give you an idea on where I come from and what I'm going to talk about. So I
started my career at Ubisoft. I joined the company as a multiplayer level designer. That was my
first job on Splinter Cell Double Agent. I was a developer for a company called Naughty Dog.
And then I moved out of my country.
I went to Germany.
I worked at Crytek as a level designer
in an unannounced title.
And after that, I joined DICE.
So I relocated again, moved to Sweden in Stockholm.
And there I stayed about five years.
I worked on Mirror's Edge on a single player,
on the DLC Time Trials.
I worked on Battlefield Bad Company 2.
I was on multiplayer.
I joined single player.
And I also worked on Battlefield 3.
Then I switched team.
I went up on...
Medal of Honor Warfighter and now I'm at Naughty Dog and I worked on multiplayer and single player
on The Last of Us. So the topic is going to be the challenges I faced and this is about
This is really inspired about my last year and a half at Naughty Dog.
And also I'm going to approach things like changing new studios and other challenges that I faced.
And at Naughty Dog I really packed up all the challenges together.
I joined a new team, new tools, new country, new everything.
So hopefully I will give you tips and tricks on how to survive something like that.
So, these are the main challenges I'm going to start talking about.
I'm going to approach the new studio, new tools, new game, and switching between single
player and multiplayer.
So, regarding new studios.
Also, when you join your first studio, I actually, hopefully,
you're going to join a new studio one day.
And when you join your first studio,
you really have no expectations about it.
At least I didn't have.
I was like, oh, I'm going to make games.
That's the best thing ever.
And then I discovered, oh, look, I can have all the perks.
I can have free video games that I worked on.
I started having t-shirts of the game I worked on, which is, for girls, is impossible.
You always have, like, XL size that you don't know where to put, or you give to your nerd
friends.
And they are happy about that.
You know...
New studios, when you start switching studio, there's always some kind of clash of culture
and your expectation.
You have some expectations and some are going to be met, some are not going to be met, but
I personally had always great experiences, you know, you trade something for something else and it's really great, but not everyone manages to survive this impact, you know.
I saw people changing companies and quitting after two weeks, a month, six weeks. They couldn't stand the new philosophy.
For instance...
Sometimes in some of the studios you're gonna have like,
at Naughty Dog when I joined,
was kind of a great surprise to me.
There was no tutorial,
no documentation for learning their tools.
And you know, some people will cringe.
I know a lot of people that would cringe,
and I was scared to death.
I'm like, oh, we're gonna survive this.
But you make the best out of it.
So it turned out for me that it really paid off.
I personally, you know, when you join a new studio,
you kind of get some time to get used to the culture.
You get some time to know people.
And not having documentation for anything,
it made me just go to the desk of the designer next to me,
of the programmer next to me, and just ask them things.
So at the end of the project, and,
And actually after a month I felt like at home.
I knew a lot of people in the project and it felt like I was just fitting and it just
required me to be more open and going to ask people things.
different companies will have a different view of what a level designer is.
Some companies will see you as the artsy level designer and you might have to step up your game
and learn how to make awesome meshes and do your own geo and you know you're
in an awesome company and you're learning from the best people.
So what better chance there to learn something new
and step up your game?
Also, you might learn that you love doing art,
and you might change your job and become an environment artist.
Some other companies, you're more like a scripter,
and you will have to learn how to script.
Don't ever get scared of anything.
Different is not bad.
Different is a great change and great chance
to learn something new that will just
make you more flexible and more valuable as a level designer.
And you know, knowing something more
will make your layout better, which
is great as a level designer.
New tools.
So for these challenges, tools are not your choice, ever.
And would you stop from working on a fantastic game
just because you have to change a tool?
I personally wouldn't, but a lot of designers
specialize on tools.
And it's a career choice.
I saw people being hired because they're
specialists in some tool.
And they would teach all of us how to use it.
And that's fantastic.
But it personally is not my main focus.
My main focus is the game.
And working on the best game, that's all I wanted to do.
And I've been lucky enough to do it.
So, my tip is adapt.
Just, you know, I don't even try to make myself comfortable anymore with tools.
I see people using lots of shortcuts.
I see people making their life easier.
You know, sometimes there are some tools that make your tool look more like some other tool
that you're more familiar with.
Really, I don't like to do it.
I like to make myself uncomfortable,
because it makes my brain stay in that state that
is accepting and humble.
So I am never lazy.
I always learn new things.
And I don't stop anything from coming and teaching me
something new.
Also, if you think about it.
the more you know, the more tools you know,
the more valuable you are for a tool
that might be developing in your own company.
And that's a fantastic thing.
You can criticize to improve.
Don't criticize just to change something
because you prefer the way something worked,
but criticize to make your life better,
to make the life of all of your team better,
and your game better.
That's the greatest thing
and the most valuable thing you can have.
Also, now for the new game challenge, so what do you do when you start in a new game that
you're going to work on?
You play sequels.
Like, I recently switched and moved to the Uncharted team, and what do you think I did?
I played Uncharted 1, 2, and 3.
Big sacrifice, right?
Yeah.
Anyways, what do you do?
This is what I call doing your homework.
This is where you study the game, discover the game,
learn the game, and criticize it.
Find out what you would have done better.
Find out what is stellar about the game
and you have to preserve.
Find out the things that you could expand and add
to the game and make it even better than what it was.
That said, sometimes you might work on a new IP.
and there might not be nothing playable.
So at that point, what you do is listen.
The first weeks, the first month in The Last of Us,
I just listened to everything that everybody was saying.
I wouldn't even put my headphones on,
and I was just full radar mode,
just trying to catch everything from the game.
Tons of questions to the people who had the ideas for the game find out everything just don't stop
When I joined the last of us everybody was super stressed. This was really intense
It was really focused and everybody was pushing their time try to put every single bit of their
Time they had on the game
And it was really intimidating approaching them.
But if you approach them, they're
going to be happy because you're making the game better.
You're going to help them make the game better.
So you're welcome to ask them questions.
And they're going to be super happy to help you.
So you can understand the game, find out what it is about.
Because you're the level designer
and the play is in your hands.
For a single player multiplayer as
I told you before, I switched various amount of time.
I started as a multiplayer level designer.
And some people are going to be loving their single player,
and some people are going to be multiplayer only.
super specialized, but to me, versatility is the greatest thing, not only for the company
because I'm a better value for the company, but for me, I take a break. I learn new things.
And when I started on multiplayer, I started learning about level flow and navigation and
how to lead the player to places.
how to put power weapons and just creating vantage point,
which is fantastic.
And then on top of that, when I switch on single player,
I learned about narrative and how to pace the player.
It was a great experience and I think that everybody should always try everything
so they can make, they can be a better value to the company and to themselves
because one day there might not be a single player game in your company.
One day there might not be a multiplayer game in your company and you have to switch it up.
Now the concrete part is...
focused on what I worked on in The Last of Us.
And I started on multiplayer.
I moved to single player, worked on the combat tutorial,
and did some work on the multiplayer DLC.
My start on the multiplayer, actually, I
didn't do any layout.
I was doing game modes implementation and I got my crash course to our scripting.
And that was actually the best thing ever.
I got the worst part of our scripting,
which was having to deal with players,
multiplayers, and network.
And I iterated, and I found out our controls.
And it was incredibly valuable for what
I didn't know was coming next.
And also, I managed to do some cover, pass on level,
and layout polish in the multiplayer.
But almost all the levels were at a stage
where we couldn't change much.
There was only one level that was more flexible, which was the dam level, and I did some feedback and coverpass, but that was very little.
And one day, I was asked to help with a single-player tutorial.
It's awkward.
In the single player tutorial, I was asked to help with the
combat tutorial and I started doing combat research. So Bruce called me and said, Hi
Elisabetta can you help us with this tutorial? We want to start and do the tutorial for the
first gun fight in the game. And there's going to be some tutorial layout you will do and
you're going to script it. Doing AI scripting and also environmental scripting. So
took me over, he showed me where I could find all the playtest
in test cases and all the tutorial maps.
So I watched them a lot.
And then I started with this little area,
which was the first encounter you had with human AI.
there was nothing there.
There was just the geo, the main geo around,
but there wasn't any cover placement
because that was not the purpose of the area at all.
And what he said to me is that
there was a cut scene in progress
and there were gonna be three guys,
one of which was gonna die
because Stasovic shooted him.
So here's how the area would go.
Joel and Tess would come over this way and then the two guys alive would take cover and Joel and
Tess would be in cover and one guy was dead. Uh in this area I learned how to use the right AI for
the place. So I started scripting AI for the first time here and I put the AI there and they were
acting funky, they were not taking really cover.
And I was like, OK, it's a first try,
and maybe there's something with the AI.
I was kind of shy and not sure if I did something wrong
or was the AI.
It's always the AI.
No, it's always the level designer.
Turns out that I didn't know that we had to use
this particular AI close combat range behavior,
and I didn't know about it because I was new.
So what I did, how I discovered it,
was like asking help to everybody.
So ask questions, and this is what I learned in this area.
And also...
We tried to have a second wave in this area
after the player was done, but this area
was way too tight for our AI.
And that's another thing I learned.
Our AI works best when it's in bigger spaces.
And we scratched that.
Also, you know, I was the first combat,
so we decided that.
Two AIs were enough for the player. In this area we also have Tess as a companion and she wasn't
really that helpful at the beginning so we stepped up their game and she's pretty aggressive in this
video that I'm gonna show. So this is the area where you come from. This is pretty tight
and here starts the cutscene. Here we go.
Let us through.
You guys need to turn around and head back if you know what's good for you.
Our beef isn't with you.
We just want Robert.
You don't want to do this.
Turn the fuck around and leave now.
I'm not going anywhere without Robert.
Bitch, I will bash your skull unless you turn around and get your dumb ass out of here.
Fuck this.
Take cover!
So she's not the most friendly person.
You ready?
Yeah.
I'll cover you.
I cannot lie girl.
Yeah, so as you can see now the AI is finally taking cover, it's behaving as I want it, and Tess is killing him by herself.
And this is pretty much the combat, and as you can see this corridor was way too tight, and this is where the second wave would have ended up fighting, which doesn't really have much space for anything, not even cover.
And at this stage, we couldn't really change much in the layout itself, so we wanted to
preserve as much as possible.
Plus it's a nice pacing after the first combat.
So this is not really a tutorial.
This is just an alley, but we thought
about having a tutorial here.
And I wanted to talk to you about this
because I learned a lesson.
We wanted to teach the player how to use listen mode.
The idea was that this is a top-down and we had a pull-up so the player and Tess would come up
towards that direction and do the pull-up and Tess would take over and say,
Hey Joel, come over here, I hear somebody's coming.
And we would have two enemies AI coming over.
And while they were approaching, the player would get a pop-up saying,
use R2 to use listen mode so you can see enemies coming.
There was a big problem.
The pull-up.
It would have made the whole combat really clunky.
And there was a drop-down in the area afterwards,
which you're going to see.
not fun, not fun at all.
And the space itself wasn't really great for combat,
so we just cut our losses, didn't even
try to make it work, and just left a good pacing
for the player to go through.
And this is how, in the end, it played.
Hey, boost me up.
So as you can see, this pull-up takes really long time.
And imagine if the AI came down here and the combat exploded
and them coming up and down and make it really weird.
So you could have killed them while doing the pull-up.
I'm sure we could have found a better solution,
but we were in such a late stage in the project
that finding other solutions wasn't really easy.
And as you can see, this area is really tight.
And we couldn't really change much.
And here we get to the point that there is a drop down
and there is another combat.
And that would have ruined pretty much everything
in the next setup.
And here is the second encounter,
which is actually my favorite.
I didn't do much layout changes here, but I did a lot of cover changes and a lot of AI
scripting. So, the main problem with the area after the playtest, after analyzing the
playtest, was that all the enemy AI was inside the warehouse, so it wasn't really
showcasing outside. And the player would just engage combat.
And that's not what we wanted for this area.
This area, actually, we wanted to have the player
to learn how to grab, drag, and kill stealthy.
So we took another approach.
We got the AI that was inside of the warehouse to move around
so you could see them from the windows outside.
And also, we got two guys coming towards the player,
so hoping that the player wouldn't be compelled to get
start shooting. And we also placed them facing conveniently other places so you could just
stealth kill them. And that would make also this area a bit unnecessary uh was too big and
too like distracting for the player. And we had this iteration just play tested and we spotted
lots of problem with it.
First of all, the player started shooting.
There was a guy in front of him, and you have a gun.
So you shoot at it.
And that didn't quite work well.
Also, they were close, but not too close.
And you still felt like, oh, yeah, I can handle them.
I'm going to fight them.
No.
Scratch that.
Let's try another approach.
We kept the area.
And we had
the enemy eye coming towards you again,
but not stopping in front of you,
so you weren't compelled to headshot them.
They would go on the side,
so we used the side of the truck,
and also one enemy eye would come over
and place himself on the side
and just be looking at fantastic crates,
which is great for the player.
I'm a firm believer of leading by example and I try to do it as much as I can.
So I had Tess to set the tone for the area.
Tess was gonna go and take down a guy for you.
And that was making the difference actually.
So she would tell you to sneak out with her and.
She would take another cover position next to the warehouse.
So here you can go and take down the guy over the truck that
is doing his patrolling.
Or you can approach the area where Tess is in,
and there would be a trigger all around that area.
So when the player approached that place,
the two enemies AI would go and talk to each other.
And Tess would take the position in the room.
to make sure she's going to help you with the kill.
So she's still setting the tone for you.
And after that, she would say, I take one, you take the other.
And if you manage to do a stealth kill,
she would shoot the other guy.
So really what the player was going to have to do
was killing two guys total, which is.
a good amount for the second combat,
and also if the combat exploded,
you had very few enemies left.
Also, one thing to mention is that,
since our AI, now I knew that it works best on bigger areas,
cutting the left area with a truck was kind of a mistake
because...
If the combat starts, it's always better to have options,
and you can also hide from the guys.
And this is how it plays in the end.
More of Robert's guys.
So here the player walks.
Two of our guys died trying to take Tessa.
Guarantee that she and Joel are on their way here
right now to get Robert.
And here the player has free range of comma, so he's free to look at where the AI goes,
and also to look at Tess doing her ninja move.
So this is me playing, I like to kill this guy.
First. Second, just drag grab and kill him.
I have less people spotting me in case I go and kill the guys in the room and his patrolling
around is not really safe.
So here I approach this area, this side, but I'm gonna go and turn all the other sides
so you know I'm not lying and Tess really says that she's gonna kill the other guy.
Yep, I lined them up against the wall and bang, bang, bang.
Executed all of them.
You take one out, I'll take the other.
They're cracking down on him hard.
I got a cousin with him.
Seriously?
Yeah. Idiot thinks he's gonna save the world.
Hope he's alright.
Take it easy, see?
Thank you Anthony.
Is our game designer Naughty Doggy helped me in this area to hook up Tess and make her look awesome?
And we go to the third encounter, which was the trickiest of all for me.
This area actually did change very, very little.
I did some cover plus in the interiors, but the whole setup was pretty fixed.
The level was far in production, and it wasn't really much I could have done to change the
layout.
I did what I could do, which is improve some things,
like the AI.
So I looked at the problem with this space and
Again, like the other places, the player couldn't really tell which was the threat, how many
enemies they will have to face if they started combat.
And they ended up getting overwhelmed in tight spaces.
And there are like three spaces in this area and they're quite tight.
So starting a combat is not ideal.
And what I did, like in the other area, was showcasing the enemies.
But in this area particularly, we were introducing destructible, which is bottles and bricks.
And since I believe in leading by example, I had Tess throwing a bottle for you and doing a combo kill again.
Unfortunately, I didn't know that that wouldn't work because of our systems having tasks doing an
animation and if the player was trolling her, she would end up doing very bad bugs and I had to
remove it. So that was not an option, sadly. So the only thing we could have done was putting a
lot of throwables around at player height and hoping the player would...
take them and also give them a chance to use it.
Like, as you can see in the warehouse on the left,
I have two enemies AI that look at each other.
So you have kind of to distract one
if you don't want to start a combat.
So the other AI would take convenient position.
One of the guy would go back inside
and the other one would take also cover inside.
But I'm not gonna put any...
other lines because this is all up to the player. Actually this is not script except for
following you and helping you in this thing but this is how it plays. So as you can see I have
the AI coming towards you. Not inviting the player to just engage combat. There are three.
and also inviting the player to take the stealthy route.
We also place this guy outside there.
But you have to reiterate on drug, rob, and killing.
So the other group don't spot you.
So as you can see there are plenty of throwables, but Yatas is not really helping in any way,
which actually makes the player fairly alone if he wants to take this stealthy approach.
So I hide this guy in case the other guys start looking for him.
And then I proceed splitting up the two guys talking.
You hear that? It came from over there!
You got anything? Anything?
I'm in for something.
So I ended up using one throwable for two guys, and I actually do a mistake from my
play right now.
I get the last guy spot me, but it kind of worked out really well because I'm using the
destructible in another way, which is my favorite way, to be honest.
So yeah, he's coming and thankfully there's a bottle right behind me.
And I throw it in his face, which is awesome.
And as you can see, it's pretty tight spaces all around, so...
Really starting combat wasn't ideal.
And this is the fourth encounter, which is the dock
encounter, and is the one that I changed the most in terms
of layout.
Do you see the water over there?
That water wasn't water.
It was a humongous space with lots of AI.
This area had also the shipping containers.
They were two tires, and you could go on top of them.
So it was really two floors.
And it created a very overwhelming space
for the player.
And latest results showed that a lot of players
just died in there.
which highlighted a few problems.
It wasn't just that.
The area was too big, and so I closed off part of it.
I removed one layer of it,
and I also made the boat unplayable.
Sad.
I like boats.
But.
it had to be done and also I scratched out all the AI that was there and just picked my bottles
and took just enough AI that I needed. So this is how it ended up to be and the main problem
actually of this area was another one. It was a layout problem. It was that, so do you see where
Tess and Joel are?
That is an elevated position with a good cover spot.
So there, everyone was engaged in combat.
I did it too.
You know, you get there, you're in an awesome position,
you're in an advantage position,
and there is a guy and there is a headshot.
How can I miss that?
And I could totally handle all the guys, yeah.
I died.
Like all the players.
So, it was really inviting to start combat and feel really powerful, but it was misleading
because there were a ton of guys inside the warehouse that you couldn't see.
So, what I did was I brainstormed with our amazing designers and we thought about a lot
of ideas.
And of course, the ideal situation would be, I change the geo.
No.
In this case, changing the height of one piece like that would have meant changing the height of
all the levels after or all the levels before.
Totally undoable. We were shipping like in a few months. Not possible.
So scratch that and somebody had the awesome idea to like use the cheapest thing we could possibly use and
it was like
it wanted me to implement it with just one of our animation
for vaulting and jumping down to just try it out.
And it actually worked.
So what we do here, we make Tess and Joel jumping down.
The cutscene guys, of course, did it better afterwards.
But that totally did it, because the player wasn't
in an advantage position starting.
It wasn't the most brilliant move.
Joel could do, jumping down of a vantage point,
but it worked.
And also I removed, I asked the artist
to remove all the cover in that big spot.
So even if you went up there again,
which was something we considered,
you were really exposed on both sides.
So it wasn't really a vantage point anymore.
For the AI, in the first part,
When you're in the cutscene in this upper space,
I actually showcase all the AI in the whole level.
They just pass by, and you know exactly how many enemies
you're going to face if you want to start combat.
And this is how we fix the first part of this level.
There's our boy.
As you can see, all the AI moving behind them, they're all guys you're going to have to face
in this area.
So the player can see clearly that there are people going inside and they're going to have
to face them if they start combat.
And
This area is actually the graduation test
to all the other areas.
So I needed a space that was flexible enough
to support all the lessons we taught the player.
I don't know who's left out there to sell us stuff.
And we also introduced the shiv, which
wasn't a big deal because we already
introduced stealth kills.
So we just put it there for fun for the player.
So as you can see, the player still feels big.
And you know, for the amount of AI, it's kind of perfect.
And it didn't really need much.
It just makes the AI act better, being more open and giving you more opportunities.
So you don't really need to kill these two guys I'm gonna kill, you can just go through the next area.
But I wanted to give you guys an idea of the space and how it feels now that it's shrunk like half the size.
Also I wanted to show how good of a player I am.
Also, in case of a combat exploded in this part of the level, the AI from the other side
would just quietly approach you depending on how many enemies were left, so to not overwhelm
you in this big space because they could sneak on your back.
In this area we had for the first time melee guys, so it was going to be kind of challenging
having everybody coming at you at once.
So the idea here is use Lisa mode because you know that there are six people but I know
this level so I throw this in the face and I kill her.
And this is my work in the tutorial.
But I wanted to show some example on the DLC
that I worked on and how working on the single player
really helped me on approaching levels.
And what I did immediately, after shipping the project,
The Last of Us, I started working on my level.
for multiplayer, because I knew there was going to be a DLC for multiplayer.
And I was really inspired from this level.
I'm not going to give spoilers, because I know that some people didn't play, but this
is one of my favorite areas in the game.
And my lesson here is that when you have a plan for...
something, when you have a plan for your level, don't be afraid of taking different things
and do your changes because it will pay off.
You're going to gain so much time and this is how it worked for me.
I knew exactly which pieces I wanted to use for my level and I went to take them and this
is how I changed them.
So, this is the bus depot and in a single player there's only one side where the player is
Going around, no spoilers, sorry.
So I had to change it slightly on multiplayer.
I had to add a whole layer with access for the street levels
to have the flow I intended in my map.
And I also added another room towards the ticket side
so it could really fit the size of my level.
And another building I used.
which is where you see giraffes for the first time.
It's this building that really inspired me
because it had an awesome potential for sniper perches
and it was a great terrace and had like interiors
that were really spacious downstairs
and I just needed a few tweaks.
So in our multiplayer, verticality is not
Super smooth, and also our radar really doesn't tell you if you're on the second floor or the first floor,
which is really paranoia, maximum level, every time you go around. It's really intense.
And having two floors is pretty much the best solution, and also...
It was working better for us and also didn't elevate all the purchase in crazy levels and crazy views.
And these are the other bunch of changes I did was opening up the second floor and
just nitpicking which place I wanted the player to be able to snap from,
closing a bunch of things and adding tons of access so the player just could go on the second floor smoothly.
I have to say I think this is our most vertical level that we have,
and it really worked great.
So when I started in pre-production, I was actually...
behind the other levels.
And I was like, OK, I'm going to take my time.
And then we started the playtest.
And I actually ended up leaving my level
because it was in a great state just from the first playtest
and taking over another one.
And this is what I mean for paying off.
If you have a plan, it just works.
And it makes everything smoother.
So.
The thing is that the other level, the only plan that the other level had, the one that I took over,
was being as similar as the single player as possible.
which really didn't work for it.
The main offender was the height.
It created a lot of slope differences
that were covered by lots of stairs,
creating lots of choke points on stairs,
which meant that...
The guys were exposed during their trying to reach interiors
and it really wasn't doing great for anybody.
So lowering it, it improved the flow and the access
towards all the buildings.
The other thing I did was scouting for better asset.
The problem with this level was also that it's the suburbs.
All houses were looking the same.
And
It's a house, it has a living room, it has a kitchen.
And as much as you change colors,
as much as you try to change up props, it's a house.
It's gonna be hard to tell which house it is.
And my idea was using different building
and I remembered from playing all the single player
more times that there was this building
just right in the area next to it.
No, I can't say spoilers.
Sniper area.
So I changed this building to fit our needs,
not having it too open and not having to access for snipers.
And it was one of our landmarks for this level.
Also, I've been looking for bigger houses
so we didn't have to fit it with just lots of spaces, lots
of houses.
And.
I found this one, which was pretty iconic with all the writings on top.
And it covered a lot of space in the levels, and it removed two houses.
And, of course, it needed changes, so we ended up removing the stairs,
and so to improve the flow, like we did before,
and removing the single-player environmental storytelling.
Because...
you know, in single player, an open window up there with something hanging is telling you
something, can tell you something. In multiplayer is, oh, sniper is going to be there, how can I
kill him? Oh, is he going to be there? Oh, I better stay inside. It really doesn't work. If it's not
used, close it. Just be straight and use a language of interaction that works for multiplayer.
And that's it for me.
You know, every game comes with its own challenges,
and you might be working on single player, you might be working on multiplayer,
and it might be chaotic.
You might join a game at the very end of it,
and you've got to make the best of it, try to understand it.
And I believe if you follow these tips...
you might end up like me, which means that I not only survive it, but I kind of look forward to the game development madness that is...
So, this is the... are the other dogs talking? Go to their talks.
Anthony is going to talk. He's awesome, so go to his talk.
and questions I think we have a few minutes...
No questions?
No.
Okay. I guess I'm really clear.
Quick question. You mentioned you use cinematic to get from like one place to another.
Is there some hesitation in like asking for a whole cinematic just to solve a little problem?
know if you plan for it.
When I joined, it was really late and it was madness.
Asking for a cinematic at a very late stage,
I was even impressed for our animators what they did.
They actually let me change a whole area and they did cuts,
so to allow me just to have cover.
And if they didn't cut it, you would see the player.
just running through things otherwise.
So if you plan for it, there's no hesitation.
We actually rely on cinematic a lot.
Yeah, I was thinking like with the memory allowance
animation has for like cinematics and everything,
is there something that makes them want
to hesitate to give you that?
No, we actually... again, it's about planning, it's about how you load your pieces of levels
and then you will manage to get everything in memory if you plan accordingly.
Alright, thanks.
No problem.
During the changes of the levels from the single player to multiplayer, how much did
you cooperate with the environment artists or did you do all the changes by your own
and the environment artist was just looking, screaming at you like, what are you doing
with my levels?
This is where I actually learned the most about level art and how our level artists
work because, you know, after the ship in the game, we had a break.
There was nobody.
And I had to find myself out what to do.
But obviously, after we needed level artists,
I can't make things that pretty.
No way.
But yeah, we allowed.
We had level artists assigned afterwards,
and they did their magic for that.
Thanks.
How does the setting of The Last of Us affect your level design?
Like?
Playing The Last of Us, I guess, had a really different feel
from going through the different levels, like a lot more corridors,
and other FPS's where the setting is a lot more open.
Like, if you think of something like Borderlands,
where you're running around, like, deserts and stuff like that.
So, how did you consider that?
Well...
You know, the game is totally different, you know.
You're slower and the environment has to fit the game more.
So you know the player is not going to run crazy distances,
so you can have tight spaces and have a tight feeling.
But for instance, if you want to combat, you build a larger space.
And in multiplayer, we knew which sides were working better.
And you know, you play test it and you get the gist of it.
So.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Hi, considering that you talk about the different passes that you did through the levels,
usually what was the time frame between, you know, getting the feedback from the previous,
you know, iteration of the level until the implementation of the next one and,
you know, the following play test?
You know, when I started, we were doing like
everyday iteration on things and you don't need a lot of players to know that something is
wrong. So if something is wrong usually we just act on it and it's pretty quick especially at
that stage you really want to play every second and we just
You know, at Naughty Dog, we sit all together, designers,
so we just stand up, grab a guy, and it's like,
can you please play this?
And everybody's super flexible for that.
And the great thing is that it's the first time
that I work in a company that is like this, so.
single player, multiplayer, and the last of us are uncharted, we all work in the same pod.
And we're all together, so, and we're the best critics and supporters for each other.
So the iteration are so fast, and sometimes I wouldn't really even go to anybody to understand
that something was wrong. And that's the main thing, just fail as fast as you can,
so you can make it better.
Okay, thank you very much.
Hi, thanks for the great talk.
Can you talk a little bit about the custom tools that you used?
For example, did you have a level editor?
Was it easy to use, hard to use?
I'm kind of curious about the process, the tools that you used.
So we have different editors and we use Maya for the layout.
So that's pretty standard.
And then we have other editors to implement a few objects
to move around, foreground objects.
And we script with a scripting language
that is kind of similar to Python.
And then we compile that.
And that's how we script.
Thank you.
Hi, thank you again for the talk.
I have two questions.
One of them, I started to mention about the AI,
that sometimes you have to deal with that.
And I was wondering if you have to also code something
or if you just work.
building the AI to, you know, certain points, see how would it work against the player?
And the second question is, up to what point do you start making the level design itself?
If they give like a rough sketch from the art or just some blocks,
and how does this affect your freedom to change and make your levels?
So...
For the AI, the things I learned was how to use the AI,
because the AI was already there.
And I had preconcepts of how to script the AI,
because I've been using different tools.
And one of the things that I learned about asking questions,
I used to script the AI that was in different states.
So it was in normal state, where I was scripting it and putting
in places.
And then I would script it for combat.
But that is not how it works for the last of us.
Our AI was working best when left by itself
while in combat.
And I had to learn it by my expenses.
I had a lot of bugs in those AI setups.
And that's how I actually, one of our designers
just came by and said, why are you using two states?
I'm like, oh, thank you for fixing my 15 bugs.
I should have asked you, but you know.
So really, it depends which AI you're using,
however you're in scripting.
And what the second part of the question?
About when do you start making the level design itself?
If you start, like the team gives you
like a block stage or a rough sketch or something,
and how does that change your freedom
to mix it up whatever way you think it's
better for the level design.
It depends.
Like for multiplayer, there is no such a thing.
We scouted from the single player.
So we didn't have sketches or any.
The idea was basically feel like you're in one place
in the game that you've been before,
and you get to play it again over and over.
And for single player, I tend to not let myself being blocked.
buy some sketches.
I like to implement ideas.
And then I just try to match it with the art.
And if I can't, I start from scratch.
Thank you very much.
Hi.
So it felt like the tutorial came in quite late
in the development cycle.
But when playing, it felt like it wasn't really.
It felt quite seamless to play.
So did you have to adapt the narrative at all
to fit the tutorial or create new narrative sections for it?
I couldn't create any unique section for it.
So I could just tweak what was there.
And we tried to really see the problems with the play test
instead of just like, I think we might change everything.
And also, finding the simplest solution and the easiest
solution.
Sometimes it's the best thing.
You don't need complicated thing.
You don't need the perfect thing to make it work.
Sometimes just finding that thing that makes a difference
is the key to make it better.