My name is Liz Ryerson. I am a game designer, composer of music, visual artist, and critic.
I did the music for Dysphoria, which you might have played. I did a game called Problematic.
I write stuff about games on my blog, and yeah, I have some art, actually, that is going to be sold at the Wild Rumpus party tonight.
Anyway, um...
This talk is about kind of conveying ideas through abstraction.
So let's get started.
This, by the way, is a screenshot from an Atari 800 game.
It's like a sort of a homebrew Polish game, in case you're wondering.
So the history of video games is kind of a history of expression
defined by technological limitations.
In hindsight, it's easy to look back fondly on the old days of games and forget all the
mind-numbing efforts that went into even making these games run.
Back then, games were constantly engaged in a struggle to make any sort of basic sense
of the language of game design and try to make it look or feel like something kind of
tangible and interesting within the strict limitations that were imposed on them.
And I think a lot of, like, older games carry this very strongly, for better or for worse.
Now of course we choose the limits, oh, sorry.
And we can do pretty much whatever we want within our own limitations
and what kind of context we're working in.
But I think there's a thing where we sort of see this gaminess,
this kind of expression defined by the limits of this technology
as kind of a prison that we need to escape from.
like as something that needs to be kind of transcended in order to like realize our ideas
or in order for games to be taken more seriously.
Games like Call of Duty, Grand Theft Auto, whatever, we think of these games as approaching
a kind of like representational realism or kind of like a documentary realism or as speaking
at the very least speaking to our reality in some more kind of real or tangible way
even if you know we don't like them or whatever.
But we forget that there are thousands and thousands and millions of tiny little details
from many different sources that go into the construction of building these realities.
In actuality, game worlds in Call of Duty or GTA are no less abstract in some ways than
Mario or Tetris.
They are way, way more detailed and convincing facsimiles of something more resembling our
own reality.
A lot of the ideas that we see in games are not really new, instead they're sort of retellings of retellings of retellings.
Maybe this area in the newest Call of Duty game was inspired by the original Alien film or a Superman comic,
or maybe it's cribbed from other games like Bioshock or Half-Life or something like that.
And I think increasingly, games have been so reflective of themselves
that they've stopped being able to acknowledge how constructed the worlds in them are.
Because we've seen an idea or a gameplay concept so many times before we start to see it
as being part of our reality.
And then as a culture, we're kind of unable to accept that these are abstractions,
because when you see these kind of images saturated everywhere around you,
it's easy to feel like they're current and relevant and kind of speak to you in some way.
And that's kind of the scary thing.
When you put something out into the world, it can affect other people in a really powerful way
that you probably never even considered.
And...
people start to internalize it and it becomes part of the way that we
construct like the reality around us outside of a game
and I think games do this in a really really powerful way
but the kind of weird paradox here is
that while game worlds are like feel increasingly real and sort of powerful
almost hyper real
uh... there's still kind of like an undeniable fakeness to it like you know
the uncanny valley that kind of stuff
and it doesn't ever really go away
But I don't think this is actually really a bad thing at all.
I think, like, contrary to popular belief, their fakeness provides us a different way
of looking at our reality and looking at ourselves, and realizing ideas or feelings that we can't
fully experience in our own reality through the language of this machine.
We just have to understand that it's a machine, and this is the language that it's speaking
in, and it is not our own reality.
And, you know, games can put us outsiders kind of might fear games because they're kind
of an unknown or they put people into this, like, trance-like state.
But it can just as easily be kind of a dreaming or meditative or contemplative or playful
state as kind of like a violent, angry, control-obsessed one that, like, the cliched image of video
games is.
Okay.
So the disclaimer is this talk is not about how to kind of realize more abstract design
ideas through AAA.
I don't have experience with that.
I am here to tell you about kind of smaller, more independent things and talk about ideas
that you might not have realized, but I can't help with that.
I think this is more intended to be inspirational.
and kind of communicating with fellow game designers
or people thinking about games,
or just curious and wanna be introduced to new things.
I'm also, you know, this is like,
I'm not gonna be up, get up here and like shit talk AAA
because I don't have time to, and it's not really worth it.
Like, you all are probably intimately familiar
with all the problems of AAA,
so I don't really need to talk about that.
So this is a game, sorry the screenshot is quite big so it takes up the...
This game's called Strange Climbing by Strangethink.
He actually has a game downstairs at the Mild Rumpus, kind of like an art gallery game.
But I like this game because it's kind of a procedural first-person climber
where your goal is just to make it to the top of this weird structure.
And it's generated, obviously.
But I find it interesting how the mechanics of the game are so integrated into the actual structure itself.
Like, the geometry kind of serves both an aesthetic purpose of just being like this weird structure
and kind of like the mood of that is like a very distinctive thing.
And also like a gameplay purpose where all those kind of jagged edges are like things that you have to interact with
and potentially like assess.
whether you're able to jump further up.
And I actually really like this game because it's very simple but it's very challenging at the same time.
And it's all just doing it within this one little structure and the jump key.
In a way, I think it's kind of applying the same principle.
I saw this when I was in film class,
this documentary about this architect, Louis Kahn,
who sort of wanted his buildings
to not hide their raw materials.
This is a big kind of.
If you saw Robert Yang's talk about level design yesterday, he sort of talks about this, you know,
philosophy of more modern architecture is buildings not hiding their materials and stuff like that.
And I think that game by Strangethink is very similar, in that it's completely computer-generated
and unreal, but it's still beautiful in a way, even though you can see that it's not
like a real structure.
It's not hiding the sort of algorithms and whatever that created it in the structure,
it's kind of embracing it.
So I don't think that like, you know, not hiding your parts
means like, like a lack of polish.
And that's one thing that I want to talk about.
Like, you know, it was a concern when I submitted my talk
that I should talk about this.
Like, I think that polish is kind of a loaded term
or at least a kind of a construction
in a lot of game circles,
because we kind of do have, you know,
established standards of what polish means.
that have come out of industry practices,
what it means visually and sound-wise
in terms of the design,
and what is accessible, what it communicates clearly,
what it means to communicate.
And usually, or at least often,
it's equated to a level of detail
or a level of this looks like it's actually
something that was designed and intentionally made.
Or it can just mean more shiny and commercial looking.
But I think the point is that constructions are kind of,
this is a construction kind of defined
by the culture of games.
And it doesn't really necessarily speak to
how well the content of the games is conveyed
or tell you about what's inside the game.
In fact, there really is kind of no approach
that's necessarily better for work across the board.
it completely is dependent on what you're kind of trying to express.
And there are a lot of kind of range of emotions and ideas
that aren't expressed through this kind of AAA idea,
or even like a more commercial indie idea of what polish means.
And I think if you look at something like Polish in kind of a more progressive light,
and you look at it as being a reflection of how well a game realizes its ideas,
it's more subjective, but it's not arbitrary.
Like, there is definitely a difference between things that are kind of like
one-off experiments and things that effectively kind of use a particular style or idea to realize their ideas.
And we're going to look at some of those.
So this is a game, it looks like a YouTube window, but it's actually a game by Steven Lovell, aka InkRipara,
who is probably the most interesting, no, without a doubt, in my opinion, the most interesting game designer who's working today.
And I'd say this game is very polished.
It was for like a Ludum Dare.
But like essentially you open it up
and it's like this YouTube window
and you're actually playing the game
that's inside the window,
but it's a finite length that like 210
that it's saying, you know,
that's as long as the game is.
And there's a narration over top with this guy,
like boring narration.
This guy is talking about,
yeah, this game is okay, I guess.
And like, and then like random like gay porn windows pop up and
you have to like click them out. And then like people like try
to message you on messenger and you're trying to like click that
out while you're controlling the thing. And sometimes the cat
just jumps on the dude's keyboard and like screws you up
just like and you die.
And like so this game is only two minutes long. It's kind of a joke game
But the way that it's presented is really like really effective because you open it up, and it's like what what why am I in?
A YouTube window like what is this it has this purpose the presentation has this purpose of sort of
defamiliarizing you with your kind of relationship with games and
you know
putting it in a different context.
And I think for this purpose, it's like a joke.
It's not really trying to communicate something
narrative-wise, but it does it really, really effectively
and really powerfully, which is why I think
it's a really interesting game.
Also, there's this other game by him
that looks, again, completely different.
Let's see if I can open it up in, okay, that's another game.
Let's see if I can open it up in a window here.
It's called The Terrible Whiteness of Appalachian Nights.
And I'm not going to play very far into it.
But it has this sort of ASCII art style.
And it's incredibly disturbing.
As you can probably tell, it uses this kind of weird, like, old computer monitor kind of font to make, to kind of, you know, give off a particular feeling of weirdness and disorientation.
It's really well reflected by the audio, and I think the audio really does the strongest work in this game.
But, I'm going to skip all this.
Essentially all you do in this game is wander around and you're this like, ASCII character
and this crazy, weird, frantic music plays in the background.
And you're this like, housewife who's aimlessly wandering around her house, kind of periodically
checking up on members of her family, and basically all she does is sleep.
And most of it you're just kind of wandering around frantically.
just like checking on your family members and uh, I don't know, the- this- the music
and stuff is just like...
There's almost kind of like a dissociative approach to the...
Like the visuals is almost like kind of reflecting the dissociation of the character.
That there's something like really disturbing sort of going on under the surface.
And that everything kind of in her life has been abstracted to these symbols
that she just doesn't know how to control or do anything with anymore.
And this all kind of builds up to a really bizarre, not safe for work moment at the end
that I don't really know what it means, but kind of reflects the mood of the game.
So I guess the point that I wanted to get across here is that this game uses that kind
of style to, you know, that we associate with very kind of older games that don't have that
didn't have the graphical capabilities to realize much and it embraces it as kind of
a reflection of the narrative themes of the game.
Another game sort of indirect contrast by him is called Slave of God.
I'll show you a video here.
It's like a really bizarre.
game where you're in a dance club and you're just like wandering around and dancing with people.
Essentially it looks like, um, like being on drugs.
Um, but like, you know, when people say like, oh this looks like being on drugs,
no this game like literally looks like being on drugs.
It like has this all these like bizarre shader effects, but um it like kind of
captures this feeling way more
Directly and sort of powerfully than other any other games that I've seen that sort of oh goodness. Well you get the idea anyway
um and
I don't know, it's really effective in a kind of a way that's hard to convey.
But the point is that these games, while they're all very different, kind of really effectively
convey what they're setting out to capture.
And they use all the tools of games to do this.
They use the visuals, they use the design, they use the interface, they use the audio,
as you've seen.
Like...
which is a really overlooked component, by the way,
as someone who's like a composer and sound designer
of like conveying sort of narrative
or ideas that you want to convey in a game.
And I think this is why I find his work really interesting.
It's all completely based on what idea he's trying to realize
and the visuals and everything are kind of just all in service
to whatever idea he's trying to realize.
And that's why I think he's...
like probably the most interesting game designer working in games right now.
So this is another designer who's a little less well known.
His name is Pedro Paiva.
I think that's how you pronounce it.
He's Brazilian.
This game's called Carro Crescia.
And like literally, it runs even faster than this.
This just animated GIF is slowed down because, you know, I blew it up and everything.
But, um, it's a short game and basically all you can do is, like, you can't cross the road
because there's too many cars, like, and you're just like, your character's frowning, and
then you go into, like, the car god, like, um, garage here and then they just tell you
you don't have a car so you can't do anything.
And like...
And that's all it is, it's like this really, like, weird, sarcastic commentary about cars,
and like, why you need a car for everything, and like,
it just conveys it in this kind of like weird, like, bootleg game-looking style,
where, you know, it just seems like this kind of like weird amateurish thing,
but it reflects kind of the weird tone of the game, and, um...
the kind of anarchic sort of ideas that he is trying to get across.
His games are almost kind of like I describe as being like anti-games.
So if I can get this to run, this is another game of his.
It's like a compilation of, it seems like some kind of compilation of arcade games.
This one's called Mel Gibson the Hedgehog.
See, I don't speak Spanish, but...
You open the game and it does this.
Sometimes it just randomly crashes, I don't know.
But these are all like broken arcade games, basically.
And this is like, as you can tell, this is, I don't know if you guys are Sonic fans, but
this is the Green Hill Zone music.
Oh no, I died.
And here's another game that I like a lot.
Yeah, every game does this when you hit start and sometimes it just crashes.
And you're like this little frenzy thing running around.
I don't know actually what the goal in this game is.
Most of the other ones have goals, but I like what happens when you die.
Anyway, that's called VHS Maluko.
And it's sort of a compilation of like...
really weird, anti-game, sarcastic takes on old arcade games.
And the games are hardly playable, but there's an undeniable artistic sensibility that runs
through his games of this kind of anarchist, like...
you know, uh, like, idea of, like, the game's, the game mechanics are dishonest, and they're
kind of disingenuous, and, and we need to kind of destroy them or melt them.
And actually, it's something that he talks about, like, called melting video games, and
he says, um, from his Patreon, it's, uh, when I talk about melting video games, I'm thinking
of corroding the borders that maintains the most diverse part of people away from the inside community.
He's not a native English speaker, so...
And the inside people stuck in.
I love video games, but I hate the mainstream culture around it.
And I think, like, the...
You know, the...
The reaction that a lot of people would have is,
oh, these games look amateurish.
But if you play them, you realize
that there's something very different about these games.
They are very simple, and they are very abstract
and broken looking.
But there's kind of a philosophy or sensibility
that's reflected in the design and in the way
that it's presented.
And I think that's something that we need to understand
is very intentional.
And it's something that
is using this kind of idea of glitch or like brokenness as part of its philosophy rather than just doing it as a trend or whatever.
So I think it's really important to make that distinction.
And it's, yeah, it's not just done because it's easy to do.
I mean, it might be easy to do and that's a good reason to do something,
but that's not the only reason to do something.
Or really, the best reason to do something.
So, like, abstraction is not just about glitch or looking weird in 8-bit.
There are plenty of, like, I think horror games are really the best at kind of realizing
abstraction, you know, embracing abstraction and using that in kind of the game mechanics,
you know, reflecting what...
They want to get across and which is usually a feeling of like terror or disorientation. This game is called nevermind
It just had a kickstarter recently
And like this is the main area that you are outside where there's this like bizarre
models of the 3d house that are like stacked
Like 3d models of a house that are just stacked up on top of each other in a really surreal way and when you play
It it's like
obviously intended to reflect this kind of idea that the house is a terrifying place
and it's like building up on your sort of the characters or your sort of like anxieties about
being in the house and you see that it's a very like easy visual metaphor that kind of reflects
what the game is trying to get across. Something that we understand intuitively but might not
necessarily be able to explain. I think like horror games do that really well.
Like I said, these visuals are very, quote unquote, polished in the conventional sense,
but it's still doing something very weird with the form that is different and abstract
and not real in like the representational realism sense.
This is a shot from Silent Hill 4, and you have this character who's like wandering around
with you in your apartment.
She's pretty nice.
But she just gets kind of...
beaten up throughout the game, especially if you play badly.
And sometimes at the end of the game,
she'll just be in bandages and just bruised all over.
But there's this room where you just sort of randomly
enter into, and a huge version of her head
just stares at you, and its eyes are sort of twitching.
And it's this really odd moment that
isn't necessarily explained in the plot or the story
or anything.
But I think it kind of.
is something that the Silent Hill games in particular are really good at doing.
Reflecting the themes of the games in a very kind of surreal way
that's hard to really verbally express why it works or what it's saying.
But it has this incredibly strong impact on you when you're playing.
And it's not just an impact of being scared.
It's also like, what is this? Why am I experiencing this?
it kind of pressures you to think about your relationship with the game in a way that you might not normally do so.
moment that I think about a lot is in Silent Hill 2, where it's towards the end of the
game. I think they do this in several Silent Hill games, but like, you're in this sort
of hotel and your character is kind of, without spoiling too much, like your character's kind
of psychological world is falling apart and you know, you have like very clear maps and
layouts in the game, but um...
And at this point, it starts raining inside the hotel,
which is already like, what is this doing?
And you open a door and you go to a completely other side
of the hotel in a completely different room,
and all the doors just start connecting with each other
in this really bizarre way, unpredictable way.
And it's something that games like,
it's almost arbitrary what door that you enter into
where it leads you in a game, right?
Like, it's just anything,
it's something that you can change easily.
But it's using this in a way to kind of reflect the mood of the game
and kind of defamiliarize your relationship with the space
and say that this is kind of a psychological world, this is not really a real world.
And I think it's something that games are incredibly good at doing.
So another game that's one of my favorite games is called Yume Nikki.
It's a free Japanese game, RPG Maker game.
And it's another game sort of about dreams.
Let's see if I can show you a video quickly.
And you sort of, you're this little girl,
and you wander around this kind of weird surreal world.
Let's skip ahead so that I can...
And you enter from your apartment, you enter into this...
I don't know. Okay.
You enter into this like bizarre hallway of doors and the doors kind of send you through
to these very surreal worlds which the further that you go into it the more kind of the less
abstract they become and the more kind of reflective of something that this girl might
be experiencing you actually see like and you're actually able to extrapolate some narrative
from it.
but it's a very kind of non-linear narrative that isn't really, like, something that you can explicitly define.
But I think, like, this game has a huge following.
People have tried to just kind of interpret the plot.
There's a lot of, like, discussion about it.
And it's all because this kind of...
just curiosity of exploring this game and like all the these bizarre symbols what they mean and
and what your relationship with them is because it's something that's just so different from
from what other games try to do because really like you have these objects that you can use to
do certain things but really basically all you do is wander around and there isn't really any
sort of direction that you're guided towards so that
kind of allows you to have your own relationship with the game and experience it in a different
way than something is like, yeah, she just got the frog power and now she can turn into
a frog.
But yeah, let's exit out of that.
I think in a way, a game like Yume Nikki is kind of a metaphor for all games because we
We enter into these doors, we enter into these digital spaces not knowing what's going to come out.
We know it's not real, we know it's going to like change us in some way,
and we're going to have some certain interaction with it, but it's kind of mysterious.
It's almost like we're kind of injecting ourselves with something without really knowing what is going to happen.
But these doors, like, through their kind of weird abstract machine language and, like, these kind of array of symbols, tell us something about ourselves and tell us something about the way that we experience the world.
And I think that's tremendously beautiful and powerful.
Games are in basically dreams.
So before I continue on my last thing, I just want to mention a few games by women, because
I didn't do that in this talk, and I feel really bad about that, but there are some
games that I also think that you should really check out.
Some games by Lilith, who made this game called Crip Worlds, which I'm biased because I did
like the sound effects and the music for it, but she has another game called, what is it
called?
Oneiric Gardens? I don't know how to... Oneiric Gardens? I don't know how to pronounce it, but it's like this kind of anthology of different weird 3D spaces that kind of seems like old PlayStation 1 games and kind of reinterpreting it.
Another game that's interesting that was almost in the IGF but not quite nominated is called Curtain.
by Laura Dreamfield. It has this really kind of bizarre lo-fi style and it's kind of more of a narrative game.
That one's definitely worth checking out. And also, one of the games that's in the Nuovo this year is called Tetragedon Games.
I think those games are tremendously, like, really, really cool and kind of use this, like, cheesy...
90s kind of net art AOL kind of old flash movie style to kind of get at their own aesthetic
thing. So those are all worth checking out. But this is a game called Judith which is
also by Ingrapar and Terry Kavanaugh who is somewhere at the conference. And it's a game
that I keep coming back to because I had a real relationship with like Wolfenstein 3D
when I grew up.
that sort of, like, there's a sort of disturbingness to that game that's never really kind of put to the surface,
but you sort of, it's sort of implied at in some of the level design, and some of the other things like that.
And so I kind of just like imagined and extrapolated based on that. I've written some articles about it that are...
worth checking out if you're interested in that.
But the thing that I like about Judith is it takes this
like raycaster 3D style, you know,
essentially 2D, 3D style,
and it kind of owns it and uses
and brings that disturbingness to the surface
as part of the narrative theme, which is about this,
it's essentially about the story of Bluebeard
and it's about this woman finding out
that her husband is actually this horrible guy
who's doing all these horrible things.
And there's another aspect to the narrative, but essentially, like, it's about this woman wandering around, kind of experiencing things passively.
And I think that it's an interesting kind of gender metaphor in there, along with Yume Nikki, about, like, the ways that women are kind of taught to interact with the world through, like, kind of passively and observation.
you know, rather than this kind of traditional masculine view of how we approach games,
where it's about interacting and sort of controlling and manipulating systems.
But anyway, that's just something I thought about.
With the history that we create, we sort of leave traces of the past behind.
Ideas or styles that we might have thought were dead keep popping up again in different contexts.
There is kind of an eeriness to the old that never quite goes away.
It's almost like a ghost.
It's almost as if it is still calling out to us to be kind of exhumed and re-explored
with all that we know now.
Conventional wisdom in games.
says that the legacy of a lot of old forgotten games
was that they were stepping stones or they were the results of technological
struggles or dead ends
or sometimes even just like embarrassments like we wanna bury them
in the ground and forget about them like
the ET story, the famous story about ET
being buried in like a
I don't know it's like a
under concrete in Arizona. There was a documentary about them digging it up. We've sort of inevitably
thrown them out for more polished or easy to play or easy to look at games. In many
ways, of course, we have improved the craft of games exponentially, design wise and game
play wise. A game as singularly industry defining as Mario was so huge because it was a huge
improvement over what came before and Mario 3 is a huge improvement over Mario.
We built that language, we know what works well, we know what feels better and smoother
to the player, but in other ways I still think we're left wanting for something more.
I know there's a lot of attitudes around game culture now that like to kind of assert that
games are bad.
games are all about like Mario and Doom and Pac-Man and that's like games culture
and that's what like gamers are and that's
that's that that gamer culture but that
that whole thing is a construction like
weird art experimental games have always existed
even before Mario and we need to
realize that like as part of the industry we need to realize
part of the history of this medium and respect it and not just like
you know, go with the Kool-Aid token narrative that everyone kind of just blindly accepts.
Here are some very strange games from the 80s. This one's called Microsurgeon.
It's for the Intellivision. You're kind of controlling this thing and you're like shooting this bacteria.
It came out in 1982, which is three years before Mario.
This game's called Deus Ex Machina. It's a Spectrum game. It's one of the first, like, art experiment games.
There's actually voiceover narration through the whole thing. It's because it was on a cassette, like...
ZX Spectrum had sort of a cassette player.
And yeah, it was a kind of interesting, ambitious game,
even though it was kind of, you know, had its own problems.
This game's called Go to Hell for the ZX Spectrum.
The same guy did another game called Soft and Cuddly,
which is also equally weird.
But this came out the same year as Mario,
and it's just as bizarre as any, like,
random weird indie game that you're gonna find online.
Probably even more bizarre, to be honest.
In spite of the technological limitations of these games,
they still speak to us,
and there's still something that makes us able to see something about them in the present.
Their unapologetic abstractness reveals something natural and intrinsic about the form of games.
I don't know, I just think that it's important to realize that this kind of experimentation has always been around.
But I believe that we need to start embracing abstractness as a virtue rather than a shortcoming.
If we're really interested in expanding the form of games, we should be leaving no stone unturned.
And of course that doesn't mean that all games have to look like...
weird 8-bit punk games or whatever, but at the very least we can be open to the ideas
that are in these games and respect them and take inspiration from them even when they're
broken and, you know, they have design weaknesses.
Games are dreams.
Their gaminess, quote unquote, is a central part
of this dream.
It's the source of their power.
It's their light.
And I believe that we do ourselves a huge disservice
to this medium the more that we spend trying
to tame this abstractness, this gaminess,
in order to build something more predictable
and representational and known,
instead of sincerely trying to explore something new
and unknown that might tell us something different
about ourselves and the world around us.
Thank you.
I'm sorry, I went a little bit over time.
I don't know if there's any time for questions.
I do have time. If you want to ask a few questions, go up to
the mic. I have a question. That was awesome. I really liked
how you made game art topics very fun and approachable. My
question is can you give us the 30 second summary of your take
on the wolf 3D aesthetic?
you said you had a whole thing you wrote about the eeriness.
Yeah. I think there's sort of a the game is about something
that's very kind of real like representational. It's about
sort of like World War II. But then there's this kind of
bizarre.
gaminess about it where you have to collect all this treasure and there's
like no way that you could carry all this treasure and they're just like
turkey dinners lying on the floor and I think it kind of it kind of toes the
line between having some sort of like realistic art and then having this like
weird gaminess that is actually kind of disturbing and I don't know if it's
intentional but it's just something that I've always kind of thought about and
had weird dreams about and things like that.
So I don't know, that's just my personal.
It's like a little grotesque, right?
Yeah, it is a little grotesque.
And that can be really kind of bad,
and that can be a good thing,
and I don't really know which way to take it with that game,
but I think it's interesting for me to think about
and look at as an illustration of other things anyway.
you felt like that other game you were comparing it with was
similar in that sense? It uses the same sort of ray caster
format but it brings that disturbingness to the surface as
part of the theme of the game as the narrative. I see those two
things as being related just because of the kind of style.
It's the same thing with like the game itself.
the game terrible whiteness of Appalachian nights. There are a
lot of old games that have that ASCII art but this is using it
in a different way and reappropriating it for something
that was always kind of there but never really kind of called
attention to. No problem.
I have a question.
Sure.
If we compare game development with art,
and if we see the path that the classic visual art followed
from some.
primitive forms, then to realism, and then to some surrealism, some abstract art.
Do you think that game development will follow the same path? And now we are seeing that it
turns from some realism to some more
abstract forms. I think there's some universal patterns but it's also not probably going to
happen in exactly the same way. But I also think it's kind of happening with a lot of indie games
and experimental games. It's always been around. It's just like it being sort of popularized and
understood it might take a while because games are tremendously complicated. There's a lot of
things that go into understanding and interacting with games.
newer generations of people are able to deal with navigating all these technological interfaces
and stuff because they grow up with it. It's so intuitive and central to their part of life. So I
think that the culture and literacy around games is definitely going to develop and that's going
to result in more weird abstract things. But yeah. No problem. Okay. I have to take it to the
wrap-up room. So I'm sorry. But I would
Thank you. If any questions, feel free to come up to me later. I hope you have a good rest of
your day. Come to Lost Levels 1 p.m.