Hello and welcome to this special edition of the 22nd Annual Independent Games Festival Awards.
As I'm sure you may have noticed, we are not all in San Francisco celebrating together.
Instead, I am in a forest and you all are tuning in from wherever you happen to be in the world right now.
I have plenty that I would love to say, but I understand attention spans are short and I'm sure you all want to get to the awards, so I'll keep this short and sweet.
These are interesting times and as a perpetual optimist, all I can think of is how much I really love our community.
Even when we're faced with extraordinary circumstances, collectively we're always moving in the right direction.
And we're supporting each other in really remarkable ways.
And while I wish that we were all together celebrating the incredible games and teams that will be honored tonight,
I am grateful that we have this opportunity to create a virtual celebration and to include
so many of you in sharing this experience with us.
So here's to you, the games and teams who received honorable mentions, the people who
worked tirelessly to make the IGF happen, and of course, best of luck to all the finalists.
So let's get this crazy experiment started.
Hi, welcome to the IGFs.
I'm Trent Custers from League of Geeks,
and we're here at our studio in Melbourne.
We couldn't come together in person this year,
but I'm honoured to be your host
for the 22nd Annual IGF Awards.
And thanks to our lead sponsor, ID at Xbox,
and a whole heap of last minute elbow grease,
we'll be doing things a little bit differently.
This year we'll be celebrating
the past year's indie achievements like this.
No envelope opening, no tuxedo,
just me, you.
and a bunch of sweet awards. ♪♪
-♪♪
Look, 2020's been kind of grim so far.
But let's not forget the heartbreak that was 2019.
And I'm talking specifically that it was a big year for video game breakups.
Bungie left Activision's bosom
and is now strutting around with that big single energy.
Reggie, our sweet, sweet Reggie, left Nintendo.
And I mean, Nintendo's gotta be pretty cut up about it.
They're dating a guy literally named Doug Bowser.
They're with Bowser.
Now, no one wants their ex to date a bad guy.
Nintendo's dating the bad guy.
And then of course, there's the messiest,
most public breakup of 2019.
Blizzard and Hong Kong.
But these are all AAA woes.
If you're an indie developer, there are more hot singles on the indie dating scene than
ever before, and they've all got a shit ton of real weird money.
That's why this IGF, we're launching Indie Daddy Dating.
We've rounded up the hottest, most cashed up daddies, and we've got them here for you
tonight.
Our first daddy has always been pretty well off, but they've recently come into a lot
of money with their newly formed Children's Entertainment Empire.
Pretty epic.
Your friends won't really approve of them, but the perks are overwhelming and they never
ask for their change back.
Our next daddy is smart, trendy, intellectual.
Your shot at everlasting love could be Apple Arcade.
This design Ford hottie will promise you the world, but once they've got you, they might
just check out.
Our next daddy is all about performance, strength, power.
with a playful jock vibe.
Meet Xbox.
They got into the dating game late
because they were all about hanging with the boys
until their 30s.
But they're our only daddy
with an Axe deodorant endorsement.
Okay, for our next daddy,
let's go a little bit more mysterious.
Flashy car, rich AF,
and they know where you live.
It's Google Stadia.
Even though they've told you 40 times what they do, you still don't understand.
Now look, if commitment isn't really your thing, and let's be honest, this is the independent
games festival after all, then our next option may be right up your alley.
Devolver, Annapurna and Raw Fury, our indie publishers.
Sure they may sleep on a mattress on the floor.
And yes.
They might even ask you to pick up the check from time to time,
but you'll never be tied down again,
unless you're into that.
Alright, let's give out some awards.
This first category terrifies established developers.
This is the IGF for Best Student Game.
A Juggler's Tale, developed by Kaleidoscube.
Stefan Oberle.
Enzio Probst.
Dominique Schuen.
Elias Kramer.
Forgotten, developed by Mutiny Games.
The Forgotten Team.
Neon Beats, developed by Okio Games.
The Neon Beats Team.
Boredome, developed by Goblin Rage.
The Boredome Team.
Nothing In Sight developed by the Nothing In Sight team.
And the winner is...
Boredome.
Thank you, IGF, for giving us this award.
It's very nice to be here.
And whether or not we receive actually this award...
We asked, you voted.
Now the winner of this award can rest easily
knowing that they've appeased our almighty overlords, the gamers.
This is the winner of the IGF Audience Award, chosen by you.
Audience Award, and the winner is A Short Hike.
Oh, wow. I'm.
so honored and excited to receive the audience award.
Thank you to everybody who voted for my weird little hiking game and
everybody who helped me get here today and make the game.
I really want to thank my partner, Dawn, who
supported me throughout the entire journey and her wisdom
and her contributions to the game made it something a lot better
and it wouldn't have been the same without her.
I really want to thank.
My friend Andrew who contributed art to the game and spent time with me while I was working on it.
I want to thank Mark for making the amazing soundtrack.
David for making the amazing logo.
And everyone else who helped contribute to the game and made it what it is today.
And of course also my mom who always encouraged me and supported me throughout this entire journey, my entire life.
So, yes, thank you so much. Thank you everyone and yeah, it's such an honor.
You can't hear good audio, you feel it.
Well, you can obviously hear good audio.
But good audio is a type of glue.
It's a bonding agent that takes all the different elements
and pulls them together into one cohesive piece.
This is the past year's greatest achievements in game glue.
This is Excellence in Audio. ♪♪♪
Excellence in Audio.
Observation, developed by No Code.
Omar Khan.
Robin Fink.
John McKellen.
Vectronom, developed by Ludopium.
Juan Urjuela.
Astrologaster.
Developed by NyamNyam.
Andrea Balcadoro.
Catherine Neal.
Jennifer Schneiderite.
Adele Kutton.
Knights and Bikes, developed by Foam Sword.
Kenneth Young.
Daniel Pemberton.
Rex Crowley.
Mu Yu.
Mutazione.
Developed by DeGhouta Fabrique.
The Mutazione Team.
Untitled Goose Game.
Developed by House House.
M. Halberstadt.
Dan Golding.
And the winner is...
Mutazione.
Hi, I'm Hannah Nicklin, Studio Lead at Digu de Fabrique.
We are totally delighted to accept this incredible honour.
Mutazione has been held by many people's hands and hearts of minds
over the 10 years since creative lead Nils Denneken
dreamt up the wonderful world of the game.
And one of the biggest influences during that time
has been composer and musician Alessandro Coronas.
Over to you, Alessandro.
Thank you, Hannah, and to everyone at IGF.
Thank you so, so much.
It's a big privilege.
And I want to extend a huge thank you to the whole team.
As we all know, making games is a gigantic team effort.
So this is also for you, pals.
You know who you are.
So thanks again.
It's a big honor and lots of love from Sardinia.
Thanks very much to the IGF Awards and judges for the nominations in this incredible honour
and congratulations to all the other winners, nominees and honourable mentions.
These next finalists found innovative ways, not just to tell their stories,
but to help you tell yours. This is Excellence in Narrative.
Mutazione, developed by De Gute Fabrique.
The Mutazione Team.
Heaven's Vault, developed by Inkle.
John Ingold.
Joseph Humphrey.
The Heaven's Vault Team.
Elsinore, developed by Golden Glitch Studios.
The Elsinore team.
Wide Ocean Big Jacket, developed by Turn Follow.
Ian Ensley, Carter Ludwick, Scott Archer.
Eliza, developed by Zachtronics.
Matthew Seiji Burns, the Eliza team.
Lion Killer, developed by Cici Jiang.
And the winner is...
Heaven's Vault
Hi, I'm Jon and I'm Joe. Hello!
And we're Inkle. Thank you for this award.
It means a huge amount to us. When we started Heaven's Vault five years ago, it seemed like a really good idea, didn't it?
I mean, yeah, it did seem like a really good idea at the time,
until we added that entire ancient language that you could decipher.
It was so hard.
Oh, and that entire narrative that you could play in just about any order.
That made the game really hard to build.
It was so hard.
Anyway, if you played Heaven's Vault, thank you so much.
We really hope you enjoyed it.
We'll be coming to Switch later this year,
and we have a new game called Pendragon, which will be out this year too.
So from me and Joe, thanks to Anastasia Wyatt, Laura Dilloway, Pirantra Mythic, Tom Blunden,
Sarah Hefford, Lawrence Chapman and Tom Kale.
So that's everyone at Inkle who helped with the project.
You guys were amazing.
Well done.
This is for all of us.
Thank you, amazing Inklers.
Thank you.
Bye.
See you later.
Game design.
We start our own studios so we can design our dream games.
And then when we're too busy,
we have to hire game designers.
These next finalists either hired great game designers
or never admitted they were too busy.
This is Excellence in Design.
Katana Zero.
Developed by Asciisoft.
Justin Stander.
Lonely Mountains Downhill.
Developed by Megagon Industries.
Jan Bubanek.
Daniel Helbig.
Noah Kerev.
Slay the Spire, developed by Mega Crit Games.
Casey Yano.
Anthony Giovannetti.
A Short Hike, developed by Adam Robinson Yu.
Mark Sparling.
Elsinore, developed by Golden Glitch Studios.
The Elsinore team.
Patrick's Parabox, developed by Patrick Treynor.
And the winner is Patrick's Parabox.
Thank you so much. I'm really, really honored to receive this
award. I'm so thankful to so many people who have helped and
supported me. So many people, like my family, my online
friends from many communities and my offline friends. I
really hope to continue to
help and support others back and to contribute back.
I'm so inspired by so many games, so many independent games,
and I'm really really happy to be here participating with my own work and to
to be contributing and helping to move things forward and to be part of it.
Thank you. Thank you so much. I'm so honored.
Excellence in Visual Art. We were actually nominated for this once, but we didn't win.
I guess that's the best thing about hosting these awards remotely, is that I don't have
to hand this award to someone else again. Let's take a look at this year's beautiful games.
Excellence in Visual Art. Mutazione, developed by De Gute Fabrique.
The Mutazione Team.
Knights and Bikes, developed by Foam Sword.
Rex Crowley.
Mu Yu.
Kenneth Young.
Daniel Pemberton.
Void Bastards, developed by Blue Manchu.
Benjamin Lee, The Void Bastards Team.
Creature in the Well, developed by Flight School Studio.
Bowden Sayer, Adam Volker.
Eastward, developed by Pixpil.
Joel Korolitz
Hyperduck Soundworks
Stone Story RPG
Developed by Martian Rex and Standard Combo
Gabriel Santos
Rafael Langone-Smith
And the winner is...
Nights and bikes.
the team that all worked on the game with me.
I also want to thank our friends at Double Fine
who kept us alive and...
made sure the game could come out.
And I also really want to thank our Kickstarter backers,
because there is no way that this game would exist
without them.
So just thank you so much to everyone involved.
It's just mind-blowing to get this award.
Thank you.
This next lineup of diverse experiences explores and celebrates the vast potential of our media.
Let's take a look at the finalists for the IGF Nuovo Award for our annual dose of WTF.
Developed by Cosmo D Studios.
Greg Cosmo D Heffernan.
Julian Solimporta Cordero.
Infini.
Developed by Barnack.
David Martin.
Emmerich Morin.
The Space Between, developed by Christoph Frey.
Life Tastes Like Cardboard, developed by Demensa.
Promisa, developed by Julian Palacios.
Andrea Chedrado.
Domiziano Mazzelli.
Martín Palacios.
Song of Bloom, developed by Philip Stollenmayer.
The Longing, developed by Studio Zeusts, Anselm Peite, Thomas Krueger, Stéphane Michel, Laura Brosi.
Pagan Autogeny, developed by Oleander Garden.
And the winner is...
The Space Between!
Hi everyone, my name is Christoph Frey.
I am the game developer of The Space Between
and I am speaking to you here from the
wonderful city of Linzen, Austria.
I want to thank you for the
Nuovo Award and I am honored to
represent an award that is dedicated
to the very adventurous
exploration of what video games can be.
So, thanks again and
I hope I'll see you soon in real life.
Bye!
Hello. Due to the circumstances, we can't do this live, so I'm going to do it my preferred
way, heavily edited, with an excessive filter. Okay, perfect. Now, all I need to do is introduce
the grand prize nominees, but first I want to talk about 2020.
Careening into a new decade here, and it turns out that this year is also a notable anniversary for the IGF.
20 years ago, the grand prize winner here was a tank combat game called Treadmarks by Longbow Digital Arts.
The founder and lead programmer at Longbow was Seamus McNally. Maybe you've seen his name around somewhere.
Shemis was just 21 at the time, but had already made a few games, and in a lot of ways, he was a pioneering indie developer.
For one, Longbow was selling their games online, digitally.
That doesn't sound like a big deal now, but back at the dawn of indie time in 2000,
there was no infrastructure and no easy sell without a physical copy.
And Shemis made an effort to share his knowledge with other developers.
about selling games online, but also about technical issues.
Even though he was young, he was already a very good programmer, and I remember how useful
his articles on 3D engines and hardware were at the time.
After Treadmarks, Seamus wasn't able to make another game.
He had been fighting Hodgkin's Lymphoma for a few years, and passed away just one week
after winning the Grand Prize.
In his brief time, Seamus showed a kindness, an independence, and especially an openness
that set the perfect standard for the IGF.
And for me personally, I'm proud to be associated with his name.
He's a great model for indies.
20 years so far, and 20 more coming up.
And now to segue, the Seamus McNally Grand Prize nominees for 2020.
Seamus McNally Grand Prize.
Eliza, developed by Zachtronics.
Matthew Sagey Burns, the Eliza Team.
A Short Hike, developed by Adam Robinson Yu, Mark Sparling.
Untitled Goose Game, developed by House House.
Mutazione, developed by De Gute Fabrique.
The Mutazione team.
Slay the Spire, developed by Mega Crit Games.
Casey Yano.
Anthony Giovannetti.
Anodyne 2, Return to Dust, developed by Sean Hantani
and Marina Ayano Kitaka.
Melos Hantani.
And the winner is...
A Short Hike.
Thank you so much.
I'm really, really honoured to be selected
amongst the amazing games here at IGF.
Uh...
I really want to thank everybody who helped me get here today.
Um...
Firstly, I'd like to thank my partner, Don,
who supported me throughout the entire journey.
Um...
She always believed in me and the game, even when I wasn't so sure myself.
And I don't think the game would have been the same without her wisdom and support.
I want to thank Mark, who made the amazing soundtrack for the game.
Andrew, for the art and his friendship as I worked on the game.
I want to thank David, who made the amazing logo.
And my mom, who supported me every step of the way.
and I really just want to thank everybody who played the game and gave me feedback and helped
shape it into something better. So thank you so so much. I'm so honored to be selected today. Thank you.
Well, there you have it. That's another IGF's in the bag, folks. That's a wrap.
Thank you to Lucas Pope for giving someone else a chance this year.
Of course, thanks to Kelly Wallach, chairperson of the IGF,
all the judges and jurors,
our lead sponsor, ID at Xbox,
thanks again for supporting the festival and making it everything that it can be.
And speaking of which, I wanted to thank the IGF team
who make all of this magic happen behind the scenes.
I also did want to take a moment to say that our hearts go out to all of those affected
by the coronavirus.
Be sure to stay safe, people.
We'll be back next year, live in San Francisco, again for another IGF Awards.
Don't you worry about that.
Now it's time to watch the Game Developers Choice Awards, this year hosted by Kim Swift.
We might even get a chance to finally find out what Death Stranding is all about.
Thanks, everyone.
Have a great night.
you
Hey everyone! So, how about that coronavirus, eh?
I'm sure you're keenly aware GDC isn't happening this week so that way we can all avoid, you know, disease and pestilence.
Since, obviously it would be super weird for me to be giving the awards in a completely empty auditorium,
I was asked to help out with a remote Game Developers Choice Awards because, obviously, you want to tell everyone who won.
So here I am, coming to you live.
Actually, take that back.
This is pre-recorded.
Say hi to the crew.
Hi, guys.
So we are coming to you from sunny Los Angeles, California.
I'm a bit disappointed, however,
that I don't get to present on stage this year
because I had this whole outfit planned.
It was pretty great.
And I mean,
Look at these shoes, these absolutely perfect, exquisite foot torture devices that I will
not get to wear.
Anyways, it is what it is, but hey, the advantage is I could be wearing sweatpants right now
and you'd have absolutely no idea.
So, welcome to my roof.
Definitely not your typical setting for the awards.
Also, this is my co-host.
This is Sundae.
You'll be seeing her more.
And also, hey, because this is at my house,
if you are lucky, you'll get to hear
the amazing ice cream truck that rolls around
with the broken Lacooka Ratchahorn.
It is just.
Fantastic.
Well, let's get things rolling.
I've been sitting on who's won for a little bit now,
and it's killing me to keep it a secret.
So you know what?
Let's head inside, because it's getting a little warm out.
Hey, welcome to the inside of my house.
Fair warning, there's probably going to be parrot noises
at some point, so be prepared for that.
Oh, hi, Sunny.
Anyways, these folks are the future of our industry.
Brand new developers making exceptional content,
showing us new facets of what games can be.
Compelling storytelling, colorful artwork,
and groundbreaking points of view.
Here are your nominees for Best Debut.
Oh, hey, I rhymed.
Best Debut.
Zaun.
Nominated for Disco Elysium.
The Disco Elysium Team.
Mobius Digital, nominated for Outer Wilds.
William Cheer Studio, nominated for Manifold Garden.
William Cheer.
Arthur Bressi.
Martin Cavalli.
Larissa Okada.
Foam Sword, nominated for Knights and Bikes.
Rex Crowley.
Mu Yu.
Kenneth Young.
Daniel Pemberton.
Chance Agency, nominated for Neo Cab.
Patrick Ewing.
Vincent Perea.
Paula Rogers.
Felix Kramer.
And the winner is...
Zaoum.
Hi GDC!
We're Zaoum.
We're greeting you from rainy London.
We're super grateful for the best debut.
Thank you.
We're sorry we couldn't be there,
but hopefully we'll all see you soon enough.
Thanks again.
Bye!
I'm not gonna lie, this right here is my absolute favorite category.
So I learned about a word, which I'm likely going to butcher saying out loud,
hypnagogia, which is that point in time,
right before you completely fall asleep.
It's called threshold consciousness.
It's like you can hallucinate and have lucid dreams.
And I really feel like innovation and true creativity in games
is like manufactured hypnagogia.
We create dream states for our players that they get to control.
And hey, that's pretty damn cool.
Here are your nominees for innovation.
Innovation Award.
Untitled Goose Game, developed by House House,
published by Panic.
Disco Elysium, developed by Zaun.
The Disco Elysium Team.
Faba is You, developed by Hampuli Arvi Thakari.
Matthias Kerlew.
Death Stranding, developed by Kojima Productions,
published by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
Outer Wilds, developed by Mobius Digital, published by Annapurna Interactive.
And the winner is...
Baba Is You.
Hello everyone, this is Arvi Teikari.
Thank you so much for awarding Baba is You
in the innovation category.
I'm super grateful for that.
I'd like to thank three people.
Anni Leskela for all the encouragement
and support over the years.
Niklas Nygren for teaching me a lot about motivation
and how to keep working on a project
even when I'm not feeling like it.
And Lukas Meller for helping me so much over the years
and teaching me many things and many ways
to make the things I do better.
Thank you and thanks to the GDC staff for organizing all of this and all their hard work and take care.
Thank you.
Once upon a time, I went to nerd school, DigPen, to get a CS degree.
I got about halfway through the degree and realized that not only do I not particularly like programming, I'm like, eh, okay at it.
But I buckled down, quit playing EverQuest, very, very key,
and graduated.
If I took one thing away from the experience,
however, was the sheer appreciation
of how difficult and complicated it
is to build the technologies that
allow us as designers and artists
to bring our visions to life.
So let's take the time to appreciate
the NOMs for best technology.
Best technology.
Death Stranding, developed by Kojima Productions,
published by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
Control, developed by Remedy Entertainment,
published by 505 Games.
Sean Donnelly, Tatu Aalto, Miko Orenma,
Call of Duty Modern Warfare, developed by Infinity Ward, published by Activision.
Apex Legends, developed by Respawn Entertainment,
published by Electronic Arts.
Todd Alderman.
Drew McCoy.
Mackie McClandish.
Chad Grainier.
Noita, developed by Nola Games.
Petre Poto.
Oli Hariola.
Arvi Tikari.
And the winner is Control.
Hey, I'm Sean Donnelly, lead programmer of Control. I'm
accepting the GDC award for best technology on behalf of Remedy
Entertainment. Thank you so much for this award. It really is a
great honor, especially when we see the competition in this
category. It's kind of insane.
Big shout out to our in-house engine and tools team, Northlight,
and of course a massive thank you to everyone who actually worked on Control,
who showed the tech off in the best possible light,
made the game play, look and sound amazing.
Thank you so much.
It's time to announce the award for Best Narrative.
First though, I had a very serious request from a friend of mine.
We need to talk.
Up for this category, we have both Outer Wilds,
and Outer Worlds.
At what point in time do you think both teams found out
about the other game's name?
And were like, oh shit, that's unfortunate.
Luckily for both of them, they are excellent,
along with the rest of the nominees in this category.
Here are your nominees for Best Narrative.
Best Narrative.
Disco Elysium.
Developed by Zaun.
The Disco Elysium Team.
Control, developed by Remedy Entertainment,
published by 505 Games.
Josh Stubbs, Clay Murphy, Sam Lake.
Death Stranding, developed by Kojima Productions,
published by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
The Outer Worlds, developed by Obsidian Entertainment, published by Private Division,
the Outer Worlds narrative design team.
Outer Wilds, developed by Mobius Digital, published by Annapurna Interactive.
And the winner is...
Disco Elysium
Hi!
Hey GDC!
We are Zahum and we are sending you greetings from rainy Revachol
and thank you so much for the Best Narrative Award.
So sorry we couldn't be there in person but we will definitely see you in the summer.
Thank you guys, bye!
Bye!
If you know Kate, you know Kate's heroes.
Kate loves strength, she loves misfits,
and she loves rebels.
She loves them so much
that she frequently dresses like them.
Kate's Thor cosplay is some of the most beautiful.
powerful costuming I've seen outside of an actual Hemsworth.
In the 90s, when Microsoft and Ensemble Studios
released the first Age of Empires game,
it contained a grievous error.
For totally benign reasons, the game misrepresented
a crucial point of cultural history,
an error that was so egregious
that a regional executive of ours was actually put in jail.
We needed a hero. We needed somebody to help us fix our problem.
We needed somebody maybe from Asgard sent to save us from ourselves.
And that's when I got to meet my favorite geographer, Kate Edwards.
Kate is a rare being, a leader introvert. As a kid, Kate would frequently look up
from wandering the playground in a reverie to notice other children following her.
And she would demand, why? Why are you following me around?
But to me, the answer is obvious.
Kate is never lost.
Born into a loving and supportive family,
her parents established a morality
based on doing the right thing,
defending the little guy,
and taking action where possible
that forms the basis of Kate's worldview today.
At Microsoft, Kate led the entire company
in the establishment of a set of processes
for geopolitical reviews and standards that is the basis for our friendly global relationships
and authentic cultural representation today.
And yes, Kate did help us get our executive out of jail.
As director of the IGDA,
Kate broadened both her global worldview and also her understanding of the games industry.
She also gained fame for her outspoken opinions on the imbalances and the injustices
that threaten independent game developers even today.
She formed a kind of Dumbledore's army of advocates.
focusing on topics ranging from crunch to diversity
to safety from online hate mobs.
Kate expanded the reach of the IGDA
to emerging game development regions
like Bangladesh, Tunisia, Egypt, and many others.
And her advocacy hasn't ended in the years post-IGDA.
Last year alone, Kate traveled to more than 25 countries,
and she spent more than 76 hours on stage or in panels
inspiring game developers everywhere.
Her global focus
is what makes her so perfect for the Executive Director of the Global Game Jam.
Although she has confided in me, she believes it's time to expand Global Game Jam's horizons.
Somewhere in a galaxy far, far away, the Rebels need our help.
I would like to thank GDC and the selection committee and all my fellow game creators
around the world for this tremendous honor of receiving the Ambassador Award this year.
I was honestly taken by surprise by this and so I don't know what to say other than I'm
truly humbled and I'm very thankful so, you know, thank you so much for this recognition.
It means a tremendous amount to me.
As we cannot be together this year because of the postponement of GDC,
obviously because we're all aware of global events at the moment,
I am glad that we can at least connect via the stream.
As game creators and as people who live in a digital world,
we have the ability to maintain this connection no matter what.
So we are very resilient in that way.
And so as I'm standing here in Hoth, in actual Finnsund, Norway, where they filmed the Empire Strikes Back over 40 years ago,
I wanted to share just a few quick thoughts to you about what this award means to me and what it means to the industry.
You know, when we talk about being an ambassador and what that means,
you know, it's about putting our best self forward and trying to present the
industry in the best light and to make change happen for the better.
And, you know, what does it really mean to make change?
I think for a lot of us, you know, we find that challenging today
because we don't really know where to start.
And I think in my own experience, where it really starts is with ourselves.
If we can.
figure out what is stopping us from taking that step to help somebody or to take that step forward
or to be a voice for someone who's marginalized. You know we have to find the confidence in
ourselves to get over our imposter syndrome and get to that point where we have that confidence.
You know whether you actually believe in that confidence or not,
it's more about believing in the reason to have that confidence which is for other people.
And I know in my experience, that's what's really been driving me.
I mean, I have been driven for a long time now by this notion that evil triumphs when good people do nothing.
And I really believe that. And so that's what has been driving my action in this industry.
Because I want people to be better and I want the industry to be better.
And I want us to treat each other with more respect and to treat each other with fairness and being inclusive in how we approach everything.
You know, at one point, John F. Kennedy, the former U.S. President, said,
if not us, then who? And if not now, then when? And really, I think that's something that all of
us need to challenge ourselves with. When we see something that we don't like, when we see something
that we are dissatisfied with in this industry, and it could be a huge issue that affects all of
us, or it could be a tiny thing that affects your local community, you have to ask yourself,
Why is it not changing?
And then how can you be that agent of change
to make it happen?
And you know, in my experience,
and I think what people have seen,
at least in my actions,
is that basically I made a decision
that I'm gonna be the one to step forward
and actually try and make change happen.
It's not because I'm better than anybody.
It's not because I have more experience than anybody.
It's just, it's a simple act of will.
And it's actually a decision saying,
I want this to change for the better
because I think it's gonna help all of us.
And so, you know, as you think about this, and again, I just I'm so thankful for this award.
And for for this kind of honor, you know, just think about for yourselves, what does it mean to
be an ambassador for this industry. And so I'm just going to leave you with that challenge. And,
you know, I know that if all of us are doing our part, and are trying as best as we can to be that
that voice for the industry and for other people.
who are marginalized, you know, this industry and this and this world frankly is going to get better
but it's going to take all of us to take that step. So once again thank you so much for this
award and I just am deeply appreciative and I hope to see you at GDC next time.
Audio teams are the unsung heroes of our industry, always the last ones to get to bring their
art to life in a game's pipeline.
And of course, those players that mute the audio and don't wear headphones.
The worst, right?
Audio really makes a game.
Corrective guidance cues, warnings of things to come, and memorable tunes.
How many times have you woken up with a theme song stuck in your head?
Let's give the audio and music on these wonderful games
the appreciation they truly deserve.
Here are your nominees for Best Audio.
Best Audio.
Death Stranding, developed by Kojima Productions,
published by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
Sayonara, Wild Hearts.
Developed by Simogo.
Published by Annapurna Interactive.
Control.
Developed by Remedy Entertainment.
Published by 505 Games.
Billa Sorsa.
Guli Gunarsson.
Luca Pirro.
Untitled Goose Game, developed by House House, published by Panic.
M. Halberstadt, Dan Golding.
Call of Duty Modern Warfare, developed by Infinity Ward, published by Activision.
And the winner is...
Control.
Hi, my name is Ville Sorsa.
I'm the lead audio signer here at Remedy Entertainment.
On behalf of the entire Remedy Audio team,
we're super excited about the fact that we just won the GDC award.
I would like to thank our development team, external partners,
and especially 505 Games
for giving us this opportunity to work on this title.
I would also like to thank you for sharing this very special moment with us.
Thank you.
Filming an award show is hard work. Um, time for snack. What do you say?
I baked muffins for the crew. Um,
what do you think? Huh?
All right, well, this next category of folks
maybe took sci-fi movies, TV, and books a little too seriously
and swore a sacred oath to bring Holodecks and Oasis
back to the real world.
Here are your nominees for Best VR AR Game.
Best VR AR Game.
Vader Immortal, a Star Wars VR series.
Developed by ILMX Lab and Oculus Studios.
Published by Disney.
The Vader Immortal Team.
Blood & Truth, developed by SCEE Studio, London.
Published by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
The Blood & Truth Team.
Asgard's Wrath, developed by Sanzaro Games, published by Oculus Studios.
Boneworks, developed by Stress Level Zero. Brandon Losh, Alex Knoll.
Pistol Whiff, developed by Cloudhead Games.
And the winner is...
Vader Immortal, a Star Wars VR series.
Thank you so much to the judges and to all of our fans.
With Vader Immortal, we set out to make an experience
that lets you step inside and live the adventure.
It's not just storytelling, it's story living.
And we're here proudly representing
our talented team at ILMxLAB.
Vader Immortal represents a new type of entertainment
that can affect people in fundamentally different ways
than other storytelling mediums.
Special thanks to Colin McKay, John Nguyen, Joong Yun Choi, Steve Hendricks, Jeff Grebe,
Ron Manum, Kurt Perry, Marissa Martinez and Aaron McBride.
Thanks to Jose Perez, Chip Carl, Sarah Baric, Kevin Boland and Skywalker team.
Thanks to the talented cast.
And to our writer David Goyer, thanks to Vicky Beck and Mark Miller,
thanks to Mike Duran and Colm Slevin at Oculus, and to Lucasfilm Story Group,
and the folks at Epic for your support.
Finally, we couldn't have done it without the talented teams at our third-party partners
Clutch Play, Ninja Theory and Virtuous.
Our medium is young, but it is very powerful, and we're just getting started.
Oh, hi.
Roadshow, right?
Yeah, OK.
Who would have ever guessed back in 2007
that the iPhone would have had this much of an impact
on our industry?
Mobile games can deliver moving and dreamy experiences,
motorcycle races, sword battles, allow us to play soldier,
and play the most ridiculous game of golf,
all in the palm of your hand.
Here are your Best Mobile Game nominees.
Best Mobile Game.
Sayonara Wild Hearts, developed by Simogo, published by Annapurna Interactive.
What the Golf, developed by Triband Productions, published by The Label Limited, the Triband team.
Grindstone, developed by Capybara Games.
The Grindstone Team.
Sky, Children of the Light, developed by That Game Company.
The Sky Dev Team.
Call of Duty Mobile, developed by Tini Studios,
published by Activision.
And the winner is What the Golf?
Guys, guys, we bought something!
It's insane!
Guys, it's that phone!
Oh my God!
Yes!
When I first started to learn about digital art
and creating the pretties for video games,
one thing that struck me is just how absolutely ugly
and gruesome things started before they became beautiful
and took shape.
Weird blobs of brown at the beginning of a piece of concept art,
chonky shapes for models,
and have you ever seen an unwrapped material
for a character's face?
Like, yikes.
It rubs the lotion on its skin, am I right?
Luckily for us tonight,
we get to see the gorgeous, exquisite, and glorious
end products of these extremely talented artists.
Here are your nominees for Best Visual Art.
Best Visual Art.
Control.
Developed by Remedy Entertainment.
Published by 505 Games.
Yana Polkenin.
Stuart MacDonald.
Death Stranding.
Developed by Kojima Productions.
Published by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
Sekiro Shadows Die Twice.
Developed by From Software.
Published by Activision.
Sayonara Wild Hearts.
Developed by Simogo.
Published by Annapurna Interactive.
Disco Elysium, developed by Zaun.
The Disco Elysium Team.
And the winner is...
Control.
Hi, this is Janne Pulkkinen, Art Director from Remedy.
I'm honored to accept the GDZ Award for Best Visual Art for Control.
Thank you. This is amazing.
Brutalism plays a big part in control, so I'd first like to thank our World Design Director,
Stuart MacDonald, for doing an incredible job with the environments.
Then I would like to thank the key members of the art team,
Antti Puomio, Elmeri Raitanen, Damien Stempniewski,
Riho Kroll, Miro Westerinen and Leonardo Kalamati.
Thank you.
Then of course, I would like to thank our creative director,
Sam Lake, and game director, Mikael Kasurinen,
for having the courage to build something this unique.
Then finally, I would like to thank the whole team here at Remedy for building an environment of trust
where all the weirdest and wildest ideas are allowed to survive and flourish.
Thank you.
The first time Roberta Williams played Colossal Cave Adventure, she was transfixed.
It was a computer game unlike anything she'd ever played before.
Literary, narrative, fantastical.
She burned through that game, then others, and when she ran out of games altogether,
she took matters into her own hands.
She sat down at her kitchen table and designed her own.
It was 1979, and Roberta Williams was 26 years old.
From that initial moment, a truly unconventional legacy would rise.
Born Roberta Lynn Hauer in 1953, the woman who would one day become the queen of adventure
games grew up quietly in the suburbs of northern Los Angeles.
That first game became Mystery House.
Her husband, Ken Williams, programmed the game, but she designed it and drew its images,
making Mystery House not just the first adventure game with graphics, but one of the earliest
examples of a separation between programmer and designer.
In a moment when most people didn't know what personal computers were good for, Roberta
and Ken Williams would strike out on their own adventure to press the limits of computing
in the name of entertainment.
Together, they founded Sierra Online, a company that needs no introduction in the annals of
video game history.
For much of the 1980s and 90s, Sierra was the largest publisher of home entertainment
software in the world, and flagship among its titles was Roberta's King's Quest series,
a bright and lively collection of eight games spanning nearly 20 years of production and
millions of copies sold.
Best remembered today for their surreal mashup of folklore and fable, mythology and legend.
Only in King's Quest could Medusa share a landscape with evil wizards or Pegasus fly
over Dracula's castle.
Overriding each of these worlds, however, was a basic narrative.
Find your destiny, find your family, and protect them at all costs.
Counterposed to King's Quest are Roberta's domestic horrors, Mystery House, The Colonel's
Bequest, and Phantasmagoria, in which families are trying to kill you and homes are places
where you die.
Roberta Williams' oeuvre expresses a narrative expansiveness few other designers have ever
endeavored.
So it's 2020, and we're here to acknowledge what Roberta Williams never doubted, that
she was a pioneer.
In the years since she left the game industry in 1988, she has been reluctant to embrace
industry recognition.
But perhaps it's we who need to give her this reward more than she needs to receive it.
That we're the ones who need to say we remember because too often the industry would rather forget.
Perhaps the legacy of the woman herself does for this industry what her games did nearly 40 years
earlier. Let us know that other stories are possible. It is my deepest honor to celebrate
Roberta Williams as the recipient of the 2020 IGF and Game Developers Choice Award.
I just want to thank the
Game Developers Conference for bestowing on me this year the honor, the incredible honor,
for the Pioneer Award for Computer Game Design.
With the help of Ken, my husband, Ken Williams, one of the greatest programmers around, and
he still is, he still is programming, he loves it.
With his help and expertise, with our very first Apple II computer.
to provide the means by which we could do this,
we were able to design our very first game,
Mystery House, back in 1980.
And I did design it on the proverbial kitchen table,
big pieces of paper.
I said I would love to have graphics if that was possible,
and rather than being a text adventure game.
And he said, oh, that's pretty hard, I don't know.
But let's see, let's look around.
And he found something called a graphics tablet
that was just like a piece of acrylic
with kind of this magnetic arm, which
is one reason why the art and the pictures on Mr. House
don't look so good.
It's not so much that I'm a bad artist, which I am,
but I'm not that bad.
It's that that was just very primitive
to try to draw pictures.
But that's the way we did it.
And people were amazed at the time.
And they were actually pictures on an Apple computer.
I finally did retire in, I believe, 1997, when we sold our company, which was one of
the saddest days of my life, and it was very hard for me.
But I did, and Ken and I went into other adventures over the years, mainly we circumnavigated
oceans around the world.
But over those years, 17 years, I...
I created probably about 18, 19, 20 games.
And then I also worked with some of our designers at Sierra.
We were so lucky to have some of the best developers,
designers, programmers, artists, animators,
musicians in the industry.
And I was just so lucky to be able to work
with all of the talent that we had.
It was just the highlight of my life,
and I'm so happy and so glad that
the Game Developers Conference decided to honor me with this very...
I'm humbled actually, I don't even have words. I'm just, I'm on and very happy and very honored
to receive this award. And so on behalf of myself, Ken, and all the people that worked with us at
Sierra Online, I want to thank you so very much.
The diversity in the design category this year is absolutely amazing to me.
Be a post-apocalyptic mailman, fly spaceships in a time loop,
wordsmith your way to success, exact revenge as a shinobi,
and be a jerk goose?
Yes, absolutely. Honk honk, my friends.
I'm issuing a challenge in our industry right here and now.
Can we strive to continue to be this diverse in the games that we offer?
I want to live in these worlds.
Without any further ado, here are the nominees for Best Design.
Oh, and that's Mando.
Best Design.
Baba Is You, developed by Hampuli Arvi Thakari.
Matias Kerlu.
Outer Wilds, developed by Mobius Digital.
Published by Annapurna Interactive.
Death Stranding.
Developed by Kojima Productions.
Published by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
Sekiro Shadows Die Twice.
Developed by From Software.
Published by Activision. ♪♪
Untitled Goose Game.
Developed by House House.
Published by Panic. ♪♪
And the winner is...
BABA is you.
Hello everyone, this is Arvi Teikari.
Thank you so much for awarding BABA is you
in the best design category.
I'm extremely grateful for that.
As for thanks, I would firstly like to thank the GDC staff
for all their hard work.
I cannot imagine how much it must have taken
to turn such a large event into a digital one
on such a short notice.
I would also like to thank the same three people regardless of what happens in the ceremony,
so if you hear the same names later or if you heard them earlier, then well, my apologies.
Anyway, I'd like to thank Anni Leskela for all the support and encouragement over the
years.
I'd like to thank Niklas Nygren for teaching me a lot about motivation and how to work
when feeling unmotivated.
And I would like to thank Lukas Meller for teaching me a lot about how to make games
and how to do the things I do better.
Thanks to all of you and have a very nice GDCA ceremony.
Thank you.
Please join me in somber remembrance of colleagues
and members of our community
that we have lost over the last year.
Let's cherish and reflect on their accomplishments
and the joy that they have brought to our lives.
You
There comes a time in the show where we all look at ourselves and think,
wouldn't it be nice if we had more things to vote on?
After all, what is an award show if not to give out awards, right?
And hey, audience rewards is like, what, now an eight-year tradition?
We're gonna hit that decade soon.
We've actually had some really good ones in the past, too.
Kerbal Space Program, Nair Automata, Beat Saber.
Let's find out who wins this year.
And the winner is...
Sky, Children of the Light.
Alright, we won!
Hey!
Yeah, it's strange that we are not at GDC,
but, you know, I'm feeling the energy,
and thank you so much for giving us the honor
for the GDC Audience Award.
And, you know, Sky has been a seven-year-long development process.
It was not easy, and without, you know,
our players' support.
Without your support, we would not start that game company
and we would not have been making these very difficult
but beautiful games.
And thank you so much to spend your time and to play our game
and also just come to GDC to vote for us.
It meant a lot for us and, you know...
Making Sky is difficult, but we feel very happy that you are with us.
And again, we won't let you down.
And see you in Sky!
Thank you!
My friends, your adorable Pepo time has almost come to a close as we have reached the penultimate of awards.
If Sun actually understood what was happening right now, she'd be super excited,
because all of the games up for this category are real damn good.
Well, here we go. The last Game of the Year nominees of the decade.
Game of the Year
Death Stranding
Developed by Kojima Productions
Published by Sony Interactive Entertainment. ♪♪ ♪♪
♪♪ Control.
Developed by Remedy Entertainment.
Published by 505 Games.
Yuhua Vainio.
Mikhail Kasarinin.
Sekiro Shadows Die Twice.
Developed by From Software.
Published by Activision.
Untitled Goose Game. Developed by House House. Published by Panic.
Outer Wilds, developed by Mobius Digital, published by Annapurna Interactive.
And the winner is...
Untitled Goose Game
Hello!
If this is being played
then that means that we have won
best game.
We really never ever expected
that our game would resonate with people in the way
that it has.
So it's very strange
and incredibly nice to receive
this award.
We had a lot of help in making this game
so we'd like to thank...
our sound designer M Halberstadt,
Dan Golding, who did our music,
Kalonica, who helped define the look of our game,
Sheree Davidson, who helped make our game accessible
to as many people as we could.
This game never would have been made without the support
of our publisher, Panic.
We would also like to thank Film Victoria
for their support, both of our game,
but also of the local scene.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
Game developers.
Bye-bye.
Well, that's our show. Congratulations to all of our winners. You better properly celebrate tonight.
And I want to give a huge thank you to Sandesh and Simon for taking a chance and inviting me
to host this year's awards. Also, let's hear it for the video editors that are cutting together
this particular video. And thank you to IMA Fit for being in my house today and filming all of this.
So, finally, I want to thank everyone for being so patient and understanding this unusual
process with GDC this year.
I hope everyone has the absolute bestest, most wonderful days, evenings, or whenever
you happen to be watching this.
And say goodbye.
Goodbye.
No, seriously, goodbye.
Get out of my house.
Get.
Go.
Go away.