I'm also very glad to be moderating this panel on the
legends of computer gaming.
Because the great thing about being a moderator is that you
can get fame by association.
And it's a real privilege to be with these giants in
computer game history and computer game future.
And I'm really excited about the chance to interview these
gentlemen in front of you.
But I have to start off with some ground rules and just
point out that very obviously, no list of computer game
legends can ever be exhaustive.
And if you know, we wanted to talk about people who possibly had done some of the most thought-provoking
games, if not most commercially successful, we would have to talk about Chris Crawford
and the contribution that he made to computer gaming.
And if we're going to talk about multiplayer gaming, we'd have to talk about Danielle
Berry and the push that she had from the very beginning, whether it was in Cartels and Cutthroats
or Mule or the Robot Rascals game or whatever.
There was always a concern with multiplayer gaming, way anticipating.
the idea of online gaming.
And if we were to talk about role-playing games, I think we'd have to insist that Lord
British would be a part of this picture.
So if we were to talk about strategy games in specific, we'd have to make Sid Meier a
part of this picture.
And I'm sure that each and every one of you could think of about three or four people
that you would like to have on this panel.
But if you have to start somewhere, this Hall of Fame starts way up here.
And I'm very pleased to be on here with Nolan Bushnell,
the video game pioneer.
Yes, very good.
Chris Roberts who most of you know because of the phenomenal success of the Wing Commander
series but a lot of people don't realize that even some of his games that get less attention
like Times of Lore that pushed us towards some iconic interfaces and like Bad Blood
that
that was even pushing Richard in some of the areas of object-oriented programming and Strike
Commander that caused many people to upgrade to a 486 even if they eventually didn't like it.
And of course later on we'll talk about the wing commander syndrome and how it's killing the
industry.
And then, without a doubt, you know, the person who proved to us that shareware was viable
and wasn't second-tier minor league anymore, the person who proved to us that first-person
perspective was the real, logical way to immerse people as quickly as possible into games,
the person who is probably most responsible for giving us the id interface that gamers
complain about if it's not in everybody's first-person game.
without a doubt, and proven many times over again,
the world's foremost doom and quake player, John Romero.
So the ground rules are, no softball questions.
I'm going to try to ask some tough ones.
I'm going to try to bait some of these guys here.
And then later on we're going to go out Phil Donahue style into the audience of those few of you who got in the multimedia theater and we're going to give you a chance to ask questions and see if you can stump the panel.
So I'm looking forward to this time together and so without any further ado, let's move right along.
Nolan Bushnell.
A lot of people think of you as the founder of the video game industry, but basically
you really started making your bones in the coin-op industry, where you were substituting
Space War and then Pong for pinball machines.
In fact, they say that not only was Atari Games really successful, but that you owned
your closest competitor, something called Key Games, and that sometimes those games
were delivered in the same truck with just the sign change.
Is that true?
It's absolutely true.
There were two major distributors in each town.
And we found that when we sold to one guy,
they wanted an exclusive.
And so I really didn't want the other guy selling
somebody else's game.
So I felt that I should have that, too.
I bet there's a lot of people here that wish they could own their top competitor.
So it was Atari games and Key games.
And then all of a sudden the console revolution came across and you let out in that with the 2600.
But the scuttlebutt is that there was a time where you were about to pull the plug on the
project and that Al Alcorn came in and talked you into going ahead.
And the rest was history.
It was actually before that.
The Pong was originally a dedicated chip.
It was an N-channel MOS chip.
And it just had all kinds of bugs in it and various things.
And that was when I almost pulled the plug.
And then, you know, it's funny that people think that
pioneering is easy.
But in fact, we couldn't sell the pawn game.
We went to all the toy companies, or the toy
distributors, retailers.
They said, no, it's too expensive,
because we were going to sell it at $99.
And then later on, we said, OK, we'll
go to the TV distribution.
And they didn't want it, because they said, gee,
we'll have to finance, and it looks like a fad.
And literally, we tried to market it
for almost three months.
Not a taker.
And it wasn't until we happened to call the buyer, the sporting
goods buyer, at Sears and Roebuck.
And we called him, told him what he had.
He says, OK.
In the next morning, at 8 o'clock, he was on our
doorstep, said, how many can you build?
We thought, 25,000, maybe, standing on our head.
So we told him 75.
And he came back with an order for 150,000.
And as we say, the rest is history, except for one thing.
We had to price it before we had the foggiest clue about how much it cost to manufacture.
We also didn't have enough money to build it.
Other than that, there was no problem.
We just said, hey, in order to do this, we're going to need to get a line of credit.
He says, not to worry, Sears Bank.
It was a partnership made in heaven.
So we pushed it through.
See, a lot of people don't realize that games on a TV is a really stupid idea.
And that the company started with $250,
not because I wanted it that way,
because nobody would invest.
They thought it was a stupid idea.
They confused the frivolity of
the activity with the frivolity.
of a business. They said, you know, how can you make money on fun? And this was a long
time ago.
Well, they're still asking that question today.
Exactly. Different reasons, Flo.
So since somebody took a chance on you, you took a chance on a
whole lot of people.
A lot of folks think that after you left Atari that Chuck E.
Cheese was your primary interest.
But you had like a half dozen high tech companies that you
lumped under the Catalyst Industries mark.
Actually, there were 17 in the Catalyst umbrella.
That's good.
Did any of them make money?
The one I watched, AndroBots, I don't think did.
AndroBot was a sore disappointment.
That was probably.
But you might not have explained to some of the younger folks what Anderbrotts did.
Anderbrott was a little guy that ran around and, you know, got you a beer and sang songs
and told jokes.
It was the idea of a personal robot.
And it was one of those things that I just, you know, you can't read Isaac Asimov without
thinking that there's going to be a robot in the future.
So I decided to build one.
the neat thing about it is we got going we got some of the
working
but the damn thing
uh...
was a mobile computer
and mobile computer but that time
in spin static electricity
environments
was not a pretty sight
because it's not the thing about it
syntax error or
a frozen
cursor
is one thing
that if you get frozen in a robot with FFFF, all of a sudden you're full speed right into
the wall.
In fact, in a robot lab that I was playing around with at Stanford, I actually saw an
end effector on a program bug thrown right through a cinder block wall.
You know, FFF, boom.
So robots were kind of an interesting thing.
It was one of those areas where we were trying to solve too many things,
power problems, static.
I mean, this was 1983, 84.
But more than that, we really got screwed by one of the big investment houses,
in which they agreed to raise all kinds of money for us.
Two days, the thing was totally oversold, totally oversold.
People were calling saying,
Nolan, can you get me stock? Can you get me stock?
And some executive at that unnamed jerky company
rolled over one day in the morning and said,
we don't want to do development stage companies anymore
and pulled the plug on it.
Not because of the sales thing, not because of the company,
because of the women fancy of an elephant.
So if you ever get in the stall with an elephant,
you've got to be careful because it can get rolled over on.
So what happened in that case is that
since everyone knew the company was oversold except must be something wrong
and it's sort of painted it
dried up the source of capital on the thing to him
had to sell it for
i had about
seventeen million dollars in the thing
sold for two
not a big deal
uh...
magna microwave uh... student
couple million now
uh...
e-tech you guys all know that automobile navigation just sold to sony
for a couple hundred million i sold it to news corp
for 50, too soon, too fast.
That was when John Evans was there.
Pardon?
Yeah.
E-Tech, there was quite a few of them.
Closed several real turkeys down though.
You know, certain things that look like they're a good idea.
We had an automatic color shade matcher called Iroh
in the cosmetics business, never go to there.
Technologists in the cosmetics business,
fish out of water, you don't want to do that.
It was some good fun.
Okay, well I've got to hit you with one embarrassing question before we move on to one of the others
and then we'll come back and let you talk about the exciting thing that you're doing
now in the games area.
But you know, I happened to be at the LA press conference that was part of the CDTV launch
and...
And basically, you made a very interesting statement there,
that I thought you might want to clarify before all these game
developers.
And that was that the educational potential
of the CDTV was sort of to make up to the world what you had
inflicted upon them with video games.
Well, CDTV was one of those things
where I consider it, on one way, a huge success.
Not in what you sold, but basically, I like to say that I proved for $8 million and in
eight months what it took Trip Hawkins $200 million in three years to sell.
I'm sorry, I couldn't resist that.
I actually still believe that if we look at
the future, that we control a lot of power in video games.
We control power to communicate.
We can focus attention.
We can do things dynamically and excitingly.
And I think that we, somewhere along the line, do always need
to give back.
to society, things that we have prospered by.
And I think that truly, we can and will solve the educational
crisis in the world.
And that in some ways, if we call it ET, not
extraterrestrial, but educational technology,
I really believe it's going to have more power in the world
than biotechnology.
And I believe that the people sitting in this room have a lot of that power.
And that if we can train people 100, 200, 300 times faster and more efficiently through
using the tools that we take for granted, I think we're going to really change the nature
of the world.
And because right now we are
seeing people holding on to the future by the tips of their fingers.
And that's because the technology we have is so powerful, so wonderful, such an enabler
for a great life.
And yet it's held by the priesthood and not by the congregation.
And I think that it's our goal, or it should be, to steel ourselves for creating the tools
by which we permeate technology into the masses.
And if we do that, then we've really accomplished something.
Anyway.
Well, at this point I want to move to Chris Roberts.
And if we had the slide from my computer up,
it would be a quote from my favorite review
of one of Chris's products.
I don't think that would be a quote for one of John's products.
Normally you would think of it as a quote for one of John's products.
But long, long ago in the bad blood days,
one of our reviewers took exception of one of those skinks-like puzzles
where in this case you had to kill this little turtle-like creature
and get the blood out of it vampirically in order to survive.
And I guess this was the nascent animal activist in Charles
and he thought it was morally reprehensible.
And I know the folks at Origin were quite upset at us for a long time over that review.
But I want to talk to you about some of the more exciting things.
For example...
I remember when you first came over from England and you were working on Times of Lore and
Richard was trying to describe the Times of Lore interface to us and he was all excited
and he made the mistake of calling it a Nintendo-like interface and saying that we're changing everything
to that, you know, and it just, you know, panicked those of us who equated the Nintendo
style game with being shallower than the PC game.
And yet, when we saw the game, it was extremely deep,
and it surprised us.
And we did notice that the influence went
on toward iconic interfaces.
What do you think the most important contribution,
whether it was in interface, or whether it
was an interactive sound, or whether it was in object
definition in games, what is the most important contribution
in all your tenure at Origin, do you think?
Well, I mean, I
The biggest thing I always try and do in everything I do is I want to immerse the player in the
environment and so I think that what I'm proudest of with Wing Commander, what I've done in
the past, is any time that I sort of remove the feeling of interface.
So, you know, like when it's in Wing Commander instead of, you know, you going over and going
on file and save, you click on a bunk bed to save or you, you know, click on the airlock
door to exit the game.
And I mean I guess the coolest thing from my standpoint is...
from putting it into something like Wing Commander and then
seeing that sort of graphical immersive interface sort of
permutate other people's games, which is kind of cool.
But I mean, that's for me.
All I want to do is I want to build an experience that I get
lost in the world for two hours, 20 hours, 40 hours, and
have a good time.
And so I guess that's what I like the most.
I think your contributions to interface have been very important because I've seen it across, you know, lots of different game companies.
Just like John's contributions to interface have been very, very important at a later period.
There was one thing that you tried in Wing Commander, the first Wing Commander, I thought was extremely important.
and extremely significant.
And yet it turned out that when the gamers got hold of it,
it was something of a failure.
What were some of the reactions that you got from people
about the losing track in Wing Commander?
Well, I mean, the funny thing with interactive fiction
is that you have to give everybody choices
so they don't feel like they're constrained to any one path.
But the problem is that you spend, say, 50% of your time
on the paths that aren't the optimum paths in the game.
And then at the end of the day, you're there going, hey, did
you play down this track?
Did you do this?
And everyone's like, no, I didn't.
And you're like, I just spent a year on that.
What's the deal?
And I think that it really came home to me when I was
sitting and I was talking to one of the dynamics guys about
The Rise of the Dragon.
And I was saying, yeah, I really loved it.
I played it all the way through.
And I did this, and I did this.
And he's like, oh, did you go to this level?
And did you do this?
And did you meet this character?
And I was like, no.
And he's like.
And he was heartbroken.
So I guess it's one of those necessary evils, because you
have to do it so you feel like you have a choice, and you
feel like the world reacts to what you do.
But you're also sitting there working on it, going, well, I
know about 50% or 60% of people aren't actually ever
going to experience this.
And I don't know.
I guess you need to do it so everyone feels happy about
they've gone the losing track.
They haven't gone the losing track, that is.
So necessary evil.
right but it seems like you shortened the losing track in
progressively aggressively
and of course with uh... filming that made it uh... very necessary
the great thing about the wing commander series uh... i thought was that it it
pushed upgrades at every new release of uh... you know
that is good uh... you know when you're in a magazine that's advertising driven
you know
But it's also good for the whole industry as a whole because people have a tendency
to buy more games when they buy new equipment because they want to find stuff that shows
it off. And certainly in the era of the Wing Commanders, the Wing Commanders showed off
new sound cards with Wing Commander 2. They certainly showed off new graphics cards with
Wing Commander 3, which is one of the few FMV games that's ever spoken well of.
And they showed Electronic Arts how to spend lots of money
in Wink-Man 4.
Oh, wow.
I mean, I will say that the process that got me there
is a long time ago.
You mentioned Bad Blood and Times of the Law.
So I came from England, and I was
used to programming on Commodore 64.
And back in those days in England, it was tape drive.
There was no disk drive.
So I was really proud about Times of the Law
because everything fit in 64K.
And there was this huge world and you ventured around.
And the game came out, and it came out over here.
And people didn't go, oh, well, it's really great because it
can fit in 64K.
They went, well, it's cool and everything, but I'm playing
this other game, and it comes on four disks.
And it doesn't have as much of it.
And I was sitting there going, hmm, I don't know about that.
And about the same time, MicroProse came out with F19.
I remember going up to MicroProse because they
distributed our stuff over in Europe.
And they were showing me F19.
And I was like, man, this is the most incredible 3D
simulation I've ever seen.
Too bad it only runs at four frames a second on a 38625,
which back then was like a $10,000 machine.
No one's ever going to be impressed or like this, because
no one's got this machine.
And it comes out, and it's absolutely huge here.
And I'm sitting there, and I'm going, hmm, well, I guess
there's a reason not to compromise and everything.
So that's really what happened with Wing Commander.
I said, OK, well, screw it.
I'm going to use every single opportunity and tool I can get on the maximum available
hardware right now to make the gaming experience as good as possible because my personal belief
is that people aren't very objective about it.
They're subjective.
They go, is this the best game I've seen?
And they don't go, oh, is this the best game I've seen that runs in 128K?
Or is this the best game I've seen in CGA?
They just go, is this the best game I've seen?
So after I sort of made that decision point in Wing Commander onwards was...
very much driven by, OK, let's make the best game possible,
no holds barred from there on.
Luckily, it seemed to work out.
In the creative process, as you were going from Times of War,
which you basically wrote virtually all yourself,
to Bad Blood, which you must have split off
some of the programming on to the Wing Commander series,
where more and more things were being done by other people.
Can you describe for a little bit how your role changed
from game to game?
And is starting your own company some desire
to get back more hands on yourself?
Well, I mean, I think it is a design.
I mean, actually, the one sad thing about game development
nowadays is that in the old days, you could do everything
yourself, and you could totally control the look, the
feel, the sound.
You do the writing, you do the programming, you do the
artwork, you do the sound.
And it could be a one-man affair, and it could be an
absolute single vision.
And now, because of what everybody expects in terms of
the quality of the product, you just can't afford to do
that, I mean, it would take you.
20 years and by the time it came out it would be old technology.
And so, you know, the sad thing is that you don't get to have that 100% level of control
over the product.
I mean, the good thing is that you get to work with a lot of other really talented people
and they, you know, in a lot of ways make your work better.
So I mean, I guess at the end of the day my role sort of moves more to being creative
shepherd and sort of evangelist of exactly how it's going to work and, you know, more
away from the actual technician that's building all the building blocks of it.
And I guess what I tried doing with Digital Anvil is I have
felt a little bit recently that in the huge industry
expansion that it's kind of gotten away from a little bit
of that sort of core vision on how products are built.
And so what I'm trying to do with Digital Anvil is have a
company that focuses on building great products, has
less people on the teams, and allows the team the time they
need to do the product and gives them the support they
need to do it.
So we'll see if it works.
But.
I mean, it's a good theory.
It's something that me and a bunch of my peer group
have been talking about for a long time.
And we figured, OK, time to put a push it up.
Well, I'm pretty excited about what you told me
about the new project.
And we're going to come back to it later
and let you talk as much as you feel like you can about that.
We want to move on to John here.
I don't know how many people know, but John was at origin
and worked with Chuck on 2400 AD.
And
and moved over. And actually, you know, Chris Roberts stole the idea of Wing Commander from
Paul Neurath and John when they did Space Rogue, which was sort of, you know, Wing Commander
with tunnels. But anyway, then John moved from there to Softdisk Corporation where he
was virtually doing a product, like a product of the month, weren't you, with Softdisk?
Every month. We had to, well, I started out...
After I left Origin, which was in June of 88, I got there to work on the, was it, Apple II to Commodore 64 port of 2400 AD.
And while I was working on that, Paul Neuron...
So you reviewed the Apple II version and that one was cancelled, right?
No, well, no, the Apple II version came out. I don't know how many copies it sold.
It was a, I liked it, it was a fun game.
So I was doing my very first Commodore programming,
converting the Apple II version of 2400 AD
to the Commodore 64, which I had to learn pretty quickly.
And it was probably three months through the conversion
when Paul Neroff really needed some help on Space Road.
And because he had to get the game done,
it had been going on too long.
So I was there to do the NPC code for him.
It ended up that.
He actually didn't use my code in the game because I left pretty soon after that to kind of co-found another company.
And he ended up getting someone else to program the NPC stuff.
But when I went on to the next company, it was a conversion house called Inside Out Software just down the road from Origin in New Hampshire.
And I worked on the Might and Magic 2 conversion of the Commodore 64, and I worked on various other ports.
And...
And I finally decided to leave Inside Out to go to Softdisk because it was an Apple II.
It was an Apple II magazine, but it also did PC work.
And this was in 1988 where the Apple II market was really dying hard.
And I needed to actually learn the PC because it was the market.
So I just called up the president of the company.
I told him who I was and what I had worked on and stuff.
I told him I didn't know anything about the PC at all,
but I really want to learn how to program it.
And he's like, come on down.
So that was really cool that he let me come down
and just learn how to program the PC,
knowing nothing about it.
And while I was at Softdisk,
I was doing utility work
and some of my games I was porting to the PC,
and I had to get something done every single month.
And about a year and three months after...
going to work at Softdisk, I was really tired of not actually making real commercial games.
I was doing these little month-long things. And I told them that I was going to leave
and I was going to like apply at LucasArts and like actually get into making real games.
And so they said, okay, we'll start a monthly game disk.
We needed some people, we got a few people in there.
John Carmack was one of the guys that we got,
he had submitted some Apple II stuff.
And so we got him as a programmer,
we got Lane Roth, who was an Apple II guy
and I've worked with for a long time.
And Adrian Carmack was an intern, an art intern.
And so he got on the team.
And so we started doing games every single month.
And Tom Hall, who was a co-founder of Vid Software
and I and Storm.
He was in the Apple II department, and he wasn't having as much fun in there as he was coming in at night, helping design all of our games.
And we could use all the help that we could handle because we had to get these things done every single month, which is pretty hardcore.
And so we made games every single month for about a year, and they're on the Hit Anthology on the vintage CD.
Anyway, we were at Soft—we started this Gamers Edge thing.
and did some games for probably a few months when
Carmack did this really awesome technology demo thing
and left it on my uh... Tom and Carmack
stayed up really late at night and uh... did this
you know duplicate Super Mario 3
but on the PC
and they uh... put it on my desk and I came in and I saw it and I was just shocked and I
couldn't work for at least three hours because I've never seen anything like that on a PC before
and I knew that that was it we're out of here
and this is, we could, it was, it was pretty funny. You see
something like that and you just, you know, nothing like
this has been done before on a PC.
So wait a minute, before you were out of there, you know,
didn't you have sort of a fan club?
Yes. There was a lot of things happening at the same time. You
know, he did the tech demo.
And at the same time, I had done some games that I had ported from the Apple II to the PC and it got published.
And I was getting these letters, you know, handwritten back then before email.
And I was getting these letters from, you know, supposedly a lot of people that liked this one game that I did.
And they're like, oh, I think I found a bug in your game.
Write me in my...
here's my address, my phone number, you know, please write.
I'm 67 years old and, you know, all these different letters.
And, and, uh, I was reading a PC games article and it was
talking about cross, which was a shareware game that Scott
Miller did, and, uh, he had started Apogee and, um.
I was reading all about it and I got to the end of the article and I saw the address and
stuff and I was like, no, I know that address.
And I'm sitting there and I just like look up on the wall right next to me and I'm like,
no way.
And all the letters, like about eight of them, they're all different names but the address
was the same.
And I was like, no.
I thought I had a lot of fans.
So, I was, I was, oh I was, I went next.
Carmack said you were upset because you found out that it was one guy and it was a guy.
Yep, I know I couldn't believe it. I, anyway, I wrote this really evil letter back to him
and, and I calmed down like the next day or two. I calmed down. I kept that letter.
And so I wrote him back another letter saying how pissed I was when I found out that he did this.
And I sent him the original one just so he could see how mad I was.
And he didn't even care. It's like, whatever, you know.
So he calls up and he gets me on the phone and was just like,
Oh, you know, this game was so great. I really want to,
I really want you to do a game just like that for me and put it in the shareware market.
And I had never even heard of shareware, but I was like...
sounds great, I could spend time actually more than a month and make a game.
And so
I said, but you know that game I did, that's
crap, you know, check this out. And I showed him a demo of
something we're doing and he totally went nuts.
You know, he's just, if you do a game for me and
we'll publish it and all this stuff. And I was like, well you know if you're
serious about it, you know, you'll have to advance us two thousand dollars.
and uh... well
so uh... well he had five thousand his bank account
so that was uh... and he sent it to us so that was uh... that was a
pretty huge commitment
on scott miller's part and uh... we got the two thousand dollar check and we're like wow this guy's
hardcore
So what we did was we started taking the computers home from Softdisk at night and especially
on the weekends.
You better be careful, the litigation may yet occur.
Yeah, well that's another part of the story.
So we take the computers home on the weekends and everything and we're writing our first
Commander Keen trilogy.
when we when we told me to a game for me he wanted no the game was about like
did we'll just do a cool game
it's like a so i see your design documents haven't changed
is because
you know i want to give you two thousand bucks i want to know what i'm paying for
so
so tom hall was in charge of the creative design of the game so tom wrote
like one paragraph that described commander king
and uh...
we just sent it to him fax it to him and he's like okay good go
He just wanted something.
It was the high concept thing.
Yeah, he just wanted something.
So anyway, we worked for three months after working on Weekends and we did the first trilogy
and we had to make it fit on a 360K PC disk and so we had to link stuff into the executable
and do the LZEXE on it and just compress the hell out of the game.
on December 14th of 1990 we released the very first episode of Commander Keen
ruined on Mars into the inter- on the
BBC's back then
and uh...
and then the next very next month you know we continued working at Softdisk
you know we're doing our game a month and we're working on this thing at night so
that was our life
and uh...
anyway one month right after we got done with the game in
the very first month's profits came in
uh...
we got a check for $10,000 and we're just like, this is enough
for all of us to live on. We figured we're going to get it
every month too. So, so we, we just told Softdisk, look, you
know, we're sorry, we started this product, this product line
six months earlier, and we're like, we got to go. This is too
cool. And, and so they, you know, they threatened to sue us
and everything. And we worked out a deal where we would
continue to make games for them while they got an in-house team up to speed.
And so the first, in February 1st of 91 is when we formed id Software, the four of us.
And until about August or September, that's what we did at id Software,
was we're getting money for...
our first game and we weren't even working on our next product, we were having to fulfill
the softest thing.
And so we did a whole bunch of games which was every month again, you know.
But we learned a lot from all that.
We actually did the very first, our first 3D engine which was Hover Tank 3D.
We did lots of cool side-scrolling games, we experimented with some different, with
puzzle games and a lot of stuff.
And we did a prototype of the Commander Keen, the next Commander Keen Trilogy's game engine.
forum. And then we did the second Commander Keen trilogy in six months, which was three
months for Keen 4, two months for Keen 6, which we did right after 4 because it was
a retail product we had to get out real quick. And then Keen 5 took one month and got that
out December 15th of 1991. And then we started working on Wolfenstein right after that.
And Wolfenstein took six months.
We told our distributor, we told them what we were doing,
and they were like, don't stir up that World War II thing, you know.
They were just like, you know, you're mowing down Nazis with a chain gun and stuff.
It's really cool.
And they were just, you know, they went and they couldn't believe, you know,
it was made major controversial.
you know they're really scared but they we did really good with our other games
so they're like okay you know so we did Wolfenstein
in six months and then immediately worked on Spear of Destiny which took us
two months
and Wolfenstein was released on May 5th of 1992 which was actually one
week
after Ultima Underworld 2 which was
you know they
Paul Neeroth likes to talk about that because he wants to make sure that he released the
first texture map game out there.
And, you know, and I tell everybody, yes, he totally did, you know, one week before
we did.
And actually, and actually, the only reason that Wolfenstein 3D is texture mapped is because
of Paul Neeroth.
I had kept in touch with him since he had started Blue Sky and I called him up while
we were at Softdisk and he told me he was working on this new game that he couldn't
tell me the name of it.
But they're using this really neat new technology called texture mapping.
And after the phone conversation I told Carmack, hey,
they're doing this texture mapping thing.
And he looks up in the air for about three seconds and he goes, I can do that.
So.
But that was, you know, we had done, after that we did a texture map game called Catacombs 3D,
but it was an EGA, so it wasn't real popular.
You know, VJ.
Wolfenstein was in VGA so it got really popular and that's where everyone goes,
oh yeah, you guys did this first action game in VGA and everything,
which was pretty, it was where the market was going.
So right after we finished Spirit of Destiny, we started working on Doom in December of 92
and you know, during the entire year we did, we finished it and it was,
that was a lot of work actually, it took us a whole year for that game.
But we released that on December 10th of 1993.
And Doom II took eight months.
That was released on October 10th of 94.
And at the same time, I was working with Raven on Heretic.
And that got released December 23rd of 94.
And then worked on Hexen and Quake at the same time.
It took about a year and a half for Quake.
Do you remember the year that Wolfenstein 3D won the best
action game award at the Software
Publishers Association?
And when Jay and you got up to accept it, and you said, thank
you, this proves that shareware is high quality.
And all of a sudden, everybody looked shocked because they
didn't realize at that point they had voted for a
shareware product.
And we also said, hey, we'll be back next year.
And we weren't anyway.
But we were working on Doom.
We thought we'd be there next year.
That was also where Jay told me, he says,
we've got it, you know, we took a lot of heat for killing
all those Nazis in the game.
But this time, we've got it licked.
You're killing demons.
Nobody can complain about that.
Yeah, we actually got a lot of comments
about killing dogs, which was pretty funny.
You can kill people, but not dogs.
So that was.
And I think Quake bothers some people that there's
Rottweilers in there.
And you can kill the dogs and you feel sorry for them.
Anyway.
OK.
So Nolan, it seems like things have come
full circle with PlayNet.
You started out by putting machines in bars and
restaurants.
You know, people would pay as they play, and now it seems
like you're putting machines in bars and restaurants, and
people are going to pay to play.
Why are you going the route of the discrete
hardware, that route?
I mean, isn't that a pretty expensive way to go when
everybody's saying just web, web, web?
Well, I believe that whenever you pioneer, you want to find
low-hanging fruit.
That is, how do you?
get into a marketplace in positive cash flow, or as
close to positive cash flow as you can.
And when you push on technology, what you really
want to be able to do is control things as
much as possible.
And right now, if you really look at the web and latency,
it's really horrible.
And everyone who says that they've got some kind of a
silver bullet.
you know it's it's still the LA freeway at rush hour and
even though you can create some passing lanes and things like that
there's a lot of problems with games over the net particularly when you want
to do massively parallel things.
So I felt that the coin op world
gives, has a lot of advantages. One, you can have a target hardware. Two, you can choose
an intranet solution if you want to, since you have total control of the whole structure.
The next area is that when you move into a new area, you want to be able to merchandise
and make changes. I mean, it really started.
from a decision I made when I turned 50 to get back
into the game business.
I'd been fooling around with a lot of other areas,
sort of going on the five year and out theory,
that do something for five years and then do something
completely different for five years,
and that way you have a very interesting life.
And I did venture capital in restaurants
and telecommunications and microwaves and mapping
and all that sort of stuff.
And each one of them was interesting.
But I decided that games were really a heck of a lot more fun.
And so when you turn 50, you say, OK, I can reevaluate
what's going on in my life and go back and do something that
I've already done before.
And so the fact that Nolan Bushnell was going to get back
in the game business, I didn't think that anybody was going
to be on bended knee welcoming me in my return.
So I felt that there probably would be a, that I had to come
in, create a nice.
place and then move out from there.
Turns out there's never been
a failed consumer game that was successful in the coin-op side.
I felt that the coin-op business was just horribly managed
because it was becoming very, very insular.
The business was collapsing in on itself because the gains were
getting to have such a high threshold.
of such a difficult learning threshold that people were leaving.
I mean, one year it was six percent of the market was giving you 90 percent of the revenue,
then four, then three, then two.
1983, the coin op business was $18 billion at CoinDrop.
Last year it was six.
That's a huge collapse.
It was really because people were getting life and the games were getting so complex.
that unless you had a PhD in Mortal Kombatness, a typical person going into an arcade had
no chance.
So I felt the business had to have a big reset.
The big reset, I decided, couldn't be in an arcade, because the arcade, getting a person
from their home into an arcade was a lot different than getting them off a bar stool to another
bar stool.
And so I felt that...
So I felt that the right place was in bars and restaurants.
So I created a countertop game, PlayNet.
This runs on a Pentium, graphics-assisted, 1.2
gigabyte hard drive, touchscreen interface, modem,
two telephone handsets, and 32 megs of RAM running on NT.
And we're off and locked and loaded.
The basic strategy is this.
download a game, you're talking about a game a month, we're downloading a game a week.
So constantly renewable content, you don't have to blow up the theater every time you
change the movie, which is sort of the point out model right now.
That it's not, that it's connected to the net.
We're also doing tournaments, because it turns out that there are a lot of states that allow
games of skill to be prized.
So we can now have prizes and cash and what have you.
We have chat, but not chat with typing because Bubba don't type.
But Bubba does spill beer all over the touch screen.
That's OK.
As long as he's put a quarter in first,
he can spill it wherever he wants.
But quarters, that's one thing.
Credit cards are another.
Because since we're on the Met, now we can do credit cards.
and cash. Our machine takes ones and fives.
And so the objective is to
have games, multiplayer games,
tournaments, chat with handsets.
Now we use the protocol of
a chat room but with voice files. So now
one jerk can't dominate that sort of thing. Plus
we can now have audio chat on top of games
over the network.
Now, this is where I do my imitation of the Statue of
Liberty, because give me your tired, your worn, your humbled,
huddled programs longing to be free, because we're going to
have an open platform.
And anybody who wants to publish, just write it to NT.
We'll give you an API.
And we'll give you a percentage of the coin drop.
And it's real easy.
It'll be real fun.
Brings a whole new idea to shareware.
And then, of course, if people are playing it and having fun
in bars and restaurants all over the world, clearly,
there are going to be people that are going to want to do
it at home.
So we see it as a good way to merchandise games, to get in
trial, and also to be in this wonderful network.
We've got this thing called CollegeNet going, in which
we'll have all the colleges all over the nation, all over
the world, linked up for massively
multiple-player games.
And I mean just think of having a doom engine, okay?
with a
Sphere of influence so that you can only see a few people around you. We're going to want to have 10,000 in the same game
Big arena, it's collapsing cost you five dollars to enter
Three shots you can take three hits, but then three hits and you're out
Last guy standing gets ten grand
That sound fun? Boy, I want to do that.
Then we'll add one other little thing.
So have you done the research? How many states allow skill-based contests like that?
How many states allow skill-based contests like that?
There's about 23 that allow it, for sure.
There's another 15 that we're going to try, you know.
It's better to ask forgiveness often than permission.
And then there's several that, you know, you just go to hard jail.
And, but, you know, there's all kinds of fun sociology.
Imagine if you could now choose your jersey colors.
Now that says that now friends can locate other friends in cyberspace.
And so they say, okay, you wear the green and the blue and we'll have a good time.
because you figure out I'll watch your back, you watch my back.
So what we've introduced is cyberspace gang warfare.
And so the sociology of the thing could get really fascinating.
Well, I think it will, but I don't know if you could take credit for introducing it
because there's a lot of quake clans out there that are pretty well beating people up.
But you can't do 10,000, right?
Not yet.
But we can work on that.
I've got the platform, you write the code.
So what do you think, John? Do you think Daikatana death matches are going to be possible over this system?
Or are you going totally a different direction?
Well, Daikatana is using the Quake technology, so...
You know, it'll probably go up to 32 players.
Okay, we'll do 32 and then 32 and then 32.
We'll partition.
We'll put doors between them, you know, partition on servers.
That'd work.
Yeah, you could like have like small groups of games and then whoever wins there can go
on to the next phase and just kind of get everybody together.
You do that.
That's got to be fun, isn't it?
Oh yeah.
Well, we had talked about the possibility of
when we were doing Quake we would have New York versus LA and we'd have these gangs.
Yeah.
Which is what clans kind of turned out to be.
We were envisioning some huge numbers of players.
And that's kind of what it's...
Our original idea was we'd have some New York...
There'd be all these clans in New York or groups of players
and the best would form a team and they'd have their own little competitions.
finally create this core team of like six players or something
and uh... then we have l a do the same thing they have their own little sort of
tournaments
get down to a core group that that's their killer group and then you have
you know towns
you know big cities major cities fighting each other
to the best city in the u s is
stuff like that and they're just they're doing that uh...
They're starting to organize clan warfare stuff, the clan war council, North American war council and stuff like that.
It's happening by itself.
That's for sure.
Chris, what model do you see in the future for multiplayer play?
Do you think this collapsing arena idea is the approach you'd be interested in or a persistent universe or what?
Well, I guess considering one of the projects we're working
on is hoping to have the ability to have 10,000 people
online at the same time, then I would definitely say yes.
I mean, there's a lot of technical issues with getting
enough people at one time in the same space and action.
So I mean, I guess the way that we're looking at handling
it is very much.
you know, let's get 16 or 32 people in one space and action and, but everyone's sort
of on the equivalent of this huge virtual chat server that's dressed up to feel like
the world and universe that we put you in.
So everyone has a reputation, everyone has an affinity with a house that we're calling
in this game that we're working on.
So it has some similarities to what they've done with Quake World, although.
We're trying to do something that's a much more
persistent universe that just exists for a year or two
years and is modeled.
What I've noticed is that there seem to be a lot of
different tiers of customers with regard to latency.
There are those who only play games where latency doesn't
really affect much.
There are those who will play Quake free and put up with the
latency as long as it's free.
There are those who pay a little bit more for Duango or 10
with a low latency solution.
And there are those who just are somewhere in between.
What are you planning on doing with this project?
Are you going to design so that latency doesn't matter?
Or do you have a latency solution?
Well, I mean, I think we have as much of a latency solution
as everyone else does, which means you do as good as you
can.
And you do things like predictive intelligence
on motion and stuff.
I mean, I will say that the one thing I have noticed with
online is that, and it's the problem that we wrestle with,
and I'm sure everyone else wrestles with, is that if you
want to hit a mass audience, it has to be free online.
So you have to figure out how you can afford to do that for
free, but I mean, I know for me, when we were like, for
instance, Dablow's a great example with Battle.net, right?
We all got Dablow in the office, and we spent.
two, three weeks killing Dabble about three or four times until we killed them on every
difficulty level with all our buddies.
And that was just very cool because the first time it felt like the multiplayer experience
that I get at the office because we've all got high speed Pentiums and we've got a very
fast network and it's cool to play games at work which everyone in this room is okay for
but the rest of the world doesn't get that experience.
It's like I go visit Ion Storm and they're all like quake matching.
I phone them up and all I can hear is...
God damn it.
All right, OK.
And so actually for me, the coolest thing is seeing games
come along now where finally that experience that's so cool
for everyone in the industry that's been playing
multiplayer games for years is becoming available at home.
And whether or not the internet is perfect, I know it
isn't, but it's the best way to get that experience at
home, which is cool because I just want people to have the
same, I guess, sense of satisfaction.
that I do when I blow someone away, or I take their base out
at C&C, or whatever.
Besides the intranet, which gets around the problem in
the small group, with your collapsing arena idea, are
you going to design around latency?
Or are you just going to put up with it?
We have a whole bunch of projects that we call them
latency-averse, which we really don't care that much about.
We're actually.
targeting a market which doesn't care about that as much,
because most of it are people that are pretty well lubricated with alcohol anyway.
So you want latency basically.
So latency helps. Latency is our friend.
Really adults. One of the things that I want to point out is that,
don't forget that demographically right now,
teenagers are the smallest group that's been in years.
It's called the baby bust.
So, if you want testosterone to fundamentally lubricate your business plan,
it's not a good idea right now because everybody's getting older.
So, the real area that you want to focus on is how can I get women to play?
How can I get older business people to play?
How can I enfranchise kids who are under 10?
And the other markets are fun, and they're really exciting.
And the 8 to 18-year-old male, 8 to 35-year-old computer jock,
that's one thing.
But we really want to focus and try
to broaden our demographics to people that maybe
have CPU processing times that are equivalent to old 386s instead of Super Pentiums.
If we talk about us as being a 60 hertz massively parallel computer,
some of us I think have dropped down to about 40 now.
Well, I have one last generic question
that I want to ask you.
And then I want to make sure that if we have some questions,
at least here in the audience, that we get a couple of them
out.
So I'm going to ask each one of you in turn,
what is the biggest mistake you ever made in game design?
And since I started before one way,
I'm going to start the other way.
John, what was the biggest mistake
that you can think you ever made in game design?
She's probably not spending enough time
on Quake's single-player game.
That's probably it
My current game is you know I spent a lot of time on my current games game design
in
Quake is a really great multiplayer game
But I really like to play single-player stuff, and I really wish that I had spent more time doing doing
Better design on the single-player game, but it was there was you know the situation and everything
That was probably the biggest mistake
Chris
I think it was Times of Law and I built this sort of Gauntlet style top down view game
and I was real, because I loved Gauntlet when I was playing in the arcades and so I wanted
to do something that had more depth and you know you can go around and you can talk to
people and you know so I was really in love with this sort of mono scale but you know
instead of just being Gauntlet on these contained maps I wanted this huge world and so I built
this huge world and then.
you know, I would leave a town and I'd walk for about 20 minutes and nothing would happen.
Finally I'd get to the other town and, you know, I'd be going, hmm, you know, that's
not so much fun.
So at that point I started, okay, well I'm going to sort of invent random monsters here
so as I'm walking from the towns I've got something to do.
And about that point I said, hey, you know, look, next time I'm doing something like this,
if there's ever a point where I'm making a game and I'm putting stuff in the game to
get around something that isn't fun, maybe that shouldn't be there in the first place.
So...
you know, interestingly enough, I was like, okay, well, I think at that point, I, you
know, I was spending a lot of time to make it fun between the cities.
And so I was like, well, you know, next time I should probably have like an overall map
and then I say I'm going to go from this city to this city and sort of scope the action
to, you know, where I had the areas of interest in the game.
So it was pretty funny because that's the way Richard had with his Ultima design originally
and then he moved to mono-scale with Ultimas later on, you know.
I'd be there on like Ultima 7 and I'd be spending two years with level designers making sure
every little single part of the map is interesting because even though that wasn't part of the
main story you could wander off over there.
So I guess for me I just felt like it was very important to focus on what the fun aspects
of the game were and then sort of exclude the rest of them.
And that sort of actually drove Wing Commander because Wing Commander was just very much
focused on okay I want to do space dog fighting and that's it.
And...
So I guess you learn from your mistakes.
Well, smart people do.
Nolan, what do you think your biggest mistake
was in the game biz?
Oh boy.
I got so many of them.
I don't think I can limit it to just one.
Probably the one, technically, that was the biggest blunder
was deciding to save the cost of a connector that had a
couple of extra pins.
in the Atari 2600 cartridge slot and not having a read-write line that really cut, I mean,
this will sound funny, but we really thought that the 2600 was going to play about 16 games
and that that was all, you know, I mean, because we thought it was really clunky. I mean, we
only have 128 bits of RAM, you know, so that's not bytes, those are bits.
And so by not having a read-write line,
it really said that the ROM cartridges couldn't be
augmented with that real bad thing.
The other part was a product called VideoMusic.
We built 150,000 chips.
We built 75,000 units, and we sold six.
And that was really a little more than that, but at full price.
You know.
If only there'd been infomercials then, you could have done the miracle thing.
But the real thing in the game business that I regret is selling Atari.
I think, you know, it was a thing where I was young.
To Warner or selling it period?
Selling it to Warner.
You know, I mean, boy, nobody could have screwed it up as bad as they did.
It's maybe the tramels.
No comment.
Well, you know, when you start a company, it's sort of like your baby.
And even though you've sold it, you kind of watch it and you hope it doesn't go to
prison and various things.
And, uh,
And it's been really disappointing to see my baby
hacked to death through just blunders.
And I kind of feel like, I mean, there's one of the
things that people don't realize.
Imagine the Atari 800, which was technically superior in a
lot of ways, a lot of things.
But remember and.
Some of you young guys won't even know this happened,
but can you imagine a company that actually said,
if you write software for our platform, we'll sue you?
How to gain influence and win people.
But essentially, in the Atari 800,
after I sold the company, I mean,
we had all this stuff designed and created
pretty much before I left.
But then the Warner Marketing got a hold of it.
and said, well, this is clearly a closed platform.
It's working the video game business.
So not only do they not release the specs or any
authoring tools or anything like that, they said, hey,
we're not going to let you distribute, and we're going to
take you to court.
So while Jobs was out evangelizing, Atari was saying
thou shalt not.
And of course, the history is history.
But Atari could have had it all with just a little bit of
intelligence.
That's your guess.
My biggest mistake tonight was not watching the clock, so
we're probably only going to have room for like two
questions from the audience.
So let's see.
Just if you can, a question right here.
The products of these three gentlemen, I'm sure, have
greatly influenced everybody in this room.
I'd be very interested to know which products have greatly
influenced them.
Oh, excellent question.
Since your products have influenced so many people in the room, which products have influenced you?
So, you've been in the middle all the time, Chris, so you start off this time.
Okay. Well, I would say that the very, very early days when I was programming over in England,
a game called Elite, which came out on a machine called the BBC Micro.
When I came over here, there was a game Larry Holland did, which was Battle Hawks 42.
which was fantastic.
Most of the, you know, all the Infocom
early adventure games I used to play like crazy.
I still play adventure games. I love them.
I love the LucasArts games.
Recently, I would say I kind of split my time
between playing a lot of multiplayer
strategy games. C&C is the one I still play now
even though I was playing it two years ago.
Mainly because I think it's for multiplayer.
game when you're a good player at it, it's the best.
And it's actually better balanced than even Red Alert
was, and I think it's better for fast-paced multiplayer
action than some of the other stuff, even though they're all
great games.
I was very impressed by iDabble recently.
I thought that that was the best application I'd seen with
integrating multiplayer over the internet in a product.
It was just incredibly slick.
So, I guess that's kind of my playlist.
John?
Well, the very first game that really impressed me a lot was Pac-Man.
Back in, geez, I think it was 82 or something.
Because it had color and it had a very different game design.
It was not shooting things. It was, you know, staying away from things.
Which was very, very interesting.
And that really got me interested in designing games,
because I could actually, from watching that game,
it really looked like there was endless possibilities
to game design, because they weren't following the trend,
which was just shooting things, shooting aliens.
After that, I was a real big Apple II guy.
And probably Castle Wolfenstein was a really interesting game,
because it was very different.
Played a lot of Infocom stuff and those guys were great.
LucasArts was also a really big influence.
Maniac Mansion and some of their adventure stuff.
And definitely Diablo was a big influence.
It was very different.
I didn't get into the real time strategy stuff as much.
I mean it was fun and everything but I really...
I like first-person action stuff, so I kind of didn't eat it up as much.
And I really like the first-person action thing, so I really watch my genre and take notes and try and improve and push it further.
But there really haven't been too many things that have really impressed me a whole lot.
Just a few different games.
This is a little bit harder, but in terms of sort of standing on shoulders, I think
Steve Russell's programming on a PDP-1 of Space War was a very important game for me.
You played that a long time ago in the arcades.
It's not that big though.
And a game called Chicago Coin Speedway, which was a driving game before video games, which
used, which is a real...
Rube Goldberg of slide projectors and various things.
But over the years, games that I particularly liked have been,
it's one that you don't hear very much, but Fool's Errand,
I thought was a very interesting.
collection of little games that were pretty clever.
Of course, Tetris was something that was
very important to me.
I've been a big Doom player.
I currently am playing with my son's a lot of Warcraft II,
which I can say that I have a seven-year-old that is a
Warcraft II level editor.
I think that there's a game that is not on anybody's list here,
but it's one called Pajama Sam from Humongous, which I think
is for my two-year-old, is absolutely a super hit.
And it's got depth and humor and really some pretty good stuff.
So if any of you have kids, I highly recommend it.
I thought of some other games.
The Ultima series, which I really liked a lot.
And a lot of Squaresoft's games, like Chrono Trigger or Final Fantasy 3.
That stuff is, I love Squaresoft stuff.
I think those, I just want to kind of mention the RPG side of things,
because I really like that genre and we're planning on hitting it.
Okay, good. One more question. The first real hand I see. If not, thank you very much for
attending and there is one way in the back. Well, there's one right here. Okay, go.
I'd say the success changed your lives at all.
Nolan already told you it was five years and out.
The question was, has success changed your lives at all?
We'll start with Nolan.
Absolutely.
I've been rich, I've been poor, rich is best.
The thing that you have to do, though, is there's only so
much eating and drinking and living money that you have.
The rest of it's sort of poker playing money.
And it determines how big a game you can get in.
And I think building in the final analysis is the most fun.
And if you can build better and more efficiently, I think
you have a good life.
And I think that there are some times when making a lot
of money, you can become insufferable for a while.
But then you have to get whacked in the side of the
head with a few slings and arrows, and it turns you back
into a real person.
And I think it helps both ways.
Okay, Mr. Fly Yellow Ferrari?
Uh, hello.
Ha!
Well, I have some cars.
And basically, I really spend a lot of time playing games
and making them.
I really don't spend too much time doing anything else.
I don't watch TV.
I rarely go to movies.
So I'm still doing what I want to do, but I can really spend
time doing it all constantly now, because I'm working and
I'm making money doing what I like to do.
And that's what I do most of the time.
I think it's cool that my parents really get a big kick
out of it, because they always tell people find out that
they.
that are the parents of the guy that wrote Doom.
And so they talk to a lot of people because of that,
because they got Doom shirts and everything.
But mostly, I can get involved with a lot more things now,
just because of the stuff that I've done and everything.
But what I really spend a lot of time doing is still making
games and playing them.
And Mr. Michael Ruehrer?
Well, I mean, I definitely think it's cool that I don't
have to listen to my dad asking me when I'm going to
go back and finish my degree and get a job that has a
little longer lifespan.
But I mean, actually, I've got to say, I mean, success is
great and everything.
But the coolest thing, if you really love what you're doing,
is that it just enables you to do what you want.
And that's the important thing for me.
That's the nice thing that I got from it, is that I can
pretty much.
in the software side, making games, get to do the games I want to make. And, you know,
I wish that upon everyone here because it's cool when you get there and it's really tough
when you don't. And I remember when I wasn't there and I used to have to beg and plead
and tell them that, you know, yeah, okay, all times didn't sell very well, but come
on, you really got to go for this week, man, I think it's going to be cool. And you need
to like give me an artist so I can do that. And, you know, that takes a lot of energy.
So, it's nice not to expend that energy and that's what I like about success.
But I do understand that I missed somebody in the back.
So if you'll be honest and jump up and ask that question.
I have a question about, you talked about a lot of great
solo player games, but you talked about a lot of new
projects for multiplayer.
What are the solo player games going to be?
The question is, you talked a lot about multiplayer projects.
Where are solo players going?
Chris?
I think in the future, there's going to be two style of games.
There's going to be
immersive single player games that are primarily story driven.
You know, I know I'm still interested in making those.
You know, an adventure game sort of, you know,
Monkey Island is a good example of that.
A Wing Commander is a good example of that.
It, they're just, they're different kind of environments.
I think right now, you know, myself and a lot of, you know,
I know John and a lot, you know.
Sounds like Nolan.
Very enamored by the whole social computing aspect of
being in a world and environment with a bunch of
other people that are real people, because at the end of
the day, no matter how great.
We are programming our artificial intelligence, just
doesn't cut it to the unpredictability and the
intelligence that a real person has.
And so you feel a real satisfaction from playing a
one-on-one game or a one-on-20 game against other people.
So I think that's very attractive and interesting.
But I mean, I think at the end of the day, I mean, the solo
game, I mean, I know I just recently played Instinct 76.
Had a cool storyline, had a cool look.
I played it for a week or two. I had fun. I mean, it was worth the $50, $60 it cost.
And, you know, that's the experience I can do myself and in my own time.
And I think that's always going to be there.
So, I mean, I think, you know, multiplayer is going to become a much stronger portion of the market.
It's not going to take away from...
the solo game, I think multiplayer is really just going to expand the marketplace and give
a new kind of experience there.
I guess what you're seeing is a lot of sort of heat and passion because it's the new thing
and we're all sort of enamored of it.
But at the end of the day, you know, I still like stories.
And if you want to be involved and have someone tell you a story,
it's very difficult to do that on a multiplayer game.
And I know because I'm going through that whole design problem right now.
And so, at the end of the day, I still like to play adventure games and,
you know, I'll play those solo and have a lot of fun.
I don't know about you, John, but...
I feel the same way.
I love single player games, of course.
I love multiplayer games too.
But actually in multiplayer, I don't like so much the whole...
clan warfare where there's like a million people in one game just destroying each other
randomly.
I really like the one-on-one game where you have a map that's interesting and you hunt
the other guy down and you really get paid back for your knowledge of that area.
I've seen it first hand.
It's a lot more fun to me than just the random violence that happens in just complete, you
know, huge multiplayer environments.
But I really like the single-player game
because it's custom.
It's created for the player to go through.
And when you're done with that, then you can spend all
your time in multiplayer.
And nowadays, we have to make these games that have so much
stuff in them.
We have to have a really great multiplayer segment of the
game, we have to have a really great single-player segment.
We spend a lot of time and money developing both of these,
and we really have to look at it and say, well, these are
really almost two different games.
We're creating one game for one person to go through,
to follow a story, and have a certain experience, which
is very different than a multiplayer game.
And now, it's almost like developing two games nowadays,
because the expectations are so high for these multimedia
extravaganzas that we're creating.
And it costs more money to create them, too.
The multiplayer thing is definitely getting stronger,
just like Chris said.
But I can't see it taken away from the single-player game.
When I got Dark Forces, I played it, I loved it,
got finished with it, and I did not
feel bad that it didn't have multiplayer because that's not
what it was all about.
And it's really-
It's basically your fault there's
a multiplayer expectation.
Yeah.
Well, the thing is, every game doesn't
have to do the exact same thing as the last game.
As long as enough games come out and everybody's satisfied,
that's cool.
You don't have to say that one game comes out
and it is better than everything else before it.
I agree. I think there's going to be both markets.
In fact, I think the single-player market will continue to be
the dominant and actually the bigger for quite some time.
But I always set little bogies for myself.
One of the things that I'm trying to do is I want to displace
every game of solitaire that's being played in the business class on airlines.
If I can do that with one of my games,
I'll consider that to be a suitable.
bogey to have achieved.
That's cool.
Well, it's been a real pleasure for me,
and I hope it was a real pleasure for you.
And I'm firmly convinced more than ever
that these really are legends of computer gaming.