Good morning everybody. Thanks for coming. Uh, welcome to Building Esports. Uh, my name is Nick
Allen. I work at Twitch. Uh, I'm also joined by Chris from Daybreak, the executive producer on
H1Z1. Uh, so we're going to be talking overall for about an hour. Um, I'll be talking about 20
minutes or so, then open it up to the, for you guys for questions. Um,
But really the takeaway, at least from my presentation, is hopefully you walk out of
here with sort of a holy shit moment of, hey, there's a lot that goes into eSports as a
whole.
And I think what you see for the most part in eSports are these top level leagues on
Twitch or on some other platform.
But underneath these top level leagues are a bunch of moving parts.
And my hope is I can just highlight this again just so you guys have an idea of like what goes into building eSports.
And today I'm going to be doing that through the lens of Rocket League.
So Twitch, probably about a year ago now, entered into a partnership with Psyonix to help build Rocket League eSports.
Rocket League was a title that came out of nowhere, surprised a lot of people, and has a lot of potential.
I'll be talking a little bit about that and about our partnership and again all these
moving parts.
And again this is a picture.
I used to work at Riot.
I pulled this off Twitter.
Someone put devil horns on me.
I thought it would be a good icebreaker.
So one caveat really quick.
Chris and I were talking about who wanted to go first and I wanted to go first because
my slides are really terrible and I figured his slides are probably really good because
I've played Daybreak games.
So.
So let's talk about the agenda really quick. So I have a friendly reminder for you guys.
Um, and I'm going to talk about identifying eSports potential. Twitch, um, has an eSports
department. And the eSports department itself...
It focuses on building partnerships with game companies around eSports, ultimately to help
them make better decisions around their titles in the eSports space.
And our department was born out of a lot of different entities, a lot of different game
companies coming to Twitch and asking, like, how do I do this thing?
How do I do it right?
And seeing a bunch of other titles just not being successful in the space.
We call that the eSports graveyard.
But essentially, that is people coming in and throwing a bunch of money.
And you see these titles just dip and disappear.
You never hear from them again.
I won't call them out by name, but you probably have some in mind of like something that blew
up and then instantly disappeared.
Twitch, we want longevity and sustainability in the eSport space quite selfishly, honestly,
because we think that if eSports are successful, they're going to be on Twitch and more people
are going to watch it.
And that's good for us, but it's just good for the space in general.
And we just want to grow the thing to be as big as we can.
So I'll be talking about eSports potential and how at Twitch we identify that.
I'll talk about the goal.
We generally have one big goal as we think about eSports at Twitch, when we think about
these partnerships.
And then we'll be talking about growing the ecosystem.
And again, I want you guys to look at all the moving parts and think about sort of the
complexity that comes in building a sustainable, successful eSport.
But first a friendly reminder.
Um, on the spelling of eSports. So you don't capitalize the M in email.
Uh, so why the hell would you capitalize the S in eSports? It looks weird when you put it
in front of a sentence and you have two capital letters in a row. Uh, it sort of undermines
the brand a little bit. So please, uh, advocate for the correct spelling. Thank you very much.
Um, if you walk away with one thing from this presentation, the friendly reminder of how
to spell eSports correctly. Okay.
So talking about identifying potential. So we talked to a lot of different game companies and
they come to us and they're like, hey, I want to do e-sports. And they don't have a clear
understanding of what that is or why it's cool or what it's about or anything.
And so we come in and we assess the game, and we try to give recommendations on what
they should do, how they can improve, what they should be thinking about.
And the amount that we sort of invest and sort of partner with them depends on do we
think that the game has a lot of potential in the eSports space.
And so the way that we evaluate that is does the game have a high skill ceiling?
And does it have some features that allow for a competitive culture around the game?
So private matchmaking, you'd be surprised a lot of game companies come to us and like
hey we want to do an eSports, well you have no way for one person or one team to play
against another team sort of like on demand.
So that's the first thing you're going to need in order to be able to create a competitive
culture around your game.
And it goes for things like
So private matchmaking, custom game rules, can the community decide what's competitive
and what's the highest level of competition around the game?
And then the leaderboards are also a really important piece that we look at.
Is there this aspirational path to being the best player in the world?
Again, it goes back to this idea, is there a competitive culture?
Rocket League does these things extremely well.
There is a huge competitive community that aspires to be the best in the world.
Also identifying potential.
So we look at is there an existing and growing grassroots community.
So these are examples of grassroots competitions and organizations
that existed before Psyonix and Twitch partnered for Rocket League.
Things like Rocket Royale, Rocket League Central,
this is Geek Core running this Rocket League tournament as well.
What these indicate is that people want to compete.
and people want to organize tournaments. Those are two brutally important pieces of a
holistic e-sports ecosystem. We forget we think much about uh the production company
The developer and the game company, maybe the broadcasting platform, but you forget
about the tournament organizers oftentimes and the aspirational path to being a tournament
organizer, content creators.
There are a bunch of small players that are important in the growth of this holistic ecosystem.
And this indicates that something is happening, that there could be more.
And so this is one of the big things that we look for when we think about identifying
potential in an eSports title.
And then lastly and almost most importantly is,
does the game company have an appetite to invest?
And there's two ways that they can do this.
One is.
Cash money. Are they willing to put up prize money that is aspirational and interesting to players?
Are they willing to support and create sustainability? Are they willing to take potentially some of their revenue that they're making on in-game items and pass that down to the players and the teams?
Are they willing to do that? And oftentimes, we talk to game companies, they don't realize how much money they need to invest to be able to get this thing off the ground and be sustainable long-term.
And oftentimes we're like, hey, well, you should do this event,
and you should do this other event, and you should do all these other things.
Like, well, we have a marketing budget for one small event in this one city,
and that's all we can do the whole year.
That isn't a sustainable long-term plan.
And so this is a really big part.
And the second thing is, and it's very closely related, bandwidth.
Engineering resources.
Are you willing, as an entity, as a company, to invest in
creating cool, compelling things in the game that support your eSports efforts.
And this can also feed into this sort of revenue aspect too.
But it's oftentimes, companies aren't willing to change their road map
to accommodate this eSports ecosystem that is super important to
the competitive culture around their game.
And so one of the first things that we ask when we talk to a game company is,
You know, how big are you willing to go?
If this thing gets enormous, are you willing to support it?
And what are your engineering resources,
your internal resources, that you're
willing to utilize to support the things that you're doing?
So again, very, very important things that we think about when
we identify potential opportunities in e-sports.
So bringing this back to Rocket League and Psyonix,
Psyonix is an amazing partner to Twitch
around the Rocket League Championship
Series and around e-sports.
And it was clear very early, though they were a small studio, they were willing to invest
whatever they needed to do to help this thing be successful, to help it be sustainable.
And that showed us that we could do something with them long-term, it would be interesting,
and we think it would be successful.
And we're going to talk a little bit about all the different things that we've done.
So that's identifying potential in what we've done.
And talking about the goal, going back to this idea of the eSports graveyard, people
generally have a top-down approach, game companies generally have a top-down approach when they
think about eSports.
I know Chris will have some things to say about this and some really good things too.
Thinking about, let's create a top-level event for the best players in the world, we'll throw
a bunch of money at it, and then that's it.
And then you have an entire player base that wants more, that desires more around the game
that you're forgetting about, that you aren't supporting.
So it's important to have a really holistic view of supporting the eSport.
And so talking about Rocket League and the way that we've done that.
So we have the top level league, which is the Rocket League Championship Series.
We're on our season three right now and we've had a lot of success.
I could do an entire presentation on just a top level league.
But to give you an idea of what goes into this, we have one person at Twitch fully dedicated
to the scheduling.
of the league and also the rules.
That's all that this person does.
He has a full-time job supporting our rule set,
supporting our schedule, working with teams
and players to resolve conflict.
And that is just one small aspect
of a giant massive league.
So when you think about even a bigger league
like the League of Legends Championship Series
that has a staff of like 120 people
to support that initiative.
You start to understand how big these things can be
and how many moving parts.
We're talking about production, stage design, hospitality,
all these different moving pieces
and all the teams that you need to have
to support these things.
We're also investing heavily in caster development.
These are the storytellers of the eSport.
They are the faces of the game in many ways
and of the eSport too.
So these are all the casters for,
this is season one, the broadcast talent.
All of these people were handpicked out of the community to come in and then were mentored
and cultivated to be the professionals that you see today.
And many times, this is what people think about.
These guys are the people that they think about when they think about Rocket League.
And they need to be able to represent the league, themselves, players, the brand, everything
extremely well.
If you have an amazing league but your casters are not talented or toxic or a bunch of different
things, you can undermine the entire thing.
So this is just one foundational piece that you have to develop.
And we have at Twitch and at Psyonix, we have people fully dedicated to growing the professionalism
and talent of the Rocket League Championship Series and of Rocket League.
path to pro. So this is a really, really important aspect that a lot of people don't think about.
When you think about football, professional football, and you think about what it takes
to be a professional and how you get there, there's a clear path for you. You play in
peewee football, and then you play in middle school, then high school, then college, and
then you're a pro.
For many eSports, you say, how do I get in this top level competition?
People have no idea.
There's no clear aspirational path for people to look at and say,
how do I get there?
I have no idea.
And so they just stop trying.
Path to pro is an extremely important.
And with the Rocket League Championship Series, we utilize an open qualifier every season
to qualify in the next round of teams.
Our first or second season had over 6,000 teams sign up for the Rocket League Championship
qualifier.
And if you think about it, there's three to four players on every team, so you're talking
roughly about 20,000 Rocket League players.
that you have to manage over the course of one to two weeks.
And we have a full staff of Psyonix and Twitch employees,
six, seven, eight people in a war room
over the course of a weekend running this tournament
and all the moving parts with 20,000 players.
And as the amount of people,
as the prestige rises for the RLCS
and more people start playing Rocket League,
the more people are gonna be entering this thing,
the more challenging it becomes.
But with that in mind, it's an important piece.
Again, the aspirational path of growing and becoming a professional is really, really
important.
Narrative development, the storylines are an interesting piece, are an important piece
of e-sports and something often overlooked.
Why do you care as a viewer?
Why do you care about these players and these teams?
E-sports doesn't have the regional alliances or the regional rivalries that we see in traditional
sports, so you need something else, something to care about and be passionate about.
And these types of stories help build that narrative,
help build up the celebrity and fame of these players
and make it interesting for the fan to be like,
hey, this is why I follow Karnovy,
the best player in the world in Rocket League.
And again, just very, very important stuff
as you think about why should you watch esports
and why should you care.
So for these particular pieces, we flew out to the houses of the players, a full production
crew, interviewed them, learned about their stories and what they're about, talked to
their families about, hey, what was it like when he wouldn't leave his room and played
Rocket League every day for ten hours, and now he's making thousands of dollars playing
the game.
We capture that, we create it.
But it takes an entire team dedicated, traveling,
to build these types of stories,
and to build this narrative around Rocket League.
Another really big piece is the live events.
Again, I could do an entire presentation on any of these,
especially the live events,
but we did our last season two grand finals in Amsterdam.
We had 1,200 people attend.
We sold out tickets, I think, in two weeks,
maybe a little bit less than that.
But there are a million moving parts to a live event,
from stage design to hospitality to hotel booking
to transportation to visas are a huge topic now in e-sports.
How do you get players from other countries into the US
to play when it isn't recognized as an official sport
by many organizations?
These are all huge hurdles that you
have to overcome that are important when coordinating
a live event of this size.
The investment for these can scale anywhere from $50,000
to millions and millions of dollars.
But the amount of work that goes into these things is astounding, putting on a massive
live event, coordinating all these players.
And I'll attest to the personal struggles I've had of coordinating 50, you know, 16
to 18-year-old players internationally, moving them over to Amstram can be very, very challenging.
And then regional expansion, and really how I should phrase this is go to where the players are.
Oceania is where we've expanded the Rocket League Championship Series in Season 3,
because that's where there is a passionate fan base of players, a big group of players as well,
that demand, they're just really, really demanding professional competition around Rocket League in their region.
And every time you expand, you run into the challenges of, can my rule set be legally
enforced in this region?
How do I do international play with these regions?
How do you build a league that is culturally relevant to the player base that's unique
to this region, too?
So all of these things pop up and become extremely challenging as you think about regional expansion.
And you can expect, in our partnership with Psyonix around Rocket League.
We'll continue to expand and we'll continue to have teams fully dedicated to thinking
about how do we go into Brazil?
How do we go into all these other regions that have all these unique challenges?
And then lastly, I think the one more major piece is,
for us anyways, is event placement or slash TO support.
How do we crowdsource competitive play?
How do we get more people involved in running tournaments
and playing in tournaments?
And again, creating a competitive culture
around the game is super, super important.
Now I can't tell you where we're going to announce some stuff pretty soon, but a big part of our work is,
hey, tournament organizer, what do you think about Rocket League?
What is interesting to you? What do sponsors think?
Like all these different things and advocating to have this at all of these major eSports events.
Get it there, get more eyeballs on it, is a really important point.
Again, just driving engagement is really important.
So I've talked about like five or six things.
I'm just scratching the surface as to the amount of
work and the amount of things that are moving when you
create a holistic e-sports ecosystem.
I haven't even hit on all of the content that's
created around this.
I haven't hit on the web development needs that need to
happen, hospitality and travel.
There are a bunch of moving pieces with fully dedicated
staff to resolving, to addressing all of these
different pieces.
So, again, it's all in an effort to support a holistic system.
It would be much easier for us to do, you know, two or three major events a year and
really throw all of our resources into that and then forget about all these other pieces.
But in doing that, we wouldn't have the results that we do.
And so this is just from, I pulled this from an infographic that we have around the season
two world championship for the Rocklea Championship Series.
24.2 million minutes watched, over a million unique viewers, 1,200 live attendants, 3.9
million Twitter impressions.
This is a result of this holistic approach to eSports,
and a really important piece too.
Without all of these things,
we do not believe we would be where we are today.
And we see these numbers continuing to grow.
over time.
And as we continue to expand to different regions, as we continue to expand our efforts
and the prestige of the RLCS continues to grow, we imagine these numbers are going to
continue to go up.
You can find this actually, the infographic from Season 2 on our RLCS Twitter account.
And again, we're seeing even larger numbers for Season 3 as we venture into that too.
So that's, again, that's a super high level.
I can't believe I've already been talking for 20 minutes.
There are a bunch of moving parts,
and really, again, my takeaway for you is
you guys are seeing probably a broadcast
or production on Twitch, but below the surface of that.
When we're talking about ESL events,
when we're talking about all these different
tournament organizers, there are insanely huge staff
supporting these massive events.
In many cases much larger than what we have
dedicated to the RLCS.
And if you take shortcuts,
In eSports, you will find yourself as a game company in the eSports graveyard.
You need to be thinking about a holistic approach that touches all of these pieces plus more.
And so after this presentation, after Chris speaks at 11, I'll be out in the hall.
I would love to talk to you guys and talk more.
If you have questions about this, I'm going to...
I'll open the mic here in a second too.
But again, just thinking about it's much, much bigger,
much bigger than what you're seeing on Twitch.
And in order to be successful,
you need to have a lot of resources
dedicated to supporting this effort.
All right, so thank you very much.
I want to open it up for questions.
So, when you are trying to organize an event, you're obviously organizing many of your own
regional events leading up to the major.
At what point do you decide to partner with existing events, eSport events, like Dreamhack
or PAX or whatnot, versus go and create your own event that's dedicated to the one game?
Yeah, it's a really good question. So in our case what we generally do is we RFP, we'll request proposals from people in the ecosystem like, hey, we're thinking about doing this event, how would you do it and what's your take, right? And so then we weigh those proposals against like what
What is it going to take and what is it going to cost to do it in-house?
What's the comparison that we make?
Is it worth it for us to do it?
Do we expect a better fan experience?
Higher viewership?
What's the marketing pull from these organizations?
So we're weighing all of this value before we would move forward with something like
that.
But generally it's a big question.
Like, do you want to continue to grow?
and it's the game player's answer.
In this case, the answer is Petsco.
This is a time dilator.
If you taste the game Petsco, you double click on it.
This is a config app.
So if you tap on config...
Petsco's after ONIC,
you double click on it.
There's a whole set ofvention names
that you can use
and look at the different events
that you have all over the world,
and you can use these to lay down
So generally when we think about who we're going to partner with as a tournament organizer,
we look at their track record.
We look at what have they done and have they been able to, how have they done with the
resources that they have?
And if they've shown that they've been able to do a lot with, you know, potentially in
some cases limited resources.
Is our contribution going to bring them to a new level?
Is it going to help them be more successful?
Or do we think that they can be,
they have the opportunity or they have the...
They have the capacity to actually level themselves up to a point where you think it's worth supporting
them.
So my recommendation for you would be to run events and prove yourself, and I'm not sure
how many you've done, and try to do something small that is indicative of your capability
and from there start requesting more support from the game company or other tournament
organizers to help support your event based on your track record of success.
Hi.
So I'm a member of the competitive fighting games
community.
And one thing I've noticed is that there's actually
been a pushback towards the concept of e-sports
to the point where it's almost seen
with a negative connotation.
Because they see it as corporate kind
of messing with grassroots events,
enforcing rule changes, trying to clean up the community
to make it look better towards advertisers and sponsors.
So what do you think is the best approach for a company that's kind of dealing with
a community that doesn't necessarily want them to be involved?
Yeah, really good question.
I've actually experienced this.
I used to work for a company called the iGen Pro League a few years back.
We actually tried to e-sportsify the FGC for a while.
We did a show with Mike Ross and some other things and it was not received very well.
So we learned a valuable lesson there.
More than anything, I think sponsors and organizations
want to be authentic to the space.
And so what is authenticity to the FGC?
If I'm a sponsor and I want to come in and support your event,
I don't want to do it in a way that makes me look foolish.
And so I actually want to be real
and be able to relate with the community.
So the FGC, it's tough because as you bring in sponsors,
sponsors innately are sort of like e-sports, I guess.
The fact that there's money is sort of e-sports
as it relates to the FGC.
But really just showing what is interesting and unique about the FGC and why it's valuable for sponsors to get involved.
How are they authentic and how can they activate in a way that is interesting and compelling to FGC fans?
And if you can solve for that, I think you can maintain the identity of the FGC while also injecting more sustainability and money into the ecosystem as a whole.
But yeah, I think the FGC wouldn't be what it is if you sort of like e-sportsify it.
So you have to continue to sort of, you know, keep that identity true.
I think the sponsors are going to want that and the organizations are going to want that
too.
Okay.
Thank you.
Hey, Nick.
I'm wondering if you have any thoughts given you talked a little bit about international
stuff, how the current anti-immigration climate really affects things and the corollary.
outfits like Twitch, other eSports organizers, game developers can do to address that?
Yeah, it's a really good question, and something that we struggle with.
It is a systematic problem.
So there are all sorts of challenges when an organization, just being frank, with Twitch
that's owned by Amazon, starts to lobby in sort of like government dealings.
It becomes pretty challenging.
There's a lot of.
A lot of different steps.
But I think we can be a testament to the credibility
and opportunity in the eSports space because,
I mean, we look at some of these eSports athletes,
rumors of salaries over $500,000 a year
in a game like League of Legends or CSGO.
It's obvious that there is some skill,
there is some skill to this thing.
It is a skill-based competition.
And it's about sort of representing that in a way to the government or to the right entities to show like, hey, this is for real and you need to take it seriously.
And so I think it starts with people sort of like rallying together and figuring out
a strategy to communicate that in an effective way and partnering with the right entities
within probably academia and the government as well to properly represent this skill-based
thing that is eSports.
There's a million different ways that we can do that, but I think it's going to take
a bunch of different entities with credibility in the world to sort of represent that, hey,
this is important and we need to resolve this issue because it's sort of being a blocker
to continual growth in the eSports space.
I think we have time for one or two more.
Could you tell me what percentage of eSports leagues slash events are managed by Twitch
or with Twitch versus the rest of the space?
Yeah, sure.
So we partner with Capcom for the Capcom Pro Tour, and that's Street Fighter V. And we
also partner with Psyonix around Rocket League.
And so we have some other ones coming up as well.
But generally we're pretty mindful to not sort of,
we're very selective in who we partner with.
We also want to be mindful of the other players
in the space and not come in and sort of like
take over like these types of partnerships.
There's a lot of great smart organizations
like ESL, DreamHack in the space that are also great.
to support your eSports efforts too.
So we have two right now and we have a few more
that you can expect to hear about in the next few months.
But really we're just trying to be mindful
of giving a little bit of a nudge in the right direction
while also allowing the other really important players
in the space to also enter into these partnerships
and help point people in the right direction.
All right, last one.
How are you guys expanding your fan base to different cultures and subcultures where they
might not actually accept an eSport as a valid sport?
Yeah, good question.
It's really hard.
I think people have a general belief system as to what, like there's a general stigma
around video games I think we can all...
Everyone in the room can relate to that a little bit, and it's shrinking everyday.
But generally our strategy is working and trying to identify what the core fan base,
less of the people that are on the periphery, that don't fully engage or believe in esports
as a competitive aspect or something that's skill-based.
But with that in mind, I think as eSports grows, as more and more stories about these
players making millions of dollars from either streaming or playing competitively start to
surface, I think that will lend credibility to the fact that eSports is interesting, compelling,
and something that you should pay attention to.
So I think as this industry continues to grow, naturally people will be drawn to it as a
Viewing behaviors around content in general are going to be changing.
There's more cord cutters and people are moving into sort of like on-demand type viewing experience.
That's more in line with like a Twitch viewing experience.
And as that shift happens and again as eSports continues to build its credibility over time,
I think more people will be drawn to it and accepting of it
in a way that many people in this room and myself are actively now.
Cool, thanks very much guys, I'm going to hand it over to Chris, appreciate it.
I'm getting set up here, as Nick mentioned, I'm Chris Wynn, I'm the Executive Producer
on H1Z1 King of the Kill.
You're going to hear a lot of very similar themes and takeaways as you did in Nick's presentation.
It's almost like we coordinated, but I promise you we just met this morning.
So I think maybe we're on to something here.
Ultimately, to kind of talk about how we've been successful in eSports, it's a pretty complicated recipe.
There's a lot of pieces that actually go into it.
If I try to take away the biggest ingredient, you know, if this were chicken parmesan, chicken
would be the biggest ingredient, and it's that we've taken the approach that we're going
to partner very, very closely with our community.
We didn't come out and say, here's the next big competitive game, here's the next eSport
that you want to pay attention to.
We put out a game that we thought was fun, and then we listened to the community kind
of guide us to say, hey, we'd love to compete, here's what we'd like to see in the game,
and then we worked with that into our roadmap.
and started to deliver a feature set to let them decide what was going to work and what wasn't going to work.
If you're not familiar with H1Z1, uh, just real quickly, it's kind of a really new, unique
game. Uh, it's a bit of an evolution of a shooter, a hundred and seventy five people
parachute into a big open world environment. Uh, when you hit the ground you gotta kinda
scavenge around the world to look for weapons and equipment. Uh, it's gonna help you
compete against all the other players in the world. There's no respawns, it's all single
elimination, so everything's on the line for you as you, uh, play the game.
What it does is build so much tension that when you win the game it feels like you're on top of
the world. I've been working on this game for over a year. I have hundreds and hundreds of
hours of gameplay. I have yet to win a game. It drives me absolutely nuts. I've come close a few
times and I tell you it's, it, every time I'm in the top ten I'm like this is going to be it,
this is going to be it and then I fucking come in second or third.
So far, we've taken a walk, not a run approach to what we're doing in the competitive community.
So in 2015, we launched our first Invitational. We did this at TwitchCon.
And what we did was invite 60 of our biggest streamers from Twitch to compete for over $170,000 in prize money.
We raised that prize money with the community.
And so we took a portion of proceeds that we sold from some in-game items and used that to form a prize pool.
Ended up being very, very successful.
It was the most watched program at TwitchCon that year.
It really kind of catapulted and sent H1Z1 off
on a big trajectory that we're still following today.
Uh we followed that up in 2016 at TwitchCon again. We opened the uh the uh the field up a
little bit. We had over 70 people involved. Prize pool got much bigger, over $250,000 this
last year. Um again, big impression, a lot of people watching it. I think we had over a
thousand hours of uh gameplay stream leaning up to the event. Um really exciting couple of
matches and uh really kinda led to a lot of uh a lot of success for us.
Um, what we've seen this year is, uh, really kind of beginning with, uh, with the 2016
Invitational, we've started to see pro teams start to form around the event. Um, and when I
put this slide together about a week ago, maybe a little over a week ago, we had, uh, I
think six or seven pro teams announced. Um, they had announced, officially announced
rosters to compete in H1Z1 and I think even since then we've had another three or four, um,
as recently as yesterday I saw a couple of announcements from some teams. Um, that's
leading up to our next event, which is called Fight for the Crown.
What's cool about this, it will take place in March, it's going to air on the CW network
in April in primetime, which is something we're really excited about.
It's also going to be our first tournament using one of our team modes, so this will
be 15 teams of 5 all competing to see who can be the last team standing.
What's going to be really cool and what H1Z1 has that's really unique there is that we're
the only game you can find where 15 teams can compete at the same time.
Every other game is one v one, one team versus another team.
And we can get every single team in there competing at once.
A really unique cocktail and
really unique mixture to see how that's gonna play out.
So it's worked for us.
We did really, really well in 2016.
We were high up on the Steam charts.
You can routinely find us in the top five stream games
on Twitch right now.
We're almost always in the top five.
In the last two weeks, we've been the number one
selling title on Steam on their global top sellers list.
The success has blown us away.
Quite frankly, we're kind of sprinting to keep up,
to make sure all of our services keep standing up
and provide the best service as we can.
So what about the game is kind of leading to that success?
From our opinion, it breaks down to these kind of simple concepts.
So to start off with, the core of the game is actually very simple.
You drop into an environment, you have to live.
Don't die.
Right, that's pretty much it.
But from there, there's actually a lot of depth layered into it.
There's a ton of strategies that you need to employ when you hit the ground.
Where do you land?
How many other people land near you?
What loot is around you?
It's all randomly generated on the ground.
So you can go in with a plan A, but you better be ready to go all the way to plan Z based
on how the match plays out.
There's also a gas, a poisonous gas ring that slowly shrinks the map to shrink the play space.
It's a 100 square kilometer open world environment.
And so that's pretty important to keep the players together and competing.
When we talk about competitive gaming, so I completely agree with Nick, please don't
spell eSports with a capital S. In fact, we talk a lot about competitive gaming because
for us it's more than just the eSports, it's more than the spectacle of watching it, it's
more than putting on the tournaments.
The heart of our game is competitive and we want that to be open to every single player
that participates in our game, not just the pros who get identified and picked up by teams.
We really talk a lot about as we're building the game that we need to make sure it's fun
to watch.
No one's going to watch it if it's not fun to watch, and so we want to make sure that we keep the spectacle of watching the action as fun as possible.
It's more than just playing the game. It's also how people are viewing it.
And then, as I mentioned before, partnering with our community is a big part of what we do.
It can be frustrating at times because you get a lot of negative feedback, but you have to understand that comes with the job and it comes with the territory.
And you have to get to the root of what people are complaining about and get down to it and try to make a game that you know they're going to gravitate towards.
So as mentioned in the simple concept of talk about this,
you know, again, very, very unique.
You're not gonna find a game
where 175 people compete all at once.
It's a huge open world.
I mentioned 100 square kilometers
and this shrinks over time.
The course of one match takes about 35 minutes,
start to finish.
Most players are in there for a couple of minutes
and then they're gonna filter out
and go into the next game.
But that depth is really key, strategy is paramount.
There are key distinct strategies that are employed
in the early game versus the mid game versus the late game
and it evolves very quickly.
The early game's all about finding loot as fast as you can
and clearing out any players
that may have landed around you.
Mid game's about really setting yourself up
for the late game and late game is making sure
you have enough equipment to survive.
You probably want a vehicle to get around the map on
and set yourself up for those final 10
that I kind of talked about.
And you just have to be ready to adapt.
All the loot that spawns in the world is random.
It's going to be different every single match.
And I've talked about the moving gas.
There's an element of crafting in our game.
So you're going to pick up items and you're going to craft medical supplies
and other things to kind of help you during the match.
Armor, stuff like that.
And so understanding that depth of the game and what you need to find
in order to craft becomes a pretty big part of the skill mastery.
Vehicles are a big part of the game.
If you are at the end of the game and you don't have a vehicle,
you're going to be at a distinct disadvantage right now.
And so, again, more skill to learn there, more to master to learn where the vehicles
are spawning at, and then finding one and understanding how to take care of it.
It uses gas, it has health. You have to make sure you manage that.
Which layers into, there's an RPG element of inventory management.
And so you can only carry so much stuff. And you have to decide, am I going to carry this extra weapon
or do I need more medpacks in case I get into a fight? Do I want smoke grenades
or do I want frag grenades?
All of this is to say you have to stay on your toes
and there's a deceptive amount of depth to this game.
It seems very simple, it can be very easy to describe
but to get really good at it, it takes a long time.
We talk about this at the office a lot.
You know, when we build our competitive game we want anyone
to be able to have a chance to succeed and do well.
And so we talk about the average Joe becoming a pro.
And so when we look at how we start to open up our competitive events, can we add a qualifying
path that any person in our community has access to and we're not just picking, you
know, the 50 best players in the world or something like that.
And so we've built in leaderboards.
We've worked with website Twin Galaxies.
They have a, they partner with the team Echo Fox where they have also a set of leaderboards
and we can use these things to determine where the skill is and you don't necessarily have
to be, you know, a big personality on Twitch in order to get discovered.
You can come at it from your skill set and be found and be invited to an event to compete.
We have a whole meta on top of the game where every single match you play in gets scored.
One thing that was really important to us there is that scoring system is non-punitive.
So your top 10 scores from all your matches determine your place on a leaderboard and
then you can work up different divisions and tiers through the leaderboard.
But you're never going to go backwards.
We always want players to feel like they're progressing and that they have something to
attain and work towards.
And then like I said in the depth, it's getting players to focus on their own skill set and
not blame things on the game.
There's more to learn, there's more to watch on Twitch.
I can go watch a good player and kind of see how they approach this strategy and get some
tips to my own game so I can continue to refine my own experience.
And then it's really about sharing that experience.
We've done a pretty big in-game integration
with Twitch with their API.
So if you would like to try to get discovered,
we sort based on maybe the number of wins you have
or the number of kills you have,
where you're at in the match.
So someone might be interested to find
the next really talented person
as opposed to the next big personality.
Again, it's trying to put an avenue for everybody.
The big personalities are gonna get recognized,
they're gonna get picked up by viewers anyway.
But how can skilled players get found as well?
And this is something that we're gonna continue
to work on in the future to have a tighter
and tighter integration with Twitch.
Keeping it fun to watch.
We talk a lot, the phrase we use is the game
needs to be as fun to watch as it is to play.
Starts with that very simple to understand game.
It's a solo experience, there's no response,
I can watch someone play, I know exactly what's going on
and I don't have to worry about they're gonna die,
they're gonna respawn at some other place in the map
and I need to understand the map.
so that I can keep track of their progress and what strategy they're employing at that particular time.
As I'm watching someone play, it's really easy to kind of go,
oh, you know what, if I was in that position, I would do this or I would do that.
And that kind of opens up your mind into thinking, oh, you know, maybe I'd like to try this game.
I think I can do better than that person I was just watching.
The game naturally is set up with a good pace
that lends itself pretty well to our streamers.
They have time in between matches
while they're loading out and loading in
and getting ready for a new match.
They even have time during games sometimes
to interact with their viewers.
So it makes it easy for them to call out subs,
to call out tips, to interact and chat.
And that's pretty important to them
and it's pretty important to the viewers
watching the experience.
And it's something our game lends very well to.
I talked about the in-game Twitch integration and wanting to push that even further.
And we spent a lot of time building those relationships with our community.
We try to fly them out to the studio every so often, talk about a roadmap, get their
feedback, show the latest progress on the game.
I talk to, I get texted every day from multiple members of our community.
Sometimes not fun texts, but we deal with them all the same.
And to kind of finish up on that secret sort of part of the recipe, our community and the
competition is what drives the game.
We have a new feature rolling out in a few weeks that we're calling Hosted Games.
What this allows is some grassroots participation in the competitive space.
So we've done some stuff in the past, a little bit more manual, and this is a system to start
to allow it a little bit in a larger scale.
where we did some things around Champions Arena, where they bring in, they invite the
best players from the community, where they compete every single week and have a lot of
fun to see who's the best.
We do things with Chicken Dinner Show, which is a show run by a few people on Twitch, where
they also do some competitions and some fun stuff.
And we've had a lot of international support that we're trying to open up as well.
We've already run events in North America and Europe and Japan in terms of our community
grassroots stuff, and we want to open that up even further.
as we support more and more of the globe.
The Invitational is a big part of, it's kind of the heart of our competition right now,
as we did in 2015-2016, we're going to do it again in 2017.
The first year was really just kind of, what can we do here?
And then we were able to open it up last year by expanding a little bit more internationally,
brought some players in from Brazil, we brought players in from Europe, we had a player qualify on site from Korea.
And so that's something that we want to continue in the future and even grow even more.
The fight for the crown, the next big event that we have going on will be our expansion
into team games, team tournaments.
We think with this and a few other features we have rolling out in the next month, we're
going to see our popularity of our five, particularly our five man, but also our two man mode just
grow exponentially.
We think that's really going to take off when we unlock some potential there.
And then the way we interact with our community is really important to us.
I personally run regular Reddit AMAs.
I try to do it every other week.
I try to respond as much as I can on Twitch or on Twitter.
I regularly watch our streamers play the game
because I'm looking to see what they're doing,
what's sort of the new trends coming up in the game,
things I need to be aware of, things that maybe we need to fix,
but also just interact with them to find out what's frustrating you,
what are you liking, how's it going,
what do we need to put some focus on.
And I also, again, personally, I write a, I try to do it every month where I write a
producer letter to the community.
Here's our current focus, here's what we're hearing, here's what we're trying to get fixed
up for you guys.
It's that just regular constant contact.
And it kind of, like I said, it's sort of get ready to kind of get the good and the
bad with it.
So what got us here is gonna continue to guide us
into the future.
As we look to expand the number of events we run,
so expand outside of TwitchCon and start to partner
with places like DreamHack and some other things
to run even more events.
We want to expand even more globally.
We have a tremendous growth curve in Asia right now.
So how can we tap into that?
We're already very, very popular in Europe.
How can we do more in Europe?
And just continue to grow the game.
With the focus being on the competitive aspect of it.
So I should have some time for some questions.
I'll quite possibly give some answers.
Hey, so I have a question regarding the prime time showing in the CW. Seeing how like you have
different game lengths for each match, how do you guys control it so like every big game
that's streamed fits within the time requirements of like, you know, prime time? Yeah, that's a
great question. So, uh, how do we handle a TV broadcast when the, when the game length can be
varying? Um, it's pre-recorded, so...
We will record the game play in the tournament in mid-March, and then we get a month to edit it.
And we can fill in with content as we need to to fill in our broadcast.
Yeah, what's up?
I was wondering, when you look at the community and you hear their feedback,
to find out what they like and what they enjoy about your game,
how did you collect the data? Did you get it through Reddit?
Did you get it specifically through them writing to you?
Did you, the Reddit MMAs?
Yeah, so how do we collect the feedback?
It essentially comes from everywhere.
So it's not just the AMAs,
it's also what people are posting in Reddit every single day.
I try to go on there every night
and just kind of get apprised of what's going on.
I see what people are posting to me, to Twitter.
We talk to our customer service department
to see what people are reporting.
One-on-one individual contact
with some of the players in the community,
as well as we occasionally put out player surveys
to collect more empirical data
to try to guide some decisions that we're making.
But ultimately it's a collection of all that stuff.
And then as we look for trends and different themes of areas
where we want to go put some focus on the game, we try to
collate it all into one big chunk of feedback to go, OK,
this is what we're going to do.
I think that's awesome.
Give it up.
How's it going?
Good.
Congrats on bringing the game to the CW.
That's really exciting.
Can you share more about that courting process or what it is
that attracted them to you and you to them?
Yeah, so how did the CW come about?
Quite honestly, it's a little bit of fortune, a little bit of luck, a little bit of hard work.
We have a pretty close partnership with Rick Fox, who owns Team Echo Fox,
and his team was the first to get involved with H1Z1.
And so as he has had lots of contacts with his other teams around League of Legends and CSGO
and the other teams that he runs,
the opportunity kind of grew a little bit from Echo Fox and CW.
And then we got involved as part of that and it all worked out as a great partnership for
all three of us.
Awesome.
Congrats.
Thank you.
Hi there.
Hi.
So you talked a lot about listening to your community about what their needs and their
wants were, but how deliberate were you in the beginning in shaping that community, if
at all, and making sure that it was accessible and comfortable for all kinds of players?
Well that's a good question. So how do we go about shaping the community? Um, you know,
ultimately I'd say it started very, almost grassroots-ish. Uh, lots of people in the, on the
dev team just reaching out to different, different people in the community and starting to
build relationships with them and starting to talk to them on a regular basis. Um, in a lot of
cases there's a lot of pretty close friendships, uh, that have, that have developed over the
last two years.
I think it's also been, I've been at, I've been on H1Z1 for a little over a year now.
I think this is also a little bit of Daybreak's DNA.
Having formerly been Sony Online Entertainment with EverQuest and some of the other games
they built, being close to their community was always part of what they did.
And so it sort of naturally fit into H1Z1 as we began to develop that game and thought
about where it could go.
So it was really...
I think it was probably a little bit less intentional than maybe the answer you were
originally thinking, but definitely just part of the natural thinking of the studio and
natural culture of the studio.
Thank you.
So you chose to run invitational style events based on kind of popularity of content creators
versus say meritocracy, people that won a lot.
And I'm just curious, in those events, how were you able to leverage kind of the personalities
of the players in an event that they weren't kind of streaming themselves?
So,
I
didn't
really
know
what
I
was
doing.
I
was
just
kind
of
waiting
for
the
next
event.
When
I
started
this
show,
I
was
actually
like
sitting
Yeah, so how did we leverage the personalities of the streamers kind of to our benefit in
the Invitational?
We did it a lot in kind of the lead up to it.
So we did a lot of promotional content, a lot of marketing content that would focus
on some of the streamers.
We did some pretty big things on the streamers that won the year before or the winners from
the year before.
And the way we generate the prize pool is with an in-game crate that has vanity items
for players.
A lot of those, most of the items in that crate are based on the personalities playing
in the tournament.
So like Ninja is one of our big streamers.
There was a Ninja shirt the first year.
There was a Ninja gun skin the second year.
So we kind of partner with them to put them into the crate
and promote them a bit.
Great.
All right, perfect.
Thanks a lot you guys for attending.
They asked me to remind you to please fill out
the evaluations as you leave.
And I hope you enjoy GDC.
Thanks.