Hi everyone, welcome today to the GDC Twitch channel. My name is Brian Francis. I am the invisible voice inside your head
I am here today
Joined as always by some of the wonderful folks who make the games that you get to play in your spare time
But in the lower left hand corner of the screen, I am joined by Albert
She who is the lead designer on the game. We are checking out today, which is super liminal Albert. How are you doing?
Good. Yeah. Hello everyone
Yeah, thanks for inviting me to do this.
Right on.
If you are not familiar with Superliminal, you are probably looking at the screen right
now and wondering just exactly what's happening, why am I picking up this cheese.
I'm picking up this cheese because I'm going to turn this cheese into the ramp just by
turning around.
Superliminal is a puzzle game currently out on the Epic Games Store where it uses your
force perspective to change the size of objects or...
sometimes the
Nature of objects as you can see this cheese has gone from being the size of a hand to the size of a ramp
Albert how long have you all been working on this game? And I guess when did you sort of first come up with the idea for it?
Yeah, so it's been a while. I think right now it kind of tallies around like six years or so, of course
You know, I haven't been working on it
you know full-time the entire time but it began when I was a student and I needed like
a student project to do you know for the end of the year um so I just made this like tiny little demo
uh you know with just with one mechanic and like three puzzles and and you know a couple years
after that we found more people and then more people and finally you know we have a team of six
six or seven people uh when we ship the game so yeah
Right on. Just for a quick housekeeping check in with chat, we have folks like Christopher Lloyd watching. Thank you for joining us, Chris.
We will be taking your questions if you have them for Albert. I guess the first question worth asking is, so how does this perspective mechanic actually work?
And how are we able to build it out to fill out all these puzzles?
Yeah, so the general idea of, you know, when I explain it is...
things are the same size on your screen but in space it actually kind of adapts
to what you know how large it seems to be right and it's all based off the idea of like
oh if you pretend to you know pinch the tower of pisa uh it looks like it looks like it should be
you know a certain size and so in this game we just try to fulfill that you know illusion
In-game however how it actually works to keep you consistent is the object that you're grabbing will be as
Large as possible and as far as possible as it can always be
So it's always you know
It's projected kind of like as far
To the distance so if there's a wall behind it
We'll try to find the point on the wall that you know it will be before it kind of collides with anything
And then just do that mechanic, then people can use that to solve puzzles.
And what was the second part to your question?
Oh, I guess.
How did you start building out puzzles around this mechanic?
Oh, yeah. So that, you know,
the kind of history of this project has been a long one.
So there was a long process, you know, to get there.
But it started out like.
there were different phases right like it wasn't um we just started out and
and just kind of went full throttle and just
uh did a bunch of stuff i think one of the first big kind of
milestones was you know i knew that like this thing called
the sense of wonder night it's like
It's basically similar to the Experimental Gameplay Showcase,
but it's at the Tokyo Game Show.
I knew that was coming up.
I was like, great.
What if I try to flesh out this mechanic that
has two puzzles?
And so from there, I just tried to think of the wackiest ideas
I could use it for and just made one puzzle each.
And that became a series of things
that then slowly grew and grew.
Right on. What was kind of building on that question? What do you think makes a good puzzle?
Like this is such a this is such a mechanic that defies how people think, although it sort of
naturally fits into it also naturally fits into how people think, like perceiving the object to
be the size it is, as opposed to understanding it's not that size. How did you what was your
philosophy for coming up with puzzles? And what do you think makes it interesting to solve puzzles
with this mechanic? Yeah, so
I think a lot of that is kind of like based on people's personal taste.
There's a lot of different types of puzzle games.
The ones that I found the most interesting was kind of like anti-chamber, you know, puzzle games that were more about
seeing something new and trying to think outside the box
as opposed to, you know, something, you know, like a sudoku puzzle, right? Which is
you know all the mechanics, you know all the elements, but it's more about
about mastery, it's more about like a series of steps. So I definitely try to try to focus on
finding ways that would give players, you know, different types of epiphanies in that sense.
And that's why, you know, if some people play this game they might say like, oh hey, you know,
it's not necessarily like scratching like the mastery itch, but there's like a lot of really
cool and interesting stuff in it. So
Yeah, that's an interesting response.
The epiphany angle kind of reminds me of Portal 2,
about how you'd sort of be shooting portals at things
for a while.
Yeah.
And I really like, I should have disclosed,
the video we're watching today,
what we're looking at today is not entirely,
it's not live.
I had to pre-record this footage
so that we could make this stream happen.
But you're gonna get, I like it,
because then we get to watch all the little epiphanies
that me yesterday had, like right there,
where I discovered that I could actually pick up the sign.
Yeah.
Speaking of yeah speaking of portal
I think like one of the most interesting parts of portal one that you know I was like wow this is really cool
Is when you realize momentum works through portals, right?
Yeah, so like that's the kind of thing that we're like, you know, can can we repeat this? Is it even possible to do?
and and that's what we try to shoot for so
Yeah, it's kind of the same thing here, right?
Like instead of momentum, it's size.
It's instead of momentum, it's size.
Like you, like I can take this little sign
and I can make it big and I can make it small.
And that's what lets me solve the puzzle
we're looking at right here.
Moving on and just also give me a quick shout out
to Yessiman, thanks for dropping by.
We'd love to, ooh.
Oh, we briefly lost you there, Albert.
Are you back?
I was getting some strange noises from Skype, that's fine.
Um, uh, uh, Albert, we're gonna see this, we're gonna see this game sort of sca- we're
actually approaching an interesting point in the game, which is where the puzzles stop
being just sort of test chambers like Portal, and you start to do that Portal-esque thing
where you go outside the test chambers and outside the simulated environments and start
solving puzzles in a way that...
sort of feel like you're breaking the game, you're quote unquote breaking the game,
even though you're not, you know, you're just solving the puzzle, the puzzle is just now
outside the narrative space a bit. How do you, did you notice anything while designing these
particular puzzles about how players approach them and if they struggled in any specific way
with when the puzzles began sort of to not be, I guess, presented in the same kind of structure?
Yeah, I think it's definitely,
I think it helps with this game because there's so many weird things we try to do even early on.
So and also I think there's part of kind of the shared language, right?
Like people have played Portal and other weird games like this.
So when usually they see this, they're not like, oh, this is like, I'm totally confused. They're more like, oh,
yeah, I knew something was coming, you know.
But I think in general in games as long as you kind of set up
uh...
expectation you can get away with anything
uh... you know some people say in puzzle games like
a lot of people talk about like oh how difficult should a
puzzle game be but i really think it depends on kind of
what expectations you set right like
in dark souls is a very difficult game but if you know that going in and if
everything about the game tells you that
this is going to be a hard game then you get used to that and and you're not
you don't feel that sense of like unfairness right so i think similarly with any type of puzzle game
as long as you set the expectations correctly and you say things are going to be weird or like oh
you have to you know think outside the box a lot then uh
It won't seem as jarring when you do weird things.
If that makes sense.
It's kind of the difference between an epiphany-driven game like this and a, you mentioned a Sudoku
puzzle game, like if you imagine an app for Sudoku games or like even a match-three puzzler,
those are sort of in very constrained environments where you're trying to use the tools you have
to solve a new kind of a puzzle you already know.
But in this game...
The environments are not constrained. They aren't just like they're set pieces, but they're not
You're sort of not
Always told that there's just one way out I guess right which is what yeah
What makes easy for players like me here to start solving problems based on that yeah, so to camp for a walk
Yeah, one of the things we try to encourage is we want kind of like the space to be interest interesting enough that people
we'll want to look around and be like,
oh, what is this?
What is this?
Is this, you know, part of the puzzle?
Is this something, you know?
Because then that, it makes the space feel a lot more,
more alive as opposed to just like,
I'm going from point A to point B.
I don't need to care about anything between, you know?
Like, you're playing around with things here.
You're looking around at different kinds of things.
That's why we try to add little surprises
or little things that you could discover
if you go out of, you know, off the beaten path.
Mm-hmm. God these moments really
Be right here cuz they're not puzzle moments these minutes. Yes optical illusions. Yeah, how do you how do you even implement this?
How do you like use unity and go? Okay. I need this to look real over here, but I need to look really fake over here
Yeah, so it's it's you know, some of this surprisingly simple and some of the hard parts are like
surprisingly hard the easy part is if you're just trying to do like a
Simple projection that looks like something else you just have a camera
stacked on a projector, right? The camera takes the image and the projector spits out the image.
The hard part is actually where, you know, like depth is involved. Because the projectors in
Unity don't have depth. So we actually have a graphics programmer called Phil who's like
really good at this kind of stuff. He basically hacks some kind of light related system that uses
shadow maps and whatever.
that ends up, you know, taking into account for death and all that.
But that, like, extra step turned out to be much harder than just kind of the original
prototypes we were doing.
Yeah.
How does the resizing work while I'm at it?
I guess, like, what's the, what kind of game logic are you using to make the resizing possible?
Yeah, so, so, again, it's like...
The easy part seemed hard and the hard part seemed easy.
Uh, the easy part is actually like,
how do things look exactly the same?
The rules is surprisingly simple, it's like,
if something is twice as far away, it gets twice as big,
and then vice versa. And that just, for some reason,
you know, with computer and it's like,
you know, it's very, uh,
specific math, it just works.
Uh, so...
And it's weird, it works in like different FOVs, whatever.
I don't know why, but it just does.
The hard part is actually finding
how far the object should go.
Because if you imagine like you have a very weirdly shaped
object, like let's say you have a sponge, right?
And it has tons of holes in it, and maybe you
have a background that's really complicated.
And you want to make sure it doesn't kind of clip
into any of the background.
So we just, it's, we did a lot of trial and error,
and it's just like a very dense.
uh layer of raycast that we're doing to more or less estimate where it should land and even if
it's like a little bit off it's a little bit uh closer than it should be it's it's fine but as
long as long as it doesn't feel uh unfair
Right on.
This is a really interesting puzzle right here,
and I'm going to be stuck here for a while.
But the reason I'm not skipping over this video
is the problem-solving process has sort of illuminated
for what I was trying to do.
What's interesting is going on right now
is I assumed that there was just an angle I needed
to view the cube at, like the last time I did.
But I wasn't.
And I thought, I looked up there, and I can see, OK,
one lamp is styled like the box.
That must be part of it.
And that strange gap over there must be another lamp.
That's all I thought was.
Ha ha ha.
I wasn't paying attention to how I can see it now. It's clear as day. The lamps are clearly
um
On the the raised out parts of the walls. I just did not see that when I was playing
Um, it's gonna take me a minute for the past me to catch up. But in the meantime, I guess um
Uh, oh god. I just walked right by the solution
Um, I guess in the meantime, um
What happened what in play testing i'm sure moments like this happen on every puzzle
Um, what was kind of your approach for and here I am just trying to use the last flute puzzle solution to get through this one
What was your response when players would enter moments like this, where they just miss the thing?
They make an assumption and they miss something, even though they should not be making that assumption.
Yeah, usually I'm actually a little bit happy when players miss the most obvious things.
Because I think that's a good case.
Because a player like you, even if you miss it, eventually you'll look around enough that you'll find it, right?
I think the opposite case actually is that...
when players go in and the room and they immediately figure it out and that is I feel like there's less of a
Moment of epiphany there some I'm actually totally happy that like you're you're you know
Trying to figure this out and you're taking time even though at the moment. I'm sure
You must be to some extent frustrated that you're like why isn't this doing the thing right and a lot of people are like oh
You know, is there a bug here or you know, is that supposed to look like like look like that or?
or something that's not supposed to be blocking and actually blocking it.
Real quick before I keep going, I'm just going to remind some folks in chat, we'd love to
hear your questions for Albert.
If you were making puzzle games or if you're making games like this, we want to know what
you think, what you're working on, what puzzle challenges you're trying to solve in making
them.
Sorry, what were you going to say?
Yeah, I'm sorry to like kind of expand on that answer a bit more.
I think there are certain things that, you know, we're happy with
if the players are kind of exploring as long as it doesn't
it doesn't become frustrating to some extent. Right.
And and those things are typically things that seem like they could work,
but they don't actually work.
So, for example.
if you took that first box and you went to the wall and you tried to get up
and if you did that like 40 times because you're like I just need to be a
little bit larger and it almost works like that feels really frustrating but
I'm you know I'm glad in this playthrough you took took that single
box put it over and you're like I'm not
going to make this jump so I don't even need to think about that
yeah and that's the best case scenario you can just
start crossing things off your list.
Yeah, and it sounds like you learned a lot from your playtesting about
like what are acceptable, like failed behaviors I guess.
Uh, yeah, um, and it's always kind of fun to see what people get stuck with because sometimes
you know you play with a lot and you're like, oh yeah this mechanic totally makes sense but some
people you know don't realize you can grab things from afar, that you can project things from afar
and you can
end up realizing that everybody will come with different expectations, so you need some
kind of like, getting process to make sure by a certain point, everybody understands
the basic mechanics.
Here's an interesting thought I had while trying to solve this puzzle, is there's a
little bit of a clambering mechanic, like I just triggered it there, but it only seems
to, after I solved this puzzle, I realized it only seems to be functioning when the game
is trying to like, you know, like...
To quote another interview I did like when it's trying to make sure I'm solving the right puzzle, right?
Like it's in a jumping puzzle game. You're not trying to time your jumps
The game is just trying to be nice to you when it knows you've done all the work
But and here I was trying to abuse the clamber mechanic to get up inside
How did you time that out and keep like like your your your your helpful mechanics from interfering with your core gameplay?
Yeah, so
The way we do is really simple. We have a ruler and
in our game engine that we can just pull out and it basically says
You know, this is this is how high your first jump is
This is how high your first jump plus like what we call like the mantling mechanic gives you
And this is how high like two jumps give you so we know
That if there's a ledge that requires, you know, at least two jumps it's high enough that you can't
get up with just one object.
And that's mostly like,
you know, from our designer, Logan,
who kind of implemented that stuff and made sure that
we were adhering
to it, you know, pretty carefully.
Because, right, because like,
you could easily, if it wasn't there, you could easily
like get up there.
The other thing about the mantling system
is that
I didn't realize it was, you know,
a thing that was required before, but because
So usually in puzzle games you want really discrete states, right?
And and what that means like you want people to know exactly when you've kind of achieved or failed to state
You don't want to keep it ambiguous. So if they get it, they immediately get it. Um, and if they don't they know they're not there
um, what's difficult about
a game where you can resize
stuff and and then this is something i've also discussed with um,
steve swing because you know
he's working on scale, is that it makes, for example,
jumping on things much more difficult.
So like in Portal, it's very easy to take one block
and know that gives you a certain amount of height, right?
But in this game, because scaling is on,
and I don't know what you call it, it's on a range.
So it means that, you know,
your jumping can also feel,
uncertain at times, like there's jumps without the mantling, there's jumps that you think you can make but you actually can't.
And that just feels bad, right? So that's why in the end we decided that adding this mantling thing
would help kind of make the game feel a lot more discreet, help make it more easily understandable
when you solve the puzzle.
Yeah.
Um, man, there's, I just can't wait.
Now that I'm so happy, I'm so happy we're past that.
Cause there's some real puzzles, uh, that I get to, um, uh, show off to the audience.
Um, that's really cool that you, uh, are going to talk to Steve Swank about this.
I saw scale at Indiecade a while back.
I know he's still working on it.
Um, so we're, we're gonna.
Um, how does it, I guess, how is it, what is it like when, um, this is not design related,
I'm sorry, but what is it like to like get to like have someone out there be working on a similar mechanic as you,
um, and getting to share notes like that?
Yeah, I, I think it's, I think it's really cool and I think it's like, you know, a healthy process and um,
Because a lot of times you're not just dealing with similar kind of design problems like,
oh, you know, you're talking about, you know, how to design puzzles.
Some other times you're also talking about just like,
you know, what kind of art do you want to put in? What kind of story do you want to put in?
How do you make things cohesive? And it does help to have
someone to bounce off ideas with that kind of exists in the same space.
So like, you know, Steve likes to talk about like,
know practices that help you kind of work better you know just in terms of
you know he talks about like deliberate practice and stuff like that and which
is really interesting so.
Man.
Yeah.
This puzzle is also another.
It stumps me for a moment, but then it gets super interesting.
This puzzle was just so interesting.
Especially I'm going to point out there's a red,
there's a window up to the top left that I looked at briefly.
I don't, I later figured out I could make a thing, a platform
to go up there, but I didn't.
And I just proceeded onward.
And I'm still wondering what's up by that red window.
Because I didn't get to explore it when I was doing this puzzle
myself.
diving into my question ball pit. First-person games like this, on the one hand, first-person
games have been super iterated on. We know a lot of things about making first-person games that we
didn't know in 1992, for instance. One of them, which is a big deal for VR, is motion sickness.
And I have to confess, I felt a little bit motion sick playing this game. And I think that had to
do with just, you know, the human brain is very dumb.
And when things change on us that aren't supposed to change,
they start getting weird.
What did you all learn about
designing around motion sickness?
And did that come up early, later, play testing?
Was it a bigger problem than you expected?
I'm just curious about that
just because I got a little bit motion sick.
Yeah, I think this is always an interesting question.
And then I think one of the big ones
that we're actually trying,
that we've implemented
that will probably be out in our next patch is...
an FOV slider, right? Because a lot of times, you know,
most people's motion sickness also depends on kind of how far
they are from the screen and what the FOV is and whether that matches kind of their natural FOV.
Besides that, we've tried different things like, because we've also wondered if it's like, oh,
there's something related to this game, right? Is it because you're grabbing this item and it's hard to identify whether
whether it's
far or close and if that's kind of messing up your brain.
One thing we realized that is that adding like a cursor in the middle
actually does help because it helps keep people focused on kind of one point.
At least that's one thing and then the FLV slider as well.
Yeah besides that you know we're still kind of trying to
figure out what works and what doesn't work. I
you know I used to have pretty bad motion sickness but also just like
because I needed to work on this game so much.
I kind of like lost a lot of that.
So for example, when I play Portal,
I would have to stop after every hour or so,
take a nap and then go back.
But so part of it I think is somehow like repeat exposure.
So I feel like people who haven't played video games
also tend to have that to a larger extent
or somebody who's like washing over your shoulder.
Man, I love the solution to this puzzle.
Because it reminds me of the end of Portal 2.
That's an interesting answer. Let me see.
I'm going to ask about...
What have you learned about teaching players? This is an interesting moment because teaching players what can and can't be grabbed.
Teaching players what can expand and what can't.
You're going to see some interesting variances on this in the next 30 minutes or so.
What did you learn about sort of like
About about that teaching process and about helping players like understand the new things they can do with this scaling power
Yeah, so there's a and that's a good question
that's actually a kind of design problem that we struggle struggle a lot with right because
It's it's in this game in particular that is and this game in a big part is about
Thinking outside the box and giving you those kind of unexpected
surprises
When you see things, so we try, we also can't do, you know, very obvious things, right?
So, for example, if every gravel item had, you know, a shimmer to it, you know, that would call it out,
then that also kind of destroys part of the surprise when you're playing the game.
So, you know, this is the thing we've talked about internally, but in the end, we've tried basically
two basic things that together, they kind of help make the problem a little bit better.
one of them is is through color right. So there's things in the world that pop
out a little bit more, there's things that don't and generally we want people
to be able to be like oh that's the thing that's interesting I should be
able to interact with it and you know theoretically they should right. So if
they see like oh there's a vending machine like we see this a lot it's like
oh there's a vending machine that's really interesting people
walk up to the one like press the button so we do let them do that and we've realized that it doesn't really
need to be
Every item that looks interesting you can grab and resize it just needs to be some like something happens, right?
and if that happens then people are
Satisfied and they know that they've done a thing and kind of reacted to it
And then they can move on as opposed to they try it and and then you know, they're a little bit disappointed
the other thing that we're trying to do is
is kind of, you know, play with size a little bit, right? So, you know, we've talked about like color
and trying to like blend things in, things that don't really look grabbable probably aren't. And
same with size. Smaller things that look like you can grab your hand generally are grabbable. Of
course, there's, you know, a couple places that we try to break this rule so our puzzles don't,
you know, get destroyed. But
We try to kind of abide that by that as well. So it feels kind of a little bit more intuitive
Yeah, this is a really interesting moment where like like
You're just getting all this
Messaging about perception is reality all of a sudden
Then you walk in the office
You're looking for something to grab and you turn around and the thing was right by the door when you grab which is like the
least
Puzzly thing but it's strangely
Uh, like you can't unless you know, it's there. You can't go grab it. Um, yeah
This level. Yeah, this level is fun because this level is kind of like
really fun
Kind of twist on the on the other levels
Because one kind of one thing that we're playing along with it's like the idea that you know in a sense. We are
Are are trolling the player but in like a very tongue-in-cheek way, right?
It's like if you see none of the puzzles in this particular level are super super difficult
But they're more like things are you expect things to look totally normal and then then they're not and that's kind of just the general theme
in this level
Right on. We're coming up on the half hour mark for our conversation.
I sound like a ruck-a-nucker, but I genuinely do.
We love hearing the thoughts of our developer audience.
This is when I started to get screwed up, when I grabbed that die right there.
And I was like, wait a minute.
So we'd love to hear your thoughts, your questions for Albert.
I am going to slightly tweak my line of questioning for the moment.
Albert, so you took a mechanic that started as a student game, and then you and a bunch
of friends got together, you got a team together and you said, okay we want to make this a
shipped commercial product.
A lot of developers get to do that, it's a really cool thing about this industry.
I don't know why, I just wanted to play around with this so I can.
What was it like and what steps did you take did you think made your transition successful?
Because there's a lot of devs who transition like their thesis games in the commercial projects
And it just doesn't work out or they have to go take a day job or something
How did you sort of make it all happen?
Yeah, I mean a big a big factor of that is time and of course
I don't think I don't think I did the process perfectly. I think one is time. That's why the game took no
you know, six years from beginning to end is because there was a lot of iteration.
There was a lot of, you know, there's a point where I got some contract work in
in order to make things work.
Um, it was then, you know, of course, I'm saying like, if we just sat down and we
were totally funded and we had a full team, you know, we could have made this
game a lot faster, but because of those basic kind of like, kind of transition
moments, uh,
Indie games in general, I feel like, end up taking a little bit longer.
The other thing though is just remembering the initial wave of people who were interested
in this game.
And so, I was worried actually, maybe like the first year or year and a half working
on the game that if I didn't get the game out soon that people would just forget about
it.
And then somebody told me that people are interested in something.
Once they will be interested in it and in it again, you know after it comes out or after the full thing
is revealed so I was kind of like
Hoping that you know, I hope that's correct. I don't know but you know, we'll test it out and see
so a lot of it is that confidence that
this mechanic in this game would would be interesting enough that people would kind of
Be attached to it again
if the full thing ever came out, right?
And that confidence, I think, especially when you're making
an indie game, does help a lot, because any amount of certainty
kind of makes things easier, in a sense, right?
Because when you're doing it as an indie or on your own,
there's so many things that you're trying to tackle with,
or there's so many kind of doubts in your mind, right?
Whether you'll ship the game and whether.
you know, the game will even do well and stuff like that.
So the more amount of certainties you can grab,
kind of, I feel like the easier that process is.
So you're saying the certainty you're able to hold on to was like we have a mechanic that works, people are interested in it, and that will work for us tomorrow the same as it works today.
Yes, yeah. Even if I showed somebody who had never seen it before, they'd be like, oh wow, this is really cool.
Which I admit, that was me.
I think I got confused with scale when I first saw it because there's a house puzzle later on that is sort of similar to what's going on with scale.
Yeah, moving on from that, I guess as an indie, how did you manage your sort of quality of
life in that time?
Because, you know, six years is a long time to work on a game.
I hope it wasn't six years of long hours on one game because that would have been very
hard.
Yeah, I don't think I'm the best person to talk about this because I've been horrible
at kind of keeping a good work-life balance.
And to me, because there's different types of people, right?
And some indies can just, you know, roll out of bed in the morning and get to work
and just have a very productive day.
I have personally like, I have more trouble just like having a super productive day.
So that's what I always try to shoot for.
And when you're at, as in, you know, doing this as an indie or by your own,
it's always hard to say like...
I need to wake up at this exact time and I need to do these things and then after this,
then I can take a break and forget about everything.
What I realized at least for me is that having a team of people around me, people at our
co-working space that I need to get up to bed to meet and to talk with.
really actually helps me in my process right. Some people need that, some people
don't. I think having other people kind of on your team, having other people that
you know will be blocked by stuff if you're not there. You know people that
rely on you and people you can rely on is part of the process as well.
Right on. Man, solving this puzzle was very strange for me because I just sort of accidentally walked into it.
Yeah.
Working with your team, I guess like, let's celebrate your coworkers for a minute because there's six, you know, the team is six.
You weren't the only person making this happen. What are some of the interesting work they did that you think is worth calling out?
Yeah, so, okay, so there's, I mean, it's like, where do I start, right?
Yeah.
Yeah, so...
First of all, there's Logan, who's our level designer.
He worked on a game right before this that was called
Four-Sided Fantasy, which is also a Puzzle game.
But he also worked on this DigiPen game
called Perspective, which is this 2D platformer slash 3D
first-person game.
If that sounds interesting, you should go check it out.
It's on Steam right now.
But so he was like the perfect candidate to be, you know, a level designer on this game.
Mm-hmm.
You know, couldn't have picked anyone better.
Other people like, we have two artists on team, Ryan and Steve.
They both come from kind of more of a triploid background, but of course they've done some
indie stuff, but they've had like tons of experience under their belt.
know, World of Warcraft and Mortal Kombat and stuff like that and you know, far more
experienced than I am.
There's Phil who's our graphics programmer, you know, he's working on his own cool little
game that is called Snell Trick.
Sorry, there's two games.
There's Snell Trick which he's released but there's also Cascadia Quest or Cascade Quest
or the name was changed at some point.
Sorry Phil
That
Has a tons of cool stuff in it, too
And he has tons of experience, you know, he worked at Microsoft for a while
But now he's like doing really cool graphics stuff for a game. There's you know, Chris Chris Floyd who you know
Used to work for mega booth
and
You know done tons of cool stuff there. He's also doing some stuff for oculus
And there's Alex who's also a programmer.
He's, you know, I think a theme here is that
because we're in kind of this co-working space,
we can find interesting people that we know
to help us along with the project.
It's like Alex is somebody we brought on,
you know, a little bit late in the game,
but he's kind of provided a lot of that
kind of finishing touches in terms of the programming.
like the UI and the controller and all that stuff that we really didn't have
kind of a lot of time to tackle at the end. So you know it's always nice to have like
that kind of emergency kind of like programming you know muscle cord to pull I guess.
So that's where, wait a minute, of course there's and last of all there's like Matt Christensen who's
doing the music for the game and he's like this Fmod guru who also teaches.
know jazz on the side so you know that's why you know we brought him in because a
lot of the music in this game is based off of like very cool piano jazz you
know mm-hmm and that was the kind of interesting atmosphere we were trying to
build so hopefully I didn't forget anyone
Um, uh, yeah, um, uh, as I limit my past self for not being able to solve this puzzle.
Um, I guess I can move on to my next question, which is, um, uh, it is one
thing always, you know, to ask, uh, talented, smart people to come
up with interesting games.
But it is another thing to then take people who are skilled at one aspect of making a game,
like in your case you made the demo, and then to ask them to also lead a team.
Is there anything that you particularly thought of, or in the last six years,
is there anything notable about leadership and working with other people
that you've learned that you think other devs should know about?
Yeah, I mean the past six years for me at least is just a very long learning process and I'm still trying to
learn and trying to figure, you know, trying to figure things out.
Among them like one of the big ones is
at the beginning, maybe let's do this way, like at the beginning I had a couple of assumptions that
you know, turned out to be more nuanced than I thought. So for example,
Coming in, you know, maybe in my student years, I would have said, you know, what's our goal?
It's just to make a really really good game
So I'm sure you know all of us will be able to make great decisions and saying what's good game
What's not just heading in the right direction, right?
of course that sounds like it if that sounds like a recipe for disaster that is it's because
Everybody
Defines things a little bit differently, right? If you say if you ask somebody what a good game is
they have different ideas and that doesn't necessarily mean anyone's wrong, it just means
there's different ways of seeing it, right?
There's so many different types of games, so there's so many different types of ways
where things can become good, if that makes sense.
And that, a lot of times that requires emphasis on different aspects.
So an artist might say...
hey, to make this part good, we need high fidelity,
or we need some really cool, interesting, one-off art piece
here.
But to the designer, they might say, you know what?
Art's not super important to me.
I just want something that's easily manageable.
I want to build out levels quickly.
So everybody has different expectations.
And if you're leading the team.
The thing you're supposed to do, apparently,
is to try to get everybody on the same page of what's
important and what's not important.
And that's a process in itself.
And for that, it's difficult because then you
need to know or you have to have a good idea.
And a lot of people end up needing to like,
I can't really explain this perfectly, but based on my gut,
we should probably go in this direction.
And a lot of it ends up being that way.
So that's why I think part of this process is so hard.
The other thing though is also realizing that you're working with people who are really
smart so generally they'll make the right decisions but that doesn't also because people
have different tastes that doesn't mean that, you know.
people will make the right decision really quickly. So what do you mean, what can you do to kind of like
help move that process along, right? I used to maybe go like, hey, I would keep it open. I was
like, hey, just, you know, do something cool that you really like for this area. But now I try to go,
well, I'm trying to do this, you know, here's an example of this, can improve on it. That's cool.
But, you know, if not, maybe we should do something, you know, simpler for this area.
You know, something on those lines.
That was really thoughtful, yeah.
I love how really serial killer this section is.
Yeah, that's all Logan.
Nice. Nice job, Logan. I hope you're watching.
I hope you got to hear that compliment, in a way.
Right on. I guess something that can get overlooked, you mentioned having two talented artists on this game.
What kind of art style did you sort of realize you needed in order to make sure that this puzzle game could be both like easy to read and also something you could fill out with like the sense of space and narrative which I don't even think we're gonna have time to talk about the narrative today but like there is kind of a there's kind of an or there's kind of a something like it's not you're not just dealing with puzzles in an abstract space this whole wandering through a dream facility thing is really seems to be well intentioned. Is there anything you figured out as working with your artists that you really needed that in this process?
Yeah, so we took a look at a lot of indie games.
Like, let's say starting with Antechamber,
we're like, we don't want to do something completely,
purely abstract, even though that makes things read
a lot easier, right?
And part of that reason is that when you're
in the actual mundane space, it's just,
things are so much funnier if you make them,
if you make things surreal.
And like, if you move, you know,
make a can of soda really large,
like that's a kind of funny moment that you can't have.
in a purely abstract space.
On the flip side, we also didn't want a very busy-looking space, right?
Because as you mentioned, yeah, that just ends up distracting, and especially in a puzzle
game, that draws you to a lot of false clues that aren't exactly there.
So in the end, we kind of went for this art style that, you know, one of our reference
points was Wes Anderson.
things are kind of clean and clear, but there's still this
interesting surreal tone going on. It's almost like a heightened
reality, right? Like you wouldn't necessarily see these
colors in real life, but they could exist. So there's that, it
kind of lies on that kind of line between surreal, you know,
something that's possible, but also a little bit magical. And,
and, you know, similar with with the mechanic as well. And, and
you know, the items in the game and the puzzles,
that's kind of the line we're trying to hit.
And I think that feels a lot more funnier
and more surreal than the extreme, right?
The other extreme you could go to that we didn't go to
is if we made things very fantastical.
You know, that would be like,
you know, if you're in some kind of fantasy world
and you have this mechanic
because you have like a special, you know.
magical ancient magnifying glass or something, you know, I don't know but
it's just
a lot of it kind of just kind of depends on
what
Kind of game or tone you're trying to shoot for
Yeah, so yeah for the looks, you know
We were referencing Wes Anderson. We were referencing, you know, things like James Turrell
Which used a lot of kind of pastel colors
There's this great kind of subreddit called
Accidental West Anderson. It's where people
take photographs that look like Wes Anderson stuff and then
you know, they just post it and share.
And
basically, we kind of like took a lot of those elements and we try to analyze
how those elements worked, right? And a lot of it is about the color and about the level of detail.
Um, yeah, and I'm, I'm really glad that, you know, it came out in a style that we,
we could work with design, but it's also interesting to look like, look at.
Right on. This is where, unfortunately, a poor old past me started getting a little confused about what was going on.
Lastly, I guess we can, as we head into our last part of our chat, we can talk about the Epic Games Store a little bit.
This is a big new store. Developers are still trying to figure out why they should be shipping on it, if they should be shipping on it exclusively.
Some developers are trying to figure out how their player bases, potential player bases will react.
Can you walk us through your process about shipping Superliminal on the store?
And if there's anything in particular you think other developers need to know?
Yeah, I don't think there was too many things that we ran into.
Of course there's a couple of kind of features that aren't...
there yet and that's both the blessing and the curse, right?
So for example, for a ship, we didn't need to put in achievements.
And that's great because that would have like, you know,
took us another, you know, week or two
to kind of like put everything in a tester thing.
Besides that, I think
I think the the kind of general process is streamlined enough that
nothing in particular was like incredibly different.
And I'm glad that's the case that, you know.
we have different PC platforms that don't feel like you're porting to a completely different
console or anything, right? Like there's no super long process that you need to go through.
It's basically similar to, more or less similar to, how you would put a game on Steam. So, yeah.
What other experiences did you have putting a game on Steam, if you don't mind me asking,
like how you're able to compare it against?
Yeah, so basically, well, before we got on the F-Game store,
we were on Steam for a little while.
And that was a way that we could get
the game kind of tested and playable in an easy format.
So we were actually using Steam for a little bit of time
before we did that.
And each storefront will have their own process, right?
But it's more like.
You need to go in and figure it out, but after you do, generally, it's relatively straightforward.
Mm-hmm. Yeah, this- you know what's not straightforward? This puzzle.
As you can see I'm desperately trying to click my way. This is one of those interesting cases where
where I could tell I was just trying to brute force it, but I didn't know what the elegant what the
elegant solution was
So we will see me in a minute here. I think this was me like I just gone on
I watched a youtuber try to solve it. Oh
And I think he'd come up he'd actually managed to get this this sort of solution to work
He managed to click it up the hill. Although once yes. Yeah, I've seen people do things that were not intended
But are very interesting, like, okay, that's actually something I need to fix.
But some of them, you know, are just cool.
When do you draw that line?
When do you fix something that you didn't intend as a puzzle and when do you just let it be?
Yeah, I think that really comes down to the player experience.
If it's a thing that, you know, leads them to be more frustrated, generally we will try to fix it.
But if it's like a cool thing, for example, a lot of people like taking items and try to...
like find really weird kind of nook and crannies in the game that they weren't supposed to be and
for that we do want to encourage so we will be kind of patching the game and adding more easter
eggs and things you can discover that you know encourage that sort of behavior right because
basically when players do that you know i feel like
They're putting extra effort into the game and it'd be nice if, as a player, it'd be nice if I was rewarded if I did this crazy thing that wasn't supposed to happen.
And I got somewhere that I wasn't supposed to go and if there's a sign over there that says, like,
you know, why did you do that? That's kind of like an acknowledgement that it happened.
We try to kind of encourage that kind of stuff.
God, I'm so close. I'm just watching my past self and I'm just like...
All you need to do is take a step back.
Take a step back.
There you go.
Man, that's the problem with doing
some of these like record exchanges.
You just look back at what you're doing
and you're like, I get it now.
You just think about what it was like when you didn't get it.
Um, well, uh, with that in mind, um, I believe I am running out of questions for the moment.
Um, I guess I will end on one final- oh, there's one.
There you go.
Oh, yeah.
Um, uh, Albert, I guess, is there any particular lesson, um, you know, this, this is Game
Developers Conference, um, we, we do things with the game developers in mind.
Is there anything you'd like other game developers to know before you wrap up today?
Yeah, there's me getting more frustrated.
Haha, um, I mean.
Not that much, but I think if anything I just want to talk about kind of like
you know the pre-production process and I think that
It's actually kind of a very hard thing to figure out. I think I think kind of games in general
aren't super good at that because
Just because of how games are like you kind of need to make something in order to figure it out
if it works, but I feel like if you can grab on something early on like, you know
even in a very broken state, you know, of this game, there was something there that we could point to and say,
you know, that's something people will be interested in even,
I don't know, like four or five years later when the game is complete.
Having that and having something like that and having the confidence kind of does help you along the way.
Um,
and yeah, and just like try to
try different things during pre-production. It's not necessarily just
keep on building the game, sometimes it's taking a step back.
Sometimes it's building a different kind of prototype, or in a different medium,
you know, going to paper or something else where we're talking to people,
in order to kind of get to where you need to be, in order to really start production.
So, yeah, I'm just saying that because we kind of went between pre-production and production a couple of times
before realizing where that line was at.
I'm sure.
No. A lot of people have been in similar situations.
Here we go, Natal420 has jumped in with a question.
And I think we've sort of covered this, but I can ask it
and we can sort of revisit the topic for a moment.
Was this game designed to have only one answer per puzzle,
or did you ever want people to solve the puzzle
through multiple means?
They comment that they were thinking about Zelda shrines
in Breath of the Wild.
They're not called Zelda shrines,
they're just called shrines.
They're shrines in Legend of Zelda Breath of the Wild.
and how they've seen multiple solutions to each shrine.
I'm going to layer on that question by pointing out that sometimes in those shrines
the multiple solutions are often people like gaming the wild physics mechanics of that game.
And this game is different. It doesn't have wild physics mechanics.
But yeah, I guess what was your...
I've noticed that there seems to be only one solution per puzzle.
But what was your thought process behind making that decision?
Yeah, we were also at some point trying to figure that out, right?
Do we want this to be more of, you know, a straight up puzzle game?
Or do we want it to have, you know, more freedom and more sense of creativity
and more toy like?
And then we said, no, no creativity for you.
But I think the real answer is it depends on kind of.
what you really care about and for our game we really cared about giving people
kind of moments of epiphany and that's harder to do if you have multiple solutions right
because what you end up doing is maybe you you know have a different epiphany and you skip this
moment you skip this thing that we're trying to tell you and in the next puzzle you get stuck right
so uh for us at least we've kind of chosen the one solution per puzzle
away, but if people do, you know, similar to the Zelda shrines, if people do find like a crazy solution,
um that they're just ahead of the curve, we don't, we try not to penalize them for that, so.
This is one of my favorite puzzles actually, this house. Awesome, yeah thanks. I love going,
I love reshaping the sizes of things and going inside them, like taking the small thing and
making it big, taking the small door and making it big. Yeah. It's very Alice in Wonderland.
Exactly. Yeah, normally I would not use that as a compliment, but here it's a compliment.
Um with that I'm going to start wrapping things up. Thank you everyone for watching the GDC twitch channel today
If you uh didn't catch the whole stream, don't worry. It's going to be archived
Um, see look at this look at this tiny door. I have to figure out how to get into um, uh, um
uh this um
Uh, this has been our chat with albert. She of the pillow castle games, uh for work, uh, the game super liminal
You can check it out on the Epic Games Store if you want to play it for yourself.
For our part, GDC is coming up in March from the 16th to the 20th to be precise.
You might have noticed that if you looked at the screen for two seconds.
We would like to invite you to join us at GDC in part because, you know, we...
We cater to game developers, we cater to people, students, professionals, indie developers.
We like having you all at the show because it's a lot of knowledge sharing, it's a lot
of networking, and it's a lot of stuff, it's a lot of places, it's a place where you can
have a lot of conversations like this conversation where you just try to learn from the people
making great work in your field.
If that clumsy sales pitch did anything for you, you can scroll down and click the button
to get more information about registration.
And if you are otherwise just interested in the way games get made, we would invite you
to follow the GDC Twitch channel so that you can keep up with the other developers we're
going to be talking to this month and next year.
This month, I can promise you, if you stick around, you're going to be hearing from the
developers behind the new MechWarrior game, which is out.
out later this month. We're also going to be talking to the folks behind Age of Empires 2 Remastered
Definitive Edition, not remastered, Definitive Edition.
And if you want to hear more about from those folks, just follow us and you'll get a notification when we go live.
Albert, thank you so much. It's been a lot of fun. Superliminals, cool game. I hope you have a lovely day.
Thanks so much for having me.
Awesome. And with that, I will take us home. Bye, everyone.
Bye.