Thank you.
All right.
First up, I have some housekeeping things.
Silence your cell phones.
And don't forget your evaluations that are probably emailed to you after you got buzzed
in.
So, yes, I am Matt Bain, as she said.
I am an animator at Blizzard Entertainment on Overwatch.
So, last year, Dave Gibson, who's over there.
He gave a kick-ass talk about how we find and animate the core of a character from start to finish.
I don't know if that's still on.
And it was awesome. It was a little fuller talk. You've probably seen it if you were here last year or it was released onto YouTube.
So I'm sure many of you have seen it. If not, I highly recommend it.
Later this week on Thursday, Jesse Davis, who's also sheepishly hiding over there.
is doing a talk on the pipeline of animation on Overwatch.
So that'll dig in a little more to the technical process
in-engine, all sorts of great stuff.
So not to step on their toes, this talk
is specifically about first-person animation.
So it's basically how we go from that to that.
Yeah, hi, D.Va.
So first-person animation.
My core thesis today is to talk about how we maintain the character, because Overwatch
is about the heroes.
How do we maintain that character as we go from this fun character design into hands
and a gun and a camera?
There is some trepidation when people jump into first-person animation because either
they're bored by it, because they don't really want to do it, or they don't really get it.
But it's...
I don't know, it's not that big of a deal.
First-person animation is actually a really great place
to start if you're a gameplay animator,
because it has everything a gameplay animator does.
It's very player-facing.
I mean, it's right there in your face.
And they're looking past your animation at the target,
so don't fret.
The animation, it's there, it's great.
As long as you're doing it well,
they're not gonna stare too closely at it.
But you also have the benefit of a locked off camera.
And no other gameplay animators can really
say they have the benefit of a locked off camera.
So let's get going.
Gameplay first.
If you ever saw a talk by a Blizzard animator or Blizzard
developer on anything, I bet you they
have a slide that says gameplay first.
This is enshrined in our card around our Orc.
So there is a lot happening.
There's a lot happening here.
It's flashy and fast and hella fun.
But the first person animator does not
want to add to any visual noise of the way of the player.
So they wanted to make your animation needs
to be responsive.
And you don't want to take too much control away
from the player.
And you have to provide visceral feedback as well as gameplay feedback to ground them in the world that you've created.
And that world that we've made is this big, bright, colorful world.
As I said earlier, Overwatch is about the heroes.
When I first started on the team in 2014 and they showed me this stuff,
they didn't have this many heroes when I started.
And I looked at everything. I looked at...
What I looked at actually was this.
They showed me these that they had already.
And I looked at it and I was like, that's amazing.
That's an animator's dream to do all that sort of wacky stuff.
And I thought, why are you making a first-person game?
This could be a wonderful third-person game.
But they're making a multiplayer shooter, which is great
because that's what I love to play.
So I took this.
from Dave Gibson who showed a very similar,
he actually showed all these slides last year
for good reason, they fit perfectly into his talk.
I just wanted to tell you that all of that,
the overlapping action, overshoots, the squash and stretch,
the snappy texture timing, all building up to appeal,
all of that translates into what we do in first person.
And this slide is also exactly what Dave showed last year.
And because
I'm sorry, I'm moving too much for this thing.
Michael Biancolana kicked ass on this animation.
I mean, look at it.
So it slowed down here at the end,
but it has everything there.
It has the snappiness.
It has some nice flow to it as well.
Shoot all that secondary action of all the little fiddly bits
moving.
And I just love this animation so much.
which kind of bugs me because there was a so you're the guy
that does first person overwatch you know my favorite
first-person animation is
zanyata
like oak
yeah me too actually
but that was michael bianca on a
Let's move on into the actual tech stuff.
So my talk is actually a little bit free flowing.
Once I get to a certain point,
I'm just gonna start showing you examples
and talking about fun stuff.
But first I just wanna show you what we're working with.
A lot of it's gonna seem kind of redundant
to people who've worked on shooters before.
But I think a lot of people might still get
some fun joy out of seeing it.
These are the rigs that we're working with.
It's a pared down version of third-person rigs.
You can actually see here that we just
take the third-person rig and cull out everything
that you're not going to see.
And the reason McCree still has his hat
is because he brings his hat down for his high noonl.
Anything the animator wants to add
to the first person from the third-person rig,
we can ask the riggers to leave that in.
If you want to learn more about how the rigs are built,
highly recommend you go to Jesse's talk.
on Thursday, but you can notice that he still has his root controller.
All the camera animation, primarily we animate from the root, even in first person.
They do have another camera bone that we add accents with, just a little extra motion.
Nothing too heavy and extreme, that just sort of gives you a little extra feeling to ground you into the world.
And I'll talk more about camera stuff later.
I just wanted to show you this example too.
He has a leg.
He's the only hero that has a leg in first person at the
moment, because Michael, when he animated Zenyatta, gave him
a floating, he sort of does this Indian style sit and
floats in the air.
And he said, well, if he's floating, his legs are free.
Why doesn't he just kick you in the face?
So he asks, got the leg in there, and now he
kicks you in the face.
This is partly how we attach weapons.
This is the classic way.
Everybody who's ever attached a weapon in a game
probably has done it at first.
There's an attachment bone that is at the very bottom
of the arm chain.
I added the outliner from Maya just to show you
how deep it is.
That attachment bone is under the hand.
which is great that means when you attach a weapon is going to follow that
arm where it goes without having to I K you can I K the left hand to that bone
too so that it all moves together without too much decent issues.
But there are cons to it as well.
This is 76 is prototype reload that I did.
So 76 if you're not familiar,
soldier 76 is a Mr America captain America almost let's try.
I shouldn't say that he's.
He's red, white and blue, gung ho, leader of the overwatch at
one point. So I thought, oh, top loading gun, top loading
reloads are tricky for me because you can get your hand in
the way of the camera so easy trying to reload that with the
left hand. I know, what's the classic American infantryman's
weapon? And it's that World War II weapon, the M1 Garand, which
I realized I probably should put a photo of one of those up there
so you know what I'm talking about.
If you've ever seen a World War II movie, that classic gun that you're firing off and
you get that ping sound and everything kicks out, maybe some of you know, some of you would
go, ooh, guns, gross.
But that's okay.
So I thought, oh, I'll just slap a new magazine in with the right hand.
But what happens...
It's parented to that bone that's
at the bottom of this chain.
So this prototype animation in Maya looks fine.
It's a little choppy because it's prototype.
But when you get it into Engine, even
if you animated it at 60 frames per second
and exported at 60 frames per second, in Engine,
you're still going to get subframe interpolation.
It's going to be variable frames per second.
So what's happening is between frames, that weapon bone
that you're animating away from is trying to go back.
to the hand that it is under in the chain.
So you end up with this wacky, wacky weirdness.
So one solution for that is to just do the reload
with the left hand.
Oh, hold on, I gotta find the,
the mouse turned off, Tim.
I got it, I got it.
reload it with the left hand. So this reload is ridiculous. I
actually like it, though, because look at soldier 76. He's
ridiculous. But it's also straightforward and basic, but
ridiculous. So I like it. He just slaps it in. I mean, that's
goofy. But he's a little goofy. It's fine. And it's straight and
to the point. And he's straight and to the point.
Later, of course, we realized we want to do more with how we
handle weapons.
So why not add a weapon attachment bone that's under
the root so that we don't have these issues of moving your
hands away from the attachment point and having the weapon
trying to follow along.
So this is Ana's rig.
She has the special weapon attachment bond with 2 hand
control bones that she can hold to.
And you can see, I put the outliner on there just so you
can see it's under the root.
If you can see it with all that text, this wall of text
that's on there.
And she's using parent spaces, which I will
talk about in a second.
I just wanted to show you her reload first.
I told you, free flowing and organic.
So yeah, she's got a sniper rifle with the bolt on the right,
so she's reloading with her left,
but pulling that bolt with the right hand,
so we can do more with taking her hand away.
There was, at one point, an attempt to fire
her sleep dart pistol with the right hand.
I think for just aesthetic reasons,
we ended up going back to the left hand.
So parent spaces, many, everybody,
okay, I shouldn't say everybody, maybe not everybody.
Certainly not Andrew.
Many of you probably have parent spaces in your rigs now.
It saves the animators a lot of time.
You don't have to set up constraints
that you know you're gonna need
every time you set up a scene with a weapon in it.
That's another thing that Jesse's gonna talk more about
on Thursday.
I just wanted to steal his slide real quick.
It's not his exact slide he's gonna use.
But we have these parent spaces built into the rig
so that what's happening here is her right hand IK
is following one of the weapon bones
that is parented to the weapon attachment.
So that right hand, the IK of that right hand
is following that weapon bone.
So when we can manipulate the weapon
to actually animate the weapon to do what we want to do
with her right hand, we'll follow it.
And then if she has to pull her right hand away,
we just use this tool here to switch her bone
to the IK bone back to default.
without having to turn on and off a constraint
and remember where our constraints were and stuff.
And then you can just move it how you need.
Oh, this next slide might scare some people.
Myolayers.
We all of our assets for a first person character are in one
myopile, which is fairly traditional.
But the traditional way to do it is to have everything on
the timeline at different points in the timeline.
If you've worked on a shooter, you've probably done it that
way. The way we're doing it is utilizing myolators, which in
the past might have been pretty heavy.
But it works great.
So now we can see every asset that we are going to have.
all there and labeled, so we can just put our base pose
on that base layer, and then each grouping of your assets,
your fire, your run, your jumps, and all that
are underneath that base pose,
so if you change that base pose,
it's gonna cascade down through those layers.
And you can still use override layers as well,
you can just bring that pose onto it,
just click of a button.
I like the old way very much of just doing it on,
The timeline is great, because it doesn't bog your computer down as much.
And you can still use MyLayers to add things on top.
So, I'm not saying this way is better or worse.
There's a lot of pros to this.
There's a lot of pros to the other way, too.
So, whatever works for you.
I just know that when I say,
hey, look at all these MyLayers,
some people go, whoo, all right.
Especially if you have the graph editor over.
Meh.
Yeah.
And this is just a way of using the MyLayers.
So, there's one run.
for a junk rat.
And then just a layer under there that has his detonator
pose, and then underneath that, we can have other layers that
have his detonator animation that's separate, but playing
on top of, so in this case, the run.
In some cases, the melee.
So he punches, but if he has the detonator, there's just a
layer that does that, so he can open his hand up and have
the detonator in it.
All right.
So let's talk about the process of animating the first person.
So the first thing we're going to do is find that golden pose.
And that is where everybody dogpiles onto it.
And this is the part where you're trying to figure out,
you're working with, so the way Overwatch works.
generally is that there's a third-person animator working
on the third person of the character, a first-person
animator working on the first person.
We've tried it in the way where one animator will own
the entire character, but scheduling needs means that's
not possible anymore.
So the third person and the first-person animator will
communicate with each other, with the character designer,
with the weapon modeler, and the character modeler.
figure out who this character is, what kind of weapon they're holding, and how it should
fit on screen. With all the ideas of making a great pose, thinking about your negative
space, thinking about leading your eye for the gun aim towards the center of reticle.
And of course the FOV, which I want to talk about a little bit later. There's another
slide I stole from Jesse.
That is Widowmaker's early prototype design for a rifle.
Oh hey, go ahead, you made it.
You can see that it wasn't really modeled
with first person in mind.
That you really just lose the sense of the gun.
And so going back and forth with.
the weapon modeler and finding out the correct camera FOV for this,
we were able to arrive at something that is a little more appealing on the screen.
It actually reads as a rifle.
The one on the left doesn't exactly read as a rifle.
So, finding the FOV means just finding the FOV for the player view model.
Because we have the benefit in Overwatch, I know a lot of modern games do this now,
but we separate our world FOV.
the field of view of the world from the player view model
so that we can scale and allow a slider for players to scale,
the FOV, without futzing with our pose,
which used to drive me nuts.
If you've worked on a shooter before,
you know that you're wonderfully crafted posing
can get stretched to hell when the player goes, nah,
I'm playing at 120.
which is great for them, that's fine, but my animation...
Seriously though...
So I love this. I love that...
I don't have to worry about where the players FOV needs are.
Because there's a lot that goes into that.
Whether, because it's a cross-platform game,
they could be playing on their couch,
they could be playing with their face buried in a monitor,
they could get headaches at lower FOVs,
they might just want a lower FOV
so they can get zoomed up on an enemy,
or a wider one so they have better peripheral awareness.
I don't care, I got my great pose
and it's gonna stay where it's at.
I find that FOV in the camera in Maya,
and then I can type that into our editor to match it.
And I get what I want, which is beautiful.
And it's just a handful of the poses that we have.
Junkrat, Zenyatta, Symmetra, Zarya, Winston, Soldier 76,
Reinhardt, Mercy, and McCree.
Just an example of some other poses in game.
Well, the time on that thing is still going.
As I said earlier, you can cheat the hell out of your poses.
You have a fixed camera.
Cheat the hell out of it.
Mercy is the first hero I ever touched on Overwatch.
And I remember trying to get a good staff grip for her,
and I couldn't get it.
And my lead, Ryan and Jesse.
Like, just fucking translate the fingers into place.
I was like, what?
Yeah, just translate the bones into place.
I didn't have experience with that before,
so I was like, you could just crank that thing out of there.
Yeah, so her fingers are all jacked up,
but you don't see that.
I mean, hopefully you don't see that.
You'll never see that side of the staff in motion.
If she's doing her quick melee like this,
she's gonna change her grip.
She's doing anything, she's gonna change her grip.
You'll never see that, hopefully.
So after you find your golden pose,
the quickest way to get a good sense of physicality on it
is to add additive overlays.
Most games do this where they add an aim pose
suite and a roll animation, or one suite that has both the roll
and the aim in it.
This is another slide I stole from Jesse.
Thank you.
This is actually on his demo reel.
So you can see that it's a spring-based.
pose the set of poses with spring value on it that we can tweak
per hero to get the different feelings.
Because this is what I want you to think about,
that they're not just there to do this and to do this.
They have purpose.
And they will give you character.
Now, this slide might hypnotize you when I play it
or make you sick.
Let's talk about this.
So these are the spring-based aims and the roles.
Each hero is different, and we can author it differently
per needs.
McCree, who is in the top left, he's a cowboy with his
revolver.
He's cocky.
He's sure of himself.
He's kind of been around the block.
And has a smaller weapon, so he leads his
target, and it's tight.
Next to him is Zenyatta in the top, in the middle.
He's a monk who's floating.
I told you about him.
So we can make his have this flow, but he's a robot, so it flows and snaps.
Flows and snaps.
So, don't just think about those basic spring aims as just something to give you the lag and lean,
but it actually gives you character.
Roadhog in the middle down there, he's... he don't give a fuck.
He's got a big ol' shotgun, and he's gonna throw his hook at you and drag you into him.
So he's super loose, and it's a shotgun.
Bastion's also a robot on the bottom left, and he's chunky.
He's not the nice, harmonious robot like Zenyatta.
He's a chunky old war bot.
Here's another one that might make you sick.
So we're leveraging the same sort of system to give us
poses for Lucio when you're wall riding.
I just wanted to show it because it's kind of neat.
I don't really have much else to add to that.
I was gonna let this play.
So on top of the additive lag and means that we have for aiming we have run
lanes too.
So we can add a little tilt to their runs when they're running side side or
forward and back.
But I just wanted to show you the character
that you get from it.
So Winston,
I used Winston as an example cause Gwen brought it up in a podcast.
Winston is actually.
three-legged in a way because he's a gorilla. He uses all three limbs to run. But in first
person, we didn't have to worry about the foot contact of that arm that's coming in.
That arm was a pain in the butt to get right. I still don't know if it's right, but there's
always that balance between what's going to give you good physical feeling in the camera
and what's going to make a player sick.
So there was a lot of back and forth
between how to get the weight and chunkiness of a gorilla
in first person without driving a player nuts,
and then reminding them that they are a gorilla
and they have this arm, but you aren't
going to see it contacting the ground,
because you're looking at targets.
So we just wanted to give the hints of it
without flashing in your peripheral vision.
I don't know if it's 100% successful, but I like it.
I think it turned out okay.
I should've added directional runs for him too,
because he's got this way and this way.
And it's got aims on that as well,
on top of that another overlay animation
that if you look up, the arm leaves the screen,
and if you look down, you get more of it.
But we never have to worry about
actually contacting the ground.
This is the part where I just start showing you cool shit.
Cool examples.
Oh, this is in Maya.
So he's like a mile from the ground.
And you can see where I'm animating from the root
to get the camera motion.
And then I'm adding a little bit on the camera,
a little bit of extra translation
that gives this feeling without rotating too far in the X.
You get that seasickness in the yaw, or the roll.
I'm sorry, the roll.
This is Bastion, Mr. Chunky Robot.
Genji, the light-footed ninja guy.
Junkrat.
I love Junkrat, because he's crazy.
I wanted to say something extra about Junkrat's run, just
because the previous slide where I talked about collaboration.
I only have five minutes left?
Holy shit.
We're going to go.
OK.
So Kyle Rauh, who did his weapon, we went back and forth
like, oh, you can add this bit and that bit, just to get this
nice, chunky, kit-bashed feel out of his gun, because he is a
junker who just made his weapon out of
crazy bits and pieces.
And so it's all about that conversation between him and
concept and
story of like who this character is and you can bring that into the first person
animation.
All those little bits and pieces are hand animated to give that feeling of
uh, when I first showed this to my wife, she was like,
why the hell is he galloping?
And my first iteration of that run in first person
didn't have that gallop to it.
But then I saw Kyungho's third person animation,
and he, oh yeah, he has a peg leg.
And so we brought that in at first.
I think that gives it a lot of nice motion.
Since we have five minutes,
I want to get to some other things.
Sorry, I actually just started going off on tangents
and I ran out of time.
This is McCree's firing.
It might be dropping some frames in PowerPoint,
but you can see how much we're stretching the gun.
So what I'm doing is that first frame that you're showing,
I usually don't export that frame.
That's the idle frame.
The very first frame is super stretched out in space.
forward with the gun barrel scaled up,
and then snap back on the very next frame
just to get that feeling.
I hope you can feel it when he fires,
but for me it's push it forward,
snap it back straight back,
and then it rocks up.
So it's kind of more like this.
You see a lot of.
I don't want to call anything out, but you see some animation that's just bang,
like this is just kind of awkward.
So we're snapping it really stretching and snapping it back just to give you
that big feeling of firing. Uh, here's iron clouds,
which I wanted to show you cause I just love how much it stretches and all the
squishy bits that was animated by Jesse.
Um, this is a, how we handle.
automatic firing for single firing we can do that big single fire and then a
little ones that we can ramp into with a accumulate pose.
That's just a single pose that it sort of ramps into as you fire and then you
let it go and it plays an added about trail
reloads. Another slide I took from Jesse.
There's a lot that you're saying with reloads.
communicating to the player that they can't fire anymore. So it's okay. Don't cover the
reticle because they still want to see the threat in the way. But move the gun up. You can
actually rotate the camera in Y and move it away from the reticle just to communicate to the
player that you're not able to fire anymore. It's pretty clear. I would avoid Frankenstein
hands, which is just sort of...
I'm like panicking now because I'm running out of time.
Actually, let's just skip it.
These are just examples of reloads that I like.
Each one, a different character.
Reapers is ridiculous.
Michael Biancolana did both Roadhog and Zenyatta.
I love those so much.
The top left one, Diva, is out of New York.
She's super cocky.
This super cocky gamer girl.
So she's like, whatever.
So we brought that into the first person, too.
And I just think it works so nice.
Zenyatta, Mr. Floaty Monk.
I hope I'm giving you something interesting.
He's just goofy. He's just a big, junky, stinky road hog. And
he's just throwing some random crap in his shotgun. And his
little buddy, his little buddy, the other junker, everything is
just, who cares, get in there.
So as the first person in the third person animate or animator are working
together, I did actually led the charge on this where it's like I did the
animation and then I was like, Oh yeah,
I can see how I could do that in third person.
May who's super nice and super happy to be there and she's,
she'll fuck you up though.
So she's like, yeah.
Oops.
Reaper, just don't give a shit.
I'm sorry I ran out of time, you folks.
Keep losing your cursor.
I blame Tim.
Look how much we're stretching out that arm and that leg on the contact frame.
That's just insanity.
It just gives you that nice snap.
So everything that I showed you earlier about the,
that showed the third person animation
with all the snappiness,
it's right there in the first person.
It's all about giving you the feeling.
The extra super stretch.
happens on the fourth frame, you snap, we brought the weapon off
screen in the first frame and started bringing the hand on and
then really stretch it out and snap back. It's similar to the
fire. Really stretch, snap and then a little hold. It's like
and I hope it reads. It reads.
Another camera thing you can run into is translating Z gives you great sense of
impact. That's forward and backwards in Maya. It gives you a great sense of
impact to have that in your quick melee. Just be aware of where your player
collision is and how far out of that you can go before you're in the wall. In the
first alpha, McCree was punching through walls. Not punching through them, his
face was going through them.
and that was because his camera was translating too far forward
in Z and snapping. I'm all out of time. Holy shh. Okay. Look
at that. That's awesome. That was done by Jesse. Look at all
the cheating that's going on. Look at that. Yeah. Because you
don't care what's happening off camera. You just care what's
happening over on the left there. Same with Genji, which
is going to play next. Yeah.
Look how cool that is.
Isn't that freaking rad?
Look how far he's stretching that arm out.
That's Jesse. Jesse kicks ass.
I know. He already told me to stop.
And I'm like, here, take out some cool shit.
Okay, that one's not going to play.
Oh, shh.
Okay, PowerPoint's telling me to stop now.
It just crashed.
So, uh...
Thank you.
Hold up.
I just wanted to put this up there while I walked away.
Thank you.
I hope I gave you some information.
I practiced this like 100 times
and never got fully through it,
so now I realize why because it was too fucking long.
You rocked it.
I hope it was entertaining.