Hello and welcome to Simple and Powerful Animation Compression.
I am Nicolas Fréchette, a programming consultant.
And the work I'll be presenting today
was done for Eidos Montreal earlier last year.
I am to remind you to please turn off noise-making devices.
And at the end, if everything goes well,
we should have time for questions.
And I'll be waiting as well at the wrap-up room on 3022
on this floor.
Before we begin, I'd like to thank two other contributors
who helped me along with the work
I'll be presenting here today.
First, Frederic Zimmer, with whom I bounced every idea
here as well as many, many more
that didn't make it into the presentation.
And both him and Luke Mamakos contributed immensely
with their past experiences working
with animation compression and the results and lessons
they learned doing so.
And of course, none of this would have been possible
without Eidos Montreal.
We'll first begin with a bit of context,
why we needed to revisit character animation
compression in 2016.
and what essentially prompt all of this.
We'll then move on and take a quick look
at the classic solutions in the industry
to this well-known problem
and what we looked at to inspire from.
And of course, we'll finish with our own special blend,
a new twist on an old technique
and the surprising results that we got out of it.
So last year, I was contracted by a game team
working with a game engine from Rise of the Tomb Raider,
which was released in 2015 on the Xbox One.
And of course, they already had
character animation compression,
and in fact, they dated as far back as 1996, two decades.
So they've been thoroughly battle-tested,
they've been used in dozens of AAA titles,
and the primary compression algorithm
is based on linear key reduction.
And they also had a fallback, less aggressive algorithm
based on simple quantization.
And we'll cover both of these flavors in a bit later.
Now, the primary compression algorithm
offered a pretty good size.
And it hadn't been an issue so far in the past or even today.
But as we were ramping up the number of characters
on and off the screen that were animating,
we started to notice that decompression
was a little bit slower than we would have liked.
And we were starting to get more and more issues with accuracy.
Unfortunately, the legacy algorithm
did not expose parameters that were very intuitive to tweak.
And animators failing to get the accuracy that they needed
on a clip-per-clip basis would revert
to the less aggressive algorithm.
And this was slowly pushing the size and the memory footprint
higher and higher as time went on.
And eventually, this culminated in a big problem for cinematics.
Cinematics of course need very high accuracy.
They're iconic moments in our game.
There's a lot of time and energy and money that goes into making them as nice as we can
possibly make them.
They're also somewhat exotic.
You can have all kinds of things and characters that get animated from animals to props to
destruction.
And the camera can get very close to them.
So it's very important to get very high accuracy.
And of course, size and the memory footprint still matter
for cinematics.
You walk into a room, and if you need to load from the
disk a very large cinematic, then that takes a lot of time.
And of course, you have to live with a runtime memory
footprint as well.
But the problem grew bigger than that.
And we reached a point.
where about 40% of our clips use the less aggressive algorithm.
And that's a significant amount.
And the reason we got here is because the quality is getting
higher and higher as we collectively
push the quality of our games higher.
And so time is really the enemy.
And this number will only ever go up with time.
So it prompted us to revisit the animation compression.
But unfortunately, the legacy code was not quite ideal to work with.
By virtue of being very old, it aged somewhat poorly, like a lot of code tends to do.
And sadly, the data format was not streaming-friendly, so we couldn't use it as a technique to fix
our issues with cinematics.
We needed a new approach.
And, last but not least, nobody really wanted to
get near it. The code was in a state
where it wasn't particularly, and a number of people
had tried in the past to improve on it
and failed to significantly do so.
So faced with these problems, we designed a number
of goals to come up with a new solution.
First and foremost, we wanted to tackle cinematics first.
They're a more isolated problem.
If we ever end up breaking anything,
it only affects a small part of the game,
and we don't grind the whole production floor to a halt.
And it's also a little bit easier,
because we can use streaming if we need to.
And they're also very good candidates,
because they have the highest accuracy requirement.
We wanted to keep it as simple as possible.
The time budget for this was only 20 days,
which is very short.
In those 20 days, I had to, of course, take a look
at the old legacy code, figure out
if there is anything to be done with it,
implement whatever new solution that we can come up with.
And of course, if we need to do streaming,
it needs to fit in that time frame as well.
If we're going to build this for the future,
we want the decompression to be as fast as possible.
We want it to scale to large numbers of bones,
which are always increasing with cinematics.
And the recent and not so recent hardware trends
is for more memory and more cores,
but each individual core is not dramatically
becoming faster and faster.
And essentially this means that it's becoming more
and more common to have a slightly larger memory
footprint if it means that we can work a
bit faster.
Essentially memory is becoming cheaper than cycles.
Of course, we want very high accuracy, as I've
mentioned.
It's an important problem for us, and we don't
want to go back to yesteryear where we had
foot sliding and these sort of vibrating artifacts.
We also had a small set of secondary goals.
Obviously, we wanted to keep the size as small as
possible, but it wasn't the primary issue for us.
Primarily because we were hoping to fix that through
streaming if we had to.
But we don't want to leave any stones unturned, of course.
Ideally, we want nothing or very little to tweak for our animators. I think we could
all agree that animators' time is much better spent creating content, polishing content,
than it is spent tweaking compression settings in the hope that the algorithm is not going
to butcher their work.
And last but not least, it would be really nice
if we could supersede that decades old code
and failing to do so, at least replace the weaker
algorithm used by 40% of our clip.
So armed with these goals, we took a look
at the existing solutions in the industry
that we could inspire from.
And they roughly fall into four families or categories.
signal processing, curve fitting, linear key reduction,
and simple key quantization.
So we'll talk a little bit about those.
First up, we have signal processing.
In this category, probably the most common or famous
is based on wavelets.
But you also have things like principal component analysis
and various database approaches.
Now, unfortunately, they're way too complex.
And even a cursory overview in the presentation here today
would be far too long.
So I will redirect you to my blog if you're
curious about this.
There's a link on the last slide.
And I go in depth as much as I could on the topic.
We chose not to inspire from this technique, primarily
because it was far too complex for our needs.
Next, we looked at curve fitting.
Curves are a very elegant solution for animation data.
It's what is typically used in Maya, Max, and Motion Builder
to represent animation data to animators.
And the reason is very obvious if you look at the graph
here on the right.
The green curve.
fits on about 60 keyframes or so.
But I only need 10 control points
to represent the whole curve.
So it's very dense data-wise.
It's very compact.
And it can very accurately represent the animation data.
So on the upside, it's a very sensible choice.
It makes sense.
It's common because it's apt.
And it's also very compact.
But the downsides are that for us, the original curves from Maya were not accessible through
our existing pipeline.
Essentially this would have meant that we would have had to recalculate the curves from
our already discretized data.
Decompression is also somewhat slow with this technique.
primarily because you, for every track, rotation, and translation, you need to search which
control points you need to interpolate from at a particular point in time. And you need
to search over and over. Now, you can keep it fast by sorting your
data and introducing a cursor, but that's somewhat medium implementation in complexity.
You have to write a lot of code to get it right and get it competitive.
And I wasn't sure if I had enough time in the 20 days
that I had.
It's also not so great for motion capture data,
or any sort of data that is very noisy,
such as offline simulation, destruction, clot,
or hair simulation.
And the reason for that is that the data,
by nature of being very noisy, is not easily
representable as a curve.
And the overhead of each control point becomes too great.
We also looked at linear key reduction.
It's conceptually very similar to curve fitting.
Instead of using a spline interpolation function,
such as Hermite, we use linear interpolation.
So we have our discretized samples,
and we'll iterate on them and identify keys
that can be linearly interpolated from their neighbors.
And when we find them, we can just drop them,
because they're trivially reconstructable.
So the technique is reasonably simple and quick to implement.
It's also reasonably compact.
We make some minimal amount of effort to exploit the redundancy in the data.
And it's very common.
It was similar to the legacy implementation based on it.
So it was very, already known by the animators and the other programmers working with this.
Unfortunately, it was also similar to the existing.
technique. As I mentioned, others had tried to improve on
it and failed, and I wasn't sure in the
amount of time that we had that I could
significantly improve on it using the same technique.
It's also like curve fitting, suffering from the same
issues of slow decompression. And again, you can use
the same tricks to keep it fast, which require
some time to implement and get it right.
And again, it's not terribly great for motion capture
or noisy data, because again, there's not a lot
of redundancy to exploit.
And the last technique is the simplest one by far.
It's just simple quantization.
We have our discretized samples, and we make no effort
to remove any of them.
We retain everything and instead just focus on
using a reduced number of bits to represent them.
So it's really dead simple, which means that it's
very fast to implement, very fast to decompress as
well. There's hardly any code that goes into this.
And it's also a solid foundation upon which to
build on, because the other two techniques, like linear
key reduction and curve fitting, essentially build on top
of this. The remaining keys that you use to
interpolate or the curve control points are generally stored
on a reduced number of bits as well.
So of course, the downside of the technique is that it's not very compact.
The old legacy implementation that was causing our size to balloon up was essentially built
around this, and it was an issue.
But we deemed it good enough because we knew we could get it in a streaming-friendly format
very quickly and solve our problem through that.
So we decided to build on simple quantization.
And then later on, if we have more time, we can build more
complex solutions on top.
So our solution essentially breaks down into four
categories, or sections.
We'll first talk about range reduction and how we use it to
increase accuracy and be more aggressive with compression.
we'll talk about uniform segmenting and how we use it for the same purpose as well as
to speed up streaming. We'll talk about constant tracks or, and animated tracks and the ratios
that, that we see in the wild. And of course we'll talk about quantization and the number
of bits that we use per component.
Range reduction boils down to talking about our tracks,
or animated tracks, in terms of their range of motion.
So for example, in a specific clip,
I might have my elbow rotate by 120 degrees around some axis.
Of course, the theoretical range is the full 360 degrees.
But in this particular clip, it's only 120.
If I want to quantize it on four bits,
The natural thing to do is to split the full range
onto 16 intervals.
And that gives me a precision of 22 and 1â„2 degrees.
And it's immediately obvious what the issue here.
I have a lot of intervals that fall far outside the actual
effective range of my clip.
So the smart thing to do is, of course, instead
to partition our effective range into our 16 intervals, which
increases our precisions by three in this example
here, up to 7.5 degrees.
Of course, the trade-off is that we now have some overhead.
We need to store the range minimum value, as well as
the range extent, in order to reconstruct our values.
we have to normalize our values within that range as well,
which is good for us, because it means that after this step,
our rotation, translation, and scale data
is now used in the same units.
It's a scale value within the range between 0 and 1.
And of course, reconstructing the value
and performing range expansion is trivial.
It's a multiply and add, which is
very efficient with the hardware.
We need six scalar values to represent a full track range.
Each track type, rotation, translation, and scale, they
all have three components.
And we need the minimum and the extent for each.
We store these six scalar values as full precision
floats in our clip metadata, which boils down to 24 bytes
per animated track.
So with this, it means that we can increase our accuracy
with a small overhead, which allows us to be much more
aggressive in the compression of the actual track data.
We can be more lossy, because the loss is not
as visible anymore.
Sadly, this is not great for short clips.
If I only have two or three key frames, obviously, the
overhead of the range information is going to offset
a lot of the gains that I'm otherwise going to have.
But in a general case, it's absolutely worth it.
And range reduction is a cornerstone of our algorithm.
Next we have uniform partitioning. We decided to split our clips into blocks of
sixteen keyframes for three reasons. And why sixteen? Just because it seemed the
sensible values, but in truth, we haven't had time to try anything else, and it
worked out all right for us. So the primary reason for uniform partitioning
is that, is that it makes seeking within the clip very fast and easy.
for a specific point in time that I want to sample,
I can quickly, within a simple index table,
find which blocks I need to interpolate from.
And this, of course, also makes it very easy
to perform streaming ahead of time,
finding out which blocks I need
and bringing them into memory.
And last but not least, it allows us to do range reduction again a second time per block.
So we have two levels of range reduction. First at the whole clip level, and once more
for within each block. And, again, we store the range information
metadata within each block. Our six scalars this time are quantized onto
eight bits, because they're essentially between zero and one.
and that yields six bytes per animated track.
You do have to be careful, though.
Because we quantize the range information here, it means that the normalization step
is now lossy, and you have to take into account that loss in order to get accurate results.
We also have a lot of constant tracks.
A character might have 200 bones with three tracks per bones.
That's 600 tracks.
But obviously, not everything is animated in every clip.
So I wanted to know the proportions
that we had to try and figure out
what was the best way to take advantage of that.
So I analyzed about 3,500 clips from various main characters.
And I found out that bones are constant about 65% of the time.
And the bind pose, 45% of the time.
And that makes sense, because facial bones, IK bones, camera
bones, they're only ever animated in the clips that
actually need them.
Tracks are also constant 87% of the time, and the bind
pose 79% of the time.
And again, this makes sense, because while rotation is very
often animated, the translation and the scale is
very rarely animated.
In fact, scale in my data set was the bind pose 99.8% of the
time.
So to take advantage of this, we use two bitsets that we
store in our clip metadata.
we have one bit per track. That tells us
whether the track is the bind pose or not.
And if it is, then of course we can
drop the entire track, because it's trivially reconstructible at
run time. And our second bit set is again
one bit per track, which tells us whether the
track is constant or not. And if it's constant,
then we store the one key that we need
with full precision in our clip metadata.
And from this follows that if a track is not the bind pose and it's not constant, then
it's animated and variable, and it's quantized and compressed normally.
And that takes us to the quantization step.
And originally I did, like, almost all the implementations out in the world do, and I
hardcoded the number of bits to 16.
and I've seen as low as twelve in the wild.
And that was that, and it worked, and it was
entirely equivalent to the old legacy implementation.
But one day, in the shower, I had a, a
striking moment where I, I thought, well, what if
I try to brute force search what is the
best bitrate per clip?
it's not that hard. So we try sixteen, fifteen, and
then we go as low as we can up until
we exceed some error threshold. And that worked out,
and that gave us good gain. And then I
started thinking, well, now that my bit rate is
not hardcoded anymore, it's variable, how far can I
push this?
So a logical next step was, you know, to
to observe that the rotation, the translation, and the scale data is, it's very different.
The units are different. The data behaves very differently. It makes sense to, to store
our, our bitrate, one for rotation, one for translation, and one for scale independently.
And so that's what I did. I brute force searched three bitrates per clip for each track, track,
track type.
And again, that gave us very good gains.
And if we can do it per clip, it's also very trivial
to now do it per block.
And this takes us to the last logical step
that we can take this to.
And it's, well, can I find the best individual track
rate per track per block?
And of course, this is really the holy grail here.
because this new variable bitrate is absolutely ideal for animation data. It's ideal for
our hierarchical data. Like everybody else out there, our animation data is compressed
in local space of the parent bone. This means that every bone has a little bit
of error due to compression, and the error accumulates down the hierarchy when we reconstruct
it for skinning, for example.
So of course, parent bones contribute more error
by virtue of being higher in the hierarchy.
So they need more bits to retain more precision.
And conversely, children don't need as much precision
because they don't contribute as much error
and they only require fewer bits.
And with a variable bitrate, we can entirely do this.
We also have exotic tracks.
We might have a track that's very noisy for some reason
in the clip, or has a very wide range of values, which
requires unusually high accuracy, or more bits.
And with a variable bitrate, we don't need to bias the
whole clip negatively.
It's also great for temporal coherence.
In cinematics, it's not unusual to have all your
characters animated in sync.
with clips that are all the same length.
But if a character is off screen for a while,
he's still animated, but he doesn't move.
And with a variable bitrate, we can, of course,
use fewer bits, if not zero, for the parts
where they're not moving.
And this, of course, adapts to all kinds of animation data,
regardless of how it looks.
We settled on 16 possible bitrates.
zero, three, four, five, up to sixteen, and twenty-three.
And the reason why we need it higher than sixteen
is that some clips have unusually high precision requirements.
For example, world space cinematics might have the root bone
be very far, or a camera bone move very far,
or maybe you're throwing a weapon very far ahead, like an arrow.
So you need more than sixteen bones in a few rare cases.
Unfortunately, 23 was perhaps a bad and naive choice,
chosen a bit prematurely.
Initially, I just selected it because it was the same
as the float mentissa minus the sign bit.
And that seems like a sensible choice at the time.
But of course, as I was writing the presentation,
I realized that the dequantization step
requires our integer to be uniquely representable
as a floating point number.
and accurately representable. And of course, it turns out
that a 32-bit float can only accurately and uniquely
represents integers up to six significant digits.
Essentially what this means is that there's some
rounding happening here that we hadn't foreseen. So maybe
something like nineteen might be enough. But really, in
truth, we could probably really measure it. I don't
know whether the rounding is really a big issue
or not.
or if 19 would be better, there's definitely room for improvement here.
We do have one edge case, which is when a track bit rate is zero.
It means that the track is constant within the block.
Now, of course, if the track is constant, then we don't need range information, because
our track extent is zero.
And when that happens, we reuse the 48 bits
that we had for our range information,
and we store our constant key at that memory location
with 16 bits per component, which is typically
enough precision for what we need.
So, so far on the compression side, almost everything is very, very trivial.
We have our bit sets, we have our normalization within the range that we're calculating, it's
a bunch of min-max, it's very trivial.
The only really complex step is the bit rate selection.
And to figure out how to do that, we need to talk about two things.
First, we need a way to compare bit rates. Which bit rate is superior or inferior to
which other bit rate? Now, it's obvious that a bit rate is better if it's slower, because
it means a lower memory footprint. But it's only acceptable if it doesn't make us exceed
some error threshold. So it's very important to be able to accurately and precisely measure
the error that we introduce. And so we'll talk about our error metric function.
And we also need a way to be smart about attacking the problem.
Up until now, I've been brute-forcing which bitrate is the best.
But now that I reach this point, I have 600 tracks,
only a handful, or 50, 80 or so, that are animated,
but I have 16 permutations to try per track.
It's a huge search space.
We can't afford to brute-force anymore.
So we need a smart way to attack this.
So measuring accuracy, it's really, really important.
And in fact, it's an absolute cornerstone of our algorithm.
And you'll see why later.
It's important because our algorithm uses it to converge
on a solution.
And of course, we use it as well to compare our results
with the other compression algorithms in the engine and
other engines.
You might be surprised to learn that it's often
overlooked and poorly implemented, even in
state-of-the-art game engines, such as what we had before.
And there's no standard way to do this, either in the
industry or academia.
They all have their own special flavor of how to
measure error.
And of course, we are no different.
And I will be presenting our own flavor here today.
There's three criterias that an error metric really needs to meet that are critically important.
It needs to account for the fact that our data is hierarchical in nature.
It needs to account for the aggregate transform, the rotation, the translation, and the scale.
And it also needs to account for the fact
that we have a visual mesh, something that we often forget
with animation data, because we're working with a skeleton.
So the hierarchy is very important.
As I mentioned, the error accumulates down the hierarchy.
This makes it very obvious that if you
use a local space error metric, you're
not getting the full view of the true error
that you're introducing.
So that's bad.
We really want to be using an object space arimetric because
it allows us to see the full impact of our changes in bit
rate selection.
The aggregate error is also very important.
It's very common, sadly, to measure the error with the
bone position or the leaf bone position.
But of course, it ignores the rotation and the scale
contribution of that individual bone.
And we need to take into account the full transform,
because the error can be anywhere, not just
on the translation.
And last but not least, the error
that we might measure on the skeleton is not.
the same or equivalent as we would measure it
on the visual mesh. The skeleton is never really
visible, right. The visual mesh is what the users,
what the designers, what the animators, what everybody sees.
And the error is not the same, because with
rotation and scale, the error actually increases the further
away you get from the bone. And we can
visualize it like this here.
Suppose I have a bone with some rotational error.
If I have a vertex that's skinned on that
bone and it's very close to the bone, the
linear displacement as a result, in red here, from
that rotational error is gonna be fairly small.
But if my vertex is much further away, for,
with the same rotational error, all of a sudden
my linear displacement is much larger. So, of course,
it's a very important property, and we need to
take it into account in our error metric function.
And we can observe that the vertex displacement
on the visual mesh is really the true measure
of our accuracy. It's what everybody sees.
It makes sense. That's what we should be measuring.
And we end up with skinning being, essentially,
our error metric function. And it satisfies, of course,
all three criteria that we just talked about.
Now unfortunately, it's way too slow.
A character might have 200 bones, but it could
easily have 50,000 vertices or much more.
The mesh information might not even be available in
your animation compression pipeline at that point in your
pipeline.
And you might not even know the true mesh
if you're doing mesh sharing between the skeletons.
And of course, some bones don't even have
any vertices that are skinned on them.
IK bones, camera bones, or the root bones of the characters,
they don't have any vertices that are directly skinned on them
that we can use.
So instead, we use virtual vertices.
These allow us to approximate the skinning.
They satisfy, of course, all three criteria
by virtue of being the same process.
And it's also very intuitive to tweak.
It's simply the vertex distance from the bone.
So we approximate the skinning with a uniform shell,
if you will.
And the output is, of course, an object space displacement,
like we want.
In practice, internally, we settled on 3 centimeters
for our normal bones, which comprise 99% of all our bones
for main characters, props, and so on.
And we also have one meter for high-accuracy bones.
And which is which is, of course, animator-defined and
data-driven, with the exception that the root bone
is always considered to be high-accuracy, just because I
wanted to be extra conservative with the data.
So now that we can properly measure our error, and which
bitrate is superior or inferior to which other
bitrate.
We need a smart way to trim our search space.
So that we can compress, you know, in this entry.
So we decided to do a two-phase approach to tackle the problem.
We do a first pass to find an approximate solution.
And then we do a second pass to refine it to the local minimum.
And this is an important distinction.
The algorithm I'll be presenting here today does not find the globally optimal solution
of what is the best bitrate for all tracks and all blocks.
We simply find a decent local minimum, so there's definitely some room for improvement
here in the future, perhaps.
And the way the algorithm works is like this.
Initially, we'll set all our tracks to have the maximum amount of accuracy.
The highest bitrate possible here, 23.
And then we begin the first pass.
And the goal of the first pass is to lower all the bitrates simultaneously in lockstep.
As much as we can, up until we exceed an error threshold, and then we stop.
with the exception that the root bone here on the top left
remains locked to full precision during the first pass.
And the reason for this is that in world space cinematics
or any clip that requires unusually high precision
on the part of the root bone here
would negatively bias the first pass.
So we leave it fixed for now.
And so we lower our bitrate as much as we can,
up until we can't anymore.
And then the second pass begins.
And the goal of the second pass is
to iterate over each track individually
and lower the bitrate as much as we can,
up until we've processed all the tracks
without exceeding our error thresholds.
So in a sense, we minimize the bit rate very aggressively here.
It also means that we maximize the error up to our threshold very aggressively.
And it'll be made obvious in a future slide.
This makes the threshold critically important.
If it's too high, it's immediately obvious because we maximize the error up to it.
I tried one millimeter in object space.
and it proved far too high. For a third-person camera on a normal character, there was no
error that was visible. No foot sliding, no vibration. But as soon as the camera came
up close to the character, you could see the artifacts somewhat fairly obviously, which
this essentially made it absolutely unsuitable for cinematics or whenever you're backing
out on a wall and the camera's pushed in closer to the character.
We settled on hard coding a tenth of a millimeter
as our accuracy threshold.
Now, a tenth of a millimeter, to put it into perspective,
is about the average width of a human hair.
So this is really awesome.
It essentially means that our animations look pretty much
like they do in Maya.
There's no visual difference that you can see.
And now we get to the results, the fun part.
Unfortunately, the game this is going to be futurely shipped
on has not been announced yet.
And so I can't show any fancy videos.
And even if I could, they would look essentially like
they do in Maya.
So that would not be terribly fun.
Instead, what I did is I ran the compression on a large
number of clips.
I aggregated the results.
I generated a bunch of charts.
And I took out some concrete examples to kind of give you a
glimpse of how it performs in the real world.
So I aggregated about 3,900 clips for various characters,
including the main character.
The total compression time was 3.2 hours on a single thread,
or 10 minutes multi-threaded on my desktop.
The total sum of the clip length is about 5.4 hours at
30 FPS.
So it's definitely very significant and representative
of our game as a whole.
Here we have the distribution of the number of key frames
per clip.
And there's really only two things I want to point out
here.
The first is that we have about 22% of our clips that
are very short.
They use one block or less.
Those obviously are not going to compress too well by virtue
of having more overhead.
And we have, in fact, up to 11% that use half a block or less,
which is not great.
Fortunately for us, we have about 49% of our clips that
use three blocks or more, and that are going
to compress very well.
The total size on disk was about 168 megs for the sample set.
And in comparison, the legacy size of the same set
was around 300 megs.
Now keep in mind, this was for 60% linear key reduction
and 40% the legacy simple quantization.
The average number of animated tracks is 56.
Here we have the distribution of the error per clip in millimeters.
And this slide makes it bleedingly obvious that the algorithm maximizes the error up
to the threshold.
As early as the 15th percentile or so, already the error is almost equal to the threshold.
But never exceeding it, which is what we wanted.
Here we have the distribution for our compression ratio
in logarithmic scale.
And we can see on the far left that there's a lot of clips
that don't compress too well, as we suspected.
They're probably very short.
And even the median, 18 to 1, is not terribly great.
But there's a lot of clips on the right that
compress very, very well.
And there's even quite a few exotic clips
that compress abnormally well.
3,000 to 1 is definitely not representative,
but there were definitely about 10 to 20 of those.
So I'm not quoting the average here,
because it would obviously be very biased and meaningless.
A quick word about the compression ratio
is that it's absolutely meaningless
unless you and I use the same formula
to calculate the raw size.
And here, my formula is the number of keyframes
times the number of bones times 36 bytes per bone.
And the 36 bytes comes from the fact
that every bone key has three tracks,
and each track is three components or three floats,
which yields 36 bytes.
And here, here is probably my favorite slide.
This is the distribution of which bit rates ended up being selected.
So horizontally, we have our bit rate buckets, 0, 3, 4, 5, up to 23.
And vertically, we have how often it was selected by the algorithm.
And there's two distributions here.
is in our second phase of our algorithm.
When we go over each track individually
and we lower the bitrate as much as we can.
In blue, we started at the root,
going toward the leaf's bones,
or parent first, children after.
And in orange, we do the opposite.
We start with the children,
and we go up towards the parent and the root.
Originally, when I wrote the algorithm,
I started at the root going towards the leaves,
and it seemed like a sensible choice to me.
And then as I was generating the slide, I wondered,
would the distribution look really different if I flipped
the loop and went the other way around?
And it turned out that it did.
And we can see on the far left that, in orange, by starting with the children first, we have
a larger incidence of lower bit rates.
Zero, three, four, up to eight, we have much more of them.
And this makes sense, conceptually, because we have more children than we have parents.
But of course, by starting with the children first, it forces our parents to retain more
precision for the same error.
And so we also, on the right of the graph,
we can see, starting at 13, 14, 15, 16, and 23,
you can't see them.
They're not zero.
They're just very small.
But they're all higher, starting with the children,
going towards the parents.
And essentially, the net result of this
is that starting with the children first, going up,
is 2% smaller in memory for no change in compression time,
no change in accuracy, no change in decompression time.
And of course, there's probably other ways,
other orderings that you could think of to try here.
I did try to take the best of the two,
essentially doubling the compression time, but the result was less
than a tenth of a percent. So definitely not worth it.
So essentially we ended up with about ten percent
of our tracks using three or four bits or
less per component. Almost a quarter, twenty-two percent, using
up to six or less.
and almost half, 47%, using eight or less.
And this is really what surprised me the most
about our results.
If a year ago you had come to me and told me
that I could store a significant amount of rotation
and translations on three or four bits per component,
which is 9 or 12, a byte, a byte and a half
for a whole rotation or a translation,
and do so with sub-millimeter accuracy,
I definitely never would have believed you
without data to back it up.
And it turned out that it was entirely possible.
Here are some concrete examples that I pulled out
from the set.
These are all for our main character.
We have a short scramble animation, which is very fast.
We have a normal idle slow animation.
We have a regular walk cycle.
And of course, a very long cinematic.
The number of animated tracks ranges from 11% to 16%, so
fairly low.
We have, of course, the raw size, compressed size,
yielding us a compression ratio, which
is very decent between 20 to 1 and 32 to 1.
And we can see the cinematic compressing very well
with 28 to 1.
I also extracted the average keyframe size,
because I thought it was very telling.
This is the number of bytes to represent all tracks at a
particular point in time.
So a whole key frame across all tracks.
And what we can see here is that essentially fits between
three and five cache lines.
So when we're sampling our clip, we need to interpolate
between two key frames.
So we need to read twice that amount of bytes, essentially,
to interpolate.
Of course, there's other things like the range
information that you need to read.
But the track data is very dense and compact.
It's all linear.
And it contributes directly to our decompression speed being
very, very fast.
These numbers are on the Xbox One in microseconds.
And they range between 27 and 33.
And there's a number of things that we can say about this
number here.
The first is it's about half or twice as fast as the old
legacy linear key reduction algorithm.
And it's also much more predictable and consistent.
The old algorithm varied a lot in decompression time,
depending on how far along in the clip we were.
Whereas here now, it's always very predictable.
It also probably could be a little bit lower.
I did not get to spend as much time on it optimizing
as I would have hoped.
And there remains some low-hanging fruits.
Another reason why the decompression is very fast
is that our compression format for rotations
is the same as at the runtime when we're blending our poses.
And that format is the quaternion logarithm.
It's essentially the rotation axis multiplied
by the rotation angle.
So three floats.
So that means, essentially, that there's no conversion
to or from quaternion.
There's no square root to reconstruct anything.
That keeps it very fast.
These numbers are also somewhat of a worse case,
because they're for the main character, which has more
bones, typically ranging between 180 and 200, I
believe, for the cinematic.
Whereas our NPCs have, of course, far fewer bones than
this, and will decompress even faster.
So in conclusion, we've really hit a sweet spot with the technique.
It's very fast to decompress, and it would be hard to make it significantly faster.
It's also reasonably compact, so much so that we decided to use it across the board and
supersede all the legacy stuff.
And we did not even need to resort to streaming, because the memory footprint was good enough
at that time.
And it's also very high accuracy and tunable,
which makes it future-proof.
If the number of bones increases,
if the data increases in complexity,
the algorithm will adapt very well.
It's also very versatile.
It works out right out of the box,
regardless of the animation, the rig,
or however the data looks, if it's noisy or not noisy.
It adapts very well.
There's nothing to tweak for the animators.
It's excessively rare for us to go and mark a bone
as high accuracy.
And when we do, we typically do on the rig.
And then it just works everywhere else.
And it's good enough that we don't need any more fallback
compression algorithm for when it messes up, because it
always meets our accuracy requirements.
So one algorithm.
for all our animations. And of course, it's bleedingly simple. It took
twenty to twenty-five days to implement, and there's so little code and it's so easy
to comprehend that there's been no maintenance on it. Only a single bug surfaced in the first
month, and it's been in use for over a year now. And this makes it very easy to build
on and improve, and I'm sure you can think of many ways that this could be improved on.
And that's it. We reached the questions. You're free to go on my blog. I discuss all of these
techniques. And I'll be posting the content of the presentation in deeper detail as well
in due time. And if we exceed the time for the questions, I'll be at room 3022 at the
end of the hall.
Hi, great talk.
What was the workflow for animators?
So you'd create an animation clip, then you'd have to go
through this algorithm.
How did that work out?
Right, so before, animation clips would be imported into
some animation set for a particular character.
And typically, it would use the default algorithm
with the default settings.
And then if in game they saw that the accuracy was not
as good as they would like, they would go and change
the compression settings as needed
and typically fall back on the lesser compression algorithm.
But now with the new algorithm, there's
nothing that's exposed for the animator to tweak.
We hardcoded the threshold to keep it simple.
But in truth, it might be a bit overly conservative.
So the compression was already part of their workflow?
Yes, absolutely.
It was always present for the last 20 years.
It was just old.
Thanks.
Hi.
You say you store the quaternion logarithms?
Yes.
And that avoids a square root.
But if you need the quaternion, you'd need a cosine, right?
Is that?
Yes.
Internally, when we're blending our poses,
we use quaternions logarithms during the blending process.
So we only ever convert to quaternions at the very end
once we have the final blended pose.
We convert it to quaternions and matrices,
and then we work with that for skinning.
OK, I was just curious about, yeah.
So we use quaternions throughout, so I was.
Yeah, it was a very unusual.
choice. It was the only engine I ever saw using quaternion logarithms for blending.
But it remains a very sensible choice for the compression format because it's three
floats as opposed to four for quaternion. And it may not be the best representation,
but it's definitely legit.
Q I think you touched on this a little bit, but did you notice any artifacting with going
between any
any additive animations being at a different compression rate than the animation that they
were being applied to?
The, well, with a tenth of a millimeter, it was never very visible. The only instances
where we saw artifacts were with very, very large props, where the vertices were much,
much further away than our one meter threshold allowed. And in those instances,
because the actual value of the vertex distance was not exposed, only the
boolean for default or high precision,
we added intermediary bones that are never animated
just so that the final bone that we're skinned on is actually closer to our
threshold and that was good enough for us. All these bones, by virtue of being
never animated, they
compress trivially.
So you saw it in your attachments, not in your blending.
Yeah.
Hi, excellent talk.
Regarding the measuring accuracy, you said you used a
mesh vertex to join data.
I was just wondering, would the curvature of the track
would be a better heuristic to choose a bit rate?
I'm sorry, can you repeat?
What would be a better heuristic?
The curvature of the track, because it kind of tells you
the acceleration of the value.
would that be a better heuristic?
Right, so you're wondering if using basically the velocity
would be a better measure.
To store the precision better.
Right.
It's possible. You could definitely factor it in into the metric function.
Okay.
The metric function you can make arbitrarily complicated.
And you could definitely use this, for example, with blend shape animated coefficients,
but then the data is not hierarchical anymore. You would have a different error metric.
But you didn't try that.
No, we haven't tried that.
I went straight to this because it was somewhat close to what
Unreal 4 uses, for example.
But I generalized it with virtual vertices over every bone
and not just the extremities.
Cool.
Thank you.
Hi.
What was the worst case steps in terms
of hierarchy of the bones of the animation that you compressed?
That's a good question.
I think for most characters, it doesn't really go...
Most of our characters are humanoids, so the depth is maybe five or six.
We did have some animals, though.
I believe we had some sort of large predatory cat, feline, which obviously had much more
bones for the tail.
and the paws and the spine was also a bit longer.
And that particular character is really what caused
the most issues and prompted the whole discussion
over the compression artifacts in the first place.
Okay, great.
Because we had a case where the character
actually carried a chain or something then.
That was a nightmare.
So we had to actually flat the sinks out
in terms of skeleton.
Yeah. That's why an object space error metric is very important,
because that way, regardless of how deep the chain is,
you always have the true measure of the error that's introduced.
But that sounds like it will start out maxed out from the beginning,
so yeah, probably wasn't effective. Thank you.
All right.
So I believe that's, yeah, almost all the time we have.
All right, thank you.