All right. So my name is Chris Reed. I'm an indie game lawyer. I don't bite, though. And
this is Practical Law 101 for indie devs. Not scary edition.
So my love of games started when I was about five years old,
watching my brother play Ultima III and Zork
on our family's Apple IIe.
And then, like an older brother, he turned around and threatened
me at fist point to sign this contract, which
my parents preserved, which says that I will pay him
all my current cash supply if I broke one of the 5 and 1
1⁄4 inch floppies with the games on them.
Not a very good game contract.
So it's not a surprise that a couple of decades later,
I ended up with my own law practice,
where I work with indie game developers and people
in the game space to help them with basically
all their legal issues.
I'm proud to announce that we've just
hired our first paralegal.
I just spoke with him on the phone.
He's having a little bit of trouble
with the billing software, but hopefully he'll get it.
With the help of my co-counsel, Mr. Phoenix Wright,
I want to make a quick disclaimer, which
is that I am not your lawyer, unless I am.
And this presentation is legal education, not legal advice,
but I do hope you learn something.
My goal today is to help all of you
identify and avoid common legal pitfalls.
So we've got.
Not a lot of time.
And the time that it would take to go over everything
that I think is important is about this long.
Unfortunately, as you know, we have about enough time
for a game of Hearthstone.
Maybe two.
I think that's mage aggro.
I haven't played in a while.
So we're going to cover five topics, creating a company,
contracts, intellectual property, infringement,
and privacy.
For each topic, I'm going to tell you
why you should care, when you should care,
and what you need to know about it.
So first topic is creating a company.
And by a company, I mean the legal corporate entity.
Why should you care about this?
Well, a company is sort of like the legal equivalent
of a suit of power armor.
It protects you and gives you cool abilities.
Some of these include limited liability.
This means that if there are debts or liabilities
that you incur in business, they only stick to the company.
That's all that's at risk, not your personal assets,
which can be very important.
It also acts as a convenient bucket for intellectual property, meaning that you can assign all the rights in the game from the individuals who create the pieces of the game to the company.
It's all in one place. The company can then license it.
It's a convenient way to share ownership and profits in the company.
It's the way that you figure out who owns what and how voting is handled.
There are tax reasons.
We won't get into them because I don't do tax,
but you should talk to your accountant.
Finally, on a sort of practical note,
having a corporate entity enables
you to be taken more seriously when business dealings.
Most people expect to be dealing with an actual company
and not with a group of people who
are individuals calling themselves a studio.
So when do you need to be thinking about this? Ideally, before you start working at all.
But let's be realistic, that's probably not what's going to happen. So realistically,
you should put this together round about the time that you start to get serious, meaning
putting in a significant amount of time or money into the project in your game. And the
latest at which you should do this and put together a company is probably before you
enter into agreements with other people, either cofounders or you start hiring people.
So what should we know about putting together a company?
There's a couple of things you want
to discuss with your co-founders or with yourself
if you're doing it solo.
First off, whether there's going to be any future investment.
Now, this may not be the case for a lot of indies,
but some people do eventually end up
seeking some outside money.
And knowing about that in the future
lets you
make certain decisions in how you structure things.
You need to know who owns and controls the company.
So what are the percentages of ownership
of people who are actual founders?
And not everyone working on it has to be an equity owner.
We'll get to that.
And how is voting handled?
How do you make decisions in your company?
These are things you want to discuss
and be clear on before you proceed.
There's a technical thing you're going to have to choose, which is the type of entity.
It's mostly a tax issue.
There are a few differences.
Just be aware you'll have to make this choice before you go and file to create the entity.
And this is the step where you fill out some paperwork.
It gets sent to the state usually.
And there's a fee.
And this is when the company becomes a real legal entity.
That means you can go start your bank account.
You can sign contracts on behalf of the company.
It's now, it comes into existence.
But that's not the end.
The last thing you want to do is draft an operating agreement or a shareholder's agreement.
This is the document where all those things you discussed either in your own head or with
your cofounders get put down in writing and agreed to formally. This is important to have
in place, even if you're a solo, a single member LLC. So companies, form one, form one early.
Our next issue is contracts. And I guarantee you that as indie developers you are going to
encounter at least one contract. So why should you care about contracts?
Contracts provide clarity and predictability
in any business relationship.
It's like the rule book.
People can go and look and see exactly what the rules are
and how it works.
The simple fact of sitting down to talk about a contract
and negotiate it tends to make people
think through more issues than they would have,
which means that you're less likely to end up in a fight
if you've really discussed this stuff.
And having it signed and in place
protects you against.
the worst case scenario and the best case. By that I mean obviously if things go wrong,
having the contract is good, you know what the rules are. But it's also the case that
sometimes things can go very right and you have sudden unexpected success and people who
said, yeah, it's cool, it's free, you can use that asset. Now that there's money involved,
they don't feel that way. So you want to have that contract in place before that point
comes. Finally, certain things require a written contract to accomplish. For your purposes,
we're talking about transferring intellectual property.
All right. So when do you want to think about contracts? Repeat after me. Before you do
anything with anyone. I couldn't be more clear about this. But I think I will be more clear
about this. Before any of the following things, which is a big scary list, feel free to snap
a photo, but it's in the vault. We're going to be talking today about two specific types
of contracts that I think are important. The independent contractor or work for hire agreement
and publishing agreements.
So what do we want to know about contracts?
Well, in general, there are certain clauses that come up in most contracts, and you should
be aware of them.
The term and termination clause.
This means, how long does it last?
How do you get out of it?
What happens when it gets terminated?
Who pays whom what?
How is it calculated?
Speaking of who pays whom.
it's important to know what people are getting paid. Not just how much, but how, on what
time frame, how it's calculated. There's a lot of flexibility within these. I've seen all
sorts of stuff, hourly, hourly with a cap, a flat fee, milestones, a revenue share and a
combination of these. But what's important is it be defined clearly so that both sides know
how it works.
And speaking of defining things clearly, you want to also define the services and deliverables.
This means the things that each side has promised to do.
So services they're going to provide or something they're going to create, like an art asset
or a soundtrack.
You want it to be very clear what it is, not just some music for the game.
There's also a section in most contracts called warranties and indemnification that most people
just sort of skip over because it looks weird. This is where each side makes a promise to
the other about certain things that they're saying are true, and then the indemnification
is where you say, and if it's not true, then I'm the one on the hook. Practically, what
does this mean for you? That means usually things like
promising that you didn't steal the IP, it's original work and someone is not going to sue
them if they use it. And if they do sue them, you promise to be on the hook. This is the
section where you can take on a lot of liability. So it's important to know what you're
promising and make sure that it's true. Finally, there's a couple other terms that end up at
the end of most contracts, where you end up getting sued, whether you can talk about the
contract or the terms of it, and whether you might be stopped from competing or bringing
along employees from someone that you work for.
So let's move on to one of the two types of common contracts that I think you're very likely to
encounter. This one is called the work for hire agreement or sometimes known as the independent
contractor agreement. It is between the developer and the contractor. The contractor could be
anyone who's contributing something to the game, a coder, an artist, a sound person, and it
could even be a company that's providing that sort of services as a company.
So what do you need to know about work for hire agreements?
A couple of specific terms that are important.
First off, they're called work for hire
because this is the agreement where
you assign the IP rights from the contractor to the company.
We talked about a bucket for IP.
This is how you take those rights
and put them in the bucket so that the company
owns all the rights.
It's very important to have that in place.
It creates what's called a work for hire arrangement.
You also want to be very clear as the developer how you're paying them. And as we said, a lot of
flexibility here, but make sure that it's clear. They may ask for some up front afterwards. Just
make sure that you know. And if it's a revenue share, just make sure it's defined properly.
You also want to define, again, the scope of work. This is tied to the deliverables. You want
to make it clear what's expected. You don't just say the soundtrack. You say, you know, up to
a minimum of six minutes of music with whatever, you know, technical specifications. You
don't have to go into perfect detail, but it needs to be not vague. Finally, you want to know
about how you can get out of the contract. For a work for hire agreement, this usually
means what happens if you just...
not feeling the art and you want to let them go, you need someone else. Well, you need to
know, this is, you normally wouldn't be able to get out of the contract unless your
termination section has a right for the company to terminate for convenience. And if it
does, well, then the other side is going to want to know, hey, what do I get paid? What
happens when I get terminated? Is there a kill fee? Think about these things.
The next type of agreement, and this is a very wide range of types of agreements, but it would be a
development or a publishing agreement. A lot of indies, even if they develop on their own, might
consider going to a publisher for things like marketing, or it may be an old school agreement
where they kicked in money up front. This is between the publisher and the developer. Don't tease
the octopus kids. So what do you need to know about development and publishing agreements?
Couple of familiar faces.
IP rights.
In this case, you're the developer.
So you want to think, am I assigning and selling
all the rights, the IP rights, to my game?
Or am I simply licensing them to the publisher
if they're distributing?
And if I'm licensing, that's not just one thing.
There's a difference between licensing in one country
on one platform for a year and licensing worldwide
on all platforms forever.
So you need to read that and know what you're actually
licensing.
Because you're the one getting paid, it's doubly important to know how that works. In a
publishing arrangement, usually there's some kind of revenue share agreement. And that
means you should know how revenue is defined, what kind of things are deducted before you
make that split, and you should know if there's any kind of recoupment where the publisher
takes, you know, makes back their money before you see a dime. All these things, it
shouldn't be one sentence. It should be a detailed section. So if it looks short, you
should be worried. It's vague.
Next, I want you all to be aware of scope creep. This comes up in the context of when you as a
studio are being hired to make someone for someone else, which isn't always, but if it's the
case, you can have a situation where you've agreed to do it for a certain budget and they keep
asking for changes and changes and changes and new features. You want the ability to say, this
increases the scope of what I agreed to, you need to pay me more or we're not doing it. But you
need that right in the contract or you can't say that.
Another thing that comes up often with publishing agreements are what are called derivative
works. These mean things that are based on your game. So for your purposes, that means
prequels, sequels, DLC, but can also mean any type of merchandising, you know, candy,
plush toys, whatever, and also things like adaptations, comics, movies. This can be quite
lucrative and a big deal depending on how the story of your brand goes, and sometimes
these end up in a publishing agreement where you're agreeing to just give them, oh,
and 30% of all the derivative works, as if that's nothing.
Make sure you decide whether or not
it makes sense for your publisher to be involved,
and who's making the decisions about these derivative works,
and who's going to pay to develop them.
Finally, yet again, make sure you know
how to get out of a bad deal.
you want a termination clause that enables you to leave if things aren't going well. A
practical way to do that, either you have a limited term, so that's only for two years and
then you can decide, or if it goes longer, you might want a clause that says, look, you need to
meet Mr. Publisher, Mrs. Publisher, I'd like you guys to meet a minimum amount of money that
you're going to make me in the first year, and if you don't hit that, I get to take my ball and
go home. I could do it better myself or with someone else.
So, contracts are everywhere. We only covered two of the main types because we don't have a lot
of time, but make sure to read them and the terms are important. Our next topic is intellectual
property, which I'm sure you've heard of and we've already mentioned it a bit. So let's get
into some details.
There are a bunch of types of intellectual property, but for indie developers, I think by far the
most relevant on a practical level are copyright and trademarks. There's a few others that can
come up, but they're very unlikely and we're not going to go over them much. Patents are
things like novel software algorithms, maybe if it's a physical thing. They're very
expensive to get. They might be narrow in terms of the protection.
trade secrets are things like customer lists, pricing models, things that you keep secret for business
advantage, and right of publicity is when you deal with the name and likeness of a celebrity or a
public figure. So, why should you care about intellectual property? Well, it turns out that
there might be a few parts of your game that involve intellectual property, like, say, yeah,
like all of it, basically, with one very important exception that we're going to discuss. So,
Moving on, when should you be thinking about an electoral property? You should be thinking
about an electoral property as far as copyright goes before it is created, and this is where
we need to go back to those work for hire agreements, get those in place, then let the
person start working, ideally. Don't do it ten months later. And when the game is released,
you should consider registering your copyright. This is not compulsory. You don't have to
do this, but it's helpful and it's cheap. For trademarks, you should think about registering
them.
and thinking about them before launch, meaning that before you choose your name and design a
sweet logo, you should do a little bit of research. At least run a Google search. Make sure
there isn't some other game out there called Overwatch. Oops. Yeah. It's important. You can
save a lot of money by running a search. So you should do it as soon as practical. If you want to
register, it takes money and sometimes you don't have the budget for this. But it will come
later.
So what do you need to know about copyright?
Well, copyright protects fixed expression
of ideas, which is lawyer speak for your creative content.
So that means things like the dialogue, the UX, the animation,
the art assets, the sound.
the music, and even the code. It's a lot of, almost all of what goes into your game. But
importantly, it does not protect abstract ideas. This is the exception I talked about. Your
game rules, your mechanics, the idea behind the game are not protected on their own, which is
tough because it's often the inspiration for the game. This is why we can't have a million
match three games and not have them infringe each other. Finally, I want to note that by
default, at least under U.S. copyright law,
by creating something that's copyright protectable, you own the copyright. Period. You
don't have to register it. There's nothing you have to file. You own it because you made
it. That's the default rule. That's why it's important to have those work for hire
agreements we talked about so that you override that default and it's owned by the
company. What else to know about copyright? Copyright gives you the following rights. For
your purposes, the important ones are the ability to reproduce and distribute and to make
derivative works.
And not coincidentally, these are the things that are usually at issue in a publishing
agreement. So let's move on to trademarks. Often confused with copyright, they are not the
same thing. The purpose of trademarks is to protect brands and consumers' understanding of
who made what. So they protect things like titles, company names, logos and tag lines.
There are two sources of how you get trademark protection. The first in the U.S. is called
common law rights. And that comes from as soon as you start selling something using
a trademark, and the selling part is important, you start to accrue rights from that date
forward. It's kind of like an XP bar that fills up over time gradually. It's based on
how widely you've sold it, how well it's known. It might be a little more difficult to
prove, so there's another source of protection which is to go ahead and register federally.
This takes an actual application process that could be rejected. It does come with certain
fees. I tell people to expect around $1,500 total. But it gives you some benefits if you
ever end up in court. It means that your trademark
unequivocally applies equally across the entire territory. And yes, there are similar processes
for the EU and other territories. And most importantly, it lets you call dibs in advance
before you've sold your game. So that's the exception to the you have to use it. Not forever
in advance, but up to three years in advance if you need that much time.
And as we said, in order to get your trademark rights, other than using it in advance, you
must use it in commerce, meaning selling it for money.
So what does this mean?
Announcing your game's name on your dev blog two years before it comes out does not give
you any trademark rights.
When you start selling the game, that's
when you start to accrue the rights.
And that's why it's so interesting and useful
that registration lets you get ahead of that a little bit.
Finally, the strength of a trademark
is based on how distinctive it is.
Something that literally describes what you do,
game company, jumpy platform, bad trademark.
Something that is totally arbitrary is a good trademark.
So intellectual property, pretty complicated topic. This is super oversimplified. But make
sure to be aware of it. Know what you own via contracts and protect it. Our next topic is, I
think, a sore one for a lot of people. It's infringement. And why should you care about it?
Well, I think you all know why you should care about it.
It takes away profit, it takes away revenue, it can tarnish your brand. It's just not a lot of
fun. So, when should you be thinking about it?
Well, as far as registering your different types of IP, for copyright, again, you should
register at release just to get it out of the way because it's simple. Then you don't have to
think about it. Or at the very latest before you might end up suing someone or at least
threaten to sue them. Because having copyright registered multiplies the damages you can
ask for. It basically just makes the hammer you're threatening them with really, really big.
For trademark, you should do this as soon as practical. I think you should register it
before the game comes out, but practically you might not have the budget, so wait until
your budget and your revenue justifies it. As far as responding to trademark infringement
or copyright infringement, I would say do it as soon as you notice. Don't snooze on it. So
let's talk about copyright infringement and specifically about cloning.
I regret to inform you that copyright infringement does not have a magic bullet solution.
It's difficult to prove in the legal sense.
There's this term substantial similarity, which makes it sound like it's common sense,
but it's not when it comes to the legal side of it.
It may be obvious common sense, but
a lawsuit is expensive and you may not win. But there are practical things you can do. So
someone is cloning your game or has stolen art assets or sound directly from you, first thing
you can do is send a cease and desist letter. This goes to the infringer and it says, hey, we
noticed you stole our stuff. You need to stop doing it by this time or else.
You can also send a request to the content host. So you could send it to Apple or to
Steam to ask them to take down the offending infringing content. This is done under the
copyright context by what's called a DMCA takedown notice. It's a formalized process.
There's a couple of requirements. Most things like Steam and Apple have a walk-through for
it. Now, I am aware that these have a pretty bad reputation in some quarters. I like to
think of them basically as lightsabers. They could be used for good or for evil. And in
this case, you're using them for good.
You should register the copyright if you haven't already when you notice the infringement.
And then you could sue. Again, a lawsuit tens of thousands of dollars minimum. You may not
win. So it does happen. People do sue in triple town. Usually it ends up in a settlement. It's
very expensive and cost prohibitive for most indies. So let's move on to trademark
infringement, which is when people have names for games that are confusingly similar to the
public.
which can be a real issue, especially in mobile where
everything is in the same list. And Flappy Bird, good example.
some of the solutions are kind of the same. You can send a cease and desist letter to the
infringer. I want to note that the tone of these doesn't have to be universally aggressive. I
think a lot of people just send out cookie cutter, really scary letters, and those are
justified sometimes. But I like to look at what the situation is, who the infringer is, and
I ask myself, what happens if this letter we send ends up on Reddit? Well, will it seem
justified or will we seem like total dicks? So depending on who you're sending it to, you
might want to take a softer tone at first.
You can also contact the distribution platforms again. While it's not DMCA, technically, Apple,
Steam, they all have standard policies for asking for stuff to be removed because of trademark
infringement. This gets the stuff down. And finally, I want to note that unlike copyright,
you do have to continue enforcing
your trademark to keep it strong. If you ignore 20 infringers and then you want to stop the
21st because that's the one you care about, they do have a valid argument that your
trademark doesn't have as much protection because you never enforced it. It doesn't mean you
have to stomp on everyone, but, for instance, King.com, Banner Saga, it was a very ugly
situation, but the part where King.com said, yeah, we kind of have to enforce our
trademark, that wasn't bullshit. Some of the other parts, well, I leave you to your
judgment.
So the takeaways are that there are no magic bullets, but there are practical things you can
do, and you should do them early. Our final topic is privacy, which I think is a blind spot
for some indies. A lot of people may think it doesn't apply to them. So why should you care
about privacy? Well, most if not all games these days collect some amount of user data,
whether it's through, you know, directly collecting it, like ‑‑
geolocation or through third party stuff. So even if you're
single player puzzle game, you've got leader boards,
that's taking data from your users and putting it elsewhere.
Twitter integration, same thing. Any payment processing, ad
networks, all of these are privacy issues.
Governments, specifically the U.S. government, state and local, and the EU have been getting a lot
more aggressive about enforcing privacy issues. And they don't just target big people. People can
and do get fined, and they have to pay money. There's obviously a reputational issue at stake.
Think about...
how the public is responding to the Apple iPhone issue.
People are thinking about privacy, it matters.
And finally, data breaches.
They can and they do happen.
Sony is still paying a lot,
and a lot of reputational damage for the hacks a while back.
So, when should you be thinking about privacy?
I think you should be thinking about it at three times.
One, during development, because this is the time
at which you can decide, you know, do we really need
to track, like, the geolocation of our users,
or would that just be cool?
It's cheaper to take that out before the game's done.
You should think about it at launch, because you need to have a privacy policy in place.
And you should continue to think about it post‑launch, because things can change.
An update might add a new feature with a new privacy issue.
You may start using an ad network.
Or the terms of the people you work with might change, and you need to be aware of that.
So what are the best practices for privacy?
The main rule for me, if you don't need it, don't collect it. I like to call this the Jurassic Park
principle. Just because you can breed velociraptors does not mean that you should breed
velociraptors. I know they're totally awesome, but they
doors. So you should know and disclose the third parties that you share your data with, because
you'll be sharing your users' data with them. That means ad networks, that means leader
boards, that means, you know, anything that is a third party taking data. You need to know
what they do with it and you need to disclose it in a prominent and accessible privacy
policy. This means
accessible from the bottom of your website everywhere and on the splash screen of your
game or at the very least in the main menu. And please, please, if you remember one thing
about privacy, do not do this. I know it's tempting. Do not copy paste someone else's
privacy policy, change the company name and say, cool, we're done. Because now,
congratulations, you are probably actively lying to your users because you have no idea what's
in there and you probably don't do what it says. That's a great way to get fined.
So what goes into one of these privacy policies? The following things. It should be simple.
It should be four-ish pages. It should be readable by a real human, not a lawyer. And it
tells them what you're collecting, how you use it, who you share it with, and how they can get
access to it and change it if there's a problem, and what you're doing to protect it. And you
want to be honest. This is not the place to hide things. You need to disclose everything,
even if you might not do it. If you may do it, say you may do it.
Finally, if your game is marketed to people under 13, there is a host of additional things
that apply because of a law called COPPA, Children's Online Privacy Protection Act.
We don't have time to get into it.
It is a huge morass.
My advice would be to talk to a privacy professional.
avoid collecting personally identifiable information like names, pictures, and potentially
to talk to a company that's called a COPPA safe harbor. These are companies that are
certified to be able to help you become compliant. You pay them, they help you. So privacy,
please take it seriously. Have a privacy policy. Keep it up to date.
So we've made it through quite a large amount of potentially dry stuff. I'm happy that you
came along with me. And with that, we've reached the end. Congratulations. Thank you very much
for attending. And I would be happy to take some questions now and then afterwards in the
spillover room and probably at the bar if you find me later, too. So great. Happy to take
questions.
think there is a mic in the middle too. You can go there.
I'm just going to say it's an awesome presentation. Thank you
very much. I enjoyed it. Thank you very much. Hey, I'm a solo
Indy and I was given some advice a while ago about starting a
single person LLC and specifically I was told that
there's not.
from the, if you're being sued and you are a sole proprietor or a single person LLC,
you are not any more protected than if you hadn't formed that corporation or whatever
at all. Is that true or is that bullshit?
I mean, again, the answer to a lot of these will be it depends, because, which is why
this is education, not advice. It does depend on the situation.
will have some level of liability protection, but it depends on how you run things. The reason
that you want to have a ‑‑ have this sort of ‑‑ the documents in place as far as the
operating agreement, even if you're a solo, is that if you make an LLC but then you just kind
of act like a person and you don't do anything, no formalities, you don't keep any records,
from a legal perspective, it allows them to argue in a dispute,
hey, this isn't really a company.
They're just pretending they're a company, right?
It's the same thing as if you have a corporation
and you never have meetings and you never take minutes
and that kind of stuff.
Those formalities matter.
One of the reasons, definitely as a sole proprietor,
yeah, you don't have any.
That's not an actual corporate.
entity. But as an LLC, one of the other reasons you want to do it beyond just the liability
protection is even if it's just you, you may work with other people. And if you work with them
and you don't really have contracts but someone's been working with you for a while, you've got
an LLC.
later on they say, hey, I thought, I remember a conversation where you were going to give me
equity. He's like, no, no, no, you're a contractor. That was our agreement. He goes, well,
I think I contributed X amount to the company. If you don't have the document that says, here
are the rules, I'm the sole owner, I'm the manager, I have 100% of the equity, that can be
more of a nasty fight. So, yeah.
Hi, thanks, that was a really great talk.
This might be a very short question.
Have you ever heard of an online tool called DoContract?
Yes.
That some indie game developers put together?
Yes, I think I talked to the person putting that together when they were doing it.
Is there a question?
No, the question was if you're familiar with it, because I used it with the composer on my game.
I'm just curious.
how good you feel it is as a contract and if you think it's worth using.
So I haven't looked in detail at it, so I can't render an opinion on it without looking
at it.
I would say that I definitely understand the budget constraints of an Indy and the desire
to use tools like that.
Usually you're better off with a contract, but here's the big
caveat. Don't use a tool that you don't understand. So, you
know, if you ‑‑ having a contract is important, but also
knowing what it does, because if you say, yeah, yeah, just give
me the contract that does X.
And there may be single sentences in there
that do the opposite of what you think they do.
And so from my perspective in my practice,
I try not to just fire off a form contract
and be like, here, use this.
I like to walk a client through it and say, look,
here's what it's doing.
Is this what you agreed to?
Does this actually conform to your agreement?
I want them to be comfortable.
And it goes back to that whole, if you've negotiated,
thought about it, you're not going to be surprised.
So.
You know, I believe the person who put it together had mentioned they talked to a lot of
attorneys. But I can't give you an official opinion on it. I just would say make sure you
understand what you use if you get it from a non-lawyer source.
Cool. Thank you.
great talk, thanks. Just as regards COPPA, without getting into it, I know you said it's big,
could you possibly clarify on the definition of marketing towards under 13s? Would a universal
audience include that or not? Sure, so the question was about COPPA and children under 13
and the privacy laws there. It's a U.S. law. The very broad strokes are that it applies to
not just, basically any Internet operator, someone who does stuff on the Internet or
collects data.
and you are included under it if your product or game is targeted at or arguably appeals to in a
major way people under 13. So, yeah, any game that's fairly simple might fall under COPPA.
the, it's concerned with the collection of personally identifiable information. So if
there's just like, if you're randomly collecting, you know, a randomized unique ID for the phone
or whatever, that's not as much of an issue as if you're taking a name or a birthday.
So that's kind of how it's defined who's under it. And you're allowed to collect that stuff,
but you're required to get what's called verifiable parental consent, which is this nightmare
that's really, really difficult because the law was designed for websites in like 99, not
for mobile apps. So, again, one easy way is to get a copy of the law and then you can
you may just decide to age gate. You put up a thing, what's your birthday, and neutral age
gate. You don't say are you under 13, you say what's your birthday, and you shunt anyone who
falls under 13 somewhere else. Or you put them into a version of the app that doesn't have ads
or anything that's going to be collecting data. That's about as deep as I can go. Trust me, it's
a very deep well, so I would talk to a privacy person or one of the safe harbor companies.
No problem.
I had a question about parody. If you say you're making a comedic game, South Park games,
for example, how does that apply? Why do you say this is a parody work and what's a violation?
So the question was about parody, making fun of things, which is a copyright question.
Fair use is a very popular topic on the Internet. I deliberately didn't address it because I
wanted to stick to stuff I felt was most common in my practice. And the number of times it
comes up realistically is quite limited. But in general, copyright infringement happens
when you use something that's protected without permission.
Fair use, of which parody is an example, not a technical
category, but an example.
Fair use is an exception to that.
So I know this gets technical, but someone
has described once fair use as the right to be sued by Disney.
And what they mean by that, I mean, yeah, it's funny.
But it's also accurate.
Because what they mean by that is fair use,
if your defense is, hey, we made this game with Mickey Mouse.
Oh, no, we were making fun of him.
He's drinking booze.
It's clearly not.
which was actually a case from the 70s. Basically, the only time you get to make that argument is in
court. It's an affirmative defense. That means you can't just be like, no, you can't take us to
court because fair use. No, no, we're suing you if you want to make your case to the judge why this
is fair use, you're going to do it in court. And by that point, you've already spent a ton of
money just to have that conversation.
What I would say is in general, if it's close to the line, you're taking on more risk. It's a
question of risk, right? So it's not ‑‑ there are no bright lines here. Under U.S. copyright
law, fair use is determined on these factors, which means, cool, a lot of things could be
fair use, but it also means to figure out if it really is, you have to go to court. That's a
game for people with a lot of money, unfortunately. No problem.
Hi, thanks for doing this talk.
Oh, no problem.
How much screen shake can I legally get away with?
The question was how much screen shake can you legally
get away with?
You know, as much as you like.
But I think the way this ties into the talk is,
I mentioned that there were a lot of other kinds of contracts
that come up.
One of them is the EULA, the End User License Agreement.
That is one that everyone makes fun of, doesn't read.
Like, you know.
It's boring.
It is important.
And that is the section where, if your game contains stuff
that might be like an epilepsy risk or may
have some medical thing, that's where
you make the giant all caps disclaimer that says, look,
if this blows up your computer and melts half your face.
Sorry. As is. Buyer beware. So that is important. And, you know, anything that might come up
through the use of your stuff is handled in the end user license agreement. And those
also are not cookie cutter. Because they should apply to what kind of game you have. Just
as a note, since I mentioned them, EULAs are a great place to handle if you've got user
generated content. That's where you talk about, hey, do you own the stuff you make in my game?
Do I own it? If you upload like photos or something or anything to my game, do we get
a license to use it?
you want to take care of all that in there.
So that's, yeah.
Good question.
Thank you.
Yeah, no problem.
Oh, last question.
On the last question, everybody.
Just kidding.
Hey, as a composer, with smaller projects or smaller teams,
we usually keep the copyrights and the IP,
but I know with larger AAA companies and games
that becomes a work for hire normally.
And I was wondering, at what point do you see that changeover when it comes to budget
or company size or what?
So the question was about composers and how sometimes the IP to the compositions is licensed
rather than assigned.
Does it work for hire like we discussed?
So it's interesting. Musicians tend to be actually the place where I see the most people
requesting that it be a license rather than work for hire. I think that has to do with
just the history of the music industry and musicians being a little more aware of IP
issues than other creative industries traditionally. I would say that it's not necessarily a function
of size. It's based on the situation, right? So from ‑‑ neither side is trying to
screw the other. What's going on is the ‑‑
developer wants to have it as work for hire because that's so much simpler. If they ever need
to remix the sound, if they're going to put it in a trailer somewhere, if they use a snippet of
it in the sequel, but not the whole thing. They just want to know that they don't have to hunt
down the person and make sure that it was within the license. Because when you license it,
you've got to be like, what are the exact parameters where you can use it, right?
Yeah.
So I think that's really something to be negotiated. A lot of times I've seen musicians say,
look, it's this much per minute of song if it's a license and I get to sell. And then in that
case you want to determine who can sell the soundtrack. If they sell the soundtrack, can they
use the name of the game and all that kind of stuff. Or if you want it lock, stock and barrel,
then that's fine, but it's going to be more expensive. So it's not like one or the other.
It's more what the parties need and what they can afford, I would say.
Yeah, it seems like the one area where it's not necessarily always switched over to the
company to own. And I don't know. I think at the lower level you probably don't earn so much
and you can actually get a lot of revenue through soundtrack sales. And if you eliminated
that then. So I think that's just a weird corner area. I don't know what I'm saying. Thank
you. No, no, that was very helpful. Thank you. All right. Thanks for coming. I'll be in the