We can get started. So first, and also thank you for coming bright and early in the morning.
So great to see so many happy smiling faces. My name is Molly Maloney and I am a narrative
designer for Telltale Games and this is Writing a Narrative Design Relationship.
And my name is Eric Sterpe. I'm a writer also at Telltale Games and both of us have been at Telltale
going on five years this year. We actually met on the job and started dating going on like four
years ago now. We're getting married.
True.
Thank you.
Yeah, no, the wedding's coming up in June, and if you're curious about whether planning
a GDC talk and a wedding at the same time is stressful...
Oh my god, like, I'm not gonna...
I do not regret it, but we didn't plan ahead, I would say.
No, the timing was a little stressful, but...
but we have we prefer discussing the idea for this talk based on a lot of
conversations that we were having with other people you know i'm a writer she's
a narrative designer with the difference between those that tell tale what's it
like working with the person you're dating it turned out when you're dating
the person you work with people the lot of questions for you all that must be
amazing all that i'm so sorry and uh... we started realizing that there were a
lot of parallels uh... between the two subjects and uh... kind of where the
stock started coming together from
So, really quick before we dive in, what we're going to be discussing in this talk, basically
what is the difference between narrative design and writing, specifically through the Telltale
lens because that's where we work.
How the two are mutually beneficial and can add a ton to your game, make it better, and
then just tips and tricks for getting the most out of a writing and narrative design
team.
So, let's dive in.
First off, let's talk about what exactly the difference
between narrative and, blah, blah, blah, it's the morning.
What's the difference between narrative design and writing?
Yeah, it's a question that still comes up a lot,
I think especially because narrative design
is a role that's still sort of being defined
in the video game industry at large.
Yeah, I like to joke that if you ask
four different narrative designers what their job is,
you get four different answers,
and it's not even a joke, I actually did ask four.
So, it's crazy, everybody will tell you something different.
Yeah, and it doesn't help that writing and narrative design are terms that sometimes
get tossed around interchangeably these days.
But at Telltale, the two roles are currently distinct.
And our philosophy is that writing and narrative design, those are two big jobs, and asking
one person to undertake both of them, I'm not saying you can't do it, but why not let
two people do one thing really well, then ask one person to stretch themselves across
two different disciplines.
Yeah, so let's talk about what that looks like specifically.
So the simple definition that we like to use at work is writing is responsible for the characters
and design is responsible for the player.
And that's a really simplified way to view it, but it actually has been very useful for us
because it provides a lens through which each
of those disciplines can really focus their energy.
Yeah. And so on the writing side of things, that looks like you've got your dialogue,
which is what your characters are saying.
You have your character arcs, which is how the characters are growing and changing
over the course of the story.
And then you have your themes and tone,
which this is the most subjective of these,
but it basically means that if you're making a comedy,
make it funny, if you're making a drama,
make sure you're really tugging the heartstrings.
For the design side, what this looks like at Telltale
is choices and consequences are a big part.
And that is, is the player making enough choices?
Do they feel good in the moment?
Are they paying off down the line?
Next, we've got branching.
Is the player experiencing unique content
and do they know it?
And then finally, mechanics, which is historically spearheaded by narrative design at Telltale,
but it really prevents your mini-games or your mechanics from feeling different or out of place
with the narrative. And so an important thing to note is that none of these say that writing is
the one responsible for the story, because what makes the relationship between writing and design
super unique at Telltale is that writing and design are sharing that story as a deliverable.
And, you know, because it doesn't matter how much agency your player has if they don't fall in love
with the story and characters. Yeah. And so...
I also find that what's really great about this is that you've also got two people who
are responsible for the story.
So that means you can have the story holders be in two places at one time.
So while Eric is feverishly locked in a broom closet writing or whatever, I can run around
and actually talk to people, evangelize what's going on, keep people up to date, ramp up
other departments, work on my own stuff, of which there's a ton.
And being able to be in those two places at once is really awesome, because again, the
writer will be doing a lot of time locked away.
So let's get more practical with this.
Yeah, because with all the stuff you're saying,
this sounds like writing and design
don't need to actually have a relationship at all.
You could just divide up the work and call it a day,
like in this classic example from the highly topical
reference of the Brady Bunch.
He's always trying to get me to watch the show with him.
Just looking at that previous slide, not this Brady Bunch,
the one from a couple before where we've got like those two
categories, right?
It would be so easy to say, OK, that's
pretty cut and dry breakdown of responsibilities.
Like, this is my piece of pie, and this is your piece of pie,
and never the two shall touch.
But those roles, I like to think of them more
as a starting place, not a paint by numbers thing
on the balance of power or responsibility,
because.
Writing a narrative design, you know, we might have different responsibilities,
but we share a goal, which is to make a great game together.
And fundamentally, it just doesn't get that cut and dry.
You're going to step on each other's toes in the process.
Yeah. And it's like how you wouldn't have those kind of cut and dry responsibilities
in a personal relationship either.
You know, like let's say, for instance, Molly went out of town and doing dishes was her job.
You know, if she got back and there was a sink of dishes waiting for her because that's her job.
She would kill me.
I would kill him.
I'd be dead.
Actually, what's funny is that I have done this to him many, many times.
But I try not to do it to my writing partner.
Yeah, and I preferably not, you know, you don't do it to your designer either.
Yeah, exactly.
So, but really, like jokes aside, like dividing up the responsibilities of who's responsible for what,
I find historically it can lead to a lot of false senses of ownership
and also just resentment, possessiveness, and feuding.
Yeah.
and killing people.
So with that in mind, let's just go through the process
at Telltale and see how the balance evolves
over the course of making an actual episode.
So first up is pre-production, which
this is the writer and designer alone on the episode.
And it's putting together the outline and initial story.
And we've been talking about the differences
between writing and narrative design,
the differences in responsibilities.
But what's interesting is at this point,
there's not a ton of difference in what you guys are
doing from the outside.
Because it's going to be a lot of you sitting around,
talking, and thinking.
Yeah, functionally, it's just a lot of whiteboard time or coffee shop time or whatever you like to do.
And it looks a lot like this image.
You've got your writer and your narrative designer kind of locked in a room bouncing ideas off of each other.
I really think the only thing it's missing is like just out of frame, a producer holding a baseball bat.
Because fun fact, you can put story and things on a Gantt chart.
Creativity is a deliverable.
Yeah, and so the thing that is different between the two of you at this phase
is what you're focusing on.
Because like we were talking about before, you know, writing is focusing on making that,
you know, making the story compelling and making the character journey feel really good.
And design is responsible for making that story really fun and playable.
Yeah.
So we had a great example of this on an episode of Minecraft Story Mode
that we were working on together.
Now, this didn't get made for various reasons, but I had this idea for the player character
in Minecraft Story Mode.
I wanted him to have a job where all he would do all day was craft sticks for other cooler
heroes.
That was all he would do all day.
He was going to start off bored and hating his life, but he was going to be destined
for greatness by the end.
So I stopped listening and bored and hating his life.
Like this is a design nightmare for me.
Like this guy is going to be bored?
Like how do I turn that into a mechanic?
Right.
But the thing that I loved about it was that if you have a character who starts out bored
and hating their life, then you know what their trajectory is going to be over the course
of the story.
Yeah, I think that trajectory is going to take them immediately to the player uninstalling the game.
But no, seriously, it's not like this is a movie where we can just show a montage and be like,
okay, he hates his life, but don't worry, it's going to get really good later.
Right. So I heard what Molly was saying and tried to find a way to punch it up. So I said, okay,
what if he's super positive about making sticks? I said, what if he's an optimist in spite of
having to make sticks all day? He's not going to let that get him down.
This is a kids game, by the way.
I don't know if you do that part.
So that shifting of Eric's point of view,
his willing to kind of bend on these ideas,
it really helped me out a lot.
All of a sudden, we have this character.
They might be miserable, but they're also super passionate
about their crappy job.
And that really gave me an inroad as a designer,
where I'm like, OK.
So we designed this super kind of over-the-top mechanic
around it, where it was almost like this DDR-esque thing,
where it was like you're crafting
these sticks in Minecraft.
And it was like this.
Awesome! Good job! Kapow!
Epic sticks.
And it was fun and it was funny and we actually laughed a lot.
And it didn't get made for completely different reasons.
But what really was great about it was Eric still got what he wanted.
This character still wanted to get away from his boring job.
But we had a mechanic that was actually fun to play.
Yeah, so we had the character arcs that ended up being super fun.
And it was a really great example of writing and design,
kind of whacking that ball back and forth, being collaborative.
Which is how it should be.
except it doesn't always go that smoothly.
No.
Yeah, because developing that healthy level of collaboration
takes time and trust.
And if your partner is going to have ideas,
your partner is going to have ideas that you don't always
agree with.
So let's talk about what happens when writing and design
disagree about an idea during pre-production,
because
It happens a lot.
Yeah.
And if your partner's pitching and loving an idea
that you don't like, it's really critical
that you keep it on the same page as soon as possible.
And in our experience, we've seen
that there are certain red flags or bad habits
that we've seen that are really not the correct way
to handle disagreements.
So I'm going to talk about our first bad habit.
We have two.
But basically, fundamentally, bad habits, in my opinion,
boil down to overcommunication or undercommunication.
So click.
There are some people who I find dislike confrontation.
And when they hear an idea that they don't like,
they just nod in agreement to everything that you're saying,
secretly hating it and hoping that somebody else,
anybody else will kill it instead of them
because they hate confrontation.
Like, I feel like everybody knows somebody like this.
Everybody knows somebody like this.
I mean it's me, in case you didn't get the hint there.
But this one has really bitten me in the butt a lot in the past.
I was working on an episode of Telltale's Batman series.
And I told people that there was a scene that I'd write
in a particular way that higher-ups were asking for.
And even though I really didn't think
it was going to be the best way to do it,
and I had a better idea in my mind,
but I really didn't want to rock the boat.
So I said, OK, I'll write it the way they want it.
I'll wait till table read.
Someone else will shut it down.
And then I'll get to fix it the way that I want to.
A victimless crime.
Right, there's supposed to be no victims.
There's supposed to be no bad guys.
What's that? The problem with the scene?
What? No bad guys in a Batman episode?
Anyway, so Table Read comes
and sure enough we get to the scene, people
don't like it, but when it came time
to fix it, they asked someone else to do it.
So I didn't even get to fix it like I wanted to.
And the big lesson I learned
is that staying silent about the things you don't
like, it's never the right answer. In fact
holding your tongue, it's just going to hurt the rest of your team,
it's going to hurt you, and if you're not careful
it could hurt the game in the end.
And I don't know if you're picking up on this yet from my overall vibe, but that's kind
of me in life too, not just work.
Like I'm not a huge confrontation guy, a confronter.
You're a lover, not a fighter.
Which I would say is a really great transition to the other side of the spectrum.
Yeah.
Yeah, because it turns out there are people who don't have a problem with confrontation.
You might say even like confrontation.
I like to call it communication.
But whatever.
I want the record to show I wasn't saying it was about her.
But there's a designer that I've worked with before,
who maybe when they hear an idea they don't like,
they might have a hard time.
I object to the use of this channel.
They have a hard time hiding how they feel about it.
You know, she or he gets hung up on it
and comes back to it over and over and over and over
and over again until they kill it dead,
even if it derails other conversations.
So yeah, this one is definitely me.
I like to call it hypercommunication, which I feel like is a good rebranding.
But I really communicate a lot by nature.
And if something is wrong, I want to see that stuff fixed right now.
Like, in my opinion, like, the longer a bad idea persists, the more people hear about it.
You just want to nip it in the bud. And functionally, that's a great place to come
at it from, but practically, it's not. It's just not useful in the room.
And there were a couple of things that I've had to really work on over time to improve on this
behavior. And the way that I did this was the first thing.
Listen and as it turns out listening is not actually just being silent while waiting for your turn to talk
Which I thought counted for a really long time
But you know actually just really listening to what the other person has to say before casting judgment was create
It was critical for me and that was aided by the second thing
Which was that I had to really remember that
everybody we're part of a team and everybody is here making a great game because they're passionate and talented and if
you're the only person in the room disagreeing with something.
I mean, I'm not saying that you're wrong, but sometimes the problem lies within.
So for me, I just found being obstinate in a meeting or trying to shut these things down
so aggressively, it usually, surprise, doesn't convince people. You can't just shout at them
or argue with them until they give up. That doesn't actually sway hearts and minds. That
just makes everybody think you're a jerk. So yeah, I learned some things along the way.
And it's funny, like I was saying before,
these professional issues were definitely
things that we were also carrying
into our personal lives.
And being in a personal relationship
when we were first tasked with working together,
it forced us to deal with a lot of those issues
kind of head on.
You know, ordinarily, I would have just gone home
and complained to Eric about my annoying writer.
But suddenly, I was the annoying writer.
So we had to talk it out a lot at our apartment, usually.
Half hour.
Not the most fun thing.
But in our experience, these two bad habits,
overcommunication and undercommunication,
those are among the most common.
I find like this kind of thing is where most
of these issues find their roots.
And it's so important to just kind of notice them
as they're cropping up.
Yeah, because if those are causing problems for you
in pre-production, it's only going to get worse
as you start making the script together.
And at Telltale, that's a hugely co-operative process
between writing and design.
So let's talk a little bit about how we make a script.
It involves something that internally we like to call stubbing, which is Telltale's term
for design's contribution to the script.
And it's where design maps out the choices and the nodes and the branches of a scene
in our software.
And one of the things that I find makes Telltale kind of unique is narrative designers are
actually the first ones to crack open the scene files that become the script.
And by leading this phase, design is able to ensure that those scenes don't get too passive,
that they're player-driven as much as possible.
But that doesn't mean we go wild.
And like, if you remember that pre-production phase, really what my job is,
is to remember the things that we talked about during our whiteboard time and transcribe those
into the script to jog Eric's memory.
Yeah. And so writing has been able to come in and use that framework to go on and write off dialogue.
And there are some writers who I talk to who worry, like, oh,
does it feel like someone else is doing your job for you?
Does it feel like you don't have enough say?
But honestly, like Molly said, it's really rooted
in that pre-production time, and it actually saves a lot of time
and energy for when you actually start writing,
because it means there's no blank page,
and there's already a rough structure there.
And in a video game, there's so much writing to do,
so much dialogue, especially in a dialogue-driven game
like what Telltale makes, it's nice to have any way
to save a little time.
And it works because, again, of that trust in the relationship
between writer and narrative designer.
That's true. Eric knows that I'm not going to go wild in the script and just start writing in all my own ideas.
That's not very useful.
So let's take a look at what this actually looks like.
So here's what a choice in the Telltale tool looks like.
Ooh.
It's not the sexiest slide.
So this is from, just for context for you guys, this is from the big exciting finale of Minecraft Story Mode Season 1 Episode 5,
which Eric and I were co-leads on.
And the choice that we're looking at, it comes in when our hero, Jesse,
is confronting the villain of the episode. His name is Aiden. And Jesse is trying to take back
this big MacGuffin that he's been trying to get the whole time called the Eversource.
It's a magic chicken.
It's a kid's game. But those blue nodes at the top, those are basically where the non-interactive
cut scenes live in our tool. And then the yellow nodes are the choices. So let's break this open.
and see what it looks like inside. I'm just going to give a super fast overview of what this is.
So here we've got a cut scene, the one that is preceding the choice. And what I've done in here,
so this is my work and we have like a stamp that says who does what, so you know. What I've done
is I've fudged in a couple of those blue director's notes kind of just to depict what's going on in
the scene. And then the pink stubs are the stand-ins for the actual lines. So the sole
purpose of these stub stand-in lines.
are to jog Eric's memory and just give him the gist of the scene that we talked about
possibly weeks before in our whiteboard time.
And Molly and I have stubbed and written for each other a lot, so we've talked a lot about
kind of best practices, and Molly knows a lot of the best shorthand used to get the
best writing out of me.
Yeah, actually we will, whenever you sit with a writer, if you're the narrative designer,
we usually talk about how you prefer your stubs.
So these are just the ones that work best for us.
So running through the thing real fast,
so we've got Reggie who's another character in the scene.
He's super surprised to see you
because spoilers, he thought you were dead.
Aiden was talking to Reggie and doesn't like being ignored.
So he spawns a creeper near Reggie
and the creeper explodes and Reggie is incapacitated
and Reggie's in some pain.
And then Aiden turns his attention to you, the cool player,
and he cannot believe that you are still alive.
How many times does he have to kill you?
And that last stub is actually a little more specific.
And there's a reason for that.
So that's what we call the feeder line.
And that's any line that leads into a choice space.
And that is something that we get a little picky
about as narrative designers.
Writing and design do a lot of back and forth about those.
Because it's dialogue, but at the same time,
it's also really integral to the choices.
And so it's kind of a shared custody thing.
Yeah.
If you don't have a great feeder line setting up your choices,
then your choices aren't so good.
And choices are technically, if you remember that first slide,
one of my pieces of pie.
So.
Then we have the individual choices themselves.
I'm not as particular about how these are stubbed
because the display text, i.e. the text in the yellow nodes,
which is actually what we'll see on the face buttons
when you're playing the game,
that display text basically conveys most
of what I want already.
So I just like to put the role play rails
in for Eric's guidance.
So we've got the first one, you've lost Aiden,
which I think is going to be our cool badass choice.
Then we've got the, you thought it would be that easy.
which is probably your snarky choice.
And then we've got the old give me the ever source, which
is our straight to the point kind of cut the crap choice.
Yeah.
And so again, like we were talking about,
designer writer pairs approach stubbing
and writing lots of different ways.
And it's important to discuss and figure out
what works best for your team.
So after all that, I'm able to come in and write lines
using those stubs as the basis for this cut scene.
Dramatic reading, please.
So.
Aiden's eyes widen, looking over Reggie's shoulder, and Reggie turns.
Oh my good gosh, you're alive! You're alive! And, you know, that must mean, is the Founder alive,
too? Is she with you? Hey, I'm not done talking to you. Aiden spawns a creeper near Reggie. What
the? The creeper explodes, incapacitating him. Jesse, our hero, comes running in. Reggie!
Not one more step. Jesse halts as Aiden stands, getting angry. I killed you once. I can do it
again. You were a fool to come back here, Jesse. And scene. Yeah. So...
I think it's feeling pretty good.
It's pretty early in the morning for that level of excitement.
I've amped up the drama in a few spots.
I've added some character beats.
You can see the note that I left there for Molly calling out
we're at a new dialogue.
And the only problem with it is it's starting
to feel a little bit long.
Yeah.
Eric's idea for this new line, I really liked it.
He actually caught something that I completely spaced on
in our whiteboard time, which was that you supposedly
died with another person.
So that's really good, but when you
start to read all of it out loud,
it's actually getting a bit long with no player interaction
whatsoever.
So I'd recommend a trim.
Yeah.
That's possible.
Which happens.
Writers love writing dialogue, as it turns out.
Yeah.
Which is good.
It's good to love things.
So part of what I do is I actually will go through.
So basically, I do the subs, send it to Eric.
Eric makes it amazing, and then I get it back.
And one of the things that I do, and director does this too,
is we look for potential cuts.
If it starts to feel like it's getting too long,
what can we trim down?
And I don't like to do this.
But it's a necessary evil to kind of keep the player driving.
So, I would also suggest that we consider cutting these two lines as well.
Because, I mean, they're not totally necessary.
And, you know, heaven forbid we have things that aren't totally necessary.
Oh, God.
Finally, I like what Eric was going for with this last line,
but the one before it is actually
going to lead into that choice space that we looked at earlier
a lot better.
So I would recommend that we either cut or move
that one as well.
Sorry, sweetheart.
I'll survive.
And these are like the negotiations that we do.
No, but seriously, something like that
really is better coming from your creative partner
rather than like an executive or someone down the road.
And I know that if it was a line I was really passionate about,
I know we'd be able to have a discussion about it, again,
because of all the trust and communication and all that stuff.
We honestly do talk about it a ton.
Yeah.
And so now we're going to move on to these choices.
And Molly knows I have fun writing dialogue like this,
so her stubs are pretty open-ended.
So for that badass choice, we've got just you and me, Aiden.
Just you and me now.
For snarky, we've got give me some credit, Aiden.
I'm a lot harder to kill than that.
And then to the point, we don't need to fight, Aiden.
All I want is a chicken.
Hand it over.
And so for this.
The first one here, Eric really took the stub
and ran with it, which is good and exactly what we want,
but it's actually getting a little far away
from the original intent of the display text,
which is it's over, Aiden.
Or no, it's you've lost, Aiden.
Whatever, something like that.
But honestly, this is a great example
where I like that line so much,
I'm just going to quietly change my display text
to match it, rather than ask Eric to adjust his line.
See?
It's a process.
Yeah, so we're joking around but what design is doing here is actually really important
And it's a great example of the different lenses that we were talking about before really enhancing the process as we go back and forth
You know, I'm focusing on the characters in the scene
Molly's focusing on the players experience through it and the combination of those efforts, you know
It's just gonna make for a stronger game in the end. So let's show you how the scene ended up in the ship game
God
I'm gonna click it
You're alive!
Oh!
Is the founder with you?
What the...
Reggie!
Not one more step!
I killed you once, I could do it again!
Just you and me, Aiden.
Just you and me now.
I really love that scene actually.
And they have a lot more energy than I do right now.
I think every scene should have a chicken in it.
It really solves a lot of problems.
But that scene I think really did come together as a great example of that writing design,
you know, being in balance and going back and forth with each other.
Yeah, and so we're starting to get toward the end of things now, and we thought it would be really useful to share what happens when writing and design might be a little less balanced in your game.
Because we're talking about a lot of the ideal versions of things, but functionally that's not always the case.
And what I mean by this is, how do I identify when perhaps one discipline might be overpowering the other, and why that can be bad?
Yeah, so first up, I've got some signs that your game might be suffering from something I'm calling writing domination.
It's a little dramatic.
I think it's cool.
So that includes, you've got cut scenes
where the player character's feeling all sorts of emotions
that the player themselves might not be feeling.
This is your classic example of you
got a character on screen who's being
super upset or angry about something
while you're laughing.
And then you've got a diverse range of dialogue choices
that are only really saying one thing.
And this is commonly a problem that
happens where a writer's written a line or a moment
that they really, really love.
And they're like, well, let's just
make sure all the choices lead right into that.
I'm angry, I'm really angry, or I'm so mad.
Right, and so that's the sort of thing that design will come in and be like,
no, no, no, we need to actually practice that a little bit more.
And then this last one's a pretty common one,
but it's the player only reacting to what other more interesting characters in the scene are doing.
This is a great example if you might have a big ensemble cast,
and so you've got all these wacky NPCs in the group with you,
and they have their interesting backstories and their cool character growth,
where you're just kind of being told and watching their story
instead of one that you're driving and playing.
I find a red flag on this one is if you have the choice,
calm down, that's usually a tip off
that two other people are doing something
really interesting that you're watching.
And so those are the kind of traps
that we have to avoid falling into.
Please just calm down.
On the flip side, you've got signs
that design might be throwing a little too much weight around.
And those include things like.
You get those super to the point lines that tell you exactly where to go and what to do
because clarity is king. Go to the place, get the thing, bring it back.
Like, it's just like not as fun to listen to.
That's very clear.
Mechanics for the sake of mechanics, because what better to amp up the emotional stakes in your scene
than a sick round of shuffle puck or some mini-game?
And then finally the old, no one can be interesting except the player, ever.
And this is actually kind of the inverse of Eric's last point, but it's one of the things
that I find design does a lot, where it's like, I like to call it dumb NPC syndrome,
because you'll have a bunch of NPCs standing around an unlocked door waiting for you to
open it, things like that.
And so we're obviously describing exaggerated worst
case scenarios to be funny here, but hopefully it's
getting to the root of what we've been talking about.
And if you take away anything from this talk,
we hope it's what's on this slide.
So first that's having those lenses through which you
evaluate your game are really important.
Because if writing is responsible for your characters,
design's responsible for your player,
then it means that they can both share responsibility
for the story, and that means that no one
has a monopoly over the two.
Which is good, because making a game is a team effort.
And then there's also the fact that.
I find if the writer and designer, if they're not supporting each other in the room, then
why would you expect the writing and design to support each other in your game?
Like it's a very fundamental thing, but it really is true.
And one of the things that I kind of love about Telltale is Eric and I are on equal
footing.
Design doesn't actually get to tell writing what to do.
We do need to agree on things.
which really makes it so that we are kind of forced to see things eye to eye in a, what
I find is a very productive way.
It means our stories are really the most important thing, which I love.
And we learned all of this the hard way.
Working professionally with your significant other is not easy all the time and it really
forced us to have some tough conversations.
I hate tough conversations.
Yeah, and honestly, one of the reasons that we really wanted to have this talk in the
first place is to allow people to kind of not end up in the position that we found ourselves
in where you'd have these tensions at work, but you can never escape them because you
live with that person.
But it actually forced us to do a lot of work.
Right, and you might not be dating your creative partner, but you are in a relationship with
them whether you like it or not.
And honesty and trust are just as important in a professional relationship as they are
in a personal relationship.
So, you know, be nice to each other.
Be nice to each other.
So really quick, I do want to thank GDC for letting us have this talk, Telltale as well,
and mostly for you guys for coming at 11 o'clock in the morning on Wednesday.
So thank you for being here.
We really appreciate that.
And please, you should be getting some surveys in your email inboxes if you could let us
know how we did.
We'd love to hear it.
And we're going to be over in this wrap-up area for a little bit.
For questions.
So we're going to leave and be in the wrap-up area.
So thank you so much.
Thank you, everybody.