Thank you. Let me start out by saying, never buy a new computer one week before GDC,
because you don't know how to work it.
So the first thing is, those of you who know me know that 25 minutes is like ridiculous.
And I'm going to rip through this, and if I don't get through it all,
I'll just finish it out there and do a poster session or something.
So we'll see how far we get.
So, what I want to talk about today is what we can learn from other narrative media.
That's not anything so unusual just by itself.
Plenty of people have talked about that, but I hope I can surprise you at least a little
today.
There are some things I think we can learn, obviously.
There are things we could learn that we haven't yet learned.
But most important, to me anyway, as a contrarian,
is that I think there are some things we shouldn't learn.
And there are things that are sort of seductive and obvious,
but I think will hold us back as we become the medium we are capable of becoming.
So, just, I know myself well enough
to know that at some point, probably several points in this talk,
I'm gonna say something like,
you shouldn't make games like X, Y, and Z.
Or you should make games like A, B, and C.
In those cases, just assume I'm exaggerating to make a point.
or a really bad joke, or both.
It's not my place to tell people what kinds of games to make,
or what kind of games to like.
Sometimes I just can't help myself.
Now, why is it important not to be too judgmental?
It's important because imitating other media seems to be a natural, even maybe necessary
stage in every new medium's development.
Building on a foundation provided by other media is pretty normal and natural.
So I want to talk about how some other media have done this.
I mean, movies started out...
emulating theater, of course. And here's an early Edison film starring the
renowned John Irwin and May Rice reenacting something from their their
show, which was quite the scandal at the time. Even as late as 1912, a lot of...
whoops...
A lot of filmmakers were still stuck in that,
let's put the camera in the middle of the orchestra
and just leave it there, because obviously that's
what movies are all about.
This is Sarah Bernhardt in Queen Elizabeth, by the way.
It took a fair amount of time, a decade, even more than a decade
after the creation of the earliest films
before cinematic storytelling, as we know it today,
came into sort of widespread.
use the techniques of cinematic storytelling.
Radio as well. Radio borrowed
plenty in terms of
bringing people from movies
into radio and bringing radio
stars into film. This is
the Jack Benny show.
I don't know why I come out here every show
and I keep saying thank you, thank you, thank you.
And look what I'm thanking you for.
you get in here for nothing.
So, you know, and this is 12 Angry Men, television 1954,
movie version 1957.
You can see the similarities, I hope.
And given that I have 25 minutes, I'm going to stop here.
OK, so this has been going on for a while.
Every medium does it.
Maybe we should, too.
But what about games?
What does any of this have to do with game narrative?
Now, this is a long quote. I hate doing that, but this is a pretty small book, first person.
And the important part of this is video games include more of the building blocks of storytelling
than any single medium has ever offered us. How could we not tell stories? And I totally
get confused when people say, oh, games shouldn't tell stories. You know, it's crazy. I find
that silly and amusing. But the seemingly simple statement that we — — —
that we can tell stories because we combine all of these other media characteristics,
got me thinking, is that all we are?
Now, no medium has survived without changing and growing beyond its borrowed roots.
And if we're nothing more than an amalgam of conventions borrowed from other media,
we're in a world of trouble.
And is interactivity, then, the one thing we offer?
I mean, that's an abused word, almost as abused as transmedia.
Not quite, but almost.
Is that the only unique feature we have to offer?
Are we just all these other media plus interactivity?
Now clearly, we can be movies with interactivity.
And just before anybody gives me a hard time, these are my
two favorite experiences of the last year.
I came to Heavy Rain a little late.
But I think we can do much more.
than even these games are doing.
What we have to do is understand how other media make meaning
and adopt the conventions that work for us,
but know enough about them to jettison
the conventions and techniques that work against us.
The key for me is to do this consciously,
to understand why we borrow something
and when we borrow something.
And so I want to run through that very quickly.
today. I'm going to talk mostly about movies and then go into some other media
even more quickly. The similarities between movies and
video games, as indicated by those, you know, my two favorite
gaming experiences of the last year or so, it seems so obvious you're probably wondering
why
we should bother talking about it at all.
They both, hey, they have moving images.
We have moving images.
They're projected or reflected on a screen.
We both have color and synchronous sound.
We both sort of create a convincing illusion of life.
Formally, we share a lot of characteristics, obviously,
movies and games.
But they're the medium of the 20th century.
And I can't even remember what I meant by United in real time.
That's pretty cool.
Okay, anyway, I'm moving right along here.
You know, I think what you can see is culturally speaking,
we share a lot with movies as well, not just formally.
The movies were the medium of the 20th century
that changed everything.
It was the first time that everybody in the world
basically could experience the same stories,
the same cultural messages at once.
Now clearly, movies and television still
fill that niche today.
But I think everybody in this room will agree.
Games have overtaken those earlier media with at least a new generation in reflecting and driving cultural norms.
So clearly we are borrowing from movies and books and comics and other media.
And there are certainly similarities even in team makeup and development methodologies that I was going to talk about until I found out I only had 25 minutes.
But there are also significant differences, and I think we ignore those at our peril.
And so, let's talk a little bit about what some of those differences are.
The ways in which filmmakers communicate, by cutting from one image to another, to give
the illusion of continuous action, while in fact breaking things down in ways that are
more dreamlike than any reflection of the way we experience the real world.
And despite the success of cinematic games these days,
and we all know and love cut scenes, don't we?
All right, maybe not.
I'd argue that even the most fundamental editing techniques,
at some point, we're gonna go,
what were we thinking, you know?
They aren't for us.
So I think we need to jettison some conventions.
See, I told you I was gonna start sounding like I was saying,
don't make games like that.
Okay, so here's an example of cross-cutting or parallel action.
I mean, it's as dirt simple as cinematic conventions come.
The camera's cutting between multiple locations.
The audience knows things that the characters don't.
And it's the quintessential cinematic moment.
Will he save the girl or not?
Films cut away from action that would
reveal the artifice of what's going on in a scene.
I was working with one director who I can't name out in LA.
on a project that involved some fairly horrific scenes.
And in the film version, the plan was going to be to...
Okay, this was obviously not a Saw film or something,
but we were gonna cut away from the really horrendous stuff.
But in the game, we had to figure out
how to make that same stuff palatable and even enjoyable,
which was quite the challenge,
and why I made a Mickey Mouse game instead.
And we had to make it not just...
I can't believe I just said that.
Anyway, the viewers weren't just watching.
They were actively engaged in the activity in real time.
And not just once, but over and over and over again.
That's something I'm going to come back to a lot.
In a movie, this basic cinematic technique
is something that.
you know, everybody expects, everybody understands, it's a great way to invoke a specific emotion in a film.
But in contrast, when we're at our best, I think, this is, this should be unavailable to us.
We should not be doing this. It breaks the illusion of immersion, which is critical, I think, to a game's success.
It wrests control away from players who want to be the directors of their own experience.
Now, barring those cinematic films that, again, I love,
please don't put me in a box of,
hey, he's the guy who hates cinematic movies,
cinematic games.
But in most games, the action is continuous and contiguous.
We either take full control of the camera ourselves,
or we leave the player the work of determining
where the camera looks
and what the hero sees or doesn't.
And sometimes we do better with cameras than others, of course,
and we're gonna move on from there.
In a weird sort of way, movies are non-linear.
And games are linear in the way they treat time and space.
It's an interesting paradox and one we really need to remember.
Now, just to bring that home, if there's a film historian in the crowd,
I bet you can guess where I'm going with this.
I want to take a look at two movies very quickly that...
that take a very game-like approach, and you'll see how well it works.
This is Rope, Alfred Hitchcock.
He did!
Oh, no, no, uh, this is, uh, you've made a mistake.
This is Kenneth Lawrence.
Oh, I'm so sorry.
You see, that's all right.
You're right.
Kenny, there's nothing to mistake.
We'll get to this in a second.
In Rope, Alfred Hitchcock was trying to make a game
in one take, no cuts, no editing at all,
just like games.
And it was a disaster, okay?
It's unwatchable.
Similarly, I mean, that's a case of borrowing a convention.
Well, a convention he didn't even know was going to exist
several years later.
But now, Lady and the Leg, Robert Montgomery's...
big directorial debut and not a very successful one.
Let's see if you can guess what game inventions this emulates.
You're a Yankee, you wouldn't understand.
I don't think a little scheme is going to work.
Pardon me, Mr. Muller, do you have the time?
What's the matter, doesn't your clock work either?
Okay, you get the idea.
Movies live and die on cinematic editing, go figure.
And when they borrow, again, it's kind of a weird reverse borrowing,
but filmmakers very quickly figured out that doesn't work.
And I think the other direction works as well.
We need to figure out what doesn't work.
Now, there are three other differences that are worth citing here.
The way games do their pacing is very different than movies.
And then, sorry, yeah, games and movies, right, I got that right.
A movie, 90 minutes to 150 minutes, more or less.
Games, 6 hours to infinite.
You know, I remember I had a conversation with yet another filmmaker who I wish I could name, actually, but it was really cool, but I probably can't.
We talked about his approach to cinematic storytelling, effective storytelling, and he was saying, let's take our time.
let's have a normal world that the player explores
and thinks it's perfectly fine,
and then after half an hour, an hour,
something strange happens.
And you realize that that's a pretty standard
cinematic technique.
A filmmaker can count on an audience
understanding how movies work
and being willing to cut them the slack
to sort of start in a normal world
because they know the action's going to come eventually.
But...
We don't have that advantage unless you're Hideo Kojima.
We have to get players doing compelling, cool, fun,
action-y things in, what, 30 seconds, a minute, five
minutes, unless it's a free-to-play game, in which
case they might play for half an hour.
But if you don't get to your verbs quickly and make them
really action-y, or at least compelling in some way, your
player's going away.
Another thing, in games and movies, there's a different approach to economical storytelling.
Screenplay, what is it, 90 pages, 120 pages, a minute per page of screen time?
Dialogue that reflects the way people actually talk, short snippets, frequent interruptions,
no incredibly long monologues.
Now, working with certain game writers
who I will not name,
I've had to take 50 pages of single-spaced monologue
and say, no, no, no.
We can't adopt doorstop novels for inspiration.
This is a place where I think we can learn something
from other media.
But, I mean, this is...
Whoops.
Don't buy a computer a week before GDC.
that's a script for a movie on the left, and that is not a game script. But I can tell
you for a fact, the script for a Deus Ex game is about that tall. Okay. From the, not from
the ground, I mean, you know, from the podium.
So, you know, the reason for that is it's not, well it's often that we just go on at some incredible length,
but it's really that even in the simplest game, we have to make sure that the hero doesn't say the same things over and over again.
Because remember, we're going to be repeating the same things over and over again.
You're going to be interacting with non-player characters who are pretty damn stupid,
which I'll get back to in a minute.
And you can't have them saying the same things over and over.
So you have to find a hundred ways to say,
I thought I heard something.
And of course, there are branching narratives and all that stuff that we all know about.
But the illusion of immersion is instantly lost if you don't have
a hundred ways to say what a screenwriter can say just once.
But here's the coolest thing I discovered working with a bunch of guys in Hollywood.
They think about wonderful moments in a way that we can't.
They think in terms of one-shot character behavior, set pieces, memorable bits of business.
I was working with John Woo.
on a project. And I'll never forget this conversation. We were talking about the character that we
were creating for a movie and a game simultaneously. And this guy, he leaped out of his chair and
started, with the movements of a dancer, started acting out the coolest thing I've ever imagined
a character doing.
And I was determined that I was going to find a way to use it in the game somewhere.
But I had to explain to this guy, one of my heroes,
the first time the player does that, it's going to be really cool.
The hundredth time, not so much.
The first time doves fly in front of the camera.
It's really cool. Once a movie, you can get away with it. If every time a gun goes off,
doves start flying, people are going to start laughing. And similarly, you know, like flying
down a staircase while shooting. I mean, it's cool once, but if you're doing it a hundred times,
it really gets silly, you know? It's not cool.
Now, we do have magic moments.
These are some of my favorites, and I'm dating myself, I know, but, you know, stuff starts
reaching out and grabbing guys and pulling them, you know, down into the depths of who
knows where.
dogs leap out and surprise you.
But those work, I think, because these games,
well, we'll get to what kind of games those are.
They work for very specific reasons
and not in ways that I think are really valuable to us.
What's really valuable to us...
is when we allow players to make the magic moments.
They're about repeated actions.
Games are about repeated actions,
where their significance and coolness
comes from the context, from what the player decides to do.
Even the coolest bit of business becomes a bore
when it's enacted over and over again.
OK, so real quick, I want to talk about some other media.
I bet if I asked you guys who had played Dungeons and Dragons, a lot of hands would go up.
How many people have played Dungeons and Dragons?
Yeah, okay.
If I asked you who read or, let's even say it now, who reads comic books?
Anybody not watch television?
Holy cow, you guys are weird.
Okay, classic radio probably not so much,
and oral storytelling, yeah, right, okay.
But I actually think there's a lot we can learn from this.
But before I get to that, I want everybody to take a second
and turn towards Lake Geneva, Wisconsin.
Oh my God, you're kidding me, I have five minutes left?
Holy cow, I'm halfway through my talk.
We will be continuing this outside.
Okay.
Okay, really ripping. Say a prayer of thanks to, uh, to, yeah, Gary and Dave.
Okay, so there are a lot of things we can learn, uh, about collaborative storytelling.
Uh, that's the coolest thing. The, the recognition that player expression and creativity are
what, what makes tabletop role-playing cool. There's no way I'm finishing in four minutes.
It's not gonna happen.
Okay, sharing just that realization, like letting players drive the story.
If we had nothing else, we'd be great.
But these are things that I think we don't want to learn.
I mean, D&D is, and role-playing ever since, has been about, you know, guys who look like
the mighty Thor and real big broadswords.
I mean, they're kind of adolescent in their behavior and stuff.
You know, we don't want to emulate what a couple of war gamers in Lake Geneva, Wisconsin,
in a basement of the library, thought was cool.
Okay?
I mean, we are the first medium that's come along in, like, 50 years.
We owe ourselves better.
We don't want to make games that are about rolling dice.
How many games, even today, are about secret die rolls?
We have better tools.
We can actually simulate what a door is and how it responds to a big sword or a shotgun.
Why would you freaking roll dice to simulate that?
It's ridiculous.
We don't have a human game master.
That's a huge problem for us, which I will come back to in the one minute I have left.
Okay, so these are the important lessons we should absolutely not learn.
Radio we're just not going to talk about, okay?
Except to say, audio is really important to games.
No matter how good our graphics get, we're still in the, you know, making them.
Oh my gosh, well bye George. I ain't going to take this thing lying down.
I got proof for all my figures.
I got receipts for all my tax deductions filed away.
Where?
Right here in the hall closet.
What? The hall closet?
I've got to, I'll get them out and sort through them.
Oh no, don't open that door, McGee.
Everybody knew what happened when Fibber McGee opened that closet.
Forget it, it's not happening for you.
You're going to have to drag me off the stage.
Okay, what about comics?
Economical storytelling, I mean, those guys get more bang for their word buck
than even the screenwriters do.
There's a little bit of interaction if you've read understanding comics.
I mean, the amount of information that players have to provide, sorry,
readers have to provide in the gutter there is huge.
And they understand the importance of iconic presentation of information and characters.
What we shouldn't get, though it's clear that we can learn something from In the Shadow of No Towers,
on the right there, you can deal with adult material, and I think we could learn from that.
But we probably don't want to deal with what a lot of comics
deal with, sort of kiddy stuff.
OK, oral storytelling.
This is the part I really am going to rip through this,
because I do not understand this at all.
My gut is telling me that there's
something about the way a storyteller interacts
with the people listening to the story that
is really valuable to us.
And I've been thinking about it for a year,
and if any of you know, please tell me.
OK?
But, you know, it's an interactive art that encourages the listener's imagination.
I mean, it's pretty crazy.
We are working in a medium that's about collaborating with our players to tell a story.
So we are dangerously similar, as I've been saying for years, to other media.
If you take a superficial look at what we do, it's very much like these other media,
but there's a point where we have to start looking at what makes us unique.
The four things that I think make us unique, we can transport players to worlds that they
can only imagine. It's not Luke Skywalker in a ship, it's you, right? We can immerse
you in worlds that seem like they're real, okay? We can remove the obstacles the player
believe. We are the only medium in history, think about this, the only medium in history
that can respond to what players do. No one's ever been able to do that in the entire history
of humankind except maybe LARPers.
And they don't care.
And we're the only medium that I can think of that it's not
happening, that can prize the repeated action.
Everything else depends on the unique moment.
OK, so when we're at our best, these are the things that I
think we need to be doing to take the next
step in our evolution.
Players interact with the game world in real time.
They're offered significant opportunities to act.
They are shown the consequences of those actions.
And the game responds appropriately
to create a unique experience at the end of the day.
Player experience comes first.
OK, so in my description, I promised.
In my description, I promised that I would leave
with some specific recommendations
for research topics.
I'm going to do that very quickly.
Okay, story structures.
We suck.
We have five approaches that I can think of.
The roller coaster that no matter how well-hidden it is,
and I think both of those games hide it exceptionally well,
you're really, the only choice you're getting to make is,
do I jump here or not?
Do I, what gun do I use to kill that thing?
It looks complicated, but that's the illusion.
It's really one, two, three, four, five.
There's the retold story.
I can't believe somebody talked about sports before.
That was so cool.
There's the retold story.
Man, I was waiting for that long, straight piece,
and oh my God, it never came, and it sucked.
The retold story is really powerful to the person telling it.
It's probably very boring to the person listening,
but it's a very powerful tool for us,
and we shouldn't make fun of it, actually.
There's the sandbox where the only story is what you create.
It's not the, he's walking away, I won.
There's no predetermined narrative at all.
There's the hybrid, where you still have 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5.
Guess what? These are the games that I make.
And lots of other people are making them now, too.
But how you navigate that first part of the story is up to you.
How you navigate the second part of the story.
And to be frank, that's the best I can think of, which is pathetic.
We have to find a better answer.
Procedural stuff, there are a bunch of experiments
that have been going on for about 10 years,
maybe a little longer.
They've worked in very small cases,
but not really in any big stuff.
You know, they point us in interesting directions, though.
I think we need some new structures, okay?
New hybrids, whatever.
I mean, if we fail, I think we end up the bastard stepchild
of every other medium on the planet.
That's research project number one.
Number two, virtual actors.
I mean, how do you tell stories?
You have interesting characters to interact with.
We're doing better on the character graphics front, I
think, but that's all we seem to focus on,
the prettier pictures.
Clearly, we've made progress, right?
But not enough.
I had to work to find these three examples of anything
better than what we were doing 10 years ago, except for
prettier pictures.
This is what the mainstream press, for crying out loud, is
saying about us.
Characters remain primitive and flat.
When non-gamers figure that out, we're in trouble.
And when interaction models haven't changed since 1990,
we've got to work harder, you know?
We've got to work harder.
I mean, the coolest thing we've done is we've attached a timer
to branching conversation systems.
Jesus.
I mean, we've got to do better than this.
We have to focus a little bit on non-combat AI.
I get in so much trouble with programmers when I say this.
Oh my god.
But we spend so much time figuring out pathfinding
and not having characters fall into holes in the ground
and stuff like that.
And how do we outflank the enemy?
We spend no time on going to the women's bathroom
and having people notice.
People still walk up to me and say, wow, that was cool.
That was 13 years ago.
Have you ever seen a game where a drink was spilled
and a character responded appropriately?
I think not.
Have you ever seen a game where there was a spurned lover
that mattered, that wasn't just a movie
masquerading as a game?
Have you ever seen a game where there was a would-be lover
that you could interact with and actually impact?
Oh yeah, I can make a one, actually.
Okay, anyway, but that's all stupid hard,
and we need to do more of that.
We need to create sets.
That's the next, that's a separate research topic
that I'm hoping someone will do.
We need to start creating sets, not worlds.
I mean, how many games can you just go into every room
and have something interesting happen?
Zero.
Yeah, okay.
There you go.
We need to give players the opportunity
to actually go where they want and do what they want.
If anybody knows how to create a virtual game master,
you know, I mean, it's sort of like putting me
in a box or something, you know, or you in a box.
That would be really cool.
We've been talking about this since 1989
at Junction Point, Looking Glass, Ion Storm, Junction,
I mean, everywhere.
You know, and we still haven't done it.
But, you know, good stories are constructed.
They're not found.
Emergence can only get you so far.
And if we can dynamically modify stories based on what
players want to do, I mean, like, in a good D&D campaign,
you want to screw with the game master.
You know, no, I'm not fighting.
I'm not going to do it.
And the game master actually responds.
I mean, that's what we need to be doing.
And that's what I mean. I want to see a game system that does that okay summing up for all the people who are mad at me now
You know
We've come a long way, obviously.
I mean, I've been talking a lot about the ways in which we're
similar, the ways in which we shouldn't be similar,
and all that.
We've come a really long way.
I remember the days when people would get up on stage here
at GDC and say, story doesn't matter except in movies.
It doesn't matter in games and pornography.
And I haven't heard the words, Warren, you're not allowed to
say the word story ever again in a long time.
OK, so we've made progress.
And we can get partway to where I think we are capable of going as a medium
by borrowing from other media, by studying them and stealing from them.
But we can only go so far. We need some original ideas, tough problems solved.
The ones that I put up here are the ones that I care about.
And I wish I had answers to any of them, but I don't,
which is what's cool and fun.
You have the opportunity, even now,
30 years after the creation of this medium,
you have the opportunity to determine
what it's going to become.
You can change the world, okay?
It's not too late.
And I challenge all of you to beat me
to the solutions to those problems.
Good luck. Thanks.