Hi, I have the pleasure to introduce you to a little session today,
the Impossible Quest Getting a Job in Games.
My name is Masha, and together with this group of industry professionals,
we will try to break it down for you into some practical tips and tricks from our side.
We want to show you seven different angles on how to pursue said impossible quest.
Here are a couple of things that are good to know.
So first of all, this intro and the sessions are prerecorded,
but our speakers will be available in the chat
during their talks.
So make sure to ask a couple of questions,
and we will try to make sure to answer them as good as we can.
This is a micro talk session and that means it consists out of seven talks and each talk is going to be seven minutes long.
A while after the GDC, you will receive an email with a session evaluation sheet and it would be awesome if you could then also evaluate our session.
And for additional information about the micro talks and in general, please check the schedule online.
So we have a broad variety of speakers,
and we are located all around the world.
And they are going to introduce themselves in just a bit.
And all of us come from different backgrounds.
So we can bring our own unique advice to the table.
And our session targets not only freshmen to the industry,
but is also meant as a motivation for people
who might be already settled in a different field
and would love to pursue their passion for making games,
or for game developers of all kinds
that are right now looking for new opportunities.
We're going to cover topics and important topics such as moving,
networking, portfolios, imposter syndrome, knowing your strengths and weaknesses,
how to be brave and many more.
And I'd say let's jump right into it and say hi to Roni.
We see us later.
Hello, I'm Roni, a dialogue engineer and editor at OWN London,
a dialogue production house for video games.
I've worked on games like Desperados 3, Biomutant, Medium and Demon Souls.
I'm here to talk to you about where to start your journey in video games as it's super
important to set yourself up for really good opportunities while in school and even prior
to going to school.
The first step on any journey into a career is knowing which field of study you want to
go into.
This, as a lot of us might know, is easier said than done, and that's totally okay.
it's good that you have just a general idea of where you want to end up. So pick something.
For instance, I knew that I wanted to end up in games eventually, so I picked 3D animation
and art because it really interested me at the time. Character building because it was just
really important to me. But then I ended up going into audio further down the line,
specifically into dialogue production. In a way, it was pretty much the same thing,
but just a different field.
Going off of this though, it's very possible that you'll find out what you want to do further into your studies, so it's okay not to know immediately.
You might even find out possibly 10 years or 20 years down the line into an already established career.
Everyone's path is never going to be linear and definitely going to be different,
but the important thing is that you keep your options open to anything and everything.
I didn't really think that I was going to end up in audio, yet here I am.
The next step after finding what you want to study is where to study, locations specifically.
There are a lot of places around the world for this, but I'll mainly be talking about
the US schools since it's pretty much the only country that I know.
I'll mainly be talking about those.
So during my research into finding schools for myself, I found out that most of the schools
that I could study game design for were on the east and west coast of America.
and I grew up in a really small town in Texas, which if you're not familiar with the geography
of the states is the exact center of the country. So I had to make a choice and take that really big
leap of faith and move to the west coast to continue my education and to find work.
This is something that's very common within the gaming industry, so be prepared to move.
Especially when starting out, you need to consider anywhere and everywhere as a possible location for
yourself and take that leap of faith to get the experience that you need.
Luckily for this day and age, the internet exists, so it'll make the process a bit easier to stay in touch with friends and family.
I've gone ahead and listed out a few US and European schools for you guys, European schools provided by my fellow speakers on this talk.
On top of moving locations for school, it's also really important to know how much you're
willing to spend for schools. Weighing how much you want someone to teach you the hard skills you
need versus how much you're willing to learn on your own. This is university versus vocational.
Available schools like universities can be full-blown with entrance barriers and everything
like that, which is kind of like CalArts or SCAD, to vocational schools like the one I went to in
Paramind.
The former will give you loads of experience and time to create work to put on your portfolio,
collaborate with students outside of your own field, and possibly even internship programs
to help you get a leg up in the field. The latter will be a much, much cheaper and quick way to
learn hard skills, but you likely won't get to collaborate with students outside of your own
field or gain luxuries like internship programs and years to flesh out a portfolio.
costs are no laughing matter, which is why it's important to consider these options.
Schools can be really, really expensive. When it comes to university in the States,
a lot of the ones I came across were about $26k per year.
So definitely look into all the pros and cons for the school that you want to go into.
There are ways to reduce these costs if you do choose to go to university like living
off campus or scholarships even, which can be a good way to reduce the costs.
There are some really, really niche scholarships out there.
One of the ones I've come across in Texas was the Tall Texan Scholarships for females,
which I qualified for because I'm just really tall.
There is also the option to learn on your own, which is a completely viable option and totally okay.
Definitely something to consider as well. The only issue is that you will have to have a lot
of dedication and willpower, I guess, to learn all the necessary things that you need to learn.
There's also, it doesn't give you the
networking availability and stuff like that. If you have any questions on this particular topic,
feel free to simply DM us in any of our social tags we've provided or ask questions in the chat.
Finally, there's what to do while you're at school. Super important,
try out everything and anything while at school. This is the time to get really, really niche.
It'll help you know exactly what you want to do, be that working on indies or triple
A's, story-based games, roguelike games, list goes on.
Or even start your own company, honestly.
The world is your oyster at this time.
And also, while it's really important to keep to your studies and make sure you learn everything
you need to, it's also a great time to be social because this is where your networking
begins.
It's also really important to have friends as well.
But depending on your school or area that you're the world in the of the world that you're in and what it offers you,
these things to be social can be as simple as collaborating on projects at school or signing up for game jams.
One particular really good game jam location or information post, I guess you could say, is itch.io.
They have a whole calendar listed there for all the online game jams that they have going on.
Another thing is you can go to meetups to get to know people outside of your own school
and possibly even meet some folks in the industry already.
As Klaus might mention in his talk already,
it's also really important to get to know your teachers and staff around your school.
because even the humblest of people, people you would never really expect,
could help you get later down the line or even vice versa.
I have plenty of friends who have gotten work through their former teachers or
even vice versa due to just having kept in touch over the years.
Overall though,
this is the time to really explore who you are as a person and begin something really exciting.
So don't let those nerves stand in your way and just help out everyone and anyone because you
never know what might happen. But thank you for listening and I hope to see some of your faces
at future events. Hi, my name is Pasha Camino and we already met at the intro. In my section
I would like to talk about networking through volunteering and the graces of imposter syndrome.
So quickly about me, I'm a game designer in the Berlin-based
indie game studio called Maschinen Mensch.
And when we're not dealing with a pandemic,
I'm also in charge of quite a couple of cool game events,
such as Devolution, Berlin Games Week, Temisphere, Womanize,
Talk and Play, and a bunch of cool game jams.
So as I mentioned, I'd like to focus
on how to build your own small network,
and presumably through volunteering.
So as we heard earlier from Roni, it's not unusual to move to a new town for education or for a new job.
And I know this can be quite intimidating, moving to a foreign place without knowing anyone.
But the good thing is that if you move somewhere for games, there is a pretty high chance that some sort of game scene already exists.
And now it's basically just a little bit up to you to find it and to get yourself involved.
Yeah, and like Reni suggested, you can find cool events at the academic institution of
your choice or through the company that you're working for.
They often already have cool internal offers, such as game jams, open mics, dojos, board
game evenings, and many more things.
Another thing would be game jams.
I love game jams.
They are great.
They are so much fun and they're a great way to network.
They're also challenging and technically challenging, but also a good opportunity to get to know others.
And there are many different game jams with many different topics, so it should be possible to find something that's particularly interesting for you.
And at the end of my presentation, I will also have a link to a sheet with useful resources, for example, lists of game jams, so make sure to check that out.
Yeah, so in general, if you're looking for game-related events,
you can often find cool events on Twitter, Facebook, Meetup,
and Discord servers.
I will also have a list of Discord servers in that link.
And of course, these are just a couple of examples.
Another cool way to look for it is basically
to type into Google game event plus the name of the city
that you're living or working in,
and you'll be surprised about the results.
And if you don't find something there, then maybe in the next larger city located to you.
And if you then found something that's interesting to you,
then also don't hesitate to actually go there.
OK, you managed to find an event that you're interested in,
and you actually went there.
Super well done already.
But I know the feeling very well of thinking
you don't actually belong there.
You don't contribute anything, or you have nothing to say.
But trust me, these events are practically made for you.
The minority of people have any idea of what they're doing.
And we all like certain parts of games or game developments.
And that's already enough to start a conversation.
It's still easy to feel quite lost on an event,
but the more specific advice on how to network
will be brought to you later on by Klaus,
so stay tuned for this too.
And I know what easily makes us feel alienated or uncoordinated
at such an event is not to have a real goal.
And therefore, one of my favorite approaches
to networking is, especially if you're a student
or if you are a junior, is through volunteering.
So find yourself a goal for the evening and one could be volunteering.
Volunteering is great and if you don't know what it is, let me quickly run it down for you.
Basically, almost every event has helping hands in the background of the event to ensure that
everything runs smoothly. Many tasks are taken over by these volunteers at an event, for example,
taking care of the batch booth, the seating, the stage preparation, technical assistance,
and many more tasks.
And at these events, basically everyone can apply to become a volunteer.
And you gain a bunch of nice advantages through that.
So for example, a free conference pass, you meet the speakers,
you get to see the speakers on stage, you get to see behind the curtains of a game event,
which is also pretty cool.
You meet the attendees, and most importantly, you meet fellow volunteers.
So, yeah.
And some of the goals or tasks can be door duty or greeting people, handing out programs,
guiding people to the right stages, handing out badges, and many, many, many more things.
So while you're actually having fun at this event, you're being able to listen to a bunch of talks,
meeting cool people, you're also helping to create a nice atmosphere, you know, a good atmosphere
and making the event run smoothly for everyone and creating a great experience then for everyone too.
Yeah, and even if you're not a volunteer, goals can help you to network, to ease your
mind basically.
For example, a goal could be, I want to talk to one other person tonight.
I want to get one other business card tonight.
Or I want to introduce myself to at least one other person.
And that can help you to move on from there.
So a big thumbs up from my side, volunteering is highly recommended.
Yeah, and how to become a volunteer you ask yourself.
And I think the easiest way to find volunteer opportunities
is to basically type into Google the game event name of your choice
and the word volunteer.
For example, GDC plus volunteer and you'll find something.
And don't let your imposter syndrome stop you.
I know, of course, that many insecurities still apply,
even if you have a goal for the evening,
or you still think you're not important enough
to talk to anyone.
And I know that I'm repeating myself here a little bit,
but it's just so important because...
you definitely belong, okay? So second, you're for sure not the only person feeling like this
tonight and you can presumably even find someone looking as overwhelmed as you do and then tackle
the task together. That could be a fellow volunteer for example. At least that's what
I did a couple of times and it worked out pretty well for me. Another thing is that
please take one step at a time.
You know, take your experiences from one event to the next one and improve from there.
We all start somewhere.
And also, do not be too hard on yourself.
I know it's easier said than done.
And on a general note, keep in mind that developers that you will meet might have produced insanely
cool games, but at the end of the day, they are also just humans.
And trying not to be too starstruck was one of the best advices that I've ever gotten.
And they presumably like games just as much as you do.
And if they do not want to talk to you, they will let you know.
But please do not miss out on a chance to talk to someone that you're truly inspired
by because you think you're not good enough or you have nothing of value to contribute
to that conversation.
So I'd say use some well-deserved confidence, please not too much, and build up your own
network and I'm very sure that you can do it.
So if you then found someone you want to work with,
then you might need a portfolio,
and that will be brought to you by Raymond in the next piece.
So thank you for listening.
Make sure to ask all the questions,
and if you still have more questions,
reach out to me on Twitter.
Thanks again, and say hi to Raymond.
Hello, everybody.
My name is Raymond.
I'm a level designer,
and I have my own indie studio called RoofCant.
Thank you so much for coming to our talk.
I should just introduce you to getting your own network and getting started.
Once you've actually got your network, it's going to be really important to be able to
show people what exactly you can do.
And that's where portfolios come in extremely handy.
So I'm going to give you a number of practical tips on how to get the most out of your portfolio.
Starting off, finishing a game is incredibly difficult.
So if you actually manage to get through the entire game development process,
maybe even release your game on something like itch.io or on Steam,
that's fantastic to show on your portfolio.
It shows that you've actually gone through all of the different phases in game development
and got the experience out of that, on top of being extremely perseverant
for being able to actually complete an entire game.
That's something that not a lot of people just entering the industry have,
so that's fantastic to show on your portfolio.
Secondly, it's going to be really important to show that you can collaborate in a team and work
together with others because very likely that's what you're going to be doing at whatever company
you're applying for. So if you've got any school projects that you've done together with other
students, if you've done any game jams together in a team, that's fantastic to show in your
portfolio as well. Now if you don't have any of this experience working in a team, as has been
mentioned before in this talk, game jams are a fantastic opportunity to get started.
One thing that is really important when you are showing off work that you've done in a team
is to explain what exactly you did. Show what your contribution was. For example,
if you're an environment artist and you're showing a screenshot of the project you did
and they chose a really beautiful looking building and then some random floating cubes right next to
it, people might judge you on the entire thing if you don't explain that you made that beautiful
looking building and some level designer decided it would be fun to place cubes everywhere because
that's what we level designers love to do.
So basically make it very clear what exactly you did on the project and that becomes even more
important when you've worked together with other people of the same discipline. If you work together
with three other environment artists it's even more relevant to show what is yours and what is
the work of somebody else.
Now if your work is a lot less visual, for example you're a game designer, you're a programmer, maybe you're a producer,
it can be really helpful to illustrate your process to show what kind of things you thought about,
what kind of decisions you made throughout the process of creating this project.
This can really give the person who is reviewing your portfolio an idea of whether you have the
kind of game development insight or the kind of problem-solving skills that they are looking for.
that's also really relevant to show work that you've done in your personal time.
Things that you have spent your free, personal, precious time on can really show what motivates
you and especially if that fits with whatever you're applying for, that can be really helpful
to show that you're passionate about this thing you actually are gonna hopefully be doing for money.
Now, all right, I've just shown you a number of things that would be really good to include in
your portfolio, but obviously pick your best stuff. You shouldn't show a whole list of 20
projects that you did out of which some are really good and some are kind of mediocre,
because the person looking at your portfolio is not going to have a lot of time. And so if they
scroll through your portfolio and click on one that happens to not be your best project,
then they're going to judge you based on that. And that would be a shame.
I've actually done this quite wrong myself at some point when I had an interview and
I was asked to walk through my portfolio, kind of show the different types of experiences
I've had.
And I started with a game jam that I did, which, you know, I liked, but it wasn't my
best work because I thought I would build it up to this awesome stuff I really wanted
to talk about.
And then they started asking me critical questions about this game jam that I did.
And I just was like, please, can we move on to the stuff I'm more proud of?
That was a bad idea.
Please do not do that.
So you want to show your best stuff, but you also want to make sure that you really take into account
what exactly you're applying for. If you're applying for AAA, then the people looking at
your portfolio are going to expect a much more specialized skill set. If you're looking for
an indie project, if you're joining an indie team, then they might actually be quite happy
that you can do multiple different things.
What's also really interesting is to consider whether any of the products you've done fit directly into the kind of work that the company you're applying for does.
For example, if you're an artist and you've made work in the style that the company you're applying for uses, that can be really relevant because that lets them see immediately whether you would be a good fit for their team and their kind of projects.
With game designers or programmers, that would be something like working on systems that these companies that you're applying for have used in the past.
Lastly, very important, get feedback. Show others your portfolio, show it to your friends,
to other people that are looking for a job in the industry. Try and get portfolio reviews because
just like a game, your portfolio is never finished. You can keep improving on it and
hopefully at some point you won't need to anymore because you will have a job. Yay!
All right, that was my list.
And now that I have a little bit of time left, I can actually go through one example of my
own portfolio.
So this is a project I did in university.
If you go to the front page of my portfolio, scroll through it a bit, you'll find this.
And what this already shows you is it shows a little bit about what the actual game is,
but it also shows some awards recognition, why you might care, why you might want to
click on this.
and it immediately shows some of that my contribution part that I was talking about earlier
because this was a team of 18 people, more at some point, so I think it's really important
to immediately highlight this is the part that I actually worked on.
Now, if you click on the project page, you're going to see a lot of just kind of standard info.
You see the trailer, you see a description fact sheet.
But if you then go further, you will see my contribution worked out much more.
I show illustrations that I made to kind of highlight how I try to communicate to the rest of the team what I thought this game might look like at some point.
You see prototypes that I made where I tested out whether the mechanics we were trying to work with, whether they would actually work, whether they would be fun.
We actually tried out a bunch of puzzles in that, and I explained that in these few images.
It shows some of the sketches, some of the illustrations that I made.
And showing all of this, obviously, not everybody going through my portfolio is going to read all of this.
But seeing all these different methods that I used, hopefully will give them an idea of my process,
of how I work, and whether I would be a good fit in their team.
So that was my part of this talk.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you want to stay in touch,
you can reach me on Twitter at Roof Guide Games.
And up next, Diana will give you some insight
from her perspective as a recruiter.
Thank you so much for listening.
See you in the industry.
Hi everyone, I'm Diana,
and I welcome you to my talk, Inside Recruiting.
I've been working in the industry for about 80 years now
in varying capacities, one of which is as a recruiter.
And as such, I've seen very different kinds of applications.
Now that Raymond told you about how to set up a great portfolio,
I would like to tell you how we might look at your application.
What else we'd like to know about you, and especially how not to apply.
So the first thing I will usually see is your
email address or username. Please get a proper email address.
Usually the chances for son of a bitch or mafia militia are not very high to be
taken seriously.
And also, if you maybe have multiple email addresses,
check if you are locked into the proper one
before sending out your application.
You might regret it otherwise.
The same thing goes for username.
If you contact me on Discord or another platform, which
actually might happen if I'm looking
for a small indie company, and then you
don't have your real name as a username,
please start the actual chat with, hi, my name is.
A name only consisting of maybe emojis and no follow up to get to know who you actually
are is not what I would like to see on a first base for a job interview.
The next important thing is please talk to me.
Hi is not really an application and please get me this job isn't either.
This is really not a good way to address your recruiter and to introduce yourself to them.
The same goes for almost empty messages or emails.
We are usually asking for certain documents,
and I cannot count the times I receive an application
with almost nothing in there.
So please, say something about who you are,
what you've worked on before, and please
attach the documents and information
we are asking for.
We sure want them.
But how do you start it all?
First off, read the job posting.
Show me that you actually understood what I am looking for and that this is why you are writing to me.
Also, never offer your talent for free, especially not if I'm offering a paid role.
Make sure that you specify what you are applying for.
I might actually have several openings, even for different companies, if we talk indie freelance.
So mention which company and which position you are applying for and introduce yourself with your profession.
On the other hand, of course, you can always send in an unsolicited application.
Maybe you are lucky and we are actually looking for you.
Some companies even offer that option on their website.
Or maybe you find the recruiter on LinkedIn. Just ask them.
Now, after talking about your first approach
and content of your application, I want to stress a very important detail
about the general appearance, which is, please help me understand you.
I might just drop your application if I cannot read it.
And with that, I mean, please don't send in your CV
or application in your mother tongue
if the company is not using that language as a company
language anyway.
Keep in mind that your recruiter might not
understand this language.
So also keep in mind image resolutions.
If you send in your portfolio and your CV.
Make it a PDF. This is always the best thing that you can do.
Try checking your grammar. Very important thing.
A simple spellcheck tool can improve your application immensely.
And these are just the basics of a good application.
But how do you deal with possible rejection afterwards?
First of all, always remember rejecting you rarely has anything to do with your talent
and of course not your person. Except if you send me emojis like the ones you see up there.
Please don't put yourself on a blacklist because word goes around in the industry.
Usually we're looking for something very specific and between lots and lots of applicants
it's very hard to make a decision but it has to be made.
And if you reply, stay friendly, maybe ask for feedback, put yourself out there, apply again.
So now that you know what not to do, here's a short checklist of things to consider before you send out your application.
First of all, what do I apply for? Which position and company are you applying for? Make sure to mention it.
Does the position fit me? And this is always a two-sided thing. Not only does it fit you,
do you fit in? Please consider both.
Whom am I addressing? So either you know who your recruiter or HR person is,
maybe even check LinkedIn, or just keep it completely neutral. You'll be on the safe side.
What do they want to see? And here we are back again at read the job posting. Usually you can
find all required documents in there. A CV, portfolio, references, maybe salary expectation
or the earliest starting date. And those are just some of the possible required informations
that we will ask for. Make sure to hand those in completely. And most of all, don't give up.
Thank you for listening. I hope these tips help you to start your journey into the game industry.
And if you have questions, please throw them in the chat or contact me on Discord or LinkedIn.
And following up, you will hear about Adinda's unconventional dive into this world.
Hello everyone, my name is Adinda, I'm a teacher at the University of Applied Sciences in Groningen
and I also own my own YouTube channel named A-Create where I share different game tutorials
and more information about game development. In my talk I want to share how important it is to
change your own mindset to achieve your goals.
I think it's quite interesting to note that some people told me that they thought that I always had
a great self-esteem and I don't think that's true. I think I just rather did instead of waiting for
the right time. If you are that person that waits for the right time, I'm going to tell you a secret.
It's never the right time to start something new. Our subconscious mind is always creating a lot of
obstacles to let us believe that we are not good enough yet. Next to that we have quite a lot of
blind spots.
which means that we are really bad in judging our own strengths and skills.
I want to inspire with my personal stories all of you to just go for it,
because I believe that you are responsible for your own success.
First, I want to share how I just started with studying game design,
how I find an internship on the other side of the world,
and how I find a job when I was just scrolling on Facebook.
Okay, so it's quite interesting because at secondary school I had the first thought of studying game design.
My friend Brian was already studying it, but I just compared myself to him which was quite bad
because he already made D&D campaigns and a lot of other games and I thought I wasn't as good as him
and my parents weren't that supportive at that time, so I didn't start at that time with studying
instead I studied Chinese.
But in my second year of Chinese, I just realized I really wanted to study game design.
So I went to the Open Day, which was in December, which was a very bad, well, it was quite a bad day
because, well, the trains were late and the venue was almost closed.
but I still went in the building and I just by mere surprise saw Brian sitting there.
He was also very surprised and I told him that I was thinking about studying game design
and he told me that he believed that if I just lock myself up and just made a portfolio
I would be able to get in.
And as he told so, he was right.
I got in and I studied game design.
I'm so glad that at that time I saw Brian there,
because most likely I needed a little push to just go for it,
to have those little extra guts.
So thanks to Brian, I studied game design.
Okay, so I was studying game design and Chinese at the same time,
so I wanted to combine both studies by doing an internship in Taiwan.
I went to the student coordinator and she, well, she shaked her head.
She said, no, you should go to Japan. I was quite confused because
they're total different countries. And, well, she told me if I really wanted to
go, I should just...
do it by myself. So I just applied, I mean I basically write my own emails to
companies in Taiwan and none of them replied me back. So the deadline of the
internship was getting close. So I just thought maybe I should just call them. So
I basically called all the companies in Taiwan that I could find. I was just like
hey hello, I'm Madina, I can speak a bit of Chinese, can you give me a job?
I felt quite stupid and basically they thought I was very cute, but most likely I wouldn't get a job out of it.
Luckily there was a very nice lady who asked me for my email address,
but she thought my email address was quite long, so she asked my Skype instead.
And that was like the golden ticket because as he gave her Skype, I could contact her back.
And I basically got a job at her company, which is great.
I think in this story, it's very interesting to know that the student coordinator wanted me to do
something that all other people already did.
but I just knew that I really wanted to go to Taiwan and I created the opportunity by myself.
And I think it is really good to sometimes listen to what you really want because you know best.
Okay, so I was just scrolling on Facebook and checking some nice pictures of cats and kittens
and then suddenly there was a job offer which sounded very vague but it was in Hong Kong and
I really like that.
But it just asked for a service learning teacher.
I had no clue what it was.
So the first thing I did was just searching on Google
what service learning.
And I just find out that service learning
is a way of teaching that not only benefits the students,
but also the community.
Well, that.
made me think because like quite a lot of games have the same purpose, especially applied games.
So I looked at all the games that I worked on during my studies and I just, we made a total
other portfolio, like a different CV and I made a total different portfolio.
focused on service learning and I succeeded in that because most likely they liked that I really
focused on it and I got the job and I think it was the best job I ever had because I made
design my own courses and teach them as well.
So in this story, it's interesting to know that I thought that the job offer was really strange,
but still too good to be true. Well, sometimes...
It is too good to be true, so sometimes you should just be a little bit curious to just go for it.
Well, that's my motto. And also, if you think that you can't find a job or opportunities in
your home country, just believe me, it is so easy to go to the other side of the world.
Well, not now, but later on it will be easy again. So please don't forget that.
I hope my personal stories inspired you to just change your own mindset and just go for it.
Next up is Jonas who's going to explain how to apply for a job. See ya!
Hey everybody, my name is Jonas Pastors and I'm a junior game designer and junior narrative designer at Gaming Mind Studios.
In my section of the Schmalky Talk, I'm going to go through the application process from the perspective of someone looking for a job
and I'm going to give you general tips, tricks and insights that I learned while looking for my first full-time position myself.
Now, to start off with a quick word about my profile.
I was looking for a job between June and September 2020, right after I'd got my master's degree.
At the time, I had about 10 months of experience within internships and general side hustles,
and I consider my expertise being within NPC design, and I naturally wanted to find a job
to reflect that. Now, to find opportunities to apply to, I mainly went through my network.
I'd created it over the course of my studies, going to conferences, talking to people,
connecting with them, and now I was able to regularly check Facebook, LinkedIn, Twitter,
anywhere where they would share relevant positions.
Another thing I did was to go through lists of companies in the general area I was looking for a job in, being Western Europe.
And what this allowed me to do was to find plenty of companies I'd never heard of before,
but who were still looking to fill relevant positions to me.
Fun fact, I ended up finding my job via this method.
A great resource I can recommend is GameDevMap,
which is a great repository of information about companies, their locations, and generally what they do,
which is really great if you're looking for something specific.
A third way to generate opportunities for me was to get my profile out there.
If you've been studying for a while and if you've been preparing to go into the industry,
it's likely that you have one or two cool projects under your belt.
What I can recommend is to get them out there, put them on sites like itch.io, present them
on your portfolio, anything to get your profile out there and maybe get discovered by a recruiter.
The way I went about this was to write a Gamasutra article based on the research I did for my master's thesis.
The article ended up getting featured and what happened was that two companies approached me to inquire whether I would be a good fit for them.
And even though there was only two opportunities of the 30 applications I wrote, I still consider them to be the most valuable because they approached me.
I didn't have to convince them that I knew what I was talking about.
Still, I ended up writing about 30, 31 applications.
And what you will find after the first couple, that there's a lot of information to keep
track of.
So what I found, it is really important to keep organized.
And I did that in a way by keeping this handy little table with the company name, with the
position, with a link to the position so I could check back later, and the general status
of the application.
And what was especially valuable I found was this last contact column on the right,
because sometimes companies will take a little while to respond to you.
And it's always good to know when they wrote last, so you know whether you can inquire without being too pushy.
What you might also notice is that I applied to a wide range of different positions.
World designer, UX designer, game designer, narrative designer.
And I had to do that because there were very few positions.
that seemed tailor-made for what I could do, so I had to be flexible. Flexible in what I was looking
for, flexible in what I wanted to do, and I was able to do this because during my studies and
generally when looking at games, I didn't just stick to the field I wanted to work in. When I
wanted to do my internship, I wanted to do narrative. The company that I ended up working with
needed game design, so I did game design for them. And now when I was looking for a full-time position,
I wanted to do game design. The company I am with now asked me if I can do narrative,
and I said, yeah, sure. So while you're studying, keep your eyes open for different things adjacent
to what you are interested in and what you're doing right now. Be curious. You might never know
what skill set you acquire at the site will get you a job in the end.
Now, if you've written enough applications, eventually you will be doing an interview.
And what I found worked really good for me was to be engaging, smile a lot, consider it a
nice conversation with a partner, not with someone who has your life in their hands.
You've written enough applications, you will get other interviews with other companies.
So don't stress about it.
Be pleasant to talk to and this already goes a long way.
However, be prepared for tough questions.
Beforehand, consider your own profile,
try to make out weaknesses and try
to come up with answers for tough questions.
Say, if there's a gap in your CV,
think about what you might answer.
What's also important is that you have your own questions
prepared.
Ideally, you have a list.
You don't need to ask all of them, but what that shows is that you have taken the time
to prepare for the interview and that you have taken the time to take an interest in
the company, and this also goes a long way.
Now, what usually followed an interview for me was a design test, and they were usually
between two and 10 days in duration.
What you see on the right is a two-day design test where I had to create some logic in Unreal
Engine.
And what's really important here is that you take the necessary time to complete them,
because the companies are looking for how you do with limited time and limited instructions.
And what's totally cool to do is to ask to postpone it if you don't have the time to
do that right now. The design test on the right I got on a workday, it was during a conference,
I did not have the time to complete it. So I asked them.
hey, is it cool if I do it during the weekend?
They were like, sure, why not?
They hadn't given me the information
that I needed to complete it, so that was totally cool.
I did the design test, and I ended up getting an offer.
So definitely take the time, and if it's not a good time for you,
try to postpone it.
Now, ideally, after a design test, you will get an offer.
You may take it.
You may keep searching.
But ideally, you will have a job at the end.
I hope these tips are useful to you and I hope to see you in the Q&A section.
Hi, I'm Klaus. I've worked as a storyboard artist on games like Hitman,
Risen of Rome and Horizon Forbidden West. In this presentation, I want to talk with you about
creating opportunities. I have six tips for you that are especially important if you're starting
your job hunt but you don't have a network yet. And then I have this one anecdote from my own
career where I did everything wrong.
But before we dive into that, a quick word on opportunities in general.
They are everywhere, even beyond all these well-known international conferences
we like to attend.
It could be a career day at your university with a panel discussion on stage.
It could be a social event that is industry related, like a life drawing class
or a workshop where industry professionals are present.
All these can improve your reach.
Secondly.
Remember, 100% of all jobs are given to you by humans.
Therefore, the more relevant people you know, the better.
Now, for some people, meeting others means a lot of stress, and we don't need that.
This brings me to my first tip.
Think it's not going to happen today.
Odds are, you will not sign a contract right there at the conference,
especially not at your very first portfolio review ever.
Therefore, relax.
The worst thing that can happen to you is that you get no job and you don't have a good time.
So please try to enjoy yourself.
You will be more approachable this way too for others who also seek those new connections.
Really, we are all there to network after all.
So what do I want to aim for?
My tip?
Go for the silver medal.
Imagine the decision is already made,
because unless you're a genius newcomer,
you will not get the first most awesome open position or gig.
Instead, aim at the second job the producer or editor
needs to fill.
But Klaus, how do I get in line for that?
By building a network of peers.
So seek business partners, not clients.
Your peers and colleagues are the most important part of your network.
It's not only about potential clients.
Use any opportunity to connect with your peers.
For example, while waiting in line for that job interview.
Ask them how they got into the industry and look at their portfolios.
If the vibe is right, see if you can get a group together for dinner.
It might even be fun because in the end we're all nerds, right?
They are not your competition.
And these people can become your friends or allies.
Companies give away jobs.
Nobody can steal them from you.
If they get the job you wanted, they were just a better fit.
And you all of a sudden have a colleague or friend at your dream company.
So when the time comes that this company has more jobs to give away,
who do you think gets the call?
They call the silver medal guy.
This is how I got my first geek drawing Transformers comics for IDW back in the day.
True story.
Point number four, be a force for good at the conference.
Be present.
Interact at a panel.
Sit first row, take notes, make eye contact, ask a question.
Always good, help somebody that is under stress,
which is a common thing at a conference.
Hold the door.
If they look lost, help them to their meeting room.
Lend somebody a pen or an aspirin.
Be giving.
Just don't be obtrusive
and don't expect anything back right there.
This way, the second time you bump into each other,
maybe a year later at the next conference,
they will remember you fondly
and that's where things get moving.
So when you made it this far,
especially with potential clients,
Get their business card.
Again, get their business card.
Don't worry about getting your card into their hands.
Assume that you will need to be able to reach them,
not vice versa.
Bonus tip, scribble notes directly on their card
after the meeting.
Stuff like location, occasion, talking points,
because when you contact them after the conference,
you want to remind them how they know you.
Anything can be important if you want to recreate the moment you met them in their minds.
And that brings me to my most important point today.
Everybody counts. I know everybody wants to get a minute with a big CEO or this superstar artist
after the panel on stage. Please look beyond that one opportunity. Talk with other people
in the line. They could be your future colleagues who might refer jobs to you.
talk with the VIP's friend or spouse right next to them or their personal assistant
or volunteer convention organizer because first it's just totally impolite to ignore them and
second they might have more industry insights and connections than you can see at first glance.
They will appreciate being seen and they will have a very good reason for being there just as you do.
Literally everybody can be important. And this last advice brings me to my unfortunate
anecdote where I did everything wrong. It was in 2001. I was in America for the first time
and I attended San Diego Comic Con in California. I was already published in Germany and had what I
thought was a high standard for comics. I wasn't into serious action comics, realistically drawn
with high-end computer coloring. So I was walking by a not very exciting looking booth which was
manned by someone who looked like your typical tall beardy comic book guy. Pretty unassuming.
and he tried to sell me his comic. It was called Battle Pope.
It was in black and white, tongue in cheek and definitely not high-end superheroes.
I wasn't impressed by the book.
I dismissed the publishing effort and him, the guy who wrote the book,
and I indeed didn't ask for his business card.
I still bought an issue of his books out of courtesy
and found it surprisingly entertaining when I read it on the flight back to Germany.
I never saw the guy again.
Later on, it turns out, he did another black and white independent comic, which was a bit of a success.
It was called The Walking Dead. You might have heard about it.
And then he also did a superhero comic, even in color, it's called Invincible,
which is now streaming as an animated series on Amazon Prime.
Yes, I completely ignored the legendary writer and creator Robert Kirkman.
So please be nice to everybody, because...
Everybody can be an important contact in your future career network.
With a bit of luck, I will see you at our next business opportunity.
Thanks for listening.