Hi, my name is Jason Grimblatt, and I work on a game called Caves of Qud that's currently
in Early Access.
Caves of Qud is an open-world, science-fantasy, roguelike, RPG hybrid where you chisel through
a layer cake of thousand-year-old civilizations.
We've been doing a lot of experimentation with procedural generation, particularly around
narrative elements like backstory and world history.
In my talk this year, I'll be showing off the results of one experiment where we procedurally
generate in-game books using Markov chains.
You may have seen Markov chains on the internet used to generate funny or surprisingly poetic
text from a corpus of source text.
In case of CUD, our corpus is every bit of text in the game, about 40,000 words, plus
some 19th century textbooks that we mix in.
Beyond just generating text, we also insert bits of world state into the Markov chain,
so that the generated text contains secrets about the world, and you could research lore
at an in-game library.
So if you're interested in procedurally generated text, come on by.