All right.
Cool.
Well, I've got to say, first of all, that I'm really stressed
because this is not really what I was expecting.
I was expecting a much smaller crowd.
Thank you, thank you.
Hello, my name is Joseph Snabria,
and I'm an art director and a concept illustrator working
in the entertainment industry.
And for the past 23 years, I've been fortunate to have worked
at some great studios throughout my career,
developing some epic intellectual properties.
And in recent years, I've begun freelancing,
expanding my work into film, commercials,
and a variety of projects.
Thank you for coming to my talk, which is The Passion Project,
a Catalyst to Creativity and a Cure for the Stagnant.
It's a talk about how my passion project has impacted my work.
and why having a passion project can be one of the best things for an artist looking to
grow.
So when I was approached to speak at GDC, I asked, what would they be interested in me
talking about?
So the response was, maybe I could talk about my experience working as a freelancer.
And I thought, sure, I could probably talk about freelancing.
But most of the time...
folks are interested in how I got there.
So I thought I would focus on those opportunities,
on how those opportunities came to be,
and talk about what I did to expand my work to other fields.
Now, this is a conversation I've had numerous times
over the years with artists.
usually who are trying to break in,
but there's also artists who have been
in the industry for a while
and have a few years of experience,
but they're frustrated with their current situation.
They either wanna go into leadership,
perhaps work on another type of game,
or they just kinda feel like they've been casted in a way.
So I thought this would be a great forum to cover this subject and talk about how one
passion project led to a number of great opportunities.
And so thinking about how things have gone for me in the past, I realized that most of
my achievements and gains over the year, they stem from a personal interest in the work
that I put into pursuing those passions on my own time.
And over the years, I've noticed this has also been the case for a few artists.
Like I've met artists at DreamWorks, a story artist,
and he had an interview with DreamWorks,
and really what got him the job was his personal comic book
that he had been working on.
It's not really what he was being hired for.
but they were impressed by the passion and what drove them.
And essentially, that's what people are looking for.
You want passionate folks.
You're not looking for folks who can do a job.
And I think that's one thing that a lot of students miss.
Or folks who are frustrated with their situation,
they say to themselves, well, I could be doing that.
Well, that's not really the point.
The point is, are you passionate about it?
So this talk is not just about passion project,
it's really about how I as an artist adapted
and rediscovered passion,
and how that passion led to unexpected projects,
and connected me to a new audience, like you guys.
And also made me a better and more effective visual artist.
For me, I was always working on some personal art,
but the work I put into it was sporadic,
and the results were kind of lackluster.
Not having any structure and not really clear
on what I was really interested in or passionate about,
it was difficult to really make any progress
on developing skills.
A little background information.
Over the years, obviously, roles and teams
have really changed a lot.
So I've done just about everything on the art team.
I started as an animator, then did backgrounds,
then character art, then technical art.
and then eventually lead artist and then art director,
and then that's when I started doing concept art.
So the concept art is more of a recent thing.
So going back, what I really needed to do
was to change my whole attitude
and approach to personal art.
What I needed to do was just draw what I was inspired by
and focus on what interested me at the moment
rather than chasing fads,
mechs and all the things that may be hot at the moment.
Then I started thinking in terms of a project,
rather than just work.
So I can manage it a lot better and create an overall plan.
Ironically, I was really good at organizing big teams
and keeping them motivated,
and making sure that we're always making progress,
because these games are very expensive to make.
But when it came to my own work, that just didn't happen.
So, these two things working together.
Well they basically made me a lot more consistent with my efforts.
So what I learned was honest hard work done consistently over time, that would be the
thing that would greatly ramp up my skill.
It wasn't the tech, sorry I know this is GDC, but it was just consistent work.
And I wasn't doing all-nighters, I wasn't just basically pushing myself into the grave,
I just tried to be consistent.
Now, like most artists, I started sketching when I was a little kid.
And I would sketch comic book heroes, space rockets, just everything.
But as I grew up, I found myself sketching less and less.
Now this kind of happens naturally.
As kids, we just do whatever.
Nobody cares.
And as a result, you're not self-conscious
and you don't edit yourself.
You're just enthusiastic.
But as you grow up, you start to realize,
especially in my experience,
that sketching maybe is not a good thing
you should be doing.
My dad got really pissed off one day
when he found out I had filled up my notebooks
with all these sketches of Spider-Man.
And so that kind of like always made me feel like
maybe I'm not doing something right here.
So it would be years later that that passion for sketching would reignite.
Now, I use sketches to help develop and refine ideas.
Oops, sorry.
And I would sketch events and record the moments.
And then I would start to explore ideas and just have fun filling the pages.
basically learning how to improvise.
So this image here is one of those Inktober sketches,
just started in one, not in one corner,
but one spot and just kind of built out.
And this kind of happens really
with all the hard work that you put into it.
All the studying you're doing,
you don't need to have the reference in front of you,
but I've done lots of environment sketches and paintings,
and that's what.
allows me to improvise, just like a jazz musician, let's say.
They study their scales, they know their instrument inside
and out.
Once they've got the mechanics down,
they're free to just kind of express themselves.
And I think that's the main thing here.
And naturally, then I extended my studies
to lighting and color.
This is a subject I was really interested in,
but I just never had the opportunity, or I guess
made the time to study it.
And so I would take any opportunity to practice,
and as I improved, so did my passion for sketching.
So this is something I would do like lunchtime.
Because I'd done a few years of painting outdoors,
I was comfortable being able to do it in that time frame.
And because I was doing it more often.
you get better, you get better, you have more fun.
It's just like a video game, you know,
you can't just go straight to level 50
and decide that you're gonna be successful
or really be realistic in those expectations.
You have to start small and build up.
Now the project, well that took some time to figure out.
And that was until I visited Stuart Engy's bookstore,
which is down in Torrance, California, for the first time.
Now, for those who aren't familiar,
this is a bookstore that specializes in illustration,
imported graphic novels,
and collectibles from the animation industry.
And one of the things that they carry
are the convention sketchbooks.
For those who don't know what those are,
these are small, self-published books,
usually by the artist,
and they're sold at conventions.
that would be my passion project.
So I made it a goal to make my own sketchbook
and sell them at the CTN Animation Expo.
This is basically, CTN Animation Expo is kind of like,
think of Comic-Con's Artist Alley meets GDC.
But it's mostly feature and television animation
and some game studios
and a bunch of artists from around the world.
In doing this, I learned a lot.
And yes, I did struggle for a bit, but I made it.
I got it done, and I was there for that first year.
And I'd made it a goal each year to put one together
and show up at CTN.
And lo and behold, three years later,
Stuart NG swung by my desk, and he picked up volumes two
and three.
And so.
I made my goal to try and get that work into his bookstore.
And so what I learned from that
was having a definitive goal and a product
really helped me fund my efforts
and get the most gains out of my time.
Now, my early experiences were not always positive
like I shared with you before with my dad.
And later on, like I said, I drew less and less,
and part of that was the frustration of blank pages.
I'm sure this is something that we all can relate with.
And the other thing that kind of really frustrated me
a lot of times was I would just have a poor start.
It's kind of like what I was just saying.
It's like, you're not thinking, you're just kind of jumping
and you're like, I'm gonna do a crazy sketch.
Like, well, it's crazy and nobody gets it.
So in general, I didn't really understand
how sketchbooks helped the bigger picture.
I remember I got, in school, they asked me to carry one,
but I never filled it up,
and it was just something that I didn't understand.
My thought on the whole art process
was that the real work was in the painting,
or the 3D rendering, the details, and all that stuff.
That was until I got this book as a present.
And it really changed my view of sketchbooks.
Now, it's a collection of sketches from Pablo Picasso.
And over the 70 years of his career,
he created 174 sketchbooks.
And this is a collection of some of those sketches
from his book.
Believe it or not, that one in the back there,
I think he did it at like 12 years old or 14 years old.
And you can see in Barcelona, it's
insane what he was doing as a teenager.
And so what was really striking to, for me,
flipping through this book was,
it was the first time I really kind of flipped through
basically an artist's lifetime of his work.
And a sketchbook is really an intimate view
of that person's work.
So for the first time, I really realized
the impact sketching has over an artist's lifetime.
I'm a strong believer that art is a lifelong endeavor.
This is not something that happens, you know,
a year, a few years in school, and then you're an artist.
Like, it's constantly evolving.
And then I saw this movie.
This is a movie about Robert Crumb,
and there's a scene where he's lamenting
about which sketchbook is he gonna pick
to trade for a chateau in France.
I was just floored when I saw that because then I saw the value not only artistically
but monetarily a sketchbook could have.
Now I started to think about sketchbooks in a different way.
Now when I'm talking about sketching, in my mind, and this is how I kind of try to approach
it.
It's really including drawing from life,
doing visual research.
This could be like drawing armor or suspension for a vehicle
just so that you can build up this knowledge.
It's also the process of ideation,
taking an idea and really expanding it as far as possible.
If you guys caught the presentation for Horizon,
all the examples that they were showing
where they were just kind of trying to figure out
the exoskeleton, that's a good example of that.
So what's the big deal?
Well, I believe that sketching is like muscle building.
It's training and being disciplined
that are essential to getting good results.
Now, observational sketching is like
taking that to a higher level.
And I think this is a good example
because bodybuilders or folks who train,
They don't train 24 hours, they don't train for 16 hours,
they have very specific schedule,
but they practice with intensity.
So it's not about time, it's about your focus.
So you get faster gains, less time,
and really, you don't need much.
You just need a notebook and a pencil, maybe gouache.
And so when I'm talking about observational sketching,
it's kind of a blanket term in my mind
to plein air painting, which is when you're going outdoors
and you're painting from life.
It also includes live drawing and urban sketching,
which is kind of similar to plein air,
but it's a little bit more of like everything
that's happening in front of you,
like people and all that stuff.
Now, observational sketching
is just a really robust exercise
where the hand and the eye and the mind
are really working together.
You're going to observe the scene,
and you're going to be studying it
for an extended amount of time.
And because of that, you're going to learn and catch
what a lot of folks fail to notice.
The lessons that you're learning out in the field
give your work authenticity and confidence.
This is down on Laguna Beach, summer day, done in oil.
And then what you're going to be doing is analyzing.
Really trying to understand all the structures and the surfaces,
but most importantly, trying to figure out how they all correlate to each other.
And then you're editing.
You're emphasizing some things and omitting when it's appropriate,
being selective.
I think one of the things I've learned as a painter
is that it's more important what you leave out rather than what you put in.
And that's because there's really not much time
to render everything that you're trying to convey.
So focus.
All that really changed my whole mindset to sketching.
And it would greatly impact me.
And it would allow me to get comfortable
with the whole creative process
and get into a creative flow.
So here's a good example where I'd been painting
down on Laguna Beach for maybe two, three years.
So I kind of,
I'd understand the rock formations and how things looked.
And so now when I go and sketch it,
I don't have to study that photo in front of me.
I know this already.
And so I would spend maybe like five minutes
for each one of those, five, 10 minutes.
But I also learned a few other benefits.
Most notably, you connect with others.
You're sketching in a public setting,
so you're probably gonna meet lots of folks,
and a few of them are gonna be fellow artists.
I'm here because probably more,
for more reasons because of all this private work that I've been doing, this personal work.
I'll give you another example. So one of the paintings I was doing, Laguna Beach,
on that day it was a cloudy day and the lighting wasn't going to change too much,
so I was feeling kind of confident. I wanted to push myself up and do something a little bit
challenging. So I wanted to do a city scene and
I ended up having to paint because of the view.
I had to be right on the sidewalk,
basically like the boardwalk down Laguna Beach.
Very intimidating to have hundreds of people
just walking by as you're working on a painting.
But, ironically, a manager from a gallery
was walking by and saw my work,
and that's how I ended up getting into a gallery in Laguna.
So it's just an example of how, by sharing your work,
lots of things can happen.
Now,
In the studio, I could also initiate collaborations and kickstart discussions.
So what I mean by that is lots of times you would walk into conversations where designers
or tech are.
debating or discussing things with artists.
And a lot of times what I would find out
is that they're really saying the same thing,
but they believe they're saying different things.
And the only way you can kind of make sure
that they're all on the same page and kind of kill that
is to just start sketching.
Sketching something on the whiteboard or on a sketchbook.
And so being able to sketch those ideas quickly
and help move the conversation forward,
that would turn out to be a valuable skillset
for art directing and visual development.
And soon I would discover how other opportunities
would discover me, or I would say,
or sorry, I would discover other opportunities,
or they would discover me.
And that's all thanks to social media.
It's how it's connected us all,
and by sharing my work, I've made it possible
for other companies to find my work.
So just post it.
Don't be shy.
Then the other thing I realized was,
rather than using solicitation tools like mailing lists
or going through LinkedIn, connecting with folks
and bugging them for a job,
I really just focused on marketing my work,
sharing the work on various platforms
and posting on a regular basis.
And lo and behold, eventually I started getting calls
and emails and work inquiries, negotiating rates and terms.
Well, that would be much easier in that scenario.
And then I started to really learn a lot about my audience,
about my work, and about myself.
So a few things I wanna share with you
that I've learned along the way
is that rough sketches equals viewer participation.
So I'm gonna give you an example.
First time I was really doing sketches for production
was for Fallout New Vegas.
Prior to that, I'd only really shared sketches
if they were really heavily cleaned up.
And well, one day,
Chris Avalon, he's one of the big designers
down at Obsidian, or was there,
he was the project director for one of the DLCs
that we were working on.
And so he drops in my office,
and around that time,
I used to be really obsessed with perfection.
Everything had to be perfect,
and I think a lot of that was just insecurity.
And so I was terrified to have him check out my rough sketches.
I was not ready to present them.
But to my surprise and delight, he
didn't wrinkle his brow with frustration and confusion.
Instead, he was excited and gleaming.
And so what I saw was that there was enough structure
to the sketches that he could read them,
but a good deal left undefined that he would then
project into those blanks.
Just like a Rorschach test or those inkblot tests
that psychiatrists use.
He saw what he was hoping to see now.
And that meant that he was not just a viewer,
but he was a participant in the story and the meaning of it.
So what I learned was, leaving some things undefined,
that can make for a much more interesting image
for the viewer.
My second lesson is that the concept is the biggest thing,
not the design.
Great ideas that are cheap,
that's what people are looking for.
So I'll give you an example.
There's this company called The Mill in New York.
They do a lot of commercials.
They're a visual effects studio.
And this was something I did for them
for a Nestle Hot Pockets ad.
They needed a wind tunnel
that a bunch of college kids constructed themselves.
And so what I learned with working the director was,
we created a great relationship.
because I could deliver a bunch of ideas real quickly.
And so what I learned right away was that the sketches
were his preferred way or their preferred way
of finding the right design for a job.
A poor design won't be saved by a great render.
So it's really important that the idea is solid.
Third lesson, narrative.
No surprise that the concepts that I would post
that had a narrative component,
well they would do a lot better.
And I think like this is an example where
I can put in little things that aren't
that big or complicated and they can pull your eye in more.
So the fact that everybody is looking away from the camera
except two people.
that kind of creates moments that people can kind of lock into.
And so what I'm trying to do is retain your attention as long as possible,
and by doing so, I think you're going to be, you're going to remember it for sure,
but you're drawing folks in, and that's essentially what we're doing in games.
We don't want people just to kind of, I get it,
you want them to pick up the controller and run around that world.
Now, that effect would get magnified when you put one image next to another.
So.
Part of my process at some point was just to create
random formats or ratios for my panels
because a lot of times I would see that
that would influence or inspire me to do different sketches.
Now, none of these sketches relate to each other.
They're just all random ideas
that I'm trying to fill in in a couple hours
so that I can see if anything in there
is worth pursuing and doing a full render.
So before I'm gonna spend a few days
working on a high-end illustration,
I want to make sure that the one that I pick
is one of the strongest ones that I can come up at the moment.
Now, like I said before, I've had this conversation
with lots of folks over the years, usually at CTN,
and when they see the work,
I hear a few common things from folks.
I'm not talented.
Well, the truth is talent is built, it's not inherited.
And others are gonna judge your work differently than you do.
So, just allow yourself the time to learn and have fun.
I think you will be surprised.
The other one I hear a lot is, I don't have time.
Well, truth is, everyone has time.
But we just struggle managing it.
Adapt and scope your work so it works with what you have.
So, I think someone was mentioning before
that they just try to do like,
They were going to do a massive game,
and it was just one student who was still in college.
And so the thing is just to keep it simple,
you don't have to do a whole lot.
And I don't have money.
So that's why I focus on sketches and simple materials,
because really, this is how you can develop your skills.
Money is one of those things where it's easy to resolve.
And so the time is really your biggest cost
because you can't buy more time.
And really, all you need is just good materials
and the equipment to be simple and effective.
You don't need it to be fancy or elaborate.
Exquisite work can be done and has been created
with limited palettes.
You'd be very surprised.
Zorn is a good example.
He used three colors and he would create amazing paintings.
So just remember it's the idea that really matters,
not the rendering or the technique.
At least that's been my experience.
Now, you're gonna wanna avoid points of friction.
So I think, or at least I believe,
at least in my experience,
that balancing that passion with life
is just part of the process.
You gotta figure it out.
I can't give you a formula.
Each one of you has a specific...
goal and obviously you're going to have roadblocks.
So what you need to do is just figure out how to get around those things.
In my case,
a lot of times why I wouldn't do work is because it was just too
too much in the way, like, oh, I got to put everything together before I can go out
and the lighting is going to change so I won't go out today.
So what I started doing was just basically packing things up.
I also changed my gear.
I used to have one of those French easels, which is like 20 pounds.
And I'm like, no, I don't want to go out painting today
because I just I don't want to carry all that stuff.
So I just simplified everything, shrunk everything down.
So it's hanging on a hook.
Backpack's all loaded.
I can just grab it and take off at any moment.
So what I started doing was, I would sketch with pencil or pen
when I just needed to work fast and light.
If I was traveling, like I am here,
I'll take a gouache kit with me.
It's really small and it's super light, easy to travel with.
But if I have the time and the opportunity,
I'm going to go out with oil because it's the one medium
that I prefer the most.
And also, I'll spend more time.
These are some of my favorite ways of brainstorming that I want to share with you guys because
ultimately I want you guys to be able to walk away and hopefully be able to do some of these
things.
So I call this the 360, it's probably a better term for it.
Basically I'm taking one idea and I'm creating as many designs as possible.
And then I'm going to see what stands out of that group.
I think one of the things that kind of helps with something like this is that the negative
spaces around the areas as you're filling them, they can influence the design.
So some characters are really stretched out, others are more square and bulky.
And then when you're trying a theme, you can experiment different things and borrow from
one design and try a different take on it.
And so what that's gonna allow you to do
is really kind of iterate and iterate on a fast level,
but without starting from scratch each time.
I call this the repurposed design.
Basically, you're inheriting something from something else.
Now, in this example, what I did was,
there's a sketch that I'd done on the back of that page,
and it was a marker that's bleeding through.
using those marks, I'm kind of just riffing off of it
and using it to influence what I'm going to draw on top of that.
And that's just to get me started.
So, the other one's a little bit more complicated.
This one I borrowed from Andrew Loomis.
He has a book called Creative Illustration.
I really highly recommend it for you guys.
And so in this example, you have a frame, a red square.
And what I'm doing is I'm running a blue line.
It's kind of faint, but it's going from the top left corner
down to the right bottom corner.
And just about.
near the halfway mark, but not exactly.
I'm trying to stick it to a quarter to a third.
There's a vertical line that's being drawn
from the top to the bottom.
Now where those two lines meet,
now I draw a horizontal line.
Now what that's giving me is four squares,
or sorry, rectangles, but they're all different sizes.
As I continue doing that,
it's gonna subdivide the frame even more.
And so what
the result that I get is, and the reason why I use this,
it's gonna give me non-uniform sizes for all these shapes.
I'd shown my work to a few folks,
and one of the things that was kind of common
was that my compositions were poor
because I was using the same shapes without realizing.
So this gave me a framework, not a rigid one,
but one that I could kind of just have there,
so that way I would avoid that bad habit
of creating all these even-sized things.
Once I have those primary shapes in place,
well then I can spend the time to render things out
because I know that the composition is a good design,
or at least that's the hope.
So I would like to conclude this
with a quote from Vincent van Gogh.
In spite of everything, I shall rise again.
I will take up my pencil,
which I have forsaken in my great discouragement,
and I will go on with my drawing.
Thank you so much.