All right.
Welcome, everyone.
I hope you had a good show so far.
Just a couple of standard reminders.
Remember to fill out the evaluation that
gets sent to you after this, because I'm
going for that high score.
And also turn down the volume on your phones.
But I am Sveit Kervall.
You can pronounce that any way you want.
I come from Reykjavik, Iceland, born and raised.
And I've.
Been working for CCP, an independent gaming publisher,
for the last 13 years.
Started in customer support, and now I'm
a lead community developer.
So the community business has been around for almost as long
as gaming, not quite.
It, of course, came along with the internet,
and it's changed a lot in the last few years
or so with the advent of powerful community content
creators in the community, and social media, obviously.
Community people used to often be back in the days like volunteers, used to work from home.
Then they got on boarded but were often stored behind those boxes of last year's t-shirts
and weren't given much thought to.
But the job has grown and there's still, I believe, in the business a lot of possibilities for community people to grow professionally.
So community teams have become a bigger asset and it's very important.
We at CCP believe that it's important to allow community people to grow and take on bigger challenges.
And to do that you sometimes have to prioritize and look at how you do things.
Rowing is fun and it builds a strong back, but it's hard and sails just get you further.
Plus you can do other things along the way like that gentleman with the book.
So a bit of background just so you understand some of the things that I'm talking about
and why they have worked for us.
I come from another world, a world of 7,500 unique solar systems that you can explore
and conquer, a world of boundless freedom, self-reliance, cooperation, commerce, conflict.
It's a very interesting world and it's inhabited by hundreds of thousands of space experts.
This is a world where only the strong survive.
I am, of course, talking about EVE Online, the infamous space sci-fi MMO that's been
around for 13 years and it's been in constant development.
And just to sum up the three things that I think make EVE unique,
it's that it has this single shard design, or there's no shards,
it's just a single universe where no matter where you are in the world,
you enter one world.
And it has time zones and all kinds of nationalities and cultures and stuff like that.
So it's very interesting like that.
It has player-controlled manufacturing and industry, which means that almost everything in the game that you need, whether it's weapons,
modules, or ships, or ammo,
it's all made by players from raw materials harvested by yourself or other players.
And then all these things are moved around and traded on a very robust market that follows the laws of supply and demand.
So there's a lot of
cool things you can do.
And of course, speaking of cool things you can do, there is very much freedom in the game.
There's few rules, no hand-holding, and you are thrown into this merciless universe
where you have to band up with other people to survive and do big things.
EVE is not an easy game. It's a game where something like this happens and where people
actually can look at this picture and tell you what's happening in much detail. I'm not
one of those people, but I can tell you some broad context stuff. This is from the biggest
battle we've ever had on the server. It was fought by over 8,000 people over the course
of 21 hours, destroying something like $300,000 in assets.
It was long enough so people could go to sleep and go to work and then come back and it was still going.
Pretty cool stuff. And there's people that organize the armies that go into these battles.
They set up the fleets with the right weapons and right compositions, organize logistics, reinforcements.
Then you have the generals that plan longer term campaigns, politicians, diplomats,
who are planning conquests and wars and making peace with these guys and these guys
so you can make war on the other guys. It's very, very, very interesting.
We have some fairly smart and dedicated people in the community as a result of all this freedom of enterprise.
So the EVE Online community, it is a relatively mature community.
It has a wide age span.
We have like young teenagers up to very old pensioners, but the average age is around 31, which is higher than many games.
Around 40% have some sort of an IT background.
It's a fairly educated community,
and a lot of technological backgrounds in the community,
according to surveys we've run.
So we have a lot of people that like to solve
complicated problems and are very good at it.
So, odds are that the person fixing your computer at work
is an Eve player.
So, be nice to them.
We have players from all nations almost colluding or colliding.
It's a very interesting environment because, like I said, with the time zones, you have to have friends in every time zone to cover your assets,
and you have to attack your enemies strategically.
You get some nationalities, like they play together because they speak a common language.
There's all sorts of dynamics that are very interesting when you don't shard up your community and divide them by what they have in common.
But community teams are, you know, we know the story.
Being on a community team is really hard.
There's so much to do.
You have to keep track of so many things.
It's like you have the world's weight on your shoulder.
I was like 6' 5' before I started this job.
But, I mean, there's a wide focus to take care of.
You have to know what everyone in the community is doing,
you have to know what everybody in the company is doing,
and you have to make sure that the communication is flawless
and effortless and productive between those groups.
And, I mean, we can call ourselves, like, bouncers,
gardeners, herders of cats, reporters, shrinks, whatever.
But the thing is that we have only a limited time.
And we have to take care of how we use it.
And I believe in sharing the load of doing all the things
that need to be done with the community
and with the rest of the company as possible.
Kind of harnessing the wind, if you will.
So if we take a look at the EVE Online community team,
we have an in-house team of seven people
that take care of EVE Online.
The broad scope is communication, localization,
community support.
That involves all project events and all kinds of things
that go on.
So.
We call ourselves community developers, and we come from all over the place.
And I want to start by introducing you to Thomas Meissen.
As you can tell, he takes care of the German community
and moved from Germany to work with us.
And as you can tell from his stern gaze,
he is called the Eisenfaust, which
means the iron fist in German.
And that's because he takes care of our army of volunteers.
So he has a multiplier on himself, essentially.
We have volunteers that do a lot of cool things for us.
They call themselves the Interstellar Service Department
and it's a team of around 100 people.
And I'm going to talk a little bit about the three top teams.
Star is a team that helps people in-game, runs in-game channels,
they moderate, they make sure everybody's behaving, and they help people.
One thing they do that's really cool is meet and greets.
We give them actual sheets with the names of players that have joined in the last...
A few weeks, last couple of weeks.
And they go talk to them and we see that the retention rate for people that are contacted
and given resources and help and someone to go to if they need help is much higher.
It's like dozens of percent on average.
It's a huge increase in retention because EVE is a complicated game and people need some help and guidance.
Then we have the Bug Hunter team which is loved by our QA people because they
Help filter out early bug reports, do a lot of testing.
They are trusted with some limited dev roles and have access to closed test servers so they can do testing and early filtering.
And they do a lot of good work for us and many of them have been around for a long time and are very smart people.
And we have the forum moderator crew, which is my favorite because I don't like moderating forums.
I'd like to be away from that if I can.
They have some limited roles, they can't ban people, but they can do all other moderation and they can escalate difficult issues to us.
And we back them up as we can. But this relieves us of a lot of work.
And the way this is set up, because we have only one person managing all these people internally.
Although they do talk to other developers and stuff, it's like one person is responsible for the whole thing.
So we need some structure.
The Space Army has a ranking system.
You enter as an Ensign, you become a Lieutenant, and you can work your way up the ranks
and get increasing responsibility and access to all sorts of training and cool stuff.
We aim to make this team as self-reliant as possible, but no more than that.
There has to be access to developers.
We deal primarily with the top people in the organization,
and they then filter down knowledge and instructions to the rest of them.
Each brand is led by a vice-admiral, which is typically someone who's been with us for many years
and is very trusted and very smart.
The point of the system, I mean, it has to be self-reliant if it's supposed to work as a team that takes the burden off us, so we don't have to mind it continuously.
The code of conduct that they abide by is a modified version of the one that CCP staff have, so they're held to a fairly high standard and they live up to it amazingly.
They do a lot of stuff for us, and we in turn, you know, we give them opportunities and an outlet for doing cool things that they like to do.
Just to give you an idea of how much work they do for us, it's 1,200 hours volunteered per month.
This is like a rough number from last year's averages.
200 hours of forum moderation alone, so you can imagine how much time that just relieves from like a team of seven that's in-house that can then focus on different things.
And it relieves itself like 90% of the daily moderation,
which is very good.
So we have more time for that professional growth I talked
about, more impactful projects that have to be done in-house.
All of this is important, but it doesn't
have to be done in-house.
So there's a lot of benefits of this.
I mean, obviously, it is time saved.
But also, the fact, what I believe,
is that your in-house team that has
to work with the community on a lot of positive things,
building things, has to spend less time in an environment
where they focus a lot of time on the negative 2%
to try to create problems on the forum, bend the rules.
Editing bad words on a forum is not the most entertaining thing
you can do.
So it puts us in a more positive.
And then you've got to think, like, why do people want to volunteer for EVE Online?
I mean, why do they take time out of their day to do this?
These are people that are above average interested in EVE Online.
They're absolutely enthusiastic about it and love it, and they are very good at it,
and they like to help other people.
The program attracts people that just selflessly help people in real life.
I mean, these are people that would help an old lady across the street,
or upload one of those mysteriously appearing torrents that none of us have ever downloaded, all that stuff.
People that just do things because they can and they want to do something for other people.
And of course it's fun to be close to the company that's making the thing that you love.
If you've been involved with EVE Online for a long time, it's fun to be close and see what's happening.
They sign an NDA, they sometimes get advanced information and stuff like that.
So it's good.
And we do actually hire quite a lot of people from the pool of ISD because we get to know them and see what they can do.
And they become trusted persons.
And we don't want people to join because of that, because we don't want them to focus on the job at hand,
but it happens quite a lot. And actually four people on the community team now are former ISD, which is amazing.
There's perks and prestige, of course.
There's free accounts, they play for free, obviously.
They get tickets to official events.
Store credit for every hour put in, so their hours are tracked,
so they earn store credit and then they can redeem that for merchandise from the EVE store.
Or, if they just hang on to it long enough and put in enough hours,
will actually just redeem their credits for a flight to Iceland for FanFest
and a stay in a hotel and everything.
So they can have a free trip to Iceland if they...
Hang on to the credits for long enough.
And then of course the color text and banners and identification, which is cool.
It's not hard to find these people. These are people that keep track of what we say.
You know, social media, all that stuff.
So we just put the word out that we need people.
And it's actually very, very easy for us to find people, which is a great luxury problem to have.
There's screening that they have to pass both by CCP staff and ISD captains and vice-admirals.
They must be in good standing, of course, not to have broken the rules too much.
And they must know a lot about the game and they must have the right attitude, which is incredibly important.
The ISD are especially good themselves when they do their screening of filtering out people that have, you know,
maybe they hunker too much for the power of moderation and all that stuff.
That's important.
And some of the current ones have been volunteers
for over 10 years and we see them at FanFest every year
and they're absolutely great people.
We love them a lot.
So here's just an example of how 2015 went.
We let in about 10% of the people that applied.
So it's a very hard system to get into.
And fewer people resigned than were accepted.
So we're dealing with low churn and a big pool
of very, very competent applicants
that we're very happy to have.
So what are the pitfalls of allowing players to do something like this for you?
I mean, obviously things can go wrong, and we've had our problems in the past.
We had, for example, we had a forum moderation team set up back in the day.
It wasn't terrible, it was great, they did a lot of good stuff.
From the early days of EVE Online, and it was discontinued in 2008.
But back then, we didn't have the same amount of experience
in dealing with this.
We didn't have the proper structures.
We gave them too much power.
We allowed them to ban people in forums, et cetera.
That showed a lot of mistrust.
And there was drama around it, and more perceived problems
than actual problems.
But it ended up that we discontinued it,
moved moderation in-house.
And then the new system was taken up in 2011.
And it's gone since then.
So since the olden days, it's been a learning experience.
And I mean, if it didn't have these volunteers, we'd either just need to add a bunch of staff to do all these things,
or we'd probably just do fewer cool projects than we are currently doing,
and we'd be focused more on like all kinds of menial tasks and management of them.
So the bottom line is that they make us better, but we in turn, I mean, we give them opportunities to do something that they love
and get more engaged with a game that they love to play.
Then I want to...
I want to tell you about Ben Gruber, who moved to Iceland from Australia to work with us.
He manages the fansites program.
Lots of companies have a fansite program of some sort, or at least list fansites on their page.
But for us, they're incredibly important.
We have all kinds of fansites that we try to divvy up,
tools that players absolutely need, all kinds of guides and things that people couldn't be without.
Because...
For EVE, they are just unusually important because the scope of the EVE universe, the depth, the complexity is such that we can never tend to everybody's needs.
It's just impossible. We don't have the resources or even the imagination to fill all these gaps that players just find for themselves.
So there's a lot of players doing absolutely essential things for us and for the community.
And so we try to divide them into these categories.
And there's certain standards set for each category.
I mean, blocks have to be updated regularly.
Tools have to be functional and up to date.
Guides have to be taking game changes into account
and all that stuff.
Then we do a biannual audit.
And if you don't get in, or if your membership gets discontinued,
we contact them and tell them why and how they can get in again.
Try to keep an active encouragement going there.
So finding these fansites is fairly easy.
Again, these are people that keep tabs on what we say,
so social media, all that stuff.
Then the benefit is that once we've
collected them into a pool of fansites,
we can send the fansite blasts with information
to these people that are experts at getting to our players.
But to find them, we maintain a formal application process.
There's a form that people fill out.
And of course, we just look for cool sites
and we wave that form in their face
if we think they should join the program.
But what are the added benefits for someone who just likes to make websites to be in a program like this?
I mean there's perks, there's similar perks to what the ISD get, there's free tickets to official events, free accounts, etc.
They don't get store credit for hours put in like the ISD because that's a lot harder to measure,
but in turn we're pretty liberal with allowing fan sites to monetize with all kinds of ad programs, monetization programs,
so we encourage that and we want people to make a little extra on it if they can.
Of course there's easier access to devs.
I mean, some of our web developers in the community have sat down with our own web experts
and gotten some help on some projects.
We do roundtables and they can come to us and work with us on all kinds of projects.
So street cred matters.
And for access to the community, if they're a trusted fan site,
we know they're good for it and we'll help them more than someone else maybe who has an idea.
So it's good. Good to be close.
I mean, this is... most of the time people don't do it for any of this.
They do it because they have a great idea and they're good at something
and they want to do something for the community
and they want to, you know, get the status that comes with it and all that stuff.
But the recognition from us is a nice bonus
and I think it's very important to do it even though people don't.
Come just for that. This, of course, strengthens our relationship with these best developers,
these third-party developers in the community. We know who they are, we get attuned to what
they can do, and we build this relationship that has a lot of benefits.
And then of course, having an official list like this that's audited regularly and officially approved with clear guidelines,
it gives helpful players, IST, ourselves, something to point to that's safe and quick and helps players along.
And very important again, this whole program with all its
benefits is just part-time work for one man.
I mean, it's not even a majority thing.
It's just like a few hours a week to run it, basically, at
this point.
It takes a lot of work to set up, but it's not
energy-intense to run.
So I want to give you an example.
of one of my favorite websites.
And this is like a good example of how EVE, the universe,
and EVE, the software, don't always see eye to eye.
See, we created a map so people could see the universe
and get some details, but it just didn't really fulfill
the needs that players figured out for themselves.
They needed certain things to plan very granularly,
all kinds of complex operations,
explorations, wars, fleet movements.
Along came a German web developer, a player who calls himself Volari in-game,
and he made Dotland Maps, which is a web-based service that is absolutely fantastic.
And I want to play a little bit of where one of our better video makers called Johnny Pugh
tells us what the difference between our map and Dotland Maps.
This looks confusing to me. This is chaos.
But if you want to make yourself an easier time of...
Navigating through a particular region in EVE Online, do not use this EVE map tool.
Now, I do understand if you just want to use the EVE client, but you don't have to do that.
You can use the in-game EVE browser.
I
would never have been able to cover as a single pilot scouting around in a single ship.
So it's not all flattering.
You know, he said some things about our map,
but I forgive him.
He's done so many good things.
But this is a really cool butterfly effect story here,
because we offer API support so players
can build these tools from using data from our database.
And a player comes along and makes something
in a game that's all built around traveling around space,
and he builds a tool that absolutely everyone uses
at some point or another.
It becomes very valuable. In turn, he obviously has a lot of server costs, so we help him advertise when he's collecting money from the community for his server costs.
And that's always gone really well, and we point people in his direction all the time, so he builds a bigger fan base and has many benefactors in the community.
Then someone, a video maker like Johnny Pugh comes along.
Starts exploring the universe, making regular video about it,
educating people on his YouTube channel,
and entertains and educates thousands of people every week.
So that's, to me, an example of raising the sale pretty firmly
with assistance from the community.
And without all these fan sites, all these tools I've talked
about, we just have fewer useful tools, way less content.
Or we just have to hire a bunch of people to make things.
But realistically, we'd probably just be a little bit crippled in some areas,
because it's very hard to fill all those gaps.
So recognizing people, even when they come not for that,
is very important because the person that doesn't come
for the recognition may still leave for the lack of it
after a certain amount of time.
People get tired, they burn out,
and if they feel they're not being listened to
or appreciated.
So we have to contribute and do what we can for them.
Then not everything fits into a mold or an application form,
and we work with community organizers on a lot of asymmetrical, one-time projects.
So they come to us with a lot of ideas, and we maintain an open-door policy,
so anyone in the community can approach us with an idea, and we just...
you know, we figure out time to talk about it over Skype or through emails or whatever,
and we just look at their idea, give them feedback on it, and help out.
Sometimes it's about a real-life player gathering, there's a lot of those.
Sometimes it's a new website, it can be even a short film or documentary.
We've had people doing things like that in the past and they need access to assets
or our internal tech people for some advice or something.
It can be an in-game charity event. We have a lot of charity events in EVE.
Even though it has its cutthroat reputation, people set up large battles, give out free ships,
and they collect donations for charity.
And we help them by advertising and making sure that everybody makes their way to them.
And my approach with this is thinking about it so that you can always do something to help everyone.
Even if it's just some advice or feedback, then take the time to look over it, give some feedback.
Some ideas are too big for now, and they need to be either scoped down a little bit,
or people just need a reality check on what they can actually do with the resources they have.
And we can help because we've built experience with that.
But sometimes it's also about, you know, you just look at an idea and someone is struggling with something,
needs something done, and we can connect them to someone else in the community, maybe,
because we have a lot of connections, so we do that a lot.
We help people connect to each other so they can work together.
And we manage a lot of relationships with these high-level community organizers that do bigger things for the community.
So we work as sort of like account managers for those people.
And the picture on the left there, it's from Evesterdam, which is an event that's held in Amsterdam by a player every year.
And he runs a crew of volunteers that helps him run like a 300-strong convention. So 300 people come to this.
Buy tickets, it's all planned very much in advance.
They have player presentations about D.Va Online and all kinds of things that players do in a game that's interesting.
We also send developers over to give developer presentations, tell them about new things in the game.
We send demos of our latest games like some VR games, Valkyrie and Gun Jack and that.
So we can give them a glimpse into the future.
So we kind of help them boost the attendance with stuff like that.
And also we just hang out in the bars of Amsterdam into the night talking about D.Va Online and giving people access to our time.
The one on the right is an event in Australia, which is called EVE Down Under, and that takes place every year as well.
I mean, another high-level convention that's organized only by players.
And there, we only sent one person, because it's very far away, and then we Skyped in to do a Q&A, three of us.
And that's another very cheap and non-committal way
to do something for a player gathering, which is really
awesome, because all you need to do is the Skype account,
and then you call in and let them ask some questions.
And it just takes a bit of time.
I mean, this was at some weird hour,
because it's in Australia.
It was like 10 PM or something on a Saturday night.
So one of us was calling in from home.
So we had two webcams going.
And we conspired to turn both the webcams upside down,
which is a joke that no Australian gets tired of.
Then there's tournaments and esports. Esports in EVE are notoriously difficult.
I would almost say impossible to run because you need our assistance to do it.
You need, because in EVE Online you can't really just set up an arena and go fight.
Anyone could come and blow you up, so there's no way to host like a safe tournament.
So we need to move people to like secluded systems that are cut off from everything.
And we need to, you know, use some dev tools and stuff like that.
But we've had people run tournaments like that before, and we have someone just on there helping.
One of them is Eve Antiqualites, which is run by a player called Nash Cadaver, who comes out of Nottingham.
He's also running amazing events over there, like real-life events.
And he ran a whole winter of tournaments.
Really good stuff, but he wanted to grow it, and he wanted the top teams in EVE Online to join for his second season.
So he came to us with a really well-written proposal.
and wanted us to make him unique shapeskins to give to every participant in the tournament.
And it was a bit of a wild idea for us because we'd never created an asset for a player-created event uniquely.
So we took a look at it and...
I managed to convince a couple of producers that it wasn't a bad idea and we went ahead
with it and it's gotten some good results.
He got all the teams he wanted, the top teams from our yearly official alliance tournament
and he has seen a bump in viewership and a lot of interest and he's gotten sponsors,
I mean he gets like sponsors like Racer and Plantronics and stuff and it's really, really
cool stuff so we're trying to push the envelope on that.
So I think it's a good example of an event that needed something from us to grow,
but all the work is done by players.
He manages a team of 12 people that run this.
We just help out a little bit.
And in return, we get so much content.
One of my favorite examples that I've been involved in is EveMeet.
And this is a website that is designed to do primarily three things.
It shows you upcoming real-life gatherings around the world.
It notifies you, if you sign up for it, of events happening near you.
And you can create your own events that other people can sign up for.
We've been rolling the idea of a site like this around for a while.
And it was like a web request internally
that suffered at the hands of prioritization for a while.
We all know that old monster.
And then I was talking to the guys that organized the event in Australia that I was talking about.
And we were doing a Skype call about that event and we'd finished all the logistical planning and all that stuff.
And then we just started talking and I was telling them about this idea that I wanted to create and la la la.
And they were just like, huh, it's a cool idea. And I explained it to them in detail.
And then, like a couple of months later, they told me they were almost finished making it.
So they went ahead and made the site. We didn't have to do anything.
Then we've been just relentless in pushing it to everyone and letting people know about it.
And on our live streams, on social media.
And we've seen, since this site came up, it's become the primary hub for players to find real-life gatherings for e-players.
We've seen a marked increase in the number of player gatherings, the attendance,
and they've been popping up in cities all over the world that have never had gatherings before.
So that's awesome.
And I mean, player gatherings, they're very important to us.
But like, why? Why do we want to push people so hard towards player gatherings?
I think they are very cool for any gamers, but I think they're particularly important for us.
Because, like I said, EVE is a very, you know, it's an intense hobby to people,
and people get dug pretty deep into it.
Meeting people that love the same thing as you that much is fun.
It's just, I mean, our brains, they haven't changed since forever,
even though, like, technology is always updating.
And our brains are just wired for face-to-face communications.
We like that.
And player gatherings do that.
We've been pushing player gatherings.
There's like hundreds of them around the world.
Most of them run exclusively by players.
We support them by advertising them so people come to them.
We send them care packages with swag.
We Skype in sometimes, and sometimes we even send people.
I mean, we've been stubbornly pushing it since forever.
We just continuously push the idea of specific meats
and just tell people about it.
Encouraging people that have never taken the leap
to go and see people in real life just to try it out.
And we find that the effects are very good, very good.
We've been going to them. This costs money, of course.
We send developers to these gatherings,
but we believe that it has great returns
and has benefits for both the developers and the players
that get to meet the developers and interact with them.
It creates a relationship, so to speak.
And then we host our own events,
and like the official FanFest in Iceland every year,
and Eve Vegas, which takes place in Las Vegas, of course,
every year, which is becoming almost as big
as FanFest, and it's a crazy, crazy party.
It's a very important thing and I think what we have felt when we come back from FanFest for example,
where we are kind of like bathed in the passion of EVE players for a week,
is that we just come out with energy. We just come out with more energy.
We're really tired of course, but it's just like...
We want to do that thing that we didn't have time for, that we thought about a long time ago,
and it's like we push harder and do more.
It increases your engagement to feel other people's passion like that,
and we believe it has exactly the same effect on players, and we know actually,
and that when they come back, if they've never met people before, that also plays.
You know, they go and have fun, drink some beers and talk, and then, you know,
when you get back to the game, you just kind of see everything a little differently,
and it feels more fun.
The pitfalls of backing player projects are, you know, there's just a few that you really have to take care of.
I mean, if you back a project super hard and it fails super hard, you'll probably take the hit too.
I mean, I've kind of run into this once or twice where you're super enthusiastic about something and don't background check it completely
and then it turns out to be a bit of a disaster and you have to do some cleanup and apologizing or something.
It's best to just be brutally honest up front, you know, friendly but honest, and just give people that feedback early on.
Do the background checks, be critical of the plans, get the plans laid out in enough detail, etc.
It's important to be fair when you're deciding which thing to back and which thing not to back,
because you may be deciding to back this project and not a similar one.
But the way I look at it, this is something that's happening outside the game.
This is essentially business.
It doesn't have to be 100% fair.
So don't let fairness cripple you.
The world isn't fair.
Just do what you think is right.
Spend your limited resources in the way that you think will have the best impact.
Then, with CSB, this is something we sort of fell into as a startup company,
and we've kind of grown up with it, and it works well for us.
It's having direct, free-flowing communication between developers and players.
We even made a song about this, almost, which is our in-house band called The Permaband.
It's called Killing is Just a Means of Communication,
because at the end of the day, even if we're shooting each other in the face,
it's all about communication, and communication is the heart of everything we do.
So we'd rather have too much of it than too little of it.
The benefits of allowing developers the freedom to speak to players in an ungated fashion, there's many.
I mean, people get good at it over time.
They feel more like a sense of personal pride and ambition representing their own work than if someone is always doing it for them.
And they also just get to know the players and what they like about the product better.
So we encourage developers to communicate with players about work,
but also just about whatever they want to talk about.
If you're on Reddit or Twitter or the forums and people are talking about something that's out of game and fun,
you can talk about what you're interested in.
Relationship building is cool.
Official communication goes through the same pathways and processes as in any other company, of course.
We just have this extra flow of freestyle communication.
The problems with freestyle communication, I mean, the biggest thing I would tell you to avoid is not having guidelines.
It's good to have guidelines, just the spirit of what you want to achieve and what you don't want to do.
If you have bad guidelines, that's bad, obviously.
Bad guidelines to me are super-ruly, really like documents with a lot of nitpicking and detail.
It doesn't have to be like that. It just gets micro-lawyered and it's not fun. It scares people away.
Then, not saying something if someone is not handling it well.
If someone is not handling communication, you have to talk to them.
Help them out, be there for people if something isn't working out, and clean up if things have to be cleaned up, and stuff like that.
But not all communication is informal and casual.
We have something we call the Council of Stellar Management, which is a democratically elected council of e-players, elected by other players in an election every year.
They're flown to Iceland for four days of summits with the
people who make it online.
And we have a lot of online meetings with them, like every week.
And there's a lot of crazy politics that goes into it.
I mean, players are intensely interested in who gets onto this.
Some of them are representing power blocks,
and are just voted in in an organized fashion by power blocks.
Some are voted in because they represent a certain play style,
or some special interest group.
And then some people are just voted in on integrity alone,
like they're great people and people believe they'll do good.
And then they come to us.
And they acted like an early...
They're like the canary in the coal mine for us.
The early warning sign if we're going the wrong route.
Like I said, sometimes eBay is complicated and it's easy to steer features in a direction that seems great,
but there's some things we hadn't thought about.
So having an early soundboard is really good.
And these people sign an NDA and they're privy to early information.
I may be forcing the wind analogy a little hard, but it's true.
We're forcing a lot of feedback from a lot of people through a very narrow tunnel
so we can signal out a lot of noise.
These people are very well connected.
These are expert players who have a lot of connections to the community.
They have above average social skills and talent.
They bring us the feedback of the people that aren't necessarily vocal on forums and everywhere else.
They bring us structured feedback.
And then the picture is from the election of the 10th CSM from last year.
We now have another election, so there's a lot of campaigning going on and we'll have
a new CSM in just over a month.
But this is a good example, I think.
This project is a good example of two things.
It's giving your players some agency in your development process
so they feel like they're part of it and also can give you great feedback.
And for us, career-wise, I think it's a very interesting project
that allows us to do quite high-level stuff.
I mean, we have to plan summits, fly people in internationally,
deal with visa issues.
We need to book meetings every week with designers, producers,
executives even.
And we have to do a lot of expectation management
and use all our diplomacy skills to avert drama all the time.
So it's a really fun project to be involved in.
And I mean, the ancient Greeks, they
had this sort of figured out before us.
We didn't invent it.
We're just making it a little better every day.
And then sometimes it's time to get your hands dirty and grab the oars and do something, create some content of your own.
And one example of that is a show that I produce and host with some of my wonderful colleagues.
It's called O7, the EVE Online Show.
O7 is like a salute that players do in game. It's an O and a 7, so it's a sign to the respect.
that EVE players have for each other.
And this is a show that makes sense for us to do in-house.
I mean, there's a lot of good media in the EVE community.
Podcasts, streams, even, you know, like tape shows,
but we have access to funds, obviously, that players don't have,
so we can do things on a higher production level.
And we have access to all that in-house development information
that nobody else has, so we...
We can use that to leverage views, and we get many times the views that any player stream can get for that reason.
But then again, even if it's our show about our stuff, it's also mostly about the players.
And we talk to players about things they do, we highlight cool projects and events that are happening, and direct people in those directions.
So we put a big spotlight on what the players are doing, but we also commission work directly from content creators.
So for example...
There's an EVE player called Hendrik Tellerdaar that makes us an 07 report every month,
where he does a dive into the politics and wars of EVE Online and tells us what's going on there.
He obviously knows a lot more about it than we do.
And it's much better at telling that story.
So it's better for our players.
I mean, it saves us time.
It gives him a bigger platform for the material
that he's making.
Anyway, so it's a win-win situation.
One other example, something we've
been just commissioned recently is Prosper Market Analysis
by a player called Lockfox.
And he's an economist by trade, I believe.
And he does a really technical deep dive
into the
complicated market systems of EVE Online to help people better speculate and leverage their money in the game.
It's very, very interesting stuff.
Again, something that would be very time consuming and difficult for us to do properly.
And then we also have a little bit of fun once in a while.
Last April Fools, we had a show hit on that day, so we called up The Mountain from Game of Thrones.
He lives in Reykjavik too, so it's not far away, and he fits into our building and everything.
We got him to fill my spot for the introduction of the show
to see if people would notice the difference, which they did.
I even put him in the same shirt, but EVE players are smart.
So if we just round this up,
we talked about boosting and supporting player projects.
This is something that I think is very important.
For a community team to be able to spend time on this,
they need to have some free time, and we have that.
Devote time to looking at what players are doing, reading up on that, and talking to them, having this open-door policy, booking meetings with them, talking about stuff.
And I think it brings a lot of benefits, and it often has benefits that you don't spot in advance.
They come to you with an idea that you wouldn't have thought of, and they come to you because they've talked to you before, and they kind of, you know, we have this thing going on.
So that's good.
I think companies should be doing this.
Any chance they get.
Volunteer programs are amazing.
They're just great.
There's a lot of things, there's a lot of tasks
that you have to do,
but aren't necessarily vital in-house functions,
like I've said.
So, I mean, we've proven that there is a positive,
you can set up a system that is self-reliant
and efficient to do things that, you know,
most companies have to do to some capacity.
So I would definitely recommend looking into that.
Plus you find some great people in the process
and get to know some amazing people.
Encouraging face-to-face meetups is a no-brainer to me.
It's something that I enjoy being a part of immensely,
and I know our developers benefit greatly from it.
One thing you can do that is very cheap and quick and easy
is to organize a meetup around an event like this,
like a GDC, PAX, something like that,
where you have a lot of people out there anyway.
So why not?
Book something in a bar, buy a few kegs of beer, just, you know, advertise on your social media,
go talk to people, see where you stand, see if you like it.
I'm sure your developers, you guys will like it.
It's... everybody will love it.
And for, if there's any managers here, it's also a great way to make your people work nights.
But, yeah, I definitely do that.
Then, you know, giving your players some agency, some stake in the development of the game is great.
A lot of people are running focus groups.
We have a democratically elected focus group.
That doesn't maybe, you know, maybe that doesn't work for everybody.
Maybe we'll have the People's Council of Krust can't be one day.
Or if people just want to do more casual focus groups that they handpick,
there's still things you can probably do like allowing players to vote on certain priorities
or final outcomes or stuff like that on certain things in whatever limited capacity you're comfortable with.
But it's fun to give your players a say.
And then maintaining direct, ungated communication is something that I recommend.
It's not for everyone, I know that, and there's a lot of companies that are very big,
where things have to be more formal and I completely understand that.
But I would definitely recommend checking it out.
One good thing about it is that we see who's good at communicating
and then we can, for example, decide to send those people to those player gatherings I talked about.
So by spending some extra time on engaging with the community and building a relationship there,
you might end up in Australia one day talking about EVE.
And like I said, if you have a chance to go the formal route or the more playful, ungated route of communication,
I'd recommend the more playful one, because we are in the entertainment business and we sometimes forget that.
But I want to end this with a video that is very dear to me.
It completely wasn't made for this presentation or anything.
A player made this for me by chance.
It's a player called Chimera.
He also plays a game called ArcheAge.
And he made this video for me in ArcheAge.
And it brings tears to my eye every time.
It's beautiful.
Very inspiring.
I just had to squeeze that in there.
It's like so fitting.
Thank you.
That's it for me.
If you have any questions, fire away.
Hi, that was a great talk, thank you. I'm an Eve player and I've been a big fan of your volunteer groups.
One of my questions though is, have you ever had any problems with the...
a legal gray area of having volunteers who are doing things that are almost like work that you would normally pay them for,
and you're paying them non-monetarily. Does that cause problems for you, and does that change your approach with them?
Are you unable to give them direction in what they're doing, or do they have to just come up with whatever they want to do themselves?
I know there was a lot of discussion about this like a few years ago, but one of the things we do,
we don't mandate like any number of hours from people.
We just want people to be active over time, but we don't mandate, for example,
you have to do this much necessarily to be allowed to be in the program.
We just, you know, you put in the time you can and just stay active and you're all good.
And that's one of the things we do.
Obviously, we just like...
We can't give every task to players.
I mean, there has to be some limit to that.
And people get into it.
They're adults.
They know what they're doing.
There's a very clear line of what this is and what everybody taking part in it.
We've been good with that.
Can you describe any positive or negative experiences with user-created content?
Positive and negative experiences with user-created content.
Well, there's...
I mean, obviously, there's always a lot of drama around some things.
Some people make content to cause drama.
We generally just stay out of that.
We don't get involved, and we try not to touch things that are likely to cause drama in any official way.
So if, for example, someone is a bit of a troll and is making content,
we probably wouldn't commission them for doing work for us.
We deal with people who...
who we trust to understand the bigger picture and do the right thing.
So, yeah, there have been some things, but nothing too terrible.
And we just take care not to, you know, when we're linking to stuff,
to make sure it's OK, it's not something horrible.
Hey.
Hey. So, I'm an absolute disaster when talking to the community.
And I guess with having so many of you developers
directly interfacing with the community,
which is something that they don't do primarily,
is there a...
A single piece of advice or training materials, or how do you prepare those developers to talk and interact with the community?
But one of the things we have in our guidelines, for example, is that we train people not to talk too much about other people's work.
I mean, we as communication professionals, we talk about other people's works.
But someone who's maybe a programmer, he's not talking about something that an artist is doing and vice versa in any detail or promising anything that they can't deliver on.
So we want people to focus on their specialty and rather summon someone else if they need to.
And then we have some guidelines on just being very professional and friendly and all that.
And even if you're doing this, like if you're just chatting to people about your favorite football team or whatever,
just always remember you are an employee first and foremost anytime you're talking to a player.
It's just something that's a common sense thing that people need to...
It needs some training sometimes, but most people can handle it pretty well.
And I think if you allow people to do it, they get better at it.
Hello. Thank you for the talk. Great talk.
I've got two questions, and maybe the answer is worth a separate presentation.
Yeah.
But first of all, we all know that when we're talking about games that have been around for quite a while,
Players there, the players know the game much better than developers.
Yeah.
And how do you approach features that community proposes?
That's the question number one.
Do you have any kind of guidelines to how you like pass stuff to developers or something like that?
And the second one...
Even if you think that the feature the player proposes is good enough,
but there are definitely way more stuff the community brings to you than you can develop.
And even if you agree that this is good, how do you deal with that, like, whining and stuff that,
hey, you're not doing this, I told you to do this, like, years ago?
So community proposing features and how we deal with the, I guess, expectation management of what these features we don't decide to develop.
Well, one thing, for example, that the Council of Stellar Management can do is that they can provide features officially with access to our internal site.
So they make like a feature cart.
for a feature proposal and they propose like roadmap changes and stuff like that.
So that's one formal way.
Then we have, you know, the regular like forums where people propose ideas and
and this active conversation that we have with players
so that like developers that are specialists in an area,
they often have like a group of people that are very good in that area
and they talk to them regularly.
It's like sort of like an unofficially also.
So they get feedback and bounce ideas off people.
So we validate ideas like that.
And then when it comes to deciding what not to do,
I mean, that's classic expectation management.
We have to, you know, there's sometimes
like a lot of noise about something
that we can't realistically get into right now,
or it's just maybe not a great idea.
And then we have to discuss it, spend some time discussing it.
Or, you know, at least if it's a good idea that we have to do,
but we can't do it now, we have to tell them to.
You know, we have to like lay down some information on when
we can do it or something like that.
Thank you.
Right, well, thanks for the good last talk of GDC, for me at least.
I was wondering, when you essentially endorse certain player-made material, websites, streams,
whatever, how do you deal with potential friction that arises?
Because let's say you endorse something that's made by a Goon Swarm player,
certain other factions in the game might find that highly unfair and favoritist,
and we know EVE players aren't the most forgiving in that sense.
So how do you deal with that?
Thing is, dealing with material made by players that are connected to factions and stuff like that,
we don't have to deal with a lot of follow-up from it.
I hope it's because we pick them well.
And like I said, I'm aware that I'm, for example,
I'm commissioning a video from a guy who's in Pandemic Legion,
who's one of the constantly warring factions of EVE Online,
I mean, I'm aware that their enemies might not like it, but we tend to pick people who have a reputation of already doing good things.
They make material that appeals to a wide group of people.
We don't allow for any direct propaganda for anyone, so we want people to keep that separate.
So we don't host propaganda, unless we advertise for
material like that.
And maybe we ask everyone to send in their propaganda, and
we air all of it.
We could do that.
But yeah, we haven't had a lot of follow up.
But we'll have to see if that comes up.
So with your user testing and your user research,
have you completely done away with some sort
of formal system for that?
Or do you use your community for that, your little subgroups
and things like that?
Do you release special builds to some
of these groups for preview of features and things like that?
Or do you still do it in a formal capacity as well?
Well, there's a lot of formal stuff.
Like, I'm not an expert in all of that, but the user testing
and all that stuff.
But we do AP tests.
We've been doing AP tests for a while.
And we do research also formally.
So it's not all just like informally chatting with the
players and all that.
This is kind of like a bonus on top of everything else.
But yeah.
One more.
Yes.
That players console group that you talked about, are
they aware of your roadmap?
The player advocacy groups?
No, the council of Stellar Madison.
The council.
Yes.
Like the best guys.
We're talking about the ISD or the CSI?
No, those that you fly here to the studio.
Ok.
Interstellar Service Department, the volunteers, they're not aware of the roadmap much except
maybe some select countries that they need to know some things.
But the democratically elected council, they are aware of the roadmap and they get most
information very early.
They get the most information out of anyone who doesn't work for CCP.
So they're very trusted.
How you doing man?
Talk was awesome.
So thanks for that.
That was awesome information that I'm going to try to implement, but I'm on a very small
team, like a team of four, so we don't really have a dedicated community team to kind of
manage these kinds of I guess initiative projects.
So I'm curious, what would your advice be for somebody who's trying to get some of these
off the ground or like places to start or route I should take?
I'm just kind of curious.
Yeah, it's interesting. For a small team, what you should start with, I would look at doing some volunteer stuff, like get some volunteers on board to help with some things that work for you.
I mean, all the more if you have a small team, then you need the help. We have one guy managing these teams as a part-time job, and they do a lot of good stuff for us.
When you get players involved, like we were talking about, they're the experts.
They often do things better than we do, you know, some of the things.
So I would do that, and I would start hunting around for these, like, what do you want to call them?
Like super users, content creators, people who want to do some extra stuff, make tools, all that stuff.
Like find those guys and do something for them.
Even if it's formal or informal, just...
Yeah.
Cool. Thanks so much.
You're welcome.
We're good.
All right, cool.
I'll be around if you want to talk.