Right, ladies and gentlemen, I'm about to reveal a secret about GDC you may not be aware of,
and that is that every year, at random, they pick one speaker who has not received any valuation forms,
they take them out into Yebubwena, and they shoot them in the back of the head.
So please, for my children, fill in the evaluation forms.
The second thing that we are required to say is that your mobile phones,
you're the noise makers, please turn them off. I'm of a nervous disposition.
If I hear a sudden noise from the audience, I may leap from the stage and that will end badly.
Welcome, hello, I'm Alexis Kennedy. I run Failbetter Games which is a studio in London
and we're an indie studio. We're up from four people in 2014 to 16 people now so that puts us
kind of firmly the mid-sized indie and what I'm going to talk about today is going to be most
useful to you if you are either a studio of about that size or looking to be a studio at that size.
I want to make this clear, there has never been any successfully substantiated
allegation of cannibalism against our studio.
These things are subject to libel actions.
We made a game called Fallen London.
It's a web-based narrative thing that's been around for years
and we're best known at the moment for a game called Sunless Sea.
Sunless Sea made using a bundle of techniques that are very popular and successful in indie
studios, which I'm calling open production because I like things that sound like buzz
phrases.
Kickstarter, early access, paid betas, getting feedback from the community early, interacting
directly with your community.
They're not for everybody. I think they're great. I spoke to Justin Ma from Subset Games earlier
today and he said he thought the idea was horrible and he couldn't imagine doing it. I can't imagine
doing it any other way so this really is about finding what fits with your studio's way of
working.
And money is always available from somewhere.
If the idea of working this way appeals to you, then do it.
If it doesn't appeal to you, look somewhere else to find funding.
There's a bunch of really specific good and bad things about building games
in front of your community with your community's collaboration.
Before we made Sunless Sea, we were in a terrible place.
We were four people, we'd be doing bits of client work.
I just had to lay off three of my friends.
And Fallen London, our own game,
was not making enough money to pay the bills.
So Sunless Sea was a bit of a Hail Mary pass.
I don't play American football,
so I may have used that completely wrongly.
It was a bit of a last desperate roll of the dice.
We were going to go bust by the end of the year.
We'd never made an actual video game.
All our work had been web-based stuff.
Browser-based traditional web development.
We'd never built a Unity game.
We thought we probably could, we thought we knew enough about game design and world building, we thought we could make a go of it, we built a prototype to make sure we could, but it was very uncertain, and it worked out.
So this is not an epoch-making headline success, but it is a solid indie success that most studios of our size would be very pleased with. We fucking were.
And the key thing is, this is a very tenable success.
If you are working in a team of two, or three, or four,
if you are wondering whether it's ever possible to make a living making video games,
there's a bunch of stuff you can do, there's a bunch of opportunities available to you
that allow you to do this sort of thing.
Couple of points I want you to take away above everything else.
This is our loop. We build stuff, we listen to our community, we build more stuff.
So first of all, we've been around for four years when we started building Sunless Sea.
And we were, as I said, in a dire place.
We didn't have much money, we didn't have many resources, but we did have four years worth of community.
If you've been working on your own, even if it's only for six months, let alone if it's four years.
You have built up a backlog of people who know you and know your work.
When you issue the call to Kickstarter, we'll come out and help you.
Or the call to Early Access or any other kind of open production mechanism.
Even if you feel like you've been plugging away and getting nowhere,
you have been getting somewhere.
Having a community is almost as good as having money in the bank.
You can't spend them, but they will help you.
And they'll help you in terms of feedback, they'll help you in terms of spreading the word, which is hugely important.
They'll help you in terms of keeping your morale high in the dark times.
So if you've been struggling, you haven't done nothing, you've just not got there yet.
And the other thing I want to talk about is sustainability.
When we made 100 grand out of Kickstarter, we felt like we had all the money in the world.
Our monthly studio burn team and rent is now about £60,000.
So, all the money in the world doesn't last very long.
Burn is much lower then obviously.
But if you're an indie team and you suddenly get a giant chunk of cash,
even if it's a giant chunk of cash after Kickstarter and the credit card companies have taken their cut,
it is just the beginning of your journey.
Same thing with the game launch.
We sold 40,000 copies in the first week of early access.
far outstripping our most optimistic projections
because our optimistic projections are pretty conservative.
But again, that was just the beginning of our journey,
that the money we made from that
wouldn't have lasted long.
And if you are running an open production process
for a game, if you're making games for an audience,
you want to bring the audience with you into the future.
You want to build a studio that will survive
the next two, three, four games,
and you want to have an audience that will help you
and trust you as you build those two, three, four games.
Here are six things. These are all challenges or problems or techniques we found to deal with some of the specific issues of open production.
And this is, I think, probably the most important of those.
Marketing.
I bet a lot of you in this room think of like flossing.
A lot of you don't, a lot of you have been around this mill.
But marketing is a thing you do at the end of your game production cycle
in order to make sure that people actually buy it.
It's not. It's not.
The window of opportunity when an indie game could just get on Steam
and sell through sheer luck is over.
the chances that your game will be so brilliant it will get picked up
uh... become world headlines and spread through sheer word of mouth
it is possible
but it's a very low chance
uh... this yellow text is a
very pungent quote from my director of communications
and uh...
I would say something slightly different
uh... I would say you would not put out a game
without debugging it
that would be criminal and stupid
you shouldn't put out a game without marketing it either
And when I say the indie checkbox, what I mean is that a lot of folk, and I've been guilty of this in the past, God knows,
read all the genuinely valuable advice on the Gama Sutra, five things you absolutely must do if you're an indie game company post,
do those five things, sell 300 copies, the game disappears in the dark without a screen.
And then you see one of those fucking heartbreaking posts on Gamasutra that says
we sung a year of our life into this game and nobody heard of it and nobody found anything.
So it's not enough to send out some press releases at the end and feel like you've
done your job. You need to be thinking about how to explain your game in a sentence or two
from the get-go. What makes a hook? What the central creative core of the game is?
And how to express it to other people?
and you will iterate your new game all the way through.
One of the things that open production allows you to do is iterate on marketing as well.
You tell your community what you're going to make, and there you go.
Huh?
And then you fix that.
When we first talked to our community about Summer Sea,
we talked to a very small number of core fans.
and we said it was going to be 2D Elite with steamships.
And nobody under the age of 40
or outside the UK at that time had heard of Elite.
Now you have because of Elite Dangerous,
but then it was completely novel.
So we took Elite out of the pitch.
And one of the advantages of doing open production
is you expose your proposition, your hook,
to gradually large numbers of people.
In our case, it was core fans,
then larger core fans we tested our Kickstarter message on.
then Kickstarter backers, then early access people.
And every stage we had the opportunity to learn and change our message
before we went full launch and before we were stuck with whatever we dealt with.
And the tagline of Sunless Sea is lose your mind, eat your crew.
That came quite late in development, just before early access I think.
We didn't get to there without getting a lot of feedback from our community
and working out what appealed to them about the game.
And lose your mind, eat your crew, we hear again and again people saying
you know, as soon as I heard that, you had me, I bought the game.
The community, this is a point that Raph van Lierop made in his talk last year about Long Dark,
another very successful, in fact much more successful early access game.
Your community can give you feedback on your game, on your messaging, on your design, on your game experience,
and that feedback is absolutely essential. It's as essential as the funding they can give you.
But they will also try to tell you how to fix it.
They know when something is wrong.
If your community tells you something is wrong
and you don't listen, you're probably blind.
But if your community tells you they know what's wrong,
they might or might not be right.
If your community tells you how to fix it,
then they'll almost always be wrong.
It's your job as developers.
to work out how to fix it. It's their job to tell you when they don't like it.
So never confuse the two. They're not an advice council,
they're a canary. They tell you when things are broken, they don't tell you
how to fix it.
exposed our game to ever larger numbers of players of community. So we started out with about 30,
we went to about 100, then we hit Kickstarter, that grew the community, then the Kickstarter
took off, that grew the community again. But in the very beginning we told our early community,
our core community, and we told them that Kickstarter was coming. So first of all,
If you are thinking of running a Kickstarter, and nobody should be in 2016 thinking of doing this,
if you're thinking of running a Kickstarter and not telling anybody about it until the day,
bang your head against a wall until the desire to do that goes away.
I don't think anybody is still doing this, but statistically somebody is.
We did it with our first Kickstarter and it's preposterous. As soon as you run a Kickstarter,
start a Kickstarter, the clock is running. You've got 30 days to make all that money.
What a shame to fail and ground you from the finish post. So tell your community.
that you're going to be running a Kickstarter.
Tell any friendly press contacts you have
I know it's very hard to get press to listen
to anything about Kickstarters.
If you have contacts, use them.
Tell them when it's going to start
and make sure that on the day,
like seven minutes past the point where you hit the button,
you have pledges on there.
Because nothing succeeds like
the indication of a future success.
If people are pledging, other people pledge.
And what you want, specifically what you want, is to have people posting this image on their
forum of choice on the internet.
This particular one.
Once you see this, you know you have a valuable proposition.
So build your chosen kettle, tell people up front, gather their enthusiasm, be ready to
unleash hell when you hit the Kickstarter button and you get that.
This.
How many of you went to the Darkest Dungeon talk yesterday?
Okay, enough people that I'll skip over this somewhat.
The Darkest Dungeon, guys.
made an amazing game with kick-ass design
and they found a problem with the design halfway through development
and they fixed it
and the fix was necessary and it was very painful to their community
and their community went absolutely batshit
they held their nerve
and they kept going, they didn't listen too hard to their veterans
that was the right thing to go do and that's why Darkest Dungeon has gone on to sell
nearly a million copies and has undergone tremendous critical acclaim.
Sunless Sea. We didn't do quite as well on that. One of the problems of Sunless Sea
is that if you die you start over. That's okay, that's fine, it's a little bit of a
roguelite with permadeath, but the experience of starting over means going
through the same content over and over again. There's not much randomness at the
beginning.
Big design flaw, I own that, it made the game much less than it could have been.
And the reason we didn't realize how big a problem it was, is that we were listening to the veterans too much.
People were talking about the end game experience, people were talking about how, what it was like when you played through most of the content.
We forgot to focus on the early game experience.
Your veterans will be the most vocal people on your forums and in your feedback.
They will really care about the game. They supported you from very early on.
You should listen to them, but you should not listen to them too much.
You should bear in mind, they're not going to be new customers ever again.
They're not going to give you unbiased feedback.
And you think you know this. We thought we knew this. We thought we'd adjusted.
Think harder. Assume it's always going to be easier to overrate than you can.
Really don't listen to them too hard.
Kickstarter itself. So here are the obvious benefits.
A chunk of backers. A chunk of money.
A third of our backers came through Kickstarter.
I'm not sure what the figures will be these days. Now it's a couple of years on.
But Kickstarter is a marketing platform itself.
So you can, if you get a staff pick, and if you've got a good pitch, you'll probably get a staff pick.
Get a good chance of getting new backers.
Once we crossed about 50 grand, I don't know what the number would be these days,
once we crossed about 50 grand we started getting press coverage without needing to chase people.
So once your Kickstarter is a success, if you actually start raising enough people to pay
attention, then the press stop ignoring you as one of another million Kickstarter projects.
You can get that far, it makes a big difference. And of course we got lots and lots of early
feedback on design which is vital. But the less obvious...
less obvious benefits of Kickstarter.
We got, as I mentioned earlier, early feedback on the message.
So we didn't just go with our first-pass marketing message and put it out there.
We listened to what people said worked and we changed it.
We were forced to explain what our vision for the game was very early on
and then forced to stick to it. Now this is a double-edged sword.
I've heard a lot of people in the last couple of days say they would hate that.
And for some studios, creative process, it doesn't work at all.
For us, it did. For us, it kept us honest because I am scatty and prone to run after new, shiny ideas.
And it was very beneficial to have that.
But if you go on Kickstarter and commit to a vision, you are stuck with that vision for the foreseeable future.
The other thing that's an unalloyed benefit, it's not a double-edged sword at all, and I can't overstate it enough,
if you've been labouring in the dark for months with no money,
suddenly 4,000 people want to give you money, that is wonderful.
Feedback on design, very quickly, that was our change in the combat system.
This was our equivalent of Darkest Dungeon's difficult balance change.
We went from the combat system on the left to the combat system on the right.
Very late in development, cost a couple of months, very difficult, very painful, absolutely
worthwhile.
Lifted the game from people going the combat's awful to people going the combat's okay but
a bit meh.
And you know, I'll take that.
Two things about that. First of all, again, something that's come up a lot in the last few talks
is the difficulty of making major feature changes in early access.
So I think of it like this. You have goodwill that you spend like currency from your community.
If you treat them well, if you treat them honestly, then you accrue more of that goodwill
and you can spend it on major feature changes. But you can't do it wildly. Doesn't mean you
shouldn't do it at all. Just make sure you have the goodwill in the bank and be ready
to cushion them when you go through. Stretch goals.
I hate stretch goals.
I think it's very easy to get focused on that number that's like a score, the funding total
at the end of a Kickstarter at the expense of making the game and to make promises about
expansions or platform ports or other things you might want to do.
You get 20 more grand funding, that will disappear in a month, in six months you've got a very
small team.
There are two kinds of stretch goals that I'm in favour of.
One is things you're secretly going to do anyway.
The other is things that cost almost no money
and are cool and attract attention.
Like this.
So I know one of our backers
paid three and a half grand
in order to get this ink on my leg
and that cost me 60 pounds.
And that's a bargain.
So if you can find stretch goals that are interesting and low cost,
then do them. Otherwise, think very carefully before committing to promises for the future.
The ending first.
The common wisdom is that narrative in early access doesn't work.
For us, it did.
We did well in early access, we did better in full launch.
And I think the reason that this worked better for us is that we did the ending first.
This is a good rule for writing generally if you're doing content,
but it's particularly important in early access.
The moment we launched the game, people could finish it, unless they found a bug.
But, in theory they could finish it, they could actually achieve a victory condition.
So you could get to the end and then over the next year we blocked in all the content in the middle.
So people could play the game through to the end, then come back and find more content.
And also they could trust us. It didn't look like we had just started writing a story and
we're going to make it up as we went along and work out what to do when you got to that point.
So if you're going to do a content-based, narrative-based Kickstarter,
always make sure you have an ending that you understand
you can always change the ending
if you have a better idea a year on, you can change it
but it's better to have an ending than no ending
Your team will go nuts obsessing on every item of feedback if they can
and chase them out of the forums.
Give them like 20 minutes to read the feedback and then say,
no, come on, you can look at it tomorrow.
Slap the rest of your team if you see them looking.
Make a joke of it, put them in the naughty corner,
but protect them because people get really hung up and really down on it.
If you have a community manager, a communications director, anybody like that to help filter stuff, that's obviously much preferred.
And, educate your community to answer.
So, if...
People... lots of people come to the game and say, I don't understand Sumnersea at all, I die constantly, it's really hard.
Our community would say, yes, it's supposed to be hard, and then teach them how to go through it.
And that would save our time responding to people.
So put the effort into educating your community so they can do your job for you, in that respect.
And don't tell people more than they need to know.
If you've got your Kickstarter running, if you're putting out a new update every month or two,
people can see there's recent activity, people can see what you're doing.
They do not need to know every detail of your roadmap.
We taught people a lot and they didn't remember most of it and it took a lot of effort.
So make sure you can show it's a live project but don't go nuts trying to keep them up to date.
We did, we had a completion chart. We had like a bar graph of 10 things
with 70% complete, 80% complete. A tiny minority of our players ever read it.
Valve is also funny about this kind of thing in early access these days anyway, so I wouldn't recommend doing that.
Always, when you are releasing on a new platform, especially as indie devs who might not have done this before,
do some sort of soft launch or some sort of limited beta beforehand.
We did our backers beta on Humble Bundle, it was a good experience,
but there were problems with the process that we found and fixed when it was still not an issue.
We did early access on Steam. My god, I'm glad we did early access on Steam before the full launch because the
Back end of Steam. I can't say too much because obviously valves ninjas will drag me off the stage, but it's a bit like
Going inside the monolith in 2001 a space odyssey. It's very confusing. Make sure you you practice things up front
And this, if you do well, if you do well, if you're a delicate creative soul, and many
of the people in this room are, I certainly am, make sure that you are ready to be supported
by your friends and your team, where you suddenly look around and see that you've succeeded
and the project you've been working on for the last 6 months, 12 months, a year, 12 months
a year, 12 months, 2 years, has finished and you don't know what to do with your life.
Make sure that somebody's there to catch you in your fall.
It sounds like a nice problem to have.
You're successful, you get depressed,
but even a fairly minor success,
you get the post-project blues.
Quick follow-through at the end.
So, we learned a lot from open production,
and we thought very hard about
how to make that work in our production process,
both in the future for other open production projects,
and more generally.
I'll skim through these, I'm short of time.
Vision is the most important thing. Again, there have been several really good talks about it this year.
I particularly recommend the Red Hood guys, Darkest Dungeon, Creative Direction, talk if you find it in the vault.
If you have a consistent creative vision, it means that your team understands you.
You're not sitting there on your throne waiting for people to bring you concept art and say,
not that one, it needs to have more shush.
and your community understand it, your community can tell you whether they like it or not
and you have a ready-made message for marketing.
So double down there.
This is what we said we wanted in Sunless Sea from day one.
Every single creative decision we made, every technical decision we made,
every marketing decision we made, made reference to that.
Points of light in the darkness, the possibility of imminent death.
The sense of being something tiny and alone, a rocking ship of a boat on a giant, dark,
hungry ocean.
The sense of coming home again.
All that stuff.
Find your creative direction.
Stick to it like a facehugger.
Culture...
What I wanted to do was say something about studio culture without any of this stuff.
I've never heard anybody say, we're not passionate about games, we hate communication, excellence
is really bad.
So some really specific stuff that might not work for everybody, but work for us.
This is our guiding principle.
Safety first, then fun, then profit.
When I said at the beginning it's important to think about sustainability, that's what
I had in mind most.
Every decision we make about what games to build and what to do next, we think about
the long-term financial viability of the studio, then we think about how much fun it will be
to do.
And after that...
we think about how much profit it will make,
because I never want to look four of my friends in the eyes,
three of my friends in the eyes,
and tell them they've lost their jobs ever again.
So if you're an indie studio,
if you're not a funded startup,
if you're an indie studio that is trying to make
a buck day in, day out,
you are often going to have to make decisions
that are temperate of the expense of decisions
that might potentially pay off big.
We have a very clear studio identity, that second paragraph. I mean that's really specific
But our audience know what we like and they come back to and respond to it. So I
This doesn't work for everybody, but I recommend
Having a consistent studio identity and making all your games fit that mold
Some people are wildly creative and want to do a different thing
With every project. I salute you. We couldn't do it. This really worked for us
and we are visible to our community. I protect my team
and my communications director protects our team
from the community but they know who we are, they know our names, they often know
when we've worked on individual bits and this humanizes us and it means that
we can pass back attaboys from our community.
Slack, who's using Slack?
Yeah, God it's terrifying, it's everywhere.
It's really good, it's just awesome.
If you're not using it, it's a chat application
that's very good at integrating other streams.
This is what you use for tracking support.
Our Zendesk tickets, our Twitter responses,
forum responses, Reddit posts, and the SummerSea subreddit,
all this goes in one channel.
Everybody can see it. We chase people out of it if they're obsessing about it.
People can comment on it snarkily in real time without users seeing it.
But it gives us one place that allows us to track community directions generally.
So that's a really revelatory tool.
Other stuff, very quickly, production things.
Where we ended up after Summer Sea was two week sprints.
Month long sprints were too sloppy, week long sprints were too crazy.
We don't do sprint retrospectives because we find that after two weeks people don't really have
enough new things to say. At the end of every month we do a review of what we've achieved and not.
Tech and content, we're a very content-driven studio.
We have a full-time writing team.
So we have writing tasks and tech tasks.
They use very similar processes, but not entirely similar.
Tech, we really focus on a Google Sheets
spready with estimates.
Content, we use something much more like a Kanban board.
We originally had a Kanban board and a spreadsheet for
both.
we found that the two together
often are a bit surplus.
So trim down your production tools
to the ones you're actually using.
This, right, I want to leave you with this.
This is what I posted on Slack
just before we launched Summer's Sea.
Some people have no choice but to crunch.
If you have any choice about crunching,
crunch is bullshit.
I've only been a game dev for seven years,
but I've been in tech for 20 years.
And the data are in.
It's really clear.
You can work overtime for a week, two weeks,
and you see a boost in productivity.
You work overtime for four weeks.
eight weeks, six months, your productivity drops.
You end up getting less out than you would.
Maybe you're a prodigy and you can work as an indie
in voluntary crunch for six months at a time,
10 hours a day, 12 hours a day,
and get good value out of it.
Statistically speaking, you can't.
Statistically speaking, your ability to evaluate
your own work and spot the defects you put in your work
drops as you work overtime.
So just statistically speaking.
Working overtime for extended periods of time is usually bullshit.
It limits your ability to find other answers.
If you get to the end of a Kickstarter, or towards the end of a Kickstarter,
and you find you're running out of money and you can't do enough,
do not work overtime for more than a handful of weeks,
and compensate your people with time off if you do.
Find things to cut.
You will understand your game much better at the end of the process than you did at the beginning,
so you know what you can get away with cutting.
Find other ways to do it. Look for other funding processes, anything like this.
If you just think, I'm going to work 16 hours today, tomorrow, next week,
you'll burn yourself out and you'll make a worse game because of it.
Conscious bullshit.
One more thing.
Open production goes both ways.
We wanted to build a community that will feed back to us.
We're also trying to build a modest ecology of indie devs
and would-be indie devs who work with us to make games
and to teach them what we've learned
and to learn from them in turn.
We've got two people in our incubation scheme
at the moment.
We've funded one of them.
We've just announced Fun Better,
the end of the second line there,
a very small funding initiative for narrative-driven games.
We're talking up to 20 grand.
But it's enough to get an interesting small narrative project off the ground.
Google our studio name and that word if you want to find out more about it.
And that's me.
Thanks very much.