Yeah, I'm super excited about speaking at GDC this year, about unleashing your creative side.
Ever since I was little, I've always wondered what it meant to be a creative person.
I tried all sorts of things to unlock that potential, but when I joined Rare,
I learned that creativity comes in many forms.
I also learned that there's no one way to put yourself into an inventive mindset.
And that you can always find inventive ways to express yourself with what's around you.
I can't wait to share what I've learned on my journey through the industry and hopefully
help other people to find their creative spark.
The most exciting thing about GDC is that exchange of ideas and it would be so great
if people could go back to their teams with new ways of thinking and hopefully we can
unleash new creative weirdos out into the world.
There's always one! There's always one!