Thank you so much for coming.
I know it's very tough after a week of GDC and GDC parties, so I appreciate everyone
that's in the room this morning.
I want to welcome to this panel that is kind of virtual.
So it's kind of ironic that we are trying to talk about the metaverse
in a virtual way with you there.
And I want to present the fantastic people that here is with me
and I will allow them to present themselves.
So anyone who wants to start, maybe Andres.
Yes, my name is Sanchez Guadalmos. Unlike what it says there, I'm no longer a senior lecturer
in technical property at the University of Sussex. I've been promoted to reader.
I have no idea what that means other than it's the same salary but a slightly different title.
Sounds impressive.
Exactly.
Avi?
I am Avi Barzev. Nobody knows my company, RealityPrime, because it's a small consulting company.
But they do know the projects that I've worked on in the past. So I'll just mention that I
helped start the HoloLens. I worked at Apple. I worked at Amazon on Echo Frames and
I've been working in AR and VR for about 30 years now.
That's amazing. So glad to have you. Dylan?
My name is Dylan Orkidi, as is noted on the slide here.
I'm a research engineer slash designer
and a deeply passionate individual
that's been focused on creating realities
and building VR experiences and advancing the technology.
Thanks to the support of the Unity Labs research staff
and my team, my work was recently presented at MetaConnect
and we've got a few new projects
that will be debuted next year.
So I'm just excited to be amongst this.
awesome roster here and explore the future. We are so lucky to have you here. And then we have
Kurt, another huge name in the digital rights frontier, maybe you say. Thank you, thank you
much. Yeah, my name is Kurt Absal, I'm the Deputy Executive Director and General Counsel with the
Electronic Frontier Foundation.
I'm also part of the EFF teams have been working on decentralization and extended reality issues.
You know, if our mission, we're trying to protect and preserve the rights we hold dear
while moving into the future or chart the course for a future
where technology will enhance our lives and preserve our human rights.
I have been a deeply admire of the work that EFF has been doing for years.
So it's a pleasure to have you all.
And to start our panel and our discussion, I prepare some.
things to put everyone together in like in the same page. I can see hands because we don't have
a camera, but I guess that a lot of you have heard about these words in the past months or the past
year. We are building in the metaverse. We are building a metaverse because the industry has
this shift that now everyone is building a metaverse and maybe we don't even know what
it is yet. This of course we know that started with the book, at least the concept and the word.
And then we have a lot of references that are going into pop culture about simulation theory,
about new realities, about virtual realities and how they're portrayed in the pop media,
in the culture. And also, we were saying that we still don't have like a definition of what
the metaverse is, like a consensus on it. Somebody said that it's an embodied internet,
other talks about this as the next evolution of the internet.
We are here to discuss that if it is something new or it's just essentially the same internet,
but now in 3D.
Also another thing that everyone is kind of debating these days is which are the defining
characteristics of the metaverse.
Because at this point, we are, as we were saying, creating some realities.
And for those, I don't believe that in the audience
that is anyone that hasn't heard about the metaverse, but maybe picture
like the good, the good place and how they constructed this reality.
And we want to talk about the ethics of creating this kind of virtual places
and this kind of everything by design places.
Also, we have been reading about the opinions that the industry has on the metaverse and
the technologies around the metaverse.
And this is from the CDC state of the game industry that about one third of the responders
believe that the metaverse will not deliver on this promise.
So we will see if we can or cannot change your mind.
Also, we don't agree in the name.
Sometimes it says metaverse.
She's talking about like.
a relationship like websites and the internet.
And also we have big topics to discuss today because.
we are kind of being sold into that there is only one version of the metaverse,
or at least the one that is being presented in the media.
But we are here to talk about big topics like decentralization
and centralization that are kind of two big philosophies
of designing around the Internet and particularly about interoperability,
both technical and legally, and how these these kind of key concepts
influence the metaverse that we will want to have in the future.
So.
Also, we want to talk a bit about wallet gardens.
Maybe you have heard of this.
It's a concept from internet governance.
When we are talking about kind of fragmentations
of the web and the internet,
and this is certainly something we don't want to reply
in the metaverse models.
So for those who are as old as I am,
you might remember the Truman Show
and the reality of that movie, portraying that movie.
So this is kind of something similar.
And the metaverse will encompass everything in our lives,
or at least is that the promise.
So we need to find ways to create a responsible design
that is diverse, accessible, safe, equitable,
and overall human rights space.
So this is our three central questions
for our panel today.
Who will control the metaverse?
About the revenue models that are we
and how they will impact in digital rights?
And what are the governance, ethical, and legal challenges
of the metaverse?
So for starting the first question about control,
these are our key topics.
So who wants to start with these ones?
I'll give it a bit of a go on the first one.
but what are the key characteristics that separate the metaverse from the current
internet or virtual worlds. I'm going to assume the mantle of the old man Niels at Cloud,
MIM, and claim that inherently there is no difference. So I would like to start with a
bit of the skeptical side. I've been writing and researching on this.
the regulation of the area for a while.
And I've seen various definitions, as you were saying,
Mikaela, about what exactly is a metaverse
and other definitions that...
I have to say that there is nothing new here, at least for us who lived through the first virtual world's craze around 2006, 2007, maybe even before.
There are repetitions of lots of grandiose claims, and it may seem that the metaverse that we're seeing may depend on who is doing it, on three definitions.
I would say that...
This is potentially going to be a virtual environment that is ruled by platforms,
or it's going to be web-3 led, or it's going to be open virtual platforms. So,
whatever the discussion we're going to have, it may depend on what
type of metaverse we're talking about. I know exactly what type of metaverse we're talking about.
we may get different versions of the three of them.
In some ways, this will depend.
The platform metaverse is just a subsidiary
of existing platforms, so it's going
to be pretty much the same.
The Web3 metaverse is going to be a tokenized utopia
of unicorns and rainbows and blockchains,
or the entirely open decentralized metaverse,
that it would be very different.
So the last two would definitely be different
from what we have right now.
I hope that makes sense.
Yeah, absolutely.
And I love like the two things like the old man yelling at cloud.
I can't identify with that.
And I also a bit of a skeptical, but I think that for me,
at least the key is interpretability.
When we have that, we can kind of separate the virtual world
from the metaverse.
Who wants to chime in on this?
If I could add something in addition to that,
I think there'll be a very important transition
that can be controlled by entities
that might potentially seek to very specifically mandate
APIs that they can copyright and they can control
that could take us away from the current internet paradigm.
and divert us from the promise of Web 3 through that practice.
And I'm seeing whispers of that.
And I do hope that we have enough awareness to make sure that we can navigate around that
and prevent that from allowing the true interoperability and the promise of what it is that I think
that we're seeking with this discussion.
Absolutely. That is what I sometimes call legal interoperability,
because to go from one metaverse to another,
if you don't have agreements and contracts that allowed out from a legal standpoint,
you are going to go like a very strict customs that are going to take all your digital goods.
And also you need technical interoperability because you need a technical architecture
that allows to portray the object and the functions of the object in another software environment.
So as you were saying for me,
it's something big having interoperability.
Kurt, you were...
Yeah, I wanna-
Putting your hand up for decentralization.
Yeah, I wanna say a few words on decentralization.
Well, first of all, it's sort of re-decentralization.
Like decentralization was a key feature
of the early internet where it was a network of networks.
And in some sense,
what you imagine a decentralized metaverse
is sort of a world of worlds where you are a universe,
at least of worlds where you can go around them
in between various ones.
But we've seen the internet has been continually centralized over the last couple of decades.
And we've seen some of the problems of that single points of controls and single points of failures.
Now, we'll talk about this a more a bit, but I think a walled garden,
it may be attractive to some as it provides additional securities that has an environment
that you might be able to rely on to be in a particular way. But it's still best to have
a choice to be able to move freely between the environments you want to visit.
So we don't want to be locked out or locked in.
So we want to have a decentralized Metaverse that is interoperable and locked open,
resisting attempts to centralize its architecture, its services, its protocols,
and that'll make it more resilient against censorship, surveillance,
and other forms of centralized control.
But we can imagine that, that we can build it.
But to do that, interoperability will be a key.
You have a consistent avatar that goes with you across platforms,
subject to your control, but not tied to a single provider.
And we will talk about more of these things.
The important thing is we're setting these technologies today,
which are the stage for the technologies of tomorrow.
I wanted to jump in on that point, too.
I think that, you know, as Kurt said, that the Internet was designed
to be decentralized for robustness and for freedom.
But we could very easily get back to centralization, even after.
re-decentralizing it, we can re-centralize it again.
And one of the things that I see,
one of the dangers I see leading to that
is that people talk about decentralization
like it's a panacea,
but what they really want is democratization.
And some of the actual technologies
that people are talking about,
especially with Web3, are prone to re-centralization.
There's a lot of discussion now about,
even though blockchain is out there,
You go through various centralized providers
to get to it.
And I think one of the most important things to think about
is with DAOs, which I think I love the concept
of trying to build democracy into our structures,
is that when just a slight change
in the way the DAO is built can make a huge difference.
If it's one vote per person.
that's democracy. If it's one vote per token or per coin or per share, that's a plutocracy.
And plutocracies invariably lead to re-centralization because they're
concentrations of wealth. The people who have the wealth have more votes, they can sway,
they can tilt the playing field in their direction without a countervailing force,
and they can get all the coins eventually. And so what we need is systems that
continually re-democratize these things. They don't just do it once, but they keep re-dividing
the pie equally so that we all have a fair say. And I don't see very many DAOs that even think
about that. There's only a few that are thinking about people versus coins.
Just a side note on that, for those who are in a DAO that is set up as a plutocracy, as Avi's saying,
where it is done by the amount of tokens you control,
you should look through the history of corporate governance.
That's basically the model of shareholders.
And we have had hundreds of years of issues in corporate governments.
I think there's a lot to be learned about mistakes that were made there
that can be applied to setting up a system that deals with that.
cares about minority shareholder rights,
or as Abby says, just go straight
to actual democratization, where it is one person, one vote.
Perhaps also a little bit on that.
One of the problems I see with the decentralization
versus centralization debate is that what we are seeing
is that it appears like the internet abhors
decentralization.
We created this network for decentralization,
with decentralization in mind,
but it keeps wanting to become centralized.
I think that there are various reasons for this.
There are network theory reasons in which
there is the accumulation of links that happens,
and there are architectural reasons for that.
And I think that actually decentralization is very difficult.
And my fear, and I'm going to keep playing the skeptic...
My fear is that even if we try to achieve it, the environment that we have right now
is going to move towards centralization.
It's already happening.
depending on the model that we are looking at,
all the metaverse, if it's going to be the meta Facebook metaverse,
it's going to be centralized by almost by definition.
So yeah, we have to be careful, but also be aware that sometimes
all the best efforts towards decentralization may actually fail
because that is the nature of the network.
Sorry, I'm going to be very skeptical.
That's fantastic.
I think that these are real problems that need to be solved.
Some of the advantages of centralization are a single point where you can have a team of
security engineers who are making sure that it is up to date, that they are putting out
patches, improving it.
We have to make sure that if we have a decentralized system, it is also secure.
That requires a bit more work.
I think it's worthwhile.
we will have a better future if there is lots of choice and people can move around and have that.
But it has to be one where they have their rights intact and part of that is having a secure and
private experience that requires a replication of some of these advantages that might become
tempting for centralization.
And that's one of the reasons why I think walled gardens become appealing.
Not that I'm going to argue for walled gardens, but security can definitely be improved.
That's the reason for a gated community, theoretically, is to be able to have
some security as to who comes in and who goes out.
But also, the reason walled gardens exist is because
they just may not be enough good content out there yet.
I think initially we should expect walled gardens to happen because it's much more economical
to build up your own content first until you get to a certain point. Like we saw with CompuServe and
AOL, you get to a certain point because there isn't enough out there that you want that you
feel is good enough, but at a certain point everything else out there becomes way better
than what's inside the walled gardens. And that's when the walls need to come down because people
are going to leave your walled gardens to go out and explore the world when the world becomes richer.
and more interesting than what's within the gardens.
And we'll see the same thing here again.
We'll see a whole bunch of walled gardens.
There won't be a lot of reasons
for interconnecting these things together
until people say they want to leave,
until people want to go and connect these things
and build bridges and build new worlds
that are bigger than any individual walled garden maybe.
Absolutely, and if I could piggyback on that, this is where it's so absolutely important to, of course, not only support open source efforts, but even commercial efforts right now that have resisted acquisition by certain corporations to foster those communities and to see where it is that they're choosing to open source certain approaches like
you know, the implementation of WASM and other technologies to be able to make sure that on a platform that say, I don't know, changes the implementation of a standard web browser and prevents others from being able to implement any other browser on that platform that we can still get around that and have just in time compilation to make sure that you can have that interoperable experience.
that goes from platform to platform when you can see the trajectory that is potentially going to
lock that out and prevent that situation here. So it's not just about application deployment.
It's also about, again, this open flow of the ability for a standard set of APIs and
implementations to be able to go from platform to platform. And we need to be very, very careful and
mindful where we're seeing those gates closed because
To be able to say we support the web is one thing, but to be able to actually support the open web
is a very, very different thing. And we're seeing different walled gardens that are very
beautifully and strategically navigating a process that will prevent that open implementation of,
say, as Kurt mentioned, which is extremely important. An avatar that can bring,
basically within itself, its own operating system, its own set of applications.
et cetera, in between these environments. And we're beginning to get the hints, in my
opinion, of the prevention of this. And I think that that's extremely dangerous. And
we need to be very mindful as to how we can prevent that situation.
Absolutely. I think that one of the bad sides of centralization is people get tied to a
system because that's where their content is, that's where their friends are, these
network effects, and it's difficult to move.
And I think, you know, avatars, I think is an example that resonates well because it's
a common thing now that people will spend a lot of time investing in their avatar and
its design, what clothes are being worn, how it interacts.
And if they have to go to a different platform, they don't want to do that all over again.
They want to be able to take that.
part of their identity with them. They might have multiple identities that they would put out there,
but they want to be able to interact with people, keeping with them this identity that they've
invested in. And the steps that try to prevent that aren't really security and privacy. I think
those parts can be handled. It is more trying to get the network effects so that everyone's
on your network and they won't. Right.
I was going to agree that this is something that we already have seen on the internet,
that everyone wants this old quote that if you are not paid for something, you are the product.
This is going to replicate in this because if you have to pay in a metaverse and other metaverse is
going to offer you like avatars and choices to create this content, you're going to prefer that.
So for me, that's a delicate balance
that we are going to have to strike
because at the same time, one of the revenue models,
and we are going to talk a bit about this,
is profiting from content.
So I think like to kind of quote this part of the discussion
is like decentralization is very tied
to the revenue models that we're going to see maybe.
So that was my two cents.
Avi, please go.
Yeah, maybe this will help close the section a little bit, but what we need to do for the
so-called metaverse is very much like what happened with the web. We need the ability to link
between different spaces so that we can point to other spaces and create semantic models between
them.
We need portals, but portals actually are like iframes. If you look at browser technology,
they need to be implemented as a sandbox because you don't want a doorway to another world being
able to either steal information or impose and create an attack surface. So you want to sandbox
it and isolate it in the way the iframes were meant to do. They didn't work perfectly, but
they were meant to do this.
And we ultimately will be creating a web,
just essentially like the web that we see in 2D,
but a web of all these spaces together
that make the greater space.
And it's less about, can I bring my middle earth?
fighter dwarf, you know, with plus one verbal sword into a science fiction battle.
That doesn't make sense semantically.
And the designers of each of those spaces don't want that to happen.
But that's not the point.
The point is that I have the freedom, as Kurt said, to have the freedom
to take what I've done and not be tied to a platform that isn't working in my favor.
And just like we did with phone numbers, we want portability.
We want the ability to say, screw you, AT&T, I'm going over here.
And that's it. Once we have that, we have the ability,
we have more power and more control over our destiny
once we have that.
Absolutely. Nobody's going to separate myself
from my virtual pet companion.
I'm going to tell you that.
No meta, no everyone.
Let's move a bit for the revenue models of the metaverse.
So, we're going to have like a lot of memes
because everyone here is kind of a geek.
So we have also seen the respondents of the GDC state of the game industry, that is a huge backlash
against NFTs and against cryptocurrencies and implementing these in games. But in the people's
eye, metaverses are kind of very related to gaming or are very kind of close to gaming.
The sentiment is strong about NFTs,
and I really love this one.
I'd rather not endorse burning a rainforest down
to confirm that someone else owns a GPG.
So my questions for you is like,
taking on this possible models of revenue for the metaverse
by seeing content and data collection on content creation,
what can we expect to see?
As the lawyer, I guess I can give it a start again.
Sorry to sound like a broken record, but it may depend really on the model that is going
to be adopted in the platform metaverse, let's say your meta metaverse.
all ownership will go to the platform.
And I'm expecting that this is going to be,
this is already what happens.
You don't own your content, you are licensed.
You receive a license that allows you
to operate in that space.
You don't own your virtual property.
All of that is owned by the platform.
by the developer, the company that operates the space. The idea, I think, of the appeal of the
Web3 idea of the metaverse is that the ownership is going to be tied with tokens and possibly with
NFTs, even though there is, as you were saying, Michaela, very rightly, a big pushback against
this. And I think that this idea is that the smart contracts are going to mediate the scheme.
The problem with that is, obviously, there is nothing that ties a token with the ownership
of the item, of the asset. So you may have a token, but you may claim or it may link you to
something, but there's nothing legal that says that that asset is yours just because you own
that token. We would have to build in a system of recognition of the ownership of tokens.
I'm afraid that it probably would make things very difficult, very clunky.
If anyone has tried to use the central land, I have tried.
I found it extremely slow and clunky, personally.
The third model would be.
to have something more open, something akin to what Second Life was doing back in the early days.
I don't know if people are familiar with that. You would pretty much own everything that you
created and you would be able to get a CC license from that. So it was still sort of
owned in some ways by the platform, but you'd be getting a very strong copyright ownership claim.
Those are the three models I think are possibly emerging.
I worked on Second Life and I don't take any credit for the ecosystem stuff that Philip
Rosedale really spearheaded.
He brought in actual economists and did a really great job of trying to create a virtual
economy that could thrive, that didn't suffer from inflation or deflation.
And I think it's worth mentioning that a lot of these models that we're seeing emerge now
are based on this idea of artificial scarcity.
which is inherently deflationary.
The whole idea of buying an NFT today
in the hope that it's going to triple
or 10x in value or go to the moon
is inherently deflationary.
It causes people to buy things and hoard them.
What we really want is a model of abundance.
And Second Life had that.
It had the ability to copy things really easily.
And people made money.
People, in fact, made...
made more money per person than they do today
off of a lot of these other systems,
including Roblox and other UGC systems.
And not only that, but the company made more money per person
than the companies today like Google and Facebook do
off of advertising models.
So it was actually, it didn't scale
because there were only millions of people.
There weren't hundreds of millions of people,
but it was a good model, still is.
And there's a lot to learn from it.
And I think a lot of people in this space just ignore that
and start over and say, well, we should just do this.
And what we're doing instead is,
relying on this craziness of artificial scarcity. The whole point of it was abundance, was that
things are now easy to copy and we should be reveling in that superpower of being able to
create infinite numbers of things and not trying to impose these limits of scarcity in order just
for some people to make money. Because clearly not everybody can make money that way. It's
impossible that we can all succeed. So let's come up with a better model that we can actually all
succeed at.
As a Star Trek fan, I support that wholeheartedly because I think about the replicators and
the thing that we could replicate everything at all kind of zero marginal cost.
And we are trying to do the opposite here because we are trying to create artificial
scarcity and close, as you were saying, something that is inherently possible in the digital
world.
Another interesting thing is like you were talking about second life revenue models and what we are
seeing in the platforms that today deal with user-generated content is like the opposite
model. It's like taking what people create in those platforms and trying to appropriate that.
And I think as you were saying, this is going to suffocate the creativity that we need in the
metaverse.
There was a meme that went around for a while,
that you wouldn't download a car.
It was like a campaign against downloading music.
And of course you would download a car.
And now in a metaverse, you can download a car.
But I think we can take some lessons from that,
is that I guess people do want to have that.
They want to have a car that they can download.
And if you make it a reasonable fee, a convenience fee,
or you pay a subscription and you get some assets
to do things.
There's a revenue model there. But if it's a revenue model that's trying to make it so that
you have to pay for your downloaded car something akin to what you would pay for a real life car,
you've got a few people to do that. But that's not creating a better world.
They're trying to replicate, as I was saying, replicate the scarcity of our world.
And one of the challenging things that there was is the internet has basically zero cost for copying.
And a lot of our old world revenue models are based on it costs money to buy the materials,
put them together, get them to a store, ship them to your house or whatever,
all of these costs. And the internet makes those costs low.
And so the good world that comes out of that is that the creators and innovators behind it can
get a larger chunk of their revenues than they currently get, and people will be paying less.
What? And the right-click mentality is out there, absolutely. And that's also something that people
have to realize when they're getting involved in an NFT. You really understand what it is.
It's a notation on a blockchain that says something often pointing to a URL. It is not a copyright
in what it is on that URL. You do not get any rights transferred to it. You get a notation
on a blockchain.
Now, sometimes that is a cool notation. It's the only one of that. It's like getting an artist to
sign something. If it's the original artist and they give you an NFT of a piece of artwork,
that might be similar to a physical signature on a piece of artwork that you buy in an art gallery.
But if you're thinking you're getting ownership in any traditional sense, like a legal sense,
that doesn't happen inherently from an NFT.
My question is, because I'm going to take advantage that there are a few lawyers in the room and IP lawyers and copyright lawyers for the worst, to ask this, is there any way you think that we can have ownership attached to an NFT?
we can create this setting in which we can transfer copyright through NFT.
Andres and I, we were talking a lot about this on Twitter because we all seen what
happens with SpiceDAO and their confusion about copyright and what...
at the acquisition of a book if they can,
what they can and can't do with copyright.
And there is this thing that is very confusing for people,
like actually owning an object
and having the digital rights, sorry,
the rights, the intellectual property rights
that go with that.
So do you think that we can technically solve this
to have, technically from the legal perspective,
solve this to have two ownership attached to an NFT?
Well, go ahead, Kurt.
I was going to say, from a U.S. copyright law perspective,
you basically have a copyright registration system
in order to file a lawsuit to enforce your IP rights.
You need to register the copyright with the Copyright Office.
You could.
Imagine a system in which you are registering that instead of with the copyright office,
registering that on a blockchain,
because that is an instance in which you want a permanent record that's featured in the blockchain hat.
But it would have to be like a better system than the registration system with the copyright office, which could probably be improved, but it's actually a pretty simple and cheap system to use.
And it's the only one that is enforced by law.
So if you have an NFT that says this copyright belongs to you and you try and then sue over it, it doesn't matter unless you also have a copyright restriction.
Yes. In other countries, we don't have a registration system. So in some ways, it could be both easier and more difficult because the transfer of copyright then it has to have certain types of formalities in the UK, for example, it needs to be the transfer of copyright has to be in writing and signed.
I think that you could possibly argue that the signature,
you can use something like your wallet to sign something,
that could be acceptable,
but I cannot see an NFT or a smart contract
fulfilling the requirements in writing.
I cannot see this working, at least on the current framework.
The only way I can imagine potentially using NFTs is to create a new format in which you can build
in sort of a dumb contract into the system in which
the NFT links or contains also in the smart contract,
a transfer of ownership.
That is the only system that I can see,
but you need to change the current standards that you have.
So it is possible, or it's also possible to have ownership
or transfer ownership of on-chain items,
items that exist only on the blockchain,
but those are extremely rare and very expensive.
there is a cost that goes into uploading information
into the blockchain.
So I can see it right now, it's not possible.
It's potentially viable.
I think that you can probably build hacks around this,
have a normal contract accompanying
the creation of an NFT, et cetera, et cetera.
But right now in the system as it stands,
it's very unlikely that you'll be able to manage that.
If I could add something in the intersection
in between revenue models and say copyright,
given the topic, I'm personally working on
and I'm working with a number of other individuals
that are working on a sort of inversion model with NFTs,
where you have an experiential economy
that creates an NFT that lets, for example,
say it's an application or a virtual reality experience.
And the participants that spend time in that experience are both investing some type of
currency at that point, but potentially also accruing a localized currency within that
specific NFT. And at that point, I can at least speak to the projects I'm working on.
the individual that spends that time there is also able to sculpt and reshape that NFT
in sort of a remixed form that will go with any exchange of that NFT to another owner at that
point. So I think that we need a new concept of copyright in the sense that it needs to be
far more dynamic, far more agile.
And that that individual that, let's say, you buy my NFT, you shape that experience
and remix it into your own form, someone else spends 1000 human hours in there,
they've accrued a different set of value, there needs to be this attribution financially and say,
copyright wise, whatever, something that can be legally defended, I think is what we're coming
down to. Because that's really all that matters here. Otherwise, you're just making the claim,
there needs to be something that as it transfers from owner to owner that we accrue this
this value that carries itself amongst user to user to user, buyer to buyer to buyer,
and is automatically attributed to anyone that played that role in that process there.
I'm not seeing that in the legal spectrum right now, but it's coming. The next generation of
NFTs will not just be JPEGs. They will be experiences that approve value based on
individuals that spend time in there at a certain point. And I think we need to prepare for that.
I don't think we are at this point.
I'd like to see a radically different system.
And a lot of what you said resonates with me,
but I think, you know, and I don't call myself
a game developer because I've never shipped a game title.
Second Life is probably the closest that I came to that,
but I think I know enough game developers to say it.
I think the game development community has been very open.
about ideas. The whole idea has been, you know, to create a genre of games and people riff off
the same ideas and of course people make money at it, but it's been a very open community,
very anti-IP protection and things like that and I love that about it and I think that.
What we could imagine is a world in which we don't worry so much about ownership,
and we don't even worry so much about copying, but we worry about giving credit to who created ideas.
We focus on the creators of the idea, which I think copyright law seems to be meant to do.
The idea that even before I register with the Copyright Office,
just publishing something implicitly gives me some protections.
I can waive some of those with Creative Commons, but I get a lot of protections
just by putting my own content out there in public.
I think that's important.
I think the idea could be if we could just do a better job of keeping track of who came up with what ideas and then who modified which idea.
So what is the authorship chain of ideas?
So I take something that Michaela said or wrote or painted or whatever and improve it.
Can we measure the value added by me and the value added by the next person in the chain?
And then if way down the chain.
it makes money, great. The money can flow back through the chain. And if it doesn't make money,
that's okay too, because the credit, the authorship credit can flow back through the chain. So if
somebody makes a completely free game or movie, they can at least list the credits of who contributed
to it. And so we worry less about what's in my wallet and worry more about what's in my history,
what's in my CV, how did we each use each other's work.
And that's what I mean by abundance, because in a world like that, it encourages us to put our ideas out there,
essentially for free, in the hope that someone else will use them and improve them and make them better,
and build a richer world from that without worrying so much about,
can I get money for this thing on day one?
I don't want to worry about that. I want to worry about creating.
I want to make things and put them out there and see them grow.
I absolutely agree with that.
And also, I did some research in something that is kind of technical
or copyright, but it's called the negative areas of intellectual property.
And I totally agree that the video game industry was as a whole
a lot of permissive on the uses of video games.
And thanks to that, we have streaming and we have esports.
as two version in industry that were built on top of video games.
And also we have seen that there are alternative revenue models
that can work because sharing content is the model of the social networks.
TikTok has this model.
It's not doesn't matter who kind of
kind of.
is copying it, but it doesn't matter who created it. And it also, who added the value along the
chain. And also we are living in a culture that kind of...
glorifies repetition because we are seeing these trends of people doing the same dances,
which in the eyes of a copyright lawyer might be an aberration.
But this is the society we are living in and how people choose to consume content.
So I totally see that that the video game industry can spearhead
this kind of change into other areas of of video of copyright.
Is it now?
Yeah, as you mentioned, TikTok.
One of the things I think has been really impressive about TikTok is this
where someone will sing a song and then someone will present a their TikTok,
which is a duet with the first song, and then someone else will come on
to harmonize with that.
And each one is making the song sort of a richer and deeper experience.
I think that's sort of what you're talking about.
And, you know, it's done singing on TikTok is to maybe done with dancing as well.
But you can you can apply that theory, I think, to video games,
to all other forms of content, each one build on.
Absolutely. And let's go to the elephant in the room, the big challenges ahead.
We know that we all love cats, so I included this talking about how we are distracted by 3D
virtual cats while humanity in the metaverse is kind of caught in fire.
So our questions for ending this panel today are these that by no means are easy.
What are the legal and ethical challenges that you foresee ahead?
And what kind of are like the more urgent red flags
that we need to be paying attention to?
Well, I guess one of the challenges with any kind of virtual reality
universe in which you are projecting yourself into that universe
is in order to do that projection,
your device has to get a whole bunch of information about you.
And in some versions of this, you know, it's just your voice and a relatively robotic avatar.
Some visions, your hands will be moving in time with your hands, your facial expression
will be sent, and we'll have a much richer experience from the person you're interacting
with.
But all that data about everything you do is now being digitized and transmitted to
another service so it can be rendered for the other party.
but all of that is a tremendous amount of information about you for which people can draw
inferences, use those to advertise, to convince you of things, maybe not in traditional advertising.
And you were mentioning the Truman Show earlier, which is an example of sort of a, you know,
very dystopia of a world. It was not a virtual world in the modern sense, but it was basically
a world in which
all the interactions were being shown to one person that were being acted, that were being
betrayed to create a universe designed for them but designed to control them. And that is something
that is possible in a virtual reality where all the things around you that you're seeing
are designed to give you an impression and leave you with a set of...
desires that fit other people's interests and not your own.
And so that's one of the risks that we have to address
and make sure that we have the power,
that the users have the power,
that people are able to keep their rights with them.
So this is an, I absolutely agree with that.
And I would say this is, of course,
given the slide and the topic here,
absolutely important topic.
I strongly feel that we need to approach
an environment technologically where we give
zero trust to corporate entities. We give zero trust to governmental entities. And this needs
to happen with the implementation of zero knowledge proofs. This has to happen with
the implementation of homomorphic encryption. For example, in the case of FaceID, FaceID can
be done right now with private biometrics. Those aren't just two words. That is a very specific
technology that uses homomorphic encryption to make sure that not only is it more bandwidth
efficient and computationally efficient.
But there is no storage of the original image that was captured on device.
Any company that tells you that they're protecting your privacy,
for example, with something like face ID and they're not implementing
private biometrics is the specific example of what I'm speaking of.
This needs to be codified into law.
This is one of the reasons why I'm one of the backers, major backers
of the XR Safety Initiative and a number of other groups
that are aware of this, and they understand that what what Kurt mentioned there.
cannot occur as technology goes from the HMD, which is still external, to whatever will eventually be
implanted within us if we accept that. We must make sure that computation occurs without decryption.
Encryption must occur and it must be mandated for anything that will actually be evaluating
anything that we express externally or internally. I've already proven demonstrations with
multiple HMD devices.
that demonstrate that we don't need, for example, as Kirk mentioned, in a social scenario with
interaction from one user to another, that never needs to be decrypted from device to device.
There is no provider that actually needs to hold that data in a raw form. And for as long as we
don't fight to make sure that we're protecting that constant encryption in between those stages,
then we open ourselves up to any form of manipulation of our consciousness that we probably, some
people may want it, but we probably don't want in the longer term and more importantly,
we wouldn't want to imbue upon the next generations downward.
We need to begin a trend of understanding that we can have pure computation on encrypted
data that is never decrypted and as for as long as we want to build a million arguments
around that.
then we open ourselves up to exactly what I think that this slide is about,
what it was that Kurt mentioned here.
And any other discussion around that is great,
but it has nothing to do with the fact that right now today,
we can make sure that computation can occur on encrypted data
that is never decrypted from client to client.
And when we talk about interoperable metaverses,
in what scenario would we want anyone to be able to have,
any third-party entity to have any understanding of what's happening there?
when right now today we can implement infrastructure that makes sure that we still have that same
interoperable experience and nothing is decrypted.
Everything else is negated in my opinion. Part of my strong feelings here.
I totally agree with you.
And as a technologist, I understand exactly what you're saying.
But I think a lot of those details get lost, though, because I try to explain
to people why face ID, when you have a secure enclave on the phone, is OK.
But face ID in the cloud is not OK.
You understand it.
But I think a lot of people don't.
That's just face ID to them.
And they say ban face ID.
And there's a lot of these technologies, a lot of the biometrics.
can be very valuable when they work for us, when they work for our benefit.
They can help improve our cognition. They can help us focus on our work.
They're really valuable technologies, things like eye tracking, which are going to be
in a variety of HMDs in the next couple of years. We'll see. Facebook's already talked about
what they're doing there. A very valuable technology for being able to help us actually
focus and relate to each other. But the key is, I mean, I think, and a way to put this for people
who are non-technical, is the question is,
Are these technologies being used for us or are they being used for someone else who isn't acting in our benefit?
And that goes to the business model.
And the reason we have such distrust at this point,
and why we shouldn't trust anybody and agree with you on that,
is because they've abused it.
In the name of the business model, the business model is going to lead
Companies who make their money off of advertising and other exploitive technologies,
not that advertising itself is bad, but the exploitive part is bad,
they are always going to tend to want to extract this information from us
and use it in a way that benefits someone else and not us.
And so what we need to be banning is the exploitation.
What we need to be banning is the manipulative use of this technology,
not the technologies themselves.
when they can be proven to be used to our benefit,
to our personal benefit.
And this even goes beyond consent,
because it brings up the next question as well.
If we just agree to it, it's okay.
These things are so complicated.
And even the scientists who work
on the machine learning algorithms
don't even understand how they work half the time,
and they just work.
And so you can't expect a lay person
to be able to consent to something
that the company doesn't even understand how it works.
So we have to be assuming
that we can't consent to these things.
And we have to be proving that they're innocuous and that they work for our benefit.
You know, in the same way that the health industry has had to prove over a year,
first, do no harm, first prove that you're actually helping people
and that and don't do experiments on people.
Don't do things that you're going to harm their health, even though it still happens.
We have laws about these things. We have rules.
Hippocratic Oath, all these things push us in a direction of saying, don't abuse people.
And we don't have that yet for all this cognitive technology, which can easily be used to abuse
people.
This falls a lot on maybe on card expertise, but a lot of the arguments that you are talking
are kind of the same arguments we are debating when talking about facial recognition and
artificial intelligence, about security, about people that.
is being, that is abusing these technologies
and because they can control it.
And this kind of creates this technocracy
where you don't understand these technologies.
So you are being a subject to them.
But this probably falls more on CART's expertise.
Well, I would say like one of the things that I actually would make a pitch for all the game developers who are looking at these technologies and developing it now, if you create a system that gives people that kind of trust that they can put their data into a system and feel confident about it, I think that's going to be a winning proposition.
And one of the reasons why people are a little leery about Facebook getting into the metaverse is that Facebook has had a number of things that have broken trust in the past.
And so getting ahead of that and saying, we're going to have a system where you have control
over your information and it's for real, then that's going to be a better system.
If people believe that that's true and you can back that up, I think technology,
that does back it up, as Dylan was saying, but I think that also we need to have policies that
back that up, looking at it from a legal policy and technology perspective to get to that.
That was a great point to kind of close the debate.
This has been amazing.
And I want to kind of speak like for hours about this
with each and every one of you,
because you are such amazing.
And my mind is blown of all the things you know
and all the things on the doors you are opening.
So we had to stop here and we have five minutes for Q&A,
for a brief Q&A, if someone has a question
that we can answer in five minutes,
which is probably not the case, but let's do it anyway.
Thank you, everybody.
Can you hear me?
Yes.
Yeah, I first off just wanted to say
thank you for talking about this.
I do talks on this stuff here on SF.
And hearing other people talk about this is very valuable.
confirms a lot of issues I've been seeing. My question is a bit about the biosensor stuff you
guys just mentioned which is for game devs how do you think a good way of educating game developers
about these biosensors and the ethical issues since game developers want to have access to the
data to use it during games?
How should they implement biosensors to use this type of data safely and securely and ethically?
I'll just take a quick stab at it to say that the first rule is never upload it to the cloud.
Use it locally and you can use it to improve someone's game experience.
Great, but don't save it.
If you can avoid creating metadata from it,
don't try to create metadata,
especially don't use it for what you don't need,
and just delete it, get rid of it.
Don't store it, don't allow third parties access to it.
Try to prove that every use of the data
is for the benefit of the player in this case.
And I would build upon that.
Absolutely agree with what Avi mentioned there.
I spoke about homomorphic encryption previously
and that I've implemented it in a number of scenarios
that are game-based scenarios at this point
where you can have computation on data
that is exchanged between clients
that is completely encrypted and is never decrypted.
So anyone right now can go into GitHub,
pull up a million repos that implement
homomorphic encryption in whatever your engine.
choices or in some abstract library, you can do this today.
You actually, you never need to decrypt the data
in order to provide the personalized experience,
be it a homepage or be it a game experience.
Just have to make sure that at the other end,
when it's decrypted on some other client,
that it can't be siphoned off at that end either.
But it would never be decrypted in this case.
That's the whole part is you only get the end results
of the operation that's performed on the data.
Just to make it a concrete example,
I know we don't have a lot of time,
but let's say it's my face
and we're worried about identity theft.
And so we have to create avatars
and we want to create eventually photorealistic avatars.
So at some point,
my face is going to be transmitted to you on your side
and we can encrypt it along the way,
different kind of encryption,
not exactly what we're talking about,
but at some point it's going to get decrypted
and the client on the other end is going to receive it.
And we have to be very careful
that that can't be siphoned off and used.
for someone to pretend to be me and impersonate me to my bed, for example, or something worse.
Hi guys, I'm John McMath, also known as the Samurai Lawyer in the VR space.
Really glad to see you all.
My question is about the difficulty of communicating technological specifications to lawmakers
specifically.
You guys have talked a lot about the need for legislation.
By way of analogy...
Sometimes I have to explain to a judge or a jury around here what mass spectrometer is or how DNA testing works.
And that's when you start to realize that there can be that disconnect between the lawmaker and the scientific grasp or sophistication.
So I'm wondering if you guys can address how do we bridge that gap.
I can go a quick on that, that for me,
I do a lot of work in education on policy makers,
but also on regular people.
And I think that one of the keys is trying to make people
understand through simple analysis
and trying to make them feel welcome into the technology.
Because for a lot of people, when they hear technology
and particularly people that come from like law
and other areas that are kind of more social,
they tend to close down.
So you need to translate the abstract ideas and the concepts
and the importance of this.
Not only just, and kind of bring those difficult technical terms
into a way that they feel welcome to understand that.
I would second that completely.
There are a number of lawyers, particularly in
I think in academia and also in policy that try to specialize in explaining technical issues to a legal audience that sometimes it usually also the lawyers.
It is very difficult because sometimes you have to get past that perception that, oh,
this is something, it's either complicated or I don't need to know about this, or even
worse, the filter that already exists is lobbyist.
It's sometimes very difficult that the technology is being explained by someone that has an
agenda and is getting paid to do that.
So it's sometimes a very thankless job.
I can only say that, you know, videos, all sorts of popular engagement that you can do
as a technologist that can be understood by lawyers and by lawmakers, it's useful,
it's very useful. I've used lots of videos when trying to explain things to
policymakers to make it easier. The more content that we can have access to, the better.
I've just tried collaborating.
I'll collaborate with lawyers whenever
you want to help try to explain these things.
And I think what matters is not just to simplify the tech,
because otherwise, if you simplify it,
you wind up with some lawmaker talking about a series of tubes
and not really understanding the details.
But if you tell it in terms of stories, and you say,
you imagine you're walking down the street, and this happens.
And then this happens, and then this happens.
Everybody can understand that.
And so that's been the most effective way is to turn these things into stories.
And then what you want is the lawyers to come back and poke holes in it to say, is that
really going to happen?
Like, is that, are you just dreaming or is that actually really likely?
And you got to be very, very clear about that.
Cause you don't want to, you don't want to, you know, cry wolf.
You want to, you want to really talk about the real dangers of, of, of what's likely
to happen based on what we know and the realities of things.
I'll just add to this that it would be great if lawmakers,
policymakers also employed technologists in-house
that would help understand these issues.
And, you know, I think we have we have a good set of geeky lawyers.
several on this on the Zoom,
but also on the side of policymakers
so that they can get that geek to geek protocol
to transfer the information
and have that be embedded in the policy.
The policy is based on the actual technologies,
not just now, but the ones that are being foreseen
so we can get ahead.
I think we don't have more time.
So thank you everyone for coming for this panel
and a big round of applause
to our incredible panelists here.