Hi, and welcome to Making the Believable Horses of Red Dead Redemption 2.
My name is Tobias Cleanthus, and I'm a lead AI gameplay programmer at Rockstar Games.
I'm based at Rockstar North, where I look after a team based at Rockstar North and Rockstar India
that focuses on core locomotion and movement in our video games.
And today I want to talk about one such example, which is the horses of Red Dead 2.
Let's have a little look at what we're going to talk about today.
I'd like to discuss where we started out at first,
and what our goals were with the horses in Red Dead 2.
We'll then go into talking about freedom of movement
and how this was critical to delivering the behavior of our horses in Red Dead.
We'll follow on with some discussion about gates and speed
and their impact and responsiveness with the horses in the game.
We'll then look at riders and how we synchronize their movement with horses.
Following that, we'll discuss the environmental awareness of our horses
and how we cope with such varied terrain.
We'll also talk about the personalities of our horses and the differences in breeds before wrapping up at the end.
So starting out with Red Dead 2.
So we had a lot to follow on from the first Red Dead Redemption.
We knew we had a big task following on from people's memories of John Marston's story.
We knew we wanted to make sure that the horse was going to be a best supporting character for Arthur Morgan and not simply like a vehicle or mode of transport.
We also knew this was Rockstar's biggest game world so far,
and there was going to be huge variation in the terrain,
and that would become very important to sell a grounded experience to players.
We also wanted to make sure that throughout the game,
the player was left with an emotional attachment to their horse
through Arthur's story and beyond into Red Dead Online.
So coming from GTA V, we had a big revamp of a lot of different code systems,
one of which was our locomotion systems,
which we attempted to unify several disparate systems for animal,
human and horse movement into one.
We also knew that we were going to change things to be a lot more grounded
compared to the world of GTA V. Red Dead's world is a much slower pace.
And so we focus quite early on bringing in our horses into this new technology.
So I want to have a look at a first example of where we got the first couple of months.
So just having a look at this, I think we'll see a few ranges of gates movements,
so walking and countering, trotting.
We'll also see some of the transitions from idling and stopping.
And looking at this, I think it'd be fair to ask what's wrong with this and why don't
we just ship it at this date?
And I think there's quite a few different points that we looked at when we were evaluating
it early on.
It definitely was very functional, but we had some problems with a very discrete range
of speeds.
There was no range nor variation, something that would become critical as we worked on
things such as the gang riding together with Dutch and the gang.
We also knew there was a very limited range of movement.
At this point, we simply had some turning animations
and some transitions to go with.
We also found that the turns were quite stiff.
With the quadruped, we found that the body would be
posing in a C shape as it turned left and right.
So as we combined those assets together,
we had to slow them down, reducing responsiveness
so that they could blend together acceptably.
And generally, a lot of our transitions were very discreet,
so they're quite lumpy and inconsistent.
And this is definitely something we wanted to solve for the ship.
So looking at this, we went back and wanted to understand what the problems we were seeing were.
Definitely functional, but missing something. And I think as I said when we started out,
we wanted to make sure that the horse was more than just a mode of transport for APPA.
We wanted to see if we could get a livelier performance, and we wanted to see if there
was a large amount of behavioural implications that we could get from vastly expanding the
amount of movement.
So to look at how we could introduce this kind of believability to the horse,
we started to look at capturing footage of real horses moving here in Scotland.
So I want to just show an example of something that we caught which very early on became
incredibly important to us. And this is a case where a horse is turning but using a lot of
lateral movement to initially do it. So this is really exaggerated because we wanted to
capture an example of it that really showed it off.
But I just want to run through and show you what I'm talking about.
So initially, as the horse goes into a turn,
you'll see it keeps his body oriented forward.
As it starts to turn, it's going to sidestep before it peels into the turn.
So straightaway capturing this, we realized that adding that extra degree of freedom of movement to the game
was going to be incredibly important.
And so this leads me to talking about freedom of movement and how we added this to the horse.
So the lateral movement that we saw in that video,
something that became incredibly important when we decided that we were going to use this
to assist the movement without having to have very slow blends
to avoid those kind of weird shapes blending left and right assets together.
We also wondered with this whether we could use it to deliver something that would in effect give a large amount of character to our horses in game.
So could we give an indirect kind of notion of control by giving a responsive movement direction but lagging behind their orientation?
It turned out to be one of the most integral features that we developed for the horse, but it was also one of the most difficult.
So I just want to show you an example of what we actually had in our first outline bringing lateral movement into the horses.
So we quite rapidly added these into our blend trees.
We would have assets blending on X,
and they would work with our turn assets and our forward assets.
And initially, it gave us the idea,
but it was a little bit slippery to look at.
So why was that?
For us, quite early on,
we found that we had significant problems
with the usage of blend trees in our tech.
So we're all kind of familiar with these arrangements of blending animations together.
They're incredibly useful, quite liberating for animators, but for us they came with a significant
amount of problems when we were trying to integrate this kind of movement on our horses.
So for one, our structures were very much explicitly put together.
they didn't actually automatically pick up features from our animations, which meant as soon as we wanted to change them
and add more, we would have to make more complicated graphs. If we wanted a different style of movement,
we would have to make another graph.
And overall, this kind of explicit manipulation of them became very, very complicated for us.
So,
we look forward to automating extraction of our features and what we could do to move away from using these blend trees and arrange
3D spaces of our assets that would automatically extract root motion or movement of individual bones
and combine our assets without any human intervention. This meant that we could then
move away from having programmers or animators having to put together graphs every time they
wanted to add any movement, but it also meant that we could vastly improve the accuracy of
what we were adding in.
So I just want to have a look at what I'm talking about when I say adding in these 3D spaces and go over the different dimensions we were looking at.
So for our 1D dimension, we were looking at the angular velocity.
This is pretty much what we had to begin with.
By improving the automation on this, then we get a more accurate result, but we still don't get rid of that problem of blending left and right masses together.
Then we introduced linear velocity onto that, just on xy.
That gives us some speed control, gets rid of our problems with discrete speeds I was talking about earlier.
But again, it doesn't help us with those problems with turning.
And so lastly, what we need to add on is that lateral velocity that I talked about earlier,
which is effectively strafing for our horses.
So what we would do, put together the groups of assets required for something like a canter cycle,
set up the system to automatically extract our root motion on x and y plus our angular velocity,
and this will then arrange those assets together. The great thing about this though was that even
for similar gates of movement, we could choose how many assets we would put in there and not
have to go and explicitly create a structure every time. So we could have more detail in
a certain place and less in others.
So with that in play, let's go back and have a look at another example with a real-life horse.
So talking about the lateral movement and what that actually enables a horse to do,
I wanted to look at an example with a horse actually pivoting around its front feet.
This kind of movement is something that became really important to us in the game
and a feature we actually added in.
So as we got this horse to turn in a tight circle,
hopefully you can see.
the vast majority of the movement is kind of pivoting around the front feet,
rather than typically, as we might do in a video game, with some kind of root underneath the torso.
And there's not actually very much forward velocity here at all, it's almost all entirely
on x or lateral velocity, which allows us to do this turn in place.
So this was something that we ended up calling drift.
So Drift added into Red Dead straight away enabled us to deliver this notion of indirect
control of our horses, because immediately we have some freedom of movement, which gives
us the ability to control the movement direction of a player or AI's horse accurately without
having to snap them into the orientation immediately.
we can then give really consistent control on that movement direction,
but choose to lag the orientation for lots of different purposes.
And again, that gives us that notion that the rider's not totally in control of the horse,
you're not steering a cow with an immediate response,
the horse is trying to interpret your input.
So one thing that is missing from this that I haven't brought up is what we did at zero.
Now,
With left and right assets combined,
there's a position at the zero velocity,
zero angular velocity,
whereby you basically need some stepping on the spot.
And with the horse, this was something that we decided
we could make a bit of a moment with.
So this is a dressage move
that's typically referred to as Piaf that we added in.
And we caught some of this in Mocha
and found that it had a huge amount of character.
So we wanted to replicate this
and have this available for us
across all of our gates on our horses.
So here's an example in the game.
Now, with this added in, this also
means that across all of our gates,
from a horse cantering to a horse walking or trotting,
they can go all the way up to their top speed in that gate
and all the way down to zero, which
gives us a great deal of flexibility
and gets rid of those discrete ranges I mentioned earlier.
So breaking it down, I just wanted
to go over the breakdown of what drift actually
is for us in Red Dead.
So with all of our horses, we always have a zone roughly in front of them where we don't
much care about adjusting their orientation. We'll respond to movement directions, but we'll very
loosely adjust the orientation as you move along. As a horse commits into a turn, then we'll start
to expand that region and gradually turn closer towards the movement direction.
And then as we can persist with that, using all of this free movement we've got available now,
we can also make the horse oversteer. So we do another thing to introduce that idea of
indirect control, making the horse oversteer because they don't know when you're going to
peel out of it. And this gives us, in effect, this kind of drifting movement skidding out and
back into straight movement. And so here's an example of that first working all together
in Red Dirt during development.
So hopefully you can see here as we go into the oversteer,
then we gradually straighten up, but the movement direction stays consistent.
Here we can see that we could then exploit the stroking, the lateral movement,
and then gradually peel back into turning again.
Here it is working on Chanceler as well.
So with all of those together, we have a great deal of freedom of movement.
and I wanted to then talk about the gates and speeds that come with this.
So I don't want to make any assumptions about what people know about horse gates,
but let's compare this to looking at how a biped moves, which hopefully we'll be familiar with.
So typically we'd look in a game of having something like walk, jog, run, and sprint
for a biped, needle movement.
With the horses, we had walk and trot, very much similar kind of gates.
And then we had canter and gallop.
Now, these gates were very different.
They're what are known as three-beat gates,
which means they have a kind of syncopated pair of first footsteps
before the back end comes back down.
And this is something I'll talk about a little bit later
because this introduces some complexity for us.
Now, looking at the gates, what we wanted to make sure we were doing
was allowing an overlapping range of motion.
we could use the gates to represent effort, but we could cater for a wider range of speeds within
any individual gate. So if you have a look at the graph that's on screen at the moment,
you should see in red we're showing the kind of minimum ranges that our gates can cover.
They're not ideal, not where we would generally want to be in, but we can run them. We then have
a yellow range which is the ideal best looking region for that particular gate, and then we have
a green range where they can overlap with the next one.
This thing gets rid of that idea of discrete speeds and enables us now to continuously
control the movement of the horse, most deterministically, through those different gates.
However, there's one problem that does come with this, and that's transitions,
which didn't have this setup. So our transitions in Red Dead 2,
initially in development, were one-shots, a bit like in the initial video I showed.
In isolation, these look really great.
You can play them and get a really nicely authored movement every time.
However, they do introduce problems for us when we're talking about trying to be deterministic.
So, it's difficult to control the speeds of them,
meaning that we would have to produce a large amount of them if we wanted them to overlap with all of our gates.
the foot cycle would define how the transition behaved.
So we couldn't exactly control the duration
that transition would occur,
because it would be dependent on whether a foot was down
or lifting or mid-strike.
And that also leads into that idea
of them being unpredictable,
because now we have some deterministic range
of velocities that we can use,
Boston a gate, and then we go into a transition,
which only picks a fixed range.
We now suddenly can't control
where we're going from or to.
So initially we tried this idea of unrolling these. By unrolling them what I mean is we would
look at the mean velocity through these and figure out frame to frame how we could adjust the playback.
In principle it was really quite a simple thing to do but it didn't look too great. We still
needed a large volume of assets for them to not look like they were playing super speed or slow-mo.
They obviously in a lot of cases looked at slow-mo or super speed because we were otherwise
speeding up or slowing down an asset to achieve a speed.
And again they were still kind of unpredictable because we still had a dependency on hitting
the right foot strike whenever we played them.
So what we wanted to look at, I'm going to go over in the next slide, which is continuous
kind of control of us moving through gates.
So we'll start off in this example looking at going from a trot to a canter.
So we're gradually speeding up throughout, trying to keep a kind of deterministic acceleration as we go.
What will happen in here is we'll go through the ideal range,
gradually get into an uncomfortable maximum range that the horse can handle.
And whilst we're in there, we'll look for the opportune moment
to continue into the transogate.
So as you can see in this example, suddenly we've gone from having quite a fixed speed at the start and end to having a very smooth progression throughout.
And this is something that became really important for us when you look at the rides with Dutch and the gang, where all of the gang could be loosely speeding up or slowing down between each other.
And the last thing we wanted to get into was stuck oscillating between fixed transitions as we had to pull different members of the group forwards and backwards.
So what's the actual breakdown of these cycles that we're using in this case?
Rather than using one-shots, we decided to introduce the idea of continuous acceleration
and deceleration. So the idea would be we would use overlapping cycles that could represent
the notion of acceleration on the horse or the deceleration and deliver a similar kind of posing
for us. With these being cycles, it means that we could introduce whenever we wanted them to come in,
independent necessarily of footstrokes.
It also means we can control the timing really precisely on them because all the way throughout
we can accelerate the horse or decelerate the horse at whatever rate we want to.
We can also vary the duration of them dependent on what reason we've decided to speed up or slow
down. So suddenly we're not just talking about a fixed gate, so going from walk to canter or
galloping to walk, we're talking about being able to make changes such as slowing down for a corner
and using these acceleration and deceleration cycles on top.
Now, with that in mind, I just wanted to go over actually what the posing of these looked like
and how we kept the animation team happy with them.
So, hopefully these will actually look a little bit intuitive as we go through them,
but let's break down our basic poses. So we've got a cancer on the left-hand side,
we've got our acceleration posing on the right-hand side,
and in the middle we've got the deceleration posing.
So, kind of intuitively like for a human.
As we decelerate, we find that the horse collects its feet back together to slow down and catch some of the inertia.
And the head goes up and back.
It's a little bit like if you can imagine sprinting along and trying to stop before a curbside.
And then for our cancer acceleration pose,
the footfall is extended and the head is down and forwards.
And again, this is probably like the example
of if you could imagine walking along
and trying to catch a bus as it's leaving a bus stop,
sprinting along to get it.
So the great thing with these as well
was that we could then replace them for different purposes.
So in the case of the acceleration and deceleration,
we also had a mode of skidding in the game.
whereby when the player unlocks a bonding level with Arthur's horse,
they now have this new move that is highly maneuverable,
where they can skid the horse and then accelerate back out of it.
What's great about this is that this just became some changes in our locomotion controllers,
where we could slow down or speed up in a slightly different way,
and then we would just condition slightly differently
which of the acceleration or deceleration cycles we would play.
with it working so fantastically for us for the gates,
we then kind of got to the point
where we started to look at our stop transitions
and our start transitions,
going from moving to idling, idling to moving.
Suddenly these start to feel very lumpy as well
in a similar fashion.
The question with this was whether we could introduce
this concept there.
So we decided to approach it looking at the idea of never stopping moving with a horse.
And in principle I don't mean necessarily never stopping moving, but what we wanted to do was
make sure that we could allow the player or an AI to let go of control of the horse, almost come
to a standstill, and then change their mind almost instantaneously and speed back up out of it
all the while without going through lots of lumpy or clicky kind of different transitions.
So we ended up using these deceleration cycles and specializing them for stopping.
So then as we detected that a character is going to come to a halt, we would introduce the deceleration
cycle for it. But again, if there's stick input or a decision to run off in another direction,
the cycle can stand up again with an acceleration and we don't lose control of the character with
a discrete transition. So the great thing about this for us is that supporting these ideas of
the indecision of control of the horse, we want to make sure that it looks like you're not necessarily
100% control in it and it's doing its best to respond to the horse.
So going through that, I just want to follow on now with a little bit of an overview of how we handle the riders.
So just beforehand, I talked a little bit about the idea of cantering and galloping being three beat gates.
And this introduced some difficulties for us in terms of how we synchronize the assets together for these.
Like I was saying, these have a syncopated footfall on the front legs with a third strike coming down at the back.
So we knew quite early on with this that we couldn't actually sink here on the foot face,
which is something that we might typically do on bipedal move.
So we started to introduce additional tags that we would be able to map out
things like we would call sink feet.
So the idea with sink feet is that we'd be looking at the extension and compression of the pose
rather than a particular foot fall.
The idea with this was that it would actually save us having to exactly match the footfall across all of our assets,
but it would also stop the mush happening when we had large intervals between them.
So just to have a look at this example.
Here's the tagging we've got. So we've got the right footfall tagged up here.
And then we've got the left footfall tagged up here.
So we still keep those marked up so that we can pass them on to our audio teams or whoever might be interested.
But then we're looking at the compressed part, sync beat,
and the extension.
So with those in play, that then meant we could have
a number of different cycles.
We weren't so dependent on the interval
between the footfalls.
So we're adding this in for the riders.
Our riders were actually supported
by additional programmers and animators.
And what we would use for them is additional layers on the horse's locomotion dedicated to a rider and a passenger.
These would be put together so that they could define the styling that matched whatever the horse might be doing at the time.
What's also quite important with these is that the horse would then tell the rider or the passenger what to do as we went through different movements.
So as we hit a start transition on the horse, the horse then tells the rider and the passenger a start motion is coming in and gives them the assets to play back.
As we hit cycles, the horse tells the rider and passenger the cycles are playing, and gives them the data.
And as we transition to stopping, the same thing happens there as well.
To get these working together properly, what we would end up doing is taking the dominant assets of the horse
and providing these to the passenger and the rider to synchronize them to it.
And this is where the tagging becomes more important.
Alongside this, the rider was actually free to interpolate the locomotion controller's values
as it saw fit, so we didn't have to have a one-to-one dependency on what they were doing,
whether it be the same angular velocity at a given time or not.
Also, we didn't have to have a one-to-one map of the assets on the rider and passenger with
what the horse provided, so they could be decoupled, for example, adding more loops
onto a cycle or playing back different kinds of digits on the rider compared to the horse.
and when they sync nicely, we also get our moments like our cliff stopping.
So, looking at what we talked about before, we had the sync beat tags on the horse,
but what we also added in was a separate set of tracks which we call a rhythm
for synchronising between the horse and the rider.
Now, the extension and compression of the legs is really important for the horse assets to work together,
but it's not necessarily important for what the rider's looking for.
With the rider, what we found we were looking for was the points where we were at our lowest
or our highest in any given cycle. So we added an idea of a track called rhythm,
and again we tagged those up separately for both characters. Now with these tags shared between
them, one thing that's great is that we didn't have to have the same number of cycles between
them. Because we weren't dependent on a phase of an animation, we can suddenly have a simplistic
loop for a rider that doesn't contain anyone near as much detail as the horse or vice versa.
What we would do is take the dominant assets that are playing from the horse,
provide them to the rider for synchronization, and map those two tracks together.
So just to show them side by side with each other,
you can see the high points and low points on the horse and rider simultaneously.
Okay, what I'd like to look at next is the environmental awareness
and how we implemented this on the horses in Red Dead 2.
So, as I said earlier, the world that we introduced in Red Dead 2 was Rockstar's biggest in a game so far.
The terrain was incredibly varied, and we wanted to make sure that you felt grounded on your horse in that world.
So, what were we going to try and achieve?
Trying to make it feel like the terrain was difficult to navigate, and it would take its toll on your horse.
We wanted to make sure that we were selling the visuals of the horse and the rider, that difficulty that was introduced in the app.
With our horses, they moved roughly around 18 meters a second at their top speed.
So that's incredibly fast, around 40 miles an hour.
And that leaves a lot of room for things to go wrong.
So we had to look at how we could use the freedom of movement
we introduced earlier to help navigate around the terrain successfully.
And those responses of the horse to the terrain is another example
of where we wanted to show the horse as an independent AI.
It's thinking for itself, responding to the world independently of the player.
So initially early on, we were looking at the responses to pitching in the terrain.
Early examples of this, we actually looked at capsule adjustments and IK
solutions to adjust as we went along them.
So in this example, we've got a horse that was just adjusting its feet
in capsule to the terrain, not doing anything particularly special.
Kind of looks a little bit odd in isolation because the rider's just
pointing out of the world's kind of normal on the ground.
With the IK solutions, we weren't really happy with the results.
So what we decided to do was add even more dimensions to our blends.
With those added, we would then have the ability to control the pitch of the horse and the rider,
independently of the speeds.
But adding four dimensions to our blends suddenly introduced some new problems to deal with.
So I mentioned earlier how we were extracting this information automatically.
With 4D, we're suddenly adding a large amount of complexity if we want to do the maths properly.
So we kind of decided we wanted to cheat our way around that.
Rather than using the exact maths as it was, we would coarsely bin our assets automatically by
looking at the incline or decline on them. We would then use k-means clustering on them
to actually group them together into multiple 3D spaces.
So looking at them separately, that meant that we would have
end 3D spaces, in this example just three, where we would then be able to go okay these look like
they're going down, these look like they're going up, and these look like they're going flat.
The accuracy of this fourth dimension wasn't incredibly important to us,
so if there was some slight deviation it's something that we could afford to ignore.
but the x, y, and angular velocities are all still very accurate.
When it comes to then finding an asset to play back or a combination of it at runtime,
it just becomes a simple lookup again for us. We provided all the velocities we wanted plus the
pitch, and that then becomes the weighted blend of two 3D spaces. But we didn't think that four
dimensions was enough for some of the things we wanted to do, particularly with cantering.
So with cantering...
we were looking at the fact that actually the horses that we saw and captured footage of
were using a leading foot on the turns when they were going left or right.
And then we also researched this and found that there were preferences for horses to be left or
right footed, which seemed like an interesting thing to add to the game. So with this in mind,
we started to then bin this as a fifth dimension, looking at the assets as to what's the actual
forefoot in them. And then
again binning them into a left leading or a right leading space. Similarly again this is then a 2D
k-means clustering. We bin them into the 3D spaces and then we're able to put them together
to have some simple lookups.
Now, what was great for us with this as well meant that similarly with the cycle, what
we did with the cycles, we could then control the blending between being left and right
footed.
So we could find an opportune moment to do it, but we could also control the speed at
which it did it so that we could get little moments like you see in the video where it
actually looks like the front feet kind of hop slightly as the foot changes.
Now, with all the detail in the environment, one thing that we had to spend a lot of time on was analyzing the terrain.
We actually implemented a system with a blackboard whereby we could post all sorts of information that we'd find on our way.
So what we would do is look at the forward integration of our locomotion controller.
And using a combination of NavMesh and physics casts,
we would validate positions on the terrain,
the inclines that we saw coming up ahead.
But we would also look at even sort of finer details
from our graphic systems, such as the depth of surfaces
or water features that were coming up,
the swarms of bugs ahead in the future,
alongside actual weather conditions,
like the wind velocity,
depending on where we are in the world.
With these posted together, we then had a large amount of data that we could then use to dynamically switch in and out different styles.
And this kind of leads me to talking a little bit about what we actually did to our locomotion system coming from FIVE.
So coming from FIVE, we decided to break down our locomotion system into a different structure.
What we wanted to move away from was these typical kind of manually authored state graphs.
We weren't keen on it, and I think, as we talked about earlier,
we found that then extending these became unnecessarily complicated for us.
So we looked at the idea of introducing atomic moves, which we would call motions.
These would be simple movements on a full body or a layer, just to achieve one thing.
A collection of these together is what we would call a motion type.
And a motion type would represent one given style.
So in the case of a horse, this might be something like wading through water or going through deep snow.
What we could do with these is inherit from other motion types and combine them together
to actually create new variations. So, for example, as going through snow got deeper,
we could then gradually replace certain assets. The selection of these was data-driven with the
information that we put on the blackboard. So, we would have large collections of motion types
that were conditioned on data such as the depth of the snow or the incline that we were seeing ahead,
or even whether it was windy in a particular direction.
In total, this was used across all of our locomotion in Red Dead 2,
not just on the horses.
So we had a breakdown of this, which looked something like
around 6,300 different motions across the game,
making up something like 2,500 different motion types.
Across that, then we would break these down into what we called archetypes,
which would represent certain kinds of characters or animals,
such as whether it be Dutch or a certain kind of horse.
and then we have our data-driven conditions numbering somewhere close to 2000.
So just looking at an example here, what we would post to the blackboard for a snow motion type.
So initially as we go along we would actually get the information out to tell us the name of
the material that we're walking through. We would be able to find the depth based on any
tread through before us.
And then, for example, if we decided it was incredibly cold and we wanted to respond to that,
we could do something like push through a tail shake to select the movement of that on the layer.
We'll then be able to author these conditions independently of the game code and let the
system actually select them for us on the fly.
So then, in this case, you can see then that we would be getting these shakes.
getting timed off regularly because of the cold weather.
Even Arthur's adjustments to reach and adjust his hat would be based on things
like the wind speed or the direction of the wind.
So often as you turn into the wind in a blizzard, like you might see early on
in the game, which is very much focused on wintry weather,
Arthur would respond to that accurately.
But again, we didn't have to code that. It was data driven.
So another thing I mentioned earlier was the speed of the horse and the difficulty of navigating through the terrain.
And one thing that we wanted to try and do was to use the extensive mobility that we've added to the horse
to try and help you avoid annoying obstacles like trees and larch outcrops of rock.
So we hoped that this could introduce this idea of self-preservation by actually increasing the mobility of the horse
in its response to not wanting to actually run straight into a tree.
Across the AI and players, we introduced different solutions.
So with the player, we actually looked initially
at whether we could get this information out of the NavMesh,
and then ultimately actually settled on things
like marking up large groups of rocks or trees
that we wanted to avoid.
We could then cast into the world
based on the forward integrated locomotion
to then decide whether we should be moving left, right,
or stopping against these.
For the AI characters, we would have velocity obstacles implemented, which would then push these shapes in there as well and use the nav mesh.
And in practice, this worked pretty well for us most of the time.
What we would be able to do is respond ahead of time and use our lateral velocity to shift the horse sideways and then allow the player to straighten back up.
So then we would try and minimize the amount of time that we were actually interfering with your control.
And by the end of it, the response of this was really, really good.
And actually what we got asked to do was to make sure that if you held the stick towards the tree
and mashed away galloping, you definitely hit the tree.
Now, I've talked a lot of points through this about how important adding the range of speed was to our horses.
We really did want to get away from discrete, kind of notchy feeling across gates.
But the other thing that this enabled us to do as we added more detailed terrain is to actually more gradually control the speed of the character as they encounter more difficult terrain,
whether that be depth of snow, whether that be going up and down a hill or whether that be going through bodies of water.
So using this then we apply these ideas of what we would call speed penalties into the game.
And the idea with speed penalties is that there are different factors that could affect the horse
which we would post onto our blackboard. We could then manipulate their incoming desired movement
based on that factor and reduce it non-linearly.
So let's have a look at an example here of the horse moving through the water.
So initially, here's our horse cantering through the water,
no speed penalties being applied.
So it's just a fixed speed the whole way.
Now, what I want to show is an example of this afterwards.
So as the effort actually increases, what we do with the speed penalties
on the water is that we actually further increase how much we take off.
So we more dramatically slow you down the faster you want to go.
The idea here being then that we show how much effort's going into it so that you see a significant
acceleration and deceleration based on your input and the depth of the water.
Let's have a look at the speed penalty applied. Same kind of input.
But again we're dramatically slowing the horse down now.
And as the depth gets shallower, we rapidly speed them back up.
And here they are side by side, just to give an example.
So, leading on from that, I wanted to talk about one of the features
for terrain awareness that we added to the game,
which I think is one of my favorites, and that's cliff-stepping.
So the cliff-stopping kind of goes against everything I've said about speed and control of the horse throughout.
Rather than wanting to give you this indirect and soft control of the horse, whether it's an AI or a player,
we wanted to actually make sure that we definitely got this moment every time and it was accurate.
So what we looked at was this tech that we introduced into the game, which we called stop-matching.
The idea with this is something you've probably seen before, but...
What we would look at doing with this is extracting a few tracks of animation data from the root or from tags such as our foot tracks.
So initially we would be looking at the translation to a goal.
We would also then look at our foot or beat cycle depending on the movement.
And in this example it's looking pretty flat, but we would also look at the orientation left to the goal position.
So with this system, what we would look at trying to do is feeding in the information about where
we wanted to be and what the current state was, and looking to find the closest match at any
given point in time. We'd actually go through these bits of data, seeking the best time that
had the lowest possible error for each of these. But alongside this, we also had a significant
amount of markup across the world. So actually, a lot of our cliffs across the world were manually
marked up by our RRT to actually show us these steep drops coming up.
This is definitely something in the future that we would like to reduce the need for.
So let's have a look at this working in an example.
So as I'm cantering along the terrain, the forward integrated locomotion will be queried
to see that we're actually coming up to one of these cliff planes. So as we see that,
we then know that we've got to take some evasive action.
So in this case, we realize that actually,
based on the size of the horse and the assets that we have available,
there is an ideal stopping position ahead of it.
We can then look at the assets to see how they end,
and then using the information in that graph that I showed before,
we can look at finding the frame with the least possible error,
where we would actually then be able to trigger our stop
and play it out to hit that position with minimal slide and minimal error.
So as we continue to go forward, we find the entry position.
As we get there, we play the stop through.
And for us, what was really great with this is that this also meant that we didn't have to rely on synchronization from our cycles into our stops.
We would rely on the output of the stop matching to come back with the best possible match that would reduce that error completely.
So then we could just go ahead and play it straight away, and any alignment in the world was minimal,
because again, we'd found the exact entry position that we wanted to play it from.
And again, just like the trees, this almost worked 100% of the time and never went wrong.
Okay, what I want to talk about now is the personalities of the horses and actually what we did to introduce these in the game.
This is a section I find kind of amusing because actually reflecting back on what we did for Red Dead 2,
a lot of what we did to introduce personality for the horse and the player's perspective was actually to add negatives in,
leaving much of the positive association with the horse actually coming out of the player's experience playing the game.
So simple things like slapping the horse and getting kicked off a cliff, a memorable moment.
What we introduced was the idea of the concepts of agitation and unruliness.
And these are sort of features of a horse whereby they react negatively to
different stimuli in the world or from the player.
So in the example video that's playing now, you'll see how I'm actually making
the horse agitated by shooting my gun and riding them really badly.
As this builds up and up and up and up and up, the horse gets progressively
more agitated until they just try and get rid of the binder completely.
This was actually implemented in a basic utility system that we called motivations.
So what we would do is take in these different stimuli in the world
and apply some increase in the motivation for agitation throughout.
As the agitation increased, we could then differentiate the assets as we go.
So in this example, I'm manually increasing the agitation motivation on the horse.
And as it gets bigger and bigger, we actually gradually differentiate more and more of the
motion type that we're playing on the horse. So we actually would have then motion types for low
agitation and motion types of medium and high. And what happens as we go through the different
agitation states is that we gradually replace different assets and introduce more impediments
to the control for the player.
all these assets were then able to synchronize back to the rider,
so we could have transitions between the states,
and we could reflect the difficulty in controlling them as they changed.
And on the way up, as they go on the way down,
when doing things like camming a horse by giving it a pat.
Not only did we have agitation motivations,
but we also had, across all of our animals, toilet motivation,
which, as that increases to one,
results in horses or animals doing the poop.
So let's have a look at some of the features of the agitation and the movement put together.
I just wanted to show an example of a bear attack, where the agitation gradually increases
and what happens to the player. So as we head towards where there's going to be a bear attack,
the horse's agitation actually starts to increase, usually before the player would be aware that
there's a predator coming up. As the agitation increases, the horse gets more and more agitated
and reflects that in its animations.
When we get to a certain threshold, the horse actually decides to stop
and makes use of this Piaf motion that we talked about before
to jostle around on the spot and give you a bit of a moment
to actually back away from this encounter.
If you don't, then the horse will actually use that motion of self-preservation
and try and escape the scene, leaving you behind by bucking you off the horse.
See there, you get thrown off,
and then this gives us a pretty stressful encounter with a bear you can fight off.
And again, I think, like I said earlier, you know, a lot of the ways that we
introduced personality into our horse was reflecting negative states of the
player and letting them fill in the positive moments.
So as you did things like work your horse until it ran out of stamina, we would
then reflect that with changes in emotion types.
As the health went down, we would also reflect that in changes
by emotion types as well.
Again, these were all bits of information posted to the blackboard that was then
used to select this emotion type automatically.
What would also come with this is then impairments to their performance,
so that hopefully we would discourage you from running your horse into the ground
because as the stamina reduces, they're more likely to throw you off,
or they're unable to move just as fast as they could in the world
because we would introduce speed penalties like we did with the water based on their stamina.
Finally, I just want to have a look at some of the differentiation we actually added for breeds.
When we actually looked at what we had for a baseline horse in Red Dead,
we were looking at somewhere around 3,000 different animations
across 23 unique movement styles or motion types in the game,
at which point that's already a particularly big chunk of our budget.
So we knew, as we wanted to introduce more variations in terms of our breeds,
that we were going to have to think of something simpler.
So Red Dead 2 actually shipped with 19 different breeds of horse.
And these were coarsely categorized into heavy horses like Ardennes, race horses,
maybe like a thoroughbred, elites, which were usually like our Arabian horses,
and standard horses, things like American Standard.
Now to differentiate them, what we actually started looking at was how we could change
their responses with their locomotion controllers.
So we had a wide variety of speeds that we could make use of because we had all these
continuous gates available to us.
So we could modify the ideal low and high speeds within an individual gate, whether
it was a large horse or a small horse.
We could also control how they accelerate and decelerate deterministically.
So, for example, our larger horses, like an Ardennes,
could have a much slower acceleration and deceleration up to a top speed,
but maybe might get a similar top speed to a much smaller horse.
We could then also impact their angular responses.
So when we were looking at the drift examples before,
where we added this notion of indirect control,
Again, we can make lighter horses seem more nimble by them reacting quicker to your changes
when they're oversteering and straightening back up much more rapidly compared to a heavier horse
that might take a lot longer to do it. Alongside this, we could then manipulate the speed penalties
we had in the game. So, for example, the strength of a horse whilst carrying the carcass of a deer
that you've been hunting might actually impact how they slow down for it. So a heavier horse
might be less impacted by carrying more stuff.
Alongside this, we also had the equipment variation, which is less to do with breed.
And with all of this, what we did try to do was ensure that there was no one single best horse,
that there were trade-offs between them, so that a player could go out there and try various
different breeds and pick the one they were most attached to to run through the story.
And what I want to just show you before we wrap up on this is having a look at the number of our
kind of standard different types of horses in their different locomotion controllers and how
they behave with the same input.
It's the same recorded input, but different locomotion controllers applied across each breed.
So hopefully on the right hand side, you can see the heavy and the elite horses.
And they're probably the ones that are going to show up the biggest difference.
Where our heavy horses are quite kind of almost lazy looking in how they straighten back up or turn.
Whereas the elite horses look a lot more agile and nimble in the way that they do it.
There's also the differentiation and the acceleration and deceleration play there.
And also their top speeds and low end speeds vary significantly.
And so with that, I'd like to wrap up.
So, generally, I think what we found was that a lot of these approaches
came together really well for us.
We spent a lot of time working on compositional and automated approaches
for the horses.
And initially, we had some skepticism among the team
as to whether this would work.
But by the end of development, we were so settled on it
that a lot of these concepts actually got introduced back
onto other characters, such as Arthur and the other humans in the game.
What we did find throughout though was that a lot of what we'd produced had a really steep technical learning curve.
So even for programmers and technical animators, there could be a lot of difficulties and reliance on a lot of experts within the company to help assist in different areas.
The technical approaches, like I said, on the horse informed everything else that we did in the game.
And we did find a massive success with the large-scale data-driven locomotion system that we added.
We didn't go into much detail about it.
us to add a lot of variation and style throughout the game, as well as introducing a few crises
throughout development where it was very easy for us to blow the animation budget.
And what was most pleasing of all for me was just seeing things recognized publicly,
like people noticing the dressage moves and analyzing them for accuracy, people being
massively concerned about how much their horse pooped, and people loving their big stupid horses
that got in everyone's way.
So looking to the future, what kind of things do we want to learn from this and take forward into Rockstar's future games?
Well, we're pretty convinced that the compositional approaches that we used for putting together Locomotion worked incredibly well,
and we want to keep pushing forward with that.
The determinism of movement is something that's incredibly important to us,
and I think we want to make sure that the responsiveness of our characters in our game, whether they be AI or player-controlled, significantly improves.
we'd like to introduce wider degrees, wider varieties of movement,
so more styles across more varied terrain.
And I think as well, one thing that's worth highlighting is that actually in
some cases we didn't achieve parity between AI and
player controlled characters. So even though they were using the same
fundamental systems, in many cases the player would be able to
actually execute new moves in a more satisfying manner than what we could
deliver on the AI characters. And this is something we really want to
improve for the future.
Alongside this, we're also looking at machine learning approaches to improve our locomotion
and animation, but there's not something I can talk about in depth today.
And if any of this kind of thing sounds like something to be interested to you,
then we are hiring.
So thanks very much for listening.