All right, so today's talk for me,
designing great UX into your board game pieces,
game board and pieces.
So first, who am I?
This is my first board game track to be talking to,
so I actually haven't had a chance to meet a lot of you,
and a lot of you haven't obviously met me.
I started way back on judge and jury decision making,
like how juries would make decisions
in cases involving complex scientific testimony
like DNA evidence or economic damage models.
I burned out of that and joined a bunch of other grad school,
psychology grad school burnouts at Microsoft Game Studios.
And we worked in the usability and play testing labs there.
And we basically studied how groups of people played games
and what made the games fun and what made them not fun.
I decided I wanted to build a bunch more games, actually,
and learn how they're made.
So I joined up with Big Huge Games.
And as a sort of producer, designer, UX person,
shipped a bunch of PC and console games.
Burned out of that, went to Amazon,
learned about social computing.
So how do we encourage people to, oh.
No, but, I don't know.
So how do you encourage people to, oh, do you need,
oh, stick this in, sorry.
Sorry about that, everyone.
All right, now I gotta figure out how this guy goes.
Okay.
All right, yeah, so went to Amazon, learned things like,
how do we convince people to write better reviews
or convince people who haven't ever written a review before
to write a review or to upload a video of them
demonstrating a product?
And then how do we, on the consumer side,
help surface that information to purchasers
in their buying pipeline so they can make
a more informed purchase decision?
Myst Games went to Zyngo where I did more social games that was kind of related a little bit to the stuff
I was working on at Amazon and then ended up at Disney Mobile made some mobile games and then for the past five years or
So I have been a consultant
The things that I do, I study human beings.
I like watching people do things.
I identify user experience issues.
I recommend fixes to teams.
I mentor game designers, PMs, and UXers,
and provide some sort of strategy
so that we can figure out how to mesh your business
and creative goals with your actual user experience,
the way people perceive and interact with things.
Why I do it, the top reason is probably the same reason
why you all are in it.
We love games, right?
So that's number one.
I love watching people play games.
I might have mentioned that a few times already.
And I love helping people make games.
I'm not the person with the idea for the next great game,
but I love helping people achieve their goals.
One thing I don't do is make board games.
I do run an elementary school board game club,
and they make games, and I give them little hints
or suggestions or whatever, and it's super fun,
but I myself don't actually make them.
Maybe I can get some part marks for doing some digital versions of board games.
So Catan is something that I worked on for Xbox Live Arcade,
helped out with how do you make the trade interface understandable and fun?
How do you communicate with people across different languages?
Also heavily involved in designing the tutorial and
onboarding experience for new players who'd never played before.
Similarly with a Star Wars card battler that existed for maybe a month or two.
Again, player progression, combat,
how do you get people into the core loop of the game?
but also the tutorial and onboarding.
And the reason why I'm focusing a bit
on the tutorial and onboarding is that it gets,
when a lot of my work that I was doing in this area
made me think about the ideal way of learning,
and it's learning as you play,
not learning then playing, right?
Learn as you play.
And this can happen in board games, right?
We all have the friend, or maybe you
are the friend, who is very knowledgeable about games,
knows all the games, knows all the rules.
Not only knows all the rules, but is really
good at teaching the rules and teaching them
in the context of actually playing the game.
So it's actually a fun experience
to get onboarded to a new game.
But typically, or fairly commonly, right,
we're all learning the game together
and trying to struggle to figure it out.
And you can see, you know, this is a familiar scene to folks,
right, piecing things together.
Someone's scouring through the rule book
and hoping that at some point or other
you'll get to fun gameplay.
So the board game exercise that I'm going to be talking about today is something I've run on all sorts of different groups.
Elementary school kids, college students, game industry professionals, other UX professionals.
I run them in cities all over the world.
It sounds exciting.
It's not that exciting, except for me, because I like watching people play games.
The basic exercise is this.
The players group up.
I give them a game that they've never played before, and I tell them, go figure out how to play.
You got 20 or 30 minutes.
And I observe players without helping them.
So no manual, and they can ask me questions,
but I'm not gonna answer any of them.
After about 20 or 30 minutes,
when I see that all the teams have some sort of game
going on and they're playing, we break it down.
So the team explains what they came up with
based on the board game in pieces.
We diff the version that they came up with
with the actual rule set,
and then we discuss how the board and the pieces
helped or hurt their learning of the game,
where it steered them right and where it steered them wrong.
And then we brainstorm fixes together.
So why would I be so cruel?
Why would I bring board games that we all love
and put them in front of people who've never played them
before and force them to struggle?
As it turns out, as we'll find out at the end,
this is a super enjoyable exercise for people,
a wide variety of people.
It's fun to play with these essentially toys
because they're just pieces and boards.
But my biggest, the reason why I do this,
and it's been kind of something that I've talked about
for years and years, is.
I believe that game improvement only comes
through pain transference.
So we need to take the pain from the player
and put it on the shoulders of the developer.
And also, we're designing these days
for a world where no one reads.
And so what other tools do we have?
Well, of course, the board and the pieces.
So my background is more traditionally in video games.
And the neat thing about video games
is they have board and pieces, but they also
have computer feedback, which helps a lot.
When you're playing a board game,
the board game doesn't necessarily
give you feedback.
actively based on your decisions.
So for Pac-Man, for instance, on the left,
the game starts, whether I'm holding the joystick or not,
my Pac-Man starts swooping off.
I hear the bloop, bloop, bloop of things being eaten.
I see them disappearing.
I see the score incrementing.
I might notice that there's some interesting blinking things
that maybe I should investigate at some point,
but whoa, there's this red, angry-looking ghost,
and he's coming at me.
I should probably avoid him.
And the other thing I want you to notice about that
is the cherry at the bottom right.
This is in terms of progression, right?
So we've set the mode on easy to start with.
So new people coming into the game
will have a better chance of surviving for a bit
and figuring it out.
If we started on peach or pretzel,
new players would just get wiped out
before they could even figure out how to play the game.
On the right, you have StarCraft.
You start in a world.
You have a little base.
You've got a bunch of machines going.
They're gathering things.
They're bringing to the base.
You can see the counters on the right.
We're accumulating resources.
Maybe I can use those resources to build things.
You start to see the edge of the map, the fog of war.
It's like, oh, there's more to this.
Maybe I should go out exploring.
And then you look at the mini-map on the bottom left.
And you're like, oh, this is a big world.
And there might be other people who are not my friends
out there, and I need to be careful.
And the other thing is, too, talking again about how to make content so that it's easier for people to learn how to play.
Starcraft starts always with the Terrans, the humans.
They're the most human-like and they have a very traditional build structure.
So people can get a sense of the game before they start to introduce them to the more exotic races.
So how does this apply to the board game in context?
So these are three of the games that I use. I use a variety of games
I'm going to talk most more about Castle Panic and Cartagena and not about Deus Ex today
But yeah, how does this translate?
And as it turns out, like, as most of you know,
this is probably the first thing that you all do
when you open up a new box, right?
Most people, most of these groups that I ran
who'd never played these games before
knew to assemble the board in a way that made sense.
They knew to match like things together.
And with this, their sort of intuitive first guesses,
they started to figure out like what kind of game this is
and how they might begin to play it
and maybe what some of the victory conditions are.
The question I have though is how do we go from here
where you're sorting the cards, it's all new and exciting,
to here where you're actually having fun,
enjoying the game, learning the strategy,
having your sodas and popcorn.
So from my perspective, when I think about game user experience,
the largest job that I tend to do and a lot of us tend to do is what I call removing the suck, right?
There are just a lot of sucky things about figuring out the game,
and they're not intentional by the game designers.
But the problem is, is that the designer has the world in their mind,
and players have to sort of share that world and be a part of it.
And there are a lot of things that can impede that sharing.
So for instance, like, is this a great initial experience
of a game?
Like, I bought a game because I wanted to learn,
I wanted to play as a pirate escaping
from a medieval dungeon, right?
I didn't want to buy a game to read a whole bunch of rules.
So when I wrote, when I put Cartagena through these groups,
here are some of the things that emerged.
The pause, on the positive side,
board set up was super intuitive, right?
They have all these pieces, puzzle pieces
that fit together nicely.
People figured that out quickly.
Oops.
Ah.
The, yeah, they figured that out.
They figured out that there's some sort of maze aspect to it
and you start at one end and where you wanna get
is to the boat, because the boat's how you escape, see?
Then you can see one person's holding cards in their hand
and they say, okay, we'll deal out some cards,
we'll spend some cards to move our pieces around
and somehow or other we'll figure out
how we draw cards to replenish our hand.
And the victory conditions are, get on the boat.
So a couple things emerged, though, that were troublesome for groups and how they got things
wrong when they're figuring out.
The first thing was that the icon flavoring.
So this is one of the, it's a theme that I'm going to talk about a couple more times.
where art and UX can be in conflict.
So the idea is you've got a bunch of pirates
you're trying to escape, but they're pirates.
So they see shiny objects on the ground
and maybe they pause and take a look
and examine it for a second.
And it makes sense.
There's keys to treasure chests,
there's gems, there's bottles of rum.
But where people got stuck was on the skull, for instance.
So if you see the skull on the board,
they thought if they landed there,
maybe they would die, right?
And then if you look at the gun and the knife cards,
they thought, well, this game must involve combat
because, like, why would we have knife and gun cards
if we couldn't attack other pirates, right?
Well, actually, none of that exists in the game, right?
These are just all abstract things
that pirates might collect on the way out of the dungeon.
And so it led them to come up with different rules
and ways to play the game, some involving combat even.
And they created card battler games out of Cartagena.
And then the core mechanic of drawing cards and playing cards.
They understood that playing cards moved them forward on the board,
but they didn't understand, and who could blame them
if you haven't played card-taking before,
the way that you get new cards is you move your player backwards
to the closest occupied space and you get that number of cards.
Not very intuitive, but once you learn it, it makes sense.
So the teams came up with suggestions.
One is, hey, let's just remove the misleading icons.
Why do we need a skull and a gun and a knife?
We can replace them with a crown and
a treasure map and a goblet or something like that.
The other thing for the card drawing rules,
they already included this arrow card which you had to read
the rules to understand why it even existed or how to use it.
Well, replace that with a quick reference card that explain
the basic rules of moving forward by spending cards,
getting cards by moving backwards.
King of Tokyo was another game that I ran a whole bunch of.
Again, it's a beautiful manual, but what can we figure out
without that manual?
So really intuitive, the idea this is a monster brawl game.
The figures are all posed like they want to kill each other.
There's Tokyo, it's on fire,
so they're trying to invade Tokyo, obviously.
There's a bunch of dice that look exciting.
They have claws, which are the way you damage people,
of course, and hearts, the way you heal yourself.
And, you know, there's monsters,
and you win the game by killing
all the other monsters, right?
The things that didn't go so well here was,
one of the core mechanics is these special cards.
So you see the four energy zombify card.
People intuitively thought that, well, this is here,
so we're gonna deal them out to everyone.
Everyone has a handful of cards that we'll play with.
Well, actually, you're supposed to collect,
when you roll the dice, you're supposed to collect
energy cubes based on the number of energy bolts you roll,
and then spend those during your turn to earn those cards.
And so we figured out that it was the disconnect
between going from bolt to cube to then bolt again
on the card that caused some confusion there,
and people didn't necessarily get that.
They knew that you could enter and exit Tokyo and that not everyone could live in Tokyo,
but they didn't know the rules for why people would come into Tokyo and why they would have
to leave.
And then victory conditions.
They understood when you look at the top card there
and you see the 19 beside the star in blue,
they understood that went from zero to 20.
They're like, well, zero is probably where you start
and 20 is probably where you win,
but how do we get those victory points?
And really, we have cryptic clues
on the bottom left of the map there
where you've got the arrow and one star
and then the square brackets and the plus two stars,
but they were a little bit cryptic.
Also, there was no way for them to guess
that the numbers on the dice actually
referred to victory points.
And you needed to get sets of three or more
to earn some victory points.
So some of the suggestions we came up with was, well,
if you're already kind of torn between,
like, you don't want to ruin the art of your game
by putting a whole bunch of UX elements on it, right?
You've already made the decision to put some icons and text
on there.
Why not just actually make it sort of stand out and clean it
up a bit so that people can figure out what's going on?
by looking at it, and it's not quite so cryptic.
And that's the bottom left that I'm referring to there.
Iconography, so for energy, for instance,
why not have it always be cubes, right?
So the dice have a cube on it,
the card has a cube as the icon,
and then you've got these cubes.
That's one way to go about it.
The other way is the aftermarket way.
You can actually buy, I don't know how many of you guys,
you all play King of Tokyo,
but you can buy the little aftermarket lightning bolts,
energy bolts, so that you can have
this consistent experience.
And then the victory points, the dice,
how do we make it so that the dice indicate
that there's a way to get victory points to the dice,
maybe coloring them.
We weren't really sure,
but some sort of pattern matching or coloring
and making that consistent with the color
of the victory points.
Castle Panic was next.
So a lot of the positives here,
people really quickly picked up
and learned a lot about the game
just by looking at the board.
They looked at the middle of the board, it said castle.
Okay, we've got a castle, there's monsters
who are gonna enter, they're gonna enter from the forest
far away from the castle.
Right, that made sense, then monsters are gonna move
towards the castle and attack the castle.
They understood that by looking at the cards
that they would get, they'd use the cards
to combat the monsters and there were certain zones
that they could attack based on what card they had.
And the victory conditions, interestingly enough,
almost every group that I've played with this ever,
knew it was cooperative right from the beginning.
They knew it was the world against them.
A couple of them riffed on some ideas
about player versus player,
but almost unanimously they knew
it was a cooperative experience.
So, the board set up, you can see on the circle here at the bottom right, they have all the
walls and the towers on the outside, which is not exactly correct.
You want the walls on the outside and then the towers are kind of the keep in the middle
and it's when the keep falls down entirely that that's when the game's over.
The rules of play, so the help text,
they had actually help text on the board
and in these player cards that everyone
could take their little player reference card,
but they were vaguely worded,
and they were worded more for reminding
as opposed to learning.
So they had more vague statements like draw up,
well how many cards do I draw,
how many cards am I supposed to have?
They had play cards, well how am I supposed
to play the cards, am I supposed to use them
to attack or do other things?
They had one that's move monsters.
Well, how many do I move?
Do I move all of them, some of them?
Do I, you know, what do I do?
And then another problem that emerged was combat resolution.
So you've got these trolls that look big
and they count to one, two, and three,
and then you got orcs who are smaller and are one and two.
But you know, what are those numbers really mean?
Are they hit points?
Are they strength?
Is that how much damage they do?
Is it both?
So some of the suggestions that the group came up with
were.
First, marking the board.
So again, this is another art versus UX trade-off thing
where maybe there's ways that we can elegantly,
so that it looks nice, put some silhouettes
of where the footprints of the walls
versus the key pieces would go.
Decoupling hit points from attacks.
So imagine if we used on the bottom right here,
if we used specific icons to indicate damage,
the cards dealt those damage to the icons,
and then you map those icons onto the pieces.
And then tidying up the help text wording
to make it relevant to both, or useful to both players
and returning players who might have just forgotten
some of the rules.
So adding things like drop to five max cards,
move all your monsters.
And finally, Quirkle.
A really neat game, anyone who, I mean,
every group always had at least a few people,
if not everyone, who'd played Dominoes or Mahjong
or something like that.
And so they quickly figured out, you know,
okay, we got a tile pile in the middle,
we draw them, we make racks,
and then we match them together
and somehow we win or lose.
That was the problem though.
These pieces are so abstract that there were like
an infinite number of ways they could possibly
put them together.
And so they spent a lot of time trying to figure out
what the rules of this game were.
And that meant that they couldn't really figure out scoring
or when the game was supposed to end.
And this was a case where we kind of threw our hands up
in the air.
We're like, board and pieces?
Well, there really are only pieces
and there's not much we can do with those
that won't even make it more confusing potentially.
But we did talk about optimizing the scoring sheet.
You can see on the left, the Quirkle score sheet's
pretty generic.
It's just columns of numbers.
It doesn't really have any guidance whatsoever
about scoring and how to play the game.
Whereas you can compare that with the rule
through the ages one.
You've got both scoring and some rules that are helpful.
So how does this help you?
I mean, none of you, I don't think,
are going to come up with the next Cartagena expansion
or whatever.
The reason why I'm presenting this stuff is more about
to talk about a process that might be useful to you.
And it's a process that supplements
your normal play testing.
So you don't use this process for early game development
where you're iterating with your core group of designers
and trying to figure out what are the fun
and interesting strategic things about a game
that you want to make.
They're not about balance feedback
or about testing for degenerate conditions
or golden paths or anything like that.
The idea is to help you think differently about your design decisions, and think hard
about the tradeoffs between art and usability, and rely less on the, well, we'll just solve
it with the manual kind of mentality, or people will Google it to figure it out.
With the end result being, let's make it easier for people to pick it up and play it, because
you can't ship yourself with the game.
So in terms of directing your energies,
I consider the gold standard to be, you know,
iterating on the board and pieces themselves.
When you fix the issues at the top of the funnel,
it means you can make for more efficient use
of any kind of additional documentation, right?
If you can clarify a whole bunch of stuff
through the actual board,
that means you can eliminate maybe sections of the manual
and replace it with things that people will,
that are known to struggle with.
And so you can prioritize.
what content goes into the manual,
and you can actually cut with confidence
things that maybe don't need to appear there
because you only have limited space.
The late production iteration is more costly
than earlier iteration,
but there's new tools to make it cheaper,
like laser cutters and 3D printers.
This is from Matt Leacock.
It was a paper prototype for a chariot racing game,
and he got himself a Kickstarter laser cutter
and made himself a fancy little board and everything.
Another vector of attack is, you know,
QRCs, scorecards, and help text, right?
Remember when you're designing these,
it's for two audiences.
One is for the players who wanna learn
how to play the game, but the other is,
sometimes it's a party game or something like that.
It comes out only during social events,
and you don't maybe play it more than once
every few months, and it's a mix of new
and experienced players to it.
The reminders are different than the learning how to play,
and so make sure you're designing for both
and testing for both.
This is also from Matt Leacox here,
the role through the ages.
He's got a really cool time lapse video on his website
that shows 24 different iterations of this card.
So it's important to keep iterating through these
during your play sessions.
The fancy manual, when I worked in video games
at the beginning, we actually shipped paper manuals
with games, that hasn't happened in years.
But the only things I ever cared about were the center fold,
it had to be controller mapping layout,
and then the last page had to be the,
oh my God, I'm stuck, we need to have the top three things
that we know people get stuck on and list them there.
Because my thought was, you're only gonna go to the manual
if you're stuck, right?
So we might as well make it easy.
The other thing you can do with the manual
is kind of repurpose it a little bit.
I talked a little bit about how you can,
when you focus on the UX at the higher levels,
it means you can streamline your manual,
maybe even cut sections of your manual
and replace it with other stuff,
like the stuff that people find confusing.
But also, I think it's really useful to consider adding these quick start modes to your game.
I learned, I sort of first learned about this when I was working on Catan for Xbox Live
and I discovered that one of the later versions of Catan actually started with the starting
map for beginners.
It's a nice balance board, it takes away the early decisions that are overwhelming to users
like where do I put my initial settlement and road.
And it makes it so that players start collecting resources right away because it's a balanced board
And then so they start building things early trading early and gets them really into the fun parts of it early on
And so investing more time into that kind of mode would be great
Especially if you can reduce the content you need to include as the traditional manual
And then for your digital content,
again, this sort of helps you streamline.
Between when my game ships or hits the shelves and now,
I might only have time to make one or two videos.
What videos do I make in terms of explaining the game?
Well, you'll have studied.
You'll know what some of the key problems are.
And you'll get a chance to make those videos
to supplement that.
I talked a lot about making, you know,
finding the sock and eliminating the sock,
but one of the other cool things
about doing these exercises,
and this is what I'm gonna wrap up on,
is that actually you get a chance to see people
using what you've made in delightful ways
that might be totally unexpected.
So in Cartagena, we had some people
who experimented with the tiles and said,
well, what if an earthquake happened
or something happened where we shifted around the tiles
partway through the game based on an event?
We had another group who said,
well, this isn't a free-for-all game, this is a team game.
And we've got the pirates on the right team
and the pirates on the left team
racing toward the boat, fighting each other over the boat,
and the first team to get on the boat
and leave the island win.
Not necessarily what Cartagena was going for,
but these are ideas for expansions maybe that you can make
or other ideas, maybe you've got some other game ideas
you're noodling on, and some of these mechanics
might inspire you to try something different.
And the final one is.
Now, I doubt the inventor of Quirkle
really wanted to make Jenga out of Quirkle.
But maybe the inventor of Quirkle is like,
you know, Jenga's a pretty fun game.
Quirkle, I like.
Maybe there's some new variant of Jenga that I can make up.
And so it gives you new ideas and creative ways
to sort of expand what you do.
And I'll end on that.
So we have a few minutes left to take some questions.
Thank you.
Do we want people to come up to the mic?
No, OK, I'll just repeat the question.
So if you can shout it out, or you can feel
free to come to the mic.
I was just wondering if there's any common UX pitfalls
that you saw amongst all the games you were testing.
That is the million dollar question.
The question's about, are there common pitfalls?
And I think
If I could write that book, I would probably
be like a millionaire and retired a million times over.
But I think the biggest thing is having this
as part of your process.
Because you start to, within your own genre of game
and the games that you make, you start to learn
the patterns of what happens.
So that's one thing is I can't give you a common answer,
but I can say that the process works if you let it work.
But one of the common things is where I talk about this.
Usually it's a creative direction problem
where it's like.
We want the game to be immersive,
and so we want the art to be beautiful,
but also we want the game to be immersive
and we want it to be understandable.
And that conflict right there,
how much art is too much art and distracts you away
from actually learning how to game play.
And as I mentioned during some of those examples,
those were some key issues.
It's like the art looked great,
but it was unintentionally distracting
and not in a good way.
Thank you.
I don't know if this is working.
Oh, yeah.
OK.
So I noticed that you were saying that for the test,
at least, you take the rule books out,
but leave the quick reference cards in.
Would you say that quick reference cards
are superior to rule books?
And if you could simplify it enough,
would you say a game would be better
if it was just two or three quick reference cards
with no rule book at all?
That's an interesting question.
So could we just eliminate the need for manual
and have these awesome quick reference cards?
I think that would be great.
I think you're always going to need some sort of manual,
especially for, like there are some games that
don't lend themselves well.
I picked specifically games that they take an hour to play,
they're more partyish games, they're not as deep.
And I think for those types of games, yes, exactly that.
Want to move away from the manual
into just like, let's start sorting things out
and figuring out how to play from the cards themselves.
So I can't give you like the overall,
like I don't, like I'm fighting for a world
where we never have to have another,
no, I'm not arguing for that at all.
But I think there are definitely classes of games
where it's not necessary to have one,
or that doesn't have to be the expectation
that I need to read the manual
before I can learn how to play it.
Hi, I'm Krzysztof from Asmode Poland.
Have you thought while this testing about the some information that you put on a board is language dependent.
And while developing the game, you want to keep some of the components language independent, language neutral.
Have you find any? Do you?
Can you tell us any good thoughts about that that you that you saw while you were exploring this topic?
Yeah, that's a good question.
So about game localization, and obviously it's
much cheaper and more streamlined
to be able to design a game once and ship it
across all languages.
The suggestion that some of the teams made for King of Tokyo,
where let's tidy up the wording or some of the cards
for Castle Panic.
Yeah, it's a tricky situation when you want to focus on words themselves as a solution.
First of all, just because words can clarify things, but people read the words as Moses
from the mountain kind of thing.
If you write something in a way that doesn't exactly make sense,
you might actually harm them more than help them.
In terms of localization, though, we
didn't see any specific trends.
We just noticed that it's, I think, as a process thing,
you'll just want to iterate more on them
to make sure that those non-verbal hints are
being effective and effectively conveying what you want.
And one thing that we struggle at is that,
like on the King of Tokyo board, it's like,
those icons were kind of meaningless to people,
and they didn't really explain what was going on.
Now, again, that also, you bring that back to the fact
that, as a reminder, it works great if I already
know the rules, basically, but as a new player
to discover them.
And then you just make the trade-off yourself.
You say, well, yeah, we can't localize this
across a bunch of languages.
And so we're just going to, just for the sake of the business,
we're going to make sure that we just use the icon-only version.
The others.
All right, I think I'm supposed to remind everyone
that I guess you'll get an email asking for feedback.
So feedback encouraged.
I love to learn and make my speeches and talks better.
And I'm happy to stick around at the end
and talk to people individually.
Thanks very much.