Hello, hello, 9 AM crowd. What is up? I'm impressed that all of you made it. My voice
you can probably hear is a little ragged, just like all of yours, I'm sure. But I'm
going to do my best to do my radio announcer voice and kind of lull you into a nice presence
as I give you this talk. So, this talk is 30 minutes long, so unfortunately I can't
go into literally everything about freelancing. That would be nice, though.
So what I'm gonna do is have a follow-up video call
with those of you who want it.
So we're gonna do a group call.
So if you wanna give me your business card
at the end of this,
I'll send out an email to all of you afterwards
and we'll do like a group chat
where you can ask me follow-up questions
because I am certain that after we're done here,
you'll be like, okay, yeah, okay,
I don't have any questions.
Then one day later, you'll be like, goddammit.
which happens with every single talk that we ever go to.
So I wanna give you a little bit more so you can,
this isn't the last interaction we'll ever have.
Also, make sure you turn off your cell phones,
noise makers, that sort of thing,
and also make sure that you fill out the surveys
for whatever talks that you go to, including this guy's.
And lastly.
Whoa.
Make sure that you give me your business card at the very end.
That's really important so that I can get you on my list
to get that all done.
So as we begin, one thing I want to mention to you
is that you are running.
a business. Most people in the music sound design sense don't actually think about it
this way. They think about themselves as artists, which is actually great. I do as well. But
we make the mistake of thinking, oh, I'm not running a business. I'm an artist. That means
I don't need to think about money. What?
That's ridiculous. No. So what we're going to do is help you think in some ways of how
businesses kind of think and how you can start thinking about that. That doesn't mean necessarily
that you have a Rolodex and that you're chomping a cigar every single day. No, no, no. But
it does mean that you are thinking about things in a more systematic way.
So a little bit about me before we dive into it.
My name's Akash Thakar.
I've worked on the sound design for Hyper Light Drifter,
some MIDI mock-up work for Destiny Rise of Iron,
just released Brass Tactics, which is a VR RTS,
just released in the Oculus Store.
Heat Signature, which is in the IGF, whoop whoop.
And I've given two TEDx Talks,
one on the power of video game music,
and another.
on the idea of following your passion
being not a good idea, we can talk about that later.
And lastly, I just released a book on Monday
called Maximizing Game Feel Through Sound,
which is now a number one bestseller on Kindle, woo!
So that is for developers on how they can
work with audio people better, yay, woo!
Like three people, just like, yeah, sweet.
So what we're going to cover in today's talk
is how business owners think.
Obviously, I'm not going to go super in-depth,
but how you can start thinking about things
to make it so that your work comes more fluidly
and that you're not doing the freelance hustle that so
many people talk about, where you're wondering where
the next gig is coming from.
How to find great work and what processes
you can use to actually get better and better clients.
Whether or not you should have a side job and the stigma
associated with that.
some contracts and other boring stuff that, you know, we have to cover.
And obviously I want to just remind you that we're gonna do a video call follow up.
And lastly, I do want to remind you that the things I say here, my way isn't the only way.
I'm gonna give you some advice that you should actually take and use as your own.
This isn't the only way to actually go about this.
And for those of you taking pictures of the slides constantly, I am actually putting these
up on my website immediately after.
So don't worry about that.
So you'll be, you'll be set.
You don't need those grainy photos.
So let's go into how businesses think in the kind of intro of this.
So they think in systems.
What they do is think about their business or their products or whatever it is that they're
selling or whatever it is that they're doing in reproducible steps.
And systems are actually just a fancy word for habits.
It's just a business word for habits.
So, basically, they think, OK, how can I sell this thing, or do this thing, or give this
service in a way that is reproducible?
How can I keep getting clients, for example, or how can I keep selling iPhones, or whatever
it may be?
That's the general gist of how businesses think.
They don't think, oh, maybe we'll sell something today.
No, they have a procedure and steps that they can go through to reproduce great results
every single time.
Apple is a great example, and Google, who are just kings of systems.
They are amazing at making things happen.
fall into place perfectly every single time.
So like I mentioned, you have to make sure
you have reproducible steps.
So some examples that I want to give you are,
OK, let's say you want to find clients.
Maybe you want to make a system based off of that goal.
I want to find clients who pay me x amount per gig.
Whatever it may be.
What you want to do is start writing down
and thinking of this in ways like, OK, what are
the steps I can take every month, every week,
every year, whatever it may be in differing time frames
that I can use to reproduce this.
For example, it could be, OK, every year I'll
come to GDC.
OK.
That's one part of your system.
Every week or month I'll go to a local
networking meetup.
OK.
Great.
That's a system.
What is my system for following up with people
after I meet them?
Mine, I use an app called Close, C-L-O-Z-E.
It's really good.
to help remind me who to follow up with
and who to keep talking to and what we've talked about.
It's a really good app for that.
But I have a system for following up with people
and talking to people,
and I follow it every single time.
And I use reminders on my phone
to actually remind me what things I need to do.
And I even spend Sundays scheduling out that week,
OK, what are my systems for this week?
What meetups am I going to go to?
That makes it so that these steps
actually start to be reproducible.
So when you have goals, which are great, I'm a big fan of goals, like, okay, I want to get six clients,
I want to get paid for my work, whatever it may be, write down systems that are associated with it.
So write down habits that you can start implementing week to week, day to day, month to month, year to year,
on how you can actually start implementing those in your day to day life.
So if you are trying to get clients, what are the systems?
What are the habits that you can do?
Showing up to events, talking to people, giving talks, or
talking to mentors and finding work that way, meeting other
people in the audio community, asking if there's any overflow
or anything like that, having follow-ups, all that sort of
stuff, those are systems that you can implement underneath
the goal, because when you have a big goal.
That's great, but it can be hard to follow step by step
when you don't really know the habits you need
to actually get there.
If you want to get better at music,
what's your practice system?
If you want to get better at sound design,
what sort of Foley work are you going to do
week to week, month to month?
Whatever it may be,
you need to think about things in that way.
So one thing I want to show you on in the kind of client getting side of things
is a little funnel that I made and basically what I want you to start
thinking about is how you can actually start getting clients and kind of moving
people through this funnel in such a way that you get more clients more easily in
an authentic kind of sleaze free way. I'm all about that.
So first up, you have something called prospects.
Now, a prospect is someone who may have worked for you
at some point in general,
but they don't really know who you are.
It could be a big company
that you know needs music or sound,
but you're not sure if they're really interested in you.
They don't have a job posting open.
There's no opening.
You don't know anyone at the company.
You don't really have any information on it,
but they're a prospect.
They're a potential client
that you don't really have much information on.
Next up is something called a lead.
Now, a lead is a client or a potential client
that you have a little bit of knowledge on.
You know that they're looking for music or sound
or whatever it is you do.
You have an idea that, okay,
they have a job opening on their website
or you heard through the grapevine
that they're interested in hiring you.
That's kind of a lead and you know that they're interested
so you kind of have a little bit of an opening.
Now, opportunities are when clients come to you,
or potential clients come to you and say, send us a demo.
Or we're interested in working with you.
What's your rate?
That sort of thing.
And we're going to talk about answering that dreaded question,
what's your rate, later.
But when you have an opportunity,
basically people are asking you to pitch to them
in some way, shape, or form.
So you're being asked to show your stuff,
or they're just generally asking, what's your rate?
Or how would it be like working with you?
Anything like that, that's an opportunity.
And then lastly, you have a client, someone
that you are actively working for.
So, what your goal though, throughout all this process through GDC, and we're on Friday
so I'm giving you advice that you can't really use for the rest of GDC, but hopefully for
future conferences, is to actually nurture these prospects.
So what you want to do is take leads and opportunities and move them to clients.
And the way you actually go about doing that is follow up.
This is actually one of the most important things.
I'm going to talk about this a little more.
But following up with people you meet,
whether it be online or in person.
In person is ideal, which is why you're here.
That's great.
Following up with them, sending them an email
saying it was great to meet them,
within 24 hours of meeting them,
or giving them some sort of advice,
or maybe they ask you about middleware
or something like that.
Following up with your potential clients
within 24 hours is the most powerful way
that you'll actually move people
from prospect to lead to opportunity to client.
That's the most powerful way.
And most people mess this up.
They get a pile of business cards.
They look at them and say, they're not interested.
And then throw them away.
Or they're just kind of languishing on their desk for
months and months and months.
And how many of you have done that and just let all your
business cards kind of, OK, like one person raises their
hand and is honest.
I know all of you have done this, so don't lie to me.
I can tell.
So when we're talking about finding clients
and finding great work, your goal is to move
like potential prospects through this funnel
through talking to them and following up.
This isn't done in a friendly, sleaze-free way.
You're not constantly elbowing them in the ribs
saying, please hire me, because that's, ooh,
we do that too much, and I hear too many horror stories
of other composers and sound designers
who are just begging for work.
That's not the way to do this.
Your goal is to actually form some sort of business,
or friendly relationship, with these people.
You want to talk to them.
You actually want to get to know them.
You want to know their game's needs.
That's really important.
And you want to know how you can actually solve their problem.
This isn't just a gig.
You are solving their problem, because they don't have music.
They don't have sound.
They don't have voiceover or implementation for their game.
And it's really important for them to actually have that off
of their plate, so they don't need to worry about it.
That's what we're doing here. We're actually helping devs
not worry about that side of their develop, development
so much.
So like I've mentioned, it's good to talk to
humans. I'm an extreme, extreme, extreme introvert. So I
have to actually train really, really, really, really hard
for the course of a decade to be able
so much as look someone in the eye.
So talking to humans is really, really important. That
is actually one of the most important things you
can do. In person is ideal. I get asked
a lot.
How do I find tons of clients online?
You can, but generally in person,
you'll find higher quality clients
and you'll get more prospects and leads
and opportunities and clients
by talking to people in person, face to face.
People will be able to trust you much, much quicker that way.
asked a lot, oh, I don't have a reel, or I
don't have a website, or anything like that.
I can't go to those networking events.
Now, this isn't necessarily for you, because you're all
here at one of the biggest networking events for the game
industry.
But a lot of people ask me if they
don't have a reel or website, is it OK to talk to developers?
And absolutely yes.
I didn't have one for like three years when I first started,
but I still got clients.
Because people just kind of said like, oh, you're cool.
Come on board.
And that is actually how it works in some cases,
especially kind of at a starting level.
People want to hire people that they like or that they know
or that they trust or that they met in person,
someone that they've interfaced with that they know
will probably do a great job and won't just disappear
off the face of the planet,
which may happen more likely with someone they've never met
and is completely online and they know nothing about.
So even if you don't have a reel and you don't have a website,
yes, talk to developers as much as you can.
Because once you have that website, once you have that reel,
once you have all your stuff ready, they'll know who you are already.
And you'll have someone to actually talk to about it.
And people will be more receptive, because they already know who you are.
Does that make sense?
Does everyone follow?
Yes?
Cool.
So one thing I'll mention to people who are just starting out,
people say like, oh, should I say no to things?
Like, should I say yes to everything that comes my way?
Generally, unless the client is super shady
and you're getting a really bad vibe from them,
and you're just starting out, and you
don't know what your strengths are,
and you're still figuring things out,
and maybe you don't have paid clients yet,
it is a good idea to start saying yes to a lot of things
so that you can get a lot of experience.
Now again, this doesn't mean necessarily
working with bad clients or working
with people who give you really bad vibes or are disrespectful.
because there's a lot of that in this industry,
unfortunately, but I'm not saying you have to do that.
But it's a good idea to start saying yes to a lot of things
and taking on a lot of work,
within reason, obviously, don't sacrifice your health.
But taking in a lot of work is really important
to getting your strengths and knowing
what you like working on,
and having an idea of what sorts of clients
you wanna work with,
and knowing what sorts of things you'll need to say
to future clients in the future as you start negotiating,
getting contracts, that sort of thing.
And lastly, you all know this, but just so you know,
one thing that you, some things that you can do
is of course volunteer at events.
That's how I actually started.
I was a CA when I first started here.
So, woo, CAs, I love them so much.
But that's how I started.
I volunteered at things like PAX or GDC
or any local events in Seattle where I'm based.
to meet people, to meet developers, to say hi to other people,
and meet all the other volunteers as well.
And that was networking that was kind of done for me.
So don't eschew volunteering from your mind. It's really useful.
Going to game jams, of course, great idea for experience.
Most of you have done this already.
And attending local events, wherever you're at.
And it may not be so local for you. You may need to travel a bit.
Some people live further away from hubs than others.
You may need to drive a bit, or even fly,
like I'm sure many of you did to get here.
that's worth it. It's worth it to actually attend events and actually talk to humans
and get in people's faces, not in a weird way, but talk to people and be actual friends
with them. So let's talk about networking on that note a little bit more. So like I
mentioned before, you're actually here to make friends and actual relationships. You're
not here just to go up to people, hand your business card out and run away, which is what
I certainly did when I started. Woo!
So that doesn't work.
That doesn't work at all.
People actually want to form some sort of connection with you.
And if they do, they're much more likely to hire you based
on that principle.
They'll realize, oh, OK, you're easy to work with.
You have a good vibe.
This will probably go a lot better than someone who just
handed me their business card I know nothing about and just
ran away.
It is worth it to form these relationships.
And I'm always about quality over quantity.
So if you can talk to people.
for a little bit longer instead of talking to everybody for one, two seconds at a time,
that's more important. Having quality over quantity is really, really important.
So one thing I'll mention is as you get more advanced and as you become more,
you know, well-known in the industry or you start talking to more people,
just showing up doesn't really work after a certain point.
Yes, if you're starting out, just showing up is great,
because you don't really know what's going on.
Fantastic.
Just do that.
But if you are a little more intermediate, a little more
advanced, your pay rate is increasing, et cetera, et
cetera, making a plan for networking events is really,
really, really crucial.
I don't just show up anymore.
I research speakers.
I see who's going to be there.
I host lunches.
I host events, that sort of thing.
You don't necessarily need to go that far.
But looking at who's going to be at that event,
whether it be speakers or just attendees,
especially if it's a local event,
you can usually see who's going to be there, is very helpful.
You can look at what those people are up to
and see what they're working on.
If you can walk up to someone and say,
oh, I've actually been looking at your game.
That's really cool.
I'm excited about x, y, z.
that's much better than tell me about your game,
because you've actually put the time in to actually research
and learn and actually make an effort
to learn about other people instead of hoping
other people will just trust you instantly.
That doesn't work.
That doesn't happen.
So don't just show up at a certain point.
It's worth researching the event,
who's gonna be there, who you should talk to.
It makes things much easier
and it kills a lot of the small talk
and you can get way easier into better conversations.
And like I mentioned, sending emails, researching speakers.
Sending emails to people who might be there
is very important before you go to that event.
Like, oh, it'll be great meeting you, I'll be at your talk,
or I can't wait to see you at this event, whatever it may be.
When I first started in Seattle,
I messaged the person who was the head of those meetups.
I just said, oh, I just moved to Seattle,
I can't wait to meet you, I'll be at this event.
Great.
Nothing more than that.
I didn't mention I was a composer, sound designer, none of that stuff.
But when I showed up, I said, oh, hey, it's so nice to meet you.
Like, oh, you sent me that email.
Yeah, let me introduce you to some people.
Because they already had an idea of who I was just a little bit, and it got rid of the
small talk.
The stranger danger was kind of gone a little bit.
And again, like I've mentioned, follow-up is so, so, so, so important.
Now, following up with people within 24 hours, you get a card.
They're cool.
You don't have to follow up with literally everybody.
But if you get someone who's interesting, follow up with
them, email them within 24 hours, talk about what you've
talked about, if you had a good conversation.
Say it was great meeting them.
Thanks.
See you later.
It doesn't have to be anything longer than that.
Don't do the thing where people send.
and it's Encyclopedia Britannica emails, which is what I
get a hundred and fifty of every single week.
Please don't do that to me.
And it's just like, here's my life story.
Here's sixteen demo reels.
Please love me.
Don't do that.
Just say hello.
It was great to meet you.
And then, that's it.
Perfect email.
So, like I mentioned, you do need a, you do
need a big network, but that'll come with time.
The quality actually matters a little bit more, and
vibrancy is what actually comes about.
And I actually learned this quote was really good
from the work-life balance talk that Penka, Brian Schmidt,
Jesse, and Larissa gave.
And that was really good.
I can't remember who
exactly, I think it was Penka that said this.
I'm not a hundred percent sure.
But you do need a
big network.
That'll come with time.
And you do need a vibrant one, which is
one that you're following up with and talking to
regularly, showing up to local events.
Those are the people who have your back.
So contracts will blaze through this really quickly.
You can ask me specific questions now or afterwards.
Use contracts, even for free projects.
A lot of people ask me, like, oh, it's free, whatever.
But if you use one, it actually helps
determine who owns your stuff.
And there is a little bit of a precedent.
I'm not a lawyer, by the way.
I'm not sure if you could tell.
But there's a little bit of a precedent set now,
where if a contract isn't set, then by default, not always,
this is kind of super gray area.
the rights can sometimes go to the client instead of you if there's no contract.
And you may not want that. You may want the ownership terms really clear.
If you're working on a free project and you're not getting anything out of it,
which I'll talk about in a second,
it is really important to actually make sure you own those rights to that music or that sound,
or you're just doing a license, or you want to be clear that they own it
so there's no kerfuffle in the future.
Now, the two major types of contracts are work for hire,
which means that, OK, this client owns all of the stuff
that I give them.
They own all the music.
They own all the sound.
They pay me, and we're good.
That's usually how it works.
So that's what I did for things like Destiny, for example.
I make something.
They own it.
I don't have it.
I can't take that and sell that later, right?
Pretty simple.
That's usually the most common that you're going to run into.
Now, there's also non-exclusive agreement, which you can use for clients that may not
be able to pay your full rate.
What actually happens here is that you retain ownership of your stuff, your music, your
sound, whatever it may be, but you're licensing an out to that client.
So you're giving it to them for some period of time where they can use it, and then you
can sell it to other clients later as well.
This makes it cheaper for the client and makes it so that you can make more money off of
it in the future.
So if you make a whole bunch of sounds, you can then say,
OK, you can have these sounds.
Maybe you have it exclusively for the next six months, let's
say, you don't always have to have a timeline,
but you usually can.
And then you can say, OK, cool, the six months is up.
I can give this to any other client I want.
I can use this in any other future game I want.
So you can make a little bit more money off the back end of
it as time goes on.
So let's talk about charging clients.
That's really important.
Now, this is a little bit disputed,
and I'll give you a little bit of a qualifier on this.
Flat fees are really important.
I see a lot of people shooting themselves in the foot
with per asset rates.
That's not necessarily the best way,
not to say it's always the best way,
but using flat fees makes it easier for the client.
I see so many people say, oh, I charge X amount per sound effect or X amount per minute of
music.
And especially in the indie world, people will see that rate and be like, that's a blank
check.
I have no idea how much I'm going to pay this person.
Even if they say it'll be 100 assets and it will be $100 per asset, they still don't want
to see that.
They want you to just throw a number out.
and use a flat fee. And it makes things so much easier for them
to not have to worry about it. They don't get blank check syndrome.
It makes things so much simpler. So whenever you can,
calculate your fee. Maybe you do per asset in your head,
but calculate how many assets, measure it all out,
and say, oh, this will be $3,000.
Here you go.
And maybe you had a per asset fee in your head, but you're
giving them the final number.
It makes things a lot easier.
Not all clients prefer this.
This isn't for everything.
But it is very useful and makes things a lot
smoother and a lot easier.
So that's my advice to you.
Now I'm going to.
send this to you guys for those of you giving me your card and all that. I'm going to give
you a template for a project proposal. So when someone asks like, oh, what's your rate?
Instead of just emailing them back, you can actually have a little bit of a PDF where
you can send them, you know, here's our timelines, here's how much I will, here's how much it's
going to cost, here's why it's going to cost this much. Thanks so much. It's a much more
professional way to actually give your rates. I can't go into one here, but again, email
me or, you know, give me your cards or whatever and I can send that to you.
Now, there's something that happens a lot called post-quote silence where,
oh, I charge this much, and then no response from the client.
How many of you have dealt with that?
Yes?
OK.
A whole bunch of people have dealt with that.
Now, this is a common thing.
This is really, really common.
This happens a lot.
The general reason that this happens isn't necessarily
because your price is too high.
It does happen because of that sometimes.
But usually, it's the client sees that and goes, OK, let me think on that.
I'm busy right now.
I'll get back to that.
And they never get back to it because emails are the worst.
So, how to actually get around it is to actually, when they say, when you give the rate, no
response, within about, you know, one to two days, give it a little bit of time for them
to respond, I usually say something like, okay, great, I'm excited to get to work on
this, I can start on the sword sounds, or whatever, some specific thing, I can start
on the sword sounds today.
How does that sound?
it makes it a lot easier for them to say yes at that point.
And it makes it so that they're like,
oh right, I forgot to respond to this, yes.
Don't mention the money in your follow-up either,
because it's really easy for us as artists and freelancers
to kind of wring our hands, like,
oh, I'm sorry I charged $100 for this.
Ooh, I'm so sorry, let me just lower this for you.
Don't do that.
Just say, I'm excited to get to work on this,
how about I start on X?
Makes it a lot easier for them,
and it lets them know that you're actually more motivated
as well to actually get started.
Now, one thing for those of you who are beginners
and you don't know how to respond to the question,
how much do you charge?
Now, this is usually beginner level only,
but not super advanced or other ways.
But if someone says, oh, how much do you charge?
And you know you have a general kind of tummy number,
something in your gut that you know, like, okay.
How about like, you know, $1,000 for this or whatever.
I'm just making random numbers.
And that's really scary for you to say that.
I've had so many people say, oh, I'm so scared to quote.
Oh my god, I have to send a dollar sign,
one, one, one, one, zero, zero, zero to this person.
What I usually do in this case, when you're that scared
and you're not 100% sure if it's too high,
what you can do is say something like this.
Normally, I would charge $1,000 for this project.
Now, I know you're a small indie studio,
or whatever qualifier you want,
especially if it's a beginner project or student project,
whatever it may be.
How much of that number do you feel comfortable paying?
That puts the ball in their court,
but they know what your number is.
So you'll often find something,
you'll often find clients say like,
oh, well, okay, I can't do 1,000, but 800's good.
Or, but there's a human psychology thing that happens
where you can easily say, oh, I normally charge 1,500,
let's say it's for the same project, 1,500 for this.
How much of that number do you feel comfortable paying?
Oh, we can't do 15.
How about 1,200?
So you can actually increase your rates, actually,
really, really easily that way.
Again, if you're more advanced, I usually just say,
here's my rate.
I don't really negotiate on that case.
But when you're first starting out, it's really terrifying
to actually wonder, is this too high?
Is this too low?
I want to leave a little leeway because I don't know
what the rates are.
I have no idea.
That's the script.
I normally charge x.
How much of that do you feel comfortable paying?
That's usually how you can go.
Now some people ask, can I work for free?
Is that okay?
Especially if it's a student game or something like that.
Yes, you can totally work for free.
You're not devaluing the industry, but.
But, but, but, but, make sure you're not working for nothing.
You can work for free, but don't work for nothing.
Most people work for nothing.
They think, oh, credit, sweet.
No, you have to get credit.
In some places, it's the law.
That's nothing.
That's absolutely nothing.
Get something else out of it.
It could be tickets to an event like GDC.
Maybe the developer can get you there.
It may be business card design.
It could be web design.
It could be teaching you how to code, whatever it may be.
get some sort of something out of it. Other
than credit. Make sure you get something else, whether
it be a skill trade or something like that.
That's really important. When I first worked for Penny
Arcade, way, way back, I was their audio guy,
I remember the final job I did for them.
I was like, how about I do this for
free but you give me free PAX passes forever,
as many as I want.
Great. I have that. I have that now.
So I have endless passes for every PAX that I could ever want.
It rules. And that was well worth it.
So people ask about side jobs.
Should I?
Can I?
Is it a good idea?
Yes.
It's a good idea.
I used to clean toilets when I first started.
So I was a public pool janitor.
I don't recommend that as your side job.
It was the worst.
It was the smells.
I actually had to wear a gas mask.
I'm not joking.
That's how bad it smelled.
So it's OK to have a side job.
So many people ask, oh, but I need to go all in.
No, it's good to have actually some sort of financial stability while you're studying
and while you're working on your craft.
That is so, so, so crucial.
And you're not a failure if you have one.
You're absolutely not.
It's really important to know that.
If you are building financial stability and hustling or working on your thing on the side,
I consider that a success so long as you keep going and doing your thing.
It's only failure if you completely quit and give up
and say, no, I'm never doing this again, this is too hard.
Or maybe you wanna pivot,
which isn't failure in and of itself.
But if you realize that, okay, I wanna do this thing,
and you're smart enough to realize
you also need money to do it,
then that's actually a really smart thing.
That's a really smart way of thinking about it.
Now, some of you are higher risk than others
and wanna go all in, fine, that's totally cool.
No worries at all.
If you have a higher risk tolerance
and can deal with those real financial lows,
Cool, but I do advocate for most people to have some sort of financial stability
because it can be a lot harder to so much as write a note when you're worried about
where the next meal is coming from, right?
So make sure you have something.
So lastly, as a reminder, as we finish up, there's no one right way.
This isn't just, this is just me going and me telling you from my point of view.
And we're going to wrap up here.
We only have a few minutes left for questions.
So if you also want to, you know, I'm
going to be able to hang out a little bit here
before I go to my next talk at 10 with Ryan Eich and Carly
Knight on the don'ts, how not to work in game audio.
So you can follow me there if you want to as well.
Also, we'll be doing that follow-up video call.
So please feel free to email me as well any of your questions.
Let me know that you're at GDC, because I get literally
150 emails a week of people asking advice.
So make sure you're at GDC, because then I'll actually have.
you know, a filter set up to make sure I talk to you guys first, you have high priority
because I get to meet you in person. I also have business cards here if you want to kind
of just grab one and go if you're off to somewhere. But that's it for today. Thank you so much
for coming. So we have a couple of minutes for questions, so please use the mic just
so it goes into the recording.
I've been so polite.
Hey, thank you for taking the time today to share your
experience.
Actually, two things.
How do you transition clients that you've started
on a trade basis?
You've got, I would call, a professional rate.
I do video production work, authoring DVDs.
And you start with clients, great clients, great people.
You're helping them in a small business with work.
to get a professional job done, but now you're trying to get other clients.
They still demand a lot of time, but they can't move with you to that rate.
I mean, how have you handled that?
Yeah, so usually there's a few ways to do it.
You can give them kind of a bonus, like an old client rate, like you give them a cheaper rate.
But if you don't want, you may not want to work with that company anymore, let's say,
let's say like hypothetically, oh, they just can't pay me anymore at all.
It's a good idea if there is a hard cutoff,
recommend someone else, so that's a good karma for you.
But if you want to transition them into a higher tier
with you, if you want to bring them to,
you're saying your rates are increasing,
it's actually not a bad idea, in my experience,
to say something like, okay, you know what,
I've been doing XYZ a lot, I love you as a client.
my rates are increasing to this number for clients now,
but I'm gonna give you this much
because you're such a trusted client.
Let me know if that works for you.
If it doesn't, I'd be happy to recommend someone else
who can do this work for you at a different rate.
Because that can give you good karma
and they'll love you for it.
Even if you can't work with them anymore
and you recommend someone, they'll be like, oh, thank you.
And maybe help get someone else into the biz,
like hey, here's someone who's starting out.
I met him at a networking.
Exactly.
And basically, you become Google to them, where they'll
keep coming to you for references.
They will not cut you off if you give some sort of
reference.
You are kind of the person machine at that point.
Like, oh, who else?
Who else?
Oh my god.
Oh, we'd love to work with you again.
It works really well.
OK.
And real quick, just as a comment about working a side
job, it helped me when I got started to pick the clients I
wanted to work with.
I didn't have to worry about taking every job.
to pay the bills.
Yes, you didn't have to worry about terrible clients.
Yeah, you learn more and you get better at your craft.
Perfect.
Thank you.
Akash, thank you so much for your presentation.
So you specifically mentioned 24 hours as the follow-up time.
Have you ever bent that rule?
Oh yeah, sometimes I have,
but I've gotten so much better results within 24 hours.
Because they remember you much, much easier.
And a little trick, the reason I do the 24 hours thing,
I never forget their name once I do that.
If I follow up within 24 hours, I remember who they are.
I literally never forget their name.
I remember their dog's name.
I remember everything.
And when I see them in three years, I'm like,
oh, you're still at Google?
How's your dog Coco?
All this stuff.
They're like, what?
How do you remember this?
It's purely because I followed up within 24 hours.
So there's a lot working there behind the scenes too.
It works really well.
Okay, thank you.
Yeah, you're welcome.
Hey, how's it going?
Hello, hey.
I'm actually a lawyer, so I really appreciated you bringing up that contract aspect.
Yes, sweet.
And I've worked with a lot of people who are just starting out, they've never read a contract
before, so I was hoping that for the benefit of the audience, you could say a few words
about any kind of cautionary tale, like you didn't think you needed to do something, and
then you had some kind of kerfuffle, and now you've learned from a mistake.
Yeah, perfect. So thankfully I've been using contracts from the
beginning, but I can share a general story. I won't name
names or anything like that. But I've seen a lot
of friends who didn't have a contract. They say like,
oh, it's just a handshake deal. It'll be fine,
it'll be fine, it'll be fine. The game tanks. It
doesn't come out. Who owns the music? Who owns the
sound? How do you know?
If they had a contract, it would go right back to them.
It'd be no problem.
But unfortunately, it was completely unclear, and
someone I know actually had to go through some legal issues.
And it turns out, no, the client owned it.
There's no contract.
So use one.
It's very useful.
All right, so our time is out, unfortunately, for today.
But I will be hanging out.
So thank you so much for coming.
Give me your cards and all that sort of good stuff as well.
Thank you.