the lessons from our mistakes, what experience has taught us about leveling up our careers.
So let's get started.
So hi, I'm Dr. Jen Shi-Lei, a people strategy consultant who is deeply devoted to human sustainability and DEI initiatives.
My passion is about managing community-based access programs that elevate marginalized voices and support divergent thinkers.
I believe people grow best in the sunshine, and I hope these talks will provide some of that sunshine for you.
I'm going to yield most of my time to the panelists, but I do have a few things to say.
Okay, so why are we here?
To lean into those mistakes.
My hope is to further break down those silos and the unhealthy aversion to speaking about mistakes.
So I'm hoping that these mistakes that are shared will be fertile ground for all of us to grow the games industry and to be better.
I appreciate the panels being up here and accepting my invitations.
So they are here to speak about thriving in a tough, ever-evolving, and often scary industry.
And at the core, each person on this panel cares deeply about people.
So I've invited them because I've witnessed each one of them working towards making the games industry better.
And undoubtedly, I hope this information will be valuable for you.
And to the audience, thank you for coming.
By a show of hands, how many students do we have here?
Just to gauge the room here.
OK, great.
Thank you.
Decent amount.
By show of hands, how many non-student job seekers out there?
Okay, so a nice mix.
Career changers.
People striving to be at least 1% better every day.
Oh, come on, everybody.
Okay, so my hope is that I've assembled a team of experienced devs that will allow you to leave this session with at least one actionable way to make a positive difference in the games industry and in your attempts to level up your career.
For us in this room, we're privileged enough to be here.
But please, as you leave, share what you've learned with your devs back home.
I want to acknowledge that there are people who cannot be here in person because of war, border restrictions, finances, caretaker obligations, and or layoffs.
But I hope that this advice reaches them too.
March 22nd.
2024.
Okay, so last day of GDC.
This is also, this is my little tidbit here I get to add.
So this is actually the last day I updated my resume.
And not just because I'm here at GDC, but because of the times that I've had to hand off a resume so quickly.
So that's my little tidbit for success.
But I'm gonna yield most of my time to folks here.
So speaking of success,
Nurturing and resilience, they go hand in hand, and it is hard out there.
And you will continue to be hard for the years to come.
But I welcome to the podium my long-term friend, Tony, who will share about how, in the face of adversity, he found strategies to be resilient.
talk about
Job search, resilience, and you, how to deal with the greatest hits of a job search and layoffs.
A lot of this is all from anecdotal experience, and I understand that your mileage may vary, but these are all personal things that I've discovered, and I hope you get something out of it.
So hi, I'm Tony.
I'm a game designer.
I focus on systems and combat design.
And I have worked in the games industry for more than 10 years.
Some of the games I've worked on includes Diablo 3, Castleville, Deformers, and the Echo VR series.
And the thing I want to talk about is four steps of job search, starting with the search.
I think, for me,
we sometimes lose focus and specific goal setting will help create proper expectations when it comes to accomplishing that goal.
For example, I want to be able to successfully run a marathon in four hours and 45 minutes within six months.
Why do I put such a detail on all those things?
Because
It lets me know what I want to accomplish, run a marathon, which is 26 miles, 385 yards, a time frame, how long do I want to do it in, 4 hours, 45 minutes, and the amount of time that I have to prep for it, which is 6 months.
This gives you the ability
to define specific steps you can now take towards accomplishing that goal.
How many days do you have to run?
How many miles do you need to run a day in order to accomplish that goal?
And also, better to be able to track your successes, and are you hitting those goals?
And also, it helps you to evaluate if the goal is realistic or not.
I could say, I want to run a marathon in a week.
Um, probably not likely.
So my takeaway from this is if you set very, very realistic and very, very specific goals, you will be able to figure out what you can do to accomplish that goal.
And the more realist, the more specific that goal is, the more you'll find that you are able to set steps to actually gauge whether you succeed or not on it.
And by the way, I know it's tough out there.
The average job search time right now, from what I was able to sort of do a brief search on the internet, is like five to six months on the average.
So that's not nothing.
So that is a fact.
And now, let's talk about dealing with rejection.
I think following the job search, we find something, we apply to something, we will always, well, some of us will end up with rejections.
This is an excerpt from my own job search Excel, and the reds are the rejections, and the grays are the times that I got ghosted.
And that is just a little excerpt of it.
So as you can see,
It's not just you.
This happens to everyone.
And the biggest thing is, when rejection happens, chances are you won't know why most of the time.
It is important to try to get feedback.
And sometimes, not all companies are willing to give feedback, but you do have the ability to ask.
And any chance that you do get feedback from a company, you should analyze the feedback, break it down, and take what you can out of it and act on that action, make it an action item.
And while there are definitive stats in rejections, according to a survey, I think most people, most successful applicants,
that applies for 10 to 15 jobs usually get 6 to 10 rejections.
So rejection is like above 50%, right?
Don't take it personally, it happens.
Well, while you're on a job hunt, what can you do?
Well, you can improve.
And what you want to strive is to be better daily.
It's easy to get into the downward spiral of a job search.
There are only so many job applications you can apply in a day.
And then you end up sort of doom schooling for more jobs.
Instead of doing that, you should find things to work on and continue to improve yourself during your down times.
This helped me utilize my downtime as a way to improve myself.
And what I did is I created a daily schedule that included time to work on things that will help me improve myself in any way.
This could be a health goal, this could be a future goal, work goal, or this could be a hobby.
You don't know what will actually help you improve.
And I think any bit of improvement will help you maintain sanity and also feel productive, which is very important during this time.
Lastly, let's talk about deservingness.
It's really hard to deal with the success of those around you, especially when you're on the job search, right?
You look around and people have announced that they've got something and whatnot.
And my takeaway is, very much like social media, you often don't get the full picture of what happens.
And this is especially true when it comes to the story of, air quotes, success.
Being disappointed at the accomplishment of others will not help you in any way.
And actually, it mentally damages you and makes it hard.
So focus on the positives and be happy for success in general.
And what you'll find often is that sometimes the people who achieve success before you, and if you maintain the friendships and the connections, will be able to somehow help you farther down the road.
So let's do a quick recap.
Focus goals.
Rejection happens.
Be better daily.
Remain positive.
I tried to come up with a cool acronym, but I ended up with a real weird word, so that didn't work for me.
But you get the idea.
And finally, we are all aware it is dangerous out there and it's not great, right?
We don't know what someone else is going through because we're not in their head, but we can be kind and support each other.
Final thoughts, for anyone who needs to hear this, you are good enough.
Thank you.
We absolutely did need to hear that, Tony, so thank you.
And now I welcome to the podium a dear friend whom I've had the pleasure of working with in Europe and visiting in two countries in Asia.
And I invite Ndinda to share her stories that she's benefited from studying and working abroad.
Thank you.
So I'm Adinda... Sorry.
Oh, it's the room.
It's the room, people.
I'm Adinda van Ooster from the Netherlands.
I'm a game journalist, a teacher and international relations specialist at Deltuin College.
I had the fortunate experience to owe in exchange between my studies, yeah don't be jealous at this list by the way, to have a full-time internship at UserJoy, a game company in Taiwan, to do a game design research master in Germany, and to work one year as a course creator at Lingling University in Hong Kong.
So Jen earlier asked who is all the students in the room, and well, speaking to the moment that I was 17, I went to Hong Kong for the first time, and many international trips followed.
My decision to go overseas was like at this moment I realized from time to time new employers really liked it that I went overseas because they see the experiences that I got with it, they really liked it.
So basically because I went abroad I get later on a lot of advantages.
And I'm not the only one.
There was a recent mass qualitative study from Erasmus Plus that showed that going abroad has a long-term influence on your life.
97% of all participants confirmed a positive influence on your life and 90% on the career path.
So for my internship, I wanted to go to Taiwan, but I had no clue to start.
It was not easy.
I went on the website and checking all the emails I could find for the companies.
And of course, no response.
and the deadline of getting an internship was getting closer and closer and I really didn't want to do an internship in the Netherlands because that's boring so I started to pick up the phone and just call them and one of the ladies that picked up the phone explained to me that it was not because well they most likely hadn't seen my email but it was so much paperwork
to let me come to the company, and also was cultural difference, and so on.
So at the moment of all those emails' rejection, I realized, because I didn't give up, I was kind of like forcing them to just hire me, basically, as an intern.
It wasn't about like they were rejecting me, but they were rejecting someone else coming because of paperwork, and I was a foreigner, which is weird.
So.
Not everyone in this room is a student.
And I believe that personal growth always goes with going abroad.
I mean, you can do it other ways, but I really believe that.
For me, it changed a lot of my own self-esteem.
I pushed my boundaries, and I learned to communicate with people from all over the world.
And I grew an amazing network, which is still really instrumental in my career today.
And I have many cool stories to tell, I tell you.
But not now, but over a beer, you can ask me any weird stories.
It's really cool.
Really, it's best benefits ever.
So at this moment, we are in a time that going remote is getting more popular and more common.
So a research by Hipmarker shows that at this moment, the remote job is very good.
And even still now, because we're having a dire time, it has 360 remote jobs open on their website when I last checked, which was last week.
There are different ways to start to work overseas.
Please talk to me after this talk.
I can unravel what you want to know.
Because this is going to be another talk.
We don't have time.
So, as I mentioned, I studied and worked in several countries overseas.
And I learned that research, doing research, is really important.
because every single country has their really little nitty-gritty details.
Visas, injections, whatsoever.
I really like this website that you see on the side.
Any visas, check before you go which country you go because it just prevents so much stress to know things beforehand.
So Jen mentioned already the resumes earlier.
I want to say that apart from visas, resumes also have a lot of different things.
There are different countries with different personal information descriptions.
Some countries like your photograph, some don't.
Your length can be different, the structure.
And maybe, I mean, I'm in America, but I hear that maybe you don't know what an A4 is.
Well, please, if you don't, search it, because it's really good to show that you understand the culture.
You show employers that you take that extra step, and that is super important.
And of course, our world is getting globalized, and people understand there are differences, but it is really that extra little amount that
makes your employer realize that you are taking them serious.
So making a decision to work overseas is a big one.
I mean, I can keep talking about this for an hour.
Please, I shouldn't.
So before that, you should make a SWOT analysis.
So write down your strengths, weaknesses, opportunities, and threats.
So for me, for example, I had education.
I wanted to teach in Taiwan and Hong Kong, but I said I need a master.
So these kind of things can differ from countries.
Your portfolio is still really important in our community.
Don't forget it, apart from the resume.
And I already learned the language, so I already could speak some Chinese.
So for yourself, write down what are your internal strengths and weaknesses, and get it noted.
Because you should also note what are your external strengths and weaknesses.
the things that you don't have control on.
So this is going to be a package of text, but it will foster out where you want to go.
So I want to stress that working abroad, especially when moving to a new place, is not an easy decision.
A lot of things need to be considered.
But I invite you to think about all the new possibilities that comes along with it.
Thank you.
I appreciate your international perspective, Adinda.
Now I'm excited for Angela's talk.
I've seen Angela work closely with so many mentees in early phases of job preparation, helping them to decode job applications for goodness of fit, and Angela renews my optimism and
She pushes boundaries of my thinking and of the mentees that she's working with in such creative approaches.
So I look forward to your talk, Angela.
Hello.
Welcome to Life Lessons from the Hunt, the job hunt.
So who am I?
Hi, I'm Angela Geis, pronouns she, they, and I'm currently an associate sound designer at NetherRealm Studios in Chicago.
I did not go to school for games.
I am self-taught.
And two years ago, I was in the middle of my own job search, learning and putting all of these tips and tricks to use.
These are my stories about the things that worked for me.
So please take or leave them as you see fit.
So throughout my time applying for jobs, these are the four big lessons that I learned.
I'm going to share two with you, and then Tony and Trento are going to do a deeper dive onto the last two.
First one will be do your due diligence research.
Network maintenance.
Welcome back to these.
and then expect nothing, prepare for everything.
Do the work to make sure you are ready for the just in cases like an interview.
But if you send off every application with an expectation of success or even a response, it will only drain your energy and enthusiasm.
And you already heard Tony talk about this.
And my favorite piece of advice, be your ambitious, passionate, and genuine self.
Because this is the only person you can be.
And actors know, and I learned in my theater career, that you shine the brightest when you are your most genuine self.
And that's what draws people in, which Trento will be talking a little bit about later.
So due diligence research.
Common advice is to know the company that you're applying for.
I found that the most critical aspect for me was to know as much as you can about who you're talking to.
So search the company, see if you can tell the size, what they're known for, the games they make, the team composition, and who you might be working with or talking to.
If you can't find something, that would be something good to ask in the interview.
Don't be like me, who is woefully uneducated in mainstream anything except, like, JRPGs and audio, and panics whenever someone from Larian Studios walks up and introduces themselves and I can't pinpoint exactly what game I'm supposed to know them from and that I can connect and chat about them with.
The multi-award winning game of the year, Baldur's Gate 3.
I do know Baldur's Gate 3.
So next, network maintenance.
Networking is making friends.
Keep it simple.
Keep it chill.
Keep it calm.
If you think about networking like this, it helps lower the pressure you put on yourself, and it helps you to be more confident and easy to approach and talk to.
After meeting someone, use Discord, Twitter, LinkedIn, whatever you like, to reach out and reconnect occasionally.
I saw this thing, and it reminded me of this conversation we had at GDC.
I played your game, and I loved the music.
This is important for keeping friendships.
Having professional friends locally can be a game changer.
If people are easier to get to, they're easier to keep in touch with.
and if you can't think of anything else to say, send a meme.
Appropriate work safe memes, please.
For example, when the winter storm hits in Chicago, you can send this to the Mortal Kombat team.
Last, the last most important thing about network maintenance
So I asked a few lovely folk for their experience in the job hunt around the world.
I pulled these quotes from their answers about finding jobs in the UK, Sweden, South Africa, Indonesia, and Canada.
And though they all have wildly different experiences, their answers to me showcase a through line that even in the international context, the most important thing for any job hunt is to talk to people and build relationships.
So if you'll indulge me, look to your left.
Look to your right.
These people next to you, they could become your new best friends.
Your future boss.
Your coworkers.
Someone who will help you navigate your next obstacle with.
Or someone you'll just smile in the hallway after this.
Maybe introduce yourself after the talk.
OK, my final and greatest piece of advice is to do your best to relax so that you can be your genuine self and to put your best foot forward.
There is only so much that's under your control.
At some point, you've prepared for everything.
All you can do now, now it's out of your hands.
The only thing left to do is make sure there aren't any red flags.
So I ran across this quote recently in Rob Bridget's book about audio.
I'm an audio person.
I make everything audio.
I really love the quote, though, so I'm making it apply here.
The thing about bullets is you can dodge the easy ones, but not the others, and you cannot dodge them all.
Dodge the easy bullets, the telltale signs, and leave the others in the hands of fate.
There's nothing you can do about those anyways.
You did your work.
You put in the effort.
You have prepared what you can.
You've dodged the nastiest bullets.
Now sit back down, have some tea, and let the winds take you where they will.
Thank you.
I'm supposed to keep track of time, but I get so lost in these stories.
Thank you for sharing that.
That was incredible.
And I want to emphasize that last part about the relax.
It's really important.
We stress out so much about trying to get that next job.
So in a moment, we're going to hear from Fauzi.
And I didn't invite him here because of his title, but because he cares about people.
When I've asked people to join this panel, I was looking for people who've been inspired, who support international communities.
So I manage a team in Europe, and I've seen through action, Fawzi supporting us, helping to elevate people finding their best job fit.
So welcome to the podium, Fawzi.
Thank you so much for the humbling introduction.
Hello, everybody.
Marhaba.
My name is Fauzi.
21 years in the business in game design and creative direction roles.
I'm currently the VP of global creative at Ubisoft.
So I oversee and help creative teams across Europe bring their creative visions to life.
I'm XCA, XKing, and other companies shipped a bunch of games from Mario Rabbids to Star Wars to Battlefields.
And I'm on the Board of Education for Future Games, which is one of the leading schools in Sweden.
And I wrote Al-Khallab, An Art of Game Design, one of the first books, if not the first one, to be written about game design in Arabic.
And I just got the Ambassador Award a couple of days ago.
Thank you, thank you.
So I've been asked to do two very difficult tasks.
One of them is to recount all of my mistakes in five minutes, which is impossible.
I could have been here for a long time.
And also to speak only for five minutes, which is also impossible.
I tend to like to do that quite a bit.
So I'm going to try my best here.
And Dr. Jen, you can always kick me when I'm over time.
And I've also listened to Angela's advice.
There's a lot of memes in this presentation.
So I want to walk you through some very anecdotal stuff that happened to me early on in my career, some mistakes that I believe that I made, or tough stuff that I've been through, so hopefully you don't have to.
I started my career in Jordan, and here we go, this is one of the first tough ones.
If you can help it, try to be born somewhere with an industry.
It makes sense.
It makes things a lot more easier for you.
But if you can't control where you're born, consider relocating entirely to be close to the industry where there are schools, where there are companies, where there are places where you can join, and people that have done the stuff that you can learn from.
Or otherwise, do what I did.
You keep learning, doing the things, make mistakes, and pick up from them.
My first project, for example, me and my friends, this is me when I had hair.
We started our own studio, there were nine of us, and we started working on the vertical slides for a Game Boy Advance RPG of the time, one of the first of its kind in the region.
And there's a lot of mistakes in the sentence that I just mentioned.
Because if you can join an already existing team or company so that you can learn from their experience, even if it's not the type of game you want to work on or the type of project you were dreaming to join the industry to do, you get to learn what it's like to be in a game team, you get to learn what it's like to work on a game, and you get to learn from those people's mistakes, and that will make things a lot easier.
a lot easier for you when you actually get to work on the stuff that you like.
You get to see what it's really like to be on the ground in a studio, regardless of its size.
But if you do want to start your own studio, we started as nine people.
I would probably say you don't want it to be a large team.
Something like anything over five people, as you can imagine, will cause a lot of complexity, especially when it comes to coordination, communication, unifying the vision, and not to mention cost.
It's really hard to get five people to agree what to have for lunch.
Imagine if you have to get more people involved.
And also, like, don't start with an RPG, you know, or a relatively large project.
What you want from your first project is that you want to finish it.
You start with something that is the smallest possible so you can learn, finish, and then move on to the next one.
Grow your skills one project at a time.
And also, try not to let your first project be your magnum opus.
If you just started running, it would be ridiculous if I asked you to win the golden medal in the Olympics.
Making games, just like any other skill, is something that you grow.
So you show up every day, and you do the work, and you grow your skills.
One day, you will have the skills and the personal insight to make that magnum opus.
And so when my first project inevitably failed We were never able to finish it and release that I took that very hard on myself and almost left the business altogether And here's one of the bigger mistakes is I was not kind to myself, you know And you really need to be kind to yourself because putting a lot of stress on trying and tying your failure to your ability to continue in your career is a sure pathway to burnout and
So, you know, fail fast, move on, be kind to yourselves.
Mistakes are part of the learning process.
And even though I'm here standing telling you about the mistakes I made, they are part of who I am and why I'm standing here in front of you today.
I have not failed.
I have tried 10,000 ways that did not work.
And when I was in an indie team, I was wearing many hats.
I could write music.
I could code.
I could do 2D art.
I could do UI, level design, and all kinds of stuff.
So therefore, I thought I qualified for all of this.
So I started applying to all of these jobs, from particle effects to level design to game design.
And at some point, I was getting more rejection letters than there were days in the month.
And that's a mistake.
So what you want to do is that you
I see a lot of people make the same mistake.
And while it's great to explore so that you can finally pick the area that works for you, and where you find your heart in, ultimately, you need to focus your efforts.
There are only so many hours in the day, and you're growing your skills, as we spoke about earlier.
Having a defined focus allows you to focus on the time and the results.
So be result-oriented.
Visualize the end goal, and then pour all of your effort towards it.
What is the skill set that you want to grow?
And how can I focus on learning that skill set that I'm missing?
What are the knowledge gaps, behavioral changes, and experience gaps that I need to add to my skill set to be able to be on my path to my end goal?
I'm going to ask you a couple of questions for you to ponder on.
Who in the industry inspires you?
What do they have that you don't?
And how do you get it?
Simple example.
Say that you want to work on Company X. Company X probably has employees.
Those employees have employee internet presence, portfolio, LinkedIn profiles, etc.
Have a look.
See what are the things that made them employable for that employer that you really want to work with.
How can you get your portfolio similar to this?
What are the skills, the behaviors, the experience that you need to grow to match?
And the only thing I didn't do wrong is that I wanted to persevere, no matter what.
No matter the setbacks, I knew what I wanted to go.
There was a person that inspires me.
I knew the skill set that I wanted to grow, and I persevered.
You show up every day, and you do the work, but you be kind to yourself.
So to summarize my advice to you, you show up every day.
You do the work.
You pick projects that you can finish.
You don't overestimate your skills and underestimate your projects.
you go to where the jobs are, you become undeniable by making yourself desirable for the roles you want, and you be kind to yourself.
Thank you very much.
Fauzi, I think your message of being kind to ourselves segues perfectly to an inspiring and important talk
from Trento about authenticity.
Thank you, Trento.
I didn't trip on the way up here, so that's a great start.
Hello, everyone.
My name is Trento von Lindenburg.
I'm the CEO of Mole Breaker Interactive, a new company founded in November 2023.
And sorry, Fawzi, we didn't take your advice.
We are a 10-person studio.
So we'll see how that one turns out in a year.
But a year ago, I was in the same position that at least a third of you were, where I was looking for a new job.
And four years ago, I had just graduated.
So today I'd like to talk to you a bit about the mistakes that led me to where I am today in my first few jobs, and why the importance of being authentic matters, especially in landing the job that's right for you.
Now, as a quick note, there is no magic solution.
Nothing that I say today will get you hired tomorrow.
And trust me, I wish I could.
Nothing.
But I hope that you can learn from my mistakes and that in listening to what we're about to share, that the job that you do get will be the right one for you.
So let's talk about my mistake.
One of them, at least.
And specifically, my mistaken approach to interviews.
We've all heard the recommendations of, you have to make sure you review exactly everything that's on the application page.
Look at what they're saying, what they want on their resumes.
Edit your resume to the skills.
Do everything to be the perfect person that they want because there's thousands of people competing for that job.
We've all heard that, right?
And while that is true, you do want to develop your skills towards something.
What can often feel like is, I have to edit myself.
I had to be and sell something that I am not entirely comfortable being.
And you start to say things in interviews that maybe you don't really feel and think.
At least for me, one thing that I often hid was, I really, really care about work-life balance.
I want to protect my team above all else.
No, I'm not going to stay here until 8 p.m.
every day or work on Saturdays, because I have hobbies and passions outside of this that I care about.
Instead, when asked, would you be willing to pull an all-nighter?
Would you be willing to work over hours?
Are you willing to do everything and anything you can to make the best product possible?
I'd say yes.
Yep.
Yes.
But that inevitably led to the realization I made the wrong career choice.
That I would land myself in a culture where I didn't fit in.
I sold myself as this person that they wanted, but not who I wanted to be.
And I did this because I was desperate for a job.
I needed something.
Even if it landed me somewhere I really, really didn't want to be.
So eventually, I burnt out.
I left.
I couldn't take that job for more than a year.
And I decided it was time to approach with a new tact.
I started with interviewing the interviewer.
We'll get on that one in a second.
and realizing that I had to be truly authentic and let my inner gremlin, the thing that I was afraid of showing, show.
Let's start with interview the interviewer.
I'll share a similar thing to what Tony shared earlier and say, I applied to over 275 jobs last year.
These are the only ones that I had tracked.
And we're going to ignore the fact that I got rejected or ghosted from all but three of them and focus on the fact that even though I was being authentic and answering and asking all the questions I possibly could, I still got three offers.
I also turned down those three offers.
Because I asked them questions like, what's your production philosophy?
What do you care the most about?
What is something that you can't stand about this job and you would change?
The answers I got were not satisfying.
They had me realize, wow, even if I get this job, I actually really don't want to work here.
And even in this economy, that meant that I saved myself possibly getting laid off within the first three months or getting burnt out all over again and possibly leaving industry entirely.
Being authentic, on the other hand, can mean a number of things.
It can mean telling the truth and being honest with what matters to you.
It can mean sharing your flaws and being able to articulate your growth.
This is what people mean when they say, don't be afraid of being honest about the mistakes that you have made.
As a hiring manager, I want to hear that.
That will tell me more than anything about the thousands upon thousands of successes that we share every single day.
which ties in with knowing yourself and being willing to be vulnerable.
Now I know this is scary because I've been there.
Being vulnerable means being open to critique.
But being vulnerable is a very key part of someone knowing who you are.
At the end of the day, people hire people.
People will hire you for who you are.
At a recent posting we put out for a social media manager, part-time role, new studio,
20 hours a week.
Not as much pay as I would have loved to have given.
We got over 400 applications in the first week.
We only were able to interview six, and the six that we picked were the ones that were the most authentic in themselves.
Not just the people who had great skills.
They all did.
The people who told me about their passion with the Neopets community.
or about a Hindu mythology comic series they want to write in the future.
For a community marketing position, that was what got me convinced those are the people I want to interview.
It helps you stand out, not like one of the hundreds of others, which is why being authentic really matters.
Be authentic not to get hired, but be genuine to get hired in the place that's right for you.
Thank you.
I want to pause with this thank you slide because I think it's really important, and I appreciate you including all the people who have supported you, Trento.
So I know we have some career changers in the room, and it is a great honor to invite our last speaker for hope and honest sharings.
So I think there's no better way to end GDC24 with Lara.
Wow, y'all are just wonderful.
Thanks for being here.
Okay.
Hi, I'm Laura.
I have had four careers before landing in games.
My kittens are named Nocturne and Fiddlesticks.
I had no idea they were league names before I chose them.
I craft.
I play games.
I have ADHD.
I have anxiety.
I sometimes suffer from imposter syndrome.
And I'm a development coordinator on Fortnite BR.
As a dreamer who once wrote a list of 63 careers that I thought might make me happy, I've always hated the question, what do you want to be when you grow up?
How could I possibly limit myself to just one option?
When I said I didn't know, people always responded with some version of, oh, that's OK.
You'll figure it out one day.
What they didn't say is, it's OK to change your mind.
During a coveted acting mentorship in college, I went through a bout of depression.
I knew I was good.
I knew I could do it.
But could I actually?
Was it a mistake to be there?
When I finally got the courage to talk to my mentor about this, their response, unfortunately, completely drained my morale.
They said, if you think you can be somewhere else and do it, you probably should.
There's a whole bunch of people who want to be here and can't imagine doing anything else.
completely destroyed me.
I actually left a career that I loved a lot because I took that word as the only option.
In hindsight, the path wasn't actually the problem.
The problem was the group of people I was with.
Honestly, my career would probably look very different today if I had been with a different company or asked a second opinion.
It took me years to feel comfortable to ask that question again.
And when I did, the answer was incredibly uplifting and it propelled me further in my career at Epic.
If you find yourself suffering from imposter syndrome, it's worth checking in and asking yourself these following questions.
You can answer no to any of these questions and still deserve to be where you are.
It might be good to check if a different version of here could help you thrive.
The voices in your head can and will lie to you.
The voices outside your head will also lie to you, even if they think they're trying to protect you.
I did want to take time to make a special call out.
While everyone deserves their place to be here, and really, everyone does, marginalized groups tend to suffer from imposter syndrome more than groups that are already well represented in this industry.
So, this one's for you.
You deserve to be here.
And for everyone else, how are you making your here the right space to be?
Down the line at a job shadow, I was very excited about.
I was talking to a person about how I loved two separate disciplines at that company, and I inquired if I could switch one day.
I was very passionate about both.
I had studied both in college.
They replied, I have plenty of people who just want this track, and they worked really hard.
If you want to be somewhere else, why would I hire you?
It's not fair to them.
I feel like I worked really hard too, but I took that as a rule of success.
Again, second mistake.
I stopped being curious then.
I pretended like my dreams didn't exist, and I burnt out really, really hard.
Pigeonholing myself caused so much heartache, and I lost years of growth.
I shied away from opportunities, and I know that there are companies out there that lost out on an incredibly passionate and driven employee.
After over a decade of that, something finally had to give.
Echoing some of Trento's points, it is more than okay to ask vulnerable questions, but take care to recognize the answers you've given are just a data point, they are not the entire story.
No one gets to tell you what your path is, only you get to decide what the right one feels like.
I absolutely love my current career, but I don't think the journey getting there needed to be so painful.
My first GDC in 2022, I didn't fully engage with anyone because I was worried I would say something stupid and get blacklisted before I got in.
I went to a wiki event and met the dream person and my dream career at my dream studio.
And the only thing I remember saying is, that's cool.
Thanks.
So take my advice.
It will always be easier to interact with people, not with job titles, not with, uh, not with job titles, not with their job, not with their title.
You may think that they're the rock stars of this industry, but they are also just people.
The memories that will stick are the moments that you have a chance to genuinely connect with each other.
Compliment a patch that someone has on their bag.
Compliment someone's gaming tee.
Talk about a talk that you noticed you both were in.
I've had hundreds of conversations since that GDC three years ago, but the ones I remember are the ones where we actually stopped and took a minute to see each other and connect.
It can be easy to feel like you're losing your identity when you get pushed out of a career or doubt your choices.
You are not one thing.
You are not your job.
You are not your title.
You aren't even this industry.
You are you.
You are made up of hundreds of likes and dislikes and interests and hobbies and opinions, just like every other person in this room.
That's the stuff that will make a lasting impression.
You can lose your job, you can get pushed out of a career, or you can change your mind and you can still be you.
On my intro slide, you'll note that my title was just one of the things on there, and it wasn't even the one that I value the most.
Lastly, I'm going to leave you with my favorite piece of advice.
If you remember nothing else, I hope you remember this.
Care, 10% less.
10% less is still an A. No one will notice that you were caring less except for you.
And the only thing that you'll notice is more energy, less stress, and more sustainable actions that will lead to a better you and a better industry.
So take it from someone who jumped from theater to barista to bookseller into games.
It is OK to follow winding paths.
It's OK to change your mind.
It's OK to try and fail.
It's okay to ask questions and be curious about your options.
It's okay to ignore advice that doesn't work for you.
I promise you will still be hireable.
I promise you'll be hireable if you pivot again.
I actually think that my job, I'm better at it because of my varied experience.
And I've heard that from more than just myself.
I've heard it from so many people.
It's not always easy, and some might scoff at your path, but it is always going to be worth it.
And as long as you're approaching things with a sense of curiosity, passion, and authenticity, you're going to be just fine.
Thank you.
I saw lots of heads nodding.
Yeah.
And I will try that care 10% less.
I love that advice.
And I really appreciate you establishing that we belong.
And now we will open up to some questions.
We won't have time for every question.
here, but we will stay around and we'll be able to answer after we have to get off the mic.
But we do have some microphones over there if you're welcome to...
And we'll alternate places, and we'll take the first question.
Hi.
Thank you so much for being here.
It's really great to see all these insights into the industry that we just really don't get in a professional level.
You kind of just want to be your best self, but sometimes that's just
Not the best approach.
So this one goes to Fossey.
I really enjoyed your talk.
And so you say you want to build a skill.
And you also mentioned that time is limited.
There are just only so many hours in the day.
You have a day job or you're a student and then you arrive home late in the afternoon, you're really tired.
How do you keep cultivating the skill set that you need in a kind of limited time or limited schedule?
So the question is, you have limited time, how can you cultivate these skills?
Did I capture that correctly?
Yes.
Fawzi, you can start and then we'll open it up.
Wonderful.
Thank you for your question.
So I think like the way I approach it, I think I go a little bit almost literal to the topic.
How much time do I have and how much time will it take for me to acquire that skill?
So I try to actually literally get the number of hours.
I do a time audit regularly for myself, which is a weird thing to do, I admit.
and I see how much time I have a week that is available for me for growth.
And I will, you know, whether it's an hour, half an hour, 20 minutes, five minutes, you know, how much time can I allocate a week for growth?
And for the skill set, how much time would it require me to learn it?
And it's amazing how you can like actually find a lot of quantifiable information to this topic.
For example, I was learning Japanese and discovered that you need 550 hours to be adequate at Japanese.
When I looked at I have 2000 hours in Dota 2, I was like,
I could probably do that.
And Angel, I saw you leaning and I was just curious if you wanted to jump in there or... Okay.
No, I'm just listening.
Anyone else want to jump in on that question?
Okay.
Thank you for that question.
Thank you so much.
My pleasure.
Thank you, Fazi.
Hello.
So my question was,
Okay, so two years post-grad, no job prospects yet.
What advice, could you touch on it a little bit, what advice would you overall have to say like, hey, don't give up yet.
Like, how do you keep that momentum going?
So the job search taking a long time, how do we keep going?
We'll do Adinda, then Trento.
So for me, I always wanted to find out what I really want.
And then I'm going to really check what should I do.
Like, for example, the Hong Kong job, I should have been a learning service tutor.
I had no clue what it was.
I just searched on Google.
Oh, OK, I guess this and this has connection with it.
So that was the way how I approach it.
I really search what do I want, what do I need.
And that's the way I look at it.
This is not actionable in the... Oh, this will get you the job.
I did audio in the past, I should know how to do that.
It's not actionable in the, this will get you the job, but it will hopefully help you feel better.
And that's find community, find a friend, find hopefully multiple people who are in the same position as you and find camaraderie.
And the, we're all looking for this together.
They'll also be able to help you develop your own skills.
Maybe you can make a game jam, do projects together, do something small and continue to develop your skills.
Like was mentioned before.
on
list everything that you're doing and your varying levels of success and then start changing the patterns of each thing and how you approach it and see what kind of result you get as you start to change things.
If you continue to do the same things and approach things the same way and get the same results, then you need to change your approach.
And if you change too much, you won't actually know what led to the success.
But if you start changing one thing at a time, you can actually see the difference that it'll make.
And then you can start tweaking the other things that aren't working.
To repeat the comment, what are you, a designer?
And then we have another question over here.
Hi.
I'm a high school student.
I'm a junior in high school right now.
I live in Colorado.
This is my first time at GDC.
Probably won't be here for another few years.
I don't get to do things like this very often, so networking for me is difficult.
First of all, way to take the step to come here.
That's incredible.
So the question is, how do we network online when we cannot be in these spaces?
So I thought I saw someone lean in over here.
I'm going to give you one for just like a year down the line.
You see all these lovely humans in the pink shirts?
They are a part of something called the Conference Associate Program.
And it is how I got my job.
It is a wonderful community that I definitely couldn't have done this without.
So applications normally open up in October.
and you decide or you get picked if you are lucky in December.
And yeah, it is one of the greatest networking opportunities of a lifetime.
Highly recommend.
Angela.
So online spaces, there are resources.
I'm worried about you because you're in high school, so I'm going to focus on other things, like local, especially like, you said Colorado, right?
Yeah, yeah, Colorado.
There's probably schools around you or something.
I find that reaching out to people, especially professors or something, they're really receptive.
If you want to learn, they want to help you learn.
If you can find also if there are other professionals in your area, they want to help you if you want to reach out.
Yes, I do know a few.
There's a few game developers in Denver.
I mean, I do go to a game development program.
I talked to my teacher about it.
But it's just, I know, you know, I don't just want to walk up to Serenity and Forge and be like, hey, are you guys doing internships?
Or like, come, like, can I talk to you?
I feel like that's kind of difficult.
Why not be a little brave and just email them and be like, hey, does anyone have a couple minutes to talk?
I'm super interested.
I just have a couple questions.
Prepare a couple questions.
Do you have 15 minutes?
And just leave it at that.
If it's super low stakes, keep it low stakes for yourself.
Keep it low stakes for them.
Everybody has 15 minutes here and there.
You know what I mean?
And if all it takes is to respond to an email to you, maybe they'll do it.
And Trento, final thoughts on that question?
I think, Angela, you mentioned earlier that networking is about making friends, asking honest, genuine questions.
And if you don't go into it with an agenda of, I want a job, and just, hey, I'm a student.
I'd really like to learn more about this.
Can I ask you some questions?
I think 99% of developers would be more than happy to make the time for that.
Okay, perfect.
Thank you so much.
So thank you everyone for coming.
We will stick around.
I know there's another question for... You probably all have questions, so we will stay around and answer questions.
For the conference associates, do we need to leave the room?
Is that correct?
This is like the last talk in this room for the day.
They will be closing the building soon, because they're ending early today.
So, you know, if you could clear the room.
Basically, yes.
Yes, so that the answer is yes, so we will meet you in the hallway