Good morning, everyone. Good afternoon. If you are joining us from the East Coast or Europe,
my name is Brian Francis. I am a contributing editor at Gamasutra.com and community manager
for GDC. If you are watching us right now, thank you for joining us. You hopefully are familiar
with the game we have right here because it was just announced last Thursday at the Game Awards.
The game is Hades from Supergiant Games.
It is available on the Epic Games Store in early access, which is a first for the company that made it, Supergiant Games.
With me in the lower left-hand corner of the screen is Greg Kasavin from that company.
Greg, how are you doing?
Doing great. How are you?
Good. As you can see, I am this is footage of me playing yesterday afternoon.
Unfortunately, we can't play live.
So if you're watching from home, feel free to mock my terrible gameplay.
Some of these some of these runs you're about to watch were not great.
Some of them were actually pretty good.
But what I'm actually very happy about and we'll get into this
is that all of them are actually very fruitful, even if they didn't go well.
Alex, you're here.
You're plunking away at something.
Who are you? Why are you here?
Hey, I'm Alex Rowe, an editor at GammaCitra.com.
I'm not quite sure why I'm here, other than I'm
excited about this game.
Greg, will you tell me real quick, if you can,
why Early Access?
And how's that going for you?
I guess there's a weekend already,
but how is it going so far?
Yeah, the second part is faster to answer.
We've been really, really happy with how it's been going so far.
Thankfully, the
you know, even given the early access nature of the game, the initial like sort of, and it's a computer game as well, like the initial sort of
technical issues and technical challenges and so on were pretty minimal.
So everybody was for the most part able to get into the game and start playing. The response we've been getting,
we've been really really happy with.
I will never ever take for granted just like having
a group of our players just actually like the stuff that we work on, I will never take that
for granted. So every time we launch a game and our players say, hey this is cool, thank you for
making this, I'm like, I wipe the sweat off my brow and I breathe a sigh of relief and thankfully
That response has been really encouraging.
As for why early access, we conceived of that aspect of this game
like with kind of as part of the whole package right from the start.
It was a high priority when thinking about what we wanted to make next
after our last game, Pyre, came out last year.
We were really interested in a game that we could like...
kind of develop out in the open once it reached a certain point and make it the best game it could be
by gathering feedback along the way, by kind of building it in partnership with the community.
For us it opened up so many possibilities, not just
from like a from a game design perspective but also even from like a narrative perspective
like from my standpoint as as the writer on our games being able to work on a game whose story
could unfold kind of a little bit more serially instead of having to sort of put the entire thing
in beginning middle and end right in that initial launch so.
We think of this early access launch of Hades almost like a pilot episode of a series or something like that,
where it's a lot of the setup, you meet a lot of the characters and you figure out what the conflict is all about,
but the kind of resolution of the story is not all in the game yet.
And we'll roll out new characters and more events in the story over the course of the early access period,
along with just improving every other aspect of the game with any luck.
Right on. I'm going to really I'm going to do some housekeeping before we continue our interrogation.
Sorry, Greg. Folks in chat, we are taking your questions. We've already got folks asking about
what other platforms Hades will be launching on. Greg's addressed that elsewhere. And there's also
an FAQ that talks about the other platforms. We've dropped that in for you in chat.
Which brings us, but if you have questions, we especially want to keep them developer focused so that Greg can talk about how the how Supergiant brought this game to life.
Hopefully said if you're a game developer at home, you can learn yourself.
Greg, which talking about platforms means we want to talk about the Epic Store, I guess.
Would you walk us through, like the decision making behind going to the Epic Store?
And what was different about it compared to your past experiences with Steam and other platforms?
Yeah, so a lot of it does tie back to the early access nature of the game and that being really key to the whole design from our perspective.
So that meant that if we were going to develop this game out in the open for a while and we expect early access to last for more than a year on this game from our initial launch,
we need to be able to move on it really quickly.
So we knew we couldn't...
We knew for sure that we weren't going to launch early access
on a whole bunch of different platforms at the same time.
That would severely, that would basically make it
close to impossible for us to update the game
in a timely fashion.
So our team size is fewer than 20 people.
Maybe there are some teams out there
who can kind of, who are really effective
at patching games on many different platforms
all at the same time,
but that is not a skill set that we possess.
as a small team and we felt it was vital to be able to focus on a single version of the game
until we get the game to a really good state and then you know during that process we could start
to look at other platforms toward an eventual multi-platform launch so that's very much our plan.
So as we were working on Hades, we got in touch with the folks at Epic and started to learn about what they were working on with their store.
And we became really excited for it. It just seemed like a really good fit given the experiment that we were making and the experiment that they were making.
Like one of the factors with Hades is we want this game to be
highly enjoyable to to watch as well as to play.
It's just a game designed around like immediacy and replayability among its
factors. You just kind of get in there and
hopefully start having fun with it and have a unique experience each time
and have the action be kind of very very readable
if a friend is next to you or you're streaming it or something
like that. And part of the thing with, part of Epic's
focus
just in general and I think with the store is to help
enable content creators like streamers and YouTube content creators to sort of like get a
Essentially get a piece of the action you've seen you you've seen the fortnight
Creators, what's it called? I think support a creator program
where
where creators basically can just get compensated for their work and
I think streamers and YouTube content creators
have had such a significant and overall beneficial.
influence on games over the years that it's really only fair that they should
be able to benefit more from the incredibly hard work that they do so on
a personal level that spoke to me I think it spoke to other folks I work
with just as part of the the priority that that Epic was interested in but
anyway that that's all stuff that they probably speak to better than I can
those are just some of the reasons why it made sense to us to go sort of
conduct our early access
experiment off to the side because folks on other platforms who are familiar with
our games are used to our games being like a hundred percent complete. We've
said in the past that we really value the completeness of our games so folks
on other platforms one day will get the kind of experience that they are used to
from us and on the same timeline as we've delivered our games on in the past
where you know typically they take Transistor and Pyre both took us about
three years to make so basically
along that we expect Hades will be done on roughly that same timeline.
So we figured if you're just if that's the experience you're accustomed to and the experience you want to have,
nothing has changed.
You'll you'll get to play our completed game
hopefully wherever.
in as many places as we can support and make sense of
once we're out of early access.
But for now, it made sense to us to run early access
on the Epic Games Store.
I hope that explanation seems reasonable.
No, totally.
And we have a bunch of good questions already in chat.
We'll get to them in a minute here.
Before we get off storefronts entirely.
I gotta ask, and we understand you don't speak for Supergiant as a whole, but just as a veteran developer yourself,
how do you feel about the proliferation of game storefronts in the latter half of this year,
especially with Epic, obviously, and Discord, and a couple others?
Like, how are you feeling about the business that you're in?
Is it exciting times or confusing?
It is exciting times. I mean, I've been, yeah, as you as you may know, I've been around the, I've been around the block a couple of times because I used to, I used to work in the gaming press way back when, you know, since, so I've been, I've been, I reported on games for, you know, like 10 years or more than 10 years starting in the 90s. And now I've been in game development for more than 10 years. So I think if you've been around long enough, you know, this stuff kind of goes in cycles. And it's
And it's aligned often with the console cycles in particular,
like what happens in the computer game industry
is sort of there on the periphery of what's
going on in the console industry.
So new consoles are announced.
There's a ton of excitement.
But as consoles sort of grow old,
then PC platforms tend to take priority for a while,
and they kind of hopscotch each other.
over the years and the cycle keeps turning that way and new platforms rise, older platforms can fall.
That's always been the way of things.
So I think broadly that we're just kind of at that point
in the cycle when new platforms start to get announced.
And it's definitely an exciting time
because you can't help but wanna sort of start,
even if you're doing it only in your head,
you start to bet on whichever horses you think
are gonna win the race.
And you start to wonder who's got the right.
who's got the right angle on what's going on, who's going to sort of thrive and prevail through all
this, and who might fall by the wayside. But generally it's absolutely a good thing.
Like anybody investing in the game industry, creating more competition for the platforms
that are out there, it just makes things better for everybody when we have more
choices as game players. I think that's the bottom line.
Yeah, I think for me it's exciting stuff.
As someone who's followed the industry for a while,
it's like, oh man, what's gonna happen?
I'm excited by the unknown in the game industry
and I think that's always been part of the appeal to it
for me that I, despite, you know,
despite how long I have been following it,
I cannot predict it.
Anyone who thinks that they could predict it,
I don't believe that person.
It takes many surprising twists and turns, I think,
like pretty frequently.
That's one of the truest things I've ever heard on this stream.
I'm going to springboard off of Spizzic's question.
You're launching into early access.
Early access has been a thing on Steam for a while.
PlayStation and Xbox have begun to support it.
The difference between Epic, the Epic Games Store and other platforms is that
it's supporting different forms of interactions between devs and players.
Could you break down, like, what that's meant for you as a team?
This player specifically, Spizzic, has questions about the lack of a forum.
But I do know that you guys have a Discord, because that was sort of the first thing that was part of the trailer.
So what was the difference in changing player communication for you guys?
Yeah, that's right. I mean, I think one of Epic's things is that it...
I think they very much want for the relationship between the developer and their player base to be as direct as possible.
And kind of not filter through them.
And it's also a new platform, right?
So it's not going to have, like...
It just doesn't have as many of the robust features yet as Steam has developed over what's it been, 15 or 20, like a long time?
Very long.
Half-Life 2 came out two times.
I almost said too long, and the before times.
Yeah, so, um...
But yeah, you know, in our case, the response, the onus is on us.
And it's been we have our we've actually been
we launched our official discord server earlier this year.
Somewhat quietly.
We've been building it up a little bit over the months.
Now, you know, now I think players who look back at that decision,
it may make a little bit more sense to them.
But we've we've never like for our part, we've never had
our player community in a central location
because because there are like.
forums and other pockets of community you know in in different places on the
internet or whatnot so launching our official discord is for us
is a place where we you know we finally have our own
kind of homegrown community there and if you play the game you'll see
it's kind of right there linked in the main menu as a means to
get in there and talk to other players or talk to us
share feedback so
I think we thought about having like a forum and stuff as well
But we we liked the vibe that discord provides and we already had enough of like a groundswell
Of players there. I mean there's other stuff like
I've seen folks point out it's like, oh, there are no user reviews on the Epic Games Store.
I'm sure I can imagine something like that might be added at some point.
We're an early access game. I think we're, of course, very open to folks reviewing it,
because we charge the same $20 that
a non-early access game might charge.
So we stand by the quality of our game and so on.
But if you want to find reviews and opinions on the game,
yeah, you'll have to look elsewhere
besides the actual storefront.
But I think, personally, I think it's not difficult
to find opinions about products on the internet.
if you have to turn elsewhere.
But so overall, I don't have a ton of opinions
about like the direct feature comparison
of the Epic Games Store versus other platforms.
We felt it was a good fit for what we were trying to do,
but as with all aspects of the game,
if that's something that players have feedback about,
I'm sure we'll be hearing about it
as will the team at Epic, no doubt.
Mm, yeah, I am.
There's a good question here in chat I want to get to before I forget.
It's from Miss Jim Cloud.
And they want to know, what was the vision you
had when you first came up with the concept for Hades?
What is the sort of driving goal here sort of as a game?
Like, was the goal to, beyond wanting to get early access,
was it just to make a game that had been on someone's mind for ages?
Or was there a specific thing you were trying to pull off with this game?
Yeah.
Yeah, the vision, I started smiling because it doesn't it
doesn't quite work that way around here. But but the in my
role, really, I'm one of the people who helps formulate the
ideas that we then pursue. And one of the things I look for as
as the highest priority is like, what
What is the overlap of preoccupations on the team?
What do the most people here want to make the most passionately?
And that's the game that we should make.
So we started having, very soon after Pyre launched, like within a month,
that game spent three years in development.
We were already eager to...
go on and figure out what our next thing was going to be.
So we started having many, many hours of conversations.
And some themes started to emerge from that.
And one of the ideas I already spoke to
is wanting to develop a concept that we could continue
to build on after it was out there,
a game idea that was extensible and not
just like a kind of a one and done game
similar to our last three games.
So that was a high priority for us.
And we were very intrigued by a design around replayability,
kind of for lack of a better term,
like a more modern design sensibility
than maybe some of our previous games
that are just like kind of have a more linear
campaign structure.
You finish them, hopefully they'll stick with you,
you know, forever on an emotional level,
but they're not necessarily games designed
to be replayed many, many times.
we were really drawn to making a game that felt very immediate, that you could
pick up and play in short stretches or play, you know, kind of for as long as you wanted
and still have a compelling experience around that. And then we started thinking about what theme
would align well with that. We thought about, you know, do we want to revisit one of the worlds
that we've created in the past because we love those worlds and that's, you know, stuff that's like
we while we've never returned to one of our past games, it's not something that we are like morally opposed to or anything like that.
We just, you know, don't want to do it unless the time and circumstances are right.
And and given given our other priorities.
It felt like once again, let's let's make something new. Let's make something that really really fits this set of design goals
and and we looked to
Greek mythology in this case as a source as
In one in one sense a well-worn theme for video games
but in another sense something that we felt was
Both a perfect fit for what we were doing and also in some ways like really under explored in certain
in certain respects, particularly our angle, we think, on the... I was, as the person doing the writing, I was very drawn to a particular
angle on Greek mythology that I feel is very true to the source material,
yet is often sort of lost in the shuffle of how this type of material tends to be adapted, which is.
the gods are a big dysfunctional family that we can see ourselves in.
They're, you know, I think part of the reason these characters have survived for thousands of years is because
they relate so strongly to so many people and they relate not because they're gods,
but because they're human. So we wanted to explore some of that. It felt like a really flavorful,
it felt rich with potential for us. So yeah, we started.
We started making it. So that's a long answer, but yeah, you know, I have a more like we wanted to make a roguelike
Dungeon crawler where you defy the god of death, you know, it felt exciting to us
Uh to to figure out what that game was going to look like. We love playing roguelikes. Um
We've been really inspired by some of the early access successes over the years.
These games like Darkest Dungeon and Slay the Spire and Dead Cells.
Games that started off really strong, like from the moment you dropped your,
you know, $20 on them, that was like money super well spent.
And then they only got better and better from there.
So we're like, oh, man, what if we could what if we could pull off something like that?
That's kind of what in our minds, I felt like the right way to do it.
And we felt that.
if we knew it's going to be early access from the start,
rather than doing it as kind of like,
oh, God, we ran out of time,
let's put it in early access.
If we plan for it to be early access,
maybe that improves our chances
of handling that kind of process properly.
Yeah, look man, this is video games. No one's going to get mad at you for making a roguelite dungeon crawler.
Um, I want to make games that feel that feel fresh also like I really value
games that feel like they have kind of a reason for for being like that just don't feel like
um, they're you know, just
kind of the same as other games that are out there, but I I think what we've made has
Has plenty of our you know, dirty signature all over it and has it has our has our particular
Marks on it to make it feel distinct. It has Jen. This is Gen Z's really good art all over it. Yeah
She I
think she is one of the I
Don't know. Hopefully she's not watching this, but I think Gen Z is one of the greatest artists
working in the industry. It's a huge honor to be working with her. She kind of reinvents her style on every single game we've
worked on. She's of course just one member of our art team though she does create the the the overall sense of style and the
look and does all our wonderful character designs and everything. So I think.
Her work, the work of Darren Korb, our audio director who does all our music and contributes
key voices to this game and all the sound effects.
He is a man of many talents and his work has, of course, really helped our games always
stand out over the years and I think this game is no exception.
So it's always exciting to see.
what my colleagues will do on each new game.
And that's, I think for us, it's been part of the fun
of kind of choosing a different theme
and setting every single time.
I'm gonna springboard off of Vogir's question in chat.
Vogir sort of was asking about is this a roguelike, and I think you just sort of answered it by comparing it to those other games.
Vogir's asking about the depth of and comparing it, asking if it's comparable to Binding of Isaac and for the Gungeon.
I would like to ask you, how does Supergiant Games define depth?
And in kind of a like
How did you sort of build yourself a template for the layer?
Like we're sort of looking at some of the systems right now that you guys used with the mirror.
How did you look at your design experience and say, this is how we can make depth that
will update that we can both like layer with what we ship first and then update over time
in kind of the way that Vogir is talking about?
Yeah, so depth in games, I think works on many vectors.
So we aspire to having gameplay depth and we aspire to having narrative depth as well.
And hopefully the two together create an overall very rich feeling experience.
But I think you're referring more to gameplay depth, so let me speak to that.
I think we look for...
We really, really value in each of our designs for our past games...
the sense that you can kind of discover different successful play styles as you go.
So we really favor designs that let you experiment, that give you sort of the latitude to
experiment, that encourage you to try different things and kind of experiment with different tools
within the context of the gameplay. And then, you know, just when you find what feels like a
perfect combination, like a kind of a very effective...
set of skills and tools and abilities and so on, maybe you get nudged into a new set of tools and abilities that
is even better or maybe just different in an intriguing way.
So I think if you look to each of our previous games, they've all done some version of that.
But in the case of Hades, I think it like really synthesizes a lot of what we've
a lot of, I think, our best ideas from our previous games.
In Bastion, there was this goal around immediacy,
like it's a game with very little preamble, you just pick it up and start playing.
And we wanted you to get right in there with Hades and just immediately get, just...
figure the gameplay out like a very low accessibility barrier,
but at the same time it merges together an aspect of Transistor that was very
exciting, which was this idea of combining different
abilities, making for thousands of different possible combinations, and
that's very much at play in Hades here, where you have
the Olympian gods essentially provide you with
different blessings, kind of like power-ups.
that you can't necessarily control which of these gods you encounter, but you can choose between the
blessings they provide. So each time you play, you're sort of like building out your character
in a unique way. So sometimes you'll be able to play and kind of go down a specific path that you
really want, like, oh, you're using the bow and you know that Poseidon happens to cause enemies
to get knocked back away from you, and that forms a very powerful...
combination that you could use, but other times you know you're not going to be
presented with exactly the options that maybe you were hoping for and you'll
have to make do, and that also I think feels true to work we did in
Transistor and Pyre, where it's about kind of like making the most of a
situation that you can't entirely control in some cases. So we find that
that makes for that kind of...
that kind of structure can make for gameplay that continues to be surprising and interesting
over time and just defining enough overlapping systems that can interact with each other to
where you know suddenly richness emerges from the play experience and in our own play testing we
find that we're not having the same experience over and over we're compelled to start new runs
that's all stuff we really really look for
Nice. I cannot think about the fact, a question or two ago,
you didn't say it out loud, but you were talking about moving to early access,
and you almost sounded relieved, this idea of not having to wait three games,
three years to put out a game, sort of get it out quickly, get it, start iterating on it.
By that math, three games is nine years, Alex.
Yeah, exactly. So, I wonder, how has your process changed internally,
both for you specifically and I think you deserve on the team, working on a game like this where
you've sort of got to be ready to go pretty early,
as opposed to having the luxury of three years
to crunch on a masterwork or something.
So tell me, how has your process changed practically
as a writer and developer?
Yeah, it's a really good question.
Our process has changed a lot in anticipation of this.
And again, it all ties back to, I
guess I didn't say this specifically,
but a really key aspect of this whole game for us
has been that we've.
We've just planned it more in general.
And part of it is anticipating an early access launch
and sort of, I almost equate it,
I hope this doesn't sound too obnoxious as an analogy,
but it's like, it almost felt like training for a marathon
or something like that,
where we've basically moved internally
to a monthly milestone cadence.
So every month.
we have a milestone where we have certain goals and the month is divided up into certain phases.
So we have, at the beginning of a milestone is when we could make more major changes to the code
and so on, and then we lock the code down, we could still make data changes, so fine-tune things.
You know, from my standpoint, I could still be adding new narrative events or changing
the voiceover and stuff like that, because that's all part of a data-driven system, and it's not like
fundamentally, you know, altering the code by me adding or subtracting events. And then
toward the end of the milestone, we're then, you know, testing, bug fixing,
polishing, making final changes to get everything ready.
And then at the end of that, we play test
and then we kind of do it over.
So we've been doing it, we've been working this way
for a number of months now, knowing that basically
once this game is out there,
we're just gonna keep doing that.
And those major updates become major updates
that we're like committed, you know,
we're committing ourselves to.
If you quit out to the main menu,
you'll see right there, like on the main menu that it says.
when our next major update is coming, that basically is aligned with our internal milestones and when
we think we'll have a whole batch of, from our perspective, cool new stuff ready to go.
So that really has been the biggest shift in our internal development, whereas with a three-year
project...
our milestones at this point in the process would be much longer, would probably span,
you know, two and a half or three months and be somewhat more nebulous in nature, I would say.
So it's a more, I think in a word, it's a more disciplined approach that we're taking,
but we've always valued planning and production discipline at Supergiant.
I think it's been key to our success that we've been able to just
You've heard from many developers, I'm sure, that finishing a project is really hard.
It's really hard to decide it's time to wrap it up and to make those really tough choices about finishing your game.
So it kind of...
We've learned a lot about that over nearly 10 years that we've been working together as a team.
And so this project sort of puts that forward. And of course, it's a little scary to commit to
major updates on a regular basis, but we've been practicing at it. We think we could do it,
obviously. Nice. Cool.
Alex, can I slide in with some folks from chat?
No, absolutely not. No, I was going to just keep talking. I was going to just
please. No, please. By all means, go ahead.
Roger. We can we can sort of step back to your good old creative director stuff.
Greg, the Lord Gersh would like to talk about the themes of death and rebirth that have showed up in all of your games.
Hades is literally about death and rebirth, as you have seen on this stream, where I die repeatedly and then get reborn and die again.
What other outside influences, like you talked about why you landed on Greek mythology earlier,
but what have you looked at in the real world to make you think about telling stories around death and rebirth like that?
That's what Lord Gersh would like to know.
Yeah, I mean, that's an interesting question.
I mean, I think it's really tough to, it's tough for me to pin down because it's my entire,
It's like it's got to be my entire outlook on I seek to work on stories that that that feel
that feel meaningful to me and I think that's the only chance I have of those
stories connecting with other people out there.
So there has to be something there that that I feel
is true and that I can spend a whole lot of time just trying to
dig for to uncover. Like if it's something with just a
simple answer, like a simple moral, to me that's not sufficient
for a story because there's just not a lot there.
But in this game's case, you know...
I don't know that death, I wouldn't, death and rebirth for sure, I can see how that would be construed as like a recurring theme through our games.
Mm-hmm.
But Hades, to me, is a game about family.
and I look to my own family experience
and the family experiences of other people I know
and other people I've heard about.
And of course, the family experiences described
in the world of Greek myth as one of the kind of most
fundamental sources of inspiration for the kind of stories
that this game will have.
Of course, that sounds maybe,
I don't know how openly I would admit that outside of like a GDC live stream, because
of course we want it to be, it's like an exciting hack and slash experience on the face of it.
But our games, I think if you know, if you're familiar with our games, you know that our
stories are always about something more than what's there on the surface.
I think it's pretty clear.
pretty early on when you, you know, meet Cerberus or whatever, uh, as like an old family dog
that you know that this is kind of like a, um, there's, there's a bit of a family drama
or a family comedy, I should say, uh, underneath the surface of this game. Um, but I mean,
I, I can't, I can't tell you.
I can never answer like what are my inspirations. It's just too many things. I play a lot of video
games. I try to read. I try to watch movies. I listen to a lot of music. Like I don't know.
I'm the sum total of all the experiences I've ever had and that informs my work.
Right on.
Well, I would love to know sort of how your work has changed
in the last couple of years as your team.
Well, actually, I don't even know.
So there's a question here in chat
that has to do with team size and bringing new folks in.
Can you talk a little bit about how
Supergiant has changed since you've been there,
and specifically since Pyre launched last time we talked?
Yeah, so I think one of the things we're really proud of at Supergiant is all seven of the folks
who created Bastion together, we're all still here working. We've worked on each respective
game in our same relative roles, so that's, I mentioned Jen and Darren and it's myself,
Amir who's our studio director and essentially like our design lead, and Gavin and Andrew.
Who are our engineers and then Logan Cunningham who's provided a major voice or more more than one in each of our games?
So each of us has continued to work together and since pyre we've been so I should say after bastion
We were we grew from 7 to 12 people and we were joined our art department expanded
with Camilo Vanegas and Josh Barnett.
And basically we have more of a support team
and a business development team
and folks like Michael Aleshai
who just handles so much of our day-to-day operations
at this point.
So we became more of like a complete team after Bastion, but we stayed at that number 12 for many, many years.
And that only changed after Pyre last year.
We realized, given our plans for Hades, that we needed...
It was time...
for us to grow a little bit and to shore up what we felt were like essentially some of our weaknesses at that point.
And so we have more design muscle now, we have more art muscle, and we've grown from that number 12 to closer to 20 at this point.
That's the size that we're going to stick to.
Because we think that being small is like really fundamental to how we operate or like I mean who knows who knows that the future holds but we all know for certain that if we
we like we couldn't even this this this space that you see we fit everyone into this room like this is our space if we
We just don't even have room for more people. So we want to rather constrain
Our ideas to what we can achieve with this team here than just like have the mindset of growing bigger and bigger
Um, because we think that a lot of our best ideas are really only possible
because of our small team size.
It's just how we work and how we sort of negotiate
through creative ideas as well.
So that's been a big and really exciting change
over the last year to like have new blood on the team
and see how much of an incredible impact
these folks have had across the board.
And you'll see them, their names are all in.
in the credits in Hades and and they're all on our team page and everything you
can find out more about everyone who works at the studio that
way. Nice so that's a good opener for Alitishan's question which is I don't
know if they're a developer or a fan but they want to know what's it like taking
all these new people into the team versus starting with a very small team
and passion. So how is the vibe in the
studio workflow changed?
now that you've bumped up to 20.
Has it been a noticeable thing or does it just feel...
Yeah, it's noticeable for sure.
I mean, one of the things,
one of the reasons we approached the process
of expanding the team like really
with a great deal of caution and hopefully care
is that we know that even if you bring in
the most talented person in the world, like the absolute best artist or the absolute game designer,
the best game designer in the whole world joins your team. It still can have a profound, it can
and will have a profound effect on the culture of the team. And that has to be approached
carefully, like you have to look for, or I don't mean to be prescriptive. In our case,
it was really important.
to bring people on board who enhanced our culture, who contributed something more than just their work.
Because they, like, it just, each new person who joins changes all of the social dynamics here.
So we're aware of that. And so we just...
try to do our best to make the right choices, right?
And thankfully, those choices have worked out really, really well.
And the reality is that we have new blood on the team and folks who are, you know,
more bright-eyed and bushy-tailed than people like me who've been, you know, whatever,
been doing this stuff for a long time.
I'mit invigorates the rest of us, right?
Like, when done properly.
So that'sthankfully, that's how it's worked out.
And we've always, like
in the past prior to some of these folks joining, we've actually been pretty, the word monastic has
been used to describe us. We're just kind of plunk our headphones on and work away and then leave at
the end of the day. Like I think, I think folks out there may imagine us to be this like, this
group of people we all, you know, hang out and have beers after work. It's like we're not, we're
not really like that usually. We're pretty focused on
on our work and a lot of us have lives outside of work and we really value that separation.
So at the end of the day, people go home and go to the rest of their lives.
So it's been really helpful to have new folks on the team who have like livened things up
and you know, more people going out to lunch and larger groups and that sort of thing that's
just made.
made things more lively than they have been in the past.
And I think the proof is in the pudding as far as the actual work,
because we've been working, you know, Pyre launched in late July,
and now we have this game in December.
And I think that some folks have expressed...
Surprise or like have you been working on this like all this time? No, we didn't we didn't get started on Hades until after we were
Well finished with pyre. So we just it's only been possible because
We're bigger now than we were
nice
Yeah, that is a good follow up here from Twindim wants to know, sort of what are the core values of your workplace culture? That's like a kind of a
man, shout out to chat for being really interested in like, just like life, quality of life and game dev. Thank you, guys.
Good questions. Thank you. You know, those are those are questions that we are very interested in as well. And in fact, so so here, I hope I can rattle these off off the top of my head. So we, an interesting thing about us
May be interesting for you to decide we did not have
stated values
as a studio until
Last year and we've been around since 2009
So we didn't do that because we were like dismissive of it. It's just because
I think it took us all that time to truly understand what our values were,
and to have some really frank conversations about it, and seeking alignment around it.
So, one of our values, for instance, is we iterate on everything.
That's a core part of how we make games.
An iterative development process is just...
how we do it and and it's important for everyone here to embrace that and and to like understand
that that re-evaluation and criticism and feedback is is is part of the process and and that mindset
is part of what enables us to I think go into an early access launch I think with a hopefully
with a healthy mindset we also say that that work our work is not
our lives are not in competition with our work, that our work contours to our lives.
So that's our view on how to manage a work-life balance.
So here we have, as a small team, we
we have flexible, like we would rather work around the challenges of people
having flexible hours and working remotely, you know, coordinating remote
meetings and stuff like that than requiring everyone to strictly be here
always at the same place at the same time. We would rather enable everyone
individually to to to position themselves to do their best work.
and to find the balance that works the best for them while knowing that their colleagues are there
to support them through that decision making and that we expect for people to be honest with
themselves around it and the team is always reciprocal around that as well. So like around
here when someone, people are responsible for their own work here and their own kind of
what like uh for example on on on the writing or something like that it's like
no one's gonna tell me
No one's going to like assign a bunch of writing to me or something like that. Like I'm responsible
for my own work, but that is a big responsibility where we are all actively involved in our own
scheduling and knowing the value of making sure that everyone has a life outside of work. We
schedule accordingly and try to schedule like very, very conservatively to make sure that
there's time for everyone to iterate and to do their best work.
and to not feel like they're just totally under the gun.
And again, it's taken us a long time working together
to figure out what is a good balance there.
I think that's always a challenge
for different developers to sort that out for themselves
and in general.
So those are a couple of our...
that that's giving you an impression of what some of our values are. But yeah, at this point, we have,
you know, they're not values that we like publicly print on our website, but that's part of them
being true to us. They're not like they're to they're not there as an advertisement for us.
They're just how we have grown to understand ourselves and and understand our relationship
to our work and to each other. And yeah, I mean, yeah, well.
That's great, and forgive me for this nebulous question, but I think it's something that people think about when they talk about things like mission statements or values.
Did codifying and making those explicit meaningfully change anything about the workplace?
Like, did it make it easier or simpler? Did it speed up meetings? Like, what did it do, if anything?
It really, in our case, it was really valuable. For me, personally, it was really valuable.
Like, the stuff I just talked about, of work contouring to your life, it really...
my own personal mindset toward my relationship with my work and just like how understanding
that it's not one size fits all was something that for me just like clicked once we did
put that.
put that particular statement into words.
It's a phrase that Amir, our studio director, put into words,
you know, having spoken to me and others about where everybody was at with respect to their work.
It's like, what's the pattern here? What are our expectations?
Are we asking everyone to just...
slave away, you know, we're a small team should we just slave away constantly forever? Well no,
we can't do that because sustainability is our goal. We've been together for close to 10 years
and we want to keep going. If we just burn the candle at both ends forever, we're not going to
make it. So how do we find the balance of making high quality games that we can be proud of while
still living our lives, you know, and because the rest of our lives
like empowers our ability to make the kind of game we make.
He asked about my inspirations before.
My inspiration ain't gonna be just like crunching
on my last project, you know?
Like that's not gonna make for a very interesting
video game over time and it's not gonna make
for a lot of content variety.
So it's really important for us.
as a group of people doing creative work to find an appropriate balance.
We all care a lot about our work. We love doing the work, so
I think one of the challenges in the game industry can be
for people to even just like pull themselves away from work, know when to
do that, but that's where I think a lot of our
experience over the years comes in. As a team, we all try to
support each other, catch each other when
You know, we made a whole game about this.
It's called Pyre.
It's about a group of people who have to support each other
through thick and thin, come what may.
So yeah, I think we've learned a lot.
And I hope it's expressed through this game
that we're working on now.
Yeah, Pyro is an incredible game. Sorry, go ahead Brian.
That was a really intricate answer.
Folks in chat, we're going to wrap up in about 10 minutes,
so feel free to get your questions in.
I do want to get you answers for those questions.
So we're going to sneak one in before I want to loop right back to the discussion point we're on.
There are folks asking about like Kittagine and others who are asking about content after the 1.0 launch.
Greg, do you know if there'll be continued content updates like there are in early access?
Or you said earlier, you know, once the products launch, it'll be the equivalent of a three year baked super giant game from before.
So we've always done like our our kind of game launches have never been the end of either
project so I think I think it's fair to expect that we will continue to I mean it's all but
certain I would say to the extent that we are able we will continue to support this game for as long as
as players
have interest in it, that's something we've always done with each of our games.
So I think since we do expect early access to last for more than a year, we were reluctant
to make a ton of promises about what will happen after we say it's reached the 1.0 phase.
But I think our goal for sure is if players are still enjoying the game, we'll want to
keep supporting it in the ways that make.
in the ways that make sense.
And at that point, we would expect it to be available
in more places and be positioned to be able to support it
in wherever it appears.
I'll just do another quick last call for questions so we can try and get them in.
Greg, yeah, like I said, I wanted to loop back on that thread about studio life.
This has been an interesting year to talk about that.
I've been trying to do my due diligence and ask whenever I can talk to team leaders whenever
I can because this has been a year where we've had stories about Riot Games, Rockstar Games,
Telltale Games.
We've had closures.
We've had...
stories about employees mistreating other employees through a culture of harassment.
Sorry, I'm not asking you to comment on those specifically, which is what I'm building to.
But I guess as the industry has talked more about this, how do you see, like,
and it's sort of impossible to ask every company to do what your company does with regards to your
values. How do you think other game developers can work to improve their quality of life in
ways like that?
just because I think now more than other,
I think a lot of developers are very concerned about this
because in some cases they feel sort of their health
and their lives are on the edge a little bit,
which is a bit dramatic.
Sorry.
No, I mean, should we, studios should be concerned.
Why shouldn't they be?
Yeah.
This is about people's lives.
So we take it seriously.
Yeah, I have a certain point of view on this
because
My mother's a neurologist. She like helps people with really severe, severe issues, right? So I
just work on video games. So I can like on the one hand, I can put my work into perspective. But,
but having said that, it's really like people work day in and day out on this stuff. And a lot of
people's lives do revolve around it for better for worse. So it is important. And studios.
owe it to themselves and to the people who work there to be introspective and thoughtful
about it in their own way. But apart from that, it's like I can't be prescriptive about it.
I don't know that there's a... I'm actually very personally like very... I bristle at the idea that
there's like a formula, that there's like a prescription, like studios must do this.
these must be the work hours, this must be the culture.
I think it really depends.
And there are different studios in different parts
of the world and with different team compositions and so on,
where it doesn't, there isn't like a one size fits all
solution for them.
And there are studios of all different shapes and sizes
that have succeeded and that have failed.
And those are all unique cases with something
for people to learn from, I'm sure.
you know, in our case, we're we're doing the best we can here based on our our
experience and our observations of what other folks out there are doing. Our
discussions with other teams are discussions internally, the kind of
trials and tribulations that we go through. But, you know, we when we
started in 2009, I don't know that any of us would have assumed we'd still be
around by now, you know, having launched our
our fourth game. We might have been optimistic about it, but I'm sure we wouldn't have expected it.
So I think the truth is everybody is making it up as they go and these discussions that
that happen out in the open are really important discussions that I think if they cause
other developers and studio leaders to like take a hard look in the mirror or ask themselves if
they're things that what blind spots they have, what are they not thinking about that maybe they
should be.
I think that's all good. There's a lot of responsibility that comes with this stuff.
Games have like a really big impact on people. They're expensive, they take a lot of time,
there are ethical issues around them. These are things that people should be thinking about
if they want to make games. I hope we are bearing that burden ourselves as responsibly as possible
and I know that there will be people out there who tell us if we're not doing that.
And for me it's like I'm
In the grand scheme of things, I'm glad that that's the way it is.
That that that I think I think there are forces in this industry
that will that will keep you honest. And I and I value that a
lot as someone who comes from, you know, a background of
reviewing video games. Yeah. You know, having a neurologist for a
mother.
Yeah, so I hope that answers your question. I'm glad I'm glad
the conversations are happening. They're really they're tough
conversations, right? It's tough to have all the context. And
and it's easy for stuff to get taken out of context sometimes
and, and people don't really and it could be awkward and but
it's, it's it's for the best for for some of the stuff to get out
in the open, in my personal opinion. Yeah.
Well, I mean, that begs the question, did the team crunch on this?
And how did it compare to the crunch on Pyre and the crunch on Bastion?
I mean, what do you define?
Define, define.
Yeah, right.
So it's like, did anyone did you feel like anyone was had to put in extra hours,
I guess, above and beyond what they were willing to do in a way that negatively
impacted their social life or personal life?
Not beyond what they were. No, I don't.
Yeah.
Like, they, they, um, they...
There's never, there's never been a moment in the history of this studio where it's like,
like, now your hours are this.
But I think, I think that crunch is much more insidious than,
than, uh, like the sort of forced work hours.
It can, it can often be that someone is in a situation where they feel, uh, compelled.
like no one is telling them or forcing them but they feel like it but they know that they have this deadline and so they're like
triangulating the work that must get done in the amount of time so they force themselves to do it.
We've we've folks here have worked hard in the past for sure. The but part of our growth on this project is to is to.
diffuse some of that work across more people to so that so that it doesn't fall on as as few shoulders as maybe it has in the past, but, you know, so, so yeah, I mean, I hope that I think the part of it is that I should say is like, it was extremely like, like every, for example, we, we worked, we worked on on Saturday, this past Saturday, or launching our game on Thursday.
We all knew we were going to work on Saturday for months in advance.
And we took the previous Friday off and stuff like that
because we we knew we had a weird week coming up with a with a launch
on a Thursday night.
So we did we we did a whole bunch of planning around our launch week
just to give you an impression.
And we.
um what was the yeah the other the other part of it is knowing we were launching
into early access it was extremely important uh something
that we talked about um and and i think made good on um over
and over to to make sure that people went into
this week as as well like unlike with a previous
game where there can be a temptation to crunch toward the end because then
you're just going to like kind of
get a bunch of time off. Here, the early access launch is just the beginning. So we can't afford
to be all kind of all tired and at our wits end and stuff right now, like because the most
important thing with a game like this is the follow-through on the launch. Not just, no one's
going to remember Thursday last week in a few weeks, they barely remember it now. What they're
going to remember when they think about our game is our pattern of being able to...
maintain it and for that, you know, that's back to the kind of marathon
Training analogy I made before it's it's really about finding a pace that that is healthy for us that we that we can
maintain
Comfortably and take the time we need and we think we're well positioned to do that
Yeah, man, I would I would kill to have another hour I would but I I can't take it
Yeah, no, yeah, we need to get a couple of these questions rapid fire up before we let you go.
Oh no, there were other questions. Ms. Jim Cloud, we're going to go back to you. What was the
greatest challenge with developing this game outside of the work stuff? Like what was really
great, like challenging in what we're seeing on screen right now?
Um, man, let's see.
I think I get another hour long question.
Yeah, I think like the, um, it's a whole, it's an entirely new game.
Okay.
No, I have, I have a, I know what exactly the thing is.
Each of our previous games has been designed more as like a linear.
experience. There's a lot of branching in games like Pyre,
and there's a lot of like reactive voiceover in all of our games, but
generally speaking there's a beginning, middle, and end,
and you go through it in a succession. So re-approaching this game
to be designed around replayability is a is like a sort of a tectonic shift
for us. It's a whole like
different mindset in how it's a whole new genre for us, despite the superficial similarities
in the combat game to something like Bastion. So re-approaching both the gameplay and the narrative,
knowing that this game is designed to be replayed, is a big shift in thinking and a big shift in the
entire underlying architecture of the game. And that was like...
that was like a bite the bullet moment really early on in development where I was like, wow,
this feels really different, but let's keep going. This is exciting. Let's see what happens.
That was like, it was the biggest challenge and a big source of excitement as well,
just to work all that out. Right on. All right. Thank you all. Thank you,
Greg, so much for joining us. That was a really great conversation. If you're at home,
thank you to everyone watching at home.
Oh man, yeah, I'm getting a warning about.
We are about to keep rolling.
The GDC Twitch channel will keep going
with some great GDC talks.
If you're an aspiring game developer,
we would love it if you stuck around
and just learned more about how games get made.
If you are a professional game developer,
we hope you find something in there that's useful for you.
If you liked what you had today,
we would love it if you click the follow button.
Thank you, supergiant community for showing up.
And ironically, if you heard too closely,
you heard the Bastion music playing
because my phone went off in the other room.
Shoutout to Darren.
Thank you Alex and Greg.
I suppose for Greg, if folks have other questions for you, I would recommend you check out the
Supergiant Games Discord.
You can literally see it when you boot up the game, and I'm sure the link to it's on
the Twitter as well, or any other website.
And with that, have a good day everyone.