Thank you.
Hi, everyone.
On that note of the meetup thing, at that same location tonight,
we are going to be doing a little sort of casual meetup get-together
to chat more about location-based games and location-based storytelling,
starting at around 6 o'clock.
So you guys are welcome to come and join us there
and continue the conversation.
And I'll remind you again at the end.
So come find us in the wrap-up room after for where that location is, I guess.
Cool, that's not what I want to do.
That's what I want to do.
So my name is Lucas Johnson.
Hey, hi.
I run a company called SilverString Media.
We do narrative design and consulting and things and have over the last couple of years
been embarking on the location-based game journey, doing specifically location-based
games at events.
And so we wanted to talk about how to tell stories in location-based games.
Again, there is an evaluation that we ask that you please fill out because it's very
useful to all of us.
You know the deal if you've been to GDC before.
So with the explosion of Pokemon Go in this past year, it's brought location-based gaming
sort of into the limelight.
It hasn't started with Pokemon Go.
There's been sort of location-based gaming for decades.
Everything from alternate reality games to,
we're seeing the explosion of escape rooms now too,
interactive theater.
There's all sorts of sort of interesting ways
that you can create stories and gameplay
in real physical spaces.
And when we talk about this, and it's anywhere from, you know, Pokemon Go, which is everywhere
in the world, to an escape room, which is a specific room, we have a very broad range
of types of experiences that we might want to talk about white mana tell stories in.
And they're all...
use similar design ideas, storytelling functions,
stuff like that that are similar
across all of these types of games,
though of course there are differences.
And really when we're looking at this range,
the question is how specific is the location?
And that makes a big difference
in the kinds of experiences you can create.
So to discuss these stories,
we've brought together this awesome panel.
has joined me from a very wide variety of backgrounds and experiences, which is super
exciting.
Unfortunately, if you were looking at the website ahead of time or the paper thing,
Sarah Thatcher is unable to join us on the panel after all, but she is being replaced
by Jenny here, who is awesome.
And Sarah will be hopefully hanging out at the wrap up room after and or the meet up tonight
So you can talk to her then as well
But let's just quickly go down the line to introduce our panel. Just
State name who you are and the kind of thing that you work on Jeff
I'm Jeff McPherson. I'm the creative director and co-founder of Motive.io,
and it's a platform launching at GDC that makes it easy to build location AR games.
And that platform came about from our first location AR game, Code Runner, which was in 2011.
Steve Peters, I'm founder and CCO of No Mimes Media.
I've formerly done some work for Niantic last year, which you may have heard of them, a
little Pokemon Go thing.
They continue to be a client.
I've been working mostly in the alternate reality gaming space, but also more recently
getting into a lot of the geolocation games in the last five years, augmented reality,
that kind of stuff.
Really, whatever.
Thanks.
doing cool stuff in relation to locations.
That's kind of what we've always been doing.
My name is Jenny Godstein.
I work for the Go game.
And we've been designing interactive adventure games
since 2001.
So our games then look a little different than what
they look like now.
We used to use pay phones and those Nokia brick phones.
And now we use all sorts of devices.
and we can turn buildings, neighborhoods, multiple cities
at once into epic games with actors
and interactive content,
and we run them all around the world.
So I design those games.
I also manage our game design team
and come up with new game concepts
like the zombie apocalypse disaster preparedness games
and any number of applied play game types.
I'm Rob Morgan, I'm a writer and I am a co-founder and creative director of Playlines.
And we make interactive, site-specific, augmented reality theatre in AR.
Using location-based data to make site-specific installations that users walk around, usually
using a mix of smartphone audio and real-world actors to do immersive VR theatre experiences.
Awesome, so you can see a wide variety of experience
from lots of different kinds of games, which is super cool.
And one of the reasons that I wanted to keep this panel
sort of a bit more of a discussion
than little micro talks and stuff like that,
so we can try to get some interesting stuff,
interesting conversations going on.
So to start that conversation,
I think the most important question we have to look at
when we're talking about storytelling for real locations, is why.
Why do we do this?
Why do we take games from the computer screen out into the real world
where there are people looking at you?
Okay, so I have been talking about and trying to push location-based, specifically audio
AR for a long time, and that conversation suddenly got a lot easier about nine months
ago for some reason.
And then suddenly it was easy to give an obligatory Pokemon Go meets.
description of what we were doing and the reason I've been pushing it for years when it we had to try and make it work
With GPS which only sort of worked was that I just really love tweaking
Context and I really love the idea especially because the other half of my job is writing for VR
I really love how easy it is to get users immersed in something where you don't
Work with opacity and replace the whole world with a virtual one
but instead you just add digital elements
to change people's relationships
with their actual environment.
And with their walk to the shops with Pokemon Go,
or for us with like a specific venue,
you change people's perceptions of people around them.
And I really like how you can recruit in
elements of set dressing or even the other people
in the scene without them even knowing,
but turn them into something that makes the user
feel like they're being watched,
or feel like they're being more self-conscious
than they would be otherwise.
So it's kind of like a newer form of context hacking.
That's what I really like about using real places.
Did you say context hacking?
Yes.
That's cool.
Like it's an art term from like the 90s I think.
But yeah, I'm bringing it back.
Yeah, it's like reality enhancement.
Really, when you're in the middle of a game like that,
everything is brighter, because anything can happen
and you're not sure what's a part of it, what isn't,
and I think that rush is as compelling
for the players as it is,
and sorry if I'm putting words in your mouths,
but I think it's as compelling for us, too,
as one thing that we commented on,
it's fun when the game games the game designer.
Yeah, that never happens.
Apparently it only happens to me.
And no, but there's this sense of kind of lawlessness
where you're going out there with a design,
but you have no idea what's actually gonna happen.
There are so many factors.
And all of a sudden, as the designer,
you are also in a game.
And I think that is maybe why we make ourselves,
why we're a glutton for punishment,
why we decide to design real world games
and not games that are a little more controllable.
It's kind of like jazz.
It's kind of like a call and response.
It's kind of like stand-up comedy in a lot of ways.
For me, the reason why is
in a lot of this stuff, almost every project
I've worked on, the goal has been
to make the player feel
like the story is taking
place in the actual world
that they live in.
as opposed to on a screen somewhere, whether it's in your hand or whether it's on your TV
or something like that. And recently with technology that's become,
I won't say easier, but it's become more interesting
and the possibilities have expanded there. But I mean that's a win,
right, when we can turn the world around us into a play space. I'm a big
advocate of, you know, public play.
And this has always just been...
when you can be walking down the street and all of a sudden the game literally reaches out and grabs you,
whether it's a phone call, that's what got me into it, was my phone rang on the way to lunch one day in 2001
and it was the beast alternate reality game calling me, literally, I wasn't expecting it,
and I forgot about lunch, I ran back into my office, got online to see what was going on,
and I thought, they're onto something here, and the rest is history.
You know, it's like...
You know, it's so personal.
It's, it just, it feels like such a personal experience.
I know a lot of you guys use audio in your games.
It's like being a part of a magic club.
Like each player has their own little secret.
With Pokemon, that was the first time that I ever felt like,
whoa, there's other humans here who are doing it too.
That was remarkable.
But prior to that, you've got this secret that is,
In our game you were a spy and you're hearing the voice of your handler constantly
Feeding you information knowing what's going on around you similar like to I guess turn-by-turn GPS except this was this was be careful
Make sure no one's watching there might be someone across the street that park
He was last seen at the park and you're like there is a there is a park
how did he know so that's comes from like you know pulling map data and GPS data and
And it's so uncontrolled, you have this factor that's so uncontrollable that your writing
has to be very careful, like a psychic cold reading is a very good technique, in that
you suggest something rather than laying down a fact that could be wrong that will break
the narrative and break the person out of it.
So you might see somebody.
You might see this.
You might see that.
But one of the things we would do is you might see somebody going for a coffee.
That guy or that girl was last, you know.
scene handing off documents to a spy, but we know that you're by Starbucks. We don't mention that so that we're like, of course
There's people with coffee
Yeah, and you're rendering it in your head. So it's a very very personal experience
Well, and you mentioned something else that's really interesting is is that social aspect?
I mean we all probably saw when Pokemon go came out whether or not you played it suddenly seeing people in the same space together
I remember going down to the beach and like, you know, a couple teenagers walked by and said hey
There's a you know dragonite down there. It's like
Thanks, like running from me, right?
You know, it becomes this very social experience, right?
I will add that the one thing about the why is for me,
I'm seeing with the proliferation of things
like escape rooms and things like that,
I feel like the pendulum is starting to swing
a little bit away from, you know,
digital to more experiential.
You know, people wanna do things that they can,
you know, we've had, now we got this little computer
in our pocket and we can do cool, amazing things,
but...
We wanted, now folks are really kind of wanting to go organic and take that next step and
get out into the real world and doing things that are tangible.
So I think that's why escape rooms are getting so popular, that's why GoGaming continues
to go strong after all these years.
And that's what's really exciting.
You know, I've got great stories about, you know, the literal walking down the street
and something happens to you out of the blue and you're like all of a sudden you're a superhero
in a game or you're a spy.
That's awesome.
There is another factor here, which is that reality is cheap and plentiful.
And it has great resolution.
It has great graphics!
And it rarely glitches out.
And that means that, like, if you can just manipulate the player's imagination...
Like Jeff was saying, the player fills in the blanks and can start telling themselves
a story if you just give them the right kind of cues.
And then they're telling themselves an incredibly vivid story that you didn't have to simulate
or pay for or virtualize.
And you're tapping into, there's emotional baggage or there's memories, especially when
it's in someone's own neighborhood that you get to ride for free on.
Like, you know, instead of, you know, when they pay a million bucks for a Beatles song
in a soundtrack.
It's not because it's a million dollar song, it's because they're trying to tap into all
of that nostalgia that this audience has.
And you kind of get that for free.
You have someone saying, wow, at that swing set that my dad taught me at, a beast came
up and I taunted him with, yeah.
So we're talking about storytelling in these kinds of games, and we're looking at Pokemon
Go and escape rooms and stuff.
Does Pokemon Go have a story?
You know, light story, like, it's about a light game mechanic, right?
You're a trainer and the story is you're collecting Pokémon.
I mean, that's pretty much it, right?
Unless there's...
Can I poll the audience? I'm really curious about that.
We should wait.
Yeah, sure. Put up your hand if you think Pokémon Go has a story.
Controversial.
Not a lot. Not a lot.
I would say it makes you tell yourself a story.
And that's the really powerful thing that it does.
And that story can be as in-depth as you like,
and you can engage with it at the level that you want.
But also, the story that it gets you telling yourself
is not incompatible with your immediate reality.
And so like.
It makes you, if it can make you take the long road
to the shops, even though you only want a loaf of bread,
then it's doing that for emotional reasons
because of competition or game design
or something that it's making you do for an emotional reason
that makes your interaction with the real world
less optimal but more fun.
At that point, I think that's a narrative of some kind.
Totally.
When I saw Sarah in the back put her hand up to that question, I know a point that she
had made is that these kinds of stories are experiential.
These are the stories of you, the player, and your experience in this space.
isn't always, though often has some element of true authored narrative,
but it isn't always about that, but it still has that sort of experiential story
that I think is really key in bringing in that emotional response,
as you guys were talking about.
And then also don't forget the story that happens between.
So often, you can play with friends or new friends,
and you create your own story.
And there are moments where you reflect on,
oh, remember that one time where we did that thing?
And so you're building your story in real time
with the help of the game.
So I think there's multiple storylines
to take into consideration and to really celebrate
and kind of fan the flames, not knowing where it may go.
So one of the things, the big major design challenge,
the first sort of design challenge
that you have to think about
when doing a location-based game, I think,
is how do you motivate someone
to actually get up and go outside?
Oh, yeah.
So it varies on the context of the game.
So if it's a group activity that everyone has opted into,
you don't need to motivate.
I mean, everyone has created this social contract,
so they're self-motivated.
If you are trying to pull people out of their day-to-day
and draw them into the game, you have
to use different mechanics to do that.
So I think the first question you ask yourself is,
is this like a ready-made experience,
or as part of the game,
am I also recruiting people to buy in?
And that requires different nuance
in how the narrative gets rolled out,
if there is a narrative.
Well, even with something like an escape room where there's that, you know, you have already
sort of bought into this experience, I think there's still even that extra level of, now
you're in the room, but we need to actually make you care.
I mean, presumably you want to be there, but there's still that extra, especially if you're
trying to do any kind of storyline, right?
I would say that...
Yeah, that's the key, is you're there,
when you're there anyway, we wanna make you care.
And I think with the question of
how do you get people outside is a huge issue,
because, right, it's the balance of the reward.
Is it worth it for me to get up off my couch
and go outside to do this thing,
as opposed to I just wanna be able to do it here.
And lots of stories from Pokemon Go of people realizing,
wait, I gotta go do this?
My avatar's not moving, how do I do this?
So I mean there's two ways to look at it, and to me it's a balance.
It's like one, there's gameplay that's casual when you're out and about anyway, right?
Oh, I'm at the bank, or I'm at the diner, let's see if there's any Pokemon around here.
And then, as you get deeper and deeper into it, and then as you get more into the game
and it kind of hooks you, then you will purpose yourself to go out and then you will find
yourself.
Pokemon Go is a textbook example of this.
lightning in a bottle, right? It's like, now it's a social phenomenon. Now I'm gonna go out and we're gonna play with friends.
But it was that initial of, I'm gonna go out and play, and sure there were people that
immediately went outside, but the whole point is it's this kind of, you got to have both, and Pokemon had the IP advantage.
the nostalgia of that. A lot of things came into fact, you know, factory, the AR thing
and sharing it on social media. People saw Pokemon on the kitchen counter and wonder,
how do I do that? And they download, they download the app and, and they initially play
it as they're out and about. But, and then as they got deeper into the game and enjoyed
it, then they started to want to go out and do it. So it's this, it's this checks and
balance between those two.
And that built-in screen grab, being able to take a picture, I think was just marketing genius.
Really?
Yeah.
You saw the image and you got it right away.
Because they didn't do a lot of traditional marketing.
It was almost solely social media.
It really went viral and it was those AR screenshots that caught on.
Magic carp in the frying pan.
Yeah.
Because we do site-specific stuff, I think we have a different experience of this, because a lot of what we do is do a fictional lair or a game lair that takes place within a conference or takes place within a festival.
And so a lot of the time we actually design our experiences to make our existing players, the people who are already on the experience, the best advert for the experience for everybody else.
Because 5%, 10% of the attendees will be playing it at any given time.
but our players are walking around with headphones on.
And we're also, in the course of the story we're telling them,
getting them to do slightly weird things that make them stand out a little bit,
making them feel natural about doing the weird thing,
and that it makes sense to them in the context of the story.
But other people walking past are like,
those guys know something that we don't,
and that's really interesting.
Then they get motivated.
So we create like VIP areas that you can only get to if you know the password,
and you only know the password if you get to the end of the story in the audio.
And so people walk past at a technology festival
and there's a bouncer and a velvet rope
and they don't know what's going on.
And the only way to get in on it is to run our experience.
That works really well in terms of pushing people
back into our experiences.
But it only works because we're site-specific.
Well, and I want to get into sort of, you know,
a lot of the specifics, narrative best practices and stuff.
But one of the other sort of major concerns
that you have to think about even up front,
is this, now that we're in the physical world,
what kinds of things do we need to think about
that we wouldn't need to think about
if we're just making a mobile game
or we're just making a computer game or something?
And I'm gonna bring up Maslow's hierarchy of needs here,
which was another tip from Sarah.
But so in most games,
we don't need to worry about the bottom of that pyramid,
which are like the base needs of being human.
You know, you're sitting at your computer,
you're gonna be safe.
If you need to pause and go to the bathroom,
you can do that.
But in a physical space,
suddenly you need to think about these other questions.
Yeah, I can say, well, we really encountered that
in terms of,
As we were developing our first location AR game, uh, the
assumption that this is gonna be a physical space, we'll make
it the lock and key, uh, mechanic of, you're gonna go
here, you're gonna go to a bank, ah, you were a hacker, much like
watchdogs, but location based and before watchdogs. And, and
you're like, I can't get into the bank, you don't have the
code. Oh, I remember, I'm gonna go now over to this location,
the Starbucks, I'm gonna run my little hacking mini game and I'm
gonna get the key. And I'm gonna go back. And on, on the moment
we tested it, we were in big trouble.
because there's nothing, you know,
when you're playing a point and click,
kinda like, oh, that's the lock,
I remember the key's over here, click.
or navigate with your controller, that's not a lot of effort.
When you've walked two blocks with no game play,
and you stop, and you're like, go turn around and go back,
and you're like, you would not believe how awful that is
as an experience.
Just even when you forget your keys and you're embarrassed,
and you don't want anyone to notice
that you're turning around, nobody cares what you're doing.
But then imagine that you've kind of got
this narrative going on, and it was a deal breaker.
And it was like, oh, that was our assumption.
Yeah, no, and that's something that we bake into all of our games, that travel has to
be less than a fourth of the experience.
And if you travel to get from point A to point B, and if you have to make people travel,
you have to fill that time with something that will keep them alight.
Whether it be I-Spy missions that they're using the physical environment to find things,
so they're looking up and out.
or something that they're discussing and negotiating
amongst their team, or something that they're
doing to prepare for the mission that's ahead.
And then the other piece of just very boring, logistical,
location-based game stuff, we always,
when the players are opting in and we can touch them
before the game, so we're not just pulling them in
and they start playing.
we always send out something that primes them
for dressing comfortably and weather appropriately
because if you are uncomfortable, you will have less fun.
That's directly related.
So we try to get people without spoiling the surprise
and it takes different shapes depending on the game,
how you communicate that information.
We try to do it as cheeky as possible,
but you have to make sure your audience is ready
physically and emotionally and spiritually
for the task ahead or else they're gonna opt out.
I'd say from my perspective, you just got to really be careful with the whole win state,
fail state.
Going off of what you were saying, I mean, yeah, if you show up and it's like, crap,
I forgot that key, now I got to walk back two blocks.
You know, that's terrible.
You got to...
there's gotta be an alternative right it's like okay well maybe I forgot that
but now there's another way I can do without having to retrace my steps
right maybe there's another mini game that's or it makes whatever I had to do
a little bit more difficult but I still I don't have to like go back or there's
no there's no you can't you can't die in
these games you know that's that's that yeah
that's the whole issue too it's like well it's not like a typical I'm playing
Fallout and great now I died and I just go back to the last save point
there are no save points
There's no spotting.
Yes.
Well, yeah.
That'd be cool.
So, although, yeah.
Well, and I think, you know, looking at the hierarchy of needs, I think that might be
why most escape rooms are, you know, around an hour in length, because otherwise you need
to think about the need to go to the washroom.
Well, I was going to say, we actually often our experiences take people into the bathroom
of wherever the venue is because that's, it's nice to kind of go into a space and you don't
normally get told a story in there, but we can have a virtual lair that happens in there
and like we've done that.
What kind of stories are you telling in there?
We've had them that like you get taken in for a sexual encounter or like someone goes
in and then they're like, this is the kind of the moment in the story where a character
breaks down and you listen to them kind of.
confessing something or being very upset.
And then they use the restroom?
Well, this is the thing, like, originally it was kind of,
should we build in a bathroom break?
Because the player is walking past,
and if they go in, then they'll go off story.
So we build it in for that reason.
But it ended up being a really intimate
and intense experience for people standing in the bathroom,
listening to the, that was when we'd do
the most intense moments in the story.
Or sitting.
Right, yeah.
But that's the ideal, is if the player is kind of there
in a private space or they're staring at themselves
in the mirror, that's an enhancement.
And also, yeah, it's an opportunity to actually create
the possibility of the player not having to abandon
the experience partway through to go to the bathroom.
It's built in.
Right, well then that leads really well
into sort of the next point that I wanted to make is,
okay, so we're choosing to tell stories in the real world
using the real environment.
So how do we do that?
How do we use the environment to enhance
the stories that we're telling?
I mean, the bathroom's a perfect example.
Yeah, sometimes I think it's an accident first,
and then you're like, oh, you can
use the environment that way.
So this one game that we have, it's
an espionage training game.
So in the course of the game, the players
are learning how to become world class spies,
a la 007 Madhahari, Archer, et cetera.
In the beginning of the game, we give them a couple of things that they need to keep,
be aware of.
And one, we say, all right, well, there's someone out in the field who's trailing you.
And if they capture you on film, and if we see that film, meaning the actor sends it
to us, then we will dock your team X amount of points.
So like...
Watch your back.
You know, like, it creates the look over the shoulder function.
And I ran this one game in Santa Monica and I forgot to hire that actor.
Like, I just spaced.
There was other things going on.
Didn't hire that actor.
So there was nobody walking around taking pictures of the teams, but they still got
that thing.
But it's in Santa Monica and there are tourists.
everywhere. So every time a tourist would take a photo, the whole team would hit the deck.
And so we realized, actually, you know what, you don't have to hire an actor
if you just put it in a well-trafficked area where people are snapping away.
I want to play that game. It's cool.
Yeah, so like the environment will leap out at you sometimes when you least expect it.
Espionage is a great genre for location-based as well, I've noticed.
And one of the nice things about that is just that it doesn't conflict with reality, right?
When you're a spy.
And the stakes are so high in espionage drama, right?
There's one or two people that are playing out basically superpowers at war.
And Paranoia is very easy, well I wouldn't say easy,
yeah, why not, it's easy to create in a location-based game
when you're a good writer like you guys are.
Yeah, I tend to start all of our experiences
with something like, are they still watching?
Or like something that kind of doesn't give you
a lot of story, but it puts the player in a heightened state
and makes them more aware, and yeah, after a while
you don't need the actor there,
like that's such a cool story, it's a great example.
Learn from my mistakes.
Well, and it's easy to do...
It's easier, perhaps, to use the environment in the specific story
when you know what exactly the environment is.
You're doing something where you know
that there's a bathroom literally right there on the route.
Our tech director, Dustin, is here,
and he had a great phrase that what we do
is often like reverse level design
in that we'll often...
we kind of have to go to a venue beforehand.
and walk around or take a GoPro and walk around
and then kind of see what story emerges from the space,
which sounds very kind of wishy-washy,
but really it's the best way to go,
oh, there's a phone booth there and it's out of use,
but we can definitely use that
and drive the player that way.
And what are the natural geographical forks
in this environment to create an interactive decision
where you go this way or that way?
But that's an opportunity that we have
that if you're doing like map API stuff,
you can't necessarily do.
Yeah, I'd say, I mean, for the stuff I've done, it's been mostly site-specific.
We, you know, most of the stuff for alternate reality games or whatever it's been like.
And there's always going out to scout the location and immersing yourself there and seeing what the location has to offer.
Sometimes you'll have to do it remotely.
I've gotten really, really good at Google Earth and different other tools at your disposal,
but there's nothing beats actually being, you know, boots on the ground.
to see what's there and also to talk to people.
And really, opportunities present themselves
that you never would have been able to research ahead of time.
But then, making something that has to be a little bit not site-specific.
That's interesting.
I always thought that having that kind of...
Controlled environment knowing where the environment that it's going to take place in was going to solve all our problems until I met you guys
Realize you guys have a lot of the same problem and brand new problems and a whole brand new problems
Whereas what we were doing is yeah our games
Well, it was adapting to wherever you were in the world.
And so we had a system set up where the writer would decide,
OK, well, this is sort of about a crooked cop who's
laundering money.
So I'm going to have a first choice, second choice, third
choice, fifth choice in terms of what's in the vicinity
within, say, a 200-meter radius.
Is there a police station?
Then I'm going to call that number one, bump that to the
top, and it will call up audio specific to that.
It's not really a branch.
It's just adapting.
I'll say that the
the cops got a, he's laundering money and he's got a stash there, go break into the
system of the police station. Not a lot of police stations around, not a lot of hospitals
around. You know, the A list of the locations that I would like, you know, to push to that
player in real time. So then we go down, we go down to, okay, is there a pool hall? Is
there, you know, things that are traditionally associated with, you know,
Shadier activities. I'm sure there's some very classy pool halls. Arcades used to be classy.
And it goes down the list and we're like, okay, a bank. Okay, then maybe a church. And then we're like,
I don't really want people going to a church and then hearing audio saying there's a crooked cop
that works at that church. We'll mix that.
But what it does, what that approach does, which is, it's very exciting, you know, as
a writer and a developer, is that you kind of have this magic level designer, which is
the world, which is tinkering with your levels, and you can fire up your game and play that
mission and go, wow, like.
It's unbelievable. He's running a racket.
You know, he's, he's, this cop runs a money laundering out of a laundry, that's number one,
and then a car wash, and he funnels the money from here to there.
And now, what's interesting is that it was a very niche game, right?
And we're actually saying, we're suggesting that there's criminal activity happening at real locations.
As, you know, Pokemon has brought this really to the mainstream,
it's now there's another responsibility we have to take is,
although it feels cool for the player,
We are kind of casting a narrative on top of a business that's not opted into it.
And we're going to touch on those ethical issues and stuff in a sec, but you wanted
to add something.
Yeah, I wanted to add, just keep in mind though, I mean we're talking mostly like GPS location.
Remember there's a lot of different sensors in the phone they can also use in the location.
I mean, what if it's not just, oh there's a park nearby, but oh, taking into account
the time of day, or the temperature of where you are, you know, what if some Pokemon only
showed up when the temperature was like below 40 degrees?
Or, you know, if you're up a certain elevation, or if it's a really quiet environment or a
really loud environment.
I mean, there's all sorts of other cues from the location that you can then gather and
bring into your game to affect the gameplay.
And you know, it can sense.
I mean, even with a narrative, how awesome would it be to know the narrative knows that
it's starting to drizzle.
Yeah.
You know, it's starting to rain and yeah, during the rain, I mean that's,
even from one of the ARGs we did back in the day,
we had a blogger girl who was talking about driving up into the mountains outside of Portland
to go do this thing, get the MacGuffin,
and she mentions in it that she's a little worried because it's starting to snow outside.
and one of our players from Portland says as he read that he looked outside
and it was starting to snow because we wrote that in real time based on the
weather information we had
and was just those little touches that again make it feel like this story is
really going on
in the actual world that I live in.
And you can tap into, you know, there's APIs,
there's data coming from Dark Sky.
And so hyper local weather.
And not to pitch my own company,
but we can provide that for you.
I like it.
Oh, no.
Well, I think as these games become more pervasive,
as we have more players out in the world playing actively,
I think the next frontier is using one game
as the environment for another game.
And one thing, one experience that I had,
I was walking up a hill in San Francisco.
at the height of everyone on their phones, Pokemon Go,
and I was the only one going up the hill,
and I could see people come down the hill,
and they were coming in waves, right?
They were with their friends on Pokemon,
you know, like, heads down, like, using their phone,
and they were coming at me, and all of a sudden,
it was like, oh, shit, I'm an asteroid.
It's like, you know, kind of upstream, salmon swimming,
the Pokemon players, and it became my game,
and so I think finding ways to,
you know, it's like tides, right?
You know, it creates these eddies
that you wouldn't have anticipated.
So how can we really play with those eddies
that happen naturally or through game design?
I think social attunement and like attenuation
is one of the easiest things to manipulate in people.
And it creates the most immediate effects
in the same way that like saying to you,
you know, if we were gonna make everybody
go around the room and turn and shake everybody's hand.
who's sitting next to all of you.
That would make the situation really awkward
and then it would completely change your relationship
with your immediate context.
And that's something that I wanna do more and more
with our games, like a data set
that we can scrape off the phone
is how many other people are playing the game nearby
within a radius of 10 meters.
At that point we can start generating impromptu flash mobs,
because the most significant part of the set dressing
is the presence of other people,
because humans are really, really attenuated
to the presence of other people,
and whether they're watching and what they're doing,
whether they're watching me and am I being weird.
If you can get the player thinking about that stuff,
then you can put them in a really interesting predicament,
and then that enhances your story.
Or, yeah, you can play a game that...
takes place in your context that other people were not even aware of,
but they're enhancing your experience of the real world, that's a really cool one.
So obviously we can talk about this stuff all day,
and we have for the last couple days.
So please join us later to continue the conversation.
But I do want to touch on, while we're still
on narrative best practices, the use of audio,
because that's come up a couple times.
And I know a lot of what several of us
have used for telling the story.
And this comes to the question of,
do you want to create a game where
your players are doing this as they're walking
through this environment?
We're using the environment.
to help tell the story, we want to make sure that the player is engaging with it. So I
know, I mean, you do that a lot with Motive.
Yeah, we have a best practice, we have a warning, we call it the desk bias or the desktop bias,
which is you're inevitably going to be developing this sitting at your desk and you're looking
at that screen and you're going to want to iterate on it to make it prettier and prettier
and prettier and the end result can be that. You've got a player, you've designed a lot
of visual cues that's staring at their phone and there's just.
It just takes away from the whole experience.
And it's frustrating.
I remember testing when that rain is hitting the screen,
and you're trying to understand some character's motivation.
It's not quite clear.
And you're like, this sucks.
So it's so critical to just keep going out there
and keep going out there.
And I think the beauty about audio is it's heads up.
And that does bring up one other point, which is when you use audio as your main way of
telling your narrative, the other forms of communicating, and particularly text or found
documents, they drop in hierarchy. And plot points and plot twists and clever things we
thought the player would figure out by reading get completely lost. And you guys have found
that as well?
Keep the story as simple as possible when you're out there.
As we get on to pitfalls to avoid, keep it simple.
Audio is cheap and really effective,
and it's often not incompatible with the user's experience
of the real world around them.
Like if you have ever been walking down the street.
listening to something on your headphones,
and the right song comes on at the right moment,
that, your reality is being augmented.
At that point, I don't really care what the data set is.
That's augmented reality,
and humans are really susceptible
to having their reality augmented,
and we just try and recreate that.
The heads-up effect of audio is really, really important,
and also, you can do things
that don't have to be physically possible.
They're as real and vivid as the player's imagination.
That's why I love audio.
Yeah, no, I think, and music, because when we say audio,
well, we're often talking about narrative.
You know, go over here, this is happening.
But music is absolutely another character in the experience.
And as you guys are going out and designing,
think of music as this.
as this tone setter, and it can do really interesting things
with how scenarios are interpreted.
So in our games often, in some of our games,
we'll take the media that the players create,
and in front of them, if we all come back after the game,
we're live mixing sound effects and music
to the photos and videos that they've already taken.
The video originally may be something that's quite somber,
but the minute that you overlay the Andy Griffith theme,
it is a completely different experience.
Or if someone's boxing and you throw on Rocky
and people, their face melts.
So it's something where I think we think of it
as kind of this orchestral background,
but it really does push narrative forward
in ways that may be underexplored.
So moving forward on sort of pitfalls to avoid,
we've talked about some of these things already
in the conversation, you know, not wanting to look,
not wanting to be embarrassed by what you're doing,
keeping the story simple because people
will lose a lot of details,
not asking them to do too much
or motivating them properly to get up and go.
So rather than sort of go through some more generics,
can I get a brief example from each of you
of something to avoid doing that you've.
A ticking clock where someone has to get to a location, particularly if they're out in
the wild, there's vehicles.
It's just too dangerous and you have a responsibility.
People will already kind of be in this world and going after this objective and be motivated
to move and step out.
So it's a tough one because it's a nice go-to to be like, got to get there before the clock
runs out.
That's a good one, Steve.
Specific pitfalls?
Yeah.
Don't tell your players to dress up like the Joker and go to the mall.
Because they'll shut the mall down.
That happened to you, right?
The police will come.
Yes.
Well, not being personal.
But you had players doing that.
From what I hear, yes.
On the advice of counsel, I decline to answer.
Yes, it's obvious.
Well, I think you have to, a pitfall is to assume that you're not going to make mistakes
as the designer, or you and your production team are going to do everything flawlessly.
Never happens.
And also, you know, learn to kind of enjoy it.
There was one epic mix-up that was very entertaining for me,
and I think it was sort of entertaining for the players, but...
We had a game in Vegas and you can't, it's illegal to take photos and videos on the casino
floor so that was off limits for a lot of the play.
So we put a lot of our actors in rooms in the hotels and one mission, teams had to go
to a room and they walked in and they were going to get grilled on sports trivia.
So we had an actor in there wearing a ref's shirt
and a whistle and was just ready to like get in there.
And then another room, they were told that it was a crime.
It just happened there and they had to go
and they couldn't touch anything,
but they had to scan the crime scene for clues
and then get out.
And then unbeknownst to them, 20 minutes later,
they would be drilled on the details of the room.
But they also didn't know that we'd hidden a guy in the closet
to jump out.
And he was dressed just, he was horrifying.
He was so scary.
And so they were supposed to kind of sneak around and then
get freaked out.
But I switched, or the keys got switched, right?
So the wrong actor went to the wrong room.
And so the sports, the team expecting sports stats got scared, you know, by this guy in
the closet.
And then the crime scene kids were getting grilled on like baseball things.
So you know.
I
think
Your player characters have no AI.
That's the problem, they're humans.
And you have no, that's the craziest thing.
You're like, no, why are you doing that?
There's nothing about this game
that means you're supposed to do that.
I just wanted to go this way.
Well, and that speaks to this question of,
you know, in video games,
traditional video games, we can have invisible walls
that stop you from going there.
And you can't do that in the real world.
People will just walk into that room.
Yeah, if your story can't survive having any,
like any 10, 20 second section of it.
If the player can't just miss that,
and your story can't survive that,
like you only say everything once,
or like you have a reveal and you have to be there,
and if you're not there for it,
then your story doesn't make sense.
It's not like a movie.
Like if you have to.
pay attention to this section and you can't afford to have the player miss it.
It's just not a story that's suited for an immersive environment because the
player will be distracted. We use mobile phones. They could receive a call and or
like they could see a friend and take their headphones off for ten seconds and
we don't want them to be able to skip back necessarily because that doesn't
feel very immersive either. We need a nice story that patches itself together
and leaves enough space for the player to be doing some of the imaginative work
but also that can survive.
you know, it's not just dominoes.
If one of those dominoes doesn't fall,
the rest of them still need to go down
the way you vaguely want them to.
And it was mentioned the, you know,
people can just walk where they want,
they don't have an AI,
and then you get this problem with griefers, potentially.
Well, and also too, I'd say that one,
on a serious answer to the question,
instead of the mall thing,
you know, keep in mind kind of that,
where that the magic circle is
and how it affects people that aren't in on it,
in on the joke.
Always be mindful of context, right?
How things appear to those who don't necessarily know
what's going on when they see a guy on the street
get a hood thrown over his head
and throw it into a black van and scoot it away.
And even if the guy was prepared for that
and knew that was happening,
number one, I don't think it's a great idea.
But for onlookers, if you're doing it in a public place,
keep in the context.
I know the people that have said,
we're gonna leave you a cache of,
it's gonna be in an ammo box left on a picnic table.
you know, in this post 9-11 world we live in,
that sort of thing's not really a great idea for the people that aren't in on the game.
And so there are a lot more ethical considerations
that you have to take into consideration with these sorts of things.
Yeah, so in a way you're designing both for the player and for whoever's around them.
And onlookers, yeah. Inadvertent onlookers.
If you're doing a multiplayer thing, and someone was talking to me about a design that they had,
and it sounded like it was fun, but one of the problems is multiplayer and you're scavenging.
And the items that you're scavenging could include things like a gun.
And you just have to imagine that.
uh... all over the world, out of context, you hear these two guys going, I got one, I found a gun, I got a gun,
did you get a gun? Yeah. Did you get ammo? I got ammo! Come on over here, I've got a gun.
Those
are the things that are not, those are the, the, kind of the byproduct of what can happen. So we're in this
kind of area where these tropes, these, these
these uh... things that are very handy to, to have in a game.
You have to think about, will someone say that out loud, standing in a park?
Consequences can become real if you're not careful.
Also beware of helpful players, because we had a...
The launch, like the first launch of one of our very first projects,
the first 15 minutes, things started going haywire,
and we started getting bugs that we hadn't had before.
And it turned out that it was because we were using Bluetooth beacons
to provide very accurate, very local location data,
so that users could like, turn left or turn right down a corridor.
have an immediate response, and that would represent
an immediate choice that they were making.
And a user had found one of our beacons
where it was supposed to be, but thought,
someone might pick that up and do something with it,
so I'm gonna pick it up and return it to the guys.
And not only were they then picking it up and moving it,
in order to try and be helpful, this good Samaritan,
they were walking around with it in their pocket
around the start area, looking for one of us to give it to,
which meant that our players were getting
a load of false positives from the end of the story,
and the story was skipping, and we've put in fail-safe,
so that doesn't happen.
But yeah, that kind of players who sort of,
who wanted to go the extra mile,
you also need to build in a reward for them,
rather than, so that everybody wants to feel like
they know something that everybody else doesn't.
That's why espionage works so well.
So, if you're gonna let people see the strings of your game,
that's not necessarily a bad thing,
but you need to reward them, rather than go,
thank you, I'll just go and put this beacon back
where it's supposed to be.
We're running a little short on time, so I do want to move forward.
And speaking of legal and ethical concerns, one of the big controversies that came up
with Pokemon Go was, of course, issues around trespassing, issues around privacy, issues
around putting a PokeStop at the Holocaust Museum, things like that.
How do we avoid those issues as writers and designers?
Well, first, know that they realize they exist,
which doesn't exactly occur to a lot of people.
It is an interesting, brave new world we're in
because it does bring up the question of,
like, the guy that wakes up one morning
and his garden in his backyard is now a pokey stop
to this, you know, multimillion dollar game
that he never consented to,
and he's not making, he's not sharing in the revenue.
but somebody is using his private property to make money off of, basically.
So there are these questions that honestly have yet to be resolved in a lot of ways.
Most people don't mind, but then there is, yeah, there's the curator of the Holocaust
Museum or there's a memorial in the middle of town that was dedicated to a certain family
that all died in World War II.
It's a very somber place.
And there are all these little different use cases
where it may not be appropriate to play a game.
And so right now, it's easy right now.
You can say, well, we'll contact the makers of the game,
and we'll have them opt us out.
But then again, if you're a big player,
and you may have your own IP, and you may have your own.
area where you may not want somebody else's IP to be invading on yours, I won't mention
any amusement park names, that may be an issue there.
So there are all these considerations that I think aren't going to go away, they're only
going to get more exacerbated as we go on and there's going to be more and more of these
games as geolocation games become more mainstream, which I really think they are going to be
now, now that everybody knows what Pokemon Go is.
So that's an issue.
I mean, yeah, we have a way of blacklisting those sites using our tech, but, you know,
it's like it needs to be centralized.
Is everybody, you know, who's constantly having people trespassing going to have to figure
out who published the game?
How do I get a hold of that person?
So...
Yeah, you're right. That's a larger question
So I think about it like this that if you're playing Pokemon go and you see a Pokemon on the other side of a chain
Link fence and you can't get at it. That is not the game not functioning as designed. That is a feature
That's not a bug
That is the way that the game introduces exciting elements to make the real world more interesting
The real world also introduces obstacles to make the game more interesting
But the world is full of all kinds of fences,
and fences affect some people more than others
for reasons of gender, or race, or physical ability.
And the world is full of unpleasant realities
that some people have to deal with more than others.
And I think the minute we're working in augmented reality,
we have a responsibility to reality,
and the player's reality, and to take that into account.
And so if your game...
if it operates in reality, that means that some people will have an experience of it which might be limited, for example,
or might, you know, you might not feel able or comfortable walking around at night
looking for Pokemon in your neighborhood or someone else's neighborhood,
and that means that experience is locked off for you, and we have to be able to take that into account and to kind of
write art that can adapt to that, or that at least, you know, takes it into account.
Yeah, no, I think it's important that anybody that's designing for these real world games
is putting at the top of their list, examining their own design bias.
And what are you bringing to the table that you're unknowingly laying on everybody who's
playing and not playing this experience that you're crafting.
So I think surrounding yourself with intelligent people,
surrounding yourself with community organizations
that know way more and better than you do,
surrounding yourself with experts in various fields.
I also think there's going to be a lot of dialogue
between urban planners and game designers,
which is going to be good and messy and great.
But I think the first thing is to ask
really, really uncomfortable questions
and see what happens.
and hire diversely. People will know things that you don't.
So the last two minutes before we have some time for questions,
I do want to touch on briefly sort of the business side of this.
You mentioned you're thinking, you think that this will become a bigger thing now that
Pokemon Go has happened. Do we think that was just a flash in the pan or is there actually
market growth potential here? Yeah, it's gonna work.
I mean, okay, Pokemon Go is lightning in a bottle. There are a lot of things happening
to contribute to its success. I mean IP being the foremost of that. But what it has done,
it has become a success case and it makes it easier to pitch these projects so you can
say, oh yeah, it's Pokemon Go meets Harry Potter or whatever, you know, and people will
understand what that is. And so when we add to that, new technologies are going to come
along, eventually wearables.
something's going to become acceptable socially and technologically. I mean, the technology's
going to increase and being able to use not only your location but being able to use augmented
reality to do the thing and say, yeah, there's a dragon flying around and there's King Kong
up on the building and that could give some really, really big potential. Again, there's
a little bit of unknown. There's a lot of people still aren't quite sure.
But, I mean, it's not going to go away, I don't think.
I mean, people are going to try new things, try different things,
and the technology is going to go forward.
And I think it's a great thing.
Obviously, Pokémon Go made money.
I assume you've heard.
But, yeah, can other experiences like this make money?
Yeah, yes, totally.
So I think the Go game has been a really interesting trial
balloon or test case on how the market of play
has changed over the years.
You know, when they first started, this is well before I got there, it was just fun.
It was just to have a good time and send people off to do goofy things in public.
And I remember being told around 2008 that shifted dramatically where all of a sudden
the majority of our clients were coming to us and saying,
We're having a morale crisis because the world is crazy, the economy is crazy, people who
are in the workplace are going through unprecedented levels of stress and pressure.
We need play as a way to let go of that for a second, just to take a deep breath and enjoy
ourselves.
And then, since then, it's changed again and again.
We see play being used as a recruitment tool.
We see play, well, we've always seen play
used as an educational tool, which I think is great.
And I'm passionate, passionate about applied play,
about using play towards something
that you wouldn't necessarily think it could be useful for,
and which is how the whole zombie
disaster preparedness games came about,
because we wanted to tackle something
that people have a natural aversion to.
How many people have an emergency kit?
Okay, good, oh good, more preppers than normal.
But for everyone who doesn't, by the way,
I didn't for a very long time,
I'm willing to wager that part of the reason
why you haven't is because you haven't gotten around to it.
It's kind of boring to buy granola bars on your Saturday.
Or you're not doing it with friends,
it's intimidating even to think about the reality.
So using play to switch those emotions around
and instead making preparedness something that is,
memorable and social and engaging and fun.
There are so many different industries and challenges
that we could be taking the mechanics of play
and applying towards creating new outcomes.
And we're seeing a demand for that,
which I think is really interesting.
People want to really maximize play as a tool
to solve all of these different problems.
Okay, so we have like two minutes left.
So we have time for like one question at each microphone
for the first people that stand up.
Can I ask something about the revenue thing
just really quickly?
There is one really unique opportunity
with that I've seen with geolocation games
and Pokemon Go has started to do it
is that presents itself and that is brand partnerships.
in a unique way. I mean they've got the one of the first things was McDonald's
in Japan
saying, oh we're gonna have these special Pokemon that only show up at McDonald's.
A multi-million dollar deal, you know, that was a great example
and that's not possible in other, I mean that's the first time
something like that has happened. It's kind of a unique new way of
you drop, you know, you grab people and you point them to
your brand and their gameplay is enhanced by doing that.
That's just a unique moment.
And I think a DLC is a viable vision.
Yes, build a DLC.
You have a campaign.
So we're going to be in the wrap-up room afterwards to continue talking.
We can talk about how to get started in this stuff because we don't have time, but I just
do want to take two quick questions.
So right there.
Just sort of I guess going off this topic
I'm working on a game right now for a museum
And I just wanted to talk about our ask you sort of best practices for working with a client
making sure that you're sort of incorporating whatever data or you know that they want to be conveying to their visitors or
You know if it's a commercial project their clients or whatever
Because we've done kind of museum and place stuff in listed buildings or
buildings that are kind of historic or you know very protective of their fabric
reassure the venue that you're not going to damage the fabric of the building
that is if they're not saying it that definitely is something that they're
thinking about and you know I mean held is the example of
Is it Minneapolis? Minnesota?
Who tried to now ban Pokemon Go
because the volume of people visiting the park
damaged their parks, which surely is,
then that's the park operating as designed.
But just reassure them that that's not gonna be the case
and that it's just gonna be a fun kind of foot traffic
rather than a scary kind of foot traffic.
We will continuing answering that in the room.
Right over here.
Hi, I'm a law student and my area of developing expertise
is property rights and augmented reality games.
So I'm really curious to hear if any of you
have had any actual legal problems
and also how you interact with lawyers
to kind of preempt these issues.
I know you guys all touched on it,
but I'm really interested.
I would love to talk to you offline after this.
We're not being recorded.
Very strong disclaimers and constantly guiding the player, reminding the player to be safe.
To actually try to effectively prevent a problem is one of the most important things, I think.
And then if you have a backup, use your agreement.
Yeah, that takes up a big part of the design process,
is getting the proper permitting
and making sure your I's are dotted and T's are crossed.
So I think it's definitely gonna be a developing space
where it's gonna come, you're in the right place.
You are in the right place.
You have the good word.
Awesome, thank you so much everybody.
We will be in the wrap up room just across the hall
and tonight at the secret location around six o'clock
if you wanna keep the conversation going.
Thank you so much for coming guys.