This is something we decided to throw in here. Steve's idea. We
always talk about the really cool things that we do in AI.
And wow, we had great success using this architecture or this
technique.
What about when things get really horked up? Completely.
Because there's educational value in that. Those of you who have read Post Mortems in the past,
it's what went right, what went wrong, and what did we learn from it.
So I think it's time for a little bit of what went wrong and what we can learn from it.
So I'm not going to bother introducing these guys, you know most of them anyway,
but we're going to kick things off with Steve Rabin.
Tales from the Tent, Trenches, AI Disaster Stories.
the portable mic. Here we go. Okay. So I'm going to tell you
about Microsoft baseball 3D. What? Microsoft made a baseball
game? When did this happen? This happened in 1998. Actually I was
working for a small company called Whiz Bang and only about
ten people. And we made the code side and Microsoft did the
animation and the graphics for this thing. But in 1998 I gave a
game developers talk on the cooperation in this game,
the AI cooperation between the players,
and I'm actually still proud of that work today.
But it's interesting to come back 17 years later
and tell you all the horrible things that happened.
Okay, disaster number one.
Why were we making a baseball game?
I kind of know why we were making a baseball game.
Well, see, nobody at the company was that big a fan of baseball.
Why were we doing this?
But I know kind of why, because we just
had made Activision's Hyperblade,
and there just weren't that many companies in the world who
knew how to make 3D games at that point.
But this was a huge disaster, because me,
I was the sole AI programmer.
I didn't know baseball well enough.
and I didn't have that bullshit detector
so that when I made behavior, it looked reasonable,
but to someone who really knows the game, it's wrong.
And I was missing that.
And it's a huge detriment if no one in the company
has that detector.
Disaster number two was the program manager at Microsoft
happened to also be the game designer,
and his solution to telling me how to design the AI
was to hand me this book.
which had about 120 diagrams like this.
And so you can imagine that's a,
you know, there's no me, you know,
you don't know why anyone's doing what they're doing.
It just says, yeah, go in this direction
if this thing happens.
So another ridiculous disaster.
And he wasn't even on site,
so I couldn't even talk to him easily.
He was at Microsoft, I was at this little company.
Disaster number three is what happens
when you combine a megalomaniac with an advanced degree
who's also one of the owners of the company?
The answer is you get a custom scripting language
is what you get.
And it was shit.
and I was the only one programming in it.
Like, the reason I have a scripting language
is maybe I have lots of designers using it or something,
but it's just the errors in it were non-existent
to compile errors,
and you couldn't debug it for anything,
and one of the benefits of a scripting language
is you could reload it while the game's running.
Well, it wasn't trustworthy enough to do that.
Probably took 10 times as long to do anything using this thing.
Disaster number four was a two year long project and for about the first year we had no 3D graphics.
And so I had to do all the AI on, this isn't it, I found this on the web, but something that looked like this.
I was making a 2D baseball game really.
And I was getting bug reports on how this wasn't right and so I'm fixing it, but I'm hyper-optimizing the damn thing to 2D.
And once we did get to 3D, oh my god, it was terrible.
people aren't facing the right way. The transitions look like
crap. Half of the AI really is making it look good. And it was
sort of just we've gone ‑‑ I made a great 2D baseball game is
what I did. So this was kind of horrible. The last thing, kind
of an animation thing, but AI is so hooked to animation. And
this was touted as a feature. Like our company had this
technology was the animation drives the motion. Notice how
his right foot is nailed to the ground.
Now this is a ridiculous example of it,
but as an AI programmer,
to get people to move somewhere,
I had to start an animation and hope the feet
would drive them in the right direction
and sort of twist the hips to get them steering right.
And when I got to the right spot,
I'd just slurp to a stand or something like that.
Another example is this guy who's rounding third base.
Kind of notice he doesn't touch the base.
That's sort of an important part of baseball.
But there was just nothing in the animation engine to make
this happen.
Here's another.
Here's the pitcher walking up to the mound.
You can see it's kind of this stilted animation.
His ankles and stuff don't move right.
So walking looks a little weird.
And then he slurps at the end anyway, so his feet slide.
So like, what the hell?
Okay. Last thing I want to tell you about this is that something
actually very funny happened is one day we imported the batter
character and he came into the game as just a puddle of
polygons. He stepped into a teleporter as a fully formed
human being and he came out the other side as just tangled mesh
of polygons with a bat sticking out of them. Because he was
still holding a bat.
Well, this system was so robust that somewhere there were feet
in those polygons and this poor thing was trying to wiggle
toward the plate. And it was slowly making progress. And the
whole time this bat is like waving like a flag out of the
puddle as he's walking up to the ‑‑ that was awesome. I wish
I had a movie. I'm sorry. Okay. Please learn from these
disasters. Thank you.
Does this work, too? Can everybody hear me? All right. I
have a couple of little, a couple of stories, actually. The
first one happened probably a little after you, probably like
2000, 2001. And it was a game. It was probably 15 levels or so.
I'm not going to name any names. I'm not that person. So...
This is not a screen shot of it even but it's very representative. It was a fairly realistic
world. There was a lot of stuff in it. And we were about, I want to say two weeks from going to a
wide beta. And this was somewhat early on when it was a PC game and it was when a lot of games
were having their editors released with the title itself. So it was, you know, you could
fuss with the levels and that kind of thing. And it was, like I said, it was a couple weeks
before open beta.
and there was some AI issue where the AI's couldn't get into
a particular spot and I figured what it was was the classic,
right? The, the, um, some object had a bounding sphere on it that
was too big and the guy couldn't squeeze by even though he
thought he could. So I went into the editor and I clicked on that
particular Coke machine and, uh, sure enough, you know, great big
sphere on it. So I'm moving it down and out of the corner of my
eye I just happened to like glance at the name of this
particular object. And it was,
quite possibly the most offensive thing I have ever read
in my entire life. And I was like, who is the level editor on
this game? Who is building these levels? Because I started
clicking around because it wasn't just this Coke machine.
It was every stupid little object in this level had a crazy
racist or offensive or some form of just ungodly name. Like
every single object in the game. And it turns out it was our
best level designer, he had had like
seven or eight of the 15 levels were just him. We counted it up.
I think there was over 4,000 like horrid things. Accordingly,
apparently over the course of this guy's career, this was his
thing. Like he was this very, you would never guess, very
quiet kind of hi, guys, how's it going? And what he liked to do
when he named levels objects was like just go berserk. Like that
was where he got rid of his anger, I guess. And so the
problem was, is that this was going to go out into the world
and anybody that wanted to could open the level.
never happened before apparently. So he was okay up until this
point. So what we ended up doing was we ended up using the
vulgarity filter in the editor. And it worked out well because
not only could we find all of the instances of, you know, we
also put him in a corner and said get to work, guy. But then
if somebody else using the editor out in the world.
made their own map it wouldn't let you save it until you
changed anything that was vulgar or whatever. Anyways, that was
that one.
The other one, this is later, this is when I was at Sony. I've talked about that giant engine I did
for the basketball game at Sony several times. And it was a huge hierarchical expert system.
And over the course of years, because it was a basketball game, we were iterating on it every
year. So content kept going more and more and more. And by the end, there was like 6 megs of
XML AI data in this engine. It was huge, right? So it was this huge tree. And we had shipped
And we were like, I want to say like a month or so into
pre-production on the next year. And one of the designers who
had had like a huge chunk of the tree kind of to himself the year
before, he came to me and he said, hey, you know, I'm having
problems with this one situation. It just won't seem to
fire. And so I go in there and I'm looking at him. And I said,
oh, oh, well, you know, this you've got this thing commented
out here. And he just went white.
And so basically if you think about he had wanted to test out
this particular part of the tree, let's say, and see how
it's a two branch right there over here is the other side. And
so he just didn't want the AI in any way to use that side. He
just wanted to test out the other one. So he just put a
comment out right there. Right? Well, when he went white, I
said, well, when did you comment this out? And he said, a few
months ago.
And so effectively this poor guy had commented out 75% of the
year's worth of work and we had shipped it. And tough noogies for
him. Now luckily the AI system was robust enough that it still
looked like basketball and luckily also he had been working
on ball handler types that were not in the top ten most played
teams. So nobody really noticed.
lucky for him. Not only that, but we got a nice feature that
was done for next year's game for free. But the thing to take
away from this is if you are, if you do have some ability in a
hugely data driven system to comment stuff out, especially in
a tree structure that you can just go way the hell up and say
oh, up here is fine, make sure that you turn
anything that's commented out bright green pulsing something
so that you can make sure that it's not that way when you ship.
And that's it.
All right, so the year is 2009, and I've just left the games
industry to work at a big military contractor
where I'm working on this character, who
is a tech demo to how we can do cultural training.
So this is a mixed reality character
she's projected on the screen.
The Marines are in this facility where
we've got live role players and all sorts of stuff
to make it feel really immersive.
And, you know, she's supposed to help them learn how to win hearts and minds, make friends, not enemies, right?
Like, they're good at combat, but we need to teach them to do all the other stuff that lets us actually win wars and not just shoot people?
which is supposed to be why we're over there.
So the previous mixed reality scenarios
were combat training right there.
They're very fast, it's hard to see,
but there's an insurgent in the back there
who's holding a gun on the poor woman in the white dress.
So you shoot the insurgent, not the woman.
We wanted to move beyond this to more cultural training,
scenarios that would last a little longer.
you know, even 10 to 15 minutes. Non-kinetic scenarios, we call them. So kinetic is things
that shoot or blow up, right? So non-kinetic scenarios. And she needs to speak Pashto,
because the Marines are going to go to Afghanistan, and what people speak in the villages where
they're going to be going is Pashto.
So we got one of the role players who worked in the
facility there. We recorded all the audio in the mocap studio
that we had also built for them as part of this project. So we
had all of the animation and all the voice recorded together. So
you play a line of dialogue. You play the animation that goes
with it. I'd like to do better, fancier stuff like I was talking
about yesterday, but I've got three months to build this
character and almost no money. I've got an artist half time and
me, and that's it. But...
I found out when we sent it to the customer to let them see it
for the first time that she speaks Farsi. Which is what they
speak in Iraq. Not Pashtun. Fuck. So this one has a happy
ending, though, happily. So we re-recorded all of the audio
with a real actress. I mean, she was real, too. But another
actress who did speak Pashtun. At a better quality because we
did it in a sound studio instead of in a mocap studio.
Then we sliced all the animations into gestures that were,
you know, about a second long.
So, you know, you've got a gesture like this
and a gesture like this.
And then you pick a gesture sequence randomly.
The gestures are tagged for the types of lines
that they're good for.
The lines are tagged for the type of gestures
that they like.
You pick a gesture sequence.
So every time you go, you know, when you replay a gesture,
you're blending from a different gesture
and into a different gesture.
And those blends are different.
So the motion is different.
So it feels like you're doing it again.
Stupidly simple. Worked much better than I would have thought. I was really worried about the
problem of getting the beats to synchronize on the emphasis of the speech. It turns out that
didn't matter at all. In fact, I had people compliment how well that worked. Which really
surprised me. I don't know if it's because we started the gesture with the speech or if it
really just doesn't matter. That it happens to happen every once in a while and people see it
and think it's good and they don't notice when it doesn't happen.
And it breaks up the repetition really nicely.
Because when you play the same animation,
you get different blends.
When you play the same line of dialogue,
you get different animations.
So even though we had to reuse assets a lot,
because this was a very fast project,
it didn't get noticed nearly as much
as it would have otherwise.
Thank you.
Thanks.
I'm Mark Singer. I am currently a... where's the thingy? Ah, okay, there we go!
Currently working as a consultant freelance, but back in the day I worked at Red Storm Entertainment.
And this is from the very early days of our stuff. We, on top of making our more larger scale games,
we also had a number of very, very small games that were...
that were on like an eight, nine month release.
So we were just churning them out.
And it was in the PowerPlay series.
It started with Politica and Ruthless.com.
And our very last one, which I'm going to talk about,
was ShadowWatch.
And it was designed to be a kind of top-down
orthogonal strategy, sort of X-com-y, syndicate-y,
Fallout-y sort of thing.
And there was sort of an onus on us in that it was coming out so damn quick to have some
really kick ass stuff, especially with the squad strategy AI.
We spent a lot of time on the AI, like lots and lots of time, like lots and lots and lots
of time.
But one of the things that we really wanted to do was have the enemy squads be intelligent
enough about their environment to recognize when they were pinned and double back on the
player and...
come through another door, sneak attack, everything's really cool.
And we managed to do this two ways, one that it was very, very room based, and this actually
is the game.
So the, our enemies just had total knowledge of the whole level.
And we kept the player's knowledge both from them not knowing that and also by using a
fog of war.
Did you mess with my slides, Dave?
Okay.
So it was a fog of war.
All right. It was a fog of war. And so they could not see ‑‑ so you would have your
enemy vanish. And it's turn‑based much like X‑com. So the guy would go around and come
out through the other door and stuff like that. And, you know, it actually ‑‑ for the
product it was, it actually did fairly good. And we were kind of proud of this. And, you
know, like a ton of time went into this. And ‑‑
This is back, this game released in 2000, so we had a slightly more, you know, smaller but more savvy audience
that kind of knows, you know, what the current state of games is.
So we were looking on the forums, and there was lots of stuff,
and we were particularly interested in what people were going to be saying about the AI.
And they remarked on that doubling back thing,
and they were amazed at how well we had faked it.
So their basic thought was, we couldn't possibly
be doing pathing like that.
So we must be pulling the guy off the map,
waiting a couple of turns, and then popping him back
at the door.
And it was kind of disheartening,
because we could have done that.
But instead, we did this really neat thing.
And this was very early in my career
and really informed my career in that when you're
doing really, really cool AI.
Make sure there's some indication of what you're doing because if you don't, then your
audience might think you're faking it.
And thank you very much.
My name is Rez Graham. I'm an independent. I was most recently at Maxis working on The Sims 4.
So this is going to be a story about a game that I worked on in 2010 called The Sims Medieval.
For a little bit of history, what The Sims Medieval is, is sending The Sims 3 back in time.
So that they can play in this fantasy world.
It wasn't just like Sims 3 with a new skin though.
We added things like professions. So we had a merchant, a bard, a monarch and so on. You
could play as any of these professions and have multiple sims and so on. We also had
quests. So what we really needed were NPCs that were smart. And I've given talks at previous
GDCs about how we accomplished the let's make sims constrained to a particular area or a
particular thing that they're trying to do. So you have quest NPCs and so on. So this
disaster story takes place here.
I took this screen shot in a brand new game and this is an
empty world where in the very center there's a pit right
there. That's my nice little pit. And in this pit lives a
pit beast who looks like that. So this pit beast goes and you
can do all sorts of things. You can execute people so you have
the executioner here who is tossing someone down in there
and all sorts of things like that. The pit beast was this
really cool thing that added to the flavor of the game.
Now the guy there on the right with the axe is Ron the
executioner. Who's this guy? With his amazing Viking beard.
Ron the executioner's job is not only to execute people but also
to throw in gigantic hunks of meat to the pit beast who then
consumes them. That's our basic system. That's Ron. He's our
NPC and that's what he can do in this world. So of course this
is a talk about bugs so we got a bug. The bug was basically the
executioner ran up to the edge of the pit and leapt in.
That seems bad. My first thought was okay. Is there some
kind of weird animation IK thing. Did he like sort of
tweak in there. No. He was in this pose. When we saw the
screen shot it was pretty clear. In this case this was a
screen shot of my player sim doing this.
Yeah, so this is the, what can happen is the player can click
on the pit and say jump in.
It's meant to be high level content.
You're a, you know, maximum level character.
You go in, fight the pit beast,
and if you win, you get epic loot.
Standard role playing game mechanic.
It's not available autonomously.
No player or NPC sim should be able to do this autonomously.
So we're like, what happened?
Well, fortunately, and I gave this talk as well
several years ago about tools.
We have tools that let us see.
We got really, really lucky because this is one of those
bugs where it happened once and they never got it again. Well,
we managed to get it just through sheer chance. And we
have really great tools, specifically this history down
here, that let's us go, oh, shit, what did he do? Why did he
choose this? And we got to walk into it. So we got to figure out
exactly what it was. It was the insane trait. On the Sims 3 this
was fine. So here's how the insane trait worked. And
I won't name any names either but this was rather crazy.
Basically what it does is if you have the insane trait it
ignores tests.
which somehow was fine on the Sims 3.
Because you don't have a lot of Sims
who need to be locked into places doing things.
In a fantasy simulation game where there's an RPG
and you need a quest Sim to stand there
with a big arrow above his head,
that becomes more important.
Or you have Ron the executioner
who needs to be at a particular place
doing a particular thing.
This can also completely break the game, right?
If we have a constable or other certain NPCs
that if they die, we're hosed.
the entire game breaks down. Now the cool thing is that the
designers came to us and like you know we like this. We like
the idea of Ron the bad ass.
right? We just want to be able to control it. That's the thing
that we really want. And so we want to allow designers to have
this control over the game. Well, we fixed it by fixing the
horrendousness that was the insane trait to make it do
something more reasonable. And incidentally for the Sims 4, we
did the same thing. We made it so that it wasn't, that the
insane trait wasn't so insane. Cool. So
What is the purpose of all this?
The first one seems really obvious to me,
my first conclusion point, but it is not
in my many years in the games industry,
which is don't bypass existing systems.
They're there for a reason.
There's a reason why we have autonomous tests in our game.
And if you completely bypass them,
if you just short-circuit stuff, then it breaks.
Fixing this bug fixed all sorts of those
it-happened-once bugs all over the place.
The second one, which is slightly less obvious,
is use automated testing.
it was painful to try and find those. We got super lucky with
that one bug on medieval. On the Sims 4 we're like, you know, we
don't really want to have to fight this anymore. Let's do
automated testing. On the Sims 4 we had a huge massive automated
testing suite that we just ran this smoke test basically over
and over and over that would find all of these little
annoying bugs. So do those things. Thank you.