Hi, my name is Chris Cantrell. I work in production over at Riot Games, which is a video game company down in Los Angeles,
primarily known for making this game, League of Legends.
I actually haven't worked on League in a few years.
Instead, I've been working on this, Mechs vs. Minions.
And Mechs vs. Minions and League are similar in that
they're both games.
They're both from the same world as far as our lore and
IP is concerned.
But the primary difference is that while League of Legends
is a video game, Mechs vs. Minions was designed for your
tabletop.
And I think initially this decision for Riot to make a
board game probably blindsided some people.
To be frank, I think it probably blindsided some people internally at Riot.
And why would a video game company, known more for this,
decide to make this?
I guess that's what I want to talk to you about today,
to go over the story of Next First Minions development from my perspective.
I was the product owner and a part of the design team.
And so I'd like to go over the three-year timeline that I went on to get this game made.
I'd like to talk about how we leveraged our...
our video game development experience
and talk about some of the design crossroads we encountered
and what motivated us as we came to choose
one path or the next.
And finally at the end, I'd like to spend
a little bit of time talking about the why.
Why did we make this game?
Why was it so important to us?
And to be honest, if this talk feels a little bit light
on complex game theory and heavier on
on the motivations behind the experiential design of Mechs vs. Minions,
that's probably because that's where I found our learnings to be the most noteworthy or compelling.
And it's such an honor to be here.
I'll be honest, I'm really proud to tell this story.
It's the story of a video game company trying to learn how to make a board game.
And that story...
Starts with this man, Stone LeBrandy.
So some of you might recognize Stone.
He's taught game design classes here at GDC
for over a decade.
But in addition to being a very prolific
video game designer, Stone also, as like a hobby,
designs board games for his family.
Like every year, year over year, he'd sit down
and he'd create a new board game
and he'd show it to his family
and they would all play it at Christmas or whatnot.
And it's exciting to me that the story starts with Stone,
because in a bit I hope to explain why Riot decided
to make a board game.
And honestly, I'm not sure if that answer
is going to make any sense,
unless I can really convey to you what it was
that was motivating Stone
when he would make these games for his family.
So over the years he made a lot of these games,
and one of them, the one that Max First Minions is based on,
was called WZD, for Weapons of Zombie Destruction.
Now, WZD was a competitive programming game
where you would take these little cards
and put them on a command line,
and that would cause this little robot
to walk around and kill this room full of zombies.
And that was basically it.
There were like 100 zombies on the board at setup,
and whoever killed the most won.
Well, fast forward to about three years ago,
Stone was looking to join Riot.
And he was talking to someone
that he'd worked with at a previous studio,
and they're like, hey, Stone,
do you remember that WZD game?
Stone was like, yeah.
He's like,
We should have Riot make that.
And Stone laughed at him.
I mean, in his eyes it was absurd that a video game
company might actually want to make a board game.
And he told him that.
And the guy was like, no, I'm serious.
I really think this is something that Riot could get behind.
And so Stone was like, look, I'd be happy to give you
the design and I'll even help out and consult on it
if you want, but if you're bringing me in to work at Riot,
I'd rather the role that I'm being brought on for
be focused on making video games.
I'm sure he was worried about the little things in life,
like job security.
And if we're being completely honest, I'm sure on some level
he wondered what poor fool they would find to drive on the
development of this project that would probably never see
the light of day.
And so that's about the time that I entered the story.
Just some back story on me.
I joined Riot about two years earlier, so about five years
ago today, as a gameplay analyst.
It was my first job in games.
And a gameplay analyst is just a fancy way of saying that I played the latest balance changes and champions on League,
and then gave my feedback on them to the designers.
Eventually, I got promoted to be an associate QA analyst on the champion team,
and then I moved over to the release team, which is the team at Riot that gets our patches out to our players, as a release manager.
And then, my wife and I, we had our first child, who we named Avalon.
So Don Eskridge, if you're watching this,
if you name your next child Mech's First Minions,
my wife says she'll consider us square.
And then I came back from paternity leave
and I joined this area of Riot that kind of focused on
unconventional ways to explore our IP
as an associate producer.
And so here I am, some guy who'd never been a producer
before, who'd never even had any direct reports,
and I just got offered to create my own game at Riot.
And I was stoked.
I mean, it didn't matter to me that it was a board game instead of a video game.
It didn't matter to me that I was terrified beyond belief or felt completely underqualified.
I was just like, yeah, I'm making a game.
I was living the dream.
Look, I don't want to belabor my inadequacies here because I do know the space.
I love board games.
I love the mark they leave on us as people.
I love the way they impact our relationships and help shape our culture.
Some of my earliest memories are sitting down to play chess with my dad,
or Stratego, or Risk, or Axis and Allies.
I love that board games provide a venue for families to create those types of memories,
or an outlet for friends who are just looking to hang out.
So I guess you could say, while I'd never been a producer before,
what I lacked in experience, I tried my best to make up for in enthusiasm.
or passion.
I remember I sat down to play WCD for the first time
and it just didn't click for me.
I mean, I liked it.
I loved parts of it.
I just, you know, I wasn't all that eager
to keep playing it again and again.
And here's the thing, I could look around the table
and just see in the eyes of the other folks
that everyone else, it just clicked.
They got it, you know?
So I knew there was something awesome there.
I just didn't think I could see it yet.
And I thought.
I was embarrassed.
I thought I was a fraud.
And so what I tried to do was I tried to look just as objectively as I knew how at this
game because there were things that I liked about it.
Like it had a lot of the same elements that I loved about Richard Garfield's masterpiece,
Robo Rally.
But it also had some things that kind of separated itself from Robo Rally that I really appreciated.
It was a bit more...
hack and slash feel as opposed to a race.
Stone had managed to kind of capture this visceral feeling
of killing all of these zombies,
like that moment in Dead Rising
where you're kind of wandering through a parking garage
just killing zombies.
There's something viscerally right-brained
to offset the more analytical nature
that comes with programming out your command line.
So you get a little bit of both types of gamers there
with that approach.
And in game design we like to talk about this thing called power growth fantasy,
which is when you go on this journey from starting weak to growing to be,
you know, very powerful, which is just like it sounds, I guess, power growth fantasy.
And Stone had managed to incorporate elements of that by leaving the cards that you would
place to program your mech to kind of grow as the game progressed instead of wiping them at
the end of the round. So you could feel your little robot grow into this powerful zombie
killing machine. That's still, I guess.
Even with all of that, from like a timeline perspective,
I went from about here to here, like months of time,
just sort of going through the motions, you know?
Being more excited with the idea that I got to make a game
than actually being excited with where that game was at.
And eventually, I kind of brought this to my manager,
a guy who also happens to be my mentor.
And I told him that I was making a game
that I wasn't really excited to play.
And I was pretty sure that when I told him this,
While I didn't think I'd be fired,
I was pretty, he'd be forced to kind of
take me off the project.
And instead, what he told me was that it didn't matter
if it clicked for anyone else or not,
that I shouldn't be the product owner
for a game that didn't click for me.
And he encouraged me to go back to Stone
and kind of talk through the portions of the game
that I wanted to workshop.
And what I did, Stone was completely ready to collaborate
and was even excited to watch his design evolve.
And I bring this story up because I ultimately learned
something that proved to be very valuable to me
that I hope I have the courage to remember
throughout the rest of my career.
And that's that you and everyone else on your team
will do your best work if you really believe
in what you're making.
You know, there's a craftsmanship, an artisanship,
that comes with passion that's just impossible to fake.
At the very least, I found that I am unable to fake it.
And so, kind of newly invigorated,
I went and I started working on the game in earnest.
And for the large part, it was by myself.
I mean, I'd go and I'd rope in a group
of random playtesters and I'd play with them
and I'd take their feedback and I'd kind of
make some changes and they'd go on their way
and then I'd go and I'd rope up another group
of playtesters and I'd kind of do the same thing,
just rinse and repeat, you know?
And this was very beneficial because in game design,
you have to do frequent play tests.
That's the meat and the bones of game design.
Everything else is just kind of theory crafting, right?
And I'm very fortunate that at Riot,
we have a lot of hardcore board game players
that I could pull from.
But I ultimately look back on this era of the development,
and I see it as one of my biggest mistakes.
See, the thing is,
you know, just by nature of them all being different people,
each play tester had a different idea
of what the eventual game might look like.
You know, so I talked to this group,
and they'd be like, oh yeah,
I think the game wants to be here,
and I'd work towards that,
and then I'd work towards this,
and I'd work towards this and this,
and I ended up with a very scattered design.
And I didn't recognize it at the time.
It wasn't until later in the process that I had a core group of playtesters that I could see the difference.
And I'll get to that in a bit, but for now, just know that eventually,
every design is going to have to withstand the scrutiny of public opinion.
But initially, when you first start working on it,
it's actually very healthy to have a very core group of playtesters that you trust
until you understand what the game wants to be.
So, by around February 2015, I had felt that I had brought the game to about as far as I'd be able to take it.
And I was ready to move into production, and my stakeholders, they were ready for the project to be over.
And so I told them that the design was about locked, right?
But I still had my doubts. I mean, what if it wasn't any good, right?
And so not knowing anyone in the board game industry,
I decided to turn to the two people
that I turn to as a player
when it's time for me to purchase a game.
I talked to Tom Vassil of Dice Tower
and Quentin Smith of Shut Up and Sit Down.
And I reached out to them
and I asked them if they'd be interested
in coming and play testing it
and telling me if I was gonna embarrass myself or not.
And I think both of them were a little bit taken aback.
I mean, Tom had never heard of Riot or League of Legends,
and Quentin was even pretty adamant
that we didn't really need him.
What we needed to do was find a designer.
I told him pretty candidly that I'd already had
a lot of designers come and playtest the game.
I just didn't know if players would like it.
And so he agreed to come take a look.
But Tom came out first, and I remember.
We were so nervous.
He gave us a lot of really insightful things
to do around the game to kind of make it feel more streamlined,
like a first player marker and how to make the turns go
quicker and the like.
And after a long day of playtest,
he was like, guys, I don't know why you're so nervous.
I play a lot of prototypes.
This one's actually pretty far along.
I think you have a game on your hands.
We're like, really?
He was like, yeah.
So we're like, okay, well, thank you very much, Mr. Vassal.
And he went on his way and we were stoked.
Like we were strutting around, you know, doing high fives.
And I remember someone even asked,
like, do we still want Quentin to come out and play it?
You know, now that we have Tom Vassal's approval.
And I was like, well, yeah.
Cause I'd never been, you know, more confident in the game.
And you know, his flights were already booked
and I really wanted to meet him.
I'm a fan of his work.
So Quentin came out and played it a couple of weeks later
and,
And he was less enthusiastic.
I mean, he said he liked it, but he
wasn't sure why he would get it to the table,
again, when it compared to everything else
in his collection, which wasn't what we wanted to hear.
And then he started talking about mice and mystics
and dissent and imperial assault and a campaign, where
you would kind of take this core.
where the game could evolve with scenarios where you would take the core programming thing like Stone's Thing
and build something on top of it with missions and hazards and a narrative
and you could just tell that as he was describing it you could look around the room
and see in the eyes of everyone that the game he was describing
was just so much better than the game we had made
and in that moment with everyone else listening wistfully to that beautiful British accent
the full situation kind of dawned on me.
to make the game the way that Quentin was describing,
I would basically have to design 10 games instead of one.
That's a lot more games.
Remember, my stakeholders, they think I'm almost finished.
So I went back to my mentor
and I kind of told him what I'd learned
and what I wanted to do and what I was afraid to do.
And he was like, look, if you believe in it,
then make your case to your stakeholders.
And I was like, well.
Look, it's already been a year and a half.
If I go to the CEO and I tell him I want to reboot the design,
he'll probably just cancel the project.
And he was like, possibly, maybe even probably.
But Chris, what's the alternative?
Do you really want to make a game that you yourself
don't believe in?
So I updated my LinkedIn profile,
and I went back to my stakeholders,
and I told them I wanted to reboot the design.
that I wanted to do missions and a campaign
and 10 different missions and a story
that would kind of evolve.
And I just kind of laid out my vision for the project
just kind of as articulately as I knew how.
Just pretty confident that they were just
gonna cancel the project.
And well, they didn't.
And I guess in retrospect,
I suspect they saw something in me
that maybe I wasn't looking for at the time.
See, I look in the mirror and I see my failures,
but they look past my lack of experience
and saw someone that really thought
that this was the best way that we could go forward,
that this was how we could best provide value to our players.
So they took a look at my prototype pieces
and my prototype art for my prototype game
and we're like, okay, hurry please, but okay.
So I hurried.
And it was pretty clear to me that if I was going to get this designed in time, I needed more design help.
So I brought in Rick Ernst, who ended up becoming the lead designer on MDM.
And the two of us worked together to kind of create a series of scenarios,
and mapped out kind of the arc of the story and the campaign.
And then Rick came up with the idea of a damage deck,
and communally drafting the command card, since we decided to go fully cooperative.
And the two of us just focused on these daily iterations,
this kind of rapid iteration.
Don't be afraid to fail, but do it fast.
We needed more playtesters,
so we brought in both Nathan Tyrus and Prashant Saraswat,
and the four of us became this core playtest group.
And if I could offer one piece of advice
to people who are in the middle
of playtesting their own games right now,
it's to do targeted playtests.
That's when, at the very beginning of a playtest,
you write down what it is you want to focus on
for that playtest, and it can be anything.
It could be game length or tension
or a new mechanic that you've introduced.
But have a very clear focus for that playtest,
and then, at the end of the playtest,
revisit it and see what you've learned.
It sounds like such a subtle shift, and it felt like one,
but what ended up happening, coming out of it,
was that instead of us talking kind of
empathetically about like, ah, this felt bad,
or this felt bad, we started talking much more strategically
around the direction of the game
and kind of where it was heading.
And the game started kind of driving
toward this single coherent vision.
Both Nathan and Prashant kind of joined us
from a background in QA.
And they brought with them this,
like years of practice over at League
on how to properly playtest a game.
And it was like night and day compared to the wandering around in the desert that I did by myself.
So, just keep that in mind.
Eventually, you do want to be able to open it up, but...
I don't think that's the only example of Riot leveraging our...
or video game making know-how and applying it to the
tabletop space.
I think another good example of that is that we decided to
publish the game ourselves.
And I'll tell you firsthand that dealing with the nightmare
that is global logistics is not the easiest way to do it.
But at this point, we're just kind of used to figuring it
out as we went.
And we got some benefits from this approach that I think you
see us leveraging in both League of Legends and MDM.
For one, it allows us to talk candidly with our players.
A lot of times when a designer gives a game to a publisher,
it's the publisher that controls the messaging of the game.
So sometimes a designer, oftentimes even a really big
name designer, isn't encouraged to kind of talk
candidly about what they've learned in their process or
even answer basic rules questions.
Well, Riot, being both a publisher and a distributor,
has taken a different
approach over the years with League, and I was eager to kind of apply those learnings
to this new space. And to be clear, that's not unique to us. A lot of the most successful
Kickstarter games out there really leverage community engagement in very inventive and
creative ways. Another benefit that we got from self-publishing was that we had greater
control over the quality that we were going to be able to provide to players.
You know, a somewhat prevailing misconception was that
Max Trust Minions was just made at a loss,
which isn't true.
We actually make a very similar profit margin, I assume,
as other board game publishers.
But the difference is, we just took all of the money
that is typically allotted to distribution
and licensing out an IP and the retail markup,
and we poured all of that back in
to making higher quality game components.
So we opted to paint the pieces
and look for opportunities to kind of push the envelope
a few places in that way.
Because at this point, we didn't just wanna make a game,
we wanted to make an experience.
I remember, when I first started on the project,
I watched a YouTube video of Rob Davio
as he was giving a talk right after he'd launched
Risk Legacy, and in the talk, he talked about,
that's him in the corner there,
and in the talk he talked about,
how they had done skin conductivity tests
on a group of board game players over at MIT.
And what they found was that board game players
are the most excited when they play a board game
when they sit down to open the box.
And then they go to learn the rules,
and that's where fun goes to die.
And to be clear, I stole that joke, beat for beat,
from Rob Davio's Risk Legacy presentation years ago.
And so I thought on that,
and I recognize how absurd this sounds,
but I...
I just thought of all the boxes in my life that I really enjoyed opening.
And the touchstone that I landed on was that moment when you first open up an iPhone.
Every piece is kind of thoughtfully engineered in its own specific place.
And for me, it created this moment of ceremony and attention to detail.
Because if Apple cares so much about getting these arguably trivial details perfect,
then it kind of conveys a sense of craftsmanship, of artisanship
that carries over to the final product, long after you've forgotten about the packaging.
And for me, that made even more sense to get it right on a board game,
because in a board game, you keep the packaging, you know?
You don't throw it out, you have to engage with it each time you interact with the product.
And so, just standing on the shoulders of giants here,
I leveraged Rob Davio's learnings
and I brought it over to Noah Adelman over at Game Trays.
And the two of us came up with this idea
to create a series of trays that would really maximize
that first moment of engagement.
It's an interesting thing,
because you could really tell that the team
was really starting to see the game take shape.
like we'd say, like our mantra,
we'll probably never be able to make a game like this again,
so let's just make the best game that we can in this moment.
And we pushed ourselves,
and after hours and hours of playtests
and banging our head against the wall
and squashing minions,
we landed with a game that we were excited
to show the rest of the world.
And then, on October 13th, 2016,
at 11 a.m. Pacific Standard Time, we launched the game.
Not sure if anyone in the world would care that some video game
company had decided to make a board game completely in-house.
And so that's the story.
That's the three-year timeline that I
went on to get this game made.
It amounts to me surrounding myself
with far more talented people.
And I guess it ends with me getting up here to speak
to you guys on their behalf.
It's an odd thing.
After we ship the game, there.
there seemed to be a common sentiment that like,
oh yeah, of course, Riot can make a high quality board game.
They probably had like a billion people working on it.
And the truth is,
there was really just this handful of people.
And each of these people, myself included,
were all fully dedicated to other projects
while we were working on it.
And with the exception of Chris Matthew over at Panda
and Noah, a lot of us had practically
no board game development experience between all of us.
It just kind of hit on a theme here.
what we lacked in experience we try to make up for in passion.
But I don't feel like I've really answered my main question.
Why did Riot decide to make a board game?
Was it because we wanted to actualize the potential
of an untapped market in the League of Legends or hobbyist board game mind space?
No. Did we want to optimize our user
acquisition and minimize churn by leveraging unconventional
retention stratagems?
No, that wasn't it either.
I think the truth is we just,
we wanted to make a game that we thought
our players would like.
You know, for the same reason that Stone would come home
after a long day of working at the office,
making games, and sit down and create something
for his family, we wanted to make a game
that we thought our players might like.
And I guess for me personally, I wanted to make something
that one day I could play with my daughters.
I'd like to end with this quote from one of my favorite storytellers.
It's actually very similar to something I heard Mark and Brandon, the founders of Riot, talk about
when they first started, you know, thinking about the idea of Riot and League of Legends
and talking to various angel investors.
And at the time, kind of the general sentiment was that PC games were dead.
Facebook games, those were the future.
If you want to turn this League of Legends thing into a Facebook game,
then we'll invest in your company.
Like the general sentiment was go broad instead of go deep.
But Mark and Brandon, they really believed in this market
in large part because they were a part of it.
They were a part of the small niche
Warcraft III mod community.
And they'd landed on a game that excited them.
And that mattered more.
You know, reaching this handful of people
in a very passionate way, that mattered more.
You know, these days.
League of Legends has like a hundred million players every month and
and even a very successful board game might only sell 15,000 units and it's entire lifetime.
So if our real goal was just to reach as many people as we could,
we probably would have been a lot better off not making a board game
or if we made a board game just like leveraging our IP to kind of
get something that had broader public appeal like League of Legends Monopoly.
But going broad was never our goal.
It was so much more important to us to really resonate
in a core way with a handful of people
than it was to reach a broader audience
in a less impactful way.
Look, I knew that, I know that Next First Minions
is not a game for everybody, and I'm okay with that.
But when I was making it, I thought of this imaginary
person that I hoped would be out there,
that when they got it, they would be as passionate
about it as we were when we were making it.
And so I'd like to end with this.
Each of us in this room have only a finite number
of projects that we'll ever be able to work on.
So if you take nothing else from this talk,
I implore you, take this.
Use your finite time to make something
that you are proud of, that pushes you,
that you can pour your heart into
and swing for the fences and it terrifies you
just a little bit, pushing you outside your comfort zone.
Look, I don't know if that will ultimately lead to a game that everyone wants to play or not,
but I do know that that game, that's a game that I'd want to play.
Thanks.
And I think we have about four minutes.
I'm close to time, but if anyone wants to talk, then I can answer questions now,
or we can go out and do it in the break-in room.
All right then.
I think they want you to talk into a microphone.
Or if you say it, then I'll just repeat the question.
I can make that work.
I just had a random question, because no one else was
raising their hand.
What is your favorite League of Legends champion?
What is my favorite League of Legends champion?
My favorite League of Legends champion is probably Soraka.
You like bananas a lot?
I do.
I played her since beta as a mid and a top.
like pretty pretty aggressive i played kind of an unconventional way of doing it
i'm gonna go with this guy just because he's at the microphone but if if you
want to go to the mic then i'll
Hi, great talk. I'm curious, you mentioned that you know you
tried pulling in random people for playtests. And you felt like
you learned less from them than when you had a dedicated group
of playtesters. And to me, that's that's really interesting
is it seems to be like backwards from what I know from video
games, which is like, oh, yeah, you want to bring in new people
because they don't have exposure and that they're going to be
seeing things for the first time. Yeah, curious, what was
what did you find that you got from the dedicated playtest
group that you didn't get from brand new people?
So I think over the trajectory of a game's development life
cycle, you definitely want to get to a point
where you want to get it to as many eyes as you can.
So that's not untrue.
But I think the point I was trying to make
is that if you do that too early in the process,
you end up creating a lot of different types of games.
And it's not very.
For me, I felt like it wasn't a very cohesive vision.
And I've seen that elsewhere in Riot.
We tried to kind of compartmentalize the R&D efforts or whatnot.
Thank you.
Hello there.
Hi.
First of all, as a League of Legends player, I do care.
So, thank you.
Second of all, in the League of Legends community,
I was talking with people as Mechs vs. Minions was announced and it came out.
Sorry, got a cold.
One of the prevailing things I saw was there were a bunch of people going,
oh wow, this is so incredible, and then other people were going, ugh, yordles.
Um, have you...
Well, it comes back to your thing, it's going to be the game that people want.
But, um, I know you said that we're probably never going to do something like this again.
Have you ever considered doing something like this again or expanding it?
I know you just said no, but...
We're not currently working on any other board games right now.
I think, you know, never say never, we're always listening to our players.
You know, if there's a sentiment that there's a community for this,
then I think that's something that Riot tends to listen to their players on.
And as far as the Ortals go, it's funny because
when I first originally kind of came up with pairing the game,
one of the things that I found was that...
we use like Oriana and Blitzcrank and some of our more sentient robots
from League in the game.
And it felt very frustrating when like Blitzcrank would run into a wall
whereas
like when we moved it to Yordles it felt silly and whimsical and it kind of
created this moment of
laughter as opposed to just frustration.
And I thought that the Yordles really kind of
helped convey that a bit.
Was it always cooperative?
No, no.
Did you want to do that to kind of balance the universe?
No, we started with a competitive game
and we switched to cooperative in part
because I found that the game could be very
spiky when it was competitive.
Like if someone drafted the cards that you really wanted.
or if they got cards that really helped make their,
it was like the cards that were dictating
success or failure.
And as soon as we made it collaborative,
then it was kind of a point of tension.
Like, oh, I really need this.
Oh, I need this too.
That's fine, you take it.
I'll figure something else out.
And it kind of created a really neat
kind of cooperative engagement.
I personally really like cooperative games and board games
because
Like in league, there are like millions of players
that are playing at any one time,
so if I want to get on and I want to play
like a game that's kind of balanced,
we have matchmaking to do that.
But you know, if I sit down with like my wife
or if I sit down with like, you know, my grandparents,
like there's a wide range of people
where like if you and I were sitting down
and playing chess right now,
and you were like, and you just crush me,
I'd be like, oh, well, do you want to play again?
You'd be like, sure, and then you'd just crush me again.
And I'd be like, oh.
What do you want to play again?
And you'd be like, well, not really.
And I'd be like, yeah, me neither.
And I think with matchmaking, you kind of avoid that.
And in cooperative games, instead of having a friend
who's much more talented than you,
at the game, it actually becomes a benefit
as opposed to kind of a detriment.
And so those were some of the thoughts on my work.
As a follow-up, did you guys kind of consider this to be?
detriment to the league player base because they're obviously very competitive and just that alone would did like
No, and the reason why is league is a competitive game, but league is also a cooperative game
You know like in order to really succeed at League
You need to get good at teamwork and kind of working with your teammates
And that's that's an element of that game too, so if we made a competitive game like that's that's an aspect of it
But you know so is so is cooperation. Thank you. Yeah, no no worries
Do you think the relationship with Riot and League has helped sales of the game somewhat?
And can we assume the fact that you're saying you'll probably never do something like this again mean that it's...
Hasn't taken right by storm, or is it just pocket money compared to league so I didn't hear the second question. I'm sorry
Can we assume the fact you?
You said you were probably never going to do something like this again, right?
Can we take that to mean that it hasn't taken right by storm and therefore you?
III think I think riot is very proud of the game
I think we're just always looking at the next hill
and trying to find the next thing that kind of pushes us.
And that's more the sentiment right now.
But you know, I loved working on this project
and the idea of making more games in this fashion
is very appealing to me.
So we'll see where it lands.
As a lover of board games that are cooperative,
I encounter a lot of issues with kind of alpha gaming
and stuff like that that we all kind of know about.
What are some things you did to avoid those in your game?
The timer, the timer was a really big,
actually for the longest time,
if we knew that we were going to do a cooperative game,
the one thing, the only thing that we had to solve
was quarterbacking.
It was like a really prominent thing
in the back of all of our minds,
because we see it as kind of a,
a problem with the space right now, I guess.
And I was really driving on like really,
like I went with like the Hanabi route,
where you like, you can't show stuff.
And like we've thought of all these really kind of,
just detrimental ways to kind of remove the ability
for someone to have quarterbacking in that agency.
But what we ended up doing, and Rick talked me out of this,
he was spot on, he was like,
let's just for like a week or two
not worry about quarterbacking
and look to add more collaboration,
more opportunities for.
for you want to engage with your teammates.
And that actually made for a much more fun experience.
So in solving that problem,
I actually made the game much, much worse,
and I'm glad that he came in to kind of
right the ship there.
But I do think that the timer,
and also maybe the complexity of the individual puzzle
for each player,
kind of makes that difficult to be,
to feel like you are the, you know,
the aficionado on every other person's thing.
Because the decision space there is pretty rich.
Cool, and as a last one, with Hanabi being a great game,
what are other inspirational games for you, cooperative?
What, what?
Other favorite cooperative board games.
Oh, gosh, there's a long list.
Pandemic Legacy, I think, is huge.
Robinson Crusoe, Hanabi, I could go on and on.
It's such a rich space.
All right, thank you guys very much.
It was a blast, thanks.