Welcome, welcome. I'm Aaron Thibault. If you're in the right place, I want to make sure. I'm VP of product development and an executive producer at Gearbox Software.
I oversee the Borderlands franchise. I also oversee all development. Essentially GM of the studio, everyone that's making games reports up to me.
My boss is Randy Pitchford, CEO of the studio and founder.
My second boss is Stephen Ball, CFO, another founder.
the two owners of the studio who are still in and making games
at Gearbox. And my third boss is the studio.
I make sure that I fulfill whatever they need first and foremost.
I also teach, I'm a professor at Baylor University, where I teach capstone and engineering.
I like working with, kind of, in that context, really small teams of students.
I have seven this semester, which is different from the close to 300 I have internally at Gearbox,
plus, you know, all the external.
people that we have close relationships with at Gearbox.
So it's kind of refreshing to do that.
And today I'm doing a little bit different format
from what I've done in past years, if you've ever heard me talk before.
Usually I rely heavily on memes and pictures
and go more for entertainment value
and giving you food you didn't ask for.
This year what I want to do more is actually cut through the bullshit a bit
and get more into what...
we're looking for anyway and what people I talk to you in
production around the industry are looking for in their
producers.
And how to move crawl, walk, run style from getting your
foot in, which many of you probably already have.
Quick survey, who in here already is a producer in some
kind of production capacity of Studio?
Awesome.
And who here is looking to go that route or making a lateral
move or something like that?
Cool.
Students? Students? A few? Wow.
I'm, I'm, first of all, I'm flattered that so many of you
who are already producers in the industry
decided to come to this talk when there are so many
other cool sounding talks out there.
And congrats to those of you who are,
students who are looking to get into the industry,
seeking out, you know, opportunities like this
to, to hear a little bit from people
who have been doing it a while.
I've been in games now going on 20 years.
I was in music before that.
I was in rap promotions and production.
I may give a couple stories there.
And I started at Origin Systems when we were coming out
of the beta on Ultima Online.
97, when I started day one out of music, was as an audio
intern.
And about three weeks later, I started helping direct cinematics.
Was there a question? Was there a...
I heard something in the corner of my eye or corner of my ear.
And we moved from there into doing some help third-party style
with other studios around the EA system.
Got to do things like go up to Dallas
and work with the American McGee's Alice team.
and work with James Combat Simulations
where Andy Hollis had his group at Origin.
We've got actually a couple of other old school Origin people
in the audience right now that I can see.
So thanks for being here.
So really for me what it boils down to is, as a producer,
what I'm trying to do all the time is to imagine the very,
very best possible outcome that I can and do everything
in my power to go after it.
And it doesn't matter where you are in the organization.
If you are just getting your foot in the door,
if you're the EP on a project, if you're a dev director.
It really doesn't matter.
I hope is your goal all the time.
You want to help your team achieve the
best possible success.
You're not just trying to kind of cover your ass or do the
one thing that you got hired to do or make sure that your
next performance review, whatever your KPIs or metrics
are for the thing that you're going to be evaluated on, that
you're just focused on that.
Really, the bigger goal is entertaining our customers.
and finding ways to manifest the best possible things.
That's what makes this really not just a tolerable thing
to do for me, but something that I'm passionate about.
And I know that there are many others who
are passionate about production as well.
However, we don't really have this kind
of discipline of production.
There aren't that many schools outside of management
that really discuss what you do as a producer or a dev director.
It's something that most of us have just gained experience from being on the ground doing it.
And many of us came from other disciplines as well.
So these are just my opinions, right?
These are just things that I've seen in my experience
and anecdotes from friends of mine who are in the industry.
But what I want is to give you work to do.
So hopefully you brought pen and paper, or we'll get access
to this later.
Because actually what I want is for all of you to, as we're
going through this presentation, think of what
examples you would use to describe the things that we're
going to talk about, what pictures that you would use to
quickly send a message about those things, and how you
would do this presentation yourself.
I'd love all of you, when you get home, to create this
presentation for yourselves and do it.
So steal it and do something cool with it.
We're going to start out, before we get into how do you
do the best possible, most awesome job as a producer, EP
in the industry.
And really, we're going to stop a little
short of the EP side.
We're not going to go deep into business.
I know some of that was already talked about this
morning, about the economics of the industry.
I think in an hour we don't really have time to go fully into the executive producer side of things,
but I'll give probably a few examples and if you have any questions when we have time, please ask them.
So coaching, opportunities for improvement.
What I've done is I've pulled some actual coaching
statements from performance reviews
that I've given over the last eight, nine years at Gearbox,
and thinking about some of the coaching moments
that I've had before Gearbox, to start with some mistakes
that we see with junior producers,
and with all producers.
So the first one is, and I drive this one home all the time,
please don't be afraid to say that you don't know something.
Because it's the, when you never say you don't know,
if you are working with a team,
and you find yourself constantly feeling the need
to answer questions as though you really know the answer,
and you don't, you erode trust with the team.
And when what you should be doing
is everything you can to build trust,
because you need to use that credibility,
you might have to cash it in later.
And so the economics of credibility and trust
are way more important than being the person who always has the answer.
It's cool if you have the answer,
but it's better if you, like everyone else,
are showing that you're just a human in the team.
Some mistakes junior producers make have to do with opinions.
The first one is, which may be a surprise to some of you,
I feel a lot of...
A lot of people in production roles in the industry feel they shouldn't give their opinion,
even if they feel they have a valid backing, basis for their opinion.
They don't speak up about it.
I think this stems from, and from those I've talked to when I've coached them,
it stems from feeling not empowered.
So if you are in a role where you don't feel empowered to speak up about things
that maybe you don't think are just in your purview,
I think that you should address that with your lead
or maybe just by revisiting who you are
and what you're doing in your role in the industry.
I remember a time, actually when I was at Origin,
and we were working on Ultima Online 2.
And I felt like messaging, there wasn't enough information
going around the studio about what was
happening with the title.
And I felt like there wasn't enough leadership on that
project amongst all the leads.
There's some people who are awesome, especially the vision
of what the project was going to be.
But when the rubber really hit the road, from my
perspective anyway, I wasn't getting enough information.
And I wished, in retrospect, after that project was shut
down, that I had gone to that senior producer and had a talk
with him.
He quickly left to go run another studio.
But I realized later why my boss, who was the head of the
we were in this team called the Rave Group, stood for
radical audiovisual experience.
We were responsible for cinematics and storytelling
and did technical animation and art.
and all the audio for our games.
Why he stuck a potato in that person's monitor
and left it there for four months,
not realizing that guy was on the way out the door.
It was kind of his passive aggressive stance
to speaking up when he didn't feel empowered.
I understood what that was later.
It was funny at the time that there was a potato
in the guy's monitor, though.
So don't be the person who puts a potato in a monitor,
is my point.
This one is the more common one that you hear.
Offering an opinion when unqualified.
Look, here's the thing.
If you're in a team, if you're in a bigger team especially,
and that team has hired designers
to come into design roles on your team,
please don't usurp the authority and responsibility
of those designers on your teams
by constantly offering design opinions.
I love that you have design opinions,
if you have them and you're offering them.
just make sure that you're helping the team use their time most wisely
and boosting the cred of the people around you
by giving them the responsibility of having and pushing forward those opinions.
I actually, every year, I have at least one moment
where I have to coach a new producer on this one.
and then not asking other so this is goes hand in hand obviously with not
you know kind of not speaking up or not feeling empowered but not not asking
others for their opinion not asking enough questions not being curious
enough what I'm looking for.
really, especially with newer producers or people who are really curious.
It becomes very helpful when you are uncovering the unknowns in your designs
to have curious people around you, especially producers who are responsible
for understanding the scope of work that is being proposed.
And so when you don't ask a lot of questions,
and people for their opinions about the validity of things,
the goodness of things, how deep problems are
going to be in things, then you're not helping your team
as much as you could.
Self-control.
Once in a while, and this goes for all team members,
but it really hurts me when I see it
from someone who's in production.
your team's looking to you to be a leader,
to be someone who sets the tone for adult behavior
and professionalism in the team, usually.
We want that of all members of our teams.
you know, my discipline now is in production,
so I can't control, per se,
or give that same message to all other disciplines.
I'll say, if you're in production,
I'm hoping that you are consciously
practicing self-control.
There's a lot of ways to do that.
We're not going to go into kind of all methods
for all things here.
I will ask you that you practice this.
is an obvious one. However, a lot of times we see information being disseminated through
electronic means that needs to be given face to face. Any time you coach somebody, I hope
that is face to face. Never coach anybody over email or on a phone call.
It can wait, unless it's disastrous, it can wait until you're face-to-face.
Also, great news is best delivered face-to-face.
It's way more impactful and you can also use it as a moment to coach in a positive direction,
not just away from a negative direction.
There's kind of damned if you do, damned if you don't things.
There are a lot of these gotchas.
So rather than say it's a failure
to make a decision before you have all the information.
I could have said that.
But instead what I'll say is that the failure is not
recognizing what the best alternative is.
You have to make decisions within complete information.
It's part of your job.
You're going to try to uncover all the information you can.
But really, you're going to have to make a lot of decisions
with incomplete information.
So you might favor making a decision
towards something that you can easily recover from.
That's always a good direction to go if you have the time to recover.
Taking too long to make a decision, well, there are some that can stand to wait.
There are some things that are painful to make bad decisions with, whether it's hiring
the wrong person or making some feature decision to do a back-of-the-box check.
on, you know, for your product as opposed to ensuring that your team can really deliver
on that thing that you're discussing. So make sure that you're weighing the pros
and cons across, across competitive decisions. So along the same lines of, you know, the
professionalism that we were talking about before.
The baseline that you set is really important, and you have
to be intentional about it.
You can't just be, hey, it's just me, and I'm on the team,
and people have to accept me for who I am.
Fuck that as a producer.
I want you to be who you are, and I want you to be
comfortable in your own skin.
But you are establishing a baseline.
And everything that you do that deviates away from that
baseline is going to be hugely impactful, especially as your
teams grow.
So you have to be intentional about what that baseline is.
If you come in and you kind of have this schizo behavior
because you're passionate about a lot of things
and you're all over the map.
OK, you might be passionate and you'll be around as, say,
assistant or associate producer for a while,
but you're not going to be in a leadership capacity
with that sort of behavior.
And I don't see anybody in here who strikes me that way.
But I've seen it and had to coach people out
of companies I've been at as a result of it.
Where they're baseline in is really important,
and you have to be reliable in that way.
Now here's the thing, though.
Because you've established this baseline,
then you can be intentional about when you use emotion.
There are times when I want to see you use maybe a lot of emotion
in order to be super impactful on the things that really matter for your teams.
You guys know about Maslow's hierarchy of needs?
Yeah, you've heard about this a lot of times.
You've probably heard other talks about it, studied it in school, whatever.
It's funny how often this really, truly comes up in a studio environment.
Whether it's something as simple as food, or the AC isn't working.
the heater's not working, whatever it is, you have to decide how you're going to escalate
your response to things that actually directly impact that foundation of what people need.
Once you've established a calm baseline, when you see things that might impact your team
physiologically, psychologically, things that impact their safety, if you hear about, hey,
cars are getting broken into in the parking lot, and
You know, you're in an environment where
you might have street lamps that are going out, whatever.
You have to be the one to care about the team enough
to escalate in a way that others understand
how much of a problem those things are.
And as a producer, this is really squarely in line
with the things you have to care about.
So...
Professionalism, you know, we're in games.
I understand we're not in a corporate environment.
It's cool, but I'll say, I'll give another origin example.
We had this stupid, terrible thing we used to do, which was
a mandatory happy hour.
And it started when the company was small, and it
continued when the company got big.
And I saw two different marriages get wrecked over the
fact that we had this forced socialized thing happening.
You have to be really, really mindful of how long do you
want to be in the industry and what kind of reputation do you
want to have and leave behind.
So things like dating co-workers, again, whatever.
Whatever your company policy is.
It's cool.
Keep in mind though once you start having those relationships grow in the
office environment through the stress that you're probably going to experience
on the kind of projects that we see all across the industry these days,
you know, that can really impact
things in the game and in your life and I don't want you to go through the kind
of things that I saw in those
days that we had 20 years ago.
It's not okay to say offensive things.
Like, it's not OK to, like, I don't want us to have to be too PC in the industry.
I curse a lot.
I use a lot of references that people would, you know, that I wouldn't use maybe at home
with my mom or, you know, or with my family at home.
At the same time, though, you have to be really aware of who your coworkers are, and you want
to boost them up and make them feel great.
Likewise, I also want you to keep in mind,
and I'll only stay on this one for a second,
that
When you're, this is especially for junior,
really new producers, because you'll wash yourself of this
if you're gonna stay in the industry at all,
is that, and anything that you bring
into the office environment, first of all,
you wanna keep any stress and negativity you're having
from things happening in your personal life,
leave that outside the doors before you get
into your studio or with your team.
Beyond that, most of the people on your team
don't really wanna hear about whatever's going on
in your personal life, whatever your drama is.
But you should use whatever strength you can draw from your personal life, whatever experiences
you've had there.
Talk about those.
Talk about the positive things that might be good examples for the team to know why
they should believe in you and why you have strength and what you bring to them.
This is one that I, ah man, probably two or three times a year I have to coach somebody
in this one.
Too much importance put on titles, on using somebody's new title or role or promotion
as a way to get what they want or enforce something or feel like now they have, they're
supposed to enforce more of what they want onto the team.
Maybe you move into a role like a producer at EA.
Some of you might be here in that particular role
where you do have some design
or quality responsibility for the title,
and so cool, that's your job.
But I see whether it's at Gearbox
or with teams that we're working with in other studios,
this happened a lot.
So we try to have a more flat meritocracy-style culture
in our studio where titles don't mean as much.
And...
I have one guy who decided that he wanted his title to be a minister of art.
I said, what the fuck is a minister of art?
He said, all I really want to do is help us hire the best people,
and I think that having that title makes me feel good about doing it.
All right, cool.
I'm going to call you an HR advisor,
and you can tell other people you are whatever you want.
But this can get in the way of good feelings between team
members when titles start to matter too much.
You guys know that.
Something that I mentioned earlier is this sort of
currency in economics of credibility.
Once you start spending your credibility.
You have to build it up again before you can start spending it again.
And these tend to be on decisions where there's no clear answer, but you have an agenda behind
the thing that you want, and so you're willing to spend that credibility that you have.
And you have to be very careful about how and when you spend it, especially if it's
something where others are pulling you to spend it on their behalf.
You can get yourself in a situation very quickly where you've spent it all.
It's like, you know, like you're spending it on a credit card.
So, the way to combat that is make sure that your decisions are yours.
That you really, really truly believe in the things that you want and that you're willing
to go to bat for.
This is really common, and this is something that as you grow as leaders, I want you to
think about a lot.
You have to see yourself as a leader.
It can be very difficult for us to see ourselves in that way.
a lot of us in the industry stay in the industry
or got into it because we didn't want to be
an executive manager at a company
or go down some other path that felt maybe more corporate
or whatever to us, right?
So I want you to see yourself as a leader.
That is part of your discipline in production
and then practice things towards that.
We'll get to that in a second.
I'll only be on this one for a second.
About two months ago, I had, this is actually,
trying to be too cool was a line in somebody's review.
It wasn't a review that I gave,
it was a review somebody else gave.
I won't tell you which of these three things was the issue,
but it was a new person who just really wanted to fit in,
and I hope you don't find yourself
in any of these situations.
Don't be that person, though.
You won't last long.
So this is a big problem that I'm frustrated that I have
coached someone for a couple years now who, in every other
aspect of what they do, is great.
But this is one that keeps coming up time and again,
which is you might be someone who's terrific at
getting along with the team,
you know, working through tasks in JIRA,
whatever task management system you use.
Like, you're really competent and capable
in a lot of areas,
but the little things keep falling through the cracks.
And this is the one that will absolutely prevent you, well at least if you're working with
me, but this is one that will absolutely prevent you from being promoted.
You can go from foot in the door, assistant, associate producer.
But to move from associate producer to a full project producer, this won't fly.
And once you've shown that you have a penchance for letting things fall through the cracks,
it's going to take a couple of shipping cycles.
or if you're in a live environment,
whatever your live cycles are,
it's going to take a few of those
to gain back the credibility that you need
to be able to get yourself in a position
to have that promotion again,
or for others to see you as someone
who can be in that kind of role of responsibility.
make sure, especially if you're told at some point that something got by you, that you
don't let any of those details get by. All of these are very important kinds of things
that have actually happened recently with me.
How many of us get frustrated about being in meetings where people just always seem
to take notes and nothing happens with those notes? Am I the only one?
Yeah.
So to move this from a negative thought
into more positive thoughts, I hope
everybody is turning everything that's happening in meetings
into actionable items.
You have to measure those, because people only
do the things that they're measured in.
Over time, if we feel like the thing we're doing is of no use,
because it's not being measured, nobody remembers that I actually
turned that stuff in that meeting into action items,
then I can easily fall back into the trap of just sitting there
scrawling crap on a piece of paper.
So if you have people working for you who are note-takers
in meetings, or if you're the note-taker, designated
note-taker, whatever, make sure that others know you're
constantly following up.
This one kills me.
Meetings with topics but no agendas.
It goes hand in hand with not having action items and
follow-up.
Just fix your meetings.
There's a lot of thinking out there about how meetings
should be held.
But just fix your meetings if you're having
these kind of issues.
Dear God, please.
And in fact, I'll give a quick note about that last one.
I wanted to train my production staff at the studio.
I now have, I probably have 25 or so producers at my round
table, maybe 30.
I wanted to train them that my expectation of producers at
Gearbox is for them to be responsible as a peer group to
solve their problems before they ever get to me or anybody
else who is going to have to then sort out
noise from the signal.
And.
To train them in that, when I began assembling this new group of producers, I told them first,
because I like to use dramatic language to convey simple points, I hate meetings.
So never call me to a meeting unless there's a great expected value to come out of it,
and only if it's almost a last resort because something couldn't get worked out between yourselves first.
And the outcome of that approach, of course,
I also gave examples of how I wanted these meetings
to be conducted to get those results,
was the most junior producer, one of,
one of the more junior producers in our studio,
now runs these producer roundtable meetings
where all the important stuff that has to get sorted out
between producers happens at these roundtables.
No executive managers, no executive producers
go to these meetings, that's by design.
And I've had requests from other executives, hey, can I go to these meetings, hear more
about what's happening?
Well, no, because if you do that, they're not going to have the discussion they need
between them.
So what I want is I want that healthy peer community to be established in a studio, especially
at our size and bigger.
I mean, we're small compared to maybe what if any of you are from, say, Ubisoft Montreal
or any of the larger studios.
But even so.
there has to be a healthy community of practice amongst producers.
You can't do that when everybody's just working in their silo.
On Borderlands 2, Sean Reardon, who's the senior producer on the project and I sat down
and we were trying to figure out, because there were some things happening around the schedule,
as always happens on any project.
What's the formula?
Actually, we started this discussion way back early in Borderlands 1 even.
What's the formula for quality?
What we care about is quality, and we're a meritocracy, and we need to create a compelling
argument about why we need to get more time for something.
How do we do that?
Well, quality results from focus and time.
We need to use these words and then turn them into something actionable as a studio for
how we organize ourselves.
Quick thing I'll say there is anything that distracts from
focus is negative.
So if you have people who are spending a lot of time
streaming, if you're doing that, if taking a lot of smoke
breaks, whatever, while that might not feel like a big deal
on a day-to-day basis, you're creating a lot of debt over
time that has to be paid.
And that's something that you have to reinforce with a
message with your team all the time.
You can only do that, first of all, if you are setting a good
example.
Giving a heads up, so the military has this term Werno,
a warning order.
It's, hey, I'm about to tell you something's going to
happen, here's the thing I'm going to tell you, and then
the actual order comes later.
And you have to remind people all the time that.
there was a discussion about something that might require
them to do work, they have to be prepared to do that work.
Because if you don't do that, you have situations where,
especially with leads who are really busy, they, I don't
remember that ever being discussed, or I don't remember
that being a thing I had to prepare work for, and I didn't
create that job posting, and I didn't do the spec for that
thing that had to happen.
So you have to keep this cadence of information so that
people remember there's a thing that they're
going to have to do.
By the way, I want to remind you,
I want you to give this talk, or a version of it,
for yourselves when you get home.
And so think about what examples you can use for these.
It's strange, but I think this happens
in a culture where.
performance reviews don't happen regularly,
that we forget part of our job is
to supervise what's happening.
We're not just information handlers.
We actually are responsible for the quality and result
of the product that we're working on.
And so supervision for a junior, and this
is more geared towards junior producers,
while I don't want you to act like you're the boss,
I do want you to remember that you have a responsibility here.
So.
It's an easy one, just don't be negligent.
Well, what happens next when we start to abdicate our
authority in the role that we do have is we might do things
like a very bad job at expectation management.
Now, this ranges across all kinds of things.
And unfortunately, it can become part of our culture if
we're not careful, just the topic of poor expectation
management.
We see it in things like press tours, where we might say
things about products that.
We're correct at one time and then later didn't, we're not so correct.
Or it might become something about what a role is, what we expect of people in their
roles.
It can be something about what the focus of our project is at the time, whether it's time
or quality.
You have to manage your triangle, right?
And the triangle of time, quality.
and money as something that you're responsible for managing,
you have to know which of those is,
there's always something that's a priority, okay?
You can't have everything be the highest priority.
And expectation management is knowing what the priorities are
and clearly communicating those.
And that can be caused,
one of the things is having unchecked assumptions.
And I had to counsel somebody about six months ago,
kind of hand in hand with things getting through the cracks.
not doing a very good job of actually checking information.
So we know that in a communication model,
there's the signal that's transmitted.
Well, if you want to know if communications really happen,
I did a talk on this last year, so let me touch on it here.
You want to make sure that communication was actually
received in the way that you intended it.
And that is your responsibility.
And it's funny to me how often.
where it's easy for us to transmit communication.
We're so willing to transmit communication,
but we do a terrible job at making sure
that that communication actually happened
and that the signal went through
and that the message was heard and is being acted on
in the way that we intended.
So I'm saying it's hard, it's not easy.
Don't distribute your attention too much.
It's easy for us to make too many commitments once.
You can go too far, right?
You can say, I'm going to enable the team to do everything.
And then it's very, very quickly, easily,
something we can fall into as a trap.
We're getting close to wrapping up the failure part of this.
So failure to deal with the producer's dilemma.
This happens all the time.
When you have somebody in a seat and you think, man, if I
coach that person, I only have that one person who can do
that thing, whatever it is.
This might be my cert or platform specialist.
Or hell, it could be the lead designer of the project.
Could be anybody.
When we fall into the trap of having to keep that one person, it could be that one bad seed that spoils the water, that poisons it for everybody.
Poisoning the well, I see less of it these days in the industry, but it sure as hell still happens.
I see a lot more qualified people, and we have grown a lot, which is good, but we still fall into this dilemma.
And as a producer, you have to be kind of at the front lines of dealing with it.
Candor and conflict in the industry, you're not everybody's buddy, right?
You're not here to make friends with everyone.
And your team needs to know that you're going to be straightforward with them.
Because the second that they start feeling that you're full of shit, you've lost your
credibility and your trust.
And they know you're no longer able to be candid with them.
They'll feel that you're trying to politic with them.
When you move from candor to politics, you've lost the team.
And you need to know when that might happen and avoid that danger.
I've worked in environments where there's a lot of politics happening, especially when
I was.
working with the military or back when I was working in music,
there's a lot of politics happening all the time
because there are scarcity in jobs or scarcity in attention.
And once you get yourself into a role
where you can make sure there's a lot of attention you can give to members of your team,
or a lot of jobs that you can provide,
or coaching moments that you can have with them,
you know, you can do away with some of the politics.
But you have to be direct with people,
or else they'll feel that you're full of shit,
and they can't trust you.
And then it's much harder for you to do your job,
and you probably won't be in your job very long.
So this is kind of the complement to that.
That will happen, it can happen if you're not comfortable with being direct with people.
If you have fear, it's okay to be afraid, but you have to practice being candid.
A lot of people have to practice that.
It's not something that's natural to everyone.
So hopefully you're in an environment where you can practice that, but you have to find
opportunities to practice.
Don't ever lie.
So moving from there, that's sort of a crawl walk phase.
I'm going to talk about the things that I think make for
super producers.
Again, not quite at the business EP level.
There's a little bit of that.
But between myself and the senior producers I work with
at Gearbox, and some at the publishers we work with,
here's a few qualities that I'd like to see you all
practice and think about intentionally.
So here's the first one.
You have to be the person now.
Say you're moving from junior producer or mid-level producer
into senior producer.
You're the person responsible for the project for the team,
or you're enabled by your lead to be one of those people.
Bad things have to stop.
And you have to go through a practice.
You should go through a process on a milestone basis,
some regular basis, where you are evaluating.
You might do this as a mid-mortem, a post-mortem,
simply something that you do as an activity with your team
members, your leads.
You have to be constantly identifying things.
Those that need to continue, those that need to stop,
new things that you should start doing,
things that need to be discussed.
Okay, you are gonna come across things that have to stop.
And the only way to break a cycle in a bad culture
or to avoid some pitfall for quality of project,
things that make studios go out of business,
is to make bad stuff stop as quickly as possible.
And it is your responsibility to do that.
The best producers walk around.
I talked about not sending all your messages
through electronic means.
If you have a team, if it's not just a fully distributed team,
I'm saying in the realm of the feasible,
you should be walking around.
Your face should be everywhere.
People should know who you are.
You should know who your dev team members are.
You should know as much as you possibly can about them.
And there are some really tangible reasons for that
and some popular thinking about the walking manager.
One of those is the ability to send that message and rally people around your causes.
You have to be able to use words and convey your words in a way about what your goals are
that gets your team members excited and impelled to do what's needed for your project.
So you have to be the person. You might think it's corny or you didn't come from a background
where this is a thing that you did or you're...
introverted or whatever, you have to practice helping rally people.
Maybe you're not the right one to actually be the rally point and do the hoo-ah moment.
That's fine.
But you need to be part of the solution to get people excited and using their passions.
The best producers show and practice.
The things they want in the macro, they do it in the micro
all the time, every day, in the smallest ways, because it
sends a vibe across your entire team and your studio
about what your expectations are from the smallest to the
largest, it's common themes.
So here are some in that, basically according to that
triangle.
The team's food, again, details.
Clearly communicating every time you branch or have a build.
Don't let those get by you.
People need to be aware of the state of the product.
that loop from intent to QA, depending on how you manage
QA and quality in your studio, this could be a huge thing.
Not just because you want to reduce bugs and defects, but
because your QA team typically is your front line of getting
a broad view of the quality of the state of the next piece of
software that you're releasing.
So this cadence of useful communication, the best
producers maintain that cadence and are
intentional about it.
You don't just, when you have information, send it.
You think about regularly what is the kind of digest?
What are the kinds of information that you can
provide on a regular basis so that you set an expectation
with your team that you are going to
provide them information?
Even if you don't have a lot to say,
provide a little bit on a regular basis
so they know that information's happening
and they'll feel a lot more secure
about decisions being made
that they're not aware of.
The best producers have a strong moral compass.
I don't think I need to say a lot about that.
But maybe it's not obvious to people coming in the industry.
It was interesting to me, this came up a lot
when I was talking with my production friends
about what makes for great producers,
is that your team can rely on you
to make decisions for the right reasons.
And that your team can recover even
if consequences of decisions are negative.
You have to practice what you want.
You have to have a shipping mentality all the time.
And now, again, the industry is really big now.
So we have people in many areas of development where maybe you
don't ship things in the same way that I do,
cross-platform and PC.
Maybe you're, hell, maybe you're shipping every day if
you're in mobile.
So there you definitely have to keep that shipping mentality.
But you also might be doing things
where efficacy is much higher than,
or you might think efficacy for, say,
if you're doing an educational game or something,
is higher than pure entertainment value.
And so your mentality is more around efficacy.
That's fine, but we're making games still.
So we want to make fun things that
are going to get out there.
When you don't include the team.
in decisions about the thing they're making,
then they're not bought in, and then they're out.
A lot of people see it as binary.
A lot of developers, they're passionate,
and they're going to see it as a binary decision.
They're either in or they're out.
You've got to keep them in.
And the way you keep them in is by keeping them engaged.
Best producers are playing games.
Hopefully you're playing games with your teams.
It's a great team building exercise if you're playing
cooperative games.
Competitive's cool too, but if you're playing co-op games
with hard missions, then those are great team building
moments, also shows you're a gamer, you're buying those
cred points.
So producer, a lot of people who are not in production.
A lot of us who are in production think of the producer as a scheduler.
I think of the scheduler as the project manager.
I think of project management as part of what producers do.
We've created titles for people who spend more time in scheduling than in other areas
of production.
But if you want to be a great producer, you better be awesome at scheduling.
You can go other directions in production that aren't as scheduling focused.
When somebody in finance, say, asks you,
are you going to hit this milestone?
And you, I wouldn't say lie, but you make a reach statement
and say yes without actually knowing
what the state of the project as compared to your schedule is,
then you're putting yourself in a dangerous situation.
What I prefer is people to come from a background of having to work with creative departments
and building lists, going very deep into those lists, maintaining data to do trend analysis
with what the outcome of the work from those lists was over time, so that you really quickly
build your  well, quickly  so that you build your bullshit filter and have the encompassing
how quickly people can get things done on your team,
what the kinds of appropriate work is for your team to commit to, etc.
The hard thing there, I think,
because I still don't see it often enough
with even just people who are only focused on scheduling and project management,
is in bracketing.
If you have any responsibility for scheduling at all,
And even if you don't, and you just
want to make sure you know what the hell's going on
in your project.
I hope that you can regularly have conversations about and build your own backwards plans and
forwards plans.
Compare the two and then bracket the window of when you think things are going to land.
Use that as part of doing your backlog building if you're doing Agile.
Use it as part of your milestone commitments or even your initial full project schedules.
The more you do that over the time, the better you're actually going to get at knowing how
much scope you should be committing to with the kinds of people you have, as opposed to
guessing or just guessing.
And ask a lot of questions for those things.
Going back to, say, music, that's definitely talent
management, A&R, artisan repertoire, kind of like
building bands or groups or working with them to make sure
that they're being promoted or doing the best
kind of work they can.
It's the same thing in games.
It is a talent management business, and hopefully you know that.
It's not just getting random people in and building a schedule around them, but rather
over time, especially in a studio environment, really crafting what the team is like and
who's responsible for what things, so your composition is good.
Senior people tend to want to mentor others, or at least rely on the experience they have
and know that it's being listened to.
So you want to have the right mix of senior and junior people.
You only go to war with the army that you have, right?
So make sure on behalf of your team
that you're committing to the things that they can do.
You need to know what their growth plans are also,
so you know what kinds of challenges
they want to accomplish next.
You have to constantly be talking
about what the goals were and whether or not
you hit them and celebrating those successes when
they happen, but always providing, kind of bread
crumbing the goals for your teams.
If you don't know what the growth plans are for your team
members, please go find out or build them
if you haven't already.
You have to get inside the heads of your team members
so that you know what's possible,
not just what you've already committed to,
but what's possible with the team that you have
and where your gaps might be for what's next.
So I think all of us are only going
to stay in this industry if we're able to innovate,
if we're able to
capitalize on the teams that we've built or are going to build in the future.
We can't do that if we don't go deeper into knowing the motivations of our people.
Your decision-making framework's really important.
It's also very important that you be able to communicate it.
And that's really hard for many producers
to communicate that they even have a decision-making
framework.
It's easy to say you're making decisions based on common sense.
It's really hard to say you're making decisions
based on any particular framework or approach.
I mention a few things here, and I'm
going to ask if you're not familiar with these,
that you follow up and discover more about them.
One I didn't write in here, which has to do with P&L impact,
is the idea of earned value management.
In earned value management, you're
comparing the product that you built
to the money that you spent.
And to people in finance, the ones who tend to control this,
you're just completely self-financed, in which case
congratulations to you.
But for those of us who are still working with other
people's money, the more clearly that you can
communicate the value of the thing that was built to the
money that was spent, the less other questions you're going
to need to answer, and the more leverage you'll have to
get new things that you need for your team.
Kinevan framework.
This relates directly to Agile, and this
is around understanding the situation that you're in.
Situational awareness, and then having a measured response
to the situation that you're in.
To go from being a good producer to a great producer,
this is something that you have to master,
is modifying your approach to the situation
that you're in with your project and your team.
And hand in hand with that practiced agility.
So, you know, how many of you now are kind of in full
or very heavily adopted agile production frameworks
in your studio?
Okay, not everyone, but many, most of you I'd say.
I found, and you probably know, I haven't found a common implementation of Agile or
Scrum or Kanban in any set of studio environments.
Everybody's doing something a little different, which I think is cool and good because it
should be something that matches with your culture.
But because it's different in many different studio environments, we need to practice before
we implement full scale, and practicing can be very hard because you have to find the
right situations to do it in.
And sometimes things don't work and we have to break them and do something different,
and that can be hard when you've fully committed to some...
production methodology and you may not feel empowered now or it might feel like momentum
is working against you to change what you've done.
So one of the ways to do that is to have some kind of incubation little project where you
can practice something different and use that as a comparison point.
We actually do that fairly often at Gearbox.
SWOT analysis, you probably know what SWOT analysis is,
but being able to identify your strengths, weaknesses,
opportunities, and threats.
But being able to then use that as a way to explain
to other, say, executive stakeholders,
or even people on the team, what kinds of things
you should pursue in your projects,
or people you should hire, especially if you're doing
gap analysis for your teams, to be able to use that
as a way to describe how you came to those answers
can be very helpful.
So innovation, I'm going to talk a little bit again about as a senior producer, or to
be a super producer in the industry, you need to be able to lead people into innovation.
You can't just be standing behind waiting for others as they're making decisions to
try to pick up the pieces from them to see how you can support the efforts that they
want.
Whether that's in some new network infrastructure that the team wants to build, going more data-driven
in your design, whatever it is, you need to be at this point, to be at this level of production,
part of that decision-making process, and funneling it, funneling the decision by asking
questions about feasibility and being part of that process.
That's how you move from chaos to structure.
This is what that framework, by the way, high level looks like.
Go out and read more about it.
And when you give your presentation,
you'll know plenty there.
I like to, on occasion when I'm talking about production philosophy, explain that a lot
of the decisions I make come from things that I've studied in the past having to do with
strategy and battle strategy.
And this is one of my favorites, Miyamoto Musashi.
Do any of you know who Miyamoto Musashi was?
Quite a few of you.
Cool.
He's the author of the Book of Five Rings.
This first point here from the quote, anyway, from the Earth
book, don't engage in useless activity.
So it's basically don't do anything that's of no use.
And when your team sees that you're not engaging in
useless activities, and when you're focusing your effort
only in those things that are always pushing your team
forward, and while in pulling your team forward.
Again, you're gaining a lot of credibility points, but also you're being efficient and
saving money and helping to create a culture of self-reliance amongst your team members.
I recommend that you read the book.
As a leader, as a super producer in the industry,
you have to quickly be able to explain to others
what your definition of leadership is.
This is something that a colleague of mine,
John Antal, the colonel, at our studio,
he's a great leader and he's a great teacher of leadership.
And he makes sure that people always can define
what leadership means to them quickly.
You have to have kind of your elevator pitch of it.
And if you want to be great, you have to know what it is for you.
Not just that there's some notion of leadership out there, but what it really means.
For me, it really just comes down to the ability to impel versus compel, and how that translates
into what I do with my teams.
So first, for leadership mastery, you have to be a great representative of your team
and your organization.
To be a truly excellent producer, everyone you work with has to know that when you are
talking with them, that you are really truly representing that organization, what it means
well.
And that you are a key person in that organization.
So don't do the things that would hurt that.
And better yet, do the things that others would kind of seek to be.
You do that yourself.
Second, you can't lead from the back.
I mean, there are theories of management,
some of which I think are basically
just passive aggressive theories around covering your ass,
which would be leading from the back.
But if you really want to be a great producer
and be able to build awesome,
teams that do amazing things, you have to be with them there at the front.
You have to be identified as somebody who's leading from the front with those teams.
You have to be a driver with them.
Succession planning.
You know, this is a really hard one.
for companies, not just as a producer and a team.
This is a really hard one for companies to think about.
You know, a lot of studios have been built
as lifestyle businesses, right?
They haven't been built as some other kind of company
that's going to scale and grow
and transform into other things.
We have a lot of studios that have people
who are making games because they wanted to make games
and they're in that.
company to make games and they're not going to do something else.
So that studio, and is represented now in the team that you work with,
are there just to be there to make games. And that's awesome.
I want to make great games. I hope you all want to make great games.
But people are not going to just be in one role forever.
And even if you can't get buy-in from the people you work for,
you yourself, to be great, need to be actively engaged
in succession planning all the time.
You need to imagine, what if you're hit by the bus?
What if your team members are hit by the bus?
What if you need to move people into new roles of leadership?
What do you do with the vacuum behind them?
How do you get them to do that as well?
You want to be awesome, you better be able to speak truth to power.
And that can be very scary. If you're afraid for your job,
you may not be able to do this. Maybe you'll be brave enough to do it, maybe you won't.
I hope you will be. I personally am not interested
in having producers who work at Gearbox under me,
who I'm not interested in having them be there if they are afraid to speak their mind to me.
So I try to create.
I believe I create safe environments for anyone to voice any concern that they have, and I
hope that you are doing that also and not penalizing people for having opinions.
Remember you have to have that baseline of being calm, and once you've done that, then
you have the credibility to coach them in some direction.
Remember I want you all to go home and teach.
what we're talking about here today, but do it in your own words, with your own examples,
in your own pictures, in whatever you want to use.
But if you want to become great and you want to be seen as someone who has a credibility
to be overseeing a lot of projects and people, you also have to see yourself as a teacher,
not just somebody who's a satellite pulling and conveying information.
These last couple are where I think you really transform.
Once you've done all those other things,
once you've stopped doing the bad things
and you've turned those into ways to be very positive
and to do great things, the way that you conduct yourself
and the way that you work with your teams,
when you think about the sphere of influence that you have
and how you can expand that for the benefit of your team
and the quality of the projects that you work on,
that gets you to start thinking about things
on kind of a new plane.
because right now maybe you're just focused,
and when I say just, I really don't mean
this disparagingly, okay?
You might be focused on the project that you're working on
and the team members that you have
and just how to do the best you can,
you know, going to war with the army you have, right?
How to do the best you can in that scenario.
But when you can expand your reach and your influence
way beyond the boundaries of that team
and the company and the project that you're in,
you're going to find all kinds of new opportunities for whatever, recruiting, for where your project
can go from there, new opportunities for building that in the IP with, you know, ancillary opportunities,
licensing opportunities, meeting people, you know, the effective networking and how that
can benefit you and your team.
So, when you think about the sphere of influence you have
and what it would mean to grow that in a way that benefits the team,
not just you, yourself, you're going to move into
this whole other level of super producer.
And then, to go even a step beyond that,
to me this is kind of the ultimate.
When you can get to that point
and then be able to expand your teammates
spheres of influence. Now you're scaling your organization and your entire organization's
capability and being the connector for your teammates to others out there in the world
to be on technical steering committees or to give talks at, you know, GDC here or at
the other regional GDCs or DICE.
To be able to expand your reach out and to learn new things,
people will come to you at that point
or through your team members who you are asking
to expand their own spheres of influence.
You're going to learn a lot about what's happening
in the world for your organization.
So in kind of the corporate world, right,
there's this idea of business intelligence
and competitive intelligence and analysis.
Really, I think for us in the games industry,
as we do need to keep innovating and learning
about what all the opportunities are for us to innovate
and where we can make money now and in the future,
one of the best things that you can leverage to accomplish that,
to have that learning to be able to actually execute on it,
is to work through your team members to do it.
At origin, back in those days, EA didn't really
want people to come to GDC.
Now, I don't know if that's still true.
I think EA is a very different company now,
and I think they're great and whatever.
But it's a different world now.
And I hope that attitude isn't prevalent anymore.
I hope there is no fear of our team members coming to
something like a GDC, or a Dice, or any other conference
where they can have great takeaways and bring them back
to the team.
Because it's the only way that I think we're going to stay
competitive, all of us, with what we're doing.
And this is kind of the key, I think,
to being able to keep making games.
So that's it.