Hello and welcome to Sharing in Success, how to compensate your team through revenue sharing.
My name is Kellen Boyer.
I'm a video game lawyer with a practice focused on representing independent game studios.
And as part of this work, I'm frequently called on to create revenue sharing structures.
And what I've noticed throughout my time doing that,
is that there isn't a huge amount of understanding in the industry about
different types of revenue share structures that are available,
and as well some key considerations that they should be taking into account
when coming up with a revenue sharing structure.
So let's first start with what a revenue sharing structure is.
It's a legal agreement, or it could be a corporate structure, where each person gets a percentage
of game profits.
So we're talking about each person who's involved in the development of a video game,
whether it's a coder or a sound person, gets a percentage of game profits.
And you wonder, what's the purpose of this?
What can it achieve?
I think it achieves two key purposes.
The first is that it incentivizes the development team by providing a chance to participate
in the game's success.
This is especially helpful if you're trying to recruit people to work on a game in a very
competitive job market by providing this additional financial incentive where they could earn
Theoretically, astronomically, more than a regular salary would be through a revenue share structure.
I think it really allows you to bring on key people with a lot of talent to work on your game.
So I think there's certainly an incentivization element here.
Also though, and I think this is really important for independent game studios,
is that the revenue sharing structure helps decrease the studio's financial outlay
by supplementing immediate compensation with the revenue share.
The reality is, with a lot of our clients, that they don't have a huge amount of money
to put into the development team.
So they need to come up with a way to pay people what their market rate is, but to do
it in a different way than just straight cash.
And I think the revenue share obviously can come in and serve that purpose.
So if the studio is faced with someone...
who would like $50,000, which the studio maybe can't afford, then maybe it's $25,000 cash
with this 5% revenue share on top.
So the revenue share can come in and supplement what the studio could otherwise not afford
to pay.
So I think there is that second benefit.
And as I noted earlier, there's this chance of earning exponentially more through the
revenue share than an increase in salary anyway.
So together I think there's great value in these two purposes of a revenue share structure.
This incentivization, it can help with hiring, and then as well supplementing what the studio's
actual financial means are with the revenue share portion.
So what are these revenue sharing structures?
I consider there to be two common revenue sharing structures, but of course with an
asterisk I am a lawyer so there's always a qualification.
I think creativity is the limit.
There's lots of permutations possible of these structures.
But even though our clients love to come up with incredibly complex structures almost all the time, simplicity is often easiest to create and understand.
And plus cheapest. Usually a lawyer is going to have to write a plan.
And so.
There's a cost component with the more complex structures anyway.
But I think simplicity is core here because you need to understand the plan and how it's administered,
but also people that are receiving it that you're trying to incentivize through the plan need to understand it as well.
So I think that simplicity is a really key guiding rule when you're coming up with any revenue share structure.
So let's talk about the two core types, the two common revenue sharing structures.
The first of which is the revenue sharing agreement.
The second, which is the same kind of structure
in the sense of you are distributing revenue,
but it's different in that it's equity-based revenue share.
So we'll talk about each of these now in turn,
and hopefully you'll have a better understanding
of what each involves.
So let's touch on the revenue share agreement.
This is a written agreement between the studio
and each developer.
where the studio agrees to pay a percentage of game profits to the developer.
And importantly, it takes the form of a royalty.
And these grants can be on a one-on-one basis,
or they can be done in a different way.
But let's look at the one-on-one.
In the one-on-one basis, it's going to be something along the lines of
following commercial release,
The company, the studio, will pay somebody, me in this case, a percentage of the game
net revenue.
Now we'll talk a bit about what net revenue means in a bit, but know that it can be on
a one-on-one basis.
Or it could be, as you saw in the slide I just skipped ahead to, or it can be based
on a set-aside pool.
And what do I mean by that?
The pool is a percentage of the game net revenue that's allocated among all the participants.
And if you visualize it this way, you take a percentage of the game revenue, say 15%,
and that's your hard cap.
That's the maximum amount of the game revenue that's being given away, distributed under
the revenue share.
And the pool, that's the 15%, is participated in by whoever you want that worked on the
game.
So you could have 20, 100 people in the pool, and they would all be participating in that 15%.
So an example of kind of pool language would be,
the company could allocate 15% of the game's net revenue
to the royalties.
That's kind of pool type language.
So which one works?
You have a revenue share agreement that's more one-on-one,
and you have a revenue share agreement that's a pool.
Which one would you want to consider
based on your particular studio?
I think if you have a small studio, up to five people,
that one-on-one, those individual grants,
I think that works.
But it does not work once you get.
to a larger team because you are going to lose track of the total percentage you are
giving away.
When you are doing 1-on-1 grants, you are not dealing with a hard fast and pooled cap
of let's say 15%.
Instead you are saying, Kellyanne gets 5, Julie gets 10, etc.
It's often easy to lose track of how much you are actually giving away.
And plus, it just becomes unmanageable.
If you have 20 team members, that's 20 separate agreements all trying to distribute 0.25.
It works so much better in a pool context.
So if you have that medium or large team, I think the pool is critical.
It's really the only structure, at least as compared to the individual grant,
that really can help accommodate multiple – lots of people, pardon me, participating in that revenue share.
And this revenue share structure is usually the simplest, but also the cheapest structure,
and as I noted, it's really the most common.
So what is this other structure?
The equity-based revenue sharing structure.
So you could do the agreement, we talked about that a moment ago, or you could do equity-based
revenue share.
And that means that the developers receive shares in a company.
And their shareholding percentage corresponds to their revenue share.
And instead of the revenue share being paid as a contractual royalty, as we talked about
in the case of the agreement, it actually takes the form of a dividend on the shares.
And I think here it's important maybe to describe what a dividend is.
A dividend is a distribution by the company.
I'll see you in the next video.
Let's multiply by the number of shares that you actually have.
And a key rule with dividends, and this plays out a bit later on in this presentation,
is that dividends must be the same for shares of the same class.
So if you have A shares and B shares, different classes of share,
you can say that the A shares get $1 and the B shares get $2 a share.
You cannot say that within the A shareholders,
Kellen gets $1 a share and Julie gets $10 a share.
You have to treat all shareholders of the same class the same in most legal jurisdictions.
And that plays out in how you have to structure these equity-based revenue shares.
Because you don't want to give someone a revenue share for a game they didn't work on.
How do you split them up?
How do you give out separate royalties or differing revenue shares to the different
participants?
And what you have to do is create a separate share class for each game.
So in a simple example, you could have common shares being owned by the founders, and then
Game 1 shares will be owned by the Game 1 devs, Game 2 shares by the Game 2 devs, etc.
And we'll talk a bit about sequels and stuff later on and DLC.
You can actually do subordinate series of game one shares, series of game two shares.
Sky's the limit, as I talked a bit earlier on the permutations.
But what you can recognize so far here is that it's complex and obviously it's going
to be costly to create.
I think it serves a purpose though, because it coexists nicely with raising investment
in the game.
And I'm not talking about publisher investment, that's never an equity-based investment, just
in advance.
I'm talking about investors that actually want to share in your company.
I think it can coexist nicely with raising investment in the game, because you could
issue Game 1 shares to people that invested in Game 1.
And those, when you declare a revenue of royalty, a distribution, pardon me, a dividend...
on those Game 1 shares, the investors would share along with the other Game 1 shareholders.
I think it's a great structure in that sense.
As you're gathering here and as I noted, it really is complex because you need to build
into the company's constituting documents into its certificate of incorporation if you're
in Delaware or its articles if you're in some Canadian provinces.
All of this language that would actually normally be in a revenue share agreement, how it's
calculated, how frequently it's paid, all of that.
You have to calculate all that but put all those calculations into these constituting
documents.
Thank you.
The form of more than one document that needs to be created internally within the company to achieve this.
So obviously complex, but I think it does serve that great purpose for investment.
As I said, it's rare. I do these maybe 5% of the time.
So now up to this point, we've talked about those two purposes, incentivization, we've talked about as well, supplementing what you could pay with your studio with the RevShare and the two types of structure. You can do the RevShare agreement.
Or, you know, it could be pooled one-on-one, or you could do an equity-based revenue share.
One pays a royalty, one pays a dividend.
But regardless of the structure, I consider there to be five key considerations you take
into account when figuring out how to structure these revenue share relationships.
The first is the percentage of game revenue to allocate.
And, you know, while I love to
To try to see if there's standards in the industry, I don't know if there's a standard
in the industry on this.
I think someone needs to do a study.
I've done studies on publishing agreement rev shares, but I've not done one yet on game
revenue percentage to allocate in a rev share structure.
So I can't say that there's a hard and fast rule.
This is what you should allocate.
But I think it's valuable to look at analogous structures.
And the one that comes to mind for me is startup stock option plans.
I work a lot in the startup sector as well, and their stock option plans
are used extensively to compensate employees almost in the same way and with the same purposes
as I'm talking about for these revenue share agreements.
And in a stock option plan for a typical startup, there is actually a pretty common size and
that's 15 to 20% of the company's shares are allocated to employee compensation.
And what I mean by that is the startup will take 20% of its share, set them aside, and
distribute that 20% among all the employees.
And in option, just for anyone's reference, it's a right to buy a share in the future.
And the idea here is if the company sells, everyone's going to hopefully make a lot of money from their startup
and from the shares that they receive through those options. So it definitely serves the same purposes here.
But I don't want you to say, okay, well startups do 15%. I'm going to do 15% because
it doesn't make sense. It's not an arbitrary determination. And it's actually not an arbitrary determination for startups either. That 15 number
is usually just a good starting reference point and
You don't have to follow it as a hard and fast rule.
And I think there's a couple things that you should take into account when determining
how much of the company's revenue is being given away under this rev share structure.
And startups consider the same two things when considering the option plan size.
And that's the number of people the company plans to hire as well as the percentage that
the company is willing to give away.
The number of people you plan to hire is really going to play into that.
Because if you're going to hire five people versus 100 people or 20 people that you're
all going to give a rev share to, that's going to factor into how big of a pool you actually need.
And as well, just the percentage you're willing to give away. Ultimately, 15%
could be too much money in your mind based upon how you think the game is or is not going to perform.
And I think when you're considering that percentage that you're willing to give away under the rev share, you should also not forget the publisher gets a percentage.
Now, this presumes you're going to have a publisher who gives you an advance for the game development in exchange for getting a percentage of the game's revenue.
But when deciding on that percentage, you need to take into account what the publisher is ultimately going to get.
Usually, if you have an industry standard based off my studies, look at my GDC presentation
last year on this, it's about 56% roughly, maybe 60% of game revenue is going to be paid
by the publisher to the developer.
So a 15% pool on a 50% rev share paid to the developer is much different than a 15% pool
where 85% of the publishing agreement revenue is being paid to the developer.
So.
Who else is getting a cut outside of the pool, the rev share agreements, is really critical
when determining that percentage.
And I know I'm using the word rev share agreements here, but I'm really talking about these revenue
share structures.
So all of these things also apply to the equity-based revenue sharing as well.
So what you're gathering is that there really is no guaranteed formula to determine the
percentage, but take into account both, maybe start from a 15% number and work backwards
considering the number of people you're planning on hiring and the percentage you're willing
to give away.
And I think as part of those two considerations as well, though, you've got to circle back
to that incentivization purpose and to the compensation purpose, because if you just
can't afford...
To pay people what their market rate is, you're going to have to have a bigger rev share than
not because you're going to be compensating more through the rev share component than
through the cash component.
So let's move to the second key consideration, and that's how you actually calculate the
revenue share.
And you've seen some of this language before, this net revenue number I used, or term, pardon
me, and the gross revenue term.
What do these things mean?
How do they play out?
So let's look at gross revenue.
This in my mind is all revenue from the game.
There's no subtraction for expenses.
And I consider this to be dangerous because there actually is a risk that you won't have
the funds to pay.
In theory, there's a chance that your expenses could exceed the amount of money you have
coming in, especially if your game's not that successful, such that you're going to have
an obligation to pay a rev share based on gross revenue.
But in reality, that money does not exist in the company.
So almost always I believe the calculation should be based on net revenue.
And net revenue, I consider it to be game gross revenue, all the money coming in from
the game that you get, minus platform fees, returns, chargebacks, publisher payment, taxes.
Ultimately, it's a company that gets to set the cost deducted from gross revenue
to arrive at the net revenue. So for each of our clients, we do completely different
structures as to what's deductible and what's not. I feel like it is a bit of a collaboration
as well with your team members, especially if you're a close-knit team.
As to what is going to be deducted, salaries, for example, may not be something you would
deduct when arriving at that net revenue number.
But I think it is really critical to say that it's a net revenue calculation.
And as for the terminology net versus gross, I don't really care what you call it.
I think it's just really important to say that there are going to be, it's a term, whether
you use profits or other terms as well, as long as it's clear that there are going to
be some subtractions that are going to be made before you arrive at that number from
which you calculate the rev share.
So the third consideration is how this revenue share is actually earned.
We can talk a bit about as well, when is it paid, but how is it earned?
And there's common approaches here too, and one of the most common ones is time-based.
Someone's time spent on the game is divided by everyone's time spent on the game,
and then you arrive at a percentage from that calculation.
What it requires, though, is timekeeping.
And while lawyers like filling by the hour at times,
it does not work in the independent game scene.
Indies hate timekeeping.
So I don't know if it works for everyone.
We certainly do see it.
I see it quite a bit.
I think it's a simple way of doing things, too.
But timekeeping may not work well.
Perhaps it would work well, though,
if you had a bunch of contractors
that were tracking their time,
just because that's natural for a contractor work.
In that case, maybe it would work okay.
A different approach, other than time-based, is milestone-based, where you grant a person a particular percentage,
but it's subject to completion of a milestone.
And what I mean by that is, you're going to hire someone, perhaps as a sound designer,
and you're going to offer them 5% of the game gross, pardon me, net revenue, 5% of net,
and they get that only upon completion of the milestone.
You could do a prorated based upon completion, but I think only earned upon completion makes a lot of sense, especially for a deliverable like a piece of sound that's going to be used in a game.
So that's milestone based. I think that works really well from an accountability perspective, because you can say to your team members, look, if you develop out this piece of code, you're going to earn the milestone.
And I think it works well when it's.
It isn't someone whose role is everywhere on the game. I think it works really well if someone's just working on a portion of the game, because I think if you're going to do a project based in the sense of, you know, develop a particular piece of code, it can get a bit complex. But another way of doing it too, when we're talking about milestones isn't perhaps a part of the project, but it could be a stage of the project development. So we could combine
time-based with milestone-based and say that actually it's the development cycle milestone.
So once we hit alpha, if you're still working with us, we will give you one percent. And if
you're still with us at the beta release, steam early access, whatever it is, we'll give you
another percentage and another percentage. So you could combine time-based with milestone-based as
a variant of the milestone structure.
But the completion of the milestone should be determined by the company acting reasonably.
You could also do the determination based upon the passage of time.
So you grant a person a particular percentage, but it's earned over the development cycle.
So for example, you could offer someone 10% rev share, which is vesting over 10 months.
And what vesting means, it's a bit of a startup term, vesting is a synonym for earn.
So someone gets 10% rev share, but it's earned over 10 months.
They would earn 1% based upon a month of work.
And if they stop, let's say, halfway through, let's say 10 months,
so they stop at five months, they would get 5% because they've only worked half the duration.
So it's kind of a time-based structure, but it's not looking at them tracking time.
It's instead looking at just the passage of time and saying, if you're...
Stay with us for a particular period of time, you're going to get a percentage of it.
Kind of tied into the milestones as well.
You kind of see some overlap there.
But you can also introduce what's called a cliff in startup land.
And what that means is you have to stay with the company for a particular period of time
and only then do you start to earn the revenue share percentage.
So if you say 10% invested over 10 months with a three-month cliff,
the cliff is this cutoff point.
So if they stay only for two months, they don't get anything.
If they stay three months, then they'd get a third,
and then it would go on for the remainder, maybe vesting in monthly period.
So you can see here that there are multiple ways for that rev share to be earned,
just timekeeping, passage of time, the milestones, and this vesting structure as well.
And I think though, regardless of what you choose, lean toward that simplicity.
Whatever works best for how your studio operates and how your team feels comfortable to, I
think that's the way to go.
But at least you've got a couple options outlined to you here.
The fourth is how do we treat non-game revenue?
What do I mean by non-game revenue?
I'm referring to downloadable content.
How do we deal with that within these revenue share structures?
Some of these structures work in a way that can accommodate these things, but I'll say
that equity-based revenue share has a lot of trouble dealing with this kind of work.
A DLC and merge sequels.
We'll talk about that in a second.
So what do you do with these?
Do we include them or do we exclude them from the revenue share on a high level at
high level?
A simple rule is the developer should only be included in the royalty for
merchandise for DLC only if they worked on that content.
But the tracking and calculations can get complicated quickly for these additional sources
of revenue.
So let's start with DLC and merchandise.
I think it's important to treat each of these revenue sources as a separate calculation.
So in the revenue share agreement, you would say that the people that worked
on the DLC and the people that worked on creating the merchandise, they would have a separate
revenue calculation and would be paid out among those people.
That's kind of high level how you do it.
But it doesn't work well in an equity revenue sharing structure.
This goes back to that dividend rule, a bit complicated I know, that I described earlier
because people are all going to have the same share class.
You can't.
Change the dividend that's going to be paid to those people in the same share class.
So it's hard to have secondary revenue source calculations, if not impossible, I've read
secondary revenue, uh, pardon me, separate revenue share calculations within shares of
the same class.
There's, there's a series way of doing it where you create a secondary class of share,
but super complicated.
So I think ultimately if that's something you're considering, probably like most people
lean toward a rev share agreement.
And what about sequels?
My rule is always create a new revenue sharing agreement,
plan, or share class for those sequels.
There's no point in using the same agreement
because your percentages are gonna vary,
the team's gonna be different.
I don't think it makes sense.
The fifth and final set of considerations
is what to think about concerning termination
of the revenue share agreement.
Because ultimately you can't keep on paying
of the revenue share forever.
It's not practical, even just from a monetary perspective,
because at some point the game is not going to be making
the same kind of money it once did,
so paying $2 to somebody just doesn't make sense.
You could set the revenue share to be fixed duration.
For example, five years.
Pretty simple.
You're going to get paid this for a period of five years
following commercial release.
You could also do it based upon a monetary cap.
So until $100,000 in royalties is distributed among all of the participants.
The best I think is actually mixed, where you say it's until the earliest of five years
or a certain percent, not percentage, a certain dollar figure in royalties are distributed.
So I think that's probably the best way to plan for termination.
In this duration and this monetary number, they're just examples.
They're not anything to follow.
And I think that's probably the best way to do it.
One thing to avoid though, and one thing we are avoiding here with this language, is to
avoid perpetual term because you just can't have this going on.
As I said, it's not practical to be looking at 20 years from now paying out some rev share.
So plan for termination because ultimately it may need to end.
Let's talk about situations where it actually may need to end.
Well, if the company is bought or the game is bought, then the revenue share should terminate.
We have had clients that sell their game and the acquirer doesn't want to deal with the
revenue share.
They want to be able to monetize the game however they see fit without any baggage from
the former studio.
So your revenue share structure should accommodate
How it could be terminated should the company or the game be bought and perhaps a final payout
Is the way to go but there's a couple ways of doing it that just go beyond what we're talking about here
You should also though plan for hard financial times. Sucks to say but that's something you have to do
What if the company can't pay or or it's harmful to pay
And by harmful to pay, I mean the company could be in a tight financial spot where paying
that revenue share could be detrimental and cause it to have not enough funds on hand
to keep on paying its own payroll.
So there may need to be a cause built in there to address the situation.
Now, I don't think the company can't pay or it's harmful to pay.
I don't think they're often a cause for termination.
But the company should be able to delay payment until it's able to, acting reasonably.
So I think in these agreements, it's great to have a clause that says if it's harmful
for the company to pay, it will cause the company to go bankrupt if they pay.
The company can delay that payment until, acting reasonably, it can make the payment
and perhaps there's an interest component, something like that to it.
But admittedly, there is an element of trust involved in this structure.
So I think it really requires a cohesive team and some trust there.
So to summarize, I consider there to be two types of plan you should look into.
The Revenue Sharing Agreement, which could be an individual grant or it could be a pool,
or the Equity-Based Revenue Sharing.
Ninety-five percent of the time I would say that the Revenue Share Agreement is best.
You should create a percentage royalty pool based on your hiring plans.
Whether you're actually doing the pool structure or you're just doing individual agreements,
you should be saying, we're going to set aside a certain percentage and that's going to be paid out among everyone who's participating.
And then consider how that percentage is vested. Is it hourly, milestone, passage of time, some hybrid?
These are all things you need to consider.
And then as well consider downloadable content, merchandise.
How those are addressing the plans,
but split those SQLs out to a new plan.
And then finally, plan for termination.
Is there an end date? Is there a payout cap?
And consider that delayed payment clause as well.
So that's it for the presentation.
My contact info is here and I'm glad to answer any questions.
Thank you.