Hi, everyone.
This talk is going to be on visual storytelling
and narrative design for Moon Studios' latest title,
Ori and the Will of the Wisps.
My name is Jeremy Gritton.
I was the art director and story lead for the game.
And I'm gonna be co-presenting with my colleague,
Chris McEntee, who was our lead designer.
Now, because this is a remote presentation,
we've split it into two parts.
So I will be covering the first portion,
which is on visual storytelling.
And then I'm gonna hand things off to Chris
for narrative design.
So let's go ahead and jump right into it.
And I think that there's no better place to start than with the prologue.
Now, if you've played Ori 2, you're probably familiar with this screen.
It's the opening scene in the game.
And something that's interesting about it is that this cliff used to be flipped horizontally.
And the reason for that is that originally, when we were first prototyping things, I was
thinking that it would be nice to have a direct callback to Blind Forest.
So I thought maybe this cliff could be one of these cliffs from the original game.
But as we built our prologue prototype and we had an opportunity to play it,
I could tell that the flow didn't really feel correct and that if we were to forget about
that connection and to flip this cliff the other way around that it would flow much better.
And the reason why I think that it flows better is that it helps us to create a more consistent
visual vocabulary for the sequence, for the prologue as a whole.
And what I mean by that is that we begin to develop a pattern, which is that the direction
indicates the theme.
So anytime that the camera or the player moves to the left, that's indicating certain ideas
like returning to the past, towards security, or towards what is known.
And any time that the player or the camera is moving to the right,
that's representing a different set of ideas,
such as pushing forward into the future towards uncertainty or the unknown.
So let's walk through the different portions of the prologue
and see how they align to these big ideas.
So in the beginning, Ori is beckoned by Gumo to come to the left
and to go to the Swallows Nest Cave,
which is a very familiar area from the first game.
So we're really returning to the past.
And then once we get there, we meet the baby owlette coo,
this new addition to the family.
And the camera begins drifting slowly to the right
as we can see how the cave accommodations are changing
in accordance with that.
Afterward, Ori exits the cave and we begin this big seasonal montage, which is this sweeping
camera with a strong rightward momentum as we're pushing forward in time and space across a series
of family bonding moments. And then at the end of the montage, Ku attempts to fly and fails,
and so the player is tasked with their first objective, which is to try to help Ku,
and so we push forward to the right in an effort to do so.
Now, once we get there, the solution isn't immediately available,
and the narration tells us that the answer lay in the past.
So which way does Ori look?
To the left, and so we return back to the treehouse
that we passed by earlier,
and there Ori is able to recover a key story item
from the first game, which is Kuro's feather.
Now, once we've retrieved that item,
Ori brings it back with them to the right, back to Ku.
We're bringing it from Blind Forest now into Will of the Wisps
to play a key story role.
The feather is fixed to Koo's wing and then Ori and Koo take off from a cliff to the right to
begin the flight sequence to begin this new chapter in their lives. And this is the cliff
that we were talking about earlier.
Now at this point we go into the flight sequence
and this has a strong rightward direction.
And you can see here at the end that Ori and Ku
are pushing forward into the right, out into the unknown.
And Ori takes this one last look back to the left
to the landmarks from Nibel receding in the distance.
This is basically where we're saying goodbye
to the first game.
Now, those were a lot of overarching ideas
that really help to inform the visuals
that we're gonna create for the prologue as a whole,
but let's take a moment and talk about
just a specific section, like the seasonal montage.
I was originally very inspired by the bridge-building sequence in Blind Forest.
I thought that this was just a great character-bonding moment, and I wanted us to have our own version
of that.
So I was thinking, why don't we really blow it out?
We'll really make the budget bigger.
And instead of having a sequence that takes place over the course of a single day, we'll
have something that spans an entire year, and we'll have all the different seasons.
And this is very useful because it allows us the opportunity to create a balance between what is nostalgic and what is new.
And that's something that I was always looking for in different moments in the game as a sequel.
I always thought that that would be great if we could strike that balance.
And so what's useful is that we're back in these familiar spaces that we know from Blind Forest,
but they have fresh new looks because we're seeing them in different ways because of the
passing of the seasons. So let's look at one of those specific vignettes, and that's this one
at the start, which is the family picnic. And this is about a 15-second scene, and we can talk about
this one specifically because it's a good way to discuss telling stories without words. So
The way that I have constructed this scene is that I have arranged the characters very
specifically in an order, one, two, three, four, and each character takes a specific
action that is meant to be read sequentially in order to tell a story. So what I'm going to do is
I'm going to pull up the original sketches that I had when I was pitching the idea to the team,
and we'll walk through these steps one by one to see how this was constructed.
So the first step, Gumo takes a large exaggerated bite of the berries, a big exaggerated scoop
and bite.
And the reason why I'm doing this is because I want to draw the viewer's attention to him.
Gumo is the first person in the lineup that I want you to look to.
And it's also conveying some of the information, which is that the family likes to eat the
berries.
Now the next character in the lineup is Naru, and she offers the berries to Kuu.
And so this is telling us that Kuu is a part of their family, that they share what they
have with her.
And then next is Koo's response.
She rejects the berries.
And what we're learning is that Koo is growing up
and we're seeing some of her individuality,
what makes her different.
She's an owl and maybe she has her own ideas
about what's good to eat and what's not.
So maybe when she was very young,
she was okay with eating the berries,
but now as the seasons are changing,
she's growing older and she's starting to develop
her own identity more and more.
And then Ori, who's been patiently waiting their turn
on the right-hand side of the screen,
recognizes the problem and directs our attention
to screen right, saying,
hey, I think the solution is over there.
And that's going to actually cause the camera to pick up
and to flow to the next scene.
And speaking of the camera, you can see how,
because it has a very slow rightward drift
throughout this moment,
it's basically framing the characters
during their key actions
at the place and frame where I want them to be.
So this is also something that's very useful.
Now, just to sum things up, getting value from just 15 seconds, each action is very deliberate.
It's providing us with new information and all of these as a series are developing the character
bonds. We're also telling a small encapsulated story about what Ku likes to eat and that she
doesn't want to eat the berries and it's also working as a precursor to the larger story as a
whole because...
This is setting up that Ku is different and that she has different desires as an owl,
and that's going to continue to build throughout the prologue as we can see that she longs to fly.
And Ori's desire to help her achieve that dream, that's a driving part of the prologue.
So
Let's move on to the flight sequence
while we're talking about her desire to fly.
And this was a fun sequence that we worked on.
I really enjoyed it because we were pushing the boundaries
with what we could do.
And let's discuss how it was constructed
and what the big ideas were behind it.
So it was really a blend of three ideas
and those were a daytime transition,
the mastery of flight and a goodbye letter to Nibel.
And it's the combination of these three things
that creates a unique flight sequence for us.
So the first one, the daytime transition.
When I first worked on the script,
I had this taking place entirely at night.
And I mean, it seemed like a good idea at the time,
but as we were starting to build things out,
the art team came to me and said,
you know, they really felt like
having a daytime transition that would provide them
with a lot more visual variety,
because they thought that if it was all at night,
things were falling too flat.
So we discussed it, and what we settled on was,
let's have Orion coup take off right at the crack of dawn and then we'll have the sun is rising
during the first portion of the flight sequence and so things are getting brighter as they're
getting happier and then they will get darker at the end with a storm coming in and everything gets
really dangerous. So one of our artists based on that discussion painted this color script and I
remember when I saw it I thought yep you guys are absolutely right this is looking awesome and let's
definitely go in this direction.
Now, I don't think that there's anything that revolutionary about this idea conceptually,
which is tying the environmental state to the emotional state. It's something that you see
all the time in film and TV. But the reason why you see it all the time is because it's
effective as a device. And so it's one of the ideas that we leaned on for our flight sequence.
The second one is the mastery of flight and this is something that the animators and I had discussed quite a bit how to convey
this and and so I'll run through some of the the different moments of that.
So in the beginning we have a shaky takeoff where they leap from the cliff and it actually doesn't go entirely as planned.
and then following through on that, lacking total control. They're flying by and they're clipping
into the treetops and they're sending the leaves swirling around and then again clipping into the
waterfalls as they're winding around the ginso tree, but then they're beginning to gain confidence
soaring higher and higher up into the clouds and then plunging back down through the clouds and
then weaving in and out of the floating rocks at Forlorn Ruins. We can see that they're gaining
confidence and beginning to perform more dangerous maneuvers.
And then in this sequence, this is something
that I had boarded originally, which
was that Ori and Koo would descend down and join
this flying V, and that Koo would feel like she was finally
one with the flock.
And one of our animators had this idea,
and if you pay attention closely to the wings,
Koo's wing beats are out of time with the other birds,
and then she hesitates and watches them,
and then she beats her wings in unison with theirs.
And I thought, when he showed me that, I thought,
What a smart idea.
Like this is a perfect way to convey the emotion of the moment.
So I think that this is a really good example of visual storytelling.
And that's also a great example of how things get better and better over time.
The next one that we have is saying goodbye to Nibel.
And so with this one, we always saw the flight sequence
as sort of a goodbye letter or a love letter
to the first game.
And so we wanted to honor the different landmarks
in the first game as we were leaving that location behind.
So here we can see the Spirit Tree,
and then the Ginseo Tree, the Forlorn Ruins,
the Sunstone and Mount Horu.
And then this moment, the one last look, this is what we talked about earlier.
So you can see how Ori is looking over their shoulder to the left, and then they push forward
and to the right.
And so I think that this is probably a good place to close things off for the prologue.
The next section is going to be a little bit different because I want to talk about our
decision-making process and story and how that informs the visuals that we create. So
this next section is going to have spoilers, but what we're going to be discussing is this
big emotional beat in the middle of the game.
And it's when our main antagonist, Shriek, attacks Ori and Ku in the Silent Woods.
And Ku becomes gravely injured because of this encounter.
Now, what a lot of people might not know is that for the majority of development in this sequence,
Ku died, and that was it. She was out of the script.
And in order to properly explain everything that happened over the course of development,
the decisions that we made, I'm going to have to go all the way back to the very beginning.
So let's talk about the early drafts.
So when I was first working on the script,
Shriek was essentially the same character,
but her relationship to Ku was completely different.
So she wasn't violent towards Ku,
and instead she was actually protective of Ku.
Now I had always seen these two characters as mere images of one another.
They were both orphans and while Ku was adopted by a family that loved her and accepted her
for who she was, Shriek was rejected by anyone that she ever crossed paths with and essentially
treated as a monster.
And so there was an interesting comparison and contrast there.
Also, they were both damaged while they were inside their eggs.
Koo was damaged by an overabundance of light from the events in Blind Forest, and then
Shriek was damaged by an overabundance of darkness from the decay in Will of the Wisps.
I thought that there was just this really interesting connection between the two characters,
and that's really what I was trying to play up.
So this image here, this shows Shriek's introduction as it used to be.
So we had something completely different where Ku was getting hunted by Howl in the Silent
Woods and then Shriek comes out and protects her in a really terrifying way by petrifying
Howl.
And we had a whole animatic for this moment, and I really liked it quite a bit.
But we also had these other moments that followed that, where it was different character bonding
moments between the characters. And I thought there was some interesting stuff there, but...
Really, the story in general was falling flat in the middle of the game, and it wasn't really
coming to a strong conclusion at the end of the game.
So there were definitely issues with this.
So what ended up happening was we had this big story meeting.
It was brought up in the meeting that things weren't really coming together yet.
So let's try flipping things around and let's have, instead of Shriek protecting Ku, let's
have Shriek attack and kill Ku because that has the opportunity for a big emotional beat
in the middle of the game.
I remember this meeting very well because I was probably the one who, more than anyone,
was saying,
Whoa, no, no, no, no, no.
We can't do this.
That is too dark.
Players are going to lose motivation
in the middle of the game.
It's going to undermine Kuro's sacrifice from the first game.
And on top of everything else that we
know is going to happen at the end of the game,
this is just going to be too much.
This is going to be overkill.
We can't pile this onto everything else
that we know will happen.
So I was really immediately against it.
But the outcome of the meeting was,
look, we're kind of getting creatively blocked
at this point, and what we have isn't working.
So let's just try this and see what happens.
So I said, okay.
And it was actually really funny because that night after work, I was feeling bummed out.
And so I, and my wife could tell that something was wrong.
So she's asking me, you know, what's the matter?
Did you have a bad day at work?
Like what's going on?
And I told her,
you know, work, they, they want these script changes, and I
don't really want to do it. You know, it's fine. Don't worry
about it. It'll be fine. But it was kind of funny because I
actually was really, really upset about the fate of this
fictional baby owl, which is probably weird, you know, or not,
I don't know. But
But you really do start to get attached to these characters as you're working on the game.
And it's not that I have an issue with killing characters, I think that's a good story device to employ,
but I really was concerned about how that would balance out with everything else that we were doing.
And so what happened was, I went back to work the next day,
and I had to focus.
And so I was starting to do some little sketches for ideas.
And I was actually really surprised
to see that I was very inspired, and I wasn't expecting that.
And so I was doing these sketches,
and then I was sharing them with the team.
And they were getting excited by them.
And so they were starting to give me ideas and saying,
oh, what if we add this or change that?
And I was getting excited by what they were saying.
So we started getting a lot of moments like these with Shriek slamming down and then stalking
towards Ori and Kuu, or Shriek backing Kuu up against the cliff and then it's very tenuous
because she's unable to fly. Or this moment here that I had discussed quite a bit with our animators
where
Shriek attacks Ori and then Ku with zero hesitation attacks Shriek.
And this is another example of something that I wanted because I think it's a good way to
do visual storytelling.
It's a small action that can say so much that even though Shriek can do nothing, or even
though Ku can do nothing against Shriek, that she has zero hesitation and attacks her when
she sees Ori's in danger.
And that just shows the love that she has for Ori, the bond that there is between the
two of them.
Now, we also had more sketches like these ones,
which included Ori finding Ku in the aftermath
and the Moki are surrounding them,
or the wisp coming out and floating around Qowlok's pool
and all the flowers are blooming,
or Ori going to Qowlok and it's dark and gloomy
and Qowlok's eyes are glowing in the darkness.
And so all of these moments, I thought,
really had a lot of potential.
And then we also have, just to come back to this moment,
This is a color script that I had painted for this.
And it's one of my favorite moments in the game,
but the wisp comes out and it floats around
and all the flowers are blooming.
And I liked this because it's very reminiscent
to the prologue of Blind Forest when Ori is resurrected.
And so I thought this might be perfect
to give players that sense of hope
after this big event happens.
but it can segue perfectly into Quolock telling us that the light here is too weak,
that it's become fractured, and that we have to make it whole once more.
So it will bleed right into the quest that the player has to go on.
But I never would have even come up with this moment if I hadn't been prompted to
by other people on the team to explore in this direction.
Now, we also had this portion of the sequence
where all of the Moki are bowing their heads
as Ori is making their way to Kualuk.
It's sort of like a cascade.
And this was another thing that I really wanted,
even though it was technically challenging to set this up.
But one of the things that you'll notice is
if the player holds their stick to the left,
Ori just stops and looks back to the left.
And this is a callback to the prologue
because we can't go back to the past
and change what happened.
The only thing that we can do
is push forward to the future, to the right.
So what really happened at this point was that I had essentially been converted, that I realized,
yep, you guys were right. There's a lot of great potential here. There's a lot of strong story
moments that I think are working really well. But I couldn't shake the feeling that the ending was
just too dark and too bitter with Ku dying. And so I basically did an alternate version of the
ending where I said, we can still have all of these beats in the middle, but we can bring Ku
back at the end.
And in this way, we would also still honor Kuro's sacrifice from Blind Forest.
So I presented it to the team, and it actually caused quite a big debate, which I was not
expecting. So about half the team agreed with me and thought, yes, Kuu should come back.
And about half of the team disagreed and thought, no, Kuu shouldn't come back. That's just,
you know, that's just chickening out. We should kill the character. That's the bolder story move.
And so because there was this real debate on the team and we couldn't come to an agreement,
things stayed as they were, which was the default that Koo died.
And it stayed that way for probably about two and a half years.
So what ended up happening was towards the end of development, we began doing UR playtesting,
and the feedback from the playtesters was confirming what I had been worried about,
which was that people were losing motivation in the middle of the game,
and they were generally dissatisfied with the ending.
So because of that, we had more discussions in the team, and I was pushing for us to,
can we please try the alternate ending just to see how it tests for comparison's sake? Because
at this point, we only had one playtest session left. So we decided to go ahead and do that.
And when it was playtested, it tested much better. And so that really reignited this whole
two-year debate on the team.
And nothing had really changed.
Some people agreed with me and thought, yes, KU should come back.
And other people thought, no, KU shouldn't come back.
And it's way too late to make a change this big, this late into development.
So we were kind of gridlocked at this point.
Moon is very democratic. It's one of the great things about Moon. Everyone is highly encouraged
to speak up about everything, whether or not it's their department. And it's really how
we drive quality in the company. But usually we're able to come to some form of a consensus.
And with this one, we just weren't able to do it. So what ended up happening was
I spoke with our creative director, Thomas,
and he told me, you know,
if the team really can't make a decision,
then I'm gonna let you make the final call.
What do you wanna do?
And I told him, well, if it's up to me,
then I wanna bring her back.
And so that's what we did.
We went back to the team and we told them,
okay, everyone, final decision.
We're gonna bring Kou back.
And, you know, half the team was happy.
Half the team was celebrating.
Yay, yes, Kou's coming back, awesome.
And half the team wasn't, and they were saying,
ah, you chickened out, you know,
we should have just killed the character and owned it,
and that would have been the bolder story move.
And I think that that's just the reality, you know,
that half the people agreed and half the people disagreed,
and if we had done it the other way,
that just would have been flipped.
So I think that there's a few key takeaways for me
from this whole experience.
And the first one is to just keep an open mind to new ideas.
I was so locked in to this angle that I wanted to play with Shriek and Coo that I essentially
had a blind spot.
And there was a lot of things that I was missing.
And I really needed other people on the team to point out to me that, hey, we can do this
in an entirely different way.
And even though I didn't agree with everything that they were saying, for me to say,
okay, I'm going to truly explore this and to try to make it work. And then because of that, I was
able to realize, wow, they were really right. Like I'm having a lot of ideas related to this
that I really like. And so I think that that's really the power of collaboration, that you need
people with different perspectives and different ideas, and it's how you bring all of that together
that's what's really going to yield a good result.
But at the same time, when you have all of these differences of opinion,
that means that not everybody's always going to agree. And sometimes if you're in a spot where
you have to make a big creative decision, like this one was for us, because it completely changes
the tone at the end of the game, you have to be comfortable with the fact that you might not make
everybody happy. And I think that it's a lot easier to be okay with that if you really do feel
that the right decision was made. And for me personally, I do think that we made the right
decision to hit the right tone and balance for the end of the game. So speaking of the ending,
let's move on.
and talk about the willow ceremony. So this was a sequence that I had pitched to the team early on
and everybody liked it so we ended up incorporating it into the game and let's discuss how this was
conceptualized. So I knew that we wanted to have this big moment at the end of the game. There was
going to be this big thing that we were building up to which was the changing of the guard between
the old spirit tree and and.
Ori. And so I knew that we wanted to have something big and mombastic and magical. And I was thinking
about what the sequence was about conceptually, and it's about the life cycle of a spirit tree.
And so when you think about a spirit tree, these glowing leaves form in the canopy.
and they break free and they disperse across the land and then they turn into spirits which
then inhabit the forest. And so what I was thinking was if all the spirits have died out
then maybe that light, like their essence, is still there scattered throughout the land. And
maybe this whole sequence, this ceremony, can be a reversal of that life cycle.
that essence of light can be drawn back to its point of origin back to the dead branches
and as it touches them it reforms back into leaves uh creating a like a spiritual
apparition of what once was and so we see this like spirit canopy
And I thought, yeah, this has a lot of potential.
I really like where this could go.
And then also for the Spirit Tree itself,
in the early versions of the script,
we always had just called it Spirit Tree number two,
which obviously, you know, that's really bad.
And so I was trying to think of a way,
how can we make this tree unique to the tree in Nibel?
And so what I was thinking was,
I was looking at the title of the game,
Ori and the Will of the Wisps, and I thought,
What if we made it, what if we did a play on words
and we made it about a willow tree and its wisps?
So it was a willow and its wisps.
And this could work out pretty well
because I like the way that the text spirit willow looks
together on screen.
And I like the way that it sounds.
And this would give us a very unique style of canopy
that would be very distinctive from the original spirit tree.
And that could play really well with this whole ceremony
that I wanna do because it might almost look like
some kind of a bioluminescent jellyfish
or something like that.
So that's really where a lot of those ideas came from.
And here's some of the sketches that I had done initially
while I was selling the idea to the team.
And this one in the top middle,
I think is valuable to talk about
because this was another example
where I had an idea and it was improved.
So when I first sketched this,
I was picturing it as,
Ori was sort of buffeting themselves
against the magnificence that was appearing before them.
But when one of our animators took this
and started working on it,
he had interpreted my sketch differently.
And so he ended up animating this.
which was much more serene.
And it was really already just soaking in this,
you know, the beautiful visuals
of what was unfolding before them.
And so it was just, it was much more calm and beautiful.
And I remember when he showed it to me, I thought,
wow, this is much different than what I was expecting.
Let's do that.
So that's another example of how things get better
and better as more and more people's ideas come into play.
Let's talk about the epilogue
because we're starting to run short on time.
And really, the game as a whole, we always saw it as being an allegory.
So, Blind Forest is about the child-parent relationship with Ori and the role of the child,
and Will of the Wisps is about that transition from childhood into adulthood.
And so, you see Ori gaining more and more responsibility throughout the game.
It starts out where Ori becomes an older sibling and has this strong desire to protect and to save
and to help Ku, and then later inheriting this guardian role of the Moki from Qo'Lok,
and then...
even later inheriting a protector role for all of Niwen by becoming a new spirit tree.
So it's really about how Ori moves forward in terms of responsibility.
Now, regardless of whether or not somebody has played Blind
Forest, we wanted the game to feel like it was coming around
full circle at the end.
And so what you'll see is that towards the very end
of the game, we have a series of callbacks.
And they're meant to work depending, either way,
however your experience is.
So here you can see the memories that are showing up
during one of these final moments.
And this is a direct callback to the memories
from the prologue of Blind Forest.
But the memories themselves are of moments in Will of the Wisps.
So it kind of works for both.
And then also, here we have a direct Blind Forest callback. Ori is making their way through the
brambles. We're really going for it here. We're really trying to drudge up all the nostalgia that
we can. And then here, another Will of the Wisps callback. We're playing on the left-right themes
from the prologue and from after Shriek's attack. And Ori really, if the player holds the stick to
the left, can only look back, and the only option is to keep moving forward towards the future.
And then we have this moment, which one of our animators
had suggested and I really liked,
which is right before Ori embraces the light,
they take out the feather, Kuro's feather,
and they look at it one last time,
and then they just let it go and let it drift away.
And I thought that that was another good example
of visual storytelling,
because it really captures the emotion of the moment.
And then here, the final image in the game,
this is a direct callback
to the beginning of Blind Forest Prologue,
and it's the birth of a new spirit,
the birth of a new generation.
And this is, when I started at Moon,
this was one of the first things that Thomas ever told me,
that this was going to be the final image of the game,
and that it was gonna be about that circularity,
about that cycle of life.
And I remember when he told me that,
I thought, wow, what a cool idea, I really like that.
And so I think that on the subject of circularity and things ending where they began,
there's no better way to end this portion of the talk than by going back to that starting screen
and talking about that one more time.
So let's go ahead and do that.
Now, if you watch this screen, the camera's pulling back
and we can see Ori on the left hand side
representing childhood and the Spirit Tree of Nibel
on the right hand side representing adulthood.
This is really telling us about the life cycle of the spirit.
And crossing between the two,
we can see this flock of birds flying by
and they're representing Kou's dream of flight.
And so it's only through Ori's acceptance of this responsibility
and willingness to move forward into the next phase of life
that the light that is born from that is able to atone for the damages to heal
Ku's wing and to allow her to achieve that dream
of flight. And so I thought that it was really cool
that we were able to incorporate all of these different ideas right into the
first few seconds of the game that we're telling you
everything that the game is going to be about right here.
And those are the kinds of discussions that I really enjoy having with our team.
And it's not that it's something that I think that players are going to pick up on,
but maybe as someone continues to play the game, if they happen to play it a second time or even
a third time, that it's possible that they might start to pick up on some of these little tidbits
that we have sprinkled throughout the experience. And I think that that's just a really cool extra
that we added into everything. So.
I hope that this was enjoyable.
I hope it was interesting.
It was a lot of fun for me to walk back through
a lot of these sequences with you.
I think that that's it for me.
I'm going to be wrapping things up now
and handing it off to my colleague, Chris McEntee,
who's gonna be going over narrative design.
Thank you.
So while Jeremy went over the sort of storytelling.
the visual storytelling aspects from Maury and the Will of the Wisps, I kind of want
to go into a few case studies from sort of the more narrative design and sort of even
in level design side of things, because there were a number of compromises and issues and
things that needed to sort of get resolved along the way throughout production on both
the story and the design side to sort of make the most meaningful and impactful overall
experience as possible.
One of the very first examples that comes to my mind when I'm looking back on the production of
Ori and the Will of the Wisps is the Silent Woods. Because the Silent Woods, it's an area
that Claire discovers at the end of Act 1 during the game, and a lot of very important emotional
beats happen.
in that location. As Jeremy has explained earlier, that's where our friend Ku gets injured,
originally died. Very strong emotional beat. It's where we introduce our antagonist, Shriek,
which is also very important so that we sort of ensure that her arc is as impactful throughout
the entirety of the game as possible. She needs to be introduced in a very good, impactful way.
And we really have to endear the player to Kuu and make them feel lost when she's taken from us
and feel motivated to push forward with the rest of the game to want to sort of save her pretty much.
And so sort of the core aspect of this was that the player would discover Kuu,
they would enter this sort of tandem gameplay mode where Ori is riding on Kuu's back,
and they would explore the Silent Woods to try to find a way out to escape. Now they've been
reunited pretty much.
But very early on, well, sorry, actually not very early on,
actually it's the opposite, quite late in the project,
when we started to piece together the world
and we were having people play test the full experience
from start to finish, we started to realize that people,
that this environment was not resonating with people.
As you can see, this is some earlier footage
from the environment, the way that it was
at one point in the game.
And you can see that it's just full of spikes and danger.
It feels mazy.
It feels claustrophobic.
It doesn't feel pleasant to be exploring.
It had these explosive monsters, which
are in the final environment, but far fewer of them.
And it's just explosions everywhere, just danger
around every corner.
And also, it was focused really on challenge and precision
platforming and this sort of oppressive feel,
and not necessarily on.
appreciating the fact that we have our friend,
that we have this new ability to glide in the wind.
We didn't get a chance to do it in a comfortable sense,
to sort of get a feel for how we're controlling
our character and stuff.
Basically, we just amped up the challenge
right back to where it was before you entered this mode.
But the issue is that you're in this tandem situation.
What we ended up having to do was remove a number
of Ori's abilities when you're in this mode,
where you're playing as Ku and Ori.
because you obviously can't do everything
with a different character controller
like this with two characters.
And so many of the moves that the player
was used to actually using, they weren't
able to actually use anymore in this environment.
So they felt a little bit nerfed in a way, right?
And that's not necessarily a great thing.
But the main reason that they felt nerfed,
one of the main factors at least,
was the fact that in the environment that we had
designed, we were placing gameplay elements.
that were encouraging the use of abilities
that we had taken from you.
Because we were so concerned about what happens
if a player backtracks here after the sequence is finished.
What happens if they come back,
they need to have new, cool, exciting gameplay things to do.
But it was actually hurting the initial experience,
which arguably is the more important of the two.
But you have to nail that initial impression
and that first storytelling beat that you have
when you're going through the Silent Woods the first time.
And then on top of that, because we had nerfed the controller so much,
literally Ori was doing nothing.
It really felt like you were basically just playing as Kuu and not Kuu and Ori together.
And so we decided to shift the focus and take a step back.
And we reworked the environment.
We put a much larger focus on more open, empty spaces,
fewer spikes, less oppressive shapes, fewer explosives and things,
and larger, more open wind zone spaces.
where the player can just appreciate the fun of gliding
and flying with Koo.
So that way they didn't feel nerfed,
but instead they felt the opposite.
They felt empowered.
They felt like they were able to do something
that they couldn't have done before finding Koo.
They felt powered up and they wanted to explore
and see all the new cool things they can do
with this additional ability.
But now that we had made the environment less intrusive
and we made the gameplay with Koo more fun,
what did we do with that space that we sort of opened up?
Because usually when we occupy the space in our levels,
we fill them with challenge and gameplay and dangers
and things like this and puzzles.
But we didn't really have that here
because we were trying to simplify.
And so what we ended up doing was we thought,
well, how can we enhance and improve on the story beats
and the narrative thread going from the beginning
of the Silent Woods until the end?
And so we started to have a look at what we actually had with regards to story beats.
It was pretty bare bones.
And that actually was a partially a contributing factor to the very strong
emotional beat, not landing the way that we wanted to, but the end of the environment.
So at number one here at the beginning of the Silent Woods, we introduced Shriek from behind like this.
So just a very simple introduction.
She doesn't see us, but we see her and we're introduced to the fact that there is a pretty
significant threat in the Silent Woods that we need to be aware of.
Then a little bit later, I'd say about a third of the way
through the environment, the player finds Kuu, they reunite,
and then they're basically confronted
with our antagonist Shriek again,
but they luckily are out of view
and they don't get spotted pretty much.
But she walks right through the center layer
and it basically gives the player this extra feeling
of like, wow, we really are in danger.
We really have to tread lightly
in this very quiet environment to not get noticed.
But then basically we completely dropped all of that until the very end of the environment.
After all the tough gameplay we had done and everything else.
And then boom, Shriek shows up.
She somehow knows that we're there despite never seeing us.
And then she basically stomps on our friend Ku.
And it felt unearned and not satisfying pretty much.
So how did we?
improve this? Well, as you can see, we basically introduced pretty much five new story beats
throughout the experience of the silent woods to sort of create a more consistent thread throughout.
So, for example, at point number three here, we added yet another shriek moment where we see her
very close to the foreground in search of prey, pretty much being us, but she luckily gets
distracted by a howl off in the distance and flies away so we can then pass safely, pretty much.
Then at A, it's not a full story beat, but basically you have to use your ability to shoot your bow and arrow pretty much that we now added to the tandem controller, so that way you feel more like you're Ori and Ku playing together, not just playing as Ku.
You can use this bow to shoot this obstruction that causes this giant skull to crash to the ground and make a bunch of noise.
And what actually then happens after that is we hear a shriek crying out in the distance
from Shriek, who hears the noise that we're making.
This is again just to sort of reinforce in the player's mind that these silent woods
are hers and that we're intruding on her territory and we're not being subtle about it.
Then at B, a little bit later on,
we actually introduce another story beat
that ties back to an earlier point in the game.
This one actually serves a dual purpose,
because at the beginning of the game,
you fight this giant wolf called Howl,
and at the end of the fight, it escapes.
It gets away alive, partially unscathed, I would say.
And players always kind of wondered,
what happens to Howl?
Like, when does Howl come back?
When do I get my round two, pretty much?
But the thing is, we never designed a round two.
because at the end of the day, we didn't have the budget or the time to do a round two.
And we kind of just left it as this open thread for a long time.
And then when we were looking to introduce more story beats to sort of increase the intensity and
really sell the threat that Shriek was in the Silent Woods, we realized that we could actually
take Howl and petrify them and have them present in the environment as sort of a testament to just
how powerful and threatening Shriek is.
So that howling that we heard off in the distance earlier that sort of drew her attention was that this creature was intruding on her territory, and she went to basically put a stop to it.
So it's this sort of, there's always a bigger fish moment where it feels like there is an antagonist that you saw before, but the real antagonist is the one that you're dealing with right now.
And you have to watch out pretty much.
Then, at number four here, we always had this kind of owl statue that just crumbled when
you would walk on it.
So you would get close, you'd try to run across, it would start to fall underneath your feet,
and it was this sort of little moment of suspense, little exciting set-piece moment.
But by itself, it was maybe a little bit dry.
And so we decided, well, we're already adding in these beets, we're already trying to continue
this thread from where you saw her at the start of the woods.
until she catches us at the end, why don't we have her be the one that causes this to collapse?
But obviously we couldn't have her discover us yet because that has to happen near the very end.
So we had her chasing some prey through the foreground into the background, but then that
force of her flying through is what actually destabilizes this sort of petrified owl structure
and causes it to collapse.
And then continuing that thread, we had her waiting just to the right side when we continued
munching on that prey that she was chasing after. So again, it feels like there's this
linear progression of things happening as we're exploring, in parallel pretty much, and we have
to sort of sneak past through these sort of fallen tree trunks and things to avoid detection. But
then ultimately, we create this final.
you hit a trigger and boom, she comes out through the environment in a sort of
here's Johnny moment that catches you off guard and shows us, okay, she's
finally caught sight of us, she knows that we're here, we're trespassers, we're
in trouble. And then we eventually continue forward and get to the moment
where Coop gets stomped and suddenly all of it starts to make sense and it feels
more earned.
And the combination of all of these things put together
meant that the Silent Woods finally landed as an environment.
And players were actually enjoying playing
with Ku and Dory together.
They were actually feeling the tense build up
to that final moment.
And that emotional beat at the very end
was resonating with people.
And so we hit our mark.
And this was one of the most impactful story beats
in the entire game.
And if we had not done those changes to the Silent Woods,
it never would have landed the way that it needed to.
Another interesting case study I want to talk about
is this big Tony friend we have who we named Polok.
We knew very early on that we wanted
to have a sort of mentor figure, a very friendly NPC that
eventually goes bad, eventually becomes a monster or a boss
that we have to fight later in the game.
So, you know, we did the concepts and things of this sage-like giant toad creature. Seems like
something out of The NeverEnding Story. You know it fits the bill. You know exactly what he's going
to be there for. But then we wanted him to eventually become corrupt in some way that
was kind of vague at the time. And then we'd eventually have to fight and kill him. And
then we would feel sad because we had to put down our friend from earlier on in the game.
So that was the general arc. We would encounter and meet Qo'Loc, we would do some quests for him,
and then eventually after Qo' would get injured, you know, he would say that he's going to help
us on our quest to go and restore the light to to sort of help her survive pretty much.
But then somewhere along the way, this starts to get vague, he got corrupted, became a monster
pretty much, and then we have to sort of dispose of him and have a very strong emotional beat,
pretty much.
So what was that looking like?
Well, he asked us when we met him to go clear the corruption.
Basically, the water in the entirety of the world of Nihlwin, the game world,
was corrupted at the beginning of the game.
And it actually hurts you if you're trying to swim in it.
And so he tells us there's a reason for that.
It's that this old water mill called the Wellspring,
the wheels have stopped turning years and years ago.
And if we can find a way to clear that corruption
and start the wheels flowing, turning again,
then the water would flow clear.
And so that's our objective.
And we would go to the water mill,
we would unblock whatever is blocking it,
the water would rush clear
and we'd have this epic escape sequence.
And then we would go back to cool lock
and everything would be great pretty much.
But then basically after that,
we would do the whole thing in the silent woods.
He would say, he's gonna go help us on our search.
The idea was that at that point in this sort of darker sort of
scene that we have of him on the left there, that was sort of the
signifier that something's not right, that he's already been
corrupted by the water from sitting in it for so long. But
that also felt kind of weird, the fact that he asked us to
clear the water, but actually it was too late anyway, we couldn't
have changed the outcome, right. But in any case, then all of a
sudden, later in Act Two, when we're exploring one of those
Act Two areas,
at the very end of an area, he would pop up out of nowhere,
suddenly corrupted, suddenly dangerous,
and we have to fight him.
And it was too difficult for the player to remember,
you know, the last time they saw Kolok,
to understand why he might've been corrupted,
did it come from the water and all this kind of stuff.
Basically, ultimately, what we wanted
was going to require a lot more work.
It was gonna require a lot more story beats, sort of.
intertwined throughout this experience and a little bit more justification.
So on the front of justification, rather than just saying that it was just this sort of ambiguous
corruption that was happening to him because of the water, we decided to create a parasite,
pretty much, called the foul presence or the stink spirit, that basically was the thing that was
clogging up the mill. And this served, you know, it solved a number of problems, pretty much,
because it added sort of a face to this corruption.
It made the escape sequence a lot more interesting.
We started to integrate these sort of corrupted
parasite-like objects on all the different wheels
throughout the watermill that you
have to unblock to get the wheels turning again.
And so it all started to sort of make sense.
And then the idea being that this foul presence eventually
would get washed out of the watermill
and then eventually corrupt QuoLock.
But I'll get there.
And so the idea being that after that escape happened,
you have a small cut scene.
And in that cut scene in the background,
you can see on the left that the stink spirit is kind
of swimming under the water.
And that's sort of for observant players
to realize that the stink spirit isn't quite gone yet.
It's still around.
But that doesn't pay off until much later in the game.
But then in Act 2, when the player is exploring and then
going through the different environments
they can find in the game.
they start to enter an area called the Luma Pools, and that's the area where Qolok is the boss of.
And so that's where we needed to start this journey of like justifying the transition from
friend to foe and how do we sort of lay the breadcrumbs pretty much to make that work.
And so we can already start seeing some more of these signs of the foul presence present.
in the luma pools that we have to break and destroy and unblock things and stuff.
And so once again an observant player might put two and two together
and start to realize that this thing is not dead and it's gone
this way pretty much. Then the other part of the puzzle
is that we we add small NPC moments that basically explain that Kolok has
actually gone to this location. So you have these
little Mokey characters.
that basically say, have you seen Qoloq?
He's gone to the luma pools.
And that already from the very beginning
of the environment tells the player
that this is where Qoloq is.
If I keep going forward, I might eventually find him.
And that sort of helped to bring him back into your mind
from so long ago in the game and make you realize,
oh, actually I should be expecting something
with Qoloq coming up soon.
And then even near the end, right before we find him
in his corrupt state, we added another cheap NPC moment
to sort of reinforce that something's wrong here
and amp up the suspense in the lead up, pretty much.
And then in the middle of the Luma Pools,
to sort of finish this trail of breadcrumbs, pretty much,
we decided to invest in adding a full QoLock interaction
moment, where we would clear out the space that otherwise
was filled with gameplay.
plop this giant toad in there and actually interact with him like we did in the early
sections of the game.
And at the end of this interaction...
He basically says that he will continue searching for this wisp
that we're looking for as well.
And he physically moves further through the environment,
signifying this is where we probably need to go.
But actually, in terms of gameplay,
we need to find another ability that allows us to follow him.
So that gives us a little bit of breathing room
where things might have gone wrong off screen, pretty much.
So with all of those breadcrumbs in place,
we've justified.
Polak getting corrupted through having this parasite that eventually makes its way to him.
We've laid the breadcrumbs so that the player feels the progression from the water mill and
where Polak was originally, to his path that he's taken through the Luma Pools, and the same thing
for the foul presence, pretty much. So now we're down to the introduction of Polak in his antagonistic
state, pretty much, the reveal.
And so our very first test for the reveal,
we just went for what we'd done up until this point,
which is sage-like friendly Qo'lok.
Being sage-like and friendly, he found the wisp for us.
What a dude.
What a bro.
But then at the very last second,
when we're about to get the wisp, it gets captured.
And so it was Qo'lok by the Fowl of Presence.
And then basically, he emerges in this parasitic state
where now we have to fight him pretty much.
But one of our animators thought that wasn't good enough, that that wasn't working, wasn't impactful.
And so he tried a different approach where we actually see that Kolok is noticeably
out of it pretty much. And he actually already spilled the beans a bit by showing the foul
presence wrapped around him, but that was an approach that he wanted to try
to sort of show that clearly something is off here pretty much.
But already, Kholak isn't speaking.
He's not giving the player this feeling of,
oh, I found the thing for you.
It really feels like it's a trap placed by this parasite,
pretty much.
And so already, we start to see that we're going
in a much better direction.
But then for the final game, the compromise that we made
was we wanted to save the reveal of the foul presence being
a part of this fight and have it be a little bit of a surprise
still while still retaining that something's
wrong with Quo Lock vibe that we had in the previous animation.
And here we also decided to lean more into the fact
that he's a toad and use the tongue rather than
his little froggy hands and stuff.
But as you can see here, now we show the player
with this reveal with the tentacles
that Kolok has become corrupted by this familiar face
from earlier in the game.
And this is where the player could maybe start to realize,
had they not cleared the mill, this might not
have happened to their friend.
I'm a horrible person.
But then also, he asked me to do it.
So it was his own demise.
Like, he was the architect of his own demise, pretty much.
So there's a lot more layers to it now.
that we've done the work to really make this land better.
So then in the fight, obviously, we
still want to have this touching reunion moment with him
that lands emotionally.
And that's not going to happen if he's just
basically a monster for the rest of the time
that we have with him.
So at the end of the fight, we made this conscious decision
that Pollock fights back.
We do the final hit, and then he starts
struggling against his captor and gets pulled off screen.
And then from that point on, we need to sort of follow Kowlok up there and sort of see what the
resolution is. We're concerned at this point, but we know that we've completed the fight,
so all that's left is the resolution. And what we discover is that Kowlok basically overtook the
Stink Spirit off screen, and he basically gets to finish that arc. He gets to have that last laugh,
pretty much.
And we found that that was very important for Koloch to have this little triumph of his own,
as opposed to us killing the thing and just freeing him. So that way, you know, he fights
back a little bit more and it feels more endearing for him as a character and everything he's been
through pretty much. And then basically we wrap and we get the Wisp back as he sort of dies and
fades away. We can continue our quest, but emotionally it really stings because we sort of
paved the way for this moment to be able to happen.
And then we completely undermined all that work by filling this path that the player goes back
afterwards with enemies, because we were focused on, oh, we don't want a long, boring stretch
filled with nothing to do. Let's put enemies in combat and things to keep you busy. But then
we realized very quickly, seeing people play this,
that it was a complete emotional whiplash because they were still completely taken by this emotional
moment. Some of them were still crying at this point. We have this beautiful emotional music
that our composer wrote and we completely undermined it by filling this path with
dangerous things and enemies and stuff. And so similar to the silent woods, we stripped away
all of those layers and we just let the emotional moment breathe and it was far more powerful as a
result.
So this final set of smaller case studies I want to share,
it all has to do with that final point I kind of just
mentioned with having breathing room, letting moments breathe,
but just sort of like global pacing as well.
Because we realize we design levels on a very micro flow
level where everything has to be very tight and fun
and challenging.
But then when you start to put a lot of these micro flow chunks
together.
to make a world, suddenly the macro flow matters in a big way, and the way that you flow from one
of those sections to another and the pacing between them becomes very significant. So for example,
at the well spring, the water mill that I mentioned earlier, the room right before that big
water escape sequence that we have with the foul presence used to look something like this,
where it was this very tight, very spiky, maze-like
challenge heavy environment, very oppressive.
And honestly, it wasn't all that fun.
And very late in production,
we finally got the okay to try breaking
this entire level apart, this room,
and doing something very different there.
And so we opted for was creating
an environmental storytelling space,
which served multiple purposes.
One, it was allowing us to actually give more insight
into the lore of the world through environmental storytelling.
but two, it also served as a pacing break
right before this very challenging escape sequence.
The player was already spending so much time
in challenge mode climbing up to this part
of the water mill.
They didn't need another room of challenge
right before another challenge.
They needed a break.
They needed to be able to relax a little bit,
soak in the environment and appreciate this place
that's been so oppressive to them up until this point.
And so we just let the artists and storytellers
go wild with a big empty room.
and make it whatever they felt was going
to be the most interesting.
And ultimately, it made for a much better experience
for the Wellspring as a whole.
Bar's Reach is another example where
we needed to pay attention to pacing
environmental storytelling and art as well.
Originally, Bar's Reach, it's our frosty peak environment
in the game.
snow peak themed pretty much.
And one of the gameplay elements we have in there
are these sort of cauldrons that you heat up
by flapping some air onto them like a bellows,
and then they shoot out a projectile.
So when this area was designed,
this was the entrance to Bar's Reach,
and it was designed purely
from a mechanical gameplay standpoint,
which is I'm introducing this gameplay element,
it's going to open the door.
I know that the player has understood the element
because they opened the door.
Cool, now let's go forward
and explore the rest of Bar's Reach.
The thing is, we had something far more interesting
that we could use to gate that area.
We had already done a prototype of Bar.
He's a large story NPC that I can't go into detail on right
now.
But he's significant for the game in a number of ways.
And we thought it would be fun to be
able to tickle his nose and have him sneeze and open up a path
pretty much to move forward.
But the thing is, when the designer was putting together
the environment, they didn't really
the novelty of that or the significance of having that in a prominent location.
So they placed it somewhere in the middle of the environment,
just sort of like to have it, but not really to use it properly, let's say.
And so then looking critically on the environment near the end of the project,
we realized that the artists needed more room to breathe.
They needed more room to transition.
And so what we did was we gave them more flat space
that they could use to sort of almost crossfade the environments.
into each other, and we also decided to replace that very gamey gating system with the cauldron
with this more interesting, memorable, striking bar gate that actually used the exact same input,
the same kind of gating, the same ability, just in a much more contextualized and interesting way.
And actually the fact that you can discover this gate so early in the game.
it adds this sense of wonder and mystery to the environment
because you discover this snoring giant bear in a cave
and you wonder what lies beyond,
but you can only discover it later on in act two of the game
when you have a new ability.
And so that was a much, much stronger gate
and a much better transition and build up
pretty much than what we had originally.
Our sort of dark, insect-infested environment,
called Moldwood Depths, it had a similar issue
where the entrance was this giant spider statue,
but it was gameplay-focused, covered in spikes.
Player has to do these sort of tricky maneuvers
to then unblock some random door.
It didn't really feel all that interesting or memorable,
pretty much.
And so while we had this nice transition zone,
certainly different from Bar, what we
was just really a better gate.
And so Jeremy did some paint overs
and suggested that we have just this giant spider statue
as purely an environmental landmark in the background.
And when we eventually have the ability
to come here in the story,
that we have some little friends
that come and unlock this big gate.
So we decided that the story was that the Moldwood Depths was sealed off years ago because it was so corrupted and infested,
but they're going to open it for us because the Wisp is down there and we need to find it, right?
And so what we ended up doing was leaning into this and created this sort of opening in the floor,
sort of to have that, to emphasize that feeling that you're going underground,
and then this sort of, you know, wind would bellow up when it opened and spores were coming out.
So it really feel like this place, this temple hasn't been opened in a very long time.
And again, similar to Bar, you can discover this statue
very early on in the game and have the sense of wonder
and wondering what's going to happen here eventually.
And when you come back and it actually does get unsealed,
it feels magical.
And again, we just put it, the design
took a backseat for environmental storytelling
and pacing, and it really paid off.
And the final example, I'm running low on time.
is the Wintorn Ruins.
So the Wintorn Ruins was meant to be
the final dungeon of the game,
a full dungeon just like the other ones that we had,
but due to production concerns and scope issues,
we decided to trim it down heavily.
But we still didn't want to give up on the fact
that it was meant to be a very tricky gameplay challenge
like everything else in the game.
And so we combined all these elements,
like darkness and explosions and lasers and spikes,
and people in the team hated it.
It really felt out of place.
And also because it was leading up
to the final escape sequence of the game, which is very, very
challenging in itself.
And similar to the well spring and the water mill,
leading up to the final challenge with a challenge,
pacing-wise, felt very inappropriate.
And so we decided to take a similar note from the well
spring and take this very linear section
that we streamlined it to and fill it
with sort of environmental storytelling,
beautiful frescoes that our art team put together.
And this also gave us an opportunity
to tell more about the history of the world of Ori
and the Will of the Wisps, and also
foreshadow the final conclusion and Ori's fate,
pretty much, in a very interesting and memorable way.
And ultimately, playing through this longer story sequence,
very linear, lacking in challenge,
all focused on story, it really ended up, pacing-wise,
being the best thing to create that sort of calm
before the storm.
right as you then approach that final escape sequence,
and then challenges you for a few hours, pretty much.
So just like with all of these examples,
ultimately, creating Ori and the Will of the Wisps
and making it the way that we made it,
it really ended up having to be a marriage of story,
and design, and art.
And we had to really compromise on all fronts
to kind of make that the best possible whole
that it could be so that this story resonated
with the players in the way that we wanted it to.
I appreciate your time.
Thanks on behalf of Jeremy and myself.
You can find more from both of us on our Twitters, basically.
And I hope you have a great GDC.
And thanks for listening.
Hope you learned something from our talk.