Hello everybody, I'm Chris Gardiner, Narrative Director at Failbetter Games, and these are
my comically enormous headphones.
And this is my talk on Sunless Skies and what we learned while we were making its narrative.
So we are Failbetter Games.
We are a small British indie company of 17 people.
And we made these games all set in the same universe
of weird Victorian Gothic horror.
We began with Fallen London,
our web-based, text-based role-playing game,
which is still going strong.
We moved on to Sunless Sea and its expansions of Mariner,
which was our first foray into Unity games.
and most recently we released Sunless Skies, the spiritual sequel to Sunless Sea.
As a company we're known for our writing and the atmosphere of our games which lies somewhere at
the intersection of whimsy and horror and I became narrative director in 2016 about halfway through
the The Mariner expansion.
Before then I had been a writer and then head writer at Failbetter.
So Skies was the first project of this scope that I'd narratively directed
and I would like to talk about the approaches that we took and the things that we learned.
So Sunless Skies is a narrative roguelike RPG. You play the captain of a space train
in a world where the Victorian empire goes to space,
finds it riddled with cosmic horror and then makes it worse.
And the game combines two modes of play, a real-time exploration mode where you have direct
control over your space train and you fly around and explore and fight enemies and gather resources.
And then when you interact with a discovery or dock at a port, we switch to an elaborate
interactive fiction mode where the player gets to explore the location in a text-based interface.
Sunless Skies was well received, both commercially and critically.
Here are excerpts from some of its reviews,
including the poignant and haunting,
I underestimated the bees from CG Magazine.
And haven't we all at some point in our lives
underestimated the bees?
So this story had a happy ending but at the start of the protest the task in front of us seemed
pretty alarming. We knew that it would be a successor to Sunless Sea and so it would be
similar in a number of ways including that split between real time and interactive fiction modes.
But the team that started out on Skies was nearly four times bigger than the one that started out on
Sea. So we knew we wanted a less centralized creative direction.
more opportunities for team members to contribute ideas to the game,
and for departments to feel confident in working more independently.
And the scale of a narrative task in front of us was pretty daunting.
It took place in a setting that by then was eight years old and had millions of words dedicated to
it. The Fallen London Universe lore bible is about 137 pages long and they are 137 pages of complicated
and dense lore and we didn't want that to put players off. We wanted Skies to be a good entry
point into the universe.
It was also set in a baroque and unfamiliar environment.
So Sunless Skies is set in space, but not as we know it.
It has winds and sentient malevolent suns
and starlight that drives you mad.
So players and ourselves on the team
couldn't rely on common science fictional assumptions
to make sense of it.
It was also, we knew, going to be really big.
Specifically, it ended up being 800,000 words big, which is 1.6 women pieces, or the first
two and a half Game of Thrones books, or 19 seconds of Twitter, which is a nightmare we
should just stew on for a little while.
And so to achieve that we knew we would need to use not only our internal writers but freelance
writers as well and that they would bring their own voices and also have varying levels
of familiarity with our tools, our law and our approach.
So today I want to talk about how we got from that very large,
very terrifying blank page to those lovely reviews.
And I'm going to focus on three ways we approached this,
beginning with establishing and communicating a tone.
And I'm going to spend most time on this one
because it was quite difficult to get right.
I think I should mention that as a narrative-driven company,
story plays a role in development
earlier than it may do for many other developers.
So for us, an early goal was to achieve
a firm mutual understanding of the game's tone
that was shared by the whole studio.
We can't expect other departments to have to digest million words of enthusiastic lore,
but even if people don't know all the nitty-gritty, if they understand the tone of the game,
we're at least all on the same page, even if we're not on the same line.
And we used a range of techniques to achieve this.
So to begin with, we established a set of narrative pillars.
I can't take credit for doing this. This was a recommendation by Michael Aidlaw of
BioWare, Ubisoft and now Yellow Brick, who suggested creating a short list of core principles
that we would use to guide the narrative of the game. And they would have three main functions.
They would act as signposts to tell us what's important and provide direction when we were lost.
They would act as creative prompts to help inspire new stories and new angles on stories.
and they would work as tie breakers in the case of disagreements. So that might be a disagreement
between two members of staff on what's the best way to go about something, or it might be a
disagreement in your own brain if you've got two different ways a story could go to help you work
out which is the best way to, which of those options would fit best in the game.
When it came to deciding our narrative pillars,
we were fortunate in that a couple of years earlier,
our communications director, Hannah Flynn,
had done a load of work with us to establish a sense
of what our work is and what was essential
to the games that we made, or at least the games
that we had made up to that point.
So when we started working on Skies,
we got the writing team in a room
with a representative of the comms team.
and we looked at all that original work and decided what of it we wanted to carry over into Skies,
what of it we were prepared to lose, and what we would replace it with. Those last two went
hand in hand. We...
There was already a lot of complicated law in Fordham, London and Sunless Sea, and we
didn't want people to have to know that in order to enjoy skies, and then have skies
add a whole bunch of extra complicated stuff on top of it.
So we operated sort of one thing in, one thing out policy to try and keep it simple.
We, from that discussion, we distilled it all down into five narrative pillars.
That might be one too many, but Skies was a big game, so it ended up being okay.
And these are the pillars that we came up with, and they would act as instructions and guidance
to the writers, and also act as prompts suggesting what sort of fiction to write about, what topics
to write in.
And we found that they worked best as punchy, even slightly provocative statements like this.
And let's go through and take a look at what each one of those meant in the context of Sunless Skies.
So the first one, stake your claim, meant that the player should have the opportunity to leave their mark on the world.
They should be able to.
make decisions that would change the state of the world, and because that captain can die and then
you could create a new captain to replace them, that new captain would inherit much of the state
of the world that the prior captain had left behind. But it also pointed us towards a number
of recurring themes in the game, which would be power grabs and territorial feuds and conflicts
between rival competing factions.
Our second pillar was, who are you in the dark?
And this was important to us because we wanted the player
to be able to construct a sense of who their captain was
through play and through the decisions that they made.
But then the in the dark clause there made it a little more specific because we were particularly
interested in how who you were might change when the laws that you were used to are weak or absent
and when the world that you are in is completely unfamiliar and different from the world you left
behind.
Our third pillar was conceal your hand.
And this was a reminder to us to find new angles
on familiar stories and to look for unexpected consequences
to player choices.
And we also wanted to layer the world with mysteries.
And the answers to many of those mysteries
aren't explicitly revealed in the text of the game.
The player has to find clues to them
and then piece them together themselves.
And fictionally, we knew that we would want to have lots of ulterior motives,
plots and schemes and big conspiracies to address in our stories.
Our fourth pillar was mind your manners,
and this was important to our Victorian setting
to help us emphasize Victorian manners and hypocrisy.
But it also acts as a reminder to us that the denizens of space that the Victorians
would encounter would have customs and traditions of their own.
What would happen when the Victorian traditions bashed into those celestial traditions and
what would be the fallout from that?
And our final pillar was nothing is sacred.
And this was a prompt to us to take nothing for granted.
We knew that we wanted in the game's story
to make changes to fundamental human concepts
like time and death.
So time in Sunless Skies is not linear and reliable
and death is not the end.
But it was also
a reminder to us to use both humor and horror.
I spoke earlier about how our...
writing style often relies on this combination of horror and whimsy and both humor and horror
contain an element of transgression to them, I think, and they work very well together. You can
contrast them to create a kind of a more effective sort of oscillation of experience for the player
and a well-placed moment of humor can underline or puncture a moment of horror and vice versa.
So I'll come back later to look at some specific examples of how those pillars
guided different aspects of the game's narrative. But first...
I want to talk about how it became obvious to us that the pillars were great for identifying
tone and for having productive discussions about it, but they weren't so great for communicating
it.
They were too high level, too imprecise.
So to communicate the tone requires a strong narrative documentation that gives the people
reading it a lot of context.
So we created a fairly simple set of documents.
We didn't want people to have to read too much.
And we started with an introduction to the high wilderness.
The high wilderness is the name for space in our game.
And that looks at what this environment was like
and what the player's experience of it would be.
And once we'd done that,
we moved on to outline the four separate regions of the game.
We knew that we wanted four different regions of the game,
each of which would feel like a different experience
to the player.
Both of those documents we did in pre-production,
and then once we moved into production,
we would do a more detailed document
on each individual region as we went through.
And that let us learn, each time we did one,
we could learn from the lessons of the ones
we'd done previously.
The actual process for making this narrative documentation
was fairly simple as well.
I would write an initial draft of them.
For the detailed documents about each region,
that would be preceded by a concepting session
where our writing team would all get together in a room
and everyone would be able to pitch ideas for ports
and enemies and stories and discoveries in each region.
And then I would take all that material
and pass it into a single document.
When I was working on those documents, I was always guided by the narrative pillars and
tried to draw them out and emphasize them.
And once they were done, I would publish them and invite everybody in the company to read,
comment, and discuss.
So everyone in every department could contribute to them.
And then after all that discussion and feedback, I would take it all and incorporate it into a
revised version of that document. And while we were working through this process, we quickly
learned some useful tricks. The aim here, I should say, was to encourage buy-in and engagement from
all different departments to the tone that we were trying to create. And some of the tricks
we developed for doing that.
included, so the first one was look for recurring feedback when people responded to the documents.
That might be lots of people saying the same thing, or it might be a bit more indirect.
It might be that a particular topic or concept is very easily misunderstood, or that you
have lots of questions about that single topic.
And this is useful stuff because the questions that your team asks will also probably be
questions that the players would ask. And once you've identified them, it's important to address
them in the revisions that you make to the document. And a couple of useful ways that
we found to do that.
included these. So first, when you identify an important concept, state the three most immediate
and important things about it. So an example here from our narrative documentation, the team
response made it very clear that we needed to concisely convey the way in which the high
wilderness, our environment, was similar to and different from actual space.
So the way we did that was by saying that it was cold, like spaces, windy, like space
very much isn't, and wonderful.
Not wonderful in a nice way, wonderful in the sense that a fairy court is wonderful.
It's fascinating, it's consuming, it's terrifying.
And then we would go on to specify three things that it definitely wasn't.
Because ungoals are important.
It is crucial to communicate what you don't want as well as what you want.
So in this case, the key things that it was important to make clear
were that the high wilderness was not a vacuum.
that it was not an impartial environment, that its laws weren't uncaring like the laws
of physics.
They were laws that were made by grand sentient entities as the result of legislation.
They were the result of argument and compromise and politics.
And the third thing that the environment definitely wasn't was easy.
It was going to be frightening and challenging and difficult.
And the third kind of trick we learned to make the documentation more effective also was very
useful when it came to actually making the game. And it was to identify showpiece concepts which
are useful for heading off questions and assumptions that people will have when they
encounter the game. And they also help you communicate what is special about your game.
So here's an example. I mentioned earlier that the high wilderness was windy.
And because that was such an important point that space,
our space has an atmosphere, we really wanted to drive it home.
So to do this, we implemented a number of winds
into the game that had mechanical effects.
So not only would they push your locomotive about
as you were trying to fly around,
But the peacock wind, for example, caused your food supplies to burst into horrifying growth,
and they would grow these disgusting nodules on that were filled with milk.
And sometimes those nodules would grow little mouths that would sing little songs.
So mechanically, that would increase the food supplies that you had on board
while you were in the wind, but it would also increase your captain's terror.
And when terror got too high, horrible, horrible things would happen.
Incidentally, if you ask your art department to draw a wind that looks like a peacock,
you get a filthy look and this. So you should be very careful what you wish for.
The second showpiece concept that we settled on that I want to talk about
We implemented this very early in the game, kind of made a big deal of it quite early in the game,
because we wanted to use it to help undermine player assumptions. And it was that time is a
resource that is manipulated by the Victorian Empire to achieve the things that they do.
And the aim was, we wanted to introduce that early, so the player would ask, well,
if time doesn't work how I expect, what else might not work the way I expect?
And we also used this concept to justify a lot of fictional nonsense in the setting.
It was used to explain how London managed to build their empire in space so quickly,
how the player can travel these vast interstellar distances, how the Queen Victoria manages
to retain her power over her empire and so on.
And here are some of the ways that we brought that in very early on in the game.
So an early character, the fastidious inspector, it's her job to ensure that it is the same
time across all corners of the Empire.
despite the fact that different places are manipulating time in different ways.
And this was inspired by the early train network in Britain, where before the train network came in,
it didn't really matter if Manchester was 10 minutes ahead of London, because travel times
were so great. But as soon as you had a train network in place, and it mattered to the minute
when trains arrived and left, it would suddenly became very important for everywhere in the
country to have exactly the same time.
And we also put this into the economy of the game.
So a trade good that you can trivially buy or sell
at markets is a barrel of unseasoned hours.
So those are three kind of tricks that we learned
as we went on to make our documentation more effective.
Effective here means clear, concise, and digestible.
So now we've talked about that process, I want to talk about how we use the pillars
to give each region in the game its own distinct identity. So Skies has four regions which you can
see here. This map also includes two of the cities in those regions and each of those regions is
linked by a transit relay which is a big device that catapults you across the sky.
And we wanted each region to be a very different experience for the player.
So what we did was we ended up separating them by picking two of our content pillars and saying they were particularly important for that region.
So our starting area was the Reach, which is this wild, untamed frontier.
Originally, we intended the game to start in London.
but we found that the Reach had a more familiar kind of trading space game experience and it gave
players a bit more of a solid footing to experience the game on when they were surrounded by all this
other weirdness. So here we repaired state your claim with who are you in the dark because
the Reach is somewhere that London is trying to claim and expand into
so it's full of settlers and gold rushes and claim jumpers.
but it's also a place of few laws and you have a lot of freedom to choose who you're going to be
there and which side you want to be on because the region is driven by a conflict between the
independent settlers, the Tacities, and the London loyalists, the Stovepipes, and the player can
choose how they want to get involved in that conflict. And while we were doing this it became
clear that combining...
the narrative pillars with the visuals of the region that we wanted, gave us a great
way to focus on a different sort of horror for each region.
And so the horror that we settled on for The Reach was the horror of the natural world
and the natural world fighting back.
And we were inspired by things like the Cordyceps fungus, which infects ants and colonizes them
and turns them into zombies and makes them climb up trees and kill them.
And then they spread their spores to places the fungus wouldn't otherwise be able to reach.
And things like those weird deep sea nightmare fish that you see on nature programs.
But the theme of The Reach was very much that nature is terrible and fish are weird.
An example story that we set in The Reach that expressed these themes was written by our own
James Chew and it was about the Parsifal, which was London's first exploratory vessel to The Reach
that met a tragic end and was colonized by a sentient fungus. So this is an example of London
trying to stake a claim to The Reach and failing. And the way James wrote it is a story of slow burn
horror that has an ending that is at once quite tragic and rather funny.
and after it the player has a wide range of choices on how they want to respond to it.
All of those choices are valid and all of them say something quite meaningful about who the character is.
Our second region was Albion which represents the city, suburbs and outskirts of London.
So whereas the Reach was a wilderness, Albion was very civilized and populated.
And the two concepts here were mind your manners and conceal your hand because we knew this is
where we wanted to lean into Victorian formality and politeness and how it concealed ambition and
inhumanity. This is an empire founded on secrets and full of plots and schemes.
And this led us to the concept of social horror, which is best exemplified, I think, in an
example port from the region called the Brabazon Work World, which was written by one of our
writers and editors, Olivia Wood.
And the work world is obviously based on Victorian workhouses where the poor were essentially
imprisoned and given room and board, but forced to work in return for it in very poor conditions.
So we wanted to take that idea and magnify it.
So they went from workhouses to work worlds.
And in addition, the empire has engineered it
so that time moves quicker on work worlds than outside it.
So that means you can send someone to a work world
and extract a year's labor from them in a month.
And people will enter the work worlds
as young, healthy people,
and emerge from them a few years later
as aged and decrepit.
And this is the foundation of Albion's expansion.
This is how it was able to build itself up so quickly.
And the mind your manners pillar comes in
because this is part of society.
This is accepted and normalized by this society.
It's even seen as a charitable thing.
And conceal your hand comes in because.
the work world's put on a palatable face and they even allow carefully staged tours of them and the
player gets to go on these tours and they will only see the truth if they look for an opportunity
to deviate from the tour and see what's really going on.
Our third region is Eleutheria, where the sun has rebelled and plunged everything into darkness.
And this is a place of revolutionaries and pariahs, where things no longer work the way
you expect them to. And there's nothing to keep you honest, but your own conscience.
It's a place of temptation and opportunity. And the two pillars that we wanted to rely
on here were nothing is sacred. And who are you in the dark?
And this all led us to the horror of the unknown,
partly of getting lost,
because when you arrive in Eleutheria,
the transit relay leading back
to where you've come from is broken.
So when you arrive there, you are trapped
and you have no idea where you are or how to get out.
And the second aspect of the horror of the unknown
we explored a lot was the fear of the dark,
which we explored a lot in the enemy design for the region.
So there is...
one class of vessel called the dowsers who worship the dark and will attack you if your
headlight is off and there is another class of vessel that will attack you if your headlight is
Oh, I've got that the wrong way around. The dowsers will attack. Dowsers worship the dark,
so they attack you if your headlight is on. And the other class of vessel will attack you if your
headlight is off, because then they assume you're a dowser. So your headlight here becomes a banner
signaling your allegiance. And if you encounter both enemies at once,
you have a decision that you have to make very, very quickly.
We also created the Grievers, which are a monster that is inactive unless your light
shines upon them, at which point they wake up, get very angry, charge you, and explode
into caustic ica.
One of our writers described them as like being attacked by an angry prolapse, which
is very much the sort of prose that we pay her to create.
And we also added invisible enemies.
So the undeparted will stalk you throughout the region
until they can ambush you.
And they are only revealed when you shine your light on them.
So together, these enemies create
kind of competing pressures to have your light on and off,
to create this tug of war of tension
that means you can never quite relax in the region.
And our final highest level area was the Blue Kingdom,
which is one of the domains of the dead.
So death is not a state of rest or grace here.
You can recruit the dead as crew.
Souls are a currency.
And it's home to a remorseless alien bureaucracy.
And this led us to the concept of cosmic and bureaucratic
horrors.
And we found that both those sorts of horrors
worked very well together because they both
rely on making the individual fairly insignificant.
One way we explored that in the region was that everyone that goes there is assigned a status
and that status determines what ports you can access and also what enemies are hostile to you.
And when you first arrive, you have the invisible status, which means you can access hardly
anywhere and everything is hostile.
And you have to gain access to one of the other statuses in order to change that.
So you might become anti-deceased, which means you will be dead one day and it's technically
only a matter of time.
And that makes you like, it's like having a visitor's visa.
You're basically a tourist in the region.
Another status was yoked, which means you perform some function or service for the bureaucracy,
but you're kind of like a roadie. You do important work, but you're not meant to be seen by the
audience. And the last status was the ephemera, which are basically the customers. They are the
spirits of the dead who are being prepared to pass beyond to some unknown purpose and destiny.
And none of these statuses grants full safety or full access. So you do have to switch between
them as you explore the area.
So I hope those examples show how we use narrative pillars to identify a tone,
how we develop narrative documentation to communicate it,
and how we used pillars to emphasize the differences between regions
and to give the player different experiences as they play through the game.
Okay so having spoken about how we established and communicated a tone I want to move on to talking
about how we put an emphasis on effective pitching and how we used effective pitching
to ensure that that tone that we had created carried through to the game.
I think, or I suspect, we probably do fewer rewrites than many companies do, which is both
good and bad. And we certainly do do them. One mistake we made during the development of Skies
was we tried to write too much finished content too early, and we were writing ports and stories
before we could see what that content looked like in situ. And as a result of that, our writers,
James and Olivia, had to go back towards the end of development and do quite extensive revisions
on the content that we'd written first to bring it.
in line with the sort of content that we'd written later.
But on the whole, I think one way we managed to get away with doing fewer rewrites is by heavily
investing in the pitching process. And by the pitching process here, I'm just talking about
whatever process it is whereby a writer shares their initial concept for a story and gets
feedback on it. For us, that generally meant the writer pitching the concept to me, the narrative
director, sometimes with another writer present.
If I was writing content, I would pitch to one or more other writers.
So throughout this section, the examples that I give, I refer to writer and director. I basically
just mean pitcher and pitchee there. And exactly who that is will depend on the specific content
and the different company. But I think that a successful pitch has a number of specific goals.
The first of which is it ensures consistent tone and storytelling.
This was particularly important in Skies,
given the range of voices that were going to be
providing content for it.
We wanted those different writers.
We wanted that range of voices to make the game
more expansive, more inclusive, and more interesting.
But at the same time, all the different stuff
that they wrote had to fit into the whole.
It all had to be congruous with the world that we'd built.
A successful pitch also
helps ensure that a writer can do their best work.
This is your opportunity to identify what a writer needs
to write this piece.
And you can use it to even out differences
in writer's familiarity with your law, your game,
your systems, and so on.
And at the end of the pitch, both the director
and the writer should have a reliable picture
of what the final content will look like.
So I like to think about a pitch as having three distinct phases to it, and the first of them is to
provide a solid bedrock for discussion, and the aim here is to ensure that the writer and the
director both understand the story that the writer wants to tell. So the writer's role during this
phase is to communicate the shape of the piece using whatever aspects of it are useful to do so,
and it can help to run through it as the player would experience it.
Meanwhile, the director's role is very much to shut up
and to listen, not talk, and let the writer communicate
the piece as they want to, without interruption
and getting distracted.
I like to just sit quietly and take notes.
Once the writer's finished, you can then
move on to asking questions.
Questions are magic.
Asking a question is often more effective than just raising
observation or criticism.
And.
Frankly, the writer is the expert on the story here. Even at this stage, the writer spent more
time thinking about the story than the director probably ever will. So it is appropriate for
the director to approach the writer with a spirit of respect and inquiry, not judgment.
The second phase is about distilling the pitch down to focus on the core story
and to trim away non-essentials.
So the director takes the lead in this phase and their feedback, its aim should be to emphasize
the strength of the piece. This is a collaborative process, not a confrontational one, so you should
respect the writer's intent, understand what the writer is trying to do and support it.
You should also try and remove distractions from the piece.
That doesn't mean stripping out everything
that doesn't directly serve the core story,
because stories are improved by nuance.
But do look at how each piece supports the whole.
The director should also propose ways to tie this content in with other content in the game.
The director is the one who has the overview of the content as a whole and has probably seen many
pictures from many writers and so knows what's going on in the rest of the game. And the more
connections you can make between sections of content, the more satisfying and convincing
the world will see. The director should also advocate for the player. So what do I mean by that?
Well, the director is the first set of external eyes on the story,
and so they should look at it from the player's perspective.
Is one ending more disappointing than another? Could a plot point be
misinterpreted? Is one section particularly confusing? Is
there an obvious option the player might want to take that's been missed out?
And at the same time, think about if there is any other content.
that what's been described to you might contradict or conflict with.
Again, the director is the one with the overview of the content as a whole.
The writer is focusing very much on this specific story and likely so.
Meanwhile, the writer's role during phase two is to advocate for the story.
Advocate here doesn't mean defend every decision to the death.
What the writer presents in a pitch should be intentionally malleable,
not a final product. So they should hold onto it lightly,
and they should actively look for ways to improve it too.
They should be prepared to accept and suggest changes to it.
However, when a change that's been suggested
would hurt the story, the writer should
be prepared to stand their ground and explain why.
And this is where the narrative pillars come in,
because when you have a disagreement like this,
you can refer to the narrative pillars to help resolve it.
The third phase is there to ensure
that there are no surprises, that both
the writer and the director are expecting the same thing
to come out of this.
So now the writer's role is to make sure
they understand what changes need to be made,
and they've got a record of them.
And if there are any lingering uncertainties,
if there's anything the director hasn't addressed,
if there's anything the writer still needs,
now is the time to resolve them.
The director, meanwhile, the first part of their role
is to contain the scope.
a lot of feedback would have been given and too often it can look like the answer to a story issue
is to add another thousand words but no it almost never is and realistically you need to bear in
mind how much the writer will be able to do well in the time they have available for it.
So the director needs to help the writer prioritize the content so that if the
any of it needs to be cut it's easy to identify which bits can be cut.
And the director should also be clear about the changes that you've agreed and revisit and
summarize them just as a belt and braces method to make sure that you're both on the same page.
So good pitching we discovered has a number of benefits. So it has production benefits,
it reduces the amount of content that has to be revisited and revised.
It also makes writing easier. Writing is a painful and usually lonely process. A good pitch at least
can help make it less painful. It anticipates and addresses problems before they arise.
There will always be new problems that arise, but if you can get rid of a bunch of them early,
it's much much better.
And finally, we learned that productive and collaborative pitch discussions help writers
develop their skills. They take lessons from them and then they implement what they've learned the
next time they write something.
And I should be clear that we got to this policy and this approach to pitching over
the course of many, many, many, many pitches over the course of developing Skies.
We didn't start out this strong, I think, but we had a lot of experience doing it.
And so we got here in the end.
And I think we've benefited a lot from it.
Okay, I'm going to move on to my third and final topic now, which is the targeted consultations
we did to support the narrative in Skies. So to write well about something, you need either
experience or knowledge. And if you lack personal experience or knowledge,
you need to do research to gain secondary knowledge about it.
We tend to think of research as reading books, but basically it means consulting expert sources,
and those sources can be people. So in Sunless Skies we did four major consultations
on the following topics. We did one on colonialism,
one on transgender and non-binary representation,
one on structuring horror mysteries, and one on how to invent an appalling cosmic bureaucracy.
That was one specifically intended to help us
invent the narrative structures for the Blue Kingdom that I discussed earlier.
and we recruited Emily Short to consult on that one. Emily Short is now currently our
creative director but she's extremely experienced in writing interactive fiction and complex puzzles
and she has also had to navigate the UK's labyrinthine immigration policies so she
has a lot of experience of appalling cosmic bureaucracies. I'm going to talk about a couple
of case studies from these consultations to show how they worked and what we got from them.
So the first one I want to talk about our colonialism consultation. So why did we consult
on colonialism? Well, Sunless Skies was about the Victorian Empire going to space.
So it was about colonialism, whether we wanted it to be or not. And therefore,
it was important that we represent the issues here sensitively and with nuance.
We approached Meghna Jayanth to consult with us on this.
She had already been a freelance writer for us before,
so she was familiar with how we worked
and she was familiar with our setting.
And the format we used was that we gave her access
to a build of the game and all our narrative documentation,
time to go over them,
and then we just let her lead a discussion on them.
And we got a whole range of benefits out of doing this.
The most obvious one was that we got pages and pages
of new story ideas and angles on stories
that we never would have considered otherwise.
Just so much stuff, more than we could ever put in the game.
It was brilliant.
And we also received excellent guidance on other sources to consult to deepen our knowledge
further. A consultation isn't the end point of you trying to gain this information. It's often
the beginning and it gives you a, it accelerates the process, but it is not the end. And the other
major thing we got out of it was a concept that is widely applicable to much of our work and that
we've come back to again and again. And it's who is paying for this.
So colonialism tells the lie that its benefits come without a cost, but someone is always paying
for them. Colonialism and empire separate the beneficiaries from the people that are paying
for something, and hide the people that are paying for it from the beneficiaries.
So it's important that you represent that and that connection. It's not only responsible,
but it also makes for great dramatic stories.
Our second case study that I want to talk about was on transgender and non-binary representation.
LGBTQA plus characters feature extensively in our games, but if we want to continue providing
good representation, we have to keep pushing the ways in which we do it.
And in particular, for trans and NB characters, we'd often struggled with finding the line between
being too subtle in their presentation and too bold in it. So how can we make clear that a
character is trans or non-binary without doing so in a way that's preposterous or blunt or ridiculous
or harmful?
And we approached a body called Queerly Represent Me
to run this consultation.
They were excellent.
I can't recommend them enough.
And the format that we used was a workshop
which started with a discussion of several officer stories
that we had written for the consultation.
We knew we wanted these officers in the game.
We didn't have full outlines for them.
But we wrote up some outlines specifically
for the consultation.
and we wrote them on topics that we wouldn't have been confident putting into the game
without expert advice. But the consultation was a safe space to explore them and have
fruitful conversations about them and work out how we could make this work.
And then after we talked about that,
we went into a consultant-led discussion on other content.
We'd given them a build of the game.
All the consultants on the panel had had a chance to play it,
and they'd all come with topics that they
wanted to talk to us about.
We got a whole bunch of benefits out of doing this.
Here's one that was very easy to do, but had a big effect.
The consultants quickly raised the issue of terms of address.
So you can choose a term of address for your captain.
The terms of address that we'd inherited from Sunless Sea
were fine, but they were quite gender binary.
They're like, my lord, my lady.
There was citizen in there, which is very neutral,
but on the whole, they were strongly gender coded.
So the recommendation we received
was to add more terms of address that were either non-gendered
or at least less extremely gendered,
so it was on more of a spectrum.
The Victorian period that we were setting the game in
made this difficult. The Victorian period
had a very gender-coded pattern of employment.
But we did find a whole bunch of new options,
which are underlining red here.
that we added to the game.
And it turned out that these new options
were popular with all players,
not just ones hoping to create a non-binary captain.
Representation improves things for everybody.
Another benefit we got was,
so one of the officers' outlines
that we had provided for consultation
was on the feline eccentric here,
who is a transgender character with fantastical elements.
I'd written an outline that I was not at all confident in, but which I thought would probably
prompt a valuable discussion. And when we came to discuss it, one of the consultants, Ash McCallan,
discussed it very eloquently and then immediately suggested like half a dozen ways
that we could write the story that were drastically better than the version that
I had come up with, just leagues ahead of my original draft.
So it became immediately clear that they were the best person for the job.
So we hired her on a freelance basis to co-write this officer with us.
And she did a great job.
And Ash would later return to consult with us on other content.
So consultations can be great ways to find people to work with.
And another example of a benefit, this is a, I include this one as an example of how detailed
the consultation could get. The prudent secretary is a character from early in the game, they were
a very significant early character. And when we introduced them, it was just with that white block
of text there, the red block of text wasn't present. So we introduced them like this.
The secretary's gender is the subject of some debate in the company canteen.
The secretary's prudence, however, is not.
Now, this was a poor way to do it. The secretary is a powerful character, but that introduction
made them the subject of company gossip, and that takes power away from them.
However, we didn't want to just cut that line. One of the consultants made the point that they
personally sometimes quite enjoy it a little bit when people are a bit off balance about their
gender.
So the revision that they proposed and that we immediately implemented was the line in red
underneath it, which we just added to the end of that paragraph. Both these facts provide the
secretary with a great degree of satisfaction. So that revision puts power back in the secretary's
hands and is much more true to the character. And this discussion led us to discuss another
principle that's become a very common feature of our work.
And it was a principle that came up in the colonialism consultation as well. And it's this,
where does the power lie in this scene? So when you are representing the marginalized,
you have to ask that question because you are always making a statement about relative power
in a scene and therefore it is better to be intentional about it and make sure that you're
saying what you intended to. You want to make sure you're not disempowering a character accidentally.
You could look at is there a form of power they could seize in the scene that will
let them assert their agency. So having talked about those case studies I'm going to talk a
little bit about how we went about organizing these consultations.
And I'm going to start with the aims of a consultation
and what you want to get out of them.
So the first thing we want to get out of them
was to upscale our writers and to improve their ability
to write sensitively and effectively about more topics.
However, consultation also makes your own research more effective.
They basically give you a leg up on it.
An expert in the field can suggest sources
that will be particularly good or complementary.
And as a newcomer to the field,
it would probably be hard for you to find and identify those sources.
And finally, a consultation can give you expert feedback
on specific content that you've written and how to improve it.
The question of when to look for a consultant is a difficult one.
And it requires some humility.
You have to ask yourself, do you struggle to write a particular topic?
Do you lack confidence on it?
Are you feeling clumsy or under-informed when you do it?
If you're...
not able to recognize that, it's going to be difficult.
But you can look at how other people feel
about your work on that topic.
Do they feel it's cliched or simplistic or unrepresentative?
And once you've worked out that you will benefit
from a consultation, you need to be able to convey
these weaknesses clearly.
If you don't know what to ask for, people can't help you.
Finding a consultant can be difficult.
A good approach is to look for representative and expert
organizations.
Queerly Represent Me that I mentioned is a good one.
People of Color in Play.
We've also had good results from.
consulting or talking to IGDA special interest groups. They've helped us find people as well.
You can also approach experts you're aware of who have written or spoken informatively on the topic.
I think gained fluency in a consultant is a significant advantage. It helps if they
understand the constraints that we're working under.
But it's not vital, I think. If you find a consultant that isn't
experienced with games, you may just need to do a bit of extra work to help to
help them to understand where you're coming from, how you work, what you can do, what you can't do.
And you should be prepared to go through several layers of contact before you find someone.
Sometimes you'll reach out to someone who can't do it themselves or they're not available or
they're not interested or they're not suitable but they are happy to point you towards someone
who can and as long as you keep following that chain sooner or later you'll find someone just
keep going. So once you've found a consultant
you need to ensure that they have what they need. First, you need to be able to give them a clear
brief, which means explaining your goals for the session and what you want to get out of it.
You also need to provide them with access to the game and guidance for how they should engage with
it. There's no point throwing a 40-hour game at them and saying, just play. Point them at the
bits of it that will be useful for the consultation.
Similarly, you should share the relevant narrative
documentation with them.
But you should be selective.
Don't just share everything.
Their time is precious.
Share the stuff that's going to be most useful
for the consultation.
You also need to give them plenty of time to prepare,
to play the game, to read the documents,
to formulate their thoughts, to prepare any presentation.
And you need to pay them appropriately.
These are experts, and this is expert work.
The structure of a consultation will depend on the topic and the consultant,
and you should discuss it with them and agree something that works for both of you.
It is well worth investing time up front to do that.
The kind of model that we've used a few times that's worked quite well for us is
half day workshops, which may start with a presentation or a discussion.
then go into a Q&A session, and then go into a period
where you get feedback on specific samples
that you've provided to the consultant.
So there are a great many benefits
to doing these consultations.
The first one is that it will elevate your work. The whole point of this is it brings expertise
that you don't have. You will, as a result of consultations, you will be able to write stories
that you wouldn't have been able to before and you'll be able to do a better job of it.
They're also creatively energizing.
They act as this amazing injection
of new ideas and perspectives.
They're incredibly exciting.
And every time we've come out of one,
everyone involved has been absolutely buzzing
and kind of excited to put what we've learned into practice.
They also, we discovered,
act as very valuable training for writers.
What you learn in a consultation
will carry over into other work.
And while I focused on narrative consultations here,
we found that they are often valuable for other disciplines
too.
So we did a consultation recently
that someone from our art department came along to,
and they asked a bunch of art-focused questions
on good ways to represent a particular topic
sensitively and accurately.
So that is, that's the sum of it. You have now experienced the creation of Sunless Skies
narrative on a one-to-one scale. It is like you were there, but I hope I've shown how we
developed a clear communicable tone to get the team on the same page, how we used a strong
pitching process to ensure that that tone carried all the way through to the game,
and how we use consultations to address
areas of weakness and to elevate the work to make it something that we wouldn't have been able to do
without doing those consultations. No talk is complete without an appearance by one of
Sunless Sky's in-game mascots, the inadvisably large dog. Here he is, he's a very good boy.
And thank you very much for attending. I hope this has been useful and that you've enjoyed it.
Take care everyone.
You