All right, let us get started with, let's keep redlining out of the mood, multiverse,
metaverse, multiverse, all the verses.
All right, let's define it.
Keep that in your brain as we're going through this.
And then keep this one too.
This one's a little bit more loosey-goosey.
All right.
Well, who are we and where are we from?
That's me.
This is all I have to do for Kelly.
That's it.
A long time ago I worked on that game.
So after that game, I left that game company.
I think there, I'll briefly touch on sort of the through line here is certainly that
game company and my tenure with them was at a time when.
distribution really exploded and I saw just this huge shift in who gets to make
a game and what games are about and that really fascinated me and I moved more
towards looking at these different levers and mechanisms in the industry
and how they do determine
who gets to make a game and why and what they're about.
So that moves me more into publishing and business
development and developer relations and working,
going from one game at a time to like 200 at a time when I was at
OUYA and then 100 at a time when I was at Google Daydream and now
work with external developers creating
experiences with Niantic for the real world.
That's awesome. I still go Kelly equals journey to me.
That's all I needed.
All right. I'm a little different.
So I'm a senior producer at Niantic working with the Black Developer Initiative, which we will be talking about.
Before then, you'll see a pair of keys.
So before I got in the business, I was a concierge.
I used to tell people where to go, where the bathroom was.
Realistically, just where the bathroom was.
When I was working there, I had a colleague who was just like,
you like video games, you should work in video games.
And to me, that logic is like infallible.
But at the same time, I was like, not smart enough,
I don't think.
You know, I don't have an in.
I'm going to be a concierge.
She said, nope.
When my boyfriend has an opportunity at his work,
you're going to apply for it.
Fast forward a few months, she calls me up,
and she's like, there's an opportunity.
You're going to apply for it.
And she was like, OK, so I'm going to tell you the website.
Have you heard of a place called LucasArts?
And I was like.
I have such things.
So there I was a contract QA tester where I worked on Star Wars and Indiana Jones.
From there, I got promoted to assistant QA lead,
where I worked on some Lego games, you name it,
pretty much near the end of LucasArts.
From there, I ran into a couple of old coworkers
who were like, you need to leave LucasArts
and come over here, we got a laptop,
you're getting a phone, we got snacks,
and it's a mobile space.
So I said, okay, cool.
So I went over there, became QA lead at DNA West,
which used to be NG MoCo.
From there.
At some point, I guess I did a good enough job where they were like,
hey, do you want to be an event producer?
I said, sure, I'll do it until you find someone better.
A few months after that, they asked me if I wanted to be
a product owner of Transformers Legends.
Then eventually, I became a product owner of another Transformers game,
and I became the lead event producer for a Marvel game.
I'm the IP guy. That's where I got started.
I moved over to Wargaming from that point and then worked some other spots until Kelly
found me for this program we're going to talk about and kind of where my focus has been
the last bit.
So what is the Black Developer Initiative at Niantic?
It was founded during the BLM, you know, the height of the BLM era.
We were trying to figure out a way to do what was right, so we founded a program to promote
and empower black game AR developers,
geolocation developers to give them opportunities.
We want to see their experiences,
and that's what we're working towards.
But what we're going to kind of go through
is certain things that we kind of learned along the way.
You want to add anything, Kelly?
No, I don't think ... I think are we going to ...
Yeah, we're going to jump ...
Show the developers next, is that what it is?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. We've got this cool slide.
That's my favorite.
Yeah.
So today, these are the developers we've currently worked with.
Take a picture.
Reach out to them.
They're amazing developers, even not in the AR space.
They deserve the recognition that they deserve.
They are some of the hardest-working people I've got the pleasure to know during this process.
All of them are, you know, starting up, up-and-coming developers in the space that,
you know, needs more of these voices, needs more of this representation.
Some of them go from adventure games,
some of them had some really crazy AR,
like audio AR stuff is really dope.
I do wanna call out, should I call out Wicked Saints now
or leave it for later?
No, go for it, yeah.
Yeah, so Wicked Saints was the actual first team
that go through our cohort experience,
the first BDI program.
And though,
They didn't necessarily move forward with us the way we would like them to.
They were able to take their prototype, their pitch deck and everything that they built,
and they were able to get a pre-seed round of $1.1 million.
So yeah, it's pretty awesome.
Really quickly, just because this isn't about BDI, but it is the context in which this talk
isn't about, but this is the context in which we work together and obviously our foundation
for our learnings here.
Just to give a little bit more context, when we created it, we really initially took the
model of external publishing and the way we engage with developers through funding a concept
phase.
We made some adjustments and tweaks, added additional programming and mentorship to it.
That was the first iteration of BDI that these teams went through.
We have since taken some of these learnings that we're talking about, applied them to
reformatting it, and are kicking off a new cohort now.
That's the general context.
Is that better?
Okay.
Said it better than I could.
All right, let's go.
I doubt that.
Yeah, all right, we'll see.
All right, let's define the problem.
We are going to define the problem.
Here's the problem.
This is from the IGDA in 2019.
81% identify as white, 7% Hispanic, Latinx.
2% identify as black, African-American, African,
Afro-Caribbean.
Guess what?
If I was to go back to 2014, it's the same statistic.
Hasn't changed.
We have newer, newer D&I initiatives, but at the same
time, that number has not moved up.
So part of the problem is access, opportunity, and
funding, right?
We know this.
We offer this.
This is what kind of most of these programs do.
But it's still imperfect.
It's not a way for us to be able to fully engage a team
beyond one of these.
length of time, like if we're just sitting here doing this for five months, what happens after the fifth month? What happens after the sixth month?
Because we're finding that in certain instances with people go through these groups
confirmation biases appear, people playing or having issues asking for help.
They don't want to go through this program, even though, or a program like it, even though we're offering
access, opportunity, and funding because it's seen as, you know, a weakness.
Even people who go through programs like this, who then hear of other people going through
programs like this, offer prejudice against programs like this.
That was good for me at the time, but not necessarily good for me as in my next position
or my next spot, my next group.
Whatever way it goes, it's the same win states.
using the same success metrics.
So here's the thing.
I don't know about all of you, but I
know that whenever I go to a company or every place I go to,
I feel like I have to be the hardest worker in the room.
I have to be exceptional just to be normal.
And this is exactly what kind of happens
within programs or initiatives or anything that
runs like this, is you're just looking for the exceptional
instead of just.
a perspective, a new point, providing experience.
It's like when you're at that point looking
for those metrics of success, and then you
look at what your company is going to establish in terms
of experience and what they would green light or publish
or produce or whatever, a lot of times they'll just then go,
well, they don't have the experience.
Well, here's the thing.
How does a team get experience if they're never
given opportunity in the first place?
This one I thought was really clever.
Hopefully you'll see the dichotomy in this.
So here's the thing, right?
We at Niantic, people who are part of the Web3 wave,
blockchain, crypto, however you name it,
we are in this emergent technology.
We are now at a moment of time where people are starting
to establish themselves and given.
potential opportunities.
But the problem is, emergent technology is the divide
between resources, excuse me,
people with resources and those without.
Eventually, when the divide is kind of nullified by the fact
that there's been mass adoption, it's no longer valuable.
It's no longer as opportunistic as a lot
of people can kind of grow up with this.
And I mean, look, this doesn't just happen in tech.
It happens everywhere.
Any place you work, any place you go, you will see that there are those with resources and those without.
But I say that all kind of doom and gloom like we can change that. Everyone in this room at least
is interested in learning how to do more or learning what we did so that's the start.
But overall the current message is the barrier to entry changes.
but the message is staying the same.
The more we innovate, the more we discriminate.
The industry is kind of optimized
with a certain person in mind,
with a certain amount of education,
biases intertwined in a pipeline.
I call it a pipeline of privilege.
You know, and when we have teams that kind of go through this
who might not necessarily have the same access
to these pipelines, like the teams we showed you earlier,
those biases play against them.
It's not built for teams who are just up and coming.
It's built for established status quo.
We need to think about creating pipelines that
provide those opportunities.
that avoid, you know, the socioeconomic side of things
that look to provide opportunities for people
who are interested in this space.
Because it's a huge effing problem.
The current message is we all need to work on this together.
Spoiler alert to the end of this.
Niantic can't do this alone. We are just one company pushing our one objective, our one mission with this, and wanting to see the space as diverse.
But everyone here who has the opportunity to work with the company, we're going to need your help.
The industry needs your help.
So here's where the metaverse comes in.
I'm sure some of you are interested.
John Hanke put out a blog post about defining the metaverse.
Niantic's is very real world based.
But this quote specifically is what stuck with me.
Helping to achieve this meta shift is our purpose at
Niantic, but we recognize that it won't be solely our work.
Such a massive evolution will require the work of big
companies, startups, and individuals around the world
to become a reality.
I don't want those individuals, those startups, and those companies to be only certain companies,
certain individuals.
If we're going to be looking at a new boom, a new opportunity here, moving into the metaverse
or whatever, we need to define lines that are free and open for all to be able to express
themselves, show opportunities, and present growth.
Why it needs to be done. This one's probably a silly slide, but it's true.
So this starts with, I have a friend. Yes, I have friends, believe it or not.
And this is kind of what got me thinking about this and wanting to work in this
space and understanding that maybe the origin story I gave you of me was
probably a little bit, I don't know, rare for this space.
So my friend, she reached out to me and was like,
hey, my son's really interested in video games
and he wants to know if there's an internship at your work.
And I said, nope.
And he's like, well, can you set up something for him?
I was like, no, we don't really have any type of internships
that doesn't count into like the senior year of college
in a role or something specific like that.
We don't really have anything for someone younger,
someone looking for other.
opportunities or space.
So I took that and I was like, OK, I can't,
I could be like, you can come sit at my desk,
but it's not the same thing as kind of experiencing it.
And I felt it would be disservice to be like, hey,
you know what?
Wait till you're in your mid-20s,
you're working at a desk, someone's
going to offer you an opportunity of a lifetime,
you're going to have to take it, you're
going to have to nail that job, and then you're
going to have to work really, really hard
to stay in this industry.
But then you'll be in it.
I felt like that was not the message I wanted to be able to
give them, because it's not fair.
I know my journey, some pun intended, I know my journey is
different than yours, but I wanted to be able to provide a
more open space.
So that's kind of what got me thinking about how do we
increase the devs in this space?
What can I do?
More devs in the space equal more experiences, more points of view, wouldn't you say, Kelly?
Yeah.
They make different stuff.
Yeah, like, I'm going to tell you, some of the designs that I've seen come through the
BDI program that we've had show a lot of different experiences that other game designs don't.
They're not just match threes.
They're built on experiences that they have from soft post-apocalyptic.
worlds that are founded because they are negativity in the world and everyone was doing wrong and just wanting to write those rights.
To those showing the whole world covered in water because humans need to do better.
To ones being able to, want to be able to just print their words and have them be seen on the streets through special locations.
Social, economic.
based ones that in social activism games,
that are wanting to empower kids of the future
so that they can have courage.
I mean, that's not like, no knock in Candy Crush,
but that's not Candy Crush, right?
This is something that someone is experiencing
and they need to tell these stories.
I want them to be able to tell their stories.
I want them to be able to see their lights.
Because I think more points of view
broaden everyone's horizon.
Wealth, let's just face it.
Independence begins with money.
With money, you can have security.
You can have longevity.
Because one of the biggest things that we all know,
those who work in the industry for a while,
is longevity is tough.
If you're able to survive a space
or be a dev in the space for longer than a couple years,
you're doing something all right.
But for that, it means you need security.
You need wealth.
One of the tenants, one of the massive tenants out of all the things that we think about in BDI, and this is truly
almost nebulous, is thinking about it in terms of, you know, generational wealth.
Being able to have someone be able to provide for someone who can provide for someone, provide for someone.
Having those opportunities to have access to wealth means that they can tell their stories, being able to tell their stories.
mean that they can be able to keep telling their stories for generations.
But it does start with money.
We need to be able to provide money in some way, shape, or form.
Can I add something to that one?
Please.
Because I like this one.
Going back to that statistic that we found,
reached back all the way to 2014 of
two percent of developers in the industry that identify as black.
I'm assuming it was there at best the previous decade, likely even lower.
And I think about, again, my own journey through independent game development, that explosion
of digital distribution, how many people were shut out of the wealth that was generated
by that shift in our industry.
And right now with XR, we're in a similar state.
It's a new opportunity.
The developers that get in now.
will have more opportunities and will be leaders just a year or two or three from now.
I think we're already seeing that in the VR space and we're seeing the trends of that in AR again.
So this is a really big deal.
It's like, you know, striking with the iron's hot.
Yeah.
This is the moment.
We could do a lot.
We need to be able to do a lot together
with this type of stuff.
Because we don't want to wait until web 4.0,
whatever that is.
I don't want to know what 4.0 is.
But yeah, Kelly jumped the gun.
Moment of time equals opportunity.
Oh, sorry.
No, no worries, you're good, you're good.
Because what I found is representation is both inspiration and innovation.
I actually wrote this, I'm pretty proud of it to be honest.
The TLDR of this really short sentence is if we are to grow as an industry and as a
people we need to pave the way for others and stop following the same cycles that we
find ourselves in.
You know, it can go from the ways to how you produce things,
to how you hire, to how you are looking for devs,
maybe with more experience,
but maybe you might want to take a chance on somebody
to kind of go back, find that experience,
help them grow in this industry
instead of discounting them right off the rip.
Like I said earlier, we need your help in this.
This is something that we need to all be aware of.
We need to make changes.
You know, initiatives and programs like this live or die by participation.
So if you have one or you know of one, help with it.
So what can you do, though?
So we have these.
These are just some ideas.
These are some things that we kind of take a look at when we work with our teams or current
cohorts and our new cohorts as well.
Yeah, share your cheat codes, which I got from the incredible Trinidad Hermodai.
You know, the idea of just all those little things that we've all picked up along the
way in the jobs, especially in, I think, our generation and older.
We didn't have a lot of formal training on the job.
We picked up things as we went.
How can you take a moment, share with someone else
like that trick you learned or that template you always use
when you're starting a game design document?
These little things I think I sometimes don't even realize
that I picked up along the way
and yeah, let other people into that.
I'm a big fan of the Kobayashi Maru from Star Trek.
because I like the idea that, you know, Kirk didn't believe there was an unwinnable scenario.
And so when I think of cheat codes, that's what I think of.
Just because someone says you can't do it doesn't mean you can't find a way to cheat it.
Because sometimes cheating's good. Sometimes.
Look at a way to be less optimized. You wrote this one, so...
Yeah, it goes back to what John was talking about earlier.
I think when I think of the system,
like how do we do things the fastest way possible?
That is often including.
biases that come through these systems that have been sort of copy and pasted throughout the history of industry from
Who we hire, the colleges we're hiring from, the way we organize our meetings, the way we communicate online
There's so many ways in which it's just easy to do it the the way we've always done it
and
It's not really about becoming less optimized,
but it just takes that little bit of extra effort
to think about how can you do it differently.
How can you be including people in a conversation?
How can you be looking at taking your university outreach
efforts and shifting them to colleges
your company normally hasn't looked at?
And it just takes a moment, and then it
becomes the optimized way.
And it becomes a new process, but it just
takes a beat to create a different system.
Yep, yep.
But also spend time elevating your Black, Indigenous,
other people of color at work.
One of the big things that I have to shout out
is that through my journey, through my way of getting
through the year, I had people who believed in me.
People who I normally wouldn't expect to believe in me,
but they believed in me, they supported me,
and they pushed me through.
And I'm completely 100% grateful for that.
And I can guarantee anyone else in your space who might be like,
hey, maybe there is a QA guy there,
but he's really interested in production, take a chance.
Or maybe someone seems really confident about game design,
take a chance.
Or when you're meeting other developers in the space,
if you have the option to work with them, take a chance.
See what they can do, because I guarantee
you'll get some stuff that's going to be great.
Do you have a D&I program?
in your team or office, offer your support,
offer your time, offer your help.
If you don't, make one, or go ask how to make one,
or go try to work towards that, or build
ERGs that are within your company that you can kind of help
support and perpetuate this stuff.
I mean, I love this note that Kelly added this
like last minute, so I was surprised.
But literally, consider how you, your team, your company,
is setting up black, indigenous, people of color employees
for future success.
This includes pay equity, career development,
opportunities for advancement.
Again, I was fortunate, but I know I'm an outlier.
I know I'm in rarefied space when it comes to this.
I would like to change that.
And like I said, don't have a D&I program work?
Find out how to start one.
Maybe if it doesn't have one,
maybe find one that does have one.
whatever works with that space.
Yeah. If I may ask you first.
Okay. John has ever propensity
to just jump in when I know the answer and stuff.
So I'm like, John, just tell me exactly what I'm supposed to talk.
So the two ways I see that most of
that second to last bullet point teams falling short.
I guess one is,
Actually, they're both kind of related to the same thing,
which is giving teams that do the work in hiring more
inclusively, but then are either under-leveling or underpaying
those people, which then set them back for the next three
to five years, at least, on their career trajectory.
Because as you know, in a lot, it's becoming.
less popular in some sectors,
but for the most part you negotiate your next job based on your last salary,
based on your last title.
So that's something to consider.
Then the second is, again,
I think we come from the school of we learned,
we got.
promoted by you know what it's like battlefield promotion like somebody
suddenly the opportunity came up and it was like you do the job and then you
figure it out and we succeeded in that but that is definitely not the most
inclusive way to go about promoting and fostering talent and so become a better
manager
Get your managers to become better managers.
Really think about how you're fostering career development
and those opportunities for advancement.
Be clear on your job ladders,
I think would be the third one.
That's great, yeah, like those Battlefield promotions,
I can guarantee I didn't have as much gray
in my beard as I do now.
Yeah, I was definitely.
A lot gray in your beard too?
Yeah, that's fair.
Well, I mean, that's all we have.
I will say that at Niantic, we try to move quick
through meetings and give people some time back,
but I guess I cut through this a little short.
But I want to thank you all for taking the time
to sit down and listen to us kind of talk about it.
Real TLDR, TLDR of all this is,
if you're working in the metaverse,
you're working in these spaces,
make them more inclusive, please.
It starts with you.