So, yes, first time.
OK, awesome.
I did not know WriteClub's happening.
I'm excited.
Maybe I can redeem myself this year,
since I came in a really close fifth last time.
Really close, I swore.
OK, so thank you.
I'm pleasantly surprised to have this big a crowd.
When I saw the crowd outside the other room, I was like, OK.
I'm forgotten.
Thank you for not forgetting me.
So who am I?
I'm a narrative design researcher.
Is this loud enough?
We good?
OK.
The long answer is I'm a film student turned web designer,
turned art student, turned comic screenwriter,
turned programming teacher, turned blah, blah, blah, blah,
blah, blah, blah, turned narrative design researcher.
This is why editing is important.
Point is, I did a lot of stuff, came around
to narrative design, and now that's
what I call myself because explaining all of this
is tough.
but who are you?
So just a show of hands,
who here has written any interactive narrative,
worked on a game, anything?
Okay, good.
Who's designed an interactive narrative?
Okay.
I may get to skip ahead on a lot of slides here.
Who's mapped an interactive narrative,
like actually made maps for it?
Okay, a few of you.
Okay.
I'll tell you guys when you can fall asleep then.
And who's coded an interactive narrative?
Yay, some ear-coding hands.
I always love those.
OK.
Twine?
Other tools?
OK.
Awesome.
I still have to spend some time.
What?
If the twine counts, then sure.
Yeah.
Well, twine can't count.
Anyway.
OK.
So as you saw from that earlier slide,
I have a lot of different things that I do in life
and have done.
But the one that I figured I'd focus on today
is this annual challenge that I have,
where every year in January and March,
I get 60 new digital media graduate students, most of whom
have had one programming class, one visual design class,
zero creative writing classes.
And 75% of them are in their first year
of speaking English full time.
So it's a bit of a challenge.
The last bit was kind of an accident.
We thought it would be really cool
to make our program more international,
and we learned, careful what you wish for,
because our program is very international,
and it's super cool, but it's a challenge.
So over the course of 12 weeks
with these relatively fresh faces,
I asked them to create an interactive multimedia narrative
that is not a simple choose-your-own-adventure.
It must not be game first, which is to say it has to be really about story.
It has to be a good experience the first time you play it,
not necessarily a positive one, but an enjoyable, in whatever sense, one, engaging.
And it must invite replayability.
Oh, and also they have to learn three-act dramatic structure,
learn character archetypes, learn basic screenwriting, cinematography,
editing, and directing principles in the same 12 weeks.
But somehow out of all of that, it's the prohibition against choose your own adventure that seems to actually freak them out the most.
Which really confused me, but that caused me to go down this line of research.
So, then they go home and think about it, and at least a quarter of them actually come up with something kind of brilliant.
Usually things that would take at least a year to produce, but brilliant ideas.
Usually we end up teaming the students up
into groups of four or five,
and we try to build small parts of those projects,
trying to get them to scale back expectations.
And sometimes they don't,
and we get some glorious train wrecks.
I should say, I have not timed these remarks
to these slides, so these are not necessarily
the glorious train wrecks.
But often there are some amazing moments of insight
and some accidental brilliance,
probably some intentional brilliance too
that we don't recognize until later.
So the weird thing is that again and again during the project,
students come back to this idea of how
do you give meaningful choices without it
being a choose your own adventure.
And you guys know the answer to this.
And we give them examples ranging from Alabaster
to the Zombies of the Walking Dead.
And they say, so we just have to add some action
to our choose your own adventure, maybe a mini game?
So then we go to F and G, used to be facade,
now it's fire watch for F, G being gone home of course,
which students especially latch on to,
which I find incredibly gratifying.
And then they all decide they're gonna make a story
about memories triggered by objects
and therefore that must be amnesia
and therefore we end up with 14 proposals
for stories about amnesia.
And at first, we kind of wondered
if this was maybe just because the starting
point for New Riders of Interactive Fiction is
the last game they played.
But then we realized, because my main co-teacher and I
are with it a decade of each other, a lot of these
reminded us of games that we played way back
when we were kids.
So we actually began to wonder if maybe the problem was
that a lot of our students don't have a sense of video game
history.
But that seemed kind of odd because a lot of our students
are in their early 20s, but we also
have some that are near retirement age.
2 3rds of them come from China, India, North Africa, South
America.
There's such a diverse range of cultures and experiences
and games that could influence their stories.
We wondered, why did a quarter of the projects
keep ending up being detective stories or amnesia stories?
This is territory that's been covered.
There are still, I'm sure, many awesome amnesia stories
to be told, and I love a good mystery.
But we wanted to kind of see if maybe there's
something else they could do.
So this is the point when I actually
started looking at their maps, such as the one
over there on the right.
Sorry, the left.
And I started looking at sort of classic adventure maps.
That's actually part of Planetfall,
I believe, on the other side there.
And we realized that basically we'd
been sort of treating the story maps as site maps.
So they were basically kind of saying, oh, well,
we're going to put this on the internet,
so it'll be a web page.
So we'll make home pages.
You can see home page over there.
And that wasn't really giving a sense of story
or a sense of place.
But when we tried to actually get them to map out things in terms of place, then we ended up with basically...
Well, I wish we ended up with Planetfall, but, you know, we ended up with sort of maps.
And basically we'd end up with the classic inventory
oriented adventure game kind of thing that is great
and I love playing, but again, since this class
was interactive narrative, we wanted to sort of
do something more, which is why I wanted to do this talk,
because I really wanted to sort of show a situation
where we're really pushing on this idea of,
no, you can't make a game.
I mean, I would love it if I could tell the students,
ha ha, just kidding, you can make games now,
because I love playing the games they make.
but instead have to be the mean teacher who's like,
no, this quarter, no games.
So as I mentioned, we were trying
to have them work with existing tools.
And with the tight time crunch, we
discovered that they often were just sort of using
the tutorials and saying, oh, well,
since the Undone tutorial has hit points,
then we have to have hit points.
And that must be how these things work.
So it was sort of a strange variation on the whole language shapes thought thing
I don't know if you guys went to the session yesterday about writing if English is your second language
But here we had two cases of English is the second language plus programming is a second language. So it was kind of a pain
But then we had the overachievers
So these two groups, which I just put side by side
to show quick clips, produced a fully interactive
top-down prototype and a fully produced cut scene
in the first week of the project.
So we're expecting, you know, sketch prototypes
and these students are jumping ahead to this.
But it's actually the advanced groups
that I was more worried about
and why I really wanted to do this mapping thing.
Okay, another quick survey question.
Who's played a really good looking game
that just didn't make sense?
Okay. Who's been sorely disappointed by a game that you know has some amazing programming
behind it or some amazing ideas and it's just awkward? Yeah, okay.
So My Secret Shame, I've never finished Heavy Rain, it's the only game where I've ever actually
given up and read the walkthrough and watched the YouTube videos because I just could not
deal.
I love a lot that's going on, and this is not a bash Heavy Rain session.
In fact, one of the things that I had to cut from this talk for length is a re-engineering
of Heavy Rain that some students and I have been trying to work on.
It's a theoretical exercise, we're not going to actually, like, make it.
But we think there's enough good stuff in there.
But the point is, it's difficult, as I'm sure many of you can appreciate.
In fact, this is sort of the remnants
of that part of the talk that I took out.
This was our starting map for how heavy rain works.
And without going into details,
and there are no spoilers in case you haven't played it
in the last six years, in which case, get on that.
But the dark area is actually the only part
where there's really a lot of evidence
that you're having an impact on the world.
There's sort of the minor touches
that happened in the first part.
And that's roughly three quarters of the story that takes place with you only sort of having
these sort of cosmetic changes and being led through the story.
And by the time you actually get to that part where it's super amazing what's going on,
you've cut off your finger, you've calmed a crying baby, you've microwaved a pizza,
you've set the table, you've run around yelling like a madman like five times.
And so in my case, I just didn't make it to the end.
Just out of curiosity, how many people did make it to the end of Heavy Rain?
Awesome.
You're better people than I am.
So this goes without saying for this crowd,
but good stories have a beginning, a middle, and an end.
And the reason we worry so much about mapping,
or at least I do, and my group does,
is because we want players to reach the end.
Or at least a stopping point where they feel happy.
Usually.
Basically, as long as they don't rage quit,
and they say, okay, I'm stopping because
I appreciate what's going on here,
I'm okay if they don't get to the end.
So this next part is the part where I might
fast forward a little bit.
I decided I would sort of go through some of the
basic shapes that we look at just to sort of do a
quick orienteering guide and then do one bigger
worked example at the end, time permitting.
So show of hands, people who are familiar with
the diamond structure, okay.
Loops in stories, just saying, I'm sure many of you know.
Okay, we'll go through these then.
So the diamond, which was actually brought up yesterday
in Cassie's talk about all choice, no consequences,
basically is the title of her talk,
all choice, no consequences.
You give the player a choice,
you then give them a result from the choice,
and then maybe you give them some choices.
In this case, I chose to use little emoji
because it seemed like there is no choice, why not?
And you go back to the thing you're at.
So they're great because you don't break your story,
but at the same time, some writers and players
hate them because they want to break their story.
If you do this, you're sort of in the safe zone of, OK,
I'm just kind of leading you along through my story now,
because every choice you make might
customize what happens a little bit, but not too much.
But I bring up the diamond, because even though it
seems like kind of an obvious loopback
technique in the time saver.
it's often underappreciated for the things you can do with it,
such as giving the player a different way of interpreting
the same events, or giving players
a choice between the right road, if you
believe in having a right road in your story,
and the hard road.
So maybe you're trying to make a fail-proof game.
Maybe you don't believe in having the death
thing going on in your games.
Or maybe you want to go back to the days of Infocom
and infinite saves and restarts.
I wouldn't mind that.
sometimes. But anyway, so maybe you give the players one way through where they just do
the right thing, they solve the puzzle, whatever you're on, and then the other way is, okay,
you gotta do a whole bunch of stuff if you're gonna get there. This is that sort of diagrammed
out. It's sort of a silly example because I wanted to just keep these super simple and
get to the actual meaty stuff.
The diamond here sort of reads sideways,
although you start at the top with,
you have to choose correctly.
And from there, you can either choose wrong or right.
If you choose right, you're fantastic,
and you miss out on going on your fabulous quest.
If you wanted a shortcut in the game, great, you got it.
On the other hand, maybe it's punishment
for the player being wrong,
so suddenly you have to go on this quest,
and you refuse to do it, so then you're in the dungeon.
But then you're given a chance to redeem yourself.
So now it's sort of a redemption story.
Like, you know, you've seen that you're a bad guy
in the eyes of the king, so you're gonna go on his quest.
Or maybe you daringly escaped the dungeon,
and so now you've decided that you're going to
redeem yourself in the eyes of the people
and go on that redemptive quest.
So you might end up on the same quest three different ways,
but in one sense it's you volunteered,
in another sense it's you've sort of been enslaved into it,
and in a third sense you've decided to do it
for your own sort of anti-heroic tendencies.
So your point of view of your motivation for the quest
changes a little bit.
And you don't actually have to write any additional code
or anything, you've just sort of thrown in a couple
of extra writing options and ta-da, you're fantastic
for whatever reason you thought you were fantastic.
So this is the kind of stuff that I do with my students
that drives them crazy, we play games like Spot the Diamond
and it's not the two things that are diamond shaped
as a hint.
I'll just have you guys look at it for like 10 seconds.
There's actually a couple of them.
So, this is a pretty simple story map,
so there's not a lot going on,
but you'll notice those aren't really diamond-shaped.
And this is actually one of the things
that the part of my research we're not gonna get to today
is getting into, which is sort of.
auto-remapping to try to find these shapes in maps people draw. So, you know, when you
draw your twine map and it's a mess, maybe you're just trying to get all your squares
to line up nicely or not have too many crosses. And our concern is more, let's try to actually
pull out these shapes that appear that might point to something going on in your story
that is desirable or not desirable.
And those of you who have done graphics programming can probably appreciate it's a pain in the neck to try to actually get a bunch of objects to move and respect each other's space and so on.
Our prototyping has been using OmniGraffle, which while a lovely tool, is not great when you get into like hundreds and hundreds of junctions on top of each other.
Anyway, so here we have...
these shapes that are not at all diamond-shaped.
But there's actually two ways here,
where in one direction the player goes off to the side,
and then down, and in the other the player goes
over and down and then back up.
But in this case it's not really up,
they just move the node down there.
So there's a lot of tricky stuff
to be done with directionality
as far as where are you trying to say
the action actually is taking place.
But if you follow the arrows,
which again is part of what we're trying to automate.
then you end up realizing, okay, well, pretty much
all my choices are going to end up sticking me
in this middle section here where something happens.
But there's also something else going on here
that is not so good, and that is a loop.
So loops are fantastic when you're trying to hit
every branch in a conversation tree,
although they can make your NPCs sound like dimwits
when you have the, you know,
could you tell me that again?
And they sometimes cause the player to realize that he or she is not making a difference in the world at all.
So, once again, in the interest of simplicity, although there are many complex examples on my website,
here's sort of the basic loop.
You have to make a decision.
Okay, I did it. Great.
Okay, do you think we did the right thing?
Hey, we have to make a big decision again.
Okay, I did it. Great.
Oh, we're in a loop.
So obviously there'd be a way out of this loop, but...
It can be really frustrating if you're in something like this.
This is a reduction project I'm currently working on.
I would be super impressed if anyone can guess what I'm
actually reducing here.
We can talk about it afterwards if you figure it out.
But this is actually only act one of this particular story.
And I'm actually not even done with Act 1, I just had to, finally two nights ago, say
this is going in as is, so my apologies.
This is the cleanest version I have so far.
But as you can see, there are a lot of sort of potential loopy areas.
I realize you can't see the arrows very well.
But you can certainly see there's a lot of areas
where sort of things dovetail back into each other
and you can get stuck in a corner really easily.
So imagine you spend a bunch of time over there
on the left side as a player,
and you're wandering through all these nodes
and thinking I'm making progress,
and then suddenly you're back to,
hey, you should investigate that same thing again.
Really frustrating, and it kind of breaks the reality
of you're investigating this thing
and you have a competent team helping you.
So once again, we'll do a little practice.
Can you spot the loop?
So again, I apologize.
The arrows may be a little small.
These slides will be up on my website as well as on the GDC
site, so you can look at them later if you find this game at
all entertaining, by which I mean the game of
spotting these things.
But if you look at the arrows, you'll see that there's sort
of a down over up.
loop happening on the left and on the right. So basically we have to befriend that darn skunk.
Which stinks. Sorry. I know. I know. I was reworking these slides at two in the morning.
Give me a break. Okay. So you probably know if you're making these if you've been writing
interactive narratives for a while, but
One caution I have for people is that once you start actually mapping your work out,
instead of sort of having that mental separation of,
oh, well, I'm the writer and I'm writing my stuff,
and I'll just give that to the other guy who will do the interactions or whatever,
then there becomes this temptation of,
oh, I'm a really creative person and this thing connects to this thing,
and I can totally make this work,
and then suddenly you've made a whole bunch of loops you didn't mean to make.
which is in fact what happened here with this student project.
One member of a five-person group
came up with some brilliant ideas at the 11th hour
and put them in without anyone else knowing.
Yeah, it was a kind of ugly beta test.
OK, in the interest of time, skipping ahead here.
So the zipper.
which is one that we named ourselves, as far as I know,
which I think is kind of cute.
Basically, lets players make minor non-story breaking
choices until you're ready to deal with major ones.
Talk yesterday actually did a really good job of dividing
things up into sort of choices and major branches.
So this is sort of the choice area, and then at the bottom
you have your major branch.
So it's basically an extended remix of the diamonds that we
looked at at the beginning.
The difference is that with this,
you're at some point planning to have a major branch
that actually is important, like an avoidable death,
or an optional romance, or something else
where you actually wanna sort of have,
where you sort of wanna have people
having a real effect on the story.
So, with the diamond, you can extend,
or sorry, the zipper, you can extend the diamonds
as much as you want, and then branch
only when you absolutely need to,
or when it's time to do it.
One example that people may not have seen of this
is Long Story, which is a really cute game that I only
found recently, which surprises me, given my job.
But it does a really nice job of balancing the there's
a little light mystery going on, but at the same time,
you actually can have a relationship
with most of the major characters.
You pick your gender.
You have three gender choices.
And.
the game is very nice about accommodating any of those decisions in different ways.
So you don't just feel like it's, you know, hello, Marcel, you actually have some kind
of like sense that the story is actually going where you want it to.
That being said, there are a lot of places where the story ends up sort of branching
back and you're saying, well, why am I back in this weird mystery that I decided I didn't
care about because I'm more interested in my boyfriend right now.
But.
I mean, that's the backbone of the story, so you have to get back there eventually.
But what's really nice about Long Story is actually it's ironically very short episodes.
So I think with the time between episodes, the Long Story folks are really able to sort
of focus on, let's make sure every relationship option is meaningful and different and cool,
and then we'll have the sort of mystery story that just plays out as it does.
So it's an interesting shift in priorities.
that works really well with the sort of zipper structure
because they can jump off when they need to
into these other parts.
So I promised narrative mapping frameworks,
so this will be the narrative mapping frameworks bit
in my last five minutes here.
But that's probably for the best
because this part gets into the really dense stuff
that I have a lot about online.
So I created map templates to try to get my students to
not basically recreate Zork or insert last game they played.
With the idea being that these are just starting points.
The idea is that they fill in the blanks,
or the lettered blanks, with story idea,
and they try to make a story that navigates.
You know, it's kind of like when you're in grade school
and you get the five paragraph essay,
and you're told, you know,
paragraph one is your topic statement,
paragraph five is your conclusion.
Same idea here.
The main idea, though, is to get students to not think
about programming constraints, and that's
why I wanted to present this to you guys as well.
The idea being to really make things visible.
It's really easy, especially with projects like the two
that I showed with my superstar students who created
cool stuff in the first week.
It's really easy to have the coding members of the team
get buried in this stuff so the writers don't really
necessarily fully appreciate what's going on anymore or maybe appreciate it but sort
of don't quite understand, okay, do I assign seven points to that? Do I assign five points
to that? Do I have to assign points? What's going on here? So with the mapping structures,
the idea is that we have sort of a more open way of visually communicating.
what you're trying to do.
And on the writing side, the goal
is to better communicate options and outcomes to your players
as well.
They won't actually see your map, of course.
But if you can say, oh, well, over here,
this is going to have a major effect,
then you might be able to actually write something
to hint at that.
So the one template I'm going to get to
is this lock and key template, which needs a new name.
So if you have any ideas, let me know, because it implies puzzle.
And it's not supposed to be just puzzles.
It's based just on the idea that the player needs to do X before Y can happen.
It's basically Boolean logic for people who have trouble visualizing flowcharts.
And it's a pretty simple idea.
The idea is you have these numbered nodes, and any set that have the same number, or one unit,
with L and U being locked and unlocked, and K being the key.
So up at the top in the zoomed-in version, we have 2K,
and we have 2L that can get us to 2K, which then lets us
unlock 2U.
And in this case, I put them all near each other
for space saving, but you can have them farther apart.
But the idea is that you actually
have a way of saying, no, these two things are actually
the same, they're just spatially apart.
which might seem a little weird,
but this worked really well with one student group,
the group that actually did the really nice looking video.
They decided to use Twine initially,
and they actually entered the template into Twine,
and then typed in their story idea.
And only after that did they say,
okay, now let's actually start breaking this thing up
and figuring out what do we really wanna tell,
let's throw out this template idea,
and actually make it into something.
What's funny is all their scribbles on the left actually ended up turning into something on the right
that looked very much like the map I'd originally given them.
But that's actually the physical layout of the insane asylum.
The story's about a journalist investigating an insane asylum.
because we still can't quite get away from the broken people,
crazy theme of interactive fiction.
But I think it's actually kind of a cool thing,
so we'll go with it.
Anyway, but what was really cool here
is that whether accidentally or on purpose,
they actually ended up sort of creating
this physical landscape that mapped the mental breakdown
of the woman, sort of the, if she goes one direction,
it's more into she's going to be imprisoned forever.
And if she goes the other direction,
then she might get out.
But since there's this whole question of is she crazy
or is she not throughout the story,
it was a really nice thematic overlay
with puzzles and stuff, but it basically showed me
they'd sort of learned something from their play through
of Gone Home as far as like how to physically tell a story,
but in a much more subtle way,
even though what they were really doing here
was sort of puzzle making.
So sadly, we do not have time to play the game
because I'm told I have one minute, but it is online.
There's plenty more to see, however.
See, I knew this would happen.
This is the stuff that we're currently working on.
This is not a big walking ad for my lab, which is the narrative
lab at Northeastern.
But I do hope you guys will come visit stuff
as we start to put it up.
Since mapping is kind of a reductive process,
I figured I should end by sort of doing the reductive thing
on my own talk, so that's the whole talk
in sort of three things.
The first two being things I hope everyone's doing.
The last one being my advice of,
if you wanted to tell an entirely cinematic story,
well, it's actually gotten cheaper now to make a movie
than to necessarily make a good game, so make a movie.
Speculation about the future.
So we're still in the discovery phase on games like this,
games like Gone Home, Her Story,
currently all still are getting comments like,
I've never played anything like this before.
Each is a unique experience
because the story is so personal.
But when you reduce these games to the most basic mechanics,
hiding everything in plain sight through good level design,
they point towards a future in which everyone
will have seen something like these games.
And that excites me, because if everybody
has seen games like this, then maybe people
will invent more games like this,
and this will become just a general medium
for critical comment.
Maybe your game will be our generation's Ulysses,
although hopefully that means your game's
an interesting and challenging work,
and not that everyone says they'll read it,
even though they're not going to.
So finally, because I know I'm over time,
good stories leave the player wanting more,
because they relish the experience,
not because it felt incomplete.
unless the ending was supposed to make them feel that way,
like this talk, which is perpetually to be continued.
So this is my obligatory thank you,
because the Lowell Institute actually paid for me to be here.
And here is my contact info, so I hope you will be in touch.
And thank you for staying over by one minute.
Class dismissed.