Right, so today I'm going to be talking a bit about the art of Dear Esther and the environments
of the game and how the environments are an important part of the storytelling process
of the game. But I think the first thing I should really do is just kind of go over the
concept of Dear Esther and some of the history behind it and its origins just so that you
can get a better idea of why the environments are such an important part of the storytelling
process of the game.
So...
Dearest has started out life as a source engine mod in 2008 and was originally conceived by
Dan Pinchbeck as an experiment to see what would happen if you stripped out traditional
gameplay from a first person game space and instead just tried to use that space to do
something different.
outside of the normal traditions of gameplay.
And in this case, it was just designed to see
if you could use that space to tell
like a deep ambiguous story about a dying man
stranded on a Hebridean island,
coming to terms with a tragic loss.
And to kind of tell this story
just through exploring the environment
and being absorbed in the story itself.
And as a research project, it actually did pretty well.
It got released, and it got 50,000 downloads
within the first six months.
And it gained quite a cult following in the modding scene.
And it's kind of around this time
that I stumbled across it myself.
And although I found it really captivating, really inspiring,
I couldn't help but feel that it wasn't quite fulfilling
its true potential, especially being built upon this idea
that it's around exploring environments and telling
a story through the environments.
So in the original mod you had this fantastically engaging voiceover narrative that plays as you
explore throughout the island and that not only gives you glimpses into the protagonist's past
and his reasons for being on the island but more importantly more interestingly for me was that it
gives you all these glimpses into the history of the island itself and its past inhabitants and
all the various plagues and misfortunes that have
that have plagued them throughout the history of the island.
And for me, this is the most interesting part of the experience,
because all of these little bits of information that were coming through in the voice narrative
were really helping me to build this world in which the story takes place.
But the problem I saw with the original mod was that this kind of visual detail that was coming through,
this audio detail that was coming through the narrative,
really wasn't being represented with the environments.
And as a result, there was this kind of real disconnection
between the visual experience and the auditory experience.
And.
As an environment artist, I kind of felt really drawn to this project because I felt that,
you know, I had this theory for a while that, you know, the backdrop that the environments
of the games shouldn't just be just a backdrop, a passive thing in which a game takes place.
And here I saw a great opportunity to make the environments more of a backdrop and make
it like an immersion tank to really draw the player in and make it an integral part of
the storytelling process.
And today I'm just going to take you through some of the processes that I went through in order to achieve this and also some of the philosophies and some of the lessons that I learned along the way.
And I think one of the most important lessons that I
learned that really made the impact on me as an artist and
the project in general was early on when I was wrestling
with the idea of how I was going to create this really
immersive world.
And I started out into the slightly naive belief that in
order to achieve immersion, you needed to be as realistic
as possible.
You needed to create this really believable world.
And at the time, I was working with the source engine.
And as some of you may or may not know, it's not
particularly designed to work with large
outdoor environments.
And as a result, I kind of ended up having to cut out any
normal maps, any fancy shading.
And it went straight back to only being able to use diffuse
maps on the textures.
And as a result, in some of the early art tests, which you can
see here, the terrain just looked really flat and
unconvincing.
And it became quickly apparent that realism just wasn't going
to happen.
And in retrospect, it was probably one of the best
things that happened to the project and myself as an
artist, because it really forced me to go back to the
drawing board and reassess what this idea was, what really
made immersion and what the qualities were
that made immersion.
And I kind of started looking into other mediums and more prominently paintings and just trying
to get some inspiration and see if this kind of immersive quality was evident anywhere else.
And I started to be drawn towards this kind of impressionistic style of painting.
There was just something about it, something about this mix of the real and surreal, this
detail and perceived detail that you see in some of these paintings that I thought really mirrored sort of D'Arresta's strange and ambiguous story.
But not only that, I found some of these paintings like so atmospheric, so
immersive and so so absorbent that I really just felt inspired to kind of
take just to study these images and try and take some of the qualities that made these
images, even though they're not representations of photo reality, and adapt that into my work,
see if I could create this kind of immersive quality in it. So the first thing I tried to
do is just kind of identify some of what I thought were the key qualities of this
impressionistic style, and for me it was kind of this really strong sense of
lighting that kind of creates the atmosphere in some of these paintings is kind of like soft
Colors just like really soft lighting and I really like this idea of
evoking emotion over
Recreating reality so only creating enough detail and enough fidelity within the image to kind of
bring across the impression of that scene,
the emotion of that scene.
And I also like the idea of using the color palette
to reinforce this kind of emotional quality
and get the atmosphere and mood
just through the colors of the picture.
So I went back to my original art test,
and I tried to adapt some of these qualities into my work,
and just tried to make it a lot more softer,
and I made the lighting more ambient,
and just kind of embraced this kind of flatness
that was there before,
and tried to make it a lot more painterly in style.
And already it was starting to come together
and look a lot more of a beautiful,
interesting place to explore.
And this kind of really inspired me to continue on
later on in level in the development when
I realized that breaking three of these boundaries of this realism
really allowed me to play with some of the designs of the island
and the colors and the kind of symbolic imagery that's in there,
which I wouldn't have been able to do being stuck inside this kind of realistic realm.
And it really helped towards the end of the game,
where there's this kind of real twist on the story
and things become a lot more dreamlike and surreal.
which I'll come to later in the presentation.
But just to sum up this point, I really
felt like I learned that realism isn't
the holy grail for immersion.
In fact, realism doesn't have anything to do with it.
It's not the fidelity of the content that mattered at all
to me.
It was actually, it turned out that it
was the message and experience that you
betray for the content that really matters
in terms of immersion.
So speaking of that content, I think
I should really just quickly talk about.
how it was built to connect the story back to the environment.
And I think the best way to do this, just kind of show an example scene from the original mod
and show how it's built up and improved upon in the remake
and some of the most important steps in the process in order to kind of build this connection back up.
So here we got a scene from the original mod in which the
narrator references at several points in the story where he
says he describes a shipwreck in the bay and the pollution
that's been caused to the island and the damage done by
it, and also the various supplies that he's looted from
it.
And it's a really good example of where the narrative details
didn't match up to the visual details, where there's this
kind of real disconnection between the auditory experience
and the visual experience.
And it was also an area that had, that ended up having a huge potential to expand upon the story just through the environment and just through this one narrative detail.
But first, the connection really starts at the beginning of the...
the kind of building of this terrain, at least it did for me,
because in my mind, this terrain is kind of like the stage
in which the story takes place.
So I like to think of a certain amount of things
to do while I'm designing the environment.
So for me, I wanted to create something
within the terrain that would be unique to this aspect
of the story.
And in this case, I wanted to kind of frame it
within the story so that.
When they talk about the shipwreck, they could identify it within the environment.
And not only that, but I wanted to expand upon the game experience as well.
So I wanted to expand upon the idea of exploration and offer something that was interesting to explore.
And I kind of came up with this idea of these huge sand dunes that just stretched across the bay.
And just to make it a lot more interesting to explore and just kind of give it the shipwreck,
this unique identity when it eventually comes in.
And this comes in in the next stage where you start to add in the details.
And this is the stage where you really start connecting the story to the environment, or
at least I did.
As you can see in the small corner there, you can see a
picture of the original scene from the mod.
And you just have this kind of little trawler with a few boxes
floating around it, which represent the
pollution on the island.
But here I've really tried to up the scale of the scene,
really try to make it a more poignant, dramatic aspect of
the story, just so that the environment is really, it
becomes an integral part of the story within the
environment there.
But not only that, I just made sure that the details of this piece were actually consistent with the story as well,
because this can be a real immersion breaker if you don't really think about this kind of this depth within the art of the environment.
So in this case, it had to be a fairly recent wreck in order for the pollution to still have a hold and for the supplies to still be salvageable.
But going beyond this, I actually just expanded upon this aspect of pollution to try and expand,
add depth to the story.
And I did this by just making the pollution caused by it just evident all over the island.
So it infests the soil, the sand, and the grass, and it's just everywhere.
And it really emphasizes the feeling that this island is kind of this miserable place,
this unpleasant place to inhabit.
And again, I just expanded upon this idea further by adding in other shipwrecks to the island.
Some of them more recent, but more importantly, some of them much, much older.
And what this does is just to suggest that these shipwrecks,
these kind of disasters have been plaguing the island
for hundreds of years.
And it just adds adding depth to that one narrative detail.
And again, it's just building upon this idea
that the island is this really cursed place.
And what these details do is just add consistency
to support the reality of the game world,
the reality of the story.
And so it's more about building a past
as well as a present.
which I think is a really important thing.
And finally, I just decided that later on in the
development to try and connect the protagonist to the
island, the character that you're portraying in some way
through the environment.
And I started to add in all these little small details
that connect to him that are randomized and just serve to
reward the exploration aspect of the game.
So every time you play it, you get slightly
different objects spawned.
And these just serve to offer a connection to the protagonist's past.
And these are just a few examples of some of the items that you can find just around the shipwreck area.
So you've got like the Jaws of Life, a partially burnt car seat, and a defibrillator.
These are all kind of slightly out of place, and they just serve to kind of link back to his past,
to kind of like give you a glimpse into...
this tragic event that led him here in the first place.
But there's also other details that are outside of this
as well that kind of expand upon the story
that's not portrayed throughout the narrative itself.
For example, in the lower left hand corner here,
you have like some burnt divorce papers
and foreclosure on a mortgage.
And these kind of just serve to kind of offer
a slightly different interpretation of the story
in the background behind it.
So, the reason for doing this is kind of to make
the protagonist, not just this presence on the island,
so you're not just this person just floating around,
but you're actually part of the history
of the environment as well.
It's kind of like making him part of the island itself.
And I think there's just, moving on from that
just a little bit, I just want to talk about
one other thing that I thought was really instrumental
and kind of.
bringing the immersion of the game up to a whole new level.
And it was something I almost missed.
I was pretty much through the second level of the game.
The whole world, everything was really coming together.
The story was really becoming connected to the environment.
But there was this real invisible barrier, this real
disconnection between.
the visual experience still and I couldn't quite figure it out and
one day I had this screenshot open and I was just kinda looking at it and I was just thinking
well it looks fine, I can't really figure out what it is
and I picked up my mouse and I tried to move it around, this screenshot and I was like
at first I was like, oh okay this is just caffeine deprivation
but it suddenly occurred to me that the reason I couldn't discern this between
the actual game itself was that everything was just completely static.
There was no feeling of dynamism in the world.
There was no feeling that this was a living, breathing space.
And this was really, I think, what this last disconnection was being caused by.
And so, hopefully this will work.
Play video.
Okay.
Ah, here we go.
Yeah, so I started to add in all these like
little random elements to kind of really bring in
this movement and this organic feeling to the world.
So you've got this wind blowing
and the grass blowing in the wind
and you've got all these leaves being picked up by that
and you've got the kind of clouds scrolling along the sky,
you've got the water flowing into the bay,
you've got the waves splashing against the shore,
you've got mist.
evaporating from the water.
You've got all these different elements that kind of create this
this kind of real organic feel to the world.
It just makes it much more,
it made it much more of a believable world.
It just really, it really just
jumped the immersion level up massively.
And it's just, I think it was such an important part of
of really making it, the world, this kind of believable place.
So finally there's just one last thing I think I should talk about.
And it's probably one of the more complex things that I use to tell the story within the game.
And that's something I call subliminal signposting.
So, subliminal signposting is just quite simply a way of using the environment to
unconsciously guide the player through some of the more figurative aspects of the story.
which are not directly conveyed through the narrative.
And most of these signposts can usually be symbolic in nature.
You can use them to navigate the player around the environment,
which is the more traditional way
to use subliminal signposts.
So using the aerial to guide the player in the right direction.
But I've used them a lot more.
I think a lot of better examples are
some of the more symbolic ones.
And these are used to portray some of the...
some of the protagonist's kind of state of mind, his thought, his feelings, his memories
and emotions, and really build upon the possibility of the island or parts of the island being
kind of unreal or a delusion of his imagination conjured up in a kind of fever or kind of
a purgatory.
And I think this is most prevalent during the caves level of the game, where the protagonist is kind of at this height of his delusion, he's broken his leg, he's got this infection, and he's been taking all these painkillers, and he's kind of reached this crescendo when he descends into the caves.
And I really wanted to create here some kind of subtle break from the physical reality of the previous levels, and kind of make it more of a symbolic journey through his own body, his own mind, and his inner psyche.
And just because it's the turning point in the game where he kind of comes to terms with the events that happen,
which I thought was really fitting.
So, as a result, there were really quite a number of prominent subliminal signposts here.
And so, for example, in this level, one of the first scenes you come across, one of the first rooms you come across is this room here.
This is just really representative of his heart,
which is one of the most important things in the story.
It's emotion, it's the turmoil.
And it wasn't supposed to represent
in any kind of literal sense or physical sense.
It's just there to serve to make an impression.
So this is kind of like very loose colors,
just the colors, the shapes and everything like that
are really designed to just bring this oppression across.
And I think in this case, I chose this one because it's a little bit more literal.
If you focus on the blue colors in the scene, you get this kind of very loose blue outline,
this kind of heart shape.
But later on, it can be even more subtle than that.
And you've got other areas such as this, this kind of is towards the end of the cave's level
where you kind of go into this cave and there's all these writings and stuff around the walls.
This is really symbolic of his kind of inability to figure out the events that happened, this
kind of fractured state of mind that led him here and his kind of tormented mind and the
infection and various other things.
And it all leads up to this probably most poignant scene in the game.
which is kind of like a mix between
uh... the kind of literal signposting
and the symbolic signposting
and it's literal in the case that you've got this kind of
it's hard to see here but it's like this car wreck
uh...
But it's symbolic in the fact that it's submerged beneath the bottom of the ocean,
and it looks like it's been submerged for decades.
And it's kind of representative of his repressed memories of this event,
and it's coming to terms with these memories.
So it's a good example of where the environment can really represent these thoughts and feelings.
I think the last really strong image comes at the end of the caves level when you're exiting out and you're exiting into the next level.
And this whole room is just designed to look like this giant eye and you're going through the iris of this eye.
And it's, you know, again, it's not completely literal, but in this case, it's kind of a bit more literal.
But.
It's very symbolic of this kind of exit of the
of the inner psyche and back into some kind of reality.
And it's...
I didn't want to create this kind of like really
surreal, like literal representation of all these things
in a level. I didn't want to do kind of a Max Payne event where you're
following a trail of blood around.
I still wanted to maintain the reality of the game world that I built up.
So doing it in a subtle way really kind of just creates this idea that people can interpret it however they want.
They might take something else away with it, and they might just think it's a case, but at the end of the day,
it's a nice way to communicate the emotional aspects of the story.
So yeah, just to conclude, I really believe that choosing an art style shouldn't really be an aesthetic choice.
It should really be a choice of being able to define your experience and support the goals within that experience.
And it can also open up opportunities for you to communicate with your audience in new and interesting ways.
And in this case, choosing the impressionistic style really allowed me to express the unreal and the surreal aspects of the story and really play with that within the environment.
But not only that, but it's not just
about creating a physical landscape.
For me, it's also about creating an emotional space
in which the player can navigate,
and using that space to really define the experience.
So all these details, the small, the large, the literal,
the figurative, are really the glue
that adds depth to the story and the environment,
and really helps to create this immersive world that's
full of mystery just waiting to be explored.
And if there's any questions, hopefully I've got time.
Thank you.