Hello. I'm Holly. This is a window. It's not a very good window. We'll come back to the window in a few minutes.
So I'm Holly, I'm half of a tiny company called Mathis & Marco,
and we make games that usually have some sort of physical existence in the world,
and usually have some sort of invitation to player creativity.
So we do things like this, which is a game called One Easy Step,
which happened outside King's College in London, where...
where people were invited to make up their own games to play on these patterns that we'd
laid down on the ground.
They weren't quite games, they were just patterns that suggested games.
So you got the things we expected, like groups of students playing with each other, or like
lecturers on the way to give a lecture who didn't want to seem frivolous, but would sort
of walk between things in a very methodical way, but definitely not jump and not give
away that they were playing or having fun.
And then we had things we didn't expect, like a guy on an hour-long business call
standing out in there in the wind one day, the wind billowing his jacket,
and we were watching from the windows on the sixth floor,
taking notes to see if the project had worked.
And as his phone call went on, over the course of an hour,
he started pacing, first within the paths of the maze.
and then balancing along the lines of the maze.
And by the time he was 45 minutes
into this clearly incredibly tedious phone call,
he was jumping from triangle to triangle,
the jacket going, ba-dump, ba-dump, ba-dump, behind him.
So we do things like that, and we do silly little things like Art Deck,
which we made for No Quarter in New York last year,
which is a game where you collaborate to make instructions for drawings,
and then you execute those drawings.
Or like this for children playing with an overhead projector.
And for children, overhead projectors are now this amazing high-tech thing that they
have never seen before.
They're excited and thrilled by something that they assume is entirely digital while
their parents stand around getting nostalgic.
We also run a little festival called Now Play This,
where last year we focused in particular on games
that had an element of player creativity.
So we showed things like Action Painting Pro by Ian McClarty
and Inks by State of Play,
and a load of different games where people were invited
to write or compose or perform or otherwise create something
within the course of the gameplay itself.
And that's what I'm talking about today.
I'm talking about games where people are invited
to create something as part
of their core gameplay experience.
So sometimes charming freeware like Nico Düsseldorf's
Castles Made of Castles, which is a fractal building game,
iOS games like State of Play by Inks,
where you're making a game of pinball
where as you splatter the ball against the sides,
huge bursts of color come out and make a,
a pattern, a record of how you've played.
And Toka Hair Salon too, where you give your clients haircuts
and they're beautifully animated.
And whatever you do with their hair, they are so delighted.
They make little noises of pleasure and delight
and occasionally confusion,
but the confusion always resolves
into this delighted face at the end.
Whatever you do to their hair, they love it.
Things like Media Molecule's Dreams, where the whole pitch is that you can create anything you want,
or Elegy for a Dead World, where you're invited to write a poem within the course of play.
And also things like Dixit and Pictionary and board games that get people making creatively.
And things like Just Add People which is a gorgeous instant architecture game where groups
of people collaborate with these little nodules and sticks to make wireframes of buildings
collaboratively.
Even things like Exquisite Corpse, you know that parlor game where you draw a bit of a picture
and you leave some lines hanging off and you fold it over, you give it to someone else,
they draw a bit more of it and then at the end you unfold it, which is both a game that kids
play in primary school and also a game that the artists from the 1920s onwards have genuinely
played as a way to generate interesting work.
So everything in this sort of range of games that invite you to make something in the course of playing.
And I think the various techniques that you can use are very, very transferable between digital and physical games here.
So over the course of the next...
however long I've got, 25 minutes left.
I'm going to be talking about why we might want people
to create things as part of our games.
I'm going to talk about what stops people
from wanting to create things,
both within games and generally.
And then I'm going to talk about some techniques
that different games use to break through
that reluctance to create,
and the way that the different techniques
encourage different particular types of creativity.
But first, why?
Why would we even want to do this in the first place?
To start off with, getting involved
in making something within a game
can increase your sense of investment
within that game as a player.
This game here is a super lovely walking game
where players generate a random walk that directs them
around a building or around a park.
But before they start playing, they
have to fold the paper of the dice
that they're using to generate that walk,
and they have to write an extra instruction on it themselves.
The designers could very easily have pre-folded these
or got the dice printed in advance.
But having that process where you're
making the thing that you then use in the course of the play
makes people excited about it.
We know this as a logic behind character creators, right?
If you've made a thing and it feels personal to you,
then your investment in the game experience is greater.
And partly because of this, getting people to create things in games is a really good
way of encouraging them to share stuff.
And again, we know this about people in general, right?
If you're sharing a picture of a cake on Facebook, the chances are it's a cake that you made
yourself.
It's not a cake you just happen to be proximate to at some point.
If you have a baby on the lock screen of your phone, it might be a baby that you gave birth
to yourself.
It's probably not.
a baby that someone else is raising even if their baby is way cuter than your baby.
When we make a thing we feel like it says something about ourselves and it's things
that say something about ourselves that we want to share with our friends and family.
Creating something within a game can provide a change of tone.
It can give you a moment away from the hurry, bury, hurly
burly of the game itself without taking you out of the game
world.
It can give you a moment to do something funny or restful
or without the stress of whatever it is that you're
trying to accomplish.
A moment to pause and breathe but still
remain within the game.
It can get people to create wonderful things,
and I guess I don't really need to explain
why creating wonderful things is good, right?
Having wonderful things is nice.
Let's have some more of them.
It can help players develop skills and understanding
about how to make stuff,
which are then transferable outside of the game.
They can make people write things or draw things
and learn about the tools and the scope of their skills
and expand those slightly.
And finally, they can just be really, really good fun.
Making stuff is nice.
Making stuff is satisfying and delightful.
We're mostly here because we're super lucky
and get to make games.
And not everyone gets to make stuff as part of their job,
but everyone has the capacity to enjoy the process of making
to feel satisfaction and delight
at a thing that they have made.
And for a form, games, which trucks so much in satisfaction and delight,
neglecting the possibility of making one of the main things that gives people
those experiences just seems silly.
So there's a load of different reasons that you might want to get people creating within a game,
but getting them to actually do it can be super, super difficult.
There's plenty of evidence that this is particularly the case for games rather than for any other form.
because, for example, games often provide people
with these extrinsic rewards.
And there's plenty of research that shows
that having an extrinsic reward for doing something creative
will lower your motivation to continue
doing that creative thing.
And also sometimes make the creative work
that you do do worse.
And there's not that many games around that
do this to use as models.
This is a quotation from a guy's MA in 2014,
which was an MA specifically looking at games that were
used to encourage creativity.
And in the introduction he's just like,
I had a look, there basically aren't any,
this MA has to be totally theoretical.
And I don't want to criticize the MA,
it was a super interesting piece of work,
I recommend going and having a look at it
if you're interested in this kind of thing.
But the fact that even someone who's interested enough
in this topic to be writing an MA on it
isn't necessarily aware of prior work in this area
means we are kind of acting at a disadvantage.
But there's also things that aren't specific to games,
but are specific to getting people to create
under any circumstances whatsoever.
So here we have this drawing of a window again.
My friend Sarah drew this drawing of a window
when I made her sit down at a table
and there was some graph paper and some marker pens
and I said, draw a window.
And because she's very obliging, she did,
but it's not a very good window
and she didn't enjoy drawing it
and altogether at the end of the process,
she was significantly less happy
than before I made her draw a window.
And the reasons that she didn't like this were
that she didn't know how to do it.
She didn't particularly know the characteristics
of the marker pen that she was working with.
She didn't really have any background in visual arts.
So being demanded that she draw a window out of nowhere
is incredibly uninviting.
I would hate it if someone jumped out and yelled,
Holly, Holly, write a poem now
when I was going about my normal day.
It's because of a lack of confidence,
which is related to a lack of ability,
but it's not necessarily the same thing.
In fact, people who have a little bit of ability in an area
are sometimes way less confident
because their expectations for themselves are higher,
and their fear that they'll look silly
if they make something bad is greater.
So you have to address lack of ability
and lack of confidence in your ability separately.
And finally, lack of motivation.
Like, I didn't tell Sarah that I would use this window
in a talk, or at least not until later.
I just said, draw a window.
She had no idea why she was meant to be drawing a window,
why she might want to do that,
and what she would get from it.
And that's another thing that people often
find themselves up against when asked to create.
Why am I doing this?
Why would I want to?
Is someone going to laugh at me?
Can I even do it?
What will I get out of it?
These three core worries, lack of ability,
lack of confidence, and lack of motivation.
And not all players will experience all of these lacks,
but someone will experience all of them.
And in order to successfully get people
creating within your game,
you need to address all of them simultaneously.
So just to recap, people often don't have the ability
and the confidence and motivation to create things
within a game.
But if they do, if we can overcome it,
there are so many good reasons to get them doing it.
So for the rest of the talk, I'm going
to talk a little bit about different ways
that games in the past have encouraged player creativity,
how that tends to work, what the different techniques are.
And the first one is by far the easiest.
You just give your players instructions.
You just tell them what to do.
And that might even be very, very explicit instructions,
the simplest of all ways to get people creating.
You just tell them to do a thing,
and maybe you even score them on how well they've done it.
That might be recreating a picture,
might be singing a song, might be doing a dance.
I'm really, really, really bad at singing, like spectacularly bad at singing.
I have a range of four notes, and whenever I open my mouth, it's almost totally random
which of those four notes is going to come out.
But I love SingStar anyway because its instructions are so explicit, and the thing that it's getting
me to focus on is such a minimal part of singing.
It's try to get a correct note.
and then do it for the right amount of time.
It doesn't care about my expression,
it doesn't care about any of the fancy singing words
that I'm so bad at singing I don't even know what they are.
And people who are really good at singing
sometimes find SingStar really frustrating
because it doesn't allow them
that range of creative expression.
But for someone like me,
having these very, very explicit instructions
is reassuring, it takes away the pressure,
it tells me what I'm meant to do
and it gives me a way to figure out
if I'm doing it right or not.
A lot of dancing games do a really interesting thing where they find a way to give people
that sort of support and comfort, but also still allow for creative expression.
So for example, if you play Just Dance just using your phone as the thing, then the game
is only looking at what that one hand does.
It doesn't care what you do with your feet.
So people who want to be fancy and be more creatively expressive can,
and people who just want to focus on that one hand can do that.
Dance Dance Revolution back in the day is still my favourite dancing game of all time
because it focuses on your feet and then leaves people who want to be fancy,
want to spin around and wave their arms around to do that.
But people who need that reassurance and hand-holding
can just focus on doing the right things.
So explicit instructions can level the playing field
by focusing on a particular area
rather than requiring everyone to be good at everything
all at once, and they can hold you safe and make it okay.
They can tell you what you're meant to do,
and you can just concentrate entirely on execution.
Sometimes you get tension between the scoring systems
and what would actually make for a good creative work,
and it can be difficult to leave space
for creative expression,
but these things are really, really useful.
Another slightly subtler way to give people instructions
is to not necessarily tell them what to do step by step,
but to give them a prompt.
You give people a blank canvas with a specific task,
but you don't tell them how to do that task.
So this, this is a different window,
and this is another drawing that Sarah did
immediately afterwards when I pointed at a window
in the corner of the flat and said, draw this window.
And this is still not a masterpiece of modern art, sure,
but it's a way more interesting drawing,
and also she had a nicer time doing it.
And at the end, she felt confident
that she had done roughly the correct thing,
because she could look at the window
and look at the thing she'd drawn and go,
yeah, yeah, all right, that's approximately correct.
Elegy for a Dead World is really instructive here
because I've been super open about their design process
and how when they started off,
people who played just felt sad.
Initially, they presented people
with these beautiful landscapes
and then just said, write a poem.
which made people feel bad about themselves
and made people feel insecure and didn't result in any poems.
And so over the course of the design process,
they iterated on this and started off
by giving people incredibly specific prompts that
might just be filling in one sentence or two
or a single word of a sentence.
And then over the course of the game,
as people's confidence grew, it became broader and broader
about the things that they were being invited to do.
So if we look back at the three things that stop people creating, sort of lack of ability
and confidence and motivation, a prompt can help with all of those.
It helps with ability by answering the question of what am I meant to do at all.
It helps with confidence by hand-holding you a bit through it and also giving you an excuse
if the thing isn't good.
Right if you are told to do something and it's terrible and it's something you chose to do yourself you feel bad
but if it's something the game has told you to do then you don't feel like it's your fault as much and
finally it helps with motivation by by sparking curiosity a
Well chosen prompt can get people wanting to jump in and finish it it can motivate them if I say
there was a young man from New York who wanted to learn how to
and I just leave a space there,
then your brain wants to fill it in.
Talk, walk, what is it?
You want to pick the best thing for it.
It's this moment that's both easy to respond to
and slightly intriguing.
So prompts do all of these things.
They make tasks less scary,
and they also encourage people
to feel like they're responding to the game
rather than just responding to something inside themselves.
They can be difficult, you can get something that's either too vague or too specific,
and you have to make sure you're allowing space for players to genuinely be expressive,
which you might need to build up over the course of the game.
But prompts are, I think, probably my very, very favourite way to get people making stuff.
Final type of instruction, slightly vaguer one,
much more enigmatic.
And I think this one is generally underused.
This is where the game doesn't give you upfront instructions,
but instead responds to what you do
in a way that makes you want to figure out what it wants,
makes you want to try to please it.
So this is Joy Exhibition by Strangethink,
where you make these spray paint gun paintings,
and they go up and aliens wander around and look at them.
And sometimes they'll stop in front of a picture.
And it might be totally random.
I think it probably is.
But as you play for the first 10 minutes,
you try to figure out what they want from a picture.
You go back, try to make a new picture
that they'll like more and present it to them.
Pippin Barr's art game does the same thing.
You basically play Tetris to make a sculpture.
Then you phone up the tiny cartoon curator
who comes along and tells you
if your sculpture is any good or not.
And I have no idea how the curator figures this out,
but trying to please them becomes the core of the game,
and you're driven to go back and do that again.
This is one of the more interesting windows
that Sarah drew, and when she drew this one,
I just sat nearby and made noises.
Like, ah, and mm, as she drew.
And I was, again, making them totally at random.
But she interpreted them enough to try to drive her to do things and experiment with things that she otherwise wouldn't have.
She had the same amount of instructions as the first time I said, draw a window,
but she also had me sitting there seeming to respond to it.
And that seeming response was the thing that drove her to explore different ways of making and different things that she could do,
in the desperate hope that, I guess, I would eventually let her stop drawing windows.
So instructions, great, but very upfront,
very aimed at a particular sort of thing.
Another thing that you can do is give your players an excuse.
This helps in particular with lack of confidence.
People are scared about making a thing that's bad.
Well, if you give them an excuse for why it's bad,
they don't have to be scared anymore.
So you can do this by increasing the difficulty, for example,
and making it really, really hard to make a good thing.
This is a window that Sarah drew with her foot.
and it's terrible, but of course it's terrible.
She was holding a marker pen between her toes.
And I think she had more fun drawing this one
than any other window.
And she didn't care that it was terrible.
And we know about this in building games, for example,
which are constantly coming up with tornadoes and dinosaurs
to get in the way of things that you're trying to make.
We know that with games like Fake Artist Goes to New York,
where it's difficult because you're trying to draw something
without giving away what the thing you're drawing is
to a spy within your ranks.
So difficulty relieves the pressure to make something good
and makes you feel better about whatever it is that you do make.
If you make it so there's no chance of making something good,
then it can be a quite shallow game.
You'll only get people engaging with it
for a relatively short amount of time.
But even that shallow engagement can be an enormous amount of fun.
Another sort of excuse you can give is limiting the control
that players have over the output of their actions.
So the relationship between what they do
and what the game does in response is maybe enigmatic,
or maybe you only get to make one decision
every five or 10 seconds.
So you get something like become a great artist
in just 10 seconds, where you're first presented
with a ridiculously difficult demand to, for example,
recreate a picture precisely.
So there's already difficulty acting as an excuse.
But then there's a really enigmatic relationship between what you do and what comes up.
You press a button on the keyboard and then something happens to your bright glitchy drawing
which might transform it, like, unstoppably, irreversibly.
And so what you start doing is not necessarily trying to do what the game tells you to do,
but exploring the possible space of things that you can make within this enigmatic tool.
You get music games like Shikian and Looks Like Music that do a similar thing,
which translate someone's physical drawings into sound.
And so what you do is explore the space of different noises that you can make.
And music games tend to do this quite a lot, right?
You're not necessarily trying to make something from scratch,
and the relationship between what you do and what you get.
can be very, very vague, but you gradually feel it out
and you're motivated to explore the space
of possible things that you can make.
So limiting the control that people have
is really great for getting them to make something
within a set of aesthetics that already exist
and explore what's possible
and make something that speaks to them.
It can be a risk that you end up with people
making things that look the same,
so you have to make sure there's a really wide range
of expression possible within it.
But if that's done, then the sky's the limit.
Okay, distracting your players.
So you give players a different non-creative task to do
at the same time that they're doing the creative task.
This is very good for being funny.
This is a window that Sarah drew
while I also got her to say her times tables
from one by one through to 10 by 10.
And when she got to 10 by 10, she had to stop.
And I think this is, of all of the windows,
my actual favorite because she was distracted
from thinking too much about what she was doing
and being worried about it because she was focusing
on saying her 10 times tables instead.
This obviously isn't a game.
It's barely a step above bullying, but...
Yeah.
But if you look at games that do this well, what they tend to do is have something where
the task that you're meant to do that is a distraction nonetheless feeds through into
the creative thing that you're doing.
So Bounden gives you a little shape that you've got to keep in a particular area on the phone
between you.
And as you start moving in order to accomplish that, without you even necessarily noticing
what you're doing, you start to dance because it's been choreographed to make you make these
graceful movements while you're distracted.
Pictionary, less beautiful than Bounden, but just as much fun.
You get the distraction of trying to communicate something, and then you don't necessarily
worry about what it is that you're doing.
And again, the thing that you're doing as a distraction and the thing that you're doing
that is a creative work are really tightly bound together.
And Action Painting Pro, which is one of my very, very favorite games of all time,
where you're a little figure jumping around, trying to keep enough sort of hearts and dollars
and light bulbs to continue making your artwork as you jump around.
But you start picking up paint and leaving it in enormous tracks behind you.
And at the end of the game, when you inevitably die,
you have an artwork that you've created.
And even if you start out trying to make a particular thing, you never manage to do that.
You get distracted by the demands of the game.
And then at the end you look with new eyes at the thing that you have made.
You can use your players against each other.
You can get them collaborating and working on a creative task together, which works really
well because no one has sole responsibility for what they're doing.
So in this case, Sarah and her girlfriend took turns to draw a line in the window, one
of them in dark red and one of them in bright red.
An Exquisite Corpse works like this as well, this collaborative art-making game that I
made a few years ago.
This super lovely thing by Scott Garner, which is a music game where you have to touch a
star and the moon at the same time to make a particular note.
But the stars are so far away that you need help from other people.
And once you start holding hands with people,
you no longer have sole control over the tune
and the music that you make as a result of it.
So you feel freed up to just experiment and mess around
without feeling like you have to create a great tune right now.
So collaborating can get people feeling less responsible.
The risk is that they have a limited sense of ownership at the end
and getting them to feel proud of the thing that they've made is harder.
Competition is another great one, getting people directly opposed to each other.
I keep using Pictionary as an example because it uses quite a lot of these techniques really, really skillfully.
You're not just distracted by having a name of communication,
you're not just given a prompt of what to draw, but you're also desperate to beat someone else.
And competition is possibly the best single way to overcome the question of why should I do this, of motivation.
You're doing it because you don't want someone else to win, you want to win.
If people are on board with the idea of games at all,
then they're generally on board with the idea of doing something
in order to ensure a victory, right?
Again, you can get this tension between the creative work
and the quality of the creative work
and the best thing that you need to do in order to win the game,
but it's still a super, super powerful way to get people doing stuff.
And finally, gifts and sharing.
So people working together and playing a game together,
making stuff for each other.
So this game where you're making music together
and what you're doing is trying to support
the other person in their music.
Or back in the days of draw something,
people weren't necessarily trying to make a bee
to communicate bee as quickly as possible.
They were doing these elaborate drawings
to send to people as gifts.
So in social contexts where people like each other and already care about each other,
inviting people to make things for each other is really, really powerful.
It can be intimidating because you need to make something for someone and they might hate it.
So you have to work really, really hard at giving people confidence.
But as a motivator, it's wonderful.
Giving players a disguise.
You don't necessarily ask them to create as themselves.
You get them to take on a role.
They're not writing a song.
They're playing a character that's writing a song.
Tabletop role-playing games have done this for ages.
Live art does it a lot.
Theater does it a lot.
This is a game where you run around with capes
that make different noises,
and it's important that they're capes
because the capes make you feel like someone else.
You tell stories.
as yourself, and that's scary.
You tell stories as some sort of drunken 1700s baron,
and it's less intimidating.
And finally, you can help people make something within a game
by making it easier for your players
to create something good.
You can do that by smoothing out the edges of the things they make secretly,
taking the thing that they've made and making it better.
We made this game Art Deck that I mentioned before,
and we spent a long time experimenting with different prompts to give people.
We spent a long time experimenting with different marker pens and crayons
and different things that people could use.
But the single thing that we did that made the most difference to this game
is we started at the end of the game putting a frame around it.
And that made it feel more like a thing.
And also it stopped people from being bad at drawing secretly.
Because the main way that people are bad at drawing
is they don't draw to the edge of the paper.
This is the main thing that art teachers yell at children
for the first two years of high school.
Draw to the edge of the paper, fill the pages, look confident.
If you have something sitting in the middle, it doesn't seem confident,
it doesn't seem like a picture.
So we just framed it and cut off the inch around it
after trying so many different game mechanics
to get people to draw to the edge of the paper and failing.
So you can be sneaky, you can make their stuff better.
Obviously it means that you're making decisions about what better is so really innovative work can often get squashed down by that
But if you're happy with that then secret improvement is great
You can give people a constraint that stops them from doing something bad
another thing that people often do badly when they're drawing is they do lots of little
Unconfident lines or they put in lots of peripheral detail that detracts from the main thing
So in this case
I didn't let Sarah take her pen off the paper and the thing that she got at the end of her
was I think more interesting sort of visually
than most of the other things that she drew.
So a constraint can make something sound harder to do,
so it relieves the pressure,
but actually it makes it easier
and it denies people access to bad decisions
that they might otherwise make.
And finally, practice, right?
We make people good at stuff by making them genuinely good
at them.
We make people more confident by getting them to do something
until they genuinely know more about how to do it.
I want to be clear that I don't think
that games that encourage player creativity should necessarily
be aimed at focusing on the quality of the creative work.
But if we're getting someone to do something over and over
again, it would be silly to neglect the possibility
that they might end up being actually better at it
than when they started.
So to summarize, these are all different techniques
that we can use to get people creating stuff within games,
to get them experimenting and making and sharing
with each other and with people outside the game.
There's particular stuff that we as game designers
in particular need to watch out for,
like the tension between gameplay and creation,
or whether people get bored mechanically or creatively,
right, there's two ways for them to get sick of your game.
But if we can do that, then we've got this area that is,
I think, genuinely one of the richest and most exciting
places to dig around in in games and try to find new
things that we can get people to do and get them to play.
Thank you.