Let's start. Wow, it's like an echo in here. I don't really have the voice for a big echo,
but you know, I'll try and be like Thor-like or something.
Thanks for coming, everyone. I really appreciate you taking half an hour out of your super
busy GDC to come and hang out here. You probably know all the sort of housekeeping stuff already,
but I think you need to, like, turn off your phones and get something scanned and write
some answers to emails later. So do those things, and everyone will love you, including
me.
So, hello, I'm Rex. I am a game maker. I've done a bunch of stuff in TV and animation as well,
but it's mostly been in games. A little bit of background. I started out,
I started out as a sheep farmer, and I gradually raised a large flock of sheep. And then one day,
I sold them.
And I took the money and I bought my first computer.
And there it is.
Well, despite what you might actually think,
that's not actually me.
But you know, I'm flattered.
And it was an Amiga 500.
The best computer ever designed, unfortunately for my sheep.
And here's Andy Warhol using one to paint Debbie Harry.
I kind of wanted to get in on this.
I was so inspired by what was...
the use of digital...
the digital device to create art.
It just seemed so much quicker and easier.
So, I got myself an Amiga and I used this incredible technology to make some very bad games.
That's one there. I'm not showing you the main screen, you can only see the UI because it doesn't get better as you go up.
And, you know, despite this image, I think I probably had some skills as an artist,
but ultimately I was just kind of a fanboy for the technology.
I didn't really have anything to say with it at the time.
So, like many people, I went off to art college, discovered life,
luckily forgot all about games for several years,
and started to find a bit of a voice.
I studied graphic design,
although I was much more of an illustrator,
because I wanted to learn about the wider context
of how my artwork would and could be used.
And that's something that stayed with me
when I'm trying to choose an art style
with meaning behind it.
And the other thing I learned was,
oh, twin screens.
I'll go this way.
Shit, right, sorry, you can go home now.
I'm not gonna tell you anything good.
It's kind of a harsh lesson,
but it was a really important one for me to learn,
that there will always be artists better than me
at drawing hands, better at drawing feet,
and particularly better artists at drawing horses.
But learning this really freed me up to make work that was less about the rendering skill
and more about finding the best way to convey a particular message or to create a certain emotion.
And the other thing I was learning at the same time
was like teaching myself the software Flash.
And I really love this software
as you could quickly pull in all kinds of media,
add audio, draw all over it,
and then start making it interactive.
And it was a very different process
from those early attempts of like making games
where I had to pre-plan everything.
Using Flash was far closer to my own creative process
and much more like playing.
So I made little interactive experiments which became quite game-like
and that was kind of enough for me to accidentally be hired into the games industry.
initially at Lionhead Studios,
and then with a close bunch of friends
at their new company called Media Molecule,
where I worked on defining the company's house style,
which I guess you could sum up as make it pink,
but also working on the look and atmosphere of the games,
as well as posing for really awkward photos.
And together we made LittleBigPlanet, and my niche on that was mainly bringing in elements of pop culture and street art.
And much of this was to try and show that the game is constantly evolving and being added to.
And if we think of the game as a graffiti wall or a mix tape, that's saying that there's never a perfect conclusion.
It's just an ongoing process of creators inspiring each other to create the next stage.
which makes it more approachable.
Everyone is able to play their part
in a sort of never-ending process of creation.
And then after five years of making LittleBigPlanet,
we wanted to do something different,
and I was given the opportunity
to creatively lead a team for the first time.
And that's when we made Tearaway and Tearaway Unfolded.
And this kind of built on what I'd learnt on Little Big Planet
of trying to take an abstract idea and make it tangible
through its art and its sound and its gameplay.
So this was going to be a handheld game
with lots of touch screen interactions.
And we wanted a world that would be very reactive
and tactile.
So, you know, we took the approach
to build the entire world out of paper
because that felt the most successful way
that we could do that.
You know, and what was interesting about that
is that it especially allowed both our team
and players themselves to successfully contribute artwork
to the game.
you know, the paper style, like, it unified whatever people made in it.
So it always looked part of this papery world.
And making Tearaway has been the biggest influence on what I'm actually here to talk about,
which is the game Nights and Bikes, which is what I'm working on at the moment.
So...
Let's move on.
Now, this particular project was dreamt up
as a smaller scale collaboration
between me and my friend Mu, who's down there.
Hi Mu.
As a way of taking a little bit of time out,
really get hands on again.
I was worried that I hadn't really been drawing
and painting that much recently.
And I just wanted to get a little bit more input into my life, take a few more walks
and get some more influences from outside of my bubble.
Also meant that I could spend a bit more quality time with these two.
Oh, I miss them so much.
So we set up a little company called Foamsword.
Contrast.
So that we could make this game called Nights on Bikes.
There it is.
Now, on the surface, this game is inspired
by coming of age movies, 1980s nostalgia.
Speed up, there we go.
And some classic video games.
I just have to call out this bike here,
that's called a Raleigh Vector.
And that came out like in the 80s
and I was probably, you know, pretty young.
And that bike has a built-in computer
that talks to you while you cycle.
I mean, incredible.
Let's make a video game about that.
So all of these things, they're all cultural shortcuts,
really.
They're there to bring players on board,
which is very important because we
were going to be crowdfunding the game.
So we needed people to have things
that they could understand and welcome them into this game.
But really, a lot of that is just the fanboy bit.
What's going on under the surface of the game
to make it its own thing?
How can it really stand apart from its influences?
Well, firstly, it's influenced by our own childhoods
and experiences, and its setting is directly,
you probably shouldn't look too closely at that map,
there's really bad stuff on there.
It's based on an exaggerated version of where I grew up in rural Cornwall, which is the
– oh, let's help you out, there we go – the pointy tip of the UK, which is where
I raised and sold my sheep to get that sweet computer.
So it's actually a very rural area with little fishing villages all hanging on to
the rocks as the next storm blows through.
It's a very beautiful place, but it's also a place that a lot of people want to come and visit.
But it's economically one of the poorest areas in Europe,
which has a big impact on the look and the atmosphere and themes of the game.
And that sketch on the right is the very first page of my first sketchbook in the game.
And that's how it looks in game.
It's a 3D world made up of thousands of little paintings.
And they're all hand painted and then layered up to create a believable 1980s rural setting.
lots of caravan parks and fishing villages
and plenty of countryside to explore in between.
The game itself has you playing as a couple of...
a couple of tough little girls on their bikes,
and they're seeking adventures,
they wanna find treasure,
and they're just generally learning
about the adult world around them,
but all done with that just almost explosion
of creativity and infectious energy that kids have.
One thing to say is that although it's set in the 1980s,
it's a deliberate choice not to go like super 80s.
Because I think there's a lot of nostalgia culture
out there that kind of makes out that, you know,
when the clock struck 12 on the first day of 1980,
everyone got a DeLorean and like.
changed into a neon t-shirt and went and looked at unicorns.
It's a lot more nuanced than that.
You have to have money to keep up with trends.
And because it's set in an economically challenged area,
we wanted to make sure that the 80s influence was a lot more nuanced.
And there was a reason that some characters will be more pop culture than others.
So how do we get started?
Well, as I was saying, it's quite a personal project
and the aim was to make a game that could be tinkered on
and iterated on as a very small collaboration
between me and Mu.
So it needed to be like generally easy to make the assets, you know, because there was a lot of them, you know, that I was going to have to paint and animate and assemble.
And previously I'd had the luxury as well of working in custom engines that were created to like fully simulate a certain look, you know, to make a world out of paper or make all the craft materials of LittleBigPlanet.
So, it didn't really have, you know,
that would be a little bit crazy
to try and do a new engine for a team of two.
Wasn't gonna move through that.
So, you know, we needed to use off-the-shelf tools,
so we used Unity, and needed to come up with an art style
that kind of I could just paint, paint final artwork,
and then just bring it into Unity as PNGs and start building.
Thematically, like I was saying, it was going to be built on pop culture touchstones such as the Goonies,
but also, you know, wanting to make it its own thing with some autobiographical twists.
And this is the important one.
This kind of suggested that it would be a game about a fairly everyday world.
but one explored by kids with lots of energy, wild imaginations.
So it's a question of like, what's that world going to look like through their eyes?
And this really was the key to represent,
the visual style is there to represent how the kids in the game would try and depict it themselves.
So as you play, you feel like you're seeing the world through their eyes,
or at least with their imagination and energy having some effect on it.
So in other words, it's all a little bit fuzzy, a little bit scribbly.
It's all painted with two brushes.
We've got this softer one for natural elements,
and then a harder edged one for highlights.
And sticking to these two brushes
has been really important to the visual style of the game
because it unifies everything.
It's kind of like the decision
to make the whole world of Tearaway out of paper.
It's a self-imposed limitation to tie everything together.
Here's an exciting bit of live eyeball painting.
I mean, I could just leave that running if you like,
but you know, maybe I'll move on to some more slides.
There's a, here's use of the softer brush
for a little bit of shading.
And then the harder one for the double-edged chin,
double-edged, double chin.
So in the early stages, many elements,
you know, the characters and whatnot,
were designed in vectors,
because it's much quicker and easier
to get the bold shapes and silhouettes.
But then I'd repaint them in the two brushes
to unify the style and just make it less clean,
like, you know, make it more human.
And then there's a final version on the right.
Just put the word final under,
final.final.final.final.psd.
And, you know, that's just been a little bit more refined
and had a little bit more detail added
and a little bit of animation.
So moving on to animation, you know, the key here was that everything needs to really convey this energy of childhood
and the way that kids are constantly shifting attention.
So wherever possible, I redraw everything three times to give it a stop-motion, line-boil look.
It really helps, you know, keeps everything moving on screen and hopefully excites your eyes
and really tries to suggest that there's no one particular way to look at any one thing.
So on the characters themselves,
I can't go quite as wild as I might like
due to the range of animations to create,
but I still try and use the stop motion technique
wherever possible, such as on Demelza's hair here.
You know, you can see how it's sort of,
it's trying to convey her inner wildness,
you know, like all that sort of ideas
that are fizzing out of her head and, you know,
and it sort of beds her into this stormy,
Cornish setting that they're in.
And the art style also means that we can add on elements where the kids, like their imagination is getting carried away and adding elements to the game.
So they're sort of seeing this wall and imagining it as a castle wall with arrows coming down.
This greasy old car crusher kind of takes on a new role as a dragon.
You know, still all painted with with one of those two brushes.
So it looks part of the overall style, but it's very clear that it's
it's something that they're projecting onto the the environment.
And a big influence on this stop motion look.
was the work of Bob Godfrey, that's quite hard to say,
the animator of Rhubarb and Custard.
And I think having lots of on-screen movement
is very important to the atmosphere of a game.
That movement really creates an energy
that translates to players.
It really sort of spurs them through the game,
becomes like a contagious energy
so that they'll run around and explore.
So that was the kind of a weird phrase to leave on screen.
But that was the animation without audio, but I think we should just hear it again with
the audio, because that's kind of a big deal as well.
Right, I'll just have to cut it off there.
But audio is a really big deal to me.
While I'm working, a lot of influences for me
come from audio.
And it's great to investigate other visual styles
and techniques, but it can be overwhelming sometimes.
So when I'm really knuckling down on a project,
you know, I'll often, I'll have the radio on
in the background, listening to that.
So I'll have, you know.
want to listen to people talking like being out in a you know working in a
cafe or something so that you you hear that or create like custom
play music playlists so that they're influencing you while you're working on
particular areas as one area.
the harbour area of the game, this particular audio, Dylan Thomas's,
Under Milt Wood, is really, really important for me.
It is spring, moonless night in the small town, starless and bible black.
The cobbled streets silent and the hunched quarters and rabbits wood limping
invisible down to the slow black,
slow black, crow black,
fishing boat bobbing sea.
The houses are blind as moles, though moles see fine tonight in the snouting velvet dingles,
or blind as Captain Cat, there in the muffled middle by the pump and the town clock,
the shops in mourning, the welfare hall in widow's weeds,
and all the people of the lulled and dumbfound town are sleeping now.
Right, let's stop there. So good though!
Like there's just so much stuff in there, I could just draw that forever.
And so audio is a really big deal.
And obviously, like, you know,
these other audio influences are all part of
what influences the look,
along with the audio design
that's actually happening in the game.
And that's such an important relationship to have,
you know, a really good relationship
with your audio designer.
And, you know, having an old friend, Kenny Young,
on the project has just gives me so much to respond to
all of the time.
So, moving on, yes, so if you're making a game
that's like 2D, 3D, you have to have one of these GIFs.
It's the law, and this is our one.
So, you know, that was just a little diversion
into how audio has inspired the overall atmosphere and tone.
But how are the individual elements all created?
Well, a big influence on those was the art
of Alfred Wallace, who was a Cornish painter.
who had no formal training and often painted with boat paint on scraps of cardboard.
And because he was from the same geographical location as where the game is set,
there's a strong thematic link.
But looking at these compositions really made me more confident to play with the fakery of making 3D environment with 2D assets.
So, started off very conservative, you know, everything was very flat, as if I was like just going to texture it onto boxes,
rather than really going as wild as you can with like 2D artwork.
I started to subvert it more.
And, you know, this started to get closer to the way that kids will draw.
trying to show all the interesting details
which matter to them,
even if like technically half of those details
are actually on the other side,
you know, it's kind of, you're just trying,
you're just too excited to like draw a thing,
so you just try and fit everything on.
And this felt like a much more accurate way
of representing the little fishing villages
and what have you in Knights and Bikes,
where the architecture is so individual.
There's a few more examples of assets.
And it really helps like, you know, painting all of these in the same two brushes all the way through the game.
You know, and it means that, you know, they've all got their own sort of angles and perspectives, but, you know,
painting them all in the same way has like really unified them.
But nobody's going to see assets like that in isolation, apart from all of you, just then.
You might want to just add loads of cool details, but I find it so important to make all of these assets in situ.
Like this, there's a treasure chest in the level on the screen above, and then I'm painting it on the one below.
And I just have to make sure that all the time
I'm not trying to add too much detail
and look at the game as a screen, as a scene
rather than as, you know, individual assets.
So I think if I was going to summarize this style,
I'd put it like this, that it's like an eight year old
is telling me what to paint
and I'm struggling to keep up
with all their ideas and stories.
It's definitely something that I learned on Tearaway.
And although you might have chosen to use
quite a naive, simple style,
you still want it to look beautiful and aspirational.
You know, I still want to show off a little bit.
So it's more fun to try and achieve that
by kind of trying to create this like,
this collaboration between the gaming characters
and you trying to like, you know, depict their stories.
So once I've done my wide research, conducted some thoughtful investigations into the style,
and strived to integrate it with the game's themes and overall ethos,
I like to cut every corner possible.
Because all of that stuff takes a long time.
And it's terrible really, but you know,
I just need to stay true to the project's goals.
So I try not to worry too much
about the details that don't matter.
This tweet perfectly sums up my style of art production.
So sometimes just by deleting or hiding the worst thing,
you make everything else better.
You know, I'd like to do it all properly,
but you know, sometimes it's just not possible.
And it's great, you know, if you do this,
that you can win back some time
to really work on the characters
or work on the atmosphere of the game.
And I try and do a bunch of things
to like keep myself inspired while I'm working.
One of my main things is to go on plenty of walks.
Yes, there we go.
This, I mean, some walks are like very project focused.
This is going on hikes around the actual real life
environments that Knights and Bikes is based on.
But the most useful walks, to be honest,
are the ones where you're just taking a break
from your everyday, you know, when you're making a game,
you're just creating this carefully constructed,
sealed world around you.
and I think it's really good to just get out and like hear the weird stuff people say and
you know just experience you know things that you haven't like carefully designed yourself
and then you can jot all of those experiences down in sketchbooks and use them on future projects.
Also like to try and use all my sketchbooks to plan everything out,
you know a lot of stuff that will never be in the game but it's
You know, it's just working out how it all fits together.
And I find being slightly removed from the game
like a really good way of just, you know,
figuring it all out on paper.
And a lot of this actually kind of puts you back in that mindset of when you're eight years old,
and you're just, you know, you used to like make up little maps on pieces of paper for
places that don't exist, but now I have the power to make them exist. It's great.
And also a way that you can, I like to try and spend some of this time that I'm sort of
claiming back by like painting, oh more eyeballs.
Like, trying not to use the flood fill tool.
You know, that was the tool that like,
you know, that was the thing that drew me to computers
in the first place, because I was like,
oh my God, it's amazing.
You just click a button and everything's colored in.
But you've actually lost that time
where you're just sitting there
and like thinking about the next job you're gonna do.
So I try, there'll probably be a cut in a minute,
you'll see me use the flood fill and I'll be like ashamed.
But, you know, it's kind of,
I think it's really good to just spend some time
with the canvas, you know, just painting.
thinking about what you're working on.
So, that's kind of nearly done, which is just as well.
Had to like speed up a bit, but we're getting there.
This is kind of a, hopefully a bit of an insight
into how I'm trying to take nights and bikes
beyond the pop culture rapper in the artwork.
So, we'll have a little summary.
It's quite a big summary, actually.
So, I should just read these, really.
So, visual influences can come from the right soundtrack,
voice, piece of literature,
and it's good to reach outside your bubble
for new influences.
Going for walks is a good way to do that,
and you can control what you're,
because you can't control what you're going to see.
Type restrictions, like painting a game in two brushes,
or making it all from paper,
can really unify everything
and give you more scope for wildness.
Try and have a think about how your characters would depict
that what happens to you in the game to you, the creator,
so it's more of a collaboration.
Be autobiographical where you can
to add some extra flavor.
Create assets in situ,
so they match the style and level of detail.
cut corners on the world building,
so that you can spend it on atmosphere and characters,
emotions, uniqueness, et cetera.
It will only look as good as the worst thing on screen,
so maybe you just delete that worst thing.
And spend some time on those quiet, simple jobs,
because you'll be spending more time in the world,
directly touching it,
and considering what you'll be working on next.
And I'm just going to finish up by showing you an actual poster for a Death Metal Festival
and all the bands and their logos.
And I've got to say, I love you Party Cannon!
So I'm going to say to you all, be yourself, make interesting choices, enjoy what you do,
soak up the world and subvert what's being overused.
and be the party canon of this industry.
Thank you very much.
I don't know if there's any time for questions or not.
Yes?
Wonderful. One of the things that I struggle with is getting your level of, like, cohesion,
which I may never achieve before I die, but that's another thing. And I always encounter a point
where I'm drawing inspiration from a whole bunch of different sources, but the style that I've
built is sort of, like, filled with internal contradictions, and I don't know how to quite
squeeze hard enough to get all the impurities out. I'm wondering if you can provide any insight about
how to do that.
Sure, how to, I mean, because I come,
a lot of my background is making videos.
I used to make all the trailers for little big planet games and what have you.
And I've always found like making videos or ways of re-presenting my work or the work of my team
back to myself like really useful because you just, you see it slightly differently.
So it's like, you know, you make a little shizzle reel for your project, you know,
so that you're just like, you know, you really distill it down into its most...
well, into its best points, really.
And I find that a really good way to,
it might just show you where the holes are,
but also it's a good way of pushing it
in a new direction.
That's wonderful, thank you.
Thank you.
Hi.
Hi there, thank you for the talk.
I am an instructor over at Purdue University
with our game dev program.
And every semester when projects come around,
I'm kind of surprised by how many students won't take up
a 2D project unless it's like pixel art.
And I'm assuming it's because they think that hand-drawn
animation or that kind of digital painting
is really time consuming and potentially a tripping
point for the project.
they have 10 weeks, do you think it would be viable for them to get their foot in the door
with the art style and create at least a decent vertical slice of a 2D project like this or would
it be too cramped for them or would they get overloaded with it?
Yeah, so I think it's totally possible to do a 2D project in a short amount of time.
I think what can help is to maybe take some influences from short films.
There's some really interesting stuff where I'm always inspired when I see how...
how simple and focused some short films are,
where it might be just a character and an object on screen.
And they haven't, I think sometimes when we take things
into the interactive world, we feel that we have to put,
like, you know, everything has to be an object.
But as soon as you start adding a few objects,
then you have to add more and more and more.
And it's kind of interesting to just, you know.
make a game about a chicken and a worm and the worm just keeps popping up and going down and
you know that's all you need. So I think just being very focused on the actual
setup of the game so that all of the assets can be like really
worked up and be the best that they can be. Thank you so much. I'll pass it on.
Cool. All done?
OK, well, thanks everyone for coming.
Have a great GDC.
Cheers.