It's 1.45, I'm gonna kick us off.
Welcome to AAA Academics.
I wanna get straight to the conversation,
so just a little framing.
This is a panel with several fantastic designers
who have worked and been very successful in industry
who have recently been making the transition
into academic institutions where they are teaching.
We have a panel of wonderful, wonderful panelists.
I will introduce them all quite briefly.
But here immediately to my right is John Romero,
who you may know from such games as Quake or Doom.
He also currently teaches at the University of California, Santa Cruz.
And to his right is Brenda Romero,
who you may know from such wonderful projects as Train and Wizardry.
And she also teaches at the University of California at Santa Cruz.
To her right is Richard Lamarchand.
Richard, you may know from such projects as Soul Reaver and Uncharted,
and Richard teaches at the University of Southern California.
And finally, we have Warren Spector, who you may know from such projects as Day's X
or Disney's Epic Mickey, and he now teaches at the University of Texas at Austin.
So, like I said, I want to dive right into this.
I'm going to ask some questions, and hopefully we're going
to have an interesting conversation here.
When I run out of questions, if there's some magical, theoretical time at the end,
we may even take a few audience questions for the panel to answer.
So, I want to start right away by asking how the four of you ended up entering the academic field.
Can you talk just a little bit about how you became interested in teaching in academia,
whether you were approached by an academic institution or you'd harbored a long passion for it,
maybe you'd been part-time lecturing?
Okay, I'm going.
Well, before I got into games as anything but an amateur,
I mean, I was in the 70s.
I'm really old.
But in the 70s, I was playing Dungeons and Dragons
and all those Avalon Hill board games and games
like Champions created partly by the person sitting
in the front row here.
And at the same time, I was working on my doctorate
at the University of Texas and figured
I was heading for a career in teaching.
It's a long-sorted story why I ended up
making games instead, which I will tell you
if things get really slow.
But I always thought I was going to teach at some point.
I just didn't think it was going to be quite this soon.
I've been making games for 30 years, which sounds like a lot, but it really isn't.
It either kills you or keeps you young making games.
But the University of Texas actually, after many, many years of many of us twisting arms,
we just, they finally said, we're going to start a development program.
And the day came when I said, hey, wait a minute.
If anybody but me is directing that, I'm going to be really upset.
So I agreed to do it and, you know, I hope I get back to making games
or make some games on the side.
But right now, a little too soon, I'm a full-time academic.
So for my part, I guess that I'd always kind of wanted to be back in higher education ever since I graduated college.
I actually remember telling my friends, soon after I joined the game industry in the early 90s, that one day I would have a doctorate of ludology.
And they all laughed at me, but...
I'll show them. I mean, yes. And now we have doctorates of ludology.
So I started volunteering at USC in around about 2004, visiting classes, giving talks,
eventually mentoring students in the MFA program.
I got involved with IndyCade in 2009. I've been speaking at GDC since 2008.
So I think all of these things were connecting together for me.
at IndieCade, actually, in 2010.
I vividly remember where I was.
I was ironing a shirt in Eric Zimmerman's hotel room,
and I had this sudden realization
that I was heading towards sort of a crossroads
in my professional life,
one of these times when we can,
where we have an opportunity to make a choice.
It was about halfway through the development
of Uncharted 3, and I realized that
while I'd had the most amazing time working at Naughty Dog,
it was a superlative place to be.
I had this opportunity to pursue the love for games and play as art and culture that I'd always nurtured,
really since the beginning of my time in the industry.
So as I started talking to my friends about what I might do next,
one of the friends I spoke to was Tracy Fullerton,
who's the chair of the Interactive Media and Games Division that I'm now part of,
and Tracy suggested that there might be a role available for me.
So I chased it up, and here I am.
For me, mine was really a happy coincidence.
I've gone into academia and then back into the industry,
and now I'm academia slash industry.
My current role actually requires me to remain active in the industry, which is...
exactly what I want. The first time it was really one of jealousy, almost.
The guy, you know, is taking college classes. I love learning.
And as a frontline lead designer, you know, I envied my friends who were talking, like,
books that have been read, you know, that were written, that I just had no time to read,
or discussions that I wanted to have about games at a level.
that we just couldn't do when we're trying to hit milestone after milestone after milestone.
So, much like you, I was at a transition point and I happened to see an ad
looking for a game designer to teach.
So I went, you know, I ended up accepting that job.
And for me, once I got in there,
It was really working with the students that made it irresistible and why I had to go back.
Like my favorite classes to teach are the intro to game development classes.
Because for many students, this is, they've gotten, you know, they're maybe 18 or 19.
This is the first class they've ever taken in game development.
They've been told all their lives, you know, this is, you want to do what?
You want to go to college for this? You're going to pay money for people to teach you games?
And you see the first time that they're in that classroom,
and somebody there is validating what they've
wanted to do for 18 years, and they're on fire,
and they've got so much passion, that's a drug to me.
I love that.
And so that's why I keep teaching.
That's how I got here, and that's why I keep doing it.
I was asked by a professor at UT Dallas, I think in 2002, to teach a class.
And so I did that probably for like a semester.
It was a cross-platform game development class.
And when it was over...
they basically told me, hey, why don't we create a curriculum
and do a game degree here at UTD?
And I was just like, this is not the place
to learn game development.
I had seen Full Sail, and I was like, that is really intense.
I kind of believe in you immerse yourself
every day for as long as you possibly
can in learning how to make games.
And that's all you do.
So I just said, this isn't the place.
We need a college here in Dallas to do that.
So I came up with the idea for the Guild Hall at SMU
and worked with these people to find the right people
to start that school, mostly because I
needed to hire people at my company.
I wanted them to come from Dallas.
I want them to be local and just come on over and start working.
So I never taught at the Guild Hall.
I just started it.
And then
And then later, basically working with UC Santa Cruz,
with my wife Brenda, we worked there for a little while,
basically shepherding students through their final quarter
of their BS degree, and had been talking to them
about starting a new, like, master's degree program
at UCSC, so that's what we developed
and what we're doing right now.
And it's a blast getting to work with.
You know, people that know how to code, but they really want to learn more about design
and how to develop really great games.
And so that's kind of what we're doing now. It's really fun.
I mean, it's exciting for me to hear that you all sort of have a passion for teaching
or for reaching the students or for being involved in these institutions.
It seems like in the end, whether you were recruited or had tinkered around it, there's a joy or a desire that's drawing you in.
But also, like Brenda mentioned, she gets to now be halftime academic, halftime industry.
So what are the obstacles, the challenges that you found taking these positions, whether they're challenges of mind?
this is a choice that I'm giving something up and I'm going to have to take this other thing.
What are you giving up?
And what are the other more logistical or odd challenges that I'm not thinking of that you might have?
Well, at the top of my list in my notes, I have fear and self-doubt, which are, I suppose,
you know, major obstacles that we all face in life.
And you know, I guess it was a very big change for me, one that I hadn't necessarily seen
coming.
I did have some time to get used to the idea and explore it and talk to friends about it.
But I'm very glad that I did.
You know, I've always tried to push myself outside of my comfort zone a little bit,
try and be the kind of adventurous person that I love to be in the games that I play.
So if that's holding anyone back here who might be considering a change,
I would say push through that fear of the unknown,
because it's certainly been an amazingly rewarding experience for me.
I think one of the things that I know holds a lot of people back,
and it's changed, so if you've actually been pushed out because of this, I encourage you to push your way back in,
is the degree wall.
So you want to teach game development, do you have a PhD? No.
But I've worked on a hundred games, tough.
And there's lots of game developers who I know are ready to move into academia who really want to do this.
and are unable to because they don't have a PhD or a master's, or maybe in some cases even a bachelor's.
But that's changing, and I'm noticing people, institutions accepting people or willing to work with people.
who don't have the terminal degree.
I think another challenge for a lot of game developers
coming in is, especially if they're coders,
so they're coming from game industry code salary
and they hear about academic salary.
And it's a shock.
And I will say, one of the things, though,
is being able to balance.
And it's full-time academic and then
slamming game development in everywhere
in all the available hours.
The supplementing whatever you're doing professionally
with whatever you're doing, whatever
you get from academia with consulting and other game dev
stuff.
But yeah, that's a wall for many.
I've experienced all of this, so I won't go back over it again.
For me, the most interesting challenge is I never realized how much of my personal sense
of self was tied up with, I am a game developer.
And now, what do I put on credit card applications?
Manager.
But that's been a surprisingly steep hurdle that I'm not actually over yet,
because I didn't have the advantage that some other people who've made this transition had,
in that I'm building something from scratch.
The Dean of Sam's Gaming Academy literally doesn't exist yet.
We're seating our first class on August 27th.
a date that has burned in my brain out of terror.
But it's been a full-time job and a half for me.
And my plan, my big master plan was I was going to do a little startup on the side.
I had some folks who wanted to fund it, you know.
No, no, not yet.
I'm hoping a year from now, you know, I'll be able to get back to making some smaller
games, but right now, I can't do that.
So what do I call my...
Tell me what I call myself.
You're a game designer.
Game developer.
Yeah, you're a game developer, yeah.
Okay.
And I think you can own that.
You're Warren Spector.
Oh, give me a word.
Hi Warren.
Do they have a code for that?
Hey, there's no death matching with Warren Spector at this show.
There could be.
He's playing again at 4.30.
Yeah, see?
You can just go down there.
Yeah, we'll be happy.
Brenda and I both own a game company, and it's right across the street from UCSC.
So it's really lucky for us that UCSC loves that we actually stay active in the industry
so we can keep on teaching the latest and greatest.
So we basically just walk across the street, back and forth.
You know, I'm actually jealous of that too.
We warned you this was going to be a conversation.
You guys have each other.
Yeah.
And I describe myself as a guy sitting alone in a room with no windows, you know.
Well, it's awesome in a way, because I just get to make a bunch of stuff up.
It's like the early phases of making.
The game I'm making right now is the Gaming Academy.
It's very strange.
Basically, what do they need to know?
Yeah.
What do I want to teach them?
Yeah, exactly.
This kind of relates to one more challenge that I have faced, which is the challenge
of learning a new profession.
Because while I do have a little riff about the commonalities between being a game designer
and a teacher, of course, being a full-time educator is his own profession.
There's a lot to learn.
So...
I've never heard the word assessment until about two months ago.
Oh yeah, they're going to judge you.
Who knew?
You get an A for play.
The, when I first started teaching, I remember,
I think he's, I'm sure Ian Shriver's out there somewhere.
Maybe, maybe not.
But when I was talking with, hi Ian.
When I was just getting into teaching,
I remember like a week before,
I did have this tremendous crisis.
Like, what if I don't know anything?
I really, what if, and I really did,
like what if my students, what if I come in
and they're like, no kidding?
And I do have this overwhelming feeling like I had nothing.
And he said, Brenda, you can go in and just talk
about hitting a milestone.
You can talk about just what is your day like in a game
development studio.
And that may be, that'll be new stuff.
But I remember Ian having to talk me off the edge.
You know, this is after 20, I don't know,
25 years in game development.
One would have hoped I'd picked up something, right?
You know?
But I did.
I had that feeling.
And it was all new to me, like having to prepare lectures
or grading homework.
You know, it's a.
It was, but still, you know, very rewarding.
Yeah, well, so now that I've asked about challenges,
I mean, what are the rewards or surprises even
that you've encountered as you've shifted back to me?
I mean, both Warren and Richard sort of gestured at this idea that
actually when you start heavily designing an academic curriculum, whether on a broad scale or for a class,
it is some of the work that you've been doing for your whole lives of game design.
What are other surprises like that, or if one of you guys wants to unpack that thought a little more?
For me, and this is actually riffing off something Warren said, to me, building
Building an academic program, to me, feels like building a game.
And I'm shipping students.
Yeah. Exactly right.
And it's very similar.
Like, what are all those systems?
What are the things they need to know?
And building that and making sure they get it all.
And also, we're in our first year,
and you guys are nowhere close to your first year, but...
it's iterative no matter what.
You have to change because the industry changes.
And so making, seeing, well, OK, so now we're the sequel.
It's the next year.
How do we want to change it?
Yeah, I mean, I guess this relates to my riff
about the commonalities between being, say, a lead game
designer and a teacher.
I was really pleasantly surprised by just how much there
is in common between my new life as a professor
and my life as a lead game designer.
The classes that I teach are studio classes, so just as at Naughty Dog where I would work with a group of game designers
and we would all be making work and looking at it and talking about it and giving each other notes and debating the qualities of the gameplay.
So I still do, just with people with a little less experience,
but who are amazing game designers, bursting with ideas,
bursting with critical thought and ideas for innovation and originality.
And like you say, Brenda, we're developing systems, processes,
and we get to iterate on them semester by semester.
Yeah, the way I think about it is, you know, no plan survives first contact with the enemy and the students.
But seriously, I'm approaching this very much like like I would if I were creating a game.
And in fact, the first day of classes, if any of you have already applied or want to apply or anything, just be warned.
Day one.
comment one from me, statement one, is going to be,
welcome to the Denia Sam's Gaming Academy version beta 1.0.
Because we're going to be changing it constantly.
Because, I mean, what I knew six months ago
might be out of date already.
You really have to keep making games to stay relevant.
I think that's critical.
Totally.
Yeah, which is what we do.
We actually have a game that's about to ship,
and we just started developing another big game.
I am so jealous.
We also do consulting, too, so we get lots of input on what's happening.
And it's useful for the students to hear, because we talk about other stuff, too.
We don't just, here's what we're teaching in this class,
but we also talk about, like, here's the latest thing that's happening in the industry
and what that means, and it's kind of here.
Everybody up on, like, it's about learning constantly.
Everything that's happening is all relevant.
Mm-hmm.
I'm actually, I'm kind of, I don't know if you have a little more to unpack there,
but I'm interested in unpacking just a little bit more.
sort of what you, the collective you,
can bring that's unique to academic programs
because you have this ongoing and past industry experience,
because you've shipped games,
from your perspective sort of as AAA superstars,
as our panel has titled you all?
Totally, sorry.
I didn't put the mic back on, bad me.
So I was just asking specifically,
To go off of what John was saying, the idea that coming from industry, there are special
unique things that they can bring to academic programs.
I'd be interested in what more you guys think you do bring from that stance.
Well, having made tons of games and shipped tons of stuff and been doing it for decades,
that experience is not anything that most students get.
And I think that's really, really valuable because we can talk about decades and how it was in that decade.
We can talk about lots of things we've tried.
We've tried, we've failed, we've done lots of stuff over the years.
And having that experience, we can tell them what's common and what doesn't change and what's really important.
And I think in the case of all of us,
our experience is very recent, too.
And in a business and in a medium that changes so rapidly,
I think recent experience is critical.
Right now, I'm in the process of hiring two full-time faculty
members.
And one of my requirements is that your experience
has come in the last three years.
And I'm even ashamed to say three years.
I want your experience to have been six months ago.
So recent experience, I think, as well as long-term
experience.
Last shift game.
Yeah.
Yeah, exactly.
The thing that I, where I see that there's a lot of values is going back to how similar
it is to being a lead game designer.
And even though, if I'm working with somebody in industry, I want my lead to have lots of
experience, not because...
I feel that she has done great things during that time,
but with the lots of experience,
I know that she has seen things go wrong.
And the value in a lead to me is that they've seen
stuff go off the rails, she can spot it a mile away,
and she's not gonna panic about it.
And so that's the value in a lead.
And you see, over the course of 30 years,
you see a lot of stuff happen.
And so,
You know, for instance, our students just hit alpha, you know, and I let them know,
and I'm sure you guys deal with this too, I said, and I saw some of you out in the audience,
so I won't mention you by name, but I know roughly where you're sitting, Ian.
I'm sorry. Did I say I wouldn't say your name, Ian?
It's all Ian.
Anybody named Ian, I'll be referencing you all talk.
Anyway, but our students, you can see just this,
like, everything, there's no way we could possibly hit alpha.
Everything's going to go to hell.
The whole world's going to catch on fire.
And just letting them know, like, you know what?
Somehow alpha will happen, and the world
will not catch on fire.
And you're going to be thrilled when it gets there.
And that's just, that's not to say that when we're shipping,
we don't feel the same way.
Well, I mean, that's what I've tried to do.
TJ's in the front row and chuckling about this very issue.
Because, yeah, you know, we work to,
we try and bring the sort of structured methodology
for our students that we've learned in the industry
that we've had to kind of struggle
to get to grips with in the industry.
How to hit alpha well, how to not slip beta.
And yeah, I think it's always really valuable
to make yourself vulnerable to the students,
to tell them, look.
I know you're working really hard and maybe it hasn't gone as well as you might have liked
to make your game feature complete and let me tell you about that one time on this one
project where we managed to pull it out of the fire at the last minute.
That freedom to fail is critical, you know.
In the game business, if I fail too often or too frequently or too recently, I get fired.
In an academic setting, every failure is a learning opportunity.
One of the things that absolutely freaks the administrators out when I talk to them about this,
but I actually want to engineer failure into the program.
Because every failure is a learning opportunity.
Absolutely.
And it's safe.
Yeah, I mean, I think it was Tracy who really drew my attention to the fact that, in a way,
a big failure is a better learning experience than a big success,
when you're just learning how to be a game developer.
So, yeah, I always try and embody that rapid prototyping credo,
fail early, fail fast, fail often, in everything that we do, you know, in the program.
And I always say, to follow up on something Brenda said,
The game is not the product in my course.
The people and the knowledge they gain are the product.
And the experience.
And the experience, yeah.
At least I hope we can take what would take years to learn
and compress it into a year.
I mean, you're not going to get it overnight,
but I think we can do a lot of compression and career acceleration
in an academic setting that we don't have the time to do
if we have the skill to do it in our real life.
And with freedom to fail comes tremendous freedom to experiment and to innovate.
Because you've got to do something to fix it.
And we've had the same experience with, like, right now, even, like, with our alphas,
where we've had some teams hit a wall where they know that they haven't done something great
and they have to do something to fix it because we push innovation constantly while we're teaching.
It's like if you're not doing something innovative and new and exciting, you shouldn't be making that game.
So that's kind of like one of our high bars
that they have to hit, and they know when they haven't hit it,
and then it's time for a redesign,
or it's a reboot or something.
So they've kind of hit that failure point
that they've recognized, and then they get to fix it.
And fix it in crunch mode.
We can keep going.
Yeah, no, I know you can.
I sort of don't want to cut you off.
I actually want to, I sort of want
to hear the four of you talk a little bit about crunch
vis-a-vis the Academy.
I don't know if anybody has thoughts on that.
I absolutely do. I think it relates to what we were just talking about because
you know part of the reason that we want to teach a
structured production methodology is so we can have the conversation about
quality of life
and certainly I've given it to myself as a mandate
to address this issue very directly with my students. You know the game
industry historically has had a problem with crunch.
with people working too hard for too long
and hurting themselves physically and psychologically
and often leaving the industry, leading to
this terrible wastage of experience.
Some of our most experienced people leaving the industry and going
to a profession where they can have a better work-life balance.
I mean, I think that the game industry has managed to really
start to work to get this under control in a lot of very
responsible ways in the last decade or so, really.
But I think that we have great opportunities as educators to
have really frank conversations with our
students about this.
And while I'm a big fan of working hard in a sustained
way for the right amount of time to achieve excellence at
a certain critical stage of the project, I really try and
encourage my students.
not to crunch in the way that some people do to their detriment.
I don't know how you guys feel about this.
It's interesting, the quality of life, I mean, I feel
you know, I have conflicted thoughts on it, right? Because
I get up in the morning and I'm awake and I'm reading about games
or I'm playing a game and then I go to work and
I'm talking about or working on games for
eight to ten hours and then I come home.
and I'm working on games for a couple hours, then I might play a game
before I go to bed. And this is pretty much my life and that is quality
for me. It would drive other people to institutions, I'm sure,
not of higher learning, but the other kind.
But that to me is a quality life and
I also recognize that's not for everybody.
It's also a choice for you. I mean, for many of us...
I don't feel like it was, though. I've been making...
Like, I don't feel like I ever had another living I could have had.
You have a milestone coming up. You know, you've got a...
Your publisher throws in a demo that, you know, is required in a week,
and, no, you can't have more time. I mean, that's not a choice.
No, okay, that's right.
You just have to do it.
Yeah, so I... And I still have that publisher, so I still eat that.
But that said, you know, I don't want the students to overwork themselves. I feel like our milestones are reasonable.
And we do talk about that. Like I tell them about the CEO I work for who says he's going to make everybody crunch in January and February.
And I was on the team and I said, why? And he said, because we did it last year and it worked great.
But there's no goal that you're trying to hit.
Don't care.
That's an actual conversation.
So I tell the students about that.
That is, that's, well, thanks.
I'm leaving, Crunch.
And we talk about all the various ways it shows up.
The death marches that I've been on,
had to crunch for nine months, seven days a week.
we talk about the range of it because you don't want to go into a place where that's happened.
You know, and hopefully what I try to encourage is you're working on your game every single day,
you know, leaving not planning well ends to disaster in the end and leads to these type
of crunches. I think that's the same stuff we would do in industry. Having said that,
okay, true confessions, there are times when crunch is really cool.
It's bonding and it's energizing.
It's pretty damn cool
a lot of the time. There are times when it's not
and I think what we have to do is communicate to our students.
you know, when it's too much and why you want to do it,
and what are the values that can be gained from it,
and what are the damages that can be done by it.
But I'll tell you, the freakiest thing to me,
and maybe I shouldn't say this,
because it's going to sound like I'm an advocate of crunch in a big way,
but the University of Texas shuts its buildings down at 11 o'clock at night.
You're not allowed in the building after 11,
and I'm going, wow, that's so not like me.
There's no crunch happening there, yeah.
That's the middle of the afternoon for a program.
Yeah, my best working attitude after that.
Well, everyone takes their laptops outside then.
That'll probably be what...
No, that won't be what happens.
We won't do that.
At our small company, when we started this last company, Loot Drop, in 2010,
and we started working on our first game, we had a really small office space,
and we had maybe, jeez, eight people or ten people.
working on it and then our company grew to 40 and we'd move to different, to two different times,
but everybody remembers that first space and
the crunch that we were on is just like the best time they've ever had in game development.
And it's just because it was a small team. We loved what we were doing, which is the big differentiator between crunch and not crunch.
and everybody got to know each other really well
and everyone liked each other.
But for me it's just part and parcel of best practices
and good methodology.
It's just a question of saying to the guys
something as simple as, hey, you know,
maybe the time when you should be working hard
on your project is not at the end, but in the middle.
When you're heading towards alpha and beta.
Because if you're all frazzled at the end,
you'll make silly mistakes at the last minute
and ruin, you know, an otherwise.
perfectly brilliant game.
Well, really.
Go ahead.
And these are the kinds of things
that you have to win through experience, I think,
unless you can kind of.
Also, just like planning correctly,
which is obviously what everybody harps on about.
Bad planning leads to crunch.
Leaving lots of time in your milestones is really helpful.
Like right now, one of the games that we're developing,
we turned in our third milestone.
We're already working on the fifth one.
And so we're like months ahead, which is really great
because if it ever gets to a point where,
oh, beta is looking like it's gonna be taking
some extra time, we have tons of padding.
and so if you can plan that and get the right number of people to do that
then you don't have a crunch. Mattie Burns said this really interesting thing
last year that has stayed with me and that I've tried to use. He said that he
feared that because
maybe as teachers of game design we might not have
our eye on the ball of the scope of our students' designs
as we might have at the beginning of their processes
and then when we get to what I believe is technically known as the
oh shit moment.
in the middle of a project, when we suddenly realize how much we have left to do,
the students kind of in school might tend to learn that they have to work
harder and harder and harder towards the end. So now,
as a teacher of game design, I'm trying to make sure that I work really hard at
the beginning of the project
with my students to make sure that their projects are well scoped. And then all of this
other good stuff kind of leads from that in a very natural way that leads toward
best practices.
Yeah, the scoping is like massively important.
That's like so unbelievably important.
Errors at the beginning magnify over time.
That's just like basic common sense.
And so we have a really great advisory board
that's there to choose.
We have our teams design three pitches.
And the advisory board, which is all industry people
and academics, basically as many of them
come as possible to vet these pitches.
And then they get to choose, and they get to just critique it,
and just scope is like the number one thing that they look at,
whether it's even doable or not.
And then from that point, then they can kind of go on with the thing
that the industry panels decided,
this is good, but you need to do this, you know,
and try and help us scope at the very beginning before they...
That's another interesting advantage of having people who've just come out of the industry.
I have plenty of friends that I can shame into participating in this program.
So we have a development council as well that's going to be part of the absolutely terrifying review process, I hope.
I mean, it's kind of intimidating going. I mean, I've had to pitch to the CEO of the Walt Disney Company, you know.
And I remember back in the day pitching to the CEO of Electronic Arts and the Executive Vice President of Sales and everything.
I mean, it's pretty intimidating. I want students to have that experience too.
Because you're inevitably going to get up in front of people who are going to make you stutter and stammer.
And getting that experience before you actually have to do it to get paid, I think, is a really good thing.
You know, this relates, I don't know why what you said made me think of this, but what an early question, the challenges.
One of the things that, and you also mentioned something about this,
going from industry into academia, you mentioned that it's
it's a whole different profession, which is obvious, but just because you're
you are a game developer, maybe you're even an award-winning game developer,
doesn't mean that you have the foggiest idea
how to captivate a room full of people.
and how to, and I wished that there had been some little boot camp for,
so you're a game designer and you'd like to come teach people.
I'm a teacher, let me tell you what I know about working with students.
Nobody on a milestone comes up to me and
you know like, I've never had to massively alter someone's life to say you
failed this course and I'm sorry but you're not going to be able to graduate.
Oh my god, it's like the worst thing I can imagine and I had to do it.
UT has someone like that, actually.
I mean, I'm sure they have many, but there's
a woman in the College of Communication, where I am,
whose job is to work with teachers
to make them better teachers.
Oh, that's great.
Yeah, I meet with her every, well, not right now,
because I'm too busy.
But I was meeting with her every Thursday
and intend to get back into that at some point.
I think this is, in fact, the session where the game
designers who may or may not be sitting in the audience
and are thinking about moving to academia would love.
those five pieces of advice that each of you wish someone had given you before you made the jump.
I'm accepting applications now, by the way, both for students and for faculty.
But do you have, I mean, in that, do you have thoughts, things that you would tell
to a colleague who came to you and said, I'm thinking about going and teaching.
What should I know? What should I do? How can I prepare?
Learn the meaning of the word assessment and learn the meaning of the word rubric.
Although the rubric's just the rules of the game, isn't it?
It's the stuff at the end that tells you the ground conditions for the clubs.
I would say, if you're thinking about it, start now on getting your resume and your background together.
every game, every article, every award, everything on your resume because that, to get a resume
that you, if you're going to work at Naughty Dog, you're going to put one thing together,
but if you're preparing a, I'm heading into academia CV, that's a massive deal.
when John was going was looking at going to
UCSC and I asked so let me see your resume and I don't have one.
You didn't have to make a resume did you? Oh yeah. I didn't have to make a resume.
They just let me skate through. Yeah basically UCSC is this huge machine.
Well what do you think he's at a machine? Yeah the state schools.
I'm at a big machine with lots of grit and gears. They knew who you are.
But it was all the way back to, I mean, every award,
all the articles.
And that's important, because especially if you don't have
a PhD, and he doesn't, you have to, and I have a bachelor's,
and I'm partway through a master's.
If you don't have that, you have to justify it with experience.
And all that experience needs to be verified on paper.
And it was a pretty massive undertaking to do that.
I don't know how generalizable this is, but my program is currently a certificate program.
The university didn't want to dive into a full degree program until it was proved out.
And as part of a certificate program, applicants for faculty positions don't have to, I mean,
I get to just pick.
It's you.
It's like an interview.
Yeah, yeah, I mean, that's essentially, I determined the requirements, the job requirements,
and I get to interview people, and then I get to pick.
And it's kind of the same with the students.
The students don't have to go through the standard, you know, the main building,
which is where the admissions department is.
They don't have to go through any of that.
Go for a certificate program.
If anybody's, if you're a game developer and you're thinking of doing it, I would do it.
Man, I've just, I love working with students so much.
And I love that, you know, like I'm working on the Trail of Tears game right now.
What's the ship they don't know?
You know, and then I have that kind of freedom to pursue projects that nobody in their right mind would ever publish.
And that I'm working with students who are just so incredibly excited.
Like, after they hit alpha...
and they showed their games in front of the review board,
the happiness that I saw among them
was enough to power me through GDC.
Isn't it, it's so exciting.
It really is amazing.
I mean, I guess that would be maybe my biggest piece
of advice that you may have heard teachers say.
You know what makes this experience so meaningful is the students, but it's absolutely true.
It's absolutely true.
The energy, the ideas, the enthusiasm of the people that we teach is the most incredibly
sustaining thing, I think, about the experience.
Another piece of advice is, I mean, I guess this kind of connects to what you guys have been saying.
I feel like I began to learn how to be a teacher here at GDC, really,
by being lucky enough to be able to give talks, by going to roundtables, actually,
and beginning to learn how to...
have a debate in front of a room of 30 people,
you know, meeting people in the halls, meeting some of my heroes, you know.
And so I think that
if you once long ago on
PBS I heard, I wish I could remember the name of the motivational speaker, but it
was a talk about transforming your life, you know, if you were
perhaps not completely happy with what you were doing and you wanted to
create a new career for yourself, then the advice that this person gave was to
not change it all at once, not don't quit your day job and throw all your savings
into this new thing, but do it bit by bit.
So consider, you know, giving a talk at a local community college or a
you know, a local university, get involved with the IGDA or, you know,
with some other game development organization
and see where it leads. Because I think that I'm very lucky that that sort of
happened to me quite
serendipitously. Suddenly, without my realizing it, without my planning it,
suddenly all the stars were aligned
for me to be able to move into this role. So... Can I ask a question related to that?
So I've given a lot of talks at GDC, I've given a lot of talks at universities,
and I may not be any good at it, but I'm really comfortable doing it.
And I don't know how that, I haven't started teaching yet.
The teaching starts in the fall.
I don't know how that's going to translate to,
I have to get up three times a week and talk for an hour and a half.
It totally translates.
Well, okay. We're done. Thanks for coming. Smaller audience. It really does. It does totally translate. I have one small caveat. I found I'm always chronically over prepared for most everything I do.
And one of the tough things for me to learn has been that I don't need to be quite as prepared with lecture materials and stuff as I think that I need to.
If I have a few good talking points for class.
The students will bring all the most brilliant information
into the room.
That's if it's interactive.
But that's one of the things you need to plan,
is that it's going to be an interactive class,
and not just a free tea.
That's true, and not a lecture class.
But I don't know if any of you guys caught the great seven
exercises for teachers of game design session that
was in this room this morning that John Sharp and Colleen
Macklin ran.
But exercises, Warren, I think they're also your secret
weapon.
My classes love programming tests.
Just like throw a pro, well, like, I guess, when they're done with this class, they're
going to be in the industry and the more prep that they get, the better.
So it's like, here's Blizzard's test, if you're a coder, you know, here's one that we give,
you know, just like randomly, just, they're not graded on it, but it's like, here's what's
going to happen, you know, it's very useful.
And one of the things, just with classes,
is I too would have this.
This is exactly what we're going to talk about today,
be boop kind of whatever.
And the current course that I'm teaching,
although I guess it's over now, but the current course
that I'm teaching over now, it's finals week.
It's over for me.
Not for you guys.
So the current course is about non-digital game design.
Really just right down to the metal.
How do you, I guess not down to the wood,
down to the prototype parts, whatever.
The cardboard.
Down to the cardboard.
And just looking at game mechanics and game design
at its most fundamental level.
And being comfortable in completely derailing a whole class, I had about, this is stupid,
but this is what I did, I had 15 minutes budgeted for discussing what is a game.
And we actually had to put, we had like guest speakers come in and you'd see like,
so let's talk about, you know, it's interesting to me, what is a game?
And you'd watch my students like, oh man, this is a week.
still talking about it now, you know?
Probably, right?
But being flexible in some of the best conversations have come up, have happened,
because these are the things that we're going to talk about today,
and then somehow something else happens.
And that's so rewarding.
Some of those...
You should take a note.
Some of those conversations can be the best.
Oh.
Great thing about, that's very different in academia that I love,
whereas if I said, yeah, we're doing something really cool in our current game,
what are you doing? Can't tell you, can't share.
But in academia, it's like, well, no, I'll just send you my, I'll send you all my notes.
I'll send you my stuff. Send me all your notes.
There's no NDAs, right? So it's, so it's very, it's very open,
which was something to get used to. You're going to post my slides online.
It's very free and I like that.
So what about the other side of this?
For the institutions, should there be any institutions in the room who are interested in hiring high-level game designers to come from industry and become a part of their program or build a program?
Would you have advice for institutions like that?
How they can make the position more appealing?
Pay better.
Prepare.
How they can also prepare their institution or prepare the situation for success.
Remove bureaucratic barriers.
I thought Disney had a lot of bureaucracy.
Allowing professors to work on the side is great.
UCSC lets students own their own IP, which is really valuable
because it means that they don't have to hold back their best ideas while they're in school.
They can just make them and own them and take them out and publish them.
That's super valuable.
I'm sure everyone's been there.
We're like, that's a great idea, but I'm not going to do anything about it yet.
I've already talked about the degree wall,
but I know that affects so many game developers.
Some of the best game developers in the game industry
don't, game developers in the automotive industry,
obviously the game industry,
some of the best game developers don't have a degree,
but they've got this knowledge that we want.
So if you're unwilling to allow them to teach
unless they have that formal degree,
maybe give them a pathway where they could do that.
You know, that's just such a needless bureaucratic barrier.
I don't have a degree.
You have a high school degree.
Oh, sorry.
High school diploma.
That's why in my program, I tell people there are three ways into the program.
Graduate from an existing game development program so you kind of know how to make games
already.
Have three-ish, one to three years experience in the game business and want to accelerate
your career path.
And convince me you're God's gift to gaming because I don't want to be the guy who turns
away the next John Romero or Richard Gere.
I'm not going to be that guy.
I guess if I had a piece of advice for an institution looking to attract people from one of the many different game industries to their school,
it might be to think about what the value proposition is, you know, for that person.
And I think that universities and other kinds of educational institutions have an amazing opportunity right now,
when so many folks who have worked in one part of the game industry or another have this burning desire to make
unique, innovative, idiosyncratic work.
And as you were just talking about, Brenda,
we have great opportunities to do that in the academy.
So that's certainly something that drew me to USC.
I'm working on an independent design research project
right now, and doing things that I always
tried to get started when I was working
as a full-time professional AAA developer.
that I just couldn't do because my whole mind was full of whatever project I was working on.
And in any case, I've often said that being at USC is like being at GDC every day.
I love GDC so much. It would be my one week of the year where I'd really get to come and talk about games and play
and the process of designing these cultural artifacts.
different unconstrained way and that's a freedom that we also have in the academy.
So you have a lot to draw people to you, so consider how you can articulate that to folks
when you're doing a job search or whatever.
All right, I'm going to circle back once more to something that came up early because it's
actually my favorite topic.
which is...
Dungeons and Dragons?
Yes.
That's Richard Hasrelli veiled my true favorite topic.
We're going to just throw this panel out now
and talk about D&D for 15 minutes.
No, um...
Vornheim, actually.
Sam's my DM in Vornheim.
But, no, so we talked a couple of times
about the similarities
between designing curriculum,
between being a teacher,
between the shared skills you have,
whether you're talking to GDC
and how much that's like...
talking in a classroom, or how the systems design work
you do as a game designer is like the systems design work
you do in potentially building a class.
So are there other things there that are really applicable?
What are the similarities for you as someone leading
your daily life between having been a game designer
and now being a games academic?
Is it a huge change, or is it a surprisingly subtle shift?
Well, in designing a program, again, I'm at a little bit of a disadvantage here in that I haven't actually started this yet.
But my process is, you know, you start with what is the outcome?
And that's very much the way I always approach design.
I mean, what do you what do you want players to experience?
What do you want them to feel? What do you want them to do?
What are the verbs? And that's exactly the way I've approached the curriculum.
Again, it's not just.
designing a course, I'm designing an entire course of study,
and it's very much that, you know, what is the outcome,
what is the output, what do the players have to have experienced along the way.
So it's very similar in that respect.
I bet it's going to be a lot like running a paper game campaign for you, Warren.
Oh, if you want to talk about D&D, I'm your guy.
I've got an agenda here. Let's go.
Mitch is taking over the panel.
Well, because I think it is, you know, those hours you spend in the evening at home drawing your maps and creating the characters and then all of a sudden the players are there in the room, you've got your DM, your moderator's shield and you're rolling the dice.
Don't forget they all have stat sheets which contain grades.
Oh, I'm not grading anybody.
Oh.
I've got a cunning plan for that.
Get some CA's, yeah.
No, no, no, no, no, there will be no grades in my program.
Saving clothes.
But improvable saving clothes.
I can't reveal all my secrets.
Oh, wait.
I guess for us, the similarities are that we're just,
we're teaching what we know.
And so we're still talking about,
we're constantly talking about the things
that we do all the time.
Like some of our classes are how to start an LLC,
how to handle HR, how to get a lawyer,
just all the stuff,
because these people need to start companies.
They need to start making stuff.
They need to own IP.
They need to know the value of IP
versus making someone else's IP more valuable.
And so we have professional courses that are just,
giving them all the information about like, here's my 10 startups and how they went.
And, you know, just tons of information about not just the game stuff, but what's around
the game development.
That's great.
And does that feel like the life of a game developer
a little bit?
I mean, in the same way we juggle and all.
We run companies, so it happens all the time.
Right, right.
Your life is juggling these 20 things.
You know, but the thing that's changed for me tremendously,
being a game developer, is that one
of the things that drew me into academia
is I felt like, having started in game development in 81,
I was a little bit more comfortable with the fact
that I was a game developer.
I was a game developer.
there were no programs about making games.
And so while I was making games,
people were studying games,
and they were writing about games,
and they were having conversations about games,
and so I would find myself going to GDC
and hanging out with the academic game developers.
And very energized by the conversations that I would be having with those people.
And then I would go back, and then I would be on to the next milestone.
And so going into academia, I got to read for the first time a lot of the stuff that was written years ago.
Some of Greg Kastikian's early stuff, you know, which is used heavily in academia.
And I finally got to read Raft's book, Theory of Fun.
And I finally got to read Homo Ludens.
I finally got to read all of this stuff that I had never had an opportunity to.
while you're working in these non-POL,
get your damn milestone stuff done positions.
So for me, I now have that time.
And I have time to re-read books that I love.
And I have time to explore questions.
And just, you know, frankly, ask ridiculous questions.
Like I had to consider the way that we,
the tactile nature of games.
Which I just, you have to make decisions and move on.
But to actually pause and think that
what used to be a tremendous,
and sometimes impossible luxury,
I can now explore the most minute game design topics
into the ground with a group of people
who are also interested.
And I like that shift in my life.
You know, building on something John said,
I'm really glad to hear that you're talking about all the stuff around games,
because as a hiring, I'm not hiring except faculty right now,
but when I hired people out of game development programs,
I don't want to say always, but eight times out of ten, I would encounter two problems.
One is, they had experience making their personal passion art project, which doesn't really
reflect what happens in the real world of mainstream game development, of AAA game development.
And they had no clue about anything but how do you make an art game.
And so one of the big things I'm trying to do with my program is exactly what you were talking about.
You know, focus not to the exclusion of everything else, but focus way more on culture, quality of life, business, you know, production methodologies.
The other problem that I encountered with people coming out of development programs is they so often think they know the right way to do something.
And they know one of the right ways.
And I really want to expose people not just to the right way according to me,
but in an academic setting I think there's an opportunity to show them
the various ways you can actually tackle the same problem.
If I might suggest you start with what is the definition of game?
Because there's about 90 right definitions.
Yeah, no doubt.
I had one thing on my mind to do with the similarities between being a game designer and a teacher.
I don't... we've sort of touched on it a little bit so far.
But I guess it's connected to the fact that I've always tried to be kind of a player-favoring game designer.
So I really like the idea of a game designer as an advocate for the player and for the player's experience.
And obviously, as designers, we're free to create any kind of experience for the player that we want,
from one that's cozy and warm and safe to one that's, like, punishingly difficult and, uh, um...
But, you know, the kind of games that I've worked on, my personal design philosophy is to do with kind of bringing the player into the experience,
and then bringing them along through the experience in a way that is best for them, if I can possibly work out how to do that with my game design.
So I guess, just before I started working at USC, I read a little bit of Bell Hooks.
Bell Hooks is an American educator and she talks about the way that in the classroom,
because of the sort of implicitly hierarchical nature of the classroom,
there's a possibility for oppression in there.
if the professor doesn't engage with the students in the right way,
if they don't draw the students out, if they don't kind of establish parity
in the community of the class. And so I don't know, I don't have a strongly
developed ideas
around this yet, but I think it's important for us as
new professors to think about this, because this is very much
part of the skill, the profession of people who have been
teachers for many decades, for all their professional lives.
Okay, I do have time for one, possibly two questions.
I saw Tracy's hand first,
and then I saw somebody over here.
I saw a hand over here.
Oh, it was that hand.
And when I say oppression, I just mean when we're working on critical...
working critically on creative projects, you know, that...
we've all heard about the horrible art crit,
where someone makes themselves vulnerable and then ends up crying.
I do think it's important that we're direct with each other
when we criticize each other.
I really like Eric Zimmerman's thing about the...
As game designers, the way we show each other respect
is by being direct with one another.
But it's a big, complicated subject
where there's lots for all of us to learn.
Okay, Tracy.
I'll repeat it if you, yeah.
OK, now, but I'll try and shout.
OK, I want to talk about industry expectations,
since you guys are coming from industry into academia.
Here's something I'm always fighting.
OK, so I also came from industry,
but maybe have been more on the side of academia for a while.
And what I'm always getting is the industry folks coming
and saying, you ought to do it like this.
You ought to be doing it like this, right?
And it's usually something like, hey, you know, in industry,
we have people.
We have 200 people teams.
So you guys got to have 200 people teams.
We got to get you some 200 people teams.
OK, let's work on that, right?
And I'm like, that's great, that's great, but guess what?
I don't know if they're ready to be on 200 people teams yet.
Maybe we should have teams of two,
and you could maybe learn to be on a team.
Because as above, so below.
They're little microcosms of the macroscopic bigotry.
How do we, though, negotiate what industry
wants us to be teaching and what we know
they're ready to be learning?
I think this is a really important sort of negotiation, because you don't want to say,
I don't want to teach that, because you do, but you want to teach the steps.
So I throw that to you because it's something I wonder all the time.
Do you mind? I'm sorry.
Warren and then Brenda.
Okay. I think you may be selling yourself a little short.
As someone who hired hundreds and hundreds of people over the last several years,
There was a point where having a degree, especially one in game design or development,
was like it was a knock. It was against you, you know, and that is no longer true.
At this point, I don't think I hired anybody in the last five years who didn't come out of,
you know, your program or one like it.
So, I think you may be selling yourself a little short and you're doing plenty right.
The one thing, I sort of alluded to it earlier, but I think there, and I think some places
like you guys are getting at it and you guys are getting at it, I think somewhat larger
teams are necessary and that's why in my program I'm...
A lot of people think I'm crazy, by the way,
but everybody in my program is going
to work on one big, in air quotes, game.
I mean, 20 people on a team is, I picked that number
because it's just big enough to start
seeing the communication and coordination problems
and planning problems and I don't like you problems
that you don't see on a team of four, six, or even eight
where, hey, we're all friends.
Let's work together.
So I don't think you need 200, but I
think you need somewhat bigger teams, which I know
you guys are doing already.
So you're right on track.
But I'm guessing that what Trace is suggesting is that just as game designers, when we're
designing a game for a player, it's not great to introduce too many verbs all at once. You
know, we want them to get the hang of the climbing before they do the dino jumping.
I think that's what Trace is alluding to. And so we sort of structure our teams to start
small and then grow to sort of 20-person teams. It just takes a bit of deliberateness about
it.
What we do in our program at UCSC is we focus on real small teams.
And we focus on developing like indie developers that can make an entire game themselves.
And teams right now, our teams are like three people, like three designer programmers with 20 artists.
So they have plenty of art.
So that is crazy.
That's cool.
They'll never see it again.
We work with San Jose State University, so they have access to an art team.
Like we tell them it's downhill from here.
Yeah, you're never going to see this quality and amount of art for a small team like that.
But as the program gets bigger, we probably won't have teams that are bigger than five
people, just so they all have really great experience.
They can't hide in a big team.
They have to make something that...
that uh... is innovative and they all have to have a really big part of that
of that uh... of that game so they so they can say yeah i made that huge thing
uh... and also the they can
they feel like they really made a whole game
To Tracy's point, it's almost like my previous week was a setup for that single question.
I began my week meeting with one massive publisher,
and I ended my week meeting with one massive publisher,
and I had first-party interaction in the middle.
And everybody knows exactly how things should be done.
And none of them are in agreement with one another.
And so it's really just a question of, well, I'll
align a Scott Faux.
I've credited him with this line.
But it's good to know.
It's very noncommittal.
Good to know.
I mean, ultimately, you can't make a game for everybody,
really, unless it's Minecraft.
So now it's done.
And, you know, likewise I don't think you can necessarily make students or have a program that's for everybody, you know.
So you have to, you know, what are you most skilled doing and then go from there.
But I, but I certainly, and I felt that pull just last week where there was.
I know, and you see what fits.
I'm afraid I won't have time for the second question because we are ending in 30 seconds.
Unless you can do it in 15 seconds, Stephen?
Yeah, so who are you shipping?
Who are you shipping?
John answered that a little bit and Brenda touched on it, but who are you shipping and
how do you build the program and what advice do you have for sales?
In 15 seconds?
Heck yeah!
In 15 seconds.
What's your product?
It's fine, I've been doing this forever.
My product is people who aspire to positions of leadership, production and direction,
and want to shorten the dues-paying period.
So instead of 10 years, it takes you 5.
Yeah, innovators, industry leaders, and craftspeople, I think.
Indie devs.
Or Indie devs. They own their own company, and they build small teams and great games.
Awesome. I also want to take a chance, my little plug chance here real quick at the end,
to make sure you all know that the third edition of Tracy Fullerton's Game Design Workshop came out this week.
It features sidebars from Richard and Brenda, a designer's perspective from Warren,
and there's a whole chapter analyzing Quake vis-a-vis Go Fish.
There are discounted copies available for GDC attendees, and I have...
tickets for them so right here at the end if you want one come up and grab one
from me
I'm in please can we have a huge round of applause for our panel they did a
fantastic job
and thank you all for coming out have a good GDC