My name is Jen-Marie Owens. I'm the head of operations for Phoenix Labs. We make a game called Dauntless.
I've been with the company since we founded back in 2014, having started my career about 15 years ago at BioWare and then moving to EA Canada after that.
I have been a nerd herder as long as I can remember, and along the way I also got to become a baby herder.
I have a nine and a half year old and a six year old, and Phoenix Labs is my middle child.
And so we wanted to come bring this group of folks together today to talk about the challenges of being mothers in the games industry when you are a minority within a minority.
So we've brought together four great panelists to talk to you today about their experiences.
I'll go through and introduce them first.
Then we'll go into our discussion questions, and then there will be time for Q&A at the end.
We were thinking we'll stop at about quarter to, so if you do have a question,
feel free to line up at that time, and we'd love to answer your questions.
So our first panelist is Latoya Peterson.
She is our newest panelist to Games.
Prior to that, where she is a co-founder of Glow Up Games.
She's the CXO there, and prior to that, she worked in news at places like ESPN and Al Jazeera.
She also has the youngest child on our panel with a six-month-old, and we're grateful that
she was able to join us despite that today.
She also has an eight-year-old.
Jenny Lee's made the longest trip to join us today from our panel, coming over from
Brighton, England, where she works at Boss Alien.
Oh, thanks.
Yep, I'm super pro.
She works at Fossilium where she leads engineering on Star Wars Hunters.
Prior to that, she was stateside in LA working at Riot Games and has one daughter who is about two years old.
Georgina is our Canadian panelist coming down from Vancouver like myself.
She started her career in games as a programmer and over the last decade has grown through many leadership roles.
Currently serves as the principal producer of core technology at Relic.
Which is what the slide says, if I change it.
And her kids are nine and twelve, and it gives us, the rest of us, a lot of hope that things
do actually get better along the way.
And lastly, Charlene Lescampe, who is the senior concept artist with me at Phoenix Labs,
and the reason that today's panel exists.
She had the bravery to stand up and say,
I think this is something that we should talk about more,
but I'm not sure what the right format is.
When she's not coming up with amazing GDC topics,
or drawing beautiful pictures,
she's keeping up with her two and four-year-old boys.
Before we continue, I just wanted to really acknowledge
that throughout this presentation, we are going
to use terms like motherhood, maternity leave, and woman,
because those are the lived experiences
that we are able to represent.
We understand that these issues affect a lot of groups
of people outside of women and people who identify as female,
and that a lot of single dads also struggle with some
of these types of industry issues.
But for us to speak of our lived experiences,
we want to use the words that are correct for us.
That is what you will hear us referring to.
There are a lot of groups that could benefit from some of the adaptations and improvements
that we're going to talk about today, and in general, most things in advocacy, when
we improve things for one group, we improve things for all groups.
So as context setting, I'll let each of the panelists give you a small summary
of what their maternity leave experience and return to work has been as we come from a lot
of different countries and experiences, and that context really affects the way
that our motherhood experiences have happened and the challenges that we've faced.
So we'll start with Charlotte.
So I had two maternity leaves.
The first one was in 2017, and my second one was right
at the beginning of the pandemic in 2020.
And so both of my maternity leaves lasted
Four months and a half, so being in the U.S., I was able
to accumulate some maternity leave from Blizzard
because I was at Blizzard at that time.
Maternity leave from California State,
short-term disability and long-term disability.
And so during my first maternity leave, my husband,
because of visa issues, was not allowed to work.
So basically, after I came back to work,
he stayed with my older one, which was incredibly helpful.
And for my second maternity leave, when I came back
to work, it was way more challenging
We were in summer 2020. We were right in the middle of the pandemic, so all the daycares
were closed. Everybody had to work from home. Plus, because California, there were fires everywhere.
We had absolutely no escape.
My husband had found a work at that time, so just picture that.
We were two parents working in the living room with two young kids,
with all the playgrounds closed, all the daycare closed,
and it was one of the most stressful years in my life.
Thankfully, now it's way better.
I'm working from home, but my kids are both at school and daycare, so now it's way more
balanced life for sure.
You may have developed the patience of a saint through that year.
Georgina, how about you?
Hi everyone.
Nice to see all of you here. It's wonderful that you've come in to see you in person.
So for my story, I started out in the games industry as a programmer.
I worked as a programmer, a lead programmer, and then a technical project manager when I had my daughter.
And I was at Radical Entertainment, which is an Activision studio at that time.
So when I had her...
I took a year off for maternity leave, so in Canada at the time, a year was the maximum
you could take.
It's actually 18 months now that you can take for maternity leave.
which is guaranteed by the government in terms of securing your job.
So I took a year off with her.
During my maternity leave, Activision actually laid off half of the studio.
My team was intact, so I wasn't laid off.
And then I came back to work on...
It was Prototype that I was working on before,
and I came back to work on a game called Prototype 2.
And about a year in, some gaming executives and people from Radical founded a visual effects
startup and I went to join them.
So I kind of left gaming into tech.
I had been thinking about leaving gaming for a while and some of those were personal reasons,
some of them were about just the conditions of the work environment that gaming has.
So I went and joined that VFX startup about a year later.
I had my son, also took a year off for maternity leave, went back.
I ended up spending eight years outside of games
and then joined games again
about two and a half years ago at Relic Entertainment.
Thanks. LaToya?
Cool. Before I start, so hi, I'm LaToya Peterson, co-founder of Globe Games.
Mitch Ukendake are my other fantastic founders right here.
I'd like to acknowledge the often invisible labor that allows us to come and do these
types of things.
So over in the corner in the yellow is Chiquita from Kitty Corp.
And so GDC actually provides childcare.
She's holding my seven-month-old son, Gabe.
And they are a part of this as well to allow us to be on stage frequently.
This is labor of women and frequently women of color.
So I just want to acknowledge that.
In terms of my maternity leave story, so the first son that I have, my son Gavin,
who's pictured here, who's eight, I was working in news, which is very 24 hours,
a lot of very high pressure environment.
And I had the standard American maternity leave, which is four months.
And there is no guaranteed maternity leave in America.
It's not a thing that in the United States, I should say.
It's not a thing that is mandated.
You normally get 12 unpaid weeks,
and that's all that you're mandated,
so that was fairly generous considering.
It's interesting when I hear my colleagues on the panel
be like, oh yeah, a year, two years.
Not a thing that can happen.
And at that time, my husband was lead parent,
and so he ended up leaving his job
and staying home with Gavin for the first three years,
which really allowed me to continue to excel in my career.
He was the one that took the caretaking penalty
so that I didn't have to.
This time around, things have been a little bit different.
My husband, having taken that caretaking penalty, was now at work and in a career that he enjoyed.
And so I did a lot more of the juggling this time around.
And we were also co-founding a studio at a very crucial point where we were about to launch and put our game into position for the first time.
So I'll talk about that a little bit more, but I ended up taking one month, and that was an informed choice that I made.
But it's definitely had ups and downs and some consequences.
And we'll talk about kind of like what are the realities facing,
particularly those of us who step out and try to do a startup,
and how that can go when you're trying to balance parenting and motherhood and,
or parenthood really, with all of these other things that you might want to do in your life.
Absolutely, thank you. And Jenny?
My maternity story is a little boring because I was at Riot and it's a large company, so
I was entitled to 18 fully paid weeks, no faffing with the state stuff, just all done
very easily through Riot.
And coming from England where the standard is at least six months and usually a year,
I shock people by saying I didn't take my full leave.
And the reason being, I was in LA and we got a daycare spot.
And when you get a daycare spot in LA, you take it.
So I went back to work early
and my husband took two months off as well.
So we had all this plan, like,
Trello board plan of who was gonna do what
and who's gonna take what leave.
All got cut short because we got a daycare spot.
So I ended up taking about, I think, 15 weeks.
Bright let you do a couple weeks part-time
to transition back.
And then pandemic hit and I ended up kind of using
the rest of my leave to do 50% work during the pandemic.
Thank you.
So while today is mostly about education and awareness about the challenges that mothers
can face in the games industry, we really hope that people can leave with practical
suggestions of improvements or adaptations that you as a parent or you as an ally or
you as a company could apply to supporting the mothers around you.
So for the first question that I really wanted the panel to go through, I'm wondering what
did you feel like was the biggest challenge that you have or are facing as a mother working
in games?
And we'll go to Latoya first.
Yeah, you know, the games industry doesn't have a lot of
acknowledgement of just that kind of a level of workload that
they're asking people to we talk a lot about crunch, we talk a
lot about all these different pieces of it. But when I came
from film, I came from television, there's a lot more
of a conversation around kind of things like core hours, where
you're not penalizing parents for not being able to make an
early morning meeting or a late evening meeting, because it's
conflicting with daycare, like those kinds of conversations
haven't seemed to quite happen yet in the games industry in the
way they have in TV and film.
Sharlene?
For me, one of the bigger challenges was definitely the lack of sleep.
Generally, like...
I would say before six months, it is rare that babies can sleep a whole night.
But because I was in the US, I was not able to take a six-month maternity leave.
And so basically when I came back to work, my babies were still waking up like two to
three, even sometimes four times per night.
And you still have to work eight hours per day.
What I did for my second maternity leave, and it was easier because working from home, was that
after lunch, for example, I would take a small nap, which was very helpful. And I wish
more companies would acknowledge that when you come back to work so early.
You don't have the same energy as after your baby is one year old, for example.
And it's totally fine because it's temporary. It's not going to last your whole career, right?
So I would love companies to acknowledge that and to let their young mothers coming back to work
being fine with, OK, you can take a nap after lunch and it's totally fine. And
maybe the very first month you're not going to work.
Exactly eight hours and it's totally fine.
As someone whose children did not sleep through the night until they were five years old,
I resonate with the lack of sleep comment.
We think maybe the six-year-old is going to start sleeping through the night soon.
Big hope on that one.
How about you, Georgina?
One of the challenges was childcare.
So I think for everybody, every new parent,
you know, what do you do with your young child,
regardless of their four months or a year or two years,
how do you do that?
In a lot of cities, it's expensive.
In Vancouver, it's very expensive.
Our solution, we were actually very fortunate
to have family help out.
So we pieced it together.
My husband took Sundays and Mondays off.
So I work Monday to Friday.
So he had Monday.
My mom helped with three days of the week and his parents helped with a day of the week.
So it sounds kind of like ideal, like wow, it's amazing.
But it's also challenging because they're not, like if you have a child care center,
it can actually be stable, right?
There's this person or this organization that's responsible for child care.
You know, grandparents can be flaky, right?
Like my mom took five weeks of holiday and so, like she went on vacation.
What do you do with your young child for five weeks?
How do you find temporary part-time child care?
in that situation. The grandparents also lived half an hour outside of the city
and we lived right by our workplaces. So
my husband would drive my daughter out to the grandparents
in the morning and then after work I would walk home
which was 10 minutes away and I'd drive out half an hour and have dinner with my
mom and
bathe her and put her in her pajamas and then drive home
and carefully transfer her from the car seat into the crib and hope she doesn't
wake up and
You do that for as long as it takes.
It's kind of crazy because you're like just on this crazy cycle of working all day,
running at the door.
You got all the time booked afterwards.
You figure it out, you collapse exhausted and then you do it again the next day.
So I think that's my child care story, which was, yeah, it was turbulent.
I think so many of those challenges in the moment you're just doing it.
It's just one foot after the other and then in reflection five years later you're like,
that was insane.
How did I do that?
How about you, Jenny?
We had the opposite problem in terms of we were, as many of us do, we moved to work at a studio
and we had no support system at all and we had to grow one organically by paying people money mostly.
But the thing I really want to talk about that I found challenging is the whole,
people don't talk about this enough I don't think, is actually getting to the
point where you have a baby is work.
Being pregnant is work. I couldn't take medication that I need that helps me actually function.
I had doctor's appointments all the time. I was high risk. And then I've had two miscarriages,
which is not something I tell my boss about because you don't necessarily want to be like,
hey boss, I'm going to procreate and bugger off for six months.
So like balancing these crazy unfair equations in your head of like,
do I tell work that I'm struggling with this thing?
Or will they see me differently? Will it hurt my promotion prospects?
And you know, I just turned 40, it took me a while to get around to the whole children thing,
so I'm very attached to my career and I'd like to keep it, thank you.
So I think, you know, looking at things like the overhead and emotional strain of trying
to get pregnant, having miscarriages, IVF, and then when you do finally get pregnant,
you're like, is everything okay?
And just that constant anxiety and extra load you're carrying around that, you know, your
partner's doing their best, but they're not living it every day the same way you are.
So if any folks in the room resonate with this, I've been there, happy to talk to you.
It can be easier than my journey, it can be harder than my journey, but it's not always Hollywood.
I will say that. And I found that just, I walked into that whole process not really knowing anybody
who'd been in my shoes and not having anyone to talk to, and having to build online support networks
through Reddit mostly to help me get through it all. And now I try and talk about it more
so people realise, yeah, I'm not the only person doing this, having this problem, having these experiences.
But it was very isolating at the time.
I remember being the only person at the company who was pregnant or had the only woman going
through that and having to leave meetings to go throw up in the bathroom and then coming
back and trying to be ready to go and on it and like not skip a beat but also just being
exhausted and your ankles hurt and pregnancy was exhausting and you didn't want to bring
it up around folks.
It was really, really challenging.
I super resonate with that.
Mat leave options can really vary though, depending on what city or what state you're
in and what your company offers or doesn't offer to top up or support you in that way.
And so I think that you're also balancing those decisions with where you happen to be
in a project's life cycle and what type of work you do and when might be the most optimal
time to disappear for mat leave or not.
I can't be the only person who is like...
tried to calculate back from a ship date.
OK, well, I need to be back two months in advance,
and so nine months before that, but then put in some weeks
for buffer in case baby comes early or late.
And when should I aim to get back at the right moment?
And then a project slips its ship date,
and all your math goes out the window anyways.
So one of the things that is challenging
is that, as we've heard, it's not necessarily common.
for women to be going on maternity leave or going through these moments in their companies.
And so one of the things that we're hoping is what can companies do
and what can non-parent allies do to help normalize the idea of maternity leave
to make those transitions feel smoother or more organic as a part of the company
instead of these weird, carefully planned, and highly controversial moments.
Georgina, to you.
I think you may have heard reports of countries that have more paternity leave.
So I want to talk about paternity leave.
When I think about the Scandinavian countries, I think it's quite accepted that men take longer paternity leaves
and there's a lot of benefits for...
for women in the workforce by men taking paternity leave, as well as for the families and for the community at large.
In Canada, we do support paternity leave, like there's government support for it,
but typically, in my experience, men in the game dev industry who have taken PAT leave take about a month of time off to be with their child.
So I wanted to share this story with you of the technical director at Relic.
He's the technical director on the Age of Empires 4 game.
So we shipped that game last year.
I don't know if any of you know it.
It's a real-time strategy game, massive game.
Shipped really well.
The team did a fantastic job with it.
So two years before the ship date, the technical director's wife was pregnant,
and they decided that he was going to take six months of paternity leave.
So she was going to take the first six months off to be with the baby,
and then he was going to take the latter six months and be in the full-time child care
while she went back to work.
So they went and did that, and in hindsight now, there were successes from his story.
So for himself, he was actually surprised that he needed a mental break after working on this
game, which was five years in development, very intense back-to-back development.
And for him to take six months off actually gave him time to just have something different to think about.
So that was a real personal wellness benefit for him.
And he also got to spend a significant amount of time with his baby.
There's nothing quite like...
being the primary caregiver of a tiny little person that changes you.
And so that was something very special for him to do.
For his wife, obviously she got to go back to work six months earlier and continue her career.
So for his family, it was great.
For the Age of Empires team,
What they needed to do was create a transition plan.
So they knew he was going to be taking six months off.
It was stressful for the team, but they looked at who would take on the responsibilities.
He has a big job.
That work was spread around, and an acting TD was selected to cover
for him while he was on his paternity leave.
So that acting TD got an opportunity to step up, to shine.
He had a huge impact on the game, and it furthered his career.
He got a promotion out of it.
So it opened up an opportunity.
for a new role.
And then for Relic, now we have a senior leader that's come back to work with a new perspective,
with a deep understanding of what it's like to be a parent, a new parent.
And he brings that to his team and the organization.
He sets an example for future dads who want to take a longer paternity leave, or what
it can look like, what good looks like for taking a leave.
And then he also normalizes maternity leave, because now women, you know, here's a man
as well, but now women taking a longer leave.
to look after their child and then returning to work is more normative within the company.
So it's, I think, a really great story that he was happy for me to share with all of you.
Yeah, it's really interesting, Kanija, that we have the opportunity for men to take covered
paternity leave, but it is really uncommon that it happens.
And the more often that we can get the idea of leave as a part of our ecosystem, the less
challenging it is for someone to put up their hand and say, like,
Hey, it's my turn and I need to go through.
We have a system.
We understand how to build a transition plan.
We understand how to bring people into a project and transition them out later.
We understand how the benefits work.
Every time a company is able to practice those skills,
it gets easier for the next person
who's going through that experience.
Being the first is always the hardest
to go through a system
and your company's building it with you.
And I think it's really important,
you mentioned that he brings that new perspective
back to the team.
You know, we talk a lot in the games industry,
I think, about people bringing their whole self to work
and being able to be themselves in their spaces,
but we tend to think of that more as like,
It's okay for you to have different hobbies, and having multicolored hair is positive,
right?
But we don't necessarily think of it as like talking about your kids at work is part of
bringing your whole self to the office.
And we've, throughout my career, one of the things that I've tried to normalize is discussing
my children actively.
In regards to my work day, and in regards to the work I do, and encouraging other people to talk about their kids as well.
So that the idea that we are parents in addition to game developers is just part of our regular discourse,
instead of this weird thing that we kind of try to pretend isn't distracting us.
Or isn't taking up any time.
And, you know, I'm on top of it.
I can do everything 100%.
Like kids are a drain on our emotional energy,
our mental energy, our sleep patterns.
And the more that we can make that a part of the conversation,
I think that we can normalize the idea
of multifaceted humans in the workplace.
But I think that regardless of how much time somebody ends
up taking off, most of us end up having
to do that transition back from.
I'm at home full time as a primary caregiver, not thinking about game development,
getting a new perspective to I'm working eight hours a day and I'm balancing childcare needs
and I'm trying to figure out what to do on sick days and Pro-D days and the summer break
and the spring break and the Christmas break.
And that transitional period can be really challenging.
And I'm wondering, Charlene, what did you do or do you wish that you had done
to better prep yourself for that change?
I think I was able to get a good preparation about that.
Like for my first maternity leave, what I made is that I actively discussed, once I
said to my leads that, OK, I'm pregnant and so on.
In a few months, I'm going to give birth,
and my maternity leave is going to last that amount of time.
Right after that, we started to discuss
about getting a more flexible schedule.
And so basically, when I was on Hearthstone at Blizzard,
we were lucky to have very good management and leadership.
And so when I came back to work in 2008,
18. I was working from 7am to 4pm. So basically I was the only one with our art director at 7am
because he was an early bird too. While most of the team, most of the Hurston team was arriving
at work around...
10 a.m., something like that.
And so I had also
pumped a bunch of milk
when I was
still at home during the maternity leave
because for me breastfeeding was very
important. And in addition to
that, there was a pumping room
at Blizzard in each building, I
think.
So when I came back to work, I was sure that I would have some milk in advance.
So if I was too stressed, you know, to pump at work, I still would have one week, you know, of milk already ready.
And thanks to that pumping room, then I was able to breastfeed my older one until two years old.
So that was very helpful.
Like that's an advice I would give to future mothers or wannabe mothers.
Try to discuss about that with your management and your leadership
because preparing that in advance, having time and like the flexible schedule
is definitely going to be very helpful for you.
I was so happy, like I was just a half hour working from work
and so being able to see your kids that...
4.30 and not just for the bedtime was so amazing.
I did that eight to four shift for a long time for the same reason.
You mentioned this idea of flexible schedules and I think that it's a statement that is very,
very clear now that COVID has had a huge effect on working configurations and how we think about work
and the division of where we spend our time that is different than several years ago when we were
maybe going through that with our children the first time.
At a holistic like project level, I would say that making games
with everyone fully remotely is still a lot more difficult than making them in person.
You know, most games have ended up shipping slip dates over the last two years.
It's been really challenging on a lot of fronts for a lot of people on project levels.
But at individual levels, there are a lot of individuals who have thrived working from home
more than they did working in an office space.
And I think for a lot of parents, it's been more of a mixed bag of blessings and curses
over the last two and a half years.
For myself, working at home with kids was very challenging because regardless of whether
another parent was already in the space, they expected me to be the primary parent.
And spending eight hours a day on Zoom meant that was either I was not paying attention
to my meetings or I was not paying attention to my kids, but everybody was feeling...
Disappointed with the amount of focus that they were getting.
And it wasn't like I could just push that time into the evenings or the weekends
because it was all time that had to be overlapping with other humans.
So for me, being able to return to the office was a huge mental health improvement.
And my kids.
We're a lot happier because the primary parent was focused on them.
They had caregiving that was not distracted by Slack or Zoom or so on.
But it's really varied for people what that experience has been like.
And so I put to the whole panel, like, what have those pros
and cons been for you in working at home through COVID?
Jenny.
I relocated countries during COVID, so it's been, it was definitely an interesting experience.
I think, you know, coming back from maternity leave right before the pandemic, about six
months before I guess, and then having to ship a game during COVID from home while everyone
was still figuring everything out.
with all daycare shut was stressful, but I think I've got to a really good steady state now.
And it's a double-edged sword, flexibility. We're all going to say the word flexibility a lot in this panel.
But for me being able to deal with some of these curveballs that life throws you, like,
hey, my daughter's nursery school right now is understaffed. Teachers can't come in because they're sick.
They're asking us to keep our kids home.
OK, I don't have anywhere else to put the kids.
So, well, the kid.
So what do I do?
Well, actually, my husband and I can look at our schedules.
We can say, OK, I'll take this meeting.
You take that meeting.
And we can be really flexible.
And we have very understanding teams that are like, OK, you know, as long as you get
your work done, we're not going to police you.
We also have a lot of good paid time off and sick leave in the UK, too.
So I think, you know, being able to say, OK, I'm going to...
I have to focus on one thing.
I don't do the thing where my daughter's working next to me.
That doesn't work for me.
My office is in a separate space from my house, so I don't walk to the bathroom
and see the laundry and go, oh gosh, I've got to do that.
I've got to clean the kitchen.
And all these things that just pile up every day from being at home.
But having got to the steady state where, you know,
I can deal with those emergencies, I don't have to commute.
I don't have to make a choice.
It should my daughter's school be near my workplace or near my home.
And what do we do if you're in the wrong place on the wrong day?
And just all that overhead is gone.
And I really appreciate just having that real flexibility to design my life with my daughter
the way I want.
And I definitely think we've learned a lot and made a lot of improvements during the
pandemic.
But it was very different when you had an 18-month-old baby and a job and nowhere to
put the baby.
So those days are gone for now, thank goodness.
You're stressed.
How about you, Latoya?
Yeah, I mean, so there are upsides and downsides.
So working at home during COVID, one of the great things that was about it was that at
some point you got to really understand what your kids are doing during the day and who
they are and how they interact, especially when everybody was on Zoom.
At one point, Gavin and I were coworkers.
And it was just much easier to give him like a little desk in my office and he decorated
with Pokemon and had all the stuff together for us to be like just kind of next to each
other working.
And you know, over time, we kind of worked out the rhythm.
So I think that was the best era of what was happening.
But there's also the flip side to it, which is like, you know, you're normally like managing
all these different things and different expectations and trading some time for another.
So like I think at one point, Anongo, who is one of the principals at the studio as
well, Anongo had looked at my calendar when Mitu and I were going through Tech Stars because
we did it remote.
And Gavin was full-time school from home,
because again, we're still early in the pandemic,
and everybody's like, well, just a few more weeks.
Like, it's not gonna be that bad.
Two weeks to flatten the curve.
And then I was like, oh, just six more weeks.
Okay, no.
So we were still in that like semi-optimistic era
that this was gonna end at some point.
And at one point, Anongo looked at my calendar
and she was like, that's not humanly possible.
Like, she was like, it's just all conflicts.
It's just all just different blocks of people's conflicts.
And I was like, yeah, that's how my life feels right now.
So it was, yeah, it's definitely a challenge
because there isn't that division.
And you know that Jen was talking about earlier,
there's not that division between like,
okay, here is when I am working
and here is when I'm at home.
Everything is kind of crashing together all the time
and you're just trying to carve out a buffer for deep work.
I feel like as a writer,
I haven't had headspace in two years
to be able to like deeply sit down
and do anything without something pulling at my attention.
But on the flip side, I also don't have a commute anymore.
We're not at risk in the same way
of like going out into the world every single day.
So, you know, there's...
Plus sides and downsides.
I know when my son went back to school after COVID,
I found in some ways I kind of missed it
because at least I knew like where he was
and that he was safe.
And then like the post COVID world is very, very different
than I think the environment that we started in.
And so really negotiating that has been
almost more stressful than keeping him at home with me,
even though there were definitely rough days.
Definitely trade-offs. I like that you mentioned the idea of competing conflicts all the time.
Oh yeah, oh god.
Because I feel like as a parent there is no concept of free time left.
There's just choosing which thing you aren't going to do in what order
and trying to decide what goes to the bottom of your Moscow list and what goes to the top
and just balancing all of the needs and conflicts.
There have been quite a few times my husband has found me passed out
and I have the laptop open on the bed somewhere.
where I was like, I can just do this one more.
That's so exciting.
Charlene, how about for you?
For me, I would say definitely has been more challenging
than having kids outside.
Like, I love working from home,
but it's way easier to have them in daycare,
especially in the afternoon.
Like, you need a time to focus on.
And so when you have two young kids screaming behind you,
During some meetings, that's definitely challenging.
But some things that I really enjoyed,
even though 2020 was an apocalyptic year for me,
was that it definitely made breastfeeding easier,
because being in the same room as my younger one
was definitely easier.
But I hope this won't happen too often.
Hopefully.
I hope this is the last year like that.
So say we all. Georgina?
Mine's a little bit different because my kids are older, so at 9 and 12,
they're obviously much more self-sufficient.
So the first year, you know, we're all transitioning and it's COVID and they stayed at home for five months,
homeschooling, challenging.
But I would say overall, there's just been a net benefit.
I live over an hour's commute, hour and 15 minute commute from the office.
And so that means working from home, I get 12 hours back in a week,
which is an incredible amount of time.
It means I'm having dinner with my family every night.
And I've always worked outside of the home,
so this has been a very different experience for me.
And with my children the age they are,
it's been fantastic to be together a lot more.
And, yeah, and so...
At this age, I would say there are a lot more pros than cons.
I like that you mentioned the commute.
I think that your relationship to your commute as a parent really changes depending on how
long it is.
For you, an hour commute is a huge amount of time lost from seeing your family and getting
out to dinner with them.
I'm really fortunate to have a 15-minute commute.
And I love my commute. It's the greatest 30 minutes of my day. It's silent. There's no one.
I just get to sit alone in a bubble. And sometimes I have a cup of coffee. No one can talk to me.
I can't get a Slack notification. There's no... It's just this absolute peace for 15 minutes.
And I never appreciated that pre-pandemic commutes were like...
I'm rushing to drop off at daycare, and then school, and then this, and then that.
And it wasn't until I had worked from home and returned to commuting that I began to
appreciate those 15 minutes a day for what they were.
We mentioned a little bit earlier this idea of juggling multiple priorities, and I'm sure
lots of folks have heard this joke that comes across.
Joke.
That, you know, if you want something done, give it to a mother.
There's this idea that we have this, we have a superhuman ability to juggle priorities
that other people don't, and mothers will figure it out if you give it to them to solve.
And I think there's some truth in that and maybe some not, so I'm curious, Jenny, do
you feel like becoming a parent has made you better at your job in any ways?
I think so. I think there's a lot of things that change when you become a parent.
And for me, one of them was just setting a lot stronger boundaries around my work
and saying, I am going, I have to get off work and go pick up my kid.
I have, like, I, for me, one of my strong boundaries is I do family dinner, I do bedtime.
And if someone schedules a meeting during that time, I'm like, nope.
And it's taken some training to make sure that doesn't happen,
especially because I work a lot with the US and they're awake and working.
But getting to that point where you're like, no, I've got that boundary.
I prioritize ruthlessly.
And I think this goes for all parents.
Like we've all had to learn this new job very quickly and it changes every day.
And just when you think you figured it out,
your kid grows up a little bit older and learns a new skill.
And you're like, oh, how do I deal with this?
And just that whole confidence that I can figure things out and I've got it.
But I will say I'm in a lead role in engineering and so my job is pastoral, I look after people,
I grow their careers, I solve lots of crazy crisis problems every day and I have a lot
of flexibility and do a lot of meetings. Back in previously in my career when I was
writing code all day I would struggle with the current boundaries I have.
Because I can just see myself getting to 4.45 PM and I'm deep in the middle of some crazy bug,
and I'm looking at the clock and I've got to go pick up my kids.
And I know I haven't personally had to deal with that because I
chose to have kids when I was a little more further in my career, but I can see that that
would have been very difficult for me at that point in my career, and so figuring out how do you...
make that trade-off and how do you set those boundaries and keep them is hard.
But I have this advantage that as a leader I can set them, I can talk about them, I can openly
stick to them and hopefully it will help those folks who are a little further,
a little earlier in their careers also keep the same boundaries. So hopefully modeling it helps.
When you mentioned dealing with crises, I think of both the best and worst parenting advice that
I have ever received was somebody telling me that it won't get better.
but it will get different.
And at the time, I was deeply depressed
when they told me that.
And over time, I've actually become to take that
as an extremely positive mantra that like,
in this moment, it may feel awful and endless,
and it will change.
It might be a different awful and endless,
but it will change and it will be a new problem to deal with
and I can just keep putting one foot in front of the other
and we will eventually come through that.
Again, Georgina tells us that it gets better, we hear.
We're very excited for this.
And I think that we've talked about
a couple different specific companies
that have had good policies or bad policies,
but even if you happen to find a company
that really treats maternity and paternity leave
as a regular part of that employee life cycle
and...
You're fortunate enough to get to work in that space.
The games industry as a whole tends to have a lot of turnover and a lot of movement and
a lot of going from one studio and one project to the next, to the next, to the next.
And so you might not get to stay with that group of people for the long term.
And I think that we don't necessarily think about the domino downstream effects that that
can have on mothers to need to be able to move between products.
projects and studios on a regular basis.
And Charlene, I was hoping you might talk to some of those challenges that you saw for
you in that cycle of having kids.
If you ask me, I would have had kids sooner.
I feel like you don't have the same energy, the same health at 35 than at 25.
And when I was 25, I was ready to have kids.
I wish I had them at that time, but I was...
I was so scared about the stigma, you know, to have the plan to have kids in my company
because especially at the very beginning of your career, like on an average, you're going
to stay two, three years.
And so after one year of experience in a company, you're like, oh.
But if I have to tell my boss that I'm pregnant,
sure, they probably won't fire me because there are
laws about that, but there's still going to be stigma
and it's going to have an impact on my career and stuff like that.
I really wish we were able to have kids when we feel ready, rather than when we feel our
company is ready.
The point of view of your employer shouldn't have an impact on your desire to have kids
or not.
I wish companies were more able to help mother and future parents, actually, even for men
in that way.
Also, something that I feel like is not totally fair,
and might be part of the reason why women
are still less paid than men,
is that a lot of benefits are based
on the time you spend at work.
Profit sharings and career revolutions, that kind of stuff.
The reason why you have less,
you have like for higher management, you have less women.
I don't think it's, I want to believe it's not
because companies are thinking, oh, she's a woman,
so she's not gonna have, she's not gonna be a lead
or a director or stuff like that.
I don't think it is because of that.
I feel.
I think it's more because when you take a maternity leave,
then all these benefits are slowed down, unfortunately.
And I wish we would rethink that way.
Like, we would rethink things about that,
like career improvement benefits, all this stuff.
Maybe it is outdated to think that it should be linked
about the time you spend at work.
Yeah, that caregiving tax that Latoya referred to, you know, it applies not just to maybe
how your salary grows, how your vacation accrues, how bonuses or profit sharing pay out, but
it also affects the type of work that you got to do on a project.
If you weren't there during SHIP, you might not get credited on the project, depending
on your company's credit policies.
You might not also just get the experience of having gone through a SHIP.
that you can then take to your next project.
So you may be seen as not as capable
because you've missed certain parts of a project
and that can affect your career growth opportunities,
promotion opportunities, and there's this downstream fall-on
from choosing to take time off to have kids.
And I think that that's one of the things that is hardest to solve
because it is the most invisible pieces of the problem.
And so, Latoya, one of the reasons that I was so excited to have you come on this panel
is that you are a founder at a company, which is a unique space to take in the world.
And from your intro, we heard that you talked about taking that a very short leave with
your second.
That resonates a ton with me.
I did the exact same thing with my second child.
We were a startup.
It was limited dollars in the bank account, limited amount of time available to us.
So I made the same choice you did.
It resonates a ton with me.
But you and I have both discussed that's not.
We're really conscious that that's not the example that we want to set for the teammates
who work with us and the women who come after us.
And I wonder how you think about balancing that need to bulldoze a path ahead for people
while teaching them and setting healthy precedents for them to walk the path that didn't necessarily
use the same patterns that we did.
Yeah, absolutely.
I mean, one of the hardest parts, so, you know, Matu and I co-founded the first all-women-of-color
game studio.
So, I think that's a huge accomplishment.
There's a lot that comes with that, including not getting the level of funding that, say,
white founders who are in similar, quite frankly, sometimes worse positions with less chops
than we had, not being able to have that type of financial buffer that allows you to give
generous leave, generous packages, generous comp.
And in the interest of also just being transparent about the things that happen, at the beginning,
at the founding of the company, I also had a miscarriage on the way to a funders meeting.
And it was so bad that Mitsu actually came to the hospital with me, bringing clothes
and stuff like that.
And we had to.
And so we're going to have to dust off and pick up and keep going the next day. So we've really sacrificed a lot to make glow up what it is. And one of the things that we're always conscious of is that we are pushing ourselves to the limits as founders, because we know like there's no one ahead of us that we have to blaze this trail and keep this thing that we built going and keep it alive.
And so, when I said I made an informed choice to cut my
Maternity short, I knew what was going to happen.
I knew that maybe my milk supply wouldn't come in in the same way.
I knew that, you know, I was going to be cutting time with, you know, the newborn.
I knew these things were going to happen.
I also knew that.
We had come so far and we were at this crucial point
we needed to ship and we just had to figure this out.
But you don't want to show that to your younger employees
or to folks coming up because you don't want them to think
that that's what it's gonna take or that it's normal.
And it's been really difficult,
particularly because the values that we wanna live
and the experiences that we have
or that we want to give people more.
And then financially, you can't always.
So like one of the big things that we do at the company
is mental health days.
Like we can gift you some time.
And especially when things get very heavy in the world, sometimes we'll just be like,
OK, we're going to shut down the studio two weeks from now for a day so we can all just
kind of recover.
And that's a thing that we can do that doesn't take huge financial resources.
But we're also trying to always be cognizant of it, like just the fact that, you know,
as founders, Mitu and I are on 24-7.
Just doing stuff like I'm rolling meetings and changing diapers and running down the street and trying to make all of this stuff work because we're in the middle of so many things.
But, you know, we have a pregnant employee right now and, you know, we're struggling because, again, there's not that structural support in the United States.
for just about anything, anything at all.
But particularly for parents in the workforce
where it's like, oh, well, this employee is a contractor
because we couldn't make her W-2.
Is she even eligible for short-term disability insurance?
Are we going to tell her that, okay,
we will give you the four months off,
but it has to be unpaid
because we don't know if we have these funds?
Is it, how can we help you?
And there are certain things that, you know,
we just can't even do
because of the structure of the system.
that we're working in.
So I think it's a mandate on our side
to make sure that we are,
as much as we need to push and innovate in the game space
and do things we wanna do,
also being there to innovate on the side of,
these are the things that need to change
because we want to show that we can have
a healthy environment for people who wanna have families
and that we have a healthy environment
for all of our employees overall.
But it's a difficult balancing act
and there's sometimes we do have to kind of explicitly be
like, okay, do as I say and not as I do.
We're gonna send you home.
We're gonna keep working.
We don't want you to do that
because we already paid this price for you.
I think a lot of parenting is also do what I say,
not what I do.
Especially when it comes to snacks after bedtime.
It was serious.
In, you know, in just in putting together this panel
and finding folks to come talk about the issue,
it really highlighted the reason
we were talking about the issue.
It was very challenging for me to find women
that I knew who worked in games
who didn't work at my company.
You know, Georgina and Latoya were both introduced to me by somebody else.
Jenny and I connected through a Discord channel for moms who work in the gaming industry,
and it was completely random.
We never met until yesterday.
We just, through Discord, decided she was going to fly here to do this.
And then as moms organizing to come here in person, making sure that there was childcare
and groceries and the kids were going to be fed for and the caregiving was in place, was
a whole set of.
Travel prep that, you know, a lot of our coworkers didn't have to do to be able to come here.
And still checking up on our families when we get home.
You know, every part of preparing for this was a reminder of why this was happening.
And I think it can often feel very lonely to be that first in the situation going through
a process or to be in a minority on your team.
And it feels like it's a lot harder to advocate for your needs when you're the only one who
has those needs at that given time.
And so Georgina, our last question and then we'll move to Q&A after that.
You know, you're a woman programmer, you're a person of color, you're a mom.
You have lived this life of being a minority and in so many different ways.
You're 20 years into your career now.
I wonder when you look back what you would tell your younger self
about about the journey that you've gone on.
I started my first job as a programmer was at Electronic Arts Canada.
There were two female programmers, I was one of it, out of hundreds of men.
So, I was often the only woman in a room, I'm very used to that.
So that certainly shaped me in my career and just being used to being, okay, I'm in the
minority, I don't have examples that are exactly like me, and you know, you just pull up your
boots and you keep going and you work hard.
You don't often want to call attention to yourself.
I think early on in my career as a programmer, I really was conscious of the fact that
I never wanted anyone to think that I was hired as a programmer because I was female.
And, you know, everybody wants to hire a female programmer because you want to have some diversity in your group.
But I never wanted to be that token. I wanted people to recognize I was there because I was just as good.
And I was just as good and I worked just as hard, if not more, to be there.
So certainly that carried over, you know, as a mom.
At Radical, I wasn't, I probably wasn't the first to take maternity leave,
but I was one of the first.
There weren't a lot of women that took mat leave.
When I was in the VFX company, it was a startup.
I was the first, I was the only one who took mat leave from that company.
They crafted a mat leave policy for me.
And I think when you're in that position, you know, I had that feeling of like,
I didn't want to be entitled.
I didn't want to ask for things, you know, that my colleagues didn't have,
the other programmers or managers around me.
They didn't ask for flexible working time.
They didn't ask for these things.
And I didn't feel like that I should ask for those things.
Because that would have only benefited me.
So now, 20 years into my career, I've kind of got some perspective.
What I want to say, you know, companies and games,
they want to retain every single woman who is listening to this talk today.
So if you're out there and you're thinking about it.
Your company wants to retain you.
They may not have policies that seem friendly.
You may be thinking about leaving,
but it's in the company's best interest
for you to stay and grow your career.
And so, you know, if there is something
that would make your life easier,
that would make it possible for you to stay,
that is a consideration that you should make
and talk to your manager.
Sometimes it's difficult.
Your manager may not be receptive,
may not be someone that you can talk to.
And so my suggestion would be to find an ally in the company,
whether that's a senior person, a person that you feel could relate to you,
whether that's a person on your team, on another team, another manager,
someone in HR, or whether it's a man or a woman, someone who can be an ally.
Because it's often easier to ask for something for somebody else.
I have a hard time asking for things, special things for myself,
but no problem going, hey, so-and-so, you know, this is their situation.
And I think we should consider this.
you know, set up for them.
Yeah, absolutely. And I think that if you have a, if you are in a position in a company where you have the ability to radiate these things, you know, making sure that it's really easy for people to find out what your benefits plans are and what your maternity coverage is and the information about where you can breastfeed is publicly available, that women don't have to go search for it. They may be early in their pregnancy and not ready to talk about that, but they can still find the information on your internal confluence or whatever.
That lets them plan and understand what's going on.
Don't force people to come to you for that information.
Radiate it outwards.
Make it normal to talk about those things to the whole team
because you never know who will eventually need
that information.
And so just having it be publicly available
at all times can be really helpful for those
who are still learning how to advocate
for their own needs, I think.
So we've got about five or 10 minutes left, I think.
And if anyone wanted to ask any questions,
we're happy to answer them.
And I think we're going to go to the wrap-up area after.
If you wanted to talk to us more,
we'll go to the wrap-up area on the third floor.
Gaze up.
I'm going to grab them.
I'm a little short, so.
Hi, my name is Desiree.
Thank you all so much for being here.
Latoya, I just wanted to say I brought a seventh month old to my first UDC five years ago,
and I was constantly running back and forth to nurse, so I see you.
Me, too, was actually my academic advisor at NYU when I had my second baby,
and I was like waddling into her office to discuss how I was going to handle my schedule when I came back from having the baby.
Anyway.
Something that I've noticed in the conversation about remote work is that before the pandemic,
I could not get positions anywhere because they wanted me to move to Barcelona, to Boulder, to
wherever it was, Seattle, California. And it kind of broke my heart to see the people who
were accepting these roles were often single, young, white men who could afford to uproot their
lives.
And they didn't have, you know, children that they were going to have to haul out of school or anything else. And I think that kind of gets lost in the conversation about remote when you have all these studios complaining that they're having a hard time finding people for mid-level or senior roles.
But they're only willing to consider people who are local or people who can move, who,
let's face it, are often either single or men who have wives who are willing to move
with them.
So I guess my question is, after saying all of that, moving forward now that we've seen
that it's possible to ship titles with hybrid and remote work, how can we sort of advocate
for more flexibility that will enable women to not only
And so, I think it's important for women to enter the game
industry and stay in the game industry after they have kids
to thrive.
And, yeah.
Yeah, I think to your question of like how can we advocate for
the ability for folks to work remotely in this post-pandemic
world, since that does often benefit women more,
one of the ways we do it is by talking about it like this.
And by bringing it into our hiring conversations,
our HR folks, and really.
Consistently bringing the topic up and discussing.
It's not, I don't want to work remote because I hate pants.
I want to work remote so that I have the ability
for my child to stay in the same school system.
So that I can pick my kid up from daycare
because I live really far from the studio.
And really going into the reasons why that benefits people,
the types of people it benefits, to your point,
the groups of people who are maybe looking
for that more than others.
And just continuing to just advocate for it and shine that light on the problem set, I think.
Very cute, by the way.
So I have four boys.
And right now I'm basically the stay-at-home, work-at-home parent.
My wife has a 50, 60-hour-a-week job that she works.
So I cook, clean, play, my oldest is homeschooled, he's 13, and in the games industry it's very
competitive to get into it with everybody who, you know, is also very talented as well.
There becomes a problem where if I don't have enough time to compete with somebody who has
all the time in social life.
It isn't trying to type while playing tug of war with something in your teeth with the baby at the same time.
The only thing that I've been able to come up with to sort of let people know that I've basically decided to start life on hard mode
is just put in my LinkedIn, I've been a dad for 13 years. I struggle with that.
What else can you do to sort of portray that this is something that you also have to contend with to sort of give yourself?
that a boost, like perhaps I don't have enough time to have a massive body of work, but I
work just as hard, essentially.
Yeah, so just to repeat the question in case folks didn't hear it, the idea is like, how
can we as parents make ourselves appealing to hiring managers and in the interview process
when we may not have the same amount of disposable time to spend on building a portfolio of work?
No, all good.
I have a slightly privilege laden answer there.
In engineering, you know, if I were to change jobs and try and do coding
properly, I'd have to spend months preparing algorithm questions.
And it's the same kind of work as I get my portfolio together.
It's a full-time job to prepare for a software engineering job these days.
And so for me, I would do the acid test of like, during the interview process, be like,
hey, I'm a mom. I don't have time for that. Do you have a different interview process?
Have you caught on? It's 2022. And if they say no, I'm like, well, you're probably not going
to support me very well as a parent if I do come and work for you. Now, I do think that answer is
a lot of privilege because I'm a bit more senior and I'm engineering where a lot of people are
starting to change that conversation. But the more that we can, within our companies and have
the parents within those companies advocate for changing the hiring process to be inclusive.
To have alternate paths for those that might not have a bunch of time and to recognize all
the different things that those people can bring to the table, I think we can change,
but it's not an overnight thing. So those of us in the room that have that privilege are inside
companies and can change the processes. Let's start doing that and making things, we change
it for mothers, we change it for fathers, we change it for everybody.
I just want to add quickly, like, you know, just definitely my husband was lead parent for three years. So understand like how that can be very tough trying to reintegrate or to go back to the workforce and one of the things that I think works best is that networking and proactively kind of trying to reach out.
Because you're not going to be able to spend the hours in the portfolio that you used to.
You're not going to be able to spend the hours of building new work and doing all the stuff that you need.
You want to tell me about it?
But one of the things that you can do is definitely figuring out if there are other folks, particularly like prominent folks who talk about having their families in the media, connecting with them, talking to them.
Because they'll normally also know like, oh, here might be a path to a company that is more flexible and is looking for somebody with your skills.
And that's easier than us trying to like just do it in isolation, because you can't compete in the same way anymore.
And if you try to do that, you will just drive yourself insane.
Yeah, well, I'm there.
But best of luck.
First and foremost, LaToya, I want to snuggle that baby.
I got to snuggle him last night. He's very snugglable.
One of the things that we touched briefly on, LaToya touched briefly on, was mental health days.
And one of the things that we haven't touched on is the fact that mental health changes dramatically for mothers.
What I'd like to hear is how would you guys recommend us, especially me, I'm brand new to the industry.
I just changed a 10 year career over to my dream career, right?
Just landed my dream job on a triple A title.
I'm super excited.
How do we advocate for ourselves when we have mental health days or we need mental health days?
Because postpartum depression is a real thing.
Even mental health, especially for our fathers.
I want our fathers to feel very heard because I've seen so many struggle.
Like we struggle as parents.
How do we advocate for ourselves as parents to say, I need a break, I'm having a really
hard day, that kind of stuff?
So for me, I think the only way to do that is to continue to do it.
And I know that sounds like an extremely simplistic and naive answer, but I do believe that in
so much of advocacy work, it is the...
persistence of conversation and the willingness to say it over and over and build a
coalition of people who are saying it and bring the attention to an issue. It is
challenging for companies to hear one person's
challenge sometimes and it is also difficult for them to
to put the corporate responsibility towards solving a problem for one person,
whereas it is a lot easier for them to do it towards solving for a group of people.
And so if it is a topic that comes up regularly, if it is a group of people who bring a topic regularly,
In the fiscal responsibility of a business,
it becomes a lot easier to then put resources
towards it and respond to it.
And so I think that sometimes in these issues,
it is just the simple persistence of continuing
to have those conversations, to bring them to the light.
And then for those who are listening today,
who are part of companies, to hear your voice saying that,
and take it back to their companies.
And like, I keep hearing people mention this,
maybe it's something that we should look into.
Maybe it's something that we need to look
at our benefits package, our vacation time,
our sick policy.
And the more that we can spread that voice through, I think, the more of a chance we
have of bringing the situations to the forefront.
Thank you for this panel.
Yes, thanks.
So thank you everyone for joining us today.
I really appreciate that you all took your time to come and hear us talk.
We'll go upstairs if you wanted to chat any further up in the wrap-up area.
And I'm always happy to connect with folks to talk more about this issue,
as I'm sure other folks here are outside of GDC as well.
So please stay in touch.
And if you're looking to find ways to support mothers in your companies
or to be a...
supported yourself. I hope that you've been able to take something away today
towards that effort. Thank you.