Thanks so much for coming.
And this talk is about 10 years with Thoreau,
in case you're in the wrong place.
I hope you're not.
And my name is Tracy Fullerton, and I just
spent more than a decade making a video game
about a classic book called Walden or Life
in the Woods, which is a pretty crazy thing to have done.
And for those of you who don't know, you probably mostly do, but I just want to be sensitive.
For those of you who don't know, Walden is a book by Henry David Thoreau,
who was a naturalist, a philosopher, and a hermit who lived alone on the shores of Walden Pond in Massachusetts.
from 1845 to 1847 and he wrote about his experiences there.
He wrote about why he went to live there and his thoughts about life and how we
should live it.
And the game that I made is a first-person exploratory narrative
with a light survival set of mechanics and it's set in an
open-world simulation.
of Walden Woods over the course of Thoreau's first year
at the Pond.
It actually just shipped on Steam yesterday
and it's also available on itch.io and on PlayStation 4
and it will be coming to Xbox this summer.
If you come down to GDC Play, we'll have a booth
and we'll be showing the Xbox demo
in case you want to check it out.
In case you aren't familiar with the game,
I want to show a short trailer to give you some context
for how it feels.
What if we could all go to the woods to live?
Good day, Henry.
Play as Henry David Thoreau in Walden, a game.
So the game was produced in my research lab at the University of Southern California,
the USC Game Innovation Lab, and it's an independent game.
I should note, though, that it's also been funded by some unique sources,
such as the National Endowment for the Humanities, the National Endowment for the Arts.
Because of that, we are able to make the game free for educators to use in their classrooms.
So in case there are any teachers in the room,
this is where you can find out about getting copies for your classrooms.
So, making a game about a famous philosopher hermit is a bit crazy.
I'm going to admit that right off the bat.
You might just be asking yourself, why?
Why not just make a survival game?
Why make it specifically about Thoreau?
Isn't he just some stuffy old writer who, if we grew up in America, we were forced to
read in high school?
Well, the answer to that, for me, lies in Thoreau's philosophy itself and the rules
of the experiment in living that he set for himself down at the pond, and the possibility
those rules offer to teach us something about the wider palette of challenge and motivation
that we as game designers should consider when we're imagining novel game experiences.
To begin with, I want to acknowledge that Thoreau and his writing are particularly American
in their influence.
I've actually taken the game around the world, and I've found that there are many people
who know of him as a recluse and a hermit, but outside America, people are not assigned
to read him in the way that we are here in our literature classes.
So usually, even if people have not read his writings, they'll still know that he went
out into the woods and lived in a cabin alone there.
And they may actually have a connection to the theme of the book, the themes of the book
which are about finding balance in life and looking for a relationship in nature
because these are actually quite universal, especially today
as digital technologies spin our lives faster and faster and farther away
from the pace of life in nature.
So whether or not the modern themes of living are more simply and sustainably our universal
ones, it is, I would say, a particularly American dream to want to go off into the woods and
live alone.
to be completely self-sufficient and apart from society.
And I know that GDC is an international audience,
so I want to address up front that yes,
this is a strange and interesting and romantic dream, this
iconoclastic strain of the American ideology.
And though I can't see you very well, just out of curiosity,
Who here would admit to having dreamed at one time or another of maybe going off on our own and living in a cabin, having the time to work on our own creative dreams?
Yeah, all right, okay, let's all go together, we'll make a commune.
So I certainly have, right?
And if you have, you probably, knowingly or unknowingly, have been influenced by the ideas
of Henry David Thoreau, who is perhaps the most famous American recluse after maybe the
Unabomber.
So, for those who may not remember Thoreau, or weren't forced to read him,
it's just a little bit of context about him and his work.
As I mentioned, he was a writer and a naturalist and an activist
who lived in the 1800s in Massachusetts in the town of Concord,
which was also home to a group of writers and philosophers
who would form the core of that generation of American literature.
People like Ralph Waldo Emerson and Nathaniel Hawthorne.
Bronson Alcott and his daughter Louisa May Alcott,
sometimes joined by Margaret Fuller, Herman Melville,
and a number of others.
And Thoreau was part of this group,
but he really wasn't much of a joiner.
He preferred to be on the outskirts and go his own way.
His most well-known work is probably
on civil disobedience, an essay about the importance
of throwing our entire lives, our bodies,
into making the kind of change that we believe in.
And this essay famously inspired leaders
such as Mahatma Gandhi and Martin Luther King
in their own nonviolent acts of resistance against the state.
But Thoreau himself was not a leader of movements like these men.
He was more interested in discovering a kind of personal truth, a system of living, if you will,
that would lead him to what he perceived would be a better, more balanced life
with a direct relationship with nature.
And he didn't think he was going to find that living in Concord, working odd jobs,
and hanging out with a bunch of other writers talking about writing.
So in the summer of 1845, on July 4th, Independence Day,
he went out into the woods near Concord and built a cabin
and lived there for two years, two months, and two days
in pursuit of an idea about how he could best
spend his time in life.
He wanted to strip down his life to its bare minimum
so that he could judge what was really necessary
and what was superfluous, what was distracting him
from really understanding the essence of life.
Thoreau called what he was doing an experiment in living.
But from a game designer's point of view, to me,
it really feels a lot like a game he was playing.
The rules were, survive on as little as possible,
learn ways to optimize your time spent on survival,
and invest that time into discovering the secrets of nature.
Maintain as high a connection to nature as possible
without failing at survival.
The natural resistance in the system was twofold.
First, time itself is limited.
And second, even if you cut yourself off
from society physically, your relationships
will make demands on you whether you like it or not.
In Thoreau's case, he did not divorce himself
from society entirely.
So he kind of set himself apart from it
within walking distance.
So these demands actually took more time
than we might imagine for someone
who we think of as a hermit living out there
in those woods.
Now, I've actually spent a lot of time elsewhere talking about my personal reasons for choosing
this book and this writer to make a game about.
I'm not going to go into that here, but if you're interested in my personal connection
to Thoreau and the journey of ten years of production, I'd suggest watching this talk.
from IndieCade, which is all about that.
Today, what I'd like to talk about
is how non-traditional Thoreau's game design was,
how he set different motivations for himself as a player,
and how basing a video game
on this non-traditional set of motivations
can produce a very different kind of experience for players.
As I mentioned earlier, Thoreau wanted to strip down his life into the barest essentials.
He decided for himself these were food, fuel, shelter, and clothing.
He lived in the northeast part of America where there are pretty brutal winters, so
things like shelter and warmth were more critical than if he'd lived somewhere else.
But these basic necessaries of life, as he calls them, are key motivators for him.
He spent a lot of time providing for them,
especially at first before he learned
to kind of optimize his survival needs.
And this is something that we can relate to
in designing basic survival simulations in many games.
We often find ourselves creating systems
for maintaining player health and strength.
But Thoreau did not want to maintain health and strength so that he could go off into battle,
or even fight natural enemies like wolves or bears.
Instead, the challenge he set for himself was to battle time.
He wanted to optimize his survival needs in such a way as to give himself more time to spend exploring the woods.
interacting with nature at all levels, and gaining inspiration from those interactions.
He used this inspiration to write pages upon pages and pages of notes in his journal,
ideas about what he saw and thought each day, and how his life and nature differed from the
life of his fellow men. The reward for Thoreau was not better clothes or a nicer home or even
better tools. His reward was a wealth of ideas and experience.
So this is where, in the design of Walled in a Game,
we had to diverge completely from a standard survival game.
Once you figured out how to maintain yourself in the woods,
the idea now is not how to level up your house and tools
or build yourself up as a warrior survivor,
but rather to build yourself up
as a lover of nature and the world.
And in fact, in the game, if you fall into the trap of working too much on your survival,
which we absolutely allow you to do, you will find that your life in the woods grows dim
and uninteresting. The possibility of the space will literally close down,
visually, orally, and in terms of the interactive opportunities.
Many players don't realize this is happening right away
because they've been trained by virtually all other games
that there's only one true path in life,
one core set of motivations that games mirror exactly.
This belief that more is better, more food, more fuel,
more shelter, better shelter, better clothes,
all of these make for a better life.
And the value of riches and success
are unquestioned in players' minds
because most games reward that assumption.
If you make a game where more is better,
leveling up is good, players feel a sense of comfort
with that and their expectations about what they are
supposed to be doing in your game confirm
what they believe about life in general.
So if your game has no other aim than to make people
feel comfortable and confirm their general assumptions
about life in a kind of acquisitionist context,
this is fine.
But Thoreau's experiment was about disproving
these assumed constants.
His philosophy was directed towards a different and more elusive goal.
And because we wanted our player experience in Walden to reflect and
in fact embody that difference, we needed a motivation system that would
subtly lead players away from standard game goals.
and those rewards and towards the kind of questioning that had originally inspired the
rote.
We needed to make a game about a unique philosopher exploring the outcomes of an experiment and
living under his own special rule set.
A traditional motivation and reward system would not suffice.
We had to refer to mechanics like wealth and acquisition, resource management, item collection,
leveling up and the like, allowing players to earn money with odd jobs, farming or selling
your manuscripts and then using the money you earn to buy better tools or fancy fishing
rods or more food storage or even leveling up your shelter with a nice iron cook stove.
But these gestures to traditional game motivation structures and
really to traditional life goals are a trap in the game.
They don't lead to the ultimate prize of play,
which was, as Thoreau would have it, a life well lived.
What generally happens in the game is that at a certain point, all of a player's inspiration
has drained away as they have focused on attaining more things or responding to the demands of
NPC friends, family, and colleagues who have literally chased after you out into the woods
and demanded that you participate in traditional social structures.
Your mentor Emerson wants you to keep writing and selling your manuscripts.
Your family wants financial aid, financial help with paying their bills,
and emotional support, help grieving their personal losses.
And the government wants you to pay your taxes like a decent member of society.
And you can do all these things in the game
if you think that that's right.
And there may even be small rewards for you along the way
by participating in these to-do items.
But the bigger prize for you as a player
lies in balancing your time between your goals
of self-sufficient survival and a constant, deep relationship
with nature and the inspiration it provides.
Only by working constantly to sustain this balance will you find yourself both strong
and healthy and able to have the time to explore and reflect on nature.
And only by sustaining this balance will you have the opportunity to fill your in-game
journal with ideas and inspirations.
The very ideas and inspirations that will allow you, playing as Thoreau, to finally
write the book that is Walden.
One thing we absolutely wanted to avoid in the game was one single win scenario.
When you're making a game about a philosopher who set out to challenge common wisdom about what makes life successful,
it seems very wrong to provide a prescriptive and singular win scenario for players.
So we made it possible for players to complete the game in a number of ways that may or may not align with Thoreau's own beliefs,
while at the same time providing perhaps
the greatest sense of achievement for those who do realize the real optimization here
is about managing time and balancing their basic and their more ephemeral needs.
So while one of the different outcomes of the games
includes becoming a famous writer
and earning substantial paychecks
from your editor in New York,
traveling to Boston to lecture
on your experiences in the woods,
to do this you would actually need to break
with your goals of self-sufficiency
and buy things like a fashionable suit
in order to go and do that lecture.
Other paths include helping your mentor, Emerson, with his own writing.
Seeking out books for the lectures that he's working on will also inspire you.
So there's some efficiency here since your goals are aligned with Emerson's.
But there's maybe a growing sense that you need to stop doing his bidding
and get back to your own experiment in the woods.
You may also take on surveying jobs in the woods, which at first probably seems like an excellent compromise,
since you wind up spending a lot of time tramping around in nature, exploring,
while earning money you can spend on food and such in the general store.
But surveying is a tool of commercial development, and as you participate in the breaking up of the woods into parcels,
you may find that you've become a servant to the needs of an expanding society,
and are no longer living by your own principles.
Following Thoreau's passion as an amateur naturalist,
you may also spend your time capturing specimens
of the wild animals you find in the woods
to contribute to the annals of science.
This can earn you both a bit of money
and some obscure credits in a scientific publication.
Again, there is a question of whether you're
following the true prize, taking financial reward from nature
rather than inspiration.
And these are just a few of the possible paths
you might follow over the course of the game.
The open world design of Walden contains within it an extremely broad possibility space for
players to explore this basic question about how best we, or Thoreau in this case, can
spend our time.
If we choose to focus purely on survival, we will never achieve the larger goal of living
an inspired life.
If we choose to focus purely on inspiration,
we will lose strength and faint away.
If we take our direction from the various requests
that others place on us,
we may find some of what we are looking for, but not all.
It is up to each player to discover in our own way
our own final reward, which in this case,
in this game, actually lies beyond the screen.
And that's because the most important thing
about game design that I learned from Thoreau in a nutshell,
after spending 10 years making a game about a book that he spent 10 years writing, is
this.
People want all the wrong things.
We think we want to be successful, but we really want to be accepted.
And we think we want freedom, but we really want security.
We are conflicted beings, and we are easily distracted from what we really need by what
we've been trained to believe that we need.
Game players, specifically, have been trained to believe they need rewards,
that they need to win, and that they need external motivation to tell them what to do next.
And to some extent, that is clearly true.
We all need some guidance to help us along.
But we don't need nearly as much guidance as we think we do, in games or in life.
What Thoreau is writing about, and what we were trying to provide in Walden,
with our very different kind of survival simulation,
is that sometimes we need experiences that untrain us,
that challenge us to upend our assumptions about what we should be striving for.
And so in a lot of ways, Walled in a Game
is an attempt to untrain players.
It uses the basic design language of survival mechanics
combined with a subversive set of non-survival mechanics, i.e.,
inspiration opportunities, and a possibility space
threaded with quests that may or may not
align with the goal of balancing these mechanics.
And it frames this experience as a narrative
about a historical character whose
life is a symbol of American individualism and free thought.
That's a lot to put on the shoulders of an indie game.
It expects quite a lot from our players
in terms of self-reflection during play,
and the ability to parse meaning from game mechanics,
and a kind of literacy about meaningfulness in play.
It assumes literacy with more than common traditional game
mechanics, and a willingness on the part of players
to accept that those mechanics are only one way of abstracting
how the world works.
If a player can recognize the difference between what is asked of them in a traditional survival game, for example, in Walden,
and what is asked of them in life in Walden,
they may make a connection that equals the philosophical discoveries of Thoreau.
In short, they may win our game.
Quite frankly, this level of literacy is as rare in game players as it is in readers of
literature.
To play and discern abstract meaning from that play is a beautiful thing.
But we as designers don't really train players to engage at that level.
We don't expect it of them that regularly.
In the same way that we first learn to read with literal meaning and to see with representational
meaning, we also first learn to play without abstraction.
But there is a beauty in reading play abstractly that if we as designers begin to build into
our systems of engagement, we may find ourselves able to express entirely new systems of ideas.
Systems of ideas that go beyond acquisition and accomplishment as universal signifiers
of success.
Systems of ideas that may lead us and our players away from traditional assumptions
about what motivates us in play and in life.
And systems of ideas that allow us to express alternative philosophies as playful experiences.
Before I conclude, I want to address one last thing,
and that is that many people, when
they hear that I've made a video game about living in nature
and specifically about Thoreau, the famous curmudgeon
hermit of Walden Woods, they conclude immediately
that this is too ironic to be true.
And I understand this impulse.
I made a video game about a guy who
exclaimed to all that we need to simplify our lives.
But here's the thing.
He's a guy who wrote a book about it,
which was the technology of expression of his time.
All media is a technology.
Words, images, mechanics, these are all technologies
of ideas and expression.
So part of me says, no, it's not at all ironic
to use the media of our time to express
these universal questions about how we spend
our time in the world.
If anything, asking these questions in a video game
is the most pertinent place for us
to experience them these days.
The real question is, do we know as players and as designers
how to understand the non-traditional philosophies
embodied in this playful system?
Do we know how to play and how to design deliberately?
I think I might have a few minutes for questions
if there are any.
So Walden, sorry not Walden, Thoreau,
brought his laundry home to his mother
so she could do it for him.
Can you do that in the game?
Yes, in fact, you can.
The question is, can you get your laundry done
by your mother in the game?
And yes, in fact, we have an option for you to go home
and not only have your mother do your laundry,
but she's also possibly sometimes baked you a pie,
so you can have pie.
You can actually live in town, do odd jobs,
and spend most of your time in Concord
if you would like to become a Concord slacker.
If you were going to spend the next 10 years of your life making a game about a different
philosophy, what would you choose?
Wow, that's really a wonderful question.
My next game is actually not about someone else.
My next game is a personal game that I'm working on, so I don't have a ready answer for you.
Right now I'm kind of embroiled in understanding how to make a game about something that is
kind of deeply personal to me.
Wow, I've got to think about that one and get back to you.
Thank you very much. It was a very interesting talk.
My question is, when you're talking about that players follow the standard path of levelling up everything,
that you will be reducing the space of possibilities of nature.
And also I've seen that something about inspiration,
and I was wondering how is any like measure of that,
that the player is aware of it, so he can increase,
or is just there and experience it.
Good question, yes.
So the way that we do that is, I mentioned,
I guess I was being pretty vague,
but yes, visually and orally.
So inspiration is denoted in the game
through the richness of the world,
the actual, the colors of the world.
but also the number of instruments in the music score.
So whole lines of the melody will fall out
as you become less and less inspired,
and the world becomes more dim.
You start to lose the saturation,
and it becomes very dull.
And you could get down to just a very, not quite black and white,
but a very dull experience with just a heartbeat of music going.
And.
A lot of times people don't feel like, they're not aware of it immediately, but
when they talk to you about their experience, they'll say, well,
I was just feeling really depressed.
And then I just decided maybe I should go take a walk by the water.
And then all of a sudden, the music came back and I started feeling better.
And we tried to make it so that it wasn't a meter, right?
Because we didn't want a meter of inspiration.
But we wanted to have a more subtle kind of system that allowed you to feel when your
inspiration was rising.
Hi, it was a great talk.
So kind of going off of that question,
are there specific ways for players
to self-reflect in the game?
Like you said, players say that I took a walk by the lake.
Was that like when you asked the players
or is there also a way for them to self-reflect in the game?
Did you design for that in any way?
We didn't design a way for them to record it within the game, but the game is paced...
Sorry, I'm not repeating the questions.
The question is, are there ways for the players to self-reflect in the game system?
There's two things.
One is...
the journal, which isn't a self-reflection, it's really a collection of everything you've done in the game.
So everything you've looked at and inspected closely will fill your journal in a kind of procedural
list of
like your notes of your experience.
But then we also just designed the game, just quite frankly, to be paced so that there's a lot of time for reflection.
There's even time for reflection when you're doing
your basic survival tasks.
I don't know about you, but when you're doing things
like physical labor, like hammering, right,
or sawing or something, there's actually quite a lot
of time for thinking, and the same with walking.
There's a lot of walking in this game,
and we wanted to have that time there
so that players could be reflecting
as they were engaged in these more mundane tasks
of Thoreau's life.
Fascinating talk, thank you.
Could you share a little bit more about the response
from players, did people generally kind of get it,
and do you consider this successful?
How do you think about success for a game like this?
That's a great question.
So there's a lot of different metrics for us.
The first is that what I've noticed
is that we have a core group of players who really get it.
And when they get it, I mean, they love it.
There's just a kind of excitement and appreciation.
And people often write me very long letters about.
almost like a journal entry about the things that happen to them in the game, the story of their experience and how they
Usually there's an epiphany along the way and they tell me the story of how they reach their particular epiphany, right?
So that to me, number one, that's a success.
We found our players.
It's never going to be a broad commercial game,
but we have obviously released it on commercial platforms.
And I would say that it's done uniquely well
for an academic research game,
because it was like the top seller on itch.io last year,
which is a small distribution platform,
but that's still really nice to be able to say.
and now we're coming to Steam.
We'll see how they treat us.
Also on PlayStation we have some people
who've even created a little players community
which I was sort of like, oh my god,
they've created a bunch of.
They're playing together.
So those are really nice.
The other side of the metric is not commercial,
and it's not even just core players.
And that is educational.
So I mentioned we give the game away to teachers.
And the love of the teachers and the stories that we hear from students
in encountering this game in classrooms is pretty extreme.
It's pretty great because it's a real game.
It's not something trying to shove educational content into a small amount
of time, it's a real experiential open world game.
The students really love that it's a full 3D immersive world.
They really love that this doesn't smell like an educational game for them.
So we've received quite a lot of praise that way.
We've also won some awards, so that obviously is a nice pat on the back.
While your game is complex, have you ever gotten comparisons with a game,
like one of the older games, Journey?
just the way it feels going through, just exploring on a peaceful premise?
Well sure, yeah. So Genova was one of my students.
And of course we have very similar aesthetics.
I would say
absolutely.
I think that's probably time.
I'm not certain exactly when we're supposed to end.
But if there are no more questions,
I want to thank everybody for coming.
And have a great GDC.