Hi everyone, my name is Véronique Lallier, I'm the Global Vice President of Marketing at Aira Studios.
We are the creators of Smite, Paladine and Realm Royale,
three free-to-play games available on a variety of platforms.
So let's talk about things that are hard.
Making game? Hard.
Making free-to-play games? Hard.
Bruce Willis in that movie that started with die? Hard.
During my presentation, I'm going to talk about how you can keep games fresh through live operations
and feature a variety of examples from our key titles SMITE.
Examples like new gameplay experiences, lore-driven experiences, seasonal events,
eSports, and more than that, probably.
And if you want to learn more about live operations, please join me in my presentation.