I'm sure many of you have already seen some of my amazing colleagues' talks.
Everybody's been sort of crushing it this year at GDC, and it's super exciting.
But it was a little bit more pressure on me.
So it says out there that the talk is reinventing God of War, but I realized as I was writing it...
that I was covering a lot of stuff that really smart people
and really good people were already going to cover
in their talks in a much better way than I was.
So I was trying to figure out
what would be a really good talk
that would be much more specific of the things
that I do on a daily basis.
So.
I'm doing something about pitching and doubting,
which is pretty much what I do the entirety of a project.
I talk to people and beg and sell,
and then try to either quell doubt from other people
while the whole time experiencing
a tremendous amount of doubt myself.
It is fantastic, it is exciting.
It's not a very glamorous job.
Everybody thinks it's glamorous,
but really it's just constantly stressful.
So in April of 2013, I started talking to Shanna Studstill.
And I initially had a pitch for the game.
And it was a little bit like this.
I don't even know if this is the exact thing I said,
but this is essentially what it was.
I want to do something really huge and bold.
And the arm gestures?
are extremely important when you are talking about shit you have no idea about.
So when I'm telling people I'm moving my arms around it's going to be huge and bold and
you raise your voice every once in a while and you know we're going to turn everything
upside down and just freak people out.
There was nothing of substance to that initial pitch but she was still interested in actually
continuing to work together because she figured eventually you're going to figure it out and
you're going to get it.
So I came back to the studio in June.
of 2013, right?
It was like the first 15 days of June that I came back
and started working with a bunch of people
and tried to formulate what it is I wanted to do
with this game that wasn't just huge and bold
and lots of arm gestures.
And after four weeks, I put together a pitch,
and I was going to be pitching Scott Rohde.
So the way the organization works is,
Shannice Dudsdill, who I had mentioned earlier,
she's heading up Santa Monica.
She's sort of the first gate that I went through, right?
And then Scott Rohde is sort of overseeing
all the studios within North America,
so he's kind of the next gate,
the person I have to pitch on that list.
And then you have Shuhei Yoshida,
who is kind of like the scary gate that I have to pitch.
And then after that, it gets up to Sean.
And by that time, I pretty much probably
have it figured out, so it's a little bit less scary.
But something I realized
when I was putting this presentation together
is that everybody above me has a fucking S in their name.
They all work for Sony.
Their names begin with S, and I realized, like, you know,
progress upwards in this company is all related
to whether or not you have an S in your name.
So today, I'm going to change my name.
And I added a few S's at the end.
That way, there's nobody that's going to overtake me.
And I will be the vice president.
of vice-presidenting.
So if you have any questions about vice-presidenting,
I am the person you're going to come to.
I'll probably outsource it to somebody else
so that I can probably finish Red Dead most of the time.
That's not a real email, so don't try to contact it.
It won't get you anywhere.
So moving on to a really smooth segue like I just did.
So what I'm gonna do is something
that nobody outside of the company has seen.
It is the very first pitch that I did.
for Scott Rohde that kind of kicked this entire thing off.
And I ended up doing variations of this pitch
throughout the duration of the game.
So I'm gonna break a little bit in the middle
and then switch to one that was from a little bit later.
And then I'm gonna talk a little bit more specifically
about doubt, about the doubt that I was feeling
throughout all of this and kind of encapsulated
in a very long winded story that I'm gonna tell.
So this is going to have director's commentary.
So I'm not really going to do the pitch officially,
mostly because it was like five years ago, and I'm old,
and I really can't remember every single thing.
But I can kind of poke fun at all the stupidity
that I had at that moment.
And you can all see how something like this game
started out really.
Really bad.
So starting off right away, we're using the old logo
because it was four weeks.
And I even put that at the bottom of the presentation.
That was to repair, Scott,
that I'd only had four weeks to work on this.
So please lower your expectations.
So it was August 14th, 2013, and this next image
was not actually in the original presentation.
I would just do a verbal description of this,
but I added it in, so there's a couple images
I had to switch out to make this thing work.
But what I would talk about was the idea
that all the mythologies of the world
are kind of like this Hubble telescope image.
They are like galaxies individually spread out
throughout a complete universe.
The world is the universe, and all the mythologies are sort of origin stories of various cultures
throughout the world, beginning at the beginning of time and stretching all the way out.
So at any given time, all the mythologies exist together concurrently, and they are
simply separated by geography.
So it was important because some people had the conception that, hey, Kratos at the end
of God of War III destroyed the world.
Well, he destroyed what they believed the world was in Greece, which was their world.
Everybody believed their world was the only world.
In fact, we still believe that today.
So
Initially we were talking about this concept,
I didn't have a really good word for it.
So I was calling it a reboot,
but I knew that I didn't want to continue to call it a reboot
because keep calling it a reboot,
a lot of people would have these misconceptions
and all this baggage that comes along with what a reboot is.
So I wanted to explain what a reboot was
by using one of my favorite things
in the entire world, Star Trek.
So the Star Trek fans, it's fantastic.
So I would talk about this concept of Star Trek Nemesis,
right, had that classic sort of familiar,
high-end TV-focused appeal.
It didn't really broaden the audience.
It was sort of appealing to people
who were already Star Trek fans.
And then the new reboot, the J.J. Abrams one in 2009,
kind of brought in that sort of new feel, the cutting edge.
And honestly, the thing that was most important,
the thing I put in orange was this idea
that theirs was an origin story.
So they were telling the story of Spock and Kirk
and kind of going back to the days of the Academy.
You can see I, at the beginning, was calling it God of War IV,
because I didn't have any idea what we were going to call it.
I thought I was going to put a subtitle at the end of it.
So I was like, whatever, we'll just call it God of War IV,
because I didn't want to confuse anybody
if I called it just God of War.
And then I ended up just calling it God of War.
It's fantastic.
So what does this mean, right?
It means that directors are the worst artists on the planet.
And I just grab an image off of the internet
and I actually have a, it means a reset, right?
It means we're going to reset everything
but in a different way, right?
We're not gonna go back and say,
well, what we're gonna do is tell Kratos' new origin story.
No, we're gonna actually continue the timeline
and reinvent the feel.
And the important part of this was to say that we did so much work developing the character of Kratos,
why would we throw all that out and start on a new character?
Because you just have to build all that backstory again.
So we're sort of treating the first seven games like the chapter one of this character's life.
But he still needed as a character to grow.
We wanted to grow the character, we wanted to grow the world.
Everything needed to expand out and give you a sense
that something was going to be different.
And wanted to, in the initial pitch,
because I didn't have a lot,
I wanted to talk a little bit about the studio as well.
So talking about how the studio was gonna play
to our strengths, because we were really good
at making action adventure games.
We wanted to make sure that we stayed on that track
of making action adventure games,
but we wanted to broaden our skills, open things up,
and feel like we were progressing forward.
Because for a long time, we kind of
got stuck in this rut of doing, hey, we did the last game.
Let's pile some more stuff on top of that.
So we wouldn't really go in and just kind of rip things up.
And then.
When you are asking executives for money,
usually you do things like the next two points.
I'm a little embarrassed about them,
but I'm gonna show them anyway.
You say things like, own the action adventure genre.
And I, at the time, was just like,
I was like cringeworthy when I was saying it.
I was like, you know, it's that aspirational goal.
Man, we're gonna do something great.
And I think for me, and I think for the rest of the team,
the concept was that we were going to own
the work that we had done, that we were gonna
really, truly stand behind everything that we had done
and really try to excel at all of that.
And then this one, this truly is the one that you say
when you want people to give you money.
Create Game of the Year.
This is four weeks in, and we said we were going to do that.
And even I thought that was total bullshit.
But I was like, all right, we're going to do this.
And it was that level of enthusiasm,
even though inside I'm going like, yeah, right.
This is not going to happen.
But it will get people really excited.
So moving on to the narrative, continuing the timeline,
growing the character, continue to sort of hammer
that same point home that we're not restarting anything.
It is the same Kratos that you know,
except we're gonna figure out how we're gonna change it.
And while I was sort of on my travels
after having left right before three fully started,
something I had learned from a bunch of different directors
was this adage of simple story, complex characters.
And.
Full disclosure, I did not listen to this first rule.
So the first year, there are several points in here
that I ignored that I was telling other people,
we need to do this, and then I totally screwed up.
So I ended up having to reboot the reboot of the script.
So we wrote a script for a year, and it was the wrong script.
I was sort of realizing that, OK, I wasn't paying attention.
I wasn't making this about the main characters.
And the story sort of meandered a little bit.
And Kratos, seeking a fresh start.
So this picture right here is sort of what people thought of Kratos.
before we sort of released the demo in 2016, right?
It was like angry Kratos, the guy who killed somebody
at the beginning of a cinematic
and just kind of stood there until the cinematic ended.
He was just an angry, violent, scary guy.
And not only did he need a fresh start,
but I think the player needed a fresh start as well.
They needed a new perspective on this character.
And in a way, I'm getting older,
the studio has been around for a lot longer,
so I was looking around at all the people
that I've been developing games with for like 10 years.
and we were all old.
And the interesting thing was this concept
of breaking the cycle, right?
And it was so multi-layered,
because it was breaking the cycle for us as a studio,
kind of getting caught in that rut of saying,
well, you know, we did the last game,
let's just keep putting things on top of it
instead of really digging in and saying,
we're just gonna rip this thing up
and figure something new out.
It was me as a developer sort of having some sort of confidence in what I was doing and trying different things,
having a little bit more confidence to try those things even though I would experience doubt all the way through all of this.
But it's also Kratos kind of raking this cycle, this cycle that he had since the beginning of the gods sort of screwing with his life,
him being an absolutely crap.
father, him sort of blaming the rest of the world.
That was one of the big aspects of Kratos' character
was it's everybody else's fault.
This isn't my fault, it's other people's fault.
That's why I'm such a jerk.
And the key to breaking that cycle
was gonna be this father-son story.
Here's another point in which I completely lost the plot
for the first year of the game
and ended up writing a story that assumed
you already knew the relationship of the father-son
and we sort of had to go and reboot that.
Now this was an important aspect.
This was really trying to cement the concept
that this isn't a new Kratos.
This is the same Kratos who's just a lot older.
So that means he still has this monster inside of him.
I was using the example of the Hulk a lot.
So I would basically say that in the previous games,
the Hulk was out all the time.
It was all 100% the whole kill, kill, kill, kill, smash, right?
No Bruce Banner whatsoever.
And in this one, I really wanted to experiment with the idea
that he was primarily Bruce Banner,
and he was struggling to actually keep the Hulk inside.
So this monster that he was keeping inside,
this monster of the Kratos that everybody knew,
was going to be something that he struggled and failed,
because failure is such a huge part of what we do,
that everything in my life just sort of ended up
in this damn game.
And he would struggle throughout all of this.
And something I was really excited about
was this concept of teaching in the narrative,
experiencing the narrative in the play,
so that you were kind of training your son,
you were teaching him about your life, right?
You were teaching him how to be a god,
and he was kind of, in turn,
teaching Kratos how to be a human being,
something he had forgotten so long ago.
And to some degree, we succeeded.
There was a lot of things that I really wanted to do.
I remember I was constantly talking about the teaching
and making that the focal point of many of the pitches.
And everybody always said, but yeah, how are you going to do it?
And I was like, I don't know.
We'll figure it out later, which is what we all do.
We just figure it out later.
And another just stellar graphic.
I mean, if anybody wants me to do any sort of side hustle
artwork for them, I'm free.
That's so good.
So the game pillars were not sort of the traditional
game pillars that we were talking about.
This was kind of the aspirational goals
of what we were gonna do with the game.
And starting off something that in the beginning of God of War
all the way back in 2003 when I was there,
we had always talked about this concept of the pick up and play
game, the fun and accessible game.
And it seems obvious that you say
we're going to make a game that's fun and accessible,
because who wants to make a game that's completely obtuse?
But I realized that we needed to say that.
There's a lot of things that we needed
to just sort of reinforce and tell each other constantly
to sort of.
change the way we were thinking.
And the next thing was really important in that.
I remember all the way back at the beginning,
we used to use two words to describe this game
in literally every single instance, brutal and epic.
And I was like, we can never say those damn words
ever again, because what we would do
is using those words would help us sort of fall back
on our old habits, our old ways.
So I made an attempt to try to figure out
how do you replace brutal?
Well, unflinching, of course.
The idea of the sort of unflinching close
and personal combat was also my early programming
to seed the concept of the no-cut camera.
So four weeks in, I was not bold enough to tell people
that I wanted to have a single camera shot
throughout the entire game, because I knew it was crazy.
But I was starting to at least seed this idea.
So throughout the presentation,
I was actually putting things in,
so eventually I could say,
see, we already talked about this,
so you agreed, it's fine, right?
And then this one is, again, another one of those,
hey, give me some money.
I'm going to say something that literally
every freaking game does.
We're going to make an interactive and immersive world.
Yeah, everybody does that.
But again, wave the arms, say it loud,
and then people are like, all right, here you go.
The next one, this was another very, very obvious,
like seamless narrative, seamless play
and character development.
This was where I started telling people about this idea
of constantly going, you know, in one sort of experience,
always feeling you can't even tell the difference
between any of it.
So in the early God of War games,
the big thing that we had done was the no loading screens,
which was a giant hassle.
On the first game, a lot of arguments over that one,
because so many things that you have to do,
so many unseen problems, and so many people
have to contribute to try to make that work.
And the no-cut camera was the same thing.
It was just me assigning a lot of work to the entire team.
It was insane.
And here's an awesome failed point.
I couldn't not use the word epic.
I couldn't find another word
that actually worked really good.
In fact, throughout the entire game,
I ended up just giving up and saying,
all right, fine, epic is the one I'm just going to accept
because operatic was not working
and most of the other things were not working.
And what I really wanted to highlight.
was this idea that in the previous God of War games,
we had exploration.
So we had a chest on the main path that you were at.
We had a hallway with a chest,
or a hallway that would go to a room with a chest.
But I wanted to really broaden the exploration.
I wasn't really admitting how big I wanted the game
to be at this point,
because I thought it would freak people out.
So I was just like,
oh, it's gonna be a little bit bigger, don't worry.
It's all good.
It's like 10 hours, 10 hours, man.
I'm not crazy, all right?
And something that Eric Williams and I had talked about in this early, early time was
this concept of simple and honest, right?
And this idea of being honest with ourselves, being honest with the team, and really getting
back to this concept of the simple mechanic being fun, finding many ways that something
individual can have different purposes, and getting back to the basics.
Right, getting back to the basics,
not only for the studio of focusing on the things
that we're really good at, but really getting back
to the basics of what this franchise was,
tearing everything out and kind of finding the things
that were sort of the load bearing walls of everything.
And the next thing was the play pyramid.
And this image, I am shocked that legal let me keep this in.
But I'm super excited about it because the road was
a really big influence for me.
I had written a short story early on that
was kind of a tone piece that helped people understand.
It was kind of the foundation of what
the beginning of the game was.
And
It was written in the way that it was just saying
the father and the son,
so even in the entire short story,
I never mentioned the name Kratos.
And I didn't mention Atreus because I hadn't figured out
the name until the end of 2016 or something like that,
because I'm super lazy when it comes to coming up with names.
I'm terrible at that.
But the play pyramid is this concept of saying,
what is making up your moment to moment gameplay?
Right?
And in a way, it's basically saying
that any time you're playing the game,
if you're not doing one of these sort of three core things,
then you need to evaluate whether or not
you should put a ton of effort into what
it is you're currently doing.
It's a way to evaluate, want to add something to the game.
Is it contributing to these sort of core concepts?
But I wanted to add another element inside of it.
which was this sort of central piece,
so that the game was about either narrative,
combat, or exploration.
And every one of those things fed into character development
so it didn't matter what we were doing,
everything had to help further the arcs of the characters.
Everything had to help get you
into the minds of the characters
so that you would never feel like,
oh, this is the time where you're telling me the story.
This is the time where I hit things.
And this image looks really bad.
And in all defense to the artists who helped me,
I asked them 10 minutes before I had to meet with Scott Rodey
if he could do something.
So this is better in 10 minutes than I
did in probably four weeks.
But I'm going to skip ahead now to the 2014 God of War
pitch for Shuhei Yoshida.
Okay, so this one was a little bit more refined.
I had already made the mistake of writing the wrong story
and telling the writers that we had to throw that story out
and that did not go well.
And then we started over, I kind of needed to buckle down
and figure out the skeleton structure
of what the entire game was so that I could then spend
the next three years doing these three hour long pitches
of walking people through the story
and then having them look at me at the end
and go like, how many teams are gonna work on this game?
This thing is huge.
So now we have a little bit fancier PowerPoint, right?
And also you can see that instead of narrative,
this is father-son.
And this was a reminder to myself,
the person who originally came up with these rules,
to follow the damn rules that I had actually set out to do.
And the father-son was to say the whole game story
was supposed to be about the relationship
between these two characters,
not necessarily about all these plotty elements
that we were really excited to explore.
So.
All of that sort of fed into the concept of character growth.
And the father-son story really is this kind
of relatable human story.
So much of the moments in this game
are just ripped from the lives of people on the team,
the writers, myself.
And this rule, the second one, is really something that
that I picked up while I was working with George Miller,
and he knew and had sort of been reinforced
by so many other people.
But I didn't really get it the first time he told me.
He's like, you always gotta dramatize your exposition.
I was like, okay, cool.
It just seems like that's what everybody does.
And that is absolutely not what everybody does.
It's insane.
So he gave me this example,
and it is a play that he went to go see.
And there are these two women on stage sitting on a couch,
and in between them is a phone.
And they start talking, and the phone begins to ring.
And it rings a couple of times before one of the women goes,
oh, well, aren't you going to answer that?
And she says, no, no, no, no, it's probably my son.
I don't want to talk to him.
And they continue talking for a little bit,
and the phone keeps ringing.
And the other woman finally says, you know what?
Maybe you should answer that.
What if he's sick?
What if he's hurt?
Oh, no, no, no, no, no.
You know, we're not really good right now.
She starts talking about the fact
that they got into an argument, and the phone keeps ringing.
And this is pre-answering machines,
which is why that phone is going to keep fucking ringing
until somebody answers it.
And as it's going, the audience, you find yourself kind of
creeping up on the edge of your seat a little bit
and it's agitating you.
You're getting agitated like the other character
because you want her to answer the damn phone.
And they go and go, and what you find out
is that you are getting all of the exposition
about this character's relationship to her son
that normally, if we were lazy,
like a lot of the times I am very lazy,
you would get from Irving the explainer,
who just comes onto the scene and tells you,
here's all the backstory,
this is the sort of situation that I had.
But in that moment, what you got
was a feeling of empathy and a feeling of connection
to a character because you were under stress.
You were taking part in the drama
and finding out about all of this
sort of boring backstory information.
And that stuck with me hugely,
because in what we do,
we can kind of translate that to play versus watch.
And there was so much in the game that we wanted to create in a play experience, right?
But it's really, really expensive.
You have all these sort of fail states and everything that you need to do.
So we did a lot, but there was still a lot more I felt like we could have done.
We just kind of continued to run out of time and said, all right, we have to pull these things out.
But then compensated and then every once in a while some other things got interactive.
So now the combat aspect, really the most important part
of this one, because I continue to love referencing Marvel,
is this idea of Marvel Comics versus Marvel Film.
So Dave Jaffe, when he was pitching the original game
back in 2000, well I came in 2003,
but he was doing it in 2002 before that,
would always talk about God of War
as heavy metal magazine meets...
Clash of the Titans, right?
It's sort of this bombastic comic book,
very mature adult, fantastic sort of experience.
And what we were trying to do
is bring it into the modern era, right?
And the games that we were playing,
the games that are exciting us of today,
we wanted to bring this in there.
We were looking at the way that Marvel
would translate comic books into film, right?
My mom would not read a Thor comic.
But she'd be damn sure she's gonna go see
Chris Hemsworth as Thor, right?
So I was like, as long as I cast Chris, I'm good, right?
My mom will play the game.
But that transition really showed
that you can take something fantastic
and bring it and expand the audience
and get them to connect to the work that you're doing.
And the context in the drama was also another important thing
of saying.
A lot of us make games that have combat in them.
You know, it's fun.
It's very sort of frenetic and exciting
to have combat in your game,
but a lot of the times you don't have any context
of this combat within the drama of your game, right?
To actually feel like, oh, the combat means something
in the overall goal, and coming up with that simple goal,
at this time I had known that we were going to
take the ashes to the top of the mountain.
Everything started to feed into this goal that was simple.
Everybody understood it very quickly in the game,
and you were able to feel like each one of these fights
meant something even more.
And to a certain degree, we succeeded.
Certain degrees, we can continue to do better in all of that.
The exploration was a whole new thing for this game because I wanted it to be so much bigger than anything that we had done.
And at the time when I was pitching this, talking about the mechanics that would encourage discovery and exploration,
we didn't have those mechanics. We were still figuring a lot of stuff out.
In fact, the engine wasn't completely ready.
A lot of things were like Lego pieces all over the floor, and I'm trying to...
hey, we need to come up with new verbs of how to make puzzles.
And it's like, OK, but how?
We can't even build anything in the engine right now.
So that was very stressful.
This time, especially when we were doing exploration,
was one of the more stressful.
In fact, honestly, the whole damn project was stressful.
But there was a tremendous amount, for me,
of this doubt in wondering, are we
going to be able to finish any of this stuff?
Because there is just so much to get done.
And the character growth, everything feeding into that one,
I had really started to cement what this meant,
continue to say teach, right?
Even though I had no idea how teaching
was gonna take place in the game,
I had that fallback of like, okay,
well, upgrading is kind of like teaching.
Your kid gets better throughout the game.
But thankfully, working with the team,
they end up kind of contributing so many different ideas
that make that initial kernel of something a lot better.
But it was important to actually see these characters change,
not just in their dramatic art,
but in their sort of visual as well as their play,
so that it actually feels like what you're doing
is growing with these characters, experiencing their lives.
So the pitching of all this stuff,
I would be pitching all the way through the end of the project.
It would just continue ad nauseum.
That's really all you do.
It's like selling cars to the team every day, over and over.
And nobody buys a damn car.
That's what's fucked up about it.
But the doubt also continues throughout all
of this experience.
And I know that everybody in here who makes games,
we all experience failure every day.
We all experience doubt every four minutes.
It's science, man.
I totally looked that up.
It's every four minutes.
So what I'm gonna do is I'm just gonna tell a story now
because I fucking hate PowerPoint presentations.
And I'm gonna talk about the E3 2016 demo.
So this story encapsulates so many versions of doubt,
so many areas of failure that we experienced on this project
and is kind of, for me, one of the most interesting
clips of game development.
So initially, we knew that we were gonna do a reveal.
We had honed in on E3 2016 as being the time
we were gonna do that reveal.
But I had no clue what it was gonna be.
Was it just gonna be a logo?
Were we just gonna show a quick clip of the game?
Were we gonna try to show a cut video together, right?
I was gonna try to sell people on a no-cut camera
and cut a bunch of shots together.
That wasn't gonna work.
Or were we gonna actually try to do a demo,
which was insane, right?
Like the first time you're gonna reveal your game
and you really don't have all the pieces together
and what are you gonna do?
You're gonna actually play a demo live on stage?
I totally chose that one,
because the thing was far away.
It was like nine or 10 months away.
So I was like, yeah, let's do the hardest thing.
And I feel like I do that all the time,
which is I agree to do something really hard
and then write when it comes time to do it.
it all, all my chickens go home to Ruth.
I'm like, what the hell, man?
Why did I agree to this?
So I started writing up different demo ideas,
just really jotting stuff down quickly.
And at the time, we had not figured out
the beginning of the game.
I had written the short story back then,
but we had not settled on,
hey, that's gonna be the beginning of the game.
We were focusing a lot on the middle section of the game,
so some stuff in the mountain, if you've all played the game.
you'll understand this part, inside the mountain.
And so I said, oh, you know what, I'm gonna do that.
I'm gonna write a demo up, it'll be inside the mountain.
It'll end at the elevator, kind of going up,
and there'll be a big scary monster reveal at the end
that screams, and then you go to black
all fucking dramatically.
It's so cheesy.
But I thought it was really great.
There was a part of me that was saying,
mm, this isn't so good.
So I was sending it to people on the team.
And I think they were just being nice, and they were like,
oh, yeah, sure, that's cool.
Oh, sure, that's cool is not the response
you want when you send somebody a demo writer.
You want them to be like, yeah.
So I got some notes from people and sort of settled on it.
We were like, all right, this is good.
But there's always something inside of me that was saying,
I don't think this is very good.
But to be honest, there is always
something inside of me that is saying, this is no good,
and you suck.
So I was like, all right, whatever, I'm going to ignore that.
And we were going to have the events people,
the PR people, and the marketing people
all coming down to the studio,
and I was going to do the pitch for them.
And it's kind of the same thing as this,
where you just get up and you wave your arms around a lot
because you're asking for money,
and you draw on the board,
and it looks really great in photos, right?
So I get in, I start doing the pitch,
and I realize like five minutes in,
that everybody's starting to fidget in their seats.
Some people are checking their phone.
I'm really losing them.
And I start to speak louder
because that totally makes the audience come back.
And that did not work.
And about halfway through the pitch, I realized.
this is absolute crap.
And you were right to think it was crap, because it's crap.
But I'm still giving the pitch.
So in my mind, I'm starting to think of ways to eject.
Like, OK, what can I do here?
I need to come up with a better solution.
This is not working.
And I start having a few ideas of potentially
the beginning of the game, a few visual ideas that are coming up
while I'm just running on autopilot on the pitch,
because I figure, why try?
It sucks.
They're not having fun.
I get all the way to the end of the pitch,
and everybody's, yeah, cool.
All right.
Yeah.
Nobody outright says it sucks.
That's usually only on the development side.
We're very honest with each other,
but people in the PR and marketing groups,
they're all very nice, they're very good people.
And they will just say it sucks when they leave the room,
or when you leave the room.
So I was like, all right, thank you, everybody.
I left the room, and I think somebody had talked
to Shannon immediately afterwards and said,
Yikes, that was bad.
You know, it's not terrible, it's just not that exciting.
We've sort of seen it before, and they're right.
Everybody does that exact same demo for E3.
So I was like, all right, I was not feeling good.
I went to Shannon and I said,
I want to take another crack at this
because I don't think we've nailed it.
I don't think we have the idea down.
And she was like, oh, thank God.
And I was like, feelings, come on.
No, she was really cool about it.
She was like, all right, Barlog,
because she never calls me by a first name.
She said, all right, Barlog, go ahead.
Figure something out.
I wrote up a quick sort of skeleton of what it would be,
what ended up being the demo that we were doing.
And we got on a conference call with the events and PR people
because they were like, dude, the first one sucked.
I'm not coming down for that.
Just do it over the phone, which really sucks.
Pitching people in person, you get the big arms thing.
That carries like 50% of the work most of the time.
And then you could draw on the board, which is like another 25%.
So I really don't have to do a lot of work verbally.
And then when you're on the little speakerphone thing,
it's pretty much just all what you're saying.
Surprisingly, the really rough pitch worked.
And they were like, okay, this is really good.
Thank you for taking our notes to heart.
And I was like, I'm not gonna tell you
that it wasn't your notes, but yes,
thank you for giving me notes.
And I took them all to heart,
and I redid everything based on what you were saying to me.
So they were like, all right,
well, we're gonna come down in another two weeks,
and we'll talk a little bit further
about what we're gonna do.
So they come down, I give them the full pitch
with the big arms thing, and that goes over really well
because everybody loves in-person pitches.
And at the end, I couldn't resist,
I threw in a little joke, and I said,
and then we can get Bear, and he can play live orchestra,
the whole thing.
And I was like, ha ha ha, and then one of the guys
who was in charge of throwing these events,
he's like the guy who does all the stage stuff
and everything, his eyes just get really big.
Like super excited and I was like wait, what happened?
And then he looks over at somebody
and you could tell there was a conversation
that had happened about this before I threw that joke down.
And I was like, oh interesting, all right.
And then they basically did not talk about it
any further than that and then said,
what we're gonna do, we're gonna do the stage show,
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
And they said, we'll be down in another couple of weeks,
we'll show you a little bit more.
So then another couple weeks go by,
I almost forget about this,
because we're starting to really figure out
how to structure this entire demo, how to build it.
And when they come down,
the guy whose eyes got really big had this little diorama.
He had created this little mock-up of a theater stage,
and it had these little slots
where you could put transparencies in
to show you what the things like the curtains
or the stage things that they would put in.
And he was so excited.
He was like, it's like when I get excited about something,
he's just pitching this, and he says,
We're really excited about doing the live performance
to the live orchestra.
And I was like, wait, what?
And he was like, this is really good.
And we were talking about this, so we're really
going to make it happen.
We already talked to Bear.
And I'm like, inside, going, fuck, fuck, fuck, fuck, fuck,
fuck, fuck, fuck.
But outside, I'm going, like, cool.
Let's do this, right?
So they give the whole breakdown of all this stuff.
And again, it's still pretty far away.
So I'm all right.
I'm like, all right, fine.
We'll figure this out.
But at the time, we're going through really stressful times
because one, engine's still getting built.
Two, the lighting was maybe 35% to 40%
of what it was gonna end up being in the final game.
And that was actually what we were gonna end up using
for E3, so there was just no way
we were gonna get that done.
Art direction, we hadn't really been able to figure out
exactly what our art direction was going to be.
We were arguing back and forth a lot.
We had some ideas.
I had some specific things.
The art director at the time had some specific things.
And we were just really trying to hash that out.
At the same time, trying to figure out the combat.
trying to figure out the enemies.
We were literally, every aspect of the game
that you could try to figure out,
we were trying to figure out.
So we were trying to take an inaugural flight in a plane
while we were building the plane
and also drawing the blueprints of the plane.
as it was taking off.
It was fantastic and incredibly, incredibly stressful.
So as we're going closer, it starts to hit
that I'm gonna have to play this thing live, right?
And it's gonna be nine minutes.
So I start rehearsing,
and I'm gonna rehearse for like two months, right?
And I think, and there's a bunch of members
of the team here, so they'll probably agree with this,
I hope.
This is probably the greatest time for the team
because I was basically playing for the team
while they all shouted notes at me
and then like wrote long emails of like,
you need to do this, you're doing this wrong,
you did this, you suck, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
And it was fantastic because I had to perfectly hit
all of these moves in an order
while we were also trying to figure out
which moves were going to be the best moves
to put in order while we were also designing them
and animating them and make them work.
And bless them, they figured out several tricks.
to sort of put the bumpers in the bowling lane,
the director version of it,
so I couldn't screw it up too bad.
So they had removed some of the potential
catastrophic failures that an idiot like me could do
if I hit the wrong button.
But still, I had to time everything,
I had to use the sticks,
I had to actually do all the combos
and everything like that,
I had to position myself correctly.
So I still had an opportunity to mess it up.
I had many, many, many opportunities
that I could mess it up.
And in a lot of my playthroughs, I would mess it up,
which was the face palm for everybody on the team.
Every time, I'd be like, I think I got it this time.
And I'd play for everybody.
And they'd be like, no, you're rushing this part.
You're not doing that part.
I was like, ah.
It was like the entire team was the director at that point.
And I was just like, take a note.
OK, yeah, that's good.
All right, all right, good.
Very, very stressful, but it was so much work
that I was like, all right, you know,
I think I can handle this, no big deal.
And as we're getting closer,
now in previous God of War games,
the thing I was remembering so much about E3
was like on God of War II,
we were burning demo discs at like 6 a.m.
the day of the show to drive them down
and put them in the machine
so people could play them on the floor.
So we really went right up against the edge.
But in this E3, we had to be done two weeks before.
So two weeks before E3, we had to be finished,
which felt weird, I think, to most of us,
going like, man, E3's not for two weeks.
This feels weird.
We're done.
What do we do with ourselves?
Make the rest of the fucking game, right?
But I was also then just rehearsing over and over
and over again and stressing about, OK, I have to hit this.
And then we had a couple of rehearsals with the orchestra.
But it was all leading up to the day of the show.
And throughout all this time, I am constantly just in my head
having this voice of, you're going to screw it up,
and having all these potential mess ups that I could do.
And on the day of the show, there
was going to be a dress rehearsal.
And then immediately after the dress rehearsal,
you had a little bit of a break,
and then the actual show would start.
So you'd kind of do it twice.
And I went down, and I'd like to go in that
we had not told anybody about the game.
So it was a complete surprise that God of War
was gonna be at this show,
on one of the PSXs I might have said,
yeah, we're working on a God of War game.
But nobody paid attention to that.
And I basically had to put a hood on and nobody,
like anybody would fucking recognize me anyway.
Like at the time, I don't think anybody had any idea
who the hell I was, but it was all for me.
I was just like, yeah, I'm so,
I gotta go stealth in the back entrance.
And so I get in and I am just like,
I hadn't slept the night before.
I maybe slept 20 minutes, I was so freaking nervous.
And just constantly going over the demo in my head.
On the drive down there, there was a care man in the car interviewing me.
And I was already nervous, but every damn question he asked me made me more nervous.
Because it was really like, so you're afraid you're going to screw up?
How specifically do you think you'll screw up?
And when you do that screw up, what do you think is going to happen?
What do you think people are going to say on Reddit?
And I was like, you know, I hadn't gotten that specific in my neurosis to say,
like, what is Reddit going to say? But I'm there now, dude. Thanks.
So I get in there and we do our dry run,
and this is the first time we did the fail run, right?
And that is that you have a kit, a backup kit,
and then the sort of ultimate fail,
the catastrophic sort of fail,
is you have to stand up and they turn on your mic,
and then you sort of apologize to the audience
that you suck and that you're gonna just roll a video.
And that hadn't been real for me until that moment.
I talked about it, but when we rehearsed it
and I had to like stand up in that empty theater
and say, sorry, it didn't work.
I was like, man, I do not want to do this again.
This is a one and done thing.
Because that's scary.
Like, not only is it screwing up the demo is scary,
but the fact that it doesn't crash, you know,
is something that you're hoping and hoping and hoping.
And if it crashes, that's just, it's normal.
That's game development, right?
It's no big deal, but it's still.
Crashing in front of a whole audience of people sucks,
right?
And I did not want to do that.
And it's a testament to our incredible team
that our game was pretty darn stable at that point.
So thank you to them.
So I did the thing.
And then Kevin Scharf, who was the producer at the time,
and I went back into the green room.
Now, the green room was basically just like curtains,
like a box of curtains backstage.
Had a couple tables and a little bar in there with some water.
No booze.
Searched everywhere.
Which I think was a good thing.
I probably really would have screwed up
if there was booze there.
So we're sitting there for, I guess we had 45 minutes
before the show was gonna start, the actual show.
And we're just kind of hanging out
and I'm going through everything in my head
and he's trying to keep me calm
but anybody who tries to keep me calm
is just making me less calm
and I'm stressing more and worrying about all the things
that could potentially go wrong
when the curtains pop open
and a Japanese man pokes his head in and looks around.
And then he just quickly closes it.
And I'm like, weird.
It's like, that was weird, right, Kevin?
And he's like, yeah, that's strange.
And I'm like, whatever, it's Los Angeles,
whatever, that's normal.
So we're sitting there for another couple of minutes,
and all of a sudden, in extremely dramatic fashion,
the curtains burst open,
and this group of people files in.
And at the back of that group of people is Hideo Kojima.
Right?
Bathed in light.
Fucking Magneto tiles below his feet.
Right?
And I was just like, oh, oh, wow.
And then I suddenly became like five-year-old me.
I was like, this is great.
And he does the Hideo Kojima head nod.
And then I do the whole like, so.
Then they just walk in, sit down at the other table,
as they're talking amongst themselves.
And I was spending like the next five minutes
trying to think of an opening line, right?
Like to go over there and be like,
so you come to E3 often?
I came up with nothing, but it distracted me away
from being stressed out and then I realized
I'm not gonna go over and talk to this guy.
So I'm just gonna go back into my own little world.
And about five minutes after that,
one of the guys stands up, walks over to our table,
and says, hello, we are going to eat Panda Express.
It is going to stink.
We're sorry.
Then he bowed and walked back to the fucking table.
Then I really thought it was weird.
And I actually at that moment contemplated
whether I was having some fucked up fever dream
and that I had not yet gotten up.
Unfortunately, they had called,
I actually, interestingly, I actually asked Kojima
if I could tell this story, because I thought,
oh, I should get permission
before I can say this publicly.
And I contacted somebody that I know that works with him
and asked him about it, and he said, yeah, okay, hold on.
Then he got back, and he said,
yeah, Kojima doesn't even remember that.
And I was like, oh, that's sweet, fantastic.
I make a hell of an impression, right?
So, they basically, curtains open again, time to go, right?
Then it's the heart beating like absolute mad.
I'm like, oh crap, oh crap, oh crap.
So Kevin and I get up and they're escorting us back
to the thing, he powers on my lav mic
which just reminds me that oh,
potentially we could have a catastrophic failure.
That sucks.
And we're going up the stairs.
And as we're going up the stairs to the balcony,
Everything's going to start, right, very soon.
People are already in the theater.
The orchestra's all there.
I realized that I forgot everything about the whole demo.
And that was a horror story of mine going like,
oh man, it's like going and taking a test
and you forget everything.
But I didn't think that would actually happen.
And it legitimately happened.
I was so amped up about this.
I was so scared about all this
that I legitimately forgot what I was supposed to do.
I couldn't remember the first button.
I couldn't remember the cue
that I was supposed to come in on.
And I was like, oh crap.
And we're sitting down and Kevin's sitting next to me.
And I'm like, do I tell Kevin
that I don't remember any of it?
Because maybe he'll remember the first thing,
and that'll get me started.
But if I tell him, that makes it real.
So if I just keep it inside, then maybe everything
will be fine, right?
So I'm just stressing the whole time, like, oh my god,
oh my god, what's the first thing?
What's the first thing?
And I literally can think of almost every game
that I'd ever played, except what I was supposed
to be playing at the time.
And at a certain point in the overture,
I had been able to see the kind of tablature screen
that was playing for Baer as he was composing
or as he was conducting.
And I was like, oh, it just came back to me.
Like an image on the screen made me realize like,
oh, I gotta hit start at that point when it says 110.
Okay, yeah, I got it.
And then it kind of just started to slowly fall into place.
And it turned out, I think several people on the team
had said that I did pretty good.
I didn't screw it up.
I think it was the best I can get.
That it actually worked out really well.
And in the end, it actually did work out really well.
People responded very positively.
That reveal of Kratos, we were really excited about Kratos
coming out of the shadows, but I don't think any of us
had any clue the kind of response
we were going to get for that.
So that was super overwhelming and awesome.
And I think the important thing about all of that
about the entire thing besides the fact that I hung out with Kojima while he ate Panda Express.
And he was not kidding.
It fucking smelled like orange chicken back there
for like an hour.
It was crazy.
Was that throughout all of it,
all of us, and me especially,
I was experiencing doubt at every single step of the way.
It was this sort of imposter syndrome times a thousand,
this feeling of what I have to say isn't valid,
what I'm doing isn't all that good.
And pushing through that,
breaking through each one of those walls
kind of led to...
Well, sadly, another wall of doubt that would be there.
But that was sort of the process.
That was the process of pushing through all of that
and ensuring that we could get to that end result.
And there was times even.
right before, in that two week span before E3,
where we're kind of refining last bits of things
in the play experience,
where there was even members of the team,
very good people, you know, not malicious whatsoever.
They weren't being mean about it, but they were nervous.
They were telling me, oh my God,
I think you're gonna screw up the franchise.
Like, this is a terrible way to present it.
One person told me, why don't we have a boss fight
at the end?
We should have a big boss fight.
I think another person even suggested
we should have Balder on a dragon
kind of come up when they're at the deer and be like,
I've been looking for you.
All these crazy last minute suggestions that I was like,
oh my god, no.
And I was basically just saying, don't worry.
Everything will be fine, even though inside I'm going,
oh, fuck, oh, fuck, oh, fuck, oh, fuck, oh, fuck, oh, fuck.
And it's something to remember, I think, for all of us
in what we do.
at any time, the next time probably,
which is five minutes from now,
you're gonna be hearing that voice in your head,
or the voices directly around you,
the people that you work with that say
that you're wrong, you have nothing good to say,
you're going in the wrong direction,
why are we doing this, you suck, you're a jerk,
well, the last two are just me talking to myself.
Remember.
that those voices are wrong.
And sometimes they're right.
Because if you remember all the way back at the beginning,
I was actually right to doubt that crappy demo
because it was crap.
And that's the messed up part about doubt in general,
is that it's right as much as it's wrong.
And it is up to all of us individually
for each individual situation to be honest with ourselves,
to trust.
ourselves to trust the people around us because they're the ones who really do all the great
stuff anyway. I just sort of bask in the limelight of their awesomeness. And really endeavor
to push through every one of those fucking doubt walls because on the other side is always
something better than where you were at from the beginning. So there you go. That is my
little chat at GDC. Thank you, everybody.
How much time do we have?
Ah, perfect.
Oh wait.
Thank you.
See, I got a slide for thanking you.
Okay, so we have 10 minutes and we can do questions.
So, feel free to ask any questions
except the following two questions.
What are you working on right now,
or is there going to be another God of War?
I can't answer that.
Two, don't ask who blew the fucking horn.
Because we're not going to tell you.
That's like the polar bear in Lost, man.
I'm not going to say anything about that.
All right, great.
Fire away, my friend.
Hi.
You talked about a situation with the E3 demo, which
was great, where you listened to some intuition
that you had to change it preemptively.
I was wondering if you could also
give an example of a time when other people's feedback,
other people's notes, were actually
really informative in you changing
your mind in the process.
Oh, that's a lot of examples.
My mind was changed many times.
OK, there's a really good point in the game
the son becomes a jerk, right?
And we had a whole slew of gameplay
that we needed to build around that.
So there was about an hour of gameplay where he was a jerk.
And we had to cut it.
So there was a point where production-wise, time-wise,
no more big arms were gonna give me more money,
that I just had to, I had to get rid of it.
But that meant that a huge chunk of the story
was getting cut out, and we needed to figure out
how to put it back in place.
And I was like, OK, you know what?
We're just going to do something really quick.
We'll do this small piece.
We'll do a small cinematic.
Because I had been selling people for so long
and begging people for so long to put more effort in, do this,
can add this extra thing, that I figured
this was the thing that's going to break them
if I asked them to go too far.
And the animators, the cinematic group,
were actually the ones that went far beyond the initial ask.
So I thought, oh, we'll be fine if we just
do this one little thing.
They're like, no, no, no.
I think we can do something even better.
And they worked with Eric Williams.
they actually came up with the moment
that something that we talked about way early on in the game
which was I wanted to see Atreus try to be rage mode.
Right, but we ended up not getting it.
Had I not cut that stuff,
we would not have had the animators be superheroes
and actually make that cinematic when Modi returns
and then Atreus gets all raged out, right?
They brought all that back
and it was sort of their contribution,
their pushing that added something,
I think, that was so critical to the arc
that I was not even able to see.
Thank you.
Fantastic.
Yes.
Hi, Corey.
Thank you so much for the talk.
Thank you.
Question.
I'm an audio guy a little bit.
Hello, audio guy.
Hey, what's going on?
I can't hear you.
Oh, really?
Oh, my god.
My biggest fear.
So as a big fan of the series, one of the biggest things
that shocked me was when you went from the voice
actor of TC Carson to Christopher Judge.
Yes.
I mean, I hated it for the first three hours of gameplay,
honestly.
Three hours it took you three hours to not hate it. All right, I'm
I feel like PC Carson was Kratos. He is amazing
Yeah, so like how did you like but then I ended up really loving Christopher judge
I like wow, this guy's he made the new Kratos. What made you like decide to make the switch?
It was a complex series of decisions.
So in the early portion of the game,
we had used TC in Ascension, a game that I did not work on,
but I had heard some of the stories of how it worked.
And TC was actually in the suit, right,
so that they were shooting a lot of these scenes on there.
TC is a smaller guy, he is a classically trained dancer,
and when he moves, it is almost impossible
for him to not move fucking gracefully.
He just floats.
He's magical, right?
And it created a lot of work for the animators afterwards
to have to kind of reanimate to make him feel like Kratos,
this big, imposing guy, right?
TC was absolutely sort of a product of the PS2 era
where you could do all the animation
and then you could record the voice afterwards.
But to get the scenes that I wanted,
I knew I had to have all the actors on stage.
because we were doing that one single camera shot.
We experimented a little bit early on
where we got a stand-in person that was large
and they would be Kratos, they would perform on the stage
and then we would go after the fact and record TC.
So we started to run the numbers on that one,
we started to run the time and apparently like 2036
was when we'd finished the game if we did it in this method.
It was insane how much work it would end up being.
So it was very, for me, a difficult decision
because.
He's such an intrinsic part of the franchise,
but I knew like, okay, if we're gonna do this,
we're just gonna have to do this.
I'm gonna have to commit to recasting,
and it turned out to be one of the hardest things, right?
Two people that were hard to cast, Balder and Kratos.
Both of those characters took almost, you know,
three, three and a half years.
I found a kid, like, in the first set of auditions.
It was ridiculous.
So I thought everything would be that easy.
It was not.
Thank you so much, appreciate it.
Thank you.
Yes, sir.
Excellent talk, excellent game.
Oh, thank you, sir.
Congratulations on all the awards.
You are awesome, and I think we all here agree.
No, my head is just getting huge now.
Thank you.
You mentioned that you originally pitched the game in June 2013, right?
Which a game that some of us may know came out around that time, The Last of Us.
I haven't heard of that. What's it about?
Yeah, it's very cool, very cool.
There are some, I mean obviously there's like a lot of similarities between the two,
even though both games stand on their own and they're very unique.
Were you worried at any point that people would draw the comparison
and whether there could be negatives to that or not?
I think a little bit.
There was a little part of me that said,
when I played that game, it was this sort of.
awakening moment, I think, for this industry.
Now, prior to this game, a lot of great games
have been doing very dark and very intense subject matter.
So it's not as if they were the first ones to do it.
I don't think they claim it either.
But they were the first ones to have a broad audience for this,
to show me, to show everybody else in the industry
that people wanted this kind of content.
that people actually were interested in something that challenged them emotionally.
And I thought, okay, this is the opportunity.
This is the opportunity now that people are actually claiming for content like this.
I did fear a little bit that people were going to make the comparisons and boy, howdy, was I right.
The first like year after the announcement was basically just like the
Last of Us of War and every other variation on that one.
Although I really did like all the gifs that
were created after we released, sort of making fun
of all of that.
But I think as we were developing,
we all realized that we were going
in a very different direction.
The two games are so, so very different.
But the fact that we were in close, we were personal,
and we were trying to tell this story about two characters
struggling to have a relationship,
you're never going to be able to escape that.
Right? That is the same way that, you know, many movies that have very high level concepts that are similar are always going to have the same comparisons.
But I think each thing sort of always stands on its own.
Right. Thank you.
Thank you. Yes, sir.
There are people in both.
Oh my gosh, sorry.
What's your favorite thing that you had to cuss or that got cussed?
What? My favorite thing that what?
What's your favorite, like, feature or thing that you had to cuss in order to get to this?
Oh, my favorite thing that I had to cut.
Does everybody remember the eagle in the background of Helheim?
Yeah, yeah, that one, there was,
that one was in all the way from the beginning.
When I had to write the story, the skeleton of the story,
I just added some eagle into the story
because I couldn't figure out how to end it
and I had to pitch the whole story to the team,
so I just threw something in there.
And I wanted to figure out a way to how to keep this eagle in
and the art director actually had fallen in love
with the eagle as well, so he was pushing
to put it in and animate it.
even when we had to cut it as a boss.
So we had to cut it as a boss,
we ran out of like so many bosses that we were planning,
we just had to cut because it takes so many people,
so much money, so much time to do one of these bosses
because we are crazy people, perfectionists,
and we wanna make them awesome and big.
And there was actually a moment.
where the eagle sort of randomly appeared
in one of the levels, like skunk work style.
So I was like, oh man, it's making a comeback.
And I think one of the producers had referred to it as,
oh man, that eagle is like a giant fuck you to production.
Right?
And I love everybody in production,
but I also really love that phrase.
That was hilarious.
Thank you.
Wait, over here.
No more?
Let's do one more, because I totally messed these guys up.
I skipped them, so there you go.
Hi, I was wondering about the E3 demo.
You were talking about how they tried to add bumpers
to make sure you try to mitigate the chances of failure.
What were some of those bumpers that were added?
They had situations where I wouldn't be able to do certain wrong moves in certain areas
so that if I enter a zone or an area they would make sure that the combo would click
the way that I needed to click it, but I still had to position properly and time each one
of those, but I couldn't accidentally suddenly pull out a special move or anything like that.
They had put some sort of invisible collision bumpers
that kind of helped me cutting corners or times
when I had to walk and rotate the camera.
So there's a lot of times where I was walking around
and I'd have to do these like really smooth camera sweeps
to kind of give people the feeling of, ah, so majestic.
So we found all these ways to kind of make it just
a little bit easier without automating anything
because we still wanted that feeling of, oh yeah,
it's actually me on the sticks doing this.
All right.
I think that's it, thank you, thank you.
Everyone's saying, the red shirts are saying we're done.