everyone to the, uh, first talk of board game design day.
Woo! Yep. Um, thank you for joining me at the, uh, crack of
10am, uh, to talk about Mansions of Madness. Uh, my name is
Andrew Fisher, uh, I'm the board and card game manager at Fantasy
Flight Games. Um, for those of you who aren't aware of us,
Fantasy Flight Games is a hobby market board game company. Uh,
we operate out of Minnesota here in the states.
Um, so I've been a designer for Fantasy Flight for about, uh, 7 years or so.
I've worked on the Star Wars role playing game, uh, I've worked on the Rune Wars miniatures
game, the Fallout board game, among many others.
Um, I was also the scenario designer on Mansions of Madness, which is what I'll be talking
about today.
Um, I also quick before I started the talk, just wanted to thank um, a few of my other
team members who helped contribute to this talk. Uh, the lead designer of the game, Nikki
Valens couldn't be here. Um, and also uh, a couple of our uh, scenario designers and ongoing
developers on the game, uh, Carl, Cara Sintel-Dunk and uh, uh, and uh, uh, uh, uh, and uh,
Grace Holdinghouse, as well as our primary programmer. We had a few different programmers
working on the game, but our primary programmer, Mark Jones, helped put together this talk, and
he's in the audience today. So I just wanted to thank them, because they were a huge help in
putting this all together. So to start us off... That's a good sign. There we go. All right.
Mansions of Madness, second edition.
This is a board game. We released it about two years ago. We are still releasing expansions and DLC for it today.
But I'll just be kind of talking about the core game development today and kind of the challenges at creating this kind of unique form of game that I'll talk about.
So quick, before we get started, I kind of wanted to do the standard GDC survey of how many people have played this game.
But first...
In our department we were kind of talking about, we were
curious about the attendance of board game design day. So I
just kind of wanted to get a sense of like, how many of you
work on digital games? Okay, so like the vast majority of you.
How many of you work on tabletop games? Alright, sweet.
Represent. Yeah, so and then finally I'll ask the standard
question, how many of you have played Mansions of Madness
second edition?
Alright, so a good number of you. Um, well for those who haven't, um, as it kinda says
in the title, Mansions is what we call an app integrated board game. Uh, you'll be excused
for maybe not quite knowing what that means because we kinda made it up. Uh, so what does
that mean? Um, well, you might be first be thinking about playing Settlers of Catan or
Ticket to Ride or something on your phone. Um,
But those are more like digital board games.
They're exclusive to that device.
You also might be thinking about supplemental apps
for the board games you've played,
like using an app to help out with your character
in Betrayal at House on the Hill,
or that cool voiceover app that comes with
One Night Ultimate Werewolf.
But those are just kind of supplemental.
You can play these games without these apps.
What are app-integrated games are?
are a game system that requires both the board game elements and the digital elements to
function. Um, ideally these are game systems that couldn't exist in the same form without
both elements. Um, we want to try to create, craft a unique experience that you couldn't
get quite any other way. Um, so what Mansions actually looks like in play, um, is...
You each play as a investigator in 1920s Arkham.
Arkham is this New England city in this world where all of the writings of H.P. Lovecraft are true.
And so you are looking into the, you know, the occult and the working of the elder gods
and kind of investigating these haunted mansions.
um, represented by these boards here. Uh, well, I shouldn't say
they're usually mansions. Some of our expansions, uh, go to
more exciting locales. But, um, usually you're exploring these
different mansions that we lay out in different ways with these
different modular map tiles. You move around the map, you roll
dice to, uh, um, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh,
figure out if you succeed or fail at different challenges,
you find items represented by cards,
and you make important decisions
that change the outcome of a branching narrative.
Each game of Mansions takes about two hours-ish to play,
depending on the scenario.
Um, and each play session of it is a self-contained experience.
At the end you'll have a story with an ending.
Um, this isn't really a campaign game, this is kind of, uh, each time you play is a self-contained
experience.
Um, all of the narrative in this, uh, board game is run by, um, the app.
Um, the app tracks, um, all of the narrative and enemies.
Basically, uh, it's kind of like...
If you're playing a role playing game where you're these investigators, the app is your
game master. It is taking care of all of those tasks for you. Um, usually, uh, we ship on a
lot of different platforms. Uh, it comes on phones, tablets, you can get it on Steam, on
the computer, and a lot of players actually, uh, we've seen online, uh, will put it up to
their TV so the whole group can kind of read it. Um, the actual game flow changes based on,
uh,
how people are interacting with it. Some people will just have
the phone and tablet and read it out loud to each other. Others
will pass it around. Others will all read it together on a
larger screen. So that's kind of the flow of the game is you're
reading from this app, exploring these mansions on the table.
Don't worry if you don't know the exact specifics of the game.
I'll kind of dive into and explain specifics as I use them
as examples. So today I'll be diving into the core
developments of this game. And then...
I'll be diving into the core development of this game and
then kind of going into a post-mortem kind of the
standard structure of five things that went well for us,
five things that went poorly for us, um, and kind of what
we learned from each of those, especially about integrating
tabletop and digital games together in the same dev cycle.
Um, I'm not necessarily going to cover them in that order,
I'm kind of going to cover them chronologically.
So with that, let's start at the beginning.
Um, so FFG has a long history of making great board games.
We've been making board games for over 20 years.
Um, we also have a media department who handles our, um, all of the supplemental
apps for our games, like dice rollers and such, and they've also, um, in the
last several years been making, um, some very successful standalone
games based on our board games.
Um, these kind of fall into that first category that I talked about. These are, um, tend to be adaptations.
They're not quite just ports of our board games to the digital space. They tend to be, they kind of tend to add to the game and, um, um, take the, the spirit of the game and put it onto, um, a digital platform.
Um, so we've had success in both, uh, in both realms. And then, uh, we actually have, uh, at this point, when we started Mansions of Madness, um, had already shipped,
one app integrated game, which was the Xcom board game.
In this game, you play as members of the Xcom organization
coordinating to save the world from aliens.
The app, uh, in this kind of encompasses a single mechanic. It shows you all the threats
coming down to the world in real time and, you know, the four of you have to sit there
and coordinate in real time answering these threats as the app spits them out at you.
And it can adjust the difficulty kind of based on how well or poorly you're doing as you
react to this app in real time. Um, but Mansions of Madness was on a whole different scale
from this game. So this was a much larger undertaking. Uh, the reason for this is in
Um, the split between kind of the day, the table top side of
things and the digital side of things, um, was pretty
unbalanced. Um, uh, in XCOM the vast majority of the game
mechanics, I could have gone on listing them, were all in the
table top side of things. Whereas the digital side just
mainly handled the real time, uh, execution of the threats.
Uh, so it was really just like a single mechanic in the game run by the digital side.
Um, obviously, you know, this project had its own travails, but it was on a much smaller
scale than Mansions was going to be and what we wanted to see from Mansions.
Um, so Mansions was a daunting task, but, uh, we got started right.
And that brings me to our, the first thing that went pretty well with our development,
which was that, uh, we prototyped early.
Uh, Nikki Valens and I, um, worked pretty early on the game and dove in pretty thoroughly
on our various prototypes to kind of see what apps were capable of, uh, in the realm of
board games and what players would, well, put up with.
Luckily we weren't starting from scratch. Uh, as, as you can see from the title of the
game, second edition, um, we are based on a first edition of the game. Uh, it's pretty
similar to the premise I already talked about, um, but instead of being a co-op game where
you're playing as investigators investigating this mystery, uh, it was what we call our
one ver- uh, one versus many game. So one player was kind of playing as the, all the
bad guys basically being your GM. Uh, this worked fine, but, um, it wasn't, you know,
as... it didn't quite fit the game experience we wanted out of Mansions of Madness. Mansions
was all about this kind of spooky storytelling atmosphere and when, you know, Mike is sitting
across the table from you, you know, playing all his cultists, it's just not quite as scary
as if, you know, it's this mystery coming out of the unknown.
Uh, so the one versus many wasn't quite working for the aesthetic we wanted to get across
for Mansions.
Um, additionally, first edition had an incredibly complex setup as you seeded, uh, you set up
the whole board ahead of time, you seeded out all the different, the narrative onto
the board and one little screw up could completely screw up your story for the whole two hour
play session.
Um, also it lacked a lot of discovery, uh, you know.
you can not read the cards ahead of time but in the end you're
getting all the content in the box. Um you can see everything
you're going to encounter in this mission. You set it up
beforehand. So it just didn't have that sense of discovery
that we wanted out of uh this game where you're, we wanted
this game where you open a door and you have no idea what's
going to be on the other side. But um it gave us a good
launching, a start, launching point for our prototyping. Um
we started by replicating first edition but adding an app kind
of in place of that one player. Um.
So at our very first step, we started by simulating the app.
We created these flowcharts, these state machines,
of the app's logic.
And we created massive, complex ones
to play out an entire two-hour scenario with players.
And then we would have the designer kind of pretend
to be the app in a playtest.
In fact, we went so far as to separate them
from the test to some degree.
Usually, one of us would sit with our back to, uh...
to the testers and just read off our flow charts and that way to disconnect ourselves
from the information on the table top and really get in the head space of like what
does this app know and what doesn't it know and how is the interface with the app and
the players. Um but in the end our app wasn't going to be speaking to them so the next step
of testing after we kind of iterated on this approach was to move to a grey box app.
Um luckily both Nikki and I have some coding experience and so we were able to uh write
some rudimentary scripts that kind of mimic the functionality we wanted to see in the
app um.
So we created this gray box that could play through an entire
scenario of mansions.
Primarily Nicky created it.
So we could code, but I don't actually think there's anything
horrible in this little screenshot I showed.
But you don't want to look too closely at our gray box.
It's pretty gross.
There's like go-to's and other things that I'm pretty sure
would make Mark over there cringe.
It was a bit of a nightmare, but it was functional and it gave us the testing we needed.
It allowed us to identify very early on before real development started what the strengths
and weaknesses of the tabletop elements and the digital elements were and kind of identify
those to help us while we were designing.
So we identified several key strengths and weaknesses here. I've just kind of showed, um,
some of the, the very broad strengths we identified. Um, I'll dive into them a little
deeper and some of the things that went well and poorly in development. But in general,
tabletop games, um, are really good at flexible effects and timings, at interrupting at any
point, at doing kind of weird incomparable effects. They also have a great tactical
interface for interacting.
um, for people to collaborate on a game very, very quickly and intuitively. Um, they also
have that social dynamic and we can actually do a lot of design around social interactions
at the table that you just can't quite mimic, um, in the digital space, I guess, yet. VR
is, you know, uh, doing some exciting stuff there, but, um, and then on the digital side
of things, um, the di- digital games tend to be much better at real time interactions.
They can handle that constant coming and going, whereas, like, when you're on the tabletop,
everybody's like, wait.
stop, uh, what does this card do? What does this wording mean? And all of that. Um, also
digital games excel at hidden information. Something that, uh, board games can often
struggle with. Um, and then lastly, digital games can handle a massive amount more
complexity than our tabletop games can.
So, after learning all these lessons and doing all this prototyping, we were ready to dive
into development proper. And this is when our tabletop team started working with the
media team. And naturally, these two teams worked perfectly together and the production
went off without a hitch. So, that's a lie. It was a bit of a mess. And that brings me
to the first thing that went wrong, and several other things that went wrong.
Tabletop designers and digital designers working together
was probably one of the biggest challenges of this product,
and we hit it right off the bat.
Some of you may recognize these icons.
The left there is waterfall management technique,
where everything's kind of in a line,
and the other one's agile.
Um, so, our tabletop, the tabletop side of things, by the necessities of, uh, printing,
require a certain amount of just linear scheduling.
Things need to be done by certain points to start being printed or produced or tooled
or whatever else.
Um, whereas our software team can be a lot more agile.
Um, and so we take, uh, two very different approaches and these immediately started colliding.
Um, uh, these teams had never really worked together before and these workflows really,
really clashed.
Um, yeah.
Um,
Transcribed by https://otter.ai
compounding this, this probably isn't super accurate. Uh, waterfall makes tabletop look way
too organized. This is probably more accurate. Um...
Well, uh, our tabletop teams are small and one of the strengths of them is how small
they are. That they can just turn around and chat with each other. They can innovate. You
know, you can just grab a card, change the text right away. It's that kind of mentality
that kind of leads and, and we allow our tabletop designers quite a bit of freedom so that they
can kind of innovate and, you know, make the changes to the game that the game needs. Uh,
this chaos isn't suited super well to them collaborating with our programmers. Um, and
a pretty big conflict for us. Additionally, this was one of the larger teams our company
had ever worked with. We tend to keep fairly small teams for our tabletop development.
And so we were scaling to a team size, working across departments. I know these are challenges
that a lot of you are probably pretty used to, but were pretty new to us. And so we struggled
with communication.
you know, just turning around and chatting in each other's
cubes wasn't really a good strategy anymore. We didn't have
like a centralized communication, uh, thing like, uh,
Slack or anything yet. Um, we didn't have centralized
documentation, we didn't have a middle man between the teams.
And so because of this, we were kind of relying on just word of
mouth and obviously this kind of hit a brick wall for us. Uh, we
eventually got over it, um, kind of early in development to, um,
uh... and improved but uh... one of the biggest steps we took was actually came from the
media team which was uh... the implementation of our tools uh...
originally you know it we were working with this gray box and it was a bit of a mess
and so uh...
yes
So the, a big breakthrough came for us at the discovery of
Playmaker. Playmaker, so we were using Unity. Um, we decided to
use Unity pretty early on. I think we used it for XCOM, is
that right, Mark? Yeah. Um, so, uh, we were using Unity and, but
the problem we were running into is our tabletop developers, uh,
us, we weren't great at coding. Um, and then we also wanted to
put developers on this pro, project who had never coded
before at all.
So this is going to be a big challenge for us and a big
challenge for communication and training and everything else.
But PlayMaker was something that we discovered.
Oh that's right, yep. So we have our gray box. Um, it, as I
mentioned earlier, it was a mess. It wasn't very scalable.
It wasn't really easy for non-programmers to, to learn
and it was just a mess to debug. Um, this line by line of go to's
just broke constantly and was a mess. So Playmaker is a plugin
for Unity that allows for visual scripting. Um, eh, allows for
creat-, the creation of state machines to, uh,
tracked a lot the flow of the game and it allowed for us, well it allowed for our media team to
create a encapsulated environment for our tabletop developers to work in so that they didn't have to
learn all the nitty gritty of Unity and could just focus on designing scenarios and focus on
the mechanics of the game.
uh playmaker was also pretty useful for us because it was
very modular um whereas with some of our other projects we
create very like specific infrastructures unit uh
playmaker allowed us to um build on it and actually we used it
for our next two app integrated games that came after mansions
of madness uh this is the road to legend app for our descent
board game and then the legends the alliance app for our
imperial assault board game both of these used that playmaker
back end that we originally developed for uh mansions
Um, so this ended up being great. It really helped with our communication
problems because we could train the developers to use this encapsulated
section of the game and, uh, er, of the dev development tools and work within
that, um, and allowed us as developers to focus on mechanics, which is where we
hit our next roadblock. Um...
So, those of you who know FFG know that we like to support our games.
We create a lot of content.
This is Arkham Horror 2nd edition, which I believe all the expansions, it's kind of spilling
off the photo there.
We release a lot of expansions for our games. We're constantly supporting and updating and
creating new and interesting ways to play these games. We need to create just a ton of content
and it needs to be novel and interesting for these tabletop players. It needs to play to those
tabletop strengths we talked about. And it needs to be compelling in person as you kind of play
the game with each other.
Additionally, as we're working on all these expansions, we're kind of looking ahead and
our media departments, our programmers, are going to be working on other projects.
They can't afford to constantly be supporting and expanding all the different app integrated
game lines we work on right now.
We need for the majority of the work for this to be done by tabletop developers.
Now this is a challenge with these kind of...
The mechanics that tabletop developers rely on to create interesting tabletop experiences
tend to have a couple of problems that clash with digital.
So as an example, let me show you just the test for Mansions of Madness.
Now a test is a moment that something challenges you in the game and you have to see if you
succeed or fail.
It's a pretty simple thing. All you really do is you roll some dice, you count up how many of a
certain type of symbol there are in the dice, and you get to have a chance to convert some of a
second type of symbol to the first type to improve your result. Um, and then you count them up, and
based on how many you get, you know whether you succeed or fail. It's a pretty straightforward
process, but upon going through all of the content we've made for mansions thus far, and
looking at all the different places in this relatively simple process that our content
interfaces with these rules.
we get this.
Um, now this is,
this looks messy, but from a tabletop
perspective, this is pretty straight forward. Um,
we have pretty solid timing rules that tell you exactly
when different things come up, um, and it creates some very interesting
effects and relationships that we couldn't otherwise
create. Um.
Obviously this can be a challenge for digital, uh, implementation because, so for example
if this test process is all in your app, we now need a user interrupt point at every single
one of these places.
The user needs to be able to specify if some content that we've created is interacting
with that test at that point.
Um, that's a huge challenge and it, it, you can see it in games like Magic, a pretty
sophisticated timing structure.
Um, I think their online implementation has done a really good job but they have this
same problem where they interface at all sorts of complex timings with their rule structure.
Additionally, the other kind of effect that we rely on a lot for development is these kind of in-person social effects.
We can do things, tactical things, with elements of the table, and of the componentry on the table, that are interesting in the rules.
We can do interesting social things, like this is an insanity that you can get in the game that causes you to not be able to speak, like in real life, for the rest of the game to your teammates.
Um, obviously things like this, uh, are a little more difficult to develop, uh, with
straight digital integration.
Um, an example, an example of this, um, is this actually pretty unique game by Harebrained
Schemes called Golem Arcana.
Um, so this is a miniatures game where you play, um, you control these different golems
on this grid and they fight and it uses this really interesting pen interface that links
to your phone and scans each of the models and keeps track of them throughout the game.
It's pretty cool, but as you can see, there's not a lot of componentry, which is a benefit,
but all of the game execution is happening on those apps.
So because of that, any time they want to develop new content, they need a programmer,
they need to script it into the game, and they're constrained by what the digital systems
can handle.
They can't kind of explore that freedom that we normally can with the tabletop space.
So because of that, the kind of lesson we learned from this challenge that we ran into
was kind of how to split up, divide mechanics between those two spaces of the game, between
that tabletop side and that digital side.
Um, we divided, we chose mechanics and divided them up pretty specifically into each space
and tried to be as uncompromising as possible about how often they crossed over between
those two.
Um, every time they crossed over it can create kind of a messy point.
Uh, for example in mansions, one of the things we didn't do so well was fire.
Uh, fire is represented by these little tokens, they go on the board, if you walk in them
they do you damage.
It's, it's pretty straightforward.
But we wanted things in the app to care about whether the mansion was on fire.
We wanted like monsters to care.
We wanted mythos events to care.
We wanted the fire to spread.
And all of this was handled by the app.
And so because of this, this simple little fire token was existing in both worlds.
And what ended up having to happen is if you go into the main menu of mansions while you're
playing, there's just a big old set fire button taking up one of our menu slots.
Because it was the only way we could...
get into the app that a fire had started through tabletop mechanics. So as you can see, that's
a pretty kludgy solution to this problem, but it's, it's immediately created by a mechanic
kind of straddling both sides. Um, so when we have mechanics that stay completely encapsulated
on one side, um, we avoid kind of those interfacing problems, which I'll talk about a bit later
as well. Um.
So the next thing, so once we divided those mechanics
between the tabletop and digital,
it allowed us to start really leveraging
the strengths of both sides.
And one of the places that really succeeded for us
was the ability to conceal complexity.
Remember Arkham from earlier?
This mess?
Our games get a little complex.
We like to create a lot of content
and keep our players,
receiving fresh new writing all the time and telling fresh new stories. Um, tabletop games
by necessity put this all up front. Think about walking up to this as a new player. You know,
you've just gone, gone over to your friend's house and they're like, no, no, it's going to be
easy, I swear. Now, behold, um...
It's, it's pretty intimidating. But Mansions is different. Mansions has even more content than
this in actuality. However, you don't see any of it. In fact, the players only know, really
know, need to know three things to play the game, which is our three actions. They need to be able
to know how to move around the board. They need to be able to attack monsters and they need,
need to be able to interact with tokens.
Um, so moving is pretty straightforward, you just take your figure and move it around the
board. So we don't really talk about that. But these other two fairly simple actions that are
just clicking on a monster and clicking on a point of interest in the app, um, are both far
more sophisticated, uh, than they originally seemed to a brand new player. Our attacks...
They're based on the weapon type you're using.
They can consider all sorts of factors.
They pull from based on the monster you're attacking.
They can pull from story relevant information.
They can consider all sorts of factors that are going on in the game itself.
All with a single push of a button.
Similarly, once you interact with a point of interest in the story.
Um, these are interacting with the state machines we put together with Playmaker. Um, when you
interact, you're getting story writing, you're making interesting choices about the branching
narrative, you're seeing the repercussions of your past choices, you're exploring new rooms
which place new tiles, you're managing the branching narrative, all of this is managed by
the app.
all at the push of a button with just a few selections by the players.
So it's taking this incredibly complex system and making it incredibly easy for new players to interface with.
And I think this approach has really shown in our reviews.
For those of you who aren't aware, there's this website called BoardGameGeek.
It's basically the IMDB of board games. It allows users to post all sorts of stuff.
It has all the information you need on board games.
And one of the things it has is a complexity rating for each game.
This is created by the users.
Now as you can see here, our original complexity rating for first edition was 3.24, and with
second edition, we reduced that by over 20% down to 2.65, all while having over a dozen,
like over 12 times the content that Mansion's first data had in that core box.
there's a downside that many of you probably have seen to this
and that it's we actually had to develop that complexity uh...
tabletop developers don't often get the chance to just
run wild we're really limited by
uh... the budgets on our
uh... printed components
you know we have x number of cards that we can afford to put in a box and that's
it
but now
the sky was the limit and our eyes got a little bigger than our stomach
in fact they got a lot bigger than our stomachs
So here is a sample of what we originally planned to put in the game. Um, so we originally
planned to have five of these branching scenarios for you to play. Each with what we, uh,
four what we call alt maps, which are basically, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh, uh,
kind of maps that we randomized some of our maps but these were
more sophisticated rebuilds of the maps placing them in
different locations and such. Um so that gave you 20 different
map significantly different maps to play on. We had 9 different
monster types with 5 attack types each. We had 6 types of
mythos events and we wanted like oh let's throw 2 dozen of each
mythos type into these 6 types. We had puzzles each with skins
um.
So as you can see, this is a pretty big list. But then on top of this, this game was coming out
fairly soon after the first edition of our game. And a lot of players were still playing that and
had just bought it. And we didn't want them to feel like that was invalidated. So the decision
was made to integrate and make compatible all of the first edition content. Which is awesome. It's
really exciting. You can use all your miniatures. But for us...
these numbers ballooned a bit. Uh, we added 3 extra alt maps,
uh, to each thing to use the first edition tiles. We added
all sorts of monsters, we added a whole new mythos type to fit
with these new types of tiles that were coming in. Um...
This got really out of hand. Dev ballooned out of control. Um, we ended up having to make a ton
of cuts to the final game from this planned content. Uh, the core game only had four
scenarios in it with a lot fewer alt maps and a lot of these, uh, attack types and events and
stuff we had to, had reduced variability early on in the game. Um, so we had to, uh,
because of how much bigger our eyes got than our stomachs.
Luckily, now that the game's been out for several years and we have a lot of expansions,
we've been able to fill out a lot of that variety by patching stuff into the game.
But at launch, we had to cut a lot of this content because of how much our development
was ballooning out of control.
Um, on top of all of this, this is all being created by tabletop developers who, as we
mentioned, aren't great at coding.
Um, we, we had a lot of bugs.
And um, our tabletop testers, they're not software QA people.
They, you know, uh,
don't have the skills necessary to hunt down and squash all of our bugs. So in fact, uh, our
media people, our, our small number of programmers ended up having to be the people who
were squashing a lot of the bugs created by tabletop people. Um, you know, we, we tried to
hunt down our own bugs, but we were only so good at it. So poor Mark over there had spent way
too much time squashing our bugs. Um...
these delays, all of that development delay, all of these
bugs added up. This project really went on a long time. Um,
in fact it went on so long that Road to Legend, which I
mentioned earlier, the next game to use this, this back end that
we developed here, actually came out before us. Um, so we, we
took a while. Um, so on top of all of this development
ballooning out of control...
Um, we discovered something on the mechanical side of things, um, in, in the game systems,
which was, um, our game had a serious lack of transparency.
What I mean by this was the players were having trouble knowing everything that was going
on.
We created all this complexity, we created all this interesting decision making, but
our players weren't seeing it.
Um, I think, upon reflection, I think a lot of this problem arises from the mediums, this
kind of difference of tabletop and digital that we've been talking about.
Um, tabletop games are transparent by default. Um, everything in a tabletop game, when you
take it out of the box, you can read it all. You can see everything. You have to understand
basically every rule in the game to start playing. Obviously that's not true. People
play Magic without reading the 140 page rule book or whatever. But, um, you need to have
a full understanding of the game to play for, for tabletop games. They start transparent.
Every mechanic is default transparent until you deliberately hide it from the players
and tell them to hide it.
Meanwhile, on the digital side of things, everything starts opaque.
You have a black screen until you add graphics, until you add UI elements, until you add sound.
Um, all, anything you want your players to know about what's in the digital side of things,
you have to deliberately put into the game.
Um, and so, you know, a lot of this, as we talked about, was being developed by tabletop
developers and so, uh, they weren't used to having to put all of this, uh, transparency
into their game.
And so, one of the issues we ran into with Mansions is that our primary interface were
these text boxes.
As you can see, the UI is pretty sparse otherwise.
But we have a lot of sophisticated information about how these scenarios are running that
we want to communicate to the player.
Um, so all of that information ended up having to come across in these text boxes.
Um, as a result we ended up spending a lot of time in these scenarios that we kind of
wish we could have been, uh, telling stories.
We had to spend explaining to them how the game worked and explaining to them how the
game worked again and again and again.
A lot of our scenarios get pretty bogged down with just mechanical text as a result.
Um.
We learned from this in our later iterations like here is the imperial assault app, Legends
of the Alliance.
We learned from it, we put a lot of our information front and center.
You have a lot more sophisticated information up front that allows you to kind of see what's
going on and these are a lot of things that in mansions we may have had to give you text
notifications about.
But
in Mansions it was a pretty big challenge for us. But it ended up being something we learned a lot
about for making these kinds of games in the future, which is that when you're separating
the mechanics between the tabletop side and the digital side and being uncompromising about how
often they cross over, one of the great ways to decide, beyond those strengths we talked about
earlier, to decide, uh...
which side a mechanic would probably be strongest in is based on the opacity of that mechanic.
Is this something that should be hidden to the player by default? Then it probably belongs in
the digital side of your game. It'll be a lot less work to work on that mechanic. Is this something
that's transparent by default? You might want it on the tabletop side of your game because the
player's going to see all of it right at the start.
And once we got a handle on this difference, and what it meant to us, and on how opaque digital games can be,
this opacity was actually super useful to us.
One of the biggest strengths of Mansions, in the end, and one of the things fans love about it,
is the sense of discovery it gets.
As I mentioned, everything in a tabletop game starts out very transparent to the player.
Um, but we could hide things from the players. We could truly surprise them. We could allow
them to interact with hidden information in really sophisticated ways. Um, and it also
allowed for really strengthened replayability. As you saw in the component list, we only
had four scenarios, so we wanted people to be able to play these a lot. And in fact, um, I'm
gonna give an example from the game. So minor spoilers for, uh, the very first scenario.
It's called Cycle of Eternity.
Um, here are some of our Unity analytics. On cycle. Um, these are the number of people who
have played each of our scenarios. Uh, as you can see, COE over on the right. That's cycle of
eternity.
It gets played a lot.
It's kind of our default learning scenario, so it's a lot of people's entry points to
the game.
You know, you've played it a couple times, but you have that friend over who has never
played Mansions before.
All right, well, we'll play Cycle again, because Cycle's a good intro.
And so game groups will play Cycle over and over again, because it, as they bring new
people into the game.
So, it's also our learning scenario, and so it's a lot simpler and shorter than a lot
of others, so it lacked that variance that a lot of our other scenarios get.
So in it, we actually got a really cool opportunity to kind of surprise people a bit.
So actually, the picture I've been showing is from Cycle of Eternity.
This is the Vanderbilt estate you are...
investigating the mysterious William Vanderbilt.
You arrive at the mansion and you meet his befuddled but kindly butler Eugene.
He's worried that something's going on with his master.
And the spoiler is William Vanderbilt's a cultist.
He's worshipping an elder god because everybody does in this setting.
And he's trying to open a portal or something evil.
So that's how the game played out most of the time.
You help Eugene helps you.
You find William Vanderbilt and you foil his plans.
But we realized that we kind of wanted
to surprise these players who were playing
the scenario so many times.
So we added a random roll at the beginning of the game
that determined a kind of Easter egg variance,
maybe like one in every 10 times.
Two seconds.
Um, we added this random variant in where one out of every ten times, uh, you get to
the big finale and William Vanderbilt is completely innocent and it turns out that his butler
Eugene has been evil the entire time.
Um, and so this was a really awesome cute surprise for players.
People would talk about it on our forums, talk about, you know, totally Eugene was evil
and people would be like, I've played this scenario like ten times and Eugene was never
evil, you're crazy.
Um, this is something...
You know, it's a cute little thing.
You know, a lot of digital games could do it really easily, but in tabletop, it's nearly
impossible to surprise players like this and to truly give them that sense.
This is one example, but the game is full of this little sense of discovery.
We have maps where we keep most of the map the same, so you think you've seen it before
and then you open a door and a room's different.
There's all these little things that we can kind of hide from the players.
and uh, kind of give them these surprises. Additionally, as I
mentioned, uh, this game branches a lot. Um, and this
also gives kind of players the ability to kind of discover
what we've created. Um, this is obviously an oversimplification,
but our main plots will kind of branch out from different nodes
to different possibilities, um, ending in different things. Um,
so this gives you some replayability. Um, you know, you
can play through the scenario a couple times before you feel
like you've seen it all, but then in every scenario, in
addition to these main plots.
we try to kind of weave in various side plots that are entirely independent and can kind of go
one way or the other and so ideally by the time you multiply out three or four side plots in
combination with the main plot going on with you know four different players playing
investigators they've never played before you kind of get this interesting emergent
combination that you've never seen before and so it allows for each scenario to play very
differently and it's something that we've been pretty happy with. Additionally...
We added on an extra layer of randomness onto this to kind of give you that variance play
to play which was our mythos events.
I touched on them a little earlier but basically they're just random horrible things that can
happen to the investigators as they play.
And as you saw we developed a lot of them and now there's really a lot of them.
We have hundreds of these things.
Um, and we put all sorts of different writers on. We grab people from the, throughout the
studio to write mythos events. They're actually quite fun, um, and these mythos events, they
pull from this random, uh, this massive list, but we tie specific conditions to each one. So
things like what rooms are in...
things that the app knows, what rooms are in the game right now, what choices have the
players made, what monsters are on the table, what items are on the table. Um, we also have
this threat system which is kind of like the director from Left 4 Dead in the sense that
it knows how well or poorly the players are doing and can kind of ramp up or ramp down
the threat to kind of keep the pacing interesting for them. Um, mostly using these mythos events.
Um.
Right.
Yeah.
Um.
Right.
Uh.
Left.
Right.
That's what's it's all about.
Um.
Right.
And so we developed this system, and this has also worked out great for us,
but it caused us to make an interesting discovery
which is that we don't really see in tabletop games that often,
which is players create intent out of randomness.
we spent all this time linking these events to like, you know, make them feel like they had
meaning in a scenario. But players will ascribe meaning to the most random things. Um, in
tabletop, they always know that's random. You know, they roll the die, they draw the card,
they know that that was completely random chance and that nothing else fed into it.
But in the digital side, because of that assumed opacity,
the players' imaginations run wild.
They think that that mythos event coming up
means something in the story.
They think that, oh, this is based on my choice from earlier.
They create all this meaning that we just,
it's nearly impossible for us to create in a tabletop space
because of how clear that is to the players.
And I think my favorite example
of kind of using the players' hypothesizing is
So when the director, when our threat system is low and it's
it's giving them kind of a reprieve, we'll give them some
flavor text and we'll say, uh, know it like, you know, uh, the
wind, uh, whistles through the, uh, through, in the mansion
creeks. No effect. Right? This is fine. Player's new, no
effect. Okay, we got a break for the round. Um, but that didn't
quite work for our Lovecrafty horror theme. So with one si-
simple word, we changed no effect to no immediate effect.
This was amazing.
Players get so mad about no immediate effect.
They hypothesize about what that could mean.
When they make a choice and it just pops out no immediate
effect, they're like, what's going to happen?
This added to that sense of dread that we wanted in a
Lovecraft game.
And so we kind of played to that strength of the digital
side and that opacity.
And that turned out great for us.
Another example of this to kind of go to another app integrated game that uses hidden
information in the digital side really well is this game called Alchemist. This is kind of a
cool game. So it's a deduction game like Clue. But instead of
there being like a murder mystery, there are alchemical formulas that you need to know.
There are all sorts of ingredients in the game. You can kind of see them, they're the cards
perched near the top of the little dividers. And each one has like elemental principles tied to
them and based on how those elements combine they form potions.
But you don't know which elements are tied to which components every time you play.
And so you just have to experiment by mashing these components together and making potions
and maybe blowing yourself up until you figure out the deduction puzzle.
This game is cool because its app does something that Clue never could, which is in Clue, the
moment you check the file to see if you're right, the game is over for you.
you've seen that hidden information and you've ruined the game for you but the app allows us to
check against that hidden information in really sophisticated ways. So in alchemists it can
constantly every time you uh use that you use those components it's checking against that hidden
information and giving you an output based on that. Um that's something that a tabletop game
can't do without a dedicated player who's basically playing the system.
And that's how Alchemist gets around it if you don't have an app, is they have a role for
somebody who just sits there and tells you what happens with your potions, but the app
allows that player to be able to play the game instead, which is really nice.
So back to mansions.
So we, you know, we went through these trials and travails and, um, finally, after all this
hard work, we're getting to the end of the game.
Uh, we're reaching the end of development, which for tabletop games still means there's
like nine months before it actually, uh, is on store shelves, but, uh, we're reaching
the end and it's time to announce the game.
And unfortunately this was another road bump for it, which was...
announcement was a little rocky. Um public reaction wasn't great. Uh when we first
announced it um there was a lot of skepticism about the app integrated format. Uh we saw a
little bit of this at with Xcom as well but when we were taking some first ed game that was
exclusively um
that was exclusively tabletop and making it app integrated.
Um, there's a lot of resistance to this. Um, people were concerned about
will my platform be supported? Will I be able to play it on X or Y?
Um, will this game, uh, be able to be playable in twenty years with my
grandchildren or whatever else?
Um, you know,
I won't be able to play this board game after the nuclear apocalypse or whatever
else. Um,
this app is going to be a hassle.
So there was a lot of skepticism but we were really confident in the product. We really
liked the game and so we were confident that when it launched people would like the game.
But then our launch came and our launch was really buggy.
All those bugs I mentioned earlier, it turns out we didn't manage to squash them all.
And we had a lot of stability issues at launch.
You can see here, this is a super unofficial poll from BoardGameGeek.
On certain platforms, certain scenarios crashed fatally, like a third of the time.
we had a bunch of annoying, and this is on top of a bunch of annoying small bugs that were also
plaguing users constantly. To our programmers credit, they got on it super fast. And like
after a week or two of panic we had gotten the build a lot more stable, but this kind of
strengthened those original skepticisms about the app integrated format and that was a pretty
uh, rocky place for us. Um, I think the main takeaway from a lot, reading a lot of, um,
people's skepticism though is, uh, ties into my last point, which is, um, why is the app
worth the hassle? This sentiment is something that we saw kind of over and over again, like,
why not just make this a tabletop game? Why not, don't just make this a digital game?
Why go through this pain in the ass to combine these two formats when I could just get one
of the other? Um.
And so I think our last lesson and something that went really right with the game.
is knowing the answer to this question and that the app needs
to be justified.
Its inclusion needs to be justified.
I think I've talked a bit about some of the things
that the app has done for us.
We feel like it's worth it.
So what's the last element here?
Well, what is the hassle of the app?
Some people might say, oh, it's pretty easy to use.
There is no hassle.
But let's talk a bit about the hassle and minimizing it,
because I think it's something we did pretty well.
Um, so this is something I think I just kind of started using this term interfacing, but
basically this is the concept of any time your system has to cross over from the tabletop
to the app, or from the app to the tabletop, any time those two sides of the system need
to interface with each other.
Um, this can be done in myriad ways, but, uh, you know, like with audio cues, with text,
with tapping, with camera, um, some much more expensive than others.
but this needs to be done in some way because we've so
strictly divided our mechanics between the two sides of the
system and they're not aware of each other. Um, so in
mansions, uh, the mansion, the app, it knows your story really
well. It knows where you're at. Um.
But it has no idea where the characters are on the map.
That's entirely on the tabletop.
It doesn't know where features are.
It doesn't know where the items have ended up.
It doesn't know where the monsters are.
All of that gameplay is happening on your table.
The app is just controlling a lot of the other aspects.
And so anytime the app needs to know that,
you need to be inputting into the app.
And also, you don't know the story.
Anytime the app needs to tell you story
or where to place tiles, it's outputting that information
to you.
And the problem with this is that any time a player spends
interfacing with the app at the table with other people is, uh,
time away from the game. Yeah, I like that, that's a picture
from Netrunner. Um, uh.
all that time interfacing detracts from that tabletop experience. It's viewed by the players
as work and hassle. Every moment that, you know, um, your friend over there is sitting
with their face in the phone waiting to see what will come out of it, um, is just kind of
viewed as wasted time. Um...
Now there's many innovative ways kind of around this.
You know, Alchemists that I showed earlier
uses image recognition to view the components.
This game here, World of Yoho by Yelo is pretty cool.
The game mat has spaces that are roughly the size of phones.
And the phones actually show the board through them
and you place them on the map.
And actually it works pretty well.
They use the accelerometer in the phone
to track where you've moved it around the map
so it's constantly showing the right part of the map
and it can kind of reveal encounters and stuff.
So it kind of gets that interfacing out of the way by directly integrating the phone into the game, which is pretty neat.
We didn't really have that option. The stories we want to tell are pretty sophisticated,
so we rely a lot on text. We have some narration,
but we couldn't afford to narrate all of that mountain of content we wanted to do.
And so,
the question...
Um, the question that helped us the most when we were kind of working on this, as we're
playing the game, asking yourself, uh, am I doing the work for the app or is the app
doing the work for me?
Um, this is, this gets down to the heart of the hassle.
Do they feel like interacting with that app is a drain on their time?
Um.
So when you're inputting, when you're doing that kind of stuff, it's going to be viewed
as you doing work for the app.
Whereas like when you're getting something out of the app, suddenly it feels like this
is a benefit, a boon to the game.
Here's an example.
Road to Legend, which was the follow-up to Mansions, based on Descent.
Because it was based on Descent...
each player activating mattered and when they activated mattered in descent. And so because of
that, um, you can see over on the left there, every time you activated, you needed to click
and turn on your own turn for all four players every round. Um...
seems simple, it's like two taps, right? But this really drained on the players, they had to
remember to do this, they had to keep that in their mind, they had to be passing around the
phone to do this on the phone. Um, this, this is kind of like that player at the table you need
to constantly be reminding to take their turn, you're constantly reminding that app to take
its turn. Um, and that was, that was viewed as real drain on the players.
Um, contrast that with mansions, every time you're clicking on one of these nodes, we're
giving you story, we're giving you rewards, we're giving you choices, um, we're giving
you stuff.
Uh, players never responded negatively to interacting with nodes on the app.
They were excited, they wanted to see what was coming next.
Um, so the way we, but the problem is, as I mentioned, the Mansions app doesn't know
a lot of things about what the players are doing.
So what we tried to do is we tried to take this rewarding experience of getting something
out of the app and harvest as much information from it as we possibly could.
So when players are interacting with the app and getting stuff out, we try to look for
every piece of information this gives us.
when somebody interacts with an app we know that investigator is
on that space cause they have to be in that space to interact
with it. We know when they interacted with it, we know how
well they did, we know the amount of damage we've given out
to them, we know the amount, how close they are to losing the
game. Um, so we kind of use these things that players view
as beneficial to get just enough information to make the app seem
informed about what's going on on the table. Um, but I think
there's a long way to go.
in interfacing. I think we've succeeded pretty well in mansions, but I think it's one of the
places that these kind of hybrid games can innovate the most. Image recognition and other
such technologies are going to allow us to kind of bridge this interfacing gap and make this feel
like less of a hassle to players. In the end, I think...
Mansions went pretty well.
Despite, it may sound like Loom and Doom
after I talked about the rocky reception,
but actually after that initial bump,
we got those bugs fixed and the game got great reviews.
It's quite beloved and it's been going on
with its expansions now for several years
and it's doing incredibly well for us.
So I think the big takeaways from Mansions development.
were obviously to prototype early, to prototype thoroughly, before you start development.
Use that prototyping to be wary of scope and to plan your scope carefully.
And then with
when you're developing for both tabletop and digital simultaneously, um, consider how you're
gonna divide the mechanics between the two mediums and be pretty strict about that division.
Um, consider the flexibility of your timing versus the desire for real time interaction.
Um, consider the opacity of the mechanic and how it's used by the players.
Consider the interfacing and like if you want it to be shared
and tactical and do you want to have social elements in this
mechanic, for a given mechanic before you decide which side to
put it on. And finally make each interface with the app worth the
hassle for the players. So that's it. Thank you very much.
Uh, remember to fill out your evaluations, um, and I think I have time for like a question or
two. Oh, yeah, walk up to the mic.
Hey, great job. Um, I just wanted to ask, uh, do you have any thoughts like on specific game
mechanics that could leverage, you know, augmented reality, things like ARKit and ARCore for
tabletop games?
Oh yeah, I mean like AR is something that we've talked about a lot. It could be really cool.
One of the things I think we think could be coolest about it is the ability, that kind of
hidden information and overlapping asymmetrical information for different players sitting
around the same table. So AR would allow an overlay of information over a board game so
that different players knew different things about what's going on there. And like gave you
that really open interface to the game.
through AR while also maintaining that really strong
asymmetry. Obviously this is something, the technology is a
little far out for us to work on it or anything but I think it
could be the potential there is really cool.
Thanks a lot.
I have a question, like you mentioned this interfacing issue between the distance that
was made between the app and the players.
Have you ever thought while developing Mentions of Madness about reading out the text loud,
I mean using any voice over or kind of this kind of possibility to...
make the game better? Yeah, definitely. Oh, I just remembered I'm supposed to repeat the
questions after people say them. I forgot to do that for the first one. Um, yeah, so the
question was, uh, have we considered doing voiceovers or narration? Um, so we originally
had wanted to do narration for nearly all the text.
Obviously, that proved prohibitively expensive.
And we talked a bit internally about, like, oh, it would be cool to like Microsoft Sam,
all this text.
But one of the things we're really going for with mansions is the atmosphere.
And at the time, they
there was no real like automated reading of that text that kind of got across a Lovecraftian feel
that we were really happy with. So we opted to just have the players read it at the table.
Also, often players reading the text together at the table can kind of be this bonding and
joking experience that has actually added to the game quite a bit. So we probably have no
intention to put anything like that in the game, I imagine. Thank you.
A great talk.
Just wondering, when you were developing the app and the
game, were you considering any sort of accessibility issues,
like in terms of the text and the speed of the text and the
colors and various other things?
Yeah, so accessibility definitely came up.
Oh yeah, so the question was, did we consider accessibility
while developing this app?
And yeah, accessibility definitely came up.
It is something that my department in board and card
is very concerned about.
we wanted to help people with. Um we definitely had to make some sacrifices um just to get
the app working. It was something we were pretty inexperienced with um but like app
contrast um scalability and stuff is definitely something we considered during development.
Did you look at those old games from the late 70s and early 80s where the technical limitations
were so big, like Odyssey 2 for example, so that you had those board game things too,
to broaden the scope of the video game?
Did you look at those interactions between analog and digital?
Yeah, so the question was, did we look at those old games from like the 70s and the 80s that
used kind of the crossover of technology? Yeah, so we, uh, what's the name of that one?
Oh crap, I'm blanking on the name, but we, we, we, huh? Oh yeah, yeah. Um, we, we, we
brought a few into the office, um, and we're playing them. It was, it was, it was a lot of fun.
A couple of them had been sitting in people's basements and didn't really work that well,
but we definitely checked out several of those and kind of talked about that.
Another kind of inspiration for this kind of game was old school adventure games and
kind of like those FMV mysteries and stuff too.
Alright, cool. So I think that we have to wrap that up there. Um, but if anybody else has
any other questions, I'll be in the wrap up area for a little bit, so feel free to come by and
talk. So thank you everyone.