Thank you for coming to our session.
I'm Sid Meier.
This is Bruce Shelley.
Thank you.
And we're gonna take you back in time to 1990,
a time when there was no civilization,
a time before civilization.
and kind of talk about the process that Bruce and I went
through to create this game called Civilization.
And we will get to our next slide here somehow or not.
There we go.
So, the approach we want to take is kind of talk about the thought process that we went through
to create the game. With the hindsight of 25 years, a lot of things that we did seemed to be the
right thing to do. Some of the things we did turned out to be the wrong thing to do. But we
would like to justify even the wrong things, explain why we did them that way, and what we
were thinking at the time. It was kind of a...
audacious game for us to make.
And the idea that we were gonna kind of compress
the entire history of civilization into a computer game,
not only the actual history, but every possible history
that could have happened of civilization,
we were trying to put into this game.
It was a time when we were young and audacious.
And we had just finished Railroad Tycoon,
which is kind of the first God game that we worked on.
We were working on Covert Action,
which was an attempt to write
a computer-generated mystery novel.
Didn't quite turn out that way,
but that was kind of our goal at the beginning.
We had just finished Pirates,
which was one of the very first open-world kind of games.
So it was a time when we were
We thought we could do anything and sure,
let's take on the history of civilization
and make a game out of that.
Both Bruce and I are kind of interested in history
and have a background in war gaming and other things
which kind of ended up showing up
in the game of civilization.
But the way that I remember the,
for those of you that are not familiar with civilization,
it's the game about world history, okay.
It starts in the Stone Age and you end up by going to Alpha Centauri, taking humanity
into space.
6,000 years of human history.
in 640K.
So the, as I remember the story, Bruce and I were,
I remember us riding on a train up to New York, I think,
and we had recently completed Railroad Tycoon,
and really enjoyed that experience,
that kind of God game-ish, start with something small,
build it.
Use your own creativity to basically tell a different story every time you play.
The idea of different systems kind of working together, the operation of the railroads,
the building of the railroads, the financing of the railroads,
maintaining your locomotives, routing your trains,
lots of fun little pieces that kind of came together to make a lot of interesting decisions.
And we were looking for another topic that would have those
kind of qualities to it.
And somehow we thought, well, history has a lot of that
going on.
And it's kind of the ultimate God game, starting with one
little village back in 4000 BC and seeing how far we could go
with it.
That's how I remember it. I'm not sure Bruce how you remember it.
I just remember we talked a lot about that kind of stuff.
Sid always had like a half a dozen prototypes on his computer. He was always noodling a new game idea, you know
And now we look at it. He'd we talk about it. Maybe he's something he wouldn't tell me about it. Then I remember
These conversations went on we played a lot of
Empire deluxe and we talked about you gave me a task to come up with ten things
I would change about Empire deluxe if I could change anything and trying to be a progressive person
I came up with 12 and gave him the list and
and and then one day
a disc pops into my desk, and I have it at home.
It's a five and a quarter inch floppy disc from May of 1990,
and it's the first playable version of Civilization
anybody had ever seen other than his computer.
I saved this as a historic artifact.
I hadn't saved the first version of Railroad Deck,
and I determined to save whatever was coming down
the pipe next, I'd save the first version.
So that's my memory.
We had played all these other games,
and then this came together enough for you to feel
that it was good enough for somebody else to look at.
Yeah, I think we need to give credit to Empire as part of the inspiration for Civ, also SimCity,
also Railroad Tycoon.
There's also a board game actually called Civilization that was out there at the time.
We played that.
Francis Trusham designed it in England and Avalon Hill had published an American version
of it.
We stirred all those ingredients together.
We're going to claim that the topic was one of the things we
did right in Civilization, that it was a good topic.
It really lent itself to the kind of games we wanted to
make and the place we were with the technology.
in those games.
And also it had a huge potential audience.
I mean, one of my talking points over the years has been
when you start a project, your potential customer
is everybody who has the platform that game is gonna be on.
But as soon as you make decisions about what that game is about,
you start to shrink your potential audience.
Well, the history of civilization is a pretty big topic,
so we had a huge potential audience.
Remember, later on when Sid gave the first presentation
I ever heard about game design.
He, one of his topic points was choose a big topic.
I said, I think we'd already made Civilization
by that time, I'm not sure, but I said,
well, there can't be a bigger one
than the history of Civilization.
Yeah, we talk about trying to make games epic.
The fact that it really doesn't cost any more
to make a game epic than to make it non-epic.
So the next thing that we kind of had to figure out
was how are we gonna approach this topic?
Obviously there could be many, many different games
written on the topic of civilization.
So how are we gonna approach this?
One of the ideas that really, I think, paid off for us
was the idea of starting very small
with that first settler, that first city.
The topic could be intimidating.
So I think allowing you to start with a very simple problem,
very simple situation, founding that first city,
that led to something else, the first settler,
the first unit, exploring.
So that was one of the ideas that we had
in terms of the tone and the approach.
Another one was to, there's a strange mixture to me
in looking back at Civ I of humor,
and incredible seriousness.
Like some parts of it, you know,
here's the lions defeat gladiators, seven to nothing.
You know, that was our attempt at humor.
Our little friend Elvis here in our city screen.
So there are ways that we wanted to make
the history of civilization kind of non-intimidating
and friendly.
But then again, there's the Civilopedia,
where we have an entry here, you know,
trying to make this game feel deep and important
and something that you should have your kids
and your parents play.
And so we were really trying to figure this out
as we went along, and there were no...
civilization games before us to guide us as to what we should do. So we kind of dipped our toe in a lot of different areas.
But the bottom line to me, I think, and Bruce, maybe you have a thought about this, is that the game was fun to play when we started.
And as long as that was true, I think we felt we were on the right track, whether our jokes were lame or not.
The game was fun, and I think that kind of what kept us going at the end.
I think we learned the idea that,
I come up with this term called
the inverted pyramid of decision making,
where the game starts with one little
settler unit on the board,
and you have a decision,
what direction that person, that unit moves.
And quickly you've got cities and more units,
and the number of decisions you have,
your choices go up like this.
I called it the inverted pyramid of decision making.
Now years later, I came up with the idea
that you had 15 minutes at that time
to engage someone in your game,
otherwise you might lose them and they'd be gone.
I think today we'd face a situation
where you have two or three minutes
to get somebody interested in a game today,
but then we had more time, and I thought we did.
I think we borrowed from other guys,
or like Empire Deluxe,
you started with just something simpler and it grew.
We captured that same sense, I think,
and I think that was a good, we did that well.
Or you did that well, let's say.
Yeah, I think our gift was to know what to steal from other games.
Yeah, how much to borrow and how much to invent yourself.
So
Was this a good, did we do this right or wrong?
I think the jury is still out.
When you look at how the Civilization series has evolved,
humor has not necessarily been a big part
of the succeeding Civ games,
but it was really an indication
of kind of how unsure we were about.
Was this game going to be taken seriously by players,
or was it something we needed to really kind of lighten up
and make more accessible in that way?
I think we found a good balance. I mean, I felt good about it.
One little point I made a note of is that I think we did a good job
of telling the players that he or she was doing a good job.
We loved the King Day parades, and there was other notices,
the newspaper reports, and...
That was all the ways that we were telling the player,
you're doing great, keep going, you're super,
you're doing a great job as king of this country.
I think we did that well.
I think that's always a question in games as you're playing,
am I doing the right thing?
Am I on the right track?
Have I spent the last hour or two wasting my time?
Giving the player those constant indications
that this is progress, this is the right thing to do,
or we're watching, we're appreciating what you're doing,
is encouraging to the player to allow them to keep going.
One thing that I guess in hindsight seems so obvious,
but we really could not call this game Civilization
as it was in development.
That was kind of our code name,
that was our internal name,
but our assumption was that this game
would not be called Civilization
because there was a board game out there
called Civilization, it was owned by Avalon Hill,
which was another computer game
publishing company at the time.
And the game had originally been designed in England.
So we were trying to come up with alternative names.
And I don't remember.
Call to Power, Rise of Nations, Age of Empires,
you know, names like that.
But we said, you know, the only appropriate name
for this game is Civilization.
So our intrepid.
marketing team went to talk to Avalon Hill, and amazingly enough, they were able to work
out an arrangement there. I think Avalon Hill was maybe withdrawing somewhat from the computer
side of things at the time, and we were able to get the name to Civilization, which I think
is actually a pretty significant part of the success of the game. When you look back at
the games that we've done...
Pirates, exclamation point, railroad tycoon.
I mean, it's those names that kind of create a picture
in your mind almost immediately of what the game might be
that helped them to be successful.
And I also actually credit this image
that one of our marketing people was able to find.
This was not created for the game.
It was actually found.
But it captures, again, the potential, the possibilities
of what your game experience is going to be.
The other point that I'll make is that our game did not really
duplicate the board game?
I get that question fairly often.
The board game was limited to a specific geographic area and a
specific era of time.
There were some cool ideas in there, but I think we added a
few of our own as we went along.
But this, I think, was a huge win for us to be able to use
the name Civilization for the game that we were making.
Okay, here we go.
This is the, kind of the classic.
perception of Civ is that it is the turn-based game. The
turn-based-ishness is at the heart of Civilization. And
interestingly enough, the first version of the game, probably
the one that Bruce has the disc of, was not turn-based. It was
more of a SimCity
zone this area for farms, zone this area for,
kind of watch things evolve over time.
And it was really when we switched over
to a turn-based mode that the game came together.
At that point, the player became totally engaged in what was happening, but was given enough
time to really consider the implications of what they were doing.
They had, could project into the future.
What I like to think about Civilization is it's a game where you are always, your mind
is always ahead of the game.
You're always anticipating.
What's going to happen next you have a couple of things a wonder being built over here. You're exploring this continent over here
You've always got a couple things going on that you're looking towards and that
You know that kind of feeds into that one more turn or that one more technology or one more
You're always kind of leaning forward into the future.
Very interesting, of course Bruce went on to Ensemble
to create Age of Empires there, which was turn-based,
I mean it was real-time.
In my mind, the reason those games are so different
is almost solely based on the fact that one is turn-based
and one is real-time.
Bruce, do you have anything to say about that?
Well, Age of Empires was like five or six years later,
and the world had changed a little bit.
The strategy games, you know, there had been Command
and Conquer had been published, and Warcraft had been
published, and these were real-time strategy games,
and they were.
Extremely successful and so my my colleagues and I were we wanted we needed to do something different
We but we love civilization, but we want to do something different. We said can we do civilization in real time?
What would that be like? Would that be it'd be different enough?
It wouldn't be you know be borrowing but we wouldn't be borrowing everything
It would be different enough to be a new a new product and it turned out it was I mean it was more than just
real time but at real time
Also, our games were played in like an hour.
Age of Empires was an hour, half hour experience,
where Civilization was a different,
longer experience usually.
So we're trying to adjust to the marketplace
and take advantage of things that had changed.
I think it's nice that both games existed
and did really well.
And we also did other things too.
We telescoped our time period.
Age one was just Ancients and then age two was.
was the knights and castles, which was the sweet spot,
really turned out.
But yeah, it was certainly influenced.
The vision for Age was let's take civilization,
move it into real-time strategy and historical framework,
and that was the vision.
Yeah, it just strikes me that a lot of the differences are based on that, that you can't play a
real-time game for 20 hours. It would be too intense. And by the same token, a turn-based
game that lasted 30 minutes or so, again, would not really be satisfying.
It's, I think this issue of turn-based versus real-time
has so many implications in terms of where the games go,
again, given the similar subject matter.
So, it was not, we did not realize at the time
that we had made this pretty significant switch
and the whole one more turn phenomenon.
had not really occurred to us. It's something that just arose
out of the development of the game. Looking back it seems to
be so characteristic of Civ, but it was a way of just getting you
closer to the action and getting you more involved in what was
happening. At the same time giving you enough time to
consider your decisions.
Really allowing us to do things like the tech tree and diplomacy, all the different things that you take some time to do in the game.
We're really based on this fact that we switched over to a turn-based mode.
Probably it was fairly uncommon in games of that time, I'd have to say.
A lot of our background was in wargaming, which is clearly turn-based or movement-based or player-time-scale based.
And that probably influenced a lot of what we did there, but at the time it was fairly different from what was going on there.
As well as the fact that...
The whole idea of doing a strategy game was kind of unique at that time.
And there were a few games out there, but strategy games were generally considered
slow-moving, boring, nerd-oriented, and setting up a bunch of counters on a map.
And it was not something that computers were supposed to be
fun for computer game players.
And the irony for us was that within a couple years,
everything was a strategy game.
It was a real-time strategy game.
It was a space-based strategy game.
So we claimed to have made the world safe
for strategy gaming by making associations.
We had to fight battles inside the company, too.
I mean, the company wasn't too excited about it.
They wanted more flight sims and things like that.
doing a turn-based strategy game was not
enthusiastically embraced by the management of the company.
It was a revolutionary concept at the time.
Until it started to sell and the critical reviews
started coming in, then they were real happy.
They want another one of those, please.
Take two.
Take two of those.
Great leaders.
Another thing that amazed and surprised us
was the Gandhi phenomenon, the Gandhi meme,
making the world safe for Gandhi.
This is a phenomenon steeped in mystery and legend.
But our theory is that.
Gandhi was not really programmed to be more of a warmonger than anybody else, but it was so out of
character for him and kind of really illustrated that the game is not about reproducing history,
but creating your own historical story. So whenever Gandhi came up with a bad attitude,
it was something that people really noticed and remarked upon.
But the idea of meeting the great leaders I think kind of goes along with one of the
fundamental things that we wanted to do with Civ.
And Bruce and I have talked about this, that we did our research in the children's section
of the library, that we were not trying to create a game that was about all the obscure
historical facts that we happen to know because we read the right book.
It was about things that everybody would be familiar with.
And that allowed players to feel at home,
to feel comfortable, to feel smart about the concepts
that were in the game because they were familiar with them
or had heard about them.
And also they were kind of interacting
on a peer-to-peer level with great figures like.
Genghis Khan or Caesar or great leaders.
So this was the role we wanted to put you in.
This idea of building a civilization
and being a great leader and being able to interact
with these other leaders, I think really strengthened
that role-playing aspect of the game.
I was gonna say something, I can't remember what it was.
Sorry.
So the kind of the byline that we used,
it's good to be king, I think that might be
by Mel Brooks, but.
It was interesting, because the idea was that
I'm a god in this game, I'm a player,
and I'm running the whole show here,
but then you add this layer in where you put
these leaders in, and so he gave you a dual personality,
like I am now Stalin, or I am now Genghis Khan.
I didn't give it that much thought,
but you put it in there, and I think it worked.
Yeah, I think there's always a question in a game of what do you ask the player to do and what does the computer kind of do automatically.
And by keeping this idea in mind that you're the great leader, that really clarified a lot of the decisions in terms of what the player would do and what would kind of be done automatically.
I also want to say, I think that we borrowed from, let's say, the children's section of the library.
But I think there was two things about that.
One is that they have lots of pictures in those books.
And when you're dealing with artists,
you need to have images that they can work with
to make the product.
Now you were making most of the art,
but this is a small team a long time ago.
And Sid did the programming, the design, and the artwork.
So the pictures were helpful going forward
in the years ahead when you had to come up
with the images to tell people.
And the other thing was that, what was the other thing?
It's already gone again.
Well, Bruce, I'm glad you mentioned our team
because...
get the small violin out. There were only about 10 of us on the team at the end and just the two
of us, Bruce and I, worked on the project for most of the time. We had 640K in our IBM PC. We
had 16 colors in our EGA palette that we could not change.
And eventually we got VGA with 256 glorious colors.
It was a very different time, obviously, technically.
But I think what it allowed us to do
was focus most of our energy on the game design.
And players were willing to use their imagination
to add a lot of the elements that we
couldn't create at the time.
And that actually was a pretty good trade-off, I think,
for us.
As we mentioned, we started the game in early 1990.
actually stopped working on it,
finished another game called Cover Action,
and came back to this game,
and eventually shipped it in late 1991.
Probably was early 91, yeah.
Sometime in 91 it was early, I think.
So overall, I think we spent less than a year
in developing the original version of the game.
One thing about the artwork is that as the time goes by,
I come from the school, I mean the first
personal computer game I worked on had four colors,
CGA graphics, and so I always came up with the school
that the game has gotta be really interesting
and fun to play, because you're not gonna
wow anybody with how it looks.
And then, you know, with the 256 colors in us,
and we could do really interesting things,
but I'm still pushing back about,
let's don't put a lot of money in art,
art's not important.
And then, you know, I had partners by then,
and they said, no, no, no, we're gonna make
this incredibly beautiful.
I said, well, okay, go ahead.
And it made a big difference when Age of Empires
was really, really nice looking.
The sun was always shining, it was pretty,
it was outdoors, it was nice.
I think it made a difference,
and I was not prepared for that,
because I come from the stone ages of game design,
when we didn't care about colors,
there were no colors to work with.
Speaking of the time we took to make the game, Bruce,
I think you have a fascinating anecdote
about the cost involved in making these games.
Oh, well, I don't remember civilization per se,
but I was asked to do a budget analysis for Railroad Tycoon.
When we got done with it,
one of the management guys asked me to do it.
So I calculated the people who worked on it,
what they got paid, essentially, and the time.
And it came out that Railroad Tycoon
had cost the company $167,000 to make.
And this was in 1989 or 1990 or something like that.
I was like, wow.
I mean, we can't hire a great programmer
for that kind of money, it seems like today.
For one year.
And Civ was similar, I think.
Yeah.
So, here's one of the great controversies of civilization.
Perhaps one of the things we didn't do quite as well
as we could have done.
I don't know if you were around in the Civ I days,
you were probably deeply involved on one side
or the other of this controversy.
Just to refresh your memory,
the question was, can a spearman defeat a battleship?
Some people believed it could, some people believed it could not. In the game it could,
not all the time, but the Gandhi phenomenon where something weird happens once, you assume
it's a standard part of the game, this became one of the early controversies of the game,
whether it was okay for a spearman to once in a while defeat a battleship.
My claim was mathematically speaking, the spearman had a defense of two and the battleship had an
attack of 16. So, you know, it could happen. The math could work out in that fashion. Other
people with kind of visual, who looked at the world visually and saw a battleship and a spearman
were not convinced.
And interestingly enough, combat,
if we look back at the history of Civilization
and the various iterations of the game,
is probably the one area that has changed the most.
That we are, we're kind of constantly looking at
a new way to handle combat.
Because there's a tension between
the view that we give you of the world as the great leader,
that you're planning cities and you're exploring continents
and you're deciding which wonders to build.
And on the other hand, we're kind of getting you down
into the nitty gritty of the combat system.
You're moving your units, you're stacking them,
you're deciding where to, so there's kind of a tension
between the role that you play as the king
over most of your civilization and your,
your role as far as combat is concerned. So at various times
we've actually considered going to a separate map to resolve
combat because combat can be significant in the outcome of
the game. We've kind of dealt with the spearman versus
battleship controversy by adding hit points in multiple rounds of
combat and things like that to make it somewhat less likely
that the spearman will defeat the battleship.
With more recent iterations of Civ,
there's one unit per tile,
there's different stacking rules and things like that.
The original Civ game had a concept called zones of control
which came from Wargaming,
which was probably the worst idea that we put in the game.
But it reflected...
my vision kind of how combat was going to work in this game. I was imagining you'd create lines of
units at your borders and you'd be trying to hold the other civs back and it would be a very kind
of look like a World War II type of strategy game.
That turned out to be not at all how the game was played.
The stacks of doom was kind of the typical mechanism,
putting together a bunch of units and moving them around.
And the cities became really very much the focus
of where combat took place, which actually worked well
because it was a lot easier, smoother,
and allowed you to focus energy on other parts of the game
as well as just the combat.
But something we had no, that I certainly had no idea of it,
that when we first put things together,
the rules that I were creating for combat
were focused around this more kind of spread out,
war game-y type of combat.
But certainly with Civ 1 and then with the succeeding Civs,
we kind of understood what was happening.
And some of the changes that have been made
in the more recent Civs are almost actually trying
to get back to that more spread out combat
and less about the stacks of doom.
One of the other things we did with Civ was we tried to make very clear what the considerations
were that went into combat.
We gave each unit an attack factor, a defense factor, and a movement factor, and those were
printed right on the unit, right in your face.
And so that with all the systems in the game, we tried to make it very clear how they worked.
So you weren't spending your mental energy trying to decipher the systems.
You were spending your mental energy imagining how you would use those systems that you understood,
how they interacted and how you would use them to accomplish your purposes in the game.
But with combat...
It was definitely a work in progress and I think we're still constantly adjusting how it works
and relates to the other parts of the game because there's that tension between how important it is
and what role you have. But I'll admit that I may have dropped the ball here as far as combat is
concerned.
Hey, I made peace with it. I mean, I think I probably raised the issue that I was the first guy to ever deal with it
So I probably raised it first. I mean, how is this?
Crummy ancient unit defeating this modern warship. It doesn't make any sense to me
You know, this ship is on the coast and here's this guy in the land. I attack him
I should have just blown this guy to smithereens. No. No, I lost my battleship. I don't get it
So this is the kind of conversation we have and he'd say well, he explained it to me and I said, okay
Okay, it's fine.
I'll live with that.
And I can think, I can play chess,
and the pawn can kill the queen on the right circumstance.
I mean, so, I mean, it's a game.
It's not, we're not trying to model reality here.
It's a game, and so I made that decision myself,
and then I had to explain it to the next 50 guys
that marched into my room complaining,
because this is stupid.
So it's your fault.
You did not convince me to change.
One of my jobs was to shield you
from everybody else in the company
who was upset about something.
So they'd march down to my office and say,
what is going on with this?
And I'm going you know, I have to explain it again. I should have put a board on my door
This is the problem with spearmen with the battleships. You know, don't bother me about it. This is the answer right here
Thank You Bruce
So another thing that we introduced with Civ 1 was the
idea of the tech tree. And again, in hindsight, this seems
so classic, so characteristic of the Civ game. And I wish I
remembered the moment when we said, hey, a tech tree would be
cool. Wouldn't that be cool? Wouldn't that be an idea that
could last for 25 years and not only in our games but in many
other games? I don't remember that moment.
But I do remember having a book where kind of the timeline of history was kind of laid
out horizontally and all these different...
unique events were kind of pegged to their specific eras and times.
And I'm going to guess that that was kind of the genesis of this idea,
that one thing would lead to another.
And it fell so wonderfully into our idea of starting very small
and then gradually kind of unpeeling the onion
and giving you more and more interesting things to do.
And I think it also kind of...
felt very Civish, this idea of,
where on the one hand we had a war game,
we also had a game where science was important.
It was kind of a fairly new idea at the time,
but really, science was gonna be an important part
of this game, and how well you did,
how well you managed it was gonna be significant
in terms of your outcomes.
So, the tech tree seemed to kind of encapsulate
what we were trying to do with the Civ game.
I love the tech tree.
I was like, how do I get the railroads?
I mean, what do I gotta do to get the railroads?
Because the railroads, I can move my units
all over my empire with one click.
They can go anywhere.
I was like, what a great thing this is.
It was cool, it was fun to come up with the names
for civil, it was part of our research.
Again, maybe the children's section,
but what were the important technologies
in thinking about, like the stirrup?
I remember thinking about the stirrup.
because I'd read histories of warfare and the horsemen in battle had been like a side
show for most of ancient times until they had a stirrup.
And now the entire power of the horse can be pointed right at the end of your lance.
It's catching your arm.
Now the horse is hitting somebody, not just you with your stupid little spear.
And it changed warfare for a couple hundred years.
I don't think the stirrup is in our text.
Come on, it's got to be in there.
I don't know, it should have been.
It's not in our game.
I swear it's in our game.
Maybe it was the Age of Empires then, I don't know.
But I, it's the same line of thinking.
It's the same thinking that here's something
to change the world, at least temporarily.
Let's move on, let's move on.
Wait, I'm looking for.
So one of the things that's fun,
stirrup was very important.
One of the things that's fun is to kind of look back
and contrast how we saw things back in that time
and how things have evolved over the course
of many Civ games.
And Bruce mentioned the railroads and the,
what we certainly discovered over time
that people would min-max and analyze the tech tree
and have these specific technologies
that they were targeting.
And they would have track back seven iterations
as to what technologies they would need to research
to get to, gunpowder I think was often a favorite.
and that was very contrary to how I saw the tech tree
initially, in fact, in Civ 1,
You might have earned the prerequisites for gunpowder,
let's say, but there was a small chance
that it wouldn't show up in your list of choices
because my thinking was, well, they didn't know
that they were gonna be able to invent gunpowder
at this time.
It was like they were finding their way
through this mysterious cloud of science possibilities
and boy, did we get some complaints about that.
So it was what we did not anticipate was how intensely
and how seriously and how analytically people
would play this game.
And that was definitely something that changed in Civ 2.
And in some of the later Civs, it would actually say,
if you want gunpowder, which is like eight leaves
down the tree, you might want to go this direction.
And I was like, oh, that's so wrong.
So it was just like the first appearance of the optimizer
in playing games?
I mean, I don't know.
The min-max player.
One of the things that we certainly have identified
are lots of different personality styles
in terms of playing Civ.
And kind of the tech tree optimizer is such a person.
And I'm always amazed by StarCraft players
that have, again, that same idea, the very specific actions
that you take to play the game.
And.
That's one way to play, but to me, that kind of takes a lot of the fun out of it.
So I guess I'm more drawn to games that are going to surprise me or give me a different challenge every time.
I think that's a question of taste.
I mean, because I like the fact that our maps are randomly generated.
You know, the game was different every time you played.
Now, like the StarCraft minimizer,
he loves the map speed.
A guy told me once, a guy at Blizzard told me once,
he got a letter from a guy.
He said, if you move this item one pixel to the north,
I will never lose StarCraft again.
That caused me so much problem.
If you just move it one pixel, I will never lose.
And he had to optimize the game to that extent.
So that's a different style of play.
People who like civilization probably were not that guy.
That's certainly something that's been a part of Civ
all the way through, is the idea of random maps,
scenarios, difficulty levels, many different ways
of allowing you to replay the game
and have a different experience, or a new experience,
or a fresh experience.
Yeah, I mean, going forward, I definitely wanted random maps
in the games that we made going forward.
The wonders of the world. History is so rich in stuff for us to steal. This was just cool,
low-hanging fruit that wouldn't it be cool to build these awesome wonders?
in the successive iterations of Civ,
we were able to actually give you wonder movies
and kind of give you some pretty dramatic payoffs
for doing these things.
But the idea of something that only one Civ
in the world could build,
and you wanted to race to be the first to do that,
gave you another way of being aware of the other Civs
that were in the world and what else was going on there.
And I think it also gave you this connection
to things that you'd heard about,
whether it was Stonehenge or the pyramids.
I think it was aspirational.
I mean, I'm gonna build a great wall,
a great pyramid of Giza.
That's pretty cool, I get to do that.
I wanna do that.
I thought that was interesting, the way we did that,
the way you did that, let's say.
I think the wonders are very popular.
Another thing we did right.
High five there, Bruce.
All right.
Thank you.
And.
Thank you, you're very kind.
So, something we did horribly wrong.
We missed out on the opportunity for modding in scenarios,
which became such a wonderful and important part
of civilization as it proceeded through the years.
Civ 2 really introduced modding as an option,
as a strength, and something that really
engaged our community.
We just didn't have the vision in those days
to imagine that anyone could design anything
better than we could.
I guess I think that was probably our thinking at the time.
Wasn't my thinking.
I don't know.
But the idea that this is a really opened up the game to a
whole different kind of player. I'd like to think that a lot of
designers perhaps got their first design experience making a
mod for Civilization or a similar game. Again, what we
found in terms of the feedback that we were receiving for our
game was that
A lot of the feedback was suggestions for improvement of the game.
Things that players liked or things that they thought should be changed or fixed.
And Civ seemed to bring out the inner designer in a lot of our players and modding.
gave those people the opportunity to express that.
And I think it was, it's probably the reason Civ
has been around for so long,
is that Modding was introduced in Civ 2,
and gave players things to do,
and kind of a freshness between the five or so years
that it took to bring out a new civilization.
So this was an opportunity I think that we missed.
Now in those days there was no internet and so we were kind of justified by, probably would have
been pretty complicated. I wouldn't beat yourself up over this one, come on. We had a small team,
we had a limited time to make this game, the management's tromping down the hall, what are you
working on today? Where's my new flight simulator? What is this stupid game? So we were under
pressure, I thought I was under pressure. You weren't, you were never under pressure.
We had to get this game, you know, you did a great job of
putting it in a box and saying,
this is what's going out the door.
And like, you know,
cause after you let everybody else in the company play it,
it was a lot of ideas were coming in your office.
And I think you did a great job of saying.
I had this idea that when you're designing a game,
your first half of the project,
you're playing forward on the soccer team,
and you're trying to score goals.
Idea, idea, idea, idea, idea.
And then the game flips over to the second half,
and now you're the goalkeeper.
You've got a game that's essentially done,
you've got enough stuff in here that's good to go.
Now you're defending the goal.
It's gonna get this game done,
and we're not gonna try and score any more goals.
You're just trying to finish this project.
I think you did a good job,
boxing it off and taking it to the finish.
Thank you, Bruce.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Kudos to Brian Reynolds for adding the modding feature to.
Hmm, so who is this young, handsome young man here?
That picture was taken three years ago.
I think another significant part of what Civilization was, was the manual that Bruce created.
It was, again, it made the game, I think, seem important, seem like a game that you
needed to play, seem that you needed to tell other people that you were playing because
it meant you were cool.
because you could handle creating a civilization.
And it was really a,
it wasn't just about how to play,
but there was a lot of background information,
there was some great historical information,
and I think it-
Suggested reading.
Suggested.
Wow.
You want to know the real story.
Right. So I think it really complemented the game in a way that we just don't, you know,
that doesn't happen anymore. But it gave the game kind of a weight and an importance that...
Gravitas is a word I would use sometimes.
Yeah, it's a shame they don't do that anymore, but you know, people don't want,
they don't have time to read.
Not even the manual, let alone the suggested reading.
I don't read manuals. I don't read a manual of anything.
It's not intuitive.
I mean, we're trained now to do it all.
Take them through the first time of user experience.
When they're done, they know how to play, and it's all seamless, and you've got three
minutes to make it happen.
Now this was actually not unique to civilization.
Railroad Tycoon wrote, again, a very comprehensive manual.
It was, even with our F-15 products,
we were trying to take this very limited technology
and make it feel awesome and epic and important.
And the manual had a significant part to play in that.
Also this has given an opportunity to tell some of the real story because like again another point
I've made over the past is that we borrowed from the historical record stuff
We thought would make a great game. We left stuff back there that we didn't think would help like there's no slavery
There's no black plague or something like that. There's no religious wars
you know, so those are all certainly part of the historic record the history of Western civilization per se but
we didn't see how they were going to add to the game.
So, you know, the idea is to entertain people,
not teach history.
I think you can learn things,
and we can introduce you to maybe go down the road
to go to the library and read more,
but we're focusing on making entertainment software.
Yeah, that reminds me, one of the first concepts that I had for the game was the rise and fall of civilization.
That you would build a civilization, but then you'd have this kind of setback,
and then you'd kind of come back from that even stronger,
and it wouldn't be so satisfying to overcome this adversity, whether it's the plague or something,
and come back even stronger and awesomer, and then it would just be awesome and totally awesome.
But...
What we found happened is as soon as this plague hit
or this setback happened, people would reload their game
from five turns ago and kind of try to avoid it.
So it became the rise and rise and rise of Civilization.
The fall was...
I think we sort of learned that lesson
making Railroad Tycoon,
because you had these floods that would wipe out
your railroad.
If you built the really expensive bridge,
you gave people, and there was no help for that.
You couldn't stop this from happening.
It was so dispiriting to have your railroad
crushed by this random event.
Computer was having the fun.
Player wasn't having the fun,
the computer was having the fun.
So that was one of your points, too.
The player should have the fun,
not the computer, not the researcher,
not the writer, not the computer, however.
So I think...
We had floods in civilization that could wreck your city and then you gave them a wall or something
that they could build and it stopped the flooding. So you built that wall and you didn't worry about
floods anymore. The player had a solution to that kind of problem.
Yeah, I think railroads is where the phrase,
what were we thinking was first.
But I will claim that Civ I introduced the idea
of global warming back in 1990,
because that was actually a thing in Civ I,
that if you had too much pollution,
the seas would rise and you'd lose your coastal cities.
So way ahead of our time, way.
too much information. Again, kind of reflecting, we had no idea what we were trying to do here.
I thought it would be cool to have all this detailed demographic information about your
Civ that would again make the game feel real and kind of you actually managing these people.
These things did not survive to any of the later iterations of Civilization.
Nobody was fooled.
This is a game and I think people more and more looked at it as a game.
kind of optimized their way through the tech tree and
analyzed spearmen versus battleships. It kind of was not
seen really as much of a role-playing experience, which
is part of what we were trying to do with too much information
here. But part of it was also these kind of attaboys, the top
five cities in the world, ways of giving you some sense of how
you are progressing and that you're kind of on the right
track.
So this is the, oh that's actually a GIF, wow.
I didn't know that.
So this is the introduction to civilization.
And in the beginning the world was without form and void.
We were really trying to make this feel like an important game.
Jeff Briggs wrote this really cool piece of music reminiscent of Copland's Fanfare.
And this is how you started to play.
that we succeeded in kind of giving you the idea
that this experience was going to be different
from what was happening in other games
and in kind of some important and significant way
that this game kind of told you something
about how the world worked
and let you kind of take over
at this very crucial point in the history of the world
and tell your own story.
So...
Again, we were bold and young and audacious,
and really trying to convince you
that this was a game of historic significance,
little knowing, of course, that 25 years later,
we'd be still talking about it.
But I think we had no fear in those days,
and this kind of represents our idea
that we had created something special.
I think Bruce talks about how he felt
that in Hunt Valley, Maryland.
I'll let you tell that story, Bruce.
Well, I just, people asked,
did you know the game was going to be great
when you were working on it?
I said absolutely.
And at some point I realized the whole world did not know,
the gaming community did not know that in this little town,
Hunt Valley, Maryland, north of Baltimore,
we were making a game that was going to rock the world.
I just felt really strongly about this game
is going to be great, it's going to have incredible success.
People are going to love playing this game.
I just felt really, I walked down, I told my,
Girlfriend is now my wife. I said, you know if I could find a job make a living
I would do what I'm doing every day for free because this is so much fun. This is so cool
What we're making is so important. I think I thought it was great. It was an incredible opportunity for me. I really loved it
I'm not sure I had the same feeling
I enjoyed making the game, but I felt it was a bit out there.
And so I felt very gratified when
we started to get some positive response.
But I definitely was up in the air
as to whether we had kind of gone too far
or this was going to work.
I knew that when I could see other people sitting down,
and myself, the time would just go flying by.
Like a psychologist called creating flow.
You get into a flow pattern psychologically,
and you just forget about the past your time.
And I knew that was happening to me.
I could see it happening to other people playing the game.
I knew that that's the stuff.
That's the real thing.
If you can do that,
then you've achieved something really successful.
Speaking of time passing,
the game shipped on eight five and a quarter inch
floppy disks, so.
Probably spent half an hour just loading it onto your PC.
Probably one of the areas that we fell down
was in actually testing the game.
looking at the credit sheet from the manual, there were, I think,
five testers that we had at the end of this project to test the
game, in addition to all the playing that Bruce and I did.
But the idea of intensive testing was not as well
established back in those days.
Even though the game was pretty solid,
there were two significant bugs in the game.
They're not bugs, but they're the kind of exploits,
I'd say we call them these days.
Oh, that's what I was going to say.
By building lots and lots of cities,
you could kind of grease your path to success.
And we actually ended up adding this idea of corruption to
balance that out.
And the other thing we didn't realize in our testing was
that the chariot unit was amazingly
overpowered for its cost.
It was a 412 for attack factor.
And it was pretty much a cool way to overrun the entire
world, so we ended up making it a 312, which was perfect.
the power of one number.
But otherwise, the game was pretty solid.
We had no option, of course, for a day one patch or any of
the tools that we have today to update things.
So a few things we missed at the time, but overall it was
pretty solid.
I wanted to leave a little time for questions, so we're
going to kind of.
End our presentation there.
And just open it up for questions,
if you have questions about the game or the process
by which it was made, or our personal lives,
anything like that.
Hello.
So I've played Civilization now for something
like 14,000 hours over the past 20 years.
And thank you for taking a good chunk of my life.
I wanted to ask, how did you decide upon the original assortment of civilizations?
Well, we were certainly looking at recognizable leaders.
I think the, again, reading through history.
We tried to give each Civ a personality, certain special
abilities and things like that that would make the game play
different each time you actually be encouraged to play the
different Civs and have a slightly different experience.
I think that...
Looking back, Chairman Mao is the leader of the Chinese.
We could not pull that off today.
There's a number of things we did there
that actually the world has changed,
and we can't do anymore.
But I think it was looking for these leader characters
that had some really interesting personality
and would be fun to interact with.
I just think that I um because I was responsible for some of the research and trying to accomplish it
So you may have asked me for what are the good choices?
And you might have said well, give me some leaders and give me some civil
I don't remember now, but I would have thought about the great civilizations
Oh, you know of Western civilization primarily, but we also had India and places like I'm not sure just we thought were significant
There's been big empires or big civilizations were worth, you know putting in the game
Thank you very much. Thank you
Okay. Hi. My name is Mateusz Pilski and I have an indie
studio called Ice Cold Games and right now we are creating a game
called Cold where you create your own cold and fight with
colds of your opponents. And because of that I have a
question. Did you have any
concerns or problems when you put in the civilization religions as tools for taking dominance over
the world? Religion has been a topic we've been very careful with. The original SIV had
a very basic system of temples and cathedrals and creating happiness.
after that, succeeding SIVs have gone more into depth with
religion systems and kind of spreading your religion and
things like that. But it's always been not taking a kind of
any sort of position in terms of one religion being better
or worse or whatever than another.
And it's kind of a fundamental idea of Civ
that we're not trying to impose our vision
of what's right or what's wrong.
Whenever the designer kind of steps to the front
and says this is how you should play
or this is what's right or wrong,
it takes the agency away from the player
and then that's kind of the designer having the fun
as opposed to the player having the fun.
So in Civ the idea is that we let you kind of explore your own
thoughts about whether you want a big army or whether you want
to create world peace or whether culture is the way to go.
I mean, you always have those options in Civ.
And part of that is us not taking a stand on specific
religious issue or cultural issues or things like that.
So that's kind of how we approach that.
OK.
Thank you.
First of all, thank you both. This game I credit with giving me my love of history. My
favorite thing of the entire franchise is in Civ 1, the end of the game, you got to replay your
game and it gave you a real good sense of this is what I did. It seems to have died in the
franchise and never gotten the same amount of effort. I was just curious why. You'll have to
come to Ed Meach's talk, which is coming up in half an hour.
I actually don't have an answer to that.
I think that we did put the replay in Civ 1,
in spite of a lot of technical limitations,
to give you that sense of reliving what had happened.
But I'll make a note of that.
Thank you.
Hi, my name is Salman from Google.
I grew up with Civilization.
I played all of them, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
And on that note about growing up with Sid,
I have my own four-year-old son.
And I'm looking to basically have him play that game soon.
But I look back at Solution 1 and there really was very high educational value.
In those days of the term edutainment, it really kind of like, that's how I get my dad
to buy CIV 2 because CIV 1 was so educational.
And that was really kind of, I felt lost.
Because in CIV 1, every time you would discover something, you would have to read about it.
And so that's the amount of stuff I learned from that game is just endless, you know, you talked about too much for GDP
I learned GDP from that
You know Chairman Mao I learned about him through civilization, you know
I would go to school and history class,
oh I already know what conscription is because
you know I discovered it.
And it was really amazing.
But in CIF II, it kind of became like
you have to click the description tab or something
I don't remember exactly.
And there was a lot of stuff in terms of this.
you know, historical sense, and learning about history and technology and all these things
that I felt, you know, has been lost.
Like, it was, it seemed like there seems to have, there was a bit of a conscious decision
saying that, hey, you know what, it's more of a game than an educational software.
But I would love, especially for my son, right, for this franchise to go more towards the
educational audience that it's originally given.
And this stuff like Civil War, I would go attack the capital
just to give Civil War.
A lot of this stuff was lost.
I'd like to see more of that.
So I'm hearing we need to bring back Civ I.
And by the way, four years is a great age
to start playing Civilization.
I think that'd be wonderful.
I do think it's true that, and if you look on the Civ forums,
players get very intense about the gameplay.
So there definitely is an audience
for this kind of streamlined gameplay,
this very focused gameplay.
But I hear what you're saying,
there's also an audience for kind of a learning-based
approach to civilization.
We don't actually talk about education
as being a part of the game.
because that's like a dirty word.
But we think learning actually is an important part
of the game.
The sense that you get as playing,
that you now know a little more,
whether it's about playing the game or about history
or about leaders or GDP.
I think that learning is kind of a secret aspect
of the game that brings you back to learn more
and to kind of feel better about yourself.
But thank you for that, for those comments.
Hi, thank you for this amazing game, it's so fun.
My question is, how do you think about adding,
removing complexity from one game to the next,
and where and how do you think about it?
Well, we, a couple things that we,
we've gotten to the point where we feel the game
has the right amount of complexity.
So for every new system that we add,
or new idea that we add,
we're gonna pull something else out
to kind of keep it at that level.
And we also have this rule at Firaxis,
which we call the 1 3rd, 1 3rd, 1 3rd rule,
which is kind of 1 3rd of the game is core.
It's the way Sim works, it's turn-based,
it's gonna have cities, it's gonna have units,
it's gonna have wonders, it's gonna have these pieces.
Another third is taking ideas that we experimented with before and kind of taking what we learned,
whether it's a religion system or an SB&R system or a way of doing combat,
and taking what we learned and making that better.
And then another third is new things, things that we haven't put in the game before.
kind of mixing those all together, those different thirds,
is kind of what guides the next iteration of civilization.
There's enough novelty, enough new to make it
a different experience, but enough of that core gameplay
that it's a SID game.
Thank you.
Hi, I'm Adrian Troy from Zooks, the self-driving car company.
I love civilization, and I also love the old 1980 board game
Civilization, which had tech trees and all these kinds of
things, and I was wondering if you guys played that and were
influenced by it at all.
That was a licensed game.
I mean, there's this cycle now.
There was originally a Civilization board game,
and then we did the computer game,
and then there was a board game based on that.
And so it's, you know, again, this synergy.
And a lot of our inspiration for the original Civ
was kind of a war gaming background and things like that.
So they're related.
And I think one of the charms of the board game
is more the multiplayer aspect,
you know, playing together with friends,
and the social component,
which you don't always get playing a computer game.
So they each have their strengths,
and I think they can reinforce each other.
Okay, I'm getting this symbol.
Thank you very much for coming.
Thank you for supporting.
Thank you for supporting CIV.
Thanks especially to Bruce for coming.
My pleasure. Enjoy.