Hello there, I am Kelly Wallach, the CEO and founder of the Indie Mega Booth,
the chairperson for the Independent Games Festival and community builder for the OneUp Fund.
And this is the Hades fireside chat with Amir,
the studio director of Supergiant Games.
So I want to welcome Amir to our virtual stage.
Hello, I'm Amir Rao. I'm the Studio Director of Supergiant Games. I've worked on all our games,
Bastion, Transistor, Pyre, and Hades, which is the game we'll be talking about today.
At Supergiant, I coordinate our work and I do game design. So I'm one of the designers who
is responsible for tuning various parts of the game and making sure that the game is coming
together.
Yeah, I'm excited to talk about our experience making Hades.
I'm excited to be back at GDC in some form.
I know.
Yeah, I've always loved this conference.
I was a conference associate in like 2004
or something like that as a volunteer for GDC.
So it's really, really cool to be back here
and to be speaking at it.
I think the last time I spoke at GDC
was at the failure workshop.
So this is like pretty good.
pretty good gap between that.
We were talking about Bastion actually.
I believe that was the last time I spoke at least.
So yeah, that was a long time ago.
My impression was Bastion was not a failure.
So I don't know what the workshop was about.
Yeah, well, you know,
the failure workshop is really interesting.
It was actually talking about mechanics that didn't work.
And one of the mechanics that didn't work in Bastion was.
we had this whole gardening game inside of Bastion
that really didn't work.
And so it was discussion of the things
that didn't really pan out inside that game,
even though the game came together pretty well.
Actually, yesterday was the 10 year anniversary
of Bastion coming out.
So that was exciting too.
So it's a lot of exciting stuff happening.
Yeah, one of my favorite kind of, um, I don't know, super giant connection
stories for me as I actually still have the bastion, um, bandana that you guys
were giving out and I don't even know what conference that was.
I feel like that was the first time.
PAX in 2011, I think before the game came out.
Yeah.
9 million years ago.
Yeah, it was, it was, uh, the, yeah, the show floor was a little
different than it was PAX East.
Yeah.
It was, it was exciting to, to see those everywhere.
Yeah, a lot has happened since then.
And yeah, so I mean, I've known you and most folks on the team since since those days.
And I think we're talking a little bit about this.
So part of my homework for this is I watched the entire Noclip documentary,
which is amazing, by the way, if you have an extra five hours
and you really want to hear a lot of things about Supergiant and game development,
I'm like, total thumbs up on it.
I highly recommend it.
But it was like a very interesting insight after knowing all of you for so long
and through so many different like games and iterations of.
not so much the studio,
cause a lot of the core components of the studio
stayed the same,
but just like to kind of be along on that journey
and then like kind of see this like climax
of how well Hades has done and been received
was like very, very cool.
So as a friend situation,
I'm like super happy for all of you.
And I'm really excited to see that.
Well, thank you.
Yeah, we are over just over the moon with the success
and the reception of Hades.
And it's one of those things where...
Uh, we, you know, we did not know to expect that, um, but it's, you know,
it's, it's been wonderful to see so many people, uh, love the game so much.
Yeah, the reactions and the documentary to you all, especially watching the Game Awards thing.
And now I can see why you like Jeff Keighley so much, just in general. It's just like a cool
situation. There's like this thread, you know, throughout. He's a very hard worker. Yeah. I mean,
the way he puts together a lot of that stuff, it just takes so much. So yeah, I've always been a
fan of the way he conducts himself and the way he puts those events together.
Yeah, but like watching the reaction of the team, you know, as they're like announcing
everyone's on Zoom, of course, because it's pandemic time and like, and also to like the
games you're up like nominated against was like legit. Yeah, I mean, not that Hades isn't a
legit game, but like, that was an impressive lineup to be up against as well too.
Yeah, we I mean, we're actually lucky. We're nominated for six awards in tonight's show
for the Game Developers Choice Awards. So that'll be that'll be really exciting as well. We
I think we won a Game Developers Choice Award for best debut in 2012 for Bastion.
So you know, the whole group of people who worked on that game is still working together
at Supergiant Games today.
And so, you know, we just feel really lucky to have been able to keep doing the work through
everything through several games through the last year and all that kind of stuff.
Yeah, I mean, I think it's incredible.
And, you know, one of the things that I had realized with the documentary is like,
I didn't realize how early Jen was on the team.
Cause I feel like she's like a little bit enigmatic in the sense of like, you know,
I don't really like hang out, like see her at conferences and stuff, but like.
She was in pretty early, right?
Yeah, Jen is one who prefers to speak with her work,
and her work is incredible.
Her work speaks very loudly, so I think it's fine.
Yeah, yeah.
So Jen Z is the art director for Supergiant Games.
She came up with all the character designs
and obviously a lot of the art direction, art style,
a lot of the execution of specific assets in the game.
Just has her hands in everything related to the art that we do.
Yeah, Jen is incredible.
There's like, I think the shocking thing about
a talent like Jen. And, and this is true of almost, um,
I say almost, cause I don't want to include myself in such a statement, um,
but of everyone I work with, um, is, uh, you know, I sort of,
when you have a game like bastion come out and you have a lot of people love it
in your first game, um, I think, you know,
a lot of us would have been right in expecting that that was kind of as good as
it was going to get for us. Um, because, you know, we came out of nowhere,
people really liked it. Um,
It was our first effort and all that kind of stuff, but like the crazy thing about Jen and Greg
and Darren, all these people I work with, is like somehow they get better and better and better.
And I think that's the like sort of...
joy of working with them as individuals, but also the joy of our chemistry as a group is, you know,
we have these long relationships that have gone over several games. And then for Hades,
specifically, we like added all these new voices. So we were 12 people for a really long time,
for about five years before.
making Hades and over the course of Hades, we grew to around 20 people,
um, a little under 20.
And so, um, you know, we've added all these new voices who are integral to,
to the stuff we've been making.
And, um, we're just so important to, to making Hades, uh, the game it was.
Yeah, and that kind of answers a little bit of like one of my, I guess, first official questions,
which I was like live journaling my thoughts while I was watching this documentary.
It's like, why is Jen so amazing?
Like that, that scene where the concept art for chaos comes up, I was like,
like, oh my God, so good.
Yeah. And I'm like, why is she so great?
Like, how did that happen?
Yeah, it's just one of those things, you know, even when you work with her, you know, she's like
really, really amazing to talk to and collaborate with. And she's very articulate about what she's
trying to do. But then there's this whole invisible process where the art is made,
or even sometimes it's happening, you know, a couple seats over and you still, you know, it's
just, it's always shocking and surprising to see what will be done with it. That's another, that's
another part of about working on a team that I feel really, really good about is.
there's a lot of like elevation of each other's work. So, um,
you know,
you know that the various parts of the pieces that other people are working on
are going to, are going to kind of like raise what you do. Um,
so even if what you do is still kind of feeling like a work in progress and that
happens a lot on the design side, um, you know, like, Hey,
when this gets good feedback, when this gets,
when this gets like a theme, when it starts to make sense, when it,
when it gets narrative and voiceover and music and all these different pieces,
um, it's gonna, it's gonna,
be different than the experience you normally have,
which is, you know, early games are pretty rough,
even Hades was.
So, I think, you know,
you can only do this for a really long time
if you're constantly being surprised
by the work of your peers and learning from them.
And so we're lucky to be able to have both.
Yeah, and you know, I think that it seems like,
like you said, the kind of core team
of the folks who had worked on Bastion have been there.
for a while and like I said, you know, I've interacted with all of you over time as well
too and seeing the work that you're doing, but you know, seeing like Darren work on music and
all that it just is like, yeah, it's pretty, I don't want to say like mind-blowing, but it's
really fascinating on like how much and how detailed and how far in you can tell that he's
like really gone and thought about this stuff and I think, you know, for me too, like art and music
are things that I love but I'm not particularly talented at, so every time that I see people do
them I'm just like...
you know, like how on earth did that happen?
You know?
And I think that that, you know,
that growth and that change and, you know,
with the audio and with Darren's work is really cool.
But then also like how he's explaining
that he's working on it.
Like there was a quote where he was just like,
I want it to sound rad when you fight a Minotaur.
to go into writing a song, right?
Yeah, yeah.
No, it's getting on the same page.
I mean, so yeah, Darren, you know, it's still,
it's still shocking when you hear the work
for the first time,
because you don't know what to expect
and it's very exciting.
Him and Greg work really closely on the audio stuff.
And in fact, him and Greg are giving a talk right now.
So if you've made the mistake of coming to this Hades conversation, instead of the one
about how they did all the voiceover, don't despair because like they are, I think you
can still rewatch it later.
But they, they're talking about the process.
Or flip back and forth between the two talks.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, you can flip back and forth.
But you know, Greg and Darren collaborate really closely on the audio experience and
Darren of course executes so, so much of it.
And Darren also.
did all the voice direction and he was the voice of Zagreus in the game.
So, um, he, that was surreal.
That was very strange.
So I, I kind of always get a little weirded out when I see people actually doing
like voiceovers, like cartoon characters and stuff too.
I'm like, that's not what you look like.
Yeah.
It's pretty, it's pretty shocking there.
There.
Um, yeah, he's just an enormous talent.
So it's, it's been awesome to work with him.
And I've known him since I was like eight years old or something too.
So that, that luck too.
Yeah, which is I also really love that, that it was just like, you know, a friendship relationship
that kind of blossomed into this professional relationship as opposed to like somebody,
you know, coming in, you know, to someone outside of games and that kind of perspective
and stuff as well, too, I think is really interesting. But then you have someone like
Greg, who, you know, is like, been very deeply involved in games for a long time. And
you know, I think even though I feel like I'm just like gushing about everyone on your team,
you know, I think that what is like this, this thread to me is this really like very high level
of thoughtfulness and like contemplation and like research and the kind of like stewing of ideas
and concepts. And I felt like that really came out a lot, like through that, that side of it,
you know, like the music, the art and the, the narrative component of it, like the three of
them talking about their work, like you can really tell that this is like something that they're,
they're really like.
contemplating on a pretty like interesting level.
Yeah, I mean, they are very thoughtful about it.
They're very good at discussing it
and they're very good at executing on it.
So it's one of those things where,
there's plenty that goes into it.
So I don't wanna make it sound like it's easy,
but they're just very,
we have the advantage of working together for so long
that like,
you know, we've developed a lot of shared just things,
shared vocabulary, shared experiences,
you know, a shared sense of things.
And when we were working on Hades,
we were sort of excited to build on all our best ideas
from our previous games,
which was like a really different mindset
than we used before, because, you know, when we...
When we went from Bastion to Transistor, we thought, you know, we need to make something new and original.
We want to make something new and original.
And so we're going to spend a bunch of time figuring out a new original world, which meant like a lot of the great ideas of Bastion, we felt were sort of off limits.
You know, like we shouldn't use those.
Those are Bastion's thing and Transistor needs its own thing.
And so, um.
With Hades, it was a little less like that.
We had made three games.
We were interested in doing something
in the roguelike genre,
and we wanted to do something more narrative.
And so we just, we sort of allowed ourself
the space to use stuff that had worked for us in the past
to build on them.
And also, you know, that just is enhanced by the chemistry,
the fact that it's the same people working on that stuff.
So we knew what the problems were
with our previous versions of those,
or we knew what was new about what we were trying to do.
Um, and, um, and so, yeah, so, so in a lot of ways, Hades is like an expression
of, of our strengths as a team and also our, um, I guess our strengths as, as
collaborators, you know, this is like the stuff we know we do well, actually
together, not just individually.
It's like, this is the stuff that we can really, really do, um, uh, at a level
that we can, we can feel satisfied with.
Um, so yeah, just.
lucky to work with them.
Yeah, and I mean, I think that that
You know how you're saying that it's kind of like a progression of all of the different games and you all like working together.
Yeah, I think that that also, to me, ties in a bit, too.
There's a point a point where you talked about how you all toil, like kind of toil on games for a long time.
And I want to get into talking a little bit about like the kind of all encompassing nature of doing a project like this.
But, you know, the time frames that you're talking about, you're like, OK, you know, we like toil on a game for like three or four years.
which is a long amount of time,
you know, like I guess just in general,
I mean, not relative to all of time and space,
you know, but it is like a long time,
but also in like game development,
it's kind of not actually a long time.
And especially I think for smaller teams
and indie developers,
like projects can go on way longer than you're imagining
just because of constraints and team size
and things like that.
And I do think that one of the things
that is very interesting
from other developers and studios standpoint
is that you are pretty consistent
with like every couple of years,
there is like...
a new game that has come out that is fully fleshed out and thought out and,
you know, and there's all these different components and stuff to it.
And so I actually kind of wanted to like, hear you talk a little bit, uh, you know,
about that, because I think even though it feels like a long time and maybe it
doesn't feel so consistent, I think out of a lot of studios, you actually are
fairly consistent and fairly like, kind of like quick in a way, um, process.
Yeah.
I, so, um, I, I feel like, um,
Part of the, so we're consistent, I think for two,
consistent in terms of like how our output for two reasons.
One is dispositionally as people who work together,
we like want to.
work on stuff, scope it down and finish it.
That is like sort of like the simple way of saying it.
Like we share this disposition.
It, we have, we are always refining the thing we're doing.
And the reason we do that in a way that works
across the board is we have this like,
value around basically embracing constraints.
So like as a small team, you have a ton of constraints,
right?
Even big teams have constraints.
And so for us though,
it's really wonderful to like work within them.
Like what are the things we can do?
What are the things we can do well?
How, you know, like when do we want to do it?
And, you know, stuff like packs, for example,
in the past where we used to bring a demo to packs
and then go back into the lab and then release the game.
And that was the only times you'd ever see it.
you know, until we tried early access on Hades, those,
the constraint of a deadline for PACS was actually useful
because, you know, going back to the failure talk
that I referenced at the top of this,
we cut gardening from Bastion four days
before driving up to Seattle from San Francisco
because we thought this doesn't make any sense
and it doesn't work.
And the constraint of that
was, you know, it was a hard decision and we had been working on that part of it for over a year.
But the upside is like almost the relief of like not having to think about it anymore. It's out.
So, so we are very like constraint driven in, you know, as a, as a team,
we're always mindful of that. And that comes down to everything we do, even.
Like, even when we're trying a new idea, we want to see some ideas show promise,
like as, you know, quickly, which, you know, uh, really does work for some
things, like it really works for certain design ideas or certain system ideas.
Um, and maybe work works less well for like really big problems.
Like, um.
like technical problems that might take months and months and months to solve.
Um, and so those are examples of the types of things, like our mindset is
usually around, like, what are the constraints we want to know the
constraints, um, we want to know the constraints, we want to know what the
problems are, we want to solve them.
And so, uh, yeah, we, we really value them.
Like constraints are, are, are wonderful.
We, we always want to know what the constraints are.
Um, and that's part of being realistic with ourselves and with each other, you
know, it's the only way we can make sensible decisions.
Yeah, and you know, I have heard that that deadline kind of like an like having an external
deadline or an external thing, you know, like, you don't you can't push packs back and you can't
stop people from coming and playing the game, you know, so you kind of just like have to get it done,
I think has been helpful for a lot of teams. But now this is also kind of like leading me
into another question that I had. And I'm kind of wondering as like, as part of the decision.
to move forward with doing a game in early access
is to just basically have another set
of like constraints in a way.
You know, I hadn't really thought about it
until you had said it this way,
but is that like partially one of the factors?
Yes, it's partially one of the factors.
So the, you know, Hades was an early access game
before it was a Greek mythology roguelike.
Coming off of Pyre.
having worked on three games in the model of,
we work on it in secret, we like announce it,
and then we release it.
And, you know, maybe a couple hundred people
will play it at PAX,
and maybe some of our friends will play it along the way.
Having done that so many times,
we were just really interested in doing a process
that was more open, more transparent,
and got us to a game faster.
And the last time we'd actually done something like that
was Bastion, because Bastion went to PAX,
I think like...
a year after it started or something like that.
It was something like that.
So yeah, it started in 2009, it went to PAX in 2010.
It released a year later.
So it was one of those things where
we were interested in doing that,
but we were also interested in the changes.
we would have to make to do that, if that makes any sense.
So like we would have to learn, for example,
how to keep a game stable over a longer period of time.
We would have to learn how to take community feedback
and integrate it into our process.
And we would have to learn what happens
when those are the constraints and not just kind of like,
you know, the deadline of packs
or when we hope the game would be done
or any of those types of things.
So.
We were really interested in seeing what we would learn from such a process.
And we were lucky that there were so many examples,
like so many amazing examples of games that had been created in early access
that were huge inspirations to us.
Like much of the Klay catalog fits into that.
Darkest Dungeon, Subnautica.
Larian's games, there's just so many amazing early access successes, and of course Dead
Cells by Motion Twin, which was a roguelike that they had done in early access.
Just seeing how it could be done well was inspiring as a game developer.
And so we wanted to see if we could do that as well.
And so, you know, the Hades was born.
the idea for Hades came out of a desire to try something in that direction.
Yeah, I think it's really interesting to hear you talk about some of the other examples of
games that have gone through early access, because I think I was talking about this yesterday,
I was like, no games go through early access. And you're like, the thing is,
like a lot of games actually go through early access, just nobody kind of remembers that.
Yeah, they were early access games.
But I remember when Early Access first like came out and it was it was kind of like met with some
trepidation I feel like because people were just like oh I don't I don't know um but even with like
going to events and things like that like games are kind of one of the few mediums where fans get
to interact with it a lot of times while it's in progress you know like nobody's kind of watching
like an undone version of a Marvel movie or something you know and then like giving community
feedback on it I mean I guess aside from like a trailer.
Yeah. Or something, but you know, I think it's, it's interesting how you're talking about using
it like as a learning experience and ways for the studio to like gain, gain new skills. And
I think you had mentioned too about like kind of practicing some parts of it. Yeah, we,
we actually rehearsed it. So before our initial launch in 2018,
We shipped three one month updates to ourselves, basically.
So we didn't do like the marketing art necessarily and stuff,
but we tried to like do a lot of the parts.
Like let's like, what would we call this thing?
This update, this last thing, like what does it look,
what does the contour of a four week cycle look like
compared to, you know, a three year cycle,
which is what we're used to before.
And,
Rehearsing it was awesome because it gave us the sense
that we were ready for the real thing.
It's a very smart idea.
Yeah, and then the real thing happens.
And then, you know, like an example of a change
we made really early on in our early access,
we went from four week updates, you know,
update every four weeks to an update closer to every,
it was more like eight to 10.
And we tried different things.
We tried four, then we tried eight,
then we did five again,
and then we went back to eight to 10.
And, you know, one of the things you can learn
in your early access is like how to do your early access.
You know, we learned a lot from those first two or three,
one month updates that got us realizing like,
hey, we could, what the game needs now
is like longer updates with more time.
our development director and the co-founder of Supergiant,
Gavin Simon, actually architected the rhythm
that we worked under.
And it was, you know, and we stuck to it.
You talk about constraints.
We did features for two and a half weeks,
two and a half to three weeks,
if you include the time to plan the update.
Then.
If a feature wasn't done, it did not graduate.
Like if there was still work left on it to even stand it up,
then we couldn't move it forward.
Then we did content for several weeks.
And then the last couple of weeks were polish.
And in the polish phase, a small, a small group of people inside the
community got to play it and then it would go out, um, it would go out.
And, you know, we also had an internal QA resources and stuff.
So, um, that we're vetting the update as we were making it.
and we would play it.
So it was one of those things where, you know,
it gave a rhythm to the whole process
that we got quite comfortable with over time.
Yeah. Yeah.
And I think there was a part in the documentary
where Greg was talking about kind of the thought
and the rationale behind the way that you also approach
doing early access or kind of having like
multiple early accesses, I guess, you know,
and then leading into the Steam Launch, you know,
which is,
where there's a larger part of your fan base and things like that.
And I think I've mentioned to you this a few times before,
but I feel like talking with you and hearing about how Supergiant runs is like when you
talk to someone who's just in a really good functioning marriage and you're like,
oh yeah, of course, that's how you would do that.
Of course you should practice a little bit of early access before you go and do early access.
Totally one and I think of that and honestly did not think of it, you know, I just I think it's
it's kind of a testament to the way that you all think about it and work together to really be like
kind of very like practical, but innovative at the same time around like how you're approaching
a change or a shift or something new with the studio.
Yeah, I mean, for us, it's the, you know, we, uh, the, the two things to say there is just,
we didn't, we didn't invent that process. Right. So we could see, we could see so many people do
it so well. So that was the first thing, you know, and we saw, you know, really specific things we
did. We saw other people do like, for example, um, the countdown clock to the next update that
was inside the main menu is something that Clay had been doing for a long time. The, um,
marking inside your patch notes which pieces of it were inspired by community feedback,
something we saw dead cells do. And you know, it's one of those things where you see these
specific practices and you go, I see what that does. It shows honestly and truthfully,
you know, which changes kind of came from people's experience with the game that you as developers
were not always having, because especially with a roguelike game, you can't experience all of it.
And as a developer, it's really hard to experience your game like a player might.
And so
All of these things kind of came together to make that like a functional process for us.
You know, we didn't have to make it up.
But I mean, I think the other thing about it is that, you know, if you have like a learning orientation,
then you can, as a group, know that part of what you're doing it for is not.
for it to be perfect, but for, for you to learn something from the process of doing it.
And then the output can be the learning, even if it doesn't always go well, even if every update
isn't always like a slam dunk or whatever. And we can do that because we have the privilege
and good fortune of self-funding our titles of owning our own IP and all this kind of stuff. So
you know, uh,
you know, like a question you did not ask is like,
why doesn't everyone just practice?
It's because everyone has different constraints
than the ones we have, right?
And so we're really lucky that our first game enabled us
to essentially choose our own destiny
in a lot of these ways
and to basically have the flexibility
to make these types of decisions
that work well for our team.
Yeah, yeah.
And I think that that's really interesting
to point out too, as well too,
like going into these projects with like,
a curiosity and like beginner's mindset, you know, because then you're kind of less attached
to it like, okay, it has to definitely look like this, or it has to come out on this day,
or it has to be this thing. And so it can be rewarding, even when it's not exactly the
way that you're imagining it would be. And another thing I'd like to kind of highlight
and there as well, too, is I think that this is not totally unique to the indie community,
but I do love this about it, that it's it's very kind of collaborative across studios
and across
like leaders and developers and people and even something like GDC, you know,
to come and share like the insights that you learn.
Cause it's this kind of like.
it's not so much a competition as it is like the rising tide floats all boats
um kind of situation and you know there's always people kind of paving the way and trying new
things and then when they're willing to share like what worked for them and what didn't what
didn't work um you know i think it can benefit everybody because like you said you know a lot
of these things were not like the first time that they had ever been done but they have been done
the first time by someone yeah no for sure and you know we we
the people I mentioned, the studios I mentioned, we talked to all those people.
Like we didn't just get inspired by them, we like went to the primary source for a lot of that
because you know another thing that we're fortunate to be able to do but it's one of those things where
I guess for whatever reason, you know, I think I feel like a lot of,
a lot of development on small teams is like people racing against their own
best time. You're not really like trying to like destroy the other one or
whatever. So, um, it's, it's, it's, it's really, uh,
it's really like sort of fortunate that you can have those types of
conversations and, and, and ask, you know, like what, how,
how might I do this? Am I thinking about this? Right.
Are we thinking about this? Right. Um, like, um, that's, that's, uh,
we have the good fortune to be able to do that.
Yeah. And then, you know, the amazing outcome or hopefully, you know,
the outcome of, of that kind,
those kinds of conversations and that kind of work is that like the games are
all cooler, right? Hopefully like, you know,
the fans are getting the best of this. It's like,
everybody's mind sharing on like, how do we,
how do we make like this experience in these games?
Just like the coolest things that they can be possible.
So people enjoy them and play them and have fun, you know?
Yeah. Yeah. And you know, especially when it comes to something like a,
like a process, right? Like production process,
at the scale of smaller teams is like pretty different,
right, than it is for like a much bigger team.
And so a lot of what...
a lot of what's interesting to talk about is like, what's your process?
Because I think sort of what you're actually asking is like,
how do your people work together in a functional way?
Like, what is the way in which your group does this?
Like, how are you thinking about this?
And so, you know, we're always thinking about that, too.
How do we work together better?
How do we
how do we make it make it?
Yeah. Make it work for each part of the process that we're in. Yeah.
Yeah, and I think there's kind of like two sort of like branches of this part of the conversation that I'm interested in.
You know, one we talked a little bit about before is the kind of like.
I think the documentary did a good job of putting this forward is like how all encompassing
working on a project like this is, especially as a small team like like.
I mean, can you even imagine the number of times you said the word Hades in the last like four years?
You know, like how many times you've seen that logo or how many times you talked about.
something about Hades or thought about Hades and like, you know, it was one of the things when I was watching that I was, I was kind of missing a bit about working on my own projects is like, oh yeah, there's this thing where at some point it's not like it takes over your entire existence, you know, some people, some people have that it seems like you all have a good like work life balance, but it is this thing where it's just like it kind of gets into like your DNA or something at some point, you know, and I think that that was like a really interesting thing that came across in the documentary, just like the kind of
Yeah, the all encompassing nature of game development
and making a project like this.
Yeah, well, you know, I think this is the part
with an early access game,
as a game developer can be especially,
I'll use the word compelling.
Because, you know, how often do you get people
to play something of yours and give you like a response
to the experience to produce so fast?
You know, there's nothing like that where.
you know, you, someone is having a problem,
you read about it, you fix it.
You know, the way we conduct our early access
through our Discord, we had a feedback channel,
an idea we got from the Rocket League Discord.
And we, you know, we read every piece of feedback
that came through and some of those,
some of those feedback got coalesced and became action,
became a task on the team.
and someone would do something about it,
and then you'd push it out.
And sometimes you could tell it would work
because someone in the community might say,
God, that's so much better.
Sometimes you could tell it could work
because they stopped talking about it as much.
Like this is just not coming up as much anymore.
And so maybe that problem is actually like gone now
and we don't have to think about it for a little bit.
So.
So yeah, it's a very, it's like a very compelling process
and it does get into every part of you.
But the truth is like these games we make,
they're like kind of, they're like kind of with us forever.
You know, we're still, you know,
Jen was just doing Bastion anniversary art, you know,
that we posted yesterday and stuff like that.
You know, still thinking about Rux and the Kid
and Zulfanzia and all that stuff.
So we're like still, you know, they're a part of you.
And I think as people dispositionally, we do get just really creatively compelled by the projects we pick.
And we know in some way they're going to be with us, no matter what they're like or how they turn out or any of those types of things.
They're just always going to be with us. It would be impossible not to think and talk about them.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And then, you know, the other kind of side of that.
Earlier thread was a bit about, you know, the process of like, how do you, how do you do this process or how does this happen?
And I think I texted you about this when I was watching it.
It's like, I think my favorite piece of television that's ever been produced is the conversation where you're having like between a bunch of folks on the team about like, whether he should like float while he has a gun.
I live for that kind of stuff.
You know, there is a lot of like, there's like this exciting, like, Ooh, like, look at the art and look at this, but like a lot of, a lot of projects are a lot of like.
let's talk about this thing in very big, very detail oriented, you know, and it just kind of
goes on and there's not like an exciting resolution in the meeting, you know, like sometimes these
things just like, they're just long meetings and conversations that go on for a while.
Yeah, it's a reference to a conversation about, you know, we have this weapon in the game that
is essentially like, it's a gun. It's called the adamant rail.
we knew we wanted to make it,
there was just a discussion over like,
well, how should it work?
And one of the constraints actually is
the way we kind of do our characters,
it would have been pretty hard
for the character to move and fire.
But every gun in every video game allows the character to move and fire, basically.
So how to get around such a constraint.
And so my brilliant idea was, you know, maybe the character could float and it would be fine,
you know, and that wasn't fine.
We didn't do that.
Instead, he plants his feet in place.
It looks sensible.
It feels good.
I'm happy to where we got with that.
But it's a good example of, you know, when you think about like functional collaborative teams,
some
sometimes I think about like, well, how much do you have to talk?
Because when you have a conversation, now we're going to be using our words.
And luckily we all practice communication well, and we,
we practice trying to improve it and, and get, and, and get good at it.
But like a way easier way to do that is to demonstrate the work.
And so, you know, if someone can make a thing and show it to you,
the conversation can be more focused around the thing that was made.
And is it getting us closer to our goals or is it pushing us further from our goals?
And so as a team, we've become very, like, sort of cognizant about
conversations that are going along. It's like what's missing here? Like what is
is there is actually something that someone needs to kind of take back into their own
mental space or work on something and bring it back to the group.
Is there really something we can talk ourselves out of or around?
And I think that's like an example of, you know,
a sensitivity to something that we we we've developed over time.
I tell you, someone who's very good at this actually, our creative director, Greg,
you know, the the the you and I have actually talked about this before, but.
Hades used to be about a different character.
It used to be about-
Yeah, I'm gonna bring that up.
Yeah, it's the story of Theseus
going into the labyrinth to slay the Minotaur.
That was originally the game we were gonna make.
And when it came time to draw the main character,
there was aspects of it that weren't really coming together.
And we're talking about it.
And Jen and Greg were talking about it.
And-
Greg felt like there was just something missing.
And so he came back from his Christmas break
and he had this idea,
which is like, what if, you know,
you play as the son of Hades,
you play as Zagreus, this character,
and it's a little known character from Greek mythology,
and you're trying to get out of hell.
And every time you try to, you fail, you know,
your dad pulls you back into your house.
And,
I think that's an example of an idea that like six or seven years earlier might have
taken us like a month or two or three to get used to.
But like in a week, a lot of the characters Greg had described in that idea were like
kind of in the game in some form.
And him and Jen were kind of off to the races on a revision.
And so much of what we had made to that point,
because Greg, of course, was internalizing the constraint
of how do we keep the Greek myth stuff that's working?
Like, how do we keep aspects of the gameplay
and stuff that's working?
How do we keep aspects of this?
Like we had this Olympian boon system
where the Olympians would empower you
and that was working too.
So like, what is the idea that keeps that,
but gets us around?
this issue we're having with drawing the main character.
And frankly, it didn't even appear as an issue at first.
It did to Greg and Jen when they were working on it,
but it didn't appear like as like a,
it wasn't like a stop the presses,
everyone let's get into a room and figure this out
and talk it out.
And so the dominoes fell really fast
when Greg came back with that.
And one after the other.
people contributed their piece to this new idea
and came together really fast.
And it was, you know,
we've had sort of main character changes
and big changes like that on other games.
They take a really long time this time of day.
So I don't know, just went way faster.
Just went way faster.
And I mean, I was gonna ask too, like, okay,
well, how long did that kind of decision take to propagate?
through because it seems like it would be a big thing but I think that you're right about there's
this kind of non-verbal like kind of component to things like that that when it was like slightly
off somehow in a way that wasn't really conscious with the team and then when the solution was
presented it was just kind of like oh yes like this is the right.
Yeah, it's like your mind opens up. It's like, you know, you see the humor in the idea he's
talking about, the characters he's contemplating, you see exactly how the stuff we've made
mostly fits with it, you know, at that point, and how it actually gets us closer to the stated
goals we had for the project in a lot of ways. And so...
you know, he tried the work, he put it in the game.
It's part of the reason, you know, Darren voiced Zagreus,
and we thought it was scratch.
Like we thought it was all a scratch for like
a bunch of months and months and months.
And you got stuck being the main character.
Yeah, because, you know, we have Logan Cunningham,
who's our principal voice actor,
who was the voice of the narrator in Bastion
and the Arch-Justice Empire and the voice in Transistor.
And, you know, so Logan is, you know,
playing all these parts of the game,
plays six or seven parts or something.
And, you know, he's,
And we're like, you know, well, Logan, of course, all of these are going to stay.
But this Darren one, you know, who knows?
And then, yeah, it's like frickin worked.
So, you know, after a while, it felt like it was the right thing.
So, yeah, I mean, even you talking about it now, I'm like, I, you know,
my mind goes from the like, oh, it'd be cool to go fight a minotaur.
So like, oh, yeah, like, you know, with the context of having Hades already out.
Yeah, yeah.
All my original ideas, you know, but like it does kind of like open up a like.
like, ooh, like that's a really cool,
like there's this and then there's this, you know?
And you know, the key thing there is it, it, it turned,
it, it, it added a more of a family story to the game.
And the family story is, I think one of, you know,
the Olympians are one big dysfunctional family
in the way that Greg has been thinking about them.
And, and, you know, Zagreus and his dad
and his principal goal of trying to find his mother.
And so all of these types of things,
you know, you, you, as creators, you bring your own experience to it, but you just, you, but you
also see like, wow, the possibilities of this are really interesting. And, and what would happen if
we, if we did it? Yeah. Want to know.
Yeah, and I mean, I think this is a good example of another question that I had actually heard
gotten from another developer around, you know, was there any kind of decision, you know, that
you guys made design-wise, business, whatever, that didn't like seem totally intuitive at the
time that now you look back at it and you're like, yeah, that was...
that was clutch, you know, I mean, that was a big answer to that, you know, like,
oh, we changed the entire main character and story of the game.
Yeah, yeah, we did that. That was pretty, that, yeah, that's a good one.
Yeah, that worked out pretty well. You know, it's, it's, it's tough to say there's two or three
things. I guess, um, there's at least a few things that we tried that I can say with certainty,
we didn't know if they would work. Um, you know, um, some of them were technical, like we,
we converted our whole engine from C sharp.
to a native C engine so that we could be on the switch at 1.0
and when we came out of early access in September 17th.
So there's probably two other things that come to mind.
So this isn't an unexpected design decision,
but it's like one of the most potent design mechanics
in the game is actually inspired a lot by
by mechanics in other games, like the,
if you remember in World of Warcraft,
they introduced the rest system,
which was like shocking at the time,
which is like, instead of penalizing you
over and over for dying,
they were like, what if you had to like, sort of,
if you like accumulated rest and you logged off,
you would get this experience bonus.
They turned, you know, mechanics that were often
kind of really punitive into some sort of positive.
sort of formatting.
And so there was, you know,
we have examples or versions of mechanics
like that in the game.
So we have this dark thirst mechanic,
which incentivizes you to try and follow
the bonus the weapon is applied to.
And, you know, we see that that's pretty effective
at getting people to try different stuff,
even though they could just use the same thing
over and over and over again.
You know, there's other things like that,
that,
that come to mind, but I'm...
Well, I was gonna say, so my other kind of
like tangential question to this,
cause there's a little bit of this
in the Noclip documentary about it,
like a kind of just really sort of like funny bug
that made it into like, got patched eventually.
But it kind of got me thinking,
there's like whole blogs dedicated to like the Sims
just going off the roof, you know,
like somebody's like through the roof or whatever.
Like, was there like a bug or just something that happened
when you guys were doing it?
Or it's just like...
Obviously you can't keep it in, but just like the best bug.
Yeah, you know what?
There was like a, I don't know if there was a best bug,
but one of my favorite bugs was the,
I like to think about it as like,
I don't know, it's something about it just like,
it's very heartwarming to me.
We had a bug.
Okay.
Someone realized when you throw the shield
and you put the Aries boon on it,
which is supposed to give it a curse,
It doesn't work.
So we're reading Discord and we're like,
geez, that's weird, did we miss that?
So we go put the Ares curse on the shield
and sure enough, it doesn't work.
And so we're like, all right, you know what?
Let's fix that, we'll push it into Knight's Patch.
Fix it, push it into Knight's Patch.
And then a bunch of people are killing themselves
in the game and we're like,
well, you can't really kill yourself,
there's no way to do that.
Yeah, yeah.
And we realized that
because the shield comes back to you after you throw it,
that when you threw the curse out,
it would stay attached to the shield to come back to you
and then apply the curse to you.
And then if you had low enough health, you would just die.
And so it was like, I like to think of it as heartwarming
because it's like everyone doing the right thing.
It's like, you know, a person found a bug, they reported it,
you know, on our site, someone fixed it.
Yeah.
And you know.
we were like, this looks pretty good. We put it in. Um, and then it's like,
Oh, everyone's dying now. Um, and then, and then we fixed that, you know,
it was like, it was hot fixed. Um, and you know, we,
we improved our process and stuff, so stuff like that didn't happen as often.
Um, but yeah, I mean, there's, there's stuff like that where it's just, um,
yeah, where it's, it's a little bit, it's one of those things where it's just really.
you, the surprises are really fun.
There were probably lots of things like that
that I just don't remember during our early access.
I mean, that's the thing that's kind of interesting
with games when you're troubleshooting,
like from before I was in the games industry, you know,
like I just kind of assumed that like whoever created
the game had this like.
godlike ability to just make the game do whatever, which you kind of do.
But really what you're doing is you're like creating a bunch of systems
that you sort of have control over, but like act in very strange ways.
Like there's a part in the documentary where you guys are putting the trailer
together and you're like.
You know, the way a lot of those like videos and screen captures and stuff is like somebody
plays it until a thing happens.
It's really cool and you record it and they're like, oh, you know, can we have the blood
effect or something?
And I just like kind of dawned on me that it's like, you can't just like make the game
do the thing that you want to do to like record it, which is like a very strange.
thing to do where you're making something that you kind of don't really fully understand and
then how you test that and how it all interacts with each other, which I think is why the Sims
has bugs that just go off the rails because there's so many systems that are interacting
with each other. But Hades had a lot of that, right? Like there's an insane amount of branches.
Yeah, interacting and overlapping systems. That's also the power of early access to help us
understand it and a really good QA team. But yeah, I mean, there's so many permutations.
and so many things that can happen in a game.
You know, for us, I think the hard part actually at first
was to embrace the idea that we were now making,
because we had made these sort of,
Pyre was our first time where we made a game
where there were so many choices
that we knew that we weren't going to experience them all.
Yeah.
And as developers.
And...
But it still went somewhere that was semi-controlled
until the end when there's all these different permutations
and the game puts together a ballad that reacts
to all the decisions you've made in the game.
In Hades, examples of things we had to become comfortable
with as a team who worked the other way was,
we weren't gonna know.
We weren't even gonna have a chance to know, actually.
how the whole thing might feel or come together
in any given update cycle.
And even, you know, it's quite interesting.
People are like, when you were playing Hades,
when did you know it would be what it became?
And it's like, what's very surprising is that
we didn't know that.
Like Hades was in early access for a long time,
so we thought we kind of understood the kind of game it was.
And we, and, you know, we started doing our final playthroughs the summer before it came
out with the ending that we had always anticipated.
And we knew we were going to have a game that had an ending.
Even if you could, if you could, well, we had, you know, it sort of has multiple phases
of that, but it's something that we, we knew we were going to put in the game, the narrative
resolution.
Yeah.
And even then it's like, you know.
It's just one of those things where we, you know,
we experience stuff, we push it around,
we try to feel out what works,
but it's still hard to play your own game like a player.
Yeah.
It's like one of the play acting things
that I find really, really, really hard to do.
Yeah.
And it's actually part of the thing with capture too.
Capture is different than even that.
Capture is performative play.
It's like, how do you play so that it,
Like one of the worst things, Greg Kassabon, our creative director, and James, one of our people
who does QA, like they did a lot of the actual like stuff that gets captured. It's like if they
have to try to recapture something, mostly as is, but just a little bit different, like yes,
they can load the save and try and do it, but a lot of weird stuff happens when you're going
through such a process. So yeah, anyway, I mean.
I mean, I guess it's deeply dissatisfying answer of, I don't know.
And yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. I don't know.
Yeah, I mean, it's kind of it's interesting.
And I'm you know, I'm sure there's a lot of other art that is like this where,
you know, to go back to the earlier thing of like, you know,
how much it kind of sinks in while you're working on a project like this,
but it stays with you forever.
But it is also something that you kind of don't have control of,
especially after it goes out into the world.
And now in a lot of ways, it is like the players.
you know, the player's idea of it and the perception of it
and the changes that were made because of those decisions
and things like that.
So it's kind of like, I don't know,
I don't want to liken it so much to like having a child
cause I don't actually have that full experience, you know,
but it kind of feels a little bit like,
it's like you kind of have this thing that you're building
and creating and, you know, have some control over
and it just, it kind of grows.
And at some point it is kind of no longer yours, but always.
always with you, you know, in a way.
And it's kind of like, I think launching a game
and that creative process to me is like one of the most
kind of like vulnerable and intense
and kind of like strange experiences
that I think a creative person can go through.
And I've seen it with so many developers, you know,
like putting something out like that out in the world,
I think is actually pretty like, I don't know,
like courageous or something in a way.
It's pretty scary.
Yeah, yeah.
Well, we have each other, so we're not doing it alone.
you know, and we have our, we have our fans and the people who were there for us from the start,
who really, um, who really voiced, you know, sort of bolster us and, and believe in us.
And, and, um, so we have those things and so you obviously want to continue to earn their trust.
Um, so you, um, you need to, you need to stay vigilant, but yeah, I mean.
The thing you said is very similar to something I've thought about a lot and sometimes we
talk about on the team, you know, it's like the part of the game that was ours was always
just the part we hadn't released because I really love this phrase that I hear Gavin
use a lot.
It came out of one of his learnings on Hades, which is like,
when we talk about the feature week,
we say the feature is done after two weeks, but it's not.
The phrase he really likes to use
is that it's like ready to begin.
It's like ready to start because now it needs content.
Now it needs iteration.
Now it needs QA.
Now it needs audio.
Now then, when an update is done,
it's actually ready to begin again
with the players in early access and their feedback
and our patching process on that,
and then wrapping that,
and then bringing that into the next.
update all the way until it's done.
So that's why I think also for developers,
the experience of finishing a game can be profoundly sad
because everything you're talking,
the upside of everything you're talking about,
of the creative, how compelling it is to work on something,
how much it seeps into your mind and your life,
the sense of the rhythm
and how many things are ready to begin.
And then you're actually at a point now,
actually we're out of ready to begin.
you're like ready to be done.
And that's like a different way of doing it.
And then, like you said, it's more than yours.
Something like Hades, which I'm very proud of,
and I'm very proud of the team that made it,
it gets this reaction partly because
of what players bring to it.
Yeah.
And, you know, the experience is a collaboration
between us and them in some way.
And so, yeah, I mean,
I feel very fortunate, the whole team feels very fortunate
to have been able to do this work, to finish it,
to have made something that so many people
have connected with,
but they brought their experiences to it.
So like they brought themselves to the game,
they brought their imaginations
to fill in the parts of it that we as a small team
can't always create, right?
There's not lavish, giant lavish cut scenes
to describe every interaction, right?
So,
the things they brought to it, I feel like very honored
that we could be part of that process for them.
Yeah.
So that part feels quite good
for I think everyone on the team.
Yeah, that's a really like kind of like wonderful way
to think about it.
Actually, while you're talking about that,
it kind of reminds me of my art teacher in high school
had said that like, basically a painting is never done,
you just decide to stop working on it.
It's like, and there are, you know,
and I've seen it in a lot of creative fields
where people just will work on perpetually,
work on something.
you know, and never like quote unquote finish it.
And I think, you know, there's so much and you can go so far down
into the process that like kind of being done with something
is just like deciding like I am done, you know.
And one of the other questions actually I had for you is like,
do you feel like Hades is like done, you know?
Yeah, so, so, you know, part of the way we, I've, I've asked and asked that question.
I find it really hard to answer.
How do you know when you're done?
And, and, and I'll answer your question in a moment, but we often try to think about
like completeness, completeness to us is different than perfection.
Completeness is like all the parts have a reason to be there and nothing is extraneous.
Yeah. So, yeah, I'm just going to have Amir kind of summarize.
I'd ask him if it felt like
the game was like done.
Yeah. What they're what they're working on now with it.
So, yeah, you know, we have the Xbox and PlayStation launches
coming up on August 13th, as I mentioned.
And so, you know, we're you know, it's still an active part of our of our
of our.
lives, you know, we just released a patch that added Japanese and all this kind of stuff. So,
you know, while we were working on Hades, we patched Pyre. We just, we just, the games are
just a part of our studio, right? And, and so they're, they're.
you know, it's always these little, little things for sure.
Yeah. Yeah. I think another one of my favorite parts of the Noclip documentary is like one of
the very last things that Danny asked you is like, what are you working on next? And you're like,
we're making, we're doing a patch. It's like literally what you've been doing for like the
whole like three year documentary, however long it was, was like, we're Danny, we're making a patch.
So Danny, Danny, Danny did a great job on the Noclip series. We're really like lucky to be
working with him. But, you know, I think.
the thing that working on it showed is just like,
Danny's amazing.
It's just like he was just a part of the making of that game as far as I think a
lot of us are concerned because he, he, you know,
he added something which we might not have done ourselves,
which is like an opportunity to reflect on it while it was happening. Um,
and so it's a wonderful gift. Um, and, and so, yeah,
we're really, we're really grateful to him for that. And
Yeah, you know, he knows as well as anyone.
It's like, wow, that stuff just,
sometimes it just feels like it might not stop.
Yeah, you know, I think that that's really poignant
to kind of say about the chance to have reflection,
especially even while you're working on it,
or even now to be able to look back at it.
You know, I remember,
I think it was Michelle Obama or something was talking about her book and she was like, you know,
we had this really interesting opportunity that a lot of people don't have is that I basically
had the time and the space to sit down and write this book and reflect on like what happened to us
over the last eight years. You know, a lot of times you're just kind of going, going, going,
and you don't really get to like kind of.
understand the progress that you're making or, you know, the kind of the true length of the journey
because you're not documenting it in that way or you're not getting the time to reflect on it. So
I actually think it's like incredibly cool that you guys are always going to have this like thing
that you can look at and see like the reactions of like, what was it going to feel like when we
launched it? And what was it going to, you know, like watching to see what you're nominated for?
Like you get to like have that, you know, recorded for yourself, which is, which is amazing.
It's an amazing gift, you know, if you, if you
if you have a learning orientation, as we do as a studio, it's really useful because you can keep
kind of taking your experience and pushing it forward and all that kind of stuff. But you quite
easily forget, I think, even if you don't have that, if you do or don't have that, like what
the experience of doing the thing was actually like at the time you did. And now inescapably,
we will always know. You will always have that. You will always have that image of you watching
yourself on Nintendo Direct. Yes, I can see that. In your hoodie.
I can reprise that scene anytime. But yeah, that makes sense.
Yeah. So we're coming up in the last few minutes here, which I'm kind of a little
bummed about because I feel like I could talk to you about this stuff forever.
I did have one last one last question. You know, is there any like, is there any game
or piece of music or book or like thing or something that you're just like really
into right now or thinking a lot about or anything that you kind of just want to like?
talk about or plug?
Yes, I want to talk about, so there's so many,
there's a lot of inspiring and amazing work being done
by a lot of developers out there.
I have personally been really inspired lately
by the work of YouthCat Studios
who made Dice and Sphere Program,
which is an early access game.
That game does like everything.
that a sensible independent developer
would tell another independent developer not to do, right?
It's like massive scope.
It's a game with a whole universe inside of it.
And like all the universe is inside of it.
And it's just, it's an amazing,
amazing, compelling game that has so many moments.
that open your mind a little bit more to what the game is
and what it could be and how expansive it could be.
And it does it in a very smart way.
I love it.
And I found out the game is made by a small number of people.
Interesting.
It's a really small team.
And I had the joy of tracking down their email
and sending them a note.
They sent something back, which was nice too.
I'm sure they were very excited about that.
Well, I was just excited.
Yeah, I was just excited to tell them their game is so good.
You know, when...
Uh, when people make something like that, that gives you like energy,
like creative energy to do stuff because you sit there and go, how did they do
this? Like, how did they do this as such a small team? How did they do this? Um,
and, um,
I just get a lot out of that.
So they've given me a tremendous gift.
Yeah, I love when game developers geek out
on other developers' games.
Like it's one of my favorite things.
Yeah, I know.
The other game that did that for me
in the last couple of years was Stardew Valley for sure.
So there's, you know, I mean,
think there's people on the team,
they can rattle off a list of them.
These are just mine for sure.
I feel quite lucky.
I don't even want to go down the rabbit hole of us.
No, no, it's okay.
We don't need to.
Anyways, so we're going to wrap up there and just as a kind of parting thing, Amir, if
there's anything like, you know, where, where can people find Hades and like follow you
and all that stuff?
Yeah.
Hades is out on, on PC and the Nintendo switch.
And then on August 13th, it will be out on Xbox and PlayStation.
of this year and thank you so much to all our players
and thank you to the Game Developers Conference
for nominating us for six awards in tonight's show.
We're really excited to see how that goes.
Yeah, great, awesome.
Yeah, and thank you so much, Amir,
for taking the time to do this
and for asking me to have this conversation with you.
I'm really excited about it.
So I'm happy we made this happen.
Yeah, awesome, thank you.
All right, great, thank you.
All right, bye everyone.