All right, so my name is Bruno Velasquez.
I'm the Animation Director at Sony Santa Monica.
I've been with the studio since 2006,
so I had a long relationship with Kratos,
about 13 years or so.
My first game at the studio was God of War II,
and that was a great experience,
working with Cory Barlog as Game Director,
and for this latest project,
had the opportunity to work with him again,
which was great.
This is my first animation bootcamp,
so this is amazing that I get to be here
with all of you guys, talk about animation.
It's amazing, I'm so happy to be here.
So thank you for having me.
And the name of my talk is God of War,
Breathing New Life into a Hardened Spartan.
So God of War, it's a franchise from Sony.
It's on the eighth game now.
The latest one came out last year.
And it centers around a Spartan named Kratos.
The first seven games pretty much
delved into Greek mythology.
And the latest one, we decided to take it
into the Norse realm.
Now, one of the biggest things when Corey Barlog first
set off to give us the mission on how we were going
to make this game, one of the challenges for animation
was how we're going to reimagine Kratos.
How are we going to present him in a new light?
We kind of wanted to not completely throw everything
away that we did in the past before,
but we want to kind of depict him in a new light,
present him in a new way for new audiences,
and also to please the fans that had been with us for so long.
So our first mission was to reimagine Kratos.
How were we gonna do that?
So most everybody knows Kratos this way.
They remember him from previous games
in a path of vengeance and rage and destruction.
You know, that was his mission, right?
It was to get revenge, to get payback from the gods.
So in order to kind of change a little bit
of that perception, we needed to focus on the humanity.
So we need to make a conscious effort
on how we're gonna show more of the human side of Kratos.
So from an animation standpoint,
that was a very interesting challenge for us.
So when you think of a character like the Hulk,
I had to make my own drawing just to be safe.
Don't wanna make anybody mad at me.
But when you think of a character like the Hulk,
you know, there's two sides of him, right?
There's the Hulk side, the angry green guy,
and then there's Banner, there's the human side.
So what we needed to do was explore that for Kratos, you know.
Those Kratos, what about Kratos?
Does Kratos have that side?
Or is he all just full of rage?
So if you look back into the previous games,
there were little glimpses of that humanity.
We didn't show them very often,
but there was a little bit, right?
He at one point wanted to save his brother,
wanted to rescue him once he found out
that he was still alive.
His brother Deimos was, fought alongside with him
for a little bit before he lost him again.
There was moments where he showed compassion
and care for his family,
even though he ended up tragically by mistake killing them.
But there was glimpses there that he missed them,
he wanted to embrace them and be with them once again.
And of course, the moment of regret and remorse
where he pretty much wanted to end it all.
He wanted to move on, he couldn't deal with it.
So definitely, as much as we showed moments of power
and strength in Kratos, there was also a little bit
of the human side kind of sprinkled throughout the games.
You know, it wasn't all about ripping people's heads off.
Well, actually, it kind of was, most of the time, right?
But we had to basically ask ourselves,
how are we gonna go from this to something like this?
where Curtis is gonna be a teacher, a mentor, a protector.
That was just something that we hadn't done much of before.
So one of the first things that we did
is we looked at his proportions.
If we wanted to have someone that people can sympathize
with more, we need to revisit the way he looked a bit.
This is Kratos from the previous games.
The proportions are a bit wacky, I gotta admit.
He's got super long arms, super long legs, a tiny head.
I mean, look at his hands.
He can crush his own head.
Just, it's a little bit off, right?
But in the end, for what we needed these proportions for,
it kind of worked out.
You know, we were going for more of this comic book
over the top style in the previous games.
So those proportions kind of read well
in the poses that we needed him to be.
Not to mention that the perspective of the game
was much farther away.
So he needed to read a lot clearer.
So those proportions worked well.
Now, one of the first things I did,
once Corey gave me the direction of like,
well, he's gonna be a father figure,
he's gonna have a son,
so I just kind of scrambled and looked for some old models,
or just grabbed whatever we had at the time
at the beginning of the project,
started posting cradles out in different situations.
In this case, I just grabbed,
actually, that's his brother Demos as a kid.
So it's a little weird to have his younger brother there.
But that was all we had to represent Atreus at the time.
So in these, I kind of just wanted to explore
what it would feel like for Kratos to be a protector.
And also a teacher and a mentor.
So here are some early poses of him teaching his son
how to hunt, how to use the bow.
And also a situation which you would never really see
in the previous games, just sitting down and talking,
having a conversation, eating and drinking.
When did Kratos ever do that, right?
So we wanted to start exploring those things.
But as you can see, the proportions, you know,
the old models, yeah, it still was a little bit off.
So as the script progressed, there was a couple of scenes
that we found out about where Kratos, you know,
the son was gonna be sick at one point.
Kratos had to put his hand on his son's shoulder
at one point, even though it took him a little bit of time
to do that in the game.
He was also meant to carry him at one point in his back
during the climbing sequences.
So I started posting this old models.
And as you can see, yes,
the proportions needed some development
in order for him to feel a little bit more human.
So the Concept Art team started working on that.
As you can see, this is very, some early concept
where he started to,
they started taking inspiration from the previous games
and the way that he looked.
I started adding the beard,
started adding the Norse motifs to him.
And as you can see, he has a bit more of a human proportions,
a little bit closer to a more relatable human.
Even his weapon, as you can see, at the early stages,
there was no, it wasn't a magical axe.
It was just a simple weapon that he was to use.
The direction of the game early on was very grounded.
It was meant to be a lot more realistic.
And in the early beginnings, as I will show you,
some of the early animation was very grounded
and more not as sort of over the top as it ended up being.
So we had to dial that in to make it work
with the direction of the game.
Here's a shot of...
The 3D model, as if it was making progress.
This is around the time of the E3 reveal in 2016.
The first time that we showed Kratos to the public,
the new Kratos emerging from the shadows.
So as you can see already, he was starting to feel
a little more human than how we previously depicted him.
But of course, he needed to, again, interact with his son.
So even though he had more human-like proportions now,
he still needed to feel like a giant amongst men.
So even the interactions with the son,
while they worked in the game, he was still a pretty large man.
The next thing that we needed to look into was posing.
How are we gonna create our poses in our animation
to best depict Kratos in this new light?
Older, grounded, sort of more weathered warrior.
So looking back at the previous games,
this is some of the poses that we went for more
heavy metal magazine cover.
type of look, comic book over the top.
And many of these poses, what's interesting
about these poses is that many of these poses
were done by the animators.
So we did not really want other teams,
like marketing teams working on our poses
as much as possible, because we wanted to maintain
the feel of the character throughout, even in marketing.
So I'm sure many of you guys have spent so much time
posing, developing base poses for your characters,
combat poses.
And then all of a sudden, marketing comes back
with these T-shirts, and you're like, wait, who made that pose?
Where did that come from?
And that's pretty horrifying.
So we definitely wanted to maintain that
across not only the game, but marketing materials as well.
So taking this concept of these over-the-top poses,
we needed to apply those to our older, hardened Spartan.
So while we did not push it as far as we did in the previous games,
we still had hints of that.
As you can see in his blocking post, still
needed to be dynamic and strong and grounded,
but a little more grounded than before.
And even when he interacts with enemies and kills them,
yes, it's a bit over the top,
but it's a little bit more grounded
than it used to be before.
So we needed to keep that in mind
as we were posing anything that had to do with Kratos,
you know, animation, combat, idols, anything.
He's not quite as hunched down as he used to be overall.
That was one of the main things.
We didn't want to get him as slow
as he was in the previous games.
Another aspect of grounding Kratos was Atreus.
So Kratos was there to help his son teach him
how to be a god, how to be a warrior, how to survive.
But at the same time, the importance of Atreus
was there to make Kratos feel more human.
In the previous games, Kratos would walk around
and meet people and maybe say a word
and then kill them most of the time.
So we needed to have an emotional anchor.
Atreus was basically there to be the eyes
and the voice of the player.
Kratos would not...
when he would travel in the previous games, he didn't wonder where this statue came from or
what it said, what message was written on the wall. So by presenting Atreus and then
partnering him up with Kratos, we were able to, you know...
sort of get conversations actually happening between two characters, which just didn't happen
before. And this way, our goal was for the player to get to know Kratos a little more and to get
Kratos out of his comfort zone. And by having a young son there that he needed to look after and
interact with, that was, it offered a lot of opportunities for us to do that.
Now, a bit of the studio culture too.
You know, as the studio grew and the team grew, so did we.
And many of the team members became parents,
we got married, had kids.
And that kind of changed the way we saw things, you know?
We wanted to tell different types of stories as well.
So this was part of the big influence
of why we decided to...
re-imagine creatives and make them more relatable.
Previously it was like the Greek era,
it was kind of like the college years, right?
You know, having a little more fun.
Well, you know, not that we're not having fun still,
but the Norse era is a bit more like,
okay, you know, let's try to tell some different stories
that, you know, perhaps we can share
with our kids someday as well, without being too embarrassed.
Not that the previous games are embarrassing,
but I would definitely wait a while
before I would show my daughters those games,
that's for sure.
And I would have to explain a lot of things.
So Kratos was also meant to be a father once more.
We felt that that was the best way for him
to have an arc of redemption,
to have someone that he needed to care for.
And that was the best way to.
for people to sympathize with him.
So speaking about the animation style,
we needed to make a switch in our animation style
if we wanted to depict Kratos in a more relatable way.
This is why early on we decided to look into motion capture.
So the previous God of War games were primarily keyframe.
About 90% was all keyframe, 10% motion captured.
And the motion capture was reserved for cinematics mainly.
But everything else, including facial animation,
was keyframed, all the bosses, combat, enemies,
all the Kratos moves.
And here's some examples of some of the early keyframe animation that we did from the previous games.
As you can see, the moves are a little bit more arcadey over the top.
Often we, you know, especially with the blades, we could just create massive arcs,
where we didn't have to worry about the camera.
And often we defied the laws of gravity.
But once we moved into motion capture, we learned a lot.
We learned a lot about the process
because we hadn't really used it for combat before.
So here's an example of a move.
And this is footage from the motion capture stage.
This is the data.
As you can see, it got us about 80% of the way, right?
And then our animation team would go in and enhance it.
Without the keyframe knowledge and experience,
we wouldn't be able to do it.
Now, these moves are, at 60,
they're actually exported with a lot more frames.
Because then, once we get into the game.
the fidelity of the chain blades would read a lot better.
That's why we had to export those
with a little bit higher frame rate.
And of course, motion capture gave us the fidelity
for scenes like this, where we really needed to
express a little bit more emotion
to try to get Kratos to feel more relatable.
So motion capture gave us
a bit of a shortcut to get to that a lot faster.
We still had to do a cleanup pass and then keyframe pass
and enhance pass on most of our cinematics,
but without essentially the amount of,
with the amount of scenes that we had to do,
it would have taken a lot longer
to keyframe out everything.
It just wouldn't have been possible.
So how do we get a team of keyframe animators
to jump on board with this notion of,
hey, we're gonna introduce motion capture into this.
It was tough at first.
I mean, we as animators,
we love to just keyframe everything as much as we can.
But motion capture is a tool.
And the way we convinced them is we bought an accent suit and
we gave it to the animators like here, let's let's just try some stuff and
What happens when you give a mocap suit to an animator?
This happens
Yes.
So HR didn't know a lot of the stuff
was going on upstairs.
We would have had to sign all kinds of waivers.
But yeah, we liked it so much
that we ended up getting a second suit
so that we can do these kind of like paired up moves.
And by involving the animators in this process,
it actually got them to kind of start jumping on board.
It's like, okay, I see how this works.
I get to shoot the data and I drive the performance a bit
and then I get to clean it up
and I get to enhance it and push it.
So it's not like I'm eliminating.
my role, my job, I'm actually enhancing it.
And then I'm getting a lot of data a lot faster
and getting me about 80% of the way,
and then we would go in, add the extra layer
of awesomeness to it with Keyframe.
So yeah, this is me.
Also, I decided to jump in and try this with myself.
But early on, having said that early on,
like I mentioned before, the direction of the game
was to be a lot more grittier and grounded
and heavier and slower, so this is some of the first
bit of data, so yeah, this is exclusive,
Kratos killing Kratos.
And yeah, and as you can see, the axe was just a basic axe,
there was nothing fancy about it.
It was meant to be just this really gritty game.
So after we had the accent suits.
We decided, okay, well, you know, let's try this for real.
Let's go over to the mocap stage.
But we felt that we needed to try it out ourselves.
So this is Erika Pinto, our lead cinematics animator,
and Mehdi Yusef, our lead gameplay animator.
So we decided to go on stage ourselves and shoot a scene.
So the first scene that we collaborated on
that we did together was the ogre intro.
There's a moment in the game where this guy
comes through the door and attacks Kratos and Atreus.
So, I was Kratos, Mehdi was the ogre.
Erika is Atreus in this case.
And I just realized that Mehdi's actually
holding a cell phone, so I don't know why
an ogre would need a cell phone, but yeah.
He's just snuck in there.
So what we did in order to approach this,
because another part of the mandate
was to do this as a one-take game,
and I'll talk a little bit more about that.
in a later slide.
We decided to go and shoot this in live action first
and rehearse it and really rehearse it
over and over and over and over.
And then before we took it to the stage.
So I'll just show you this video and walk you through it.
So this is the footage of us rehearsing the whole scene.
Yeah, we had to get creative with the scale,
with the sizes to represent the sizes best as possible.
That was definitely fun and challenging.
Now, this is the footage, the video footage feed
that was on stage.
And this is how you see the scene being shot
in MotionBuilder, the MotionBuilder feed.
Now, the tricky thing about this scene
is that even though everything looks lined up
with the camera, the characters are interacting,
they were all different sizes.
So when we got to the stage, we had to deal with it.
We actually had to shoot the scene in separate spaces
so that the scale, in relative world space.
and we had to rehearse it in a way
that we were interacting with each other,
but apart from each other.
Now, as you can see there,
Dory, who's our director of photography,
is holding a marker.
This is before we had a virtual camera,
and he was actually walking around pointing the marker
and looking at the screens up on top
to get his framing right, right?
So that he can frame all three of us.
So he was using Kratos as the anchor.
for the scene and just in order for us
to be able to interact with each other in different scales,
we had to do that in our own separate acting spaces.
Now, what that got us was a scene that had all the
characters in a relatively solid timing
with the camera all in one, right?
And that is when Mehdi had to come in
and do the key frame pass on top.
But without this early sort of rough block out of the scene,
it just would have taken a lot longer to do,
a lot longer to pull off.
So he had a very solid base to go off of,
and this is what the final scene ended up looking like.
So it was definitely a lot of fun to do that.
And we got to learn a lot.
And as leads, if we went through the process,
understood the process,
then we can better have our animators join in with us
and help us out to get this done.
Definitely, you know, it went a little bit up to our heads.
But then after doing a full day of shooting,
we realized that we can't do this ourselves.
We need experts.
We need professionals to help us do this.
But it was great to at least go through that process once
and figure out how it all works.
So the benefits of motion capture for us,
it gave us a solid foundation for our keyframe animators
to push things a lot further.
We were able to complete over three hours of cinematics
in our game.
Without motion capture, it just would have been really tough.
And acquiring motion capture data
allowed us to focus on other cool things,
like stuff that couldn't be motion captured,
like these scenes that are mostly all keyframes.
So the dragon is all keyframed.
Kratos and Atreus is a combination
of keyframe and motion capture.
And of course, there's no way you can mocap this guy.
And Kratos and Atreus flying through the air,
definitely keyframe as well.
So it just freed us up.
It freed us up to do a lot more of this stuff.
So moving a little bit over to the narrative process,
we also needed to revisit our narrative process
to see how we're gonna depict Kratos
in a more relatable way.
So early on in the project, Corey,
he had the idea and the mandate of,
I wanna do this entire game as a one-shot, as a one-er.
And the reason for that is he wanted to
essentially sell the player on the idea of you're there with Kratos and Atreus
every step of the way. There's no like cutting away to meantime and the bad
guy's lair, you know, he's you know making this plan over there. No, no. He wanted
you to be there alongside Kratos for the entirety of the trip so that it felt
like you were there taking the trip alongside with them.
And this was done to enhance the personal narrative
between Kratos and his son.
So early on, we started,
how many of you guys have seen the movie Hard Boiled?
Show of hands.
Okay, all right.
Not as many as expected, but that's okay.
So,
We looked at a lot of films that had scenes
that had no cuts in them for reference and inspiration.
But there's one particular scene
in the movie called Hard Boil.
It's directed by John Woo, it's a Hong Kong action film.
Now, I was unable to secure the rights to show you the scene.
So I'll quickly describe it really quickly
just to make my point.
So in it, there's two detectives, two police officers.
There's one named Tequila.
I mean, that's his nickname, Tequila.
And the other one's Alan.
So they're going through this hospital,
having this intense shootout.
All of a sudden, elevator door opens,
Alan looks over, shoots someone
that's coming out of the elevator,
and then realizes that he's wearing an ID.
He's a police officer.
He just shot a police officer.
So he's in shock.
So his partner Tequila grabs him,
drags him into the elevator, the elevator door closes,
and he's just sitting there.
I can't believe I just shot a police officer.
This is, I can't believe I just did.
Tequila says, don't worry about it,
it wasn't a police officer.
don't worry, we need to get out of this thing,
we need to survive this.
You gotta keep focused on keeping us alive.
So the elevator doors open, they go out,
another insane shootout happens,
and soon after, Tequila says,
oh, by the way, the thing that happened
way earlier in the film,
I kinda shot a cop too by mistake,
and I know it feels horrible.
I can relate to you.
And then Alan says, wait a minute,
so you're saying that the guy I just shot in the elevator
was a police officer?
He goes, yeah, yeah, he was.
And then they go back to insane shootout.
Now everything I just described was all done
without any cuts, and all with practical effects
without any cuts.
So can we take that, so we saw that,
and we're like, okay, that's an amazing scene.
It had action, almost like gameplay,
and went into a shocking moment for one of the characters.
realizing that he just killed a fellow police officer,
he gets, you know, consoled by his friend,
and then his friend reveals to him that,
hey, I went through the same thing.
And then back to action.
So we got inspired by that.
We were like, that's amazing.
They were able to pull it off just as one scene.
Now how can we do it for the whole game?
So this is one of the first scenes early on
in the E3 demo that we showed
that kind of has a bit of that going from action
to an emotional moment back to action.
Ah!
Oh boy!
Wait!
What?
Off the ice! Now!
I am so sorry. I...
Your deer is getting away.
Yes, sir.
So without cutting away, we were able to have action,
a moment, a teaching moment,
where Kratos is trying to teach the sun
to take out the creature,
to an honest mistake by Atreus,
to a moment of bonding between them, so.
That was definitely something that we wanted to carry on
throughout the entire game.
So we needed help.
So we brought in Dori Arasi.
He's a director of photography that helped us get
everything that was on the script planned out
and laid out in a way that we can actually execute
the one take within the cinematics.
So if you guys have the time to spare,
definitely on Wednesday,
if you have a chance to go see his talk,
he's gonna dive a little deeper
into the emotional connection
through the cinematography in our game.
So please, if you have a chance to go check it out.
Because of this...
one-take approach, we had to,
we basically had to shoot our scenes more like a play.
We had to think of them more of a play than a movie.
Everything had to be done,
rehearsed very well and very closely.
Because we wanted you to have the experience of
watching a play that was happening in front of you,
being in a play that was happening in front of you,
rather than watching a movie, right?
So that was one of the mandates.
This is why we had to kind of start thinking about
plays rather than film, when we got inspired,
our inspirations.
And because of this, we had to do a lot of key,
a lot of previous, lots and lots and lots of previous.
And we employed all sorts of methods
for different situations.
So.
When we had things that were just impossible to shoot
or where characters had to cover large distances,
we used the keyframe method.
This is a scene in which Kratos is pushing a large hammer
and he and his son are riding it down all the way
so they could shatter the ice below.
But yeah, this is no way we could have done this
any other way to visualize how we were gonna do it.
The other method was we were fortunate enough
to have a small motion capture space also within our studio
where we could do previz.
We could do just simple motions before we went over
to the main stage.
So there were situations where we needed to previz characters
interacting with the environment or interacting
with certain creatures that we just needed to do it in 3D.
So yeah, that's a.
We needed to figure out the scale of this bore.
We needed to figure out where Freya was gonna be
interacting on the shelves,
where the characters needed to be standing and placed.
So this was how we would show this to our director
before we would get approval.
And then finally, my favorite way of doing previous
was live action, where the animators had an opportunity
to have a bit of fun.
And this is just one of the previous scenes
that we did out of many, many scenes.
The reason why we use live action
was because we could then go outside, go upstairs,
shoot a couple of scenes.
very quickly, show them to the director, get feedback,
and within the same day, we can go shoot them again.
And if he had more feedback for that, we can shoot it again.
And then it was just cost effective
and the speed of it was great.
And on top of that, we had to have a lot of fun.
That was something that might catch.
Well, that was a perfectly good waste of an afternoon.
How are you not seeing? There is nowhere to hide up here.
It's... it's a trick my people have. A special way of not being seen.
You can turn invisible?
More like I can step into the realm... between realms.
Huh.
And your mind can't understand what it's seeing, so it actually sees nothing at all.
It's how we avoid using the weapons that we actually craft.
But it doesn't seem to work on dragons though.
Hm, your brother wanted to know if you're eating well.
I can tell him that you are.
Brock asked about me? Was there meat on his breath?
You let him work on this again?
Come on.
So we have a couple of dwarf characters in our game.
So if you're wondering why they're just walking around
on his knees, that's why.
So we can get the scale approximation right.
So shameless plug number two.
If you have the chance to also go see Erica Pinto's talk,
she's the lead narrative animator.
And she will dive a little bit deeper
into the process, cinematic process, a lot more
than I am doing here.
So continuing on with this principle
of shooting everything as a play,
because of that, it became very apparent
that we needed to focus on rehearsal a lot more.
We couldn't just have actors show up the day of shooting.
So we did a lot of table reads,
a rehearsal day would look like in the morning,
get everybody together on the same page,
read the script, get everything planned out.
And then we would go step by step through each scene,
and Dory would film them, live action takes of every scene,
and then rehearse with them, the blocking, the staging,
the beats connected to their dialogue,
where they needed to be, when they needed to be,
at certain positions.
And here's a bit of the rehearsal footage
that we did for the opening of the game.
So some of you guys who may have played the game
will recognize this from the opening.
And action.
So this is the opportunity to get notes over to the actors
to dial in all the performances.
Also to work out where all our props are gonna be.
I want a big one.
And block out the timing of the camera.
So that rehearsal day became very critical.
So on shooting day, we did an all-in-one approach.
We captured the body data, the face data, the face cams.
We did audio recording.
So for the final performance,
I mean, we did have some ADR sessions,
but yeah, we pretty much got most of the dialogue on set.
And also the virtual camera.
So by the time a scene was delivered to us,
everything was pretty much dialed in
with the timing that we wanted.
So here's an example of us shooting a scene.
Corey's back there with the writers
overseeing the scene delivery.
And we get to see everything through MotionBuilder
as it's being shot.
So as you can see, this is a careful rehearse dance
between the actors and Dory
to ensure that we hit the beats accurately.
And our goal is to do it all in one take.
So another important part of the process was casting,
getting the right chemistry between our actors.
To make Kratos feel more human,
the anchor, emotional anchor was gonna be Atreus.
Luckily, we were able to find the right people for the job.
Christopher Judge as Kratos and Sonny Selgic as Atreus.
And once we got them together to do their chemistry test,
as I will show you in a second,
once we got that, we knew we had the right people.
Also, something that helped us out was,
even though we weren't casting for height,
It ended up being that our two-star actors
pretty much felt like Kratos and Atreus as it is.
They were the right height.
And then that made the cleanup process
and adjustment process a lot simpler
once we did the motion capture.
Now, one of the things that people like to say
is that, oh, don't work with animals, don't work with kids.
But for us, there was no other way to go
than to actually get a child actor.
There's no way that I feel that a adult
could pretend 100% to be a kid.
And it became apparent early on,
after we brought Sonny in.
This is one time we were just at the stage,
started messing around.
I might have said to hit play on the recording, maybe.
Maybe I did, maybe I didn't.
But yeah, definitely this kind of childlike movement,
you're not gonna get this from an actor,
from an adult actor.
It'll be a lot tougher.
It'll be a lot tougher for sure.
So this is why it was important for us to bring in Sonny
and to work with him.
Now, as I mentioned before, the chemistry test,
we actually hired Atreus first.
We found Sonny first,
since he was gonna be the emotional anchor for the game.
And then we brought the actors
that were trying out for the part of Kratos
to do the chemistry test with him
to see if it was gonna work.
I'm not fit to be a father.
Become everything I never wanted you to be.
Run.
Run far away from me.
But you have changed!
You're not a monster!
That is exactly what I am!
Not to me!
You will fail.
How you deal with it
is what makes you stronger.
My father
Yeah, so when we saw this, we knew we had the right people.
All right, so moving over to the combat animation process,
I wanna talk a little bit about that.
Early on, one of the things that was thrown out the door
was the blaze of chaos.
So,
The Blades of Chaos have a lot of history.
They have a lot of baggage with Kratos.
So what better way to present the character in a new light
than start stripping away some of the things
that were present in his past?
So early on, we decided that, and it was very scary.
It was like, how do you remove the lightsaber from Luke?
Right, like, no, you wanna try to maintain
as much of the character as possible.
But by stripping away these weapons,
it made him feel maybe,
a little bit different, more vulnerable in a way.
But at the same time, we wanted to replace those weapons
with another iconic weapon.
So this is why we decided to create an axe,
which is a little bit more,
it fits a little bit better within the Norse mythology
that we were moving onto.
And it sort of fits the fantasy of Mjolnir in a way,
the Thor's weapon, Thor's hammer,
where you can throw it and summon it.
But it wasn't like that at the beginning.
Like I mentioned before.
the moves were supposed to be very grounded and methodical
and not very magical at first,
because the game direction was to be a lot grittier.
But as we play tested and we moved forward,
we discovered that, hey, we need to kind of inject back
a little bit of the old God of War games into it.
So here's another pass, an early animation,
where we started like getting a little bit more
of that old Kratos movement back.
One of the things you notice is that he's actually throwing the axe as a boomerang.
This is when we start introducing some of the magical nature of the moves.
But they were gonna be part of the combo originally.
So before there were just gonna be button presses
and the axe would come out and fly out
and hit the enemies and come back automatically.
So it wasn't until the breakthrough for the axe
was definitely being able to throw it
and being able to summon it back.
And I mean that completely ties into the fantasy of Thor,
you know, the Norse myth.
So once we did that,
it definitely was what got us over the top
to be able to.
to make this into a...
a weapon that would stand side to side with the blades.
And in addition to that, the history of the axe
was that it was given to him by his wife,
rather than being given to him by a god
for as a weapon of destruction, right?
So it was more of a weapon of protection,
given to him by his own wife.
So already the story behind the weapon was different,
to try to make him feel a little more connected to it
in a different way than anger and rage.
Also, we had to deal with a new camera, right?
So since we needed to be closer in the cinematics
and the gameplay, so we had to be closer in the combat.
Long were gone the days where we could just do
crazy arcs over the top, you know?
And even though the Blades did make it back
as part of the story, sorry if, spoilers
for those of you who have not played the game.
But we couldn't get away with,
with doing these wide arcs anymore because of the camera.
We had to be up close.
So yes, we still had to animate everything
to look good from every angle,
but we particularly had to focus on making it look good
from a new camera perspective.
So as you can see, we pulled in the chains way more,
way more than it used to be.
It was meant to just read enough with the camera,
but still retain the same feeling from the old games.
And here's some examples of how both the axe and the blades
look from the new camera perspective in-game.
And as you can see, we definitely moved away
from the grounded feel.
And even though Kratos is jumping up in the air,
but he's not jumping as crazy as he used to
in the previous games.
So there's a nice blend that we were able to achieve
between the grounded and the previous games.
and also to utilize the keyframe animation talent
that we had in our studio.
But having said that, we still needed help
to get great motion.
So this is where Eric Jacobus comes in.
Now, he is an amazing stunt performer,
but in addition to that, he's a great director,
he's a fight choreographer,
and stunt coordinator, so he does pretty much everything.
And in addition to that, he has a great understanding
of the motion capture process.
He's one of the few stuntmen that I know, at least,
that is interested in motion capture technology
and how it works and how to best use it
for all kinds of needs.
So I came across a YouTube channel, his YouTube channel,
and I recommend if you guys have time,
take a look into his YouTube channel.
He has an amazing array of short films that he's directed
and he's put together with this amazing action.
And because of that, I was like, whoa, this is great.
This guy can do a bit of everything.
But the thing in his YouTube channel
that really attracted me the most
was a series of videos that he created
where he was reenacting moves from games,
from fighting games.
And let me give you an example of that.
Yeah, so he's essentially taking something
that was probably mo-capped and heavily worked on
by animators and key framed,
and then he's just recreating it in a live action.
So it's pretty amazing.
It's almost like he was doing exactly
what we needed him to do.
And having this direction of trying to make things
more relatable and grounded,
what better way than to get him in
to try to do the moves for us?
So he would lay out, his performance would give us
80 to 90% of the way so that we can then take
and push them a lot further.
So once I saw this video, I said,
please can we contact this guy?
Let's get him in our building.
And what happened was,
uh... before his
actual audition for for kratos all we said is
you're auditioning for kratos, he has an ex
that's it, that's all we told him
and days before uh... he was meant to come in for his audition
he sent us this all on his own
So as you can see, without any direction at all,
he was already brainstorming all these awesome,
cool ideas that we could use.
So at that point as well,
what was revealed to us from that footage was that,
okay, yeah, we need to work with this guy,
but we need to make him part of our team.
We need to bring him in.
So what we did a lot of was we brought him into the studio,
we walked him through the entire story,
we explained to him all the creator's rules,
what he can do, what he cannot do,
what kind of character he is,
what kind of personality he has,
what type of movement he does.
So we really got him involved
as almost like one of the members of the animation team
so that he would truly understand the character.
So that it wasn't just about,
okay, come in this day, here's your list,
and then just start acting these moves,
just copy what I'm doing.
So that was,
We tried that at first, and we got some good data,
but it wasn't quite what we could end up doing.
If we practiced with him more,
sort of like how we did with our actors
for their cinematics.
So here's an example of one of our animators, James Che.
recording sort of the motions that we needed to capture.
He's just kind of demoing for Eric
ahead of him coming into the studio.
And then we brought Eric in
and we just spent an entire day rehearsing,
practicing move, just.
so that we would have this footage ready to go
once we went over to the mocap stage.
And by the time we went to the mocap stage,
we were very efficient because he knew exactly
what to do.
We could always bring up the video footage
that he himself shot with us,
and then execute all the moves.
So here's an example of a move going through every step.
So this is James Previs.
Then we bring Eric in.
Then on stage, he knows exactly what to do.
And we can be a lot more efficient and focus
on the quality of the movement rather than the idea.
And this has been polished and enhanced by our animation team.
So yeah, keyframe animation is still critical for us
to push this stuff through to the next level.
So in conclusion, I see I'm running a little bit out
of time, so I just wanted to, you know.
Kind of recap, in order to breathe new life into Kratos,
we definitely had to focus more on the human side,
which we tried to do through animation
by getting more subtlety through motion capture,
by getting the right performances in.
We needed to evolve our animation team
to embrace the motion capture technology,
but also continue to play on the strengths
of key frame animation.
And because of that, we revamped our approach
to combat and narrative.
And again, finding the right actors
for not only the cinematics, but also for your combat motion
is essential.
But having said that, couldn't have done it
with an amazing animation team.
They did an amazing job, as well as the rest of the team.
They really pushed through to get this project out the door,
and I really appreciate all their help and effort.
Thank you very much.
So I think we have around eight minutes or so.
If anyone would like to ask any questions,
I would really enjoy answering anything you guys
may want to know about.
Oh, I believe there's a microphone in the aisles, right?
On each side?
Yeah.
So I was playing through the game, I'm not gonna spoil anything, but there was this moment where there was like a big reveal and
then Atreus's face got covered by Kratos' armor, and I had to reset and to
strip away that armor and see the scene again just because I wanted to feel and I couldn't see Atreus' face in that one.
Did the team ever consider like going back or forcing the like...
to use default armor on the scenes or maybe even animating the pieces so that they couldn't block
the view during cinematics? So that definitely was a big challenge for us because
this is the first time that you can, you know,
armor up Kratos, pretty much play dress up with Kratos.
And early on, as we were developing the scenes,
we knew that there was gonna be some there,
but once we got the concept and actually
the armors were made, there was a lot of situations
where we had to deal with that.
Unfortunately, we couldn't deal with every single situation
like the one you encountered, but...
we did go through some lengths, especially the most critical scenes that we felt we wanted to
not have any distractions. And while I don't want to steal the thunder from Erica's talk,
but she definitely goes into that a little more. But there was one particular situation where
when Kratos is pulling the boat and the sun is on the boat and he's pulling,
there's a rope slung over his shoulder, right?
So in that, it was so close there that you could see armor clipping depending on what armor you were using.
We actually created on a separate layer variable rope animations.
And there was maybe five or six different rope animations that would play specifically with what armor you were wearing.
So that way we could avoid, it would like,
okay, play rope animation A with armor sets one through six.
So there were situations where we did.
Unfortunately, we couldn't get through all of them.
But if we were to do this all over again,
we would definitely keep that in mind in the future.
Yeah, great question, thank you.
Hiya. So how challenging was to do seamless transitions into the cinematics to go from
gameplay into the actual into cutscene to have that awesome transition that you did?
It was very painful, very painful.
But over time, we developed a couple of tricks.
So most, a good percentage of the cinematics
began with a player interaction, right?
So at least we would know, you know,
opening a door or pulling a lever or something like that.
We would know that
where the player would be and where the camera would be.
So that helped with getting into cinematics.
The ones that were more challenging
were when you were just walking in a certain open area.
So for those, we had to do some careful planning
of the level layout where you would kind of get funneled
into a certain area by the art as you were walking.
And we had a bit of tech that would sort of take over
the character, over the player, without really trying
to make it as non-intrusive to the player.
But definitely, there's moments where you can walk backwards
into a scene, and the game would kind of take over
and spin you around slowly and walk you into the scene.
So hopefully people didn't do that too much.
Probably in the second playthrough,
when you can anticipate where there's a scene coming,
you could probably mess with it a bit.
But yeah, it was just careful planning,
knowing, trying to use the interacts as much as possible,
and kind of limiting those funnel points
where the tech would take over
and kind of steer the player into the scene.
Did you actually take control of the player to move it into a position?
So basically just seamlessly took control from the player and move it to that point.
So we actually did. Yeah, and we tried to make it as subtle and non-intrusive as possible.
and within a reasonable radius so that you didn't feel that you were being cheated.
You were like getting pulled when you're like,
oh, what's going on? My controller is not responding anymore.
So we try to make it, that's why the funnel points were very important.
Where like if you're already walking down a hallway,
the player already felt like, okay, well, that's where I meant to go anyway.
I'm sorry, just one question.
So how many mocap sessions you ended up recording in this project?
Oh, mocap sessions.
Oh, wow.
I don't have the number right off the top of my head,
but I think we had around 30 shoot days for cinematics alone.
Yeah, it was quite a bit.
OK.
Hey, so you mentioned earlier that when characters
were off the ground that it was keyframed animations.
So does that mean all the Valkyrie animations,
which were stellar, were those all hand-keyed then?
Yeah, so a great majority of those were done by Dennis Pena
and yes, they were keyframed.
Oh, that's awesome.
Yeah.
Tell him he did a great job.
Oh yeah, I will, I will, for sure.
I have a quick question on facial animation.
I hope that's not, that's probably done in another talk,
but I'm just curious about some of the biggest lessons
learned on getting those facial expressions
to read in cinematics.
Yeah, so we work with a really great partner,
Cubic Motion, and we were able to send the RL data with them
to get processed, you know, from the high-res videos.
So what we did is, once we got the actors' performance back,
We did an enhanced pass where we wanted to push a couple things here and there.
So we did spend a lot of time.
Some scenes were just perfect as is, driven by the actor's performance.
This is why it's really critical to get really good actors to work with you.
But definitely we wanted to, in certain cases, push it a little more.
So we did some work to keyframe on top of that as well.
What made you all decide to go with the staggered
Peter Jackson style shot in that pre-vis mo-cap scene
as opposed to just having you all right next to each other
and fixing it in post?
Oh, so that particular one, you're talking about
how it was being cross-dissolved?
Yeah.
Oh, that was just for, I wanted the talk
to be under an hour, so.
Yeah, but that is actually, that take is actually done
We did have one transition that we did
while we were doing the previous,
but most of our takes were done,
like live action takes,
were done like the one that I showed
with the guys on his knees,
were pretty much all in one take.
That particular one with the ogre
was cut down for time,
but in addition to that,
that did have a natural cross to solve,
just because we were just learning
how to do the stuff.
Yeah, that was one of the early ones that we shot.
Thank you.
Yeah, you're welcome.
Any other questions?
Yes, and then if there's no other questions,
we are hiring, so please, please apply
if any of you guys are interested.
But yeah, this is amazing.
I'm really happy to have been part
of the animation bootcamp finally,
and I'm definitely gonna enjoy the rest of the talks
for the rest of the day, and I hope you guys do as well.
So thank you very much for coming.
I really appreciate it.
Thank you.