to the state and future of board game design,
where I have with me, when you're ready.
Welcome, thank you.
My name's Paul Dean.
I'm one of the founders of Shut Up and Sit Down.
We have a huge games area.
Thank you. On the third floor in the corner of this hall, so if you'd like to come and play
games or look at games or watch other people playing games or just sit at a table and eat a
sandwich, which a lot of people are doing at the moment, please come by because we're there
like all week and it's quite a lot of fun and there's a lot of different interesting people. I
have very limited games design experience. I have been one of the team who helped create the
latest version of the Paranoia RPG, which is coming out soon I think, I hope, because we
finished it.
With me are people who are going to be better at introducing themselves than I will.
So I'm going to start on my left side with this fellow.
Who are you, sir, and what have you recently done?
Let's see if this microphone... Oh, microphone is on.
Hi, I'm Jeff Engelstein, and I guess my most recent games that came out were
the Dragon and Flagon board game and the Fog of War.
I've got two new games that are going to be coming out in the spring.
Pit Crew and The Expanse, based on the sci-fi show.
I'm also on the, thank you.
I'm also on the Dice Tower podcast,
do the game tech segment there,
as well as the Ludology podcast,
which is a hour-long podcast about game design
and various game-related topics.
Oh, yeah.
Good, okay.
Succinct, I heard succinct was the keyword.
I've been told to try and keep these people succinct, we'll see how that goes.
On my right, immediately next to me, I have a Canadian.
Would you introduce yourself, sir?
Hi, I'm a Canadian, and I'm sorry.
My name is Eric Lang. I'm a board game designer, a tabletop designer. I've been doing this for a
long time. I've been done, I've designed a lot of board games for Fantasy Flight, Cool Mini or Not, some work for Wizards of the Coast.
I've done some digital work on
Duelists, the online trading card game, which we're doing a talk for on Friday.
I've never been on Jeff Engelstein's Ludology podcast, so that clearly I'm the lesser of the guests.
It's a definite snub.
And a bunch of other games that I'm forgetting here in this moment.
You did Blood Rage.
I did Blood Rage, there we go.
And furthest on my right I have the foremost expert on Eric's portfolio, as Eric isn't.
You are, sir?
My name is Rob Davio, I've been doing professional board game design since 1998, 18 years, 14
of which was at Hasbro, so I've worked on a lot of classic games, Clues and Monopolies
and Risks.
I've been doing about four years on my own, where you probably, if you know me, know me from asking to rip up cards with legacy games.
So, Seafall, Pandemic Legacy, Risk Legacy.
I also am part of a new company called Restoration Games, where we take old games that are out of print and restore them.
and bring them back and I get the cool title
of Chief Restoration Officer.
So I spend a lot of time actually also thinking
about the business end of things like graphics
and pallets and shipping and warehousing.
And you also design Blood Rage.
And I also design Blood Rage.
You will notice on each side of you there are microphones.
If you would like to queue up and ask questions,
we will be taking questions from the audience.
Do not be scared.
This is probably the nicest panel that we have at GDC
and the most approachable people.
So if you want to begin queuing up at any time.
feel free. Until then, I want to open... I mean, I assume that we all know that board
games have really taken off. I assume that we all know it's become recently in North
America like a billion dollar industry. So it's a thing now, otherwise none of you would
be here and interested in this. So I'm going to assume that you know that a lot of the
design practices are similar, a lot of the foundations are similar. Why, Jeff, is it
a particularly good or interesting time to be a games designer right now? For board games.
Well, I think that there's a lot of really interesting things going on.
One is just based on the expansion of the market itself.
probably about 10, 15, 20% year-over-year growth
in the number of games coming out.
I think last year there were over 3,000 new board games
added to the Board Game Geek database,
which is a lot of games.
It seems like the audience is growing, at least for now,
and so we're getting a lot of,
you can do a lot of interesting things
and you'll still be able to find
some type of audience for your game.
I've also been really excited about a lot of the new
techniques that are perhaps taken from video games or certainly from movies and stories are bringing more narrative into games and
you know with games like pandemic legacy that Rob did and and others that
There's a lot more
Very interesting type of work being done that we haven't seen before whether it's episodic games like time stories or the legacy games
where
things are going in different directions and there's just a lot of creativity.
So I've been very gratified to see that and that it's gotten some consumer acceptance.
It's not just little art projects, but it's things that you can put out there and will actually sell.
Jens, is that true? By the way, because you're on different sides, you're now opponents.
Yes. So I will disagree with the Honorable Representative from New Jersey.
Yes, the pie is growing, but I feel like the number of games and the number of publishers,
the number of designers are growing faster.
And we are at a point where it's getting hard to get attention.
Right? It used to be if you had a name as a designer, that might be enough.
Or if you had a brand, that was enough.
Or if you had great art, like, now it feels like you need to have all of those three and get lucky.
And get the good reviews.
And if those all come together, you'll get three to five months in the sun
to try to make some money on it.
And then the next big shiny thing comes around.
And if you don't get all of those, you might get three to five weeks
before the next shiny thing comes around.
So it's good right now.
I can make a living.
I made a living off it last year and I'll make it this year.
But two years from now, you know, I don't know how long it will necessarily last.
Wow. But you were looking at me like I was...
No, that was, uh, coming from a chap who's established and has quite a cool portfolio...
Eric, do you agree? I mean, you've made a lot of different games...
You told me to oppose him!
This is the...
Oh, you can agree or... Well, I mean, surely you are constantly getting work.
You seem to be releasing games all the time. Are you not okay?
I, comma, Professor Gloom, I guess somewhat agree with Professor Doom...
But to a degree, I mean, it has never been a better time to be a, academically speaking,
it's never been a better time to be a game designer.
I mean, the foundation of the craft of game design is at a level that it's never been
at before.
I would say the average.
The average middle-enfranchised game player now understands game design probably to a level that top-level game designers in the 70s and 80s didn't understand at all.
There's a wealth of great material online from established game companies, Wizards of the Coast, even Fantasy Flight.
increasing our body of knowledge to a greater degree.
Because of that, of course, it is also increasing competition.
Because within every gamer, there is a budding game designer.
We're all creative people, we all like to express ourselves.
And like writing, game design appears to be very easy on the surface.
So there are many, many more people who want to become game designers
than there are slots for professional game designers to earn a living.
But.
I embrace that, I think it's, to me, it keeps me on my toes.
Rob and I actually discussed that a couple weeks ago, right?
We don't really feel like we're at the head of a curve,
we actually feel like we're at the top of a cliff,
waiting to be, like, at any time,
waiting to be pushed off by the smarter guys
that we're gonna come, or smarter guys, or girls,
that are gonna come in here and just kick our asses.
Wow.
You told us to oppose him.
But isn't this not sort of partly how it should work?
Like the best people should be noticed?
That's energizing, yeah.
If the barriers to entry particularly,
like you can paper prototype a board game
in your house with paperclips and cardboard
and things like that and you don't need to learn Unity,
you don't need to learn GameMaker.
Surely having the barrier of entry low
is a positive thing and it gets,
it fills the world with juicy ideas.
No, yes, absolutely.
But I think that, yeah, it's certainly,
if you look at the industry as a whole,
I think it's very healthy and exciting,
and you look at the, it's a great time
to be a board game player.
Yeah.
But yeah, I mean, in terms of a designer,
there's, yeah, it's very, very difficult to get noticed,
and I will certainly agree with that.
And that's why I'm, one of the things I've seen
is it seems like licensed games
tend to get pushed to the front of the line.
There's so many games that are coming out
that it almost seems like a lot of these licenses
are the bigger names.
So you'll see like, just to take a random example,
you'll see like Pandemic has 87 different variations
because it's got that brand name,
it's got that recognition.
So you see what you're seeing in the movies
where it's just another X-Men movie
or another Avengers movie or whatever,
you're kind of seeing that in the game world
as well as a way to get attention and to get noticed.
Is that a way to get good regular work or a way to more reliably make money?
Is it even a good idea to perhaps create a game that you can sort of paste a theme onto later?
Well as a designer, if you have another pandemic...
So... I'm not the pandemic, he's not there.
Yeah, no, I think it's actually... This is a business.
We're talking about the business of making games.
It's different than the passion for making games.
Like when you said that inside every gamer is a game designer, something I talk about is...
A lot of people can make games and have a game and play with their friends and that might be enough
Or they might want to get one game published but never leave their day job and that's enough
what we're talking about if we're talking about the business of games and Eric and I do it full-time and Jeff does it part-time is
What do you need to do to make a living at it?
And then you start putting all these business parameters around,
like what's the brand recognition and what's the art and what's the release date
and do I make it language independent and what's the audience
and all these sort of unsexy things when you talk about game design
because it's about game publishing then and the business of it
rather than the joy of just making a game.
I heard right yeah, there's a thing called Kickstarter, and if I put my game on it. Yeah, I
People would just see that my name is really good
And they'll pledge a lot of money
And I won't even need a publisher and then some people somewhere will print it and send it out
And I'll make a lot of money because I've seen people make
Insert adjective here sums of money on there is that a solution is that a symptom of the situation that we're in
I am fascinated by this, I'd like to know more about it.
Tell me more.
No, um...
Because if...
Maybe this is my interpretation, it feels to me like Kickstarter is filling a hole,
or sort of like it's a panacea to some degree.
I don't know if it's filling a hole,
so it's filling a hole on the supply side of the market for sure, right?
Because it does bypass the...
It bypasses the critical processes of publishers, right?
So, there is...
The bar of entry for producing a board game is of course much lower than a digital game,
especially on first blush.
But it has increased the number of games that are coming out of course,
so the supply side is much, much higher than the demand side at this particular point.
It is creating a lot of, I guess we call it painful successes, right?
Where people who succeed, especially modestly on Kickstarter,
then suddenly have to become a publisher, de facto publisher,
and it turns them into a full-time fulfillment house,
which is an extremely difficult logistics.
logistical business and most people don't want to do that.
None, I think all of us included.
I've done it, I don't want to do it.
No, I do it for two years.
Yeah, no, the act of making, designing a game
is like hard work but fun, like writing a book
or making a song or any creative endeavor.
And then the act of turning that into production files
is like a different sort of fun project.
And I think most people or many people who use Kickstarters,
and I think a lot of people don't feel this way anymore,
and there's ways to, like third parties that can help you,
the act of moving pallets of cardboard on boats,
the fun tends to drop off for most people at that point,
and it becomes incredibly medieval.
Like where you're talking about like dock workers and cargo and lading and getting it onto trains and trucks and breaking things down.
And it is not exceedingly difficult.
It is very, very easy to do if you are willing to lose money doing it.
Wow.
Like because every step of the way, you're like, oh, we kind of, we should have done that.
Oh, this should have cost less.
Oh, this should have been in a smaller box.
Oh, we didn't take into account this customs fee or we put the wrong age grade on the box and now we can't sell it here.
And so like there's these.
We did meet minimum standards in Brazil, whoops.
Yeah.
So there's dozens of little mistakes
you can make as a publisher that will either prevent your game
from being sold, or you'll spend too much time,
or you'll lose money, or not make the profits you
had projected because it kept taking pennies and pennies out
of your game.
So that's the hazard to Kickstarter is.
Not everyone looks at what happens when you get the money.
And again, a lot of these stories were from three, four,
five years ago when it was a little more Wild West.
I think there are many people who know that now
and do their homework.
Surely now we have hundreds of kickstarted people
who all talk to each other and say,
do it this way and I did this and it went wrong
and all the problems are solved.
I wish.
But I mean, I think it's instructive also that's.
I'm probably not super qualified to talk on this because I've been predicting the demise of Kickstarter publicly for like
Six or seven years now or it probably since it first started so I don't have a great track record
But I mean you do see you know you still have your big mega successes like kingdom death
Which was what 12 million dollars or something insane like that?
and and scythe and things but
The bigger guys that used to be doing it,
like Cool Mini has publicly said
that they're gonna start backing away
from the Kickstarter model
and go with a more traditional publisher route.
Queen was doing more Kickstarters
and they're backing away.
You know, Stronghold tried it
and they're not planning on doing another one.
So I think even,
Stone, Stonemire Games, I believe, is also,
they've said that they're not going to be doing as much
on Kickstarter who did Scythe.
So I think that you're starting to see people
go back to a more traditional publishing model
except for, you know, the very small guys
or the new people that are trying to break into the market.
I do want to ask you guys sort of a couple,
we're talking about the state and future of design,
design-related questions as well,
otherwise I think we'll fall down a business hole,
but we have a gent who has a question.
Yeah, so I,
Automobile and appliance manufacturers learned last century
that making something that you're going to own
for the rest of your life is not a good business model,
and we need you to buy a new one every five years or so.
And I feel like the legacy style games
are these consumable board games where you play through it,
and I don't have my shelf of games
that I've had for 20 years that I play through it.
you know, 12 times and I'm done.
I'm wondering is that a space do you think
the whole industry is gonna move towards
to keep people desiring and purchasing new content?
Oh yeah, I can start there.
I'll finish it.
Yeah, I think the industry... I think game players right now are already way too eager to play everything that comes out or turn through their pile or play something won and be done.
And then the cult of the new exists when you got three thousand things to choose from it's easy just to be like, oh, maybe this is better, right?
Chasing the high of like the perfect game.
I'm giving a whole talk tomorrow morning at 9.30 about Legacy games, so I'm not going to derail this to do that, but
um, one thing that Legacy tried to do, which is often seen as doing the opposite, where you talk about like a
consumable or a disposable game, is I wanted to give you a reason to play it 15 times.
I didn't want to restrict you to play it 15 times, I wanted you to be like, that was fun, and if I play it a second time it'll be different,
and the third time it'll be different, and so that was actually a way to try to get you to go back to a game
rather than play it once and put it on the shelf and do the next one.
So I don't think anyone's trying to do anything consciously,
well, I don't want to say that,
Time Stories is sort of disposable.
Not disposable, usable.
It's like a coloring book, you know?
It sort of is.
Just before you answer, Jeff,
I want a quick sort of poll of the room.
How many people here have, in terms of like buying games
that you might not get around to playing,
who has a game that they bought that they haven't yet
played there in their house?
Oh my God!
What a surprise, Jeff.
Um, yeah, I, I, I think that there's definitely a trend towards that.
And as, as I, as I said in my little opening statement, I think that one of
the really interesting things you can do with kind of a limited play game
is explore narrative and story.
You can build narrative arcs into games,
and a lot of games have that,
and successful games do that very well,
but it's hard to build a real true story
with turning points and stuff like that
in a generative, procedural way,
where it just kind of arises naturally
out of what's going on.
by having games like Time Stories or things like that,
it gives the designer space to go into that.
And I'm curious to see how it plays out,
because it's easy to plug in modular content
if you're a digital platform.
Once somebody buys it, the distribution is a lot cheaper.
With a board game, you're invested in something.
I think that maybe with marrying apps with board games
to push through different types of content.
I've always wanted to do a game like
Tales of the Arabian Nights,
which comes with that giant thick book of adventures
and basically like a choose your own adventure
paragraph thing.
I'd love to just see all that in an app
and then I can just, as a publisher,
I can just push new content out through the app
to get people to pull it off the shelf again
and say, hey, there's all kinds of new adventures in there.
Go in and do it and you have the framework
and you can do it.
I think that's very interesting.
But I, and I know I'll leave this to Eric to rebut,
which I know he will, since we were talking about it earlier,
but I kind of liken this with games to movies,
and there were some movies, I really,
thought Schindler's List was extremely well done,
but I'm not gonna go see it,
like Airplane, which I watched 75 times,
I'm not going back to see Schindler's List.
So I think there's different experiences
where you can have something that's kind of one and done,
and then there's other things that you will keep
going back to and experience in a different way.
Go on, shoot him down.
Well, so, we'll shoot you down afterward.
But as a direct answer to Aaron's question,
that I do believe that we are going to head
into a slightly more, I guess, disposable,
we'll call it, experience.
for board games and I think it's going to happen more organically than by design and that's mostly because of the state of the market.
What we're talking about before the market is the supply is over is overstepping the
is outpacing the demand by a huge amount. We're coming out with more board games, arithmetically more board games every year.
than the year before, and the growth is like 15 to 20 percent per year, which is a great
growth curve by the way, but it's supplies outstripping that. So, we talk a lot among
game designers, we talk about the experience curve of the game, what it is, the lifespan of a game
in everybody's collection from the time they buy it to the time they stop playing it.
And for most people, the fun to work ratio is at its highest in the favor of fun during the early discovery curve of the game.
So, the first two or three games that you play when you're just discovering what the different strategies are, regardless of whether it's a legacy game or a regular game.
We're discovering the new strategies, the cause and effect of all the cool mechanics in the game.
Those are by far the highest, where you increase in skill and you increase in understanding the most between sessions.
And that curve almost always flattens, especially with more modern, slightly more procedural games,
that flattens very, very quickly.
Four or five games in, you kind of get it, and then you become incrementally better and better over time.
That's much less sexy than moving on to the next game and getting that high of the really...
awesome part of the discovery curve. Legacy games are great at that because they're all discovery all the time and
even in we're noticing
by trying to even some other games that aren't fully legacy games like mechs versus minions game like the Harry Potter deck building game
freedom of the priest is
FF game, I don't know what they build fruit. They build fruit. Thank you
Where they build discovery elements into the game, even though it looks like by artifice, but it's in there
It's a they're just deck building games that you
Discover new part you unwrap new parts of the content later on you don't change anything. You just unwrap it
because that's a lot more fun.
And it also eases the learning curve.
So I believe that we are headed in that direction.
The more successful games will have a slightly more,
will be focused more on first play experience,
first play, second play, third play.
Which disposable games can do much better
than other games which have to sandpaper
off a lot of the edge and a lot of the discovery
in favor of replayability.
So yeah, I do think so. I think maybe by this time in five years, I would predict that maybe
close to 75% of the market will be discoverable games.
Wow, we've got a question patiently waiting on the side for a while now.
Yeah, so as I was waiting I came up with other stuff to say.
So I wanted to go back to the discussion about Kickstarter versus publishers.
So I've got a background in digital games, I've been currently working on some edible games,
which are tabletop games where you actually eat the game, so it's very much consumable.
You're awesome.
But so I'm looking for like the next step I'm planning to make a cookbook and like you're
talking about like I don't necessarily have that many people who know me in the board
game world, right?
So do I try to approach a publisher or do I go to Kickstarter?
Like how, like if somebody who doesn't necessarily have a big name behind them, where do you
recommend people start?
I can talk to that at least to start out, which is to me,
the question you should ask
is not about necessarily the name,
but how much work you want to do
once you're done with the creation
of this cookbook and the game.
If you want that to be the first 10% of your experience
and then you're doing marketing and PR and booths
and logistics and sales tax,
And you really like that, like you like owning a small business.
It's not as exciting to me, but there are people like,
really enjoy the logistics of it, then that's the first question you should ask.
And if you say yes, then you can ask, well, can I succeed at a Kickstarter?
I think too many people are interested in knowing whether they would succeed or not,
or whether it's fun or not, without thinking of how much work they want to do.
If you want to write the cookbook and come up with edible games...
and then be done and move to the next creative endeavor,
then you want to find a publisher.
And that's the big decision,
is how much do you want to do after creation
versus the creation itself?
And I'd actually like to add, as a...
You also probably want to ask yourself if you want to be...
What is your victory condition?
Is your victory condition that you get this cool cookbook into the world?
Or is your victory condition that you become a game designer?
That you have many more ideas that you want to publish
that you think are viable to publish.
They're two different tracks. They're two very different tracks.
One of which, if you want to do this for a living,
if you want to make more games than this,
then...
especially nowadays in an age where there are so many
designers out there that are looking to make a name
for themselves, you actually will probably have to focus
a little bit more on some of the externalities, right?
Jamie Stegmaier is actually a great example of this.
I don't know, is he here?
I don't think so.
He could run this panel.
Yeah.
You're doing a great job, Paul.
Paul.
I can mute this microphone and say things
that people won't know, only you'll hear.
So build your, part of that, it all boils down
to building yourself into a brand.
Be awesome and be awesome in public.
I mean, that's a career in one sentence.
Start a blog, share your thoughts on game design,
both in the public sphere and in the industry sphere.
and build yourself up as a name and a brand
and make sure that every...
focus everything you have on your reputation.
Every game you put out, there is an extension of your reputation
and always make sure you're putting out the best game
at any given time.
Which means, of course,
we'll talk about later, throwing out 90% of your stuff.
I want to briefly ask Jeff then,
is this why you don't do this full-time?
Because there would be too much?
Yeah, you know, I...
My real business that I actually make money on,
which we can talk about the monetary aspects of it too,
but I have a company that does product manufacturing
and importing and distribution and stuff like that.
That's what I do, so I do that all the time.
So for me, when I designed a game,
it would have been very easy to roll that into that
and just find the right factories to do it
and I could handle all the importing and stuff like that.
But I knew I did not.
want to do that.
The fun part for me personally was the designing part
and that creative aspect of the engineering of the game
and I didn't want to get involved in all that backend stuff
that Rob was talking about
because I know what's involved in that.
I didn't want to have to go to all the conventions
and be the guy sitting behind the table in the booth
and pushing their product.
And some people are great at that.
Colby Dowch started really small with Summoner Wars.
Just I remember him sitting at a little two by six table.
and just pitching it and turned it into a tremendous company,
but I knew that that's not what I wanted,
so you gotta decide what you wanna do.
I will say I like the eating game.
Eating idea is fantastic.
There's a game called Attack Vector Tactical,
which is insanely complicated,
but the tutorial for it is you put M&Ms all over the board
and you fly your spaceship around
and you have to try to shoot the M&Ms
and you get to eat them as the reward.
And that always goes over really, really well
when I'm teaching that game.
That gets people right through the tutorial.
Another question, sir.
You three are exceedingly good at your jobs,
and not just once, but over and over and over again.
And I would love to try to figure out why that is.
And my way into that, perhaps, is
I'd love to know, when you go to work as game designer,
what is your day?
What do you do?
Succinctly.
So boring.
I'm always at work when people say,
do you get to work from home?
And I say, I have to sleep at the office, right?
So I will talk and I've always got something
in the back of my head or like even walking around here,
there's is constantly turning.
A lot of my day is getting to the end of it
and not getting done 90% of what I thought
I was gonna get done because it's hard to be like perfectly
in the creative zone and not get distracted
and not be like, well, I'm gonna start this.
Oh, I got stuck.
Well, I'm gonna start something else.
And I got stuck and just keep going around like in a circle.
But mostly it's just.
making something bad and then having the level of comfort
that it's going to get better.
And I think that it really comes down
to stubbornness on my part.
The stubbornness like, no, not good enough,
not good enough, I'll take the time,
I'll stay up late, I'll drive an hour
and playtest it one more time.
Because fear of not paying your bills
is a very strong motivating factor.
But I mean, it's spreadsheets, it's graphics,
it's cutting cards, it's play testing,
it's Skype calls with another designer.
When you get to the business aspect of it,
then it's contracts, then it's talking to publishers,
then it's running to the bank and doing things like that.
But if we're talking just pure design,
for me it's sketching.
but I can't sketch, so it's typing and spreadsheets
and moving to the right problem to try to,
the right software to solve the problem you have
at the time.
Like when you, numbers aren't very creative,
but they help in one way, and then you can draw pictures
or get into Illustrator and just make something
look pretty when the numbers don't work.
That's just me, and I'm trying to keep it succinct.
I'm sorry, I was not trying to be too snarky.
No, it's fine.
But a day is a long time.
Okay.
Or is it a part-time day for you, Jeff?
Can you compartmentalize it?
Yeah, I can, although I do a shocking amount of game design during meetings
during the day at my real job.
Wow.
I mean, for me though, the key is that I've got to have
at least like three, four or five different game design projects going on at the same time
because I always run into roadblocks
and the way my brain works is I need to be able to take one thing
and just set it aside and let it lie fallow.
for a day or two or three and have something else to pick up and work on.
And then by the time I run into a Roto-Black on that, something in the back of my brain has said,
oh, do this and do that. So that's, if I was just focusing on one game the whole time,
I think it would be very challenging for me. I need that downtime.
Oh, I mean, Rob and Jeff got the procedural parts down very well.
So I guess the only thing I can add is that...
To do this for a living, I've come to the realization a couple of years ago
that game design, at least for me, is of course it's a career, of course it's a job, it's a vocation,
but it's a discipline and it's a point of view.
So the discipline is about...
structuring the way you think and the way that you act,
view everything through the lens of play.
And there's always, that's that running monologue
at the back of your head in every activity that you do.
So everything, I don't really play games
specifically for inspiration to play other games.
I play them for fun, to make games, I play them for fun.
I go on a walk to get inspired for games.
I go travel and talk to smart people like Paul
for it to get inspired for games.
See, I can compliment you too.
But the, and the discipline about it is that
that I have a, I maintain a critical faculty
for every creative endeavor that I both take part in
as a consumer and as a creator.
And it's just, I spend a lot of time researching.
I do panels like this.
I just got a cool idea for a game
talking to Rob a little bit earlier.
You're not getting co-credit for it.
I am, I kept that to yourself.
But everything that they told you is true, but you have to you have to filter everything that you
you have everything you think about and basically it has to use up the
Almost the totality of your bandwidth if you want to be doing this full-time
You can't really be thinking about anything else and you can't compartmentalize it
As a part of what you who you are
so
One thing, you don't have to stand in wait, you can,
is if you're thinking of making games
or doing any creative endeavor,
everyone, there's no right way to do it,
but everyone has your, you have your own unique way
that you can probably get unstuck,
and when you figure out what that is, go do it.
Like, some people draw and some people write.
I have discovered two things.
If I need to solve a deeper problem,
I need to drive where I can't check my phone or do anything and I need to have classical music on
because I'll sing along with regular music and silence is deafening, but classical music fills
it. So driving on the highway for like an hour is a great way to solve like a deeper problem.
When I've got a more like top-level problem that I want to solve,
the best way for me to do it is to try to explain my problem to someone else,
because in the act of explaining it, I don't want to look dumb,
and my brain just fills in some placeholder answer to make...
It's like when you're trying to explain a dream,
and in order to make sense, you sort of change the details to make it into a real story.
I do that when I pitch a game, and I'm like,
no, never mind, I don't need any feedback, my brain just works.
But I can't do that, I almost got a dog, just so I could...
do that, but that seemed like a strange reason to get a pet.
You know what though, that works for me.
I do find talking through problems, verbalizing them, somehow does something in your brain.
It finds a different part of your brain.
Just talking, sorry, just real quick, just talking about being a full-time game designer or whatever,
I mean just in terms of the economics of it, just so you guys know, you know, you...
If a game sells for 50 bucks, the publisher, assuming you're not a publisher yourself,
but if the game sells for 50 bucks at retail, the publisher's selling it for $20.
You usually get like 5%, 6%. Okay? So you get a buck a game.
Most hobby game print runs are like 5,000 to 10,000 copies.
So you're making $5,000 to $10,000 for the game.
So if you spend a solid year designing a game...
you can do the math.
That's not necessarily viable.
So you've got to be working on multiple projects and over
time building things up and have a back catalog and things
that will start to give you royalties accruing.
Hi.
I wanted to ask about the thought process, both from a
business and from a design point of view, when it comes
to iterating and expanding on a game that has already
released.
The decisions that go into the original design,
do you have an idea that you think,
oh, OK, maybe that would be really good
and we put that to the side as a potential expansion
down the road?
or make sure that the original game has some good hooks that that'll plug into?
Does it have to do more along the lines of like,
oh, we sold more than we thought we would,
maybe now's a really good time to sit down and think about a way to make it
so more players can play it at the same time,
or talk to some people about...
maybe re-theming it or something along the lines.
When do you feel it's worked best for you
to consider adding more components
or keep pushing a project that has succeeded?
Yes.
So if I can reframe your question, you're asking about the
How do we decide whether a game is expand whether it is expandable?
Do we think about it at the beginning or is that something that generally comes?
later on in the product I
Think I think of all three of us. It's
It is really both. Of course everybody wants to design internally, we all want to design the next great lifestyle game,
we want to design the next ticket to ride, the next monopoly, something that can be expanded infinitely,
in infinite ways and make infinite monies.
But some games just naturally lend themselves toward a more closed, complete format.
If you're, in my opinion, the more honest you are with the design, the more you just leave it out there with your playtesters.
It will...
organically leads itself to one or the other. You can engineer a closed game to become an expandable game by putting more hooks in, by putting a little bit more complexity in.
Or you can decide, or the publisher can decide for you, we are designing a lifestyle game.
My background is in trading card games and living card games.
So I naturally think in terms of expandability, and most of the games I work on are...
designed to be theoretically infinitely expandable.
So I design usually, the way I do it is design a hook,
a good core game with a really, really,
really solid foundation and theoretically,
theoretically infinite expandable hooks
that I can't necessarily as one designer
that I can't possibly see all ends for.
So that it is not necessarily solvable
If it's not solved by me and my design team,
then it will be not solved in five minutes
by the rest of the internet and the real world.
I think about it, I don't design quite the same way
Eric does, even though he just said it.
No, you don't.
I feel like if you're spending a lot of time
trying to design hooks for expansions
or building your expansions and rolling out
the first six SKUs for this product line,
you're gonna be very disappointed when 99% of the time
that it doesn't come to pass.
I feel like when you design a game, most designers put too much in and have to take it out.
So you probably have a pile of ideas that are already the start of an expansion.
And if not, if it sort of takes off and suddenly the publisher says,
I think we got a hit, we're going back for our third printing and maybe we should do an expansion,
you probably can find some way to get to it pretty quickly.
Some games won't, and some games I've seen that really strained to do it,
where they've had a success and then they expand, and you're like, you didn't need that.
But if there's a faction, there can be more factions.
If there's not a two-player game,
there can be a two-player game.
So it's there.
I don't spend a lot of time planning for them
because you just don't know what's gonna succeed.
I say that and there's season one
on the front of a game that I did.
But.
So Jeff, I mean, you have done the Space Cadets games.
Yes.
Is that what happened?
That you had certain ideas that didn't quite fit
in one of the games so they ended up in another?
Um, no, actually, um, for when we decided to do the expansions for both Space Cadets and Dice Duel,
we really started from scratch.
Okay.
The stuff that wasn't good enough to make the cut the first time just wasn't.
good enough.
We didn't want to try to rehabilitate it and bring it back.
So, yeah, we started from scratch
and designed some new systems and things like that.
The only thing we did say was the name for the expansion
for Space Cadets Dice Duel,
the alternative name was Diefighter.
And I love that name so much,
but the publishers didn't have to do it.
So when we did an expansion,
I said we have to call it Diefighter.
Please don't clap for puns.
A question.
Yes.
Earlier, Aaron Forsythe was asking about the future of potentially disposable games.
You also mentioned Kingdom Death, which is a successful but niche game.
And I'm wondering if you could comment on the potential future of niche games themselves
as an alternative to disposable games.
Games that have very small but rabid audiences, or games that are perhaps so expensive that
people are sort of coerced into playing them, otherwise they didn't justify the purchase.
I like this question because I've never been asked it and don't have an immediate answer
I mean if you talk about niche meaning a very small audience the question I go back to is say like
Well, why did the publisher make it because if the answer is they just wanted it out there and they didn't care about money
Then they're just gonna make the game that they want to play and hopefully there'll be a few hundred people who find it
I used to make a joke about the markability and viability of games and say,
like, don't design a game that takes all day and 17 people to play because it'll never catch on.
And then MegaSiv came out and I was like, oh, or it will.
I don't know, with the growth that we're talking about
and the supply growth and the double digit
year over year growth, there's going to be games
for everyone coming out and it really comes down
to why the publisher wants to do it.
Is it just, is it to get a wide audience?
Is it to get a specific audience?
Is it to take a game that they've played at home
for five years and they really love it
and they just want a few people to play it
so they can sort of pay the bills to go to conventions?
I don't have a clear answer because I think
that there's just so many different reasons
that you would do it, but maybe one of these two people
or three people will have a better one.
Well I mean, I think that, of course there will always be niche games, right?
But it's, as Rob said, whether it's intended to be a niche game is a factor.
And, I mean, board games are physical games, so they're always going to be subject to, in economics, the tyranny of objects.
They're always going to be...
there are going to be hard manufacturing costs and economy of scale,
which you lose once you are printing for a small audience.
The manufacturing is getting cheaper, it's getting more automated,
but the marketplace is also becoming a little bit more and more dominated
by big publishers or conglomerated publishers with more economies of scale.
So as long as there is room in the market for...
less career-oriented or less...
It's starting.
Wow.
I've been doing that in this room all day. I get used to it.
Or publishers that are a little bit less...
profit-motive...
That's really distracting.
It will happen, but...
Again, it depends on... There are a lot of externalities that matter here, right?
A lot of our industry is driven by network externalities.
So gamers meet in game conventions and they meet at game stores, game cafes.
The more they remain viable, the more localized small cottage industries will be able to continue making small games.
But they're going to be subjected to those local economies.
Jeff what do you think? Do you agree?
Yeah, well when I was talking about
where the game industry was at a year ago,
or a year and a half ago,
I said very strongly that it's definitely a push
towards faster, shorter, simpler games.
Love Letter had just come out and was super popular,
and it just seemed like nobody,
before it was like, you know,
when I was growing up, people used to play
three, four hour games,
and then it was like two hour games was normal,
90 minutes, and now it's like if it's over 60 minutes,
nobody wants to look at it.
But at the same time, like you said,
you've got those,
it seems like there's a little pushback now,
and you've got these big,
heavy games that are coming out that are finding a market and are in there.
So I'm interested to see kind of if it's just, you know, going to be pulling on both ends or where that's going to end up.
But I would love to see, I mean, I think in some sense that
because of the physicality of board games that there's opportunities that are missed.
I, you know, I would love to be able to do a series of really quick one-off type designs to explore
different issues and things like that,
which I think the video game world does fantastically
to have more like art projects in a way than games.
I'd love to be able to do a quick game about
being a refugee and experiencing life as a refugee
and the choices that you make and things like that.
That's not necessarily gonna be commercially viable.
So you either have to...
make it where it's print and play
or somebody can just blow it out themselves
and just do it, or charge $100 and have it be
like an art project kind of a thing
where it's just a very limited audience.
There used to be, with James Earnest,
had his company CheapAssGames.
I don't know if that model could have... I guess there are some people like Button Shy
that are trying to do these things, but they had a subscription service. I used to send
them a check for $50 and then every three or four or five weeks a game would show up
in my mailbox in an envelope and you had to sply your own pawns and money and whatever
and cut the cards out. But there were some fantastic ideas that went through there and
I'd love to see that kind of a model come through as well to allow some of this more
niche stuff to find a home.
So like a lot of people in this room, I'm guessing,
I had a job that I hated and I was in a lot of meetings
that went very long and I had paper in front of me
and I decided to try to design a simple game.
And I sort of got to a point where I was obsessed with it,
probably to an unhealthy degree,
and I was forcing my friends to play test it
and it was like actually straining a lot of my friendships.
And so it was really strange.
And then, so I kind of like let it drop.
due to social pressure mostly, and I was like kind of,
I kind of hit a roadblock like you were describing.
And then now, like a couple weeks ago,
I noticed that there was like a game
that's coming out soon that has a lot of,
it's not the same, but it has a lot of similar ideas
than the game that I was sort of working on half-heartedly.
And so I guess I have two questions, which is,
one, how do you deal with like,
people telling you that you probably shouldn't spend so much time on this crazy dream project and
Also the social pressure of like the only people that I have to play with the only people I know who play board games
Are also like the friends who I play video games with and they're sick of playtesting this crappy game and to how do you feel?
How do you deal with like I mean you guys probably you know you guys
live and breathe board games, so you have ideas all the time.
So what's it like to have that one idea
tinkling in the back of your head,
you focus on something else, and then six months later,
something very similar comes out, and you go,
oh, I almost had it, you know what I mean?
Particularly that latter one, is that a thing
any or all of you have had, I want to ask?
Absolutely. Well, I mean, to speak to number one,
fuck them. Follow your passion.
Wow.
Number two, yeah, number two, we've talked about this a lot, actually.
Do you want to tell my insane story?
You have so many, I actually don't know which one you mean.
The throwing away of every...
Oh, yeah, you did do that, didn't you?
Eric like last year was putting up on Twitter that he had thrown away all of his prototypes like physically digitally gone
Not set him aside, and I was like he must be speaking metaphorically
And then we were working on a project and we took a Christmas break and we came back and we had spent
Eight months on it, and hours and hours of meetings, and I had flown to Toronto, we had played it,
and I was like, I'm not feeling it.
He's like, me neither, and he was just done, and we threw it away,
and started on something new, and it was actually one of the best decisions we ever made,
because we would have labored and labored to have a game that was like a B-minus,
and we just both could see it. I'm not sure that I would have had the bravery to like...
throw it away quite like that, or literally throw things away like you do.
Sometimes it's good to put games on a shelf
and come back to them because you have fresh perspective. Sometimes it's
good to realize that this was a good idea but it's not
a good game, at least not now, maybe not ever. And the hard part as a game designer
is figuring out
when you're stuck.
versus when it's a bad idea.
Because you're gonna get to that point where
you're stuck and you're like,
I'll just start the next thing
because it's shiny and it's easy
and it doesn't have any problems yet.
And you can keep doing that and you will learn things,
but you'll never learn to get past that first
obstacle that you reach.
I've had games I've designed,
I've played games that I get mad
because I didn't design them
because it was so obvious in retrospect
and you don't see all the work that went into it.
I've seen games where I had like half an idea and then two years later someone came and
was like, yeah that was my idea but they did the work, they did the sweat to do it and
they had it come out.
There are a lot of games that are like a lot of other games and you know, you can still
keep working on a game if it's similar to another game.
Just make it your own.
It'll be different.
Agreed.
Yeah, I wouldn't worry about that.
It's, um, there are, the reality is there's so many games, there's very, very, very few
new ideas.
The chances are almost, you know, it's almost a certainty that the game that you've come
out with that somebody has done something similar at some point, or you're in, you know,
you're combining and mixing and matching ideas from other places.
So, um, you know, I would just proceed with it.
And, you know, like, like Rob said, if there's...
You know, just if you can put your own twist on it, come out with it, and it still will be fine.
In terms of playtesting, I feel your pain on that.
That's always an issue with a game group of, you know, you have your friends over.
I know Eric has a dedicated playtest game group.
In my situation, I played kind of the long game, and I just had kids.
which ultimately worked out really well.
But now they're out of the house.
So that had a narrow window when it worked.
Well, I was gonna say, Jeff,
you said you often have three or four different things
going around in your head at the moment.
How long do they sort of live for
before they get thrown away metaphorically or literally?
It's variable. I mean, some I'll work on, you know, some I'll work on for a couple months and it'll be obvious that it goes nowhere.
The Fog of War, the first concepts of it were literally 12 years before publication, 14 years before publication I worked on it, before it was finally ready to go.
Wow.
And that one, that was a really new idea. I mean, that was something that I was trying to do that had never been done, that had never seen any games that had been done, so it just took a lot of time to wrap my head around it.
Hi, I know a big part of the game design process is like
iterative design and play testing.
So I was just wondering as more play testing tools come
out like on Steam or through other sources, how has play
testing evolved and where do you see that going?
I'm super excited to try like Tabletopia and some of these other tools for playtesting,
especially later round play, later stage playtesting, where you want outside groups to do it,
because that's always a challenge to actually print up sets and get them to testers.
And actually, hardest of all is when you send stuff out is to get them to actually get back to you.
You'll go on Twitter and say like, hey, I've got this game to test, can you guys look at it?
And you get a thousand responses and you send them out and maybe two people get back to you.
So yeah, I think it's going to be great to be able to actually get groups in there and watch them play
and to be able to interact with people while they're playing the prototype.
Surely, were we just saying you had sort of the same playtest groups that you tend to play with?
Yeah, I was just sort of lost in thought a little bit while Jeff was talking in the good way,
because I struck the idea that there probably could be a whole panel about the different stages of playtesting groups and playtest needs.
But the real short version is that it starts out usually I'm playing the game against myself,
and then every step I'm weaning it away, both from me as a player to me being there at all,
to like eventually strangers at the end.
So getting a core playtest group at the beginning.
who knows game design and is fine playing something broken
and you changing it in the middle
and playing the same thing five weeks in a row
with slight changes is kind of vital.
You don't want to do that digitally
or send it out at that point.
But to Jeff's point at the end,
you want to just have a group play it
that you don't know at all.
And you're not there and you can't,
even with your body language be like,
you, where they know they did something wrong
and then see how that is.
So there's like.
probably three or four different playtesting stages that I'm just
thinking about now, but it's kind of interesting to get back to.
Oh yeah, it totally could be its own panel.
I mean, to answer your question, like, where do we see playtesting going?
So one of the big advantages that digital...
the digital medium has over the over tabletop of course right is real-time analytics and and perfect analytics and
It's I mean working on dualist for is a joy right because we can
we can spread our testing over thousands and thousands of players and analyze the data in seconds in real time and
Synthesize that like so quickly. That's it's hard to do in play testing. I actually do I've spent
A lot of time in many years cultivating a group of about like 100-150 playtesters that we have locally and my wife runs that full-time
So we do cycle through playtesters a lot. That's a it's a big
I would say it's about a quarter of our day. That's our job, but
One of the things like Tabletopia and hopefully maybe a little bit more advancement in VR and stuff like that
is we actually might be able to get as close as we can to transforming blind testing,
what we used to do with sending games out to groups to play blind,
but not being able to observe their body language.
And so we might be able to capture that a little bit better in real time
and start to be able to run full analytics on that for tabletop games.
I see that being a reality in like three to four years.
And I think that'll be, that'll change so much
about the way, in my opinion, that games are designed
that you'll, I think you'll, right now the minimum bar
for a tabletop game is that it's not broken, right?
Which I think that very soon the minimum,
that won't be a thought anymore.
The minimum bar for a game is that it's,
It's it plays. Well. It's fun. It matches its playtime exactly it is fun for all play counts it has multiple
roads to victory
That'll be the same minimum bar as not broken is today because of that
The question here we've got about five or six minutes left
We can run over a little bit because I think we're the last session after this question
I'm gonna just jump in and possibly with one of my own as well that I really want to get out
Thank you. Can you speak about the future of CCG and TCGs, not magic?
Oh boy.
And also maybe some of the economy, but not just the economy of it, but the future of it.
I hear you talking about board games, but CCGs?
That's a valid question. I mean, surely they are perennially popular in one form or another.
Sure. So, I mean, CCGs are...
I mean, there's still so not I mean you can't talk about CCGs without talking about magic
Unfortunately, I'll keep it relatively short by magic is it was the first it is still considered by many to be the best they've
And I'm not just sucking up to the Wizards guys in here, but they do a phenomenal job on it
and they continually set the bar for design development, but
there has been a huge renaissance in the development of CCGs with
notably Hearthstone and many games that followed since I work on a game in that space.
There is always, they fill a clearly defined and demonstrable need for a perpetually discoverable game that you don't have to throw away pack after pack.
That has this really cool institutional memory, which is in everybody's collection.
I don't think that's fundamentally going to change, but they're also the single type of game that is the most subject to this buzzword called network externality,
where the value of the game is equal to the number of players playing it.
So, sadly speaking, it's not a wide open market.
It's not something where a whole bunch of indie games can survive.
In any medium where every advance that is made, there is going to be one winner,
a very, very clear winner that takes a lion's share of the market,
which will be magic in the real world, in the tabletop world,
Hearthstone in the digital space, and whatever the new innovation is,
the new medium is in the next space.
Star Wars Destiny just came out from Fantasy Flight.
I'm sure a lot of you guys have played it.
It's cards and dice.
like Dice Masters, but any other game that follows them is going to fall subject to the same thing.
So I think there will always be...
something in that space that will always be cheaper and cheaper to obtain for the player,
because especially as we expand into the parts of the world with a shrinking middle class
or just a burgeoning middle class.
So I think fundamentally the games won't change,
but maybe the packaging and business model will a little bit.
What do you think makes a good CCG?
I'm sorry?
What do you think makes a good CCG or what is the...
That's a good one.
What makes a good...
What makes a good CCG?
Richard Garfield.
Yeah.
I think we'll...
Sorry, guys.
Sorry, I...
It's a long question.
It's a long answer.
It's a whole panel of itself.
It could be a whole panel and I'd love to talk to you about it afterward.
I think we'll have time to get to the rest of you folks who've come up.
Thank you all for coming up and asking questions.
I want to throw something at all of you because I am worried that if I don't ask it, nobody else will.
So we're saying that it's relatively easy to paper a prototype at home.
It's relatively easy for maybe all of us here to try and make a board game and design a board game
and be a one-time board game designer or occasionally a board game designer
or a successful board game designer if our work is good enough, if our ideas are smart enough.
So why are we just four guys stood up here, and why am I only meeting guy game designers pretty much all the time wherever I go?
I don't know.
You know, I think it's a problem. I think that it's something that hopefully will, you know, I think part of it was just that...
I think that the current group of game designers kind of came out of, you know, game design
in the 80s and the 90s when it was more, you know, D&D and cosmic encounter and stuff like
that that didn't attract women as much at that time.
So I think there's just sort of that class that kind of grew up.
I'm hoping that it changes.
My daughter, Sydney, co-designed a bunch of games with me
and it was, I think that I was very proud of that
and she's done a great job with that
and brought a whole different perspective
on a lot of stuff.
So I'm hoping that it's gonna just be something
that will take.
time to do it. I don't feel like there's necessarily a bias against
women coming and pitching a game that would be turned away versus other ones.
I'm just hoping that it's just because of the nature of the early 70s and 80s gaming
and that culture that it's kind of a hangover in essence from that.
Do we agree?
I guess this is the part where I get in trouble.
I mean, I do believe we are absolutely institutionally biased and sexist.
It's not purposeful, but it...
something that we need to get better at, and a lot of us speak pretty loudly about it.
We're not particularly welcoming to women and minorities in gaming,
because it's just not something that comes up in conversation often enough.
I screw up still, all the time.
We make games where we still casually put one-sided cheesecake into a game art,
We're still a little bit too objectifying toward women as we are toward men.
Part of this, in my opinion, we don't have enough women in game design.
It can't possibly be because women aren't interested in game design.
If you look at the marketing data for mobile games, over half of it is women.
We're all creative people. Almost like we said before, in every gamer is a game designer.
So the same number of women must be creative and want to get into the game design business.
It is mostly up to us to be more inviting for women to become game designers.
In my opinion, we have to do it from the top down.
It's not like we should say, more women should come up and design games.
No, we have to be more welcoming.
It's a long and ongoing conversation,
but it is the burden of that falls on us,
rather than on women.
If that makes sense.
I agree with some combination of what they've said,
and in order to keep things short, I'll just add a couple new points,
which is I've taught game design at two different colleges
over the past couple years, and I've been encouraged to see
almost half of my students have been women,
where I think that, you know, so like,
it looks like this next generation is seeking it out
and getting the opportunities.
And so I think hopefully there's some sort of
change happening at the bottom as well as happening top,
and they get the opportunities.
you know, when they're looking for jobs.
But I mean, it's still there as an underlying thing.
I work full time with my wife.
She's an art director, graphic designer,
and a hardcore gamer.
And it still cracks me up when we will sit down
and someone will teach a game to the two of us
and assume that I'm going to crush them.
And she always wins.
and I never win, and they just don't see it coming.
You can tell they're always kind of like a little bit like,
a girl just beat me.
Like it's this weird thing that's just ingrained
at a level that is not out yet,
but I'm hoping every incident and every change
and every student, every person starts adding up
to a larger change.
How do we help get that out? How do we help change it?
Because we're the people on the stage here right now talking about this
and who are going to be on film and watched later.
So we're pretty much at the top of that, right?
Well, step one, any women in the audience interested in being game designers for a living?
Come talk to me in five minutes.
Come talk.
Yeah, I mean, there's things, I'm part of Restoration Games,
and we're doing a game which is, you know,
I know there's a cutting edge theme,
but we talked about, we put it in the Italian Renaissance.
It just works there.
But, you know, so it should be like the Medici's,
and they should be all just white guys on the card art.
And we just decided, we put in the book like.
This is not a history book.
So there's Asian people and people of color
and women and older people and younger people
and all body types.
And so like the company that I have an active say,
I'm just like, no, we're kind of showing
a cross section of the world,
even if it's not historically accurate.
Which I think no one would have thought of 20 years ago
and may have thought of 10 years ago and said,
yeah, but we can't do that because it's not right.
So I'm trying to do it where I can
in terms of least portrayal and things.
But yeah, like Eric said, if, you know, see me, see us.
try to help. A question. Yes.
I have a question about accessibility in board games.
I play with a colour blind board gamer and why am I still
sticking dots on the red cubes?
What a good question. Some of my favorite video game designers are actually colorblind, and some of them have started...
You know, it's very easy to modify video games to do this. It doesn't seem to be a thing in board games.
It does, we just suck at it right now. We're getting better. We really are.
Like, it is a...
Especially among some of the bigger publishers, a lot of us...
We have a pretty good checklist of development before we put a game out.
out the door.
And this checklist is expanding
and in good ways, in positive ways in my opinion,
but generally it takes a mistake
to add something to that checklist.
And colorblind accessibility,
haptic accessibility for blind players,
those are both items that are on the checklist
for more and more games,
if we can possibly help it.
We recently, with Blood Rage,
we totally screwed up.
like publicly admitted no problem.
Like we put, we had a really bad color scheme
and it was pointed out to us by players with,
none of our play testers played with final components
and was pointed out to us.
And now it is on the checklist for every single,
for every single game that we do on the Pantone scale
to make sure that it does not trigger
the most common types of color blindness.
We'll never be perfect,
but we're getting there, hopefully.
It's a.
I had a question about gameplay versus theme.
When you guys are developing a new game, do you guys
typically think about new gameplay mechanisms, or game
mechanics, or how to merge existing mechanics?
Or do you come up with a theme and then try to match
mechanics to it, and then kind of a follow up?
Have we reached peak Cthulhu yet?
Because it seems like everything wrong.
No, no, there's no peak Cthulhu.
It's Cthulhu all the way down.
Always room for Cthulhu.
Cthulhu is the ice cream of gaming.
I will tell you, it's always a little bit different.
Every designer's gonna tell you different.
Every time I work on a project's different.
I tend to do mechanics or mechanisms later,
but not always.
Sometimes it's theme or story.
Sometimes it's an emotional experience that I wanna get.
Sometimes I'm inspired by something way out.
I tend to be inspired outside of gaming
and then use gaming tools to make it a game.
So I might be inspired by television or,
like my daughter goes off to college,
my first child this fall, and so like,
what's that feel like?
And is there a game in that feeling?
The answer is probably no.
But like, that's like an interesting,
like how do I get people to an emotional space
or something like that?
So the inspiration comes from all different places,
but Susan McKinley Ross, I don't know if she's here,
but she did Quirkle and she talks about
how she does mechanics.
And most of our games are abstract.
And if I do an abstract game,
as soon as I hit my first sticking point,
I need to put a theme on it to figure out
how to get unstuck.
So it differs from people.
Jeff, you gonna?
I have a few.
Very much, I teach this to my class.
This is the very first class that we do
is experience first.
It's not mechanics, it's not theme, it's experience.
You know, it's real easy to say
I'm gonna do a zombie game,
which is the Cthulhu of two years ago, I guess.
But, you know, are you going to be an entire nation fighting off zombies?
Are you just going to be trapped in a mall?
You know, you've got to get to that experience, what I call the experience or the emotional core.
And I think that's what really carries you through, even if you end up totally changing the theme later,
if you've got that experience, or another way to look at it,
is the story that you want the players to tell when they're done.
Interesting. Player perspective, the end goal maybe rather than the start goal.
Thinking backwards.
Right.
Hi, thanks for the talk.
Thanks for sticking around to answer the last question.
So I was kind of inspired.
My question changed as I stood in line
by the question about diversity.
I was curious to learn a little bit more
about the development team behind a board game.
Because often you see like the designer's name on the box.
I assume that's like the main guy
and that's all of you guys, right?
It's only the designer, that's it.
All right, well I'm wondering, you know,
my wife was not a gamer, she didn't grow up a gamer,
she's recently started playing board games with me,
but there aren't a lot of themes that appeal to her,
you know, in the same way that they appeal to me.
I'm wondering if that's because teams are not as diverse,
like video games require these huge collaborative efforts,
whereas board games can be kind of one guy's idea
all the way through.
And is there more that we could maybe be doing
to diversify the development teams behind board games
to get those new perspectives in?
Yep.
Oh, okay, cool.
Yeah, but it's always going to be, they're going to, I mean, board game design, I think
just by its nature, both the economics of it and the way that it's done is always going
to be smaller teams.
So it's, you'd have to really make sure that you had it built in.
I, you know, I cracked up during the early, the Mechs and Minions.
presentation was given and his last slide was like,
you know, we had such a small team working on this game
and they show a picture of like 15 people
that all contributed and I'm like, you know,
I've never been involved with more than three people
developing a game, so this would be like
a huge, massive project, even like Fantasy Flight
and stuff like that, you know, they have maybe,
you know, five, six, seven, eight people,
so it's not done on the same kind of scale,
but yeah, I mean, if you bring in other voices
and other people, that's gonna help diversify it.
Well, as board games become bigger budget, and this is happening actually at Fantasy Flight, this is happening too,
there is a little bit of a cultural shift.
So, I mean, of course, the designer is the person that gets their name on the box,
because we're fragile creatures with egos that need constant attention.
I mean, of course, there's behind every board game. There's a development team, an art director, artists, a producer
and on the flip side, there's a sales team, marketing team, etc, etc, but
I was actually inspired about 15 years ago or so and I teach this to every single team that I work with on the board
game side. I was inspired by the way that Wizards of the Coast defines
design and development, which could be a panel in and of itself.
And I'm slightly redefining it, so I apologize if I was revert.
But design and development, we're essentially beginning and end, for all intents and purposes.
It's a Venn diagram of skill sets that is very, very...
That's a high degree of overlap.
But the development team is,
the development team is, sorry,
designer is essentially responsible
for the vision of the game.
They're the ones with whom the idea is born,
and they have to, it's their responsibility
to execute on the idea and make a game
and be responsible for the vision.
Development team being responsible for carrying the vision,
taking another set of eyes to that viewpoint
and matching the actual experience
in a multitude of different.
environments to match that vision.
The board game teams are becoming bigger.
They are, like even Fantasy Flight now,
they generally have agile teams, about two or three people,
that work on every different game.
So there's usually a lead person, which is the designer,
but there's a back-end development team where somebody,
besides the designer, has final call on certain things.
The answer to your question, how we diversify that,
the same way we diversify everything else.
Just bring more people into the industry,
make the industry more appealing
for more different people with different perspectives,
and let them fall where their talents lay
rather than where we want to engineer to put them.
Right, and I guess that's kind of the quick follow-up, right, is if the reason there aren't
that many women in is because you have this generation of men who played D&D growing up
and becoming designers, do you then now have the same problem where you have the generation
of men playing the games made by the men who played D&D and you don't ever get that new
sort of inroad?
At some point you have to break the cycle.
Yeah.
But I've been super gratified.
I mean, I went to Origins 3 in 1978, right, and it was like 100%.
guys and even you know in the 80s and 90s and now if I go to Gen Con or I go
to our local game conventions it's usually you know pretty close to 50-50
women men and I know that there's issues and there's you know behaviors which
are not acceptable things like that but in general it's so much different now
the culture of board gaming than it was back in the 80s.
I think we will have to take the rest of the questions outside if you folks don't mind
doing that because I'm sure the panel are nice enough that they would do that.
Thank you everyone for coming and for your questions.