Is that going to go?
Yeah.
Hi.
My name is Matt.
I've been a game designer for like 10 years now.
I did eight years in Reykjavik, Iceland,
with CCP Games on EVE Online, which you may have heard of.
And I spent the last two years in Berlin, Germany,
with a company called Sandbox Interactive,
making Audi Online, which you probably haven't.
But that's what I'm going to talk about today.
Let me start my timer.
So, things I'm going to talk about today.
I'm going to try and explain what this Albion thing is that I make,
at least to the degree where you can understand the rest of the talk.
I'm going to explain what I mean by economy balance and why it matters.
And then I'm going to kind of walk through...
our balance process or like kind of our economy setup process for Albion.
I'm going to talk about setting goals, why they're important, how we set up the relationships
between things, a little bit on doing the math, filling everything in, and then kind
of what happens when we ship, how we deal with feedback, how we kind of iterate on it
as a result.
I'm going to try not to talk too fast because I've been a little bit jet-lagged, so bear
with me.
Thank you.
To explain Albion, I want to briefly thrash through the family tree of Western MMOs.
Ignoring Asia because it's convenient, not because it doesn't matter.
I don't need it for this.
But we love you, Asia.
So we start off with multi-user dungeons back in the late 70s, early 80s.
Basically a way of allowing people to play versions of Dungeons & Dragons
on university mainframes with their friends.
And we kind of build from there.
In the late 90s, we get the two kind of beginnings of modern MMOs coming through.
We get EverQuest and we get Ultima Online.
EverQuest we can already divide this tree branching in two now.
EverQuest is kind of what we'd refer to as a theme park game, or an early version of
a theme park game, which is largely about gaining experience and leveling up and getting
loot and progressing through the game to the end game.
Ultima by contrast is what we'd refer to as a sandbox game.
It's much more about giving players a world and some tools
and letting them interact with each other and figure out for themselves how to have fun to a large degree.
They run for a while, they do okay.
So early 2000s, we get them for the next iteration.
Yeah, World of Warcraft really kind of consolidates
the theme park approach.
It adds an extensive questing system,
which really gives you those rides in the theme park.
So you know, you get on your quest
and you go do the quest and it's wonderful.
And then you're done with that quest
and you move to the next quest.
Very much again, progression focused
and getting to the raids kind of focused.
Eve, by contrast, is kind of Ultima in space.
It's still very focused on players interacting
with each other and kind of emerging gameplay
and kind of seeing what happens in the world.
Probably the biggest departure there
is that Eve goes single sharded.
Most MMOs do what we call sharding.
They split the world up into multiple copies of itself
and players connect to a particular shard
and that's where their characters and their friends are.
and they play on that copy of the world.
Eve, everyone connects to the same world space,
the same instance essentially of the world.
That's kind of quite a big step for sandbox games
because it really means everyone is interacting
with each other as much as possible.
From there, World of Warcraft leads to basically
all the MMOs in the universe.
World of Warcraft makes a lot of money, as you may have noticed, and everybody else wants
some of that money, so they go after that.
And that leads to a lot of MMOs, and on the sandbox side we kind of get Darkfall, which
you may have heard of, which is kind of a more PvP-oriented version of Ultima.
and then not very much at that kind of scale,
and now I'll be in a Fitzen over here.
We're inspired by Eve, we're inspired by Darkfall,
and we're inspired by the original Ultima.
That's kind of where we fit in.
So we are an MMO, we're like World of Warcraft,
in that we're a shared, persistent fantasy world,
but we're not like World of Warcraft
in most other respects.
Hopefully that gives you a sense of where we go.
I was going to do a slide explaining what is this Albion thing, but then I realized
we made a video.
What is Albion?
Albion Online is a sandbox MMORPG in which you get to write your own story instead of
just following a laid out path.
Explore a vast open world consisting of different unique biomes.
Everything you do has an impact on the world.
As in our player driven economy, every piece of equipment is crafted by players from resources
gathered by players.
The equipment you wear defines what you are.
Switching from knight to magician is as easy as swapping your armor and weapon.
Or be a combination of the two.
Venture out into the world or into dungeons and face Albion's inhabitants and wildlife.
Go on expeditions to encounter even more challenges.
Fight other players in open world clashes.
Fight over territory or city control in tactical group battles.
Relax by retreating to your personal island.
Build a home, grow crops, raise animals.
Join a guild.
Everything is more fun when you work together.
Leave your mark in the world.
In Albion, everybody matters.
Yeah, so that's kind of basically what we do.
It's single sharded.
It's very sandboxy.
It's very player oriented.
Three kind of things that I'd pull out that I think
make us stand out.
Albion is we regard ourselves as properly multi-platform.
We're releasing in July, we hope,
on PC, Mac, Linux, and Android tablets,
with iOS following soon after.
We're targeting tablets and we're targeting 2GB of memory because it's kind of intensive,
but it's not just like a companion app.
What you play on your tablet is the same client, it's just a different build of Unity, connected
to the same game world with the same stuff.
You can go raiding and PVPing on your iPad if you want.
That's led us, for example, to our art style you saw,
is very kind of simple, but I think looks really good still.
Makes us think a lot about accessibility
and about complexity of the game,
kind of trying to bridge those two audiences
with the traditional MMO crowd, which
is kind of our primary audience, but also bringing it
to the mobile arena as well.
Another thing that we do, we focus on small team PvP.
A lot of sandbox games, particularly something like EVE, you've probably heard of 5,000 people
fighting out in the system, which is cool.
And we still have the opportunity for that in our open world PvP.
But in terms of conquering territory, we take a break from that direction.
The way you take another guild's territory is you pick one of their vulnerability slots
in their time zone and then you bring five players and they bring five players and we
wall it off, wall the territory off into like an arena and you fight it out with the equipment
both sides have brought.
So even though there is opportunity to go big, if you want to be, you can be a small
guild if you've got five people and five good fighters and a couple of logistics and
crafting people.
you can claim your own corner of the world without needing to bring hundreds of players.
So that both kind of brings, I think, a different direction to some of our PvP
and also informs a lot of our thinking because we have to think about this, you know,
tightly balanced, small-scale engagements.
The third thing we like to wave around is this UR Uwear thing, which works really well
for us.
Obviously it gives players a lot of choice, which is good for them.
It also means that kind of the more macro level, we've got like 45 base weapons and
27 armor sets, I think, or 27 armor items, and they all have spells attached and a choice
of spells and you can mix and match those completely, which leads to a lot of variety
in PvP, which is what we're going for.
It means that.
every fight can be different because players are constantly looking for that
improved build and that counter build and all this kind of stuff
so it keeps the PvP as fresh as it can rather than
like there's no classes, there's no restrictions on this stuff so you're not
just like oh it's a monk he's probably running one of
these three builds we know how to deal with that
you see someone like he's wearing a plate helmet and cloth hues what's going
on here it just leads to a lot more variety and
interest there. So that's kind of that's the game we're
talking about hopefully
That gives you almost enough of an understanding to understand the rest of this talk.
I'm going to get into the meat of it now.
What is economy balance and why?
I have a philosophy background so I like why questions.
I also find the answers to them really useful in kind of informing my thinking.
Hopefully it will help you too.
So I'm going to be talking about, yeah, what is economy balance, why do we care about economy
balance.
I think these are important questions.
So, economy balance, we take at Sandbox
a pretty expansive view of economy.
basically all the macro scale balance in the game.
We're not worried about stuff at this,
for economy stuff with like, you know,
does the axe do more damage than the sword?
But like, does the level one axe do more damage
than the level three axe and how much?
That's already getting into economy territory
because it's a power scaling issue.
So yeah, economy means all the macro balance.
It means obviously resources and money,
our silver and our various resources you can collect.
It also means the progression system.
We have this tree structure and you earn fame,
which is our version of XP in different areas of the tree.
You use a double-handed sword
and you get better at double-handed swords.
But the balance of that ties in, the balance between, like I was saying, equipment tiers
ties into the economy balance because it's all of a thing.
Our farming system, for example, and everything else at that kind of scale of the game where
we're trying to balance resources and macro level stuff against each other, all falls
under the aegis of economy balance and it all gets approached generally the same way,
the same kind of process, which is what I'm going to talk about in a bit.
Why do we care? I like this question, I think this is important.
I'm going to do some theory.
We want our game to be good, right?
And I don't like using the word fun because I think it constrains too much what we can
be doing with games.
Like if you ask someone who's climbed Mount Everest if they thought it was fun, they would
probably say no.
That doesn't mean it wasn't good.
So I'm going to try not to use the word fun too much in this talk because I think it's
too constraining for what we can offer as a game, particularly when you get into virtual
worlds like we do.
And we think our economy balance can make a huge difference to whether or not our game is good.
So we do want to think about it carefully and we do want to get it right.
So let's talk about motivation.
I've been relying for many years,
I used it a lot on the Eve team,
and I've been using it as well at Sandbox.
On a model that I borrowed from,
or we borrowed from Scott Rigby and the folks at Immersive.
I think Scott's doing a talk later today,
so you should go listen to him,
because I'm gonna try and skim over it,
and I'm gonna get some of it wrong, I apologize.
But hopefully it gives you enough
to understand where we're going with this.
So in this model we have intrinsic motivators,
for starters, you have autonomy.
feeling like you're in control of what's going on,
relatedness, feeling like you're connected to other people,
and mastery, feeling like you're improving in skills.
And these are our intrinsic motivators.
These are things that just make people feel good.
And if you can get them doing all three of these things at once,
then they're pretty much guaranteed to be enjoying your game.
The real tricky one for MOs and other long-running games we find is usually mastery because mastery is not
Being good at something. It's getting better mastery consumes
That's why you have to spend so much on on content in theme park games for example because the content is consumed as you go
Once you've beaten something you've solved it. It stops being interesting from this point of view
So yeah, if we can hit all three of these then we're probably in a good place
By contrast we have extrinsic motivators
This is basically any kind of external reward.
So making numbers go up,
particularly numbers relating to your character,
your level, your XP, your money, whatever,
and getting stuff, everything to do with loot
and that kind of thing.
And it seems the human brain really likes this stuff.
It likes seeing numbers go up faster.
And it gets very motivated by almost getting what it wants.
So if it almost gets that amazing loot drop it's after,
Combined with the fact that human brain is awful at probability
means it's very easy to trick it into thinking it was almost there and to keep trying.
And this extrinsic stuff is very compulsive.
It's not necessarily enjoyable, but people will do it anyway.
And they will keep doing it until they run out of things to improve
or they hit some kind of break point and look at themselves and say,
why have I been grinding walls for 60 hours?
And they can walk away from your game and never come back at that point.
So it's kind of a fragile way of people getting people held in.
So yeah, we have these two different things,
intrinsic and extrinsic.
And when the two compete,
when there are different activities with different motivators
competing for players' attention,
this kind of tends to happen.
The extrinsic motivator always wins.
Another way of breaking it down is saying
the intrinsic stuff is what your players will enjoy
and the extrinsic stuff is what players will do.
And your economy, obviously, is all basically your entire
extrinsic motivation system.
Another way of defining economy for our purposes
is all of the extrinsic rewards in the game.
Your economy is basically one giant incentive structure
that tells your players what to do.
As they go looking for the best ways to level up,
whatever that best way is, is essentially
what your game is telling your players to do.
So, if we look at a traditional MMO, we make a simple Venn diagram, we break it down into
three areas.
On the left, that is the left for you, yes, we have the blue bit, you have your intrinsic
motivators.
This is areas of the game, the pure blue, that are intrinsically motivating, but are
not extrinsically motivating.
This is wasted potential.
This is all the bits of your game that are good, that no one is going to play because
there's no reward for it.
In the middle, we have the bit of your game that is both intrinsically and extrinsically rewarding.
This is the good bit of your game, the bit that people will play and enjoy.
And on the right, we have the grind.
This is all the stuff that's purely extrinsic.
This is killing a million wolves because wolves are the most efficient way to level up.
There's no kind of...
It's not good.
You're not enjoying killing the millionth wolf particularly.
But it's very efficient.
Generally speaking, the problem here is you're missing mastery.
You've figured out how to beat wolves 200 hours ago.
You're not learning anything.
It's just kill the wolf, kill the wolf, kill the wolf.
So yeah, this is the bit of the game that is usually called the grind.
This is why we're grinding.
It's because it's grindy because there's no intrinsic value in it.
So what we are trying to do as an economy balancer
is we're trying to do this.
We want to make it so that the intrinsically rewarding parts of our game and the extrinsically
rewarding parts of our game are as much as possible overlapped.
And in particular, at a more subtle level, we want to ensure that the most intrinsically
rewarding parts of our game are also the most extrinsically rewarding parts of our game
and vice versa.
So that as players try to optimize that process and they try to find what's the best way of
doing this, the game doing that takes them to the best parts of your game.
Right?
Economy, balance, success, you can do that.
So yeah, that's basically the theory.
Let's move on to the next bit.
So we have that, we have our whys.
Let's talk about how we actually go about doing it.
What I am gonna do here basically is try
and take you through a kind of a simplified
and slightly idealized version of an earlier iteration
of our economy balance because it was still at that point
simple enough to explain in an hour.
Hopefully, like, the important thing for me here is the process, right?
It's how do we do this?
The fact that Axe takes 32 resources, the why of that is probably not nearly as useful
to all of you as how we get to that number.
So that's what I'm going to try and focus on.
And we're going to start off with goals.
If I had to define design in a simple, soundbite-y way, I would say that design is art with goals.
Design is art that's trying to do something in particular.
And the goals are kind of what drive that.
So let's talk about some goals.
Well, let's talk about why we do goals more to the point.
A few kind of bullet point reasons.
I find it brings a lot of clarity and a lot of honesty to the process.
It makes you pin down up front if you start off with your goals.
What you are doing and why you are doing it helps everyone to understand kind of where we're trying to go with these feature
And the same way to just writing anything down will often clarify the thoughts
Writing your goals down and getting them pinned down somewhere
And can really kind of give you a good foundation to build off
You know where you're going and what success is going to look like when you get there
I found it's great actually for team harmony.
The Eve design team in particular is like 15 or so people and we'd have disagreements
sometimes about how to do something, like where we're going with the feature, how we
wanted to do a particular thing.
And the more I was thinking about goals and applying that to my design work.
the more I realized that most of those arguments were happening
because people had different goals,
and we hadn't stated what the actual goal for the feature was,
and therefore they're talking past each other.
This guy talking, trying to design a feature for veteran players,
this guy trying to design a feature for new players,
and of course they can't agree on anything
because they have different goals in mind.
So getting them pinned down and everyone on the same page
can avoid a lot of those things,
and when you get into those discussions, if you stop and say,
hang on, what do you think we're trying to do?
What do you think we're trying to do?
that's often enough to actually to defuse the entire discussion or at least bring it down to a level where we're talking about the same thing to each other.
Um,
I've also found goals great as a supporting structure. Um, I kind of a simple level just having something to go back to when I'm when I'm stuck or I'm struggling. I'm not sure where we're going next. Let's go and look at the goals where we're going with this feature. Um, how do we want to get there? It's really helpful.
and kind of at a broader level,
goals bring you into kind of the area
of like constraint-driven design.
You're narrowing down your possibility space
by specifying what you want to achieve
and that limits your options,
which for me makes it much easier to design something good
because I'm much more focused on how exactly do this
rather than where in this great big blue sky
are we gonna go with this feature.
So laying out those constraints early on
and kind of pinning down the options,
I find really useful to taking it to a better place.
In principle, obviously, goals should be perfect and immutable and laid down at the beginning in stone tablets.
In practice, that doesn't happen.
We find that some of our goals are wrong, or we want to do a feature in a particular way,
we really know we want to do this, but it doesn't match our goals.
And it's fine, I think, to go back and change those goals, so long as you actually change the goals,
change what they're written down, and make sure everyone is on board with what we're doing next.
Goals should not be...
They should be constraining you in where you're going,
but they should not be limiting your overall design.
They should be a tool to help you rather than something
to stop you from getting to where you want to go.
So let's set some goals.
Yeah, there's kind of three stages to our process, I guess.
The first is the setting goal stage,
where we sketch out the outline of what we want to do.
Second step is going to be talking about relationships,
which is filling in the details,
and then step three is the math,
which is basically doing the coloring in.
So I said we're going to go through a sample economy set up
and I'm going to lay out some goals and then we're going to go over them
and figure out how to get there.
So goal one, incentivize the best parts of the game.
This is the theory I was talking about earlier.
We want to make sure that the most rewarding parts of our game
are the bits that players will enjoy the best.
It's a good starting goal, nice and straightforward.
Goal two, we for our game want to allow as much as possible
everyone to compete.
We don't want to have huge gaps between the veteran players and the newer players.
We want to try as much as we can within the context of everything else working
to allow everyone to have a fighting chance in every battle essentially.
So that's going to be driving some of our thinking.
For reasons that I will get into more...
As we go through this, we want to maintain fairly stable price ranges.
We want fluctuations in prices, we want a player-driven economy, we want the market
to be uncertain, but we're going to want to keep it within a certain range and not let
things drift too far out of bounds so that we're not basically violating our balance
assumptions.
On top of those three, this is kind of order,
this is not strict ordering,
but it's a general sense of the priorities.
We want to maximize the enjoyment of the non-core audience,
which basically, we know from experience from our game
and from other sandbox games that some players
are not going to want to do PvP, for example.
And even if we think it's the best thing since CySquared,
some players are just like, I really want to play your game,
but I just want to play in the safe area on my own.
That's okay. We need to make sure that our really good bits, our guild versus guild and so on,
are as good as they can be. But then we want to try and make everyone else happy as
much as we can on top of that. So that's kind of a secondary consideration that's always in
our head. How can we fix things for them as well?
And finally, we're going to try as hard as we can to keep the math simple.
There's a place for complex math, but it's a fairly rare place.
So as much as we can, we're going to try and keep it straightforward.
It means that it's easier for us as developers
to work with all the numbers we're doing,
because we're making a lot of numbers.
And it means for players, the simpler and more easy to grasp the math is,
the easier it is for them to develop an intuitive understanding
of how the game fits together without having to go and build their own spreadsheet
to figure out what you were doing.
So those are kind of our core goals.
Step one, do the outline.
Next step is step two, building relationships,
filling that outline in.
So, goal one, incentivize the best bits of the game.
We think that the best parts of our game,
the most intrinsically rewarding, is our PVP,
and especially our guild versus guild,
like territory warfare gameplay.
They score really high on our intrinsic motivators.
You're out there with your guild,
fighting other guilds who you know,
and you're next door enemies who you love to hate,
so you've got a lot of relatedness.
Your guild has control over where it's going and who it's fighting.
You get a lot of autonomy out of that.
And because we're doing PvP, and we have this complex
you are what you wear equipment meta game,
each battle can be different, so we can have strong intrinsic rewards
as well as strong mastery, because we're constantly
facing new challenges to overcome.
So we think that's the best bit of our game,
and we want to make sure the people go there.
So we have 8 tiers of resource in our game, and we have 5 resources.
The first 3 tiers are effectively training resources.
We don't really worry about them from an economy balance point of view.
The game kind of starts at T4, so we have T4 to T8, our 5 primary tiers.
that we're worried about.
Our world is divided into clusters,
which is like a region, a zone of the game.
They're like 800 meters aside, I think, or something.
Squares that make up the world.
Each cluster has a tier.
The tier of the cluster determines the resources present.
So a tier six cluster has resources up to tier six.
So when we set our world up,
and you can't really see this, but it's there, I promise,
like in the outlands and the PVP area
where the highest tier clusters are,
and the very kind of most competitive areas
where the very highest tiers are.
So the T8 clusters are.
where the kind of the core of the guild versus guild happens.
So the places where all that fighting happens,
all that good gameplay happens,
also have the best resources and therefore the best rewards.
Cool.
So that's kind of our core thing.
You get rewarded for doing things that we think you'll enjoy.
Second goal, allowing everyone to compete.
What we're going to aim for here, in simple terms,
is a low power gap and a high rarity scaling.
What do I mean by this?
So we have a power progression between tiers.
You can have T4 equipment, T5, T6, T7, T8.
Each tier is more powerful than the last.
And we want to get that gap as low as possible
so that the T8 people aren't so far ahead of the T4 people.
So we looked at other games, we looked at our own game,
we play tested, we talked to players,
we worked through it all, and we figured out eventually
that about 1.2 per level, per tier,
is about what we're looking for.
That's about as low as we can go.
So T5 is 20% more powerful than T4.
T6 is 20% more powerful than T5.
And therefore T8 is about twice as powerful as T4, 2.07.
So one T8 guy has about the same stats as two T4 guys.
That's about as low as we can make that
without the tier step feeling empty
and like what's the point in getting high tier gear?
And that's kind of where we hit with that.
By contrast, rarity of resources in the world,
we're gonna go much steeper.
We're gonna do three times per tier.
So each additional tier is three times rarer than the last.
So T8 is 81 times rarer than T4.
What we're trying to do here is basically make the very high-end stuff incredibly expensive.
Kind of the ideal balancing fallout of this setup is that T4 is common.
If you want to go PvPing, you can always afford some T4 gear.
It's not completely valueless because we want death to have some meaning.
It makes the fights more interesting.
But it's accessible.
T5 and T6 is kind of what you work for on an everyday basis.
That's where you want to be hitting for most of your fights.
And then T7 and especially T8, the T8 right at the top,
are very rare.
We want the big guilds to be saving up their T8 equipment
for critical fights.
If most players never see T8, at least for the first year
of their game or whatever, that's fine with us.
That's in a healthy, balanced place.
We want this because the high-end gear needs to exist to act as a wealth sink at the high-end
because otherwise you can get massive wealth disparities between different levels of player.
And also to give everyone a long-term goal.
You're always working towards something once you get there.
your final goal, you're kind of done.
Like, we found an EVE that like,
the biggest shipping game is a Titan,
it's 20 kilometers long and it takes six months to build
and it's worth like hundreds of real world dollars
or whatever, and like, something like,
last time I looked many years ago,
like half of all Titan pilots had unsubscribed
from the game because they'd won.
Right, they got the biggest thing, game done.
So we want to keep that high end as rare as we can.
and as I say, use it as a way to sink resources
and sink wealth out of the world
without being completely overpowering to everybody else.
So that works out nicely.
Next thing we want to do, we want to keep these,
as I said earlier, keep these price ranges stable.
To a certain degree, we want price flow.
Obviously, we have a player market,
open economy, player-driven economy.
We want prices to shift according to supply and demand.
This kind of balances out the income per hour
that people get in different professions,
because time is essentially the ultimate resource
for any game like this.
We want to ensure that people who are killing mobs
to get silver are making the same kind of money
as people gathering resources.
And if we have the market, then those two will balance out as people, if it's not worth doing.
People, if there's too much of something, the value of that thing will go down.
People will stop doing, collecting it so much.
The supply will drop, the value go back up.
Like, it's a nice, happy relationship.
But we want to keep the overall prices within a band.
This is good for a couple of reasons.
It means that people can't,
the high-end girls can't run away with wealth
by monopolizing the high-end resources
and basically forming a cartel or monopoly there.
that can cause problems because they get so much wealth that it distorts the entire game.
We also have this thing obviously where we have these five versus five fights.
You can't just bring more people to deal with the wealth imbalance, so we're a little bit
more constrained in terms of what we're okay with, with disparities there.
And finally of course we need to make sure at the broad scale that those fighting areas,
the GBG, the PVP areas, Guild versus Guild, player versus player,
are more valuable than the safe space.
If that gets out of whack,
then our whole game swings out of true.
So we're gonna try and keep those under control.
How we're gonna do that is we're gonna have overflows
and underflows for everything.
So we have, as I said, we have our resources,
we have our silver, as kind of the two things
we need to balance off against each other
to a large degree.
We have a couple of features.
We have this salvage feature that lets you take a crafted item
and salvage it, and that gets you 75% of its resources
back as resources and 25% of its resource value back as silver.
This means that players can turn resources
into silver through this method at a rate that we set.
We also have a feature called transmutation.
You can take some tier forward to the transmuter.
which is a building, you give it a load of money,
and it may give you some T5 wood.
So you can improve your resources
by spending large amounts of silver on it.
This means that you can turn silver into resources.
So now we have this back and forth flow between the two
at rates that we set, which is important.
What this ends up doing is building a price channel for these things.
If you're selling resources for less than its effective silver value,
then some player will figure that out,
and they will buy the resources, craft them up, salvage them out,
turn them into silver for more silver than they bought them for,
and that will...
bring the price back up again as the demand shoots up and everything
because people are getting free money.
That gives you an effective floor on the price.
And similarly, transmutation, if you're selling above the transmute price,
then someone can just, you know, you're selling T6 at above the transmute price,
someone can buy some T5, transmute it up,
and sell it, and then put it on the market for profit, essentially.
Free money again.
That will tend to drive the prices back down,
so we end up with this nice channel between salvage and transmute.
So that gives us our underflows and our overflows,
gives us our price controls.
But as we're building relationships,
what we need to do is we need to find
what that relationship is.
We assume that the sort of expected price
based on rarity follows the rarity curve.
So the sort of the natural price for each resource
goes up by a factor of three each tier.
We get our salvage price, gives us a nice floor.
And we get our transmute price, which gives us our ceiling.
This is a log scale, because it flattens it out.
So we have this price channel.
And then we need to decide how that relates to the rarity progression,
because that's kind of the core relationship here,
is how do those two things map together.
So we decide that the low end, at T4,
we want to have the salvage price be about what the implied rarity value is.
We want to ensure that those prices at T4 are low,
but we want to hold them up a bit.
We don't want T4 equipment to be worthless
because that makes dying worthless, which makes it boring.
We also want to ensure that new players coming up,
they're just getting to T4 for the first time,
they're harvesting T4 resources.
We don't want that to be worthless.
So this kind of generates a flaw.
Worst case scenario, they can salvage it out
and make silver off it.
So harvesting T4 is never not worth anything.
The transmute price we want high at this point,
because we don't want veteran players bypassing
those new players and just transmuting all the T4
they need themselves.
We want to ensure that it's not worth transmuting down here,
basically.
By contrast, at the high end, we want our tier 8.
We want the implied rarity price at or even slightly
above the transmute price.
so that we're ensuring that as much value as possible is coming out of that
while keeping it under control. Because the limit at the high end is
respawn rates
in the territory that gills control rather than harvest time, they're
basically waiting for the resources to come back.
So it's basically free resources, it's always going to be worth it for them.
But we don't want that price to shoot through the roof,
and we don't want to,
both because we don't want those girls
to become fabulously wealthy,
and because we don't want to lock everyone else
completely out of the highest tier gear.
So, in fact, we'd be happy if most of our tier eight
came from transmutation.
It means there's a huge silver sink.
We're sinking a lot of silver out of the economy,
which keeps our inflation under control, makes us happy.
It means everyone can get it, but it's expensive.
We obviously don't want people salvaging
high-tier equipment, that would be crazy.
So we have these low and highs,
and then because we're on a log graph,
we're just gonna say, our rarity scaling
basically needs to hit like this.
So we have this, in addition to these numbers now,
we have this thing called item value, IV,
which is kind of our arbitrary silver equivalents
for a resource, and we wanna say the item value,
which is basically the salvage value,
is about the same as the rarity value at T4.
And the transmute cost is going to be 10 times that.
So you're always going to have this item value, which is what salvage returns,
and above that you have the transmute value.
And we know it's pinned.
The two things, salvage and the resource value intersect at T4.
We want them to cross over at T8.
So our item value progression is about 1.66.
And that is basically our economy setup.
There's a whole bunch of numbers
that are gonna follow on from this
as we math out how much of everything
on all the respawn rates and so on.
I'm gonna talk about it in a second.
But our core economy setup is this slide.
This is the basic relationships
that determine how everything fits together.
And we'll do the same process for silver and for fame,
our equivalent of XP, and for farming
and for everything else, we'll go through this process
and how much do we want and how fast do you progress,
how much fame do you get per hour, how much is it worth,
how long does it take you to max things out,
all this kind of stuff.
But it's all just a set of relationships and core numbers
that say this is how the game fits together.
And that's our relationship building.
So we have these goals.
We have incentivizing the best part of the game.
We're doing that through saying the bits, the GVG
and the PVP bits, have the best resources.
Allowing everyone to compete by keeping that power gap low
and keeping the rarity progression steep.
Someone didn't listen to the phone warning.
We're maintaining stable price ranges by having these overflows and underflows.
Our salvage and our transmute to keep things in the channel.
They can float around all they like inside that,
but we know that they're not going to get too far out of bounds.
And then along the way, maximizing enjoyment of the non-core audience.
That's things like, for example, transmuting means that you can get to T8 from the safe zones.
You can only harvest up to T5, but you can save up the silver to keep transmuting up and up and up.
It will take you forever, but it's there.
Making sure that T4 and T5 are available in the safe zones
so that you can kind of,
you can kind of gear up to go do PvP
before you have to go into the PvP areas.
All this kind of stuff is just, you know,
ticking away in our mind.
How can we tune this to make them happy?
And the math is pretty simple.
It's all geometric progressions
because we don't find the need at this point
to make it any more complex than that.
Cool, so let's do some coloring in.
Doing the math.
We have our relationships,
we've got all these free-floating relationships.
We need to pick some anchors, or at least an anchor,
to kind of pin that down to some actual numbers.
For this, what we decided to do,
we looked at saying, okay,
the high end of normal PPP is tier six,
and for the people we think are playing at that level,
We reckon there's going to be this many,
and they're going to die this often.
We need about 10,000 tier six per day
across all the resource types.
So that kind of gives us our anchor point.
We know then that if it's 10,000 T6,
because of our three times rarity progression,
it's 30,000 T5, and 3,000 T7, 3,333 T7, and so on.
From that anchor point and our relationships,
it all flows out, and we make a giant spreadsheet.
And we go away and we do Excel.
And this is what I'm actually doing at work right now.
The last couple of weeks, it's making more spreadsheets.
There's a lot of work involved in this for us
because we need to math out everything in the game.
But there shouldn't be surprises.
We always check the numbers at the end of the process to make sure they don't look insane.
And sometimes there are things we want to fiddle with a bit for player experience reasons,
like we've been thinking a lot recently about how long does it take tween finding resources
to harvest and can we kind of tune that to be more enjoyable without breaking our overall
economy.
But for the most part...
We don't want to be fiddling.
If we find ourselves wanting, having the urge to change a lot of numbers at the end of the
spreadsheet process, then we know we've probably done something wrong in either our goals or
relationships and we want to go back and change those.
And we'll usually have like, the setup variables will be in the sheet somewhere,
I'll talk about this some more in a second.
So we can just go, okay, what if we change it from 3,
power of 3 per level or 3 to whatever per level, to 3.5,
does that give us more what we want?
Okay, and we're working at that level of the numbers rather than
tuning individual values.
Because we want to have these clear relationships that are driving all
our stuff.
So in the context of this, in Excel, I want to talk a little bit about some Excel best
practices that we've developed.
Because I think it's cool.
I like Excel.
It's my friend.
The table feature is amazing.
Who here knows what I'm talking about?
Okay, cool. Some people don't. This GIF is going to blow your minds.
Come on.
So you can basically select a thing, and then you click make it into a table.
And then it's a table.
And then you can add things. You can refer to them using their column name,
which is wonderful, and it auto-extends, and you can filter based on the thing.
Oh, so good.
I learned this at Sandbox and I was just like, this is amazing.
So this is definitely a thing we use a lot.
Gives you the color coding, gives you all the stuff.
A particular little trick I picked up is the variables table.
If you make a table that is a single row...
and you call it vars, then you can,
rather than having to refer to $a, $32
as your balancing number for this,
it's vars primary mult.
That's where it is because the columns are single cells,
so it returns a cell rather than an array.
So I often have these little settings tables
just to let me put all the values in one place
and it's really easy to understand.
Which brings me to my next point,
usability and maintainability of Excel.
We're getting deep into nerd country here, I know.
But I think about this a lot,
because we have big spreadsheets.
We have a master sheet we've been using
for like three or four years
that has all the kind of core data in.
We've got various spin-off sheets that we use.
And there's different people using them at different times,
and you have to come back to things that you've done
from six months ago, and we update things for new math
and all this kind of stuff.
And kind of keeping those spreadsheets fresh and usable and present is kind of a challenge.
So we think a lot while we're doing this about sending them off about color coding so we can see...
Can I get back to this?
Ooh, over here. I should have put this in a new thing.
We can see here, like, the orange tables are static game data we're not touching.
Green is our primary setup.
The green cells are the cells that we want to tweak most.
The red cells are output data that we're going to put into the game and so on.
So we can look at a sheet and say, okay, I want to fiddle with it.
I know I'm fiddling here and here because that's where the green stuff is.
All this kind of stuff.
I use the comments feature in Excel a lot.
You can comment cells, leave notes yourself.
So this is why I did this gigantic formula,
because in six months time, when I come back to it,
I have no idea what it's doing.
And generally thinking about the robustness of formulae,
making it so they can deal with adding and removing columns
or changing column names.
It's a whole bunch of theory to do with VLOOKUP and matching
and stuff that I don't want to get into.
But we think about this stuff a lot.
We want to make sure that our Excel can survive
being punched in the face by people
who don't know what they're doing.
That's point two and point three.
I'm a strong advocate for automating all your exports.
There's obviously an argument you made
about it saves designer time
if it has to do everything manually,
but then you get into an argument with your programmers
about whose time is worth more.
Obviously, the designer's time is worth a lot,
but let's just sidestep that.
Let's talk about bugs, right?
If you put things in by hand,
and I've done a lot of hand entry in my time,
Eventually you're going to fat finger something and you're going to add or miss a digit somewhere.
And something buried deep in the bowels of your game is ten times more or less than it
should be.
And if you're a small team like us, you probably won't catch that if you've just done a thousand
numbers by hand.
And then some players will and they'll destroy your economy before you catch it and it's
a complete pain to unpick.
If you've automated all your exports,
you've built a nice mathy Excel table
that's all formulas so there can't be any individual errors,
and then you push a button and it goes into your game,
then that kind of bug doesn't exist anymore.
The bug where you've done something wrong
and everything in your game is a factor of 10 out
does exist, but you spot that because it's really obvious.
So we've had our CTO made us a nice little Excel plugin
that you click a button and it writes it out
to our XML format, which is lovely.
So I strongly, strongly, strongly do the automation.
ignore the arguments about efficiency of time and just say it's going to stop you from breaking
your game because I've seen it far too many times.
Yeah, and then we ship the thing,
and then we see what happens.
For a couple of reasons.
Firstly, we used to calculate on Eve,
we'd generally get 10,000 players online after downtime.
So we're gonna get 10,000 man hours of QA in our first hour,
which we can't match pre-launch, period.
That's too large a number.
On top of that, at a more kind of detailed level,
a more subtle level,
If your game is simple enough for you to predict how it's going to play out,
then it's also simple enough for your players to predict how it's going to play out,
and some of them are smarter than you, and they will solve your game and put the answer on a wiki.
And then, everybody knows that the most efficient way to level up is killing wolves.
Everyone is now killing wolves.
Congratulations, your game is boring.
So I'm of the opinion that your game should be sufficiently complex that you do not know how it is going to get used.
Which is kind of a scary thought.
But it seems to be the only way to square that circle of keeping people engaged over long periods.
They need a game that they can't see the end of, they can't see the simple solution to.
Which means that you're going to have to you know you want to take a good stab at it and all this work
We've done here is doing that trying to figure out where we think everything's going to settle and we have these you know
This is part of why we have these minimax things these overflows underflows the the price channel
So that if we've got something horribly wrong it the game still catches it
But there's no real substitute for putting it out there and seeing how it goes
So you're going to have to iterate on it you have to see how it performs, and you're going to have to
make changes when you realize the mistakes you've inevitably made.
Basically how we're doing this is we're doing some science.
We're going to make some mental models.
We're going to make some predictions based on those models.
We think the economy is going to do something like this.
We're going to put it out there.
We're going to test those predictions.
And then we're going to use those measurements, those tests,
to refine our model and have another go at making it better.
And there's a lot of things that play into this.
Obviously, we use analytics, we use metrics.
They're great in particular for the measure step,
figuring out what's going on.
We also involve our players a lot.
We talk to our players, we have forums,
we have a hand-picked group of players
called our Roundtable, because we're Ethereum,
who give us more direct and more focused feedback.
We have Discord, we have Reddit, blah, blah, blah, blah.
Always try to talk to our players,
because A, they will tell you where to go look in your data.
B, they will give you a lot of qualitative information, and C, they will help you understand
why, which is the real crux of the issue.
How do you build a causal understanding of what is going on in your economy so that you
know that if we change X, then Y will happen?
If you just rely on metrics...
which are great and all, you get some data points,
and you're like, oh, okay, okay, okay,
this is probably doing this.
And if your game is really simple, that's great,
and if you want to maximize the height of the line,
you just keep going right.
If your game is complex, then a model may tell you,
actually, no, it's going to do this.
Right?
And if you try to use your metrics to min-max that,
it's going to...
best case take you to that peak on the right and then stop
and worst case you're going to go over it and you're going to crash everything.
So, metric's good, but metric is good in their place feeding into your models
and not just being blindly trusted
because your game is simple enough to be solved
to solve your balance with metrics, it's too simple
and your players will fix it, solve it for you.
So always in this, always looking at our feedback,
always looking at our analytics,
always trying to kind of, once we've shipped,
to go back and constantly working back
towards those core goals to bring our economy
into the place we want it to be.
So, that kind of is gonna wrap it up.
Understand what you're doing and why you're doing it.
I say I'm a philosophy guy, so that kind of works for me,
but I think it's important generally.
Set clear goals, invest time early on in your process
and set in the goals for what you want to achieve.
Spend a lot of time thinking about the relationships
between things, that's the core of your economy set up,
is how things relate to one another,
what it's telling your players to do,
where the incentives are,
and where that's going to end people up.
Your math should be unsurprising and uneventful.
Do your Excels well.
Make lovely spreadsheets with pretty colors.
These tables are awesome.
And yeah, math it out.
And if you need to make changes, go back and change
in your goals and your relationships
during your final numbers.
And then we ship and we revise and we look at our analytics
and we listen to our players and we figure out
how to optimize the game.
It's never gonna be perfect because if it's perfect,
then it's solvable.
If it's solvable, then it's boring.
Cool.
That does me.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Any questions?
We have people at microphones.
Wonderful.
Hi.
Hey.
So near the beginning of your talk, you went over the difference between extrinsic and
intrinsic rewards.
Yes.
And you mentioned that one of your goals is to basically overlap them as much as you can.
And so the first thing that comes to my mind is how can you superimpose this, how can you
do a micro three way or a simple three way reward?
there is a lot of research out there that
if you give extrinsic rewards to behaviors
that are intrinsically motivating,
that it actually reduces the intrinsic motivation.
Most of that research is in the context of workspaces
and job performance, but I was curious
if you've encountered that trend in your work
and how you've dealt with it.
So the question is basically, what about all that research that says that extrinsically
awarding people for intrinsically awarding stuff makes them like it less?
More or less?
Yeah, that's the thing.
In an idea world, in a simpler game, we wouldn't need all these structures, but...
I'm not sure how you avoid having extrinsic motivators in a game like this.
I'm not sure how you'd make an MMO scale game without any kind of XP or money or anything.
Which would be an interesting thought experiment, but I don't know where you'd go with that.
So given that we have them...
we might as well use them for good, right?
I know what you're talking about, I totally agree,
and it would be ideal if we didn't have that,
we didn't have achievements, we didn't have any kind of
sticking an RPG system on everything.
But in a game where we kind of,
we don't see an obvious way to avoid it,
we've just got to kind of make the best of it,
if that makes sense.
Thanks.
You're welcome.
I just had a quick question about inflation.
You said before that as far as I have inflation,
there's that whole security system that brings it back.
That's fine.
I was kind of more curious about your end game players
and inflation on a player level.
Like just over time, accumulating resources,
how you would deal with sinking them,
like gold sinks in WoW for instance.
Okay, so the question, if I understand it, is how do we kind of ensure that individual
players don't get runaway wealth that ruins everything for them?
It's a good question, because inflation has historically been a big issue in all kinds
of persistent world games.
A couple of things.
One is to always have a higher goal that they're aiming for, that they can throw money at,
is a nice way to get them to spend.
But the thing we found, like, so we found on EVE, my data's all two years old, someone
will shout at me if this is wrong now, but...
money in the game went up over time and average money on players went over time, but
market inflation was pretty much flat.
What we think is going on here
is that
the players, particularly the players who generate lots of wealth, who are into that kind of
gameplay, they see their wallet as their high score.
so they don't accumulate all that money so they can throw it at someone, they accumulate
their money so they can say, I've got 3 trillion isk, how much have you got?
And that's kind of their motivation, my assumption at least, their motivation for gathering all
that money so it doesn't impact the gameplay nearly as much as you'd think because they
don't want to spend it, if that makes sense.
Totally fair, thank you.
I'd love if anyone did some research on that and told me definitively because it's an interesting
question.
Yes, very interesting question.
I'm Ted Castronova.
you know virtual economist. This was a wonderful talk. I'd like you to design the real world economy.
I've got it like a 3000 word rant on why the financial system is completely badly designed if you want it.
Well yeah. Can I. I want to get your car. Anyway a question. What do you guys do about gold farming. I just looked up the
price of Albion silver and there it is. Yeah. So what do you do for that third market.
So we have a system, the same system that Eve has more or less, where you can...
We have in-game silver and in-game gold, and silver is the main game resource, main game currency,
and gold is bought with real-world money.
You can buy... We have a premium subscription that increases all your progression by 50%,
so you really want it, and you can buy that with dollars or with gold,
so you can trade gold and dollars, or silver and real-world money effectively on the market.
That puts a limit on it or dampens down the gold selling.
On top of that, various enforcement programs
that I don't know the details of,
but I know people are doing.
It's just a scourge of everything ever.
I'm not aware of a silver bullet solution.
But yeah, we have the gold thing
so people can trade money for game time and so on.
And we just try to stamp on them wherever we find them.
Sadness.
Hi.
Thanks a lot for the talk.
I really enjoyed it.
My question is about AI participants in the economy.
I don't know if Albion has these, but I know that Eve does.
So I'm just curious what sort of goals or approaches you take on getting AI players
to participate in such a way that doesn't cause players to either ignore or abuse them.
So you talking about AI in terms of player one bots or in terms of our
Intervention the economy no like in player
Factions or NPCs who are gonna buy sell or generate pieces of the economy, so I said again
In-game factions or NPCs?
Right, okay, so yeah, yeah.
Developer side AI rather than player side AI.
Yeah, okay, so question is how do we intervene, basically, in the economy in an automated way?
Largely speaking, we don't.
We have things like, for example, when the game goes live for the first time,
it takes several days for people to get enough food supply
to supply the buildings they need to make food.
So we have some, like, sell orders for food
the first week of the game after launch to kind of kickstart that.
But otherwise, I don't think we have any artificial buy or sell orders in the game.
It's all entirely player-driven.
they can bootstrap everything themselves beyond the food issue so that's not a huge problem
and yeah we don't mess with that side of things very much at all.
If I'm answering the question correctly, do we have an equal amount of each resource type in the world?
Five minutes, thank you.
Yeah, we have, yeah, at least certainly the level I'm talking about here,
we do the math so we know how many resources of each there needs to be
and then we tune the spawn rate of each individual resource type.
There's slightly fewer wood nodes in the world because there's less forest,
therefore a wood node has a slightly shorter respawn time.
So yeah, we try and keep that pretty flat across all things because the goal is...
like the equipment construction setup is designed to use everything equally.
Obviously if players find, for example, that cloth armor is way better than leather armor,
then there's going to be a surge of demand on cloth and drop for leather,
but that's cool, that leads to all kinds of interesting market effects that we're very happy with.
Hi, I just want to talk more on the, or ask a question about the inflation.
Did you consider a pure bartering system where there is only a player market?
If I want your sword, you want chicken heads, I give you five chicken heads for a sword,
rather than a silver, gold, coin, currency?
So the question is, did we consider not having currency and just doing barter?
I don't think we did.
There was actually an interesting thing a couple of tests ago where players were...
Everyone was very obsessed about being self-sufficient.
All the guilds wanted to make all their own stuff, so they weren't actually using silver at all.
They were all about harvesting, telling all their players to go out and gather resources so we can build our own stuff,
which led to a really weird place where no one needed money.
which mess with our game quite a lot.
But broadly speaking, the main problem with trying to do that,
it's a really interesting approach, but the problem is that
it really clogs up the market because if you have X,
you need to have, you must want Y that's being sold,
it means it's much harder to find a market match,
whereas having silver as an intermediary means that
you can always offload stuff.
Silver's basically a way of just...
or money and currency in general is just a way of time shifting trades, right?
So it means that you can offload that sword for some silver now
and I can turn the silver into the eggs I need later
rather than having to wait for a silver to eggs trade to show up
or doing some weird thing where I, you know,
trading for yammick sauce or whatever
to try and get myself to what I want.
So it would be cool, but I think it ends up clogging the market up too much
for it to be workable, at least without doing a lot of thinking.
Yes.
I don't think there's any more questions, I think I can stop there.
That's wonderful.
Yeah, so thanks for coming, you've been a lovely audience for me to fill out your forms
and stuff.
I'm going to keep talking so that guy can't clap.
No, I'm done, cool, thank you.