First of all, thank you all for coming.
It's great to see you guys here.
My name is Derek Sakamoto.
I'm a senior user interface designer on Hearthstone.
And I'm here to talk to you about how we went about
creating an immersive user experience.
Really quick bio.
I've been at Blizzard for a little over 12 years now.
My first job was on World of Warcraft,
designing the UI for that.
I worked on Vanilla to Wrath of the Lich King.
After six plus years of that,
it was time for a change for me,
so I was fortunate enough to be able to move on
to Team Pegasus, which in turn became Hearthstone.
Yay, right?
So for the next 30 minutes, I'm gonna talk to you
about some of the high level ideas and principles
that guided us to get Hearthstone where it is today
in terms of UI and game.
So number one is finding your seed.
Let's get physical.
And UI gets to sit at the big kids table.
Finding your seed, what am I talking about?
To me the seed is like a muse, or like a,
it's like an image, or a movie, or a song,
something for your team that they can all look at
and understand the direction that your game's gonna go in.
So before I show you our seed,
I'll show you what Hearthstone was like
before we had a core idea to work from.
And as a warning, people outside of Team 5
have not seen these images,
and maybe a lot of people on Team 5
just because the team is growing.
So I introduced to you Warcraft Legends.
This is a build called Fire and Ice,
and this was the build that got us greenlit.
And I think at this time we had maybe the Rogue and the Mage,
and then Warlock was still a work in progress.
But clearly this is not what we wanted for Hearthstone.
Another idea we had was having a world map
where you travel across Azeroth,
unlocking regions and zones,
doing single-player quests and content to unlock them.
And this is actually a screenshot of our Flash prototype.
We created the whole game in Flash first,
and this was all working.
We had adventures that worked single-player,
and those were all done by Ben Broad, I think.
And here we go.
This is a pre-alpha visual target for our game.
And I think everyone's pretty happy that we
didn't hit this target.
It just has no life.
It looks like Tron.
And it's super complicated.
This is not what we wanted for our stuff.
And there's a bunch of other stuff that we did,
you know, for single player.
There's books, there's crazy weird 3D cards,
there's hologram cards.
I'm just glad I have a job after this stinker.
Hearthstone in the Forest, you know,
this mock-up had me stumped.
Eh?
And this was matchmaking, and then,
this is a real gem.
We knew that when we were doing our matchmaking,
we didn't want to have a screen with a counter going up,
you know, just counting, searching for players or whatever.
So we kind of went too far the other way and this is what we
ended up with.
Hero.
Match.
You go and do battle.
Right?
Pretty awesome, right?
So let the record show that the path to Hearthstone as it is
today was not obvious or clear to us.
So this is why you need a seed,
otherwise you're just running around in the bushes, right?
You're just out in the weeds doing whatever.
And this video was created by one of our 3D artists,
and it was a result of a super long meeting
between me and the artist,
just trying to figure out what could we do, you know?
What would be our vision?
And so, here's this box, you know, you zoom into it, there's a world map, there's zones to choose
from, you choose your hero, and it rips open the map and you zoom down into this crazy world where
people are battling, right, it makes it feel like it's alive, there's other people there with you,
until you find your match, bam, like that, and then you zoom out, and then you're on the game
board.
And that's not really Hearthstone,
it's kind of Hearthstone today,
but I think this really gave us something to latch onto.
Like, this could be something, you know,
this is pretty neat.
And so that's why you need to find your seed.
And once this box idea was established,
it kind of grew roots into the team,
into the team's minds and hearts,
and it grew strength and was able to grow up
into this tree, and it branched out
and created all kinds of different fruits,
which I'm about to show you.
So this is our box if you haven't seen it,
if you haven't played our game.
And once we had that, we had a framework
for what we wanted to do with our UI.
You know, it feels like maybe a jewelry box
or a music box or something.
And it became more obvious about how this stuff
was gonna work.
We wanted little trays and little things like keys
that would kind of fit in that environment.
And came up with the making,
an idea for making lame loading screens,
like tightening hinges and that kind of stuff.
And then once we had this box, it was always sitting on the table.
And we were kind of, one day we got to thinking, where is this table?
You know?
And we decided, well, maybe it's in an inn or a tavern,
or something like that.
And once we had that idea, it kind of just
created another burst of creativity.
So this is our splash screen for mobile.
This is a loading screen.
It's like you're walking into the tavern,
pushing open the doors, and there's
a really warm, inviting glow coming in.
Except for when the servers are full,
and there's a sign outside.
It's like, table's full.
But that was pretty cool.
And then here's the key art.
And we informed the key art, you know,
but in turn, the artists who did this
really fleshed out the world in the context
of playing Hearthstone in the world of Warcraft.
And it really got us excited,
because that's cool, right?
And this is something that was really awesome.
Like, this seed was strong enough
that we were able to give it to a third party,
and they were able to fully realize that tavern
as the BlizzCon final stage.
And that thing is incredible.
and we're still trying to figure out how we can chop
into little pieces and get in the office,
but so far, so far no dice.
This doesn't really have anything to do with anything,
except that a lot of us either worked on WoW
or are big WoW fans, and our game was inspired by WoW,
and then it kind of went full circle,
and now it's inside of WoW, which is really cool to us.
So the obvious question.
Having a CD, that's awesome, right?
That's great.
But how do you find one, you know?
That's the real question.
And having done so, I have no idea.
But I can tell you kind of how we went about
searching for this.
In the beginning, we started out with this
really awful, flat, parchment garbage.
And then we decided, well, this game should probably be 3D.
And we wanted to be more physical.
As a side note, this mockup was called Simon Says, I think.
I don't know.
And then we knew we wanted more magic as well.
And then on top of that, we wanted to layer some charm,
which is kind of one of our things.
And then finally, we kind of said,
well, let's really make it feel valuable
and feel constructed,
and this is kind of where we ended up.
So, finding your seed.
The path to your seed is never direct,
unless you're super lucky or a super genius or something,
which we're neither.
you should actively look for it early in your project,
just because it'll make the rest of things
go so much smoother.
Because it just makes everything better.
It makes everything fit and feel like it's one thing.
And I think you must find it.
If you want to have a shot in having your game
be something special and have a true vision,
I think you need to find it.
Okay, section two, let's get physical.
What the heck does this mean?
into development we had been doing 3D UI and I took a step back and was thinking about
what the trends were in UI development at the time. It looks like everything is moving
to flat UI design. Everything is really slick, really smooth and just completely 2D. I mean
it's completely maybe two-tone or something like that. And once we really started thinking
about it and thinking about what was right for our project, we kind of just embraced
it. We're like, dude, let's get physical, you know?
Physicality can be big for us.
I have no idea if this age range is right or not.
This idea of physicality really started to
trace roots through all of our project
and influence things in expected ways
and some unexpected ways.
It makes things feel valuable.
These are objects people can relate to,
the materials people can know whether they're
worth something or not because of the gold and gems and these kind of things.
And it's important for us because as a free to play game we really want to
respect
you know players time and money that they spend and give them things that
feel really good.
And being a card collecting game, the core experience is opening a pack.
So a lot of us, we collected cards as kids, and there's something about opening a pack of
cards. There's the crinkle, the foil, there's the smell when you open it. And we kind of used
the tools we had, which are visuals and sound, to try to replicate that joyous experience,
you know, something that cool. Another thing is that this physicality unifies the
experience. I'm going to show you a couple of screens.
This is like our announcement screen for next Rammus.
This is just our matchmaking spinner.
And then this is our store.
So you're selecting cards and the store moves around.
And these are all different UIs, and they
live in different planes.
But I think having them all be physical and move
in the same similar ways, like there's a lot of bounce going
on, there's a lot of over rotation kind of things,
makes them feel cohesive whether the player realizes it or not.
Here is a semi-unexpected one.
It's a happy accident with touch.
And that Hearthstone was supposed to be,
the main platform was desktop.
And it would be nice if we got into tablets,
but it was not a sure thing by any means.
And so when we designed things like the cards,
they would tilt as you drag them around, and they swoosh.
And when you tap the board, dust flies up,
all this kind of stuff.
Once we translated it to touch, it
was a little bit magical to me anyways.
And for me, that's the best way to play the game,
is with your finger actually moving around these pieces,
and it feels like you're part of that world.
this is kind of a selfish one. It's fun to work on this stuff. A couple of us like to make
things. One guy whittles. I like to do woodworking on the side. Another guy is into
World War II stuff where it's old and you can feel the construction of it. For us to be the
geek out on that while we're building stuff is really fun. This is kind of a big one. As a
card
collectible card game, you really need to have this over the shoulder appeal, which is that
someone is walking by and they see your game being played, they need to be interested and be
like, oh, maybe that's cool, maybe that's something I should try. As opposed to, you know,
it's like this Tom and Jerry stuff. But as opposed to seeing all these words and numbers and
just being kind of turned off by the whole thing up front without really giving it a chance.
this one is also in for selfish reasons. These are board clickable. These are things to fidget
with while you're playing the game. Our 3D guys do a crazy job on these things. And I included
this particular one because my two-year-old almost every night asked me to play Hearthstone.
And what he means by that is load up this board and launch that rocket ship. So that's why
that's in there.
So another cool unexpected thing is that fans have embraced it.
You know, once, if you design these things to be physical, it's kind of not a big leap
to see that they could be brought into the real world.
And I think fans are really starting to connect with it.
And once they build these things, it really jazzes us up and, you know, gives us, makes
us excited because these are things we designed, but people are actually realizing these things
for themselves.
So we have cakes, you know, we have wooden boxes, we have this thing, which, I mean, it's a
play piece, but it's cool that he was excited to make it. Let's just say that. Wallets. And
then this cake really takes the cake, if you know what I mean. Like, I want one of these at
my birthday. And then this is the holy grail, right? This is the box. And I think everybody
wants one of these things. These things are awesome.
So this image is terrible, terrifying. I included it because Ben Brode hates it. Makes him
feel really geeky. So taking the stance on physical UI, doing this, it's not all roses.
There's definite downsides to doing it. But I think if you are aware of the downsides and
you have answers and reasons for why they're okay, I think it's good to do these things. So
number one, it's hard to expand.
On the left side of that screen, there's our nine heroes.
And it's like, what happens if we add another one?
I don't know, right?
But our stance on this is that it's finally crafted.
Everything has its place.
And we tend to design for now.
And what that means is we have tight deadlines.
We can't try to foresee everything in the future
and make it expandable in all different ways that
may or may not happen.
So we design for now. And that's why we try to make things have their own little homes. And
we do have this tradition on the team of screwing over our future selves. We say, oh, what
about this thing? Future Derek will figure it out. He'll be smarter by then, right? And
obviously, time comes around and we go, dang, you past Derek, you're such a jerk. And that
happens all the time. Just always cursing our past selves.
Another downside is that it's very resource intensive to
create. This is just our collection manager. This is like
two years of my life, which is awesome. But these are all the
things that we go through to try to get to where we are, you know.
And it may not seem obvious when you look at it, but it's a tough
road to get there. And the argument to this is that our game
is UI.
We don't have huge virtual worlds and monsters running
around.
All we have is our board, and we have the box.
So it makes sense for us to invest our resources
in doing this.
This is a big knock against us.
This screenshot is from Reddit.
We look at Reddit a lot and are sad sometimes.
But this issue is not the most efficient navigation.
And so for this example, it takes a ton of clicks
to do something that maybe should
be a lot more straightforward.
And our answer to this is that we generally design for flavor over efficiency. We design this box
to fold open, the drawers to slide around, all for you to have a sense of place of where you are
in this box. You can't instantly jump from place to place because we feel that that kind of
disconnects you from the experience. However, when things are this bad, um,
This is going to even get worse when we go to phone,
because some of these screens need to be moved
into two separate screens.
We realize this is a real problem we need to solve.
So it's something we're looking at.
And so it's nice to have a point of view.
But once things start affecting the player,
I mean, we have this in the middle of our campus engraved
in bronze, gameplay first.
So there's definitely times when you need to make compromises.
This is a future issue, maintaining across multiple
platforms. We have desktop, tablet and phone in the future.
And I mean, desktop and tablet are pretty similar, which is
good. But phone is a complete overhaul. So moving forward is
going to be challenging, I think. But from a company
perspective, it's worth it. Take a step back if we can get
traction in the mobile space because it's someplace we
should probably be going. So let's get physical. Physical UI
is awesome in the right context.
There are significant costs of doing it.
It's great for touch devices.
And if physicality is not the thing for you,
you should find that trait that most informs your games
and really run with it to its full potential,
because you'll get a lot of good results out of it.
My final point, which is UI gets to sit at the big kids table.
And what I mean by this is that,
this is not true of every project,
but I've seen it where designers come up with a game,
they come up with mechanics,
and then they're like, let's slap a UI on top of this thing.
And the other aspect of that is,
I've seen UI be kind of a second class citizen
in terms of production.
Maybe they get a dedicated programmer, maybe not,
or maybe a dedicated artist.
And so, these are some issues that
I think we tried to address.
So we didn't wanna be,
off in the corner eating chicken fingers and hot dogs
and spilling milk on ourselves and crying or whatever.
We wanted to be at the big kids table.
And so it's a testament to our leadership,
I think, that UI design was given a fair shake
and was given a parody with game design.
And one way this works is that.
Sometimes design would give us very loose design,
maybe a couple sentences, and we'd start doing mockups,
and then design would come and be informed by those mockups.
And it was kind of like a canary in the coal mine situation
where if the UI was super complicated looking,
then maybe design needed to take a step back
and see what design was causing those complications,
and maybe removing those or mitigating those problems.
So here's just an example, here's our play screen.
We used to have a ton of text on this describing the play mode,
describing the hero class, and their power,
and all these numbers.
And we just got rid of it all because nobody reads, right?
We know this.
And also, we didn't want the screen
to be too scary to just frighten people off
before they actually play the game.
And they would learn all these details through playing
the game, which is what we want.
In this case, we had designed a board and we had the menus that we liked, but only seven fit.
So we're like, well, maybe we'll just shrink them down as you start adding them.
And I think we all decided that this was not a good idea because it would mess with the physicality of our stuff.
When you see things zooming bigger and smaller, it's subtle, but it affects your perception of the value of these things, I think.
And having just a seven-menu limit is an interesting play mechanic, I think.
Our decks used to be 60 cards,
and that would mean that the area on the right
would scroll three whole pages worth,
and that's really hard to keep in your mind
at any given time,
and it was a deal breaker for new players for sure.
And so we reduced the deck size to 30,
and even that is quite formidable to new players,
so we're working on trying to ease that transition as well.
This is a pretty old mechanic.
The priest's hero power used to give the next minion you play
plus one attack and plus one health.
And so we need to show that on the board.
And clearly, it clutters up the board with more numbers,
and it encroaches into the minion space.
So the hero power was changed.
Then that's an example of pushback.
And so the priest just heals two from anything.
And this is very old, but this is a concept of the chain.
where an idea where in card games you play a card,
your opponent can play a card in response to that card,
and then you can say, no, no, no, I wanna play a card
in response to that card.
And you can see this gets really complicated visually.
And so it was on the chopping block,
and then from a design standpoint,
it really just bogged the game down,
and wasn't cool, so it was gone.
That was the design aspect of it,
and here's the game pipeline version of it,
where we have access to the same resources
as the full game, because we kind of are the game.
So here I am, the singular genius, right?
This is our team around 2012.
I'm just toiling away in obscurity, obviously.
But that's not the case.
It's a real team effort.
I mean, a third of our team, we have a design director,
art director, 3D guy, designer, and tech artist,
all kind of working together on UI.
And as we expanded recently, we're a lot bigger now,
we doubled our UI design department,
which is, we got another guy.
And that's Max Maul over there and he's doing the phone transition for us.
And then so now we have even more firepower.
It's crazy what we can do with this team like this.
And so getting to see the players, I wanted to show you what it looks like to take a feature
from beginning to end and who's involved with each step.
So here's UI design.
This is a version of our wireframing.
This is about as wireframing as we get.
We don't use Vizio or anything like that.
It's all back of the napkin stuff.
So this is UI design and then programming
if we think there's some issue that might come up
with our initial sketches.
And now we're just iterating with UI design and 2D.
And then at this point, once design feels like
we have the requirements in our mockup,
like they may not look good, but at least they're there.
then they usually drop out of the discussion
and we just kind of wheedle away,
trying to figure things out.
Once we get to a point where we think we have a good idea,
we bring it 3D to look at it and say,
is this reasonable?
Will these things actually work being modeled out
and will they be able to slide under each other
and all this kind of stuff?
And then here, you'll notice there's a big change
between these two.
And this is part of our design process
where in the middle of mock-ups, design will find out,
oh wait, we need to show rewards,
or we need to have keys that open and close these things,
or something like that.
So that's why that mock-up changed so drastically.
And this is when 3D and programming
are coming in to really start doing production on it.
And then here's the final deal.
This is what it looks like modeled.
And then we bring on tech art to do effects and programming.
So this is it in motion.
Yeah, so that's everybody all working in concert. I think the results are kind of cool. So
that's how the sausage is made. To recap. Yeah? So find your seed. You know, it will make
your project better and it will save you a lot of work in the long run. Physical UIs are
awesome in the right context. And good things will happen if UIs appear to the rest of
development. I guarantee it.
So that's all I have to say. I'd like to leave you with a little bit of our culture. So thank
you all for coming. I hope you have a great GDC. And I don't know if we have time for questions
or comments.
I was just kind of curious, does Blizzard plan on releasing any tools to the Unity community,
trying to get back to the community, because of obviously their success with Hurston?
Do I need to repeat the question on this?
There are currently no plans to allow modability or anything like that, like kind of what we
did on WoW.
Just because of our audience and hopefully we're trying to make a really tight experience
for players that's really highly designed.
Go for it. How long did it take to find the seed and how many
people were working on the project up until that time?
It's hard to say but I think it was definitely less than ten.
And it probably took, it's hard to say because we were also
bringing people on but maybe a year or so, something like that.
Along the lines of how UI design was influencing game design, I'm wondering if there's been
hearthstone UI design influencing wow UI design, like perhaps with the garrisons or something
along those lines? Are you cross pollinating? We have a UI group that meets together, but
there's no explicit cross pollination, but I think people in the company are starting
to look at this style and saying that maybe there's something there that we can bring
into other games.
That's for sure.
You mentioned with the Naxxramas where
you had to change your mockups to add
like the keys and the rewards.
Were there any other points where things really
changed the way that you had to approach it because
of some element?
Or was it more in the direction of where
you could change the priest hero power because the UI needed
it to change?
There's examples of both.
I can't think of any off the top of my head.
But definitely there's situations
where we just had, this was the mechanic,
so we have to deal with that.
I can't think of any up the top of my head, but definitely there are sides where we have
to compromise or design has to compromise.
So we all know that Hearthstone have a lot of the brilliant
visual effects during the games.
But I feel that when we move that to the mobile platform,
so constrained by the power of the mobile device,
there is a great decrease on the frame rate.
So how do you make the decisions between the trade-off
of a great, brilliant, awesome effect
with a very smooth frame rate to guarantee the experience?
Thank you.
This is more of a question for engineers, but...
I mean, do you sacrifice some of the effects there?
No, we don't intentionally sacrifice any effect.
We design the coolest effects that we can make,
and then smart guys figure out how to optimize it.
Okay.
Thank you.
So a successful card game usually create a lot of
opportunities for illustrators for doing all these card
illustrations.
And I want to know where Hearthstone team find all the
illustrations for their card?
Do they use existing art resource from the Blizzard
library, or are they actually hiring and giving commissions
to other illustrator create a new card?
It's actually all of those things.
We have a pool of existing art which we use,
and then if there's things not there,
then we'll commission either external artists
or we have internal artists who will handle those things.
So there's our art director right there.
Yeah, so it's all those things.
So I'm another UI designer, so it's cool to hear.
The big table comment.
When you guys were early on in the process,
did you make any argument about the validity of the UI design
and that, hey, this is as important as the game design?
You had mentioned you guys don't have a big world.
It's all UI stuff.
So did you make that argument, or did you
show data analytics or anything?
I was very fortunate in that I had worked with a design director for a number of years on World of Warcraft.
And that experience made us really think hard about UI's role in game design.
And so I think we came to an agreement together on that.
I did not have to sell somebody on this idea that that's the case.
I think you can look at any kind of board game type
translation of that.
You can make that argument.
This game is UI.
It's important.
And maybe, hopefully, maybe Hearthstone
could be an example of that.
I don't know.
I would like to think that could be the case.
During the creation and designing the UI,
how much were you locked down with the overall gameplay
design?
Pardon me? How much?
How much were you locked down already with the gameplay design?
We were locked down in the fact that it was going to be a card game.
Okay, nothing else. But the game design was progressing the same way?
Yes, they were progressing at the same time.
And like I said, they were informing each other of what this could be.
Once we started getting into this physical space,
then the design started to think differently about how things work.
One more question?
How much time do you expect the creation of the Hearthstone UI for phones to take and do you
have any planned release date, this quarter, next one?
Um, soon? Next couple months is what I can say. It's pretty far along and it's looking pretty
awesome. So. Okay. Thanks. Okay. I think that one more? Okay.
Yeah, I noticed that you, in Hearthstone,
you can't really make anything during the other player turn.
Yes.
I wonder if this was like an early game design decision,
or if it was like you explained before,
also something that was driven by the UI design.
This is not.
It was semi-UI, but it was really
the designers who didn't like that flow of play, because.
you have to pay attention a lot.
So it just felt like it wasn't a good flow for us, I think.
And once we switched to the idea of these maybe secrets that
could trigger another play, something like that,
it just made it like when it's my turn, it's my turn.
I'm trying to solve a single player puzzle.
And I think that is kind of the appeal of the game.
And will we get more deck slots?
It took you this long to get this question?
I had to ask it.
We know it's an issue and we are looking at it. Yes. That's not like a hand wavy answer. It's
really something that's on our radar. Okay. That about does it. Thank you so much.