You
We are pleased to begin the second half of our evening
and welcome you to the 22nd Annual Game Developers' Choice
Awards.
Please welcome the host of the evening, Osama Dorias.
Thank you.
Knock, knock.
Halo.
Halo!
Halo, everyone!
My name is Osama Dorias, and I am so honored to be your host for the 22nd Annual Game Developers
Choice Awards.
I've learned to always start with my best joke.
It helps set the tone and manage expectations.
The Game Developers Choice Awards have always held a special place in my heart,
because these are our picks for the best in our industry.
My friends, it feels great to return to an in-person ceremony.
Now, world circumstances being what they are,
This event will look and feel a bit different from what we're used to.
But don't worry, we have lots of safety protocols in place.
Everyone's vaccinated, we've got masks, we're working on getting everyone unionized.
And I promise there are no NFTs tonight.
All of our awards are all completely fungible.
That was an interesting choice.
I think it's okay if things are a little different.
I mean, what are game developers, if not adaptive and resilient?
2021 was a wild roller coaster of a year.
But despite everything, so many amazing games came out.
And everyone in this room knows that releasing a game at all is a miracle.
In light of this, I don't think it's fair that we can't give everyone an award.
So I made an award for everyone who released a game this year.
Isn't it beautiful?
This trophy is all of ours.
But we're going to keep it at my house, okay?
Is that okay?
Whoa, it's heavy.
But really, let's get on with the show.
I have a personal goal to make as many dad jokes and puns as possible tonight.
So let's start with unpacking these awards.
We start our show with the award for the best debut.
An award for studios starting out their legacy on the right foot.
From the artful escape to Wildermyth, each of these games showcases the bright future of game development.
and I can't wait to see what these studios come up with next.
Every first game has a special place in our hearts,
but it's incredible to see a studio
knock it out of the park on their first try.
Usually, it takes two.
Okay?
So here are the nominees for the best debut.
Best Debut.
Emberlot.
Nominated for Kena, Bridge of Spirits.
Iron Gate Studio.
Nominated for Valheim.
World Walker Games, nominated for Wilderness.
Beethoven and Dinosaur, nominated for The Artful Escape.
Shedworks. Nominated for Saber.
And the winner is...
Iron Gate Studios.
The best debut winner couldn't be here tonight, but they've sent an acceptance message.
Hi, I'm Josephine.
I'm Robin.
And I'm Lisa, and we're from Iron Gate.
Thank you so much for aiming well on this year's best debut. It really is an honor.
It's been a great time working on this game, and we're happy to hear that you appreciate the game so much.
Thank you so much for everything.
Bob, hey, peace out!
So, what's a video game's artist's favorite soda?
Sprite!
Thank you, Tim.
Thank you.
Someone liked it.
OK, that was a bad one.
I'm sorry.
Video game art can range from 8-bit pixels to photorealistic worlds,
complete with puzzles, with reflections.
It's breathtaking.
And above all, it's interactive.
You can't step into a movie and see the grass move when you swing your sword,
or open a glowing chest and get what's inside.
These games are exemplary for having some of the best art
that our medium has to offer.
Here are the nominees for the Best Visual Art.
Best Visual Art.
Forza Horizon 5,
developed by Playground Games,
published by Xbox Game Studios.
Mike Brown, Don Arcata,
Gareth Harwood, Fraser Strachan.
Kena, Bridge of Spirits, developed by Ember Lab,
published by Electronic Arts.
Mike Greer, Wanjalu, Vic, Intrasamba, Julian Vermeulen.
Deathloop, developed by Arkane Lyon,
published by Bethesda Softworks.
Ratchet and Clank Rift Apart, developed by Insomniac Games,
published by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
Psychonauts 2, developed by Double Time Productions,
published by Xbox Game Studios,
is set in Teesboro, Montgomery.
And the winner is...
I'll get it open.
Ratchet and Clank.
Uh, thank you. This is crazy. Uh, so thank you GDC. Uh, thank you for, uh, the other nominees. All those games were just beautiful and amazing and we're in great company.
Uh, Grant Hollis, our amazing art director. Marcus Smith, creative director. Mike Daly.
Uh, the entire awesome and amazing Insomniac art and tech teams.
Uh, all of our supportive families and all the fans that love these characters as much as we do.
This was a dream project.
It's why I wanted to work in Insomniac,
and it's kind of amazing to be up here.
So, thank you.
Thank you.
Has anyone heard anything about the best audio award?
No? I guess we'll have to play it by ear?
No!
Yes, thank you, that was a clap.
Excellent sound design highlights and uplifts the best parts of our games.
They make the highs even more exciting and the lows even more emotional.
And an excellent soundtrack can stick with us long past finishing the game.
I've had the elevator music for Dead Rising stuck in my head since 2006.
I'm not going to sing it to you, don't worry.
Creating exceptional sound design is a unique challenge, and I think we all underestimate
the impact and satisfaction that comes with a well-placed chime or crash.
So let's honor the nominees for Best Audio.
Returnal.
Developed by Housemarque.
Published by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
Luke Coutier.
Simon Gumbleton.
Harry Kruger.
Unpacking.
Developed by Witchfiend.
Published by Humble Games.
Jeff Van Dyke.
Angela Van Dyke.
Ella Van Dyke.
Deathloop, developed by Arkane Lyon, published by Bethesda Softworks.
Marvel's Guardians of the Galaxy, developed by Eidos Montreal, published by Square Enix.
Steve Schipkowski.
Forza Horizon 5, developed by Playground Games,
published by Xbox Game Studios.
Mike Brown, Don Arcata,
Gareth Harwood, Fraser Strachan.
The winner is Unpacking.
Holy crap!
**Cheering**
Uh, I think the, uh, key word here is, uh, underestimation.
I-I just totally underestimated the size of this game and the reaction to this game.
And, uh, look, I just really want to thank...
Tim and Ren for inventing this game, and the rest of the Witchbeam team,
Nart and Angus and May and Emily for supporting us and just making this a reality.
And I couldn't, I just cannot believe this.
Thank you very much!
Here tonight to present this year's Ambassador Award is video game writer and content creator Alana Pierce.
Hello everyone. I struggle to think of a person who is more deserving of receiving this year's
Ambassador Award than my friend Stephen Spock.
This award is for someone who has helped the games industry advance to a better place,
and if I were to give Steve one criticism, it is that he has tirelessly tried so hard
to advance the games industry to a better place that it has probably come at his own
expense.
Steve has effectively dedicated his life to championing video game accessibility, sometimes
even braving the inner workings of Reddit.
Can you imagine telling Reddit you think disabled gamers should be able to play FromSoft games
and coming out of that on the other side filled with good vibes?
No.
No, you can't.
And yet, even though it is undoubtedly hard and taxing, Steve persists where others won't
because Steve is the best of us.
If you don't know Steven Spahn, you're missing out.
Not only because he's one of the funniest people I know, to be clear he paid me to put
that in the script, I'll take the $50 after the award is done, thanks Steve, but he's
also incredibly accomplished.
Steve is the Senior Director of Able Gamers, which is an organization that's dedicated
to improving accessibility in video games, and enabling more people with disabilities
to be able to play video games.
He recently managed to raise $1 million for Able Gamers for his 40th birthday as part
of a campaign he called Spawn Together.
That's more than most people have accomplished in our entire lifetimes,
and Steve did it to celebrate his own birthday.
Most of us sleep in a little bit longer and order a pizza.
Steve banded together a huge team of people to raise a million dollars,
all in the name of providing gaming peripherals and hardware
to people who may not be able to play games without them.
He also managed to repeatedly murder me in Among Us,
and beat me in Fall Guys repeatedly, probably all in the same day.
Actually, I take back everything that I've said.
Steve is horrible.
Hashtag cancel Steven's phone.
But really, outside of his work directly with AbleGamers,
and his work being the only righteous troll
in the entirety of Twitter.
Steve has also done a tremendous job
of recruiting people outside of the industry
to talk about video game accessibility.
People like Ryan Reynolds and Brie Larson,
some of the biggest streamers and content creators
can't help but be on Steve's side.
And this is supposed to be a speech about his work,
but I can't go on without mentioning
that part of it is because he's so incredibly kind,
engaging, charismatic, and...
Incredibly ridiculously handsome. Okay, now he's just editing the teleprompter. He can't keep getting away with this
I could talk for a really really long time about why I'm honored to call Steve one of my best friends and how I'm so
Proud to have been asked to present him with this year's Ambassador Award
But I'm worried that he has slipped more sly compliments about himself into my script. So that is it for me. Welcome Steve Spahn everybody
She doesn't realize I can't hold that award.
It's an honor and a privilege to share this evening of inscription with you.
Years ago, before my first industry event,
I stayed up all night meticulously writing
the importance of helping people with disabilities.
The very first day, I presented that information
to a lead developer at Rockstar Games.
He ignored me.
Instead, looking right over my wheelchair,
directly at my invisibly disabled,
able gamers partner, Mark Barlet,
then crumpled up the pamphlet,
threw it in the trash, and walked away.
I was devastated.
It was at that moment that I knew there was no seat at the table for someone like me.
So I set out and made my mission to make one.
People tell me I am strong, resilient, inspirational, but I'm here to tell you that I am not.
I am here.
I didn't quit because my options were to be those things or die.
I chose not death.
I didn't choose this life.
but I'm gonna make every second of it count.
It is just impossible.
Do you know how many times as a person with a terminal disease
and as a disabled man as I am that I have been told the words,
it's impossible?
You're never going to live past 10 years old.
It's impossible.
You won't live long enough to see the end of college.
You're never going to find love.
It's impossible.
You'll never make people care about game accessibility.
I am here to tell you that not everything is impossible.
One thing that I have learned is if you fight for your limitations,
you will never lose them.
Never limit yourself or allow others to put limitations on you.
You must trade your cynicism for optimism.
The truth is, being disabled is very difficult.
For people like me, we don't get a break.
There are no weekends, no vacations from being disabled,
and no break for people taking care of us either.
at being an advocate on top of that,
where not only do you have to deal with your own challenges,
but you have to convince others to change the system
that makes things so difficult.
There are moments where it all just seems too much,
where I don't know if I want to do this anymore.
But in my darkest moments, I am thankful for my support network,
for my mom, for my friends who remind me that every failure,
every setback, and every difficult day is an opportunity to grow
and become a better person.
And when all else fails, I have video games.
I have one place where I can retreat, collect myself after a bad day,
enjoy exploring the universe with a friend,
defeating dragons with my family, make a new friend,
or even meet the love of my life.
For disabled players, video games can provide a window
into an otherwise inaccessible world and provide opportunities
to share experiences that might actually be impossible anywhere else.
We just have to make sure that they are as accessible as they can be to as many people as they can be.
I chose to make it my life's work to represent, to be the representation I couldn't find when I entered this industry.
But I didn't get here alone.
I'm forever grateful for everyone who ever believed in me, believed I could win a prestigious award like this one.
And even when I didn't believe in myself.
Advocacy is hard.
Making games is hard.
So I'll make you a deal.
Together, we can ensure that this is an inclusive industry for everyone.
I'm not going to stop.
I won't quit.
And neither should you.
What an exceptional speech from an exceptional person.
Tim, this is you, right?
Thank you, Stephen, for all that you do.
A truly well-deserved award.
I'm honored to share the stage with you.
If I've learned anything from tonight,
it's that everyone needs to name their games in a way
that makes puns easier.
How do I make a pun out of Forza Horizon 5
or Guardians of the Galaxy?
I mean, writing puns is hard,
but writing games is even harder.
Every year, we talk about how far game narratives have come.
And it would feel like a cliche if it wasn't so true.
Video game narrative progresses leaps and bounds every year
as we continue to learn that having a cohesive,
engaging narrative can pull an entire game together
and help us see ourselves in each other's art.
And I think connecting and seeing each other in that way
is more important now than ever.
Here are the nominees for the Best Narrative Award.
Best Narrative
Marvel's Guardians of the Galaxy, developed by Eidos Montreal, published by Square Enix. Mary DeMorrow.
Deathloop, developed by Arcane Lyon, published by Bethesda Softworks.
Are you talking about us?
It Takes Two.
Developed by Hazelight Studios.
Published by Electronic Arts.
Yeah!
What are you doing?
You're not feeling it?
No!
I don't feel you!
Psychonauts 2.
Developed by Double Fine Productions.
Published by Xbox Game Studios.
Tim Schafer.
Unpacking, developed by Witchbeam, published by Humble Games.
Ren Breyer, Tim Dawson, Annie Vandermeer.
Why did it make these so hard to open?
And the winner is Psychonauts 2.
Thank you so much, oh my god.
I wanna officially declare this purple jacket uncursed.
The jacket is uncursed.
There's so many people, when you say narrative,
there's so many people on that team that make things happen.
There is a script, and there's a producer who organizes the script,
and a casting director, and a director in the studio,
and an engineer, and an actor who brings so much life to the characters,
and animators who add so many jokes and so much life to it,
and then programmers who make the whole scene.
You actually play all the dialogue, play properly,
and people edit the dialogue,
and an effects artist puts a tear in the character's eye,
and someone plays music, and then you cry,
and you're like, this game has such great narrative.
But none of those people are here tonight, so I'm going to say it's just a script.
Except for Zach, he's here.
Everybody, Zach, our lead, our animation lead on Tekken Ops 2, please say something.
Hey everyone, it's an amazing honor. I mean, it all goes to Tim, obviously.
That's the credit, goes to him. But I was honored to be...
15 minutes of cutscenes.
Well, yeah, yeah. We had about six hours worth of animation cutscenes in our game at the end.
But I'd like to thank my animation team for bringing his script to life.
Chris, Miyuki, Ray, Jerry, Faith, Alex, and our amazing rigger, Adam.
Thank you all. It was just an amazing time.
And thank you, Tim, for making these amazing worlds and characters for us to bring to life.
Thanks so much!
So I started working in the industry at a time that was more hostile to people with my complexion.
Microaggressions were commonplace. I learned to develop thick skin when I was a junior with no
power to enact any change or even to speak up. And even as I climbed the ranks and got the
COVID-19 senior title, I faced many difficulties.
I've attended conferences with an all-white diversity panel.
I've spoken at conferences where I was
the only non-white person in the advocacy track.
I've been the target of alt-right hate groups
who wanted to get me fired.
And through, sorry, and though we still have many problems
as an industry that we must address.
we have to take a moment to celebrate how far we've come.
All games have the potential to have a positive impact.
More and more games are rising to that challenge,
working hard to be inclusive and thoughtful
and to inspire empathy in all of us
for the betterment of humankind.
So let's celebrate the most culturally impactful games
of this year and
Here are the nominees for the Social Impact Award.
Social Impact Award.
Before Your Eyes.
Developed by Goodbye World Games.
Published by Skybound Games.
Will Hellworth.
Graham Parks.
Oliver Lewin.
It Takes Two.
Developed by Hazelight Studios.
Published by Electronic Arts.
What a relationship to finish!
Uh-huh, yeah, you feel that?
I'm on fire with that guy.
♪♪ -"Chickory, a Colorful Tale,"
developed by Greg Robanoff,
published by Finji,
Alexis Dean Jones,
Lena Raine,
M. Halberstadt,
Madeline Berger. ♪♪
I opened this one early, so I'm not profitable with it.
And the winner is Boyfriend Dungeon.
The Social Impact Award winner couldn't be here tonight, but they've sent an acceptance
message.
As the studio head of Kitfox and lead designer and writer of Boyfriend Dungeon, thank you
so much to those of you who...
I felt Boyfriend Dungeon deserved the Social Impact Award, but it's really rewarding because
it's really the reason why I enjoy making games.
I want to think about the person playing it and what they're feeling, and my greatest
dream is to affect culture in a positive way.
And if people are getting that out of Boyfriend Dungeon from our silly sword smooching game,
what they see themselves represented.
they feel like they can explore a side of themselves
that games doesn't normally let them explore,
then, well, I'm more deeply happy than I can express.
So thank you very much,
and congratulations to all these wonderful games.
I would like to thank everyone on the Boyfriend Dungeon team
for being themselves
and in all their beautiful, different ways.
and my mom for giving me confidence,
and my partner for always believing in me
and for encouraging me to make Boyfriend Dungeon
in the first place for many years
before I could take the leap.
So, thank you.
Please welcome the presenter of this year's Lifetime Achievement Award,
Supergiant Games Creative Director, Greg Kasavin. ♪
Thank you.
So, last year, the Dragon Quest series of role-playing games
celebrated its 35th anniversary.
It's an iconic genre-defining series that sold more than 70 million copies around the world,
produced any number of successful spin-offs, and been adapted into movies and television.
There's even a Dragon Quest-themed cafe in the heart of Tokyo.
When I was a kid, I fell in love with the original Dragon Quest for the Nintendo Entertainment System,
published as Dragon Warrior here in the States, though...
I never could have imagined that the series would have such a steady presence with me through most of my life.
It's still going strong.
Dragon Quest XI launched in 2017 to widespread acclaim,
and Dragon Quest XII was announced less than a year ago.
But what's more amazing to me than that,
and even more amazing than all the phenomenal worldwide success,
is that Dragon Quest's original creator, designer, and writer,
Yuji Horii-san, whom we are honoring this evening,
has been there for every single installment of this series all this time.
You would be very hard-pressed to find another creator in this industry
who has stuck with their game series for more than 35 years,
much less a game series of such influence and lasting impact as Dragon Quest.
In an industry so fraught with uncertainty where so few...
have the privilege of stability in their work and in their lives,
Hori-san and his collaborators managed to stick with their series,
delivering beloved hit after hit for well over a quarter of a century.
All this time, Hori-san has served as designer and writer on the series,
creating these classic tales of good versus evil, and triumph over adversity,
filled with heart and warmth,
and designed to be highly approachable for players of all ages.
He's credited on many other games as well, notably as supervisor and scenario designer on the Super Nintendo classic Chrono Trigger.
It overwhelms and inspires me, thinking about just how much joy Hori-san's work has brought to so many people in this world and for so long.
In a 2011 interview reflecting on 25 years of Dragon Quest back then,
Hori-san described the series as being about overcoming hardship.
It's like climbing up a steep mountain," he said.
You have to keep climbing, climbing, climbing, climbing,
and then at the end, you finally get to the top
of the mountain and you see the beautiful view.
I hope Hori-san has had a chance to see that by now.
Unfortunately, Yuji Hori-san was unable to travel
to GDC this time around, but he sent us
a short acceptance video we would like
to share with you all now, thank you.
Hello, I'm Yuri Horii.
Thank you for winning the GDC Award, which is a prestigious award.
I've always loved manga, and I've always wanted to be a manga artist.
I was in the manga research department at university,
and I helped to write manga and to make original works for professional manga artists.
I also wrote illustrations and articles for magazines.
After graduating from university, I worked as a freelance writer.
At that time, the world was undergoing a big change.
The computer was introduced.
I read about the computer in the newspaper and was fascinated by it.
I bought a microcomputer and a personal computer.
I had always liked math, but I became addicted to computers.
I learned programming and started making my own games.
That's when I discovered Enix.
Square Enix was doing a game programming contest,
and I was able to participate in my own game.
That was the beginning of my gaming life.
It was about 40 years ago.
New Sensation was an action game for me to play as a hobby,
but I was invited to play it alone,
so I decided to make an adventure game that I was interested in at the time.
in a violent slaughtergoing between players.
That is a serial killing in Fortopia,
where a guy demands for a command
that will allow him to carry out murder in the real world.
The game has been battered still more
and the tournament industry is booming.
I think the appeal of computers is that they can program various reactions to input,
and I think that's what makes them so interesting.
In other words, they create various gimmicks by imagining the player's actions.
I thought it was a very fun job to create stories on this system.
And I thought it would be very fun to make a story for RPGs like Wizardry Ultima, which I also like.
I'm looking forward to it.
Dragon Quest will be released in a short time frame, just like the manga.
I think it's like a manga written on a computer.
Our team is currently working on a new work, Dragon Quest XII,
which is the new main story.
I think many people around the world will be able to play this work.
Please look forward to the sequel.
And we're back for blood.
Blood.
That was a little long.
The Oscars, the Grammys and the Golden Globes all have one thing in common.
They do not have an innovation award category.
But we do.
That's why it's so exciting to work on games.
Every year, even after all of this time,
there are thousands of games that do something
we've never seen before.
We have just barely scratched the surface
of what's possible in our medium.
And maybe someday, we might even be able
to make a functioning door.
What a time to be alive!
Friends, please join me in celebrating the nominees
for the Innovation Award.
Innovation Award.
It Takes Two, developed by Hazelight Studios,
published by Electronic Arts.
Wildermyth.
Developed by World Walker Games.
Published by World Walker Games.
Unpacking.
Developed by Witchbeam.
Published by Humble Games.
Tim Dawson.
Wren Breyer.
Jeff Van Dyke.
Inscription, developed by Daniel Mullins Games, published by Devolver Digital.
Daniel Mullins.
Deathloop, developed by Arkane Lyon, published by Bethesda Softworks.
And the winner is...
Unpacking!
Okay.
Uh, oh my god!
Th- Thank you!
Uh...
Four years ago, Tim arrived at my apartment with a pile of boxes in tow.
We'd been dating for a year and a bit, and, uh, that day marked an exciting new chapter in our lives.
It ended up being even more significant, though,
because it was also the day we came up with an idea for a game about unpacking.
Um, now I just, I can't believe how much this game has changed our lives.
It's taken us around the world, introduced us to so many people, so
many opportunities, and now we're here.
Um, everyone has been so nice and supportive all week so far.
Um.
Yeah, I just can't believe it.
And I could not have asked for a better team.
Tim, who is the glue who holds this whole project together,
and who also held me together through some
of the roughest patches.
Jeff, with more experience in games than the rest of us
combined.
Angus, who practically reinvented isometric pixel art
working on this game.
And the rest of our amazing art team, Michelle, Joe,
and Stacey, who each put a bit of themselves into the game.
and got it to an unbelievable level of polish.
And Annie, who helped us come up with a believable cast
of characters you never get to see.
Damon, who helped us make the game more accessible
with fully remappable controls.
Victoria, with her god tier community management skills.
And Emily, who took over from her recently
and has been smashing it.
And of course, Sonatan, who has always believed in us and supported us through the good and the bad.
Thank you all so much for making this game what it is, and
thanks everyone here in the audience.
Yeah, thank you so much.
I've been in games for nearly 15 years, and in that time, I've learned that games can
basically be boiled down to two ingredients, heart and math.
I get the heart part, but math is really hard.
Technology is advancing these days at the blink of an eye,
and these developers are working even faster than that
to bring us the best of what the new platforms
and mechanics can accomplish in an interactive medium.
I can't even tell you how much math is involved in that.
It's incalculable.
Thank you.
So let's see the nominees for the award for everything that I'm not smart enough to understand in video games.
The Best Technology Award.
Best Technology
Halo Infinite. Developed by 343 Industries. Published by Xbox Game Studios.
David Berger, Dean Johnson, Danielle Gianetti, Mike Romero.
Forza Horizon 5, developed by Playground Games, published by Xbox Game Studios.
Mike Brown, Dom Arcata, Gareth Harwood, Fraser Strachan.
Ratchet & Clank Rift Apart, developed by Insomniac Games,
published by Sany Interactive Entertainment.
Returnal. Developed by Housemarque. Published by Sony Interactive Entertainment.
Ethan Watson. Christo Junkula. Marku Valanen.
Hitman 3. Developed by IO Interactive. Published by IO Interactive.
And the winner is...
Ratchet and Clank.
All right.
Excuse me, deep breath.
This is way scarier than giving my talk earlier today.
So, oh, sorry.
Can you hear me now?
All right.
First, thank you everyone.
It's so humbling to be counted among
all the amazingly talented developers here.
And it's an incredible honor to be recognized.
I'd like to begin by thanking all of my colleagues
that came up here with me.
I was telling our director earlier this week that there was no way in hell I was going
to come up here by myself.
This is truly terrifying.
But on behalf of all the engineering teams at Insomniac, I'd like to begin by thanking
all Insomniacs.
Without your vision and support, frankly, most of our games would be just really well-optimized
programmer art.
I'd also like to thank the Advanced Technology Group, the ICE team, and all of the other
tech wizards that built the platform that made Rift Apart possible.
I'd also like to thank our family, friends, and loved ones that stood by us every step
of the way as we brought Ratchet to the finish line.
And finally, my good friend, Elan here, has a few additional words for us.
Thank you.
Thank you to everybody who supported every one of us when we were getting started.
Pay it forward.
As a career game designer, this is the category that's closest to my heart.
When I started making games, there was a moment when I had a very hard time playing games.
Something that I had done my whole life up to that point.
All of a sudden, I was starting to see behind the curtain.
The magic was fading.
I asked myself if I had made a mistake.
I wished that I could turn it off, to go back to how I used to play games.
As I was coming to terms with my new reality, something unexpected happened.
I was starting to develop a love for the craft that I didn't believe was possible.
It was stronger than the love, than the one it replaced.
Now
I could see the source of the magic and the intentions behind it.
Game design is invisible until it's not, and then its beauty can blind you.
Here are the nominees for the Best Design Award.
Best Design
It Takes Two, developed by Hazelight Studios, published by Electronic Arts.
Psychonauts 2, developed by Double Fine Productions,
published by Xbox Game Studios.
Tim Schafer, Seth Marinello.
Woo!
Halo Infinite, developed by 343 Industries,
published by Xbox Game Studios.
Jerry Hook, Paul Crocker, Tom French, Troy Mashburn.
Deathloop, developed by Arkane Lyon.
Published by Bethesda Softworks.
Inscription, developed by Daniel Mullins Games.
Published by Devolver Digital.
Daniel Mullins.
And the winner is...
It Takes Two!
The Best Design Award winner couldn't be here tonight,
but they've sent you here.
They sent us an acceptance thank you.
I hope you could read fast.
Applause
Please join me in taking a moment to remember those colleagues, peers, mentors and friends who we lost this year.
Every single one of them has made a tremendous contribution to our art and our industry.
They will never be forgotten.
Okay. I have another one for you. What do you call a Deathloop sequel set in a restaurant?
Death Soup.
The drums were too loud.
The joke wasn't bad.
It was the drums, right?
It's okay, everyone.
We're getting to the end here.
Be patient.
I'm almost out of puns.
I know that everyone wishes that they could vote on which of my jokes was the best tonight.
But here we have the Audience Award instead.
The Audience Award is always one of my favorite because it could be literally any game that wins.
I think Wordle has a shot this year.
All right.
So here are the winners of the, sorry, here is the winner of our Audience Award.
Ready for it?
Valheim.
So the Audience Award winner couldn't be here tonight,
but they've sent this acceptance message.
Hi, I'm Lisa.
I'm Robin.
And I'm Josephine, and we're from Iron Gate.
Thank you so much for giving us this year's Audience Award.
It means so much to us that you like our game.
It's been a lot to have your support this year,
and we really hope that you'll continue to love the game for a long time to come.
We're finally here.
It's the biggest award of the night,
but it's still not bigger than Lady Dimitrescu.
Alright, wait. I had a joke for this one. Hold on.
What do you call it when Lady Dimitrescu...
Wait, I messed up her name.
Lady Dimitrescu spills her drink?
Resident Evil spillage.
Yeah!
Is it getting better or worse?
I... that? Okay. Alright.
So here it is, our Game of the Year award.
These nominees represent some of the best voices, best
technology, best design, best narrative, and best innovation
that our industry has to offer, all wrapped up
into five spectacular games.
Each of them deserve to win.
for being not only an example of where we are now,
but a glimpse of where our industry is headed as a whole.
Here are the nominees for the Game of the Year.
Game of the Year.
Inscription, developed by Daniel Mullins Games,
published by Devolver Digital.
Daniel Mullins, Jonah Senzel, David Hegeman.
Forza Horizon 5.
Developed by Playground Games.
Published by Xbox Game Studios.
Mike Brown, Don Arcata, Gareth Harwood, Fraser Strachan.
Resident Evil Village.
Developed by Capcom.
Published by Capcom.
Deathloop, developed by Arkane Leon, published by Bethesda Softworks.
It Takes Two, developed by Hazelight Studios, published by Electronic Arts.
I feel stuck.
And the winner of the 2022 Game Developers Choice Award
for the game of the year goes to Inscription.
That one was really unexpected.
I don't know how you compare those games.
I think, like, should you have made the cars faster
in Forza or something?
Like, uh...
But I was trying to think, like,
I didn't think this one would happen,
but I was trying to rack my brain
for some, like, thank you deep cuts.
So I was thinking of thanking my grandma
for being one-fourth of my genes,
but also she actually is the voice
of Grimora in Inscription.
So she is a voice actor.
My dad let me film him and I he's a secret boss in inscription and there's one version of him that
has like a yoga like pillow on his head and he's supposed to look like a mushroom man and he he put
up with that um and that's cool thank you and thank
As we wrap up our night, I believe my total pun and dad joke count comes to about 13.
We call that a Troy Baker's dozen.
All right, that's 14, right?
Genuinely, I would like to end the show by giving a final congratulations to all of the
winners and all of the nominees and everyone who shipped or even worked on a game this
past year.
You've done the impossible time and time again.
I admire all of you and consider myself extremely lucky to be your colleague.
I'd like to thank everyone who made this show safe and possible.
The production crew backstage, the GDC organizers, the volunteers, and the CAs who brought us
all back together this evening.
Please give them a round of applause.
I'd like to end by asking everyone who's watching here and back home to cross your arms like this.
Do it.
Now, squeeze gently.
We've all just shared a much needed communal hug.
The past few years have been really tough, but we have each other and we will get through
this.
So thanks for coming and for watching.
Please stay safe, and don't forget, we're stronger together.
You