Hello, can you hear me?
Excellent.
I can't see any of you.
This is awesome.
I'd like to congratulate all of you
for finding the secret talk.
I feel like the Foo Fighters at South by Southwest,
the secret show that no one knows about.
Congratulations again.
What I want to talk about is sort
of an interesting question I hear come up a lot, which is,
why do people play massive multiplayer games alone?
I mean.
if you think about it, they're in the title right. The title of the genre is Massively
Multiplayer Games. It seems like people who aren't playing Massively Multiplayer Games,
say Massively Multiplayer, are missing the point somehow. They're like, it'd be like
playing a first person shooter game without picking up any guns, just throwing flowers
at the bad guys or something. Is there something wrong with these people?
Now this is something I've been thinking about for a long time because, well, I've been making
Massive Multiplayer Games for a long time.
I've also been talking about them, writing about them, thinking about them, playing them.
And one of the things I'd like to point out is that I noticed a long time ago that even
though everybody said that you should be playing Massive Multiplayer Games with other people,
I was always trying to find ways to play them by myself.
So it's always something that I've seen as a play pattern inside of these spaces.
Now, you know, personally...
A lot of people who follow me and have known me over the years know that I like to talk
about various game design issues that sort of permeate the MMO sphere entirely, such
as should we have permadeath?
The answer to that is no, by the way.
Should we have virtual economies?
Should they be sandboxes or theme parks?
Are classes and levels destroying the genre?
Well, one of the things that started showing up relatively recently, and I've certainly
seen it on our boards, and I've started seeing it on the boards of our competitors...
is people asking on our boards, can I solo in this game?
Now, these are massively multiplayer message boards,
right?
And so they don't actually say it this nicely.
They more along phrase it something like,
do I have to really group up with a bunch of mouth-breathing,
knuckle-dragging idiots in order to do
the most basic, stupid, banal tasks in your stupid game?
Yeah.
Why is this an interesting question?
This is an interesting question because the answer used to be,
No, you can't solo. You have to play with other people.
You really couldn't do much of anything in EverQuest unless you grouped up.
If you tried to, like, play Yuoso, you'd be assassinated when you left the city gates.
Shadowbane was a worthless game if you played solo.
But since then, the answer has become yes.
Games like World of Warcraft and Free Realms and City Heroes,
which I consider one of the principal games that did this early on,
all took the stance that...
you should be able to play most of the game by yourself.
Not all of the game.
There's still stuff we reserve for groups.
But you should be able to do a whole bunch of the game
by yourself.
And I think this is interesting because this
is a full revolution of game design canon.
It is something where we've all collectively
changed our mind and said, whoa, we were wrong before.
Now, there are still some zealots that say, hey,
we make multiplayer games.
And people who play multiplayer games by themselves are doing it wrong.
And they sort of have this attitude that people who play by themselves are psychos or weirdos,
you know.
You know, he kept to himself.
He didn't bug anybody and he freaked out.
But one of the things that we have to keep in mind when we talk about the loners and
think about the loners is that the loner is also a heroic archetype.
Right?
People don't imagine being a serial killer, but they certainly imagine being Batman or
the Lone Ranger.
And more to the point, if you really think about it,
being a loner is an inherently social thing.
You can't be a loner in a single-player game
because you're not setting yourself apart from somebody.
In order to be a loner, you basically
have to have a group of people that you're being standoffish
and kind of ignoring.
So being a loner, there are people
who want to sort of be the loner inside of the game environment,
because, well, to them, that is part of the heroic fantasy.
Anyway, I don't want people to think for a second
that we should be making just solely massively single player
games.
At the end of the day, our unique selling proposition
is still social.
It's still massive.
It's the things that we do well.
You know, raids are what WoW does
that you can't do inside of, say, a Baldur's Gate or Diablo
or one of these single player or lightly multiplayer RPGs.
Similarly, EVE Online.
There's a whole bunch of things that you
can do in a space game.
if you don't have to worry about the massive technical problems and social problems that
being a massively multiplayer game brings to the fore.
But this is what excites the imagination, right?
This is the stuff that gets in Slashdot and Wired Magazine.
The really big epic fights.
That's what the genre does really well and we have to embrace that.
Similarly the City Siege games, like your Dark Age of Camelot, your Warhammer, your
Shadowbane.
These are things that excite the imagination about the possibility of the genre, the idea
that there are lots of people that are somehow working together or working against each other
for a common cause.
And these are our unique selling proposition, and we have to concentrate on this stuff because
in order to get this stuff to work, we have to kind of back off on this stuff.
We have to back off on the cloth sims and on the animations and on the getting every
lock of hair exactly perfect.
We will never be able to do as good with, for example,
our avatar art as the guys who are only drawing two avatars.
We will never do as good as the guys doing environments
when they only have to design an environment
the size of a pizza hut, and we're
trying to make an entire continent run in our engine.
We have to arrest our selling proposition.
So how do people who solo, people who play by themselves,
people who are loners fit into this?
So.
It's worth just thinking about.
And I think it's worth thinking about what
we could consider one of the original massively multiplayer
environments, which is the city.
It's in New York City, one of the largest cities in the world.
And it's got, I don't know how many.
I probably should have done the research.
9, 12 million, whatever.
It's got a lot of people in there.
The fascinating thing about New York City
is that even though it is.
definitely a place that is bustling with humanity.
There are a couple of things that we should notice as we think about
loaners inside of massive multiplayer spaces.
The first is that oddly enough, Manhattan has the largest percentage
of single individual dwellings of any city in the world.
That's Manhattan rent prices, guys.
Right?
They are paying a lot of money to live by themselves.
a lot of people are choosing to live in New York City and still be solo.
The other thing that's interesting about the big cities is that, well, people who are strangers
coming into these cities find them alienating, find them overwhelming, find it hard for them
to get a handle on what's going on.
And so the thing to think about is, and this is a Mark Twain quote from some years ago.
A domed and steepled solitude where the stranger is lonely in the midst of a million of his race.
This Mark Twain guy said this like a hundred years ago before skyscrapers and taxi cabs
and all of the stuff that makes New York City what it is today.
Even then it was seen as an alien hostile place.
And we have this sort of mentality and I think it's sort of funneled by TV where if you watch
say CSI New York you think that New York City is a death trap, right?
you think that is a scary and alien place,
where there aren't communities.
And sort of the myth of America,
real America versus fake America or something like that,
is that people who live in the country
are more social and more civic minded.
But sociologists have found that's actually not true.
They've actually found that people who live inside of cities
tend to be more social.
They tend to be more civic minded.
They tend to have stronger social friends
and they tend to be less likely
to describe themselves as the country.
and part of this reason is because inside of the uh... the cities
is easier for them to find
other people that share their belief systems it's it's easier for them to
find groups from the belong to new york city is full of
thousands and thousands of little circle social circles whereas you know podunk
usa may only have one or two and if you don't fit in
you don't fit in
so anyway i was a fun digression
let's go back to uh... our loaners and talk about
uh... how they need to fit into our social games
One of the things I want to keep in mind is that a lot of people
see loners, people playing by themselves
inside of a massive multiplayer games as an aberration.
But it's really not.
There are a lot of different reasons
why people are playing alone inside of your social space.
Some of these are actually healthy reasons.
People are choosing to play that way.
Some of these are broken design states
that designers need to be taking more seriously.
And each of these have different design challenges
that they're going to present to you.
So what I did is I helpfully made the list of 10 different kinds of loaners.
Every time I see this slide, I initially think I wrote 10 different kinds of losers,
but that's not what I wrote.
Because loaners are not losers.
A lot of these people are loaners for good reasons, for valid reasons,
and sometimes unfortunate reasons you need to fix,
but sometimes because they're happier that way.
You know, the one that we spend the most time talking about...
is the person who logged in for the first time.
This is the person who's just bought your game,
has just come into the space, knows nothing about anything,
doesn't know the social conventions,
doesn't have any friends, doesn't
have any clue what's going on, doesn't even know where fun is.
And as you may know, we spent a ton of time
trying to figure out how to get them into the game,
into a social circle, because the theory is once they're
into a social circle, they're going
to be more invested, more interested in what's going on.
Now, a lot of times our tabula rasa player.
is going to be, he's going to have come in with friends,
but that friend might have washed out, right?
He came in with a friend, but that friend,
the game wasn't for him.
Or that friend isn't getting on for another two days
because the pre-order is backed up.
Or that friend logged into a different server by mistake.
And this guy is riding solo until that comes along.
Now, our first instinct as game designers,
especially the more social engineering types,
is to try to jam these people with other people
as quickly as possible.
There are some pitfalls to that.
One is overstimulation.
You have to be really, really wary of this.
So a lot of people, MMOs are incredibly complicated things.
I mean, the interfaces on even our simple ones are incredibly labyrinthine.
As a result of it, it's really hard for people to learn how to play these games.
And some people really do not like to learn.
to interact with other people until they've actually figured out what's going on, how
their class works, how their GUI works, how to get out of town, things like that.
And so if you think back to Asheron's Call back in the day, they had a fealty system
where basically the high level players would get an experience bonus for every experience
point that a low level player earned if that low level player had declared fealty to them.
and the end result was that higher level players would basically camp Newby Town
and recruit low level players as soon as they came in the door.
Of course, what this was to low level players was an instantaneous sales pitch
of, hey, come in,
sign up for me, you know me, I want you to sign up for me, right?
A lot of people, and Sherry Granere, who is one of the experts on women
in game design, points out that's a lot of
women players in particular.
uh... don't like to learn with any social pressure they want actually to
be able to
get a handle on the game before having this kind of pressure put on them
uh... to prove that they're good to prove that they're wrong proof they have
skills
they would actually rather learn in a vacuum
uh... and then uh... sort of once they're ready to join a social group
once they feel they have their footing
then actually start looking for the social circles
and so is you that you as the designer you want to encourage them to get in the
social circles but you have to also leave them some space
so that they can actually get a handle on things.
One of the corollaries of the New Kid in Town problem is the
Hollow Earth problem.
This is an old MUD term, which describes what happens in our
class and level-based MMOs.
When you have a game where there's a content progression,
and you do level 1 to 10 content, and then you're done
with that zone, you go to 10 and 20 content, and then you're
done with that zone, what happens is that people who
come in late to the game.
are going to find, even if they want people to group with,
they might find that there aren't any there.
As an example, if you log into Cataclysm today
in World of Warcraft and start up a Worgen or a,
what was the other one, a Goblin today,
you're gonna find that Newby Town in those areas
is a lot less crowded than it was in November and December
when that game, when the expansion pack actually launched.
Most of those people have sort of graduated
to the higher level content,
and if you crave that social interactivity,
uh... it's just not there to be had and this is over design problem that all
these level based games
uh... have to have
and even if you do get to max level you might find that
the end game has gotten incredibly cliquish even if you want to get into a
social circle
it's very hard for you to do so because you have to basically earned other uh...
uh... you have to earn your spot in a guild and and and earn uh... prove that
you earn a spot
in the raid in the battleground in the arena fight in the uh...
the strike force for your territorial control game.
And it may be that those spots are very limited and hard to actually come by.
The second group is probably the group that I'm most like.
They basically see other people as a tragedy, right?
They see them as like a joke.
For them, they wouldn't want to group with anybody in the barrens, but they think they're
good clean fun anyway, right?
These are the people who like to slow down for car crashes.
This is probably my category as well.
They see other people as content.
And one of the things I want to stress
is this is way more pervasive than most people casually
think it is.
So very recently, a media studies group did a study
and found that 90% of the readers on most mailing lists
and message boards never post.
Right?
They go to the message boards, and they read things on the message boards,
and they never bother to post.
And some of them still log in daily.
It's just that they're just absorbing the content that other people bring
to the table.
They find the value in actually watching this,
but they don't necessarily feel they have to post in order to get
the value outside of this community.
And I want to stress, this is not new.
These numbers were also being thrown around back in the Usenet days
when all the alt groups were around.
And if these people find value in lurking,
who are we to tell them they're wrong?
But the thing about the concept of other people are content
is that it really puts an onus on you as the designer
to be sure that you have a social critical mass,
that you be sure that the space feels full and crowded
and interesting.
So this is how casinos used to be designed.
The trend of how to design casinos.
was to make them bigger, more grandiose, more palatial,
with the high ceilings.
And we want this to be a temple of opulence.
And this is the Aladdin, I believe.
You can't go there anymore because it failed
and has been destroyed.
This guy, his name is Bill Friedman.
He is a famed maverick casino designer.
And he basically did some research
and found that a whole bunch of people
would stay at the Aladdin.
and then go gamble someplace else.
And what he found was that the reason why
is that these are very lonely and desperate places to gamble.
And if you think about playing a slot machine for hours on end,
it is a grind.
It is a lonely, soul-sucking experience.
However, if you play it in a room like this,
where the ceilings are low and the areas have alcoves that
sort of keep people together.
there is always content going on around you.
Right? You always feel like there's something going on around you.
And while you're hitting that button on that slot machine,
you know, you're going to see people winning over there.
There's always going to be the sound of somebody winning around you.
There's going to be people fighting or getting drunk or,
you know, there's going to be like cute waitresses nearby.
There's always something going on when you get more people closer together.
And this is true of any social space. For example.
If I was having this talk right now in a room that only had 50 chairs, this would feel like
a very cozy and dynamic and standing room only talk.
But instead, we're having it in this very, very large room, and you guys are all feeling
sorry for me for being the last talk of GDC.
And that's okay if we're just giving talk, if we're teaching classes.
But if you are in the business of, for example, running a club, running a bar.
You know, you want to prove that your space is the IT space.
And part of that is being sure that the place feels like it's hopping,
feels like it's crowded and it's coming in.
But we don't necessarily design our MMOs for people watching.
We don't necessarily design it so that there are lots of people interacting.
We try, you know, lots of designers still think it's important to have really big,
super big worlds so that people get really spread out and those populations get diffused.
And that really, really fights with what the social needs of the space are.
Now, sometimes your new kid in town comes in and it's famously said that all babies
are born sociopaths.
They don't know anything about anything.
They don't know what's right or wrong and they have to be taught that by their parents,
by their teacher, by their clergy, by their boy scout troop, whatever.
Much can be said the same for massively multiplayer game players.
They come into an environment and every environment has different rules for what is right, what
is wrong.
So for example...
What's correct in Quake is different than what's correct in Ultima Online, which is
different than the social mores of World of Warcraft.
And this can even be different per server.
What's acceptable on a role-playing server is completely different than what's acceptable
on a PvP server, and most of this is based on social convention.
Now, players have to learn these rules in order to fit in, and most people will actually
try to.
Sometimes they don't want to.
Sometimes they don't bother to learn.
Sometimes it's funny, right?
So...
if you ever want to kill an entire weekend, you can go to lamebook.com and see about the
people who just do not understand what is appropriate or inappropriate to post on Facebook.
And on Facebook, that's funny because you actually have control over your social circle.
But in MMO, you don't necessarily have control over your social circle.
It's a wide open landscape.
And as a result of this, the power shifts and the people who are sociopaths can actually
do the griefing.
Now, Raf Koster, who's sitting right over there,
said this some time ago on his blog,
where he pointed out that basically the more indirect
your communication is with the people
that you're talking to, the more anonymous you become,
the less inhibited that you are in your social behavior.
And he came to an interesting conclusion,
which is something for the game designer to take to heart,
which is that it may be that the right way
to solve griefing inside of your environment.
is to increase empathy, not necessarily punish people.
Get people to recognize that the person at the other end
of that mud, connection wire, is actually a real person,
as opposed to a nameless, faceless person they can abuse.
And this is something that we see in real life as well.
We have a ton of studies that talk about
how even the smallest nods can get people
to actually care more about other people
and want them to do them correctly.
You are more likely.
to be rude in traffic if you make eye contact with the guy you're about to cut off.
You're more likely to give money to a bum if he manages to catch your eye.
That being said, some people never learn
and you should not be afraid of expelling them from your environment
if at the first sign that they prove that they cannot be salvaged.
So on to loaner type four.
Some people are playing under unique conditions.
Sometimes they're playing at lunch.
They're playing at their desk.
Sometimes they're playing at home while their wife and kid
are asleep next to their desk.
Sometimes this is the only way they play,
and sometimes this is only how they play some of the day.
These people are playing under unique constraints.
And this is a good excuse why you always
need to have some level of solo content in your game,
some stuff for these people to do.
These people can't commit.
to playing in a dungeon for 45 minutes because their lunch break might end then.
If your dungeon can't be done in 45 minutes, they'd have to abandon you and leave you there.
They might not be able to put on voice chat, for example, because they can't talk and wake up the kid,
or it's just too embarrassing to put on the headset while they're at the office.
So these people might want to do group content,
they just are in a position where they cannot for some part of their day,
but they still want to play their game.
It behooves you as the designer to give them the social content
that they need, or the solo content that they need and want
so that they can play when they have the availability to do so.
Good news.
We're hitting the mass market.
And we're hitting the mass market in a big way.
The bad news is that means, that does not mean that we get to stop making games for
pimply-faced nerds and other people that just want to keep to themselves.
If you get the mass market, well, depending on what study you choose to believe, between
25 and 50 percent of the general population is considered introverts.
You're still going to be getting a whole lot of people who would prefer to keep to themselves
or even if they do want to group up with other people.
would rather not be the ones who initiate the contact, for whom talking to the pretty
girl at the end of the bar is scary and terrifying to them, right?
And in fact, despite the fact that playing video games is bigger than it has ever been
in the history of time, according to the Center for Disease Control, and yes, the fact that
the CDC is doing studies on gaming should tell you what the government thinks about
our industry in general, studies of the CDC have shown that
gamers are still more likely to be introverted.
Right?
And there are some dangers.
They've also, like other studies,
have shown that introverts are more likely to be depressed
and more likely to have social problems, clearly.
But they also found that the people who play these games
actually see video games, online video games, MMOs,
social games, as a way of getting the social food
that they need, the social play that they need.
They see it as sort of a.
a surrogate for social interactions inside the real world.
For them, it's easier to have these interactions inside the game.
And that's okay.
In that respect, we're actually doing a service to these people.
But at the same time, we have to keep in mind what our mechanics are forcing these people
to do.
Even if I'm an introvert inside of your game space, that does not mean I want to go out
and recruit people.
Don't make me.
I do not want to ask 30 strangers if they want to help me kill something in Vampire
Wars.
Why? I'm an introvert. I don't like asking people for anything.
There are people that like to do that. There are people that like to reach out and you
can actually give them a lot of the impetus, a lot of the push, a lot of the control in
actually doing things like building groups, running the dungeons. Give extroverts the
tools to do so and allow the introverts to pass off.
the control over these responsibilities to the extroverts, and the extroverts will have
fun doing it, and the introverts will be relieved they don't have to.
Even little things, like if I'm an introvert and I want to find a guild, give me a way
to advertise passively.
Give me a way that I can reach out to people in a way that it doesn't feel like I'm rejected
if I don't succeed.
Now, this is an interesting design challenge.
All the time inside of our social spaces,
our social circles disintegrate.
This might be that the friend that you play with all the time
has decided to stop playing the game,
or your guild has just collapsed because of guild drama
or something else.
And suddenly, you had a social circle,
and it used to do social things.
You used to do the raids.
You used to do the dungeons.
You used to do the territorial control.
And that entire social structure has utterly disappeared.
This is a broken game state.
and if you think about it like this guy has just gotten dumped by his social circle
and you think about all the emotions that you had going on inside of you the last time you got dumped
you can understand that this is scary and what is your job as the game designer?
Your job as a game designer is to set up the rebound relationship as fast as you freaking can
and get them back and play the game that you want to
because these people don't necessarily want to play your solo game
they're happy playing the raid game, they're happy playing the territorial control
before that was all jerked out from under them.
One of the things that our games don't do well enough is
have redundant social groups.
So sociologists in the field of social networking
have this concept of weak ties and strong ties. And if you think about your
real life,
your life is primarily defined by your strong ties. This is your wife,
your kids, your parents.
the people you go to work with every day.
If you go to church, it might be the people that you see at church.
And your weak ties are your more distant relationships, right?
These are the guy that you worked with three jobs ago
and the kid that you went to high school with.
Facebook, if you think about it, is primarily a way of collecting these weak ties.
What sociologists found is that, you know,
strong ties sort of govern our day-to-day lives and our day-to-day interactions.
Weak lives is what we turn to when chaos strikes.
When you lose your job and all of your co-workers are also now scrambling and finding your jobs,
that's when you're going to go to the guy that you went to high school with.
That's when you're going to go to the guy you worked with two jobs ago
and see if he has any leads on another job.
That's sort of, these weak ties act as sort of a social safety net
for individuals that allow them to actually get into the next thing.
MMOs aren't designed that way.
We generally encourage people to...
get into a guild as soon as possible,
and then these guilds become very solid,
and they become very insular.
And they don't interact with other guilds very often.
In fact, very often there's intense competition
between the guilds.
And so when that guild dissolves,
it becomes something of a nightmare situation,
and there's a very real risk
that players wash out of the game.
I don't have the answer for this,
but this seems like a great place
for an enterprising designer to find a solution
that we can all steal.
Now your kid who just got off the bus, he gets all the way to level 50, he's maxed out,
he's there because he's heard about your unique selling position, he's heard about the territorial
control and the raiding and the battlegrounds and all the stuff that's in game, he really
wants to be in an arena team.
But he's got this problem, he doesn't know if he's good enough.
And very often he may be right, right?
A lot of these games are hard.
And in-game is really hard on purpose,
because we're trying to create challenges that
can keep you coming back over and over again,
keep you engaged, and actually be a challenge.
But that also means that it can be very hard, again,
to get into that mean girls clique,
to actually get into a social circle
where you can actually prove that you belong
and where you can be a contributor.
Jonathan Baron famously described it as glory and shame.
We have Tom Cruise representing glory.
We have Bill Buckner representing shame.
uh... i'm a red sox fan
uh...
what john said is that glory is the reason why people play the most they
want to be the guy that plants the flag on top of the tower they want to be the
guy that lands that final death blow when they're only three eyes left in the
raid
that's what they envision their head
and shame is the reason why they don't they're afraid of letting everybody down
right there afraid of being the person
uh... who waste half an hour of everybody's lives because they just
couldn't get the job done
And very often it's because they don't understand that there might be low impact roles that
they can take.
And one of the things that John Baron did in his game, which was a long time ago, it
was called BattleTech, was they basically had cannon fodder roles.
The idea was you needed a stream of newbies for whatever their game design was that you
would send out on the battlefield and you would tell them, yeah, you're going to go
out there, you're going to really far, you're going to take a few pot shots, then you're
going to die.
It's OK.
You want to come back.
You want to go out there and do it again.
And these low-level, low-skill players could come in,
feel like they're contributing immediately
to this in-game activity, and gain some comfort
with the social structure, gain some comfort with the GUI,
gain some comfort and understanding of what
is going on at all around them, and gradually work their way
up the hierarchy of whatever they had, guilds or clans
or whatever it was.
Finding ways so that players can actually
contribute to a guild in a way that is not going to induce shame is, I think, something
that is very important to getting people who don't want to be loners into a social circle.
And you know, one of those things to keep in mind is to keep in mind how hard it is
to actually learn how to play some of these roles.
Who here has ever played a tank?
A tank.
And inside of Massive
In WoW or in
It's hard, isn't it?
And it's a binary switch.
You either know how to do it or you don't.
And when you don't, there is a lot of death,
and there is a lot of carnage, and there
is a lot of people who are really, really mad at you
because you suck and you're terrible.
Right?
You learning how to tank is asking four other people
to die over and over and over again
until you can figure this shit out.
That is an enormous social pressure.
And it's an incredible barrier for getting good tanks inside of your Trinity-based role-playing game.
Some people just want to play by themselves.
And not all the time.
I actually used to play Star Wars Galaxies. I was a Master Crafter.
My biggest pet peeve for that game was that I couldn't stop...
I couldn't log into my account without people bugging me for pants.
As soon as I logged in, they would see me come in, and it would just be an endless span
of tells, why haven't I made you your pants yet?
It was very, very frustrating.
Some people just want to get away from their responsibilities, even their online responsibilities,
but they still want to play this game.
And that's okay.
Being by yourself from time to time, even in little bite-sized chunks, can be very,
very healthy.
There's been some research done that found that some people prefer having a commute to
not having a commute.
That's crazy, right?
Well, now if you think about it, that's 20 minutes that you have that you aren't being
bothered by your boss, you aren't being bothered by your wife, you aren't being bothered by
your job responsibilities, you aren't, you know, being bothered by your kid.
It is that small period of alone time that you have that you can...
laugh or cry or crank ACDC on the radio or pick your nose or whatever the hell it is
you like to do when you're by yourself.
And so giving people a way to play along, giving people a way to escape, to jump to
alts, to do other things
is something I think is actually very valuable and something I think that
people
sometimes understate the value of.
And some people are loners because, well, they think that other people are idiots.
I admit being somewhat sympathetic to this point of view, but these people, they may
even like the idea of taking part in the raids, but they, oh, geez.
I was in a raid once.
It took us 45 minutes to actually get everybody in the same place and get started and get
going and whatnot.
If these people, this is a possibly slightly broken player state.
If they want to raid, you want to get them in there, and you need to find ways to knock
down these social barriers so that they can actually get into the game.
A lot of these people have been scared off by guild drama.
A lot of these people have been scared off by incompatible guilds.
Somebody once described being in a rock band as...
like being married to four other people. Being in a raiding guild is having, is like being
married to about 40 other people. And it only takes, you know, finding your way into a bad
guild to sort of color your relationship for the whole game, right? If you find yourself
into the, uh, leetspeakcooldude guild.
Your idea of what that game is going to be is going to be entirely different than if you actually stumble into the guild that likes to quote Shakespeare.
And yes, I have found that guild.
And it was weird.
So actually finding, you know, you can never make guild drama go away.
But one of the things you can do is do what you can in order to help people find compatible guilds, find guilds of people like them, find servers of people like them.
Right. So.
Back in Ultima Online, one of the things that they had was they had a guild full of people
who liked to play elves, which pissed off the people who were also role-playing, who
believed very firmly that elves did not belong in the Ultima universe.
But these people who played elves all found themselves and they went off and played by
themselves and that's actually part of the magic of the internet, is that it's easy for
like-minded people to find each other.
And our games, with all of our server divisions,
often put in arbitrary barriers that
make it too hard for you to find the right circle of friends.
Your game is infinitely stickier if you can
get them someplace compatible.
Just a side note about voice chat.
On the balance, voice chat is good for the social in your MMO,
but voice chat is also a commitment.
When you start talking, you reduce your own anonymity
to other people.
So I've noticed when I've played raids, the people who
refuse to turn on voice chat are very frequently the people
who wash out of the guild.
Because it's just a way that they haven't signed into your
game experience.
Yeah, sometimes there are also guys pretending to be girls,
and girls who don't want people to know that they're
actually girls and stuff like that.
But sort of the retention inside the guild is much
stronger once they actually commit to other people by
turning on their microphone.
And some people just won't play your game by themselves.
And that's OK.
I saw a study of World of Warcraft data.
Somebody had analyzed the armory and found
that a huge percentage of players in the armory
had reached level 70.
This was back when level 70 was max.
But had no raid gear, no dungeon gear, and had no PVP gear on.
Which is to say, they went from 1 to 70 playing by themselves.
and if that's the game that they want to play
okay
is important to remember that there's a clear difference between between being
alone and being lonely
and i think we all kind of we know that but one of these is a lot healthier than
the other
uh... in this book which is good
uh...
being lonely is actually vaguely not good for you
right it is
been known to call psychological problems
It has been known to cause physiological problems, like high blood pressure.
On the other hand, almost any psychologist can tell you that having some alone time,
choosing to be alone, can be actually very healthy for your mental state of being.
I found this interesting.
This is how a hotel did some research on the kind of people that play their games.
19% of them is in a group that they classify as the loner.
Now, I don't know if you're familiar with Habbo Hotel,
but at the time that these metrics were done,
Habbo Hotel was a purely social game.
There weren't any game mechanics.
There weren't any rats to kill.
It wasn't like that, right?
It was a social space.
And yet, even in this space, 19% of the population
was just preferred to stay by themselves
and do their own thing.
So anyway, wrapping down, one of the things I think that you should all take away is that
even if we posit, which I think is important that we do, that the in-game stuff, the massive
stuff inside of our games is the unique selling proposition and is the stuff that we should
polish and really deliver and really, you know, that's what we need to compete with
each other on and that's what we need to compete against the single players on.
Alone is the default state of the Massley multiplayer.
And this is both on the macro level of the first time they
log in, they're alone.
And they're alone until they actually find a social circle
to run with.
And even once they do that, every day that they log in,
they are alone until they actually find someone to run
their dungeon with, until they find somebody to get in a
battleground with.
And the game needs to understand that and recognize
that and offer them the single player gameplay, the solo
gameplay that can act as the backbone of their experience.
even if they want to socialize.
Consider the bar.
This is probably one of the oldest multiplayer environments
in human history.
Bars have now become incredibly sophisticated
in offering excuses for you to come to their bars
and interact with other people.
Speed dating, book clubs, Super Bowl watch parties.
They don't force you to take part in these activities.
If you want to come and watch trivia happen,
they're more than happy to take your money and serve you
drinks.
But these environments are richer because of that.
And they're hoping that you'll come in and actually find
people and come back on a weekly basis for the trivia.
They're hoping that you find a social clique that you want
to associate with that bar.
We build little communities.
And it's very important that we do that.
We're trying to create strong social ties.
We're trying to find the extroverts and the evangelists
that can actually encourage people to come
into this game space.
We want our gameplay to be richer because other people are there.
But one of the things that we have to acknowledge as Massive Multiplayer Designers is that our
magic, our secret sauce, this stuff, the raids, this is hardcore stuff.
This is hardcore gameplay.
Even a basic raid is incredibly hard for players to grasp and get comfortable with.
You know, this gameplay in EVE is hardcore gameplay.
You have to figure out how to get the solo player.
in a position where they want to take part in this, where they feel comfortable with
the social circles, where they feel like they can be contributors.
You know, this, crazy hardcore, and man, I hope you have a good machine to run most of
these games, because, you know, it is an entirely different game than what you're going to learn
when you play Solo.
And that's okay.
You just have to figure out how to walk people to the conclusion that playing these games
is okay.
You know, people start any game that they play as casual.
And this is true of whether or not it's Bejeweled or Puzzle Pirates or World of Warcraft and Star Wars The Old Republic.
They start casual and uncommitted to your game space.
And as they do, they get more and more deeper into the game.
They're going to get closer and closer to the hardcore experience and the different activities inside these games are going to be tailored more and more to these different people.
You notice then the massive multiplayer charts that has this progression of what's going on inside the game, it becomes more and more about grouping.
And it becomes more and more about coaxing people out of their loner shell and getting them into these higher level in-game experiences.
But it's hard, right?
Actually getting people from casual to interested and interested to committed, and especially going down to hardcore.
You know, if hardcore is massively multiplayer game experience, you have to overcome a whole bunch of social problems.
You have to overcome a whole bunch of...
you know, shyness, cliquishness, distrust, fear of commitment.
You have to overcome all of these issues to get these people to actually go down the ladder
and play those games.
And you know what?
It may be that you don't want to.
It may be that they're happy to stay at that casual level, that interested level, and not
go further down the ladder.
But at the end of the day, being lonely is a problem that you have to solve.
But not being alone, right?
Being alone can be healthy.
If people choose to be alone, they're not lonely.
That's okay.
people of all walks of life value being alone.
But if you're actually in a massive multiplayer environment,
the irony of being lonely is inescapable.
That's all I have for you today.
Thanks for coming out.
And I'll take any questions you have.
Thank you.
Any questions at all?
There's a microphone back there, I think.
You were talking about the weak ties problem.
That made me think of a system in Dark Age of Camelot where you could combine guilds into alliances,
and a system in Final Fantasy XI where you could have multiple guilds link pearls in your inventory
and decide whether you wanted to be in a guild or not in a guild, moment to moment.
The guild leader could revoke your link pearl, but you could carry very many of them.
Do you think there's a reason we've gotten away from those more complicated multi-guild connection systems?
So the question was that there have been games that have experimented with that sort of thing,
such as allowing people to have multiple guild affiliations, or having guilds join into alliances.
And is there a reason why people have gone away from them?
I think that in many cases it's because the game designs have kind of gotten away from
them because they don't understand what's important about them.
So Shadowbane had alliances, for example, and that provided that social safety net.
If your guild collapsed, you would often jump to someone else in your alliances.
But you know, when you have... in Shadowbane, we didn't design the alliances for that reason.
I mean, actually, right now, I'm trying to remember if they were informal or not.
They were codified into the experience.
you know we put the alliances in because we didn't have factions the way that
for example World of Warcraft has factions
uh... and as a result of that we need to create sides
uh... dynamically on the fly
you know similarly uh...
Marine 59 which I also worked on had guilds and secret societies
right
uh... and
I put it in specifically for this reason
uh... but the secret society was kind of
weird and you could really do anything with the secret society because it wasn't a secret
anymore and you know more to the point you know one of the things I've seen talked about
is having two guild affiliations that presents a you know really simple gooey issues like
okay how do you send tell to your second guild right you know how do you interface with both
guilds and so I think it's a lot of how do you make it simple enough that people can
actually understand.
and interface with it without mucking up what is already an incredibly complicated user interface.
Thanks.
Any more questions?
We have one more question.
This may be simple, this may be not.
EVE Online specifically has a guild or corporation history.
Do you think something like that is more of a good thing or more of a bad thing?
I know in EVE Online, if you're trying to, if you're...
if you've pissed off your alliance or whatever, and you didn't do it for the benefit of somebody
else, it can be really hard to move on to somebody else's corporation or alliance because
of those prior standings and because those are just written in stone on your character.
I think it's a very good thing in your classic server-based MMO, because it really helps
to address the problem of sociopaths.
uh... you know once you realize that you'll have a black mark on your record
for as long as you keep this character around
people actually start to
play nicer really fast
uh... the question is always is it impossible for you to hit the reset
button
i don't know how well it works in eve to be honest i haven't played eve very deeply
uh... but you know cautiously i'm in favor of people having a history
to deal with the problem of uh... sociopathy
So, not so much a question but a comment.
I think one of the issues when we start talking about soloing versus grouping,
especially reading the blogs,
you know, there tends to be people that fall into each category.
One of the big issues about people who like to group is, you know,
they feel like the pendulum has kind of swung toward the soloers.
I know personally in one game I play with my girlfriend,
it annoys me to no end when I go do the signature quest and,
oh, no, sorry, it's solo only.
You have to break your group.
And I think, you know, that's one of the things that a lot of people who like to group find annoying,
where, you know, our games kind of really so much cater to the solo that it becomes,
well, the default assumption is obviously people are going to solo.
So, especially when we want to tell a story, we're going to do the feature quest that, you know,
we have to go through solo.
And especially if you've built a character where I'm going to, you know,
especially when I play my girlfriend, I'm always going to be playing with her.
So I build a character so that we kind of build our strengths and weaknesses together.
Now, all of a sudden, we have to separate.
Now we feel like, you know.
incomplete and it gets really frustrating.
So the answer I would give to that is that
splitting groups is almost always bad.
You know, you don't want to force people to play solo because
even if you ascribe to the fact that people should be able to solo most of the time,
there is such social pressure regarding
getting a group together, getting the group on the same step of the quest, getting the group
uh... you know started the same time on the same step of the instance and and
you know how everyone having the quest before they get the door
you doing any group contents really hard so anytime you make them break off from
each other
you risk them getting their experiences out of sync again and you you increase
the chance that they won't form back together again
uh...
do i think that it's uh...
bad to have solo only content
uh... no i think that having solo only contents ok
I just think you have to be wary of, if you put it on the critical path that a group might
run into and therefore be forced to splinter.
Some designs, it might be unavoidable.
Anybody have anything?
We have another question.
So, how do you feel the random dungeon finder, which basically lets you come together as
a loner with potentially other loners that break apart, do you think it helps that or
do you think it just makes it more okay to be a loner in the game?
I think that it creates some very odd behavior.
I think it has many good points.
I think one of the problems that I have with the Dungeon Finder
is that it creates a very odd sense of lack of empathy
for the other people in your group, because you know that you'll never see them again.
You know, before you had the cross-server stuff.
uh... union you pissed off the tank if you need another part tank
uh... that you know there was enough of things go around
uh... so you really don't piss this guy off but now people
feel like they can be jerks to the tanks with impunity
uh...
i also think that also makes the strong tie weak tie problem worse
uh... because again
a lot of times if your guild would fall apart, you would say, hey, I did some dungeons with
this guy, he was fairly competent, maybe his guild doesn't suck. And now you don't have
that sort of social network that's sort of in the background. That being said, playing
from the, as the experience of the loner who likes to run bugs, and because I play healers
mostly and therefore high valued, man, it's a lot easier to get groups. And so if you
can put up with that psychology, it might be the right decision for your game.
Anything else?
I'd like to thank you for coming to this talk,
and thanks for coming to GDC.
And I guess we'll see everybody next year.
Oh, everybody should have a white piece of paper.
If you could just pick them up and circle the word excellent
and give them to the person by the door.
Thank you very much.