Hello, everyone.
All right, we're going to go ahead and get started.
Quick warning, some things in this talk
might be considered spoilers.
Also, please do not record the talk,
and please fill out your talk evaluation
that you'll be sent over email.
A copy of this talk will be available on Gorilla's website
after the conference.
So you'll be able to download this presentation
if you want to see it, rather than
having to take pictures of every slide or something like that.
The title of this talk is Balancing Action in RPG
and Horizon Zero Dawn's Quests.
So how much is Horizon an action game
and how much is it an open-world RPG?
Truthfully, I can't answer that question.
We never drew a line in the sand and said,
yep, this is it, this is the perfect balance.
When I talk about finding the balance,
I'm gonna talk about my own experiences searching for it.
the open-world RPG concepts I applied during development that worked,
and the action and gun concepts I had to learn, sometimes painfully.
Here's an outline of the talk.
First, I'm going to describe my background a bit,
and that'll give you some context for what I brought to Guerrilla and to Horizon.
Second, I'm going to walk you through an early vision of Horizon's quests.
Third, I'm going to talk about open world quests versus what we call bunker quests
and do a deep dive on two examples from Horizon to illustrate the differences
in technique and approach we used for each.
Fourth, I'm going to talk a bit about my own shortcomings and the things I learned
from Guerrilla's institutional knowledge of action game level design.
And fifth, I'm going to try to introduce some rules for thinking about balancing action in RPG.
Lastly, I'm going to leave a little bit of time for questions,
but if you want to, please come up after the talk.
and ask me any questions you might have that we don't have time for.
Hi, this is me. My name is Blake Rubichet.
I'm a senior quest designer at Guerrilla Games.
I was hired in 2015 to join a new team that the studio leadership identified
would be necessary to supplement the design team that Guerrilla already had.
That new team was the quest team.
This team. This is the quest team at Guerrilla Games.
Hi, guys.
So prior to working at Guerrilla, I was a quest designer on the Elder Scrolls Online at ZeniMax Online Studios.
ESO embraces the Bethesda model of open world RPGs like Skyrim and Fallout.
Quest designers at Zoss write, design, and script their quests, but level design is a separate discipline entirely.
Before that, I was a world builder on Star Wars The Old Republic at BioWare Austin.
Old Republic is a take on the BioWare model of RPGs.
Again, we had separate level designers or architects at BioWare.
The common theme here as far as what I brought to the table is that my experience was scripting, narrative design, and quest design, not level design.
I arrived at this production with swinging into full gear.
Horizon had a very strong, very compelling vision, but one that didn't fully encompass the game we ended up making.
Majestic wilderness, awe-inspiring machines, and exotic tribes.
These were the aspects of the game that drove our early design thinking.
And let's not forget Aloy, of course.
But what about quests?
That's what my team had been hired to make.
What did quests look like in the world of Horizon?
Let me paint you a picture.
Evening.
It's raining.
Aloy wakes from unconsciousness, lying in a smoking crater.
She stands, dazed, and starts moving
towards a burning village in the distance.
Aloy enters the village.
Everywhere she looks, chaos reigns.
A villager approaches Aloy and begs her not
to pursue the machine that attacked the village.
It's too dangerous.
Aloy being Aloy, she follows the path of destruction out of the village,
passing the bodies of Nora warriors slain by the beast.
A herd of machines blocks her path.
Aloy picks a machine off from the herd in the plain
and overrides it, making it her mount.
Now with a ride, she makes haste to pursue the rampaging machine.
Aloy catches up to the hunting party sent after the beast
in the nearby mountains.
All but one are dead.
The last hunter tells Aloy to beware.
The beast is near.
From nearby, our quarry, the mighty Thunderjaw,
shrieks and attacks.
Aloy engages with and defeats the machine in epic fashion.
Pretty cool, right?
This is an early illustrated version of the E3 trailer
that we would eventually use to reveal Horizons to the world.
This kind of quest I can understand and wrap my head
around, given my background in open world RPGs.
A quest like this is very similar to a quest like the Ice Giant in The Witcher 3.
Big monster destroys town, protagonist tracks monster, protagonist kills monster.
I'm being reductive, but you get my point.
This was my wheelhouse, but this was not exactly the kind of quests we ended up making.
This is the story I just told you.
There are many quests in Horizon similar to this, but almost half of the main story of
Horizon differs.
That difference led to a lot of lessons for me on action game design.
You'll notice that I bolded and underlined all the indications of place.
There are no interiors in this story, and indeed, there were no interiors at all in the vertical slice of Horizon.
These are the main quest chapters of Horizon.
The quests that I bolded are quests that take place at least partially in interiors.
Seven out of 16, more than 40% of the main story of Horizon takes place at least partially in spaces we call bunkers.
But what is a bunker and how does the design of one inform us about balancing action and RPG?
As I mentioned, the early vision of Horizon focused a lot on exteriors, machines, and tribes,
but we needed spaces in which to tell the stories of the old world.
Bunkers are those spaces.
Whereas open-world quests in Horizon feature big outdoor spaces and combat against large, monstrous opponents,
bunkers are relatively tight, linear interiors featuring cover-shooter combat against primarily human opponents.
If open world quests resemble the quests in other open world RPGs,
what do bunker quests resemble?
I'll give you a hint.
But more on that later.
To return to the theme of talk, each of these types of quests
requires a different balance of action and RPG design thinking.
Each required a specific set of tools and experience
that didn't always completely overlap.
To illustrate all that, I'm going to talk about two quests specifically,
Freeheap and the Grave Horde.
FreeHeap was one of the first side quests I pitched and built,
and it was also a bit of an experiment.
As I mentioned, I'd come from designing MMORPGs,
and so did our quest design lead at the time.
We wanted to see if we could build a quest using
the same kind of structure we were accustomed to that
would also work for Horizon.
It was also a bit of an experiment
on how open world we wanted our quests to be.
This is what FreeHeap looks like today,
but it was not always so.
Initially, we tried a very open quest concept.
Three quest locations, each essentially a pocket level
connected by the open world.
A benefit of this type of open design
is that it gives players a lot of options
for how they approach your quest and the challenges within it.
Also, within the context of a multiplayer game,
it spreads your players out and it prevents bunching.
Unfortunately, a major downside of this design
is that players can bumble into the goings-on of your quest
without realizing what is actually going on.
Many open world RPGs suffer from this problem to some degree.
One way we solved this problem on Elder Scrolls Online
was to get the quest bestower to come to you.
Whenever the player approached the vicinity of the quest,
some Yahoo would come running out of the distance,
hey, I have something for you to do.
This just didn't work for Horizon.
As we developed the game, it became more and more cinematic.
For any significant character,
we wanted to stage their conversations,
and we needed a definitive location for that.
Case in point, the bestower for Freeheap, Petra.
Ha, I've calluses older than you.
I've calluses enough if you want to test me.
Ha, she sparks. I believe it, Flamehair. Petra Forge Woman.
Uh, Aloy, Machine Hunter.
Mm, Machine Hunter, eh?
Huh, I could have a use for you.
Straight of it is, we're being muscled out of our own claims.
That's why I've been working on this scrap-spitting beast.
It's a dispute settler.
That conversation happens here in Freeheap,
and it can really only happen in Freeheap because of the staging,
the things that she references, the propping that needs to be there.
We really wanted you to have a context of the situation in Freeheap,
as regards the Banit camp or the Scrapper Den,
the other locations in the quest,
before you went there.
So we employed a tried and true strategy.
We added big damn walls.
This is an MMO technique used to onboard open world quest
and quest locations.
Basically, you limit the number of approach angles
and make sure all those vectors of approach
lead to a quest bestower.
But now with the added walls, we started
to lose the open feeling of the quest.
It became more and more like a linear level.
To combat this, we focused on the level design
of the transitional spaces.
This is an early gray box of the transitional space leading up to the banded area.
Because we lost so many vectors of approach to this quest location,
I wanted to maximize the variety of traversal options available to the player in the space.
We called this the Jungle Gym concept.
These early paint overs emphasized the verticality, the route variety,
and the range of movement options through the space.
If you saw David's talk earlier, he was talking about this as affordances.
So we really loaded this area up.
This is what it looks like today.
You can see if you have a look that there's
a real variety of options presented to the player here.
We wanted to let them come to this bandit camp
and get into it any way they wanted to.
You'll see plenty of zip lines.
You'll see tightropes.
You'll see vertical options across the top.
You'll see low options in through the gate.
And tons and tons of affordances.
Because we lost the vectors of approach.
We still wanted to give players a sense of flexibility.
This new, more closed design still offered the player a choice
about which quest objective they wanted to accomplish first.
But that too eventually fell to the wayside.
Again, this was due to the fidelity of the story we wanted to tell.
This is the quest today.
The quest has three acts, each of which correspond to a movement within the story,
an area, and an objective.
The quest is bestowed here by Petra.
Petra needs Aloy to recover some components she will use to restore a weapon she's working on.
Act 1 takes the player to the bandit den, where the human bandits have stashed stolen power cells.
Aloy breaks in, takes the cells, and we foreshadow retribution by the bandits.
In Act 2, Aloy enters the lair of the scrappers and grabs the parts she needs from the scrapper piles.
In Act 3, Aloy returns to the quest bestower.
Petra to give her the collected power cells and parts.
Petra uses the return materials to restore the weapon,
just as the bandits arrive and attack the town.
So here was the rub, and this is why we ended up
going with a linear quest.
If you did the scrapper layer section first,
and then the bandit hideout, it didn't make any sense
that the bandits showed up immediately
after this guy shook his fist at you and said,
we're going to come and get you.
It wasn't as strong a story.
So we eventually decided that we wanted you to go
to the bannet layer first, and that's just the way
that we directed you to do it.
This narrative structure naturally suggests a looping flow,
so we built a special one-way shortcut
from the scrapper layer back to Freeheap to facilitate that.
Why?
Because backtracking is the devil.
The problem was players never used it.
They didn't know it was there.
What we needed and we didn't have the time
was a breadcrumbing system, so we built one.
Very importantly, there was a talk earlier today
that talked about breadcrumbing.
And I think this is a very good time
to point out the differences between action and RPG
because in action games, breadcrumbing literally
means placing little objects along the path
to lead you somewhere.
When we talk about it in terms of open world RPGs,
we usually mean a system like this.
So in World and on the compass, we add these markers
and we literally tell you where to go.
It routes you along roads, it routes you to doors.
and I'm going to explain a little bit about how that works
because it's very important in the context of an open world game.
Let me share with you some images from the design doc
I wrote for this system three years ago.
As you can see, I am an artist.
If a quest objective takes place in a space
with a discrete number of entrances
and the player is outside of that space,
the breadcrumbing system will point you to a valid entrance
into that space, like so.
We do that with a marker like this.
Important point, a door in this context
is a crack in a wall, a ladder, whatever.
It doesn't have to literally be a door,
it's just an entrance into the space.
A level in the traditional sense
doesn't have to worry about stuff like this
because it is a bounded concept.
A level starts and a level ends
and everything in the middle is the level.
In an open-world quest, you can go in,
go halfway through, decide you wanna go somewhere else,
get something else, power up,
and then you have to find your way back.
That's why a breadcrumbing system is really vital
in an open world context.
So this is what I did.
I defined the scrapper layer as a discrete space
with two doors, like so.
When the player collects the parts necessary in the area,
I simply invalidate the door they came in through
and I open the other door.
Then the breadcrumbing system takes them out.
Simple.
As an experiment in open world quest design,
what did FreeHeat teach us?
Multiplayer online RPGs, though open world,
require you to structure your quests in a way
that single player open world RPGs just don't.
Story informs our quest structure a lot.
Openness will often take a backseat
to a great story in Horizon.
Lastly, invest in player guidance systems.
This is extremely important and will save you a lot of heartache
in open world games.
As a contrast, I'm going to talk about the Grave Horde.
Grave Horde is a linear bunker quest taking place
around the middle of the main story of Horizon.
As I mentioned before, there are a lot of main story quests
that take place in bunkers.
Here's an illustration of what I'm talking about.
If you add cauldrons to that, you begin to get a sense
of how much linear interior space
there really is in Horizon.
This is the earliest wireframe gray box
of the Grave Horde done in Maya.
If Freeheap's flow is like a loop,
this sucker is a straight line.
Compare the gray box wireframe above against the shipped version below.
I've added these colored areas to indicate the spaces that correlate to one another.
As you can see, a lot of the spaces stayed.
They hung out between the first design and the last.
The macro level design of this quest stayed pretty consistent throughout
development, because that's what I was familiar with, and I got it pretty much right.
That is not true of the micro level design.
Quickly, let me define what I'm talking about here.
Macro level design.
Each space is a significant moment, aka a beat,
that's what we call it, of the level as a whole.
The image on the left is an in-game map
of a starship level from Star Wars The Old Republic.
That's what I mostly worked on when I was there.
On the right is an image of an in-game map
from the Grave Horde.
In both cases, rooms serve as story beats
or gameplay beats, with the corridors in between
sized to help the pacing of the overall level.
This is the type of level design familiar to RPG designers like me, given my background building dungeons in Elder Scrolls Online and starships in Star Wars The Old Republic.
So I thought that this was like directly applicable.
Micro-level design. Each space within the level is itself a story and must be designed with its own beats.
This is the type of level design familiar to action game designers more so than role-playing game designers.
This is also the type of level design I was least familiar with given my background.
This is the earliest playable gray box of the armory combat area of the Grave Horde.
The armory is right smack dab in the middle of the level, and it's one of three combat spaces in the bunker.
The beat before the armory is a puzzle, and the beat after the armory is kind of a story moment.
So it made sense structurally to do a big combat beat here in the middle.
Here's another angle for you.
The lines indicate the intended player path for clarity's sake.
The red line is kind of what I expected most players to do.
The purple lines were, I don't know,
other things you could do if you were going to be sneaky.
And the yellow box is where I expected the bad guys to go.
So feedback on this early gray box
was a negative, to say the least.
And I think you'll know why if you saw David's talk earlier.
This led me to one question.
I got bad readability, overly simple, uninteresting,
like a bad Killzone level.
But what is a good Killzone level?
I had no idea.
Our creative director had 10 years
of experience making Killzone,
whereas the Quest team had comparatively little experience.
In fact, remember the team photo from earlier?
Only one guy on the Quest team had worked on Killzone.
The rest of us arrived to Guerrilla
with Horizon as our first project at the company.
I went to my boss at the time, distraught, and I said to him,
I don't know if I'm the best guy in the building to do this.
My knowledge of action game level design is limited,
and there are a bunch of people at Guerrilla way better at it
than I am.
His response to me was, you're right.
Let's get you some help.
Let's make use of some of that institutional knowledge.
This led to me being sent the Killzone guide
for good level design, TM.
I want to share some wisdom from a small part of the document with you and show you how I applied it.
So, readability.
Very important page for me.
Entrances, exits, alternative paths, flanking options need to be clear to the player.
The player also needs to recognize where the enemies are, it needs to be clear what can be used as cover,
and this needs to be done in conjunction with viz, environment art, and lighting.
This slide helped me realize something very important
about this room and about the way I was thinking about this.
I was thinking too much about the content of the room
from a top-down perspective, and I
wasn't thinking enough about the way the player saw the room.
This is a view from the entrance to that gray box room.
This is the exit and the goal.
Because this is a small crawl space and because genius,
I put a whole bunch of boxes in front of it.
It's not very clear.
Speaking of the boxes, this is where all the bad guys are supposed to be,
but because there's so many boxes, you have no idea where they could be standing.
These tanks are supposed to be your cover, but you can't tell because they are
regularly shaped, and they're much too close to the entrance to be perceived in
their entirety.
Anyway, you get my point. Red, red, red, bad, bad, bad.
My readability really sucked.
This slide was also gold for me, but not in the way you might first expect.
So...
Encounters must be multi-staged.
Roots leave player efficiently through the environment.
Provide opportunities for flanking.
Keep multiple paths within the same area.
Create variety in heights.
I thought to myself, I think my level has these things.
But then it occurred to me, this.
This made sense to me.
I could do this.
So what I decided to do was I tried to take elements
from this and put it into my level to see if they worked.
If this was a good kills on level, I think I could do this.
Are you guys familiar with the term aping?
We say aping when we mean that we copy something, right?
That we emulate what we see other people do.
The funny thing is apes actually don't learn this way.
Humans learn this way.
And adding elements of this to my level design
taught me a whole bunch of things.
So I reworked my gray box to match the example as closely
as I could.
I kept the armory feeling with the tanks and the ammunition boxes, as well as adding small
sub-interior rooms as offices.
Basically, I learned a lot by trying to copy the example as close as I could by aping it.
The new design offered multiple routes that led the player efficiently through the space,
the routes offered flanking opportunities, and a variety of heights.
This is the new view from the entrance to the room, much more readable and much more
optimized.
As we moved from proper arted building blocks into proper arted.
building blocks, we ditched the straight ramp that was into the room and replaced it with
this switchback staircase for a very important reason.
Jumping down right as you enter the room is an option, but this banister is kind of a
mild barrier right in your way.
It helps to encourage you to have a look around the space before you just go straight in,
guns blazing.
And that's what I really wanted you to do, look around.
Here's what that looks like to the player.
Now I'm going to show you what this looks like in the finished game.
So as we round the corner and we actually get our first look
into the room, you'll notice that the goal is clearly lit.
That's where you need to go.
As you proceed in, the total area reveals itself to you.
And the bad guys reveal themselves to you.
And your options slowly reveal themselves to you.
If you look around the room, the enemy placement
will help to inform you what your options are in the space.
Also, a very important tip I got from one of the other designers
Use your pickup placement to actually show people where they can go.
Lighting is really important, but pickups are actually a great way to tell players where they can and can't go.
Here are some still images of the finished product.
Kudos to the environment artists and the lighting team that worked on this.
It's an incredible result, as you can clearly see.
The goal of this space is clearly lit and highlighted.
Enemies aren't hidden. Their placement and pathing makes player options clear.
This space is multi-layered.
It has multiple paths and contains sub-interiors with collectibles and goodies to find.
I don't know if it's a great level, but I do know it's not like a bad Killzone level anymore.
So, putting it all together.
What lessons can we abstract from these two level examples from Horizon about finding the balance between RPG and action?
First, these two concepts are not opposing forces.
I'd encourage you to consider them as lenses.
in the way that Jesse Schell uses that term in his book,
The Art of Game Design.
Each represents a viewpoint from which you can consider your design priorities.
So, concept one, macro versus micro.
As I've demonstrated, open world RPGs focus more on macro design,
whereas action games focus more on micro design.
When you think about a quest's macro design,
think about structuring your quest in service of the story.
When you think about a space's micro design,
ask yourself if the area is designed
to demonstrate the challenges
and the options at the player's disposal.
Concept two, approach.
Freeheap shows you should try to design your quest space
to funnel the player to the quest bestower,
and thus the beginning of the quest.
It is equally important, as I demonstrated with Gravehorts Armory,
that you need to think about how players approach individual spaces,
not just entire areas.
A player's first view of a room has to tell them a lot about it.
Concept 3. Movement.
RPGs are principally interested in players' movement from space to pace,
and from beat to beat.
I explained a bit about breadcrumbing to demonstrate how manipulating the player's guidance system
can ensure optimal flow through a quest space.
The Jungle Gym concept in FreeHeap was an attempt to capture how movement itself can
be engaging and can provide a feeling of openness.
There are many things you can do as a player to make spaces themselves more engaging, more
fun and more joyful.
Case in point, the big ride from the end of the grave hoard.
So we knew throughout development that we were going to have this quest in a high place
and we needed Aloy to get off of a mountain.
So I added this gigantic zip line.
I put this in and I expected it to get cut every single time it went through review because
it's crazy.
But people got it.
When they played it, they were like, wow, this is kind of fun.
It's kind of joyful and I kind of get it.
I'm amazed that it's in the finished product and I'm so happy that it is.
Concepts four, final point.
Though we may fancy what we create as art,
it is also entertainment.
To make a film reference, sometimes we're Wes Anderson
and sometimes we're Michael Bay.
Strive always for engagement as well as emotion,
for feeling as well as fun,
and meaning as well as explosions.
Thank you.
I'd like to thank Guerrilla Games and our publisher, Sony, for supporting me giving
this talk.
I wouldn't be here today without the faith, patience, and gratitude that they show me.
I'd also like to thank my team and the rest of the designers at Guerrilla, from whom I
learned so much.
And now I've got some time for questions.
Microphones, bring them on.
Also, if you'd rather, you're welcome to come
and find me after the talk,
or email me or at me on Twitter, at BigRebo,
whatever makes you comfortable.
Hello.
Hi there. So you have a lot of experience working on MMOs and quest design there.
Did you face any resistance from the team at Guerrilla when you came in and were talking about like,
let's take some of these MMO learnings and put them into a single player game?
What did that process look like? Did it feel organic to kind of take that and transition into single player stuff?
Well, like I pointed out, the quest team was really new.
And I was really lucky that I came on board along with a guy named David Ford, who was the quest lead on Horizon.
And I had worked with him on Elder Scrolls Online. I followed him to Amsterdam.
So, things that we wanted to try, like I said, the experiment with FreeHeap was really,
hey David, can we do a quest objective like we did on Elder Scrolls and Horizon? Let's see if it works.
And he was always open for that kind of experimentation.
Granted, not everything we tried worked out. We had to break a few eggs.
But Guerrilla was really supportive and they knew that they needed the kinds of experience that we brought to the table.
They knew when they were making Horizon that they needed people from experience and from types of games that they didn't have a lot of experience with.
Well I think it worked.
Thank you.
Hi.
Hello.
Do you have any advice as far as making an action adventure map and communicating with
your art team to make sure that the design is still communicated when they go through
with 3D modeling and making the whole map?
You know, I could probably give a whole other talk on that, but with Horizon, we knew in
the open world that we wanted to emulate the natural world, the real world.
So when I was building something like FreeHeap, I actually knew kind of the part of the United
States where it was supposed to go.
And we looked to real locations in the real world for inspiration.
When you're building an underground space, a bunker, you don't have those natural touch
points.
You don't have a natural frame of reference.
It's a lot like a kill zone level.
Another thing is when you're working with really big areas, if something changes between
your gray box and the kind of arted product, you naturally get small changes.
But with big areas, those small changes don't matter as much.
They don't cause a lot of turbulence.
Whereas if you're dealing with very small spaces, small changes can change the feel a lot.
So you have to work very, very closely with artists, especially if you're working in tight areas and small areas.
They need to know how changing a boulder from, you know, moving a boulder five meters,
they need to know how important that is.
Thank you. Sure.
Yes.
very macro level as far as players can do quests in any order, especially the side quests.
Do you have any lessons learned for making sure things ramp up properly or whatever over
the course of the game?
Well, this is a slide I wanted to add, but it's interesting.
I think if you think about most open world games, like I think that Skyrim is a great
example, the game is shaped a lot like sort of like you, the world, and Horizon is actually
shaped like a funnel.
that gets bigger and bigger.
So the first couple quests of the game,
you're on a linear path,
and then the world starts to open to you.
And you need to be keenly aware
when you're making an open-world game
of when that world opens.
If you know when those points of broadening are,
you can get a much better sense
of how you can design your inner connectivity.
Does that help?
Yeah, sure.
I just was curious if there was any lessons
that you guys learned, and that sounds interesting, yeah.
Yeah.
Kind of going off of the environment art question,
what was your experience with like when working with art,
like on FreeHeap, being like,
okay, we need to add some extra affordances.
We need to potentially limit player movement.
We need to like put this massive wall.
Like, can you describe that process
and kind of like how you guys solved some of those problems,
whether it's like quick concept or stuff like that?
It's all about goals.
If you make it clear to everyone what your goals are and what you're trying to accomplish,
I often say that design is like sort of being the advocate in chief.
You have to be the chief advocate of a piece of content.
You have to make sure that people understand not only what it is,
but why you're doing the things that you're doing.
We know that we needed to get the player to the quest bestower.
Something that we did on Elder Scrolls is we actually had the ability to have a quest be bestowed anywhere.
On Horizon, we never developed that technology.
It's something that we made a deliberate decision about,
that we wanted our conversations to be
staged in very specific places so they
could be really high quality.
When we made that decision, it was easy to go to the artist
and say, hey, look, we made this decision for these reasons,
and this is why we need giant walls.
That wasn't always a popular decision by no means.
But when you can understand it and explain it,
it's the natural decision.
I think we have time for maybe one more?
Negative.
If you'd like to, you can come and ask me any more questions you might have.
Thank you so much for coming to the talk.