Hi. So this is actually going to be a very dense talk. It is
about 30 minutes. It may be 31 minutes. So there won't be any
time for questions. If you want to talk to me afterwards, I'll
be running over to where the One Life Left podcast is happening
and you can come over there and talk to me. I'll also put my
e-mail at the end of the talk.
So thank you for coming out.
I am an artist, game designer, and I guess most importantly,
the writer at New Challenger, and I'm
working on a game called Treachery in Beatdown City.
But my first job in the games industry
was working at Rockstar Games.
I worked in the production department
for about 4 and 1⁄2 years, which
meant I made a lot of trailers.
And I knew basically all of the writing and cut scenes
backwards and forwards.
I'm also in some games.
I'm in this cut scene audio wise. I am, if it's not really clear, I'm the black boxer who has no
facial animation. I'm also this guy who is pretty awesome. He's quoted on a red dead fan
Wikipedia as saying you looking to hell it up. That was an interesting role to play. I
basically got grabbed whenever they needed a secondary black voice actor in things.
but I also got to survive to the undead nightmare,
which is kind of rare.
I write a lot of stuff.
I helped write this article.
I think this is a pretty epic article.
Also, Anna Anthropy just told me
that she's using this article in her class
that she's teaching, which is pretty amazing
and pretty humbling.
So we're gonna kinda jump into things really quick.
When I talk about...
breaking molds, I actually don't think that these are things set in stone. I think they're
things that are mostly in people's heads. I think it's basically like a lot of well
intentioned ignorance by people who just want to do something good but they just might not
have
enough researcher stuff they think they're doing a good job when they're probably not. So I've
been thinking about how to work my way up to this first way to start breaking these molds but
it's very important to start with this point. The first thing you need to do is end cis,
white, gender, cisgender, able bodied white men as the default in your games. It's kind of
weird. We've all seen this before where we're told they're the most relatable.
that people that aren't all of the above aren't. And I've never seen a report where people said
that this is true. So now that I dropped some heaviness, I just want to have a little quiz for
you guys. So this is about relatability and popularity. There is a 90s urban sitcom starring
and named after a well-known comedian.
He has a few friends and a notable nemesis. One friend is a
neighbor who comes over and takes food. Another friend is
bald, wears glasses and has job problems. And in one episode the
main character's apartment is robbed and he contemplates
leaving. This show is very popular for its time slot. Does
anybody have any guesses? Just blurt it out. Martin is the
correct answer.
I can forgive you for maybe thinking Seinfeld, but no.
So now that we talk about this, a lot of the stories that we
have and the set-ups can be read multiple ways.
And it's really up to the creators to fill in the blanks.
None of the basic set-up for Martin or Seinfeld call for
anybody in particular.
So we've seen these images a lot often with different
configurations of white dudes that sometimes randomly throws
the prince of Persia in there because people, again, make
images that still they don't even know. They just assume all
the white characters are just in everything. And it's kind of
weird because these characters often play a big helping of
generic archetypes, right? It's like sad, depressed dad, angry
war guy. The guy who is supposed to be Nathan Drake but with less
of a budget and a completely different genre.
and a much worse script that was written in half the time, but hey, Nolan North is playing the
character. I feel most of these characters aren't that interesting, not in and of themselves, and a
hell of a lot of them look like each other.
and if we remove characters driven by white imperialism like Drake who's destiny is to steal
from cultures and destroy stuff while doing it. Max Payne who murders hundreds of Brazilians
under orders of other lighter skinned Brazilians and Michael from GTA 5 who's a rich guy
complaining about his life and gets in trouble because his inflated ego tells him he can do
whatever he wants all the while dragging a black guy along for the ride.
If you get rid of them, you're basically left with this. In my opinion, of course. What we have
are these three guys who are all made by Japanese developers. Frank West is a critique of
journalism in a game that is a critique of the U.S. beef industry. Francis York Morgan is a
really interesting ode to Twin Peaks. And Naked Snake is a man who is decidedly anti-imperialist
and hates the government and decides to set up his own military base in Africa.
So I just want to talk about like none of these characters are
interesting by default. I'm just going to go back for a second.
And my argument isn't really to just stop making white protagonists, it's just that you need to get rid of that as your default in your head.
You have to really start working really hard to justify why you have to make a dude who's white.
And if you take those steps to actually really justify why you're doing that,
then hopefully you will make a character that will be a lot better and won't just start murdering a bunch of brown people just for the heck of it.
So you have to really think, why is the nihilist, often sexist, sometimes mildly or overtly
racist, manipulative, grumpy, snarky, imperialist character relatable to players? The lengths
that people go to make the case for these characters is often very ridiculous. So case in
point, we all remember the ghostbusters, but wasn't there a fourth one? There he is. So Ernie
Hudson was actually interviewed recently.
I'm going to read you a bit of this interview.
When I originally got the script, the character of Winston was amazing and I thought it would
be career changing.
The character came in right at the beginning of the movie and had an elaborate background.
He was an Air Force major or something, a demolitions guy.
It was great.
The night before filming begins, however, I get this new script and it was shocking. The
character came in at page 68 after the Ghostbusters were established. His elaborate
background was all gone, replaced by me walking in and saying, if there's a steady
paycheck, I'll believe anything you say. And so basically he panics, he can't sleep, he
goes and talks to the people and he's like, what happened? And they're like, we wanted to
give Bill Murray more stuff to do.
And what did they give Bill Murray to do?
He basically is the loser jock lovable sexist trope
from the 80s.
He's the worst of the three scientists.
He doesn't care about his job.
He tortures a guy with electroshock therapy
basically because he wants to sleep
with the woman on the right.
He stalks her. He basically feigns interest in her because he also wants to sleep with her. He
goes to her job and waits for her. He also goes into her house under false pretenses because he
actually doesn't know anything about ghost busting. So he goes to her house, doesn't listen
to any of her problems and just wants to nail her.
and then they kiss and have a baby just in time for the second movie. So Ernie Hudson talks
about this and he says, you know, we talk about every man characters in games and this is what
Ernie Hudson had to say what people think about Winston. Well, he's sort of an every man. This
is what people say. He's kind of the guy who helps the audience understand.
And then Ernie says, I love the character, and he's got some
great lines, but I felt like he was just kind of there.
And ironically, this is what games writers use when talking
about why they make these white dudes the main character.
What the audience sees in Winston is a mostly
apolitical shell of a person.
And every man.
Now I want to talk about this game, talk about The Last of
Us, people were really happy about Ellie's existence, and
they should be.
And they were also very happy with the DLC.
But I think like what if Ellie was the main character, you know, instead of grizzled Joe Joel
And it's really weird because when you're Grizzle Joel in just the game mechanics, Ellie is an
invincible character that just runs around with an AI that actually can't kill her. So then the
whole story of him being a protector doesn't actually work because you can watch the AI just
like try to hit her and nothing happens. But also, Ellie is in the subordinate role and Joel is in
the main role, but what if Riley was in the main role and Joel was in the subordinate role? Now
Like, if you were Riley and you were maybe the character that needed to be protected
or whatever, but you could also give out orders to the person who's supposed to be protecting
you and then you have to worry about getting hurt all the while not being a grizzled dude
but actually being a queer black girl starring in a game, that would be pretty awesome and
it actually doesn't take that much work.
As writers, if you were to take the stand on this grand stage of AAA.
you would make the games industry better for it. Who better than one of the biggest studios
also to make that the standard? Who is more protected and if they aren't doing it, who can?
So more steps. Be specific about your characters, be detailed and be deliberate.
So now that we've started with a blank slate for who your default characters are, you should
work on making your characters that are unique and very explicit in who they are. This might
kind of sound obvious, but even in a text light game, you can create compelling characters by
choosing a few explicit character traits and having a few choice quotes that explain who
your character is.
In general, being deliberate is also very important.
So when I started working on Treachery in Beatdown City,
my goal was to make the fighting game characters
that I'd love to see in one.
So these are my characters.
Bruce on the left is a black man born of a Jamaican family.
who is a millionaire.
He grew up in the projects.
His family was good friends with the local Chinese family
and got a lot of his sensibilities,
like his love of anime, from that relationship.
He's always been exceptional in math,
so he skyrocketed in school
and was able to use his instincts in the stock market.
He loves Capoeira and Jeet Kune Do.
A lot of these details are fueled by people that I know.
Like one of my best friends is Chinese.
I learned about anime from him.
Lisa, to the right, is a Puerto Rican woman who has always been middle class.
She's in the police academy.
She's taking after her dad because he kind of really wants her to do that, but she just
wants to be a forensic scientist, and she really wants to be an MMA champion, and she
fights in a lot of underground fights that end up sometimes getting broken up by the
police, ironically.
Brad, in the middle, is a Texas-born man of royal Spanish and Mexican indigenous descent
whose family had to flee Mexico into America, therefore they are illegal.
When he was younger he was an independent wrestler until being called up to the big leagues where
falling out over his family's heritage made him lose his job and his title.
And now he works as a community center worker helping the poor. He's a wrestler and is very
sensitive about it being called fake, which Lisa does often to mess with him,
but she also really looks up to him.
So there's also issues. So beyond the heroes that I worked on, making the enemies have a very
distinct variety of characteristics of varying genders and racial, ethnic and socioeconomic
backgrounds. Every character has one page to describe who they are. This helps me not only
write their dialogue but know what neighborhoods they should be in, what it means to not be in
that neighborhood, who their preferred people to hang out with are.
Why would the cops come to help them?
Will the cops fight alongside them?
It makes some very interesting encounters
that leads into the gameplay,
like what happens when a punk is hanging out
with a local bar socialite.
It's been a very monstrous task, actually.
I've been working on this for a very long time,
and I know none of the characters are perfect,
but the effort put in creates very satisfying dialogue
in the game overall.
So now talking about maybe missing out on specifics, this is Cole from Gears of War.
and I want to talk about him for a little bit. So just bear with me a little bit. These next
two clips are going to be kind of interesting. So Coltrane is a mainstay of Gears of War and
he was based on a character named Terry Tate who was in some Rebot commercials and it's an
actor playing a football player. And he was voiced by this guy Lester Spate. And so that
sounds kind of cool, right? They're being influenced by other media. So this is Terry Tate.
Hey Laura. Hey Paul.
Well that's not Terry Tate.
Hey buddy.
Woo! You know you can't bring that weak ass stuff up in this humpy bumpy.
You killed it Joe. You made some money. You know that baby.
Else you here for a long day. A long day.
Cause Triple T's up in this bitch!
Some people said I was crazy when I brought Terry on board,
but I'm a firm proponent of paradigm breaking,
outside the box thinking.
And, since Terry's been with us,
our productivity has gone up 46%.
Ha ha ha ha!
Break was over 15 minutes ago!
Bitch, I am an enforcer, man!
Don't nothing go down in my house.
It's 100% hard, baby.
Sure, I jack a few fools.
I give them the pain.
But sometimes it's about intimidation, you know.
It's mind games.
So, all right, I'll see you later.
Ah!
St. Fraser, St. Fraser!
Get ready for the pain, woman!
The pain, take cover!
Oh no!
Oh no, I got it!
It's the man, please don't hurt me!
Please don't hurt me!
Thank you, Terry!
Thank you, God!
Ah!
But what's really impressed me
is how Terry's become part of the Felcher family.
He fits right in here.
Surprise, kid!
Happy birthday!
Woo!
As profits increase, the margin reaches a second break-even point here,
after which enterprise falls into loss.
Any questions?
So now look at his video game counterpart.
Jack, plug in and see what you can find.
We cannot allow the Lumbers to pollute the surface.
We must bury their infection here.
The world is rightfully ours!
Delta Squad is in your house, bitch!
You hear that shit?
You grimy ass bitches are going down!
Like way down! Get it down!
Show down, you ain't gonna even know what's where, cop!
Your ass is gonna be clapped!
So yeah, that's enough of that.
So it's interesting, right?
So Cliff Bleszinski is quoted as saying,
those of you citing Cole as a bad stereotype, guys,
that's just Lester being Lester.
But if you look at the two characters,
in two minutes, Terry Tate is developed way more than Cole,
who took about three games to get to that point.
To get to anywhere plausible of not just being
a cartoonish black person.
When you look at Terry Tate, he is a part of office culture, throwing birthday parties.
He is valued as a team member for his intelligence, which can be seen by him performing presentations.
And yes, he tackles people because he has to uphold civility in an often apathetic and thoughtless office world,
which lacks basic decency most of the time.
he works because you wish you were him or you wish somebody like him was around. This is why
the comedy works. And this was also not the first version of the commercial. They aired one
during the Super Bowl which was a lot more tackle heavy. So obviously they thought about his
character and they wanted to develop him further. Whereas that's about two minutes to
develop his character. Whereas Cole took two games which is about saying waiting for two
full seasons of a TV show. It's like two ten hour games.
And so this kind of bleeds into like Luther with Key and Peel, Obama's anger translator.
Luther's job is to express the pent-up feelings of the president. He is less articulate and
jumping and shouting, but the skit these behaviors are about are not who he is as a person,
they are what he is paid to articulate. He is an actor playing an actor. This can be seen when
he either says something the president didn't mean to say,
or when he backs off of the actual president in real life.
This is why this skit works really well, because he's a
paid actor. And then they also went to the length of going in
real life to flip the situation. It's pretty interesting. So I
just want to, you know, speaking about specifics, this is
Clementine from the walking dead. This is her parents. She's
black. No question about it. I will be talking about this
later.
So give your character a world view,
give your character player world views,
that's really important because
it might seem kind of obvious,
but player characters world views
should be reflected by the world around them
without them having to speak for all people.
That's also very important.
This calls back to focusing on being specific.
Lincoln Clay, I like bits of Mafia 3, I think overall it's pretty decent, but I can't get over
the fact that he's very apolitical, and aside from a small handful of missions where he's like
real mad at really overt racism, like the KKK, he's very in the middle about his feelings. I
mean, I feel like he's basically John Cena.
His beliefs are hustle, loyalty, and respect, and he won't kill women.
Those are his only scruples in life.
And this is pretty weird because as a black man in the South in the 60s,
he seems he should be a lot angrier.
And the fact that he doesn't reminisce enough about, you know,
like being in the war that he was just transpired, he doesn't have PTSD.
It's like he forgot everything that's going on. He's essentially not a person. He's just a
shell of the players to use. He's the eventual black man who murders and feels no remorse,
which is a big problem. See, he has a good time, right? No PTSD here. Seemingly unbothered by
the current state of the U.S. mostly. And he's so happy when he's with these people. I
actually really wish there were more scenes about this because in this game they basically
This is what I would like to do in the game. That's all I want to do the whole time. And I
think that's what Lincoln, that should have been his first thing to do. Go kill all the KKK. But
the first thing he does is kill a bunch of black people, which is kind of weird. The thing is go
kill the Haitians. That's the mission.
which we heard about in another game a long time ago,
that seemed to spark controversy
and now it sparked zero controversy.
And it's kind of weird because the player doesn't ask
a goddamn question about this
because he's just a classic puppet
for the player to inhabit.
He's a shell of a black man.
And then there's the issue where his best friend, he's actually really interesting. I like this
dude a lot. But he's the classic white nihilist angry dude who's the driver of the story.
There's even like an extra after credits bit with him which is kind of interesting. He's
basically the main character. And that's really weird because if you're making a story about a
black dude and then you define him by a white guy, that's a little weird. Also, like...
And speaking about, like, I don't expect, like, Lincoln Clay to speak for all people.
That's not my issue with it.
My issue is that Luke Cage on Netflix stars a guy who a lot of people like, a lot of people
who watch the show like, but he's actually a pretty conservative dude and he's the hero. He
doesn't like young people's culture. He thinks they're uncivilized. He constantly critiques
people. A lot of people watching it would probably disagree with his political views, but
because he's a black dude who reflects bullets and can just fight the cops, people like him.
Method Man is a fan of him on the show and it's actually one of the most beautiful things
I've seen.
So speaking about this, we need more than two, more than two, not just two people in important
roles in a game of marginalized descent. Because one of the key things is we are not a monolith.
So there's this show, A Different World.
It was an amazing show.
It stars, it kind of stars over the time,
this guy Dwayne Wayne.
He actually starts in the first episode,
he's in the women's dorm room,
kind of just harassing all the women.
And it's not a good look,
but actually what happens five seconds after that,
he gets thrown out of the women's dorm room
and you don't see him for five episodes.
and the show switches to focus on a group of disparate black and white women and their problems.
And that's pretty interesting because the show for the whole, even though they open,
like the shot is actually Dwayne Wayne looking at the camera, talking to the camera,
and he's not the main character. And he's actually brought back to run for Mr. Tillman
in a lone man running in a beauty pageant, which...
Everyone tries to like, heckle him, and it's interesting because like, women are barking at him, whistling at him,
to basically pay him back for all of the sexist comments and behavior he's had, and he owns it,
and he says, I deserve that, but also we all need to look at each other because we should all stop doing this.
the show eventually shifts to him and he ends up, he's like a math whiz, he got a perfect score on
his SAT and he uses that as part of his pick up lines and he eventually graduates as top of the
class and becomes a game developer. Who knew?
So quick story. This is fast and furious series. This is Tej. He is a hacker and a technical
expert. He's been in the series up to eight now or whatever next year. I love the movies. He's
been doing it for a while. This is Roman Pierce. Roman Pierce represents toxic masculinity of
the group. He's also kind of a coward and everyone makes fun of him for it. The two of them
are very opposed and they along with everybody else have to go rescue a hacker named Ramsey.
No one knows who Ramsey is. We only know that they're on this bus. When they rescue Ramsey,
Ramsey is an attractive black woman. And Ludacris just falls in love. He's like, wow, you
hack, you're way better than me in everything. I just want to get to know you. And Tyrese just
wants to ogle her and is like, that's not what hackers look like. And Tej's response is, what
do hackers look like? So basically what we have ‑‑
is you have a very short, concise discussion with two black men that has checks and
balances and tackles the social norms of hackers and programs, what programmers are,
end scene. Stop murdering us to follow the plot.
for their plot. So this is watch dogs 2 which I think is interesting. It stars a black guy and
everyone wants to clap for it. I like Marcus. I think he's cool but who else is in this game?
We have dead mouse and cool lady on the side who is actually very cool. And then here's
another key art. We add green hoody dude. You know, a sign of greatness. Then we have Rob
zombie added to the group. And I kept hearing about this black person on the dead sec team.
Here he is. It's actually really hard to find key art for him because of a lot of things. He
exists basically to walk around in one mission with Marcus to allow him to have a
conversation about racism which is weird because him being used as a stand in to do this is
racist. And then he's dead.
immediately after talking about racism in tech, the only other
black person on the team is killed. His death doesn't
matter. His life didn't matter. He is a one dimensional
character basically there to be deus ex blackina. He is murdered
by this gang. This gang is a less than one dimensional
Mexican gang that is basically just there to be the bad Mexican
gang. Don't do that. You can't just write a black character and
then just throw every other minority under the bus.
So, but they really do build up this dude. They build up daft punk all the way. And, you know,
it's really weird because, like, he's not that interesting. Like, they just want you to, like,
he's a lonely dude, he's a hacker, he wears a mask. That's basically who he is, but they keep
putting him in missions. And it's like, why is he white? I don't know. Like, but they keep
putting you into these missions, so they probably should have just killed him. And
would have killed him, a guy you have been spending a lot of
time with, that would have been awesome. But what if they rewrote
him as being a Mexican guy who is also in tech and he is
talking to you and he is like man, I'm a brown person too.
That's really awesome. We are in tech and he likes this mask
because he is really big into lucha libre. And in lucha libre
you basically wear your mask until you die.
Then you kill that dude that you spent like 10 hours building up and you really care.
Instead of just killing the one dimensional black dude.
And then you bury him in his mask like you would a luchador.
Like El Santo who's on the left only showed his face once in public.
And it was right before he died.
Avoid defining your characters by trauma and oppression.
In story, I actually, this is a bit of a story about me.
I had this problem where I'm writing these characters
for the game and I'm trying to do something like
about New York and it deals with fights that come from
like wrong headed conversations occasionally
and I defined my characters in ways where I kind of made
the white characters symbols of gentrification
and the black characters and other brown characters
as symbols of hood mentality and that basically
split them up into like people of different economic statuses and social statuses and
That's really bad
and it's like if you define somebody by being poor or being harassed or being
Brown and the way people treat them then you're just robbing them of their agency and I was doing this and I finally sat down
And I basically took all the characters. I did a review of all of them. I compared them to each other
I compared them to the world that I expected them to be in which is fictional futurism
I decided to stop and change and go in a different direction. I kind of took parts from
everybody and made them all a little deeper. So getting deeper. I want to just bring up this
show, Amen. It's a very interesting show which is about a pastor in Philadelphia and he wants
to keep everything in his church firmly under his control.
And so we learn a lot from this intro. He just gets out of his car, plays double dutch, gives
everyone dap on the way in. And he's got swagger. And the interesting thing is he was actually
created by this dude on the right, Ed Weinberger. He's the only son of a Jewish butcher. They are
very different people.
He got his start writing jokes for the comedian Dick Gregory and he would tour with him during
the civil rights era so he kind of learned a lot.
And he basically says that working for Dick Gregory is why he is successful.
He has founded numerous shows, co-created numerous shows like Taxi.
And that's what I'm trying to say is that if you want to be great at what you're doing,
you basically have to
this guy would drive around this dude. This was his first job. He would do odd jobs for a
comedian who was way better than him to learn everything that he could. And then he went on to
write shows about black people and everybody else. And also, I don't want to go without
talking about Robert Townsend who is on the back, on the side. He made Hollywood Shuffle which
is an amazing movie about how black people are treated in media. So one more quiz.
There's a show about a bunch of friends. It's another urban sitcom. One of the friends could be
called quirky and some of the friends sleep with each other. This show was also very popular. Any
guesses? Living single. Not friends. Friends was based on living single. So I guess I don't
have much time so I'm going to just...
quickly. I actually have no time. So I'm just going to end on this. Don't stub in replacements.
MLK and Malcolm X are not the same as Charles Xavier and Magneto even though Marvel wants
to tell you that Magneto is based on Malcolm X because Magneto can throw an aircraft
carrier a thousand miles across the world and blow up an atomic bomb and Malcolm X just
wanted people to start treating black people right.
That was his endgame. If you think that this is equal to this, then you should stop writing.
Zootopia was a bad movie. It used animals to separate people but we're all the same animal.
If this conversation would be between two foxes, not a fox and a rabbit or two rabbits, we're not
separate. Black people aren't carnivores and white people aren't vegetarians. That's not the
way it works. And even the writer about it basically said that it was supposed to be this
nuanced thing and it's not nuanced at all. I kind of ran out of time. So thank you.
One last thing. All these women are black but they were all played by white people. Same
thing here. Neil Druckmann said it was totally cool. If someone at the top of a studio is
telling you it's totally cool to put people in digital blackface you need to take a stand
about it. You might have to quit. You might have to ‑‑
have to do something, you might have to put this person in their office on a different world.
They protested just because he was censored on radio. If you can do that, if they're college
students, you can protest somebody who's running your studio who just decides to dress someone
up in digital blackface. Thank you.