so stressed right now, please be gentle.
I mean, yeah.
So yeah, let's start this thingy of mine.
My name is Patryk, and now the difficult part,
which is Grzeszczuk.
And it's an issue every time I check in at a hotel
outside of Poland.
because I am from Poland.
Yeah, and I am a part of 11 Beat Studios.
It is a studio responsible for This War of Mine,
among the other titles.
And today I wanted to tell you a bit about This War of Mine,
but from a marketing perspective,
as I have a pleasure and an honor
of being a part of marketing team at our company.
But before I will get to the subject, I would love to start my presentation with a little twist.
So let's start with the results of what we have achieved.
This War of Mine, an amazing game.
I was a child, I was always wondering what happened to those people at war.
This War of Mine showed us the true face of the war.
In this War of Mine you can experience the many fates of affected victims in war.
We really feel the true meaning of being in war.
This War of Mine is a game I love playing.
Because it sets me in a vulnerable position that forces me to make hard choices.
It's not about suicide.
It's about how we survive.
Will you remain a human or you become an animal?
A game that will change your perspective
and make you appreciate that you live in a peaceful country.
Yeah, I'm gonna skip the rest of the video because it's not an important part.
So, this war of mine takes a special place in our hearts,
because we believe that it has allowed us to break through from kind of a niche.
space which is survival simulator thingy into the mainstream not only gaming wise but also
and maybe it's only our perception but we feel that right now we are in a we are a part of
kind of a mainstream culture but at the beginning
This War of Mine wasn't even about war.
It was a survival simulator, like post-apocalyptic survival
simulator, that took place in a shelter.
And actually, that was an internally used code name
for the game.
So it was shelter.
And while visually, as you can see, and even gameplay-wise,
to some degree, it was quite satisfying,
and we were happy about it, emotionally,
It just wasn't it, you know? We were looking for some...
solution to leverage the game, to bring it to the next level, but we were struggling. We didn't know
what exactly that should be that could allow us to make that happen until one point in which our CEO
Grzegorz shared an article with the whole team and the title of the article was One Year in Hell
and the article told the story about the longest siege of a city in modern warfare.
but written from a perspective of a civilian survivor actually living in that city at the time.
And once we read that article, we knew that this was it.
We could use it as a foundation and then build on it.
and then create something really meaningful.
So we started this widespread research.
We used books as a source of inspiration
and we used other articles and stories
told by our parents and grandparents
because in Poland we have some kind of an experience
when it comes to being a part of a conflict,
not only on the winning side.
But we also used modern news as a source of inspiration
because you do not actually have to look very far
to find new information about warfare and conflicts
and how those not only affect modern societies,
but also reshape modern societies.
So we used all of those bits and pieces.
to create a new version of the game, which you know right now as This War of Mine.
And it worked. It worked very well, at least for us.
To know that it works actually, you had to play it.
And our objective as a marketing team,
as a marketing department, was to convince people
that it is a meaningful experience,
long before they actually had a chance
to play the game on their own.
So we were looking for some way to communicate that,
to pass the message, and at the moment, at time,
War was a very popular theme when it comes to video games.
And actually, I think it's the same right now, right?
So war is a popular thing when it comes to video games.
But at the same time, my perception is,
and our perception was at the time,
that most of those...
war-themed, war-based games share similar point of view.
So you usually play as a strong protagonist,
hero, running, gunning, blazing,
so there is no empathy there.
There is no reflection, there are no emotions there.
like deeper emotions, let's call them like that.
So we decided to use that as a foundation for our campaign.
We decided that we want to tell people that we are different,
that we stand in opposition,
that we want to question the status quo,
if that makes sense.
So we use the duality of the world as a starting point for our communication.
So the shift of perspective, if you will, right?
So we wanted to tell people that there are two sides to every story.
And when it comes to the conflict, every conflict.
Every war happens at someone's doorstep.
And this War of Mine is a game that allows you to cross that doorstep
and to see what lies on the other side.
So that was the foundation for our communication strategy.
But English is not our first language, so we struggled.
with bringing that strategy to life and converting that,
translating that into action, putting that in motion,
if that makes sense.
Even when it comes to the title itself,
the first title was War of Mine.
And we were quite happy with it,
till the point in which one of our friends
from the United States asked us
if we actually had mines in our game.
So we were like, okay, we have to change something.
And we did.
And we ended up with This War of Mine.
Actually, Guns N' Roses and their Sweet Child O' Mine
helped a bit.
So, yeah, so This War of Mine, that was the final title,
and it is a final title for us, and it works.
And my perception is that it works because of two factors.
It stands out because it's a kind of an unusual structure,
but at the same time, it's very descriptive.
It tells you that it is a game about war,
but at the same time, it's a personal point of view.
It's something different.
It gives you the emotional layer of the game
because you've got subjectivity here, right?
And it was the same case when it comes to the claim.
We knew that we have to explain to people
what this war of mine actually was about.
So we came up with different claims,
with different sentences.
We wanted them to grasp the idea in a sleek, perfect manner.
So, but some of them were too long or too short.
too obvious or too complicated.
We ended up with the one that we liked the most
and it was in war, not everyone is a soldier.
And here you've got the same thing that you had in a title.
You've got the idea grasped in a short way
and quite obvious way.
So you know that it is about war,
but it is not about shooting, running, gunning.
It's about the shift of.
perspective. So when we had that foundation laid out, we knew that we have to define the identity
of the game. We have to explain what the features are, but not gameplay-wise, but emotionally,
if that makes sense.
So we wanted to tell people that this world of mine is serious, it's non-military,
which was very, very important for us, apolitical, insightful and human-centric.
And the apolitical part was especially important for us, because when you get into politics,
you can way too easily divide people, you can make people angry, and we didn't want to do that,
actually. What we wanted to do was to provide people with meaningful experience they could
relate to.
to no matter what their beliefs or political views were.
That was our goal.
That was our objective.
And we did that, and we wanted to
and had to maintain the coherency
every time we did something,
every time we launched new.
activity and it paid off a lot because right now every time you see This War of Mine
and not only the game itself but also key visuals, trailers, videos, whatever it is,
you know This War of Mine is This War of Mine. You can recognize the game.
That's because we were consistent and every time we...
told people something about this world of mine, it was the same way of telling the story,
a political way, human-centric way, kind of an insightful way. At least we want to.
believe that. But being coherent and being consistent means that sometimes you have to say
no, you have to say no to your community. And in our case it was also like that. A good example
is the zombie mode. People wanted us to prepare a zombie mode for the game and I can understand
that because this World of Mines seems like a perfect game for that. You've got the shelter,
you've got all the mechanics there, you've got people trying to survive, so all the bits and
pieces are there actually. But
While it could be quite entertaining to play that kind of a mode, we didn't want to do that because for us this War of Mine just wasn't the game that you should play in that kind of a way.
At the same time, internally, we played a bit with the game because when you deal with such an...
Tough subject, you have to release some steam at some point.
So we played with the color palette,
we had mutant rats at some point,
we had some additional elements,
but we never planned to release those elements.
That was just for an internal use,
but outside of the studio,
this world of mine was what it was and is what it is.
if that makes sense.
And what about the fun factor, you may ask,
because games should be fun, right?
Well, no, in my opinion,
because not every game has to be actually fun.
In the same manner, like, not every movie has to be fun,
and not every book has to be fun as well.
So our colleague from our studio, Paweł, who is a senior writer, and he was a senior writer at that point,
he explained that very well. He told in one of the interviews that we do not aim at the fun factor.
For us, it's all about the experience.
because the game should engage player
and the game should maintain the idea.
If the message is important and the gameplay is shallow,
that is devastating for the game,
such a game as this one of mine, at least.
So yeah, so that was the strategy.
That was our, and that was our approach.
But let's get to the media point
and to the touchpoint matrix.
So because of our budget limitations,
we had limited budget at that point.
We focused on digital communication, especially social media, PR related activities and event coverage.
Because that worked for us quite well.
And when it comes to digital communication, video trailers were very important for us.
Because right now, if you want to be efficient with your communication, you should use video.
a lot. Video is a thing right now, which is an obvious thing to say. So this is one of
the first trailers for This War of Mine. Maybe you have seen it.
you
So as you can see, bless you, as you can see we've got the same idea repeated over and over.
We are talking about the shift of perspective, we are talking about people, about their emotions,
their experience. Because please be aware of the fact that we had no track record at that point,
so people had to be aware, we had to build the credibility.
credibility for the game, we had to build the awareness.
I've got kind of an advertising background.
I come from an advertising agency,
bunch of those actually.
So I like those short videos very much.
I usually use those 30 seconds, 60 seconds, 90 seconds
videos, so those short bits that can tell you the story.
quite well, I would say, quite well.
But designing, writing scripts for those videos
and then producing those videos,
we keep in mind three, like, important,
very important, crucial even, rules
that we have to keep in mind
to just be efficient with what we do.
And those rules are,
Maintaining the idea and always closing the story.
So I know that games are very complex,
that you have so many elements that are good
and engaging and fun about your games.
But you should still maintain the focus
on the most important thing, on the premise of your game.
Everything should follow,
but the premise is the most important part.
The second thing is that you should keep the right pacing.
Even though.
those advertising videos, those trailers are quite short.
They still have this structure of a long story.
You've got this three to five act structure,
so you've got the introduction part,
you've got the tipping point and the resolution,
the punchline, if that makes sense.
And we are usually constructing our videos like that
because long story short, it works.
And the third part is the overarching narrative.
So we have defined a universe with our communication, a universe of this world of mine,
and we wanted every bit of content, no matter if it was video or key visual or an interview
or whatever it was, it had to fit that tonality of the game.
it had to fit all of those elements of the identity of the game, if that makes sense,
because that helped and that defined what this War of Mine really was.
really is. And usually when we think about game marketing, when we think about campaign, we think
short term, we focus on the launch window and that makes sense because this is the most important
period in your campaign because how well your game is doing in the launch video highly influences
the overall
result of your campaign and the overall success of your game, if you will.
But at the same time, supporting your game long-term and preparing and running this long-term campaign
can help a lot and can get you a long way.
So because of that, maintaining the relationship with our community in social media
is also a very important part of what we do.
we use social media and we perceive social media as a communication channel.
So we use paid media quite a bit, I would say, those paid posts and so on and so on.
But at the same time, social media as a channel is also a part of the universe of our game.
So we treat it in that manner as well. So we post all of those content bits that
could be interesting for those people who are very much into our game.
So, because of that, we treat social media as a part of the, let's call it, enhanced edition of the game.
So, if you like the experience, you can find additional bits and pieces of that experience in social media.
It's kind of a limited DVD, you know what I'm talking about.
So, yeah, and it works because...
Our community is very engaged and very active.
And we do not limit the activity of our community.
We value that part very much.
And right now we've got a board game happening
and we love the board game.
It's not our initiative,
but we support that initiative a lot.
We almost had an independent movie based on our game,
and for us it's okay, because we never perceived
This War of Mine as a beginning of the franchise.
We do not plan to make a sequel,
but at the same time, we like the fact...
that our community is active and co-creates the universe of this world of mine with us.
And we are happy about it. We do not limit the activities as I said before, but we do maintain
the coherency of the brand. So we have to make sure that every bit of the
content that is related to the game.
No matter if we are creating the content
or our gamers are, it should be in line
with the identity of the game, so everyone
would know that this World of Mine is what it is.
And it works for us, as I said, because people
seem to like the game, even though.
Yeah, even though it can be a struggle, it can be exhausting and sometimes it's even exhausting for me.
And we had and actually we have good media coverage, not only gaming wise, not only in gaming media,
but in let's call it mainstream media as well. And I strongly believe that we achieved that because
We are focusing on emotions, we are focusing on that mind premise and tech, gameplay, all of those
features as important as those are, those only follow and those support our communication,
but our communication is focused on the big idea, right?
And we won some awards and we had good sales.
And when it comes to sales,
I strongly believe that the first part,
meaning the sales within the launch windows,
those are mostly based...
on the fact if your campaign, if your marketing campaign is good or not.
But at the same time, long-term sales rely mostly on the quality of the game itself.
You can have an exceptional campaign, but if you have a mediocre game, you won't have good sales,
which is kind of an obvious thing, but my point is that your marketing campaign is an integral part of your game,
not something that is next to it or whatever.
You have to make it a coherent thing, and those elements...
should support each other very strongly.
And yeah, we learned a lot in the process,
not only designing, but running the campaign.
Early into the campaign,
just after we have released the trailer,
I played.
A while ago, Emir, a survivor from Sarajevo, reached us
and we were very happy about it because he told us
that he liked the game very much.
And we're like, okay, so it works.
So we are up to something.
This is it, we've got it.
So we invited him to share the stories.
He came to Poland, he came to Warsaw,
and together we have created a launch trailer for the game.
And that launch trailer combined his memoirs with our gameplay,
so we cooperated and we achieved a great result.
We love the trailer very much.
It's kind of a live action mix with gameplay.
You can Google it up because I don't have,
unfortunately, time right now to play all the bits.
but we were quite happy about it.
And the lesson here is that sometimes
those opportunities emerge.
And you have to push things forward
just to chase those opportunities and use them
because they can get you really, really far.
But at the same time, when it comes to the cooperation,
you will cooperate with some external partners,
some agencies, some video production houses and such.
And those cooperations can be good or bad,
or they can fall somewhere in between,
but you have to maintain,
no matter how much you trust your partner,
you should always, always maintain the art direction.
You should keep it under your control.
Because at the end of the day, it is your game.
And at the end of the day, it is your communication,
your campaign, and your results that you want to achieve.
And no one from outside of the company actually
can feel the matter of your game as well as you do.
So you should be the one making those decisions.
Because even if you have a poor partner,
if you have a good control over the art direction,
you will be just fine.
And yeah, and the piracy, which is a fun topic, isn't it?
So we encountered that problem at one point,
but we decided not to fight with the piracy
because we are not Metallica.
But instead of that, we decided to show some empathy.
So Karol, a colleague of mine from our team, he posted a message on Pirate Bay thanking,
actually thanking people for liking the game and for showing interest in our game.
He encouraged them to buy the game, but at the same time he told them, okay guys, I know that
for many reasons maybe you cannot buy the game, so I'm gonna share some Steam codes with you.
And PR-wise it was a very good move because
it didn't cost much, you know, it was, those were just few codes, but at the same time we have gained
good media coverage, we have gained good feedback from our gamers, from our players, but honestly...
while it was a PR move, at the same time it wasn't.
Because this is what we believe.
All the people that play your game
are part of your community.
And OK, maybe they didn't pay for your game,
but they can contribute in so many different ways.
They can.
give you good feedback. They can enhance your reach, the reach of your communication. They can
build awareness for your game. So maybe they won't give you their money, but their friends may,
or friends of their friends, and so on and so on and so on. So fighting with people, you will gain
nothing. You will lose energy, you will lose time, and you will lose money. But supporting each other
and maintaining good relations with your community, you can...
win something at the end of the day and probably you will.
And yeah, and last but not least,
because our game is about casualties of war
and the expansion pack titled The Little Ones
is about kids, it's about children during the time of war,
we decided to start the cooperation with War Child.
And that was amazing for us because
We not only helped a lot because we have gathered a significant amount of money for them,
but it allowed us to reach mainstream media once more.
But our learning was that no matter how good the initiative is,
no matter how good your idea for an activity, for an activation or a short campaign burst is,
Usually it's a one-shot and it was like that even in terms of our cooperation with War Child,
because it's a long-term cooperation, we are cooperating still, but even after we gathered
a significant amount of money, it was hard for us to gain interest of media once again.
So they covered the story once, but then it wasn't.
hip enough maybe. So I think that while maintaining coherency and consistency is crucial when it comes
to the efficient campaign, at the same time you should diversify your activities
and keep them fresh to maintain the hype simply.
Okay, so just to wrap things up,
as I have like three minutes more,
these are the key takeouts, at least from my perspective,
when it comes to this World of Mine and its campaign.
So first and foremost, we worked on our strategy
quite a lot, I would say.
We iterated and iterated.
We wanted to polish it.
as well as we could.
So working on your strategy as long as necessary is crucial,
but once you have it, you should stick to it
and use it as a foundation,
not only for the first part of the campaign
or the first trailer, launch trailer,
however you want to call it,
but for the whole thing, for the long-term activity.
Everything you do, everything you treat as a follow-up.
for the first hit should be in line with that strategy.
And start your marketing work early
in the development process, I would say,
because you should, at least we do,
but I think that you should as well
treat your marketing campaign as a part of your game.
It is the same universe.
It should be made from the ground up
in close cooperation with your dev team.
Make your media planning adequate.
I mean, of course, it is about reach,
it is about awareness,
and it is about feedback from your community,
if that makes sense.
But at the same time, the reach and awareness
and all of those factors are important
as long as you use them in the right channels.
Otherwise, it's just buzz.
You do not want to spend all the money to be on TV and on in the radio or whatever.
You want to be where you want to be.
Those specific channels in which your gamers, your gamers are.
Not some people, your gamers, your gamers are.
And while you should plan ahead, you should also be prepared for changes,
because our market is dynamic as hell.
Everything changes.
And you're going to have to adjust your campaign.
You're going to have to adjust your strategy.
This balance between keeping things as they should be and adjusting them on the go,
this is the perfect thing that you should grasp. And I am happy to tell you that I think that
we have grasped it and it worked for us a lot. And last but not least, good marketing is important,
but good game is a must. Because good marketing can build you kind of a foundation for the launch,
can build the hype.
but you have maintained the hype with your game
and maintained the hype with all the things that you do
around your game in the long run.
So yeah, so that is all from my side.
Thank you very much for your time.
It was a pleasure for me.