Good afternoon, everybody. Welcome to my talk.
I'm Toby Hines. I'm the lead character artist
at Sony London Studio.
Just before we get going, I just need to remind you
that you'll get an email about a quarter of an hour
after this talk, and if you could give any feedback,
that would be absolutely brilliant.
Okay, let's get going.
So, this talk is on the development of the characters
for Blood & Truth.
This is the new action shooter for PlayStation VR.
Bluntruth has been developed by Sony London Studio.
Our primary goal is to make groundbreaking VR games.
We released VR Worlds in August 2016.
This was conceived as a set of experiences
to introduce players to PlayStation VR.
Anybody played VR Worlds?
Good.
And did you play the London Heist?
Excellent.
The London Heist was by far the most popular of these games.
We were able to analyze data in the months after we released VR Worlds,
and it was twice as popular as the next most popular experience.
Now this might have been down to just people enjoying shooting things in VR,
but the feedback we got from playtests, reviews, social media and forums
told us that players found the character interactions really immersive and fun.
As you can see from this selection of quotes, the experience of having characters stood
before you in VR and interacting with them is very powerful.
Simple things like a character handing you a cell phone and being able to take it out
of their hands have real impact in VR because you're in the same virtual world as them and
you're physically performing these tasks.
So to take these learnings from the London Heist and have them form the pillars.
of our next game became the main driving force behind Blood and Truth.
How far could we push the envelope on character interaction and player immersion?
This generation of VR is still finding out what works and what doesn't work.
But there are already a lot of rules and commandments about what you should and shouldn't do
that have been put forward by various people.
Two of the big ones relating to characters have traditionally been
realistic characters don't translate well in VR
and players don't like their avatar to depict someone else.
Let's start with realistic characters.
The consensus being, making believable characters risks straying into uncanny valley, unsettling
players and ruining the immersive experience.
To avoid this for the London heist, we had stylized characters.
Now that worked for that tone of experience which was larger than life and over the top,
but we didn't want that style to become set in stone.
And once we'd finished VR Worlds, we knew we wanted a grittier, more serious tone for
the next project.
So we were keen to investigate more realistic characters.
We felt they could work in VR, we just needed the right conditions.
And making highly realistic game characters is very subjective.
People are hardwired to judge virtual humans
with every ounce of scrutiny evolution has given us.
And in VR, players are naturally even more critical
of realistic characters,
because we're essentially fooling them
that we inhabit the same world,
and there's no filter.
Added to this, the higher frame rate
we have to maintain for VR
means we can't use the same game memory budgets
reserved for regular console characters.
But what if the solution actually lay in the advantages we have in VR?
If we could create characters realistic and compelling enough to be believable and immerse
the player through their interactions with them, they'd be less inclined to...
And if we gave the player the starring role in the story and missions,
so they were never a detached observer,
again the focus would be on the unfolding drama
rather than whether the eye shader or skin shader was absolutely perfect.
With this approach we felt confident about exploring more realistic characters.
Now the second rule, players don't allow their avatar
to depict someone else.
The theory being that a VR experience will be spoiled
if a human avatar is a different gender or race to yourself.
To avoid this, there should be no determiner
of race or gender visible on the avatars.
This is why the player wore leather gloves
throughout the London heist,
but we ended up with weird situations
like sitting in a pub wearing leather gloves,
which is a bit odd even on a cold day.
Now this makes sense.
If the premise of your game is you're meant to be you
experiencing something amazing or magical,
but for a game like Blood & Truth,
where you're a James Bond, John Wick style hero,
escapism and role-playing is the whole premise.
Arkham VR, for example, is cool
because you get to be Batman.
I'd already mentioned giving the player
the starring role to immerse them.
Blood & Truth's key pillar is be the action hero.
So we are very focused on convincing people
they are this person and letting them revel in it.
So it seemed natural to have the hands of our hero
represented in the avatar.
The most important thing for us was the player
gets to feel they are Ryan Marks, SAS soldier,
embroiled in London's criminal underworld.
Scanning and photogrammetry.
Making realistic game characters
is challenging and time consuming.
More and more developers are utilizing photogrammetry
and 3D scanning to do this with impressive results.
And when it came to making realistic characters of Blood and Truth,
we thought it would be great to cast, costume, and scan real actors to play the key characters.
Essentially create digital doubles and use these same actors for the mocap sessions.
The game is set in modern day London, so we could easily cast suitable actors and buy appropriate costumes.
As an initial test of Blood & Truth, we downloaded free photogrammetry humans from the web and
reviewed them in the PSVR headset to see if they held up to scrutiny.
This enabled us to see highly realistic characters in VR without spending months making full
characters.
They actually read really well, which was great.
Problem was, we're a central London studio with limited space, so it was impossible to
build and maintain a permanent photogrammetry capture stage on site.
So we decided instead to look at handheld 3D scanners.
These could be used straight out of the box.
We'd simply book a meeting room with suitable lighting
and get scanning.
So I did some research and organized a demo at the studio
with Artec scanners.
The character team and I scanned a bunch of clothes
and heads so we could assess the detail
that we could capture.
We also scanned some poses for clothing deformation.
The results were really encouraging,
so I did a pitch for our leadership team,
and on the back of that we were able to buy an Artec Eva
and a Spyder scanner.
Now we moved into pre-production
and began looking at R&D and workflow.
We did some tests to simulate deformation on clothing.
The idea was we'd scan people in various poses,
capture the changes in folds,
and use these in game to make the clothing
look more realistic.
Here's a video of the first test we made,
using normal map blends and mesh blend shapes.
So there's no cloth sim going on here,
it's all blend shapes and normal map blending.
The next step was to create
a full benchmark character model.
We scanned me in a suit, not for my dashing good looks,
but it was a good test to see
if we could create an accurate digital double.
From this, we created a fully textured and rigged character.
We reviewed it in the headset again, and it looked great,
the first real validation of the process we were taking.
It also served to define mesh and texture budgets
and timings on how long these characters would take to make.
Then I wrote a detailed production guide
going through the workflow from start to finish.
This guide was then adopted and added to
by the character team, and we could send it out
to Outsource as we brought them on board.
Initially we planned to handle facial rigs and blend shapes in-house,
and we worked with the animation and the rigging teams on initial tests.
We were getting some really good results, but it soon became clear this was going to be a monumental task
to get the level of quality we wanted for all our key characters.
This led us to seek a third-party vendor who specialized in this field to partner with us.
What the facial test did achieve though,
was a good base head mesh and UVs,
which was low poly enough for our budgets,
but still looked really good in the headset.
We could get a third party vendor to adopt this,
for our, adopt this topology for all our key characters,
sorry, for all our characters.
Character tiers.
Before production, we decided to split the character
into two tiers based on their level of fidelity.
Tier one was for key characters with speaking roles
who the player would interact with in drama scenes.
Tier two were for characters the player
would encounter during missions.
Let's talk about tier two first.
These were mostly male NPCs split into different factions,
such as the Street Gang and the Militia Fighters.
Each faction had four to five gameplay classes within them
with names like Heavy and Maniac.
We received concept art to use as character look guides
and briefs from design on the role of each gameplay cast,
which also needed to inform their look.
These are some of the Street Gang concepts.
They occupy a derelict tower block in the game
where you have to infiltrate
and rescue one of the key characters.
And this is the private security faction.
These are highly trained soldiers you encounter later in the game.
We decided the best way to get as much variety as possible
was to create these characters using a modular system.
So upper, lower bodies and heads and headgear and hair
could be interchanged to create many NPCs from relatively few pieces.
We hired a costume buyer to source clothing to match the concepts
and use some of our own.
You may notice this turn up later on.
I sourced and purchased the military gear
from various websites, mostly Airsoft ones.
And I contacted companies such as Bates Footwear,
Crye Precision, and Mechanics to license army boots,
clothing, and gloves to add more authenticity
to the private security faction.
And we licensed this awesome Ronin ballistic helmet
from DevTac in Japan.
We also brought a full set of riot armor.
I tried to order this from China originally, but I discovered I needed a government permit
to do so.
I was about to give up when I found a place in the UK that had a set for sale.
It's very cool.
All the tier 2 clothes were scanned in the studio with the Artex.
They were adjusted to fit a single scan body to use as a kind of mannequin to dress with
the scans.
We processed the scans in Artex Studio and then in ZBrush we adjusted them to fit over
the male body exactly.
and then began cleaning them up.
I could do an entire presentation
on just scan clean-up best practices,
but I won't bore you with that right now.
With this method, we could use the same rig
for all the Tier 2 characters.
We also had a pool of female assets
created as well for pets and civilians
that also were fitted to a single body and rig.
For the tier two heads, we scanned some of our team
with the RTX, basically anybody we could find
who looked intimidating, and we brought some scanned heads
from the 1024 web store to add some further diversity.
We ran these heads through our pipeline,
so they all used our base head topology and UVs.
We handled the facial rig for tier two characters in-house,
because we only needed it to be fairly basic
for barks and eye tracking.
Here are some Maya grabs of some of the finished tier two modular parts.
So this is a couple of the street gang upper bodies.
And here's a couple of the private security pieces as well.
We later added some accessories to the drop leg character on that guy so he could carry
brass bags or shotgun bandoliers to add a bit more variety.
Tier two characters came in between 30 and 40,000 tries.
Our creative services department made logos and designs
to add color and believability to the clothing
of the tier two characters.
Now, tier one.
As I said before, tier one were key characters
with speaking and dramatic scene roles.
We received concept art and biography to use as guides.
The next stage was auditioning and casting actors.
Once cast, we got their measurements,
brought costumes, and got them in for fittings.
Unlike the tier two characters,
they would be exact digital doubles,
so their bodies and rigs were unique.
After searching for a suitable vendor
to create the tier one character heads,
facial rigs and blend shapes,
we chose 3Lateral in Serbia.
They adopted our head topology
and were pleasantly surprised how well it held up,
and we were really pleased with the results.
Here are some of the heads
before we added hair, makeup, et cetera.
James Arntzer, our lead tech artist,
wrote some cool eye and skin shaders and lighting tweaks,
such as being able to procedurally generate shadows
from eyelids and using bent normal maps
to remove lighting artifacts.
The first step of Tier 1 was to scan the actors in yoga gear
or tight-fitting clothing at the studio
while doing the wardrobe fitting.
We create a base body for each actor in the rig pose,
much as we did for the Tier 1 characters and females.
Male and female bodies, sorry.
This base body was then used as a ref model
to dress with the clothing scans.
And it also worked as a representative placeholder
for animation to use for mocap previews.
Originally, we were gonna scan the tier one characters
in costume at the studio,
but as we were taking them over to 3Lateral
to do head scans,
we decided to scan their clothing over there too.
The main reason for this
was for the clothing deformation scans
I spoke about earlier.
We'd scan actors in a rig pose that matches the base body
and then a set of poses to capture clothing deformations
for fold to then create fold and crease normal map
blends and blend shapes.
We decided on a small set of poses
based on the most regular movements and deformations
we were likely to see in the game.
Some of these poses are hard to maintain
while capturing with handheld scanners,
so using three-lateralist photogrammetry's capture stage
made a lot of sense.
Let's talk about hair.
Getting hair to look good in the headset is a challenge.
Alpha is very expensive, and polycards can get very heavy
geometry-wise.
And the headset resolution can cause scintillation or shimmer
on hair, which can be distracting to players.
Luckily, tier two haircuts lend themselves to being non-alpha,
as the hair was either gel-backed, partly
shaved, or crew cut.
For the Tier 1 hair, we created a wig mesh with no alpha on it
that would define the big volumes of hair,
and then we clad this with alpha cards.
Again, James wrote some cool shaders
that blend card intersections
and would offset hair strands to simulate depth.
He also worked with the graphics programmers on techniques
to minimize any scintillation or shimmering.
Here are some examples of the finished Tier 1 characters
taken straight from the engine.
This is Michelle, who's your adopted sister in the game,
played by Clarissa Clayton.
This is Deacon, who's your SAS buddy,
played by Brian Larkin.
And this is Nick, your brother,
played by Jay Taylor, wearing a familiar leather jacket.
And this is Tony, the ruthless head
of the rival Sharp firm, played by Stephen Hartley.
Tier one characters came in between 40 and 50,000 tries.
And here's an example of one of the finished clothing deformations.
This is one of the characters' t-shirts, and this is how it looks in motion.
VR offers unique challenges, but also unique opportunities.
In VR, the player is the camera, and by that definition,
free to look at whatever they like.
I spoke earlier about trying to keep the players focused
on their role in the story.
But with the free camera, it does give us opportunities
to put nice details on characters
that hopefully players will notice.
The avatar, for example, the avatar hands, for example,
are something we expect players to scrutinize.
So.
If you hold them up and flex your fingers,
you'll see wrinkle maps and mesh blend shapes changing,
so knuckles and tendons appear on the skin
and the skin wrinkles realistically.
We also created blood flow maps
to simulate color changes in the skin.
So for example, the knuckles whiten
when the hand is drawn into a fist.
Adding details on characters are also great storytelling devices, especially in VR.
Easter eggs that allude or give hints to the history or backstory of a character.
Adding details, players that will hopefully notice and wonder about their meaning or significance.
Here are some examples on the Tier 1 characters.
Kayla, who's one of the main adversaries in the game, has this skull and flag motif
on her leather jacket and these war-like biblical quotes tattooed on her arms.
This alludes to her covert US military past and her somewhat precarious state of mind.
Deacon, your SAS buddy, has these tattoos on his arms.
Members of the SAS sometimes have tattoos
of the regiments they were recruited from.
In Deacon's case, the Royal Marine Commandos
with this dagger design,
and the Latin motto, Acta Non Verba.
How's everybody's Latin?
Does anybody know what that means?
Actions, not words, which is a very Deacon-like trait.
And on his left arm, he has the flag of St. Andrew
as the actor who plays him is a very proud Scotsman.
When we first meet Deacon, he has injuries from being interrogated.
When you're reunited with him later in the game, we wanted to give the player some idea
of the passage of time, so his injuries have only partially healed.
The bruises are a deeper color, and he has steri-strips on some of the bigger cuts.
We wanted to give Michelle a sleeve tattoo.
We found out the actress, Clarissa, who plays Michelle, has Filipino ancestry, so we did
a traditional tribal tattoo.
And your brother Nick wears this silver ring,
and you're given it later in the game.
And if you hold it up closely,
you'll see it has blood and truth inscribed in Latin
on the circumference.
We work with the tech and tools team
to create a character assembler and viewer
that runs in our editor.
We can load various tier two modular parts
and build a character from those.
And we can pick colors and change the roughness on clothing.
using RGB masks exported from Substance Painter.
We can also change the build of characters
to make them thinner or more muscular.
These characters can then be saved as prefabs
for the designers to use.
And we can also use this character, sorry.
We can also use this viewer to review characters in VR.
The headset is key to getting assets signed off
with the art director, animators, and designers.
There's a really nice tactile quality
to reviewing characters in VR.
It really feels like you could reach out and touch them.
And being able to lean in and check out details
is really cool.
Thanks for your time, everybody.
I hope that's given you some insight
into Blood & Truth's characters.
Before questions, I just wanna show you
a bit of footage from the game.
So you're the first people outside of the studio
to see this.
And just to warn you, there's a bit of strong language, so brace yourself.
Make sure they're looked after.
That American bird.
What do we know?
She's military.
Professional.
No wonder you shit yourself.
Yeah, you're not wrong.
No one knows anything about her.
It's weird. You can't...
Hold on.
Go ahead.
We need to talk about what we do next.
Give him a slap in terms of fucking behave.
He's just trying it on because Dad's gone.
No, he's gone way too far for that.
He's not gonna start an all-out war. He's not big enough.
Well, he clearly thinks he is big enough.
We need to push back hard or we're finished.
Tony's gotta go.
Got it. Thanks.
We know where Tony's gonna be tonight.
Private party at his casino.
Great. He might as well be on fucking Mars.
Yeah, he'll be surrounded by his best people.
Then the last thing he'll expect is me turning up.
No way, Ryan. You are keeping well out of this.
It could work.
No, it's madness.
Could you do it? I can do it.
Did you hear what I just said? You are not getting involved.
But I'm already involved.
I could be in and out of there before anyone knows what's happened.
I deal with situations and people a lot heavier than Tony Sharp.
Ryan's right.
What the fuck are you thinking?
Tony won't stop here. We know that.
Mum, Ryan's trained for this.
Anyone else, you wouldn't think twice.
But it isn't anyone else, is it, Nicholas? It's your brother.
Okay, okay, fine.
At least we know where Tony will be tonight.
We can keep an eye where he goes afterwards and then pick on Mumin.
Why risk waiting?
If we've got a chance to take him down, we should do it.
Alright.
But the first sign of trouble, Ryan, we get you out of there.
Of course.
What weapons we got?
Let's have a look.
So it goes without saying, thank you.
It goes without saying that needs to be experienced in VR,
but even that moment where the characters are talking amongst themselves
and then you speak and everybody just turns to look at you
when you're in the headset, it's a real kind of,
whoo.
And this attention is suddenly on you,
and you are suddenly just brought into it.
So yeah, I'm really looking forward to you guys playing it.
If you have any questions, please step up to the mic.
Got some t-shirts here.
If anybody wants to ask a question, you can grab a t-shirt.
Thank you, everybody.
My own here, yeah. Not only for the t-shirt, I promise, but I stepped in just a few minutes late, so I apologize if this was addressed.
But in London Heist for PSVR Worlds, those characters were already, especially for the time, really impressively detailed.
Were you using any of the scanning approaches for those characters back then, or is this an entirely new pipeline?
Entirely new pipeline. Yeah, yeah. The London Heist ones were.
I mean, you know, we'd be doing high detail sculpts in Zbrush,
but it was all from scratch.
So this was a, I'd used photogrammetry
at a previous studio when I was working on Formula 1
to do Formula 1 drivers,
but this was doing it for all characters.
So yeah, it was a new pipeline altogether.
Gotcha. And then for the scene that we saw at the end there,
was that motion captured?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, absolutely.
Awesome. And then for the purpose of just going into this
obviously more complicated approach,
do you think this is uniquely kind of key for VR
because of the immersion and how close you are?
Or is this just more generally
kind of the future of all game production, would you say?
I'd like to think what we're doing is going to be a step forward than that
until you try it.
But when people do try it, it is...
You know, the feedback we get from people trying it,
it's really immersive and it feels like a step forward.
So not only the drama scenes, but the missions as well.
So yeah, I'm excited about it.
So I hope we're pushing the medium forward.
Great. And sorry, just one last quick one.
So for the last scene was that it was motion capture,
but were they simultaneously acted or individually?
Yeah, they were acting together
and it was facial capture as well.
Cool. Thank you.
Hello, I'm curious when you're dealing with a conversations dialogue between the playable
character and the NPCs, do you encounter any lessons or non-obvious lessons when the playable
character speaks, how does the player feel like it's their body doing the talking and
not just some other specter in the room?
It's a good question. It's one we thought about a lot, whether to make the character a kind of silent Gordon Freeman or whether to actually give him a voice.
And I think to reinforce that idea that you're playing this person and to make the player think they are Ryan Marks, it felt natural to have his voice because then you are, you know, to us it feels like we're...
making the player this person.
You have the role-playing side of it, which I spoke about.
Is his voice the first voice you hear in the game
to like familiarize the player with like,
oh, when you hear that voice, that's you?
Or do you hear a lot of other people talk for a while
and then just his voice comes up?
Or do people just understand
and there isn't really any necessary special considerations?
I think there's one voice before you.
Which is a chap called Carson who's basically in a kind of interview with you and recapping events.
So he comes in, introduces himself and then you get to speak.
So yeah, that's that's the first time you hear your own voice.
Thank you.
Okay.
So, real quick question is the voice of the main character, is that modulated in any way to like,
because people's voice when they actually talk sounds different in their, when it's in their head,
if that makes sense? So do you, do you modulate the voice at all for the main character to kind of
like, you know, change it ever so slightly so it sounds like it's...
I'd have to get one of our audio guys in here. I imagine they're...
I nearly pushed the whole lectern off here.
It's not actually attached to the stage.
So that would have been a brilliant way to finish.
Very rock and roll.
Yeah, you'd have to ask our audio team.
Their attention to detail always blows me away.
So they may well be doing, how do you hear your own voice
in your head?
I know certainly when I hear this back, I'll probably go,
oh, I sound weird.
But yeah, they might well be doing that.
But I haven't got an answer for you, I'm afraid.
Thank you, sir.
Anyone else?
Well, thank you everybody.
Cheers.