Hi everyone, welcome to the GDC Twitch channel.
My name is Bryant Francis, I am here again.
Back after, I guess we've been away for at least a month, sorry about that.
We are here today playing Slay the Spire.
You probably know about this game.
It's sold only a couple million copies and it's topped the Steam charts consistently.
It's been around for the last couple years.
I think it released in Early Access in 2017.
But this year we are streaming it.
Hey, you know, it's a good game. We like streaming good games.
We like talking to the devs behind those games.
But also, we are streaming it because this game has been nominated at the 2020 IGF Awards,
which will take place at this year's Game Developers Conference.
The date will be March 18th, 2020.
You can see in the upper left-hand corner, this year's GDC dates.
In the lower left-hand corner of the screen, I am joined by Casey Yano.
Hello.
Casey, how you doing?
I'm doing great, thanks.
Uh, as far as I know it's pronounced Shamus, but it's written like Sumas?
Um, if I get in trouble for that, oh well, that's on me.
But every year I've been, you know, going to these awards for the last few years,
and I hear it pronounced Shamus.
Um, and you've also been nominated for the IGF Award for Excellence in Design,
which, as far as that design goes, we are seeing it on screen right now.
For those of you who don't know, Slay the Spire is a roguelike deck building game where you take this hero on a roguelike adventure
using cards that you acquire through your adventure to build your deck and create unique strategies that change on every run.
Just looking over a chat real quick, I can give a quick shoutout to VVSPA who says,
Yo Casey, so I think that's a friend of yours, I hope it's a friend of yours.
Oh yeah, definitely, I know them very well.
For the folks in chat, we want to hear from you as we talk with Casey today.
We are taking your questions, we are going to be chatting about how Slay of the Spire got made,
and you will have the opportunity to just put them in chat, I'll grab them, and we will talk to Casey about what you want to know.
Casey, like I said, Slay the Spire has been out for a little bit,
and this is the first year you all were nominated for an IGF award.
I guess, how does it feel? How does it feel to be nominated by, you know, your fellow developers?
Or, I guess you submit yourself, I guess developers submit themselves.
How does it feel? How does it feel to be chosen for this nomination?
Oh, I mean, it's very exciting.
I mean, I think IGF was like, maybe one of the first award shows that I was like, kind of like, aware of.
That's kind of how I discovered a bunch of indie games.
Because it was, you know, indie game centric, right?
Um, and so in that same vein, I was kind of like,
like, wow, like, it's like, it's like the independent one.
I guess because I'm making an indie game,
it means to me that it's like,
a nomination for an indie game versus,
um, like, just games in general.
Now Slay the Spire has been out, uh,
it was going through Steam Early Access since, uh, 2017,
but it was nominated this year because you all, like,
officially released the game, right?
Yeah, I think we also just forgot to submit it the year before.
Yeah.
I do remember reading the guidelines saying that you are able to submit a game even if it's not,
um, like, complete-complete, but like playable all the way from start to finish.
Um, but I just, I guess we just missed the deadline, I think, uh...
Early Access is pretty hectic, I think. At least for our schedule.
Yeah. We can dive into Early Access. I guess, like I said, this is kind of an interesting
situation because you all have been out for a while. But I guess, let's go back to the
days of Steam Early Access. Why did you go with Early Access and not kind of just decide,
hey, we're going to release, we're going to work on this until it's done and then release it?
I would say that there was like...
a very large potential amount of features that we could have added to the game, but
it's also like, how much, how, is it worth it to add all of these extra features?
And so we were like, maybe we can get, you know, we can gauge how popular the game is,
and if it does well, we'll add some of these extra features and more content, and if not,
maybe we can cut it a bit short, and then, you know, we'll call it a day.
The project.
So I guess that's kind of why we released the game.
with two of the characters complete out of three that we were initially planning on and that way we
could have been able to be like oh like this is working on two and then we're gonna finish the
third one and then once we're content complete you know it's like then we'll just say like this
is it like this is good like like people will maybe be happy that we make another game instead
of like adding more on you know a game that maybe you know wasn't really popular but
Wow, these are a lot different.
That process was, it was a lot of work.
Mostly it was a huge scramble in the beginning, mainly because we had, what was it?
We were missing localization.
I guess it depends on how early we're talking about.
In the very, very beginning, we were just kind of like making hotfixes, and then we
were like playing around with balance very quietly.
And then we were like, what are we supposed to do once we're out of early access?
And so we looked at a bunch of other games, and then we were looking at our pace based
on how much players we had, which I think in the first week or so we had about maybe
like 2,000 to 5,000 players, which I don't know if it was a lot or not.
But at our Discord, we had a Discord server, and we had maybe like five active people.
And so we were like, hey, we're going to update the game.
We're just going to update it whenever, whatever.
And that was going to be great because...
It's just a very casual exchange between updating the game and then people telling us what they think.
Like a very small handful of people telling us what they think about it.
And then we're like, oh, maybe we'll work on those things.
And that's actually what we did before Early Access as well.
Like, just like we had a private channel, we had our friends, and then they would give us feedback.
And then we would just make those changes.
And so we would update almost every day when it was private.
And so when we hit Early Access, we were like, oh, we'll just update once a week.
And so we just decided that it would be like this one week update release cadence.
And then it got bigger and then the bigger it got, the harder it got to do the one week release.
Because there was just so much more bugs to filter through, so much more feedback to filter through.
And I guess that's kind of like the strange momentum that we rode throughout almost all of Early Access.
That's so interesting. I'm guessing, and it sounds like that was the case, because with more people giving feedback, you just found more things that you needed to work on and that just stretched out the time between updates.
We actually kept up with the weekly updates for a very, very long time. It was too much. But now it's kind of done. Kind of.
I'm going to swing over to my question pile.
How do you think, I'm going to ask one more question about Early Access before I move on.
How do you think Early Access, like it's, you know, Early Access is sort of an interesting
feature because it helps developers, like I said, build that audience, start getting
feedback on their game early, and sort of solve problems in a different way that they
couldn't solve if they were just trying to release a finished product.
But how do you think that going through Steam Early Access influenced your creative vision
and your design for the game?
Because Slay the Spire is this really cool, like, the deck building approach, the cost, the way these mechanics sort of loop together.
Obviously, there's some of these ideas, the ones you had at the start, but like, what do you think came out of your community-focused design approach that comes with Early Access?
Hmm. Let's see. That's a good question.
I think definitely it shaped our content design.
I think we shipped not with 75 cards, but like 70 or so, and we were just like adding a few or reworking a bunch.
and you kind of start to get a feel for what kind of things are popular or not popular.
I mean to this to this day I think some of the cards may not be the most popular,
but at least like you'll be able to know what is and is not over time and then of course
at least we collect data not like I think we have like checkbox but we have gameplay data
that's uploaded and then we can make balance changes very quickly and we can kind of test
out a bunch of other like strange things.
I think when we started working on the game, it was kind of more on the serious side.
And then I started adding kind of like strange jokes and like very bizarre creatures.
Those were like very positive.
But we also didn't want to like go overboard.
It's like a very jokey game.
I mean, depending on who you ask, it is or is not like super jokey.
So we kind of have like this very serious facade, but like there's all this weird stuff
that happens in the game.
Because I don't know.
That's just kind of what we.
figure out works for us and our game.
Um, and maybe it has to do with the art style.
Maybe it has to do with my strange writing in the game.
Maybe we should have hired a writer, but so I guess those kinds of
things are heavily influenced.
Um, choices that didn't feel meaningful.
You know, we kind of try to update and I guess, yeah, we uploaded
and updated a bunch of things.
Yeah.
And we just have more and more questions when people play.
And questions people have.
The more we even change up, like, what kind of metrics we gather,
so we can make meaningful changes.
A very good example is, like, when people pick a card, we know...
So we get information on what cards people chose over what other cards they chose.
That way we can gauge, like, a preference of what card they choose.
And this is sorted on, like, difficulty, and, like, where in the game you are.
Um, and so we have that kind of information on top of like the win rate.
And so every card kind of has like, like a, how fun is it value?
And like, good, is it value?
And we try to, I think we have realized that a perfectly balanced game may not
actually be like the funnest of games to play.
And so I guess that's like one, one thing out of all the.
Yeah, what's a good example of a card in Sleight of the Spire that is really good but not really fun, or really fun but not really good?
I guess I'm curious, like, what kind of examples you've encountered.
I see. We have a lot of straightforward defense cards.
And I think there are definitely personalities where people just want to, like, just, like, increase your numbers exponentially.
So there are cards that will, like, double, like, your strength, which is a very basic example of, like, a card that's, like,
that looks like it has a lot of potential, but if you don't understand the game fully,
a card for instance that will double or slowly ramp up your strength throughout a whole combat
is actually, to balance this, they have very high costs.
And I think a lot of new players choose them without consequence, and they end up dying
pretty frequently.
But those are high potential cards that people love, whereas more simple cards like game
block drop, oh we just saw it, I think you just chose it in the stream here, just shrug
it off.
It's like your game block, your draw card.
And it's very hard to see why that's useful
if you haven't played too many deck building games.
It's like pretty boring, but also very core.
If everything is wacky, nothing really comes together.
So the cards that are a base are generally not popular at first,
but I think people start to understand how to play the game pretty well.
And then they see the value.
And seeing that value is so fun!
It's like learning the game!
Oh my god, actually, Shrug It Off, funny you mentioned it, we're gonna see in this run that we're doing.
Shrug It Off became one of my favorite cards, uh, because I would mix, um, Shrug It Off with, uh, Body Slam.
I upgraded Body Slam to be zero, to cost zero, and the combo would be Shrug It Off, Body Slam, uh...
Which would just cycle through it both kept my armor up and you know, let me kill really quickly, which I was so
I just was playing this yesterday and I was like, oh, I'm in trouble like I'm sucked in
Let's see, um
moving on to
Another design question. I have I'm really fascinated by how this game uses punishment and curses because I hit a point yesterday where
Whenever the game would present me like, like we just saw the Golden Idol opportunity, you know, uh, take this, get a relic, gain a curse, um,
there was a brief moment where I, you know, was trying to weigh the cost-benefit and then
midway through the run I began to realize
um, curses may
make it
Harder to do, like you can see the injury that just pops up right now.
Curses make those moments harder, but overall engaging with them makes a run more fun.
That was sort of a decision I realized yesterday.
I basically said yes to every curse that came my way because whatever positive thing came with it invariably helped me out.
What was kind of your, I thought that was a little bit different than how roguelikes handle this sort of thing.
Could you explain your design thought on those kind of negative, you know, those negative trade-offs?
Oh, like negative trade offs for games?
Yeah.
And rogue links, I guess?
Yeah, when we're in this game, yeah.
I think we mostly want decisions to be based on, like, what is your current situation?
Mhm.
Versus, like, something that is good and you get something bad.
Why I say that is because you can make a deck that is very resilient to curses.
There's like an obvious example where if there's a relic that gives you strength, if you have curses.
But I'm not gonna use that example.
But because it's a deck-building game, if you're making a very, very large deck, like you're just getting a lot of cards,
if you think a lot about it, the strikes and defends are kind of like curses in and of themselves,
because they're kind of low-value cards, and that's on purpose because we want to encourage people to try out new cards
so they can discover more of the intricate mechanics of the game.
And curses are kind of like in that same vein, in that like, you're like, oh, this curse gives you vulnerable, but there's a relic that can make you.
You know, maybe not vulnerable.
Or there's a curse.
You know, like, the curse doesn't matter too much if you're drawing a lot of cards.
And in the end, you know, if you draw five cards, but if you draw two of them as curses,
that's like, your opportunity in that one turn is so terrible, right?
You pretty much, since the average cost of a card is generally like one or one point, you know,
slightly higher than one, like, you're just, you're chosen to just play three of those cards that you drew.
And that's like, really bad.
And so I guess in that way, we noticed that most of the curses, at first we had some other
negative traits like losing max HP or losing gold or some other random stuff.
But I think in general we discovered that negative things that you can interact with
and have control over, especially cards.
So I guess curses in that way are a good example.
Some people still don't like them, that's fine, you know.
Maybe there'll be another better solution.
That's a really good answer.
Moving on to another part of the game's design.
This fight was really interesting because the way the attack curse swap off here worked.
I sort of felt in these days that slip into my deck, I was so fascinated by how...
Like the 2-1 alternate here, you know, two cursors, one attacker, and then two attackers, one cursor.
Something about that just, like, made this fight really hard to think through,
especially as it added more of those exhausts to my deck.
Going to kind of a broader level about design in the metagame with the map, I've got the
interview up that a friend of GDC, a friend of Gamasutra, Joel Couture did with your partner
Anthony Giovannetti.
Cool, I got the name right.
We got his interview with Anthony here and he talks about how the map that the player uses to navigate the quote-unquote spire
was inspired by FTL and how it was valuable to have
layered decision-making to add an element of risk-reward.
Could you talk about the map process from your end and what you sort of thought worked really well about it?
Hmm
The map process. The process for making the map. I'm sorry. Also making the map. Yeah
Let's see.
I think we wanted breaks from combat.
And then we also wanted intense ups and downs, right?
Because we didn't want you to feel too comfortable, but we also wanted reprieve.
So it's kind of like, you're going, you get minor heals, you get stronger, you get minor
heals.
And then so there's a composition that we wanted to aim for.
And there are some explicit decisions too, like the very first.
room is always a monster room in each act and then you know the very last one right before the boss
is a campsite um and in the center there's always i don't remember exactly which row like maybe like
row seven or so of each act is always a treasure room so and those used to be more random like it
used to be kind of like a mixed bag that is more exploratory but it actually the closer each path
was with slight differences the more meaningful like it was actually harder decisions um when it
purely random, not like completely random, but much more random. It was very clear what
like the best path was because generally people would weigh an event over an elite and things
like that. So I guess, I guess the lessons learned was, everything is really random.
You actually have less choice when creating the map.
more rows, uh not more rows, more columns. So we had more and more paths but we actually reduced
those numbers and reduced the height of the entire level a bit but that's mostly probably because of
game length. I think we felt like the game was kind of like going on too long or like the deck
was becoming too like perfect by the end. Yeah. So we were like trimming it shorter and shorter until
we were getting it perfect in which like you felt overpowered just before the boss or like you were
When you say, like, oh, I was almost, like, invincible, like, that's, like, a good feeling,
or, like, perfectly become invincible based on the difficulty that you're playing.
And so, I guess that's, like, the balancing act of...
creating a map that we discovered.
And that was a lot of testing.
We changed the map many, many, many times.
Yeah. How did you feel when you sort of hit that point,
when your original design scheme called for a very random map,
and then as you got further along, you realized,
oh no, we need to actually tighten this map and take more control over it.
Randomization actually leads to less choice-making, I guess,
but authorship means more choice-making.
It's a very inverse relationship between those two things.
Here we go. Here's Bodyslam, my favorite card.
Let's see. That's a good question.
We... Our design document is not very big.
To put it simply.
I don't know why, but Anthony and I are very, very on the same page of design.
I think it's because whenever we see an interesting game design-wise,
we just play it together.
I don't know, our design brains would kind of meld together in a strange way.
And so when we were making the map,
we were like, oh, what are we going to fight next?
Are we going to have a monster or an event?
And then one day I would just be like,
I don't remember if it was Anthony or myself.
That's how vague it is, with design right now.
It's just like, we need a map, right?
We used to have these doors that showed up in the background after you defeat an enemy,
and one of them was like another monster, another one was an event.
And there was no map view.
and you just choose different options until you reach a boss which is at a predetermined number.
Like after you fight 10 enemies you're gonna fight a boss.
But once you saw a map you could see ahead and kind of plan it out.
And I remember one of our testers not liking that because if they saw all the way ahead
they felt like the game was like analyzing the map rather than going through it.
And so that's kind of like that's like a previous thing we just talked about
which is about balancing it up but.
Yeah I don't know, design wise, we just kinda try things.
Almost nothing was set in stone in the beginning.
Right on, actually one thing I'll say about the map that I appreciate is when you're looking
ahead and choosing a path it sort of affects, you sort of look ahead to affect what you
do right now, but then once you get sucked up in the combat, or once I get sucked up
in the combat, I found...
A lot of that planning got thrown out of my head, not out of a need to improvise or anything,
but just out of like, oh, I forgot whatever active thing I was thinking about five minutes ago.
You know, same way you walk through a room, you forget what you were thinking about in the other room.
And then I would make different micro-changes, you know, on the pa-
you know, your left-right branching right there.
But, uh, when it came to...
But, I still think it mattered that way back at the beginning of a run, you know,
I decided to go up this route instead of that route, because, um, it, uh,
it affected what long-term choices I had.
So that's something I appreciate about the map existence.
But, like, I was aiming for this treasure chest right here,
because I hit a point where I was like,
I like treasure chests!
So I'm gonna make sure I chart that way, no matter what happens along the way.
Let's see here, just giving a quick look around, just folks in chat, a reminder, I always worry
I sound a bit desperate when I'm asking for questions from chat, but genuinely, we like
your questions folks, we love hearing from you and sharing your questions with our guests,
so if you've got them, share them, and if you don't, that's fine, I've got plenty to
ask.
Casey, I'm going to step away from design for a moment and talk about this game's wonderful animation.
Like, look at that word cackling and floating in there. Look at the way the text...
Funny enough, that reminds me of Tyranny, which is the only other game I think...
The only other major commercial game, because Twinedell developers actually do this all the time, and I just don't play enough of those games.
But, um...
What?
Sorry?
I was just shocked. I felt like wobbly text was like a huge deal in like indie games.
Oh yeah, wobbly text is, but like the key emphasis on specific words.
Oh, words.
Like say Celeste is a game that has a lot of wobbly text,
but you, Tyranny, and a few other games will actually like call out specific words.
And Tyranny, they do a mouse highlight thing where you can...
I'm going to highlight over and get some extra text and do some really cool meta design stuff in that game.
But even here, that's just text animation.
The card animation, there's all these little animations that make this game...
Again, I was sitting here playing this game and I went,
oh no, I'm in trouble, I'm going to get sucked into this thing.
And it was one half because of the design logic
and the other half because everything just felt good to do with the animation.
Would you be able to talk about your team's process for doing that?
How you were able to do it with such a small team?
I
can't
because we don't want people getting frustrated about what is mysterious about the game while
we're playing and have to leave or look it up because then it feels like research more
than playing a video game.
And so I guess that's kind of the reason for it.
The colors actually was heavily influenced by I would say Ocarina of Time, especially
in the events.
And that was because I generally don't, when I see a large block of text, I generally don't
read it.
Not because I don't like stories.
That, as, I feel like when it's kinda like forced, then I don't like to read it.
And so naturally I would kinda get into the story and sometimes I'd replay a game and
be like, oh, like, I'm kinda interested in the story because I just skipped everything
and suddenly there's like, now I'm a dragon or something.
And so those are the only times.
And so since I didn't wanna read the text, I just wanted to highlight the words, to kinda
be like, bubbling, take damage.
You're going to die if you choose this option or if you're going to get a good thing, but also this other bad thing.
And then the image is just kind of like, for the events, just help out massively because it kind of like,
has a theme of like what's going on in the event.
And I don't know, it's kind of hard to explain, I guess, especially for the events.
But I thought that was a lot of useful information, especially color, the way you described color.
Yeah, over time the colors became more like purposeful, but some of the older events they
would have, they would just have colors just for flavor.
So they might be a bit confusing as they, as they're not as consistent as the other
ones I'd say.
Gotcha.
Well thank you for sharing that.
I'm going to shuffle along the question board here.
Something that also got mentioned.
In Anthony's chat with our Gamasutra cohort, was the idea of kind of the Rube Goldberg machine of design where by the end of a run you're stringing individual cards together to create these wacky combos.
As I mentioned, for this run, Shrug It Off and Body Slam became the dominant force for my run.
How did you...
Go about looking at your game and saying,
okay, we have these individual card ideas and these ones string together.
There's Rube Goldberg and these ones don't.
Or these ones show up in testing, we didn't even know they string together.
Could you talk about that process of kind of the combo system?
That's part of what makes this game sing so much.
Oh, I see.
Um, well, the short answer is you just have to play your own game a lot.
But I guess the longer answer is we try to...
evaluate cards. So we make a bunch of cards that we think are interesting mechanically at first,
and we just kind of toss them into like the deck, right? Yeah, like an actual card pool.
And then we play it a bit. And then we're like, this works, this doesn't work. Like this UX,
or this kind of mechanic might be fun as like a physical game, but it's not as fun,
you know, in a digital game. So that happens pretty frequently. So we kind of like,
try to figure out what feels good in a game.
In
a nutshell, in
and it just ramps very slowly.
And you just, I guess you just feel it all out.
And then the rude Goldberg happens when you try to combine two mechanics at once, but
not in a way that it's so, there are some cards that are very exclusive.
Like we're on the topic of strength.
And so like a card that doubles your strength is like completely worthless for a non-strength
deck.
Yeah.
That's actually a card that is.
not good for making very strong synergies, but it also has a different purpose, which
is if you are in that specific type of mechanic, it makes it very, very good.
You go all in.
So it's like an all-in card, where all the cards are more flexible.
Shrug it off gains block and draws cards.
So it's like a high utility, just easy-going card.
Then you start, and then we choose one card, which is for each character, that highlights
one mechanic.
And for the Ironclad, that's like, applies vulnerable to the enemy.
And so we have another card called Dropkick, and that is if the enemy is vulnerable, you
deal damage and you draw a card and you gain energy.
And that's good because, so Dropkick by itself, if you don't have any vulnerable playing cards,
it's not, like applying debuffs in most video games is not enticing, I think, at least in
my head.
But since their starting card gives you the opportunity to apply Vulnerable every single game,
having Dropkick as part of the pool that's only good with Vulnerable is fine.
But generally we just have to identify what works and what doesn't.
The Ironclad is the easiest just because it plays off of the core mechanics.
I guess there is a...
We added Exhaust for this character. We wanted it kind of Exhaust themed.
But we did explore other themes as well like self-damage.
It ended up not being very fun, or very, very difficult to gauge how useful it was because
I think the healing in our game is very, very restrictive.
And also, it was hard to balance HP loss and healing, but that also somehow scales with
other characters.
And so that's why the main relic is kind of like a healing relic.
So it's kind of just, I don't know, it's very easygoing.
We also tried different relics in the beginning too, and even different character...
I think we called them loadouts.
Where we had different versions of the Ironclad, which started with different relics and a different set of starter cards.
But that was eventually replaced by...
I guess it's just called Nyao.
We called it the Gashapon System in the very beginning.
Which stands for...
Like these machines in Japan.
Yeah, gashapon systems where you get a random capsule out and it has a random prize.
Exactly.
So instead, we have our gashapon system.
Whenever you start a new game, you kind of randomize what you start with.
That was more like, there's more potential for wackiness than us saying like, hey, like
this is a character that thrives on HP loss.
Or hey, this is a character that thrives on strength.
Or like, this is a character that draws fewer cards, but is much stronger.
So, um, just trying a lot of things and then I guess highlighting what is fun and then
taking away what is, what is not fun.
I'm going to shuffle while we're talking about cards and finding cards and stuff.
One of the things that drew me to...
that helped me get the...
excuse me...
that helped Slay the Spire draw my attention was...
I was reading a blog post from game designer Tom Francis
who made Gunpoint and Heat Signature and some other cool games.
And some really interesting thoughts about the card, Tools of the Trade.
Tools of the Trade?
Yeah, Tools of the Trade.
And he said it's an interesting card because it's a card that lets you draw six cards instead
of five, which you can see here I drew five, but then you discard one.
In his feedback it says you're still getting five cards at the end but you have a slight
amount of choice over what card you get.
Um, and he compared it to a guard card in another game we streamed called Nowhere Prophet.
Uh, um, that- oh god, I'm blanking on the studio name for that, but go check out our stream with
the Nowhere Prophet dev. That's Martin- oh, I'm forgetting his last name. Martin's a great guy,
check out that game. Really- I know Nowhere Prophet. Yeah. I think- I think we- I think
they announced their game before we announced our game. We were like, whoa, someone else is making
a rogue-bowler game.
Yeah, he made a comparison that the power to choose a card from your hand to discard and then draw another to replace it and Tools of the Trade are really very similar.
They're almost the same thing because you are gaining your fixed hand of cards and then just having slight agency over what one of those cards is.
But he said Tools of the Trade is interestingly a quote bad feeling card because you're looking at a hand of six and getting rid of one as opposed to selectively changing one card.
So I've got the blog post in front of me right now.
I'll drop it in Twitch chat if people want to read it, but um, I was curious if uh, how like good feelings about drawing cards
Uh, like how you were sort of navigating that decision path about you know, bad choices good choices for that kind of thing
Hmm
I didn't think too much about good choices or bad choices. Honestly. Oh, that's fair. I guess. Um
I don't know. We generally think about the overall value of cards. Yeah rather than like
feelings of outcomes
I guess sometimes, maybe we do it subconsciously.
I don't think we actively design upon it.
Um, I think we made Tools of the Trade because we wanted something that gives you...
Because we had a discard synergy in the second character.
And so there was a card that gave it to you once a turn.
And that was what was interesting about it.
Yeah.
More so than a good feeling, bad feeling.
Hm. I have to read the article.
I'm not entirely sure why it would feel bad to play Tools of the Trade.
because it just gives you more opportunity.
But I'm not sure.
I don't think I share the same emotions.
That's fair.
Maybe you don't.
I mean, these are very subjective.
Factors we're dealing with, and that's why we at GDC and Gabasutra love talking about it,
because sometimes it's math, and sometimes you can say objectively something is a certain way in games,
and sometimes it's very subjective.
And that's what makes it such an interesting art.
For my part... Oh man, I had a follow-up question on that.
I'm blanking on it. Why am I blanking on it?
Oh, yeah.
Since you said you talked about the value of cards, um, uh...
I have a, uh, I play a game called X-Wing Miniatures, which I talk about way too much.
Um, and in that game, it used to be until very recently, there was kind of the equivalent of,
you know, like one gram in the game. Like one thing was costed in such a way that you could
kind of gauge how everything was costed around that one thing. Um, in that game it was one unit.
Um, and that was recently changed so that the cost, that that was less clear. Um.
And I'm curious, like, what in your power measurement toolkit did you use to sort of say,
this is equiv- this is equivocally, this thing is equivalently worth, you know, one point and it does x result.
And everything orbits around that way, you know, measurement.
Did you have any tools like that or did you use something else to figure out your power?
Uh, that's an interesting question.
Um, we didn't have like a baseline, I would say.
Yeah, I guess the baseline wasn't the previous characters.
Yeah.
Because we just, we try to keep the same, like, win rate.
And so we just have to look at the overall composition.
We like to joke that Bash is the perfect card.
Yeah.
But it's actually, I think, probably slightly weaker than most of the cards we want it to
be at this point.
Just because of the, maybe because of the natural power creep.
I kind of blame, kind of the community feedback, maybe.
I think, yeah.
It's interesting to make new cards or modify cards and somebody would be like,
it's almost similar to this card, but it's slightly like weaker.
It's just the worst card.
And so and so maybe we took that as valid criticism.
But am I not?
That's not always the case.
So some of our cards are probably some of the newer cards are a bit too strong.
Maybe. Yeah.
Should have followed.
Maybe I should have used units, you know.
But I mean, it's impossible to gauge.
um, within different characters, how good or bad a card is.
Even if the- even if it does the exact same thing as another card,
Mm-hmm.
just the character being different, having a different relic, having a different card pool, having different synergies,
um,
it just makes a very large difference.
And I think there's also a ton of anecdotal evidence
that a character might feel better than another character,
just because
you've played more runs as the newer character
after having so much more experience in the game.
And so,
I mean, we have to- we just have to re-evaluate things over and over again, I think.
Yeah, that's fair. It's interesting how often we try to grasp for questions about design and design decisions, game feel, all these things, and sometimes the answer really does just come back to you, you just got to test it over and over again.
I do wish there was a formula that would speed up the process very quickly.
Yeah.
Um, alright, uh, let's see, uh, let's talk about, um, I don't know, you know, it's great to spend 40 minutes talking about, uh, game design.
It's one of the coolest things you can do in this profession.
Um, let's talk about, I don't know, production, quality of life.
You and, uh, your collaborator...
You and Anthony, you work remotely, you and I discussed that before the call started.
And you don't work out of an office, which means you guys are two indie gevs who get to do this on your own time.
And for some people that's the dream, and for some people that's a nightmare,
because it means their home office is now their work office, and they don't have a place to compartmentalize.
How have you felt in your indie development life, and how have you managed to keep your space productive, I guess,
and feeling good so it doesn't feel like your house is a place you need to escape from?
I see. So currently I actually don't fully work full time from my house slash office.
Yeah.
I actually, when I did work, just from my house office, I worked too much. It was kind
of the opposite. Maybe I had the opposite problem.
Yeah.
I probably have some kind of compulsive disorder. But the point is, I would generally just start,
I would wake up and I would drink coffee and I would just work until my wife would come
home from work.
and then I would realize I had not had breakfast, lunch.
And so, I guess that was kind of like
the general way that I worked.
Um...
I'm not exactly sure how it was for Anthony.
I didn't really ask him quality of life questions too often.
Um, I'm not saying that it's good to work a lot.
Um, just that, that's just how
I guess my personality and my brain is wired to deal with things.
Um, I don't really plan things, I just kind of wake up
and then that day I write a to-do list of what I want to work on.
and then I just do that.
And I guess we generally worked, I think, six days a week.
We're a pretty long time.
And you know, obviously there are times
when things are slower, maybe we're waiting.
We have to get a build ready for like an event,
and then after it's ready, we're just kinda like,
what do we work on?
We're not gonna like update the build.
So, I mean, we may change in other branches and stuff,
but there's ups and downs, as always, like release time.
Building on that question, the question, if you are watching this and you've been following GDC this year,
you know, we put out the State of the Industry Survey where we try to poll developers for questions ranging from market-based to quality of life-based.
And a big, big topic we keep coming back to every year is a lot of quality of life questions that have to do with...
You know, work hours, crunch, does your company make you crunch, do you self-impose crunch?
How do you feel you and your collaborators handled that particular challenge of, you
know, you mentioned you work a lot, but when you set your own schedule, you're the only
responsible for that.
There's no producer saying, they're going like, all right, we got to meet, get ready
for E3, it's 20 hour work week, boys and girls, and people who do not identify with either
of those genders.
But yeah, I'm curious how you deal with that.
It sounds like you enjoy working, so that's a plus.
Yeah, I do like working.
Well, I mean, it's very different for indie games, I think, compared to AAA.
I think that if you have employees and they are full-time or salary, you know,
if they're coming to your office and working,
they should work how much they expect to work,
and you shouldn't force people to work,
because there will be long-term ramifications.
I mean, it's not much for me to say, because I just don't...
Like, I've just never been in that position.
Like, I've never really managed people in that way.
Like, sure, we've had contractors, but those...
We have...
In those dates for the contracts, we know when things are going to be finished.
And so we never really forced anybody to work overtime.
Um, like we worked overtime.
We don't really talk about it being overtime or not.
When we were like looking for packs, it was just like, oh, we need to, we
want to finish this by this date.
to
release.
It doesn't really matter too much whether or not, you know, you meet expectations.
Uh, yeah, wow. How does it feel then to transition from a game having no hype on release to, um...
I don't know, we won't, you know, exaggerate Slay the Spire's success and say you guys are at Minecraft or Fortnite levels, but, uh, you guys have a dedicated community, you've sold a couple million copies, and, uh, um, game, you know, big streamers will just regularly pop on your game and interest, sort of, attract new audiences sometimes.
How, what, how's that, how's that felt going from sort of A to B there?
Uh, it's just, it's kind of surreal.
Cause, um, I don't know, it's just something about I think interacting
with digital mediums, it's very difficult to kind of parse, like
the crazy changes that happen.
Yeah.
Like one day we'd be like, oh, like, like Kripparian is like streaming our game.
And we're like, what?
And so we would like hop on the stream and we'd be like, like, like, oh, like,
we like, we love, we love the game that you streamed like Diablo 3
back in the day and stuff.
Yeah.
And then he...
And then Crypt would just be like,
Oh hey, developers!
Or be like, oh...
But I think it's very relatively unknown
that our studio is like two people.
Yeah.
So maybe they thought it was like a weird corporate-like thing.
But it's, you know...
It's very friendly.
I don't know.
It's kind of hard to answer the question because
I haven't really
parsed it too much.
It's just a strange feeling, yeah.
Yeah, that's fair.
Um, God, I don't think...
I think if there's only one thing I've become convinced is that, uh,
no individual human being can deal with the concept of fame,
and that's why people who are famous have teams of people who manage it for them.
Um, and if you don't, they don't, then terrible things happen.
Um, but that's a personal opinion.
That's not a...
Universal truth.
Anyway, moving on, we've got about 15 minutes left in the stream here for our folks in chat.
If you've got any questions, drop them in, we will take them before we get out of here.
For my part, let's see, I guess...
Looking ahead for you and Anthony, what's next for Slate the Spire?
You've got an awards show next month, so I guess you guys will probably have to...
I don't know about a suit, but y'all will be picking out some collar shirts for that ceremony.
Or you can show up in t-shirts, it's fine, it's a game developer ceremony.
No! I will not be there with a t-shirt, that's messed up.
That's fair. Anyway, what are you guys interested in?
We have to show up in a t-shirt.
Um, what are you guys excited about for the future?
What are we excited about for the future?
Um...
Oh, my alarm is going off.
Are you excited to take care of that alarm? That's what you're excited about.
Oh, you're funny.
I can't hear it, fun fact, so...
Oh, it was someone else's alarm.
Huh. Um, anyway, sorry.
What are we excited about?
Um, that's a good question.
I think we're...
We're still working on... I don't know, we don't really
plan too far ahead in the future.
We're finishing up.
We're helping out with some porting work, and there's some localization work and some
other, like, a lot of work related around Sleight of Spire.
We generally kind of like talk about it each time afterwards.
We don't constantly ask, like, how do we feel about working on this next?
If we're both feeling good about it, we'll probably push forward.
I'm not sure.
I think we're also kind of like into maybe pursuing different projects as well, but nothing
is completely set in stone.
It really depends on like...
I'm not really sure.
I think that...
I think if there's a good idea for Slay the Spire that you want to work on, that gets us excited to work on it.
Then it's...
Because we're also really into content design.
And so maybe...
Maybe...
I'm not too sure.
If we'll be expanding.
I'll have to think about it.
It's not... I guess it's not sure. That's the answer.
That's a good answer. I don't say that's a good answer. It's, you know, hey, no one knows the future.
No one knows. No one knows what they gotta be ready for.
So, being ready for that is the same.
Being ready for what you're not ready for is a good...
Way to do things I think. Anyway, um
After that ramble, I guess I will I guess my my last question because coming up with questions is
Genuinely challenging and sometimes you just run through your list
Y'all, we're here, we're streaming this because y'all are nominated for the IGF awards.
There might be other developers watching this now or later who are also hoping to one day, you know, participate in those awards.
Oh man, these little guys weirded me out so much, I was like, where did they come from? What is going on?
Anything cute?
Yeah.
What's this guy with the confusion thing on his head?
Anyway, my question would be, I guess, if for developers who are interested in participating in the awards,
What would you say to them? You know, like, they're an indie dev, just like you were when you started developing this.
They want to make something that's IGF, ready for the IGF. What's your thoughts for them?
Hmm, like, to make like a video game, you mean?
I don't know, make a video game, market a video game, I don't know, like it's basically like the...
I'll roleplay this for you as it's a developer, they're working on something indie and cool and it's neat,
and they're looking at your IGF nomination and going, man, like I'd love to be there one day too.
I guess, what would you say to that person?
I see. I would say that if you try new things, and it's clear that you're trying new things,
then people will be very receptive to that and they'll support you.
But I think if you're trying to make...
like a knockoff, like I think some people think that they have figured it out by working on
some kind of genre or some kind of like aesthetic that they think works, then people will catch
onto that.
I don't know.
It just has to be genuine I think, and if you are I think it's very obvious.
So, work on what you think you want to make, you want to play, and not what you think other
people want to play, but what you genuinely
Think
you can do it.
Right on. I know I said before that we have 15 minutes left on the stream, but like I said,
sometimes you just run out of questions. You make a nice list, you do some research,
and you go through the list, and then you look over, and there's 10 minutes left.
And thankfully, because I run the show, and not a network, not ABC,
not Netflix, not Hulu, because I'm in charge.
I hate to say it when the show hits.
With that in mind, thank you everyone for watching our conversation with Casey Yano today.
The game has been Slay the Spire. You can check it out on Steam. I know it's on Nintendo Switch.
What other platforms is it on, Casey? I should have gotten that much sooner.
I think it's currently on Xbox One, PS4, Switch, and PC, Mac, Linux.
Sweet.
And it'll be coming out on more stuff.
Even though there was more stuff to put it out on.
But yeah! You should check out Slay The Spire if you haven't already.
It's a good way to kill three hours of-
Three plus hours of your day and just not even realize they passed.
Yeah, this stream is really distracting.
Um... Where the game itself?
Yeah.
Oh yeah, um, uh, yeah, oh my god, watching my own...
Because I know more about the game four hours after playing it for four hours than I did at two, you know, one or two.
I get to look back and watch my own mistakes when we pre-record footage like this.
Um, yeah, uh, for, for, um, for folks at home, if you'd like to see, uh, Slay the Spire at the IGF Awards,
you can join us at Game Developers Conference in person March 16th through 20th.
The awards themselves will be on the 18th on that Wednesday.
That'll be in the evening and you can everyone with a GDC pass can attend
If you are going to be at home wherever you are in the world, you can watch this twitch channel if you hit that subscribe button
Not subscribe follow follow subscribe is a different thing on Twitch. Um, if you hit that follow button
You will be able to watch the awards ceremony live, which will include the IGF Awards, where Slay the Spire is nominated,
and the Game Developers Choice Awards, where a whole bunch of other games are nominated.
For the rest of February into March, we're going to be doing our best to talk to a bunch of the nominees.
We've actually already... It's funny, when I was booking people for this month, the next, I was like,
wow, we streamed a lot of these games already before they were nominated.
That... Big and small. That was something really special.
Um, uh, uh, EC94, uh, this guy is talking about moving his mouth because the guy you are looking
at is Casey, and I am Bryant. I am invisible, uh, because that's some of the trade-offs we
have to do to run this stream. Um, but I appreciate you joining us, EC94. Um, anyway, with that,
um, yeah, we'd love it if you followed the channel. Um...
If you're interested in other information about this year's IGF nominees,
Gamasutra.com is running the Road to the IGF, a series of articles interviewing a bunch of IGF developers.
So if you enjoy hearing from Casey, I will drop the one with Anthony into chat,
so you can read what he had to say about this really cool game.
With that, I think that covers it.
Casey, if they've got more questions about the development of Slay the Spire, where can they ask them?
I'm always kind of hanging out in the discord, but if there are any questions
Posted in other like social media things even our Twitter even our support email addresses
We pretty much always answer them. Yeah, I would say I don't know we're very transparent
I think compared to I don't really say compared to anything because I've never asked other developers
Questions, but I don't know we're always around so
Right on.
As we close today, I'll just note that when I saw that this little slime had a bowler
hat on, I paused, I laughed a little, and then I moved on.
Yeah, EC94, Casey is a dev for this game.
Casey is one of two developers, plus some contractors for Slay the Spire.
I would say we have two and a half developers.
Yeah, two and a half.
That makes sense.
In fact, if you go into the game...
Oh man, yeah, we'll let EC94's comment go through before I close the stream.
They say thank you for the amazing game.
They love it.
You're welcome.
Thank you for playing.
With that, now I will officially click the closing button.
EC94, if you or anyone else want to check out the full stream, it's going to be archived on our Twitch channel,
so you can watch the full thing and our highlights.
And then I'll also kick it over to YouTube so you all can watch it there as well.
With that, have a good day everyone, have a good Wednesday, and enjoy the rest of your week,
and enjoy your time in Slay the Spire. Bye!