I'm here to talk about interactive pacing. We're going to do it by talking about The
Last of Us Part 2. So, let's talk about pacing. And when I say let's talk about pacing, let's
not talk about graphs. We don't need these graphs. We don't need any of this at all.
Instead, the way I'm going to approach this talk is that...
we're gonna treat pacing like running.
So as the person going through a story,
you're the one setting the rhythm, the tempo,
the actual speed that the story happens.
We try to give that to the player in Last of Us Part Two.
And I also might maybe talk about one graph.
Like, just, just, just one, just this one in particular.
It's not really the same as the others, I totally promise.
But we'll kind of dig into that and you'll see what I mean.
But yeah, before I get ahead of myself, who am I?
So my name is Evan Hill.
I was a level designer at Naughty Dog,
working on Last of Us Part II.
Currently, I'm at Obsidian, working on Outer Worlds II.
I also did a bunch of other games,
but the main thing we're here to talk about, obviously,
is The Last of Us Part II.
And even more specifically, the museum flashback scene.
So this was one of the main things I worked on
at my time at Naughty Dog,
and one of my favorite things I've ever made, ever.
I think it really connected with people,
and I credit a lot of that to this approach that we took,
kind of allowing people to set the tone for themselves,
set the pace for themselves,
and the results kind of speak for themselves.
Shout out to Gene Park,
and I apologize for maybe ruining his shirt.
But yeah, I just wanna kind of share this process,
this weird approach that I haven't really seen talked about
as much in branching narrative-focused games,
which has been a passion of mine for just decades.
So let's kind of get a quick overview.
First, we're gonna start with the where and why,
then we're gonna go into this three-part breakdown
of how the core content.
of interactive pacing and story kind of works,
and specifically in this level.
Then we're gonna dive into the extra spicy stuff
about what I call secrets.
They're a little different than what you might think.
And then I'm gonna cover a little bit of like
how I actually did it.
And then I'm gonna have an hour long talk
in the level design summit tomorrow,
if you want that but for an hour.
But let's jump into it.
First things first, where and why?
So,
As I kind of talked about before,
the goal with this level was to have
a player-tuned experience.
You figure out the rhythm that works for you.
I don't want to outstay my welcome for even a second
because given as we'll see what this level is,
if I overstay my welcome as a designer,
if we overstay our welcome as a team,
it's gonna just collapse like a house of cards.
It's gonna get boring.
So what do you need to do this?
Well,
That one graph I talked about.
This is a four-part story breakdown
that is really common in Asian literary traditions.
Ki, sho, ten, kets.
Real easy way to understand it is
it's the anatomy of interesting events.
It's really straightforward.
First, you have the introduction.
You let the audience understand what's going on.
You take those ideas and you develop them.
You set more stakes.
You add more complications.
You then take all of that tension, twist it about,
give it new stuff, rattle them around.
That's your climax, that's your payoff.
And finally, you have a conclusion.
Like I said, it's not too complicated,
but the best way to think about this
is not like those previous graphs,
like some kind of magic formula,
but as the anatomy of interesting events.
This works for analyzing everything from a baseball game
to a meet-cute between you and somebody else
to just what makes a good story
that you wanna tell your friends.
Even a good tweet, even a good joke.
A good example of it being used in some places you might expect is like the Mario series
currently.
This is the cornerstone of their level design.
It's this four-part breakdown.
Mark Round does an amazing job explaining this more in depth on his channel, Super Mario
World 3D's four-step level design.
But yeah, me personally, the best place I learned about this format and this process
is from Manga in Theory and Practice by Hirohiko Araki.
Yes, that is a JoJo's reference.
But yeah, literally there's like a couple pages in this book that trump almost every book on writing I've ever read.
I'm not saying that lightly.
But uh, yeah.
Main thing to take away right now is we're not gonna be talking about this as a graph.
It is just the anatomy of interesting events. So going from that...
we can kind of understand that we're not just talking about optional content or side quests
or collectibles. This is something that's more fundamental to the moment-to-moment experience
that the player has. This includes things like how immersive sims allow you to approach
different situations, how puzzles work. Looking at the system we had, you get introduced to
mechanics, the mechanics complete and develop, you have an aha moment, you solve the puzzle.
It's very, very universal.
Even RPG leveling systems,
we're not talking about dialogue systems,
I'm talking about the fact that you get
that one piece of your build,
fundamentally changes the way you play,
move on to the next level.
So, even without challenging mechanics,
we can give the player tools to shape their experience.
And now, why are we focusing on this level in particular?
Why this specific part of The Last of Us?
It's a really brutal game, honestly.
It has some really amazing combat,
but we also cared a lot about creating
a lot of human moments,
things that focus on character and rhythm.
And I think the museum level
is where we took that the furthest.
So as an overview, this level has no combat or stealth,
doesn't use any of the core mechanics
that we had previously.
It's mostly dialogue.
And critically of all,
the reason I wanted to bring it up in this talk today,
it's totally linear.
for the most part, there's no branching story,
there's no alternate endings, and yet,
we still worked to, again, create this interactive
experience, this interactive pacing.
So the big goal for me, as I mentioned already,
was perfect timing.
I wanted to reward the people who wanted to linger
and enable the people that wanted to rush.
So we had to create systems so that both of these
radically different spectrums of players
could have a compelling time.
How do we do that?
Oh, jumped the gun.
The first and most critical part
is what I call focal points.
These are the important and unmissable parts
of your experience.
Literally, your, whatever it is, leveling system,
level, story, moment, combat encounter,
should be complete with all of these
and literally nothing else.
Anything in addition to these,
if it makes the story worse,
it needs to be added to this list.
and finding out which one of these moments work
and how to build these moments goes back to this anatomy.
So we're gonna go through an example
of what these moments were in this level
and kind of roughly talk about
how it fits to this structure.
So for those that maybe don't know or need a refresher,
the flashback level starts three years in the past.
Joel is just...
messing with Ellie.
Like they've taken out and gone into the wilderness.
He has not explained why.
It's her birthday.
She starts asking what the hell his surprise is gonna be.
And in response, he shoves her into the river.
Which is extra shocking if you played the first game
because we have not established that Ellie can swim yet.
So as the player, you are now underwater
and we teach you the swimming mechanics
in the game that we added.
And as that big twist.
You know, set up, develop, twist.
Ellie already learned how to swim.
She's actually great and you're totally safe.
And then they just quip at each other and continue on.
That's the first kind of arc.
The next part is you move further into the forest
and Joel does actually reveal
what his big ass surprise is gonna be.
Turns out, it's a fucking dinosaur.
He has brought Ellie all the way out
to the remains of the Wyoming National History Museum
and her brain just fucking explodes.
They then get to explore the museum.
And as we're kind of going to dig in,
that's where a lot of this really interactive stuff comes in.
We did not want that part to be too long
or too short for the player,
so that when the final payoff happens, it's going to land.
Like Joel, in addition to just taking her here,
knows about her love of space
and has gotten a recording of the Apollo launch.
and then hands it to her into the middle
of an authentic space capsule.
And she gives her this perfect moment where,
yeah, she can imagine that the world's
gonna be a better place,
that it's gonna go back to the way that it was.
They both get to share in that.
They both kind of align in that single moment.
Again, set up, develop, pay off, conclusion.
And then finally, because Ellie is also riding this high,
is really generally curious,
she wants to see more of this museum,
this amazing place that Jill's taken her.
Unfortunately, uh, she winds up getting lost in the last annex, totally alone, gets attacked
by a boar, and then also finds a bunch of graffiti referring to the fireflies, the one
thing that they're still not really talking about. And the relationship starts to unravel
from there. Again, setup, develop, twist, payoff. But as we pointed out, this is just the
high level beats, this is the most condensed that this story is. You know, as I told it
right there, it's not...
it's fine, like you guys get it, but, you know,
I don't see anybody crying.
So, how does the player seek out more?
How do they add and kinda season this experience
with more of what they want out of it?
And that brings us to prospects.
So prospects are these exact added things.
For other games it might be like side quests
or optional encounters, you know, dungeons.
Like a Skyrim prospect would just be a dungeon.
But the most important thing to take away
of what a prospect is in this format
is they're clear options.
These are not hidden things.
These are not special things you have to search for.
You can see them, you get them.
You give the player a bite.
and then let them decide how many to take.
The idea is, if you have a set of prospects,
they all should take the same amount of time.
Doesn't matter if it's about 10 seconds
or an hour of content.
The player needs to know what they're getting into
in order to do this thing that we're talking about,
season their experience.
All of you have probably done similar things.
Like, everybody's playing Elden Ring right now.
You can look at the map and be like,
all right, cool, that's a boss fight.
I'm gonna go somewhere else.
But in this level in particular,
we tried to showcase this as best we could.
So early on in the museum,
we just have one little skeleton,
one dinosaur to mess with.
You're able to walk up, you see and interact.
Ellie has a little quip, Joel has a response.
Great, you could also skip this.
That's why we put a second one in the next hallway.
Again, you can interact with it.
Ellie does a little quip, Joel responds.
Great.
And then you turn the corner and you see this.
a whole cornucopia of these weird little moments.
And by that point, without having to say anything,
without a tutorial, without anything else,
as a player, you're able to look at this
and be one of two things.
Cool, moving on, or I will do every single one of these.
And that's what we allowed for,
like everything that seemed interesting,
everything we felt that needed to be said or could be done,
we just piled on and on.
And even more importantly though,
is for those first group of people,
you can have whatever opinion you want about them,
it's also clear how to move on.
There's this big staircase in the back,
when they walk up, they really like make it clear,
like, oh, hey, we're moving to something else.
And then we also put a hard valve,
a hard level design term where you can't go back
to just signal.
Hey, once you move past here, there's no backtracking,
there's no nothing, or should you wanna go?
So again, you give the player a byte,
you let them decide how many to take.
And kinda going back to our format,
this is kinda the first half of the equation.
You know, I'm setting the player up, I'm developing it,
we're stretching that second part
to be as long as they want.
You know, it goes right up until the point
where you get to say like, eh, I'm done.
Alright, like, this is cute, but what else you got?
And that comes to the second half of the graph,
where we answer the other question
that kind of comes with this format,
which is, cool, we've got prospects,
but how do you keep it from being repetitive?
Like, I'm literally telling you to be repetitive.
Be consistent.
Okay, it's kind of boring.
So how do we spice that up?
That's where these things I'm calling threads come in.
Like, it's a bad name, I don't know.
But the main thing I wanna talk about
is how it uses this ancient tool
used by an illustrious group.
Improv actors.
What we need to do when we're dealing with prospects
is yes and the player.
Anytime you interact with one of these things,
anytime you go about this, there should be,
again, we don't wanna be predictable,
there should be a decent chance.
that we're gonna take it, we're gonna run with it,
we're gonna yes and it, and we're gonna throw it back.
It's pretty straight forward, again, believe it or not,
this is kinda similar to what we're talking about already.
You take the player action, you react to it,
and then when you build a thread,
you expand and you throw it back.
So, yeah, like I said, same formula we've been talking
about here, but it's that back half, it's that extra layer
where the player's like, oh, cool, this is gonna be
a 30 second interaction, oh wait, it's a 40 second
interaction, oh wait, that's a joke, oh my god,
this is memorable suddenly.
So yeah, it's the back half of this graph.
The yes and prospects.
So let's look at some examples in the level.
So one of the early prospects we kinda give
is the fuckin' hat.
Simple thing, seems a little innocuous,
Ellie picks it up.
She says equip, Joel reacts, great. You know, she thinks it looks great, he thinks it looks
lame. But then, we also let you mess with it. All of a sudden, like you see this
interactable, you kind of ask yourself like what the fuck is this? No, no, no, no. Yes.
Yes and. Yes and Joel hates it.
Yes, and you can put the hat on Joel as well.
Yes, and he then gets into it
and just delivers a super wholesome moment
that you only get if you lean into them.
You only get if you engage with the prospects.
We reward you.
We take in and listen and say like,
all right, cool, I see what you're doing.
I'm gonna add, I'm gonna react, I'm gonna yes and.
And this works for moments and connections, big and small.
It brings that sequence to life.
You know, everyone listening around,
like you heard laughter there.
Like that's the thing that we're talking about.
It's that little bit of surprise,
that little bit of twist that goes it from being repetitive
to something interesting.
You know, so like some small examples are like,
as you're talking, Ellie and Joel can just start talking
about Jurassic Park.
And it just keeps developing until like,
oh, they're actually gonna watch this movie.
You know, he promises her.
They move on.
You can actually sit in the space section
and just have Ellie fire truck or fire hose about space
for like six different interactions and just keep going.
And again, it doesn't have to be these big moments.
Brings the sequences to life.
It's this back half of the structure.
Can we take it further?
How do we ratchet this up to 11?
How do we make these types of moments really stick out?
That's where we get to secrets.
These are the mold breakers.
So threads build off of prospects.
You think you know what you're getting into,
we kinda give you 50% more.
It's a good way to think about it.
This stuff just catches you by surprise.
This is the stuff that does not follow a pattern,
does not actually sit with what the player's expectation is,
and it's how you make something memorable.
They're memorable departures.
These aren't hidden collectibles.
These are just twist on twist on twist.
It makes the player feel like anything's possible if they lean in.
The other thing to be kind of careful about is, like, these are not the focal points.
Do not be afraid to let the player miss it out. If they care, they'll hear about it.
Like, these need to be moments that are big and interesting, but can be completely optional.
do not need to be a part of the story.
So like a really clear example that I'm
not only just really happy about,
but like how it came about was great,
was the first time we showed the leads,
one of the early mock-ups of this level,
one of them just chimed in, first millisecond.
Can I climb that?
And then we did.
And this is something that like I'm sure
even a lot of people who play the game
might have totally missed, but have heard about.
Like the constant reaction I always see with this
is like wait, what, you could do that?
What the fuck?
has this whole interaction, Ellie's able to get on top, she fuckin' jumps down, uh, and, yeah,
for the people that engage with it, they're, they're on cloud nine, they're, they're like
what the hell else is here? For the people that didn't engage with it, if they still liked it,
they come back and they're like, wait, what the fuck else is there?
you know, but it's also smaller things, like Ellie can find this mirror in the bathroom and
then we just give you this whole freaking mini game where you're able to just pose her face and
look like a doofus because you just get to be her for a moment, you get to mess around. You
actually get to find out that, oh hey, you can put hats on Joel, there's an achievement for
that. And you know, and then this is kind of like the, the, the borderline between them,
Fred, Threads and Secrets, this is like a little hat moment. Um, you know, other small
things like you can find this pallet off in the river.
She quips at Joel like, oh hey, let's write on this.
Like, totally optional.
But yeah, the main goal is like it makes players
feel like anything's possible.
It keeps them from just kinda condensing down
and just consuming your content like it's predictable.
But that's all nice.
I've given you guys a good framework.
How do?
How do we find these moments?
We talk a lot about scripts and planning and structure,
but.
In my decade of doing this,
the only thing I can honestly say is just iteration.
Like, it's writing, we're telling stories,
good writing is rewriting.
And specifically the approach of Last of Us,
we kind of took the approach of storyboarding
more than script writing.
And if anybody here knows about storyboards,
they also kind of know how rough they can be,
and that's a really critical part of why they work.
This is an example of a storyboard from Knives Out.
Soak it in.
They did not care about making this look good.
They just wanted to know
if this would be interesting or funny.
And hey, that scribble's pretty funny.
And this, this like extends to a lot of other media.
Like, guess who drew this?
Look, look at this mess.
This is by Hirohiko Araki.
This guy's been in the Louvre.
This is how he sketches his ideas out.
You wanna see what the dinosaur looked like the first time I put it in?
I'm sorry.
This is what one of the leads looked like and said I wanna climb it.
And so we did.
And all of this is really critical,
because we didn't know if this moment would work.
I had no idea whether we were even gonna keep this dinosaur
or all these other things.
I wanted to get it done in 20 minutes and just show someone.
And after putting it in front of them,
seeing they wanted to climb it,
I'm like, all right, cool, we can move forward with this.
This is doable, this is workable.
This is something we can put this much effort into
instead of spending a couple months and then deciding, eh.
But that's the generative part.
But how do you also, like,
I don't know, vibe with it.
How do you build that iteration?
How do you discover stuff?
And that's where I think, like,
another thing we don't talk about enough is inspiration.
So for me, working on this project was a huge challenge.
Like, there's none of the guardrails
that we normally feel as designers.
No core combat, no nothing, all dialogue.
And I got super lucky,
because then I suddenly found the work of one Naoko Yamada.
This is a Japanese anime film director.
She is...
Just a master, she's on par with Hayao Miyazaki.
Not mincing words here.
She mostly works with Kyoto Animation
and all of her films are the kind of subtle,
beautiful stuff that makes me cry every fucking time.
And if you even like my work a little bit,
check every single one of these things out.
I'm dead serious.
But another thing we were looking at too was Firewatch.
Again, had a really similar structure
to what we were doing.
So just the fact that I'd interacted
with this game years ago,
I was starting to chew on this problem,
I was able to break down like,
oh hey, this kind of interactive pacing is what they did.
Like I could decide to kind of live in a moment
or do these types of things.
Didn't do any hard branching.
We didn't need to have a big payoff.
Just these little things that let you kind of
linger in a moment really add a lot.
And then the final thing is like in addition to,
it's like okay, we know what we're trying to do.
We know where we're getting our input.
How do we get this on the page?
How do we actually figure these moments out?
Honestly, we just kind of improv'd it.
The way we worked was we would have a short outline,
I would do something horrible like that dinosaur
we did earlier, and we would literally act it out
together as like a strike team.
Yeah, no, I wish I had footage of this.
They would never let me show any of this.
But we're talking like, when you get hit by the boar,
me or one of the leads would literally like,
tumble onto the floor, roll around,
like, ah, it's gotta feel like this.
Just to see if these rhythms, if these emotions are valid.
Like, if we're able to sell it,
then maybe we can get the player invested into it.
If I can't sell it, if I can't make it interesting,
even with like, all my energy,
like, maybe it's a bad beat.
Maybe it doesn't work.
And then that feeds back into like,
oh, we're using all of these tools,
like we're using improv and, you know,
finding out what works for us by looking at other media.
And we just gave it to the player.
Like, that's the other way to think about it.
Like, find what works for you.
Like, don't worry about copying my formula
or looking for graphs,
but just get in tune with what makes it fun for you
and then try to make that thing happen to the player.
We're interactive, like we can do that.
But yeah, that's pretty much it.
It looks like we're actually gonna have some time
for questions, which I'm really excited about.
But yeah, follow me on Twitter.
We've got a website and stuff.
Also have some stuff on the horizon on the side,
doing some audio drama with some cool people.
And yeah, check out my stuff on Outer Worlds too.
And also watch Liz and the Bluebird,
and The Silent Voice, and The Hakey Story.
They're all real, real, real, real good.
We do have time for questions.
Hi, great talk.
Thank you.
So, I want to know about prospects in relation to threads and secrets, because
prospects, threads, and secrets all have like some aspects that are in common, in
that they are like, for instance, a thing in the environment that you can walk up
to and press triangle on, but all prospects should be roughly the same like
Size?
Correct.
So does that mean that if you have too many threads,
threads and secrets can break the size rule,
so does that mean that you can screw your like,
bread flour ratio up by having too many threads
and secrets and not enough prospects?
Absolutely correct.
Like, that I think hits to the core of the balancing act.
And like one of the things that like I can't solve for,
you can solve it for your content as it comes to it.
But that's exactly what we're kind of getting to.
Even back to the key shot and cats.
the big part is that unpredictability.
You want a little bit of it.
You want a little bit of consistency with your prospects.
But then if you're just threading all your prospects,
you're just back to having prospects.
You're just doing the same thing over again.
You have a list of sidequests
of all equal length, size, and weight,
and it doesn't feel good.
But yeah, finding that ratio,
I can't give you like a rough estimate
or anything else like that,
but no, what you said is you're on exactly
the right wavelength to be asking those questions.
Cool, thanks.
Hello.
Thank you very much for the talk.
Thank you.
I'm curious, as a level designer,
I do a lot of work like this.
Maybe you're gonna cover this in your talk tomorrow,
so maybe this is a good segue to come back to that.
Come to my talk tomorrow.
Sorry.
How do you build this in the earliest stages
when you're stubbing it out?
You showed that one image.
This whole thing is full of moments
that essentially won't sell the way they will
in the finished product until way at the end of development.
How do you actually stub in things like the hat
and things like that early on?
Do you use storyboards or title cards?
What do you use?
So we would normally get this kind of jank
in-engine walking around.
And then as I kind of touched on, we would just act it out.
Like, I'd use my physicality, we, like, I would play Joel,
one of the leads would play Ellie or vice versa,
and we would try and, like, feel out the dialogue and just talk through it.
Like, the hats literally just came from a stupid joke I did,
where I was like, oh, you know, maybe she finds a stupid hat,
oh, maybe she puts it on a saber-toothed tiger.
It got a really big laugh that I wasn't expecting,
and then all of a sudden I'm like...
okay, we're gonna do this.
And yeah, from there, in the talk tomorrow,
we'll kind of dive into what are the next steps
of like how do you actually build a playable prototype,
how do you shift that to production,
how do you polish something like this,
and all of the processes and stuff in that iteration cycle.
The big answer for that is have a really,
really competent team and keep them on track
and it can work out.
Cool.
Thanks.
Hello, my name's Ethan, I'm a narrative and level design student.
That's my voice, that's weird.
Um...
So, um...
If you're able to talk about it,
can you talk about any, like, components of this story
that you all tried that didn't work,
and why those didn't work,
and why they didn't end up making it in the game?
Oh, you mean, so stuff that got cut,
or just didn't work out?
Um...
I think, like, somewhat vaguely.
So, like, the other flashback that I worked on,
the one where Ellie and Joel go to, um...
the hotel and then fight the bloater.
Um, initially they were gonna find the strings.
Like they, they're like, oh we're gonna set out,
we're gonna try and like find these strings,
it's gonna be a metaphor for repairing our relationship.
And then we dialed it back.
When both for scope, of like, oh hey,
like this is a whole third of the level
that we don't wanna make.
And then right when we were asking that question,
we're like, oh they don't find the strings.
That means they don't repair their relationship.
it spirals out.
So it was actually like a thing where cutting that element,
we then looked through our story framework and analyzed it
and said like, oh, all of a sudden,
this actually makes it better, this developed.
So like cutting down the rhythms in the outline stage,
like we didn't get very far.
We kind of got to like the playable prototype
of like the music store.
A couple of times we looked at it like,
this is too much, this is too complicated.
Cut it, level's now two thirds as long.
And the reason we went really fast and forward with that
was because we realized, oh hey,
makes the story work better.
Awesome, thank you.
Hello.
I'm Paris.
You talk a lot about unpredictability.
And I'm curious how you balance unpredictability
with player intentionality,
making sure that players are doing actions
for a reason that they actually know of.
And especially with The Last of Us,
it's like I see a prompt
and I might not necessarily know what that leads to.
So if you could speak to that.
Yeah, so we kind of covered it a little bit in this talk.
The initial two exhibits that Ellie kind of sees
in isolation, that's exactly what we're attempting
to do there, where neither of those have big threads
attached to them, there's no big yes and,
and by doing two at once, we're simultaneously
letting the player, like, oh hey, you can skip things,
oh hey, these things are of all equal size.
and it keeps us from like lowering the amount of people that go without touching anything
before they get to the main room. So again, it's it's a light touch there, but in general
like that's where that four part structure you can kind of break down and understand
with. It's like that development part, uh that first half of like setup and development,
that's why you kind of want to do it in order. That's where like you don't just want to go
big twist, big twist, big twist, cause they didn't, they weren't expecting anything.
Cause the unpredictability, the subtle part of it is,
it needs to happen after they start forming predictions.
So you do the things that set their expectations first,
and then you do the crazy stuff.
And like that constant flow back and forth
is what generates that feeling of story,
of like experience, the ahas, the oh shits, or the oh no.
Thank you.
Hello friend.
Hello.
I have a question related to secrets and threads,
secrets in particular, because you said
that it's OK if people miss them.
And I guess I'm wondering if after the fact,
how much data collection or studying
did you do to basically get an idea of?
for particular secrets, what percentage of players actually found them and how did that
impact your mental model for how you approach these kinds of things in the future of like
I want to go into a secret but last time I did only 20% of the people found it. Do those
things kind of factor into your decision making? That's just more of that.
Yeah, so uh, it kinda comes out in iteration. Uh, we did a lot of playtesting on the game and
say for example the dinosaur climbing, uh, I forget what the exact number really was, but we
in conceptualizing like this, we're honestly happy if like 10-20% of people got it. Like
and we just ate that content scope.
We felt that like having that quality was there.
Now there were times in play testing
where that was not the number that we were hitting,
so we would do things like
increase the affordances around that.
Some like just basic level design getting thrown at it
where we made it more clear,
we made it look more like a ramp,
we highlighted it more,
we had Joel walk by it more to just kind of.
nudge and nudge and nudge until we felt it was like
a little more consistent.
I don't know the final ship numbers,
but yeah, when we did a Game Maker's Toolkit on this level,
like one of the common comments was like,
wait what, you can climb the dinosaur?
And yeah.
It looks like we might be out of time everybody,
but I think I'll be in the wrap up room,
and yeah, thank you so much.
Thank you.