So, hello everyone. My name is Eric Pangilinan.
And I'm Christian Nakata. Hi everybody.
And we're here to talk about our experience with making cinematic environments for Uncharted 4.
First we'll share some basic principles that we use when we design these environments.
Then we'll talk about how cinematics were made back in the last generation and how it compares to how it's done now.
Then we'll go over a general workflow of what we use at Naughty Dog to create these environments
based on an environment artist's perspective.
Christian will show two case studies on two related environments, one in the beginning
and the other one in the end of the game.
Hopefully by the end of this presentation, you can see how we apply these principles
to our environment to help tell a better story.
In a cinematic, the environment is one of the components that can tell the story.
The other component is the character.
The character usually gets most of the focus, gets most of the screen time,
the most polygons, the finest shaders, and the best lighting.
While the environment, it usually takes a back seat.
Like in this slide, the environment is all blurred out and completely in shadow.
But that doesn't mean it's not important, nor is it an afterthought.
A lot of things need to be considered when making cinematic environments.
When we try to tell a visual story, the environment and characters go hand in hand.
It's all a matter of composition, lighting, camera angles, and motion.
Like the character, but without dialogue, the environment can tell a lot of stories.
It can tell layers of stories in a single shot.
Far more efficient than explaining it in dialogue.
So it's a very important medium, and we need to understand and use it effectively.
Every prop, graphic design, every polygon and texture that you make has to have a meaning
or a function in the screen to help push the story forward.
Let's examine some of the cinematics we made for Uncharted 4.
In this scene, Nate just got caught red-handed lying to Elena.
He told her that he was out in a salvaging job in Malaysia.
But instead, she finds him in a dingy motel in Madagascar,
planning a dangerous treasure hunt with Sully
and a man she never met.
She is really pissed off.
Drake and his gang are in an awkward position,
and Drake is trying to talk his way out of it.
The camera swings back and forth between the emotional exchange of Elaine and Drake.
We want to show the contrast between these two shots.
We want to show who's getting his ass kicked and who's doing the ass kicking.
So there's dialogue here and there's body language, but through the environment you
can help this out by enhancing the meaning of the scene.
Where you put the characters in this space can affect the way you perceive their emotional state in the story.
Here we see Elena being closer to the wall, showing more stability,
Drake further from the wall, and further from his companion, showing separation and distance.
Their stability, this stability reinforces Elena's dominant position
and makes Drake's position feel alone and unsupported.
So this is just spacing.
Shapes and lines are powerful tools
that can enhance the shot too.
Notice behind Elena, there's a lot of straight
and angular lines, the maps on the wall,
the map on the table, the sharp edges on the picture frame.
Straight lines are usually meant to relate to direct,
being direct, aggressive, and strong.
Curvy lines usually mean soft, passive, and organic.
And behind Drake, you'll see round baskets in the wall.
We continue this theme as the scene plays up
all the way in the end.
Elena closer to the wall, bold straight lines in the back,
and Drake is contrasted with a deep background
with rounder shapes.
Not only is it interesting and dynamic
to contrast the two opposing shots,
but the shapes and lines will add to the intensity
or the passivity of the mood.
So why are there square shapes behind Sam?
These two supporting characters, Sam and Sully,
are symbolical of the conflict within Nate.
Sam represents the selfish side of Drake,
the side that misses adventure
and adrenaline of treasure hunting,
and Sully represents Drake's conscience,
the side that makes him stay with Elena and give up danger.
But like how we use lines and shape
on the previous slide to show mood,
we want to use that here to show the contrast
between these two characters.
Like Sully, for example, we frame round basket shapes behind him to really emphasize his
mood.
Sully is like a father figure to Nate and should know better to advise him.
He also knows Elena very well, so he's in a very embarrassing situation for his involvement.
Again, with a bit of dialogue, combined with Sully's expression and body language, a focused
camera, the round shapes help soften the scene, the audience get the message.
Another thing we want to point out is how we use lines and shape to show the relational
groupings of the characters.
We add an inset in the wall.
At first we did this to break up the space and push it further to accentuate the feeling
of depth.
But in this framing, the inset conveniently groups Sully and Nate together, representing
their closeness and affinity together.
But the framing in the inset also pushes Sam outside.
And the cabinet door is used as a frame to separate Sam
to represent that he's an outsider in the group.
And a different shape represents him
as having different motives and goals than the rest.
So within this one picture,
using the visual tools of simple lines and shape,
you can tell an unspoken story
of Drake's personal struggle
between his conscience and desires.
So here's another scene.
Sam rescues Nate from the orphanage, and they both barely escape the mansion.
Another very emotional night for Nate.
Eventually they ride down to the docks, and Nate is feeling sad and confused.
But Sam feels very confident and very optimistic for their future.
Here we want to contrast the two spaces, the docks where Nate and Sam are standing, and
the bright city skyline.
Symbolically, we want to make the skyline represent their dreams, and the docks represent
their abandoned situation, since they are orphans.
To emphasize this division,
We used the moonlight to light the docks and make it look more desolate, abandoned, and
cold.
Then used the warmer city lights to make the skylight look more lively, bright, and warm.
We used shape to contrast the skyline and the docks.
The skyline has a lot of vertical and horizontal lines representing stability.
And when you turn around, you'll see the docks is more made up of slanted roofs and awnings
that create more angular shapes and shadows and deeper insets.
In the beginning of the scene, Nate is still disturbed about what happened.
He's not sure about a lot of things, including his brother Sam.
Again, we want to show the separation between the two brothers.
It's like the previous example.
We want to use lines to divide the scene.
So in this picture, the bridge is the element that divides the space.
We use a lot of vertical lines in the scene.
In this picture, the lines of the bridge support
are used as a barrier between them.
They act like barrier between the brothers.
in other shots as well.
For example, the pillars behind Sam represent those barriers.
And as you will see Sam trying to walk towards Nate's,
trying to convince him.
Each time Sam walks towards Nate's,
he's breaking through those barriers.
In the final shot, Nate is convinced
and Sam offers him his hand.
Using lines to contrast values can help represent
two characters that are having opposing goals,
mood and personalities.
Lines and shape and scale all help direct the eye
to create a flow in the composition.
Earlier, Nate and Sam starts out
on the left side of the screen together.
Because Nate was bothered by what happened
and didn't share Sam's excitement,
he wanted to show, we want to show a divide
between these two brothers.
To do this, we had Nate walk away
from the frame he shared with Sam
and walked to the right side of the screen
in his own space.
We use motion to use your eye to track Nate
to the opposite side of the screen.
We use several lines in the screen
to direct your eye to Nate as well.
Most obvious lines are the ones
that are formed by the bridge.
Perspective will attract your eye
towards the vanishing point.
And other lines, like the elevated freeway
in the shoreline, as it ramps down to Nate,
and the other invisible one are the buildings
that decrease in height towards Nate.
In the previous shot, we discussed directing the audience eye.
Interestingly, the human eye can only focus on one thing at a time.
Even if we have a wide field of view,
we can only concentrate our attention to one area of the screen.
This is very good for directors,
because that means you can use visual tools
to actually control the order of what the viewer looks at.
Similar to the last slide, movement is the first thing the viewer will notice.
The second thing the viewer will notice is the brightness and contrast, and that's why
Nate and Sully are lit very well and also wearing light-colored shirts, and they're
also nicely silhouetted.
Scale is the third thing that the viewer will notice.
So because Nate and Sully are closer to the camera, we perceive them as bigger.
And so we have four things working for us, movement, brightness, contrast, and scale.
This is enough to attract the eye of the viewer
to start with Nate and Sully,
and then move on to Sam and Elena.
And for that, we use the vanishing point
to lead your eye to them.
So these are just some of the principles we use
when we construct a scene.
There are more, but we'll have to move on,
and we'll just call it out as we go.
So before Uncharted 4, we pre-rendered all of our cutscenes.
And that was a big pain in the butt.
Why did we do it?
What was the advantage?
First, it didn't require a lot of programming resource.
It just needs someone to schedule
and keep track of all the renders.
Number two, we can max out the settings of the shadow quality,
the number of lights, the texture resolution
to get the best image and then capture that.
Because we couldn't afford that in real time
in the PlayStation 3.
It's also easier to edit a pre-rendered image
or a pre-rendered sequence with post effects and transitions.
But pre-rendered pipeline had...
major drawbacks. The main thing is like pre-rendered pipeline, the transitions are not seamless.
It's either you're going to hit a black frame or it's going to be very abrupt. Also the
quality between the two scenes are not going to be the same visual quality because one will
have the highest settings and others will have the lowest.
You're also going to get inconsistencies with prop acquisition.
For example, if you acquire a rifle in the game and you move into the cinematics, the
rifle won't be there.
We also had issues with procedural effects like fog and particles, water, because it
is procedural, you can't just render a certain number of frames, you have to re-render the
whole thing.
But the biggest drawback with pre-rendered...
pipeline is that you have to render it.
And we have a lot of cut scenes and there would be a lot of backlog in the render farm.
Any mistake, change, update, you had to re-render the whole thing again.
And before you saw an update, it could actually take days because iteration time was also
a big problem.
In U4, we did two hours and 45 minutes of cinematic animation, which is about 112 cut
scenes.
That could have been a lot of renders to manage.
So that's why some people at Naughty Dog think that switching to a real-time pipeline was
the biggest technological and workflow advancement in Uncharted 4.
Because you only have to worry about memory, frame rate,
and random crashes.
So you basically treat it as if it's a regular level.
So let's get into the workflow.
Making a cinematic environment is pretty similar
to making a regular in-game environment.
But obviously in the in-game environment,
you'll be motivated, it is motivated by the gameplay.
Plus in the in-game camera,
we'll mostly be behind the character
and some other limited view.
The cinematic camera can do anything.
So the environment only needs to look good
where the camera's looking at it.
But for the most part, they're all the same.
So the first thing we do when we get a cinematic assignment
is to meet up with the creative director
to get an update on the story and backstory.
He gives us a general direction and insights about the scene
and it's our job to pitch him something good.
We do this mostly with concept art or storyboards.
Sometimes we help out the concept artist
by providing him with a block mesh or gray box.
The block mesh is already vetted
to follow the guidelines of the scene
so it's pretty close to what we want.
The block mesh is very rough.
It represents the space you're building,
and it's useful for first pass shape and size study.
It also helps us discuss with the director
what are the important spaces in the scene.
It also gives us a good idea of the assets
and building blocks we need for production.
we send this block mesh to the animation department
and use it as a guide for their mocap sessions.
A lot of things can change during the mocap session,
and most of the time, they never use the set,
so it's always good idea to not invest
a lot of time figuring this out.
Or you can build modularly so you can change things quickly.
When the animation comes back, we plug it into the scene.
The next step is to create a previs camera
so we can see what's going on.
We also do a depth of field pass,
so we also know what are the things that are blurred.
The lead cinematic animator then pitches a camera pass
to the director for the entire scene.
When this gets approved, we can now watch
and determine what are the scenes we actually see.
Then we do another passive concept,
and we do this for an advanced block mesh
that have more context to the camera angle.
We apply the visual principles of composition
we discussed earlier to the block mesh,
using the shapes and the lines,
leading the eye, dividing the space,
applying contrast and affinity
throughout the layout and space.
But this is the point where you can do
your visual problem solving
and work stuff out with the lead camera guy
so you can help compose the better shot.
Since we know the camera angles,
we can start doing some lighting.
So we give some general direction to the lighting guys,
either in color scripts or reference pictures or movies,
and we start out with a generic sky,
and then later on we replace it
with something more custom to the scene.
After the initial lighting pass,
we sometimes do a lighting key
and fine tune the lighting for the characters.
At Naughty Dog, we have a cinematic lighting team
that's separate from the in-game lighting team.
So you'll have to watch out for lighting transitions
and make sure that it matches between the two.
Because our cinematic schedule is also different
from the gameplay schedule,
we might decide on lighting setup
for the gameplay first or vice versa,
and it might not work out for the other.
Even before the advanced block mesh stage, the initial block mesh will still be enough
context to start creating asset lists and props for building blocks.
Since the production of this props can take a while,
it's smart to start with the list early
and send them out for outsourcing for production.
Prop selection is very involved
and it takes a lot of time to get it right.
And you can't just put anything there.
Everything has to be in contact with the scene,
the story, and the character.
It has to be functional as well as aesthetically pleasing.
Then about a month or two, we continue integrating assets from outsourcing.
Some of these props end up going to the technical team and they make physics objects out of
them like the bumpables and moving electrical wires, banners, flapping, all that kind of
stuff.
The sound and special effects like rain, fog, lens flare also comes in at this point.
And we do weekly reviews to polish and optimize until it's done.
There you go.
So I'm gonna pass this on to Christian,
and this is the part of the talk
we're gonna highlight those two environments
that are involved.
And what's basically the difference
between this and other levels,
other than nobody shooting at you,
is that all is designed to explore
and discover the story as it unfolds
one cinematic piece at a time to enjoy.
Hey, so now we're gonna take a look
at two different environments,
the townhome and the beach house.
In both these cases, we build an actual level with gameplay
around a few specific cut scenes.
Both of these levels were meant to reflect the place
that our main character is in his life.
And the idea is that through environmental storytelling,
we're trying to underline the character growth
of Nathan Drake in Uncharted.
So at this point in the townhome,
Nate is seemingly trapped in a normal life.
He works a basic job to earn a living,
he isn't rich, but he's doing okay.
So by the time we reach the beach house scene,
we want to emphasize how much his life has changed
and become much more of what he and Elena want.
So it's easy to point out that one takes place
in an older suburb of New Orleans
and one takes place on a dream house on the beach.
The contrast alone should show enough of a difference.
Job done.
But we found that there was so much more to tell
to try and bring a degree of believability
to each scenario.
Aside from the animation and lighting, from an art standpoint,
to fully tell the story here involved a purposeful use of color,
graphic design, specific environment storytelling,
and a bit of chaos to make a plausible space.
So on the townhome again, this was a very cutscene-driven environment,
meaning one or two cinematic shots
inform the majority of the look and feel of the entire level.
It turns out to be the cinematic that involves Nate and Elena having conversation over dinner
that's the one that drove most of this one.
So when we started Townhome, we began with a block out of this very specific scene.
Now ultimately, that layout turned out to be one of the greater challenges here,
as we needed a space that would work for the immediate story beats,
but eventually would work for the rest of the level as well.
Basically it means we were locked into certain architectural
and interior design choices early,
as that had to be applied to the rest of the home afterwards.
So with each room having somewhat specific story beats
of their own, this was a bit tough at times.
Eventually, after multiple iterations,
the final outside interior and exterior of the home
did not really line up at all anymore.
But, you know, since you never actually leave the space
and go outside, this wasn't a huge problem.
So working on the townhome actually turned out to be quite organic.
And we got through the complete block out of the interior
before we started considering what the outside of the space should be like.
And again, I mentioned earlier that this was meant to be an older neighborhood in New Orleans.
So we ended up spending a good deal of time looking for reference using Google Street Maps, actually,
to help us identify a likely candidate that we could draw from.
It's a lot like scouting a film location, basically.
So we blocked out the entire neighborhood in the beginning,
but we only finalized the things that you could actually see
from any one window in the home.
You might be pretty surprised actually
at the slice of life that you can get from Google Maps.
We used some of that to our advantage
in adding a bit of environment storytelling
to show what kind of lives the Drake's neighbors were living.
So backyard tools, play sets,
a towel hanging from the balcony.
The idea was to give the player just enough information
so that they could start to imagine
what Nate's townhome looked like from the outside.
So now, this is our first interior environment
we're looking at.
And in creating a scene like this, Elena's office,
specific environment storytelling is factoring in a lot.
And I'm showing a little bit of an iterative
block mesh process that I'm gonna end up
talking about a little bit later on.
But the idea here was that we would take a basic
block mesh and then take it to a next level
before we actually started to execute much of the final art.
This kind of helped us manage a lot of the details that went into the environment storytelling.
So back to those details, what we're trying to establish more here is who Elena is.
Her work is pretty important to her.
So showing things like her sticky notes for current work assignments,
awards, education background, travel books,
and even a penchant for collecting antique cameras,
this all adds up to a lot of detail.
And one of the advantages of an area like this
is we were able to add all that geometry and texture
since the space was pretty small.
The main thing working against us here though
is really just the time you need to create all of it
and assemble it together.
And we had a lot of people in-house working
on the graphics alone here,
involving at least the concept department,
some of the marketing team,
of course the background team too.
At one point in production,
we even hired a graphic designer
to help with some of the workload.
So here now we're looking at the master bedroom.
And what I find interesting in this area
was this is where we really start to get into questions
about what makes a living space believable.
So early on, of course, we looked at a lot
of reference material online for bedrooms.
And it's easy to find things showing
the latest trends in linens and et cetera.
But one of the things we started to realize
was that people are really reluctant to show
how messy we can be in pictures online.
It turns out people would much rather take pictures
of their really cool stuff,
and it's all really clean and neat and stuff.
So, but really though, it's this clutter
and small amount of chaos that helps a scene
seem more like a living, breathing space.
So, starting with a bed that's still unmade,
what kind of lives are Nate and Elena living
as working professionals?
and they probably don't have time to always make the bed.
And clothes are scattered around here and there,
various items cluttered on top of a bathroom sink.
So the point really though isn't that they're dirty
or completely disorganized,
but that they're busy people with busy lives.
And this was probably one of the cornerstone ideas
when we designed this and other living spaces
like the beach house and even Nate's office.
And it's also one of those things that's really easy to
overdo, as I'm going to talk about in the next slide.
So that leads us to this space.
This is the kitchen.
Now, one of the areas we went a bit too far with with the
chaos, and it definitely had to rein this back in.
So at one point, the area was starting to look like a
kitchen nightmare.
At the time, it seemed more realistic that when someone cooks in the kitchen,
they leave a mess behind.
At least, I tend to do that anyway when I cook.
So there really comes a point, though, when too much clutter or mess
can become distracting.
And here, the idea was just to make a believable space,
not how messy the kitchen can get when someone decides to prepare food.
So we wanted the attention to stay focused on the right things about Nate and Elena,
especially in regards to the story beats here.
Another thing I found interesting I'm going to point out here is...
It's just a unique opportunity we have
for a certain type of environmental storytelling.
So the fact that there would be another kitchen
later in the game that we would be able to contrast with too
led to some interesting opportunities.
So one of which came up with the fridge.
Not only did we come up with the idea
for using the front of the fridge for literal storytelling
by using sticky notes,
but I think you can often discover a lot about someone
from the foods that they like to eat.
So all the items inside the fridge were designed with the idea that again,
as busy people, Nate and Elena ate a lot of convenience foods,
takeout boxes, prepared foods, sodas, and more snack items. Again,
busy folks with busy lives. Later on,
this will come up when you get to go through Drake's kitchen at a much
different stage in their growth as people.
So, so far we've gone through a good deal of the Drake's townhome and haven't really
talked much about the area you start out in, the attic.
This is Nathan Drake's sanctuary, or man cave.
So this is where we get to relive many of Nate's past adventures and real interests.
So we had the benefit of starting with concept on this one.
We only had the additional challenge of teasing out all the details from within that image.
Like the Malaysia job, for instance, that you start off the scene with,
that actually had real maps, notes, and images that were all created from real historical research
and had an actual mini-story to it.
Speaking of details, we got a pretty good idea of what that composition looks like from this side of the attic,
but what about the other side? What about all those small artifacts that we had to create?
This was a pretty packed space with some actual gameplay, so we needed to be careful about making too many assets
or not enough to fill the area out properly.
So we came up with this way of working more iteratively, and I kind of talked about that a little bit earlier with Elena's office.
So we ended up...
After we got the concept, we moved into a basic traditional block mesh to work out both the cutscene and the gameplay.
But then we did an additional more detailed block mesh that indicated placement, color, and composition on a much smaller scale.
So props placed on shelves, for instance, would get this treatment.
That way we knew as much as possible earlier on what was needed in the space,
and we tried as much as possible to only create those items.
That gave us much more time to work on some of those items
that people tend to take for granted, the mundane stuff,
like, for instance, cardboard boxes.
Yes, cardboard boxes.
We took the time to craft some very detailed boxes.
We cared about why they were crumpled and where,
and this took weeks.
But in the end, it's funny, because at a glance,
it's just a box, but it actually ended up
being one of the most reused assets in the entire game.
So fast forward to the end of the game, the beach house.
Now we wanted to show that the Drakes were doing well
and living the life that they always wanted.
The character arc here is mostly complete
and now we're just highlighting that result.
So in stark contrast to the townhome,
this space was meant to be more airy and vibrant.
And we also started with a more generous
and forgiving block mesh.
Forgiving in the sense that the story beats
gave us a bit more flexibility in designing the space.
And two cutscenes help dictate the flow of the layout this time.
This is the Cassie video game sequence and the locked armoire scene.
In retrospect, it seemed like an easy idea to art up.
The Drakes are successful, so sure, a beach house.
No problem, right?
But in reality, though, we felt that we had to justify
as much of the Drake's new lifestyle as we could
to make this seem as realistic as possible.
We had to ask ourselves,
how would Nate and Elena choose to live?
What kind of environment would they surround themselves in?
So we end up sticking to the basic theme in the end of a tropical location and comfortable living.
But from there we did a lot of research into different decor
between Spanish colonial, craftsman, one with nature concepts,
bohemian and of course world culture themes factored in as well.
Early on we came up with this concept.
that if we mixed and matched furniture styles,
that things would just naturally seem more grounded.
So here we're looking at the family room
and we were able to introduce a huge,
a variety of influences into the scene with a decor.
The idea here was based on a concept
that people just don't buy whole sets of furniture
for the entire house at once.
More often, what ends up happening is a general mix of style and color,
as people gradually accumulate a set of furniture over time
in accordance with their lifestyle.
So in the townhome, we saw a restrained version of that happening
based on Nate and Elena's situation at that time.
Most of their furniture was just simple, practical, and necessary.
But by the time we get to the cabana,
the drakes are fully embracing the things in life
that make them happy.
So the mix of decor is much more colorful and expressive.
Again, though, there was a time
when we went off the rails again.
And this was when,
just trying to get just that right mix of decor.
So at one point, the idea of having a tiki bar
seemed like it would fit right in
with this idea of mixing in different things.
You can almost picture Sully visiting with a Mai Tai cocktail in one hand and a cigar in the other.
But with an exotic mix of furniture, we thought, why not?
Of course, only after we actually ended up putting in all this effort into it
did we realize that it had nothing to do with the character
or the central themes of the story we were telling here.
What was worse, it stood out and called attention to itself,
and it made you wonder why they had this insane tiki set up in their house.
In creating many of the spaces in the environment,
we could really explore a lot of different looks
for furniture and decor,
but we couldn't have done that with as much freedom
without a central color scheme.
So for the most part in the cabana,
we stuck to a very beach side color palette.
Using the cool blue, it balanced out pretty well
with all the warm colored woods.
The interior patterns and tile colors
were just extensions on that.
Adding to that color scheme,
we also pushed a lot more foliage throughout the interior.
Keeping with this basic theme helped unite
all the more exotic looks from room to room.
And we did this to a certain extent
with the townhome as well,
just using a much more neutral color scheme.
Coming back again to talking about
environmental storytelling,
we can revisit the fridge here a little bit.
Now we can complete the fridge character arc.
So note Nate and Elena's current lifestyle
and how much has changed from when they lived
in New Orleans to now,
not only has the outside of the fridge changed
to a more updated and modern style,
but we altered the details here.
Both the sticky notes and the contents of the fridge
continue to help punctuate the changes
in Nate and Elena's life,
with healthier and fresher food choices.
As mentioned earlier, Cassie's room was one of a couple of key areas in the epilogue level.
Not only did it help inform much of the layout of the rest of the house,
but it also set the tone for the sheer amount of detail throughout this level.
All this detail was vital to creating Cassie's backstory.
You only really get to this one level to get to know the latest Drake,
so any environmental storytelling we could do here was pretty important.
We started this with a basic idea of who she was and a few concept images.
Going from there, we created a basic block in the room for the starting cutscene.
And we also created a first-pass list of all of Cassie's interests,
so we could immediately figure out how it was all going to fit
without giving her the biggest room in the whole house.
With that in mind, we also wanted to allow for the huge influence Cassie's family's life would have on her interests.
The creative side from Elena, Cassie's interest in art, books, music, and photography.
And the adventurous side from Cassie's high-adrenaline father, Nate.
So showing all of the rock climbing and surfing imagery in the posters, that all added up.
to one cohesive personality, we hope, in the end.
This meant we needed a lot of elements
to help make that believable in one modestly sized space.
Now, not only did we have a large amount
of environmental storytelling to figure out,
but also a less restrained amount of clutter and chaos.
Many kids you probably know
have to be told to clean up their rooms.
Now Cassie, despite her maturity and her varied interests,
is still a kid, so we allowed for that element
to come through in developing her personality.
This is where using another round of more detailed
block mesh again came into play.
Not only was it important for efficiency's sake,
but it also helped us figure out how we were going
to navigate around all this stuff
that described a character you were only going to get
to have one chapter to know.
So having color and even an indication of that final graphic design on that block mesh
was also very helpful for the final result.
Color and pattern in this room probably changed four or five times before we struck on something
that worked.
In the second of the two primary spaces in Beach House,
we had the family workspace.
This was an area that was made around the cut scene
where Cassie finds the key to her parents' locked armoire.
The focal point here was the armoire,
but the spacing had to allow for key points
in the cinematic and also the bits of gameplay
leading up to the moments between Cassie and her parents.
So once we established the main parts of the scene in block mesh, we could go crazy from
that point again with environmental storytelling.
The concept shown here is one of the things we looked at when we started to set the right
tone and mood for what we would be going for.
So Workshed was what we ended up calling this space.
It was meant to give enough of a backstory about what Nate and Elena have been up to over the years in crafting a successful business out of their love of adventure and exploration.
And we ended up combining the features from many different types of work studios to get the final result.
So this is part photography studio, part printmaker studio, part study library, add in a bit of museum, antique store, warehouse, and then let's tack on a small mudroom just to keep some equipment on hand.
that. On top of all that, it still needed to feel homey, so we used a lot of the
warm woods and red tones from the rugs along with the lighting to maintain a
sense of comfort throughout the area.
Again, like Cassie's room, the area required a lot of asset creation to provide environmental
storytelling.
This is probably one of the most exacting areas in the level with regards to specific
So most every newspaper article, map, or magazine picture had to stand on its own merits.
We really tried to repeat things as little as possible throughout Epilogue, despite the
large volume of detailed assets.
The armor itself is most likely the densest area
between both the townhome and the beach house.
We were able to get concept help with that area
and it still required the two stages of block mesh
to get everything working well enough.
Another particular challenge involving the workshed
was in creating the newspaper and magazine wall.
Now deceptively simple,
this wall required a block in all on its own.
We had to get that to scale with basic color, layout, and even content to a mild extent before executing the finish.
Again, this was to help minimize the effort that would be needed to get what we needed for this location.
So combining this with all the images in Cassie's room between the posters, the prints, and the postcards,
there were a lot of unique images that we had to make.
Getting to the composite 2D images you see here
required the assistance of many different departments.
We were able to reuse some of the images
from other situations, but for the most part,
everything here had to be unique
to just this section of the game.
So a little bit about our process for doing that.
So first we had to determine the amount of space we needed,
and to do that we had to put in a basic block,
and like I mentioned, we had a rough layout,
and then we got some basic idea of content.
Then we asked our animation team to do the poses
with the characters that we needed in the photo,
along with an occasional proper backdrop.
Then, on to lighting.
After that, the images got a final pass
from the concept team if it needed more details.
And then, we actually had one more stop
with the graphic designer to add the final touches
and put things together into a more polished layout
with type and logo treatment, if necessary.
Now occasionally we got lucky and were able to reuse a piece of concept that just fit
the look and vibe of what we were going for, but this seemed to be really rare and didn't
happen nearly as often as I would have liked.
So it wasn't just enough to give the impression of what the Drakes were all about in Epilogue,
we also literally wanted to show some of that work in action.
So initially this was pitched as a more creative work area for Cassie.
We had an easel set up with paintbrushes and all that.
But again this didn't help the story here as much as we wanted.
So we came up with a better idea where we could show more day-to-day operations through
an actual ongoing job.
a bit more elaborate storytelling here to help further flesh out the adventure of work for hire story beats.
And this had to go through several iterations, initial block in outlining the space,
then we did a lot of refinement as we went along until we arrived at the point that you see here.
This is one of the few areas between the townhome and the beach home
where we use a good portion of the space to just tell one story.
When we started the process, we thought that just using the one work table would be enough,
but eventually it became apparent that we were going to need a lot more detail to really
sell this concept.
So ultimately, this seemed to need at least three times as much content as what we initially
thought.
The Mayan ruins job here is just one part of many elements that helped us tell the story in Cabana.
In conclusion, a great deal of story though was told by many environmental details like this across the game.
Successfully using those details to our best advantage all came down to how we managed them.
So to wrap this up, I just want to bring it back to the beginning where we show the importance
of using environment as part of the storytelling.
Whether it's a small prop or lines on the wall, nothing should really be random.
Everything should have a meaning and a reason to be there.
So knowing your visual tools and principles, it'll help you communicate better and identify
opportunities to enhance the story that you're telling.
Thank you.
I guess we have a little time for QA.
Yeah.
Oh, I think, oh, I'm sorry.
I think you're supposed to go to the mic so that people can,
sorry.
No.
You want to go first?
You can go first.
Hi.
Earlier you said that you had two separate lighting
teams for your cut scenes and for the in-game play.
I was wondering why it is that you'll
have that and what the advantages and disadvantages
are for that.
I think that's more of a legacy setup.
Like before, because we did pre-rendered and stuff,
it required.
the in-game team to be more technical and like the level differently,
so they had to deal directly with the game.
The cinematics are more film-oriented,
so that's more of a legacy setup.
We're moving towards unifying both of them
because it's basically almost the same now.
Okay, all right. Thank you.
Hi.
So, quick question. What would you say is your personal favorite examples of using an
environment to tell a story, whether in your own games or any games you've played?
Wow. Environment examples in our game, for example? It could be your game, a game you've
played.
Let's just go back to the Maya job, for example.
I like that piece specifically because we set it up where the story actually, the environment
actually pushed you into the story so it funnels you into the story.
into the cabinet.
So the reason why we changed the story
from the Cassies workshop into an ongoing job
was that we needed sort of piece the puzzle
to funnel you into different parts of the cabana
so that you end up in the cabinet.
Thank you.
Hi, thanks for coming today. What's some of the language like working with prop designers
for like having a unified theme so that it fit each room mood or message?
I'm not sure what you mean exactly.
So you mean how do we figure out which props to use?
Almost like being an interior designer, right?
Right.
A lot of it have to do with the story
and putting yourself on the shoes of Elena or Drake
and trying to sort of personify what they would do.
The rest of it is just curating,
balancing the colors and style.
So, yeah, and that's really where the iteration,
the iterative block mesh really kind of helps out
because it gives you context for those things.
So, I mean, you can kind of just create a list
like we talked about earlier with Cassie's room.
You just, you start thinking of things
that might work for that personality,
but you don't ultimately know how well
those things are all gonna work
until you actually start putting them together.
A lot of times you put in your personal taste in there,
but then you're forgetting that this is not your taste,
this is Cassie's taste or Elena's taste.
And that's something that you always have to
take away from yourself and consult, let's say,
other directors to make sure that the story and the feel,
because a lot of people,
that's the biggest problem we ran into,
is that everyone has an idea of who Drake and Elena is,
what do they eat, what clothes they wear.
So all of us have to sort of agree and argue, like, nah, she's not going to shop there,
that's too cheap or something. Or Drake's not going to get there, that's too lame for him.
He likes this brand better. So a lot of that happened during selection, just selection of
toothbrush and toothpaste, like, oh, they're all organic, they have to go all organic,
and stuff like that. So it's like back and forth of just trying to figure out who these
characters are. And that's what made Uncharted 4 kind of unique, because
In the previous games, they were just like shooting and blowing things up,
but this time, you really had to go to their house and figure out who these people are.
And that was probably one of the interesting things in making all of these environments,
is that we had to figure out, like, who are these characters we've been working on.
Unfortunately, it's the last game we're making, so it's like, oh well.
Thank you.
Hi, I find the amazing amount of thought and detail
that goes into your storytelling very inspiring.
So congratulations, first of all.
Thank you.
I'll watch big budget movies, era movies,
and the costumes sometimes look like they freshly
came out of the costume department
or wherever they make them.
Cars are polished, don't have any dents.
So how come, what was the process for you guys
to come to realize this is so important
and how can you first?
Afford to spend this much time and effort into developing a game like this. How do you?
Plan the timeline so that it goes hand in hand with the engineering effort somewhat not how many people work on
this whole process
How did we determine scope is that like the basic question of it all
Because it's pretty much like a scope question, right?
How do you determine how much assets need to be made,
how much the engineering needs to be made?
And that I actually don't know.
Yeah, how do you guys coordinate this with engineering
so that this is not a bottleneck in the whole process?
Do you guys?
I think that a lot of, for me anyway,
working on the cut scenes that are presented today,
we're very self-managed at Naughty Dog.
We really don't have any producers there.
So we have to do the best job we can just
to keep our personal schedule.
you know, in line so we can ship things. And some stuff in there didn't come online
till like literally the week we were going gold. I mean like those 2D images in the
magazine wall I was talking about, those things took like six weeks. And so if you
didn't, if we didn't block it out and plan it off like in the beginning, then I don't
know what we would have ended up with in the end. And that all kind of came down to
just, again, just managing your level. And everybody at Naughty Dog
I mean, has to become very good at managing their level in that regard.
Does that answer your question?
Sort of.
I have just two aspects to my two questions.
The first is with the sheer magnitude of assets
that you guys create, are you able to reutilize any of them
from, say, Uncharted 4 in the next Last of Us?
Is there any kind of recycling that you can do?
Oh yeah, yeah, definitely.
We always plan on assets that we can recycle over
and either change the color or a little bit of style.
Most of the time, most of the assets
came from previous games.
And what happened was, because it's PlayStation 3,
we sort of had to next gen it.
So a lot of our assets are being moved forward and just like updated.
Brilliant segue because I haven't experienced the Uncharted update release of the Nathan Drake collection on PS4.
Since you guys are always iterating up to the last second, did you guys revisit things about the original games for the PS4 remaster?
Such as like changing the cutscenes from pre-rendered to live or changing the environments in that version?
I think we always, I think as a rule in Naughty Dog, we always like have post mortems in the
end and we take it very seriously and we try to improve pipelines.
Like for example, like our lighting engine, we change it almost every game.
Our game engine, we always change it every game just to keep on pushing, to squeeze out
more from the PlayStation.
So it's sort of natural for us to always like...
Revisit our pipeline and how we do things our engines and our tools and just even redo it from scratch
Thank you kindly
Hi
So I'm completely amazed by the environments in uncharted 4 is
Is this perfect blend of art and technology?
I think
One of my biggest questions when I was playing the game is,
kind of what they asked before, is how do you
manage all those assets?
Because I guess you have outsourcing people,
people working outside of the studio, right?
But at what point do you say, OK, we need to fill this?
It's like, now we know everything we want here,
so all these assets come from outside,
and you have one guy putting everything there?
How do you?
We have three guys.
Okay.
Seriously.
Who else?
I don't know who the third guy is.
But anyways, yeah, we actually don't have a lot of people.
But we do a lot of, because we've been doing this for a
while, we kind of can predict how much is needed.
So in one of the slides, once it's even block mesh, you can
sort of imagine, OK, you're going to need this, this, this,
this, and so that asset list is already generated early.
And so you can predict stuff.
We've done enough environments, I guess, to know
what are the basic stuff, and then we can
always add on to it.
In terms of managing, I guess we have, that's a totally different talk, that's like we have
a management software where we can track everyone's task and stuff.
So you have tools to fill these gaps, right?
Yeah, yeah.
It's a task management software, that's pretty much what it is.
Awesome.
Thank you and we are waiting for Last of Us too.
Me too.
Oh, question about the, as far as in-game cinematics,
in-game environments versus your cinematic environments,
how did you come to...
balance out the footprint of the space?
Because a lot of times, like, you know,
if it's in-game, you have to consider player movement,
and visual clutter and stuff all over the place
definitely interferes with that, as you mentioned.
So, like, did it matter that, I mean,
is there a difference between the size
of the in-game spaces and the cinematic spaces?
If you load it up, you'll notice
the environments are usually 25% bigger.
And the spacing, we figured that out
because the player has like a sphere
for basically its collision,
and you can test it out to see if he can go through spaces.
So normally we would leave some space in the pathways
to make sure the player won't snag
or get caught in the collision.
But if you notice, if you open the file,
everything is scaled 25% bigger,
and that has something to do as well with the camera.
Okay, thanks.
Hi, thanks for the talk.
I would like to ask you guys about your pipelines, and in specific, how do you guys, the art
team, connect with the design team?
Like, you showed us the blockout of the hotel environment, and then you said that, I mean,
the first question basically is, are those blockouts made by a designer or the artists?
It depends.
On cinematics, the artist makes the block out.
And in design, in the in-game one,
it's the designer who makes the block out.
So there's two kinds of block outs too.
It's like the design block out,
which is very primitive and only figures out game design.
Some designers are artists too, so they can elevate that,
but what we do is we take an additional step for the artist
to go over that block mesh and art it up more
where they're considering sizing
and visuals and aesthetics for it.
So there's different levels of blocking out
and different people that are doing it, yeah.
Okay, and the second part about concept art, because you said you got the blockout sometimes overpainted by artists,
but you also use concept art as, I don't know, inspiration for the setting, how you can set the setting, how you can set up the lighting.
So, how do you approach concept art basically?
So, concept art, there's two kinds, or there's multiple kinds.
One is like a previs, where they have no blockout, they just have a general idea from the creative director of what...
he wants to see, it's more of like a mood board.
And then after that, you move into the production concept
part, which is more of you already have a gameplay
and block mesh, and then you give it to him to just flesh
out the details and the look.
And then you also have, which is like lighting keys,
which is more focused on the relationship
between the environment and the characters
and how the lighting affects both.
Okay, thanks so much guys.
Thank you.
Hi. First off, thank you very much for coming out. My question was mostly about how you
maintain cohesion within your environments. So you say that you're very self-managed. Is
there some tricks that either you personally have or you as a team use to keep that very
strict cohesion?
Cohesion and visual cohesion?
Like keeping the game...
Yeah, cohesion like within visuals and within like,
you know, Nathan and Elena are very organic, like you said.
Keeping like the cohesion of the characters
and the environment storytelling.
Organizationally, I guess we have a lot of meetings
and reviews.
We review it very, like almost every week or twice a week.
And that's pretty much how we maintain the look.
And then we spot things that throw us off,
and then we say, you know, that's not Drake,
that Drake wouldn't do that or whatever.
And so, yeah, we keep an eye on that a lot.
And I guess it's just through meetings that we do.
In the beginning, we also define that in the concept,
like in costumes, we look at the different kinds of clothing
that each of them wear, and we try to match that
with the environment so that it doesn't clash
and it makes sense.
So we also do that kind of stuff,
where matching what they wear, the hairstyle,
how much clothing they're gonna be,
and depending on the environment they're gonna be in.
So if it's like a snowy level,
they're gonna be wearing thicker clothes and stuff.
Yeah, that's pretty much how we do it.
Thank you.
Cool.
I think we're good.
Thank you very much.
Thanks, guys.
All right.