OK, so my name is Stefan Englund.
I come from Finland.
It's a bit cold there right now, so it's kind of nice to
be here in very warm San Francisco.
I work at Supercell as a game designer, and I've now worked
in the Clash Royale team for roughly one year.
I joined the team really soon after the global launch, but I
had the privilege.
to follow the development very closely as I was working at Supercell in other teams.
I played very actively in all the internal playables.
We are a small team.
There's a photo of the team.
Current developer team.
So we're 16 and I'm the only one with the title Game Designer there.
Everybody is very much involved in all kinds of different aspects of design there.
So everybody is kind of a designer.
And we are super independent, just like other teams at Supercell,
and basically all the decisions regarding Clash Royale,
like the game itself, is done by this group.
So it's cool.
My main areas that I work on is card balancing,
the game's economy, and system design.
So that gives me a pretty holistic view on the whole game.
But I, of course, run all decisions by the team and we discuss everything very openly.
In this talk, I will focus on card balancing, which is perhaps the part that I'm most passionate about.
And I feel that it's also the one that I've learned most about during this past year.
So, let's get going.
So, I'm going to talk about a few topics here.
First of all, I'm going to...
talk a little bit about Clash Royale, like what is Clash Royale,
introduce the game a little bit and talk about some things like how we
do the upgrade levels and how we handle the balancing there.
It's kind of like a background information for the rest of the talk.
Then I'm going to talk about our goals for balancing.
Why do we do it and what are our thoughts and define some terms here.
Then I'll talk about some of the key principles we have.
when we think about balancing, what kind of things do we think about there?
And then how do we decide which cards we then rebalance,
what are the things we think about and take into account there.
So, let's get started. Clash Royale.
First of all, how many here have played Clash Royale?
Okay, quite a few.
Nice. How many have not played Clash Royale?
Okay, there's a few. It's a free game, you should try it, it's pretty nice.
Alright.
So, well anyways, Clash Royale, so it's a
real-time PvP game, and it has its roots in
collectible card games and MOBAs, but it's like a bit
of a mix of those genres and then tailored for mobile.
And in Clash Royale you...
collect cards, upgrade them, you build a deck of eight cards,
and then you go to battle against random players
around the world.
And it's real-time PVP.
You generate this resource called Elixir
during the course of the game, and then you
use it to cast cards on the play field
and to rotate your deck at the same time.
And you have like three minutes.
plus one minute of overtime to try and destroy all the enemy
towers.
And usually, pretty much 30 seconds into the game,
there's already total mayhem and chaos on the field.
And the units, they move and act by themselves
when you deploy them.
And there's still plenty of decision-making
to do with things like timing the placement,
and managing the elixir, optimizing the deck cycle,
defending, counter-pushing, et cetera.
Something I want to talk about is the.
stats we have in the card, or the cards basically.
They actually have quite a lot of stats.
Like the knight is like a very vanilla, very basic card
in the game.
And even that has quite a lot of attributes.
So I'd like to think of these like.
compare the cards in a way a little bit more to like,
let's say, League of Legends heroes than,
like let's say, Hearthstone cards.
There's way more like parameters that you can tweak
and that affect it.
And so even like a vanilla card has that many like things,
not to talk about them, like a more complex card,
like Electro Wizard that shoots multiple targets,
stuns them, and when you deploy it,
it does a zap effect and so forth.
So from balancing perspective, it's of course nice that there's lots of these parameters that you can tweak.
You can do like a really small thing like adjust a little bit of hit speed here or movement there
and it can tweak it just a little bit to the card.
But one thing that's tricky there is that it actually makes...
it's a bit more challenging to mathematically balance the cards
to figure out that this is a good spot for the card
compared to, let's say, Magic the Gathering
where you have mana cost, attack, and defense.
And that's basically it for a vanilla card.
So it's a bit trickier.
And of course, also to not make it too easy,
we have then the upgrade levels and the different rarities.
So I want to, like...
use a few minutes to explain how we do that,
like how we handle that thing.
So I'll start with the commons.
So commons, there's 13 levels of commons, right?
And for each level, when you upgrade it,
we give exactly 10% damage and 10% hit points more.
But we don't adjust any other stats.
We don't adjust the hit speed.
We don't adjust movement speed or radius or anything like
that, because when we touch only these values, we ensure
that the interactions between the cars actually remain the
same from when they are at the same level.
So as an example, archers, one archer would two-shot one
goblin at level one.
And at level 13, the interaction is exactly the same,
but the damage and hit points are just higher.
So this helps keep me sane.
So how do we handle, then, the different rarities?
It's actually kind of simple.
We start at the higher level, but then we
upgrade them in the same method, like 10% each.
So basically, a level 1 rare has the value.
of a level three common.
And an epic starts at level six,
and a legendary, a level one legendary
is basically like a level nine common.
And then the place, and what we have there
is this thing we call the tournament cap.
That's a card cap level that we use in tournaments,
and also in friendly matches in the game.
We actually like not only cap cards there,
but we even level up cards to that cap.
And that is the spot where we.
balance the cards. So when I make values for a new legendary card, I balance it, kind of
compare it to the level 9 commons and see from there. So this ensures that the interactions
remain the same at all equivalent levels. And then it basically ensures that at max level,
if everything is at max level, then we have the same balance that we have at the tournament
And then we think of the level differences there.
Then more of a bit of a spice to the game,
or something you can specialize in things and so forth.
So it's like a spice thing.
But the main thing is to balance it there.
And something to note also that I want to mention
is that between rarities, it's not meant
to be more powerful as such.
The idea is that the more rare the card is,
the more exotic mechanics we introduce,
and the more advanced mechanics.
So as I had earlier, the knight, very vanilla card.
It's a common.
And then we have electro wizard with all kinds
of crazy abilities, and it's a legendary.
So that's the idea.
And the same applies to when we go upwards in arenas.
The abilities get a bit more complicated.
It's also cool for introducing the cards gradually
and introducing mechanics gradually for the players.
All right, so that was the basics.
So let's jump to like.
the actual topics. So let's talk about the goals of balancing.
It's usually quite good to figure out why you're doing something and
think about the goals of what you're doing. Then you'll kind of have something to aim for.
So for balancing, I would say
it's fun to have fun and interesting gameplay. Also includes
depth and so forth.
And then have variety, so there's a variety of different play styles and
different deck archetypes that are viable.
And then the game feels fresh, both with new cards making the game feel fresh,
but also that in between games you have surprising moments and stuff like that.
So the game feels fresh.
And if I would have to sum this in one sentence, it would be that...
you want to have a healthy metagame.
So that's the ultimate goal, the quest for the healthy metagame.
So let's define what this healthy metagame really now
means.
So let's start with metagame.
So first of all, metagame is not exactly a dictionary term.
And I didn't find anywhere a proper definition for it.
And it can mean many things, even
like game developers seem to talk about it
with different meanings.
But.
Players of PVP games and developers of PVP games, when
they talk about balancing, they usually, like metagame is
kind of an established term.
And for the purpose of this talk now, metagame means the
cards, combinations, and strategies that the community
at large have found most effective.
So the metagame is not something that the developers
create as such.
And unfortunately, they rarely even predict perfectly.
But.
Balancing is then the tool that we can use to steer it in
directions that we want.
But as a player and a developer, I actually find
the concept of metagame quite intriguing and interesting.
I feel it's kind of like the idea that we are the toy
makers, and we create toys, but we don't really know what
the kids will figure out to do with them.
And usually, it's something totally
different that we intended.
But that's also exciting.
So that's metagame.
So what's then healthy metagame and an unhealthy metagame?
So you could think of it as being a state of fun, variety,
and freshness.
And to cover the total extremes, let's first look at
what would be a broken metagame.
It's not like a realistic state, but a broken metagame
would be where you have nothing.
It's like.
Yeah, it's broken.
So an example would be this type of card.
You just instantly win the game by playing it.
It doesn't make any sense.
But there's no strategy.
There's no interaction.
There's no variety.
It's just stupid.
But this is really not a realistic state,
if you think about it.
Already common sense says that you can't make a card like
that.
So what's then a perfect metagame, which is kind of
unrealistic. So that would be like everything is in perfect balance, everything is in seamless harmony,
everybody loves everything in the game and like everything is just like absolutely fantastic.
Like it's not really like, it's kind of utopia, it's nice to kind of maybe strive there and...
think about it and dream about it, but we need to be honest with ourselves.
People have different tastes and we can't really reach it.
So instead we have something in between.
We have unhealthy and healthy metagames.
The unhealthy state might be a bit tilted.
You maybe have only two viable playstyles,
there's not so much variety.
Maybe it's kind of fun for a while.
And a healthy one is like there's several things that are going on.
But it might be maybe less varied, but it's really fun or something.
And one way to look at this is kind of like think of it as a diet.
So it's kind of like, you know, it's nice for a week in GDC, but you know, you kind of...
Like, yeah, you know that it's not good for you in the long run, and you will kind of feel bad afterwards.
And the healthy one is like...
That's where you want to be, and you know that it feels good
in the long run to be there.
So all right, this slide kind of looks like we're talking
about something completely different here.
All right.
So that's the definition of unhealthy and
healthy metagames.
So then let's talk about some of the key principles we have
for balancing.
So first, this is how we do it.
That's basically it.
Any questions?
No?
Just kidding.
So make everything overpowered.
Or well, make everything feel overpowered, to be more
precise.
So let me illustrate this a little bit.
So let's take chess, for example.
I mean, it's an archetype of a very balanced game, right?
And a game that would only have chess, soldiers, duking it
out, that would be extremely balanced.
It couldn't be more balanced.
But to be honest, it doesn't sound to me that much fun
and exciting.
But overpowered, that's kind of like the Marvel Avengers.
So certainly, they're all overpowered.
And we could argue about who's more overpowered than the other.
But they all have their unique traits, their unique moments,
when they are the best and kind of balanced, in a way.
between each other. So the concept of making everything feel overpowered is about making
everything fun and exciting. And this has of course a lot to do also with character design
and art style, but that's not the topic now. So how do you, with game balancing, make
something, everything feel overpowered? So how would you...
make these superheroes?
Or in Clash Royale's case, how would you make all the cards
feel overpowered?
So an alternative way to say this is each card
needs its moment.
So there needs to be some purpose for the card.
Or more technically, there needs to be enough situations
where the card can bring huge positive value.
And you can then switch out here the card to heroes,
spells, characters.
whatever the game has. So an example from Clash Royale of a
card that feels overpowered is Pekka. She's this like giant
robotic warrior thingy that deals insane amount of damage to
a single target and can take a lot of punches. So she can
really feel overpowered in those moments.
when she's smashing through some really powerful unit and then
still going for a big counter push.
And if she reaches the tower, she can easily,
with a few swings, take it down.
So Pekka is super overpowered.
Everything is good.
But unfortunately, everything needs a counter.
Too bad for Pekka.
And for Pekka, there are actually plenty.
So in fact, she's considered by top players.
to be one of the weaker cards in the game,
because she's so easy to distract and counter
with actually very low value cards.
But that's actually the thing.
That's what keeps her in check, and that's
what makes gameplay interesting and allows the metagame
to evolve.
So you have these counters to cards,
but you also have the counters to the counters,
et cetera, et cetera.
So the metagame evolves.
And this is basically what makes everything that feels
overpowered to not actually be overpowered.
And another thing that's good with having multiple counters
is that it acts as a safety net.
And yeah, this pretty recent card, Elite Barbarians.
If there are players who have played it, you might know what
happened.
So it's two very fast and strong barbarians, and they
are extremely devastating when left alone.
But when it was released, it was actually very, very weak,
like kind of the weakest card in the game.
And it was met with a lot of disappointment.
That's from the forums.
So yeah, my bad for the value, sorry.
Really.
So a few weeks later, we buffed it.
But it was a bit too much.
And my bad again.
So sorry.
Sorry also for players, if they watch the video ever.
So I definitely learned some lessons there.
And it was really very powerful indeed.
And for a few weeks, we had a pretty action-packed gameplay
when they were smashing through all the towers.
But the good thing is that the tools to counter it existed in
the game, and players did use them, and players did figure
out them.
So having counters for everything acts as a safety
net.
So it's not an excuse to make bad balancing, but I do think
that it's inevitable that mistakes happen.
So having a safety net there, having multiple counters, can
turn this disaster into perhaps a little tilted and
unhealthy metagame.
So make everything full overpowered, but everything
also needs a counter.
And something I have to.
say here though is that these two principles were heavily, heavily inspired by Blizzard.
So Blizzard's approach to multiplayer game design as presented back in GDC 2008 by Rob Bardo
was really inspirational talk. And in general like Blizzard's games have really been and can
continue to be a great inspiration at Supercell. So yeah, I wanted to say that don't take my word
for it like for the stuff that I mentioned like.
So yeah, you can find actually this talk online still,
at least the audio of it.
So it's worth checking out.
All right, so make everything feel OP,
but everything needs a counter.
So let's move on.
So a little bit about new cards and old cards.
So something that's important to us
is to make new cards meaningful.
Because if the goals of balancing
are to offer fun, variety, and freshness,
going to make sense that you have to make the new card meaningful. If the new card is not used, it
doesn't meet any of these criterias. So you're going to have to make it meaningful enough so
it's used. And something that I want to bring up here is that we often get these comments and
speculations about how new cards are overpowered, so we just monetize them then. But the thing
is that that's not true.
There are, of course, places where we think about
monetization, obviously.
But card balancing is just not one of them.
And I honestly think that it's hurtful, both in the short
term, but especially in the long run, if you have
monetization as an actual goal for balancing.
Because it's just like it contradicts with the other
goals, with the actual goals.
So yeah, just wanted to clear that out.
So making new cards meaningful is important.
So they actually have an impact on the game.
So you could say we aim to make new cards balanced,
but we kind of round up a little bit.
Hopefully not like elite barbarians up a little bit.
But an important part in making new cards meaningful
is to try to fill a gameplay gap.
So maybe there's some spell or units that's missing,
or something needs like alternatives or counters.
So just to make sure that the new card clearly has its own spot
and isn't just like a strictly better version of some old card in the game.
So as an example I could mention the Ice Spirit.
It's a single one elixir unit that sacrifices itself, deals a bit of damage
and then freezes the building and units that it hits.
And the idea kind of came from having an alternative to the one elixir skeleton
which was the only one elixir card at that time.
And Zap was and still is a very versatile card in the game.
So that stuns the enemy.
So this was kind of also meant as an alternative to Zap.
And then we had, prior to this update,
we had released the Fire Spirits.
And it was kind of a cool mechanic
where they sacrifice themselves and explode
kind of like as a fireball.
So we thought that we could utilize the same mechanic
and do a more chill version of the Fire Spirits.
So having a purpose for each card.
is important and it also ties to our strategy of keeping the total card count reasonable.
It's also important for us to keep old cards relevant though,
so like the iconic Baby Dragon and Mini Pekkas.
So we do rebalancing of old cards to keep them relevant and in the changing metagame.
And whenever we do that, we aim to stay true to the soul of
the card.
So essentially, that means that we try to avoid these
complete reworks of the cards.
And instead, we do smaller changes to the basics.
This also makes it a bit easier to predict, because a
complete rework is essentially like making a new card.
But another thing that's important is that when there
are a lot of players playing the card, so it
This way, it can play like it played before.
So while we communicate about the changes quite a lot, not
everybody reads it.
So it's nice if the players can still play the same way.
They can deploy it on the same spot and play it very
similarly, so it feels familiar.
So make new cards meaningful, but keep old cards relevant.
And then something we decided very early on is that we want to keep on rebalancing.
We want to do regular, semi-regular balance changes.
We've been doing balance changes roughly once per month.
And there's no exact science to this cadence.
It just felt like that was when the metagame felt like it was getting a bit stale.
So there was this feel of that we could have a little bit of change.
So we did that.
we chose the one month cadence.
And at the beginning, the reactions
were a bit negative, maybe, towards the balance changes.
But over time, as we just kept on doing them,
because we felt that it was important for the game,
players started to actually appreciate them,
and they started to look forward to them as well.
So it was a good thing.
But there's also like the metagame really needs also time
to evolve by itself.
So you kind of need to find the sweet spot for your game.
Like what is, how do you want to approach this?
And an extreme of like not giving it enough time
is that players might start to take it as a crutch.
Like that they.
that instead of figuring out counters to the current meta
decks and so forth, they actually just roll their thumbs
and wait you to do a balance change.
So it becomes a balancing act of being a crutch
and then managing the frustration of the players
when you're not addressing imbalances.
And something that we notice when
doing these different kinds of changes
is the buffs are.
we learned that buffs are nicer than nerfs.
And it's quite natural, it makes sense.
Because nerfs tend to hit cards that are used a lot
and that are very powerful.
So there are a lot of players who get a bit disappointed.
And so it's not something that we want to do lightheartedly,
but we of course do it when it's needed.
And it makes more sense to nerf one card than the buff,
like 69.
So, and buffs on the other hand, they hit cards,
there's not that many use, so those who use them
are of course super happy, and those who don't,
like, they might be happy that there's a new card
coming in into the meta maybe,
or then they just feel indifferent
because they don't have to deal with that card usually.
So balance changes are always complex.
complex things so communication is very important.
So it's not just about informing players that hey,
this is the change we did, but it really helps
with managing expectations because the buffs are never,
we never intend buffs to make the card
the most used card in the game.
Likewise with nerfs, we never mean to kill the card.
It's still supposed to be relevant,
it's still supposed to be used,
but just be slightly weaker and be in a better place.
So when communicating, it's a good spot to give reasons,
background, and some context to why the balance
changes were made.
We always make this in-game post about the changes, and
then we have in our blog a bit more context and a bit longer
descriptions.
And then also, what helps a lot is that there's a very
active community of YouTubers, streamers.
and so forth that are doing even more in-depth views
of the changes and all the ramifications,
all the indirect changes, et cetera.
So keep on balancing regularly,
knowing that buffs are nicer than nerfs.
So that's basically like these key principles.
So next up is to talk about
how we decide which cards to rebalance.
All right, so there's 70 cards in the game right now.
But it doesn't really make sense to tamper with all of them
at once, obviously.
It's too big of a change.
And the ramifications become impossible to predict.
So how do we decide then?
I think it boils down to like three parts.
It's we listen to the players, and then we utilize data.
But at the end of the day, it really boils down to these two
kinds really make the decision for you.
In the end, it boils down to intuition and just like
knowing your game.
All right.
So let's talk about listening to players a little bit.
So feedback and analysis from players plays a very big role.
We are very, very fortunate that we
have a big and very passionate and active community.
And many of the best players from all over the world
are actively writing strategy articles, analyzing the cards,
analyzing the metagame.
So the community and the players can't make the decision for you.
It's like an invaluable tool for like.
that you should listen to. And by following the community, you
really can get this pulse on the players' feelings. You have to
look sometimes a little bit between the lines, like what's
actually the root of the problem there, because complaints about
a certain card, the balance for a certain card, might not
actually be like that specific card is...
imbalanced, but it might be that there's just lack of variation,
for example, rather than you need
to nerf that specific card.
And one thing that's worth realizing
is that, especially after a game has matured,
the developers are really not the world's best players.
Definitely not.
And the players can really, really teach you
about your game.
embrace this swallow your pride stay humble, there's a lot to
learn from the players and I have an example of this where
this like kind of for the first time really really struck on us.
So that's this there's this
you to burr the I think this was the video that made it made
him famous to
John from or in students and back in April last year the
game was like one month old.
He made this video about how to use the one electric
And the team watched this video.
And we were a bit surprised at what things you can do with
that only one elixir, and that skeleton.
And yeah, at that moment, we really learned quite a lot.
Not just about the skeletons.
A lot of players learned about the skeletons at that point.
We had to nerf it after a couple of weeks.
But we also learned a lot about the game.
And about the fact that how much depth there actually is in this game.
And the fact that players really can and will teach you about your game.
So that was like a valuable lesson learned there.
We still have these moments every now and then like with some videos that we watch.
Oh, this is how you play this game.
And something that's also related to listening to the players
is that the top players are the trendsetters in the game.
So. .
I mean, they have access to all the cards.
They tend to experiment and craft the new decks
to outwit their opponents and gain the edge.
And quite often the trends then slowly trickle downwards.
And another example where this concretely dawned on us
was when we had our first live tournament.
So that was also in April 2016.
So that was a nice month for learning.
We had this invitational tournament in Helsinki.
And there was this young Finnish guy called Jason,
who ended up getting to the finals,
and then he beat everybody on stage 3-0,
including some of the top players in the game.
And he was using this deck that no one else had ever tried,
and it immediately got dubbed the Jason deck.
It was a pretty basic deck, really,
and only contained common and rare cards.
He played it really well, and after the tournament we really got to see for the first time the effects of esports and this concept of top players being trendsetters.
When we saw how the deck use rate went up.
So yeah, people saw the tournament and people definitely tried out the deck.
And it helped that it was only using very basic cards.
That was quite cool.
Cool to see.
So, listen to the players.
To get a second opinion, you can also check out data.
You can use it to verify stuff.
So for us, using data means mostly looking at use rates
and win rates.
And a bit definition time again.
So I suppose use rate can mean different things
for different companies and different games.
But what we track is percent of battles
where the player owned the card and used it.
And win rate is.
percent of battles where the player used this card and won.
So we look at these metrics both at individual cards level
and also for full decks.
So what do players use and what do they win with, basically?
So what we read out of these metrics, then.
First thing to mention is that use rate is the main metric we
use.
And the thing is that it really tells directly about what is the state of the metagame, right?
And if the goal is to have a healthy metagame, then it makes sense.
UseRate is the one that shows you how you're doing with that.
So when looking at useRates at different arenas,
you're going to get a feel of what the players see in the game.
And you can then back this up with what the community is talking about.
And maybe some of the comments that you see in the forums
might be actually coming from just a certain trophy range
where a card might be overused, and so forth.
So use rate is a pretty good indicator.
And it's also something that I think is a good indicator of
something being overpowered or underpowered, because very
strong cards also tend to be used quite a lot.
But win rates, they tell stories, too.
So it can, for example, be a good indicator of sleeper
cards or high-skill cards.
These type of cards that not that many use, but those who
do, those who specialize in them, can be winning
consistently with them.
So it might not be a good idea to not buff that kind of card
too much.
Depends.
And win rates, though, as well as use rates, they also
heavily are affected by the current metagame.
So obviously, if some.
good card is used a lot, the counters might get used a lot and so forth, and the counters might be good for winning games and so forth.
I want to mention here now that these are not necessarily the best metrics for some other game.
You really need to figure out, understand your own game and figure out what you want to achieve using the metrics.
So I think for example a game like Hearthstone, I think it would be very useful to look at things like
win rates across different classes to get the different classes balanced between each other.
And in a one-on-one fighting game like Street Fighter,
I'm sure they track the win rates between different matchups with different heroes.
So that's something that you have to figure out for your own game.
So, when we look at these metrics, we look at different arenas, different trophy ranges,
from the
from the top players and also from the challenges, which
is the in-game tournament system, which is played
with tournament-capped cards.
And when it comes to evaluating the balance
for individual cards, we really mostly
look at the top players and the top challenge players.
because they have access to all the cards,
they know how to use them,
and they are kind of the trendsetters,
as I mentioned before.
So I think that's a good place to start.
But we do look at also lower arenas,
what do players see there,
that we don't mess up their game too much.
So what is then a good use rate?
We have in the game currently 70 cards,
and it's eight cards per deck,
so that makes roughly 9.4 billion different permutations
Which is nice.
We don't have quite yet enough players to fill that, but we'll
try to get there.
So if everything would be used perfectly evenly, it would
make for an average use rate of 11.4.
But that doesn't make much sense, does it?
We can't expect all cards and all combinations
to be used evenly.
And it can't be the goal either.
Like a deck with.
only the most expensive cards in the games.
It won't win you many games.
I see a gentleman here is changing his deck right now.
Right.
So how do you figure out then what's a good use rate?
That really then boils down to knowing your game.
So when we look at the use rates then and ponder why,
ponder about them, we might think, OK,
why is a card popular?
Why is it used so much?
So maybe it is very powerful.
Probably is.
But it could also be that it's just a very, very good counter
in that current metagame.
Or maybe it's just like an extreme versatile card,
like the zap.
It's a cheap, versatile card that fits almost every deck.
So it makes sense that it has a higher use rate.
Another way to look at this is to think of target use rates.
So for example.
you might look at different main attack cards.
They should be viable alternatives to each other, right?
Like cheaper ones fit more decks for sure,
but ideally they are all viable and they are kind of...
you can look at them and compare them to each other.
Or direct damage spells, maybe like an even easier example,
that they have their own twists and situations,
but they should be really viable alternatives to each other.
So these are all quite objective ways to look at the
use rates and think about what is a good use rate and how
does it look.
But then there's also a more subjective way to look at it,
which I call spiciness.
So there might be these cards that are a good spice to the
game, but we don't want them to be used too much.
We don't want them.
They are just there for variety.
So if we first look at bread and butter cards, we would
have the iconic Barbarians.
It's an iconic common vanilla staple card that can be considered for most decks.
And it's fine if it's used quite a lot, especially if the meta is such that it's a good counter there.
And then there's like spicy cards, and the X-Bow is an example of that.
So it's this building that rapidly fires arrows at a huge
range and can reach the enemy tower from the other side of
the river.
So it's very powerful when it's played well.
But we deliberately actually don't want it to be among the
most used cards in the game.
And this is something we learned during the beta,
because there it was quite powerful, and it was used by
almost everybody.
And the community, and in the end, also we felt.
that it fits more as a spice to the game rather than this main
strategy used by most players.
But spice is important.
Spicy cards are important.
They add a lot of variety, keep the game fun,
keep the game fresh.
So I think you should have these type of cards as well.
And I think metrics-wise or data-wise, a good way to
recognize a healthy spicy card is that.
It has a low use rate, but a pretty high win rate.
So that means that there are these highly skilled
and specialized players that are using it and win with it,
but it's not really seen in every match.
Next bow is, for example, a card that has a super low
use rate at lower levels.
It's quite hard to use well, but actually top players,
every now and then, it tends to become used quite a lot,
actually, and in some tournaments, in some eSports events,
we can see, might see it at like.
Quite many of the players on stage are actually using XBow.
So I think it's in a fairly OK place at the moment.
So you need to understand these things.
And you need to be able to look at the cards and the game
from very different points of view.
And it's also actually important to understand
advanced concepts of the game.
Especially if you're the person actually doing the balancing.
I think you really need to understand how the game works.
Sure, you will be learning all the time from players and by playing yourself,
but you need to understand what the top players, for example, are talking about.
So in Clash Royale, there's plenty of these things.
You could have the elixir advantage,
the concept of defending and counter-pushing, multi-lane pushing,
a bit more advanced stuff like knowing all the card interactions,
or what different deck archetypes exist and how they work.
what kind of opening moves there are,
identifying the deck cycle, breaking the deck cycle,
understanding what's spellbaiting and building
decks around spellbaiting, kiting troops,
the pros and cons of having the flying attribute in a card,
because it's not always good, and the pros and cons
of having slow units, fast units, very fast units.
You need to understand these kind of things.
The point is not to now go through and explain all these.
The point is that you need to know your game.
right? So play your game a lot, both during development and release. It's really important.
And this is something like during the development of Clash Royale, it was played a lot. As we saw
with the Orange Juice video thing, we didn't figure out all the things. But it was played a
lot in the company and even there, players outside, people outside the team were
like coming up with good strategies, teaching,
like kind of teaching, teaching kind of the team
about like all kinds of stuff.
So it's really important.
Play a lot, both during development
and then after release.
So to figure out which cards to rebalance,
we listen to our players.
We learn from them.
We utilize data.
But in the end, you're the one who has to make the decision.
So it boils down to like understanding the game.
and intuition.
So that's basically the topics covered.
But the quest for the healthy metagame, it continues.
So we have unhealthier metagames, but with a
persistent game that's meant to last for years, it's really
a never-ending process.
I mean, new cards are added, new game modes are added, and
the player base matures, the players learn more, and we
learn.
more and more. So the eternal quest just continues.
So I feel that there was like a bunch of things now in this presentation, but I still feel like
that I only like really scratched the surface of things regarding gameplay balancing.
So here's some little selection of talks and articles and videos that I personally found very
useful and inspirational. Some expand on these concepts that I talked about and some...
are about other interesting concepts around game balancing,
things like power creep, counterplay.
So I really recommend checking these out
if you're interested in this and if you're doing this stuff.
So yeah, you can take a photo.
I'll have a little pause before I go to the next slide.
All right.
So just to recap the things.
from this presentation.
So the goals of balancing are to offer fun, variety,
and freshness, which feeds to a healthy metagame.
And some of the key principles we use
are making everything feel overpowered,
but having counters for everything,
and making new cards meaningful,
but keeping old cards relevant,
and keeping on rebalancing,
knowing that buffs are nicer than nerfs.
And to decide what to balance,
listen to your players.
utilize data, but at the end of the day, just play, play,
play, play the game and know your game.
All right.
I'll leave this here, and we can have a little Q&A.
Thank you very much.
Any questions?
Hi.
Fantastic talk.
Thank you so much.
I read everything about it.
I came in a little late.
I wasn't sure if you had mentioned this,
but how big is your balancing team?
Is it just you?
Is it like six people?
It's me.
Really?
Yeah, the Clash Royale team is in total 16 persons.
So that's like all the developers, and the QA guy,
the community manager, data analyst, and so forth.
So yeah, I'm the only one.
But all the card ideas come from the whole team.
Yeah, yeah.
And also balancing.
We bounce around the ideas with the whole team.
Cool.
Awesome.
Thank you.
Hi.
Thank you for the talk.
Thank you for flying away from the cold to come
visit us down here.
When you were doing the internal balancing, and I
know you joined the team after it launched.
Were you testing out all the different levels or were you using the tournament level as
your model that you would then build off of afterwards?
Both. So there were plenty of tests where we started from scratch,
and I started from like zero and also at the same time tested the progress
and the economy and the first few days, first seven days.
We also had like a 30-day company playable where everybody was duking it out.
So there you got kind of the different levels.
But then we also had these tests where we everybody had like this same like equivalent level cards and like
We're playing this kind of like more like eSports-y things
When the goals of those different tests were to either test the metagame
Which is why you kind of you know tested the or excuse me the progression
And that's why you were testing the you know the progression progress
And then the goal of the other the balance tests was more just figuring out if you actually had a competitive game
Yeah, you could say that. I think there was also for the balancing between the troops also with the
kind of the meta progress and stuff like that. So it was also to test those, like how do the early
cards work and how does it work when you like early on get an epic card that's actually like
kind of a level six card in a way compared to the commons that might be like a level four and so
forth. It all works out. Thank you very much. Thank you.
Hello.
Will it make sense to show real-time metrics publicly
to the users?
Maybe.
I think one trick it might be that it might tilt the metagame
even more.
So if there's cards that are used a lot,
then they get used even more, and so forth.
But it could. There could be some stuff to show. I don't know.
Yeah.
Thanks.
It's a nice idea.
So piggybacking on that a little bit, how transparent are you with the players about the balancing that you're doing?
And how do you, as kind of a community question, how do you manage their expectations and keep them from...
There's a little bit of reluctance to mess with the stats too much because people get upset.
How do you balance all that? And do you use communication to do that?
I'd like to think that we are quite transparent about it.
But yeah, I do feel also that we could do a better job at
explaining this kind of stuff, like what are our goals with
the balancing, and what do we think about when
we do the balancing.
So it might sometimes feel very shallow, our
explanations maybe.
Do you explicitly expose the stat changes on a website or
anything, or just people find out about it by playing the
game?
No, no, I mean, we yeah, we post like the we put always before we do the stations,
we post them like in the inbox and we post them in our blog with explanations why we
did it and and then also like we do some cooperation also with some influencers
that they they get kind of access to the information and they can do videos about
it perhaps. And some, of course, do like.
just proactively, so they go more in depth in things like they might talk about,
like their ramifications and their own opinions about it and so forth.
Wonderful, thank you.
Thank you.
Hi. So in recent months, you guys have increased your release cadence of new cards.
Has that affected your process in any way?
What are some of the challenges there?
Yeah, it's become like infinitely more stressful.
So in the beginning, when we released our first card, we
released them all at six cards at a time, four cards at a
time, and so forth.
But it was in November that we decided to go with that.
OK, let's release one card every two weeks.
And these are many, many good attributes.
People got to focus on that one card.
At the time, it wasn't a huge amount of cards.
And also, it kept the game fresh.
But it was actually quite challenging for me, because I
had to think about the balance of new cards that we were then
developing before even seeing what the old cards were doing
to the game.
We had to do balance changes in between when there was only
one week or two weeks to the next card being released.
And we don't know what it will do to the game.
So it has definitely added challenges.
And we are actually now changing.
We announced it already that we are changing that cadence,
partly because of this, actually,
to be three to four weeks.
Awesome.
Thank you.
So this will kind of piggyback off that question,
then I have a small follow-up afterwards.
But so you mentioned that while conceptualizing cards,
you made sure that every card had a specific scenario
it provided utility for.
So every card has its moment, right?
So do you think that there would be a point
that every niche utility would be filled,
or do you think that the release of new cards,
it creates new utility, new niches
for there to be utility for,
and do you think that you could pretty much
have an endless amount of cards,
or do you think there's a point where?
you know, every scenario has its niche card, I guess.
Yeah, so...
Yeah, it is challenging to,
always more and more challenging to come up with new uses
for the cards.
and to again fill like a new gap and find a new utility.
We still have a bunch of ideas, of course.
And something we discussed like regarding the like,
like kind of how many cards fit in the game,
how many cards does it make sense?
That's something we talk about a lot,
but we don't have, it's not yet in any way a problem.
And we don't have like.
We're kind of not there, but it's something we talk about.
And then something else.
So with Clash of Clans, like Supercell is also one of their amazingly successful games.
There has been just like a huge kind of subculture of the industry that just focused on like cloning that game basically.
What do you think of like the current sub industry, I guess, of Clash Royale Clans and the success of those?
And how do you see that industry like growing?
in the close future, I guess.
So, do you mean, what do I think about clones and copying?
I guess, yeah.
Okay.
Well, I mean, like totally blatant clones, let's say,
that you seriously just copy-paste,
copy the whole code base and stuff like that.
That, I think, is a bit disrespectful.
But, like, I don't...
Seriously, I think most games are not really clones.
They really, I think most games try to find their own thing.
They are inspired, heavily inspired might be,
like by a game and they take it.
And I think it's more, almost flattering.
And I like this genre and I'm happy to try out
these new games.
It's cool that you guys kind of pioneered
a whole new genre of game, but thanks.
Thank you.
Hi.
So when a card is either overpowered or underpowered,
sometimes that's because the numbers just
need to go up or down a little bit,
but other times it's because what it qualitatively does
is either not healthy or too weak or something.
What kind of factors do you use to determine
whether you should be adjusting the numbers on a card
versus adjusting what it does?
So, what's the question? How do I decide which stats to change in a card?
Was that the question?
It really depends on the cards and the situation.
I don't think there's any one rule.
For example, just trying to...
So that it's staying true to the soul of the card that I mentioned.
that I don't make a fast unit slow or make a fast hitting unit too slow and so forth.
But looking at what makes sense,
which is the moment or the place where this card is too weak or too powerful
that needs tweaking.
Is it that it doesn't do much damage?
Does it have a hurtful interaction with some card?
That it one-shots something that maybe it shouldn't one-shot and so forth.
It really depends on the situation.
I guess the thing that I was specifically referring to is cases where, if you think
back a while ago when Elixir Collector was steadily, the HP was dropped, the HP was dropped,
the HP was dropped, and then eventually you decided actually we need to change the cost
and the Elixir generation rate at some point, and then the card was in a healthier place
after that.
What prompted that kind of change of approach?
That's not really like, I don't know.
We just discuss kind of like different things and like what would make sense.
And maybe also like sometimes there might be good suggestions also in the community
about like that this could be like tweaked in this direction.
But I don't know. There's not really like any process for that.
Thank you. Sorry, I can't answer that better.
Hi. Here.
You have a monad system that is based on time.
in your game. I'm very curious how you decide if a card needs to cost 5, 6 or 7.
Can you answer that please? Yeah so when we kind of do new cards one thing that then like
quite early comes up is like at which elixir cost should we try to kind of get this card?
What is kind of an elixir cost that maybe we want to get like a new card there or
It would be cool to make this card into like a seven elixir card and then we try to balance the stats accordingly
So this again like not really like any
strict process to this, like it's just like flying. Sometimes it's like, okay, we start with a card,
like this could be cool as a seven elixir card, but then like things, maybe like the artists create
like a cool character and then it's like, okay, this doesn't anymore make sense as something
tanky, so maybe we need to like change this into something else. So I don't know, doesn't really
like it. My question is regarding to if I play a card that cost seven, I have to wait another
X seconds to cast another card.
Do you take into consideration this fact?
Yeah, OK.
Yeah, that ties kind of into them,
like how the elixir works and the deck cycle.
So it's kind of a trance thing, like how to go there shortly.
Let's say, like in Magic the Gathering or Hearthstone,
you have this, or Magic the Gathering,
there's this concept called the Jedi curve, where you have
like that a one elixir card or a one mana card should be one one,
a two mana card should be two two. This is the thing you're talking about, right?
Like, so how do we define like,
what is the stats of kind of a three elixir cards? And that's the thing.
That's like,
it's kind of mathematically a bit like trickier to define because there are all
these parameters, like.
affecting it. So we kind of compare to the existing cards that okay there are other three
elixir cards or the other four elixir cards have these kind of stats so maybe it should be like in
this place maybe it's like a bit weaker with damage than compared to mini pekka for elixir
or maybe it has a bit more hit points and so forth. Okay thank you.
When you launch a new card, you have this fantastic pie with data from players' feedback and
actual data from them. So what happens before that? When and how do you decide to launch a new
card? It boils down to intuition alone? Or what sort of data do you gather before? Because you
don't have the player's data yet. So it's all team data internal? Or you use external play
testing for a new card?
So what's the question now?
What's the process you follow to decide that the card is
ready and in a well-shaped, ready to launch in the game?
So when a new card is ready and we want to release it.
Well, we kind of have set a deadline for the release, for
the next version.
So we try to get the card ready by that time, I guess.
But that's not really what you're asking, I suppose.
But I'm trying to wrap my head around the actual question,
maybe.
Should we ask maybe, how do you get the data
to tell that a card is ready to be launched?
What's the trigger point?
We don't really get any data for a new card
when we're making a card, if that's what you mean.
So just intuition-based?
Yeah, so we put it out, and then we
see how players use it like this.
We just test it internally and try to figure it out.
I think we're running out of time.
So I have to wrap this up.
There's actually this wrap-up room.
I see you at least have some questions.
Maybe others have.
I'm going to go to this wrap-up room.
It's right across.
I think it's overlook 2022.
Am I right?
I don't know.
So I'm gonna go there if people want to come there ask more questions. You're welcome to do so
Okay. Thank you very much