Okay, so sorry about the technical issues.
My name is Daniel Olsen, I'm a freelance composer, and I've been working on Year Walk and Device 6.
So that's what I'm going to talk about today.
First, I started making music back in 1995 on the Amiga, Commodore Amiga.
That's when I also started making games with my friend.
So I drew pixel art in Deluxe Paint. I don't know if anyone ever used that.
And I also started doing chiptunes in Protracker.
In 2001, I started my first real job in the game industry at Massive Entertainment.
Before I moved on to a bunch of other companies, and every company I worked at I tried to pitch
my music, but it didn't always go that well, until I ended up at Southend, which was a
small company, and they, as they grew, they gave me a bigger...
possibilities to grow as a composer and sound designer.
And my last project there was Ilo Milo,
where I worked full-time with only music and sound.
Six years ago I moved to California
and left the game industry.
I worked for PlayStation R&D for a while
and created sound effects libraries.
Music and art for in-house projects.
But it was only for a short time before I left and started working in the tech space.
Because that's what pays the bills.
But I really started missing working with games.
So in 2012 I contacted Simogo that I used to work with before at Southend.
And they actually started their work on their fourth game.
And they actually talked about contacting me
about making the music.
So that was really lucky.
So I ended up working on their fourth game, which
was Year Walk.
I don't know if anyone here played it.
OK, a few of you.
It's a.
For those of you who haven't played it, it's a first-person 2D mystery horror game based
on an old Swedish myth called Year Walking.
And people run out in the middle of the night around Christmas to get a glimpse into the
future and they see all these weird creatures.
So the whole game is based about you running around in a dark forest and experience all these strange things.
The other game is Device 6. I don't know if anyone played that here.
Okay, same people I guess.
It's quite different.
An interactive mystery novel where your text is your map and your narrator.
And it's heavily influenced by 60s spy movies and general weird things.
It's quite lovely.
So...
Both these two games have been really...
Both of these two games got a lot of praise for how engaging they were in narrative, both
in design and audio.
And for this to happen, there was a lot of pieces that had to fit together, and the audio
was one of them.
And that's what I'm going to try and explain how we went about and did that.
Okay, next one.
So how do you make music engaging?
How do you engage the player?
And how do you make a scene in a game engaging?
I'll try to answer how we try to solve these three things.
I think, first of all, music can...
You can have a really beautiful track that's really great by itself,
but it won't necessarily make a scene better if you add it.
Also, if you have a track that's perfect for one scene,
it might make another scene really weird because it won't fit,
even though they're very similar.
So basically what it comes down to is how and when you use what track.
So basically you need the right song for the right moment.
What I like to do, because I'm not a schooled musician, so I find my own ways to figure
out music styles.
So what I like to do is kind of like an actor and get into a role before starting working
on something.
So what I do is...
I find a lot of references for music.
For Device 6 and Year Walk, I had Simon and Jonas helping me putting together a playlist.
And then we... I would listen to that for weeks. I would not listen to anything else.
Because for me, when I sit down and write music, I think you make like hundreds of decisions, small decisions all the time.
And you will unconsciously just pick the solutions that are closest in your memory.
So if you have been listening to a certain style of music, you're going to make a decision based on what you've been listening on.
I don't know if this is true, but I think it works for me at least.
So, then you have to write the song.
I don't think...
There's any right or wrong way to write music.
You can do orchestral.
You can do...
Uh, one more.
You can do orchestral or analog, like here I have some bananas hooked up through wires.
Or this crazy guy, Savi Lozano down here.
He can play music on anything.
My point is that it doesn't matter how you make the music, but the music has to be emotional somehow.
For me, music is all about emotions.
So music that makes you feel one way or another is doing something right,
and a track that doesn't make you feel anything is pretty useless for me.
So I made this pretty little chart for you,
and what I'm trying to say is that any emotion is good,
but the guy on the right, you want to stay away from that.
Because if you don't feel anything when you're writing the music,
chances are that no one else is going to feel anything when they listen to it.
So, it's not enough to just have a perfect track when you're trying to create an emotional
scene in a game.
You also need to consider some other factors.
And that's the pace of the game, character, camera movement, what's going on, and are
there other sounds like ambient noises, people talking, or whatever it could be.
And the goal for me is to try and draw the player in and make them feel connected to
the experience.
And if the music doesn't fit well with the game, the player will feel disconnected.
So what you want is to create a unified, coherent experience
where the result is much larger than the individual pieces.
And that's not just the music and the sounds working together.
That's everything, the entire narrative.
So it doesn't matter how brilliant your music is by itself.
You can't create magic if your music doesn't work together with the other elements.
So how do you do that?
This is by far the hardest thing.
I mean, at least for me when I work on music.
Because I usually just...
start writing and then after a while I realized, oh, I'm writing this kind of music.
So I have an example here for Year Walk where I wrote a piece that we all really liked.
And I think I intended for it to be in the menu, but it was even too intense for the menu.
So, I'm going to play this in three versions.
This is the original version.
Okay, yeah, so the game is really, really slow.
And it actually worked really well without any music at all, but it was extremely scary.
But adding this music just made it really weird, because all of a sudden it didn't feel connected to it.
So what I tried to do was make it slower and try and consider more the pace of the game and how delicate it was.
So we're going to play the next tier.
So this still didn't work. It was too intense for the game.
Like every little footstep mattered in the audio experience.
So what I finally tried to do was...
record this piece without any metronome at all, just to try and get a more natural flow to it,
more like a wind or maybe someone breathing or something.
And it turned out like this.
Okay, so that finally worked, and we really felt like that enhanced the entire experience.
And we're quite happy about it.
But it can be quite a process and kind of hard, because you tend to get attached to music that you write,
and you have to remove all the stuff that you like.
But then in the end, it makes everything better, so it's better for everyone.
So, and then there's another thing that I've been thinking about.
In most successful audio projects I've been working on,
I noticed I've been doing this, or we have been doing this,
and in most, after realizing this, I also noticed that most games that I admire, they also do this.
So what it is, is that,
a way to connect the player to the music.
So my idea is this, that if you are at a restaurant with a friend and you're talking to each other,
you're having a good time, and your favorite song starts playing, you might not notice
because you're so into the conversation and the drinks and everything.
But then if your friend would say,
Oh, I love this song.
Then you would notice, and then you would probably pay more attention to the music.
And this is something that we did in both Year Walk and Device 6.
I don't know if we did it.
consciously or subconsciously. We did it anyway.
On the title screen, our ear walk,
you have to tap for the logo to appear. And every tap you do
plays one note in the theme song. And we have parts where
there's this woman singing in the forest
and you have to find her.
by listening to her voice.
And in device 6, the entire game starts with mentioning a radio,
and you will hear the music playing from the radio,
and Anna is talking about how she hates that music.
I think these things make the player aware that, oh, it's music.
And even if you don't do this, again, throughout the whole game,
I think subconsciously people notice and feel a little bit more attached to the music.
And Zelda is a really good example of this.
Every game there's something with music.
And I think Nintendo in general is really good at doing this.
So, here's one more thing.
We did this in both Year Walk and Devise 6.
We tried to blur the line between sound effects and music,
so the player shouldn't necessarily know if it's music playing or if it's...
a sound effect, and we did this by
Simon Fleser from Simogo, he can handle all the sound effects.
But he asked me to compose some sound effects with the instruments that I write the music with.
And then I handed them off to him and he would maybe change them or just use them as they were.
Here's one example from device 6.
If you listen after the analog sounds in the background.
Okay, so I took those sounds and I stripped them out, and I handed them over to Simon.
And he took these and he tweaked them, and used them for transitions and other effects,
and mixed them with his own sounds.
It was quite effectful.
And also here's some examples of bleeps and bloops that I made.
I think you can hear most of these in the game actually.
So yeah, that's one way we try to bridge sound effects and music and bring them together
to get more of a coherent audio experience.
Another thing I notice I've been doing in almost every project is audio collages.
So pretty early on, when you have some music and you have some sound effects,
just put it together, like edit it together and try and get a feel for how the audio will sound like.
And you will notice pretty quickly if it sounds like a game you want to play or not.
And then you can make some decisions from that.
Here's an early collage from Year Walk before we had any sound effects in it.
This is an early version of the music too.
So from this, what stayed was the footsteps.
Although Simon spent I don't know how many hours tweaking those footsteps to perfection.
But the breath didn't make it and the scream didn't make it either.
Here's another one from device six that Simon put together.
For every old blackboard there are now hundreds of new electronic computers.
The prospect of domination of the nation's scholars by federal employment,
project allocations, and the power of money is ever present and is gravely to be regarded.
Yet in holding scientific research and discovery in respect, as we should,
We must also be alert to the equal and opposite danger that public policy could itself become the captive...
So this one is more of a conceptual piece, but when we heard it, I think all of us got goosebumps actually.
Because it really encapsulated what we wanted to achieve with the audio.
And I mean, it doesn't take a lot of time either, so it's really worth doing.
So is there anything else you can do to make your music fit better?
Something I always do is that I try to make a lot of contrast between the songs.
Even though all the music are in the same universe and the same world,
it doesn't mean that they have to sound all the same.
And, I mean, these are my personal opinions, of course.
But I try to make as wide a range of emotions as possible.
And I think it's more important that the music fits well with the scenes in the game than on a separate soundtrack.
So that's something I usually think about.
And it's also really important to let go of your ego and listen to what other people think, because they're usually right.
And even if you get some gnarly feedback, it's a good chance for you to just improve on your work, because usually it will end up much better.
And in the end, it's not your own personal creation that matters,
it's the game as a whole that is important.
And if the game is excellent, people will think your music is excellent too.
Another thing that happens in almost every project is that I...
I set up all these boundaries and I write music and then I can't write anymore because
I feel like I don't have any more ideas.
And I usually notice this because whatever I write will sound like a really bad copy
of what I wrote previously.
So what I tried to do then is to challenge myself and challenge the boundaries that I have.
And I always think about a GDC talk from 2011 by Yoshio Sakamoto,
who made WarioWare and Rhythm Heaven, two of my favorite game franchises.
So he says something like this.
I tell all my artists, composers, and sound guys to pull down their pants, underpants, and expose themselves.
Of course he meant this metaphorically, but I think what he was trying to say is that they can't be afraid of exposing themselves in their work.
Because if they're holding something back, it will show.
And you can't be afraid to just go all in.
And if you do that, you will just make better stuff.
So I try to think of this when I get stuck, and I try to challenge the boundaries that I already set up,
and see if I can stretch the concept further.
And don't worry about limitations or anything, I just...
just go ahead and do stuff that I shouldn't be allowed to do,
according to my own rules.
And a lot of times I realize that I haven't been playing the entire field.
The concept was much bigger than I originally thought.
And other times it will just create ideas for more music.
So in this I'm going to play an example of a song where I...
I tried to challenge Simogo.
I didn't think they were going to like this because I thought it was too extreme and too
outside the concept.
If you play the game, you will feel like this is not outside the concept.
But at the time when I wrote it, I felt like it was definitely in the outskirts of what the concept would allow.
But Simogo loved it, and I liked it too.
And it ended up in the game, and it was all good.
So, a little summary.
Pay attention to the pacing of the game.
It's not important how you create the music, but it should make you feel something.
Remind the player that the music is present, and don't forget that audio implementation is a really expressive tool.
Oh, I guess I forgot to mention that.
Okay, just really quickly.
How you implement the audio is crucial to the entire experience.
And this is something that Simon Fleser is so good at.
And the reason why EarWalk and Device 6 both turn out so well.
If you think of the music and the sound effects like the chords and the melodies of a song,
The audio implementation would be the rhythm.
And I would hand over songs to him and he would flip them backwards and pitch them up and down and layer them on top of each other.
And just create these really cool things.
So, if you're not doing the implementation yourself...
Make sure you work really closely with the person that's doing it, and you have a tight connection.
Because that can really elevate something that is okay to something that is excellent.
Okay, next point is create contrast between songs.
Don't play it safe. If you get stuck, try to challenge yourself.
And that's all.
I don't know if there's time for any questions.
I think we ran over time.
We're a little over, but we can take two questions, if there's two quick questions.
Hi, thanks for the presentation.
One of your points was creating contrast between your songs within a project.
What elements do you focus on to maintain cohesion across all of the songs for a game?
What I focus on to contain a coherent sound between songs, even though I try to make them different,
is usually just sound design. I try to keep similar instruments, or if I have a certain theme,
I try to make that go through. Or like in the VI case, I had these background noises,
I would add them in or something like that.
So you keep open to the idea of...
of tempo and rhythm and genre and all that sort of thing
and just try and keep a sound palette to use across your songs,
like the same types of sounds?
Yeah, so if I use the same sounds between songs differently,
I always start, I create one song and then I,
for the next song I continue with those sounds
and then I just add on and add on
until I have a big library of sounds.
Thank you.
Hey, on one of your slides you had a bullet point that said
shortest frame of reference, and I wasn't sure if I missed it
or you glossed over it and I was curious what that meant.
The shortest frame of reference I was referring to
when I would listen to music, the playlists,
and when I write music, what would be closest in my memory.
Thank you.
Alright, thank you very much.