last day of GDC.
This is my 21st consecutive GDC.
So yeah, a great fun week.
And it seems that every GDC is crazier than the next.
So I'm Jason.
I'm the co-founder of Execution Labs.
Execution Labs is a early stage investor in game studio.
So we are an equity investor.
We become partners with the companies we invest in,
long-term partners.
And so
You know, our philosophy is one of long-term growth, long-term sustainability or survivability.
And we talk to a lot of companies, we talk to a lot of studios, we talk to a lot of developers.
And the sort of the inspiration of this particular talk on
you know, entrepreneurship and avoiding studio disasters
really kind of inspired by a bunch of the stuff we do
with our own studios, but also with some of the problems
and challenges we see with studios more broadly.
Over the past few years, we've invested in,
or we've done 25 deals.
Not all of those studios are still alive. So out of the 25, 20 of them are still alive.
And so, you know, from an investment point of view, 80% survival rate is actually not that bad.
A few studios or projects you might have heard of.
Kit Fox with Moon Hunters was released last year to much fanfare.
We have one of our original teams, Double Stallion, launched a big IP with Cartoon Network called OKKO, Lakewood Plaza Turbo, on mobile, which was an interesting sort of attempt to launch a new IP on games before launching it on television, so an interesting experiment.
One of our teams is Outerminds, the crew that does the co-productions with PewDiePie, so
the actual PewDiePie branded games, very, very successful team.
Another example is Diluvian, an underwater sub-game that was just released a couple weeks
ago through Gambitious.
And then earlier this week...
Children of Zodiarc's produced by a bunch of ex-Ubisoft developers called Cardboard Utopia
was just announced, published by Square Enix, which is interesting for a Japanese RPG.
I don't think you can find a better publishing partner than Square Enix.
and a lot of other cool developers and projects.
And so, you know, the past few years I've been talking a lot about entrepreneurship and funding and pitching and so on.
A few weeks ago I was in Germany at Casual Connect and I did a presentation on why your studio will not get funded and that kind of got picked up quite a bit in the media.
Not everyone liked it, so this was a Facebook post from Jamil.
For folks who know Jamil, he's head of strategy for games at Google.
But I know Jamil a long time, and the issue he took was primarily because
I said the first reason that you're not going to get funding
is because you're making crap games.
And he took offense to that, and I think it was slightly out of context.
In that sense, I think it's probably an important time to warn you all that this is a lecture on entrepreneurship in the business track.
And so commerce and money is an important part of that discussion.
And while I've been in the game industry a long time and believe in the creative and expressive power of games,
and games as a medium, and it's an amazing canvas to create and express ourselves,
If you're talking about the business side,
then obviously we have to be concerned about the dollar
bills.
And so in respect to Jamil's concern and criticism,
I will say that the initial tip, the starting tip, the baseline
tip, is all of this only matters to the extent
that you're working on great games.
Right, no amount of entrepreneurial savvy,
no amount of salesmanship or pitching skills
or all that kind of stuff is going to matter
if you're not making great games.
So we're all going to just sort of take that as a given.
Everyone's game is awesome.
And we'll go from there.
All right, so when talking about entrepreneurship,
There's all kinds of stuff, more so in the non-gaming space.
And you can find all kinds of memes and tips and stuff
that don't necessarily say games,
but relate back to us.
This is founder of LinkedIn, Reid Hoffman,
saying something that we can all relate to in terms of the need
to iterate on our ideas.
Or here, the infamous Dave McClure, very well-known early-stage investor, you know, kind of saying
how most startups are pretty clueless, right?
It means that you're still not quite sure what you're building, not quite sure who you're
building it for, nor do you know how you're going to make money.
So that kind of sounds like a lot of game developers, although he's not talking about
game developers.
This one I thought was cute.
It's stressful, risky, challenging work to be in business, to be in the game business,
to build companies, and so on.
And then if you look at more so the kind of textbook definition of entrepreneurship.
It usually involves these three core elements, which I think most people should be familiar
with, right?
You know, setting up and operating a company, you know, doing it in a context of risk and
uncertainty, right?
We don't know if this is going to succeed or what's going to happen.
And then the third one being an intention to make profit.
And for game developers, the first two
may be sort of obvious or a given,
but oftentimes the third one is forgotten.
And so I often talk about the definition,
my own definition of indies, because there's
a lot of confusion over who's an indie
and who can call themselves an indie,
and it's sort of a loaded term.
But I always talk about Indies as people or developers or companies that have creative independence, right?
So they're working on the things they want to work on, they're working on their own ideas,
and that they have legal independence, right?
So that they're their own entity, no one necessarily owns them,
they're not part of a larger company, etc.
So that to me is what an Indie is, right?
Creative freedom, legal independence.
Now if we take all of those...
developers, studios that qualify as indie,
creative freedom, legal independence,
I like to categorize them across two other axes.
One is the degree of commercial intent,
and the other is sort of quote unquote vision.
Vision is just my catch all term for doing meaningful work,
doing something creative, doing something innovative,
doing something different, doing something visionary.
And so this is where we would put
the kind of stereotypical starving artists.
They're doing visionary work, they're doing interesting, innovative stuff,
but they're not really doing it in the context of commercial intent.
They're not thinking about profit, they're not thinking about making money,
they're just, they have something they need to express themselves, they're creating.
So they're kind of, you know, stereotypical starving artists.
This is where we would put the, you know, the sellouts.
Right?
They're intending to make money.
They want to make money.
But they're not doing anything particularly visionary.
So maybe this is where we put all the studios that
are making Candy Crush colognes, or trying
to attempt to make a Clash Royale, or a MOBA,
or something like that, where they see something else that's
making money.
And they're just going to kind of do the same thing
and hope they make tons of money.
So that's not super interesting either.
They're just lost down here.
Because they're not doing innovative work,
and they're not really trying to make money.
Now, I mean, I'm joking, but let's
say this is where students might go.
They're still trying to find their way.
Maybe really kind of junior people
that have just left college, and they're
trying to figure things out.
So ideally, the ones that are lost sort of find their way
into one of the other quadrants as they mature and explore.
And then over here is where what I
would call the independent entrepreneurs.
So, they are indies, meaning they have creative freedom and legal independence, and they're
doing so in the context of commercial intent, right?
So they're trying to make money, the third bullet on the textbook definition of entrepreneurship.
And they're doing something visionary.
They're doing meaningful work, innovating,
pushing the boundary, et cetera.
And I think some of the sort of past discussions
about identity around Indies has really
been this sort of struggle between a binary definition
of either you're a starving artist suffering
for your craft, creating something meaningful,
or you're a sellout that's making nothing worthwhile,
but you're trying to make a buck.
And I think it's important to unpack that and really understand that there are other
sort of more nuanced definitions and that this kind of happy medium on that spectrum
of being an independent entrepreneur exists.
So who are some of these independent entrepreneurs?
Some folks may recognize Tanya Short.
She's the head of Kitfox Games, one of the studios
we invested in.
Historically, her background is in design, MMO design,
and writing and narrative.
But she is very entrepreneurial.
She leads the Kitfox team, very community and press
influencer-minded.
And she also handles all the budgets and that kind of stuff.
And although the work they are doing at Kitfox
is very innovative.
they really are trying to build a studio that is profitable.
Maybe someone I think most people know, Rami Ismail, one half of Vlambeer.
That dude is a hustler.
I mean, he is a killer business person and is an entrepreneur, really textbook entrepreneur.
But no one would sort of question that the work that he does and that Vlambeer does,
the games that they do, are cool and innovative and fun and all that good stuff.
Nathan Vela.
For those of you who know him from Toronto,
co-founder of Cappy or Cappy Barra Games.
Another studio doing really innovative, compelling work,
beautiful work.
But Nathan is a really savvy businessman, business person,
also is co-founder or partner in Indie Fund.
Jenova Chen.
Jenova Chen arguably is one of the best designer,
creative directors on the planet today.
And a journey, a masterpiece, of course.
People don't necessarily recognize that they're really smart at business, right?
They were a student team coming out of USC and had a three contract or three project contract with Sony
And then soon after got several million dollars of funding from from from the valley investors
So, you know, creative genius doing amazing games, masterpieces, and yet also in the context
of commercial intent, you know, really, really savvy business side.
John Blow, likewise, and of course there's Tim Schafer.
You know, again, an indie doing visionary work, meaningful work, but doing so in a context
of commercial intent.
So, the first sort of real tip is to embrace that identity.
recognize that you're not a starving artist,
but that in fact you are an entrepreneur
or an independent entrepreneur, indie entrepreneur,
and to really sort of take on that identity and own it.
And that's sort of an important first step.
And we don't see a lot of developers doing that.
They're almost embarrassed to be talking about money.
They're kind of ashamed that they're
trying to do something innovative,
but they need funds and so on.
So it's a weird sort of.
situation so embrace that identity.
This is Richard Atlas, an entrepreneur, an indie entrepreneur from Montreal.
We did not invest in them.
He's the co-founder of a studio called Clever Endeavor.
Some of you may recognize the game that he and his team worked on called Ultimate Chicken Horse. It was released last year
They had a successful Kickstarter
They I think they sold probably about a quarter million units on Steam at least according to Steam Spy
So the game has done, you know pretty well for a three-person team
And they were I don't know if they won who won the design award last night at IGF
Was anyone there?
I don't know who won.
Quick, someone Google it.
So maybe they won the design award last night,
or on Wednesday night.
But anyway, so they were nominated for Best Design
in the IGF.
which is not bad for a few unknown developers
with zero experience starting their first company
essentially coming out of school.
And I'm kind of shooting myself for not having had invested.
So kudos to Richard and the team.
I think what's important to recognize
is the business side was intentional.
When Richard was starting the studio, he was thinking about starting a studio.
Not just making a cool game, but the idea that he needed to start a studio.
Interestingly enough, Richard came from an engineering background, had no prior experience in games.
like many of us, was passionate about games and wanted to move in that space, but realized
he needed to build a business.
Found some co-founders, was able to get some friends and family funding,
and when they were prototyping Ultimate Chicken Horse, they did it, as many people do, in a game jam,
and their game got some attention, so they knew they were onto something.
Intentionally, they planned to go to PAX to get feedback.
And one of their things early on was,
I mean, when they were starting, it was about two years ago,
so that was really the start of the shift towards the importance
of influencer marketing and streamers and YouTubers and so on.
And sort of Richard latched onto that and said,
OK, we need to design a game that's going to be fun to watch
and that the streamers are going to want to play.
And so he would go to shows and hustle like crazy
to meet all the YouTubers and talk to all the people
that were managing the YouTubers.
And everything he did was really intentional
about thinking about this game as a product.
How was he going to enter it into the marketplace?
How was he going to get noticed vis-a-vis others?
How was he going to optimize the game and the design
and the art style to be viewable?
And so I would say it was intentional.
Another example of intention are the folks from Riot.
I mean, this is going back a few years.
Brandon's a buddy of mine from way back.
And I mean, I knew him when he was out trying to raise funds
for Riot back in the day.
he thought, or they thought they were onto something.
It wasn't just, ah, we want to make this cool game.
Now, if you talk to Brandon, he will admit readily
that, of course, he did not or could not ever imagine
the success that they've had with League.
But they did intend to build a business
and create a game whom they thought there was a market for.
And if they did the right things,
they would be successful.
And so they made these intentional decisions
around that.
And so that brings up the notion of uncertainty versus by accident.
And so it's one thing to say, listen, I think there's an opportunity to make a MOBA, and
there's a competitive market out there.
We're not sure if it's going to succeed, but here's our thesis and our assumptions of why
we think we're going to be successful.
And then these are the steps we're going to do to attempt that.
Is much different than saying, I'm just going to make my cool thing, and maybe by accident.
you know, it'll be successful.
Which is also kind of that difference
between intentionality or hope, right?
As investors, we cannot invest on hope.
We can invest on uncertainty, we can invest on your thesis and assumptions,
we can debate whether or not those assumptions are correct,
we can sort of work towards trying to resolve some of those assumptions
to see if they're right or wrong,
and that intention or intentionality has to be there.
We can't just invest against,
eh, maybe by accident we'll be successful,
maybe hopefully we'll be successful.
as tip two, this kind of catch-all of be intentional.
Even this week, many of the developers we were talking to
would say, ah, well, we created this cool little game
idea at a game jam, and we liked it,
so we're just going to work on it.
Well, have you looked at the market?
Have you seen your competitors?
Do you think there's an audience for it?
Ah, no, we just like this little mechanic,
so we're going to play with it and see what happens.
So, you know, if you're an entrepreneur and you're building a business, you need to be
intentional about building that business.
And one of the things I will often tell developers is designing your business is as important
as designing your game.
So in that sense, from a design point of view,
it makes me think of an old lecture from Will Wright
many, many GDCs ago, where he talked
about the notion of local maxima,
which is sort of mathematical stuff.
I'm not smart enough to actually compute local maxima.
But he was talking about it in terms of design, of game design, in sort of the term that he
used was the opportunity space of gameplay, in that as developers you don't want to get
caught on a local maxima, which means you're at the bottom of one of the hills.
when you're at the bottom of the hill,
you don't really know how high the hill is,
and so you start climbing.
And if you're climbing the hill on the left,
and you get to the top of the hill,
you feel happy that you conquered that hill,
and then it's like, oh crap,
you realize it was a much higher hill
that's actually a much better design,
and I shouldn't have been optimizing
for the local maxima of the small hill,
I should have been on the bigger hill
and optimizing for that local maxima.
And so I think that applies to the business side as well,
in terms of.
that are built.
In that I've often criticized developers
who make couch co-op or local multiplayer games.
Despite the fact that couch co-op games are really fun,
and they show well at events and show well at PAX,
fundamentally as a product they don't sell well.
Because it implies that I have friends.
and that I have four controllers,
and I've got a sofa at my house or my home.
And so you kind of get this false sense of confidence
when everyone's cheering out there at the Indie Mega booth,
and then you release it on Steam and you sell 500 copies.
And so couch co-op games are the Little Hill.
And you have many, many developers
that are building couch co-op games,
and they're optimizing for a local maxima that
inherently is not very high.
And so as an investor, any time someone
comes in with a couch co-op game, it's like, sorry.
You're on the little hill.
Not interested.
That doesn't mean you shouldn't make it, but if you're looking for funding or a publisher,
they're mentally placing you on a hill.
Now, of course, lightning can strike at any time, and maybe your local co-op game is so
crazy amazing that you're going to be way past the local maxima, but as a rule of thumb,
this is the kind of thinking that goes into it.
So I don't know, what kinds of games are on the better hill?
I'm at multiplayer games, I don't know.
MOBAs, things that inherently can scale.
But the problem is, of course, no one really knows
how high the, that's part of the challenge.
But this also does require that you have some sense
of what marketing is.
And most developers get marketing wrong.
in part because they only think about marketing as advertising and PR.
And that's not marketing.
Marketing, I mean, famously there's the four Ps.
One of those Ps is promotion, advertising and PR and so on.
Another P is price.
Which means, what's your business model?
How are you pricing it?
So many developers debate about it.
Do I make it $15 on Steam or $20?
Do I allow sales or not?
Or do I go free to play?
That's price.
Determining the price and the business model
is part of marketing.
Another one, P, is placement.
In the context of the game industry, placement could be, well, which storefronts, which platforms
am I on?
Thinking about where you're going to deliver or distribute the game is part of marketing.
And critically, the fourth P is product.
So actually thinking about and determining what product,
meaning what game are you making, is part of marketing.
And so when we work with our teams,
we try to instill that thinking into them,
that marketing is not relegated to,
I'm gonna put some ads.
but it's really sort of in a much more holistic sense.
And what does that mean?
That means you're thinking about who's the audience.
You know, which hill am I climbing and optimizing for?
Can I get some sense of how tall that hill might be?
Have I done, have I looked at SteamSpy
to see what my competition looks like
and how they're selling?
Have I, or gone on App Annie if I'm mobile.
Have I played the winners in that category
to see what they're doing
and try to think about why they've succeeded?
And did I download a bunch of the losers and games that have failed in that category,
and understood why did they fail, and then, you know, where's my game?
Am I closer to the winners? Am I closer to the losers?
You know, and often that's sort of a fine line.
Many developers don't do that, that competitive analysis, market analysis, audience analysis.
I mean, it's still sort of voodoo magic, right? It's not like...
there's a recipe and just follow these ten steps and you've done your marketing or your analysis.
But, you know, in most cases it's just completely forgotten about and ignored.
And so...
Doing that kind of more broad or holistic sense of marketing,
thinking about the choice of the product that you're making,
and the audience you're delivering it to,
and the price point, and just all those things, in part,
will help ensure that you don't get stuck on a local maxima.
And so that would be the next tip.
is don't, by accident, get caught on a local maxima.
If you're gonna climb a hill,
at least do some homework to determine
if you're probably climbing a good hill.
Because remember, as an entrepreneur,
one of the things is the intent to make profit.
And so don't just end up by accident
on a hill that has no real potential.
That being said, we're gonna make lots of mistakes.
And there's all kinds of stories of failure throughout our industry.
This is an article from quite a few years ago.
You may recognize Arana Gozi and Alex Rogopoulos, co-founders of Harmonics out in Boston.
Famously, they created Guitar Hero and Rock Band at the time.
I think this is an article from 2009.
So at the time, those were still billion dollar franchises.
But the article here kind of goes on
about how they had 10 years of quote, unquote,
horrendous failure.
And that they struggled, and they were exploring
the opportunity space.
They were climbing all the different hills for rhythm
action games, and music games, and all this kind of stuff,
until they sort of discovered the tall hill, which
was good guitar hero and rock band.
And so, you know, part of that, you know, marketing process is this notion of discovery.
You know, obviously, you know, Angerbirds is another one of the famous stories where
Rovio had 51 other games until they, you know, discovered the little red bird and obviously
then that, you know, blew up.
But I mean, I do a whole other lecture just on the value of failure.
And what many people don't fully respect is that amount of time,
that amount of exploration, that amount of failure
is a necessary ingredient to discover the success.
There's no way that if you just sit down and say, OK,
let's make the next billion dollar franchise go.
Like, we just couldn't come up with it.
So anyway, that's a whole other lecture.
I won't go further than that.
But.
That failure is valuable.
And so it's funny because just last week before coming to GDC,
I saw a pitch from some really experienced developers,
primarily from the AAA space.
And they were pitching, saying,
well, we're from the AAA space.
We're going to come to mobile and conquer mobile.
We have all kinds of new ideas of how to, you know,
take over in mobile.
And no one on the team, despite their pedigree,
at least in the materials that were provided,
had any experience in mobile, no experience in free-to-play,
had not worked at any companies in the mobile space.
And so I dismissed it.
And I wrote them back saying, wow, lots of talent.
you know, interesting idea, but you guys have, this is your experience.
And he wrote back, oh no no no no, we worked at game companies, but we didn't like them in the mobile space,
and we were on a few failed projects, but we didn't want to put anything that looked bad on our,
you know, on our resumes and the pitch deck and stuff.
And I'm like, dude, I almost threw your thing in the garbage because you, you know,
you didn't show that you had been in that space and had any experience.
and so they were trying to shield themselves and not show any of that failure.
And as an investor, I always prefer that someone else has paid for that failure.
Either out of your own time or working at some other company,
that is super, super valuable, that failure.
So don't hide that.
A very famous book, who's read The Lean Startup?
Okay, everyone else should read it.
And I have some other book recommendations later,
but this is Eric Ries,
the author of Lean Startup.
And unlike most other business books
or business book authors,
Eric actually worked in the game industry for many years.
I mean, more in sort of social, online, virtual world stuff,
but at least we can kind of consider him one of us
to a certain extent.
But he's not in the game industry anymore.
the lean, people get lean startup wrong, right?
They think of lean as not paying a lot of money,
like we're gonna tighten our belts and we get lean
because we're eating ramen.
But that's not what lean is in this context.
It's about reducing waste, right?
It comes much more from the automotive space
and all the stuff there.
But.
Although Eric doesn't talk about lean startup in this way,
I view the methodologies presented in lean startup
as a recipe for systematic failure.
And that's a good thing, surprisingly,
although I say it like that.
And so one of the key learnings that Eric talks about
as a startup, as a small company,
is to accelerate the rate of learning.
And when you're learning, you're succeeding, you're failing.
And that also relates back to the notion of local maxima.
You have the landscape.
You don't really know which hill is what.
So you have to start climbing the hill.
And as you climb the hill, you're learning,
is this a good hill to climb?
And you want to accelerate the process by which you can learn.
And who's really good at that?
Supercell.
I mean, you know, lots have been written about Supercell,
but the most important thing is how they fail,
and how they value failure, and the whole process
and their culture about, you know, anyone can kill a project at any time.
And so, you know, each of those tombstones was a little hill.
And they recognized it was going to be a little hill,
and they said, folks, the hill's too little, kill it.
you know, let's climb another hill and see where that gets us.
And be able to accelerate that process by which they learn which hills are the good
hills and how many hills do they climb, and their whole company is built on that process
of learning, iteration, discovery, going up the hills, calculating the local maxima, realizing
it's not a good hill, bailing on it, et cetera.
And this also relates back to the notion of sunk costs.
And so the next tip is don't fall in the sunk cost trap.
Cost is one of the most dangerous sort of mental traps that we have as humans.
Right, that if we spent six months of our time and our savings to work on this
cool couch co-op game and then some crazy guy named Jason says you're not
going to make any money with that game why are you making it?
Well, you're going to ignore me because you don't want to lose the time and money you
already invested in making that game.
And so that there is the sunk cost trap.
And in reality, what you've spent, what you've sunk is gone.
You will never get that back.
And all your decisions should be made on a go-forward basis.
So as of right now, if we keep spending time and money on this couch co-op game, is that
a good business decision?
And a lot of people don't do that because it's a psychological weakness or a blind spot
of humans where you don't want to let go of the money you already or the time you already
or the emotion you already spent.
So Supercell for example.
They don't care, right?
The sunk cost trap, they don't have it,
but they're one of the few studios that thinks in that way.
And again, I mean, I think some of my failure lectures
up on YouTube, so if this notion of the failure piece
and sunk cost traps is of interest,
you can Google or check me on YouTube.
Partially, this also requires that
you have some sense of vision.
And a lot of developers, a lot of entrepreneurs
don't take the time to have vision for their studio.
It's not just like the creative vision
of the game I'm building.
It's the vision of the studio, the kind of company,
the pillars, the roadmap of where
we want to go as a business, the kinds of games we want to do,
the kind of culture we want to have, et cetera.
We often talk about this in the context of scaffolding.
That as you're building a business, you need to be thinking about the scaffolding you're
constructing, like you're building this amazing skyscraper.
In order to do that, you have to build the supporting structures around it to allow you
to go higher and higher.
So this is what we call scaffolding.
And if you don't have a vision, it's impossible to make decisions.
that lead you to constructing the scaffolding.
And so, for example, let's say right now we're
working on a couch co-op game.
And once that's done, we're going to do a VR racing game.
Once that's done, we're going to do an idler on mobile.
And once that's done, we have an idea for an MMO.
And essentially, you're restarting from scratch
every time.
Because there's really not much learning and value
that comes from doing the VR racing game to go to the MMO
to go to the idler on mobile.
It's just too random.
You don't have intention.
Whereas if we say, OK, we want to make competitive games
on this particular platform using procedural generation
because we have expertise in that, and I don't know,
whatever, narrative something.
Then the first game you make will have some elements
of procedural and narrative and whatever we said.
And that may or may not succeed.
But the tools you've built, the technology you've used,
the design learning you've had, the person you hired,
the coder you hired that has expertise
in procedural generation is now part of the team.
So that when you go into game two,
It doesn't mean it's a sequel, but it's another game that's
competitive with narrative and procedural stuff.
You're going to take all that knowledge and tool set
and pipeline and the people you used to build the first one,
now you build the second one, and it goes much faster.
Kit Fox, actually one of our studios,
kind of has that sort of vision.
And they had an idea of what the third and fourth game
they really wanted to make was.
But they knew on day one as a startup, they didn't have the resources, the production
capacity, the recognition to get to that third or fourth game, so they kind of backtracked
and said, well, what smaller game can we do now that we have the means for that then allows
us to build the scaffolding to build the second game, and then that one hopefully will build
the scaffolding that will allow us to build the third and fourth game.
That's a very powerful thing.
But you have to be thinking about that vision.
You have to have that roadmap so you
can make those decisions three or four games ahead of time.
And we just don't see that from a lot of developers.
Samantha is co-founder of Artifact 5, also one
of the studios that we invested in.
They're working on a cool, surreal, very emotional,
mature game called Anamorphine.
They've won a bunch of festival awards.
I think they just won Best Narrative at the Game
Connection.
earlier this week.
And it's their first project.
Individually, they've worked at other companies.
So from a production point of view, they're experienced.
But this is their first initiative as entrepreneurs
in their own studio.
And they're just finishing up on anamorphine.
And they're trying to think ahead to the roadmap.
They have the second game they want to work on.
So part of our thinking to come to GDC
was to get some work for hire.
Because there might be some cash flow gaps in their roadmap.
And so I'm going to go to GDC and see if I can pick up
a contract or two.
And I said, don't do that.
That's not part of the vision.
Making some Mickey Mouse game for Disney,
how does that serve your vision of building
mature, surreal, emotional games?
You know, like, why are you going to distract yourselves from that vision?
Oh, well, cash flow.
I said, no, you're building your business with a certain vision, with a certain roadmap.
You have to stick to that.
And the advice I gave her in that particular situation was, now, if you go to GDC and you
find someone who has a movie or an author that's writing a book or a TV show that is
mature, surreal, emotionally driven.
and they need a game done, okay, well now you're talking, right?
There there's potential collaboration, a partnership to happen
that then serves the vision of your studio
and also contributes to the scaffolding of where you want to go.
And so, you know, not that inherently doing work for hire is a bad thing
and in some cases it's necessary just from a survivability point of view,
but make sure you're doing it.
that's still serving the vision and still serving your roadmap
for scaffolding.
And in part.
you need to know that before you go out and hustle.
So Samantha would have really wasted her time
to try to pitch Disney to do some work for hire contracts
or Cartoon Networks or whatever, because that's
not the DNA of their studio.
And so you need to know what you're
selling before you go and hustle.
As another example, also before GDC,
some real veteran developers came to me for some advice
and feedback on their pitch.
And.
They're working on this cool project,
but really they were trying to find investment for the studio.
They had been working on this vision
and thinking about the pillars of the kind of company
they wanted to build.
And so they wanted to come to GDC to find partners
to invest in the company.
And as developers, really, they're
responsible for some of the biggest franchises, billions
of dollars.
So from a pedigree point of view, it's like, yes,
you want to back them.
Really amazing.
But the deck they had.
was like 31 slides.
One slide was the name of the company,
and the other 30 slides were about gameplay mechanics
and the creatures and all the stuff about the game.
I said, well, hold on a second.
You just said you want to sell the pedigree,
like you as founders, your track record,
the vision of the studio,
and you want partners to fund the studio,
and yet you've shown me a logo
and 30 pages of weapons and mechanics
and creature designs.
And, you know, someone who's interested in investing in the company, say, well, I'm not
interested in that.
I don't need to see 30 pages of monsters and whatever, weapons and stuff.
So as the next tip, you really need to know what your vision is before you go out and
hustle, before you go out and find your partners, before you actually know what it is that's
unique and valuable, what you're doing to go out there in the marketplace.
All right.
Next up is revenue versus proof.
What I mean by that, there's kind of two modes of a business.
Either from day one, we're going to go make revenue as quick as possible.
We're going to bootstrap and get a product on market as quickly as possible to generate
revenue because revenue is king and revenue allows us to then build the company and so
on.
So very revenue focused.
Some developers are in the camp, but it's quite rare because often games take a long time to make and need a lot of resources
And it's not an easy path and so most developers are selling proof
Or often what we refer to as
Selling the sizzle versus selling the steak
And so developers tend to sell the sizzle, the pedigree,
our track record, we went to PAX and won an award,
look how awesome the game is, play it, it's fun.
You're selling the hype, the excitement of you,
of the game, of the roadmap, et cetera, versus the stake,
because you don't have the stake yet.
Some investors, a lot of formal institutional investors,
often look past the sizzles.
I don't care about the sizzle, show me the steak.
They invest based on revenue and stuff.
They're sort of more the banker style.
The problem with the sizzle is that no investor
wants to invest to make a bridge
that ends in the middle of the river, right?
Then we might as well have not spent a dollar
to go halfway into the river, right?
Because that bridge that's been built is useless.
And so investors tend to want to ensure that you have a plan,
roadmap, vision, et cetera, budget, and so on,
that gets you to the other side of the river.
And developers tend to be very bad at that.
We often get this sort of pitch where.
Here's my monthly burn, so times 12, that's how much money I need.
So I can work for another year and just get stuff done.
So that sounds like, all right, well, we're just going to start building some of the bridge,
and then 12 months runs out, and we're in the middle of the river, and it was a big
waste.
And so you need to think about budgeting, planning, operations more like a rally, checkpoint
to checkpoint.
You need to ensure that the budget or the revenue, the funding you ask for, the deal
you get, at least gets you to the next checkpoint.
And that checkpoint should be defined not as three months from now, but it should be
defined as the thing that I need to have the proof to convince the next investor to give
me gas in the tank to get to the next checkpoint.
And so this is why there's a whole other lecture I do on funding models and funding stages,
lifecycle and so on, where you approach different investors at different stages, right?
So the very beginning when you have no proof, it's love money, friends and family and fools.
And they're only, you know, only because they love you,
they give you the money, because you have nothing.
So that's the first sort of bit of gas in the tank.
And then you use that money to hire a programmer
and get an artist and make a prototype,
and then you go see some angels,
and then they give you a, and they say,
well, that's really cool.
Okay, I like this sizzle.
I like where you've progressed.
Let me put some more gas in the tank
so you can get to the next checkpoint.
Right, and then the next checkpoint is,
I don't know, you have a first playable, whatever.
And then that allows you to do a Kickstarter
or scores you a, you know, a publishing deal.
But if you're starting at zero, you can't go to the people that are used to investing
at later stages of the race because you're not ready for them.
You haven't built up enough proof.
And so when you're doing your planning, budgeting, fundraising, you always need to budget slash
fund to key proof points.
And it's hard.
You really have to think about, OK, if I'm future me.
And I got to do stuff now and pay people now.
And what's the next thing that's going
to be good enough to convince someone else to give me
a publishing deal or do a Kickstarter or get investment?
As opposed to, I'm just going to keep going for a few more months
and see how far I get, and the bridge is halfway in the river.
On premium, let's say if we're thinking of a Steam game,
oftentimes that could be the next checkpoint
is hitting early access.
Just as an example.
And once we're in early access,
then we see how the game performs,
and that could give us then the confidence
to keep going or convince another investor.
As a side note, one of the problems is
if you've only budgeted to get into early access,
you're in trouble.
Because you need time and resources to iterate and address the feedback you're getting.
So it's not like every little penny until we release it on early access.
It should be every little penny to release early access and have enough time to address the feedback and improve and iterate.
If you're on mobile, it's more like getting into a soft launch.
And then seeing what your KPIs look like from soft launch,
and then having time in soft launch to iterate,
to build enough proof to then go see a mobile publisher
distributor and say, look, I used my earlier funding
to get into soft launch and iterate, and now here's my KPIs.
Now I want the big bucks or the big deal
to then take it to global launch and so on.
So that's an example of what I mean by checkpoint
to checkpoint or proof point, not just, eh,
I need some money to pay my bills for six more months.
You know, that involves a great degree of trust.
And oftentimes, you know, while there is, you know, data in your hand, you know, we're
all here at GDC, this is a really community-driven, close-knit industry.
One of the most compelling lectures I ever saw was from Nathan and Chris from Cappy,
Cappy Barra again, where they did a lecture called Beers with Friends.
And surprisingly, that was a business lecture.
And the point of Nathan was that, you know, fundamentally, we do business with the people
we like.
You know, we, I want to see you succeed.
I think you're interesting and doing cool stuff.
And that matters, right?
And it often is this notion of you're building long-term relationships.
Often what we see is.
A developer wakes up one day and is like, oh crap, I need some money.
Who are the people that have some money?
OK, VCs, publishers.
All right, and they walk out the door that morning and say,
I'm going to go get me some money, because I need it right now.
and they knock on everyone's door,
and you have your first coffee, then another meeting,
then you meet at GDC, then you meet at E3,
and it's like a year later,
and you're still sort of chatting,
because no one's gonna kind of just give you the money
because you waked up one morning,
walked out on the street and said,
I need me some money.
And as an entrepreneur, if you're not accounting
for the time it takes to nurture those relationships,
you're in trouble.
And so we always like to see developers
that are going really early.
And in some cases, even before you are working on a game,
let's say you've done one game and you're
thinking about the next game.
That's a critical time to come to a GDC, for example,
talk to publishers and partners.
And a great question when you're at one of the parties
and, oh, you're a publisher, what are
you looking for these days?
So don't pitch them your thing.
Get them to talk about what they're looking at.
Because you haven't really decided which hill you're going to climb next.
And those are really valuable conversations.
Whereas a lot of developers will say, well, I've got nothing to show, or I'm not ready
to show, so I'm not going to talk to anyone.
It's a lost opportunity.
Never mind, just on a human level,
you need that time to build rapport,
you need that time to build trust,
you need that time to build business friendships and so on.
And so the next tip is make business human.
Think about it as relationships.
Think about it as friends.
I'm not saying you're gonna invite
every publisher, biz dev person to your wedding,
but just think of them as human beings,
not those things that will dispense cash
when I need it when I wake up one morning.
Another great entrepreneur is Eric Zimmerman.
Here in the picture with his wife, Natalie, an architect.
Eric is more well-known for design.
He wrote Rules of Play, he teaches design at NYU,
speaks every year at GDC, does the Game Design Challenge.
Eric and I used to run the session.
So Eric really is known from a design point of view.
But Eric is also a great entrepreneur.
And so by my definition, an independent entrepreneur,
although now he's somewhat more focused on the teaching
side of things.
But Eric ran a game studio called
GameLab in New York City for many years
and was making indie games before we even
were calling them indie games.
It was making casual games before we even
had a label for them, casual games,
and was very, very, very successful.
One of the things that Eric really imparted on me
was
being open to other ideas and other knowledge.
And Eric's well known for being really rigorous about how
he talks about design.
He's not like, ah, it feels fun, so that's what I'm going to do.
He's in the same school with Mark LeBlanc, Doug Church,
and Warren Spector, Robin Hoedeke, who really think
about design in a systemic way and build
models of thinking about how to converse and share and so on.
And so I think as a community, we're
pretty good about that when it comes
to the creative elements.
And GDC is an example of that.
Let's get together, talk about design,
talk about level building,
talk about programming, whatever.
But we're not particularly good at that
when it comes to business.
Inherently, because if you're a designer,
you want to talk about design,
not budgets or whatever.
Notoriously, a lot of people don't read
and go to other sources of knowledge.
So I mean, I mentioned the Lean Startup as an example.
Everybody should read that.
And there's a bunch of other books.
There's so many books, of course.
Startup CEO is a good one.
Innovators' Dilemma is a really interesting one
to sort of understand the kind of broader macroeconomic shifts
in technology industries.
Art of the Start.
is a good one if you're just sort of starting out as an entrepreneur, thinking about how
do I pitch my business, how do I think about how I articulate what I do.
Another one, business model generator or generation is a good one.
Venture deals.
If you're talking to VCs, if you're talking to angel investors and looking at doing a
formal investment into the company.
this will be the best $50 you will ever spend, venture deals.
It really gives you the full inside scoop.
Now, you'll still need a lawyer, but you'll at least
know what they're talking about.
The one I'm reading today is called The Art of Strategy.
And really, there's so many books out there.
Now, in isolation, just reading books
will not teach you to be an entrepreneur.
You have to be feet on the ground, in the juice,
climbing those mountains, failing, iterating, learning.
But if you're doing that day to day,
grabbing a book and saying, there's
this whole whirlwind of stuff in my head and challenges
that I have, and then you read a book,
you're like, oh, crap, I never thought of it that way.
The author has taken the time to give a model to it
and help me see things that I didn't normally
see in what I'm doing.
And so the tip here.
is do not rely on first principles.
Don't rely what comes naturally out of your gut or your head
because there is so much knowledge
with regards to entrepreneurship, business,
in so many elements and aspects.
Now, some of those books and some of those lectures
will not ever say the word game.
So there is a bit of translation, like, well,
how does that apply to game industry?
So there's a bit of work there to do.
But there's so much knowledge, so much knowledge out there.
And I think if you thought about all
of the other elements of what we do in the game industry,
if we all just relied on our gut,
that would be crazy to think that we would only
rely on first principles.
And then the last sort of little bit.
Fellow Canadians, Ray and Greg, co-founders of BioWare,
worked on many awesome games of course, which most folks know,
Mass Effect and Baldur's Gate and all that good stuff.
Maybe it's because they're Canadian, but they were always so humble,
despite their success.
despite the millions and billions of dollars,
they sold the company twice over.
And a bit like the sort of don't rely on first principles,
I mean, Ray in particular was always like this notion
of having humility.
That things are changing all the time,
despite whatever success you've had today
doesn't guarantee success you're having tomorrow.
You have to be humble and have humility,
you have some pride, but also understand
that you always need to be learning.
And then actually Brandon from Riot
used this term, humbitious.
which he said is kind of the entrepreneurial, crazy spirit
of like, against all odds, I have this crazy ambitious
and confidence I'm gonna go and conquer the world,
but I'm also gonna do so at the same time
and be humble about it, and realize I don't have
all the answers that I need to get help
and ask for assistance and sort of treat business
as a human thing as I go out there
and explore the opportunity space of what's possible.
And so my last tip today is, despite going out there
and wanting to conquer the world
and build successful businesses,
do so in a mindset of ambitiousness.
And hopefully with that, you can all go out there
and build amazingly successful studios.
Thank you very much.
All right, I think we have a few minutes for questions.
I'm happy to address stuff that was specifically mentioned,
or if you have sort of other questions,
I'm happy to dig in as well.
Yeah, go ahead.
Well, thank you, first of all, for the talk.
I wanted to come here to shamelessly ask
if I could pitch to you sometime.
Are you making a couch co-op game?
No, I'm definitely not.
We can talk after, yes.
Thank you.
I love couch co-op games.
They're super fun, but it's not investable.
Awesome.
Yeah.
Oh, yeah, go ahead.
Hi, where would you recommend we can find or look for investment?
Ah, yeah, so I would recommend again looking at my GDC Europe talk on funding models and funding stages.
The answer is it depends, and it depends on,
it depends on are you looking for funding for the company or funding for the project?
The company.
Yeah, so all of the publishers, Kickstarter, all the stuff you were thinking of as project finances out the window.
So then you're thinking about the company, then the next question is what stage is the company at?
Am I just starting? Do I have a product? Am I pre or post revenue? Am I in growth stage?
And then each of those life stages of the studio will then determine...
For a city investor in the early stage, where could...
And where are you based?
Here, in San Jose.
OK.
Well, I mean, they're standing on every street corner.
Yeah, I mean, so early stage seed investing is a bit more difficult.
Yeah, the thing is that as a gaming company, I have been here for five months,
and there's not a lot of investors interested in gaming companies.
So that's what I'm asking.
Yeah, well, because most game companies are not doing some of the things
that we talked about, where game companies don't have a vision,
they don't have a roadmap, they aren't thinking about their company...
Well...
They're not thinking of their company as an investable thing.
And you have to be human.
You have to have empathy of saying, well, why is this guy
over here with money going to give it to me?
It can't just be because I need it.
I have to think about what I'm doing as a legitimate
opportunity, and how do I frame it in that way?
And that's not an easy thing for folks that have been so
focused on making games.
It's like, what's the business?
What is the actual opportunity?
What is that vision?
and roadmap. So yeah, check out the lecture on funding models and that will give a bit
more insight.
Okay, thank you.
All right, thank you. All right, go ahead.
Hi, Jason. How are you doing? Great talk.
Thank you.
I have, like, a kind of specific, but you said about the vision, about how you would
counseled this company to not go for Disney and all this kind of stuff or work for hire.
We are currently meeting with an investor and he wants to invest in one of our games
which we try to do narrative heavy, heartwarming kind of narrative games.
But he told me that his intent is to move forward because he wants a company that helps him create educational games.
So right now I am a little unsure if I should like proceed because he wants to invest in one of our projects.
But I don't know if I should keep like the relationship going because I don't think that our vision is the same of what he's looking for.
Right.
Yeah, so I mean a really good situation where it's like
they're putting money on the table and you just want to
grab it, but if you do that, it sounds like you're going to
end up in sort of conflict down the road.
Because like, OK, well you took my money.
Now I want you to go make me these boring educational games.
Or it's like, well, I want to do these
heartwarming narrative.
Like, well, hey, I own part of it.
So that's a difficult thing to do.
And a bit like, as you say, the advice I gave to Samantha
was, if you understand.
Really what your vision is as a company and what you want to do you should only ever accept
partners investors deals
That feed in or scaffolding to help you build that vision
Even though he may be dangling a bag of money, and it's like I'm hungry. I wanted a bag
It's like that's where you have to have that entrepreneurial discipline to say well. This is what I'm trying to build
I'm not going to distract myself
So that's a sort of a conversation you have to have there say hey, buddy
I mean, I'm not interested in educational games
This is what I'm interested if you want to invest that because that vision is interesting to you or we can keep talking
But otherwise it's probably a bad idea to take the money and then later have that conflict or tug-of-war
Yeah, but I mean always nice to have some money in front of you, but thank you all right Dave
All good. So Jason, you talked about, you know, sort of, uh,
picking the hill you're going to scale and assessing its size.
And in general,
we learn about the height of those hills from the flags that the previous parties
of climbers have planted.
What's your approach as an early stage investor to assessing, you know,
hills that climbers haven't gone up yet.
Like where there's clouds and you don't know if it's this high or that high?
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, well I mean, so that's a bit where the sort of, you know, the guesswork comes from,
right?
And so early stage investors, essentially that's the risk they're taking, right?
If I'm a growth investor, well I'm adding a billion dollars over to Riot because they
already placed the flag at the top and it's a known thing, whereas the earlier I go, the
more sort of fog of war is around the base of the hill.
So some investors are set up to do that, which means inherently they're going to accept more
risk, more failure.
So you need to talk to investors that have comfort around that as opposed to later stage
growth investors.
And then on our side, I mean, it's part of us trying to be...
I mean, have our own little sort of half-broken crystal ball
in terms of looking at the trends
and hearing what the buzz is.
And do we go VR?
Do we go e-sports?
What's going to happen with social?
Like all these things, you're trying
to sort of make sense of it.
And then if you're a developer that comes in and says,
I got a crazy idea.
you know, I'm seeing these trends and I think I can build a profitable business that sort of weaves its way through some of these
Trends, you know, that's like oh, that's interesting. Okay, we were also seeing things moving in that direction
All right. Let's talk
whereas
Normally we get really bored by people that say well
I saw the flag that riot put way up there on top of the mountain and me and my one other buddy
We're gonna climb that Matt is like no you're not like don't you know?
So but that's because we're built as an early stage investor
And so we're looking for those kind of risky and there I mean the valley has those early stage investors as well
But you have to talk to those ones not the not the chicken ones. Yeah, not the scaredy-cat ones. All right
I think one last question
Thank you.
So you observed correctly, I think,
that many of the business practices and ways of thinking
are portable across industries.
And for example, the books that you
suggested that are applicable for any type of startup.
One practice in other industries is
that people who know the business
hire external management consultants
who know how to build a business who are coming from outside.
What's your thinking on that for gaming?
Smart.
Are you an external management consultant?
Not in this industry, but yeah.
Yeah, I mean, I think there's a difference between I'm
in it every day, and I'm struggling
and fighting the fight.
And then I go and grab a book, and there's
some nice diagrams and some language
about how to make sense of my daily struggles.
I think that's valuable, as I mentioned.
Hiring an external consultant is another version of that.
Saying, I need help making sense of my daily struggles.
Here's a guru of some kind, so we'll pay him or her to come in and make sense of...
And there's value in that as well, though it's usually quite pricey versus buying a book.
Yeah, I mean, I'm someone that likes to get input and knowledge from everyone and everywhere.
So just sort of treating it as another input point or data stream, I think, is valuable.
Yeah.
Thank you.
I mean, fundamentally, you just do not want to rely on your own gut instincts.
You have to leverage other resources and knowledge.
Yeah.
All right, folks.
Thank you for coming, and enjoy what's left of GDC.