So today I'm going to talk about my level design process.
This is a process that I developed while I was working
on Sunset Overdrive, and then I later applied
while I was doing the initial layout
for Manhattan on Spider-Man.
And so I'll go through each step in the process
and describe how the lessons I learned
on Sunset Overdrive helped me
while I was building Manhattan.
So just a little background on myself.
My name is Josue Benavidez.
I'm a senior designer at Insomnia Games,
and I've worked there for over 12 years now.
And one of the great things about working at Insomniac
has just been all the different games
that I've got to work on.
So on the Resistance games, I worked on multiplayer and co-op
and then on Sunset Overdrive, I got
to design most of the night defense bases and traps.
And then on Spider-Man, I got to do the initial layout
for Manhattan, as well as work on hero progression
and traversal.
And something that I actually struggled with quite a bit
early on was level design.
And this became a real challenge when I was working on Sense
and Overdrive because I was tasked
with building lots of different bases back to back
without a lot of time for iteration in between.
And so I tried to figure out how I
could be a more effective level designer, how
I could build bases faster, better, and more efficiently.
And really, I was looking for a step-by-step process,
particularly to help me overcome one of my biggest challenges,
which was this, figuring out where to even begin.
And I looked up a lot of guides and best practices
and tips and tricks, but nothing that I felt
was totally comprehensive.
Nothing that could take me from this
to the beginnings of a layout to bring it into 3D
and then to final.
And so because I couldn't find anything
that could help me guide me through the whole process,
I started building my own process
and I started to build my own step-by-step process.
So on the first base, after I built the first base,
I wrote down what worked and what didn't work
and then tried to carry that forward onto the next base.
And then I kept iterating and I kept updating this process
after each base.
And so by the end of the project,
I had a pretty solid process for how to build bases
in Sunset Overdrive.
And then I moved on to Spider-Man,
and on Spider-Man I was tasked with
doing the initial layout for Manhattan.
And this felt like a huge task,
and it was almost a little overwhelming
because building something like Manhattan
feels like it's so different from building something
like a Sunset Overdrive base.
But I learned that when I felt overwhelmed,
the best thing to do was just to try to rely on my process.
And so I actually went about laying out Manhattan
using the same steps that I had laid out
for building bases in Sunset Overdrive.
And so that's what I'm gonna go over today.
I'm gonna go over each step in the process
and talk about how each step applied
in both Sunset Overdrive and Spider-Man.
And so this is an overview of the whole process.
And it's define, research, experiment,
confirm, execute, and then reflect.
And it probably seems pretty simple,
and that's because it is.
In my opinion, good design is really about
just applying simple ideas in the right order.
I don't really expect anything that I say today
to really blow anyone's mind.
But at the same time, along with this sort of
simple step-by-step process, there are also 27 sub-steps.
So, this allows us to get into a little bit more detail.
So step one is define.
And this step is really about clearly stating
your intentions for a level or for a space.
And in my opinion, this is both the most important
and yet also the most difficult step to get right.
Because it's really hard to know
what you need to do before you do it.
But if you can clearly define
what you're trying to do up front,
it allows you to avoid a lot of rework.
And so I have a lot of techniques that I use
that try to help me define my intentions early on.
And so I try to break down my intentions
into high-level goals.
And I divide these into thematic goals and gameplay goals.
So really thinking about what are the thematic elements
like the audiovisual experience, the emotional experience,
and the narrative experience.
And then what are the gameplay elements?
What are the mechanics that are in the level?
What's the interactivity of the level?
What are the different functions in the level?
And I form these goals around key questions.
So I ask myself, what sort of story do I want to tell?
What emotions do I want players to feel?
Do I want players to feel scared while they're
playing through the level?
Or do I want them to feel joyful?
What challenges do I want players to overcome?
And most importantly, what makes this level special?
What are the lasting impressions that players
are going to have?
What are they going to remember most?
And then if I'm having trouble deciding between goals,
I always try to pick out ideas or goals
that either scare or excite me the most,
because those are ideas that are interesting,
at least to me.
And I think self-reflection is really important
when you're building a level,
because the level should be fun for you.
If a level that's fun for you is at least one better
than a level that's fun for no one.
And I know that I appreciate risk.
And also, these are your high-level goals.
They should push you.
They should be trying to get you outside your comfort zone.
And it was actually kind of scary
when we started working on Manhattan
and thinking about trying to build a city that
was much bigger than anything we had ever built before.
But in the end, I think the payoff was worth it.
And in a lot of ways, I think we went beyond even
our own expectations because we set these goals that
pushed ourselves.
So now that you're trying to form your goals,
it's also important to make sure.
that you're aligning your goals,
particularly when it comes to thinking about
how your thematic goals and your gameplay goals interact.
Because a lot of times, you may find
that you have conflicts between these goals.
And any of these conflicts are things
that you want to try and resolve early on.
Because later on, when you get further into development,
they can be major points of friction and cause rework.
This is a lesson I learned the hard way on Sunset Overdrive
when we were building the first night defense base.
So I was struggling a lot with trying
to make the gameplay work.
So night defense is like this tower defense mode
where you have enemies streaming in
from different angles and lanes.
And I was struggling with making that gameplay work
with my thematic elements.
And so I ended up just throwing any consideration
for the theme away and focused solely on the gameplay.
And I actually did that by just sort of carving out
the lanes that I wanted the enemies to take
to get to the base.
And I got something that, from a gameplay perspective,
I thought worked pretty well and was pretty well balanced.
And then when it came to trying to figure out the layout,
I just sort of filled in the in-betweens with geometry,
but didn't really think about what the actual
thematic element of the base was gonna be.
And so this put a lot of pressure on the environment team
to try to realize the space and make sense of the space.
And in the end, it didn't really make very much sense
because I didn't bother, I didn't have the forethought
to think out what the theme was gonna be.
And so what we ended up with was a weird mishmash of things
where it's sort of like this diner
at the bottom of a corporate office
in the back of a neighborhood next to a shopping mall.
Didn't really make sense, even a game like Sunset Overdrive.
So when I moved on to the next base,
I wanted to make sure that my thematic and my gameplay
goals were better aligned.
So I knew for gameplay, I needed things like rails
and surfaces to grind on, but I also
needed ways to create lots of small substructures
to form lanes.
And so I came up with the idea of a brewery, which
would allow me to have a lot of things like pipes and vats
and things to bounce off for traversal,
but also allow me to create lane structures better.
And the transition from the rough art to the final art
was a much smoother process because I had worked out
the theme ahead of time.
And so the artist and the environment team
could really just focus on applying Sunset Overdrive style
and not trying to figure out what the space actually was.
So on Spider-Man, we knew we had potential conflict
with some of our goals.
One of our goals being that we wanted the world
to feel like a real place, like the actual city.
And the other goal being we wanted the traversal
to be smooth and fluid.
So when you're building things like a real city,
you come up with lots of elements
that are potential hazards for traversal.
I didn't bring a laser pointer
because I thought it would be a lot closer to the screen.
So, sorry.
So you have important details for real-world elements,
like things like billboards, little air conditioners.
You've got water towers, right?
Those things are necessary to build a real world,
but they become potential hazards for traversal.
So we made sure that we could support those things,
but that also whenever we included an element like that,
we had some traversal move or some way
that the player could overcome a flow over or through them
smoothly.
So while you're building your goals,
it's also really important to rank your goals.
You want to try to form them in a hierarchy if you can.
And most importantly, if you can,
try to figure out what the most important element of your level
or your space is.
This will help you while you're iterating on the space.
This will help you while you're resolving feedback.
But also, this will help you when you're considering
spaces between each other.
Because
You might have similar goals between different spaces,
but you might find that the priority shifts a little bit
between each space.
So this is the boat base on Sunset Overdrive.
And in this base, the boat theme was really
the theme that took priority.
We had to pull back a little bit on some of the gameplay
elements, but that was OK because we knew we really
wanted to have a base on a boat.
This was an idea that came from pre-production.
This was an idea that we thought would be really
important to include in the game.
And I'm glad we did because I think it adds a good amount of
variety to the total number of bases that we had.
So when we were thinking about the goals and defining our
goals for Manhattan.
Again, one of the main goals we had is we wanted it to feel like a real place.
We wanted it to feel like the actual city.
And more importantly, we wanted it to be familiar to people.
We wanted it to be familiar to players, even to players who have never actually been to
Manhattan, who maybe are only familiar with the city through TV and movies.
And what this meant was that we had to focus on things that people had seen before in TV
and movies.
And that meant we focused a lot on the landmarks.
And so, and I'll just, I'll go over to this side this time,
for fairness sakes.
And so, what we have here is we wanted to make sure
the landmarks were called out, even in the rough form.
So you can see that there's this big, tall
structure thing here, and even though you don't know
what it is exactly, you can tell that it's probably
pretty important, and we wanted it to stand out.
And also, we've got another kind of little structure
here too, that's called out, and also seems like
it might be a pretty important thing.
And this is something that we wanted to be evident,
even in the rough form.
Because when we took it to final,
those things ended up becoming important landmarks
like the Empire State Building, the Chrysler Building,
which are probably two of the most iconic buildings
in the city.
And so we wanted to make sure the players could
see those from different areas of the city.
And the landmarks ended up being the actual foundation
of the initial map.
So we went about creating the first map
by just plopping down all the different landmarks
that we wanted, and then including some of the roads
that we knew that were going to be important.
Iconic.
like Park Avenue.
And then from there, we filled it
in with the more generic roads and locations.
And this became the layout in the first map for our city.
So step two is research.
And I think for a lot of people, this step seems pretty obvious.
Of course, you're going to do research on a location,
particularly if you're building a location like New York,
which is based off of real space.
But I include this step, and I think
it's an important thing to consider,
because I found a lot of times I was
overconfident on my own knowledge of a topic.
I would think that I already knew a thing,
so I didn't need to do that much research.
And then when I eventually went back and actually did research,
I found details and things that I had missed.
Also, when you're starting on a new project
or you're starting on a new level,
It can be really tempting to try to just jump in
and start building right away.
But it's important to take a step back
and try to do a little bit of research
because a lot of things that you can learn,
there's a lot of actual time you can save yourself
by doing the proper research first.
So as an example, this is the first layout
for the brewery base actually that I showed earlier.
And I was super excited to start on a new base.
So I just started laying things out in 2D.
Because I figured, oh, I know what a brewery is.
I mean, I've been to BJ's.
They have things like pipes and vats and things.
I get it.
And so I just started laying things out.
But then I realized.
You know, this stuff's not really working out.
The layout's not vibing right.
Things don't seem to make sense.
I was struggling with why was I having such a hard time
with the layout.
And I realized it was because I didn't do
my proper research.
And so I ended up stepping back,
doing more research on breweries,
and then I found structures and things
and more useful tools that I could use
when I was laying out the space.
So when you're doing research,
it's also really important, if you can,
to try to go beyond just reference images.
Places in the world are meant for people.
They're meant for people to use them.
And a lot of times, there's a lot of times
the getting into the mindset of the people that
are meant to inhabit the space will
help inform you on the decisions on why
those spaces were constructed.
And so if you can get an understanding
for the actual people that inhabit your space,
it helps you understand the reasoning behind that space.
And for Spider-Man, I actually ended up
reading a lot of travel guides for the different neighborhoods
around the city.
And I even joined some of the online communities
that were really just meant for people who lived in the city.
And one thing that I learned from this research
was that people like to talk about the subway system a lot.
People who live in New York are always posting about,
either there's a delay, or there's a shutdown,
or the subway's flooded.
It's really a major element of their everyday life.
And because we were trying to bring the city to life
for people, for our players, we knew this was something
that we wanted to include.
And even though our city doesn't have an actual functional subway network,
we still tried to deliver on that theme by having it as part of our fast travel.
So whenever the player flash travels, you get to see Spider-Man taking the subway.
And it's just a good way we can connect with people on and
make the space feel more real.
So speaking of allowing research to help you do some of the work for you is.
you can really learn from what other games have done.
A lot of times, something you're trying to do
has been tried before.
And my favorite version of a prototype
or a first pass at a level is something
that's been done in another game.
Because you can see what sort of issues come up
when you try to take something to final implementation.
And just because something doesn't work in another game,
doesn't mean it won't work in your game.
There might be techniques or circumstances
that you can apply that will make it work.
But at the same time, there's no reason
to repeat the same mistakes exactly as another game did.
So one issue that I knew that we might run into from playing
other Spider-Man games was rooftop spaces.
So rooftops actually are a significant part
of a city space.
And yet, they're a big challenge for a character like Spider-Man
because Spider-Man needs tall things to swing from.
And generally, when you're on a rooftop,
you don't have anything to swing from.
So we went about trying to handle this by first making sure that whenever we have a low space right here,
we try to have a tall building next to it so there's something for you to swing from.
And then on our rooftops, we also try to include lots of elements for the player to either parkour or vault over to help you cross the roof quicker.
And in the end, we actually ended up
creating a brand new traversal move called the point launch,
where you can actually just zip to an object on the roof
and then bounce and leap off to allow you to quickly
and fluidly overcome rooftops.
And so we ended up taking the rooftops from a problem space
to something that's more in the player space
and included in the gameplay experience.
And then speaking of playing the other Spider-Man games,
during research, I think it's really important
that you actually play the games, particularly the games
that relate to the content or the project that you're on.
I hear a lot of discussion about, as developers,
how much should we be playing games?
And I think, as a designer, it's really your responsibility
to play the game.
And then also, give the game the time it needs
to really understand the experience.
A trap that I see people fall into is,
they'll pick up a game and play it
for maybe like an hour or two and then drop it
and think that that's all they need to do
to get the experience.
I found a lot of times mechanics or the real insights
in other games don't really unlock
until kind of the later half of the game.
And then for Spider-Man, I actually
went through and played every Spider-Man released on console
since the first Spider-Man on PlayStation 2.
And I played through them, most of them, all the way through.
And there were a lot of things that I learned in those games
that I wouldn't have missed had I dropped the games early on.
So again, I think it's important.
So if you can, play the games and give them the time they need.
So step three is experiment.
And this is where you get to dig in and start trying ideas out.
But I call this step experiment because it's
important that while you're at the stage,
you're trying to answer questions.
So again, I think that when you're
starting on a new project or a new level, it's very tempting.
to want to just dive in and start building things
that you know.
If you know what a thing is supposed to be,
you just want to make it.
But at this stage, it's not really
helpful to work on what you know.
It's more helpful to work on things that you don't know.
So you want to focus on things that you
need to prove big questions that you have or major risks.
You want to try those things out sooner
and then get those things out of the way
so they don't cause conflicts later on.
And while you're building these experiments,
try to build them in a controlled way
where you can control for variables
and you can get results that are quantifiable if you can.
This is where you start building metrics
and this is where you start to define things like
how big should spaces be,
how many characters are gonna fit in there,
how long is it gonna take the player to get through it.
And when you're doing these experimental layouts,
It's also important to not really think of them as a rough.
I think of them more as sketching,
because you're trying to get to your answers quickly.
And so you want to focus on just the things you need to do
to answer your questions,
and not get too hung up on details
that don't really relate to the questions
you're trying to answer.
So as an example, this is what I would consider
a sketch for the first layout of Manhattan.
And I call it a sketch because none of the building details
are really accurate.
In fact, a lot of buildings aren't even called out.
There's a lot of blocks that are just
sort of one square per block.
And there are a few landmarks in there,
but again, it's not very accurate.
The only thing that this really does answer
is how big is the city going to be?
And what is it going to feel like when
you're inside a city this big?
And that was what I was trying to answer with this.
I wasn't really trying to get into the details of building
heights and swing metrics.
I was just trying to figure out, what's
it going to be like when we're in a city the size of the one
we want to build?
Compare this to something like this,
which is a little bit more accurate to what
we built in the final game.
So you've got buildings that are called out correctly.
Things are at the right height.
This is definitely a much more detailed rough.
This is what I would consider a rough and not just a sketch.
This layout, however, took us weeks to get to.
And in fact, I needed to work with a Houdini expert
to generate a lot of this procedurally.
Not something we could get to quickly.
Whereas the previous example, this one I built in,
I think, maybe a day, two days max.
And so I was able to quickly get to answering the question of,
does this feel like the right size space for what
we're trying to build?
And during experimenting, it's important to try to be agile.
Again, try to work quickly.
Try to get to your answers quickly.
Don't be afraid to throw things away.
This is the safe space to try things that aren't going to work
and then just toss them when they don't work.
And if you can, work in physical.
I think it helps to bring things into the real space
and bring it out of the computer.
So as an example, hopefully you guys can see this,
when we were talking about traversal,
I got this little toy on a string
that I was just like, okay, how does swinging work?
Because our swing model is a physics-based model.
So I was like, okay, well, can he just do this?
What does it work when you're doing this?
And so we would work in the physical space a little bit
when we were talking about traversal.
And then how that applies to level design
can come back to that sketching idea.
So I talked before about how I sketched the lanes out
for that first sunset overdrive base,
and while not considering the theme was a bad idea,
sketching things out on paper actually did
what was really helpful in defining the gameplay.
And so when I built the other bases,
I actually started by just sketching out
all the different lanes on paper,
and so I could quickly get through lots of different lanes
and lots of different layouts by just drawing
lines and sticks and circles.
And then I just had to make sure that
whatever layout I came up with
would have some kind of recognizable theme in the end.
And while you're also working quickly
in this sort of experimentation phase,
it's important to make sure that you're keeping
the player's perspective in mind.
So I think one trap that's easy to fall into
is when you're a developer,
is you can get kind of locked into editor space
where you have top-down knowledge of the entire level.
But players don't have top-down knowledge.
Players have a limited FOV, generally speaking.
And so they can only fit so much into one view.
And so while you're building and while you're sketching,
it's important to consider that.
What is the player going to actually be able to capture?
in one view.
And you can do this even if the game's not playable.
And in fact, again, talking about sketching,
sometimes I would start a layout,
before I even did a top-down 2D layout,
I would just try to draw a little perspective sketch
of what a player might see standing
at one point in the level,
just what are the different things that are called out.
And again, it just helps you get
into the mindset of the player.
So our experimentation in Spider-Man
was focused a lot on defining building metrics, sizes,
and scales, and also traversal standards.
And one of the first metric we worked on
was the city block size.
We wanted to define how big were our city blocks going to be.
Were they going to be real scale,
or were they going to be something scaled down?
And so I started by building a bunch of different city block
layouts, different sizes.
And again, trying to create experiments
that control for variables, I tried
to use the same geometry in each experiment
and making sure that the only real difference between them
were the size of the city blocks.
And so at the top, we have something
that's a little bit more like the size of city blocks
you would see in the real world.
And in the middle is something a little bit more in between.
And that's what we ended up on.
And then another big metric that we worked on early on
was trying to figure out the size of street widths.
And so again, our swing model is based on a physics model.
And with that kind of a model, the smaller gap
you have between swing points, the more reliable swinging
feels.
But at the same time, the tighter the space
you put the player in, the more confined they feel.
So we had to try to figure out what's that sweet spot
between street widths.
And I did that by building one almost infinitely long street.
And it started with very narrow streets at one end,
and it progressively got wider and wider and wider
as you went down the street.
And then we would just swing up and down the street
and try to figure out where was that sweet zone?
Where did it feel right on both ends?
So for the city, for the building heights,
we wanted to make sure that we could get a good diversity
in building heights.
And I also wanted to make sure that we could standardize.
We could say that, hey, this area is a low building height
area, this area is a mid-range building height area,
and this area is a high-range building height area.
But we wanted to make sure that those different height ranges
would read against each other.
So that if we have an area like Hell's Kitchen, which
is supposed to be a low height area,
you could tell where that is supposed
to be versus an area like Midtown, which
is a medium to high rise area.
So I built a little test level where each area was called out
by a different color, and each area
was contrasted and set next to a different height range.
So we can make sure that those two different heights
would read well against each other.
And then we experimented a lot with Central Park too.
Central Park is a major element of Manhattan,
and it's a major consideration when you're building Manhattan
because it is central.
If you change the shape and size of Central Park,
you actually change the shape and size of the entire city.
So we wanted to make sure that we got the size right.
We wanted it to feel big and impressive,
but at the same time, we wanted it to be manageable.
And so at the far right, we have something
that's a little bit closer to the actual size of the city.
And again, we ended up on something
that was a little bit more in the middle.
So at this point, you've been playing
with a lot of different ideas.
And you've been doing a lot of different experiments.
And you probably feel like you're
ready to really start building stuff.
But before you go into more final implementation,
it's important to take a step back and to verify.
that you're on the right track.
First thing to verify is just your goals,
the fundamental things that have been driving you so far.
Sometimes you set a goal for yourself and you achieve it,
but in the end, the results you get
really aren't the thing that you're looking for.
And so this is a point in the process
where you can take a step back
and redefine your goals if you need to.
You also want to make sure that all the experiments
and everything you've been working with
are at the proper scale and have believable logic
and believable flow.
If you've been doing experiments at the wrong scale,
the results you get aren't gonna be accurate
when you start doing final implementation.
If you've only been working with a single scale clue,
like maybe like the player height,
you may not realize that things feel out of scale
when you start implementing things like doorways
or smaller props.
And you also need to make sure
that it'll eventually actually run
when you deploy it on your platform.
So again, at this point, you've been kind of blue-skying it,
just trying out ideas.
And you may not have been taking a lot of consideration
to the technical aspect of what you're trying to build.
And the tricky thing about this step
is that you don't always know the exact parameters
and the exact technical constraints
you're going to have when you do finally
deploy it onto the platform.
So you need to consider whether or not
you need to build in safety nets and have ways
that you can scale back if you need to.
And you also, before you go forward,
need to make sure that you're sharing your vision.
Again, at this point in the process,
you might have been working very quickly.
This whole up until now, it could have only been a few
hours, and before you go through to final implementation
or start doing the more expensive work,
you need to make sure that you're sharing what you're
trying to do with everyone else.
And also explain your goals and try to explain the intent
behind what you're trying to do.
If you show people what you were trying to,
if you tell people what you were trying to do,
and they see what you actually did,
that really helps inform them on the shortcomings.
And if you can, as much as possible,
only move forward with complete confidence at this point.
You've been working fast, and you've been working loose.
Hopefully, everything you've built so far
can be thrown away, and you can start over if you need to.
And this is the point to start over.
After this point, things get more costly,
and it becomes much more expensive to do rework.
And so you want to make sure that you're
very confident when you start doing final implementation.
And I also think this is the step that
scales well with the project.
So for Spider-Man, we had been defining a lot of metrics
and a lot of standards.
But I wanted to be very confident
that we were building the right thing
and that we were going to build the right thing,
because we didn't have a chance to try
to build the entire city and then start over
if we didn't build it right.
And the city is very different and very varied.
There are lots of different areas and architecture
and layouts throughout the city.
So I wanted to make sure that metrics
that we were defining for one area of the city
were going to work throughout the whole city.
So I took our map layout that we had made,
and I took slices from it, and I composed those slices
in a scaled-down version of the entire city.
And this became our first real practical test
of all of our metrics.
And this became our main testbed for all of our metrics
and traversal standards that we had been building.
So after you have confidence and you
feel like you're ready to go forward,
now is when you start to apply all of the metrics
and the standards you've been building.
Now is when you start to really define the final rough.
You want to snap things to metric.
You want to clean up your edges.
Ideally, this is where the rough actually
starts to look like the final game,
or as close to it as you can with your level of resolution.
And you also need to make sure that you're integrating
the rest of the gameplay that you've been building.
So hopefully before this point, you've
been playing with gameplay, and you've
been doing experiments, but you need
to make sure that it's all connected,
and that the game plays the way you expect it to play.
And inevitably, you're going to run into some conflicts
when you start doing implementation
of the final gameplay.
And so you may need to adjust.
And hopefully, you don't have to do major rework.
But this is a case where you may have
to step back through the process and redefine some of your goals.
So one issue that we had in Spider-Man
was the road network in the bottom half of the city
is very complex.
And that's because a lot of these roads
follow most of the roads in actual Manhattan.
And so the traffic system we had been building
wasn't really built to handle this.
And the traffic system we were building
was mostly built for four-way intersections.
But some of these intersections have five or even six ways.
But we knew this was still important to have these really
complicated intersections because, again, we
wanted it to feel like the real city.
And the real city has these types of things.
So what we ended up doing was, for some
of these complicated intersections,
we ended up just blocking off a few of the roads.
So one road might be under construction,
so there was no actual traffic going through it.
or one road might just have parked cars in it.
And so we converted some of our six or five-way intersections
back into four-way intersections so
that we could achieve both the goals of building something
that felt like the real city, but that would actually
work with the traffic system.
And then at this point, you get to a point in your level
where you basically just continuously test and iterate
on the level.
So you've been testing and iterating on it
before this point, but this becomes the entire process.
And this is pretty much where you take the game to final.
And during the testing and iterating phase,
you're going to come into contact with a lot of feedback.
And so it's important to have a plan for how you're
going to resolve your feedback.
And this is where I like having those goals
and that hierarchy of goals, because this allows me
to better evaluate feedback.
And it's important to also not be dismissive.
you can have a very personal attachment with your level.
And so sometimes you can get a emotional response
to feedback.
But that's the advantage of comparing everything
to your goals, because it allows you to detach a little bit
emotionally.
And so when you get feedback, you can go, OK,
does this feedback align with what I'm trying to do?
Maybe this feedback is pointing to a goal
that's a lower tier than the goal I was trying to service.
And so it's OK to ignore it.
Or maybe this feedback really does
tell me I need to make some adjustments to what
I was building.
So when we were starting to execute the final rough
across the city, we started to actually build
the rough into more detail.
So once we were confident with all of our metrics
and we knew that what we had been experimenting with
was the way we wanted to go with the city,
we can start building the rough and start
matching the buildings more to their final form.
So the rough started to look more like the final level.
And we could build those details with a little bit more
confidence that the details would carry through
and wouldn't be lost in the final level.
So the last step is reflect.
And even though this is the last step,
this was actually the first step in the process for me.
Because this whole process started with me just thinking
about how I could improve my process
and how I could do better the next time.
And then a fortunate part of this step
is it usually comes after you've run out of time.
I find that I always have the most insight
after I've run out of time to act on it.
And so I try to learn from that, and I
try to carry that insight forward
and do better the next time.
Now, I also have a little bit of what
I call kind of a dubious personal philosophy,
in that even though I've run out of time,
I always think to myself, is it really too late?
So.
Because in that reflection process,
I try to think to myself, well, is there anything
that I can still act on?
Is there anything that I can still do to improve this?
And so I include this as an important part
of trying to think about what can
you do to actually improve the level in its final stages.
So one example of that on Spider-Man
was something that we.
wasn't part of the initial layout of the city
were the faction bases.
So we had these different bases around the city
that have enemies and thugs in them
that you can go through and battle
in sort of a challenge type mode.
And we ended up implementing these
kind of late in the process.
And we actually had to rework a lot of final art
to get them in.
But we knew it was worth it
because we wanted to have those spaces
that would challenge players.
And we wanted to have spaces that would really allow players
to exercise their mastery of the game.
And reflecting on the whole project,
and thinking about what I could do better,
I do think that initially I was so focused
on all of the metrics that I didn't build enough space
in for the environment team in some of the.
to add details to some of the street level stuff.
And we actually did end up having to rework
some of the street metrics.
So after we built about half of one of the first districts,
we realized we didn't have enough space on the streets
to include the props that we needed
to really make the world feel detailed enough
to make it feel real.
And that was one of our major goals.
We wanted it to feel like a real space.
We wanted it to feel real.
And so we made the decision to change the street metrics,
which ended up having to do a lot of rework
in that first area.
Luckily, we did this soon enough to where it wasn't
detrimental to the whole project.
But it would have been better had we considered, or had I
considered, that had I considered a better buffer
zone for the propping spaces early on.
And we also did end up shaving off some
space from the city.
So we actually ended up taking off some
spaces from the sides.
But this ended up being okay because we found that if we took space off the sides, it still
felt right.
It still felt like Manhattan and it didn't really disrupt the layout or it didn't disrupt
our landmarks very much.
We also considered if we could take space out of the middle of it and we found when
we tried to take space out of the middle, it disrupted a lot of things.
It made the shape not feel like Manhattan and it disrupted the position of all of our
landmarks.
And so considering our goals of trying
to make this feel like a real space,
we knew that we would be OK if we took space out of the sides,
but we needed to leave the space in the middle alone.
And I think that all of the experimentation, all
of the confirming that we did, and all the planning that we
did, and all the research we did,
really shows off when you compare the initial sketch
to the final product.
Because there are a lot of similarities between the two.
And so reflecting on the actual process itself,
during applying the process on Spider-Man,
is when I really thought about experimenting with intent.
And so thinking about this as a scientific process
and not just as freeform experimentation,
but trying to actually answer questions.
And then also thinking about using evidence
to support what I was trying to do.
So again, one of the scary things about building Manhattan
was it's a huge level.
And we didn't have the time to try it once and then restart
over and try it again.
So we had to be sure and confident with everything
we were trying to do.
And we basically needed to accurately predict
what the outcome was going to be.
And I find that when you're trying
to make accurate predictions, it's good to have evidence.
So I started thinking about the experiments I did
and the research I was doing as evidence
when I was trying to predict how well the final level was
going to come out.
So in summary, you want to define,
so define your thematic and your gameplay goals,
form goals around key questions,
and resolve conflicts you may have
between gameplay and thematic goals.
You want to do research,
you want to make sure you do research
even if you think you're familiar with the content,
and you want to try to go beyond reference images.
And be sure you play the games
and make sure that you give the games the time they need
to really understand the full experience.
And then when you experiment, try to answer key questions.
Try to build controlled experiments.
Think of this phase like sketching,
so don't get too hung up on details yet.
And be OK with throwing things away.
Being OK with starting over if you need to.
And then confirming, you need to make sure you step back
and verify your goals.
Check your scale, your logic, your flow.
And if you can, only move past this step with confidence.
And then execute, this is where you define the final rough,
this is where you lock down metrics,
you clean up your edges.
And everything should start to finally play
like you expect it to.
And then finally, reflect.
Consider what you could have done better,
consider what about how you can improve the process,
and consider whether it's really too late
to try to improve your level.
And so.
The main point I have is a base in Sunset Overdrive
is a very different type of space from the city of Manhattan.
Yet the same fundamental process was used to build both.
And that's really the power of a good process.
And that's really the power of good old-fashioned level
design.
Thank you.
So I think they're doing questions now,
if anyone has any questions.
There's microphones if you have questions.
Yeah, you can go first, you go first.
I'll go back and forth.
Hello.
Hi there.
Okay, so I'm wondering each steps,
how long, for example, like for,
take Spider-Man as example,
how long did it take for each steps?
How long for each step?
Well, it would have been good if I had recorded that.
So for example, to get to one thing I do know
is to get to the initial map, basically that first map
where we had everything filled in.
For me, that was about three months of work.
I know that because I started on the project in January,
and I had to get the map done before my daughter was born,
and she was born in March.
So it was about a three month process.
And then from the rest of that, the process
kind of blends into most of the game.
And sometimes you do step back and go back and forth.
So it's not always done in discrete chunks.
OK, thank you.
So I just want to ask about the DLC.
When you guys had to work, when you finished the game
and you had to start on the DLC, how
did you approach the level design for the DLC
as well, knowing that you're going to reuse the same map
but change some things in it?
Well, I wasn't as involved with the DLC,
so I can't speak to that as specifically.
I do think that there are a lot of constraints
that go into that, though, when you're
trying to approach spaces that are already built.
And that was actually some of the challenges
that we had, actually, with the.
just the initial release game, because the city was so big,
we had to basically start building it from the beginning.
And we ended up having to do a lot of final art
before we had a chance to build all the gameplay
in every area, because we needed to basically just start
building final art almost right away.
And so there were a lot of challenges
that a lot of designers had, because they ended up
having to build in a lot of gameplay spaces
that were already final.
And so it's always just looking for opportunities where.
you can build something new and looking for opportunities
where you can reuse spaces that are already used.
Okay, thank you.
How you doing?
My name's Josh.
I work on a relatively large map too.
It's 8K by 8K in Unreal units.
Oh, nice.
Mine is 3K by 8K.
Yeah, I saw.
Early on in development, once the levels really
started taking shape, we obviously
ran into performance issues.
It being such a big map, obviously it probably
came up when you guys were building the city of Manhattan.
What kind of challenges did you have with performance,
and how did you solve those issues?
So performance was the big consideration for us.
Actually, part of the 8K limit was beyond 8K,
there'd be dragons, I guess.
There's some sort of math issue with going beyond that.
And so they're like, don't go bigger than that.
So that was the initial boundary.
But we did have some previous history
with streaming on Sunset Overdrive.
So we had some metrics that we could build from.
And we knew, and again, talking about scaling,
we knew there were certain things that we could scale back.
And so we had idealized metrics that we wanted to hit.
And we knew there was ability to scale there.
And then ultimately, one of the things we do at Insomniac
is just sort of rely on our awesome engine
and technical teams.
I don't know what those guys do.
I think they're wizards.
But I just say, hey, I want to do this thing.
It's going to be insane.
Can you do it?
And somehow they figure it out.
Hi.
What part of the process do you start
worrying about where the story missions take place
and how many collectibles there are everywhere, all the sort
of gameplay specifics like that?
I mean, we were trying to map that out from the beginning.
We tried to make sure that each of the locations...
I think one thing that helped that we knew
that a lot of those things were probably
gonna pivot around landmarks too,
because that makes for interesting gameplay
if you have a mission or something that takes place
at a well-known location, right?
Particularly in something like Manhattan.
So, we tried to make sure that there was
a good distribution of landmarks
to help people build missions around there.
We would map things out early.
So we would map things out early.
We would do sort of speculative mission flows
throughout the city, and then just
try to accommodate whenever missions did come up.
Thanks.
OK.
You mentioned playing games and studying them
to learn things from them and play through the whole thing
to learn things.
Do you have a specific process or things that you look for
or how you go about doing that to learn the most
and get the most out of it as a designer?
Yeah, I mean, obviously, it's a little bit easier
when you're making something like Spider-Man, right?
Because you just go play all the Spider-Man games.
But I also looked for, I try to find common elements
or common threads, or things that I want to achieve
that either have been done well, or maybe were tried
in kind of a crazy way in a different game.
So, obviously, you play through all the Spider-Man games,
but then there are other games that take place in New York,
and so it's important to try to play those games.
There are also games that are trying to go for just the feeling of New York.
And so I work with looking at games that achieve critical claim,
right, or are related to what I'm trying to do,
or to just do something unique and novel.
And in terms of finding those games, I guess
that could be a difficult challenge, right?
There's lots of diamonds in the rough out there.
I feel like that's why it's important just as much as you
can try to do research and try to play games.
Because what you'll find is by researching for one game,
you may see an interesting or unique element
that you can maybe remember.
And then you can come back and revisit
that when you are doing research for another thing.
So it just helps us try to, as much as you can,
try to build that repertoire of interesting mechanics
and interesting games to reference.
Thank you.
Hi, I love all the transference from Sunset Overdrive to Spider-Man.
That seems to be like a key thing.
Was there anything you thought players overlooked in Sunset Overdrive
that you were really proud to bring back in Spider-Man
that maybe they didn't catch the first time around?
I mean, you know, we were really proud of and I guess felt like
Sunset Overdrive was overlooked in general.
But again, a lot of it just comes, again,
with just sort of the basic principles of the design
and trying to build the diverse and different layouts
for the world.
There are a lot of other principles
of just trying to invoke.
One big thing that I was really big on with Sunset Overdrive
was including natural elements.
I was really big on just adding trees and waterfalls
and anything that could anywhere we wanted.
And for Manhattan, I was super big on Central Park.
I wanted Central Park to be this really beautiful, natural space.
Because I felt like it was important that we gave players
a break from the city.
And so a lot of the effort that went behind making sure
that Central Park is actually, compared
to the rest of the map, a pretty massive space, even though it's
totally different from everything else.
A lot of that comes from.
all the desires to create natural spaces in Sunset Overdrive.
And so I think that was a big inspiration that was brought over.
So I thought it was really fascinating what you were showing about the burden on you specifically
building the layout for this space, this massive space.
And specifically with regards to level design.
What kind of division of labor came on later in the project?
To what extent did...
Were you able to then start breaking chunks up?
And when were you able to start doing that
from your base layout state, if you did at all?
You mean division of labor between the design side
and the environment side?
Specifically, actually, within design,
like did you then, once you got your core layout built,
did you then start dividing up districts for other designers?
Or was that primarily your responsibility
the whole way through, and then working with environment art?
Or?
Well, that was actually the original intent,
was to basically try to do like a first pass
layout for the city, first pass like designer layout,
and then.
the other designers would come in and build the gameplay
into the level.
Unfortunately, what happened was,
because we found we needed to start building the level,
so building the actual final art so quickly,
and a lot of the initial gameplay ended up being
things more like interior spaces,
a lot of designers ended up having to actually
build spaces into final art,
instead of being able to come back and work in the layout.
One thing we started doing later on
was a lot closer to the phase where
we started considering bases that I think
would have been good to include sooner
if we were to rebuild the whole city again, which
I don't think we will, is to try to get people to basically just
build speculative space.
We did that in a few areas where we were just like,
we don't know, but this is maybe a space for something cool.
It's like an arena.
Put something there if you want.
And so we built some of those, but I
feel like we could have built more of them
because.
We ended up doing things quicker on the art side
than we could keep up with on the design side.
Thank you.
All right.
All right, everyone.
Thanks for coming.