My name is Nolan Carnahan.
I'm an Engine and Graphics Programmer at Ember Lab,
the studio that made Kane and Bridge of Spirits.
And in this talk, I'm going to cover some of the VFX
and tech art that went into realizing
the dead zone restoration sequences
and the round abilities in game.
So for some context, Ember Lab is a small animation studio
turned game studio.
and Kena Bridge of Spirits was our first big game.
The studio had previously worked on the effects
for commercials and short films,
but I imagine more of you would probably recognize
the team's work on Terrible Fate,
a Majora's Mask fan film that went viral
apparently five years ago
because time has no meaning at this point.
That said, I personally joined the team to work on Kena,
and while I certainly did a lot of work
on the content I'll be presenting,
I do want to stress that it was definitely a team effort
across.
art, programming, and design to arrive at where we did.
So for anyone not familiar with the game,
Cana Bridge of Spirits is a third-person
action-adventure game featuring the spirit guide Cana
and her fluffy round spirit companions called the Rot.
Throughout the game, you come across this corruption
covering the land that we called Dead Zone,
which usually manifests in locations
tied to lingering spirits struggling
with some sort of tragedy from their past.
In-universe, the Rot Spirits are a key component
of the cycle of death and rebirth
and can eat away the dead zone to restore balance.
By using the Rot, Kena is able to destroy
the dead zone hearts, the source of the corruption.
And upon doing so, the player is rewarded
with the restoration of the environment.
We call these sequences dead zone clears.
And in this talk, we'll discuss the goals
that we had established for these dead zone clears,
showcase some of our earlier prototypes,
and break down the different layers of VFX and tech art
that went into.
achieving our visual and storytelling goals,
and then finally share some concluding thoughts
and some lessons learned.
So starting from the goals,
we first wanted the dead zones
to feel threatening to the player,
in harsh contrast to the inviting nature
of the rest of the world.
The spaces should not only be filled with spiky roots
and boldest growths and thick fog,
but the transition back to the healed version of the forest
should be obvious and noticeable.
We also wanted these dead zone clear transitions
to take place in real time as much as possible.
The transitions in some of our prototypes
hit a lot of environmental changes behind cut scenes,
which felt somewhat disconnected from the player's actions.
Bringing it closer to the gameplay makes it more fun to do
and it makes the player want to do it over and over again.
And finally, since the Rot Spirit companions
are such a key component to fighting back the dead zone,
we wanted to make sure that the VFX feedback
reinforced their place in the story.
As Kena has access to a variety of rot-powered special abilities,
we wanted those abilities to have a smaller scale version
of the cleaning feedback scene in the dead zone clear sequences as well.
So these prototypes showcase an early version of Dead Zone,
one with larger spaces packed full of corruption,
tall enough to physically block the player.
However, this vision wound up changing over time
because of both art and design considerations.
In this early version, the player could throw bait
to attract the rot or move them around directly,
like the rot cloud in the shipped version of the game.
This version is obviously quite crude,
lacking any sort of feedback
when the larger dead zone clumps are getting destroyed.
This later prototype used a render target
to mask out areas that were cleaned by the rot,
which is then sampled by other materials.
The cleaning of the landscape material was somewhat successful
and closely resembles what we shipped.
However, these larger dead zone clumps push their vertices
down into the terrain,
which causes a lot of weird visual artifacts
when the player is slicing through the middle of a mesh.
In addition to the visuals, we had a couple other problems
with this version.
The meshes need to be very high poly
in order to support this deformation,
and LOD popping would be exacerbated
when you're cutting into a mesh.
Handling collision was also very challenging as we did not want to dynamically adjust the collision based on which parts of the model were cleaned.
And instead we just wound up disabling collision and we made the player take damage when they walked through it, which didn't look very good either.
As these collision issues also caused problems for navmesh generation and other things of the like, we wound up going away from this approach to ensure that the combat worked well in these spaces.
In this last bit of prototype footage,
you can see how a prototype dead zone clear
was not yet accomplished in real time.
You might notice that these blue and purple flowers
only appear after the camera cuts to black.
This flower growing in during the cut scene
is meant to incept the idea in the player's mind
that the plants grew back in,
but it's not quite the same as seeing it actually happen
during gameplay.
So next I'm going to talk about how we built
the final version of the dead zones in engine.
There are roughly four layers or ingredients involved,
and each of them uses different solutions
to solve their unique problems.
The first is the landscape, the base layer of the terrain.
And then after that, I'll cover the foliage
and how it builds on how the landscape is cleaned.
And next, I'll cover the improvements that we made
to how we handled larger dead zone meshes.
And finally, I'll cover the systems that we built
to drive lighting and ambience
when the player is in the dead zones
and how we turn them off during the clear sequences.
So I'll now go over each of these layers in detail
and show how they all work together.
Our landscape material supports two additive layers
that can be painted on top of the underlying material.
In Unreal, this requires checking the no weight blend
checkbox on the landscape layer info.
The first is a dead mask that just
makes the underlying material appear dead.
And the second is a harmful variant
of the dead zone that slows the player down
and will kill them if they stand in it for too long.
The dead mask.
tints and desaturates the base color
and makes the material appear a little bit glossier
by modifying the roughness.
And on the other hand, that harmful dead zone one
layers a different tiling material
on top of the underlying material,
which makes the border between the two a little bit more clear.
This layer also modifies the physics material
so that we can detect when the player is standing on top of it.
So to implement the cleaning effect,
we have gameplay objects right to a top-down.
render target that is centered on the player's location.
The red channel of this texture encodes the clean state.
So for example, when the player destroys a dead zone heart,
a circular shape extends outward
and marks different areas as being cleaned.
The material uses pixels world space position
to compute the correct location
at which to sample from this texture.
And the value that is sampled is used to fade off
both of the additive dead zone layers
on the landscape material.
Since the landscape can be visible from afar,
we actually have two render targets set up
in a similar manner to cascading shadow maps.
One render target of higher resolution
covers the area immediately surrounding the player,
and a second lower resolution render target
covers a much larger area,
which allows us to have dead zone appear being cleaned,
even from very far away.
Just like in cascaded shadow maps,
we also ensure that the render target
is snapped to the nearest texel.
so we don't have any weird sampling artifacts
from it smoothly interpolating between
when you're moving small distances.
There are a couple of limitations with this approach.
One of the obvious ones is that the render target is top down,
so we can't have dead zones layered on top of each other,
but this didn't really wind up being a problem in practice.
This also only supports cleaning dead zone.
So while we thought that dynamically authoring dead zone
might be interesting from a gameplay perspective,
we didn't wind up actually pursuing that.
So yeah, just above the landscape,
we have ground cover meshes like our grass, clovers,
and flowers, which add depth to the terrain
as well as other larger plants,
like ferns and some other stuff.
We use Unreal's built-in instance foliage system
to place and render these assets.
For assets that need to be used in the dead zones,
we set up two foliage types for each plant,
both a clean version and a dead zone version.
And we use the appropriate version when doing level dressing.
So if the artist is placing Assets on top of somewhere
where they painted Dead Zone on the landscape,
they would make sure that they place the Dead Zone versions
of the Assets instead.
And so obviously, we also need two sets of Materials as well,
and the Dead Zone Foliage Types have different Materials
assigned that support being cleaned.
Having two sets of Foliage Types and Materials
did lead to some minor issues, like keeping both of these
in sync when we were making changes
to things like Material parameters.
But ultimately, I think this wound up being the right call.
We had tried out using a single foliage type
that could detect when it was in dead zone,
but that added additional complexity
around detecting what landscape layers were below the mesh,
which is not super easy to do out of the box.
It also increased the shader complexity for every mesh,
even though most meshes were not going to be transitioning
from cleaned to dead zone.
Given the asset density that we were targeting,
it did not really seem to be a trade-off
that was worth making.
So these foliage types are generally cleaned
the same way as the terrain,
by sampling from the red channel
in that cleaning render target that I mentioned earlier.
And they use that value to lerp colors
and other Material parameters.
You might also notice that some dead zone plants scale down
and disappear when cleaned.
This is handled by scaling the mesh in the vertex shader
based on that same value sampled by the Texture,
or sampled from the Texture, I should say.
This does leave us with a problem, though,
in that if we remove a lot of dead zone versions of plants,
we are left with bare patches of the landscape exposed.
So we solved this problem by having other plants grow back in
and fill in those bare spots.
Certain Materials actually start with a scale of zero,
and they scale up instead, based on the value
sampled from this time, the blue channel,
instead of the red channel.
One big reason that we separated these
into two separate channels,
is we want the flowers and other plants to grow in a little bit
delayed relative to when the dead zone gets cleaned.
So having them separated into two channels
allows the viewer to take them in as two separate events,
and it makes everything feel a little bit less in sync.
Adding this wound up being a big win from an art direction
perspective as well, as it enabled the artist to dress
spaces with vibrant plants and large flowers that would not
look correct in a dead zone space,
even if we did desaturate the colors.
So whenever the dead zone clear occurs,
all of these plants rush back in,
and they fill the space with life.
This also allowed us to stop loading in levels
to bring in Assets and have it all occur in real time.
One obvious drawback of scaling foliage like this
in the vertex shader is that there are locations
where we have two versions of plants in the same area.
We have dead zone plants that scale down,
and we have the plants that grow back in,
and they scale back on top of those ones.
To optimize this, we could have theoretically written some code
to modify the instance foliage system
and have some code that tries to call out zero scale instances
or something like that,
but we did not actually have the time to make any big changes.
So instead, we just made sure that we did not go overboard
with this effect.
At least any of the zero scale instances,
all of the triangles that are generated from them
have zero area,
and so they at least get called during rasterization.
And then one final bit of visual polish on the ground cover
assets is what we call overgrowth.
The green channel in the cleaning render target
encodes an additional value that we use to temporarily saturate
colors and scale up plants beyond their normal size.
You can see this effect take place
when destroying a dead zone heart
or removing the rot in the rot cloud form through the grass.
This effect provides some additional bounce
during dead zone clears.
It makes everything just feel a little bit more animated.
And finally, you can see all of this work on the foliage shaders
come together in the context of a dead zone clear.
It is easier, I think, to see it in the viewport
rather than the debug render target view,
but the blue channel is slightly delayed to the red channel.
So you might notice that the flowers grow in a little bit
after all of the grass turns green.
Also note that the green overgrowth channel
is the only one that does not stick around after the clear.
That effect is temporary.
The next ingredient is the larger dead zone meshes
in the space.
This includes the bulbous, gnarled dead zone pods,
but also trees with some larger dead zone growth sprouting out
of them.
These larger meshes are great at blocking progression
through a space, and they help sell the idea
that the dead zone is taking over.
Whenever a dead zone clear occurs,
these meshes dissolve out, allowing
the player to get past them.
These meshes are actually Blueprints rather than
instance foliage.
A big reason for that is we did not
want to use the cleaning render target,
since we would run into the same issue
that we had with the prototypes, where things would be,
we would just be cutting through the middle of a mesh
whenever those effects were going off.
And another problem is that during the dead zone clear,
the cleaning effect moves out so quickly
that it would wipe over the larger assets
in a fraction of a second, which wouldn't look good either.
So instead, what we do is we dissolve out
all of these assets on their own timeline.
By giving them more time, the player actually has a chance
to take all of this in.
Compared to the prototype version where the meshes
could be either, could be partially cleaned,
these meshes are binary.
They're either cleaned or not.
So that makes it easy to disable collision
on these when they're cleaned.
To make the dissolve still feel connected
to the dead zone hearth's destruction,
We built a tool to adjust the time
that it takes for each one to start dissolving out.
So what happens is when the dead zone cleaning effect goes out,
these meshes are not dissolved by the time
the cleaning effect reaches them,
but rather they start dissolving out
when the dead zone clear hits them.
And that gives them enough time to sort of be spaced out,
and they just dissolve out on their own timeline,
and they can take however long they need in order
for it to look good.
The dissolve in the shader is a pretty typical noise-based
dissolve that brightens the edges
to cover up the transition.
A lot of the assets also spawn particle effects,
like little splashes and snapping roots
and a little bit of distortion to help cover stuff up.
Some assets like trees also lurp
between two separate diffuse textures,
which just gives us a little bit more texture variation.
You might notice that there's a little bit of moss
growing back here on the tree.
And note that for the handful of assets like trees
that stick around after the clear,
we don't actually disable collision on those as well.
So as with most things that are Blueprint adjacent,
we did run into some performance problems
with our initial setup for these assets.
We had originally set up these Blueprints
using dynamic material instances
to allow tweening the dissolve parameters per instance,
but we moved away from that since it breaks instancing.
Since version 4.22, Unreal automatically instances
draw caps.
draw calls that share the same mesh and materials,
which can significantly reduce the amount of draw calls
that get submitted to the GPU.
But since dynamic material instances
can have different values
for their different shader parameters,
they need to be rendered as separate draw calls.
The other problem is that it's expensive on the CPU side
to update a lot of material parameters.
The default interface for updating material parameters
involves looking up the parameters by name,
which involves a lot of string comparisons.
This was especially bad during level streaming,
because we would wind up updating a few parameters
on hundreds of dead zone Blueprints.
And on some of our levels, we were paying something
like 30 milliseconds
just to create the dynamic material instances
and update all of the parameters on these assets
just so they could get into the correct state
on the level load.
So to solve these problems, we switched to using
an Unreal feature called Custom Primitive Data.
Custom primitive data gives you access to 32 floating point
numbers on a per primitive level that can be modified just
like material parameters.
But it does not require you to make dynamic material instances
just to set these values on a per primitive basis,
or a per instance basis.
So as you can see in these images
that I stole from the Unreal documentation page,
in the shader, instead of reading the parameter value
by name, you instead index into that float array.
So you just specify the number of the index
that you want to use instead.
Since a lot of our shader parameters
are actually exposed from material functions
and not the material itself, we set aside,
we set up like a convention to set aside specific indices
to be used for certain effects.
So that would allow us to avoid any conflicts
if you just drop in random material functions
into different materials.
So for example,
Index 0 might be always set aside to store the dissolve amount,
or index 1 might be set aside to always store a desaturation value
or something like that.
So since we don't need dynamic material instances anymore,
the renderer is able to instance all of these dead zone meshes.
And another thing that is also a benefit is that since the parameters
are referenced by index instead of by name,
updating these values on the CPU side is a lot easier
because we avoid all of those string comparisons.
Custom primitive data does have some drawbacks though.
One big one is that it is a per primitive setting.
And that means that if you have multiple materials
on the same mesh and you want them to have different,
different values for their shader parameters,
you won't be able to do that.
So in our cases, whenever we ran into that,
we wound up just falling back to using
dynamic material instances for those meshes.
So the final key component to the dead zone
is the lighting and ambience.
All of the lighting in Kena is real time,
which gave us the ability to finely tune
the look of each area in the game, including the dead zones.
Lighting artists control the lighting in different regions
by using custom post-process volumes.
Similar to the built-in Unreal post-process volumes,
our volumes drive the lighting and fog parameters
based on the camera location, fading in the values
as the camera gets closer.
Artists can modify a variety of properties like sun
or skylight intensity or fog density,
and plenty of the other in-depth parameters
that get exposed on the light and fog components
so that they can finely tune the look of the space.
Similar to post-process volumes,
all of the parameter overrides are optional,
so a volume only needs to specify a value for things
that it actually wants to override.
For dead zones in particular, we generally just
decrease the sun intensity, increase the fog density,
and bring in a little bit of chromatic aberration.
And all of these parameters are not actually stored
on the volumes themselves, but we store them
in data asset configuration files.
Swapping out the configs in the editor
is a very easy thing to do, and it can be a great way
to find a config that is close to what you're
looking for when you're setting up the lighting in a space.
Another benefit of having the lighting configs
as separate files is that it avoids a lot of the source
control conflicts where people would run into issues having
to check out the same levels.
So for each dead zone, we wind up
setting up a post-process volume that
controls the look of that particular space
when it is a dead zone.
And during the dead zone clear, we gradually
fade out the contribution of that dead zone post-process
volume to avoid a lighting pop.
Artists can also preview the contribution of a volume
by toggling it in editor.
So this makes it very easy when you're setting up the length
for a space to see both the before
and after version of the dead zone clear.
So finally, in this breakdown video,
you can see how all of the different layers
come together for the final product,
starting from just the landscape,
having the foliage, having the rest of the scene come in,
having these dead zone meshes,
which you'll see dissolve out slowly
once they get hit by the clear.
and then the lighting and the fog changes
that dissolve out at the beginning.
So now I'm going to talk about how we achieved
the rot-powered special abilities in the game.
There were two big goals that we wanted to accomplish
with these abilities.
First, we wanted to make sure that we captured
the collective nature of the rot
and their role in cleaning Dead Zone.
While the rot are typically animated characters
represented by skeletal meshes.
They transition through different representations
during these abilities,
including Alembic geometry caches
for fast morphing transitions,
and Niagara particles for when the rot are swarming together.
So first, the geometry caches are used in cases
where it would be hard to synchronously animate
multiple rot.
So to create the geometry caches,
we animated low-poly rot meshes to follow animation curves.
There are generally only a few base curves
that are then tweaked slightly to create different path
variations for other rot to follow.
This ensures that there's some level of visual cohesion
as all of the rot are swarming in.
The meshes are also stretched as their velocity increases,
with care taken to preserve their overall volume.
You can see these used at the beginning of the rot bow
and bomb abilities, as well as the rot hammer.
For swarming behaviors, we use a Niagara sim
where each rot is represented by a particle.
The normal skeletal mesh versions of the rot
can be quite expensive,
and so we wind up scaling down the number of rot
that are visible on screen
depending on what platform you're playing on.
However, we wanted to ensure that the user
could see all of their collected rot
when they're in the rot cloud form.
So we chose to represent them with static meshes
in the Niagara particle system
to reduce their animation and rendering cost.
This Niagara simulation runs on the CPU
so that we can easily keep the particle locations in sync
with the rot characters.
This allows us to switch from the particle system
version to the skeletal mesh version relatively seamlessly.
The Niagara simulation distributes rot along a spline.
When binding enemies, the spline is
generated dynamically by adding points
that follow an animated path.
As you can see here, this is the version
that just has the spline.
On the other hand.
When in the rot cloud form, the splines actually follow the bones in the skeletal mesh.
This ensures that the spline has a consistent length and the distribution,
and it has a good distribution even when the cloud is standing still.
The rot particles are attracted to points that rotate around this spline.
The radius and angle of rotation of the attraction points
is somewhat randomized per particle.
These settings are also controlled both by curves
that allow you to define how the values change over.
the length of the spline.
So you might want more thickness at the head
and less at the tail.
And they're also controlled by scalar values
that can be adjusted.
So for example, you can globally scale up the radius
if, for example, the player collects more rot.
These Niagara parameters can also
be driven over time by animation curves.
This allows animators to adjust the simulation's behavior
to better match the animation.
So for example, if the rot cloud is moving fast,
the attraction strength might need to be higher
to prevent the particles from lagging behind.
To accomplish this, we just have some blueprint code
that samples specific animation curves by name,
and it routes those values into the Niagara system.
We animate these values as scalars
rather than absolute values
to avoid stopping any other global changes
that are being passed in.
Like for example, if we're adjusting the radius
based on how many rot you have.
So in this breakdown of the Rot Hammer,
you can actually see all three stages,
starting with these rots swirling in as a geometry cache,
and then turning into a Niagara particle system
as they come bouncing out.
And then finally, they change back
into their skeletal mesh form
when they hit the ground and come tumbling out.
As previously mentioned,
these abilities also are tied
into the Dead Zone cleaning system.
all of the abilities right to the cleaning render target
so that they affect the landscape and the foliage,
but they don't affect the larger dead zone meshes, which
is good in our case.
Not everything cleans in a circular shape, however.
So we needed to add support for drawing trails
to this render target.
While this was originally built to provide the feedback when
moving around the rot cloud, we wound up
using it in a variety of places like the bind feedback,
or the bounce during the rot hammer,
or the cleaning trail left behind from the rot arrow.
One problem we ran into was that the cleaning mask render target
is top down.
So there isn't really an easy way
to encode that cleaning is happening
at a particular height value.
So one of the early problems that we ran into
was, for example, if you take the raw arrow
and you fire it into the air, ideally, the cleaning effect
should decrease as the arrow gets higher off of the ground.
But in our naive approach, it didn't do that.
So we fixed this by just simply performing traces down
to find how high off the ground it was whenever we were adding
a point to the trail.
And then depending on the distance to the ground,
we adjusted the strength for that point.
And the shader takes that into account,
and it fades out the effect.
So put all together, we think the dynamic feedback
for these abilities gives the impression
that the player is fighting back the dead zone every time
they use the Rot in combat.
So hopefully that gives you a brief overview
of how we achieved the dead zone transitions
and rot abilities in Cana Bridge of Spirits.
I think that there were two big takeaways for us
that we've already somewhat alluded to.
First, ideally the VFX is used to reinforce the world building
rather than just using it to make stuff look cool.
Especially in our case, we struggled a lot
to establish how the rot actually cleaned dead zone,
but we found that good VFX feedback
did a lot of heavy lifting when it came to getting players
to understand and accept how the stuff worked.
And second, we derived a lot of value by building stuff in layers.
So while none of the individual parts of the dead zone equation are particularly complicated,
each layer provides different feedback from the last,
and they all work to produce something greater than the sum of its parts.
And by staggering the effects of these layers across time,
we were able to make each part read separately from the others,
instead of getting lost in the noise.
So I guess we're a little short on time for questions.
So I will say, if anybody has questions,
I'll probably be hanging out in the room 204
down the hallway if anybody wants to ask questions afterward.
And you can also shoot me an email if you want to.
My email is on the slide, my work email,
and I'll try to get back to you.
And if you have any other things
that you want to contact the studio about,
you can always hit up our contact email,
contact.emeralab.com.
But I guess I just want to thank you all for your attention.
And yeah, I want to thank everybody else who
worked on this content and helped
me prepare this presentation, because it was certainly
a good bit of work.
So thanks.
Thank you.
Good night.
Good evening.
How are you?
How have you all been?
Good.
Good evening.