Let's also go over some fun stuff.
So one, A, you're going to tell your friends that they
could see the talk on Vault.
Two, we know that there's a lot of people inside and
outside for portfolio reviews.
And it's really important, our team here, everybody here, we
want to see you.
So we will make sure, don't worry about the time, we will
see the very last person we're going to get
through this together.
OK, let's turn the volume up here.
let's have some fun. Are you guys ready?
Alright, I want to hear it. I need to feel the energy right now. Alright.
Alright.
Sweet.
My name is Allison Kelly
and I'm a private consultant to some of the top tier gaming developers. Why don't we
introduce ourselves, guys?
I can start at my end. I'm Claire Hummel. I'm the art director at Campo Santo,
currently working in the Valley of Gods.
I'm Darren Bacon, I'm the lead concept artist at 343 Industries, who develops Halo.
I'm Gavin Goulden, I'm the lead character artist at Insomniac, working on Spider-Man
for PS4.
I'm Wyeth, I've been in the game industry since the turn of the century, which is fun to be able to say.
And I've been a production artist, lead artist, art director, and technical art director at Epic over the last 12 years.
Hi, I'm Greg Furch, I'm the art director at Fraxxas for XCOM.
I've been there for about 21 years, I just passed 21 years, so...
Yes, I'm a dinosaur.
And Greg, I thought you were only, you know, 21.
Yeah.
Okay.
And then Sean Robertson, who is on the panel, but we couldn't fit him up on our stage, could
you just wave your hand?
I bet he went to go get coffee with slacking.
Or bourbon.
Ah, that's true.
That is actually probably true.
Okay.
So how did you guys get started in the industry?
Anyone German?
Sure, I'll take it, every time.
I technically got my start when I was 14 years old and
emailed the website Neopets and said that their art was
bad and my art was better.
And so I worked there for about seven summers.
And then when I graduated from art college, I ended up at
Xbox, they were recruiting at RISD, the college I went to.
And I was absolutely expecting to get into animation, but
they made a very compelling offer.
And 10 years later.
still in games. So you took it. Yes, it worked out. Yeah.
Darren. Yeah. Um, so, uh, when I was in art school,
I kind of spammed every game development company like up and down the left
coast.
And I was living in Pasadena and ended up getting a sort of a contract position
for an internship in Seattle.
And I was like making just enough money to pay my rent back in Pasadena.
But that's sort of, uh, how I got in. So the takeaway, I guess, was.
I just was super motivated and wanted to just kind of find any foot in the door I could.
I'm going to start doing a duet here.
So I actually went to art school to work for film and
effects.
Didn't like it because I wanted to make a character
art portfolio.
Dropped out, moved across the country, worked a bunch of
random jobs while working on my portfolio.
Got my foot in the door for a mobile company working on
prehistoric.
mobile phones way before iPhone, uh, you know, like old sports
games and stuff like that and eventually I just worked my way
up through pixel art doing, uh, I guess what would now be
hand-painted last gen, last, two last gens ago, uh, and then, uh,
on from there for about 15 years now.
My story is obtuse and complicated.
So I'll tell the one important piece, I think, for you guys,
which is there was a moment where there was a game
developer I wanted to work for who put out an entreaty.
This is a long time ago on Blue's News or some archaic
website way back in the day.
An entreaty to have somebody come and test their game.
And I was working as a graphic designer, but I was not a game
developer.
And they put out this entreaty, and I wrote an
impassioned email to that person.
And out of 350 emails, they picked mine.
And that's one of these stories where you just have to keep pushing yourself,
you just put yourself in these situations where people could find
that you are a person of good taste.
And something in that email was appealing to them.
And so I said, come by and try it.
And they were not hiring.
They did not intend to hire anybody.
They were not even looking.
They just wanted somebody to come try their game.
And within six months, I was working in the industry
because I made an impression on them and I showed them my portfolio and so on.
So, just find a way in the door and then show that you have good taste, and that's going
to be a good entry point.
Yeah, I just kind of stumbled into it.
I was in art school doing illustration and actually doing editorial work while I was
in school and kind of, there was an internship for a company called MicroProse.
Anybody ever heard of that?
Crickets.
Wow.
Sid Meier.
Ever heard of Sid Meier?
Yeah, I hadn't when I was in school.
I didn't know who the guy was with the big office.
And so, yeah, I went to respond to an internship for
doing illustration, which was what they were
looking for at the time.
And yeah, it was supposed to be a two-year job till I got my
freelance self settled.
And 23 years later, I'm still doing it.
So it kind of stuck.
Oh, and I want to say one more thing, because Sean has
gracefully not had a seat.
And he's off getting bourbon, as we've already established.
But he tells a story every year.
And I'm not going to tell the whole story.
I'm just going to say that that man saved every rejection
letter he ever received.
and he received dozens and they were in
they were printed out, he got them in the mail after submitting his VHS reels
decades ago. But he saved those things and they were his motivation
and he is an absolute badass and that guy got rejected a lot
so keep that in mind. So what is the most common issue you find in portfolios?
I'll lead us off.
I would say that for me, the most common issue that I
really see is portfolios that don't really have a voice.
I can guarantee that everyone in this room has a voice for
your art or whatever you're working on.
And a lot of times, it's really easy to fall into the
trap of aping what you already see in the industry of trying
to sort of repeat that back, because you see that it's
successful, so you want to do more of it.
But it's important to remember that.
what makes good art in this industry is usually new and fresh and exciting.
And whether that's the research you're doing, your personal interests, your life experience,
bringing that to the table and having it come through.
in the work that you're choosing to show to people instead of just the same paladins and
the same space marines over and over again, and the same environments that have those
spiky rock formations that don't really exist in real life.
If you show that research and it comes through, it really makes your work stand out.
Even if there are people who are technically better than you, if that concept and intention
comes through in your portfolio, it's super important.
Yeah, Claire's right, except if you have really cool space
marines, you should show them to me.
Yeah, I think the voice thing is like the key takeaway. I
think if you, at least for me or what I've noticed, if you are
super passionate about something, it's going to sort of
show itself in the work. So it's sort of like, it's chicken and
egg thing, but...
If you are super passionate about it, the result will be
more inspiring work and stuff that other artists maybe
haven't seen before.
Can I rant about pet peeves for a second?
So a few things about portfolios for me that stand
out as common problems.
One would be no focus or thinking that having a
quantity over quality is better.
Generally, I find that a lot of, especially like newer portfolios will have like everything
you can possibly do is in this portfolio, but what that actually does is waters out
or waters down your actual skill.
So focusing more on, you know, your best discipline, your best pieces and just editing that down
is way better than showing you can do everything imaginable or at least attempt to.
And then having a portfolio of only sculpts for a game art.
position is just makes my blood boil. I never want to see one ever again.
I won't belabor any of these points other than to say take your entire portfolio, divide
it in half and subtract two pieces and that's the number of pieces you actually should have
in your portfolio.
Why, just to elaborate on that, you want to see two amazing,
not a bunch of mediocre.
You'd rather see two pieces that are really amazing.
You're only as good as your weakest piece.
And the classic thing we'll do is
we'll look at your first piece, which is usually the thing
that's in your ego as the best thing you've ever done,
and then we'll just switch to the last page.
And if they're really dissimilar, we're like, ah.
Yeah, okay.
You know, and you can immediately see there's this big, you know, difference.
Either it's taste level or it's a lack of awareness or it's a lack of just putting in
the time to even your quality.
But it's the first thing we see for sure.
Yeah, this is probably weird coming from me, but I think it was like Coco Chanel that said
before you're leaving the house, like, you take off one piece of jewelry or something
like that.
Actually, it was add another piece of jewelry.
Was it add?
No.
Yes, it was add another necklace.
It was add.
Really? Yes. Add another necklace? Okay, well in my version... So, I guess, so Darren's changing the brand.
What does Coco know? Chanel had terrible advice. I'm pretty sure of that. What does Coco Bacon say? I'm going to double check.
Greg? Take out something.
I just think, you know, it all kind of goes to that quality versus quantity thing, but like Claire said, I think...
is the voice part of it, like that's how you,
that's a powerful way to think about how you edit your work.
Like if it's not scatter shot,
you're not shooting with a shotgun.
And so trying to think about it,
I've never actually heard somebody describe it that way,
but the voice and like how that applies to it,
it's really right on.
Like use that voice to help you kinda,
thin the herd. If it doesn't fall within your voice, maybe it shouldn't be in your portfolio.
So that's a really, really good point.
How do you decide what format is the best for a portfolio
and when is it appropriate to have a demo reel?
I'm looking at you.
Opinions?
generally for anything that would require motion is what you should use a demo reel for.
For like character art, I mean, you know, concept art or anything that is generally still
that you could sell within a series of images, you know, like a turnaround of just static
images is far superior than doing like a demo reel just because, I mean, I can get into it.
the loading times, you'll end up skipping around just to see like different angles of a character.
You'll probably have a lot of your work missed. Compression, for something like this, it's going
to be load time too. You're just really, you know, shooting yourself in the foot. But for animation
effects, things that actually require you to see motion in the work, a demo reel is the way to go.
I would say for character models also a lot of places like Art Station or if you're building
your own website you can embed Marmoset viewers and things to view models.
You should still have turnarounds because those suckers do not always load but it's
so much easier than having to wade through, as you said, just like skipping ahead on a
demo reel for a single model.
Okay. Yeah, I think concept can be super simple. Like I, I once
submitted a demo reel and I don't know why, it was just like
that was the format they wanted but it was, it seemed odd. I
wouldn't, I would like rather just thumb through JPEGs than
scrub through a video. First. Yes. Are blogs appropriate to
include in a portfolio process versus practice?
We were kind of talking about this yesterday.
I feel like it's really interesting to see someone's blog as an addition to your portfolio.
So if you have a website, being able to have it as a link at the bottom of the page or
a drop-down menu of all of your social media, it's a great way for someone to look at your
curated portfolio of the work, your best work that you want to put in front of someone.
And then if an art director is thinking, hey, I want to see more of this person's work.
it would be fantastic if there was an Instagram or a Tumblr that I could click through to.
And so that gives them the option without overcrowding your portfolio.
The other thing I just want to say about something like a process blog is one of the main things
that we're looking for is the ability for someone who is applying to self-edit because
we can see what they view as their apex work or the varieties of things they want to show.
So, if there's a big process blog and you're like, hey, look at all my work.
I don't know when you're learning or when you're experimenting or
when you're trying something outside of your comfort zone.
And I don't know what you consider good.
I just see a bunch of stuff.
So, to me, a process blog or a link like that is not in any way, shape, or
form a portfolio.
Cuz it tells us absolutely nothing about you editing yourself
down to the essence of why we should hire you.
What role should traditional art have in a portfolio?
This is funny because this came up yesterday.
We all talk about what we're going to talk about a little
bit, kind of pregame, the day before.
And so it's really funny.
When we talked about this, and this is actually kind of going
back and forth over the years a little bit, but it was funny.
Traditional media came up yesterday, and we were talking
about is it important to see figure work?
And it's kind of funny, I think we all kind of came around to the fact that like, you know, it's like, no, like, if that's not what you're doing, like, I don't, I'm going to see that, we're going to see that in your work, whether or not you provide us with, you know, figure drawings, you know, it's going to come through in the other stuff.
And so, yeah, it's kind of.
Yeah, I like, I respect really good figure drawing.
Yeah, absolutely.
It just doesn't really fit into the equation.
And you can kind of like suss it out already with most concepts that you see.
Like, can this person understand anatomy, right?
Yeah, it's true.
And I think, like, at Art Center, they used to always say, like, you have to get really good at drawing the form,
and you either do it through figure drawing or the car, so, or like automotive.
And so I think it's sort of like, as a result of being a really good figure drawer,
you'll most likely, you know, have really good foundations and good art skills.
and at best it's a small positive for your portfolio
and at worst your figure drawings are really good
and it's not coming through in your concepts,
then that's a huge ding to your portfolio.
So you wanna be really thoughtful about that.
I did want to touch on the idea of just traditional work in a portfolio or in a games pipeline.
There are definitely people who do it, who do traditional concept work, but it's definitely
it's a lot harder when you have to scan things, when you have to do iterations on pieces.
So it's not like, oh, I immediately wouldn't hire someone, but if someone is not proficient
in Photoshop or the ability to quickly move around and move at the pace of a games pipeline.
then that definitely can become a problem.
With most artists having a presence on ArtStation, is there any benefit to maintaining a separate
portfolio site?
Oh, Gavin, you look like you have an opinion on this.
I should start speaking over it.
Yes, it's beaming.
In my opinion, no.
basically if you're at the stage where you create a portfolio looking for your first job,
any time you have to spare should be spent on making that work better. So if you're spending
time web designing and trying to get your portfolio working right or anything like that,
it's kind of a waste when ArtStation already exists and it's already searchable, it's already
like a hub for people to go to like us looking for new contractors, new team members and stuff
like that.
So...
You know, for me it's better investment just to put it back
into work instead of in a website.
I will say it's also, it's nice if.
if someone has, if you're using ArtStation as your primary portfolio to use the ArtStation
Pro that allows you to have a domain name and a polished portfolio site. I personally,
I keep my own portfolio site using Squarespace.com. Because it's so much easier to just like toss
work up there without having to like label all of the stuff that I use for it. But pretty
much.
As you said, like ArtStation can just turn into a portfolio site now.
So if you want to have one, that's fine.
But yeah, do not waste time.
Do not feel like you need to learn CSS and impress people with your web design skills
just for a portfolio site.
Greg, do you have a comment?
Yeah.
I mean, I think that's...
I think that's right.
It's always, it's not bad.
I, it's not bad to have something else that you can find.
But yeah, I think it's taking away too much of your, of your, if you're seriously, you're
that pressed for time, you know, trying to get your work done.
Maybe you shouldn't do it, but, but I think, you know, having this other presence sometimes
to kind of separate you from the herd is sometimes it's not a bad, a bad choice.
custom layouts in art station. Also if you have multiple sites
keep them all up to date. It is so sad if someone finds your
deviant art and you haven't updated in eight years. They're
like this person is not great. They're nine years old.
So keep the content relevant and also have it maybe in one
area, like you don't want to have one site that's eight
years old and one site that's brand new, because when
someone's trying to look for you, you don't know what
you're getting.
Right?
So do you expect to see models and animation in game
engines?
Yes.
Please.
Is that because maybe you're from Epic?
Any real time preview that is applicable to game technology,
Allison.
Where's your game engine?
I just like to make fun of them.
You've got to show your work in engine.
we have huge pet peeves about sculpts that are like renders
in Max or whatever.
It's near pointless, and I basically don't care.
Like, that's how strongly I feel about it.
You have to show that you can go all the way through the
pipeline, all the way to the bitter end, because all the
easiest stuff is in ZBrush, not discounting the incredible
talent that happens there.
But the easy work is there, and then making it look good
at the very, very tippy top of the mountain way down here,
that's like the 90% hard case.
So you've got to show it.
You've got to show it.
I mean for character art animation really like any of the disciplines I find almost
like the creative part is half the job and then the problem solving technical implementation
is the other half.
So as much as I love ZBrush and sculpts and you know modeling and whatever package and
just normal animation reels and stuff, it doesn't show that you.
can put it into context so you can only do the actual art part, not the game development
part and uh that's what we're doing. We're basically hiring very skilled problem solvers
more than an animator in Max, you know, or Maya. What are people animated? Maya?
Who's to say? Anything. Whatever you've animated.
The fact that these jobs are problem solving is such a good point.
Like, that is very much the definition of working in games,
is you have these limited parameters, as concept artists, but especially as modelers, as animators.
And understanding that you have to work within those parameters and find creative solutions is so important.
Should a portfolio be as broad as possible, or should it be specialized in the given style technique?
I mean, I think it depends on studio.
You know, we were talking about this earlier, but for a company like Insomniac, we have
more specialized roles.
So again, going back to the problem-solving thing, I mean, I want a creative character
artist who can, you know, adapt their abilities to our project, right?
So style doesn't necessarily matter, especially because we have such a diverse portfolio,
but...
You know, as long as they show the skill, they show like the technical know-how and stuff like that,
they'll generally be a good fit.
But for a more independent company or like a smaller team,
I find that it's going more into generalization.
So weighing more on that like technical side or the, not jack of all trades,
but having, you know, a multidisciplinary portfolio is almost more fitting.
Yeah, which the summary there is know who you're applying to.
You've got to be aware of the company you're applying to and
tailor your portfolio.
There's no such thing as a one size fits all portfolio ever.
You have to know exactly who you're sending it to, you know
exactly what you're applying for, and then you tailor it,
take out stuff that's not relevant, put in extra stuff
you might have that is.
That's the thing.
I actually feel like in my position right now, I'm actually seeing this shift in the
way that we're hiring in that I'm not looking for something that's super diverse, but I'm
looking for somebody that has a second skill.
They may not be great at it, but they're pretty good at it.
And so as I'm hiring now and I'm seeing this...
in both what we're doing at Firaxis and with some of my
other friends in the industry, is that we're actually
kind of looking for just a little bit more than a specialization. So we're not going
fully like I want somebody to do everything, but I want somebody that's got this primary
thing that they're really good at and this other thing that they're pretty good at that
I might be able to leverage later. And so I kind of feel like there's some shifting
going on right now. So I don't know how you guys feel about that.
I would you recommend showing that in a portfolio to have like so if you have like five levels
and character art and then like one level and you know shader artist or something like
that would you just so that you know we don't go back on our.
over quantity thing. So would you have a few pieces of character art and then an example
of like shader work or something like that?
Yeah. Yeah. I think if you're really good at one thing and you've got this other thing
that you're pretty good at, it shouldn't be a huge drop off. And it should be something
like related. Like if you're an animator, right, and I don't want to just hire an animator
anymore. I want to hire an animator that's got cinematic skills, right, that's got some
sort of cinematic understanding and tendency.
That's easy enough to build into your reel, right?
If you're an environment modeler, maybe you can do some layout as well and world building.
So I'm not just looking for a prop artist anymore.
I want somebody that can give me a little more if I need it somewhere else and has a
little more diversified interest.
But I don't know.
Well, if you think about what you're talking about as a
color wheel, you're talking about complementary colors.
You're not talking about like, I'm an animator who also
lights whatever.
Like, those are weird.
Like, I don't understand how to parse that portfolio.
But if you're like, I'm an environment modeler, but I'm
also doing set dressing, a little lighting, and I can do
some post-processing, you're like, ah, that's the guy.
Absolutely.
I don't know.
I kind of feel like there's, I do feel like there's something shifting right now.
I don't think we're the only ones.
I mean, budgets are getting huge and I think people are starting to look a little more
like, okay, can I get something that's a little bit, a little bit more than just this scalpel.
But again, it's got to be something complementary to what they're doing.
It's if you're an environment model, or if you're a world builder, maybe you're into
lighting, right?
And so you're getting just a little bit of something extra, but it's not completely in
left field.
So.
I do think I find that as well.
So it's not so much like I'm looking for.
a person that you could put in on the animation team from character art or something. But
I think almost all of my hires have been leaning more towards the technical side. So knowing
like shader set up, knowing like all of our like best practices for like our, you know,
our engine and stuff like that. Like I'm kind of looking more at that on top of all the
art. So it's like, well, you know, I can kind of have both. I have somebody who knows like
the technical side more too. So they can kind of help out for sure.
How do you avoid portfolio cliches?
and actually put more originality in your portfolio.
Darren's looking for space marines.
Yeah.
Just add more space.
Eventually it'll come around, right?
Space marines will be different now.
You know, I think it's kind of gets back
to what we were talking about earlier.
If you're finding what you're passionate about
and letting that drive you,
it's gonna be harder to sort of wind up
producing that stuff.
But it happens, I mean I think there's also a level of
execution too, right?
Because like a lot of things can be cliche, but if you can
sort of do it, put a twist on it or something or do it your
own way, I mean I think you could probably say a lot of my
portfolio is a cliche.
But I just execute it differently maybe.
So yeah, I think it's just like, it's kind of like how
you do it.
Yeah, I'd agree with that.
I feel like a lot of my interests are very tropey, like I love westerns, I love dinosaurs.
I'm working on a game about Egypt, and it's all about finding that particularly interesting
way.
For me, it's often like a historical event and very research heavy.
But if you can bring something new to the table, like I follow a lot of artists who
do very cool space marines, so I feel like I need to make sure that my stance on space
marines does not follow me out of this room.
There's a quote about originality that I love,
which is that the definition of it is two things you know
combined in a way you didn't expect.
And that, I just adore that phrase,
and I live my life basically that way.
And I think that's exactly how you reflect that
in a portfolio, which is it's okay to derive
from things that are known.
In fact, that's where all the things come from.
Just find a little bit of a bias that makes it yours
so that we can infer that when we look at the portfolio.
I hope someone's taking notes for me.
It also has to build your personality in it.
What role should school projects have in a portfolio?
Can I see this a lot?
Well, you know, I know I don't want to throw my other bus,
but I think you have to have it at a certain point.
Do your best to remove it as fast as you can.
Yeah, I feel like schoolwork is very clearly schoolwork.
If it's an individual project, and it's
being assigned to 30 different people,
you start to see that repeating project.
I look at my classmates who graduated the same year I did,
and you can definitely see those same assignments
in all of our portfolios.
You want to get it out as fast as you can.
And if you work on a group project,
be abundantly transparent.
about what your role was and where people helped you.
It's not a weakness to say this was a group project, here's who did this and this.
In fact that shows that you work well on a team, that you can collaborate with people.
So do whatever you can to edit down your work on that project to really focus primarily
on what you contributed.
So we're going to take this time, we have a couple more questions to go, but if people
would like to ask some questions, I'd like you to line up and we'll begin after two questions.
You just can line up and ask your question to the panel.
So what area of the game art production do you see more demand and talent than supply
for?
I think tech art is huge and it's also one of those things that's still defining itself.
It's a really broad thing and that's actually kind of breaking down into specialization.
And then I think UI, I mean if you went to the show earlier this week, the first two
talks I saw were talks on UI and they were amazing.
I don't think the industry is about right now is that this generation is going to define
itself by like more model fidelity.
Like we've already done that.
Like I think what you're going to be seeing, like the way I see next gen right now, it's
about the trailing disciplines.
It's about animation.
It's about effects.
It's about audio.
It's about UI.
Like.
those are the things that are going to get more fidelity now.
So it's a little more subtle, but it's
going to be really robust.
And so I think that those are places
where if you're trying to find your place
and you have an interest in those things,
those are you, as an effects artist,
you will never look for a job if you're good.
You'll never have to worry about it.
I think to piggyback on UI, too, just good graphic design.
not, it's hard to do.
Mm-hmm.
And also, I also see that moving into more of a motion graphics role.
Yeah.
Mm-hmm.
Right?
Like, it's not about just like, like buttons clicking, it's about movement.
It's kind of an animation thing.
What it reminds me of is like when you play like Halo or some sci-fi game and they're
like, here's a future car.
And it's like, no one knows what a future car looks like,
but that's not it.
Likewise, like when you see the world,
when you walk outside GDC and you look around,
like there's really good graphic design everywhere.
And to put that into the game,
it's generally just like someone
who's not a great graphic designer
who's just sort of putting in environment art.
So.
If you wanna get hired forever,
get into effects, tech art, or tech animation.
And you will, I mean, there's an incredible amount
of demand across the entire industry for this.
Do you guys want to answer some questions?
Oh, yes.
Yeah, because we're running out of time.
Yes, but I do want to make one more point, just because I
think it's valuable.
Particularly with student work, what I end up seeing a lot,
this is something to just keep in mind, oftentimes when
you're doing student projects, you're comparing yourselves to
your other peers in your class.
You're not comparing yourself to the right people.
and you're like, oh, I'm doing pretty good compared to the other people in my class,
but you're not going out to the, you know, the poly counts or the art stations or whatever
and comparing yourselves to the actual competition for the job you want,
which is other people at your skill level who are killing it in, you know, kind of across the board.
So don't fall into the trap of just looking at the two people on either side of you and going like...
yeah, I'm doing okay, yeah, nice, like progress, you know.
You gotta be looking at the industry as a whole
and the quality bar and shooting for that
rather than the kind of insular side of it.
So just a little warning and the only reason I mention
is because it happens all the time.
Also, we are also talking about the industry is really small
so be nice to those people.
Because like we, I mean, even when like
we're all chatting on this panel,
like we all know each other through some, you know,
connection.
So, even if in school, you know, you are not nice, then it gets around.
Yeah, you're never good enough to be an asshole.
Yeah.
That's awesome.
Here, here.
So, let's answer some questions, please.
Hello.
Hi.
So you mentioned how you wanted the work to be shown like in game engine.
Usually I show my work like in Substance Painter because it's re-topoed so like that's the
whole point of showing it in engine, right?
So like, is it okay to show it in Substance Painter, or do you still want it in Engine?
No, it's not okay to show it in Substance Painter.
Okay.
It has to be in Engine.
There's a whole host of problems related to getting something to look good in Engine that
aren't applicable to looking good in Substance.
Yeah, you have to go the whole way.
Got it.
Second question is, you mentioned that you should send a specific portfolio to each company,
but how do you do that if you only have one website?
I'm just talking about if you're making an introductory
thing that's talking about your skills.
I mean, admittedly, if you only have one website, fine.
Just have your best work.
But if you're doing something like, hey, I'm submitting a
resume, make sure that you edit that to the kind of
strengths that you are applicable to that job, and
then include that as a little bit of an annotation
alongside the site.
OK, thank you.
Hi.
Hello, I had a question about environment modeling.
Could you just speak a little more into the microphone?
Hello, is that better?
Yeah.
That's weird.
I had a question about, you talked about environment modeling and trying to separate yourself from the rest of the people.
You mentioned like blockouts and post-processing and lighting.
Can you explain a little more about the technical aspects?
Like I'm trying to, what could I do to really learn more technical aspects?
Would that be like substance design and material work?
Like what would you recommend I start doing?
I've dove in a little bit into that, but like I'm trying to figure out how to...
more go to technical aspects. Is that really getting into the coding? Because I'm pretty bad at that.
So... I think, um, one of the things you can do there, uh, yeah, of course,
substance is, is, is definitely worth, uh...
having in your arsenal because everybody's using it, it's the standard.
Um, but I think that, um, you know, looking at doing modular, if I'm
understanding your question right, like thinking through systems, like
doing modular systems for building so that not everything is, is unique.
Um, trying to think economically, like, like doing a modular system that
doesn't necessarily read modularly.
Um, that's problem solving that we're looking, that's what we're looking for.
Right.
Uh, cause you're, you're able to work, you know.
more efficiently. And again, it's the problem solving aspect of it that's so crucial.
If I'm answering, I think I'm answering your question about it. Yeah, so if you don't want to get into coding and you want to do something, what can you do?
So yeah, I would say those are like, the systems end of it is really important.
Okay, so like the more production side, like trying to make more like modular kits and how to like,
I guess get the most out of the time I'm working on it.
Hi.
Hello.
Just a little nod.
Hi.
So I am a 3D artist at an automotive engineering company,
so not Indie Games, but it's full time.
But I would like to get into games,
and I would like to do more stylized environments.
So I was wondering, it's also a military contract, really.
It's something I can't actually share or show in portfolio.
So I was just wondering, how can I
show skills and growth that I did there,
while still apply it to a new resume or portfolio
or anything like that?
So basically you're looking to take a way more realistic portfolio, the skills that
you learned at that job and how to put it into a stylized environment.
So I can't show anything.
So I just want to know how can I voice what I did there and still say I did it without
any real proof basically.
Yeah, well, I mean, at the end of the day, like NDA is NDA, and you might not be able to show it.
It's not just your situation. It would be like a lot of a lot of companies, you can't do that.
But I mean, you're already learning skills that would be like hard surface modeling that you could
easily apply into a like a personal piece that you could show. Just unfortunately, that's probably
something you have to do on your own time that
that goes the same skills, but it would be transferable.
You just have to take that modeling information
or knowledge that you have and then apply it
to a real-time environment.
And I think that NDA thing is something
we all struggle with because of the industry.
And so keep in mind that that, like, pay attention to that
because it really means something.
if you violate that, people, like, we don't want you to violate it. So, and anybody that
tells you to violate it is giving you really bad advice. But yeah, it's a personal project.
Personal work, yeah.
So, actually, if, how would you handle doing an ART test, like, while working a 40 hour
plus job?
The ARC test should be reasonable.
It shouldn't be something that...
Yeah, also, I know Wyatt and I have talked about it before.
So I test everybody, well not everybody that applies, but everybody that, you know, kind
of breaks through the threshold, I guess.
So everybody that we're interested in we test, but it's also a very reasonable test that
should be done over like a weekend or something like that.
It's nothing that is...
unreasonable. And I think if somebody is testing you that is
unreasonable, you should tell them. Maybe that's part of the
test. Maybe they're diabolical in that way. But you should,
you know, you should stand up for yourself for sure if it's
too much.
Awesome. Thank you so much.
Hi.
So I'm a 2D artist and animator, and I'm
noticing that there's a lot of division between 2D and 3D.
And I know that the industry wants a focused, specialized
sort of skill set.
But is it better to kind of broaden that horizon
to get at both 2D and 3D, or just stick
with one side of the fence?
I think like we have environment artists and 3d artists who are also doing their own sketches and stuff and generally it makes the art better
And it's great if they like come to concept and we're like really busy
So it's like the the more sort of like
Simple questions that a 3d environment artists or a 3d modeler can solve for themselves is like a huge step up, right?
so
So my question was and I've heard some differing opinions on this
I'm I'd like to hear what you guys have to say about it should game
Fan art play any role in a portfolio and if it does what role should it play?
I wrote a long spiel about this on Twitter since I've gotten a lot of jobs from fan art.
I think you should be very careful about fan art that you put in your portfolio, and it
should definitely play a second fiddle to your original work.
But there are pieces of fan art that I think can speak to what you bring to the table.
If you were just...
drawing exactly what they're offering. If you're just drawing on model Overwatch fan art and putting it in your portfolio,
that tells me nothing about you as an artist. But if you're doing some interesting take on something, you're improving on something,
you're showing what you bring to the table.
then in a way, showing that you can play around in someone else's sandbox can actually be
a really compelling thing.
So I don't think it's ever like a scarlet letter on someone's portfolio, but you want
to be really thoughtful.
In the same way that you're thoughtful about the other work you put in your portfolio,
make sure your fan art holds up to that.
It's not just good illustrations, it's good concept art.
I would bring up to you, not just to try and get on Claire's good side, but
You've done your Disney princesses before? Oh, yeah, and she also
Did our Lutece and Elizabeth concepts for Bioshock Infinite and while that's not fan art, that's professional art
They're all very well thought out and show like a knowledge of, you know, costume construction
and things like that.
So even if it was fan art, it's taking an insane amount of knowledge about that outfit
and showing your deep understanding of it.
So it's not just, hey, I made Tracer, you know, it's like I broke down the costume and
how it works and I'm applying that to all my personal pieces and stuff like that too.
So.
Yeah, when I got that job on Bioshock doing Young Liz and the Luteces, they specifically
were like, hey, we saw your historical Disney princesses, you want to work on Bioshock?
And I fell over and died and then took the job.
So yeah, it can definitely be a boon to your portfolio if you think about it right.
And also, Claire, I've actually heard a bunch of these guys to comment about that, that
it's your attention to detail from like, everything that she was wearing, you know, and I think
that that was a really valid point too.
Yeah, being thoughtful, right?
Yeah.
Thank you so much.
Hello.
Hi.
So my question has to do more with the beginning of the talk
when you were talking about spamming studios.
How do I be aggressive in my networking
without being annoying and end up getting blacklisted
in a very small community?
I know that's a tricky question.
I don't know.
So I worked at Bungie.
And when I finally got an interview there,
I had this weird connection problem at the airport
because the driver.
couldn't call me because the cell phone I had on file was like five years old, because I've
been spamming them for like five years or something, right? So it depends on how you do it
and I'm sure you guys can chime in here, but, um, yeah, use your best judgment, but at a
certain point, like there's just not a lot you can do, I think, other than try to get your sort
of foot in the door that way.
If I could just kind of interject with something which is,
oftentimes it's not no, it's just not right now.
And so I don't think anything over like a yearly cadence is
really that useful, but there are a lot of places that
actually love to see the same people come back over and over
again.
and if you can see some progression there. Plus it shows a little bit of passion for
that person toward your particular company. Like I don't just want to work at any game
company, I want to work at yours because I like what you do and your vision. I think
that's healthy. So I don't think you have to go out of your way to push hard, just send
the pings, send them off every once in a while and show some consistency there and some humility
about it. I think that can be healthy.
Yeah, and also try to find out who the art director is and that sort of thing, you know?
I originally got an interview at 343 doing the same thing with Kenneth Scott, who was
the art director then.
And the same at Bungie, it was the same approach.
I just didn't spam them all the time, I just spammed them once or twice, went away for
five years, spammed them again, and then it worked out.
So I would add to that.
you spam or ping a company, show difference in your portfolio.
So it becomes spam when it's the exact same thing.
And you're just like, hey, remember me, remember me.
We probably remember you.
And it's like a not right now, but it was not right now
based on that portfolio.
So if you improve your portfolio,
maybe that's a good time to connect again.
Rejection letters are never personal.
I mean, it's, and they're most likely the person
may have forgotten anyway.
So it doesn't hurt to send another time.
I'm still trying to figure out
how they let you get away for five years.
Like, I think you, yeah.
It was a later thing, right?
Yeah.
Come back later.
But I think that's, I mean, again,
just going back to like the rejection letter thing,
like y'all are looking for your jobs.
I mean,
You've seen Darren's work, it's amazing, and it took you five years, you know, like paying these guys sometimes.
Yeah, and I kept improving.
So, I mean, it's just a, if you're just starting your career, that's something to really think about.
Or Wyeth and Greg, both of you guys have seen some people's portfolios for the last couple years
and have seen their progression get better and better, and they request to see these guys,
and I think that also forming that connection helps as well.
Yeah, we've had people who came back, because this is like, what, seventh or eighth year
we've been doing this?
People who come back a couple of years in a row, ask for one of us in particular, and
then following year we don't see that person, and then we'll get a nice email like, hey,
I got hired.
So just to share like a small success story or whatever.
So I had reviewed the portfolio of an artist named Colton Orr last year.
He actually applied to my team this year, remembered his portfolio.
He went through the usual paces and we hired him.
So he's just joined our team.
And I mean, it's kind of hitting that connection, right?
So we reviewed his portfolio, gave him advice on this, this, and this.
He listened to it, he executed, and that progress was noticeable for sure.
Thank you for your time.
I had a question about what would your thoughts be on portfolios that feature multiple mediums?
So like if you had a character or some kind of structure that you had conventioned into
maybe a model figure or a toy or you even made a costume out of a character you made,
what are your thoughts on featuring something like that?
I don't think that has much business being in a portfolio,
honestly, if it were me.
I want to see the stuff that's directly applicable to the job
that we're hiring you to do.
I think that's the perfect kind of thing if you want to
put it in your personal blog.
If I want to learn more about you, if I've seen your
expectations for what you think your best work is, maybe
I'll go to your personal blog.
In fact, I will.
And I will go to your Twitter, and I will find your Facebook,
and I will find your postings on Polycount, and I will find
all the things on the internet to make sure you're not an
asshole.
That's definitely what we're going to do.
But that's a perfect thing to show as supplemental work.
But I don't think, for me, that that has much business
being in a portfolio.
Yeah, I hide that stuff.
Like I've done product design work and theme park work.
And I'll do random stuff here and there.
And I generally do not post it anywhere.
Because I'm sort of trying to, what I'm putting out there is
sort of like the brand.
And I don't really want to dilute that with anything
else.
I see, thank you.
Hi.
Hello, I'm Max.
First off, I'd like to thank you guys for just like talking,
give all this valuable information.
But my main question is,
as you guys kind of mentioned earlier,
the emerging job of technical artists.
My main question is,
is there like a global definition of technical artists?
Or is it more defined by like specifically
what your companies need?
I'll take that because that's what I do all day.
No, there isn't.
And actually, there's a strange schism between even the phrase.
There are companies who call tech artists tech animators.
And there are ones who call the tech animators tech animators
and tech artists tech artists.
And then there are tech artists who make shaders.
There are ones who write code.
There are ones who write pipeline like Python scripts and ingesting data in and out of GCC packages.
There are tech artists who do visual effects.
There is absolutely no definition in this space other than I would say you have to have good taste
and you can't be afraid of the technical side of problems.
So if I just wanted to give a broad, generic definition,
which isn't that particularly helpful, it would be that.
What I do all day is I make visual effects, I write
shaders, and I do aesthetic stuff.
Like I'll do lighting, or I'll do whatever it takes to make
something look better, to try to push it from 90 to 100.
That's kind of like my role, basically.
Um, and so while there isn't a specific definition, I think if you learn shaders, you learn some
effects, don't be scared of code, dabble in some HLSL and make sure you have good taste,
that's a pretty good start to tech art.
Awesome, so is it more like, so then you can incorporate, you know, programming into like
artistic, like if you're putting models and stuff on your portfolio, you can show that
you can incorporate like blueprints, like in Unreal, and kind of get them to do other
things?
Or write a really cool shader to do something interesting, like a non-traditional shading
model, something.
Or like a tool, like having, you know, some kind of...
modeling supplement or something like that for the team is also an example. So it kind of depends,
you know, like what I was saying. I mean, at Insomniac we have shader artists, technical
artists and technical director which is technically a rigger. So they will do tools based on
rigs. Our technical artists do tools. They're really more the mediator between art and
programming. Like they're the people.
Smart enough to understand what programming saying but have an eye for art so they can talk to a caveman like me
So they're kind of like the force multiplier in that way and then with like shader artists. It's now it's
Substance it's a lot of substance designer for sure
Awesome. Thank you very much that that helps a lot. Thank you
Just a couple comments.
You will be receiving an email about our talk.
Please give us a good review so that we can come back here
next year and talk to all you guys again.
If we get enough good reviews, will we get a bigger room?
I know, we need a...
We will fix that, I promise.
We will be fixing that.
And also, I feel, I apologize to this side of the room,
since it's been all on this side.
We're looking at you in spirit.
Hi, guys.
One thing that you guys talked about earlier that intrigued me was talking about having a second strong skill set.
The example you said was an animator with cinematic skills.
So what role would, say like a short film or like a music video, would those kind of show the cinematic skills?
Or is that not really applicable because it's not in the game industry?
I think I'd probably rather see it in the context of your animation, like your animation
with that, because you were talking about video editing or composition, like cinematography
like that.
Yeah, I think I'd rather, I mean, it would kind of translate, but I'd rather see it like,
hey, I animated this thing and I made this really cool shot to go along with it, like
you know, like an action cam kind of thing.
So.
So the camera enhancing the animation experience.
So I don't know that a music video or something would really tell me that.
But, yeah.
It's risky.
Yeah.
I think you can, like, if you just focus on your main, like, I don't know, like...
If you focus on like your main discipline, right, and you think about what story you're
trying to tell with that piece, I think if you continue down that path and see what you
can do to plus it, that's what will give you like the secondary skill, right?
So if it's environment, it would be like, well.
what story am I telling with this piece and then modeling it out, doing it like in a modular way,
like using like substance, creating all that content, lighting it, telling a story with the
character art, maybe it's adding like blend shapes and things like that to kind of show more emotion
in your character with animation. You know you could be making, make a film in Unreal,
which is free, you can get it anytime. But things like that, you could do a video in a game engine
that isn't...
you're not editing video in like whatever, after effects or something like that. But having all of
that in Unreal that's more context, you're not just animating, you're actually, now you're
telling a story, you're doing your own cinematic and, you know, you're increasing what you
already were doing, you know?
Yeah, like take, take your, take your walk cycle instead of just, you know, guy walking
three quarters at me looping, do that and then show me something with a dynamic camera,
right? Like it's just plussing what you already have. You don't have to do a whole other
thing, it's like enhancing it.
Thank you very much.
Hello.
Hi.
I'm preparing a portfolio piece for TechHeart.
And my question is that because TechHeart is so diverse, so I'm debating on...
Should I focus on just one specific area like rigging?
Or should I just show that I have know-hows
in every dimension in general?
Yeah, it's a tough one.
At some point, you're going to have to realize that a company
is also going to have to be compatible with you, and not
just with the scatter shot broad approach.
I would rather show someone's show really peak excellence in
a technical area, and also show some ancillary knowledge
around that area, like Python, or like HLSL, or like really
nice shader work that's visual and beautiful and shows
complexity.
So, I think when you're starting out, I'd rather see you get good at something very
specific and show mastery there and then express a little bit of ancillary mastery around that
and then you're just going to have to wait for the company that matches well with needing
that part of you.
I think it's going to take you a long time to get really, really good at a really broad
array of things and have a portfolio like that.
So that's not where I would start.
Phil or me.
Thank you.
I appreciate your answer.
Hi, I'm wondering if there is a tasteful way to sort of show a time frame in which you worked on a portfolio piece.
Like maybe game jams or time lapses or something like that.
I guess in my opinion the time doesn't really matter, it would be the quality.
And I know, like, it's kind of common to be proud of how fast, like, a turnaround time was. But
honestly, man, if it's bad, it's bad. It doesn't matter how long it took. And if it's good, it's
good. Things like speed, turnaround time, shortcuts, workflow, I can teach you that. But it just needs
to be good. We're already going to learn that from you with the test, which we're inevitably
going to give you. The test is already going to tell us that. All right. Thank you.
Hi, I was wondering, so everyone says you should have your best piece first in your portfolio,
but what if your best piece is not one of your most recent?
Does that reflect badly on you?
No, I don't really, I don't worry about your portfolio necessarily being chronological
in any way.
Okay.
Some of my favorite pieces are a couple years old and very jealous of past me.
But that's still work you've done and it's, you know, in recent enough memory I think
that's totally fine to structure your portfolio as strongly as possible.
Okay, thank you.
Hey guys, I'm Andrea, so I'm a final year student majoring in games art and specialized environment art.
So I want to
My question is, is personal branding important and also
presenting your work, so like
getting screenshots from a game engine, especially like
kind of like a shooting camera.
It should be like something like more cinematic,
so inspired by movies or more like game related,
so mostly like first person view or third person, so.
I mean, it's a tough one because some of this comes down to the company you're applying
for.
So, just know your strength.
This is one of those areas where we're not going to be able to tell you what's right
because we don't know what you're good at.
When in doubt and the options are wide, pick one thing.
So if there is a lot of context and you're like, I could go anywhere, I could do anything,
that means you just haven't kind of settled in yet and we don't actually want to see those decisions
happening in your portfolio. We don't want to see the schizophrenia of the decisions.
Pick something and show some kind of apex decisions in that area.
And we actually don't care what you pick, just be good at something and that's where you start.
Okay, now just thinking about how you present your work,
is that like a bad way to present your work?
Or like, it's like, it doesn't really matter,
like, yeah, just, I like this angle,
yeah, is that composition is okay?
I just take a screen and like, yeah.
We'd rather just see that you have good taste.
So it's not really about that decision,
it's about doing something aesthetically pleasing.
It's not really about the presentation per se,
in that regard.
Maybe like look for reference.
Yeah, that's a good point.
OK, thank you.
Thank you for a great advice, guys.
I have a question regarding using specific software
to create art.
So basically, you can use whatever program
is in the market right now, like Photoshop, Gimp, or Paint,
if you're desperate.
Or basically, you can model in Maya and animate in 3D Max.
So basically, does it make sense to apply
for a Maya-specific company if you're using
3D Max for most of your work?
I don't really care what you're...
All of our guys have made a shift at one point or another,
whether it's animators going to Maya.
Some of our modelers now going from Max to Maya.
If you understand one and you're good at it,
you'll be able to, we're usually reasonably confident
we'll be able to figure out the other one.
And honestly, I don't really care, again,
because it now comes down to what's in the game.
Whatever gets me to the game model, I don't really care.
So, I mean, we're pretty.
I think a lot of us are pretty flexible about what your
authoring tool is.
It doesn't really matter anymore.
Yeah.
So thank you.
Uh, I mean for me personally I've gone from like Lightwave to Exocyte to Max to Maya to Max to
Maya, now Max and Maya again. Uh, all of my team they use whatever they want, Max, Modo, Maya, uh,
but in the end it'll just all go into the game engine so it's you, as long as you show that
knowledge of putting something into a game engine, like the real time aspect of it, that's all
that matters to me and we can work, we've worked our pipeline to accept, it's agnostic, it can
take whatever, right?
Uh, something like substance is just really more of the, you know, pack leader in that way. But
what you really need to know is like PBR. You need to know like real time shaders and how to
properly create textures for, you know, modern engines, right? So, uh, it's not, you can do that
in Photoshop if you want. You might be able to make paint.
you might be able to do it in paint, I don't know. But uh, but
it's the knowledge that matters more than whatever software logo
is on your art station. You know what I mean? Cool, thank you
very much.
Hi, thank you so much for the talk.
You mentioned earlier that you would look through people's social media after they piqued
your interest to see if they're not an ass.
Would you be suspicious if you looked up someone and saw that they didn't really use Twitter
or Facebook very much?
Would that be a red flag?
No, not at all.
Okay, thank God.
Well now I am.
Get his name.
Yeah.
Ha ha ha.
Hey, thank you very much, guys.