Good morning, everyone.
Thank you for coming so early.
I'm Yasuda Fumihiko, the director of Team Ninja Nioh.
Yes, good morning, everyone. Thank you so much for coming out.
I know it's still pretty early considering GDC week.
GDC week is a very long week for everyone.
So, thanks so much for coming to our session.
My name is Fumihiko Yasuda,
and I'm from Team Ninja, game director for Nioh.
We have tried to revive the classic Samurai game in GDC as a modern action game.
I am very happy to be able to talk about it.
So I'm really excited today to share with you the stories about how we sort of revived the samurai action RPG game,
which turned out to be RPG game, but the samurai action genre and the lessons learned, reintroducing a classic game to a modern audience.
It's rare for Team Ninja to talk about the production process here.
I'm nervous too, so I hope this will be helpful for everyone.
Today, I'd like to talk about Nioh.
And it's pretty rare that we, our studio, Team Ninja,
share some of these stories in sort of the public forum
or panels and sessions like this.
So I'm a bit nervous, but hopefully I can share some stories
that will be of help or informative for all of you here today.
First of all, I'd like to talk about the history of the title Nihono.
So I'd like to start out with a brief history of Nioh.
Nioh has a very strange history.
It was in 2005 when Shibusawa Kou, the founder of Koei,
announced the title.
It was made by Koei, but it didn't go well and was discontinued.
After that, Koei and Tecmo merged,
and in 2011, Team Ninja was in charge of development.
So the development history of NEO is it's a bit complicated
As you may know it was announced in 2005 which is quite some time ago
Ko Shibusawa the founder of Koei first announced this title NEO and initially began
development on the Koei side
But after a few unsatisfactory attempts, it was sort of put back in the closet shelved
away for a while.
And then soon after Tecmo had merged with Koei, Team Ninja was chosen to take on the
Neo project and ultimately began development in 2011.
In 2011, we started with Ninja Gaiden as the base,
an action game like Samurai Gaiden,
but we realized that it lacked independence,
so we stopped developing it.
In 2014, we started again with Team Ninja,
including Hayashi, the studio head.
We started with a team of 8, and announced it at TGS in 2015.
And in February of this year, we finally released it.
And so in 2011, we started the project.
The overarching sort of, I guess, goal or theme
was that we would make a Samurai Gaiden action game
based on Ninja Gaiden franchise.
But even that, it didn't really work out.
So we just continued that direction
and then put it on sort of a pause for a second.
In 2014, we restarted the development
with a new direction.
with about eight people in the beginning,
including Hayashi, Yosuke Hayashi, the head of Team Ninja, and myself.
The game was announced to the public at Tokyo Game Show in 2015,
and then it was finally released just last month on the PlayStation 4.
In 2014, I participated in the project.
In the beginning, I made the concept and target of the title clear.
So the first thing I did when taking over or restarting the project was that in 2014,
that was to define the target audience and a new approach for this title.
We decided to target core gamers and make a game that's unique.
Above all, we, Team Ninja, are the core gamers, so we made that choice.
I personally felt that Team Ninja should not attempt to make a user-friendly or accessible
to accessible of a, I guess, a game targeting a wide consumer base.
I wanted to take an approach that separated us from most traditional AAA titles released
in the West to develop a specific type of game targeting hardcore gamers who would enjoy
this very challenging content.
Because they, and ourselves, are the most dedicated and die-hard of all gamers.
So our target audience in the new approach aimed directly towards what we call in Japanese
Shinigae, and a Massacore concept and gamer community.
I was involved as a director in Ninja Gaiden 3 and Ninja Gaiden Z,
but I failed because the concept and the game I made from there
didn't meet the expectations of the core game players.
So, based on that reflection,
I decided to develop the game while always being aware of the concept and the target.
So I was also the director in charge of Ninja Gaiden 3 as well as Yaiba Ninja Gaiden Z
two different projects which I learned
very difficult and valuable lessons from and based on those experiences
I really just had to remind myself in the beginning of Nioh's
development that I should never compromise our core audience and the integrity of our work
So one thing that we thought about was, as you see in the slide here, we were asking
ourselves, okay, what are we going to do to make sure that we keep on track of our core
concept and approach?
As everyone who is here makes sure that you're aware of the opportunity.
That we are constantly limited in terms of budget and technology.
It's always an issue where we are not satisfied with the concepts and our current social considerations.
We decided to have the player experience the game,
so that he could have direct communication with the game.
So I think most of you here are developers yourselves or at least in the development community
So I think you would understand or agree with me, but we have to continuously struggle or juggle a lot of elements under various
Constraints that may be time budget
technical issues and so on so
I think that we all get to a point where we feel very anxious
whether our concepts and direction meets the players' expectations.
So we decided to reshape the development process
by communicating directly with our target audience
throughout the process with these game demos.
Instead of it being released right away,
but beginners want to check out the gameplay
anduzzle components in advance.
At the time of the development cycle
when feedback is received,
we try to release multiple trial and errors boards.
Even though the development process may take a few years or even longer than now,
during this period of process we have decided that
I wanted to make sure that the players' expectations and the direction of the game were not deviated.
As I said earlier, the title Nioh has been expected by many people for more than 10 years.
I wanted to hear his voice as soon as possible.
So the demos became a development tool to validate and confirm our approach rather than an advertisement or marketing or PR sort of tool.
They were to be released several times in this case and ended up being a few times, but during the course of development, mid to late term, where feedback would be utilized or addressed.
As this game took quite a few years to develop, I wanted to confirm whether there was a gap between
the game direction and the players expectations during that period. And especially with NEO,
because it was announced 10 years ago and
there were people who were still hoping or maybe following, looking forward to it,
I wanted to make sure that those fans
were getting the information and being able to sort of communicate back with us
and to look forward to the final product.
And this is the actual schedule of the trial version.
In April of 2016, the Alpha trial version was released.
In August, the Beta trial version was released.
And in January of this year, the final trial version was released.
So as you see here, the schedule, it ended up being three times. The first one starting in April of last year. The second one, the beta, being August. And then just before the release, during just one weekend in January, we had the last chance trial demo.
We had a plan to improve the game and gather feedback on the alpha and beta versions.
But we didn't really want to do the final version,
but we didn't have a lot of reservations, so we were told to do it.
The main goal for the alpha and beta demos were to collect feedback and improve the quality of the game.
The last chance trial demo, I actually was sort of hesitant or opposed to doing that.
and it was released for just a small amount of time,
just one last weekend.
But that was because I was told or informed that
our pre-order numbers were not as high as we had thought.
So I went ahead and committed to doing a last chance trial demo.
So here's a quick snapshot of the results from the alpha demo.
We don't have much data on this.
This is the data from all over the world, so you may not understand it.
In the US, the response was very positive.
However, the response in Japan and Asia was very poor.
This is just...
I think the difference between the way of thinking and the way of enjoying the trial version is a big reason.
But it was interesting.
The point that the tutorial is not enough and the player's operation is more like this was actually the same content.
So this chart that you see here is not divided by region
or territory, so it's hard to tell.
However, I'll give you some information on what we saw,
is that many players in the West were quite positive,
overall, about the demo, but that was actually not the case
with our players in Japan and Asia.
We sort of concluded or realized that this sort of gap is
probably caused by cultural differences and how they
perceive difficulty. And probably some of the
contrasting ways that players navigate through or perceive
what is an alpha demo and a beta demo. However, interestingly,
there were common opinions such as a lack of tutorial elements
and improving user performance or controls.
Speaking Japanese
So what we did here is based on the feedback that we got, we made these improvements for the alpha phase.
We collected the data from the online survey,
but there were very few players who gave their opinions through the official survey.
We had to go and get information ourselves.
There were many positive and negative opinions on social media and the bulletin board,
so it was very helpful.
So gathering information from players was definitely not an
easy task, as you may also have experienced.
The data that I showed earlier is a combined result of a
questionnaire together with the demos.
But since the players who provided these opinions and
filled out the questionnaire were very few in numbers, we
had to kind of proactively go out and seek where everyone was
talking about whether it was through.
the boards, the forums, or social media.
We had to really go out and dig further so that we had
enough feedback to really look at.
And I think people were a lot more honest and open
about their feedback and opinions in those areas.
And throughout that process, you know, there were new things that we learned or discovered,
such as, I don't know, I'm not sure if I'm pronouncing it correctly,
but is it waifu or weeaboo or get good.
These are new terms to us.
And so once we completed the alpha demo process,
collected the feedback, three months later,
we went to our next step, which was releasing the beta demo.
This is the result of the beta and alpha online survey.
As a result of the improvements,
we can see that the feedback on almost all topics has improved.
And so the top is the alpha demo results, as you can see.
And then the lower being the beta.
After making these improvements based on the alpha feedback,
you can see that pretty much in every single element,
the feedback was increased on the positive side.
So I'd like to go in deeper with what we ended up doing with that feedback, going from the
alpha, implementing and reflecting, and then reflecting the feedback, and then going into
the beta demo.
The first problem that we encountered had really nothing to do with the feedback that we were actually getting.
It was more about that our own staff, our own team members became way too influenced and affected by the opinions of the players.
I even gave suggestions like,
let's make it A because the player said A,
or let's make it easy because the boss is difficult.
So all the suggestions I collected from the players
were not answers, but questions.
I made sure to never forget that
we are the ones who answer the questions.
So for example, if someone saw feedback that says,
oh, we want this to be changed,
just because some of the players said that,
or even maybe a few players said that,
we didn't want it to be like,
okay, that's something that we wanna change.
Or some of the feedback that we got was,
make this boss battle easier.
Do we make it easier?
Probably not.
We needed to really think about it.
Same with the difficulty level, not just with the boss battles, but throughout.
Therefore, I tried to remind everyone that we are the developers who are creating the game.
And by attempting to consider all these various sort of range of feedback that we were getting,
we weren't arriving to a solid solution or an answer.
But these were rather more questions that we were supposed to be asking ourselves.
The most specific example is the one at the top.
There was a parameter called durability, which was not very well received.
Many people suggested that we remove it.
But we thought that removing it would be the same as not working.
So we decided to change the parameter to the IOD parameter.
We decided to remove the player's burden and the elements that the player disliked,
while maintaining the same effect.
So, one notable change that we made is the one at the very top to the removing the equipment
durability system.
Now, if we had just said, okay, let's do that, we're going to cut that out, then that would
not be probably the right answer.
or the right solution that we were looking for.
So what we did was we didn't entirely remove it,
but rather we changed it to a weapon familiarity system.
That way it had the same sort of effect or result
from the player standpoint,
but we just made an adjustment or a change
so that we still kept something
that we wanted the players to feel
as they were playing the game.
I also wanted to make it open world.
This game is a game where players can play again and again after the game is over.
I wanted to keep the load shorter.
I wanted to keep the load of the retry shorter,
and I wanted to keep the density and frequency of the battle high.
That's why I decided to make it open world.
Another opinion was to create an open world system, the third one here.
This was also rejected as we wanted to shorten the load time after death
and raise the frequency and density of the battles.
The other bullet points that you see here are some of the changes we made.
We adopted some of the feedback regarding the behavior of the camera lock-on feature,
increasing level of difficulty, and so forth.
So it was pretty easy to determine whether to incorporate opinions about the technical issues or disregard some of the negative feedback.
But what was really important was to really stay true to the concept and approach that we had from the very beginning of the game.
And it might be a small thing, but something that we learned, an important lesson, is that we opened up about the feedback that we received.
We made a promise to the fans that we would improve the game and make it a good game.
So, in sum, I have the good and the bad, so we'll start out with the good.
and if it is correct, you can correct it.
This is one of the original purposes of the trial version,
and I think it has been realized in a very good way.
So the first one being acquiring player feedback,
and obviously not just that.
But we were able to then take that and proceed
with adjustments, reflect some of the feedback based
on the player's response.
This was the main objective of the demo,
so we were very satisfied with the results.
The second one was a great experience for the team.
we started to find answers ourselves,
and use this sort of information to develop the game.
And also it was a really positive learning experience for our development team
Not just myself, but everyone who worked on it. We were able to find
answers and things that we wanted to still
sort of keep on our checklist and what has happened is that we are able to then take that and
whether it's going to be in the form of DLCs or updates we'll be able to
follow through with some of these things that we still have remaining and wanting to do
And finally, by taking communication,
I think that with new titles like Nioh,
we can start from zero,
but we were able to create a very good situation
where fans can exist even before the game is released.
And lastly, establishing new fans.
Even though we have been creating, producing,
and putting out games under other franchise names,
Neo, technically, would be a brand new IP.
So if you think about it,
we're really starting from scratch.
There was really no fan base to begin with.
But the fact that we, through these demos,
we were able to gain new fans
and start establishing a Neo player community.
I'm not a fan of this game,
but it was an experience I had when I was in the U.S.
I was really happy to know that SIE
would be collaborating in the U.S.
And another thing is that this title is actually published by Sony Interactive Entertainment Group
and I think all territories and
what happened was is that after seeing the results or the positive reception of the alpha demo we were able to
put together the publishing deal with Sony Interactive.
So that meant a lot for us.
And it proved that this game was going
to be something that they would support throughout the launch
and with marketing.
SPEAKER 1 IN JAPANESE
So obviously, after the good, let's look at the bad.
The first one is spoilers.
I don't think there are many people in Japan who are expecting a story,
but it was a player's first experience,
and it was a side effect of stealing the fun of experiencing it for the first time.
So the first one is spoilers, and I don't know if spoilers is the most accurate term here, and also I don't know if
people looking forward to Neo were really
wanting to know it from a story or a narrative perspective.
But nonetheless, to be able to check out the game
prior to its final product or final release,
it does take away from being able to experience
that first-time impression.
So that might have been something
that was not really intended in terms of spoiling it,
but that you do get that feeling of knowing something
prior to its final release.
The development team was also under a lot of pressure.
Because this is a demo, it's something that the customers will be able to touch.
We had to realize the quality of the product.
I think that was a huge burden on the development team.
Secondly, it was a really heavy burden on the development team.
Even if the demo is at an alpha stage, the quality still needed to be reflective of a
final product or a stage within the final product.
So that was something that we really had to concentrate and make sure that it was good
enough quality to put out as a demo.
Lastly, during the time we were streaming the demo, no one was working.
We were able to see a lot of reactions online,
especially the ones on Twitch where we were streaming gameplays.
We were able to see their gameplays in real time,
so we were watching those all the time.
There was a problem that no one was working at all.
And lastly a really big problem none of our guys were able to work or concentrate on what they were supposed to be doing
You know we were happy that people were checking out the demo, but it's very hard to block anything
That's maybe made online and are made available online
And so we were constantly checking on these players who are live streaming on Twitch, and we just couldn't
We just couldn't ignore that and so it wasn't a very productive time spent,
time well spent during this period.
But it wasn't all bad even though we couldn't concentrate on our work because we were seeing
a lot of positive reaction and responses as they were streaming.
I felt this way through this trial version.
The first alpha demo was basically free, and anyone could play it.
I think it would have been better if it was limited to a few more people.
So in hindsight, I felt that the first alpha demo could have been limited
To a certain number of players to some extent. I don't have any specific ideas
But maybe I feel that it would have been more effective to limit the amount of players
I think it's because there were a lot of people who were like,
if you can play for free, why not try it for a few minutes?
Especially this game is very fun and you'll die very quickly.
So there were a lot of people who were like, what is this?
And they let go of their hands.
And maybe even a purchase to play demo option.
What happened was is that because it was free to
download, free to play, there was a very, very wide variety
of feedback and opinions we got.
Yes, that's important.
But at the same time, there would be players who would
probably play for a very, very short amount of time.
They would die instantly.
And then that would then become their first impression and maybe only impression.
So there is this feeling that maybe we should have limited, we should have had a way to
limit the number of players who had access to the demo.
As I said, there were many points of regret and bad points.
We don't know whether it is right or wrong to implement this trial version.
However, it is a part that is definitely required and approached,
so I think it is a very good thing to do if you are prepared.
And so I want to mention here that there is really no correct answer with regards to conducting game demos
Or in the way that we did this time around. I think there's both the good and the bad
it's definitely a
Requirement for us developers to at least listen to the players voices
whether that takes shape or form in the way that we did or not
I think it's just fundamentally important to have our ears open so that we can listen.
So it's important for us to prepare and come up with new methods to acquire these valuable insights from our fans.
With confidence, I can say that. Even though it was our first
time kind of operating in this way and changing the way that we
developed the game, we are seeing results in terms of
reaction, reviews, and even sales numbers. So I do want to
say that this was a great learning experience. Not only
that, but I think it added value to the entire project for NEO.
Lastly, I would like to say that we have created Nioh by communicating with players through the demo.
I would be happy if you could learn more about the development process.
So that was a very small window into our journey with Nioh and the communications that took place
with us and the potential fans.
I hope this provided you with a better understanding of our creative and development process and how we ultimately shaped this game.
This was our first attempt, so it was a very unique experience for the team and I.
We were able to see what kind of expectations the players had for Nioh,
and how they wanted us to respond to the game.
The biggest thing we learned from this was that
we were able to feel that our concept and goals were correct.
We were able to feel that our concept and goals were correct.
I've said a few bad things today, but I think the biggest advantage was that we were able to develop with confidence and strong motivation.
So it was a unique experience for myself and the team.
We learned so much about our intended fans and their expectations for this game.
More importantly, this user engagement provided us with an opportunity to reaffirm our direction
and gain the confidence to steer boldly forward.
It added motivation for us.
As an exercise that was designed to learn more about our fans and gain valuable feedback,
We ultimately learned a lot about ourselves, our own selves in the process.
And so that is a priceless lesson that we will not forget.
It may not have been all good, but in addition to what I said,
we've learned about our own strengths as Team Ninja and what we're able to achieve.
So we want to definitely take that and carry that into whatever next project we have.
And so that's it.
Thank you again for coming,
and I hope I get the privilege to speak to you again
someday in the future.
Thank you.
So we have about 20 minutes,
and we're gonna open it up to Q&A.
There are two mics down the aisle here,
and we are recording audio,
so if you could come up if you have any questions,
and we'll take one at a time.
Hello. I was wondering if you have any hard and fast rules on when to look at feedback seriously.
Like if you see 10 forum posts, you're like, okay, maybe we should look at this.
Or there's a hundred forum posts about a single topic, you're like, we need to fix this.
What is your standard in judging whether the response is positive or not?
Not really.
I don't have a standard.
Everyone has their own standards.
So the short answer is no, we didn't really go by any sort of guideline in terms of quantity,
the number of feedback.
and not quality, but it wasn't that we had a threshold that we thought we should meet
and then start looking into feedback. It was really about the content, what they were saying,
what we thought was something that was important that we had to bring it up and reflect
into the next. So we started with really no guidelines and just looked at the raw responses
that we were getting. Thank you. Thank you.
I can't see. Is there one person?
Hello, my name is Ilya. First of all, thank you for the
question. I have three simple questions. First one is how
technically do you distribute the demos?
Second one, how many players participate in both demos, in
three demos? And the last one, how technically did you gain
results from the feedback? It was emails or maybe Facebook
page or maybe some special mechanics in the game?
Okay. I just want to make sure the first one was you asked how
did we distribute the demo? Okay. So you mean outside of the
PlayStation store and that?
So it's just was the PlayStation store demo. Yeah? Okay.
I can react.
Yes, that's right.
The first question was how many people were watching the demo,
and the third question was,
you went to a lot of places to get feedback,
but were there any particular SNS sites that stood out?
Like Facebook?
The second question was,
what was it again?
On average, 700,000 to 800,000 people downloaded and played it.
So it's global?
Yes, it's global.
What about the third one?
The third one...
What was it again?
Was it on Facebook?
It was pretty much just NeoGaf and Regit.
OK, so the way that the demo was distributed
was you could download it for free
through the PlayStation Store.
And that was the only way.
There was no other method of distribution.
The second question, how many players?
So approximately, this is on a global level,
approximately 700,000 to 800,000 downloads of the free demo.
And then thirdly, in terms of where social media channels,
where did we sort of hone in on or look at?
It was really everything, including NeoGAF and Reddit.
So anything and everywhere that you can think of
that we can collect feedback, we were trying to cover.
Thank you.
All right, thank you for the presentation first.
My question is, how did you prioritize the choices you had
to make during development?
Was it more depending on how strong the player feedback was
to make this or this specific choice on the top of the list?
Or was it more depending on how time-consuming it
would be for your team?
I think you mentioned this earlier, but what kind of feedback do you think we should get?
Is it something like, this is a small amount of work, so let's do it.
Or is it something like, it's going to take a long time to do this in Japan, so we can't handle it.
Is there a priority?
Well, I think the limitations are...
The budget and the time limit are huge.
When you make a decision, you can't avoid it.
When I was deciding whether to play or not,
the biggest thing was, as I mentioned earlier,
the concept and the target of this game.
I think it's hard to make a perfect 100-game game.
As for this game, I...
I think this game has a lot of good points, but we wanted to protect Nioh's unique combat.
We didn't compromise and focused on what we could do.
So I mentioned this in the presentation a little bit, but yes, obviously we had a lot
of constraints, whether it was time or money or just resources.
Even if we wanted to maybe address something that we thought was really important, we would
just have to make that call at the end of the day to say, yes we can or no we can't.
But really it comes down to the very main sort of theme of today's presentation is that
we wanted to keep true to the game concept and approach that we had set for ourselves
and hopefully for the potential consumers later on.
and we didn't want to sacrifice anything
or affect the concept in a way that we didn't think
it was gonna be the Neo that we set out to do.
Additionally, what I can say is that
I hope it comes out right, but this game has a lot of good qualities from many different types of maybe games.
I don't think that's necessarily a bad thing,
but in doing so, we did want to really have a Neo-like, a Neo-specific combat experience,
and I just wanted to keep that.
very tight and very important and that was a high priority.
We didn't want to mess anything up in delivering that combat experience.
So we put a lot of weight and focus and concentration on that.
All right. Thank you.
My gun. Hi.
Do you feel the timing of the demos was appropriate?
Do you feel now in hindsight that doing them earlier may have been more beneficial?
Yes, the timing when I was making the alpha demo and when I was making the beta demo,
was the exact same with the timing when I was making the whole game.
I think I should have done the beta demo earlier that time.
We had a title that was based on the beta version.
It's true that we didn't have many options,
but I think it would have been better
if we had started working on the beta version earlier.
In a way, maybe we could have...
time the beta testing or the beta release of the beta demo a little bit earlier.
There was quite some time, I think about three or three and a half, four months in
between the alpha and the beta. It did sort of work in parallel with our
development process or sort of knee-deep into us creating the game, you know,
developing and really aiming for
hitting some of these schedules and milestones we had.
So we could have probably pushed up the beta demo a little bit.
However, at that same time, we were
very aware of these other titles that were coming in
or maybe aiming for release at the same time.
So we had to make sure that we hit our schedule
and not hopefully be in a super competitive time
frame for release.
And so those were maybe some guidelines
that served us to do demos at a certain time.
time. Thank you. Hello. Thanks for the talk. When the idea for
these public demos came across, did you encounter any resistance
from Sony or Koi or even internally at Team Ninja and how
did you kind of address that and mitigate the potential risks of
doing something like this?
When you decided to do this, did you ever think it was risky for Sony or the doctor to do this?
Well, Sony never said it was bad, but the development team was against it.
That's it.
I agree.
But everyone knew that the schedule would be tight.
So we were against it.
But there was also the new IP.
So we decided to put it out after 3 years.
It was more of an experience than a risk.
It's not a taste of cooking.
I remember convincing everyone that it was very effective.
I can say that our own dev team was entirely opposed to the idea.
So it was a really tough decision or a tough call.
But the main thing was that we knew that if we had executed this plan that we put in place,
that our schedules were going to really be tight.
And we were, you know, basically it was a race against time.
But when you think about it...
you know, releasing a new IP already has its own challenges
in trying to communicate what this title is all about.
So, you know, three years down the road
to not have released anything
and to put it out on the shelves
and to hear sort of feedback for the first time,
that's also a risk in a way.
And so I feel like maybe going through this,
we were able to mitigate those risks.
and people picking up a brand new IP for the first time.
So I'll use an analogy for maybe cooking.
You know, when you have a dish
that you're aiming for or targeting,
you add ingredients and you add spices
and you add umami along the way.
So that's how we maybe saw this
as perfecting the dish at the end.
We had to make these fine adjustments in the middle.
Great, thank you.
Thank you.
Good morning.
I'm Keira.
Nice to meet you.
As a designer,
How were you guys able to take player feedback and actually
dissect what they were saying to actually help with the game?
For example, instead of just taking something like a player
would say, oh, I don't like this about the game, or this
part sucks, or something like that, how do you actually take
that kind of feedback to apply to the system and say, well,
they're actually talking about this mechanic.
They don't really like how this works.
Or maybe this can be improved or tweaked a little bit so
that it's easier for the player to understand it.
I'm a designer, so I can't say I'm a designer, but I get a lot of feedback.
For example, you mentioned earlier that it's okay because it's okay.
But if you say it specifically, what do you have to adjust or change to reflect that feedback?
What kind of criteria do you have to meet?
So, for example, if you change the system here, it will be like this?
Yes, when you consider it, you should look at the problem without bias.
and we started discussing it.
After that, we had to find a solution to the problem.
We had a premise that we wouldn't satisfy 100% of the players,
but we wanted to satisfy as many people as possible.
That was the main reason for doing multiple trial versions.
Otherwise...
I think it was difficult to tell if the changes were good or bad.
I did it twice, actually three times, and I think it had a very good effect.
So there wasn't really, similar to the answer that we gave earlier, there wasn't really a rule book that we really played by.
We would collect all the feedback, look through it, sort through it, and the most important thing was that we had to look at it from a non-biased point of view.
So we would take sort of ourselves out of the equation once and then look at it from that perspective
but then also to jump to the other answer that we had earlier is that
Next thing is we have to work within some time and budgetary constraints and technical
Maybe constraints that we maybe wanted to do but we knew that we couldn't achieve
We knew that in making these changes or reflecting these adjustments in the game
you know, we're not gonna make everyone.
100% happy.
It's almost impossible to make a perfect game for everyone who's going to be purchasing this game.
Knowing that, we would make
adjustments, changes, implement new systems, and so forth, hoping that by the time...
This is in the alpha, but then by the time we reflected that in the beta,
they would be either addressed or sort of proven. And if not addressed, we would make that sort of open.
And so by doing an alpha and beta, and as a result, we did do the third one,
to kind of make sure that we can check that earlier feedback in the next one
was actually a really good, I guess, idea or plan that we followed through with the feedback from the users.
Thank you.
No other questions?
Everyone's very quiet because it's in the morning.
Oh, OK, I see someone walking up.
Hi.
I was curious what kind of telemetry and metrics you are tracking over your alpha, beta clients and that kind of thing.
Thanks.
In the game Nioh, there is a blood sword in the game logo.
It is a blood sword that can be used when a player dies in an online game.
The data shows how many people died in which stage and in which place.
The data shows the difficulty of the game.
to other machines.
So as you see in this logo too, the katana zuka,
this is something that, so whenever a player dies, we were capturing
where, location, and when.
So that was something that
was, amongst other data that we collected, that was something that was kind of an obvious thing that we wanted to catch.
And it also would tell us or inform us kind of the difficulty level
demo, but obviously from the results we would see where
people were dying the most or the least.
One more question for me. How was your experience testing this
game with players and getting feedback from them significantly
different from doing something more like traditional internal
focus group testing or something like that? Was the nature of the
results very different?
If you test the players with the general public,
what do you feel is the difference between the event,
the one in the club and the one outside?
What's new?
And the format for the Focus Group has changed.
I went through both events
but the players in the Club
In some cases, there were honest reviews
Also, there were quite a few players who gave scores
So that was very reassuring
So we actually did both. We still did our sort of usual traditional methods.
But obviously when you put something out in the public and they're free to say whatever in the public forum,
there's a very wide variety of feedback and opinion that we
could get. So that was probably the biggest difference. When
you go through maybe like a focus group test, there's maybe
a questionnaire that's already given or it's already, you know,
fit in a format that they have to follow. So that was number
one. And then obviously the volume of responses we can
gather from doing a public demo is very different from doing a
kind of restricted time scheduled, whether it's QA testing or focus group testing.
Hello. Thank you for making a great game. I noticed that Neo
has the very best performance options on any game that we've
seen on console. You can pick 1080p, 60 frames per second or
you can go HD. And this is something that's a big topic of
discussion among players now is that the performance and when
you guys have it on PS4 Pro.
you can choose between resolution or high frame rate.
And I was wondering if your team was in tune with these
discussions and the desire for higher performance on console
games now, or if that was just a company internal or team
internal directive of your own to bring out the best of your
tight gameplay?
The setting of Nioh is the most important part of the story.
It's not something that was decided by the team.
It's not something that was decided by the players.
It's something that the players can enjoy.
We know that it was very well received.
But this is probably due to the trial version.
Since it's an action game, we always put the final optimizer at the end.
But since it's a trial version, we couldn't optimize it enough.
Not only the action, but also the RPG elements are very strong.
We were actually going to prepare both options for the Alpha version,
but the engineer gave us an idea and we thought it was a good idea to incorporate it.
It was very well received, so we decided to include it in the product version.
And PS4 Pro was also announced after that,
and it worked very well with that.
I think it's all thanks to the demo.
Performance wise, you aim for the highest even during development, but it's really the last stretch that we put in so much effort to make sure that the performance isn't lagging.
And so, you know, while we put out a demo, we would hear some of this feedback and our engineer would try to say, well, maybe we can address this.
Let's give it a try.
Knowing that this is not just a pure action game,
but it has its RPG elements as well,
we're like, you know what, it might actually be good
to offer these user, or these settings, and have a user.
pick and choose kind of what they want to do. So thanks to some of the feedback
and discussions we had post alpha demo
it I think helped our engineering team to look into that direction and at the same time the ps4
announcement came out and so we felt like it was a natural fit or a good idea for the game.
You've set a very good example for all games on console,
so keep up the good work.
Thank you.
I think we should learn other games as well.
OK, I think we have time for one last one.
I have another question actually.
So, how do you feel about doing more changes to the game in the future
alongside season pass content, for example? Do you feel you should
still
do changes to the original gameplay experience or not?
What kind of information will your users need, as well as how late an update and dlc should be available, in the future?
I want to make sure the release is on time.
and we are considering a Day 1 patch or an update after the release.
I think the communication will be the same as the one we had in Nioh,
so I think we will be increasing the weight of the game.
So obviously, you know, release day and what you get out of the box or download,
the first thing that you open up is really important. We need to have the
game there. But as, you know, online day one patches or updates or DLCs become
more and more of a common thing, we kind of expect to get more. And we, thanks to
the demo and the feedback, but continuing on that path we feel like there's going to be...
a wealth of opinion exchanges, hopefully for Nioh,
and we will take a look at it and see when the right timing
or what the proper content is that we can reflect
in these updates and DLCs coming forward.
So we will, in a way, probably put more weight
in doing that than we did for our previous titles.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
I think time's up, so this is the end.