Hi everyone, welcome to the GDC Twitch channel.
My name is Brian Francis, I'm the contributing editor at Gamasutra.com.
I am a community manager for GC, and I am here today playing a game called Outer Wild.
Oh no, it's got THE Outer Wild in my overlay, that's embarrassing.
Uh, sorry about that.
Um, I am going- I am not going to be able to fix that for the stream, I am so sorry about that.
Oh, are you set? Yeah, it happens a lot.
Oh boy.
Um, anyway, uh, hi there everyone.
I'm joined today, after my embarrassing mistake, in the lower left-hand corner of the screen
by two wonderful folks from Mobius Digital.
Those folks are Lone Vernell and Wesley Martin.
And also in the lower left-hand corner of the screen is Alex Guaro, who is a content
master for GC and also contributing editor at Gamasutra.
Alex, how you doing?
Uh, pretty good. I'm sorry I didn't jump in earlier, but I wanted to follow good podcast etiquette and wait until I was introduced.
Yeah.
Uh, yeah, let's, uh, let's talk about this game. This game's real good, right?
We should probably let, um, we should probably let them introduce themselves, I think.
Sure, go ahead.
Uh, Wesley, uh, Wesley Lone, could you please introduce yourselves for our guests?
While I figure out where the heck I'm going.
I'm Wesley Martin, art director on Outer Wilds.
And I'm Lone Verneau, designer and producer on Outer Wilds.
Nice. Thank you guys so much for joining us today. Why don't you, I think, you know, most people who
are watching probably know the story, but just in case, can you talk a bit about where the idea
for this game came from and sort of how it came to fruition? Sure, yeah. Outer Wilds was started
over eight years ago now as a student project at USC
and as a thesis project at USC.
And there were a couple of starting goals with it.
One of them was to create a world
that changes over time drastically,
like environments that, as you explore them,
they change in great ways,
like Thorough Hollow, for example,
which is a planet that falls apart
over the course of the game loop.
as it's being bombarded by its volcanic moon.
And then the other goal was to create a game about exploration and like the real, the actual
feeling of real space exploration.
So you know, not going out there and shooting aliens and trading, but the feeling of trying
to understand what's out there, trying to understand.
the laws of nature and how it all works
in a way where we are powerless to these massive galactic forces, right?
Oops, I think you're falling down into a black hole.
I am, I'm working on it.
No pressure Brian.
Good moment to highlight the powerlessness.
That was sort of like how the sort of our goals starting the game and hopefully we achieve some of these.
There's also sort of a third like smaller goal of creating a space exploration game that feels more like real space exploration.
Where you know with NASA you're going out there to discover things just because you're curious and not for gain.
And so that was like a huge.
part of designing the story and the mechanics of the game.
If you want to talk about that, I'd be curious to know more what that was like, but also I'm really curious to know, like, what's it like now that it's shipped and released and you've had it out for a few months?
Like, how's it going for you guys?
Like, did it, you know, like, how has it been?
Um, I guess if we do it chronologically.
Yeah, I can, I can briefly go over like the history of the project.
So, you know, it started as the student project was 2013.
Yeah.
And.
Alex and Loan kept working on it for a couple of years, and then IGF was 2015.
And right after that, in the summer of 2015, is when they decided to bring it to Mobius Digital,
which is where they both worked at the time. And that's when I got hired on, was like,
okay, we're turning this into a fully-fledged project. And so we hired up on our team and
kind of got going. We did a crowdfunding thing.
And that did not give us enough money to last for more than like a year.
And towards the end of that year we struck up a deal with Anapurna.
And they've been wonderful to us ever since.
But basically in the course of working with them we were like, you know,
we want to make like the true version of this game.
And so we scrapped a lot of our work at the time and kind of started fresh with the art direction.
And really aimed for like making it a...
a fully realized experience.
And so that's what we've been working on for the last four years.
And as you move towards ship, and then shipped it last year on Xbox, and I think on PC and
other platforms as well, how did that go for you?
I was meant to ask, how was the launch?
How was the run up to launch?
Was it what you expected?
Was it harder?
How did it go?
First of all, I'll give you a piece of advice.
If you press the jetpack up, there's a prompt telling you how to use the booster.
That will help you significantly in traveling around.
There we go, yeah.
That does help, yeah.
I'm just trying to figure out... I was trying to get somewhere, and now I'm just trying to figure out how to get there.
Anyway, continue. Please, focus on the questions. My terrible gameplay will resolve itself.
It's that.
Yeah, I mean, it was definitely a bit of a challenge to bring it to more platforms.
And we're definitely still working on that right now.
But yeah, I mean, it was a lot of work from both the art team and the tech team.
And as I mentioned, we're still working on that side of things.
Because Outer Wilds is such an experimental game, it was never really intended to be brought
to this level of polish.
So when we made that decision, like, yeah, we're going to polish this game and make it
like fully presentable and fully realized, there were a lot of things that just weren't
in the game, like streaming assets or, you know, just like when you say functionality
that you would expect, because we hadn't needed it up until that point.
There was a lot of back-loaded work where it's like, okay, we need to go in and fix all the bones underneath everything in order for all of it to layer on top correctly.
It's a pretty big process for our team and the tech team to go and optimize everything properly and get it into tip-top shape.
Yeah, go ahead, sorry.
Oh, and we faced so many issues that most games don't face just because of the nature of the game being...
a full-fledged physics simulation where whether you're there or not things still happen.
The destruction of Brunel Hollow that you can observe in real time if you're on the
planet still happens if you're not there.
If you leave your ship somewhere it might get tossed up by a tornado or destroyed by
a meteor.
Everything is always simulated and as a result.
Plus everything is built on spheres, which means creating new tools for that.
It was a lot of challenges that increased in complexity as we increased the quality of the visuals and the amount of content.
Yeah, I can only imagine. Real quick, we should have said at the top of the stream, and as folks filter in and out,
We will absolutely take your questions from chat.
If you have any questions regarding game design and a specific game in general,
please put them in chat and we will harvest the good ones and relay them.
Most of them are good, too.
Yeah, because this game is good also.
And I bring that up because this game is sort of is unique and maybe not unique,
but like it's very rare in the fact that most of the game's discoveries
are sort of tied to play.
So, you know, it's not that I think we're going to get in
any kind of spoiler territory here, but like.
The meat of playing this game is the discovery of how everything works, at least in my experience.
So, you know, when we talk about things like Brittle Hollow being destroyed,
you know, that's because the whole place gets blown up in 22 minutes also.
So we should actually, let's talk about that real quick. No, let's talk, let's stay on this.
Because I want to talk about the art direction and how you sort of came in,
especially you Wes. Like, you know, one of the most remarkable things about this game in my experience
is the way it models real scientific principles like physics and gravity and that kind of thing.
And also phenomena like black holes and white holes.
And I'm just curious, as you were revamping this game's look and coming at it with a bunch of new
tech and art, what, if anything, did you take from real science to try and figure out how to
make these look realistic and striking in the way that they are?
Yeah, that's a good question. It's a lot of complicated things interacting,
but I'll try and sum it up as quickly as possible.
Early on we made the decision that like sort of one of the core things that makes Outer Wilds feel like Outer Wilds is that it doesn't lie to the player.
And you know, that's a relative term because all video games have to lie on some level.
But like, for example, we don't arbitrarily limit where you can go.
There aren't like invisible barriers or things like that.
It's like if you can see it, you can go there.
And so that was sort of like.
Something that I think made the alpha really special and we didn't want to lose that.
We wanted to make sure that everything in the game felt correct.
Even if it's not actually correct, it needs to feel correct to the player.
It needs to respond in the way you'd expect it to.
You need to be able to test your hypotheses because it's a game about doing science.
And so if it lied to you, then that prevents you from being able to test things and kind of ruins the whole experience.
So that led us to do things like, you know, we tried more...
complex visual styles with higher detail, but then players would either get distracted or we couldn't have accurate collisions
so people couldn't climb on things and it just kind of cheapened the whole feel of everything.
So a lot of the art direction for Outer Wilds was choosing where to use our detail and
simplifying everything else so that it focuses players on the things that need to be active.
Right. What's an example of somewhere where you chose to really put a lot of detail?
I'm the village we're right now is actually a very good example.
It's one of the more dense areas in the game in terms of there's a lot of
characters to interact with and a lot of things to learn there.
And so players would just spend hours at the beginning of game of the village,
not even realize it's a space exploration game and you know,
give up cause they didn't understand what's going on.
And so we had to carefully tune things like the lighting in the village that
like lights are near points of interest. Um, we had to remove excess details.
Thank you.
Ignore me, I goofed.
You're doing great.
Don't worry.
We had some mini-games and things like that that we had to cut because players were just
getting distracted from the important thing, which is learning about space, getting curious
about space, and getting launch codes.
And so we had to cut away everything.
And that's also one of the reasons why the game doesn't have enemies that you fight,
or things that you collect, is because all of that extra stuff distracts people from
exploring for the sake of knowledge.
Oh, that's interesting. Did the team ever consider putting in collectibles or combat or anything like that?
No, that was very early a decision we made.
Because the goal was, on the design side, definitely to create a game where players were driven by curiosity alone.
And so the best way to prove that hypothesis was by removing every other possible rewards.
Right?
upgrades if you have, like, collectibles, if you have any of that, players might be
exploring for the sake of finding these.
So we, from pretty early in the development process, we decided that the only reward you
would ever get in the game is knowledge.
The only thing, there's no upgrades, there's no tools, new tools you get to unlock or whatever,
the only thing you gain is knowledge.
And sort of our base for the game.
This whole game feels finely tuned in a way that I kind of struggle to comprehend.
From the macro scale of the 22 minute loop, to the way that different planets have different
gravity scales and different movement speeds.
And actually like, as you play this game and play the loop over and over, you start to
realize that at certain points in time, certain things will happen.
And you need to be there to see it or to do something about it.
And all of that I imagine must have been like...
At least haphazardly planned and timed out, if not carefully tuned.
So like, what was that like?
Can you tell me what your guiding principle was in trying to sort of nail down
something like a 22 minute time loop and how you,
what challenges you faced in trying to get that just right?
Um, play tests.
Yeah. Lots and lots of play testing.
Uh, we play tested like once every two, three weeks,
let's say three weeks to be safe counting vacation.
We play this once every three weeks for.
You know, three years.
Basically as soon as we started at Mobius, there were regular playtests testing,
you know, whatever we had just been working on, as well as like,
longer stretches of the game for new players.
Hmm.
Oh!
Don't forget your spacesuit.
Yeah. Is it not on by default?
Is it not on by default?
I did this yesterday, yup.
I was like, I would never forget to put that on, and then I immediately did.
We are learning so much today.
I guess that's a spring brotha! Let's let the organicness of the moment play into that.
I think of a lot of games that look at that moment and go,
Oh no! Like, we can't let the player do that.
Instead, you guys seem to have gone,
Hell yeah, the player should be able to do that every time.
They should be able to walk outside the space on every run.
They should be able to die right when they get into space.
You already mentioned that that was a decision pretty early on to reward curiosity and learning,
and you know the player should at some point get stopped being a knucklehead and figure out
they need to put on their space suit. But um, uh, what other decisions did you need to make to
uh, complete that vision and make sure it wasn't just like a weird hog horse I guess that that
would that would that would only akin sometimes? I think for a lot of that fine-tuning it's just
we as developers are
and they were kind of obsessive about it.
Like, sort of made sure that everyone who joined the team
was just as detail-oriented and believed in the vision of the game just as much.
So, you know, everyone from the Creative Director all the way down to just junior artists who were hired for a brief time,
they were still on board with like,
yeah we're going to make sure that this piece of art or this bit of level design or this
lighting and the way that it interacts with the area
None of that is going to trick the player into doing the wrong thing, we're never going to fake anything.
And so it was just, really just a lot of hard work and dedication to that principle of
we need to make sure that players are playing this for the right reasons.
Right on. I guess we can give a quick shout out to Auditory who said they finished the game a couple days ago and they love it so much.
Awesome, thanks.
Alex, I will throw the question all back to you now that I'm done dying in dumb ways.
No I'm not.
Have you?
No.
Incorrect. Incorrect.
Oh man, I just like this game so much. I could just talk about any one of these planets for an hour.
I also, have you guys played The Outer Worlds at all?
We did ask that too, for the record. If they played that game.
I haven't had the chance. It's been pretty busy.
Yeah. So is that, I'm just curious, like, it doesn't...
Sometimes it can be hard to tell from the outside whether funny goofs like that, when
two notable games share a great name or a great launch window, whether that actually
gets on anyone's mind or whether it affects business at all.
Did coming out so close to that game and sharing such a close title have any impact at all
on your launch strategy or was it just kind of like a funny goof?
I think we were definitely aware of it.
We've had the name Agarwiles for a very long time.
I think we saw when they registered the domain name, we're like, huh,
hope that's just one of those that they don't actually use.
And when they announced it, we're like, okay.
And so that was something we were aware of, but ultimately like the games are of
such different like scales and such different target audiences that from our
perspective, it was like probably just better for both games because the
distinction and like the.
controversy around the naming, you know, just got a lot of press for both of us.
And so I think it ended up being just kind of like this funny thing that was
good overall for exposure for both games. And we probably benefited more because we're a
smaller studio and, you know, we're not already known, but I think it was definitely helpful for both.
Yeah, I hope so. We got a good question here in chat from Luzu who wants to know,
during those playtests, was there any specific things mentioned that helped you a lot?
Or on the flip side, was there anything that came up during playtesting that you ignored?
Also, thank you so much for one of their favorite games ever.
So yeah, playtest, interesting feedback that shaped the course of the game or
pushback that you chose ultimately not to go against because it sort of
conflicted with the vision?
That's a good question. I think generally that the main thing about
playtests, we're not like a
like a number, statistic, you know, we don't use playtests.
like in a statistic way of like, how many person players reaches A and does C and whatever.
It is more on a qualitative side of things.
And as a result, I think all feedback is useful, though it's not to be necessarily interpreted
literally.
Like, you know, a player might find an area too difficult or might find a mechanic confusing.
But the way they'll express that might be, you know, might not be in such a manner.
So it's a lot of interpretation.
So I don't know if there's anything we ignored per se as much as like, you know,
sometimes people complain about something and we're like,
but actually the problem is here.
Right.
Making them feel, you know, but yeah, I mean, tons of things.
One real quick example, just because you're here at the moment.
A lot of playtest changes were just simply like adding more lights to things.
Like players weren't finding the escape pod, which is supposed to be one of the key entry
points for each planet that has an escape pod.
And so like, yeah, just adding that big glowing border around the door, all of a sudden players
see it and they go through it.
And a lot of times it's just as simple as that.
It's like, hey, this person played for two hours and they didn't find anything that's
supposed to be obvious.
How can we make it more obvious without like beating people over the head?
One of the playtests things that really impacted the game a lot and that was a lot of fun for
us was when players figured out solutions to puzzles that we hadn't thought of.
There is, for example, a place in the game where you're supposed to time things.
in a certain way to activate something.
I can't spoil it too much.
But then a player tried to use their ship to sort of like protect them from what was
affecting them.
And we were like, oh, this is a really clever idea.
We should implement it so that that works.
And so a lot of times, players came up with really clever solutions.
And we decided to make sure that these solutions
would be like sometimes these solutions worked already but we're a bit janky so we're like okay
how can we make it you know more consistent so they don't feel like it's weird and you know
so that was really great the fact that there's now multiple solutions to a lot of the puzzles
because we saw players do that try things and we implemented it.
Oh I'm so glad to hear that because I think
You know, one of the striking parts of this game, I was telling Brian earlier this week,
is that it sets up, because of the way it allows for emergent gameplay,
it, you know, all the systems interact and such,
it sets up opportunities for, like, emergent stories to emerge that mirror, like,
you know, Gravity or Contact or Apollo 13 or something,
where you're just trying to figure out how to get your spaceship back in the air or something.
Like, I had a situation a night or two ago that was very similar, where I had to...
You know, there was a thing coming that I had to avoid.
And I basically it was like a timed event and I used the ship to survive it.
And I think that's like a really striking part of this game.
Was that it's so crazy to me that that came out of the playtest
because it seems so core and integral to the to the concept of the game.
But, you know, I'm impressed to hear that.
Yeah, I just here's a I'm sorry, Brian,
are you going to go back in that black hole again?
Oh no.
Something's happening.
Virtual Hollow's actually a good example of a place where there's a lot of weird ways
to solve problems because if you're really good at using orbital mechanics, you can use
the black hole to slingshot yourself to all kinds of places that you're supposed to get
to in less crazy ways.
So that fun testing in the game is like, hey, I wonder if I can get there with a well-timed
slingshot.
We always enjoy seeing speedrunners figure out weird ways they can use the physics of the game to work it out.
Yeah, it's really remarkable there aren't more like, and I imagine because it's so difficult, but there aren't more games about playing with gravity and slingshotting around in space.
Gravity just, uh...
Yeah, there you go. A classic for sure.
So what I meant to get on there before I got distracted by Brian's fantastic journey is we were talking this week also that this game has so many opportunities.
for storytelling and it also has a real character and atmosphere to it that is warm and convivial
and almost melancholy and very little of that comes out of the game design or out of the
actual planets.
It comes so much out of the music and the bits of writing and the bits of art design.
And so I'm curious to know, can you speak to the process through which you try to enrich
this basically orrery with character and mood and atmosphere?
How did you create?
those feelings and emotions in a game about space?
It's a really good question. I think there's a lot of different factors that went into it.
I think from an art point of view, we knew pretty early on that that was sort of the tone we were
going for. Because it was already there even back in the alpha version of the game, is that sort of
camping in space vibe. Where it's sort of like the end of summer and you're sitting by a campfire and
So that sort of wistful, like, this is all coming to an end, but it was a good run.
And, you know, feeling like you're, you're in this friendly outdoor setting, that's all about exploring and,
you know, enjoying what you have while you have it.
And I think that was, that was there very early. And
as we were revamping the art style, we tried all kinds of things, you know, making the alien stuff more alien or
You know, changing the scale of things to make it more epic or exciting.
And really in the end, we kind of had to dial all that back because it ruined that
feeling of camping in space.
And so in the end it was like, all right, what kinds of things do you find at a
camp? What kinds of things do you see in a national park?
And we referenced a lot of like the old national park ad posters like the 60s,
which is also when NASA was really big.
So it's like fits really well with the NASA aesthetic.
And.
So a lot of it was just making the decision to make the art less exciting visually in
order to make it feel more comfortable and familiar, which sort of enhances the alien
feeling in the end because of that contrast.
But it's sort of counterintuitive and it took us a while to figure that out.
Oh yeah, I'm embarrassed to admit I didn't pick up on it earlier.
There is a real, like, this is camp, down to like the makeshift uniforms and the patch
together stuff and everyone's just kind of...
Taking it easy. Casey Yano here in chat with a shout out.
They're a big fan of that 3D boosty HUD thing.
That UI is great.
Any was that tricky to design and implement to give people a sense of how
they're flying through space? I imagine it must have been hard.
Oh, yeah. Yeah, we tried a lot of different iterations for that.
And I'm glad that one works because that one was one of my little additions
to the game. It used to be like a thing that spun more.
And I was like, what if it was just like a 3D?
Like every axis was represented and you could see in that direction.
And we tested it out and we're like, Oh yeah,
people get it now when they're flying up or down. Um, so glad you noticed.
Nice. Uh, yeah, it's fantastic. I,
something I've been wanting to get onto and maybe this was a good time to is
sort of the, the business of how you get the word out about this. I mean,
it seems like having the, uh, uh,
the buzz around the IGF and then now the GDCA, uh, must've helped. But like,
how did you get?
How did you get this game in front of people who you thought would like it?
Like did you, was it a lot of marketing? Was it someone else's thing? Or did you guys do a lot of
social media and stuff? Like how did you find the audience for this?
We were lucky enough that we had a really committed group of fans from the alpha.
It was a really amazing community to have
that was absurdly supportive. It was great to have them as sort of
ambassadors for the game.
So I think
we had that massive advantage from the start.
And then
Annapurna of course
like the fact
coming as an Annapurna game
you know, immediately gives a certain
respectability in the scene and so I think
a lot of people just...
These two audiences sort of helped.
It's players from players, you know, Max Thurier.
That made it happen.
I think it's also...
Anand Purna made a lot of really smart decisions,
and I think one of the best things for us was being on Game Pass at launch.
No one's heard about the game and it's the kind of game that you really have to dive into blind to experience at best.
Game Pass was really good for getting that initial wave of people who would advocate for us.
And, you know, those people are all spreading the word to others, which is wonderful.
But that initial, like, people giving it a shot, I think, was largely due to Game Pass.
So, that was...
I just had a wow moment. This is Valhalla. It's Fallen Partner in front of me.
Yep. Yep.
It's here now.
It's good, right?
Yeah.
Well, every hour of this game is like that.
You're like, oh, oh, it's so good.
I'm about to find a tree and refill my oxygen even though I have no fuel and the moon's
going and some of the crash into the sun.
Yeah, man, godspeed.
Listen, so yeah, you talked about Game Pass being big.
I'm curious.
Do you think this game would have done as well if it hadn't had access to a subscription service like Game Pass?
If you just put it out as a straight up pay to download title, do you think it would have done as well?
It's hard to say. I think that it's possible it would have done as well eventually,
but Game Pass definitely sped up the reception a lot.
It's the game that has to...
spread by people talking about it and Game Pass is a way to get a bunch of people talking about it really fast.
So it could have happened by streamer. It could have happened by chance.
But Game Pass was sort of a way to ensure that it would happen more quickly.
Nice. Yeah, I ask because like
at the office we talk about, in the industry, we talk about like how subscription services and sort of Game Pass-esque
offerings are going to change the way people play games and find games.
I'm always on the edge between whether it's a wonderful thing to have access to those services,
because people can discover things without a lot of barrier to entry.
They can just dip in and check it out and at the same time it feels like maybe it might,
in the long term, devalue the value of a game if you can just get $200 for a monthly subscription.
How do you guys think about it as this happens right in front of us?
I mean, there is something to say about, in particular for a game like Attawalsa,
it's very experimental.
And that's best played not knowing about it.
Like, Game Pass is just perfect, you know.
And subscription services are very useful.
I think there's definitely an interesting...
I think it's going to push a certain amount of innovation and experimentation.
Because if you have access to that many games...
Maybe you don't want each of them to be just a slight twist on a previous game.
Like you might be more interested in shorter experiences. You might be more interested in
things that you might not have tried before because you weren't sure you were going to enjoy
them. So I think it's going to open very interesting avenues for games and in particular maybe also
hopefully meaning that we have less of a
monopoly on, you know, selling games on different platforms.
Yeah, that'd be great.
You keep calling this an experimental game, and I totally agree.
Like, so much of what you've tried here in the systems and the way they interact
is very experimental, and it's like a wonder in some ways that it all works so well as it does.
But at the same time, it just feels strange to hear you talk about this game that way,
because it's a game about exploring space, and that seems like a fundamental...
category of what interactive entertainment could be.
And yet when I think about space exploration games or games that remind me of this game,
the one that comes to my mind is like Lunar Lander, which was decades ago.
So I mean, it's hard to argue with you. There aren't a lot of games like this.
There aren't a lot of games that try this blend of exploration and that kind of thing.
So like, why do you think that is? And beyond that, like,
do you think you'll continue to try and make games like this going forward?
I think.
A quick aside, it's also worth noting that when the project started in 2013, that was
before things like Elite Dangerous and No Man's Sky and all of these new space games.
It's kind of been a resurgence that we're now a part of, but when the project was conceived
there had been no space games for a long time.
Yeah.
And also, at the time, games were a lot more hand-holdy.
The project started when Zelda Skyward Sword just came out.
And so I think that shows where the industry was at and where the most games gravitated towards a very hand-holdy, linear approach to things.
And it's really exciting, the latest Zelda being proof that I think the...
While we worked on Outer Wilds, a lot of other people also gravitated towards more open exploration
and more trusting the player.
And I think that's a big thing that games such as Dark Souls have brought to the scene.
It's this idea that as designers we can trust the players not to be, you know, we don't
have to tell them what to do at every step of the way.
We can just present them with fun environments and great mechanics, and they'll experiment
and try and they can figure it out on their own with this great UI and a lot of playtests
to make sure it is understandable.
Um, man, uh, I was talking to, um, Hugo Mar- Hugo Martin of id Software, kind of about the same thing.
Um, uh, he was talking about how, about, you know, again, fighting that instinct to just make
everything easy. And he, he outright said, you know, there was a trend where games couldn't be
hard, which is, was his words. Um, uh, man, this place is weird. This place is weird. I'm
uncomfortable. I'm going away. You should go in there. Please go in there. No. Please,
please go on Dark Bramble, please.
Fine.
It's for the stream.
This is fine.
All right.
Let me push it.
Um, anyway.
Yeah.
Uh, yeah, this is interesting just cause I've heard triple
E devs talking about the same thing.
A different way.
And it's interesting that like the dark souls lesson was kind of that.
All right.
I'm in.
Yeah.
Uh huh.
The dark souls lesson was.
Good.
Good luck in there.
Yeah, I think it is certainly interesting to see this, to see what feels like a renewed
and reinvigorated wave of teams, you know, studios and developers trusting players and
not sort of handholding them through the game.
I wonder, I wonder if we'll ever go back around the other way, you know, like, will there
be a backlash where suddenly there's a huge emphasis on intuitive tutorial design or streamlined
tutorial design or what have you.
Wow, Brian, you nailed it. Good work.
But for now, what I kind of wanted to get at was,
do you feel rewarded by pursuing this philosophy of game design?
And are you excited to continue doing it?
Are you still interested in making games that are about exploration
and not holding the player's hand about discovery?
Or are you excited to work on something that is maybe a little less experimental?
I think it's a little bit of both.
We're all kind of...
Outer Wilds was a very difficult game to make.
We often joke that it's exactly the type of game you should not make.
Like, our advice to people is don't make Outer Wilds.
It's really just not a good idea.
Okay.
It's just...
There's a lot of tools in game development that are built around assumptions.
Like the assumption that you're going to make things flat.
Because that's what you do.
You're going to have a flat plane, and you're going to build everything on that flat plane.
And when you're building these spherical planetoids, there just aren't tools to do that.
And so you've got to do it yourself.
And it's a lot of little things like that.
Like, game engines are built around static objects that don't move.
And anything that interacts with physics is marked as not static.
Because it's different and needs to behave differently.
Everything in Outer Wilds is not static.
So we couldn't rely on a lot of things that static objects can do and
optimizations that apply to static objects because nothing is static.
Lighting?
Lighting.
Yeah.
We, you know, lighting is all based on like either lights are everywhere or
lights are localized, but we wanted lights to be spherical and that's, you
know, not really how they're built.
Um, and so a lot of the game was just like, okay.
We need to do this thing that every game does because that's what you do in games, but we
can't do it because the game engine or the 3D modeling software just doesn't support
spheres or movement on a fundamental level.
So that's, at least from an asset creation, from an art side of view, that was the biggest
hurdle that we had to overcome, is that the tools are not there and we had to make a lot
of our own tools to do it.
This is a silly question, I guess, but did you make those tools available to anybody else?
They sound useful.
Or is it all internal?
It's all internal.
We've talked about maybe trying to package them to make them accessible to more people.
But you know, like any internal tools, there's a lot of shortcuts that you use.
And we're like, that would be a lot of work.
We haven't done there.
If a lot of people ask, honestly, that is something we would happily try to take the
time to do.
I would love to see more spheres in video games.
Spheres are the best.
Brian, get in there.
Don't be chicken.
Get in there.
I'm trying to get to the thing.
I'm orbiting it.
Well, just fly inside the planet.
It's good.
It's a good look.
I'm backseat flying.
Come on, let's go.
I call content here.
I'm backseat flying.
Come on, let's go.
I call content here.
I'm backseat flying.
Come on, let's go.
Well, then I hope you find something that is a little less strenuous to work on for your
next project.
I just love this little navigator thing down in the lower left hand corner for this ship.
Oh, you know what's great?
That whole UI is great, we should talk about that, but also, unbuckle and look down to
your bottom right to find the eject button.
Because you're going to want that eject button at some point.
Is there an eject button?
It's on the console. It's on the console. There's like a little thing you flip up.
No, it's to the left. This is good. This is good content.
Anyway, there's an eject button on the console.
Tell me about that eject button. Who put that in there and why?
I'll take partial credit for that.
Please. I spent a lot of time working on the ship,
and one of the big goals for the ship was to make it
feel like it's sort of twofold.
It's both the player's home.
You want the player to feel like it's a safe space
and that they can.
you know, like have a lot of useful things there.
So it's not just jump out of it and be on your way. Um,
but we also wanted the ship to interact with all the systems in the game.
And so at some point we were like, Hey,
we should make it so the ship can like break apart. So if you slam, you know,
one of the sides of the ship, it can actually get pulled off and you know,
your ship can damage and you end up with those cool Apollo 13 moments where it's
like you're spiraling out of control. And so.
We took a lot of effort to like go back and make the ship modular so that we could break it apart and you know,
have it actually systems can break individually and all of that. Uh,
and while we were doing that, we were like, Hey,
we've just made it so the cockpit can just like pop off the front of the ship.
Why don't we just put a button in that does that just for fun?
Pressing it too much. So we kind of had to hide it a little bit. So it wasn't.
Yes, but.
Sorry. I'm not obsessed with this object.
See what else. See.
This whole planet is so good.
Yeah, and also like, I love the eject button. I'm so glad you put it in.
These little light up indicators on the HUD, these like very analog thrust indicators,
were those also yours or were those a result of playtesting?
Because I can't remember if those were in the original build or not.
No, the original, the Alpha ship was pretty barebones.
Yeah.
I think a lot of us on the team are a big fan of...
um, diegetic UI stuff that's like built into the game itself and not just on screen.
Um, so that's why like a lot of the HUD elements only appear when you put on your helmet,
just because it's actually like a thing in-world that's being projected.
Um, we make an exception for button prompts just because people need to learn how to play the game
and it doesn't make sense for that to be in-world.
But yeah, we, we, we took the, we went the extra mile to make all of the ship
and all the player tools communicate information physically.
instead of just something popping up on the screen because it makes you feel like an astronaut.
You feel like interacting with these instruments and you feel like
you're a part of the world and you know that's the same reason why we put your body in the game
so when you look down you see your feet is to make you feel like you're there which heightens
the sense of space. Did you learn anything fun about physics or space exploration while
you're making this video game? Oh god.
Seems like a fun project to work on if you're really into NASA.
Oh yeah.
Our technical artist Logan programmed all the shaders.
And so things like the atmospheres around planets, that's a shader that Logan wrote.
And a lot of research went into like how do atmospheres work, actually.
Because in order to get it to look right, it has to pretty much just receive light in the same way.
A lot of times during the project we would take a dive into something like that.
It's just like, alright, for the black hole in Brittle Hollow, that's just actual black
hole math.
Yeah.
That's so exciting to me.
Maybe it's childish, but there just aren't a lot of opportunities to put your face inside
a universe and see what a black hole does.
And this is one of them.
And I'm so glad to hear you guys put some work and research into actually making that
look what it might actually look like.
Ugh.
Um.
Boy, what was I about to ask?
Uh.
Brian, you distracted me with this beautiful planet.
Shucks.
Well, anyway, we're coming to the end of our hour.
We got about 15 minutes left.
Folks in chat, if you have any questions, uh, about this game or about its
development or about what their devs are going to be up to now, please put them in
chat and we will be very happy to relay them.
Uh, Brian, you're doing great.
Do you have any pressing questions?
No.
This is one of those games where all my questions get thrown out by the concentration it takes to play it.
Where did that island even go?
I'm really not sure.
It's just something. We're on giant's teeth.
Yeah?
Yeah.
We're running this tornado. This is what's happening.
You're killing it. You're doing great.
What could go wrong?
How are you guys feeling about all these, uh, all the awards and coverage and stuff? Do you feel like that was, uh, worth the time?
We should probably mention the awards they're nominated for, man.
Right. Well, see, I was-
I left them in the back. Can you grab that?
Uh, yeah, I would be happy to. So, after, uh, winning the IGF a few years ago,
uh, now I believe you're up for Game of the Year at, uh, Game Developers Choice Awards.
The Best Debut, Best Divine, uh, Best Design, Innovation, and the Narrative Award. That's-
That's a good slew of honors.
How are you feeling about all this awards coverage and what it has done for the game?
Has it been just an alloyed good?
Has it been worth the effort of investing in that kind of coverage?
Or has it been in any way interesting?
I mean, it's always really awesome to be considered for that sort of awards.
It's been the reception.
both critically and player-wise has been wonderful.
Personally, I mean, it's a huge honor to receive awards.
I think some of the fan letters we've been receiving have been
just heartbreakingly wonderful.
And that would be personally my greatest reward,
is hearing about parents playing with their kids and
their kids wanting to
learn about science or become an astronaut.
And that sort of thing has been incredible.
Yeah, that's fantastic. I'm so glad to hear it.
Do you have any strong concerns at this point about supporting
this game? I mean you're talking about porting it, it sounds like it's still a
lot of work as you continue to work on it, but like
in terms of support, is it just patching and bug fixing now or do you have
anything else you want to do with Outer Wilds as a...
We've actually made some significant changes post-launch.
Maybe more changes than we should have.
Oh, how come? Tell me about it.
We've tweaked the level design in several areas to try and help players
figure out some of the in-game solutions to things because
we just didn't have enough playtest data.
And once everyone's playing it, you get more data.
Added some fun little features like...
The ability to doze off at campfires to pass time a little bit more quickly,
which is that we always wanted to do, but we didn't have time to release.
So just we're still fiddling with it a bit.
It's definitely it's hard to put down.
Nice. I know this is not necessarily the first game for all of you.
I'm sure you have a variety of experience on your belt.
But this being having its origins as a student project
and now hitting this so much far later, it feels like there must be
Some like well-deserved like honor and like pride, but also like is there any, is it,
are you stressed at all about making your next game after this?
It seems to have done very well.
It's certainly being well-received by folks like us.
And now you guys are going to have to move on to something else.
Is there any like weight about a sophomore slump or any concern about what you're going
to do next or is it just all good vibes and optimism?
It's definitely a bit scary moving forward, yeah?
Yeah.
It's a hard thing to follow up.
So, I think we're all...
It's a little bit of both, right?
Because the positive response to the game means that we found an audience that wants
this type of thing, which is the type of thing that we want to make, generally speaking.
So that's super exciting to see, that there is an audience for a weird game like Outer
Gardens.
But it's also like...
Outer Wilds was a seven-year project, and a lot of blood, sweat, and tears went into making it.
And it's very daunting to think of going through that process again and taking a big risk.
Yeah, I can only imagine.
Uh, well, we are, uh, oh, actually.
Brian, you were looking at that writing a minute ago. We should talk about this writing. It's great.
It's the whole conception of an alien thing in this because everything in here is really smart.
I think it's a smart way to think about alien life.
Right, so let's start with the writing and go from there.
Can you guys speak to what influenced the design process for this kind of like totally,
to me at least, being very uneducated and American, like relatively novel way of writing
and flowing sort of curly Q scripts?
Where did that come from, if you know?
So we worked very closely with our writer, Kelsey Higginbotham, with all the writing
in the game.
One of the prompts we had was the idea of making text something you would explore,
the same way you explore everything else in the game.
So we wanted to make it spatial, we wanted to make it explorable.
And Kelsey had the idea of using her own way of taking notes.
this branching kind of like forum style.
Oh, interesting.
Instead of like this linear writing, it's more of a like, you know, it's a branching forum of conversations.
That was, yeah, I think she was mentioning it was kind of influenced by our own way of taking notes.
And so we took that and then we played with the visuals.
And I think we looked at a lot of different influences and we ended up picking Spirals as the best way to do that.
But yeah, Chelsea has done an amazing job creating the writing and building so much characters into these stories, right?
Because none of the writing is just backstory.
All of the writing is usable.
useful information that you can actively use in-game.
It's really important for us to do that.
And we learned that as we developed the game.
But like, there's such a...
Players are so used to see writing as lore, as you know, bonus thing that you just read
if you want to, when you have the time.
And so like, we had to sort of teach that to players and, you know, make sure they understood
that like, no, everything you read...
has actual, like, you can use it.
It actually talks about something in the world
and you can use that.
But as a result, you know,
we could have made the writing very dry.
And so we were really happy
because it was able to put in so much like character
and humor and drama and romance into that writing.
That is about, you know, telling you dry facts about the world.
Yeah, no, absolutely.
I think Brian can attest I can I can sometimes be a harsh critic of writing
and video games, and I think like the writing in this game is
is really affecting for how sparse it is.
You know, it is so much just like info on the walls,
environmental storytelling, yet nevertheless, whoever, you know,
the writer was able to like really bring a sense of character and like pathos
to these.
uh... wall scribbles so like i think that's great
you guys make the uh... and i don't understand why no other game developer has
has uh... not
A for this goal is you guys take the ancient civilization trope and manage to
Flip it on its head and instead of all the writing either feeling like it's coming from
Scientists or I don't know at best scientists if it feels like if ancient writing feels like it's come from inside a world
It'll be scientists or something or people who would be leading logs
Or it's it's it presents as unsellable
intelligible gibberish
reinterpreted by the character that you're piloting
It's uh... here, it's people.
Just feels like people.
It feels like notes that could've been left five minutes ago.
Um, and the translation mechanic doesn't get in the way of that.
And...
I like that a lot!
It makes me want to learn more about these people instead of...
I hate to say it, uh, two of my favorite game series, AAA game series, both that both relied on ancient alien metaphors.
Got more and less and less interesting the more I learned about them because everything felt very sterile and...
And less... less... less suitable.
Um, I will start wrapping things up today.
Uh, I'm... I'm a little tired.
My ship...
is gone.
Error.
You're doing great.
I don't think it's March 8th.
You want to suppose that?
March 18th.
18th.
Yeah.
It's March 18th.
I'm tired.
Um.
We're...
We're worse.
This country is tired.
Um.
Yeah.
So if you want to attend in person, if you have a GDC pass, everyone can attend.
If you want to watch online, in the comfort of your home, uh, you can do that too.
Just stay tuned to this Twitch channel.
Um.
And...
Oh, that's why you hit the follow button.
Um.
Other than that, that's all I've got for today.
Thank you to Bone and Wesley for joining us, and if they have more questions about the making of this game, where should they ask them?
Support, support at Mobius Digital Games.
I'm still waiting for a developer to just go, don't.
We have a small team, so we do see your emails.
Yeah.
And we also, we don't participate a lot in it, but we...
Check the subreddit as well.
The Adderall subreddit.