Hello, my name is Julian Quijano and this is Fandom Ready.
First of all, before starting, I need to point out,
as you may have realized by now, that English is not
my first language, so expect some mistakes.
I hope you can excuse me.
If you have any question, feel free to ask it in the chat.
I'm the creative director at Beautiful Glitch.
We're an indie studio in San Ivercelona, in Spain.
You can follow us in Instagram and Twitter.
There's a handle in there.
And we are the creators of Monster Prom.
Monster Prom is a multiplayer narrative adventure
with latency mechanics and party game mechanics.
And it's more than a game.
It's a franchise.
As we have a content DLC called Second Term
and a sequel we recently released called Monster Camp.
And we are planning more sequels to go.
But today we are talking more than just video games.
We are talking about fandom.
So we want to show your fandom, which is wonderful.
you can see here. And not only that, we want to show you some numbers that we believe are tied
to having a fandom. Because often we hear that it's better to have a fan than just a consumer.
And we agree. But we also think it's important for the purpose of this talk to show some numbers
that we believe are tied in some ways to having fans.
and not just an audience.
Stuff like a very high conversion rate on our products
that goes to show the loyalty of our fans to the fiction.
High average in Kickstarter campaigns
as goes to show that people is very willing
to pay more than just the price of the game
because they are very invested in the game.
And even social media, where we have more than 50,000 followers both on Twitter and
Instagram, having more than 1 million likes in Instagram in 2019.
And this is not to unharm, it's for two reasons that I'm showing you this.
For once...
Sorry.
It's just in case that you don't know Mozart Brum or Beautiful Glitch, I think it's important to
show you our credentials because you are here listening to a talk we are giving about fandoms
and whatnot and so I think some of these numbers and these pictures goes to show that indeed we
have a fiction ourself that has grown its own wonderful big fandom and also it goes to show
the value of it.
since we are spending now half an hour on what effectively is a series of tricks and
advice on how to turn your fiction into fertile grounds for a fandom to grow.
Because this is what this talk is about.
What over the years, thanks to Monster Prom and observation and our and other fandoms.
insights we have come up with on how we believe that, aside of, of course, crafting a great
product, you can do to, let's say, increase the chances for a fandom to grow around the
creation you are working in. So, before going into the specific insights, I want to talk a bit
about, oh, sorry.
Here, I want to talk a bit about the process
of becoming a fan.
I'm sure a lot of us are fans of different fandoms.
And so I want you to think on the process
because it will be useful in here later.
So we start as strangers, strangers in the sense
that we know nothing about the fiction.
Then we receive a first impact, right? Someone talks to us about the fiction or we see something
in somewhere and then we go into mere consumption. We read a book, play a game, watch the episode of
a TV show and maybe we have some interest after that and we discuss it a bit with friends or even
leave a review.
Maybe then we decide to consume more of the main products,
like watching more episodes of the TV show,
playing more games of the franchise,
reading more books of the series.
And maybe our interest keeps growing.
So we are not just only discussing,
now we are defending the fiction.
Now we are even recommending it to other people.
And slowly you can see how
As a consumer, you are starting to have more and more value
for the creator because for once, you are, of course,
consuming more products, but you are also
even helping the creator in spreading the word
and getting more consumers.
And then we go into the deeper levels,
which I think what comes next depends
a lot on who you are as a fan.
And it goes to show that there's many ways of interacting
with a fan.
Maybe you go into full immersion and you observe all the information out there about the fiction,
like wikis and theories. Maybe you want to consume more products other than the main ones.
So you are now not only playing games on the franchise, but you, I don't know, you bought a
body pillow case. Maybe you go into socialization, meaning that you become an active participant
in social circles around the fandom and you meet new acquaintances and even friends.
Maybe you want to create.
And so depending what's the craft you like, you draw fan art, write fanfics, do cosplay,
make memes, craft theories, whatever speaks to you. Or maybe you do a number of things. It's
whatever suits you as a fan, again. And this is a process, again, I think we all know, but I think
it's interesting to now flip it and think how it goes for the creator. And for the
Benefit of this talk and to more easily convey the points and insights we have come up with,
I would establish three different parts with three different goals.
For once, as creators, we need to create an enticing first bite. Like this means
to make the shallow levels of your fiction
very accessible and appealing.
So a stranger will feel, you know,
enticed to that first interaction with your fiction.
Then you have the goal of achieving a smooth transition
from bite to binge.
This means that create the different levels and parts of your fiction in a way that, yeah,
you get that first bite, but then before you realize you get the second bite, the third bite,
and then suddenly you are in directly, sorry, you are actually binging. And then when you're
binging on the deep levels, I think there's also a goal, which is managing for people to binge from
their heart.
And what this means to us is that people that are on the deep levels are not just spending a lot of time and that's it with your fiction, but they're also starting to connect in deeper levels of values, identity, emotions, so they truly connect with your fiction.
Basically, all this builds on the idea, on the notion that right now most fictions,
and I recommend yours if you can make it so it goes this way, are actually multi-layered.
Multi-layered in the sense that there's many layers of consumption available
and are accessible for someone that wants to go in it casually and deep levels for
the person that wants to become a fan.
And I say, before checking specific tricks, that...
Sorry, one second.
It's good for a creator to ask oneself
if the creation has opportunities
for all of these multi-layer levels of consumption.
These mean many things.
Like, for instance, some questions
that you could ask yourself as a creator of a game.
Are you building not only a great game, but good spaces for debate, like a Discord server?
This is maybe dumb, but do you have at least one character that's very easy to cosplay,
so people that's maybe not very skilled in cosplay can still feel comfortable cosplaying
one character? Are you...
Karim, sorry, Karim for your community spaces.
So your fandom is an enjoyable place to find
and to meet new people that loves the same fiction than you.
Are you, the theme is open for Sonas
like Monster Prom has Monster Sonas.
Is the theme you have chosen open for this kind of content?
Do you have mysteries that will lead people into many theories?
And of course, you don't need to fish for all of this.
Each fiction is different.
But I think it's useful to spend some time reflecting on if you have opportunities for this.
Like, open your fiction to this type of multi-layer consumption.
But enough of that.
So, provided these three goals...
come up with a number of insights, advice, tricks
to manage, to achieve these three goals.
And we found like eight to 10.
But of course, because we have only 30 minutes today,
we will focus on one trick or one insight per level.
Let's start with the first one,
which is getting that first bite.
So, this is ways
to get a stranger to have a first interaction
with your fandom.
We found three potential ways of maximizing
the chances of this happening,
which are exploring theme trends,
offering a big first choice, a first big choice,
or having a high pitch.
And now we are focusing on the second one,
offering a first big choice.
So.
This idea is based on a market, all the marketing trick,
or at least that's how I learned about that
when I was studying advertising.
And, sorry, it's based on the idea of
when you're creating something
and you want to market it to an audience,
it's very important to frame the perception of that audience.
This is easier understood if we put an example.
Let's say that we are now trying to sell soda instead of making a game or creating whatever.
So you can ask people, do you want to drink soda? Yes or no? But the thing is, 50% of those
options are not of our interest. We don't want people choosing, I don't want to drink soda.
So the idea is to override that question and go into a different question, that first big choice,
that kind of throws people into already thinking in terms of drinking the soda.
For instance, it would be like, which soda speaks to you?
Sweet strawberry soda, exotic papaya soda,
or super cool blue flavor, whatever that is.
And you can see the idea is to override the drink soda,
yes, no, and get people just wondering,
okay, which one I would drink.
That this is not like a magic trick
that will everyone drinking soda, but it has an effect.
It's, let's say it,
helps you to make your audience, people,
to go past that first wall of disinterest
and actually check what this soda is about.
And this, which feels very specific
and soda-centric right now,
and then basically means
Sorry, it's basically present in many fictions too.
Like for instance, the thing on some popular ones
is like a Harry Potter, which instead of telling you,
do you like Harry Potter?
Yes or no.
Do you want to read it?
Sorry.
It directly says, in which house would you be?
Slytherin, Gryffindor, Ravenclaw or Hufflepuff.
And again, instead of thinking I am interested in Harry Potter, or even if you know you are not
interested, you feel a bit enticed to check which one is yours. Right? Or even with video games.
I myself have never played Fire Emblem, nor do I have an interest in it.
Sorry, not sorry, but to which they are owned, I think they say in English.
And the thing is, recently they released Three Houses, which was very popular.
And it did the same thing, basically also with houses.
and it actually worked because instead of saying pass, I don't want to play any Fire Emblem,
or I don't want even to check what Fire Emblem is about, they got me checking the houses because
I wanted to know which houses I would choose. And again, no magic trick. I didn't end up.
playing Fire Emblem.
But it's the first time in my life
that I actually care enough to check about the game.
And that's a huge first step
that we are trying to achieve as creators.
So the power of a first big choice.
Give me one second.
I will sum it up this way,
which is human beings are often like,
They tend, sorry, human beings tend to organize information
in categories and groups because that makes the information
more easily digestible, digestible.
And so these create shortcuts and make easier
to understand complex structures,
like the fiction you are trying to sell, for instance.
And so we are also appealed and attracted to these kind of informational categories.
We are like, when we see them, we want to decode them. So there's a power in that.
In Monster Prom, there's no houses or teams,
but we have the characters.
You need to choose between six love interest.
And so we did this into a lesser degree,
but the six characters have clear school tropes.
They have a clear monster types,
and they're even minus one are super clearly coded
with colors that are very,
present in the character design. So you have the red demon who's a bad boy, the green gorgon who's
a mean girl, the blue ghost who's a party animal, or the purple vampire who's a hipster.
And so now that we have understood this, the next question would be like, can this become
more powerful? And I think yes, with what I call sexy themes. And this is a
funny way of saying universal unrecognizable categories or symbols.
And as we can see here, one example, there's like Zodiac.
Just if you are wondering, this Zodiac thirst
is nothing about this talk specifically,
but just as an example, so I can show you
that we're not only sharing this information,
but we applied ourselves.
This is like some concept we have been playing around
around the idea of a sexy thing, which is Zodiac signs.
And I will show you some concepts, sorry,
when I'm explaining this.
So.
These sexy themes are stuff like zodiac signs, but also elements, planets, deadly scenes,
major arcana. You can think of probably of many universal categories that people easily recognize.
And you can also think on many fictions that use that, like Sailor Moon with the planets,
Homestuck and Saint Seiya with the zodiac signs, Avatar with the elements.
And again, it has the power of this first big choice,
but also is so freaking recognizable and universal.
And even sometimes people have one of these symbols assigned
or they previously chose which one they really like,
that you can even go further into overriding
the first disinterest.
that people maybe even want to check theirs.
Like, I'm a Capricorn, and then I
tend to check the Capricorn characters when
the characters are coded with the zodiac signs.
It's, again, the power of this first big choice.
But it's not only about offering the first big choice or using universal and recognizable themes
that work as categories, but also you need to, of course, translate these universal categories,
symbols, etc., into something that feels yours, part of your fiction.
And again, of course, you are not,
this is not something that you need to do,
but these are like advice insights.
And I would say that it's worth checking
if this makes sense with your fiction,
but if so, I think it helps.
So yeah, making it yours.
The goal here, I think is when you create these categories,
this first big choice,
it's good if the options have distinctive,
visual distinction.
and a clarity of tropes. You need to make the choice very distinct from each other so people
feel even more pushed like subconsciously into choosing one that speaks to them.
In the end, it's a lot about that, about our tendency to seek a sense of belonging,
even if it means belonging to one group, house, category, character in a fiction,
and our sense of identity and how we are continuously defining ourselves and looking
for ways of defining ourselves. And so we...
carry these symbols, for instance, in a way that has some strange and intriguing power.
Like, again, the zodiac signs. I myself am a Capricorn, and I don't believe in astrology,
but I carry the sign in a strange way because it's a sign that was assigned to me at birth,
and I have built some connection. And so there's at least an intriguing power to that, and I think
fictions can benefit from using it.
So to sum it up,
sexy themes are universal and recognizable.
They appeal to a sense of identity
and the need to define oneself.
And they throw a complete stranger
into checking the fiction and doing a whole dive within it.
It's building yummy choices
that lead into a strong sense of belonging and identity.
And again, overriding that first part.
turning getting that first byte. So, let's move on to the next part.
The immersion. So, the smooth transition from byte to binge. And these are insights on many
degrees of depth from the byte to the binge. For instance, twisting the trope is something that
in my opinion is closer to the byte. And the one we are checking now,
which is the power of the relatable, is closer to the binge.
What's that about? Let's think for a moment on a TV show. It's Space Bounty Hunters, right?
You have the first episode and it starts with a brawl so you can see all of these characters
like striding to cool fighting. It's selling the action of the TV show.
And that's all cool, but I think it's even cooler when a TV show does something different,
like you watch once on minutes and the actual show starts with them a bit before that. So you
have them ordering food at an intergalactic pool for dinner, restaurant, whatever, or dinner.
And so you can see them like what they order, how they eat, what they drink,
or even them having a menial conversation about anything.
And I believe there's a power in that.
Actually, this that I am describing
is very similar to the first scene of Preserver Dogs, where
you have fantastic characters, in the sense
that they are not your every man,
but criminals in this case.
And you have them eating at a dinner
and discussing about, if I remember correctly,
the tipping system in the United States.
And it was a great choice, I think,
It painted you the characters in a very clear way,
but also in a way that was relatable in the sense
that they were doing something that even if there were
criminals or space pirates, as they will be in this TV show,
they still felt close.
And there's a power on making stuff relatable.
I think it's obvious on how it grounds your fiction in what
can be recognized and seen as something close to us.
So I think there's a value in mixing the fantastic and the mundane. The fantastic is also good.
Like, of course, you can create something that's completely mundane and that's completely fine,
but many fictions benefit, I think, from having fantastic setups. Some people ask us, like,
why Monster Prime are monsters? Because they're like comedic exaggerations of myself and my
friends when we were on our 20s, most of the characters.
not Miranda, I don't know any person like Miranda.
Luckily, I guess.
But the thing is.
We chose to make them monsters for no good reason other than monsters are cool and they're popular.
And so yeah, there's value in a fantastic setup and nothing against Miranda, but at least as a
real person, I think it's at least one I would want to be close to. The character is funny.
So we know that there's value in the fantastic, but also it's good to space them on the underneath.
People want to see this fantastic hero. No matter how epic your story is, people connect with and
care for what's humane, for what's relatable. And so I think you need to put that into your
fiction no matter what.
Another good example we talked before,
and I think it talks about another value of this,
is Harry Potter again.
Because many people,
even if they didn't care that much about Harry Potter
and the ones that care, of course did,
has wondered what if I was in Hogwarts, right?
Because Hogwarts, aside of being a magic school,
was a school and that's something we can relate to.
and that let us do something very important for a fiction to make people do, which is projection.
I think it's very good that your fiction manages to make the audience project themselves
into the fiction's world. And that's thanks to having, sorry, details, parts of the fiction,
or a big part that's mundane, that's something that we can relate to. So...
You want your fiction to be enough fantastic,
so you want to imagine yourself in there,
but enough mundane so you can imagine yourself in there.
Right?
There's...
A couple easy challenges, tricks that can help you
brainstorm ideas for these.
It doesn't need to be your next game or creation,
but at least something you can brainstorm for one,
two hours to practice this,
mixing the mundane with the fantastic.
And he's working on a very popular formula,
which is mixing a fantastic thing with a mundane setup.
And the most popular one that we have seen to exhaustion,
sorry, is a school for whatever fantastic. We have Harry Potter and the Magician's School
for Wizards. We have My Hero Academia, School for Superheroes. We have the Daily Class,
School for Assassins, and we can go on. So...
I challenge yourself, spend one hour brainstorming an idea that, for instance, something that changed the something fantastic, a school for, I don't know, let's say for deities.
So you can make it the school is for a specific pantheon, like Greek gods or many pantheons.
And every clique in the school is a different pantheon, or maybe a different type of deities like eldritch deities.
And you get a way weirder fiction.
Or maybe you can do the opposite.
And I challenge you to change the mundane setup.
And you have, for instance, a company
that's like gray, boring offices.
But what they do is create new worlds.
They are like creators of worlds, but in a gray office.
Or you have a law office for superheroes and all the law
issues they have.
But it's not about the superheroes.
It's about the lawyers, the fiction.
Or you have a PR agency for gods that are trying to get a bigger following and you follow
the work in the PR agency.
Try to do it.
Try to brainstorm this for one hour or two.
So next, let's go into the last part, the true depths.
So
Transcribed by https://otter.ai
This is again about building true connection
with your audience, with your fans,
on values, on emotions, on identity.
And we have found two ways,
two things that you can care of around this,
which is voices and values and ship dynamics.
And I'm guessing that in the chat,
people will be asking for ship dynamics maybe,
but it's the other one, it's voice and values.
That's where we're checking today.
So, for devices, it's very simple.
It's about you need to flesh your characters out.
This is so obvious, and yet I fail to see it
in many fictions I consume,
like really fleshing the characters out
and following all the steps
to make them feel real as a main goal.
We will check some of the steps we follow in Morse code.
Some are tied to insights we haven't seen today,
but they're pretty self-explanatory.
For instance, tropes.
Like.
We identified and chose recognizable tropes for our characters, monster types, which are
tropes on themselves, school tropes, and don't try to reinvent the wheel.
Of course you will disrupt these tropes a bit, but you also want to keep stuff so these
are the pillars for your characters.
You want to find themes like semantic territories that you will use for the characters narratives.
You want to build some depth. You want to spend some time asking the right questions. What's the
upbringing of the characters? Who are their family? What's their backstories? Why they are the way
they are? Let's not just make them one way, but let's try to understand how they come to be that
way.
And details, this seems more like non-important,
but it is because we are built not only
in our big, deep stories, but also in our little details.
And this builds a rapport with the audience
and also gives the characters a lot of texture,
which is super good.
So think of little details.
Spend some time, and I sometimes fail
to see this in characters on popular fictions.
Spend some time creating details that
give texture to the characters.
And finally, values, which is very important too, because we all have values.
And if your characters need to feel real, they should have to.
Like the specific ways in which they understand the world that surrounds them, right?
And the main goal, I think, is to get a variety of voices.
that feel real and unique and different,
that help people to project and to identify with.
And I want to speak for a minute on the idea
of telling this variety of,
so showing this variety of voices
and telling these diverse stories.
And sometimes people worry because they think that telling diverse stories is a bit too specific and it can be niche.
And I don't think so.
Because, yes, of course, some of these stories may feel niche.
But there's two things to keep in mind.
For once, no matter how niche or specific a story is, I think there's still dashes of the universal.
In many specific stories, there's values and situations and experiences we can all understand and relate to.
the finding our own truth or getting our voice heard.
And so you can build specific stories looking into the,
also into the universal details that can help other people
to relate with those stories.
And also, of course, there will be still parts
of the specific experience of a character
that maybe people can relate to that easily,
but there's no issue with that.
I think there's a richness in listening to stories
that are far from ours and learning from experiences
that diverge from ours.
And there's risk to that, I don't think so.
If we can connect with the story of a space pirate
and I can assure you,
my experience is far from being a space pirate,
I can probably connect with other many stories.
So be calm, don't worry.
I think there's no risk in telling these diverse stories.
So.
Here we are again. Now, to sum up, it's cakes, bites, binges, and early in between.
This is a different metaphor, the idea of doing like focus on the first splash,
ways to draw attention powerfully, focus on the dive and the ways to invite people deeper,
focus on the true death, on how to connect on deeper levels of emotions, values, and identity.
We have seen some examples. And that leads us to the conclusions.
And I would love to tell you that I found a super cool,
conclusive sentence, all those cool talks that say something
and you say, whoa, that's super, like, a big truth.
But I didn't find anything like that.
And I'm sorry, and I hope you can excuse me.
And I said, even if it's not so cool and short,
that the main idea here is that you
need to understand there's value in having not just
an audience, but a fandom.
So build your creations with the concept of fan consumption in mind,
making them multi-layer and caring for every layer in it.
Draw people's attention, hook them deeper, and keep them in love.