So good afternoon everyone, and thank you for attending this presentation.
My name is Nadege Jozsa and I am a Senior Project Manager for Localization Services
at Sony Interactive Entertainment in Europe.
So this presentation has been created together with Nadine Martin, Senior Manager for Test
Services, and Chris Burgess, Manager for our Localization Tools at SIE.
So yes, it took three of us to come up with a recipe
on how not to screw your localization.
So with this joint effort, we would
like to share with you what we have been experiencing
and implementing for years of localizing
exciting games at SAE, and what we
see as essential steps towards efficient, cost-effective,
and painless localization for our dev teams.
So it is our ambition that you will be able to walk away today with a good few tips, either
to establish a new localization process or tools, or just to answer some of the difficulties
that you are currently facing.
So, after this presentation, at the end, the three of us will be available for Q&As, should
we have any time for this.
But the cherry on the cake today is that Chris will be holding two poster sessions, 15 minutes
after the end of my presentation, where I will be going more in-depth into some of the
tool features that I will be touching on today.
So please come along.
It's going to be Indie Overlook 2018.
And we'll be waiting for you there as well.
So before we start, show of hands who here is from a dev
team, and who from a localization vendor,
translation, audio testing services.
OK, that's a good mix.
So starting now with a brief intro to localization at SIE.
So since last April 2016 up to December 2016, so in a
duration of nine months, we have worked on 108 full titles.
We have translated, culturalized, and adapted 15 million words.
We have recorded 18,000 hours of dialogues in studios across the world.
We have set up 75 or over 75 servers on our localization dedicated to.
We have tested more than 1,000 patches and overall performed
450,000 hours of testing globally.
So whilst this will give you some context on the
localization scope of challenges that we face at
SAE, we found that the solutions that we have put in
place have been effective, whether your project be small
or large, complex or straightforward.
So now, as a developer, you will be in charge of integrating
one, 10, or more languages into your game.
The big question usually is, at what time do I need to
think of localization?
In our opinion, the earlier, the better.
Getting to meet with your localization experts as early as possible is vital in order to
allow the people who will really look after your localization to immerse themselves into
your needs, your game, your objectives, and also to share consultancy.
Conversely, for us localization experts,
it's essential to meet with you early
to understand how to adapt our processes, our tools,
to your needs.
And most importantly, to determine together
the most appropriate pipeline that will
suit the needs of your game.
So this traditional waterfall model would be best suited where the full game is already
in development, where the source script and audio is already well underway, and where
there will be minimal fragmentation of assets needed.
So in practice, this means...
After meeting our development teams pre-alpha, localization is done during the alpha phase
with a view to deliver the majority of the localization assets by the beta milestone,
at which point our localization QA colleagues will take over for the first sweep of localization
testing before we all move into the pickup session.
So traditionally, we have also followed this pipeline,
and we still do for many of our titles.
However, where our developers have adopted
more agile processes, and where the source assets
remain unfinalized a lot longer,
we really needed to find a different approach.
And that different approach was realized
through this pipeline.
So this one is a more iterative model
that we use to match the development processes
whilst still retaining localization efficiencies.
on such a model, localization, so translation, audio services,
and localization QA for the testing
effectively become one team.
And we will be collaborating really extensively
on each of the rolling localization cycles.
So as you can see, the tasks are completely identical to
the previous waterfall model, but the sequencing has been
adapted to match the development processes and the
way the development are building their game.
So here it is.
Our ingredient number one towards efficiencies
is for the main stakeholders to actually meet early in order
to determine together the most appropriate pipeline
for the needs of your game.
So one of the other challenges that we usually face is to get all the main stakeholders to
work towards the same efficiencies without all developing ad hoc processes, ad hoc tools
that will certainly benefit their own process but will completely disregard the process
of their calling departments.
So at Acai, we do so through one common tool,
our localization asset management system.
So LAMS is a proprietary tool that
has been developed internally.
It's a cloud-based system for source and localized text,
audio, and subtitles.
It has, in fact, become a central repository
for the majority of our games for the source
and localized assets.
And with it, it has really become.
a point of convergence for all the various disciplines in localization.
So, the reason why LAMS has in fact become so popular with our dev teams is because it
is flexible.
It's integrating with whatever workflow has been agreed upon,
and most importantly, it is integrating
with the development team's existing tools.
So let's explore the top features
of what localization tools should
display to support and promote effective localization.
starting with the most crucial and basic of feature.
Allowing access to all the various disciplines involved
is the cornerstone of all the steps and improvement
that we are about to discuss today.
So if you take nothing else away today,
please remember to make a priority of this
for the next localization tool
that you will build by all use.
And if possible, take this further by allowing or by using a tool that will support multiple
different file formats so that all the teams involved can all work in the best of their
process yet still do so in harmony.
With LAMS, there is no risk of overwriting assets, because
the tool will prevent the tester, for instance, to
update some strings should the translator already be busy
working on it.
transparency on what lines is being worked on by whom means no delay, no unnecessary
duplication of work between tester, translator, and so no unnecessary costs.
So once our access is granted, work can start in earnest.
And as we have seen, a lot of disciplines and a lot of people will be involved in your localization process.
And often in our industry, we are likely to be working with people scattered all around the globe.
So the tool that you build by our use should really help to ease the communication between
all the various disciplines, keeping everyone on the same page regardless of your geographic
location.
So at SAE, we allow searches and display configurations to be saved and shared.
And this means that you can be sure that someone
who is on the other side of the world
will see the exact same results as you are.
Say on a project, developer based in Europe
wants their localization partners in America or Japan
to work on very specific sets of strings.
By sharing their display configurations with their colleague departments, the assets coverage
will be identical for everyone, and there will be no risk to work on incorrect or outdated
set of strings.
And most of all, there will be no time wasted on back and forth and back and forth of email
knowing what to do.
Yeah.
So, as we know, translation is underway, and with it comes the eternal problem of the context.
When translating any size of project,
there are bound to be queries.
And without the visual support, terms can really
be open to interpretation.
So take the word fire, for instance.
So make sure that the tool you go for has a system to allow these questions to be asked
in the context of the text they refer to.
So for us, this means an integrated Q&A system where our translators can ask their queries.
And developers or production can answer almost instantly.
We even sometimes get our functional QA tester
to answer these questions, because this
will save a great deal of time to our developers.
And we also allow these replies to be images,
because one image can say 1,000 words, or 1,300
in our localized versions.
So with this system, there are no unnecessary spurious bugs
by testers.
The testers gains really more awareness of the choice of
wording of the translator.
And there seems to be more respect overall between
translator and tester.
So now, once your assets are localized,
and because our European languages are typically
30% longer than our source English,
you should expect that the localized assets
will be different to the source English.
I know, that's the GDC insight that you've paid for.
So, for this reason, make sure that you can communicate
the constraints on text length restriction
and audio technical specifications
ahead of the localization phase.
And ideally, make sure that you can enforce them
through your tool.
So, the simplest thing to have to start with
would be to have a character count.
You can take this further by allowing for a line count,
and further still to allow different character limits
for different character sets.
Then you can move that feature along to the audio
by checking simple file properties.
And in fact, you could look at any other aspects
of the audio, such as the bit depth, the sample rate,
the duration, or the volume.
In any of these cases, the tool should really make it easy to identify where your localised
assets are not compliant with your source assets and should ideally report or alert
the stakeholders for the corrective actions to be taken and the issues to be resolved.
And if you want to get really fancy, you can even enable your tool to automatically fix
these volume issues.
So our LAM system will check the text length restrictions and the audio technical specifications
upon upload of the localized assets within our tool.
For instance, should the audio assets be mismatching with the source, the system will report the
issue and send a notification to the various disciplines or stakeholders.
So the time saved here is significant because we do not have to wait for manual checks by
either our development teams or by the localization project managers, the testers, the translators,
because the discrepancies in compliance.
will be notified upon upload of the localized assets
within the tool by the system.
And the fixes will be pretty much instant,
whether by your localization vendors
or by the tool itself.
So now taking the thoughts on audio a little step further,
we are going to be looking at subtitling.
So it will be a great help if everyone involved
in the process can make changes to the subtitles,
both to the text and the timing.
So really, it could be through some simple markup
in the translation, or it could be splitting
the subtitles into their own entity.
The key thing is that it should really be nice and simple for the right people to go
to and change.
But, again, this builds on having that centralised accessible system for collaboration.
For us at SAE, the rough idea is that our LAMS team
has set up a UI that uses the waveform of the audio file
to hand slide us to get the timing just right really
quickly.
So unfortunately, there is work here that I can't really talk about too much because
it's patent pending for our LAMS team, but what I can say is that the immediate benefit
observed is time and cost saving.
So, on Until Dawn, for instance, our subtitles were automated at 93%, meaning that neither
the developers, nor the translators, nor the testers needed to take any time at all to
manually split the subtitles out, because the tool did that itself.
And that really represented a great cost and time saving.
Now, not forgetting the fans of reporting out there,
whatever localization, whatever approach you will take
to your localization tool, there is,
or there are certain things that you will want your tool
to be able to tell you.
How far have we got?
How much more do we still have to localize?
So going beyond the reactive reporting,
what you might want to see is proactive reporting.
Reports that your system will be providing you
without you necessarily having to go and request it
each and every time.
So exactly what that looks like is entirely up to you.
It could be a pop-up box, a message,
or a good old-fashioned email.
So if you think back a few slides,
and I hope you were paying attention,
I spoke about saving and sharing particular searches.
So these actually form the backbone of our automation,
of our automated reporting.
Users can use any of their searches or any searches that have been shared with them to
create report subscription.
Then LAMs will email the report of their choosing for the search of their choosing in the layout
of their choosing and at a time and frequency.
So, or we can also use the data to create visualizations to provide at-a-glance reporting.
This one being for our programmers specifically.
So talking of access being the cornerstone of improvements before.
Remote access should not just be limited to people.
for your localization tool, you will want to either build
or make sure it has an API that you can use.
As a developer, this will give you a range of options
and opportunities for improving the efficiency
of your system integration, the localization,
the localization testing.
This service mentality also allows for integration
into other systems and opens up some really interesting
possibilities.
One of these possibilities has been
to enable LAMs to support our streaming video tool.
So let's look at a short demo clip.
So the concept on that one is that by using the unique string ID,
or simply searching for the string,
the testers are really quickly able to navigate to the particular asset,
watch the relevant recording footage,
and verify this asset while still retaining the context.
Additionally, you can also see a graphic display of the PlayStation controller on screen.
So the testers know what buttons are being selected at the time the assets are playing,
meaning they can really verify whether the text and the action are actually matching.
So automation for localization has been extremely successful
at PlayStation.
And we continue to invest in refining our capabilities in
this field.
And in fact, development and refinement are really high on
our list of priorities for the future.
And we have already outlined priorities for the future.
Starting with our tool, we are in the process of implementing
a validation tool for the naming conventions.
So as we know, getting our text right in the game is important,
but getting the naming conventions right
is actually essential.
So I will not go too much into it,
because Chris will be talking about it a bit further
during his poster session in 15 minutes in the Overlook 2018,
if you're interested to know more.
Now, with any new hardware, new challenges emerge.
And in VR, we are addressing the player much more directly
than ever before to create some really, truly immersive
experiences.
So to maintain that, we must make sure that the player is
spoken to appropriately.
So within LAMS, we will allow the use of variance
so that different versions of one same line can be provided.
And by variance, we mean either male, female, even young, old,
really quite a wide range.
So in a sense, our devs control the variants that their title
will be supporting.
LAMS as a system becomes the enabler.
And the translator will be free to choose to use this as and
when their expertise require it is right to do so.
So for localization services.
We are hoping that our translators in future will be able to verify their own translations
in-game much more systematically in order to really catch inconsistencies and incorrect
meanings, mistranslations.
and really clean their scripts to make them as immersive, as creative and as emotionally
engaging as possible.
We are also wishing to improve on audio volumes in future,
and by potentially centralizing the audio mastering service
for all languages in one studio.
So this should enhance the quality
of the immersive experience for those titles
where volumes could create issues.
And finally, we are also looking at having embedded project managers at our dev teams
whenever and wherever this is required by our developers, either kick-off time or training
on LAMs.
This will be to really be able to support our development teams as effectively as possible.
For our tools, for our localization testing,
the tool support and automation, like the video capture
solution that we've seen before, already
allows us to reduce the amount of localization testing
the test, sorry, the amount of testing
that the localization testers have
to perform within the game.
And in future, we expect that this testing effort will be further reduced and will turn
more into validation and verification of the localised assets.
So the benefits will be reduced costs, reduced time and better utilisation of our lock expert
teams.
With our tools and automation efforts,
we can also map the bugs in the game.
And this might help to identify bug clusters
and makes it easier to actually investigate
the root causes of a bug.
In addition, we can also map the paths testers have taken
through the game.
And this is really super helpful for coverage
and for progress tracking purposes.
Linking this data into LAMS, we will also be able to visualize the data, which will
help see progress at a glance, and then the project leads can use this to prioritize testing.
So, in conclusion, if you take nothing else away today, please remember.
to meet with your lock experts early, so they can draw an efficient plan of action adapted
to your needs.
Then, invest in a tool, any tool, because with it the opportunities towards efficiency
and quality will become endless.
For this to happen, though, please remember to empower
your localization partners.
Let your localization expert teams access the tools
so that they can manage the localization
and deliver what you need, when you need it,
and in a manner that will be most effective for you.
Finally, for the localization testing,
use the potential of the tool and go
as far as validating and automating your localization
testing for maximum efficiency.
So thank you very much for attending this presentation today.
I hope that you enjoyed it.
I'm not sure whether we will have any time for questions.
Yeah, we've got time for one or two questions before we all
move on to the poster session of Chris, where he will be
going more in-depth into the tool features.
So I will invite Nadine and Chris to come up on stage if
we have any questions.
If you want to join me.
May I go first?
Matt Whiting, Lionbridge Game Services.
Very interesting talk.
I wanted to ask Chris, how do you instrument your games so
that you can do the automated audio testing or the testing
you were showing up there on the screen where you can see
where the lines are displayed, what the controls are being
pushed, and so forth.
I don't know which one is working.
So that does place a.
very, very slight burden on the dev, which is always something we're trying to avoid,
but because this is tied to their engine and what's happening at runtime, there's a little
bit of work for them to do. But all it requires is for them to just output a little debug
string indicating, we're here, we're displaying this particular sort of identifier of line
at this time, and then...
everything else is handled by that video capture service
that's kind of picking up on what's happening to the pad,
what's happening to other things.
It just sort of annotates the video to say,
at this time, you can see this string.
Come and have a look and check it's okay.
All right, thank you.
So I see this is a great tool.
I see that it's proprietary.
So is it only open to games that have a relationship with,
that are going to be launched on PlayStation?
Or are you guys also opening this to maybe PC games?
And also for the version that basically,
if we use this tool to produce a localized version,
is that going to be restricted only
to be published on PlayStation?
Or does it become?
the properties of the developers.
Okay, so that's a little bit above my pay grade to make any kind of formal announcements
on.
So I'll speak historically.
It's only ever been used for titles that we are developing or publishing ourselves.
That might change in the future, but I'm...
I'm not going to stand here on video and say that,
because we've got too much.
I understand.
I think it's just if this tool is available,
I think a lot of people would be very, very interested.
Great tools.
Thank you.
Just wait outside with the checkbook,
and I'll be right over.
I have a couple of questions.
One, do you guys manage art assets in your tool?
Like if there's signs that need to be changed from English
to other languages?
We have done once, but that's only because that's what that
particular project required.
The system can do it.
It's quite happy to.
It is kind of agnostic as to what the actual asset is that
it's looking after.
All it really cares is there is this item that needs to
exist for these languages.
I will track it and make sure that it exists.
And if the text required from that changes,
I will prompt somebody that they need
to update that asset as well, be it audio, texture, or even
a 3D model.
Anything should, in theory, be possible.
And then my other question was, do you, does this support all the languages, like Chinese,
like analyzing the audio files for, you know, non-FIGS languages?
I know you showed a Japanese example, but I didn't know if that covered everything.
Yes.
Yeah.
It should cover all real languages and also fake ones as well.
Cool.
Thanks.
More a general question than related to the tool, but yeah.
The process becoming structured like this with tools
keeping track of changes and so on, do you think we will
arrive in the point where localization edits happen
also post-launch?
Because it used to be that we had the game on the disk, and
that was the game.
Now we are in a world where you have the disk and then you have the day one patch and so
on and so on. Localization usually never changes. There's new stuff, but if there's a mistake
in the code, it will be fixed in the patch. If there's a mistake in the text, it's unlikely
that it will get changed, at least historically. Do you think we might get to that with time
and tools?
Do you want me to take it?
Yeah.
Okay.
So I think that that is already something that does happen.
And please feel free to correct me if I'm wrong.
But it's because of the combination of the access and
the empowerment.
Because in order to change that text, all it requires is
the tester to notice it's wrong.
And if they're within the video toolkit to be able to
change it there, if they're looking at it directly in
LAMS just to make a change there, that will go into the
next build of the game, whether that is.
the gold master, the day one patch.
And without the need of a new submission.
It's just normal in the flow of the patching.
Yes.
He said.
OK, thank you very much for attending.
And please come along with us to Chris's poster session
if you're interested in more in-depth tool features.
Thank you.