Hello, everyone, and welcome to building cognitive accessibility into your games.
Hi, I'm Jay Justice.
I'm a consultant.
I work independently, but I'm available for full time.
So, my most recent work has been on the game Stray Gods, which just won Game of the Year at the Australian Game Developer Awards.
So, congrats to that team.
I've also consulted on Idle Champions of the Forgotten Realm and the upcoming Read Only Memories by MidBoss.
And with me I have some amazing developers that I am so excited to be getting to speak alongside.
Please introduce yourselves.
Yeah, hi.
My name is Tara Velker.
So I am the accessibility lead for studios at Xbox and I first want to say that Jay does not do themself enough justice.
This panel would not exist without Jay.
They literally did all of the work prepping the submission.
I didn't even give anything to Jay on time and they still made it happen.
So I wanted to talk Jay up.
When I am not here at Xbox doing accessibility stuff, I'm the
co-director of the Game Accessibility Conference, where I get to work with amazing folks, and one of the people that I love when I get an opportunity to work with is the great Morgan Baker.
Wow, that's a great transition.
Hi everyone, I am, oh, can you hear me okay too?
Am I close enough?
Cool, awesome, because I can't hear myself.
So, I'm Morgan Baker, my pronouns are she, they, and I'm the Game Accessibility Lead for
electronic arts in my free time.
I like to organize eSports tournaments, play tabletop RPGs, and play with my two Corgis, Midna and Zelda.
Can you guess my favorite game?
But it's a pleasure to be here, and I want to reiterate, thank you, Jay, for inviting both of us today.
Absolutely excited to talk about my favorite topic, cognitive accessibility.
and hopefully you will show on your surveys that you will definitely submit at the end of the session that it's also one of your favorite topics.
So please do not forget to fill out your surveys because that is how we know how well we did.
So I will only ask that twice, once at the very beginning and once at a reminder on the end.
But please do not forget to fill out the surveys at the end.
And Morgan, thank you for sharing your pronouns.
I forgot to share mine.
Mine are she, her, or he, him.
She Heart.
Yeah, so we all have a little bit of a different background in accessibility and just game design and game development in general, but I talk a lot about gaming being a three-step process.
That the first thing we do is we get information from the game.
What do we see?
What do we hear?
If it has haptics, what do we feel?
and we take in that information and then we process it.
And then as we process it, we determine our course of action and then output back to the game.
We tell the game what we want to do.
And it's this three-step process that is blank a game.
Doesn't matter how complex it is.
But cognitive accessibility specifically is something has interrupted the processing part of that three-step process.
process for playing games.
And so when we're talking about cognitive accessibility, we're talking about making sure that people can process the information correctly so that they can provide the right output to the game based on the information that they have received.
Yeah, absolutely.
And adding on to that too, it really ties into the idea of like perceptions, so making sure that you can process this information comfortably, you're able to comprehend it, and you're able to use the product with ease.
Of course, when we talk about cognitive accessibility, it's universal and everyone wins when we're constantly thinking about it.
And so it's really important for us to consider these barriers that occur in the nature of processing information.
Okay, so we've defined it very clearly.
The next step, who is cognitive accessibility for?
Everybody, everybody, but really though.
Players with conditions related to processing information, including but not limited to ADHD, TBIs, PTSD, and many other neurological and mental conditions.
And literally anyone who needs it can be both situational and temporary.
You guys want to expand?
Yeah, I think what a lot of people don't realize is, you know, yes, having ADHD is going to impact how you interact with a game.
Having a traumatic brain injury, like having a number of, even one good severe concussion can interact how you play with games.
And even things like PTSD, again, about how do you process information.
can all be part of it.
And sometimes it is neurological, sometimes it is going to be more specifically related to mental health.
One of the things that you're gonna see up here is like, we all have cognitive disabilities.
So like, you'll notice we're all up here with our notes and everything.
They're like, oh yeah, like we wrote stuff down to make sure that we can hit it.
So for us, you know, it is a wide range of things that all have a very,
that all have a very similar set of needs.
I cannot talk about the irony about putting a talk about cognitive accessibility by a bunch of people with cognitive disabilities at 5 p.m.
on a con day.
We are struggling hard up here.
So, you know, who is cognitive accessibility for?
It is for us.
Exactly.
And also, too, I like that I wrote down my... It's so suiting.
At a cognitive accessibility, I, like, wrote down notes for myself, and I'm like, come on, Morgan, you got this.
But I haven't narrowed down to thinking about cognitive accessibility for myself.
I often think about conditions as we've talked about, like processing, but we also have, like, processing speed, learning, memory, attention, focus, mental endurance, and all these things overlap, and it's holistic.
every disability, every condition, whether it's permanent, temporary, or situational, it is holistic in this nature.
And so, again, it's for everyone, but especially we want to think about those who really, really need it.
And if you want to think about hard numbers, remember that a lot of people who have processing disorders may not even consider themselves to be disabled.
So there's millions of people who would benefit from getting more accessibility
that would actually address some of the issues that they're having with processing information.
Well, and I think something that's really common is there are a lot of people who, first off, never receive a formal diagnosis or are diagnosed super late in life.
So not only do we have people who do have these diagnoses who don't identify as disabled, there are people with these conditions who have no idea that they have these conditions and that they've basically been playing their life on hard mode the entire time and no one told them.
Yeah, that's totally true, and especially we have to really recognize that there is a stigma sometimes too around it, and we want to have that contextually when we're thinking about our games and designing our games, knowing that, you know, people will have different worldviews with cognitive accessibility.
Of course, there's nothing wrong with ADHD, OCD, I'm like a hot mess express over here, choo-choo all aboard.
But, you know, I think, though, it's important for us to think about that stigma constantly to make sure that we are approaching our cognitive accessibility with the utmost sensitivity for our players.
Very well said.
All right.
What challenges do people who would benefit from cognitive accessibility face when playing games?
Some challenges or barriers include cognitive overload, sensory overload,
on
you know these challenges.
One of the things that I tend to think about is basically for some reason the amount of info coming in short circuits the processing part.
Like it's overcharged.
It's a transformer exploding.
You know you want to continue but the input is way way too much.
And, you know, that just means when that happens for a lot of people, you shut down.
But that's only for certain people.
There are going to be other people where the reverse happens.
There's not enough information coming into the machine for you to justify continuing running it right now.
So that's when you get distracted.
You do something else.
on
talk talk
Yeah, especially when we talk about overstimulation and endurance, we have to think about the short-term versus that long-term as well, right?
So the idea of the short-term of so much information being thrown at you at once that your brain, I say, it works.
Let's be honest.
Where we have the long-term of the constant pressure of trying to process information, and every single person has different thresholds, and so we need to design accordingly, thinking about these different thresholds.
So, like, for example, we have different thresholds that relate to someone who may have, like, a visual processing disorder versus an auditory processing disorder versus anything else.
Maybe it's sensory.
Maybe it's sensation.
And all these things kind of combine together to create, well, what we need to address, cognitive accessibility, right?
And so that's something we constantly need to think about and actually for myself sometimes I describe it This might not be helpful But I say I have a basket and I can only put so many beans in the basket before they all just start spilling out and everyone has like Different types of basket sizes for like yeah my so I have bad auditory processing so my basket for auditory is very small and
but have good visual processing, so that basket's much bigger, and so we need to think about constantly how we can accommodate and think about our designs and our games in a way that is accessible and approachable to everyone with different sized baskets.
I told you it's not a perfect thing, just roll with me here, okay?
But I think you can roll with the basket analogy, because what's really nice is like, you know, I have a basket, but I'm just really particular about how full my basket is.
Like, I just want it to always be the same level.
There was actually a really great talk at the Game Accessibility Conference
by an accessibility consultant named Shell Little, and they talked about the sweet spot between being overwhelmed and boredom, and how so many things can add beans to that basket.
And so for Shell, they have talked about having ADHD, and for them, even just having, like,
you know something that's like an animated like circle that shows your amount of mana but if it's constantly moving every time that's moving that's adding a bean into the basket like none of us are saying you know what the cool core loop of my game is watching that animation
Right?
Like that's not what we're saying.
Like that was not the core loop for fun.
And if someone came up and told you, like, hey, all I can do is watch that animation of that little potion bottle in the corner, you'd be like, oh, crap, there's a whole bunch of game they're not getting to.
But that's because that animation put too many beans in the basket before they actually got to go and play and enjoy your game.
And as Morgan said, there's a lot of things that add beans to that basket.
It can be the sound.
It can be animations.
It can be haptics.
there is a lot.
It could be your inventory management.
But again, as Morgan highlighted, it could be different for everyone.
And I'm sure that it's different for Jay.
I don't know what beans add to your basket.
We're just running with the beans in the basket panel.
Yeah, the big barrier, it's like all of these things are different bricks in a wall and the big wall, the thing that makes people stop playing games that they were otherwise really enjoying is the fact that they're unable to process the information because there's too much of something or there's not enough of something.
And the big issue that we have is that a lot of games don't really take into account that you don't need to be throwing so much information at the player.
You can figure out a way to make something
maybe more modular, maybe more customizable so that you can pick and choose the things that are going to be getting an input.
And we're going to talk more about that on the next slide.
Okay.
So this is how we do it.
What are some of the best practices for cognitive accessibility?
You guys had some great suggestions earlier.
Allowing manual saves any time.
We all need this.
Offering trigger warnings.
Offer easy to understand subtitles.
Sharing accessibility info ahead of launch.
Regular testing for light and motion sensitivities throughout production.
And evaluating menu animations or UI to determine if they're truly necessary or off the ability to turn the little mono thingy off.
Alright, please tell us more about some of these because I think these are really great suggestions that can help people who are currently developing games get the idea for making it more accessible in the pipeline before they finish.
Yeah, so one of the first things I want to call out about this list is some of them you may not realize unless you live in the cognitive accessibility space like we do, is it's not immediately clear, wait, why does that help?
Like having easy-to-understand subtitles, like why does having easy-to-understand subtitles work?
I mean, obviously, more again, different, deaf, like clearly, like that's a required feature, but like I don't have
you know, any sort of issues with being hard of hearing, but I always play my games with subtitles.
And why is that?
Well, if I'm taking in enough information, like if there's a bunch of sounds, like at some point, my brain will still not really understand what's being said.
And so I still need that secondary channel of information to reinforce what I'm hearing to kind of lock it into place.
And, you know, there, I mean, there's, I don't want to, like, I could personally talk about this slide for the next,
45 minutes.
But I think what I just kind of hit on that one, maybe I'll let Morgan and Jay talk about more, and then I'll just give a 20-minute lecture on trigger warnings.
That sounds good.
OK, all right.
Morgan.
Yeah, no, but I think you're bringing up a good point.
And it kind of goes back to the universality of when we're thinking about cognitive accessibility, right?
Designed, for one, extends to many.
It's beneficial for someone who is deaf or hard of hearing, but also beneficial for someone who has auditory processing,
or the intersectionality of it all.
And actually, the intersection of that and deafness, as a fun fact, is extremely high.
So, as a little tidbit for today, just keep in mind that these features are beneficial for someone who has, say, deaf or hard of hearing.
They have a hearing condition.
or it can be beneficial to someone who has visual processing, auditory processing, or like, honestly, subtitles are just really nice because maybe your kid is in the room and they're being really freaking loud and you're like, you know, I don't know what's happening in this game anymore.
Amp it up the subtitle size.
Well, I think even like the example of like, you know, having kids in the room or other people in the room, like as someone with ADHD, one of the reasons like having manual saves is really, really important to me is because I will lose track of when the game last saved and I will get distracted.
Even if it's my favorite game in the entire world, Alan Wake 2, I will get distracted and I will need to be able to make sure that it has saved because I know I'm going to
end up getting so distracted I won't come back.
So being able to be like, hey, I need to save right now.
It's also really important because there are times I know I'm getting ready to go into something that is going to be cognitively challenging, and there is nothing worse than starting a really cognitive challenging task, but the save being like 10 minutes before that cognitively challenging task starts.
So all of a sudden, like, not only did I just die, but now I have to redo whatever I did, which I don't remember for sure.
like, oh, it's a puzzle that I should already know the solution to?
Nope.
It's gone.
Like, as soon as that was completed, my brain has dumped that information.
We're not coming back to that.
So if I have to redo that now to get to my new cognitively challenged thing, I'm going to have a lot of issues.
So being able to, you know, make sure I've saved so that I always know, hey, I get to have a point where I can start fresh or I don't have to remember that thing that I did 20 minutes ago because I got to save after it was done is really, really important to me.
Same.
I can't tell you how many games I've just never gone back to because I was like, I'm not doing this again, I swear.
New.
So sharing accessibility info ahead of launch is extremely impactful, and I'm so happy to be seeing so many more companies do this because it tells
your extremely large disabled audience that there is going to be a way for them to experience this game.
It gives people an idea of what to expect and it gives really helpful information about how your game is going to be able to be experienced by others.
It's fantastic and I really appreciate getting to see that a lot more and I hope that it's something that gets done more as well because it shows that the company and the developers had taken the time to do research and to really implement these practices into their game because they're ready to go.
with this whole list.
There's been a bunch of titles lately that I've had.
Have you noticed the Ubisoft ones that came out?
Oh, no, the Ubisoft ones are great.
And Jessica, is it Roche?
Roche?
I love how I gestured towards Morgan, like she would...
She works at Ubisoft in their marketing division and she did a great talk about their accessibility marketing plan and how Ubisoft specifically built a framework to get that accessibility out.
ahead of the game's launch so that players can make informed decisions.
Because especially in the cognitive accessibility space, being able to make an informed decision as a player is absolutely key.
And we'll get a little bit more into that.
I actually submitted a bunch of slides for Dead Space, which isn't even the title I worked on.
That was Morgan's title.
Because they did some great stuff around informed decisions, which is why trigger warnings are so important.
Yes.
brought it all the way back around.
I talk a lot about trigger warnings.
And you're going to when we get to that slide.
I know.
All right.
First up, what are some examples of cognitive accessibility in games that you've worked on or played?
How are they beneficial?
Can I please do this one because I love this one so much?
Okay.
So this is an example of an always available training area from Jedi Survivor, which was a fantastic game.
I absolutely loved it.
This really helped the player experience getting to Train as a Jedi.
And if you forgot how to do a move, it didn't take you out of the gameplay at all.
You were meditating as Cal.
It was something that was always present.
You could just get to a save point and you could just do this.
And it really helped keep the flow of the game going without making it feel like they were... No one's going to ever say that this is like, oh, it's easy mode or whatever.
You're not going to be able to make a player feel bad for needing more training because it's something that
is just part of the gameplay experience and it was just so well done.
I've had other games that were similar, like Monster Hunter has a very easy access training area as well, but this one just felt so rooted to the core of the game itself that it was just perfect.
It made it easier to beat bosses that I don't think I would have been able to beat otherwise because I was able to practice so often and not feel like it was taking me out of the game because it was just part of
what
isn't something that's only locked to a specific difficulty or whatever, they're going to be less likely to use it because it's othering.
And players with cognitive disabilities, we don't want to be othered.
We are regular players.
And so taking that time as a developer to make these instances
core to the experience, and as weird as it sounds, give the player permission and know that it's okay to do this, is actually really important.
And your language and how you access these things really can help inform how comfortable the player feels in engaging stuff like your tutorials, your trials, or even going back and looking up information that they already had available.
at all.
And so this is a perfect thing, right?
Because it's helpful for, let's say, you pick up an item and you're like, I just literally don't get how to do this.
I want to practice it.
I want to understand it more, really comprehend the mechanics around it, and really have that information processing in that kind of space with no sort of penalty to practice.
But it's also helpful, too, if you're just like, I literally just don't remember what's happening anymore.
That happens to me all the time, and I can see many of you as well.
All right.
Next up, Dead Space.
I mean, technically this is your game, I just put the slides in, so I'm not sure who's supposed to... I mean, maybe we could do a little twofer here.
So, in addition to ADHD, I do have PTSD, and for me, being able to make an informed decision is really important.
I'm really lucky that I have most of my PTSD under control, but I need to be able to make informed decisions.
Like many disabilities, how impactful it is varies day to day.
There will be days that, like, I am unstoppable and I can see things related to my trauma absolutely no problem.
There are other days, if I'm not in a good spot, that seeing that content can actually trigger a physical flashback.
I hope that you never have to experience one, but if you do have one, your body literally feels like it did at the time that you experienced the trauma.
And it is weird.
You're both in your body and not at the same time.
It's not great.
Zero out of ten.
Do not recommend.
And there are some games that have some, like, pretty shitty content warnings.
Like, I won't name the game.
but there was one that I played that the content warning was basically like, hey, this game talks about serious topics.
Cool.
The topics in the game were actually, these are graphic, it was rape, the Holocaust, and child sexual abuse.
and how are you supposed to make an informed decision around those things if you're only told, hey,
there's serious topics in here.
Like, maybe one day, I don't want to play a game about the Holocaust.
Like, it's okay for me to make that decision, and it's about empowering me to make those kinds of decisions.
And as a person who loves horror games, who very frequently have these very serious or traumatic topics, I really, really want to have that, which is why I was so obsessed with the Dead Space remake.
And also to reiterate some things, so we actually did a talk at GA Conf, which you're the co-director of, I did a talk with Christian and myself talking about this, where specifically for Dead Space there is kind of two features happening.
One is that you can hide the scenes, visually hide them.
And the second one is that we have a content warning that comes up before the scene happens, and we try to time it so that players, if they read the content warning, they can make that informed decision to say, not today, maybe I'll pause and, you know, come back later.
And actually this goes back to like informed purchasing decision conversation where actually the Motive website has an entire section dedicated to these content warnings that show how they work but also to details each content warning so you can just read them before you even jump into the game.
So we try to do that for folks so they can make that decision before they ever even purchase the game if that this is something that they want to experience.
Yeah, and it connects back to what we were saying earlier.
Like for me, as someone with PTSD, my processing sometimes just breaks.
And so it's me looking at my machine and being like, do I think it can handle the stress?
Or do I think that my processing will shut down if I look at that topic?
which is why having these are so great and why, again, like, I cannot, like, stress how great of an example Dead Space is in both being very transparent about the topic matter that is covered and when it is covered and also telling you in the game, so, which is double great.
As someone with PTSD and ADHD, oh, sure, I could read, oh, Chapter 5 is about this.
Do you think I remember that when I get to Chapter 5?
No.
talk, because your question will probably be answered for that.
Okay, and then this was the one that you sent me for Grounded, which has an arachnophobia mode, which I have arachnophobia, so thank God.
I mean, well, we can do the same thing.
You can talk about what it meant to you as a player, and then I can talk about it from the developer's side.
Okay, so unfortunately, this is a phobia that makes a lot of games just unplayable for me, but luckily, this one turned something that I physically cannot look at without feeling ill and I'm going to panic and not be able to function to something that's honestly kind of cute.
like this.
Would you like to access those options now?
It's yes, so fast.
It doesn't make the player feel shame.
It doesn't actually have any kind of negative connotation whatsoever.
It's just an option.
It's completely a neutral choice and it just makes the game playable.
It's just accessibility in a nutshell.
We're not trying to tell you what's good or what's bad.
We're just making it playable for you.
And this was actually something that originated from out of the dead team itself.
So I do want to be transparent.
This feature shift before I was in my role.
So I am telling the story of I have heard from the devs.
I was not personally on the feature.
I don't want to steal credit because they're amazing.
But basically there were some folks internally who were like, I am not into spiders.
And so this is making it stressful.
So there was actually user research done internally within Xbox where we ended up taking people from across Xbox, not just on this particular dev team, and talking to them
about their experiences and how their arachnophobia manifests.
So it's not called the spider slider, but I like to call it the spider slider.
How that manifests.
So what you see here is the danger dumpling.
So this is the least spidery spider you can get.
But for some people, there was kind of a middle ground of like, oh, when it is full spider, that is when I can't handle it.
But when it was halfway through the spider slider, they were absolutely fine.
So that kind of shows that how spidery it had to be to trip the phobia was unique for everyone.
So being able to customize it unblocked people with that phobia.
But again, it comes down to, you kind of hit on it earlier,
You know, being able to stand up to a spider isn't the key part of Grounded.
It could be any creature.
Like, it didn't actually matter what creature it was as long as it fit in the Grounded universe.
So if we could unlock the ability for more people to play by just making it a danger dumpling instead of a spider, like, that's pretty straightforward.
Because again, like,
that it wasn't explicit in the game score loop that it had to be a spider.
A spider makes sense for grounded contextually.
I mean, you're little people and you're fighting bugs and all that stuff.
But like, why did it have to be a spider?
No, it was really about this kind of combat moment and this having something bigger than you that you needed to be able to make decisions around, you know, didn't actually have to be a spider.
Do we include the example of the lasophobia to the setting that they added?
was
of
the actual encapsulated fear around the actual fear of Sorry, I should have said it's the fear of giant open water So the idea of like no way like if you put me in a cruise ship, I will probably cry Although I really want to go on the Disney cruise so bad.
Oh
Maybe one day, if you blindfold me, I may be able to... Maybe you just always have an interior cabin, I don't know.
But then again, I like horror games, so maybe it'll just be like a horror experience the entire time for me.
Y'all are having fun, you know, having your mixed drinks, and I'm crying, you know?
I'm just, I know this isn't the topic of this panel, but I'm picturing you and being scared, but like, and having like a kind of like Five Nights at Freddy's vibe, because it's a Disney cruise.
Y'all are hilarious.
Oh my god.
It's funny you mentioned Horizon Zero Dawn because the slide I forgot to put in for myself was Horizon Forbidden West because they added a feature that allows you to change your concentration time and to have Aloy do an auto heal and also basically remove some of the load of trying to remember all the things you have to do at once to loot the robots as you're killing them, to remember how to aim, to do everything.
And it still works in a way to make it feel like you're still playing as Aloy.
It doesn't make the game any more, like,
It's still extremely challenging, but it removes a bit of the mental load of having to remember to do so many things to avoid dying.
And it's just a fantastically accessible game overall, but I really appreciated the cognitive features that they added to make hunting not quite as arduous.
I died so many times, and I was like, let me just turn these features on, and it just made the game even more fun for me.
All right, so next.
What cognitive accessibility features or design choices would you like to see become standard in the future?
So navigation assistance is one I added because I really appreciate games that don't just throw you out like naked and afraid, you're just in the woods, you're just out here trying to find your way.
I want every game in the future to have just press L3, tell me where I'm going, give me a ping, give me a direction, something.
An easy to access controls guide, just knowing what controls do what.
And I'll let you go on about your favorite thing.
I mean, yeah, useful trigger warnings.
If you have a trigger warning that's not useful, like, thanks for wasting both of our time.
Like, just please, just make it useful.
And Morgan, I know you suggested the tutorials, especially that was your thing.
of
team.
talk.
I hear some folks will talk about this, like, tutorialization, and I've seen folks even play around with the idea of, like, learnability, the idea of, like, being able to solidify that in the memory and then also being able to revisit it whenever you want to, once again, reinforce your understanding and reinforce your comprehension.
And also, too, if you just literally don't remember.
Speaking of don't remember, persistent on-screen prompts that you can toggle on and off as an option, but I really appreciate how in Monster Hunter, I don't remember how to attack.
It's been three months.
Oh, it's right there.
Literally, it is always right there.
I don't remember how to swing from tree to tree.
Wait, there it is.
It's just part of the heads-up display, and it just makes it so much easier, and I would love if more games did this.
So I know that there's a big move to make games more cinematic, like you're watching a movie, but I want something to remind me that it's a game.
It's okay for the game to know it's a game.
I'm good with it being a press A to attack in the corner like an arcade.
So I know it's aesthetic for a lot of games, but I think it can still be accessible.
Yeah, and I'm one of the people who also forget controls all the time, especially if there's a game where there's something like a stealth element where you're supposed to come behind someone and then do something very specifically.
to stealth kill them versus like loudly throw an axe or something.
I will accidentally loudly throw an axe unless that like, hey, don't forget, just just press L1 and you'll stab them silently.
Like I need to have that reminder.
I'll just be like, oh, and no, and then everyone will be alerted and I'll die because I could not in the heat of the moment remember what button is the do it silently.
This is the stealth part of the game, you idiot button.
I'm always the meme.
I tried to kill a guy and gave him my rations.
That's me every time.
There's too many controls.
Oh, man.
Okay.
And I remember, Morgan, you wanted to expand a little bit more on better motion and licensitivity considerations.
Yeah, absolutely, especially for this one.
Remember we were talking about earlier, like the overload and stuff like that, because it's not just the information you're presenting, but the extreme of that information, right?
So for example, if I have like, yeah, this one thing to have a prompt that says like, press A, but if you have a flashing in someone's face and there's all these visual effects around, that's changing the way that someone can process the information.
And so we want to make sure, or if it's moving around too, which then we can talk about motion sickness too, all of this is connected.
It's the brain, welcome to the brain.
Yeah, I know, right?
All three of us also get motion sick.
Thank you for asking.
So we're just a combo, the three of us.
But that's something we need to consider.
And actually, I will give a shout out to Electronic Arts, actually, which released Iris last year, which is a free photosensitivity testing tool designed for games.
Anyone can use it.
You can go to our website and you can download the code.
You have to build a front end for it.
But yeah, that's a tool that's available to everyone in this room right now.
So definitely check it out.
And I definitely, the cost is $3.99, again, versus the other ones out there, which cost significantly more money.
I just want to reiterate, if you're looking to do it, that one is very cost effective in that you don't have to pay for it.
And this last one I added based on my experience in game development class with other indie devs who are just starting out and learning how to make games.
Teaching everyone who is learning how to make games right now that it's a good choice to just at least attempt to present information in as many ways as possible when developing a game can actually help you figure out ways to make your game more accessible early in the process as opposed to trying to finish the game and then do it later.
Because if you're thinking about how your player is getting information from you, it will give you an idea of where the gaps are in what you're making so that you can actually help them get over that barrier before you've even made it.
And a lot of my classmates were asking me, because they know that I do accessibility consulting, but I also, like, I'm working in Unreal and I'm learning how to make games on my own.
But, like, I can't make a game accessible by myself.
I'm just one person.
I'm like, you do not have to single-handedly hit this checklist that we all, like, have in our imaginations of every single possible access need.
Like, that's not what we're saying.
We're saying, based on what your game is, what information is important for you to give the player
and how else can you do that using the blueprints that you've learned in class?
I'm not trying to tell you learn everything right now, but knowing what you know, how else can you do this?
Just starting with that small thought can really empower a developer to reach a goal they didn't know they could reach because they didn't know it was possible.
The gist of it is that I preach this everywhere, even in the drive-thru at McDonald's.
We're going to make things more accessible.
Ma'am, this is a Wendy's.
Exactly.
You know, I absolutely love that Jay added and brought this up because it again gives me a chance to talk about Alan Wake 2.
So, one of the really key things is like you can do this like re-giving information to people in cool and creative ways that can be enjoyed by everyone.
I'm
playing, she's an FBI detective, trying to solve this case.
As you go through, there is literally a board where as you learn new things, you pin it to the board and you get to connect pieces of information.
And when Saga learns something important, it gets put on the board.
And if she is able to draw conclusions from learning multiple things, she's like, oh, case closed, puts a note on it about what she learned from all of the information that she was able to collect.
and this exists that the player is always able to go and look at it, and you can always go back through any of the key pieces of information that you have, and you can even go reopen closed case files so that you can learn more information.
So for me, that's a really, really cool way of providing this information I received primarily via audio, via in-game conversations in another way, but also going a step further and contextualizing it
with other key pieces of story information that I have learned in the game, and that also helps inform what your next objective is going to be.
You can also view your current game story objective at any given time on the same thing.
For me, I view that entire mind board as a great accessibility tool, because it gives me that information, it gives me that recap, but other people love it as well.
You don't have to be prescriptive.
like Jay was saying, you can come up with cool ways to integrate this level in accessibility that is new and radical and engages all of your player base.
And actually, this, I know we kind of are touching and getting into this where, so oftentimes when I'm working with different studios and dev teams, when we talk about accessibility, you typically can bucket into
of
accessible to people who have temporary, permanent, or situational cognitive conditions, just by design, exactly as you're describing.
You don't need, this is like the story of all of our lives, is oftentimes when people say, accessibility, I have an accessibility menu, and it's like, that's great, but like also too, what are we doing in the actual fundamental design itself?
We can elevate our games when we're thinking about accessibility early and often fundamentally through the actual design itself.
And this is an excellent example that you brought up for this.
Oh yeah, you can see I'm getting a live pedestal right now.
Like, ah, accessibility matters!
But of course, it's a balance.
Both will always be necessary.
But this is an excellent example in the context of cognitive accessibility, where you can have it baked in.
That's right, I'm making a baker reference, because my last name is Baker.
And that's it.
Thanks for coming to our talk.
If you have any questions, we have a microphone set up.
Oh, the polite applause is so sweet.
Thank you.
And again, please don't forget to fill out your survey.
If you liked us.
If you didn't like us, please don't fill it out.
I just want to add something that I experienced from working with people with intellectual disability in the last few years.
That's a group that is highly dependent on personalization or individual settings.
At the same time, they can't often do those settings themselves.
They are relying on other people to do it.
Like, for instance, a day activity center has staff that needs to help them to set things up.
And I've worked also with games in these settings.
And one of the issues is that the staff is not tech savvy.
They're not gamers.
They like to help to work with people.
So it's a hard time to get them to actually learn how to make the settings understand what the game settings are and what it means for the person and so on.
So it has to be made super simple so that the staff can actually understand how to adapt it for the individual person.
One way of doing it could be to have, like, instead of having a menu with settings, you could have like a wizard style.
You get one question at a time, step by step, and then you could more easily, at least, make correct settings.
But there's another way.
It is proposed by a professor here in the US called Greg Vanderheiden, who is kind of a
superstar in accessibility is behind the W3C WCAG guidelines and many other things.
And he has come up with this concept called the Global Public Inclusive Infrastructure, GPII.net.
And one of the ideas there is that you can have some universally
available preferences that is individualized and easily available.
So you could adapt any type of application.
It's not all about games, but I think it can be also applied for that.
We require, of course, that the game industry joins forces and come up with this kind of a universal format that all game companies could
I'm so sorry, you didn't have a question?
Now it's just a comment and an addition to what you said.
You're focusing a lot on the game itself, that's great, but also think about how to make the settings, because otherwise all the features of accessibility can be in vain, because they will not be able to play the game anyway, because the settings cannot be
Yeah, we have limited time for questions, but this will be a great topic to cover at the roundtable, the IGDA Game Accessibility SIG roundtable, where we can have a proper discussion.
Great point, thank you.
Hey there, I'm Lindsay.
First of all, great talk.
As someone with ADHD, I resonated with so many things and it was just awesome.
My question relates to my role, actually.
I'm a narrative designer at Hasbro, so I work on tabletop.
Working in narrative on tabletop means that you're responsible for a lot of the onboarding and making rules clear and accessible for everyone.
So I was just wondering, in your experience with playing tabletop games, is there anything that sticks out to you specifically that you think could improve the onboarding experience?
Ooh, good question.
Well, so for me, handing me a rule book is like a no-go.
It's not going to work.
So for me, it's always, like, I am more like, well, the number one way that I will learn a game is if someone is there to teach me, which I get.
You cannot ship yourself with every game, as much as I'm sure you would love to.
So for me, I do a lot better with, like,
so normally I do not do well with verbal instructions so I acknowledge that what I'm getting ready to say also doesn't sound like it would make a lot of sense so a lot of times it's visually being able to see what is happening like the cause and effect so for me it's not as much like verbally hearing instructions like that's not going to work either because I will stop paying attention but having even if it's just like gifs in the middle of written instructions like hey like you're watching a board game or here's your paper
Do you want to see this instead?
Like, go visit this website where we've inserted GIFs in in the instructions.
That is way more likely to sink in because I will see, like, the connection of what I just read and what it translates to in the game itself.
So that's something I need.
But I know, Morgan, you've got a lot more, like, actual... Morgan's got actual accessibility work in board games, so...
Yeah, no, but it's absolutely true.
When you're thinking about this, you want to connect the dots, right?
And so actually, well, speaking of board games specifically, one thing that I like is, so I used to do consultancy work over at Exploding Kittens, which is a lot of fun helping with accessibility there.
Super cool.
I'm
And so this is something that's really helpful because it reinforces, hi, I have ADHD, so when I love board games, I will drool.
If you sit me down, I will just not understand what's happening.
I see all the colors and the pieces.
And I'm just like, my brain goes this way.
And then people are like, hey, Morgan.
I'm like, yes.
Oh, sorry, you were talking and compounded with the deaf thing.
And so you want to make sure that you have things that can create
team.
you can
side effects.
I saw a lot of myself and I was like, wow, this makes a lot of sense.
And I'm struggling.
Wow, this makes a lot of sense.
Oh my God.
Okay.
I'm seeing, you know, a lot of them ended up, you know, really relating to me.
And I was like, yeah, that was me.
You are me.
And we, I get you.
So for my question is, for someone like me, I'm kind of trying to transition out of the clinical field.
And I've always been a gamer, always been
I love ADHD and D&D.
Those things go really well together for a lot of beautiful reasons.
But I'm trying to get into more of the accessibility and video gaming world.
And I love the fact that you guys touched upon executive functioning, basically, and all the way you break down stuff and making cognitive accessibility in games.
What would you give as an advice for someone who's looking to get into and kind of doing what you guys do?
Great question.
We all have such different paths.
So if you ask anyone who works in game accessibility, how did you get into game accessibility, we all came from radically different backgrounds because it's such a new field overall.
I guess the good news is there's not a clear cut path forward and you can use your previous experiences and forge your own way.
And the bad news is, is there's not anywhere clear-cut, so I can't give you a guidebook, and you're going to have to forge your own way.
But honestly, I think a lot of good accessibility work comes from connections and being able to learn from a wide breadth of people.
Because everyone in accessibility comes from different backgrounds, you are constantly learning from everyone else in accessibility.
Like, I learn shit from these two constantly.
So... For me, I came from education, and I work in games now.
How did that happen?
So, yeah So like honestly, I I would start with finding a game accessibility community that it's easy for you to connect with whether it's finding people who are doing groups Meetups locally or whether it's joining something online like the game accessibility conference has an online discord I've been discord.
Yeah, it's just finding those things and then making the
the connections and you'll like again like there isn't a guide but like you'll start to see your path forward as you get more information so that's not very helpful but it's honest.
No but it's true too just to add sorry is that there's like also things like accessibility game jams are happening and stuff like that and so that's a fantastic way to start and I will always say this it's good to focus on accessibility but accessibility touches everything in games right that's what we've been talking about there's probably people here from every single
background, you know, doing different things in games.
And so the nice thing is to get into accessibility, no one's stopping you, right?
If you work in games, you can just do accessibility.
And I think that's the beauty of it, right?
And then as you fall in love with it, if you find that this is something I want to focus more and more on, then you can kind of start exploring the career paths for that.
I mean, that's basically, I was a game designer.
I mean, like, we just kind of all kind of fell more and more into this field in that way, so.
I wish there was like a manual.
I don't think any job has a manual in this industry.
But this one definitely doesn't.
Hi, I'm Frederic and I have a question for Morgane about the
Oops, sorry.
How about the trigger warning in this place?
How can you avoid spoilers with this?
Do you avoid spoilers in the trigger warnings in Dead Space?
Oh, that's a great question.
And I have to give the full-blown credit.
So for the trigger warnings in Dead Space, we call them content warnings.
Pick your tomato, tomato, right?
But the way we avoided that was we went through the entire script and the narrative team
went above and beyond to make sure that they wrote language that wouldn't necessarily spoil things.
If you've played Dead Space, you can imagine that there might be spoilers as you're saying certain things.
If you know the game, it kind of involves mental health at the end of the day.
And so it was completely on the narrative team, and they went through and did mitigation and went through different risks, looked through the actual language itself,
to make sure, is it telling the players what type of content?
And I talk about this in the GA conference, where a lot of the content warnings are grounded specifically in violence towards humans.
And so we made sure to write the warnings in a way that can convey that information quickly, one, but also make sure that it doesn't spoil anything else or kind of pull someone out of that immersion.
I give the full-blown credit to the narrative team for achieving that.
Okay, thank you.
Great question.
That was a hard one too, if you know the game.
Hi, I work for a platform which is mostly centered around user-created content.
Do you have any suggestions for how we can add accessibility but for
you know, UGC for things that are end user created.
Is it like mods?
Is it art?
Like, what's the content?
Sort of everything.
It's VR chat.
Oh, okay.
Well, I think the first thing is, so accessibility in any space is as much about culture change as it is about the actual technical or design implementations.
So, honestly, like, one of the first things that I would do is, because it's reliant on UGC, like, you cannot personally go in and verify every single piece of content to ever to be accessible.
That's just not feasible realistically.
Like, that does not scale.
And so, honestly, what I would start with would be having an educational moment or push for your platform
to do the education and training to give to your content creators so that they understand what it is and what it's important.
So the first step would be kind of creating that educational moment, but the second thing is you'll need to figure out some sort of rewards.
Like, if they have done it, how can you reward them?
So, like, one of the things that exists on not just Xbox but also PlayStation is our accessibility tags in the storefront.
So if you meet certain criteria, like your subtitles are the right size, the right contrast, etc, etc, you can get the subtitle tag in the storefront.
Having subtitles does not guarantee you the subtitle tag, because they have to be good subtitles to get the tag, right?
So, like, is there a way where you could kind of have some process that
Hey, if a developer has said, like, hey, we have done accessibility, is there a way that you can make their UGC more prominent?
Can you give it a higher rating?
I don't know enough about I get VR sick, so I don't really go into VR chat and that kind of thing.
That's kind of how SEO works for accessibility outside of games, right?
If you're adding all text, the SEO actually improves for it.
So you can think about it through that lens of rewarding.
I love that.
Rewarding the players for thinking about accessible design and those who are creating the content itself.
I don't want to spread misinformation, but I think Roblox might have a very similar system to this.
Oh, I think that's right.
I think they even had like, they put out guidelines too.
They actually know.
All I'm doing is subconsciously copying what Roblox did a couple of years ago.
Thank you.
We have time for one more question.
Hi, my name is Monica, and I will stab my eye.
I recently started a UI UX tech club, and I really want to include accessibility in the planning phase as opposed to the end.
But I have no idea at all about accessibility besides the link for the URL and adding ALT.
So I'm learning a lot, and I'm part of the video game development club at my school.
And I'm usually in some kind of leadership or game manager position.
And honestly, we're all learning, and there's not much time.
So I've experienced, at least in the game area, where accessibility's kind of just chopped off.
So I was thinking, and I heard that there's not really a manual, but I was thinking, are there some resources out there that are super bite-sized so we can focus on one aspect of accessibility?
Because we also kind of, not argue, but we're like, what about subtitles?
What about something else?
And I'm like, I don't know which one to pick.
So it's kind of hard.
Yeah, so there is a lot.
We've all been in accessibility for years, so what we would do would be different.
So I guess there's two things.
For each individual title, what you go to tackle will not be the same, because it is going to be dependent on your team size, your tech, what you've already done.
and what is the fastest, easiest, most bang for your buck is going to vary.
That being said, there are a bunch of guidelines that are publicly available, including the Xbox accessibility guidelines, but they are very, very dense.
So for me, an accessibility expert, those are really easy to work with, because I already have that background.
Something that may be more easy for you to consume is gameaccessibilityguidelines.com, and one of the things with that website is it's broken down into basic, intermediate, and advanced.
so that if you are brand new, you know kind of like, hey, these are some of the most important ones that you can start with and tackle those.
There is also some really great other things that Xbox has put out.
Transparency, I did not work on them, but the team of folks who did are fantastic, such as there's the...
Microsoft Gaming Accessibility Fundamentals training course, which is a learning course that you can take that will give you a lot of really great information.
There is also, everything has acronyms and I never remember any of them, and I feel really bad because Brandon's right back there and he would like actually know the names of these things.
But one is the person, there's one that has personas that like break down some common cons.
Oh, I'm off the hook!
Gaming Experience Disability Guide.
And there's also a great one on in-person events that Brandon actually wrote, but I would recommend all of those resources.
Thank you so much.
Yeah, thank you.
And I think with that, we're out of time.
They've opened the doors.
Thank you.
Don't forget to fill out your survey.
Fill out your survey!