On GDC Podcast Episode 6, we've got artist, designer, marketer, and brazen overachiever,
Gabby D'Arienzo. I almost messed that up, of Drinkbox Studios to talk art, creativity,
death, and more. Also stay tuned for exciting GDC 2020 news, including our
State of the Industry Report, and help us find out where Alyssa went, back in a sec.
Oh, hold on a second. Hey, cats!
Hey everybody, this is Chris Graft, Editor-in-Chief of Gamasutra, and I am here with not Alyssa
McElhune.
I'm here with Alex.
Alex, can you introduce yourself?
Hi, I'm Alex.
I'm not Alyssa McElhune, but for today at least, I'll do my best.
That's too much information.
So we're just going to leave it there.
So Alyssa isn't here.
Alex, we're privy to her whereabouts, aren't we?
Yeah, I think she's at lunch
No, no, she is in a high noise situation. Oh, right. Yeah. Yeah. No, that sounds rough
It's being recited. Hmm
Yeah, it's you can't really do that when there's hammers, uh, just burying themselves into
the side of your building.
You can't really podcast.
Yeah.
And you could if it was like the, this old house podcast.
I mean, well, if she could be podcasting, then why, what are we doing here?
I would much rather hear her side of the story.
I'd much rather hear a podcast from deep within the bunker that is Alyssa McAloon's apartment.
Yeah, just the hammering and the jackhammering, the scraping, all the ambient sounds of a
house being sited.
That's what we should move GDC next year.
GDC 2020.
That's the segue.
You mentioned GDC.
GDC 2020 is coming up.
That's taking place March 16th to 20th.
Registration is open at gdconf.com.
That's like, it's now...
Two podcasts away one podcast away. Yeah, man. How you feeling about it? I feel like she's gonna be pretty solid this year
We just pronounced the death stranding talk. We got a bunch of other cool stuff coming up. I'm like i'm starting to warm up to this year's
uh
Smorgasbord of content on offer. Yeah, you've really been using the word smorgasbord a lot like lately and I approve
I'm swedish
I didn't realize that was a Swedish thing.
Yeah, man.
I'm very US-centric here.
Yeah, and it's not only any Death Stranding talk.
It's Hideo Kojima.
He's going to be talking about the game where
you deliver the packages.
About strands, about strand games.
He's going to talk about themes of connection,
how to express that through game design.
It's going to be a banger, I tell you what.
So don't miss it.
It's also gonna be about death, which is what we're gonna talk about
kind of in this podcast too.
We'll mention death.
We won't dwell on it.
I mean, we might, I don't know.
About 40 minutes into every podcast.
If you're a frequent listener, you know, that things get super existential.
Really?
Yeah, it does.
Alex hasn't listened to any of the podcasts yet, but that's okay.
I'll prepare accordingly.
There's also going to be a talk about the level design of outer wilds.
Oh, right.
Yeah, that's really cool.
That game, man. That game's something else.
It is something else.
There's also the Goose game.
That's going to be...
There's going to be talk on the Goose game.
Oh, yeah. So something I didn't know,
and I don't know if anybody listening knows this.
When you go check out our talk on the Level Design Summit
about Untitled Goose Game,
it's about how they scouted the locations
using like film scouting techniques.
It's really fascinating. I can't wait to see it.
Yeah.
I wonder if they brought a goose to the scouting locations and just kind
of let it do whatever it wants.
And, you know, they probably got a goose to do the scouting.
Honestly, I would know.
Does the goose like this farm area?
Honk once for yes.
In my experience, geese don't really like anything.
Yeah, they don't. It's true.
Also, we did announce the nominees for the Game Developers Choice Awards.
Oh, right, yeah.
Yeah, Death Stranding is leading that.
And then there's also the finalists for the Independent Games Festival Awards.
And you can see all those on, I guess, I don't have the, I have the URL in front of me, but I'm not going to read it out.
No.
But you can Google it.
It's more fun, it's a game, to go find it for yourself.
It is.
Oh yeah, so...
I might also be in show notes too, no promises.
We do have a guest, though, now that we got all the morning announcements out of the way.
She's lurking in the background currently.
As of now, currently, she is the art director of the Toronto-based Drinkbox Studios, which
you might know from Guacamelee!, is one of the games they did.
She was previously art director and co-founder of Laundry Bear Games, where she worked on the IGF finalist Amortition's Tale.
Death.
Her credits also include Super Crush, KO, Parkitect, and the wonderful Celeste.
She has spoken at GDC in the past, and is also speaking this year.
at GDC 2020. 2019 Forbes 30 under 30. That's awesome. And she's an advocate for, and she's
a helpful voice within the game dev community. She's a kind of a, just a really supportive
person and advocate. It's great. So let's please welcome Gabby Darienzo. Hey, Gabby.
Hey, thanks for having me. Yeah, thanks for joining us.
You were on mute a second ago because I think your cat was having a conniption.
Yeah, he's still, he's still meowing.
So if you hear any kind of like high pitched mews, that's, that is me.
Yeah.
We're all about the high pitched mews here on the podcast.
So can you, can you tell us a little bit about your background in art and just as an artist
in general?
Sure. So my background is actually in graphic design. That's what I studied in school.
So I kind of like tangentially got into video games. After I graduated school,
I started working on the marketing team for a local game studio here in Toronto,
which is where I'm from. And when I was working on the marketing team for a little bit,
Eventually they moved me over to the game side, so doing art and UI UX design for the game side of
the team. And around that time, I also started to get more involved with the indie scene,
both here in Toronto and also just online, starting to go to events and stuff, and taught myself how
to use Unity and started teaching myself how to make my own games and how to do 3D modeling and
blah, blah, blah, blah.
And you know, I started getting a lot of people who
Reached out asking me to do some freelance work for them. So I left my full-time job at that studio and
started freelancing and
Freelanced for like four and a half years
yeah, and got to work on some really cool projects like Celeste and Parkitect and like you mentioned and
Also, within that four and a half years, I co-founded my own studio, Laundryware Games,
which is a studio I founded with my partner, Andrew Carvalho.
We got to make A Mortician's Tale, which is like my baby.
And so we made that together.
And then...
Yeah, I guess back last September, so like four months ago, however long it's been,
the people at Drinkbox offered me a job. And that's like, I've wanted to work with them for
so long because they work on such cool projects. I'm such a huge fan of Guacamelee and Severed,
which are also really big games about death. That's like a topic I'm very into. And so
they reached out, they offered me a job. And so I'm working with them now,
which is really exciting. So that's kind of my background and how I got into games.
We're going to hit like every single one of those things that you talked about.
Yeah, let's do it.
Now, let's let's start with being an art director at Drinkbox.
I'm not an art director at Drinkbox.
I'm just like a senior artist.
OK, sorry.
That's all good. Don't worry.
Senior artist. Yeah.
Well, we like to give promotions away here.
Nice. On the podcast.
That's official.
Yeah. So what does it mean to be a senior, like artist there?
Yeah, so the art team at Drinkbox is only like four people. And so it's really exciting to be
a part of them. For the longest time while I was freelancing and even at Laundry Bear,
I was often the art director on a bunch of different projects, or not even art director,
but only like the sole artist on a lot of projects. And so it's been a while since I've
gone to work with a team that's like over two people. And so working with Drinkbox is really
fun because I...
I obviously am a big fan of their games, I'm a big fan of their artwork, and so being able to work
with other artists, especially like an existing art director who's been doing art direction for
their games for years, is really exciting because I get to kind of, you know, take a step back from
art direction and really learn from them. And I've already, it's only been a few months, and I get to
learn so much from them. And so it's been a really, really, really, really good experience. And it's
great too because one of my biggest fears about taking the job with them was like, oh, I'm going
from...
being an art director to being just like, you know,
like a regular artist and am I gonna hate that? Is that gonna...
Am I not gonna be able to make decisions and stuff?
But the folks at Drinkbox are so lovely and my experiences are taken so seriously
and they listen to me a lot and I get to make a lot of decisions. So yeah, it's really it's really cool.
Yeah, so I think the term senior artist maybe is a bit confusing.
to some people, but basically I get to do a lot of art and UI and marketing and
just a whole bunch of stuff at Drinkbox. That's kind of what my role is now, yeah.
I actually, this is, I'm so curious.
I was talking about this with someone else recently this weekend.
Um, and I don't know if you can speak to this, but you just joined and sounds
like you're really enjoying and feeling comfortable there and learning a lot.
Um, can you speak to the onboarding process and what it was like to join up
with a, with an established studio after sort of doing your own thing for so long?
I talked to a lot of devs who are either really excited or really, really nervous.
About joining a big studio after they've been working on their own for a while.
And I never really know what to tell them because I've never done it myself.
So I'm curious, like, what was the experience like for you?
Yeah, it definitely was a little bit nerve wracking, especially
going from working at like a two person studio and freelancing
on a lot of really small teams, right? Like the Celeste team was
only like six people and Super Crush is only like three or four
people like it's very, very small. And so Drinkbox is about
13 people, which isn't drastically bigger, but it is,
you know, like they have their own processes and they have
You know an existing team making existing games. So it was a bit nerve-wracking
But it was quite smooth, right? They're really good about their they they're really really organized and have a really good production pilot pipeline
so coming into the onto the team, it was like
You know, they showed me their tools. They got me on boarded onto the art
I'm pretty one of my favorite things to do and the reason why I love working in indie games, especially is
I really love stylized art and kind of adapting to other people's styles.
And so the games we're working on right now have two new styles that I'm not super used
to working on, and I'm really, really, really excited to be able to make art for them and
adapt to them.
Yeah, I don't know.
It was pretty smooth, is basically what I'm trying to say.
That was a long answer.
But it was a pretty smooth onboarding process.
And yeah, it didn't take very long for me to feel very comfortable.
And I think probably the weirdest thing is like having a schedule and routine again.
Because when you're freelancing for so long, it's like, oh, yeah, I can wake up whenever
I want.
And I can like work out of a coffee shop, you know, like, you get very used to running
your own schedule and doing your own thing.
And when you work at a studio, you know, they have their own like, eight to four, nine to
five.
And you're like, Oh, yeah, okay, I got it.
Like, I got it.
So yeah.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Thank you.
I gotta be there on a certain time and get things done, which is probably a good thing, I think.
I think it really is. I thrive underneath schedules, and so it's kind of nice to have
that again after so many years of not having that. I think a lot of creative people are like that,
which is what I kind of want to talk about. It's interesting. You went from
full-time studio, and then you did freelance for a number of years, and then now you're going back.
Can you tell me what it was like, you know, that life as an artist that is taking contract work,
what are some of the ways that you, for people who are out there here either trying to break
into freelancing or current freelancers who want to stay freelancers and even those freelancers
who want to maybe pivot into full-time, can you talk about your experiences as a freelancer?
What are some of the ways?
that you survived that kind of life and how did you end up leveraging that into a full-time position?
Yeah, I think the biggest thing is, a lot of people don't think about this when they want to
do freelance, but it's like 20% just admin and accounting, right? You're not just doing 100%
of the time doing fun art or game design or programming or writing or whatever it is that
you're doing freelance. It's like, you have to, you're basically running a business. And so a lot
of your time is spent responding to emails and doing accounting. But it's also things like self
marketing. You know, like
putting yourself out there on social media, going to events, making sure your portfolio is always
stocked with pieces, and if you have a slow period with work, making sure that you use that time to
find more work or fill your portfolio with pieces that will help you get more work. It's like,
it's a lot of that kind of stuff. And I think if you are a person who is maybe not keen on that,
then freelancing might not be a thing you're interested in doing. But I love that stuff.
I love marketing. I love running business. This is one of the things I enjoyed about running
Laundry Bear as well. And so for me, it was like a lot of that kind of stuff. And so I think a lot
of it too is like networking. I hate the term networking. It feels really business professional
and that seems like such a contrast to what we do in games. But
Essentially, just like making friends, you know, going to events and being social on
the internet and just making friends.
And then when people are like, oh, you know, we need an extra artist on a thing, or we
need to hire someone to do a logo, they think of you.
And that's like how I got a lot of my work when I was freelancing.
That's how I started working with...
I became friends with the Celeste developers long, long, long time ago when they were working
on Towerfall.
And so when they were looking for another artist, they were like, oh, yeah, Gabby, let's
just hire her.
So I think...
Anybody who's interested in freelancing, that's a big thing I recommend, is just making
friends, just getting friendly.
You don't have to go to events and shove business cards at people necessarily.
I advise against that probably, but just making friends and putting yourself out there goes
a long way if that's something you're comfortable with doing.
I think just the experience of making so much art.
both professionally, like, both from freelance projects
and also just on the side doing my own thing,
that helped really build up my portfolio.
And, you know, it's full of a lot of really impressive games
and impressive pieces that really, really helped me
get this job at Drinkbox, and I think would help.
I think that that was a big thing that, like,
would probably help a lot of artists
if they're looking to exit freelance life,
is just, you know, building up your portfolio.
Do you think that in particularly like the indie deaf community, and this is why I respect
what you're doing, like when I was internet stalking you for research for this, like one
of the, you know, you're known as an artist.
But I think like one of the first, if not the first result from you was a video of a talk that you gave at an indie conference about marketing, about Amor Mortician Stalin, about niche marketing.
Yeah. That was for Full Indie Summit, I think, two years ago, last year, which is like an event
based in Vancouver. And that's like not a thing that like I do professionally. Like I would never
you know, choose to work somewhere as like a marketer per se,
or freelance marketing. Like I don't think...
That is the thing that I am best at and or want to do full-time.
But I think a lot of it comes from my background in graphic design and marketing,
and my first job was in marketing for games as well.
It kind of just, like, it ingrains things in you that you can't help but think about.
And when you are self-marketing yourself as a freelancer,
but also running your own business and making your own indie games,
I think that's a huge part of it.
Something that people don't really think about is...
marketing yourself.
I know I listened to one of your episodes,
was it
Hannah Flynn?
I listened to that today about marketing
and I was just nodding my head vigorously
like, yes, yes, excellent.
And a lot of the stuff that she told us about marketing for, Hannah Flynn is a marketing
director at Failed Better Games.
They did Sunless Skies for people who don't know.
But one of the things that the good marketers with successful games, they say, market early.
Like, start right from the top.
Tell us a little bit about that and how you did that with The Mortician's Tale.
Yeah, so Mortician's Tale was a game that I started thinking about back in like 2015.
And it was just like an idea. And you know, this is subject matter that's like,
very close to me and a thing I'm really interested in. And so I remember right
from the beginning when I started to prototype things.
And started to share it on the internet
and share it with people.
And started to get some kind of interest and traction.
And you're a funeral director in this game, right?
Oh, yeah.
Sorry, I guess I should explain what the game is.
Sure, yeah.
So for anybody who hasn't played A Mortician's Tale,
it is a 3D narrative driven game where
you play as a mortician running a funeral home.
It sounds really gloomy and doomy,
but it's actually quite soft and very, very
sensitive.
brightly colored and you know you kind of it's it's very short but you kind of
go through the story of the funeral home and how it evolves over time and you
also get to see kind of the stories between each of the different the bodies
you take care of we released that back in like 2017
and it won a bunch of awards and was nominated for an IGF award. I did a GDC talk about it,
and it was a really, really cool thing to see people excited about this game.
And so, yeah, I started prototyping Mortician's Tale back in 2015.
And yeah, basically, as soon as people started getting interested in it, it was like, okay, yeah, this is like a real thing that we should actually do.
And as soon as my my co founder, and I decided to make it our thing, like a thing we're going to make.
That's when I started to think about marketing.
And that seems like really early for a lot of people, a lot of people when you say that to them, they're like,
really right at the beginning, that's so early though. And also for a game that is so niche and
so small and so indie, that seems like a really weird thing to think about. But I think it's
such an important thing to kind of consider when you're doing your market research, is also like,
okay, well, you know, how are we going to talk about this game? What is our audience? How are
we going to reach them? And that was a thing that we didn't have the budget for.
the capabilities of hiring someone to do this for us. And
so I did it myself was, you know, I did all the marketing,
I did all the social media, we went to events ourselves, we got
a little bit of help at the very, very, very end, like, a
month before we launched the game, just with PR stuff, just
like getting someone who has more experience with that to
help us reach out to people that we didn't have context for. But
yeah, 95% of the marketing was was me. And I think that that's
like, you know, a big thing I bring to
A big thing I'm excited to bring as well to Drinkbox as well is like, you know, I started
working with them and I started doing art with them.
And then they were also like, oh, you have a bit of a marketing experience.
And I was like, sure do.
So it's kind of fun to be able to bring that to them as well.
And it's a big like fun part of being an indie developer as opposed to working AAA is like
being able to wear multiple hats and really enjoying that process.
I think also there's a certain amount of, at least from the des I speak to, who, who
talk about, you know, starting in a project early.
If you commit to marketing yourself and thinking about your demographics and getting the word
out there and announcing your project almost, you know, from that first month, then you
commit to finishing the project.
And that's hard for some people.
Yeah, that's, that's totally fair.
Yeah.
So kind of segueing back to the artist side of you.
Kind of a general question, but I'm curious,
what is a good productive day for you
as someone who makes art?
What does that look like?
Uh, let's see. That's an interesting question. Definitely like the way I like to start my day
is, and I don't know if everybody does this, but I like doing it, is I get to my desk at work,
I like make a tea, and then I have a bunch of websites I go through.
only for like five or ten minutes, like it's a very, very short part of my day.
And I just like look through inspiration. And even if that inspiration's not like directly
tied to the games we're making, it's just kind of a good way to fill yourself with creative
inspiration, but also kind of just like, see what's out there and kind of like,
slowly but surely pick up on trends. Whether it's not even just like from games and game art,
it's also things like...
I look at architecture blogs, I look at graphic design blogs,
and I look at like packaging design and like, you know,
like painting and 3d modeling and things that are not really
related to what we're doing. And it's just like a really good
way fashion, blah, blah, blah. I don't know, it's a kind of good
way to start my day. And it like, it helps me feel super
inspired. And also helps me get motivated to be productive. And
it's also like, yeah, like I said, like
a good way to keep on top of trends and get some ideas for making some interesting game art.
And so I think that a good productive day for me starts with that. And if I don't get that in,
I find that I don't do as well. It's nice to be surrounded by that stuff. And then,
yeah, being able to just like...
go into work and again I think having a team of people of other artists is has been so excellent
for my my mental health especially as an artist it's just like having people that you can kind
of bounce ideas off of and just kind of um brainstorm things with is is really nice and
it's been a while since I've had other artists to do that with professionally and freelance it's
like in whatever discipline you're in it's kind of a solo thing a lot of the time isn't it
Yeah, and I have other collaborators I work with, and on Super Crush I had a little bit of an art
team, like a small art team. So that was great that I could have other people I could talk to
about things, but largely, especially as an art director, a lot of the pressure falls onto you
to make those decisions. And so oftentimes it was like, oh god, I don't have anybody to talk to
about this. And so having a team that I can talk to about these things is really nice. It's really,
really good to be able to be like.
I'm thinking about this. What do you guys think?" And have people to be like yes or
no about things. It's good.
So we asked about how you start your day and we should ask, do you have any trouble ending
your day and do you have any ways in which you sort of work through the process of leaving
your work at work and sort of moving on and going home?
That's a good question. I think that's something that I used to be really bad about,
especially freelancing. And I think a lot of freelancers have this problem. Oh, there's a cat.
Hello. Sorry, just jumped into my lap. When I was freelancing, I had a big problem with
working too much.
And this is gonna be a big thing I talk about in my GDC talk, which is about like burnout
and creative block.
But when I, especially when I first started freelance, it was almost like a badge of honor
to work too hard, you know, like, oh, I worked so hard today that I forgot to eat some meals
or I worked so hard today, I didn't look at the clock and now it's 11pm.
And I remember feeling so proud of myself for like,
oh, I worked really hard today.
And years of doing that kind of slowly burns you out
and also kind of ruins your work-life balance
because you get home and you're like,
oh, the grocery stores are closed.
I guess I'll just eat whatever.
Or you're like, oh, well.
you have a hard time like decompressing and getting to bed because you're still thinking
about work because you've been working all day and you have to get up in like six hours to get
back at it again and like I don't know I used to be really bad about that I know a lot of people
a lot of like not even just artists but also programmers and writers and designers who are
just as bad about that kind of stuff and I think
Certainly, working at a studio that has a rigorous 9 to 5 makes it a lot easier.
Because it's like, okay, well I have to get this work done.
And at 5pm, we all gotta leave the office.
And it's like, okay, it's a good way for me to like...
Yeah.
A good excuse for me to walk home and that walk home.
And do a podcast.
And like just, yeah, like just kind of stop thinking about the work you've been doing.
And then like, you know, get home and don't jump on other projects, which I used to do a lot.
Sorry, I cut you off.
What's up?
No, no, no, I'm cutting you off, sorry.
I'm just saying, because everything that you're describing right now, like, uh,
you know, I, I freelance did contract, uh, writing for, uh, you know, for game
business sites for like four and a half years or five years or something.
I don't know a single person who freelances anything that has good work
life balance or had good work life balance while they were freelancing.
Right.
because it is just a thing where you're at home, you never leave work, and you find excuses
and reasons to keep on going, or, you know, like what you were saying, it's like you also
have that badge of honor thing going on, which is twisted.
So once I, you know.
I think that's very encouraging that Drinkbox is a studio that says, you know, five o'clock
and that's it.
I think that's how places should be because otherwise, you know, people can say, oh, we
don't force, you know, crunch.
We don't force crunch.
But they also don't have management that tells people, go home now or you're over hours now.
You have to go home.
And that's the kind, I mean, that's management support is what you have.
That's great.
Yes, 100%. That's like, yeah, the big thing that Drinkbox seems to be very aware of and
very good about. And it's excellent. It's Yeah, it seems like everybody there has really,
really good work life balance. And that's something that I really appreciate. In general,
but also for everybody else I work with. And as like a studio setting an example for other
studios, it's it's really important. And I'm Yeah, should be standard across. Yeah, everywhere.
But you know, that's, that's like a bigger issue.
Like with burnout then while we're on this topic now
You know
I guess I'm wondering how you would recognize that in yourself in that moment, because you
said that you were burnt out for like a year or you were just like had creative block.
I'm wondering what are the signs, were you able to look back at that retrospectively
and say, these were signs that I couldn't recognize in the moment?
Oh, yeah, 100%. It's, it's really easy for me to look back
at now and be like, Oh, yeah, that that is a sign, but at the
time, no idea. And like, I think a lot of it was, you know, like,
so just to kind of give some context, I'll talk about this a
little bit in my GDC talk, but I'm happy to talk about it now
just to kind of give some context. But basically, after I
after we shipped a mortician's tale, which is a very personal
game, we worked on it really, really hard for a long time.
I got really, I felt like super burnt out and just like unmotivated.
And I think a lot of that wasn't to do with the project, but it was because I was doing
art direction on two new projects.
So one of them was Super Crush KO, and one of them is a project I was working on with
my studio Laundry Bear.
And I think art directing on two game projects.
pretty much more than full time, because I was splitting like seven days, not five days.
I think A, that's a lot of work to be doing, but B, you're kind of, you're shifting your brain
around so much, right? Because you're doing, it isn't like you're like, there's an existing
art style that you're hitting and you're like, okay, on these three days,
I'm going to do 3D art. On these two days, I'm going to do 2D art.
it isn't like that. It's more like, okay, I have to think of and be in the creative headspace and
concept art for one game and come up with ideas for one game and do the same thing but completely
different on another side. And that's, I think, creative work. I think any work in general,
there's only so much you can do before you get burnt out, but I think especially creative work,
whether it's art or writing or whatever, just like thinking of concepts for games even.
I think is especially tiring to like have to context switch constantly
Yeah
And I think that burnt me out and it wasn't you know
The people I was working with the team behind super crush ko and also my co-founder
Neither of them were pushing me to do this
This was just entirely self-imposed and I think a lot of it was like I was getting very in hindsight. It's very clear
I was getting very
frustrated and
just was making a lot of really bad decisions. And I think a lot of it was I felt the pressure
to like, I have to get it right. I don't have time to concept and think of ideas. I just have
to get it right immediately. And we know that that's not the way that anything works. There's
the, you know, games especially are very iterative process. They change so much,
they evolve so much over the development.
And setting up this expectation to get it perfect the first time, not realistic.
And I think I was pushing myself to do it, not just for one game, but two games.
And that really messed me up.
Because I was like, if I don't get it right, if this art isn't
completely unique, then these games won't sell and these
companies will go under and blah, blah, blah. That sounds
really like that sounds so bizarre and so like, huge, but
that's kind of a lot. And when I talked to a lot of game
developers, that's kind of how they feel. And I think a lot of
it is just like the indie space in general is, you know, it's
very, there's a lot going on right now. And I think a lot of
people are just kind of panicking. So that panic on top
of
thinking about art, also, you know, working on two things at once, and just coming off of a game
that was very personal, I think they just kind of all added up to this burnout. And I think a lot
of the signs, in general, are things like, yeah, just feeling really frustrated, feeling really
unmotivated. I just like didn't want to, I didn't want to work on these games at all. And I was
really excited, you know, in my headspace, I was very excited about these two projects, but like,
when it came down to sitting down and doing the work,
I just didn't want to do it.
I just could not push myself to do it.
And it's also things like I got really defensive.
I was very defensive about my own art,
which is something that I'm embarrassed to talk about,
embarrassed to admit,
but I think it's important to kind of speak about
because I see a lot of other artists go through
the same thing where, you know,
I was very defensive about like, you know,
my co-founder would be like,
oh, I think this art would be good.
And I'd be like, what?
Like, what's wrong with my art?
Or like on Super Crush I would make a really weird decision and
Mobine Vickery who's the lead designer and the
Programmer and like the owner of Vertex Pop who makes Super Crush
He would be like, oh, here's a critique of a thing. I would get very defensive about it
and that's like a very clear sign if you're a person who you think that you might be burning like burnt out or
you know someone who might be burnt out, I think that's a huge sign. Is someone just getting very,
very defensive about the work that they're doing, right? And I think a lot of it too was just like,
it was bleeding into my personal life as well. Like I was getting really, I was exhausted all
the time and like just so stressed and having a really hard time decompressing. Like it's just,
I think burnout, I don't, I don't mean to like go on and on about this because it's pretty sad.
it's such a big deal. And I think it's it's something, you know, when we think about burnout,
when we hear the term burnout, especially in games, we often think about, you know, AAA,
big studios forcing their their employees to work. We think about I think about like Rockstar,
that marketing pitch where they were that article that was like, Oh, yeah, our employees are
working hundreds of hours to get Red Dead done. Like that's what you think about when you hear
burnout. But I think
a lot of people, especially indie devs, we really have to consider that a lot of it is
self-imposed, right? We're putting it on ourselves without even realizing it. And I think, was
it GDC that did, I think, the state of the industry report?
Yeah.
Right? I think you guys were talking about that earlier.
Yeah, I was about to say.
One of the things, yeah, one of the things that was mentioned in there was like, was
talking about crunch and burnout. And if you feel, I think that I can't remember what the
exact wording was, but it was something about like...
why you feel the need to crunch. And very, very small amount of it was like, someone's forcing me
to and the very, very large amount was either like, it's self imposed, like, I feel like I need to,
or I wear it as a badge of honor. Like, I think a lot of me that's not entirely indie devs,
I could be triple A devs too, right? But I know a lot of indie devs that just like,
either they don't notice that they're doing it, or they do it because they think it's like,
you know, you can't be indie unless you work.
16 hour days and that's just not true.
And there's so much more.
I mean, you've talked about it,
but like it is what you face in AAA and then some,
because so often you are the whole company.
You are, I mean, the, you know,
you live or die based on how, what your game sells.
And so like, absolutely.
It is a culture of rife with overwork
and with pressure to overwork.
Do you think there's anything you could have done differently
during the period you were burning out
to sort of avert that or stave it off?
I definitely think there are some things in hindsight that I could have done sooner.
Luckily, I was able to kind of, I think the burnout lasted way too long.
And that kind of sucks in hindsight.
I feel like I wasted a lot of time.
But there were some things that I was able to kind of
Do and get support in that really helped and that kind of helped me overcome my burnout
I think my only regret is I didn't do them or didn't know about them sooner. And
Again, this is a big thing. I'll talk a lot about in my GDC talk
But a few of the things were things like, you know
Admitting that I needed help and admitting that I wasn't feeling like motivated or excited to work on things
right and I think as soon as you're able to admit like I'm not having fun doing this and
your colleagues, your co-workers, whoever you're working with can kind of help you, you know? Like
it's not... I don't have too much pride to ask for help or wait, I do have too much pride? I don't.
It's very easy for me to ask for help. And so, you know, that was a big thing that happened on
Super Crush was Mo, again, the designer, the programmer, he saw that I was really like frustrated
and getting defensive and kind of struggling with coming up with art.
And this was pretty early on in the development of Super Crush.
And so, and he was like, okay, you know what?
Take like a couple of weeks and just walk away from this.
Don't try to hit what we're doing here.
Just kind of like, come up with what you like.
Just just kind of do what you want.
Like, do your own thing and come up with an art that you want to come up with.
The context here is that I was having a really hard time coming up with a style for the game.
And it was like...
it wasn't bad, necessarily, the things I was coming up with, but they were very safe.
Like, I think I was falling into some, again, some of that pressure to like,
oh, I just need to be different. We need to be different. We need to have a different art style.
And subsequently, I wasn't really making any good decisions. I was just kind of making safe decisions.
And so as soon as I was able to kind of walk away from the project and just like...
take a mental break from the game and just kind of like look at art for art's sake and start
concepting things for fun. That's when I was able to kind of bring in some colorful palettes,
bring in some interesting character ideas, and that's like really where the art for Super Crush
came in. And that was like, again, just having Mo be able to be patient enough and have the
bandwidth to just give me that few weeks to do that.
That was tremendous.
That helped out a lot.
I think things too, like, and this is a thing I didn't learn about until a couple
months ago when I started working at Drinkbox, but the concept lead at
Drinkbox, Augusto Keano, or Kusho, he is an incredible concept artist and he
came up with the concepts for both Guacamelee and Severed, right?
And something that he said to me, kind of offhandedly one day, was like,
oh, you can't be too precious about your concept art. That's what he said.
And I think it was just in response to me being like, oh, I'm not very good at concept art.
And he said, yeah, well, you know, it's one of those processes you can't be too precious about.
And that stuck with me so much because I was like, oh, no, you're right.
I have this whole tendency to be like, I have to get it right the first time.
That completely negates what the whole process of concept art is for, right?
Concept art.
I don't know what the writing equivalent is or what the programming equivalent is, but
concept art is basically just like sketching out as many ideas as you possibly can.
Doesn't matter if they work, doesn't matter if it makes sense, you just do it.
And when you do that, when you just let your brain kind of go into this creative flow and
think of ideas, you're going to have some good ideas.
And it also kind of gives you, again, working with a team of people, it's really easy to
kind of give them concepts and have...
other people say, hey, I really like the direction you're going in here.
And that kind of opens up the ability to do even more stuff like that.
And so I kind of, I really love that.
It's definitely made making concept art a lot more fun and a lot easier.
And that's the way it should be.
I really wish I had heard that, you know,
when we were starting to concept stuff for Super Crash,
because I feel like that would have made things.
just more fun and more easy and breezy and just, you know, would have would have given me more
motivation to actually do the thing. Yeah. I wonder, it sounds like you're, you're deeply
passionate, not just about the work you do, but about improving that work and learning new ways
to do it. Is there any kind of advice you would give, you know, fellow game artists who are
looking to improve their artistry on sort of what you can do? And what do you do like on a regular
basis to try and get better, you know, like broaden your skill set?
Yeah, it's a great question. I think part of it is just doing
it as often as you can doing anything as often as you can,
right? And that's that that sounds really simple and easy to
do. But you know, when you have a full time job and hobbies and
groceries and like errands, you get a run sometimes that that
space fills up.
But just making a little bit of time every day to just draw a little bit or model a little
bit or write a little bit or whatever, whatever it is that you do, just doing a little bit
of it every day or every other day, really that practice adds up.
And I, last year, my partner bought me an iPad Pro.
So I had like the Procreate and a pencil.
And I noticed that I started drawing way more often.
And when I look at my art
and how it's evolved over the last year,
it's the difference in my skillset is way bigger
than it was the previous years before that,
because I wasn't doing any of that stuff, right?
And so I think just like daily practice is a really really important thing.
But I think part of it too is also just like, you know, making the effort and the time to to learn new things and learn new skills.
And very fortunately we live in a time where.
Whoa, hold on one second.
Hey, cats!
Oh my god, stop.
Oh, buddy.
Everyone okay?
We live in a time.
You guys hear that?
Oh, just a little bit, yeah.
Oh my god.
I have two cats.
We're gonna turn the volume up on that in the final edit.
Great, really good.
Talking about inner conflict, you just have the two cats fighting over me in the background.
Yeah, creative block is really hard.
Interesting analogy, cats.
Jeez. God, what were we talking about? Talking about art. Oh yeah, just like, we live in a great
time of everything's on the internet, you know what I mean? And so if you're like, oh, I really,
I really want to improve my skills in 3D, you can, because there's so many tutorials and so
many resources and Blender is free and Unity is free. Like, there's so many things you can do to
just learn. I think a lot of it is just committing to putting the time into doing that, you know? And
I don't know, I think a big thing too, and this is like, this might sound kind of out
of left field, but I think a thing that's really helped me is finding hobbies and interests
that are not related to games and art.
Sorry, I'm laughing at my cat.
No, it's great.
I love it.
I don't even notice anymore.
There's a whole drama going on back there.
It's because I'm sitting at a microphone and not paying attention to them.
So they're like, we got to cause trouble.
Jesus.
Yeah, I think getting into hobbies.
can really like things that are not related to games, right?
And this is what I talked about earlier about getting
into the office every day and looking through art blogs
and architecture blogs and giving you
ideas of things that are outside of games is a really good idea.
But I think also your personal hobbies and interests,
it helps a lot when they're not connected to games.
Because I think if you're a person who is only
interested in video games, it really
narrows what your...
what your kind of like creative capabilities are, right? If you're only
ever looking at what games are doing, you're not seeing what like, animation
or film or comics are doing. And so I think just like, having interests that
are not games is really important. And that can be anything that can be sports.
It doesn't have to be visual, it doesn't have to be like writing related or
whatever you do, it could just be like, you know, it could be pottery, it could
be woodworking, it could be
Going for runs just anything that is outside will ultimately like let you have that creative freedom to just like
Do something that is different and also I think probably give you the headspace that you need to kind of get away from work
You know, right when you're not thinking about work
It's kind of a rest like resting your muscles that you can get back to work and really yeah
I mean, that's what you said, you said that scent would sound out of left field, but,
you know, I, I hear game developers, mostly the ones who make really interesting stuff,
say the same thing, but you know, there, there was definitely a time where, you
know, everything is like military shooter type thing.
And it's like, okay, this game was definitely made by a gamer, you know?
And it's kind of like, after a few decades, um, people kind of want something.
new, you know. So I think that's totally great. Such as, like, if we can get back to Mortician's
Tale, because we're kind of winding down here, but I want to talk about that real quick. And
why is it that we talk about interests outside of games, death positivity and commentary on that.
It's not exactly, you know, you know, Halo.
But where did that come from?
And why is death positivity important to you?
And what's the death thing with Gabby?
So for anyone who doesn't know what that is,
death positivity is basically similar to sex positivity,
I guess.
The idea that if we talk about a taboo thing,
it makes it less taboo.
And when we make things less taboo,
we're able to have really open and honest conversations
about those things.
So yeah.
For me, death positivity is really important because it allows you to kind of like be more
aware of what is going on in that industry and what's going to happen to us and our loved ones
when we die. And that sounds really like super goth and very sad. But for me, the importance
of it is when you are able to kind of be open to talking about that kind of stuff,
you can make really important decisions for yourself and for others.
And that's always been, not always, but a thing I've been really interested in for a long time.
And I have a few friends who are morticians, which is hilarious that I just kind of draw
that crowd. I don't know. I have no idea. I'm not a goth, but...
I was gonna say, you don't seem goth, the stereotypical goth.
No, not at all. I think I'm just like, deep down inside, maybe there's something about me that...
But I think this has been a thing I've always been interested in. And I think just
their jobs are so fascinating and so beautiful. A lot of their work has nothing to do with, you
know, the taking care of dead bodies. It's also about supporting people and having empathy for
people and...
And I just think that's a really, really fascinating thing, and that's kind of what got me interested
in the subject matter, and what kind of inspired me to make this game about it.
But also, you know, I had a podcast for a little while about death in video games, kind
of my two worlds colliding.
And also a big reason why I wanted to work for Drinkbox is because their games are so death positive, right?
Like Guacamelee! is such a beautiful, beautiful game.
And Severed is one of my favorite games ever.
It really subverts the expectations of what it means to kind of collect things.
And I don't know, it's just like...
Yeah.
What did you notice about death, like in video games,
and how, like, give us a little, like,
taste of what we would hear on your podcast about death
in video games.
Because I'm interested, like, there's,
I'm sure there's, you've probably
found a lot of stuff to say about it.
There's a lot of death in video games.
There sure is. And I think a lot of it too, I don't really have anything all that profound to say about it. But a lot of it is, you can really tell when someone has experienced a loss in their life, or whose culture is a lot more open to talking about death and loss and grief. Because when I interview someone like I did, like a long time ago, before I was working at Drinkbox, I interviewed Kousho Kiyono, again, who's the
the concept lead at Drinkbox. And he talked about Guacamelee and Mexican culture and folklore
as a person who's from Mexico. And you can really tell that this is a subject matter that he's
comfortable with. And a lot of the people I talk to my podcast, you know, the team behind Edith
Finch, like very, obviously very, very, very comfortable with talking about it. And you can
really see that in their games.
is they don't shy away from it, they're really open,
death is often very beautifully showcased.
Whereas there's been a few developers, and I won't say who they are,
but when I talk to them about death, it's very clearly like,
ah yes, it is a thing that happens, and we've put it in our game
mechanically for these reasons. They very clearly don't have
that experience, and maybe don't have that comfort
with the subject matter. And that's fascinating to me.
And I'll never call them out on it, because it's totally understandable to feel that way.
Especially like...
in Western culture, we're really, really quiet about that kind of stuff.
And we don't talk about it as much. But it's so fascinating to see, you know,
like the personal stuff behind each game. And you know, like, I would love to, and I don't do the
podcast anymore. But I really wanted to talk to the Outer Wilds team, because that game is like,
they do such cool things with death, right? And I really want to like,
just speak with them about it and their experiences with it. Because I get the
impression that at least one person on that team has some really
like you know have some experience with that and that's really fascinating to me so time to
relaunch the podcast yeah i'll listen to it coincidentally and uh you know not to totally
get off of video games here but like coincidentally this morning i was listening to uh i think it was
like this american life and it was about uh the whole episode was about digging and like what
you know you can you know find digging
And one of the segments was about how,
and I didn't know this, maybe everyone knows this but me,
but in Greece they run out of land to bury people
and they don't really cremate much out there.
So after like three years or so,
the family comes and they exhume the bodies.
their relative and it followed, I think that she worked, like she works at NPR or something,
but she went back to Greece to meet her father who was digging his mom up, so her grandma.
So by the time they get there, the dad is just kind of like,
kind of freaking out understandably.
Yeah.
And saying stuff like,
I hope that, you know,
mom is totally decomposed by the time we,
by the time we dig her up.
And then they do,
and then there's a very specific process
of how they dig the people up,
like from the head to the toe.
Fascinating.
Yeah.
Yep, and then they just like take the skull out and then they put them in boxes.
When they die, they wear socks so that they know that they got to the end of the body.
Oh, interesting.
Yeah, and then they put them, clean up, put in boxes like so the guy's mom is in back in the
in the shed and in boxes that were blessed, you know, and then that's how they handle death.
I mean, and at the end of it, it was really cool because he was very nervous and kind of afraid of what what's going to be like, but their whole family felt more at peace.
Yeah, understandable.
Yeah. After going through that process.
So, hmm.
That's really beautiful. And I, there's so many different ways
that different cultures handle it that are just so just so
beautiful and so hands on. And I really wish that was a big part
of Mortician's Tale, which is, it's very Western focused, you
know, you you make what you know, and all of us are based
here in Toronto, Canada. So we just kind of went off of what
the Western death process is.
And so Mortician's Tale is very much about that,
like how, you know, cold and there's just like no interaction
between us and our dead and that's, you know,
and hearing stories like that is really,
I'm a little bit envious.
Like I wish that we had experiences like that
and were able to kind of take care of our own
and that's really cool.
That's really neat.
Alex, I want you to dig out my body.
After three years.
Say what's on the record?
Yeah, yeah. Keep me in the, uh, in your shed if you have one by then.
If not, I'll take the, uh, the kitchen or something.
Yeah, beautiful.
Absolutely. Okay, on that note, I think, thanks so much for joining us. This has
been completely fascinating. I'm glad that we got an artist on here too, you
know, and just talking about the process and creativity and I think that a lot of
people think that, you know, you just go to your desk at drink box and start
doodling until something good comes out.
Yeah, yeah. Probably not how it works. We found out that's not how it works. Not always, yeah.
Yeah, not always. So, uh, yeah. Thanks again for having me and also my cats on your podcast. Yeah,
I do feel like we should ask for their names for crediting purposes. Oh, um, one of them's named
Bastion after, you know, the Overwatch character, and one of them's Meredith, and I could go on for
hours with my cats, so maybe I should leave. That's the next podcast. Yeah, well, we'll make
sure to give them a proper credit there. So, thanks again, and best of luck with everything.
Thank you.
Yeah, have a good one.
And we're back.
What do you think of that, Alex?
I think that was pretty great.
I can't believe that you agreed to exhume my body.
Hey man, that's what I'm here for.
That's what being colleagues at GDC means.
It means ride or die.
Ride, die, and dig.
That's what it is.
We call it the old RDD.
Man, we just talked about so much death, and I've been playing so much Death Stranding,
and it just is on a whole nother level.
It's like really not even...
relevant to the conversation of
Meaningful death rights, but I don't know
How much death is in actually in Death Stranding? I mean you 3d print roads out of death. So there's like a lot of it
big crisscross America
Do you consider that death positive? I think it really is a very death positive game. I don't know if it really
Don't know what it's trying to say about death. It's not as good as morticians tail. It's too high concept for me
Yeah, morticians tail kind of guy
Now Kojima he was like pretty
like Metal Gear Solid 3
Was three right you walk down the the stream and then you see all the ghosts of the soldiers. Oh, yeah the sorrow. Yeah
Yeah, I mean you actually you actually addressed like all the death
that you
you know, made happen. Yeah. Yeah, he did. But also if you happen to have killed one
of those poor souls by shooting them in like a really private place, they would have like
a really silly animation when they were walking down that really somber river. So it's hard
to take it terribly seriously. Hey, just being real. That's just video games, I guess.
Yeah, it absolutely is video games.
Anyway, Gabby, great, great guest.
Uh, her cats.
Yeah, also phenomenal guests.
Top 10 for sure.
At least, I would say at least as good as Gabby was.
Um...
I don't know. That's tough. That's tough. Better than me.
I would have, I would have, I would have placed Gabby a lot further up the scale
compared to her cats. If it weren't for that, uh, little, uh, fight that they got
into that really sold the drama for me.
Yeah. I was going to say that was the high point of my podcast, but, uh, you're
right. I'll take that into consideration.
How do you, how do you title these?
Is it, do we have to like come up with a fun catchphrase?
They're going to be like a fun kick somewhere.
Well, we'll find, we'll find out.
Yeah, we'll surprise people.
I guess that they'll know by now probably.
Oh, I guess they would.
Uh, what, what we title the podcast?
What would they tell us?
Yeah.
What were the cat's names again?
Yo Gabby Gabby was my favorite.
That's probably too much though.
No.
Anyway, let's talk about something real quick before we go.
GDC did release, we mentioned it during the podcast, that the Earth...
This is still the podcast.
Yeah.
Earlier in the podcast.
Yeah, I didn't want to draw focus away, but yeah, the State of the Industry report is out,
and it is real hot.
We have tons and tons of exclusive data that you are going to want to check out.
If you go to gdconf.com, there's a bunch of stuff.
I think we recently just highlighted the fact that there...
was a lot of conversation in this year's survey about sort of like new stuff, like especially
subscription services and the Epic Games Store and that kind of stuff. And we got a lot of
interesting feedback from the devs and other professionals we surveyed. I think we ran this
little story today. Check it out if you have time. It's all about how when we asked, I think it's
like nearly 4000 people we survey every year for this.
And we asked him, like, how do you feel about subscription services?
You know, let's talk about it.
Like Xbox Game Pass, like your Apple Arcade, that kind of stuff.
Like, is it going to devalue individual games?
And what we got back was really interesting and mixed.
It was not a strong yes or no.
It was a lot of confusion and a lot of like.
um, concern from our, uh, survey respondents.
And it's really interesting.
So you should go out and get the report.
It's, uh, it's available right now for free.
So, uh, go download it.
It's on Alex.
Yeah.
It's free.
It's subs on me as many copies as you want.
Oh, okay.
That's great.
Yeah.
I highly, uh, highly recommend checking that out.
Uh, GDC state of the industry survey.
How do you feel about game subscription services, Chris?
Are you still on Apple arcade?
Um, are they, are they sponsoring this podcast?
Okay.
Then no, actually I actually canceled it, but I'm trying to be better with my budget.
Um, but I'm probably gonna re up it at some point.
I am a, uh, an Xbox live game, games, pass game pass.
Oh, you got a games pass.
I do. With the PC. With the PC. Yeah. So I am just drowning in video games.
This is one thing with subscriptions is that there's, you get so many games and it's the
same thing with my like Kindle Unlimited. You're just, you have so many choices that you just end up
not playing games or not, not reading anything. I mean, I eventually play
something, but it's about like three seconds of a game. And then I close the
game, open another one, play that. That's not really hitting the spot. Close that
open another one. Yeah. Until do that 10 more times. And then you just open up
Netflix and watch it all over again. Millions time.
Yeah, see, this is the problem with smorgasbord. It's like not to take it
back. But like you have all these options on front of you have like an
array.
of just mouthwatering choices, and you just can't take any of them.
You just got to take a couple nibbles and leave.
What is on a real Swedish smorgasbord?
Yeah, this is how we stay in such good shape,
is we have these just tables full of mouthwatering dried fish and flatbreads,
and we just, we can't pick, we can't, can't eat any of them.
Seems salty.
Yeah.
Is that, can't be that good for you.
I mean, you know, you look fit.
Yeah.
But how healthy are you at?
It's, I mean, it's, it's all a sodium that that's literally, that's all.
It keeps me alive.
Death positivity.
You are preserved by all of the, you're just mummified by all of the
salted fish that you've been eating.
I wonder if anyone's still listening to this anymore.
Who can say, I had the opposite problem with you, which is where I am not
watching my budget and I'm still on all these services because I only play.
one to two video games a year and that is a problem like
When you talk about games like you say that you say you only play one or two video games a year
But you play a ton of video. Okay, but so far this year. I've only played one or two video games
All right, everybody if you're still there if you made it with us to the end congratulations
you win a free year of Apple Arcade. No, you don't actually.
You do win a free copy of the GDC 2020 State of the Industry
Report. Download it right now today at gdconf.com.
Smorgasbord of data. All right. That's all for this week, then
check us out on iTunes, Google Play, Spotify, and
YouTube, yeah, I think we need to upload the last one yet.
I don't know, I'm afraid of YouTube commenters,
so I've kind of been dragging my feet on that one.
But if you like what you heard, like and subscribe.
Yes, please.
Thanks, everybody.
Thanks, Alex.