Good morning from an atypically sunny London.
My name's Steve Bailey.
I'm an analyst with a company called Omdia.
And today I'm going to be taking you through a presentation
about the defining themes of the console market.
Now, consoles are a somewhat unique hardware group
in the games landscape,
in that they are specialist devices
dedicated primarily to the act of playing games.
and have been active for over 30 years now.
And in that time, people would often claim
that the days of consoles are numbered,
the consoles are dinosaurs due to die out
and be replaced by smartphones, tablets, whatever.
But that hasn't happened.
Instead, we have Nintendo Switch setting new sales records
and the new Xbox and PlayStation machines
can't be manufactured quickly enough to meet demand.
So we're going to talk about the value and appeal of consoles through the lens of several key topics.
And those topics will be split into two groups.
The first group looks at the outgoing generation of hardware, that is the PlayStation 4 and Xbox One.
These released in 2013 and as is typical for consoles, their sales start to decline about
five years or so after launch, at which point they are replaced by an incoming generation of consoles.
In this instance, the PS5.
and the new Xbox Series S and X.
It's this incoming generation
which will then define our second group of topics.
So as we said, let's begin by looking
at the outgoing generation.
And our first topic is about the industrious use
of back catalogs.
Sales of back catalog games have become
increasingly important for publishers in the past 10 years.
And the number of mid-size publishers
have seen record results on the back of making greater use
of their older games.
And some publishers now even employ legacy portfolio
managers purely to take care of this function,
this side of the business.
On the screen, what you see here is the share
of each platform's game catalog that
was being sold at a discount via the first party download
stores around the end of December last year.
So on PS4, for example, around 1,000 games and bundles.
That's about one fifth of the catalog.
was being sold via discount.
And that share is even higher on Xbox and Switch.
This is now very common for consoles.
In the space of a generation,
we've seen digital discounting go from an occasional thing
to a constant and pronounced part of the offering.
Some of this discounting is now quite extreme,
up to 98 or 99% of the resting price,
often making these games cheaper
than the equivalent of those being sold on a disc.
in a box. But it's not just about discounting, it's about making full use of that old catalogue
of games. Publishers have become much less protective of the launch value of content
within certain series and franchises, and instead understand that it's perhaps worth
giving older content away for free if it acquires customers for your newer titles and brings
players into your ecosystem.
In the olden days...
let's say pre 2010 or so, launching a game console was almost a fire and
forget experience. You would launch a game for $50, $60, whatever, and there
will be this intense, narrow window of sales. And after that window closed,
with the exception of certain franchises, commercial activity would drop off a
cliff. It was really kind of do or die, uh, incredibly front loaded, but thanks
to digital, the current console marketplace has a longer tail to it.
And with that
a broader and healthier sense of opportunity.
Our second topic is that of digital only hardware and by that
I mean consoles that can only play games downloaded via an internet connection
and won't take any discs or physical media.
2019 saw the launch of the first mainstream digital only tv console
the Xbox One S all digital edition and it's a hardware tier.
that we expect to become a standard part
of the console offering from sure on out.
But here's the thing with that.
Console started implementing digital only game catalogs
as far back as 2004, starting with Xbox Live Arcade,
and then expanding to include digital versions
of packaged games in around 2009 onward.
Indeed, this idea of digital only game content
is now very common on all console formats.
So why was there such a large gap between this?
and the launch of digital-only machines.
Part of the reason is that Xbox attempted
to introduce something similar to a digital-only console
as far back as 2013 with the launch of the Xbox One.
The console was unveiled at a pre-launch event
in around May of that year,
and it pitched the device
as requiring an internet connection
and for games discs to activate licenses
rather than represent any traditional sense of ownership.
effectively positioning it as an all-digital device.
But the problem with that is that Xbox tried to pitch this as compulsory
and did so to an early adopter audience and both of those things backfired
meaning there was a cooling period before the topic
could be visited again. Now this illustrates the care with which you have
to approach the console audience especially your enthusiast users.
This is an audience that you need to appease
in order to give your new console its earliest momentum.
And you can do that by changing the proposition significantly
and telling them it's compulsory.
No matter the wider technological trends,
you have to balance any such progression
with the needs of this highly engaged
and well-established audience of players
who've been playing console games possibly for decades.
So digital-only consoles could have happened
quite some time before 2019.
but they needed to be offered as an option alongside consoles
with disk drives, rather than lumped onto the player base
as a sudden obligation.
This is a really good example of the kinds of balancing acts
that consoles need to be constantly thinking about.
And in this example, it's a case of balancing progression
with tradition.
Our third topic is the rise and fall of Mixer.
You might remember that Mixer was a user-driven
video streaming platform similar to something like Twitch
that was bought by Microsoft in 2017
and was symbolic of its intentions to develop itself
as a competitor in the game space.
These kinds of platforms define a lot
of the modern opportunity around marketing
and community in games.
And Microsoft's ownership of Mixer would mean
that it could be integrated more closely
into its own platforms, especially Xbox One and Xbox Live.
More than that, I presume that Mixer was planned
to become a jumping off point
for Microsoft's cloud gaming platform,
in the same way that YouTube and Twitch
could be used for Google Stadia
and Amazon's Luna, respectively.
However, despite the opportunity,
running such a platform can be a deceptively complex act,
as you can see from this diagram on the screen.
On the surface, enabling video streaming coverage for games
might seem like a simple end point,
but actually implementing that kind of thing
involves a great number of stakeholders and a lot of layers.
It also involves hitting a certain scale of audience in order to offer the kind
of return needed to drive such a platform when it comes to appealing to the
brands and star influences that you have to have on board.
So Microsoft closed Mixer in 2020 and then decided instead to partner with
Facebook gaming in the hope that Facebook could provide both the needed scale.
and the influx of new users into Xbox's ecosystem.
What this illustrates is that consoles
can't do everything in-house.
They can't do everything by themselves.
Sure, on the one hand,
there's a way they can operate outside of certain trends,
but on the other, there are certain regards
in which they need to embrace
the wider technological landscape.
Again, it's another great example
of the kind of balancing act
that goes into operating a console.
Our fourth topic, excuse me, is about the maturing
of a hybridized approach to how publishers
make money from games.
And by that, I mean it's become less and less common for games
to focus on a single business model,
certainly in terms of how, say, AAA games and free-to-play
games sell themselves on console.
So this maturing has been happening for quite some time
and means that even.
Traditional single-player games like Delta May Cry 5,
as you can see from this slide here,
now have very complicated life cycles
where the publisher switches from one approach to another
and back again, as befits the opportunity.
This is an important facet of game consoles, right?
You have an audience that is used
to using multiple business models
and distribution methods.
That gives publishers room to create all kinds
of different approaches to their games.
So just to labor that point, we have some further examples
of this complexity on the screen here.
So on the left, you have GTA V and Overwatch,
games that even after years on the market
can still charge a premium entry point.
Even though they both still monetize,
they direct multiplayer experiences
via microtransactions.
In the middle, you have two games that were premium
for a good number of years
and have now switched to free-to-play.
and monetization via expansion content and season passes.
And on the right, you have the two of the biggest
free-to-play experiences on console,
Apex Legends and Fortnite,
both of which have released package special editions
to capitalize on a certain section of the audience
that likes to buy content in such a format.
A lot of free-to-play games these days
indeed launch with premium adjacent offerings
in the form of special editions,
founders editions, and so on.
Part of the issue with free-to-play is that it's often seen as a business model, and it's not.
It's a way of accessing games that can have profound implications for game design,
for marketing, for distribution, and monetization,
but it is not in itself a business model.
It's, in fact, a collection of business models,
and the same applies to premium games.
That's why the picture is more complicated than it first appears,
and helps explain why consoles, despite being very old,
are actually quite stable and adaptable.
Now, as we can see from this chart here,
which covers most of the past decade,
this is spend on console content and services,
premium spend in light blue, subscriptions in pink,
and expansions, premium DLC, et cetera, in purple.
Subs and DLC have been part of the landscape for years now,
exhibiting gradual rather than explosive growth.
And that's gonna remain the case for the future.
What you'll see is a marketplace
that offers a balanced approach
to how console players are monetized.
where subscription will become a significant and complementary
part, a net positive, but doesn't obliterate
the rest of the landscape.
So with that in mind, let's move on to the incoming generation
and the topics that we feel will define the next few years
for consoles, such as PlayStation 5, Nintendo Switch,
and the Xbox series.
First, let's look at the topic of generations.
By generation, we mean that there is a cycle at work.
A games console launches and gains momentum
across the space of four or five years,
and then hits a peak, and then goes into decline,
and sells fewer units each year
until it's eventually succeeded by a follow-up console.
This idea of generations is still very important,
but seems to be poorly represented.
Over the past 10 years, we've shared time and again
the generations are ending,
that console hardware will no longer progress in jumps.
But that's how it stayed,
and that's how it's likely to stay
for most of the coming decade.
This chart here shows the annual sales volume for console
from PlayStation, from Nintendo, and from Xbox,
and covers a 25-year period.
And you can see over the past 20 years
some very obvious cycles in effect.
There's definitely a strong pattern at work here.
Nintendo is where the pattern is least obvious.
Thanks to the impact of the Wii U,
that was its 2012 console that struggled to sell.
And it essentially curtailed the typical duration
of the generation, meaning that the Switch launched in 2017
instead of hitting, say, 2019 or 2020,
like the most recent installments of PlayStation and Xbox.
People are once again saying
that this generational transition is gonna be slower,
more protracted.
because players have less reason or desire to upgrade.
And I would disagree and say that if it wasn't
for the hardware shortages and the impact
of an unprecedented event like the COVID pandemic,
we'd actually see a transition happening
at a similar rate to periods in the past.
Thinking back to 2013, excuse me,
which is when the PS4 and the Xbox One launched,
there was a lot of talk about how the transition would be a lot slower,
about how the improvements in new consoles were less tangible and less
important. And to help facilitate that more gradual transition,
major titles like Call of Duty, Battlefield, et cetera,
offered cross-generational upgrades.
PlayStation 2 launched its own cross-play, cross-save, cross-buy initiatives.
But if you fast forward from that point to 2015,
every publisher we talked to was taken aback with how quickly the generation had transitioned.
So this expected slowing didn't really happen. So it's not outrageous to suggest that the same
thing would happen again. And from that perspective, I think something like the Xbox Series S variant,
a cheaper stepping stone into the next generation, is arguably more of an experiment than a necessity
at this phase in the generation.
Now, this next chart shows just how many years consoles
continue to sell after they've been succeeded.
The blue shows how many years each console
was the primary offering.
That is, it was the latest and best machine
available from that manufacturer.
And the pink shows how many years after it was succeeded
that it continued to sell over 100,000 units per year.
Once it sells less than 100,000 per year,
we consider it discontinued for the sake of this graph.
And I think people tend to be surprised by this
in how quickly consoles fade from sales activity.
The PS2 had a lot of time in the sun,
thanks to the console discovering a long tail of activity
in emerging territories around the world.
But apart from that,
I wouldn't say there's a huge change over the years
in that ratio of the pink to the blue.
Perhaps the pink portion is becoming slightly larger
over time, but this is a 25 year picture.
And what we're seeing here.
I think goes against this idea that hardware generations are
dying out.
So a question that follows on from that
is, what share of unit sales happens
when a console is the primary offering, which is in the blue,
versus what happens when it's been succeeded,
which is in the pink?
And I think the picture is even starker,
here, illustrating just how much of the console buying
tends to taper off once a new machine enters the picture.
Now with the PS5 and the Xbox Series X console selling for $500,
there is the possibility of this picture changing for them because they could
enact a much greater extent of price drop later in their life cycle, in their
twilight, extending that pink area towards something more akin to the PlayStation
2 than the PS3 or the PS4.
So this idea of generation.
doesn't just apply to hardware of course,
but also to content and to services.
And when we say content,
we just talk about the games themselves.
How much distinction is there on the content front
between generations?
And this is a part of the picture
that's becoming more fluid.
On screen, what you have here is a measure of content
overlap between hardware generations.
So we can see that for Xbox,
the overwhelming majority of the available game catalog
works on both old and new consoles.
But for PlayStation...
overlap is much smaller. Now this data is based on store listings so the PlayStation figure is
actually going to be a bit higher as there are a number of PS4 games that also work on PS5 that
are not listed as such on the stores themselves. But I think what you see here is still an effective
indicator as it illustrates the respective intentions of the manufacturers. This overlap
is something that Xbox has been deliberately working towards for the past five years.
Whereas for PlayStation, it's a more recent endeavor.
We often get asked whether this idea
of cross-generational functionality
will cause the hardware transition to slow down
or to speed up.
And I think it does neither of those things.
What it does offer is protection.
It keeps people in your ecosystem.
It keeps players on your machines.
That's the important thing with backwards
and cross-generational compatibility.
If new hardware is in short supply,
it means your old platform still has a strong content supply.
And if someone buys the new hardware,
but new exclusive content isn't ready yet,
then updated versions of fan favorite games,
keep them active on your new hardware.
It's about the ecosystem play basically.
And that brings us neatly to our second topic
for the incoming consoles.
And we'll start.
by talking about something we've referred to plenty of times
already, which is balancing acts.
Over the years, it's been very easy to dismiss consoles
as outdated, to call them dinosaurs,
say that they're about to die out, but they are still here
and they are still going strong.
And that's because they are this deceptively complex collection
of balancing acts and quite adaptable with it.
10 years ago, people were saying that cloud gaming
would kill consoles.
But now, consoles are one of the best places
to explore the potential of cloud gaming.
Apple TV was supposed to kill consoles, but didn't.
Steam boxes were supposed to kill consoles, but didn't.
Likely because the manufacturers realized
how difficult it was to pull off the right balance
between price, performance, evolution,
accessibility, and so on.
Now, consoles are not invincible, of course.
They are always ripe for disruption.
but their ability to represent multiple forms of distribution
and business model can make them resistant,
along with an audience that is highly engaged and happy
to spend a lot of money.
Next, we look at how the messaging has changed
in recent years by manufacturers when
it comes to how they approach facets
of their respective ecosystem.
PlayStation remains the most balanced,
and I don't think there's much to be said there.
On that front, at least not compared to Xbox and Nintendo.
So let's start with Xbox.
Xbox has been putting great emphasis
on its content library subscriptions,
Game Pass and Xbox Live Ultimate in recent years.
Drawing that conversation away from hardware,
somewhat and signaling a change of emphasis for the company.
Now this change makes sense for Xbox.
What we have here is the total number of consoles
sold over the past 20 years.
by a manufacturer.
And this is not to disparage Xbox, you understand.
Launching a console takes billions of dollars
and a staggering amount of effort.
And to sell this many machines,
it's an enormous achievement indeed.
But it's an area where Xbox is unlikely to see much growth.
And this helps explain its change of emphasis
into a services-driven arena as a company.
It's an area where it has much greater experience
and potential, and it's attempting to get a head start
on the future and aiming to arrive there
before its rivals do.
So Xbox's Game Pass strategy has three distinct phases.
The first is the short-term phase,
which was between launch in 2016 and 2020,
where the object was to reframe the conversation
around Xbox, in which I think it has been very successful.
Then you have the long-term goal from 2025 onward,
where Game Pass and Ultimate aim to drive the bulk
of Xbox's console business.
It's a vision that's coherent
and to which the company has made a huge, huge commitment.
However, we still have this middle phase
between now and 2024.
And in that phase, the company has to continue
selling hardware and really start delivering
on its first-party software
in order to scale up the audience
for Game Pass and Xbox Live Ultimate.
Anyway, if you want to know more about subscription and cloud,
a colleague of mine named George G.G. Ashfordly
is running a separate talk at GDC on those very topics.
Next up, we'll take a look at Nintendo,
whose strategy, by its own admission,
has become hardware-focused again.
For my money, that is a shift away
from when the console launched, and it
seemed to be shifting more emphasis onto Nintendo Switch
online.
But when it comes to the use of Switch Online,
people are asking, why is Nintendo not putting more
and more weight behind the online service?
But first of all, it's typical of Nintendo
doing its own thing at its own pace.
Few companies have the strength of IP that Nintendo does,
and it's preferring to exercise control
over its ecosystem while it still can.
For now, that means prioritizing getting people
onto Switch hardware first and foremost.
Arguably, this is gonna change.
especially towards the latter half of the hardware cycle,
when the successor to Switch is lining up for release.
And I think at that point, it will become a priority
to shift people into an online ecosystem,
as that makes it easier then to migrate
them between generations of hardware.
Now, there's an interesting thing happening
when it comes to this idea of ecosystems.
And it's the more seamless things become for consumers.
the more complicated they become behind the scenes.
Subscription and cloud may simplify the offering
for consumers, but behind the scenes,
things actually get much more difficult
to track and to implement.
It's why this ideal of people being able to play
whatever they want, whenever they want,
on whatever device they want,
is a long-term challenge that's gonna take
many years to solve.
And so, one big part of the problem there is,
where is a player acquired?
Where are they retained?
Where are they monetized?
And these potentially now become very fragmented questions
that make things a lot more difficult
from an operational standpoint.
To put it more generally, across the next decade,
the business is entering its third wave of complexity.
Not just console, but I think the entire market.
I'm not really sure if we're really ready for it.
It's obviously nice to talk about this unified,
seamless offering for consumers.
But the tensions between companies and platforms
in terms of who owns the IP, who owns the user experience,
who owns the infrastructure, is only just beginning.
There are gonna be lots of clashes and fights
over this in the coming decade.
And I think Apple versus Epic is just the beginning.
Anyway, we're not gonna dig into that too much further here.
We're gonna move on to the third topic,
which is Heartland.
Now, there are some very interesting battles taking place
when it comes to the key regions in the console marketplace,
such as in the US between Xbox and PlayStation.
As you can see here, we have the install base,
which is the number of consoles sold by generation
across the past 20 years,
and how PlayStation weighs off against Xbox there.
Now, the US is the biggest console market in the world.
It's also the main stronghold for Xbox.
It's where Xbox 360 pushed ahead some 10 years ago,
and it's where Xbox One held the most steady,
despite the challenges that the format faced.
So the question is, what's gonna happen next?
We're currently forecasting PlayStation and Xbox
as neck and neck, but there's obviously
a major, major tussle taking place here.
PlayStation is now headquartered in the US,
and is aligning itself with big Western brands,
such as Spider-Man.
If PlayStation can hurt Xbox here...
could limit the growth that Xbox has ahead of it for the next three or four years. Conversely,
of course, Xbox has shored up its position in the US via acquisitions, like when Xbox bought
Bethesda recently for many billions of dollars. All the headlines were about Xbox bulking out
Game Pass, which is completely true, but there's also this matter of re-reinforcing
its position in the US. We should not overlook that.
On a similar note, let's look at Europe,
which remains a challenge for Xbox
because both historically and arguably in the near future,
the cachet of PlayStation remains just too strong for it
to make much of a dent in things.
But again, this could explain the value
of a services-first approach from Xbox.
A different tech might end up giving it
the kind of traction in Europe
that hardware is failing to generate for it.
Finally, we have Japan.
And this time we're looking at PlayStation versus Nintendo.
And we're also including handheld here
because Japan is very mobile oriented.
One thing to keep in mind here is that
since we don't have a full cycle picture for PS5,
we've used the PS4 as a lifetime install base.
And it tells us that even if PS5 sells as well as PS4,
this encroachment from Nintendo will still continue.
So could we,
Perhaps see a future where Japan,
one of the biggest console markets in the world,
becomes the exclusive playground of Nintendo.
And finally, we touch on the topic
of curation and discoverability.
Excuse me.
Here on the screen, we have a three-year picture
of what's been happening on Nintendo Switch.
In terms of content released digitally onto the platform.
The blue bar shows how many games have been released on the platform,
which was around 700 games in May, 2018.
Also, that was just one year after release.
I thought this unprecedented volume would slow down,
but it's just kept that release rate ever since.
Recently hitting 5,000 titles, which is a record for a games console.
We also have the pink line, which
shows the percentage of the game catalog that's under $20
at any given moment.
So at any given time in the past three years,
around 80% of the Switch's catalog
is selling for under $20.
It's a lot to have to compete with in terms of visibility
if you're releasing a game onto the platform.
The topic of discoverability remains critical for consoles
because the manufacturers have to be
able to demonstrate value to content partners.
If you were going to release a game onto my machine,
what return is there for you?
What value?
Why should you bother?
Primarily, this is done via establishing
an install base of hardware,
which represents an audience of potential users
and therefore buyers.
But increasingly, with digital and connectivity
facilitating so much game-related content,
what's the point of releasing your game onto a platform
if it just gets lost in the crowd?
And it's not as if...
there aren't a growing number of alternative platforms
out there to release your games onto.
Again, it's one of many, many balancing acts
that console manufacturers have to perform.
Anyway, that brings this presentation to its end.
Thank you for tuning in.
I hope you found it enjoyable, or at least interesting.
Have yourself a good GDC,
and take care of yourselves out there in these crazy times.
Bye-bye.