Hi. Hey. So my name is Ryan Stevenson and I'm Art Director at the game studio Rare.
And today I'm going to be talking to you about the art of adventure on Sea of Thieves.
I'm going to be covering some of the visual pillars that we made during the making of the
project. Also showing you some of the early work around creating the visuals and some things that
have never been seen before. So to begin with, who in the room has actually played Sea of Thieves?
Ah! Say an ah!
Nice, very pirate-y.
So, well, release day was actually yesterday.
Brilliant.
Thank you.
So to begin with, I thought as a reminder to everyone, is to start with the launch gameplay
trailer.
Yay, yes sir.
Woo!
So, to talk about the art journey of Sea of Thieves,
I need to tell you a little bit about the studio first,
and also about how we came to make this pirate adventure game.
So, I joined the studio 17 years ago,
but that's nothing compared to Rare,
who's been around for over 30 years now.
And we have a rich history of games
with a wide range of themes,
so hopefully you're familiar with some of these games.
and as you can see that there's a wide variety of different genres and there's also different themes within it.
As you can see we like to experiment and I think it also speaks to the fact we like to change what we work on
and how we work at key moments throughout, through the years.
And one of those interesting moments came in 2014 when we were just finishing
the Kinect Sports Rivals series of sports games.
and we realized that the following year, 2015,
was actually going to be the 30th anniversary of Rare.
So we worked on Rare Replay,
which was a collection of games,
of 30 games from 30 years,
and those games really speak to the history of the studio
and the character and the charm of the studio, I think.
So we had this eye on the past, but at the same time as looking at the past,
we wanted to think of what the future was going to hold for Rare.
So a small group of us came together to define that future,
to try and think out what was going to be our next game.
And Project Athena was born.
Well, kind of.
So when we first started Project Athena,
we had no preconceived ideas what it could be.
It could be anything from a racing game to an RPG.
But what we did have was a design vision.
And that design vision was for a group-shaped narrative.
So a group-shaped narrative to us is a game
in where the experience of the player changes
depending on who they meet within the world
and the interaction between those players.
A game where natural conversation was going to be key
and also that would cause a wider range of emotions
as they played the game.
And also, so we did all that,
but we still didn't know what the game was gonna be.
So we did have a divine vision,
but we still didn't know what to do.
So to solve this, we actually created a whole bunch of one
sheets that went upon the walls around the studio.
And these one sheets were one page design documents.
And this is the one that we produced for Sea of Thieves.
We had hundreds of these upon the walls.
But it wasn't until this one went up that we realized that
we'd found our muse.
The idea of a group of players working together and
communicating to sail a ship and meeting other crews within
the world was just perfect for a shared world narrative.
We also realized that there was a world where
The players would be able to understand the tools and the world quite simply.
So, what do you do with a compass or what do you do with a treasure map?
It's pretty obvious and it plays into all those genres and films that you've seen over the years.
And there's one other thing that we really liked about this idea.
And that's the game series, and that's rare.
So we're actually in the middle of England, nestled
about as far away from water as you possibly can.
And the thing we really liked about this idea
is that it's no secret, even though we're
about as far away from sea as you can get, we love pirates.
We've managed to crowbar pirates into most titles
that we've made over the years.
My particular favorite is the fact
that we've got a zombie pirate in Grabbed by the Ghoulies.
That's a haunted house game.
There is no reason why pirates should exist in it,
but we still crowbarred it in.
So yeah, so that's the reason why.
And we just loved them.
So we had a vision and we had a theme that we wanted to go after.
So the project could really begin.
So at the start we separated it into two different streams.
One was going to be creating a lo-fi gameplay prototype.
This prototype actually was this rich experience
that would feature all of the features that you actually see within the game that you've been playing today.
And that actually stayed with us for a long period during the dev.
And the other stream that we created was the visual development stream, so my area.
And whenever I like to start a project, I like to start it by defining some art goals
and challenges.
So right at the start, we realized we had two main goals that we wanted to go after
with Sea of Thieves.
Goal number one was to create a modern rare game.
So we wanted to create a game that spoke to the magic
and charm of the studio, the playful nature
of where we make games.
And also, we wanted something that would redefine visually
what AAA meant to us as a studio.
So a rather lofty ambition.
And also from a gameplay point of view, we knew that Sea of Thieves would be a game
where there's going to be a lot of humor.
We wanted to capture that old, rare kind of humor within it as well.
So, and the visuals needed to match the tone.
The second goal, which was really important,
was to create a timeless visual art style.
So the idea was a timeless visual art style
would avoid being outdated by advances in technology,
and it would scale quite nicely over different platforms.
We're going to be making a game that would be on PC and Xbox.
So it would be low spec as well as high spec PC.
This approach is actually something
I've used before in the past for Viva Piñata.
And if you look at the screenshot,
I think it's aged really well.
This was taken in 2007.
So, and I think it's part of the fact that there's a strong visual stylization to it
that's meant that it's aged nicely.
And that's the same thing I wanted to do with Sea of Thieves.
So we had our two goals, we also had art challenges as well.
I think these, everyone gets these with making games, you get some challenges that just come
along the way.
But the first one was to capture the magic of a rare game.
Now that sounds strange, I've just talked about capturing that magic, and also had it
as the art challenge.
But the reason why it was a challenge is at the start of the project...
it was going to be without any of the normal rare elements.
So we thought we weren't going to have NPCs,
we thought we weren't going to have a story
behind lots of elements within the world.
So I needed to work out how we were going to get that charm
and that character within the players
and also the world surrounding them.
The other challenge was it was going to be larger
than any game we had made before.
Right from the get-go, we knew that this was going to be
a massive open world and something we hadn't done.
and it was going to be a style of game we'd never made in an engine we'd never used.
So for this we used the Unreal Engine and it was the starting point
so we needed to do some learning as well about it.
At the start of the project as well, I did a lot of research. So I've watched probably
every single pirate film that you could possibly do.
It's not very easy to go out and pretend to be a pirate, so I've decided that was
probably the best way to
understand the theme because we wanted something that embraced the tone of the world.
Once we digested all that reference, we started work on the artwork itself.
These are some early examples of the concept that was done for the very inception of the project.
My background is that of a concept artist.
It's always my go-to at the start of a project, with most development it is.
We've also got a great team at the studio that just jumped at the challenge of creating an adventure game.
So we explored the islands and whether there was volcanoes,
there was an early idea of what the edge of the world could be like.
And here's some early explorations into characters as well.
So we were really trying to find the themes.
Well, we were trying to find what kind of pirates these were going to be,
whether they were going to be...
and heroic, or when there were going to be dirty rotten pirates, which we ended up leaning
towards, or how characterful they were going to be, whether they were going to be really
cartoony or whether they were going to be fairly realistic.
Through all this work and all this concept development, we started to create the art
pillars.
So the art pillars, with projects, there's always the overarching pillars of the project.
There's always the design direction, the gameplay, the engineering, something that ties it all
together.
But I also like to create individual art pillars for the art team that sits alongside it and
supports all of those themes.
And I like to create the art pillars based around the goals and the challenges that I've
already mentioned.
And I also like to create the rule of three.
So like with anything, three is always good.
And if you're an artist, you know,
aesthetically three things together is a nice balance.
So this is the first pillar that defined the look of Sea of Thieves.
So visual pillar number one is an illustrative approach.
So in Sea of Thieves we wanted to suggest structure and detail rather than define it.
Granular noise is removed and replaced with a more expressive approach to textures.
These are combined with simple construction to create a rich and vibrant world.
So this pillar was created to create that timeless art style that I've mentioned earlier.
So the simplification that I'm talking about is, in a good example here, is where the silhouette
of the forms are kept quite clean.
Something I'm a big believer in is that you can get nice visual complexity through combining
simplified forms.
One problem that I've seen over the years, and I've done it myself, is as a concept artist
you'll create a nice...
image and then you start extracting all those elements out and working up the
design for each of those individual elements
and you end up pouring tons of detail within those elements and then sticking it all back
together
and the final image is nothing like what you started with because you just
added so much noise into those individual elements when they recombined.
So here's an example of the do's and don'ts.
So obviously that palm tree over there,
over on the left, is very noisy.
It's got lots of detail within the bark.
Where on the right, it's far more simplified.
There was something that I was, we were aware of as well,
is that by simplifying the form,
we would end up with a surface detail
that could end up looking very tube-like
or quite a bit too simple, really.
So what we ended up doing was looking at
how we could add fasted surfaces
within those details as well.
So from a distance, the form would be fairly simple,
and then as you get closer,
you'd see a nice surface within the objects themselves.
We also, from the simplified forms, we also wanted to capture an interesting aesthetic within the textures.
So it was inspired by concept painting, where you can get very brushmarky and very expressive
with a lot of the different elements within it.
It's a way of making sure that the world is simplified but never flat,
because those textures have that detail level within it.
Another aspect of the inspiration for this was by...
I'm going to attempt the name, Kazuo-san,
who, he's a renowned painter of background and layout
for studio Ghibli films.
This one's from Spirited Away.
I think a lot of people find Ghibli films quite inspiring
and take a lot from it.
The thing that I thought was really interesting
was how the surface of the wall
has lots of different values and hues within it,
and there's also these brush marks.
And around the door, there's some nice,
really defined, called-out areas of wear and tear.
This was something that we wanted to try and capture within Sea of Thieves.
So for this we did some early tests on texturing.
So an expressive texturing approach.
You can see that the rock at the top and how it is at the bottom
and also how we're removing detail from the leaves.
These were really early on so we did evolve slightly from this
but it shows you the initial outset.
The next image is when they started to all come together.
So this is actually an image taken from a game capture
with renders added to it and paint overs
to try and stop pulling together that vision
to really try and define what it could look like.
Here's some call outs to those areas within the brush marks,
so the way the brush marks are on the palm
or the palm tree trunk, and also the rocks.
Another aspect of the simplification that we were looking at was how we could reduce
noise within blocks of color.
So what I mean by that is that the, for instance if you look at the palm tree, you've obviously
got that very big green top and the trunk itself is made mainly from brown notes and
colors.
The same thing with the grass, it's got quite a purity to it.
The idea around this is that you get a clean color read from each of those objects, so
we're not spreading lots of different colors over the trunk of the tree, it's not got green
moss going up it, it's not blurring altogether.
So the idea would be that if you actually do blur the image and blur the internal detail,
it still gives you that read of that environment, because it's staying pure to it.
So as an example of these rules in action,
I'm going to show you two images.
So this is the first one.
So that's one of the many chests that you can find in Sea of Thieves.
So those of you who have played the game
will have probably found this in the world and run around with it.
And here's another version of that image.
So for the keen eyes amongst you, you'll
realize the first one is a concept art,
and the second one is a 3D model.
So this was the really kind of high five moment for us in the game.
We'd really managed to achieve the ability to get that textures,
the simplified look, the separation of the colors within the object.
So that was quite a key moment when we realized we could do this.
And this was the right approach.
Another important part for me about creating an illustrative approach
was the way we treated lighting.
So I like to think of it as painting with light.
So it was such an important part of the world.
We wanted the world to be vibrant and expressive,
and we wanted the world to heighten the emotions
when you're on the sea.
So those storms that were dark and moody
and those beautiful sunsets,
they were all derived to make you feel those emotions
when you look at them.
And the inspiration for that came from looking at color keys found within 3D animation movies.
Just love the way that they push the vibrancy within it,
and also where they're not hindered by overly realistic lighting.
They do heighten it to make them a motion of that moment within the film.
These images are from my favorite, one of my favorite artists, which is Nathan Foulkes.
I really recommend you go and look at him.
He's got amazing charcoal work, and his color keys are phenomenal.
So, the ones down in the corner here, so there's two of the images are from Rio.
The one in the bottom right is from Puss in Boots and the top one I think is from Spirit.
But yeah, I just love the way that that worked and we wanted to capture a bit of that within the world.
So, here are first tests doing that.
So, we were looking at the way that the light could change one environment,
how by having those different colored keys within the world, we can make the mood change.
So, these were the first early tests of that.
And here it is applied to a three-dimensional environment.
So this was taken from my diorama.
And you can see that we were playing
with the colors there again.
And we were also looking at the way
that weather changes a location.
By having it rainy, you could get a different emotion.
I just looked out in the crowd.
There was one of our tech art directors
was just smiling at me, because you can remember this
from back in the day.
And this leads me nicely to what I'm going to show you next,
which is the.
Engine, Viz, Dev.
Or getting to know Unreal.
So obviously, we needed to get to know Unreal as a studio.
The art team had never used it before.
Maybe some of them had used it in passing,
but a lot of us had not used it to make a main game.
So we decided the best thing was to create a small diorama, a little chunk of land
where we could test out all these theories that I've been talking about.
We could test the texturing, the simplification,
and just some of the tech that we were playing with at the time.
So I'm going to let that play for you now.
So that was our first test to prove this all out.
As you can see, it contained a lot of interesting things
within it with the simplification that I talked about,
but it also had two elements that turned out
to be really important for the game.
And also leads me quite nicely to my next art pillar,
which is pillar number two, a sea of motion.
So, in Sea of Thieves, clouds form and waves crash
and also sails billow in the wind.
The plants would sway in the breeze as well.
From the swell of an ocean
to the swinging of lanterns below deck,
the world was never still.
This is especially prominent in the water
and also the sky, weather, and the passage of time.
So this was really important
to create that sense of a living world
and that drama of being on a pirate ship,
sailing through the waves.
and it became quite obvious when you look at a screenshot of what the game looked like
and we could see this within the prototype early on
that there is a lot of water, there is a lot of sky
so that was going to be our world
it was a world where you could go to islands but the player would see this a lot of the
time
so there's a big chunk of boat as well
but if the player was to look to the right or to the left
they'd end up seeing this
so again, more sky, more water
So we knew that this was going to be a really important part of the game.
So the sea was going to be this big powerful character within the world.
We wanted it to be dynamic and also feel like its own entity.
It had a power to force the player around in the world so as their boat is crashing through the waves.
triggering these emotions as you ride over the crest.
And it also became one of our highest visual bars within the game.
And it varied from appearance depending where it was in the world, so from calm
lagoons to big storms
to just the open sea.
So...
there is an action.
So, interestingly enough, I spent quite a long time thinking about
water and how stylized it should be within the world.
I did experiment with creating something more stylized,
but realized that as soon as you start removing
some of the essence of what water is from it,
it just didn't feel like that element anymore.
And you actually see that with, again,
in animated 3D films, I'm a big fan of them,
and you can see that water within it
is often treated as realistic water.
And the reason for that is because
it just doesn't feel right if you change it.
But we did add stylization to it, so it's fairly realistic in the way that it moves and acts.
But the way that the light cascades through it,
and also the tones and colours that we added to it,
each of those things are hand-done
to create that sense of an expressive painterly kind of quality.
Also, the seafoam as well has got a very defined pattern within it
that we repeat to kind of mimic the paint marks
that you find within the textures as well.
So there's the water and now I'm going to show you another video which is just focused on the water.
So enjoy our lovely waves.
Everyone always says they're beautiful.
Okay.
Thank you very much.
We have got a great rendering team
that put that all together,
but it really was a huge effort from both the rendering team,
also the tech artists, the lighting people,
and there were so many people involved in creating that.
So going back to that image, we'd sorted the water,
we'd obviously, that's in the bag,
but we'd got the big sky above it.
And we also knew that that wanted to be a character as well,
as equally as powerful as the water.
So for this, we looked at lots of reference
to try and get inspiration.
And through looking at this reference,
it became quite obvious that we wanted the sky
to have these big, bold forms within it,
and then to almost have a sculptural quality.
They should grow and change and dissipate and even cast shadows across the environment.
The sky needed to not only create a sense of wonder, but also fear.
The moment that you sail into a storm, how does that really feel?
So with that, we decided we needed to try something a little bit different.
which was to create large geometric, geometry-based clouds.
So this was early concept for how that could look.
And the idea was that I painted all these different
big shapes out and looked at how they just disappeared
into the horizon, also how that they would be really nice
as you sailed underneath them and they passed overhead.
This was how that they should look in the game
in the sense that they were more fluffy
and more kind of like expressive.
So that was the early exploration into that.
By having large geometry-based clouds, we also realized that we could do some quite
interesting things.
Maybe we could make a skull appear in the clouds, which would be quite an interesting
thing.
And this was an early idea for Skull Island.
We realized that we wanted to put a skull island in the game.
It has to be in every pirate trope.
But rather than have a big island carved out of a skull, we thought how about having a
big cloud above it.
This was an idea early on that actually got used later within the development for something
else.
Who's attacked a skelly fort?
Has anyone done that?
So for those of you that don't know,
if you sail across the waves,
you can see a big skull on the horizon.
It's the sign that a skelly fort
has appeared within the world,
and you can go and battle the skeletons within it
and maybe steal their riches.
So again, I've got another short video to show you,
which is the clouds in action.
Here we go.
a
you
We even had some really interesting fun tests of putting
the shape of a ship in the sky as well.
So we really did just throw lots of things within it to
see what would happen.
Again, the tech art team put this together.
It was a phenomenal piece of work.
Alongside those clouds, the clouds, the water,
I also wanted a world in which there was just that sense of movement within it.
So I've mentioned those big, bold things, but also the little things were important.
The world needed to have a sense of life.
And I think through those small little moments, it just shows you how.
how just it's peaceful to watch it just move.
There was one moment where we didn't have the trees swaying
in the breeze and they just felt like concrete.
And as soon as we turned it on and we actually got it in,
they just started to really move
and it just felt so beautiful.
You almost kind of realized how much you'd missed it
when it wasn't there.
So I'm now gonna...
As this is playing, I'm going to talk about something else
I'm going to share with you next, which
is something we've never actually shared outside
of the studio before, which is the art CG trailer.
So really early on, we'd obviously
were developing the art style.
We had this prototype that was going
to be rich with gameplay that was developing
and really powering along.
But we needed to prove out more of the art style.
We weren't actually building all of the world at that point.
So we tested out on the small island, we created the rules,
we'd done a few art tests ourselves,
and we needed to test those theories more.
So for it, we decided to create a CGI trailer.
And we actually worked with a partner
we've used several times in the UK, which is real time.
And to begin with, we started by just exploring more areas that could exist within this trailer.
So we looked at islands, we looked at the clouds again.
We looked at what it would feel like below the ship, so how it's kind of all cozy and
warm and also that close feeling compared to the outside.
We looked at moments of finding areas of interest, such as an undead pirate captain that would be sitting on a throne.
We also started working on defining our characters even more.
So, this is the first three characters that really started to get that Sea of Thieves style.
And I'll talk a little bit more about why they have the Sea of Thieves style in a bit.
And through making this trailer, we were able to test things out,
such as our lighting that I've mentioned,
and also take some of our early block-out models of the ship
and really work them up.
So for example, like this ship here.
And we also looked at early aspects of what our first kraken could look like.
So there's some of the exploration about what a tentacle would look like.
Through this process I found it immensely useful.
We were able to prove out lots of different ideas.
and also give lots of different feedback,
play around with the different approaches to things,
look at the way we're treating decks of the ship,
look at the way that we're building the world,
look at the detail, even the angle of the ship
and the twist of the ship,
the way that it was made to feel a little bit rickety.
So I'm gonna play that video now,
but I'm not actually gonna show you the full trailer.
What I'm gonna show you is parts of it
and also some of the tests that were made through it,
because I think that was the important part.
It was proving out these theories.
always end on a bang.
So, yeah, so that was a really, really fun thing to do
and I feel immensely lucky in my job to be able to go and.
explore visuals like that.
So now we're gonna come to one of our last pillars,
which is a world of stories.
So as I mentioned before,
we were gonna be making this characterful rare game,
but it was going to not have any NPCs in it,
and it wasn't gonna have any of the normal rare thing
that we were gonna have.
We did get it, we did actually start adding it in,
we realized how important it was to it.
But right at the beginning,
we needed to work out how to make that feeling
come across through the entire world.
So we knew that the pirates were going to have these really fun adventures,
and they were going to have really nice locations to go to and explore,
that would have this sense of story, have this sense of history within it.
But we also wanted to make that character and that story and that rare charm
sing through every single aspect of the game.
So, for this, we made it so that every single item has its own story.
So, as you can see, there's a shovel and a blunderbuss,
and the way in which it has a sense of history to it.
And this was applied to every single item within the game.
and every single part that we actually built.
So nothing was new as well.
So this is a fairly kind of shiny sword,
but it has a sense that it's got chips in it,
it's got dents in it, it's been used before.
The idea was that you'd have stolen it from another crew
or found it within the world.
So everything in Sea of Thieves is secondhand.
The idea of Sea of Thieves is this bubble
of pirate adventure.
So no one's making lots of new swords.
They're fixing a lot of swords and bringing them in.
So the three important aspects of creating this life story
that really sang through,
and that was wonky with logic, I will explain that,
wear and tear, and patched and repaired.
So Wonky, which turned out to be a cornerstone of conversations around the art direction,
is this.
So Wonky is a general term to cover distortion and disruption of surfaces that have been
caused by its history.
So they can be poorly built, damaged, or even warped with age.
There's an example of what it is and what it isn't.
So it's amazing when you're doing stylized games how quickly...
it sometimes can just turn into quite tropey,
to put it in a better word, of cartoon-stylized forms.
So you can get a lot of stylish pinches or distortions.
And what I wanted to make sure was all of this wonky feel
wasn't through just askew items.
It was through the fact that there was a history within it.
So here are some examples of that.
We have the deck of the ship.
well, the stairs down.
So the rail is warped with age, and it has this slight bow in it.
And the steps are even and worn.
Another example within the world is, oh, there's a crate.
This is an example of it when it was done wrong.
So the crate, you can see on the left there,
it just, no one would make a crate like that.
It just feel, you couldn't stack them.
They would just fall all over the place.
It wasn't wonky.
it was just cartoon distortion.
The one on the left is a more see-if-the-easy crate,
in the sense of it's been made out
of a mismatched piece of wood.
It's got the wear and tear within it.
So they're the two examples of done right and wrong.
Here's some more examples of the deck of the ship,
the way that there's chips and dinks.
And these are really an example of how much care
and love we put into every single item within the world.
Another example is the beam of wood that's around the.
the post that's around the captain's door.
So rather than, if it just went in
and it was flat geometry, it would feel overly clean.
But as soon as we started knocking corners,
as if someone's ran through it with a treasure chest
and knocked it around a few times,
or even where there's a cut mark,
where a sword has been slashed against it,
these things all give a sense of history.
So, the wear and tear even expanded to the characters themselves.
So, no matter how smart the clothing would be,
so the character on the left there,
she's got kind of like an admiral kind of clothing,
but it's still patched and repaired, it's still got areas of dirt and wear,
and that continued within all of the clothing through the game.
So we had holes and rips and torn edges.
So, again, this pillar tied into all of these,
everything within the game.
So more examples of it.
This was a term that we ended up using all the time as well.
So there was wonky, there was dinks.
If something didn't look CFDs, we'd normally say, make sure
it's a little bit wonky and add some dinks.
And it worked every time.
So I love it as a system.
So again, you can see the chips and the dinks
within the thing.
So a skeleton's head to the clothing, to the swords,
it really was something that just kept working.
Another aspect of creating this sense of history
within the world was patched and repaired.
So if you look at the deck of the ship,
there are actual kind of like planks of wood
at right angles to what they should be.
Now I know every sailor would probably tell me
this is not how you fix a ship.
And I did have a conversation with someone on the team where they were going,
you just wouldn't do that.
Um, but it speaks to the fact that I felt he spoke to the fact that these
pirates were, didn't really care.
There were just sluggishly kind of dirty pirates that were just sailing around
the world.
So these ships needed to feel battered and worn.
And this started to give a little bit of that character within the deck of the
ship itself.
Also, the patched and repaired expanded to things like the sails,
where we have patches on the sails,
and we used a lot of wraps within certain items
to show that it was shorn up for stability.
So the idea of that was that you could apply that to it,
and it would have that sense that it's been broken,
and a pirate's picked it up, wrapped it up themselves,
rather than take it to a blacksmith and then fixed it.
So it had that sense that it was out on the ocean waves
having an adventure of itself.
So these were the visual pillars to ride from the goals.
So from the illustrative approach that we took
to the world in motion.
and a world of stories.
These were the three things that detailed the entire game
and really guided our vision.
These came together fairly early on within the development
and they just kept helping us through everything.
So every time we put something new in the game
that we weren't sure about, a new material
or a new substance, we were able to look at it
and apply this thinking to it every single time
and it would instantly just feel like Sea of Thieves.
I've included this picture of World of Stories because this is something I didn't mention
earlier on but I thought it was quite interesting, is another aspect of World of Stories that
we add is we actually put our players into the game.
So when a player has done something particularly noteworthy on our forums, in the world, on
Twitter, within the game, we often immortalise them within it.
And this is the Georgian Kraken.
So there's a character called Clumsy George on the forums,
and he was one of our players.
And he wrote a story about fighting a kraken with a broom.
And so we turned him into a tavern.
So he got his own tavern in the game.
So again, we're adding history to the world all the time.
So, you can see that even from the smallest element within the world, these rules are
applied.
So, from the way that these small bolts, nails that got knocked into the wood and the way
that they split the wood, that's the dinks, that's the wear and tear, that's the story.
The way that the items all have that sense of history, from a broken hurdy-gurdy to a
tankard to a blunderbuss.
It all got applied.
And to our characters as well.
So here are the characters.
So we were knocking teeth out.
We were adding scars to them.
Our system actually enables you to create heroes
within the world, but also dirty, rotten pirates.
And the idea was that I think there's enough lantern-jawed
heroes in games, so it's nice to be able to show
the other side of it.
From the skeletons that you fight as well that you've seen earlier on with it with the
breaks within the face and the dinks and also those hidden moments of exploring within the world like finding the secret of a
sunken treasure treasure ship and
The interesting locations like one of these ports which it has a sense of story to it
Like how did that ship get up there? It was obviously a big wave or a kraken through it
So I'm going to finish up by showing you some interesting then and now moments.
I talked about the prototype and so I'm going to show you some pictures of the prototype
and actually what it looked like in game.
So the prototype continued, we continued working on the prototype for quite some time in the game
so it ended up where we were putting box models back into the prototype
to represent certain of the game world elements.
So this is one of our ports that you can explore
and this is what it looked like in the prototype.
This is what it looked like in game.
And there's another one.
So here's an island within the world.
And this is what it ended up looking like.
This is Shark Bait Cove with an interesting shark statue
in the middle.
And you may get eaten by sharks if you go into the water.
And also the deck of the ship, of course, important.
And that's what it looked like in game.
So it was really fun doing all these things.
A really fun thing that I don't know if any of you have seen the prototype
within some of the videos that we've actually released,
the world was filled with Tic Tacs for a long period of time.
So they always get a laugh.
They populated everywhere.
The mermaid, if you've ever seen the mermaid in our game,
she pops out of the water when your ship sinks
and she comes to your rescue.
The mermaid form of her is truly frightening
when she pops out of the water.
This massive buoy of a character pops up in front of you.
But that's what it looked like in game.
So few of the Tic Tacs have been hidden.
And finally, there's an island there next to the ship.
And here it is in game.
So this was a really interesting journey for us, making Sea of Thieves.
Sea of Thieves is a game about a pirate crew in a shared world adventure
with the freedom to choose their own adventure
that speaks to the charm and playfulness of Rare.
So that's the end of my talk,
and I'd just like to say thank you for coming today,
and if you have any questions at all, please do let me know.
Any questions?
Excellent.
Hi, Ryan.
Hello.
Thank you very much, and congratulations
for this release.
Thank you.
I have a question about the lighting.
Yes.
In your video, we see that the sun is almost
on a vertical trajectory.
Is it still like that in the game?
And if yes, is it a deliberate choice related
to art or a technical issue?
We played around with the way that Sun, I would have to think, the technical artist that did it.
We did actually explore different configurations of it, and we decided that just worked for us.
Really, it was as simple as that.
Okay, thanks.
Hello. Hello. I just wanted to say this game looks absolutely beautiful. Thank you very much.
And I was wondering, because you talk so much about putting history into like the items and
the characters, I was wondering what your process was for that when it came to conceptualizing the
islands, because there's so many different islands. Did you like create an individual
history for each of them, or?
So we did, yes, we did create a theme.
So to begin with, within the prototype,
they were just designed to create the feeling,
different feelings within it, whether it was a big valley
or lots of different islands together.
And then once we had those configurations of the landmass,
we started to look at what we could do
to create that sense of history.
So for instance, there's an island called Snake Island,
and we started adding lots of...
cave painting style things within it and also little artifacts and areas within it.
So yes, it was each, the artists kind of were given an island and tried to come up with a theme that they could dress it.
We've also got a riddle system when you're solving adventures within the world.
So you have to go around with a map and solve riddles and those riddles all tie to
those moments within the world that you can find. So it was key as part of gameplay and as well as the lore of the world.
Thank you. Okay.
Hello.
Um, sorry I'm losing my voice.
That's alright.
So I wanted to make it known that me and my group, when we first got in, we like immediately lost our ship.
And so we saw the Merman, and we named him Marmon the Merman, so I want to make that canon.
I'll have to talk to our writers.
Puns.
Okay, so I want to know how you decided that there wasn't going to be a tutorial.
Because that was like my favourite part of the game.
That there wasn't a tutorial?
Yeah.
That was born out of the fact that the prototype...
Okay, so, interesting story.
So yeah, so the prototype was made and we were just concentrating on the main mechanics.
And there was a big debate over how much of an onboarding there would be,
but there was a sense of trying to get discovery.
So, in the trailer in 2015 for E3, I think it was,
we actually invited a whole bunch of rare fans,
or people that entered competitions, to come and play the game.
And we've got these test labs at the studio,
and we put them all in a lab, and we didn't tell them anything.
They didn't know it was a pirate game.
They didn't, oh, maybe they did know it was a pirate game.
Yes, they knew it was a pirate game.
They didn't know what the mechanics were
or how to play it or anything.
And we just put them in the room
and then we all stood watching the feeds going like,
are they gonna work this out?
And they just started to work out.
They started to come together on the ship.
They started to climb.
And I think it was that approach to creating tools and
objects in the world that you could just understand to
interact with.
So the hope is that with a light bit of gentle prodding
in the general direction, people will
discover it themselves.
And that was, from talking with the designers, that was a
key part that they wanted to try and get across.
Okay, and so how did you decide that that would be better?
Because there's the risk of people immediately getting bored
and like, oh, this game has nothing in it,
when there's really a lot more than that.
I think it's, we're gonna look at feedback,
obviously, from players as well,
to see what actually happens.
But I think there's a lot of people
that appreciate it as equally need it.
So we're gonna weigh that up, and I think that's the thing.
First off, I just want to say your implementation of HDR
is probably the best I've seen in any game so far.
It is gorgeous on my big 4K TV.
It's amazing.
Great rendering team.
It's fantastic.
I did have a question about the transitions
of the weather and the sky between biomes.
Yes.
It's fairly instantaneous.
Like, you could be a green sky, and then it
goes perfectly blue, like, 10 seconds later.
Is that an intentional decision, or is that
something that's going to still be worked on in the future?
I think there are areas where it goes quickly.
So it really does depend how big the transition
between the zones are.
So we've actually shrunk some of those transitions down
for gameplay.
So we've actually brought the islands together and those
zones together.
So for those of you that don't know, see if these are
separated into three zones.
And there are a big three.
There's actually four different lighting zones
within the world.
There's a central neutral one.
And we squash those together.
So that's the way it is at the moment in the world.
But we're.
continually improving.
So now you've said that, I'm definitely going to go and
check that out.
Anecdotally, there's sometimes where you'll be sailing and
it's like you're just coming out of a storm.
And then it's like the sky is all green.
And then a split second later, it's like
perfectly blue skies.
It's like nothing dissipated.
It just sways.
Right.
I'm going to look at that.
Sounds like a bug.
Thank you very much.
Northeast side of the mountain.
Right.
We'll have a look at that.
Yeah, thanks for the talk.
It's really inspiring.
I'm curious, was the timing of the launch just a coincidence
with GDC?
Or was that planned?
It was just coincidence.
I see.
And I did debate whether I was going to do this.
Jeff actually invited me to come in and do this talk.
And I did sit at the studio going like, launch week, GDC.
But it was an opportunity to be here and actually.
and talk about the game so close to launch it felt like a fun thing to do
and how did the launch go?
exponentially hugely well uh... just massive uh... so
we've got more numbers than we ever dreamed of coming into the game
there's some ridiculous numbers like five thousand people a minute
trying to enter the game, it's just crazy
so very good awesome congratulations thank you
i think there's no more questions
So that's it. If anyone has got any other questions for me, I was actually told to remind
you of one thing, which was the questionnaire that gets sent out in email to you. If you
could fill that in, it's really helpful to the GDC organisers because they will know
what talks to put on next year if you found this interesting. Hopefully you did. If you
didn't, come and talk to me. I'll take the feedback anyway. And I'll be outside if anyone
wants to have a chat with me about anything. Okay? Thank you very much.