OK, so welcome, everybody.
It's very crowdy.
And I'm very happy to show you an overview of the hard
direction and the production pipeline we
use to create Heavy Rain.
Being there, talking from this side of the desk
gives a lot of emotion.
And it's quite a good thing, because at a
Quantic, we really love emotion.
So the title of this session is How
Heart Was Used to Create a Unique Cinematic Experience.
So just remember a few words of this title,
Create a Unique Experience.
Because when we start Heavy Rain,
it was really in our mind, not just making a good game,
but creating an experience.
Sometimes it succeeds.
Sometimes it fails.
So first, let's talk about Quantic.
We have been established in 1907 in France.
So I think that my accent speaks for myself.
We are 100 full-time employee, and we have in-house motion
capture facility, a 3D scan, and a sound studio.
We also develop experience based on emotion, as I already said.
Heavy Rain is a new format.
It's called interactive drama.
It's a blend between film and game.
It has been released last year exclusively on PS3.
So who am I?
I don't even know myself, but I can give you some key points.
So my name is Christophe Rousseau.
I'm the graphic director of the studio.
And I start in the old garage game time in a company called
Delphine Software International.
They do flashback.
So I joined them for the sequel.
Thank you.
Thank you for them.
And I work on motor research on PC and PS1.
I left the company to move to the movie and commercial
industry.
And I came back to video game as a lead set in 2001.
And I work on Fahrenheit, The Indigo Prophecy in US,
and on Heavy Rain.
How many people play to Heavy Rain in this room?
No.
OK.
So I will just show you a quick trailer for people
who don't play Heavy Rain.
Are you prepared to suffer to save your son?
You have five minutes.
Agent Norman Jayden, FBI.
Name me.
My name's Scott Shelby. I'm a private detective.
I'm investigating the case of the origami.
I'd like a run.
Madison Page, 27.
Single.
Ethan Mars has had psychological problems since his first son died.
He is haunted by visions of drowning bodies.
A few weeks ago, after one of our usual sessions, I found this on the floor.
They must have pulled him out of his pocket.
Ash, I want you to assign every available man to finding Ethan Barnes.
I want you to keep an eye on the train stations, the airports, the bus terminals.
I want every cop in the city on his ass, so that if he moves, we know about it.
You're gonna die, you son of a bitch!
I swore on my son's grave that I would kill the man who murdered him.
Just don't believe he's guilty.
Your other son was a shepherd. What was his name?
Everything I did, I did for love.
So it's a little bit darker, but let's go.
Let's talk about a few main topics.
First, the story.
After that, how we create the world of Heavy Rain.
and the characters, how do we animate them,
and the fifth main character.
So what is the vision behind Heavy Rain?
First of all, we wanted to create an experience that
engage the player emotionally and explore
the potential of interactive storytelling.
But we are also targeting a much more mature audience.
Every Rain is a new genre.
It's not based on challenges.
There is no boss to beat, no solving puzzle.
There is no game over.
You can lose one of your main character,
but you can still play the game and continue to discover
the story in the way you choose.
Every Rain.
A story is a multiple path story, so we have to write it
and also to produce it, all the different paths.
So some numbers, because everyone is a massive project,
2,000 pages of script.
It's very huge, because we have to write all the path,
all the dialogues.
all the gameplay, all the mechanics.
It means 70 unique sets, four main playable characters,
20 secondary, additional, many days of mo-cap shooting.
Hopefully, we have an in-house facility,
so it's much more easier for us.
Many body animation, many facial animation,
a lot of localization, and 60 scenes.
So Heavy Rain has a 2,000-page script.
We start by reading it.
And believe me, it's a huge task.
We do an initial list of mood boards
to identify some specific places directly taken from the script.
We do some visual research to identify a city, a place,
where the story can take place.
So it starts with some sketches, picture, some mood board,
maybe some K-color board.
Some rough art concept on some specific scene.
Here it's the crime scene.
I don't know if you remember, but it's
a huge scene in Heavy Rain.
And also color board just to under the feeling and the look
and feel we wanted to make on Heavy Rain.
We identify Philadelphia as a potential city,
but we wanted to avoid doing a French postcard
vision of this city.
And believe me, it's hard, because I'm not
an English-fluent guy.
So we use a movie scoot to tour to Philadelphia.
We take a plane.
and go scooting.
But we don't stay in the center of a city,
the historical center.
It's quite pretty, but it doesn't match to the script.
We try to go deeper to the suburbs,
from the middle class suburbs to the poor area.
The main goal was to avoid having a kind
of ideal vision of the city.
So by taking pictures, we identify some visual grammar.
But I will talk about it later.
Many picture, and sometimes some dangerous meeting.
Because on one.
And specifically in this picture, I remember that we were taking picture with the team
and the scout say, go in the car.
We don't notify that someone is coming with a gun and asking why we were taking some picture
of his district.
So I get in the car, never left it.
And we do all the scooting by the car and from the car.
No, I'm kidding.
Just for this part.
So we also went to an industrial area
trying to find a warehouse, whole power plants, piers.
We also visit people living in Cape Cod.
We go to a police department, hospital, office, newspaper.
I can't put images in my slide because there
is some privacy in there.
But we are very proud to be able to scoot this kind of location
because we've got to scoot.
couldn't have been done.
So we came back with a new understanding of a city
and sometimes emotion.
We have a huge documentation with many picture,
many video references.
We also identify what we call a visual grammar.
I mean, I don't know if you notice in the picture,
but there is many warehouse, bridges, electric pole,
electric power plant, many things
very linked to industrial, I mean, past industrial.
So we took these elements.
And we try to dramatize the vision,
because Philadelphia is just an inspiration.
Because everyone is a blend of game and movie,
we decide to recruit a design team
very close to the movie industry.
So set designer and architect are
in charge of creating and building realistic location
at human size and very precise blueprint.
Interior designer and researcher provide a precise vision
and documentation for the production team.
Set concept artist are.
in charge of illustrating the vision
and providing final art concept, and specifically light setup.
And the CG artists were in charge
of giving a virtual life to all these visual researchers.
So their goals.
First, creating realistic location at human size.
What does it mean?
Usually, in video games, all the location and spaces
are very large, huge like stadium, because you know,
we need to avoid collision issues and camera issues.
It's easier.
But we don't want to do that because we really
want to be close to a movie.
So we can't afford that.
It's also very hard to keep a realistic dimension,
because visually, when it's wrong,
you can see it very quickly.
We also find visually and strong atmospheric location,
specifically by scooting.
We also have to ensure consistency regarding
characters and gameplay hotspot.
Because we are talking about a game close to a movie,
it's a blend between game and movie,
we need to match location and characterization.
But also, we have to manage all the gameplay hotspot.
specifically to be able to match to the main mechanics
and the plot.
We provide a key color on each set and scene.
For people who play to every rain,
they can notice that there is a huge gap between the beginning
of the game.
and the rest of the game, I mean, before the accident
and after.
Before, it's very bloomy, colorful, very clean.
It's a kind of hideous life.
And on the rest of the game, every color is color wash.
It's rainy.
There is few saturation.
It's very diffused light.
It's chaotic and dirty location.
We do that.
just to improve the feeling of the happy time versus the bad time.
We also provide invisible storytelling.
So what is invisible storytelling?
Imagine the first time you go to someone else's house.
When you enter a room, you can...
identify many things at the first sight.
Maybe it could be a huge amount of books or comics,
baseball stuff, domestic mess, TV set or no, furniture style.
All these elements provide you information
on the people living here.
This is what we try to do in Heavy Rain.
We don't want to tell the past of a main character
during hours of cut scene and dialogues,
because remember, we had 2,000 page of script just
for the main plot.
So we try to provide visual background,
small pieces of their life.
And also, we asked the artist to make it stunning but depressive.
The initial design has been developed in 15 months.
So what is the design process?
The design process is quite simple.
we first build some sketches and blueprints for each location.
And we need to respect the gameplay hotspot.
We built in parallel a 3D placeholder of a set.
It's gray boxes.
And visual documentation package in mood boards.
We test the 3D placeholder directly
in real time in the engine.
And when it's validated in terms of gameplay, animation,
camera, we can finalize the art concept and the documentation,
package it, and it's go to production
for outsourcing or insourcing.
So here is some example of the blueprint.
So remember, it has been done by architect, so it can be built.
And sometimes we had to stop them because they
want to add details and too realistic details,
but saying that we need an electrical plug here,
and we need that.
And no, stop it.
We are making video game.
We are not building a house.
And also, they had a hard time when they came back
to the movie industry.
Because with video games, we are very strong.
We can do anything, just in 3D.
When they came back to the movie industry, it's hard.
There is some budget.
And wow, when you're trying to do an office in a church,
you have to find it.
You have to budget it.
You have to build it.
So here is some mood boards and picture references.
They provide a huge documentation on materials
for modeling and shading.
It's also give to the artist some messy places reference.
I mean that it's always hard to put some chaos in a set,
except in fantasy games.
But every object position has a reason in the everyday life.
When you go home, you throw your book on the sofa,
newspaper on the table.
And it has a meaning.
It needs to be real.
So providing chaos needs to provide consistency.
on the set.
And we've got a precise mood board for furniture, too.
You can see on the bottom left the gray boxes.
And here is a material board reference
for shadows and specularity.
And the concept art give atmosphere, key colors,
and a light setup.
So this concept art is taken from the Hisan House.
This one, too, is bedroom.
And so it goes on.
So many, many art concepts, because we have many locations.
And sometimes, lights setup, etc.
will change in the same location.
So it doubles the number of hard concepts.
Sorry, my computer is slow.
So the outside.
Let's go to the production team.
So in-house.
We are organizing small core team for each type of asset.
Each core team is in charge of producing, managing
all of the sensitive art and technical-driven assets,
and polish all the data coming from the art hosting partner.
So we can see that it's not a huge team, in fact.
Well, we have really a small team.
but with very skilled artists.
And we also do many months outsourcing.
So the set creation process, it's placeholder,
real-time testing, production in the Maya viewer, icing.
I mean polish, doing the lighting setup,
putting the visual effects.
and doing the post-processing.
So you will see a little video.
It's a placeholder.
And you've got the data coming from the outsourcing.
And after that, the polishing.
I think you can see the difference.
In this video, you saw the real-time testing.
So just do a pause.
We've got some dimension constraint,
because every set is recreated during the mock-up session.
So in this video, all the red objects
mean animation, maybe gameplay and interaction.
And for the blue surfaces, it means hand contact.
So when we send it to production,
it means that 3D production, but also.
animation and mocap production.
So when we've got a 3D placeholder like that,
we just have to recreate it on the mocap facility
and do the shooting.
And in parallel, we can also produce the polish set.
And this is a final result.
testing.
So we can also validate collision.
We can improve motion kit.
We can test camera shot.
So everything.
It's a kind of a skeleton for the production.
It's the same for the cinematic.
It's a kind of 3D storyboard.
So we can solve some technical issues.
visual issues, many issues, in fact.
Let's talk about the design of the characters.
So on the character side, design is slightly different
because every rain is based on emotion, story,
and characterization.
So characters are.
one of the main focus.
We need to find actors able to play, to give emotion,
to perform a scene like in the movie.
So everything starts with a casting
to identify the right actor.
And we do the same for the main characters,
but also for the secondary one or for sidekicks.
After that, fashion designer and art concept
provide mood boards and a final vision of the character.
Everything is packaged for production.
So here is some picture taken from the casting.
So the casting is done from board.
by agent, but also we've got video casting with dialogue
and scene to play.
This is Mr. Shelby before it was Ethan.
And this guy is not really an actor.
It's a guy.
who come in a free open casting.
And we say, oh, it's got a good look for one
of the secondary character.
So get on board.
This is a classic fashion design board with many details, rings,
all this small detail matching to the characterization.
And after that, final heart.
We also do, not in this case, but we also
do what we call the turnaround, just
to help the artist to do the body modeling.
So on character, the process is quite classical.
We do a photo session, 3D scan session.
We do the resurfacing in ZBrush.
and we produce and finalize the skin shaders
and specific visual effects directly in the Maya plugin.
The animation setup is also, I mean, rigging and skinning
is also done in Maya.
We do animation for body and for facial.
So this is a classic photo shooting.
Same guys.
This is a 3D scan.
So you can notice that it's not a magic tool.
It's quite precise, but we lose many details
in some specific area, like here's convex surfaces or airs.
So it's not a 360 degree scan.
So we are not able to perform a full body scan.
Concerning the resurfacing, we developed a tool
that enables us to project a face template
to match the 3D scan.
So it's quite useful and very quick,
because it ensures that each face has the right topology
for muscles and facial animation.
And all the micro details of the flesh,
I mean wrinkles, imperfection of the skin,
are added in ZBrush.
You can notice, too, that this guy is going much more badass.
So because we think that his face was too flat,
so we tried to make him much more aggressive.
So sometimes we have the freedom to change a little bit
to improve the characterization.
The body is totally built in ZBrush.
It's finalized in Maya and in the QD viewer.
And the polygon budget is close to $20,000,
approximately $10,000 for the head and $10,000 for the body,
depending on the fashion design.
We also do facial animation.
So we can test facial expression directly in the QD viewer.
So it's not blend shapes.
It's a bone-based system.
So let's talk about the tools.
After Fahrenheit, we've done a huge post-mortem,
and we asked the R&D to build a real-time viewer directly
integrated in Maya.
Because we really think that real-time visualization
is crucial in terms of production, but for artists.
We use Maya 8.5 integrated in OpenGL engine viewer,
directly linked to a PS3 remote.
So we can send automatically the data directly
through to the PS3 dev kit.
So the QD EPR Shed, it's a nodal material editor.
We've got our own shaders.
We've got real time on shading network and lighting.
The advantages, it's improved the artistic control.
We can build simple and complex shaders.
It's an artist-driven shader.
No need of a code.
It's easy to recruit, because when you're coming from a CG
and you know Maya quite well, it's the same.
But there is some disadvantages.
It means that you can build many, many, many shading
networks, and very complex.
So artists need to become much more technical.
The Maya Realtime Viewer and the PS3 Remote.
So we've got, as I say, real-time feedback
on shaders, lighting, animation, visual effects, and particles.
The main goals are always improving
the artistic control, polish, decrease time consuming export.
I mean, when you have to export, check in the engine.
So you saw some bugs where you need to do some visual retext.
You came back to your package, do the retext, re-export.
So it's boring.
And it spends too much time specifically on Fahrenheit.
So we say, no.
We need to have a much more smooth pipeline.
We also can do much more iteration.
The post-processing editor.
So it allows us to manage post-processing
as a 2D composite layer.
As you can see, the GUI is very close to the Photoshop style
layer.
So it's really easy to handle for juniors and for seniors.
We can do many iteration without changing any data.
So we can add a layer for saturation, for contrast,
for light, for luminance.
We can add depth of field, and we've
got the real-time feedback.
So everything is compiled in a kind of preset.
You save it, and you can send it to the camera department
or to the script.
And they can change dynamically the rendering.
So for prototyping, it's quite useful.
And for the final tuning, too.
We also had two tools.
It's an ambient occlusion manager.
I'm talking about everywhere, because now we don't use it.
But on everywhere, we are making ambient occlusion.
It was a huge Atlas sharing, quick baking, much more quick
than a mental ray.
And we can do some retakes in 2D package,
send the Atlas to Photoshop, fix some bug,
and get back to the engine.
The other tool we are still using it,
it's the ambience control.
It's a curve-based editor.
We can animate all editable parameters from any type.
So light intensity, meshes, specular power, skin shader,
attribute, texture, texture map, mask, everything.
So animating characters, I mean, the body part.
So we've got 28 Vicon.
I'm talking of an old time, because now we are 74.
The marker set is 55.
And we have many, many days of shooting.
We also use some stuntmen, because there
is some dangerous session.
I mean fighting, falling.
You will see a video.
So.
We also need to have some generic skeleton
with some archetype matching to the stuntman.
So the performance is split.
So we can reuse many small part of a session.
There is massive work on preparing the props.
As I said previously, we can build for real
on the mocap facility each set.
So each set need to be rebuilt.
And we've got a script always taking notes of any changes
during the session.
It requires a new approach of directing
because actors have no references.
And also, it's a huge investment from actors and long-term
collaboration, because we shoot many, many, many days.
And we really need to have the actors in-house,
because they are doing the body session, but also
the facial session.
So on facial, we shoot with camera.
We've got a much more complex marker set
because we need much more detail.
Last day of shooting, but I'm not sure that it's the,
I'm not sure that the actors agree.
We do the facial capture and the voice recording
at the same time.
Facial animation is split from body.
So it means that we can use any facial animation
on any body animation.
So it's quite useful, specifically
when you're talking about a game with many branching, many story
branching.
So it's very useful.
You don't have to redo all the animation
because they are standalone.
We also can do retargeting between characters
because the facial rigging has the same template
for every character.
Think about it.
When you do a facial mock-up, you
need to have the same acting as the body session.
So it's quite a huge issue for the actors.
So let's have a look to a kind of making of.
Come on!
Ah!
So I was supposed to show you some video of facial animation
taken in real time.
But we've got some issue between video and sound.
So nothing is synchronized.
It's not.
It's an epic fail.
So let's move on.
On the fifth character part, I mean the rain.
So when we scoot in Philadelphia,
it was supposed to be a rainy season.
We spend 10 days scooting, and it rains one single day.
Another epic fail.
We were a little bit disappointed.
So we start to build a huge collection of documentation
about rain, rain effect, just to identify
the main aspect of this natural phenomena.
So rain can be very different.
Can be smoggy, very diffuse, heavy, hard, very aggressive.
It's changed the color, the light, even the animation.
Because you can see that when it's raining,
people always doing like that because it's very aggressive.
So with this huge documentation.
The concept artists start to paint over a real picture
of a rainy day, just taken from the web.
And they try to improve, to maximize some of their aspect.
I mean, light diffusion, reflection, saturation,
specularity.
And it gives us a better understanding
of what we need to recreate.
So you can see that it has been paint over.
But rain, it's also small details.
Skies.
light and diffusion of light.
So I will show you in this video some example
of wet environment in heavy rain.
So this is the crime scene.
The butterfly power plant.
Some highway.
A junkyard.
The doghouse.
The highway taken from the taxidermist.
So in this video, you can see the different layers
we used to improve this rainy effect.
So a quick overview, because we need to have some lack of time.
Rain effects are not just compound
by layers of particles.
Usually, people say, let's do particles, and it's raining.
OK.
It's 2D layer and 2D sprite.
We also add some atmospheric effect with camera shaders
and post-processing effect.
We change materials specularity, and we do many adjustments.
We also add some procedural ripples.
We've got also the bouncing effect
by adding secondary particle.
And we also use wind effect created by VertexWind.
But I'm not very proud of this part, because it sucks.
Also rain.
It's rain.
on props, there, but also on this car.
So you can't afford to not having rain on a car.
It's raining everywhere.
But it's the same on the windows.
It's very dark.
So as I say, rain interacts with all props.
We had some reflection effect on transparent materials,
animated normal maps, ripples effect,
animated UV texture map to create some flow effect.
We animated a mask and video for the weeper.
It's not a dynamic fluid simulation.
And we synchronized video with Mesh's animation.
We also had to create over-fluid effect, not just rain.
For people who played heavy rain,
there is a huge sequence when Madison had a shower.
So this is not Madison, sorry.
Next time.
We also have a huge sequence when a car is floating.
So we are supposed to do that in real time.
It's a huge challenge.
This sequence has been canceled because it
was too paranormal for the story.
So the icing hasn't been finished.
But in fact, we were flooding the Ethan house.
with water.
So MISC effect done by dynamic particles, collider setup
for the shower, secondary bounces also on the shower.
We animated crack mask, meshes, swap for explosion,
for window explosion.
We've got 2D decal also for crack windows, sprite,
reflection materials.
Thank you.
What is water without fire?
So let's burn.
We do fire meshes with a UV texture slide, smoke meshes,
UV slide.
We fake also some lighting variation,
add some fire and sparkle particles, reflection meshes.
for heat effect, additional smoke particles.
And we need to do that for a 360 degree camera.
And we need to avoid field rate issues.
So here is the final result.
It spoils a little bit but...
So a conclusion.
AVN requires a lot of high detail and high quality data.
Also, many tips and tricks, because we
can't afford technically to do everything
with real-time simulation.
Rain is still, for me, difficult to simulate in real time.
And the other challenge we have to solve
was avoiding a hunkany valley effect.
It's been a real daily fighting.
Interactive drama is a kind of juggernaut.
many data management, many things to produce, many paths,
a huge testing step.
And also, it requires a new way to work, especially
regarding the complexity.
And we hopefully add many tools to help us.
The communication.
for us is quite crucial, because we've
got some artistic team in-house, but also overseas.
Not on the same page, because there is some cultural gap.
We need also to communicate cross-department challenges.
And also, we need to communicate with publisher.
Every rain is not a first person shooter.
So you can't do a vertical slice of a story and say, oh,
that's it.
You can't do that.
So in the early stage, we have one scene.
We can test it, show it, show many graphics.
But the project start to be really strong
when everything is built.
so close to the alpha.
Because you have the big picture,
you can handle the story, the complexity of a story.
So it's quite hard to communicate to publisher,
but also hard to communicate to the team,
because they always saw some details, some scene, some set,
some characters.
But they can't handle the big picture.
even if they had to read the script, 2,000 pages.
So we had to communicate the art direction,
to do micro synopsis, and always, always communicate
internally with the team.
We also had to make people more productive and creative.
So build a solid pipeline, provide tools.
and also increase the creation phase versus the data
management time.
So in conclusion, always try to be challenging, to be involved,
and to bring new concept to life.
Thank you for attending.
Thank you for your passion.
Sorry for your ears.
And thanks to the Conti Dream team, because without them,
we can't ship the game.