I'm Kim Swift and I was a level designer and the team lead on Portal.
And I'm Eric Wilpaugh and I was a writer on Portal.
So we're here to talk to you today a little bit about our techniques for integrating narrative and design
sort of phrased as a portal post mortem giving examples of what we particularly did.
So, in case you're wondering, post-mortem means we will be talking about stuff that's
in the game.
So if you haven't played the game and you're one of those people that gets all squealy
and upset, you know, whenever someone tells you something that you hadn't heard about
a game, then, you know, you might want to leave the room, you know, or not.
That's my two.
So here's what we're going to try and cover to be a first of all, I'm going to make a real brief case of why you should care about anything we're going to tell you.
Secondly, I'm going to go real quickly into our narrative philosophy, which is sort of our crackpot theory of how gameplay and narrative should be combined.
And third of all, we're going to talk about how we took the crackpot theory and tried to apply it to our development process.
So in particular, why should you care about how we did this on Portal?
Well, first of all, we had a really small team with about only 10 people at once working
on the game.
It usually was anywhere between like five and seven.
And it's been pretty popular and, you know, for a surprise.
And despite the game being kind of unorthodox.
So after all is said and done, we actually don't really have any regrets, unlike this
poor guy.
So, you know, now, why would you care about how we put together our narrative and design?
So, by itself, our story wouldn't really make a whole great novel.
You know, don't get me wrong, the dialogue's just really, really funny.
He's probably about the funniest manual ever made, just in case you were wondering.
Set in a bar pretty high for the talk.
Sorry about that.
Nothing funny.
See, there's no ad living now from a point of view.
And on its own, the gameplay, it'd be alright, but honestly, a little on the dry side, honestly
it would be a race to see which one would fail the fastest on its own, but because
we had a really tight integration of both our story and our gameplay, it seemed to
really resonate with people and, you know, it worked.
Like Kim said, our team size kind of imposed a lot of constraints on our design choices.
So, our design methods from the beginning had to be low impact on both our time and energy budgets.
But this kind of helped us creatively sidestep a lot of our constraints.
For instance, Gladys being a disembodied voice.
might not have actually occurred to us if we'd had a ton of animators and a ton of resources
to make her a little robot buddy that followed you around or something, and yet it kind of
turned out to be just the perfect solution to the narrative and portal.
So here's a crackpot theory.
The idea is that games tell two stories.
There's a story story, which is sort of the sum total of the game's dialogue cutscenes.
And then there's the gameplay story, which is the story described by the actions the player takes in the game world.
And if you lower the delta between those two stories, the closer you put them together, the more satisfying your game will be.
Or at least that was our theory.
There's a lot of games that I think suffer from a high-story Delta, but since the Game
Developers Conference, if I run down a lot of them, it's going to be like super dick
moves.
So I'm not going to do that.
I don't really want to die today.
Yeah, I'm going to mention one game that I actually like a lot, so it should be non-controversial.
It's also kind of old.
is Clive Barker's Undying, which is a first-person shooter that was released like six years ago.
And it's a good shooter, and regardless of what you may think about his style, Clive Barker,
and that's him wearing super scary pair of pants.
He's a talented writer who actually, in interviews, I think seems to care a lot about the story in his games.
So, Clyde Barker's on Dying. You play this World War I war hero who goes to Scotland to visit the castle of one of your war buddies.
And the castle is sort of infested with ghouls, and you're shooting a lot of monsters and
there's a lot of death and destruction all around.
But pretty frequently as you're going through the mansion, the game all of a sudden stops
to play one of these cutscenes where you sort of calmly interrogate one of the members
of the staff.
You know, you're sort of, you know, what do you do, how are you doing, how are you feeling,
stuff like that.
Meanwhile, at no point does your character just grab the help by the label and say, you know, like there are monsters five feet around that corner
killing everyone they come across, you need to run. Now, the two stories make absolutely no sense when you smush them together.
An idea, or I'm dying, is one of the first times that I remember a good game sort of being undermined by a disconnect
between the story the gameplay was telling and the story the story itself was telling.
So, with all that in mind, our fundamental portal narrative design goal was that the
story story would never ever intrude or contradict the gameplay story.
For us, the less was always more, and we were ruthless about it.
We were ruthless about trimming the narrative fat, tightening our belts, and then trimming
it even more.
Portal was going to be a lean storytelling machine if it killed us.
And usually it meant killing me, because it was a lot of good lines that had to get
cut.
And we're really sorry about that.
It was worth it.
So, enough about how we feel about games,
like let's talk about how we practically
applied these feelings.
First of all, we're gonna talk a little bit
about our playtesting process,
which by the way, in case you were wondering,
it's really important.
Second, reflecting story in your environment.
Next, evolving narrative out of gameplay,
and then again, vice versa,
evolving gameplay out of narrative.
So, playtesting is probably the most important thing we ever did on Portal.
You know, actually sit down and watch people play your game.
Don't just, you know, have some other company playtest the game and then send your report
afterwards.
It's, you know, just not going to be as valuable to you as just sitting down, having someone
play your game, and you watch them and see how they react to it.
You can find out what your players actually want by watching them.
In the case of Portal, we adjusted our gameplay to what players looked like they needed.
Did they need more training?
Because clearly they were really confused here.
You know, maybe they needed more reinforcement of what we trained them on.
Because they wanted to use those new skills.
And in addition to that, we also adjusted our story to enhance essentially what our players were feeling at that time.
Yeah, and frequent play tests help keep us objective about our design decisions.
Watching play tests is a great way to expose pretty quickly what isn't working.
One rule we had narrative-wise was, at the end of a play test, we would ask play testers
to just...
Tell us the portal story back beat by beat and if they couldn't tell it to us
We took that as a real clear sign that they just weren't interested that we were failing and the fix for it
Almost always was just to cut more story cut more exposition. It usually meant cutting something that initially seemed
Essential to the story and as it turned out it just made it stronger every time we cut something
Says something about the writer. Yeah, I'm sorry
Another thing is, playtest early and often, on the far side there, you can see what the
first room in the game actually looked like, you know, maybe a couple weeks into development.
And then on the other side, you can see what it finally shipped, you know, as.
And we literally started testing this room the first week that we got to Valve and started working on the game.
We hacked portals together in some horrible way, but we're glad it doesn't exist anymore.
And we were already making better decisions about what our levels were like.
So I don't know, it's kind of hard to make out.
But in the first picture, there's kind of like this shimmery force field, which was the original cage for the player.
And we got rid of this pretty quickly because our playtesters just didn't understand what it was.
They would walk up to the forest field and they were wondering why they couldn't walk through it.
So they would just trace the edge of the cage five times and get really confused.
So we changed it to glass just to fix that problem.
So not only did our play testing help us
get a better narrative and get better gameplay,
it also helped us refine our art direction.
As you can notice in the later picture,
it's a lot cleaner, it's a lot simpler.
We extracted any of the elements
that didn't really have any relevance to the player
and it really helped us teach the players
what they needed to know.
So, as just kind of a digression, I labeled this slide advice because this is the only
one I'm fully behind as advice of anything we're going to say today.
This is actually good advice.
If you're writing a funny game, first of all, God help you because it's unpleasant because
tough guy dialogue is just about as macho the 50th time you hear it as the first time,
whereas funny dialogue is funny once, maybe.
About three years ago, I worked on a game called Psychonauts that I helped write back there.
There's more people clapping than bought it.
Now I lost my train of thought, working at Psychonauts, Double Fine, oh, so Double Fine
is kind of structured, everybody sits in one big room, there's 40 people maybe, sitting
in one big room, and it's, you know, the two and a half years that I was there, no game
development, it's 12 hours a day, six, seven days a week.
And so I've had to sit there in the middle of this pit of people working on Psychonauts
hearing my supposedly funny dialogue blaring out of 40 monitors to just brim stony silence.
And it was just, it was torture, it was psychological torture for me because Tim wisely had his own
office somewhere where you didn't have to hear the brim stony silence.
So, yeah. This is you writing a funny game, you are going to exist in a black cloud of
despair for however long it takes you to make the game. But, so here's the advice.
Trust your instincts, try and remember your initial reaction, people's initial reactions
to seeing it and, you know, do whatever you can do to not despair.
But the first part, the part that helped us a lot, again, on Portal, is play tests.
The more often you play test, the more often you actually get to see someone, hear in your
dialogue, seeing the game for the first time.
And it's honest to God, whatever the benefits of play testing are for the design team, for
a writer.
But it is the only way really to maintain your sanity during the two or three years
that's going to take you to make the game.
Or Prozac.
Yeah.
And all, yeah.
Medication.
So another thing we tried to do when we had to cut exposition was to, if we didn't want
to cut it all together, was to try and embed exposition in the environment.
When we were initially talking about it, we had some e-mail ideas for embedding an e-mail and we were actually using e-mail to talk about putting an e-mail and at some point we discovered that reading e-mail wasn't actually that fun.
Did you enjoy reading that last e-mail? I was like, no, it wasn't that exciting. We probably shouldn't have put it in the game.
So that was one of our rules, and the idea was try and be creative about reflecting
and storing the environment, and again, easy to say be creative, but if you apply a ruleset
and then you're ruthless about the rules, it's amazing how creative you can get in a
big hurry if it's a choice between coming up with some novel way to embed your exposition
to the environment and simply cutting it all together.
So what we did in Portal, at least one of the things we did, was to have these little
wall scribblings in the behind-the-scenes areas of the game.
And honestly, these were really quick and easy to do, like they really only took like
one or two days tops.
And they were pretty effective at telling a story.
So here's an example of the room.
And you know, I'm going to show you a little bit of what I'm going to show you today.
Put yourself in the position of your characters.
What would they do in the situation of the game?
So in this case, we had this idea for a character
that we called the Ratman.
And he was supposed to be a fellow escaped test subject,
just like you, and he's a little loopy.
And we originally wanted you to actually meet this NPC
at some point in the game, but we had two artists.
It wasn't really feasible.
So rather than just sort of cut our back story on this guy, we decided to manifest
him here in these rooms.
So I asked myself if I was trapped inside an insidious facility bent on my destruction
run by a homicidal AI, what would I do to pass the time?
So, another big tool we used was to try and evolve our narrative out of gameplay.
Like Kim said, we tried to write to enhance what playtesters were feeling,
which required me to try and keep the story as wet as possible.
A big, big hurdle to overcome to just not get attached to any piece of writing.
And, yeah, because it was just going to disappear at any given time,
and we'd have to think up something else.
And the same goes for gameplay, too.
Don't get too attached to anything.
You might need to cut it, and it's probably for the best.
So here's an example of that, like the way to companion cube.
So we're going to talk about this first from a game design
standpoint of one day we sat down and decided
we wanted to make what we called the box marathon level.
So where essentially you've got your cube at the beginning
of the map, and then you take it all the way through to the end
of the map, and put it on a button.
It's supposed to be a big, long obstacle course.
So the first thing that we tried was having sort of this moving platform, you know, over
a goo pit where you'd have to stand on it with your box and avoid stuff, kind of similar
actually to the last test chamber that we shipped.
And you know what? It pissed players off, like, to no end.
They would end up destroying the box by dropping it in the goo, and they'd get really annoyed because they had to go back to the beginning of the map,
and, you know, they didn't really want to carry this stupid thing with them everywhere.
So we went back to the drawing board.
The first thing we did was remove the moving platforms over the goo, you know, so you couldn't destroy the box,
and we added more gameplay events where having the box is necessary for you to solve the puzzle.
So here's a couple examples. One side there you can see that we use the cube to kind of make a dynamic set of stairs there to get up those platforms.
And then on the other side, it's a puzzle where you have to put the box on one of these buttons and then go stand in another button and get this energy ball through those doors into a catcher thing.
And these work pretty well in terms of making players at least somewhat take the box with
them and not hate it, but players were still kind of forgetting it.
They'd leave it at one puzzle and then go to the next puzzle and go, oh crap, and then
have to go back to the beginning and grab their box.
So we said, okay, maybe if we redesign this room so that way you're always kind of facing
this button and taking a look at it.
So that worked pretty well, at least, to remind players, by the way, you need this at the
end of the map.
But, you know, we needed something else, like players really weren't getting that attached to the box and there were still a few people that would kind of forget it behind.
And so, Eric to the rescue over here.
Though as much as possible we tried to, you know, put hints for our players, you know, in the environment, whether it be through lighting or geometry.
You know, when all else fails, great dialogue really was a great tool for us to give a hint to the player.
Yeah, I've been reading, luckily, these declassified government interrogation manuals, and one
of the things...
They're awesome.
I recommend them.
They put it up on them.
They're really cool.
But one of the things they talked about was that isolation leads interrogation subjects
to start becoming attached to inanimate objects.
And kind of just something clicked.
It was like, well, you're sort of alone this whole time.
And maybe if Plattus psychologically
needles you a little bit, you know, it would work.
And crazily, I mean, they know what they're doing.
They're government interrogation specialists.
They were right.
Yeah, it totally worked.
It's super duper work.
No one ever forgot their box after we put in that dialogue.
That's for sure.
And sort of as an afterthought, you know,
we put these pink hearts, they're so pretty,
on the cube, just to kind of cue back to the dialogue,
there's something special about this box
and you should take it with you and take care of it.
Yeah, that worked.
And honestly, this was a really great thing for us
just because it had a dual function
as far as the ending of this map went.
And the first thing is, well,
At the time that we were finishing up this map, we were also working on our ending boss battle,
and we had settled at the time on...
just disintegrating these little parts of Gladys.
And we had an incinerator in the map,
and we didn't train our players.
So obviously they had no idea what they were doing,
and they'd have to press the switch
to open up the incinerator,
and they completely ignored it,
and then they would wander around the room
and then get really angry at us.
So we obviously had to train this somewhere,
and we had a great idea of where to put the training.
Yeah, originally, up until almost the last minute,
at the end of the companion cube level,
you just had to just leave the companion cube.
You had to abandon it because you couldn't bring it with you
into the elevator.
And Gladys made some reference to it being euthanized.
And it was sort of sad, but it wasn't really
a good ending to the level.
So putting the incinerator there and having you
be forced to euthanize it was just an awesome way to end it.
and and in addition to that it was also a great place to train the player
because there is no stress there is no pressure for the stress of killing
well yeah it was a little stressful
But more like, you know, there was nothing shooting at you or, you know, they didn't have a clock ticking down, like, oh my god, I've got to do this in 10 seconds.
And we did that because, well, players do not learn anything when they're completely stressed out, like, they just won't absorb anything.
So putting the training there was pretty good.
Also, it provided a really great point to our narrative as well, because, you know,
you get to incinerate Gladys the same way she made you incinerate your best friend.
The whole companion cube saga was just a really great example of how the gameplay kind of
influenced the story which then turned around and influenced the gameplay.
Okay, so having said all that about how it's gameplay, gameplay, gameplay, no narrative,
we did reach a point where we discovered that gameplay wasn't really working by itself.
And this was the original ending of Portal.
Honestly, the biggest obstacle to us when making Portal was our ending boss battle.
You know, we look at other games, okay, we know what a boss battle will look like in
a first person shooter or an RPG, but what in the world is a boss battle going to look
like in a weird environmental puzzle game?
Yeah, the first thing you'd think, or at least the first thing we thought was that the boss
monster for a puzzle game should be a deviously complex puzzle.
And that sort of innocuous sounding conclusion
really just gave us a lot of headaches and pain.
So we're gonna show you a few examples
of some things that we tried as boss battles
and eventually abandoned for one reason or another.
So the first one that we tried was James Bond lasers.
So, literally, they were big giant lasers that would follow the player around trying
to zap them, and obviously we cut this.
Here's, I know, aren't they pretty, isn't that nice?
These are training maps that we had for the James Bond style lasers.
where essentially you'd have to place your portal in front of the laser and then place
one on a wall and then redirect the laser at that weird orange thing sitting in that
glass wall.
and, you know, break through and be able to get to the other side where you would meet
Gladys.
That's Gladys there in her giant shimmery cube face.
Don't you love temp art?
It's great stuff.
And once again, you'd have to redirect those lasers at those, you know, which you find
out are orange plugs supplying Gladys with power.
And you know, the end.
Yeah, it was not good.
The lasers were extremely boring to dodge
and kind of difficult to tune
because we would make them follow the player kind of fast
and then it would be unfair
and if we slowed them down, then they're boring.
They were also really difficult to aim,
believe it or not, through a portal.
It was kind of a pain.
And it was also hard to tell
if you were hit by the lasers too,
so we abandoned this idea
and instead chose to use a rocket launcher.
So the second attempt that we had was portal combat.
Um, sorry, I had fun with Photoshop one day.
So, you know, we had a lot of players, you know, test our games that were hardcore first-person shooter players.
So they were like, we need more action and you need to jump around and be a crazy portal ninja.
And so we were like, yeah, okay, sure, we'll get a shot.
And, you know, it didn't really work out very well.
Here's a picture of a level that we actually shipped in the game.
And this is what it originally looked like.
So this was supposed to be the first time
that you would meet Gladys,
and you can see that there's a rocket launcher there.
We had put it in at that point.
And you would have to redirect your portal,
redirect the rockets and use your portals
to shoot Gladys in the face.
But then that's Gladys, yeah.
She's a bunch of roller mines.
So this was, yeah, it was okay.
But we then made it a little bit more complex, so she would rise to the top of this room
and then all of these little pillboxes would pop open with turrets in them
and the rocket launcher was still on and you'd have to try and redirect the laser and hit her again.
And all the meanwhile the turrets are firing at you, the rocket launcher is firing at you and just not fun.
So, yeah, the high-intensity gameplay sucked.
In fact, it sucked so bad that I'm talking when you're supposed to be reading this, is that true?
No, no, it's all right.
But anyway, I'll finish it. It sucked. It was bad.
It sucked so much, I'm not gonna let Kim talk about it, but it sucked, because I hated it so much.
No one paid attention to Gladys, any of her dialogue, because there's just way too much stuff going on.
And we had playtesters who'd come in who were sort of hardcore counter-striker shooter fans,
and they were able to wring a little bit of enjoyment out of it,
but the vast majority of our playtesters who had sort of gotten used to the slower-paced cerebral nature of Portal
were just frustrated and confused and dissatisfied, which was absolutely not the way we kind of wanted to send them out the door.
So, the final attempt was to have a chase sequence.
And that's Gladys there as the kitten.
Isn't she cute?
So here's kind of what that looked like.
This is actually a continuation of the previous section,
where Gladys would rise up to the top of the ceiling.
Well, after you hit her with the second rocket,
she'd rise up even more and would zoom down this hallway.
And you would actually have to follow her by flinging a couple times and getting up into this hallway.
Honestly, the pacing was just horrible because players wouldn't necessarily see where she would go.
They didn't know where they were going, so they would wander around for a while, and
they'd eventually realize, oh, I don't think I've been there before, and, you know, kind
of get up there.
But, you know, if it's a chase sequence, it's supposed to be action-packed, you're supposed
to be going, going, going, and, you know, instead players are just wandering around confused.
And then, once you actually got up into this hallway, we wanted to make it seem like, oh, Gladys had sprung some sort of trap and to kill you.
So we had all these pistons kind of like break out of the walls and, you know, try and crush you or, you know, block you from getting further.
And we also, you know, had these turrets and stuff pop down from the ceiling.
And if you actually played the game, you can see that these hallways are kind of similar to what we shipped.
And we took a lot of stuff out because...
Yeah, this, I'm going to bother reading down, this failed in every way it's possible for a level like that to fail.
It had bad pacing, players didn't really know what was going on, was glad us making the pistons come out at you,
and every solution we came up with to try and fix those were either too expensive for us to do or just made the gameplay even worse.
So a complex boss battle, yeah, it didn't work.
And the thing that we actually learned from all this
was that the more complex that we made our puzzles,
the slower the pacing actually got,
because players would have to stop and think
about what they were gonna do next.
And if you watch an action movie and you get to the climactic sequence, there's something
happening all the time.
And in our game, when we wanted it to be climactic because we made everything more complex, it
did the opposite thing than what we expected.
So it's funny to us now, but we were desperately screwed at this point because episode 2 was
winding up.
T.F., after 10 years, was going to beat us out.
And, you know, the episode two guys are running around,
they're like, our final battle is going to be
100 striders, and you're going to be driving a car
and running into little mini striders.
They're like, what are you guys doing?
Like, it's a secret.
So, but again, once again, our old friend PlayTesting
helped us.
There was a point, and I don't know why we didn't realize it
earlier on, but there was one piece of feedback
that we were getting, that there was a point in the game
that PlayTesters felt, excuse me,
was both climactic and satisfying.
And it's the fire pit.
It happened about 2 thirds of the way through the game.
The testing proper, the regular testing.
Well, I'm going to take a drink of water.
It's almost over, and Gladys is kind of talking you out.
You're riding this platform into a fire pit.
And you eventually, you escape out of here.
But playtesters were just consistently telling us,
not only was this dramatic and exciting,
they kept telling us that it was actually like,
it was a really tough puzzle that I felt super satisfied
to solve, which absolutely made no sense to us.
Because,
yeah.
Yeah, I know, it's a good thing.
Portal, Portal 2 is just going to be this picture over and over.
When it comes right down to it, at that point in the game, that's about the easiest puzzle in Portal.
You place a portal on the wall next to the fire pit, and then you place one in the safe area, and you just hop through it.
That's it.
So we then had to sit down and reflect.
Like, what in the world made this so climactic?
And one of the things that we learned was that, well,
it had time pressure.
You know, there was only a limited amount of time
while you're on that platform
before you're gonna get burned alive
to place your portals and escape.
I think I've said before, you know, time pressure makes people think something that is a lot more complicated than it actually is.
Another thing was it had a really high visual impact. I mean, you can't really go wrong with a platform heading straight into a giant pit of fire for visual impact.
And, you know, it's something that our players have never seen before in the game, and so it's, you know, something new.
is also a dramatic high point, because for the first time,
Gladys is pretty openly trying to kill you.
And also for the first time, you're able to assert a little bit of control over your environment and escape from her.
And like Kim was saying, all of those three things combined made it so that an easy puzzle
was sort of feeling like a much more complicated puzzle.
which allowed us, led us to the realization that we've been holding on to this idea
that we needed a complex puzzle at the end and it simply just wasn't true.
So here's what we actually shipped in the game is Boss Battle.
You can see Gladys there with her little personality spheres.
And then next to her was a hatch where a rocket launcher would pop up.
And you'd have to reorient the rockets and hit Gladys, take one of those spheres,
and then put it in the incinerator by getting to the activation switch with your portals,
and then getting back to the incinerator and tossing it in.
The end, done.
So, taking the four lessons we learned, this is how we applied them to the final claddus battle.
First of all, it was time pressure.
We were ourselves under some time pressure, so instead of getting fancy, we actually just had a timer
counting down to something that would kill you.
And we decided that thing that would kill you would be some neurotoxin, because it was also really cheap
just to make a green particle system.
You laughed, but it's seriously true.
Yeah, 100% true.
So, you know, visual impact.
Well, on one side of the screen, you know, on the far side over there,
you can see a piece of concept art that an artist at Valve, Jason Braschel,
did for us. Thanks, Jason.
And on the other side there, you can see what we actually shipped.
So everything in this room visually is pointing at Gladys.
You know, got the geometry of the stairs leading up to her,
got all the lights pointing at her.
But you know, after all this time of hearing Gladys heckle you and harass you, you know,
we wanted to make this room have some serious impact.
And you know, I think it did its job pretty well, and you know, it's not like any other
room in the game, and so I think it really gave players a sense of satisfaction.
And then in terms of a high dramatic moment, putting some time pressure.
to the puzzle, made it so that I only had to write, like, six minutes of decent dialogue,
which is in stark contrast to all our previous attempts, which required me to write infinity
minutes of excellent dialogue.
Which makes Eric crack.
Yeah, that was a bad time for me, writing the infinity minutes of dialogue.
And finally the easy puzzle, you know when all of a sudden done portal is a puzzle game
but all the things that we learned led us back towards you know we need to simplify this
puzzle so adding time pressure and then you know having it be a very dramatic room and
have a lot of really interesting points made by Gladys, scaling back the puzzle allowed
players to really absorb this moment and have a good time.
And, you know, honestly, at least for me, there's nothing more frustrating than getting
to the finale of a game and not being able to beat that stupid boss battle and see the
ending of the game, which, in our case, we really wanted people to see or rather hear.
So, we wanted to leave players, you know, with a real sense of satisfaction, and, you know, scratch that.
We wanted players to feel genuinely happy and leave the game with a smile on their face.
So, yeah, we sat down and kind of made a list of what makes people happy, and then we kind of made a list of what we could put in a game,
and then put it into Excel, and PivotTable, and...
The catchy song kind of floated to the top and this is Jonathan Colton who we got to
write our catchy song.
Who is wearing his best hat by the way.
And so you know when all of a sudden a lot of this actually came out of our constraints.
We had a small team, we had a limited amount of time and frankly we just couldn't make
a giant FMV epic finale of Doom and the cost to happiness ratio of putting a song over
some scrolling text was really high.
So, the moral of the whole thing for us was just try to fully embrace your constraints as fuel for creativity.
Honestly, without the constraints that we had, I truly believe Portal would not be as good a game as it turned out to be.
And in addition to that, you know, have faith in yourself, have faith in your writing,
and in the skills of your team, because they're your best resources, you know.
And once again, play test, play test, play test, and when you're done with that, play
test some more, because honestly, you will get the most valuable information for your
game out of watching your play test, and it'll make for a better player experience in the
end.
That's it.
So we deliberately kind of kept our top short because, you know, we kind of assume people
had questions because we keep getting asked questions.
And so, you know, we wanted to just kind of make our point and then leave the floor open
to you guys to, you know, ask us whatever you want.
So questions?
You?
Is there a microphone?
Oh, okay. Okay, fine.
Can you hear me okay?
Yeah.
Okay, so my question is you touched earlier on not using emails for voice recording for like, like, story segments in your environment.
Um, and, you know, we're most probably, I think, however, a lot of successful games use this a lot.
Most notably Resident Evil and most recently Bioshock.
And they're all bad games.
Next question.
No.
Oh, yeah, I have no idea. None of these are actually prescriptive.
You know, go for it if you want. It was just a personal choice we made.
I think it can work out just personally. I don't like to read that much.
I don't like to read in-game. I mean, I like to read books.
But when I'm in a game, I just want it to kind of happen and we not have to read that much.
And Eric, we had been talking about this before, and Eric made a really good point, which was,
You know, how often do you use a voice recorder to leave secret messages for your friends
and family?
Well, I mean, yeah, that's the thing.
These futuristic games, there's always like, oh, we're in the future, and everybody's
leaving messages on PDAs.
I can go buy PDA for $8 at Best Buy now, and nobody's using it to deliver messages to me
ever.
So, yeah, we just...
So that's our own personal hangup with those two things, but I think they're fine in games.
Uh, guy standing at the mic?
Oh, there's people at the mic.
This isn't plugged in, so if I start standing here anyway, it would look like a good place to stand.
Yeah, it's a great place to stand, gotta say.
I wanted to ask this question because I thought it was exactly the type of thing that I think of Eric normally really against.
Why does Gladys have an incinerator in her room other than just in her room?
There's actually kind of a funny story.
So the question was, why does Gladys have an incinerator sitting in her room?
And the answer is actually kind of fun.
Like, we were talking sort of like a backstory, and they're one of, like, so they created
this giant AI, and they weren't really sure at Aperture Science if she was going to go
out of control, so they made this room so that way, you know, if she did completely
lose her mind, they could, you know, incinerate her and get rid of her.
There's a red phone in there that is supposed to be, there was a guy who, that was his job
to sit there and call somebody, if it looked like the AI was going rogue, and then they
come and throw it in the thing, and it sadly didn't work.
It really was bad by aperture science, they're sort of half geniuses, half morons, so.
So you mentioned playtesting as a really critical step, but also not outsourcing it to another group.
How do you go about selecting and acquiring a steady supply of new players throughout your process?
How did you guys go about doing that?
So the question was, how did we go about getting new playtesters all the time to playtest our game?
Do you know how easy it is to go walk out to the nearest GameStop and say,
hey, we've got this game, do you want to come play it?
And I mean, yeah, it's just like, yeah, of course.
And also we had friends and family come in and play tests.
Gabe's kids actually play tested for us.
You want me to say something?
Oh, just in Valves, there's a lot of people working at Valves
who are kind of heads down on their own projects.
So we had a lot of people who could just come in,
you know, from other parts of the company as well.
And did you ever have people come back for like additional tests or was it sort of a
you test once and that's all the useful information.
So the question was, do we have people come back
and playtest again?
Usually we would have people playtest once,
but we had a few playtesters, mainly at Valve,
who seemed to really like Portal and were stubborn,
so they wouldn't really get frustrated easily,
so when we would have a puzzle that we wanted to try out
that was really, really rough,
and we just wanted to see if the concept was good,
we would usually grab one of those guys
and have them sit down and chug through it.
In the developer commentary, you said there will be more portal games, and obviously your
first couple of sides show you're having a lot of success, and when that happens you
get a lot of resources, you won't be a little tiny team, so what kind of, are you afraid
or how will you overcome the challenge of not having as many constraints, and next year
you have to say the question.
Oh, so how will we make a next portal if there is one?
How can we keep some of our design philosophies if we have a lot more resources?
It's a good question.
I don't know.
I'm scared to tell you the truth.
I know how it's going to work.
I'm trying to just bask in the moment now about people bugging me about the next one.
Let me enjoy it for one minute.
No, but seriously, I don't know.
I, yeah, I don't know.
A little bit of a personal flashback for me, but as I remember toward the end of Narbacular
Drop, there is a puzzle where you're required to
to aim through one of the doorways and put a portal on the wall on the other side in
essence to shoot through, which was very elegant as a way of pushing the mechanics of the game
to its limit, I suppose.
And I noticed, of course, that in Portal, you chose for one reason or another not to
allow the player to fire the...
the portal gun through one portal.
I can think of a couple of reasons why you might have done that, but I was just wondering
if it was for technical purposes or as part of a larger idea of some sort.
So the question was, so in our Baccalaureate Drop, we gave players the ability of being
able to shoot one portal through another portal, and we decided to not do that for portal,
not because it was technically technology-wise impossible.
but more for a design purpose, like, you know,
we wanted players to learn something in particular
in a certain level, and so giving the players
suddenly the ability to bypass all the training
that we had tried so hard to construct
and, you know, just seemed like
shooting ourselves in the foot, essentially.
In the first trailer for a portal, the portals seemed to have sort of an almost liquid quality to them.
Now they're more like holes in the wall.
Also, they were a blue and a red part of the portal, and now it's a blue and an orange one.
What triggered this change?
So the question was, why did we change the look and color of our portals?
Well, honestly, we went through just a bunch of just iterations and as far as blue and
orange goes, you know, we liked orange better than red.
I mean, it really just boils down to that, like, we liked the color choice better in
the end and, you know, we left it sort of up to our artists, like, you know, what do
you want the portals to look like?
and the liquid quality, and it was kind of like they were rippling at the edges.
Yeah, so I think what you're referring to as far as the liquid quality of how the portals were looking was
that was an opening shader for it, and we just decided to change it.
Honestly, it just sort of, we decided one day.
I just wanted to leave a comment.
I just want to thank you guys for the end of the turret level.
The most satisfying thing that I felt in that game was picking up that last turret and walking
into the elevator to the field and watching it just turn into a ball of ash.
I want to thank you guys for that.
Yeah, yeah, no problem.
Yeah, we also really like the way they screened too.
So I have a question. I'm a student and you guys started out as an indie developer.
So I'm just wondering if you have any suggestions for students and what not
who are hoping to get into the game industry and break in like you guys did.
So the question is, do we have any advice for student developers on how to break into
the industry?
Make games, make as many as you can, and fail, because honestly failing, you'll learn a lot
of stuff.
Like, I can't tell you how many times we've failed on our game designs working at DigiPen.
Like, yeah, one of them worked out, but you know, we had three others that were not the
best games ever.
And honestly, you can't tell me how many times you've failed on our game designs, but you
Practice makes perfect, right?
So the more things that you have on your resume
and your portfolio to show to game developers that,
look, I did all these projects,
I worked on them from start to finish,
it obviously shows that I have commitment to the project,
right?
So make games, like whether it be a mod
or a student project, just make as many as you possibly can
and have fun with them.
Thank you.
So when I spoke to people that also played
portal about the fire pit puzzle, one of the things
that we talked about a lot was the fact
that we felt like we had broken the game somehow
by escaping like this final ending,
and that there was this moment of sort of shock and confusion
about what to do next when you suddenly had gotten past
what you imagined was the game's end.
And that was a very powerful moment in the way
that it defied conventional game narrative.
So I'm wondering if that, I don't know,
that defying a conventional game narrative was something that was intentional
in the design of the level, or whether that was just something that
that was an accidental occurrence from what you set up.
Honestly, that was one of the very first things...
I've written the question.
Oh, sorry.
Oh, I forgot the question.
I was just going to talk about it.
No, was it intentional the sort of way that you feel maybe like you've broken the game
after the fire pit?
And I guess there was some unintentionality there because that's one thing that virtually
never changed.
The beats as far as you start in the relaxation ball at some point during the game, although
I think maybe it was earlier in the game at one point, you escape the fire pit and then
you would eventually meet Gladys, was in there before...
anything. I mean, the test levels with no dialogue basically had that structure, just
because we had this intuitive feeling that it would work, and it just ended up working
better than we thought. So we can take some credit for it, but not total credit. It just
worked really well.
So, when I first heard about Portal, I went and played Narbacular Drop really thoroughly,
and when I played Portal, I noticed there were a lot of similarities.
The one big difference was that Portal had all this humor, a profound amount of humor in it,
and I was wondering what the decision was, how you decided to throw in the comedy.
So the question is, why did we decide to throw in comedy for Portal,
because Narbacular Drop really wasn't that funny.
And, you know, there's something inherently funny about portals, like, you know, especially,
you know, you put one of them, like, both of them on the floor, and you drop a box,
and you see it, like, popping out back and forth, like, there's something kind of funny
and visceral about it, and, and, well, honestly, Eric's really damn funny.
Yeah, well, I mean, given a choice, that was kind of in my comfort zone, like, if my task
at Bow was to write...
stuff for Portal. If nobody was going to object, I would just make it funny, because that would be
something I was more likely to succeed at.
Because you like despairing?
Yeah.
Hi. I have no problems harvesting Adam from Little Sisters.
I love kicking innocent bystanders to bloody pulp in lots of games.
But why, why, why, why did you have to kill off the companion Q?
So why did we kill off the companion cube?
Well, I think we explained that in the speech, didn't we?
You can thank the United States Secret Service.
Actually, I don't think it was a Secret Service.
I'm a secreter than the Secret Service.
I have two questions, and the second one's quick.
The first one is, it sounds like there's
a lot of trial and error and rework that went into Portal.
Did you have to do anything to smooth that over with management,
set their expectations or anything like that?
So the question is, there's a lot of trial and error with the game, obviously, and did
we have to convince our management that that was perhaps a good idea.
And honestly, the way management works at Valve is a lot different than it does at other
game companies.
We don't really have producers there.
We have team leads that basically, you know...
maybe do like administrative stuff every once in a while and do some PR.
But, you know, honestly, the people working on the game get to make the decisions about the game
and have direct impact on what they're working on.
And, you know, we've found that it just makes for a much more, you know,
satisfied group of people making games.
Fantastic.
Also, like the playtesting, the commitment to playtesting wasn't our insight.
That's...
That's the valve philosophy. That's how they make games. If we hadn't done that, then we would have been in deep trouble.
Okay, fantastic. Second question. Is Glados still alive? And when will we see her again?
So the question is, is Gladys still alive?
And when will we see her again?
Well, did she not listen to the last song?
The song is called Still Alive.
That's kind of a failure of writing if you don't know that she's still alive.
It tends to be 100% still alive, thank you.
And as far as when you'll see her again, who knows?
Alright, hi. I had a question about your development background and how you guys scored yourself like an awesome seed by working with Val.
So, were you still making a question?
Well, no, go ahead.
Oh, okay. So the question is...
How do you guys score yourself like a position to work with Val?
So the question was, how did we end up, like, hooking up with Valve to make Portal?
So, as far as, like, the team goes, with the exception of Eric, we were all students at
DigiPen Institute of Technology, and we created a game called Neurobacular Drop, which was
our student project for our senior year.
It was, you know, the predecessor to Portal, you know, you had two portals on the wall and it was an environmental puzzle game.
And every year, Digipent has an expo for graduating seniors.
And Valve came by, took a look at our project and thought it was interesting enough to drag us over to Valve and have us present the game to Gabe Newell.
And after about 15 minutes through our presentation,
told us to be quiet and then asked us what we were planning on doing after we
graduated. We were like well hopefully you know paying a loan, getting a job,
eating food and you know he offered us a job on the spot essentially to come in
and create portal using a source engine and you know that's how we ended up
there and and Eric's got a different story.
Yeah, I worked, I'd been just doing a lot of writing and then I went and I worked at
Double Fine for a couple of years and then I left Double Fine and I was just back to
freelance writing and for me it was just I got a mail one day from Gabe Newell and said
do you want to come work at Val?
I have another quick question, why didn't you guys submit this to IGF?
It seems like a perfect candidate.
Was it the reason you guys got picked up by Valve?
So the question was, why didn't we submit the game to IGF?
So Narbacular Drop actually was in the IGF student showcase
three years ago.
The Japan submits the games that they find
to be interesting to student showcase and the IGF.
We didn't make the indie professional section,
but we made it to the student showcase.
Thank you.
Hi, how did the element of cake come into fruition?
So the question is, how did the element of cake
come into fruition?
It kind of started off as like an inside joke.
I mean, really, it just was one of those things.
I think originally when we sat down to you guys were showing
me the game, there was something about cake in there.
And it just seemed like it's a comedy tool, obsess over one
thing that maybe you wouldn't expect to obsess over.
And we just, it really didn't have any deeper meaning than
that.
Yeah, we were just kind of having fun.
Yeah, fun work, work fun.
Yes, yes, yes, yes.
We were working very hard.
And having fun.
You're turning out to be sarcastic, it was hard working.
Yeah, no, no, it was hard working.
I'm awesome.
Alright.
Jeez.
The conference is turning ugly.
Hi guys, two quick questions.
First, was there any reasoning behind making all the characters
and the references in GLaDOS quotes and such female?
So the question is, why did we decide
to make our characters female, GLaDOS,
and the main character?
So as far as the main character goes,
Gabe actually made a suggestion one day.
We were at the time looking to find
what we wanted to be the main character or protagonist of Portal.
And you can see some of our earlier shots of the game.
There's like a balding dude as the main character.
And that was just 10-part.
Like it was something that we used a citizen model from Half-Life 2
and just kind of fixed them up a little bit and put them in just for our testing purposes.
But anyways, Gabe came up to us while we were looking to figure out
what we wanted our main character to be and said,
well, why don't you make it a girl?
And we're like...
Alright, sure. I mean, it really didn't stretch beyond that, the sort of little, what-if.
Okay, why not?
It's like post-feminist. It didn't even occur to us not to make it a girl.
No big deal.
And as far as glados, well, there was the awesome glados pun, which kind of made it seem like we had...
It had to be female, but really, we knew an actress, I mean, casting is hard,
because we knew this person was going to have to carry the game, so we needed an actress...
Or an actor.
or actor, actor or actress, who A, was good, and B, wouldn't be offended when, you know,
the first third of our recording sessions were just us playing her text-to-speech and saying,
say this exactly like that back to us, because actors say that sort of thing.
But she was super nice about it. And so that kind of informed that.
Okay. And the other one is just to officially shut my friend up. Is cellist high board?
No, another failure of writing. Chell is not a cyborg.
There's no, she's not a cyborg. That was those ridiculous cheese things.
Cyber shoes?
Yeah, her future shoes.
Hey, this might have already been addressed at some point,
but I got in late, so I have to ask anyways.
Obviously, Portal was a very short game
that met a lot of very popular success.
Do you think this might start making a movement back
towards the idea of shorter games being on the market?
I mean, right now, the huge pressure
is everybody wants 20 plus, 30 plus, 40 plus hour games,
because everyone wants to get as much out of the game
as they possibly can for what they're
paying out of their wallet.
Yeah, I mean, I, oh sorry, do you think Portal would influence more developers to make shorter
games because according to the questioner, people want longer and longer games, although
I'm not 100% sure about that. You know, everybody at Valve, all the people I know who play games
who are adults now, the...
common complaint is they never finish a game. Nobody ever finishes a game that I know who
is in 14. They don't have time and also they have 40 hours a week to play World of Warcraft
2. That's a year gaming time. So there are some practical constraints on how long we
are going to make it, but if we could have done anything, I really wanted to make a game
Pete everybody who played it would be able to finish you know you'd be able to it's weird to be playing these games are trying to tell a story in a game where
Almost everybody it just sort of peters out you know you just stop playing at some point and never finish it right
Thank you very much
Hello, two-part question. The first part is, you mentioned that a lot of dialogue had been cut from the game.
I was wondering if any of it had gotten recorded and or put through the process of being somewhat final for Gladys.
And if so, is there any chance you could release it on one of your websites?
Because as a member of the portal mapping community, we would give our ITs to have extra Gladys dialogue.
So, the question was how much of final dialogue got cut and could we release it?
So, it wasn't a lot of final dialogue, virtually everything went through the text to speech
as temp audio and a lot of it got cut.
at that point. And some of the stuff that got cut, a lot of it I'm just not super proud of,
so I wouldn't want to give it to anybody. And if it is good, I'm going to use it somewhere else.
Not to be mean?
Yeah, not to be mean, but probably the chances are somewhat slim.
I had to try. Thank you.
My question is, were there any considerations for making a multiplayer or cooperative experience?
So the question was, were there any considerations for making Portal a co-op or a multiplayer game?
Yeah, we thought about it.
Actually, I don't know if we ship this or not, but we played around for a little while
actually having multiple sets of portals, and it is technically possible.
We just didn't really have the time to think through what would the gameplay be that was
fun.
The immediate conclusion that we actually tried a little bit was, oh my gosh, portals
and deathmatch, and it's less fun than you'd think it is, honestly.
It's actually kind of frustrating.
Hi, you had a lot of really good advice about keeping it wet, keeping the project wet, not
getting too attached to ideas and being willing to cut things or make changes later.
I'm just wondering what your experience was for balancing that with the need to get a
project done and the kind of tendency of a project to kind of gain momentum the further
it goes along and be harder to make changes later than earlier.
So the question was how do we temper a game, you know, the longer you work on it, the harder
it is to, you know, sort of cut things and is that kind of what you were saying?
Yeah, okay.
You said it better than I do.
And playtesting, you will know right away if your idea is good or bad.
You know, if you watch your players and they are just totally frustrated out of your mind,
and you can't really, you know, necessarily like pinpoint ways to fix it, then cut it.
Because, so, you know, one of the things that we do making our levels, at least,
is we try and get them up and running once we come up with an idea, okay, we want, you know, such and such objectives.
As we try and get it up and running within like two to five days, like really, really fast,
and then we start running play tests through it.
And if we play test it like maybe, you know, three or four times and we find that it's just really not working out,
then it's going to the cutting floor, or going back again to design phase and, you know, re-mangling it to work.
So we never really got to a point where, you know, it was really, really difficult to cut something because, you know, we were always play testing and getting reinforcement for whether or not our ideas were good or bad directly from, you know, people we consider our customers.
Thank you.
Yep.
If your development team were, or your development process were a style of painting, what would it be?
Wow. So, if our development process were a style of painting, what would it be?
Maybe a...
Cubist?
I don't know. Yeah, Cubist painting.
Have a good one.
Yeah, I'm out of it too.
Sorry.
So Chell obviously has a very good set of DNA, and you mentioned that it was Gabe's
idea to make her female, and Gordon Freeman has good DNA.
Is there any?
So the question is, are Chell and Gordon going to hook up, essentially?
I don't know.
I mean, you guys have access to Gary's mod, right?
You can do what you want.
Yeah, I was just wondering, you kept on talking about how you cut off a lot of things in the
narrative and like cut off a lot of exposition and stuff like that, and just really streamline
the process.
And I was just wondering, do you think that it's possible, I mean, do you think there's
a way to make exposition and narrative like interesting and fun for the playtesters?
So the question is, do I think there's a way to, I think you're saying is there a way
to include a lot more exposition and still make it entertaining?
I mean for me personally, I'm sure there's somebody who's a genius who could do it, but
I personally don't, I mean I like it when there is less, my own personal taste is less.
So for me, probably, probably not.
I do as little as possible.
Games aren't good at telling like, long expository stories then?
Yeah, I guess I'm not good at it, but I'm also not good at sitting through it.
I mean, I just don't like it that much in games.
When I play a game, I like it to be as concise as possible.
Honestly, game writer, but I'm not even 100% convinced that games are the best medium
for telling epic, long stories.
I kind of think of what I do is more of like providing a film score.
You know, movies aren't about the music, but the music is definitely an important part
that enhances the experience of watching the movie.
So the writing is something that enhances the experience of why you're there, which is playing the game.
And honestly, for me, there's something to be said for leaving things to people's imagination.
You don't have to have someone sitting there next to you dictating to you exactly what's going on at all times.
You know, people are smart, giving credit.
And I know for me personally, it's kind of fun just sort of imagining up what I think some of the storyline is.
Playing through portals, one of the biggest surprises that I had was finding references to Black Mesa inside of it,
and then references to Aperture and the Borealis inside the Half-Life 2 Episode 2.
Around what point in development did you make the decision to drop portals into the Half-Life universe?
So the question is, when did we decide to cross-reference between the two games of Episode 2 and Portal?
kind of like, you know, maybe in the middle of development or so, we...
Well, middle of development for you, but I think when I came on it, that was in the...
the earlier meetings. That was just one of the constraints on the game. Initially, because
I think they weren't sure exactly where they were going to position it, and also because
we were still using a lot of half-life art. So it sort of made sense to tie them together.
As Portal kind of got its own identity, we worried less and less about it. Like, you
know, we're not going to have to have the G-Man appear or something. We can kind of make it
a little bit more subtle and not have to dwell on it too much.
Thanks.
Two questions.
I have a friend who says that the best games teach us something.
What do we have to learn from Portal?
So the question is what do we have to learn from Portal
because the best games teach people something?
You know what I say? It takes one.
That's a tough one.
Well...
If anybody has an idea, just get out of the house.
Don't trust anyone or something.
Don't trust anyone.
The cake is a lie.
We definitely wanted to explore the idea of manipulating space and thinking about a 3D space in a different way.
And so, you know, throughout Portal, we're kind of teaching you to look at a situation in a way that you haven't before.
So I don't know if that kind of answers your question.
You'll do.
Also, I noticed that the companion cube is kind of silent.
Does it have any dialogue in the sequel?
So the question is, will a companion cube
have dialogue in the sequel to Portal?
I don't know about this sequel, but you're talking about it.
So this might be a little bit proprietary, but I'm curious.
How did you guys and Orvald figure out, or when did you figure out it was an evolutionary process, how you were going to sell the game?
So the question is, when did we figure out how we were going
to market and sell Portal?
So when we initially started Portal,
it was supposed to be just a seriously short game,
like maybe like, I don't know, 15 minutes, just
like a quick tech demo.
And then the further we got on the game,
our constraints would change.
And I guess about the middle of portals development,
we had started talking about doing the orange box.
And it would just sort of seem like a really reasonable conclusion
that it should be packaged with...
Other games that you know have a lot of clout and are awesome games and you know from our standpoint like that's that's great
You know
We're we were seriously honored to be packaged with you know TF2 and episode 2 because we think they're truly awesome games
You said that you used the play testing as kind of a method by which you tested whether or not the players got the storyline.
And I wondered, as the game length grew, how, when you compartmentalize the testing, because grabbing people for 8-hour, 10-hour play sessions isn't always possible,
did you get them to give you that feedback, even if they're only playing maybe one or two levels?
Uh, well, a lot of action.
Oh, sorry. Uh, how did we...
get people to experience the entire story if they didn't playtest the whole game.
Luckily, because Portal was a pretty short game throughout most of its development,
no point was it so long that it would take people eight hours to get through it.
Please don't hit me in the face.
Sorry.
What was I going to say?
If somebody didn't finish the game, we weren't super worried about asking.
We did occasionally have playtesters who didn't make it through.
But most of them...
We sat and watched them for the entire time, and they made it through.
I know that this question has kind of been beaten to death a bit, but it was about the
storyline, you saying less is more.
Would you say that that policy applies to other genres besides just portal, or is it
just mostly for that type of...
I mean, there's definitely, oh, does Less is More in terms of story apply to other genres?
And again, I don't know, I don't have a sure-fire solution for every genre.
I mean, in terms of my enjoyment of a game, Less is More.
So, but again, if you're making a giant RPG, you probably need to say who baguette whom and where the hammer came from.
So Portal and Half-Life 2 have a very different tone in terms of the writing and the sort
of themes, the thematic elements.
If you ever do try and tie the universe together and do something with the cross-referencing
you've done, do you have any ideas for how you might resolve that?
Well, so how do we resolve the differences in tone between Half-Life universe and the
sort of Aputure universe?
And actually, it was something I thought about, and I honestly don't think it's that big
a problem, because the Aputure universe, the tone that you're seeing, is mostly gladus,
right?
You're seeing things, even though you're playing a character, you're actually kind of experiencing
the world through Gladus' eyes.
So, if Chell is out in the Half-Life universe, no action that you took as a player is really
in direct contradiction to anything that would happen in the Half-Life universe.
Inside the sort of Aputure Science Fun House, there's a different set of maybe tonal rules.
Physics-wise, they're the same places, and even art-style-wise, so I'm not super-duper
worried about it.
Is that Paul?
Yeah, it is.
uh... is there any chance of an art book
uh...
just say that again
is there any chance of an art book uh... is there any chance of an art book
uh... i'm talking about it with anyone that is interesting idea they're
talking about it in more than orange box sort of thing uh...
most of our concept are honestly with jason brashill designing the uh...
the gladus battle which is some awesome awesome artwork which you can
there's actually a print i think that you can buy of it
uh... look at the website yeah
but uh... a lot of the other stuff there i mean compared to tf or half-life
the there isn't a lot of really awesome
uh... concept i mean we've got a lot of thumbnails of stuff but uh... like
there are a whole lot of like really
you know, great, you know, pictures that we have, you know,
rachel did maybe, like maybe six or so, but essentially,
you know, we've just got a lot of thumbnails of, you know,
the turrets and the gun and a bunch of other stuff.
Also, why are the portals ovoided?
So the question is, why are the portals ovals?
Well, ovals look better than rectangles.
You know, we wanted something to kind of fit the bounds of where the actual, like, you
know, where you can pass through the portal to be, and so we kind of just build an oval,
you know, through the rectangle where the portal, you know, technically is.
The game alludes to a lot of backstory that isn't really fully explained, like the fact
that you're a test subject for no explained reason.
How much of that backstory is actually written and referenced to, and how much of that did
you just sort of say, oh, we'll let the player kind of use his imagination?
So the question is how much backstory is there that isn't in the game?
And there's a fair amount.
There's a lot.
Ah, yeah.
A lot of, I don't know, there's probably a 15-page document about Aputure Science.
There's actually a little bit of it is on the Aputure Science website, kind of hidden
in there somewhere.
And I'd written up a bunch of stuff in the beginning just to kind of help me.
And actually, at that point, I thought maybe I'd get more in there.
But, and I sent it to Jonathan, too, that kind of helped him get into the sort of mindset
of the whole thing.
But yeah, there is a bunch.
Hi, I think I speak for a lot of people on this, that Portal really was a huge triumph
because it was so creative and it won so many awards and it's got so much acclaim and it's
so different.
I was wondering if you could speak a little bit on how you think that's affecting the
community of games as a whole.
So the question, so it's like how portal impacts the community of games as well?
Yeah, and the approach to making games as a creative medium.
I don't really know.
Yeah, I mean it's kind of too early to tell, I hope it.
I mean, because since we made Portal, we made a game that we sort of like, so if more people
make games like Portal, I would probably like them, so that's good.
But I mean, you just look at it this year, it seems like the independent games are...
Getting really good.
Awesome.
Yeah, they're higher production quality and also higher profile, so maybe it'll mean
people take risks on, you know...
with more oddball games.
Good evening.
So I had a question about, in terms of, like, my background
is film and that sort of media.
So my question to you as writers and developers of this game
is, what are your influences?
What did you look like?
What did you think of as inspiration for Portal or
inspiration to get into the game industry?
And how does that influence how you
attack this game, this project?
So the question was, do we have any influences that kind of inspired us to make Portal or
against the gaming industry?
So for me personally, like every other person on the planet, Miyamoto is definitely an inspiration.
I grew up with Nintendo games and I was kind of raised on them, so from an early age, I
wanted to be a game designer.
And, you know, as far as just kind of interesting games that actually get published, you know,
Katamari Dimashi was a really great one.
Do you have inspiration?
Oh, well, direct inspiration for Portal was...
There's a book by... Who's the Dune guy?
Frank Herbert called Destination Boyd.
It's about people that clones that go into space and they're tasked with building an AI.
And there's always this fail-safe mechanism because the AIs always go crazy and kill everyone.
And the crew doesn't really know that that's what happens and then they blow up the ship.
And it just fails and fails and fails because the AI goes rogue and they blow up the ship.
There's like one mole guy in there who knows that he's supposed to blow up the ship.
So that was an inspiration for that.
In the game industry, I just...
Okay, no Isaac Asimov for anything like that or uh?
Not you know, I'm honestly not when I was a kid I read a lot of science fiction
But I don't read a lot of science fiction now and so but I mean I know as mob
I'm sure indirectly Robert Sheckley is a we actually named a character in episode 2 Sheckley after Robert Sheckley
Just because he writes kind of funny science fiction. Yeah, I was a kid. I love this stuff. Thank you
Because we have to catch a plane at some point, so if we can just do these three, and there's nobody else, that's easy.
Hey, I have a question specifically for Eric. If the portal design process was an animal, what would it be?
That's Anna, who used to sit right next to me at Double Fine, so that was her joke question, I'm not going to answer.
Okay, so my question pertains to the current slides.
The slides.
Yeah, we were actually waiting for someone to actually ask us what in the world did we put on the slide.
What's the significance of the two shots?
And if you were each one of the characters in each of the pictures, which would you be?
Eric's the one crying.
I don't know, it's friendship and fire.
Two pictures we just had, we couldn't quite fit into the talk in any meaningful way.
And we thought they were pretty funny.
I think one of those is the crying guys, is my Steam community ID too.
And that's Ray Moore.
Hi, so I was actually wondering about the development team.
Because you're female and that's kind of unusual.
How many girls are on the team?
So the question was how many girls were on the portal team?
There were two, myself and one of the artists, Realm Lovejoy.
Right on.
Do you think that helps in the creativity process
in making a unique game, having that different perspective?
So the question was, does having females on a game team
make for a better game, giving you a unique perspective?
And I don't know.
No, I mean, honestly, I think whenever you're on a game team, no matter what your gender,
you want to make a game that you would enjoy to play yourself, like that's the dream, right?
So I mean, I guess that could, by extension, mean that we made a game that perhaps girls
could like too, but honestly, I hope that it's fun for everybody, personally.
Having girls on the team makes the room smell better.
Thank you.