Thank you for that lovely intro.
Hey everyone, thanks for coming.
Alright, we've only got half an hour so let's get into it.
I'm Joshua Boggs and I'm a game designer and director.
Prior to Framed I've been in the industry for about 8 years now.
Some of that time is spent in AAA and some of it at various other studios.
I've been independent for about 4 of them now.
I've been lucky enough to receive a bunch of awards or accolades, but that's not all
there really is to me.
I'm also an attention seeker.
And this talk is kind of about how that addiction for approval and recognition ultimately damaged
significant parts of my life.
I'm going to try and keep it together, so forgive me if I'm...
things get a little bit dark. But yeah, this talk is basically
for those that may be going through something similar or for
those who can see someone they care about doing something
similar. They just can't recognize it. Okay. So if you
don't know what framed is, framed is a puzzle game where
you rearrange panels of a comic book to change the outcome of
the story.
We've managed to achieve a fair amount. A lot of stuff that I kind of put on my bucket list of whatever I wanted to do in life.
And we managed to get a lot of attention.
So why did I do this? What was my goal?
To be honest, I don't really think I'm alone in this.
I was just really unsatisfied with my life.
I didn't really grow up in the best family.
I was pretty much told consistently that I could achieve anything.
In hindsight this is clearly biased and privileged, but that upbringing, that desire to be more
than what I came from never really went away.
So no matter what relationships or achievements I had in my life, I was still unsatisfied.
I always needed more.
I needed to fill that hole in my life.
I needed to be relevant, to be remarkable.
And it kind of all started like when I was in my teens, I used to do this little thing called the deathbed experiment.
And it's basically just like, you know, we don't like to talk about death a lot, but you can use it in a really powerful way to make important decisions about your life.
And the way it kind of works is you just fully imagine yourself on your deathbed looking back on your life, you know?
Like, what are you proud of? What hasn't happened yet? What's meaningful to you?
So when I imagine this, I just imagine myself needing to leave some sort of legacy.
I want to be remembered for pushing the medium forward that we all love so much.
So I threw myself into my work.
And did I achieve what I set out to do?
Yeah, I did.
I did tick off everything on that list.
I had every major festival and took home or was nominated for almost every award going
on the circuit.
But did that make me happy at all? Not at all.
And it's because I wasn't getting the recognition I felt I deserved, or more importantly, I felt that I wasn't getting the recognition that I felt I deserved.
I felt my whole life was leading to this, and I was going to achieve it no matter what.
I needed more. I was getting praise that I needed, but I just wasn't satisfied with it.
So, rewind just really slightly. We first flew to Japan and submitted to IGF China and Tokyo Game Show
and that was kind of like the beginning of the addiction, I guess.
What should have been a boost in confidence became the start of an addiction.
An addiction to approval and external validation and attention.
I thought I was prepared for it, but I didn't really realize that the destination had changed.
It was no longer like a ride to the top, it was a ride into hell.
And I was hooked.
I was finally being recognized by people I'd respected and looked up to for so long.
And you can see the signs of it in the previous slides and if you saw my other talk as well,
that focus on awards all the time.
You know, I lie to myself when I say that it's all for the PR, but it's not really
what it's for.
I want people to see how good we are, well, I guess how good I am.
I need the recognition, the validation, the attention.
I need to be relevant.
I wanted to be the next big thing, and I wanted that by any means necessary.
The goal originally came from a place of good intentions, to be respected.
You know, they say the road to hell is paved with good intentions.
Ultimately, like many artists, I just want to be known and respected for what I create.
I want to build a legacy. That's what I need.
I need to be remembered when I'm gone.
I don't feel I'm alone in that.
We all feel that we need to leave some part of us on this earth when we're gone.
And I confuse that with fame.
But I imagine that's a significant reason we all create.
If you're really honest with yourself, why do you create games?
Once upon a time, fame was bestowed on those who earned it for saving lives or heroic deeds.
Today fame is more of a form of currency, it's a social currency.
And like any form of currency, it distinguishes the classes of people.
It defines the class of its social media citizens.
It defines who is influence, who is power, who will be listened to.
and we're addicted to it. You can see this in almost every post someone makes that features
themselves or tweets curators specifically to get as many likes or retweets as possible.
Just sort of everyone crying out to be noticed. We are basically a generation of creators
crying out to approval for our parents.
And I did it because I felt that validation would fill me with
some sense of satisfaction.
And one thing about perceived success is that it always seems
greater from the outside than it is on the inside.
On the inside, all you can think about is how you're not doing
enough.
You put on that facade that you're happy and satisfied.
You look in the mirror and you put on the mask, that happy face
that you need to greet everyone with, that friendly demeanor.
You put it on because without it, you just won't succeed.
You tell yourself it's for the PR, hoping that someone will believe it.
But at the same time, the expectations of yourself and your teammates at this point
become unrealistic.
You chastise yourself for not being front page everywhere, for not doing more.
You fool yourself into this childish fallacy that if you just try harder you can achieve
anything, that everything is in your control.
So you continue.
You continue to push yourself.
You continue to lie to yourself that it's for the game, that it's for PR.
But deep down you know what it's really for.
You know the real reason you're projecting your own unrealistic expectations onto others.
Why you've pushed everything else in your life to the side.
The real reason your game is so awarded prior to release.
Why you've got a spot on the silver screen before the main film rolls.
And why you've lost sight of your values.
Why you need another drink.
It's not because you worked hard for it.
It's definitely not because you deserve the success either.
It's because you're an addict.
But it doesn't really matter.
Because all you can think about is that next head of validation.
When people talk of cost, they often talk about the time they
spent building a company or a certain product or a game or
anything really. They talk about the dinners they missed. And
that is valid. That is a valid sacrifice.
For a lot of late entrepreneurs and people who really throw themselves into their work,
it's not really what they're talking about.
What people really mean when they talk about what they gave up to ensure they succeeded,
what they're really talking about is that they sacrificed themselves.
They lost sight of those values that made them who they were, what they hold themselves
up to, what they hope to pass on to others.
They gave them up to succeed, to tick that goal off their list.
And I did the same.
I turned my back on everything that made me strong.
My skills I discarded for more relevant ones.
My values I threw away so that I could...
Become someone who can maybe fulfill that dissatisfaction and emptiness I have in me.
This is your brain on attention.
You submit to every show you can, knowing that no matter what happens, you can only
possibly feel worse.
If you win or are recognized and you get your hit and you manage to maintain your feeling
of normalcy.
If you don't get mentioned at all, you crash.
You're flooded with feelings of inadequacy, insecurity, and failure.
And the culture in our scene breeds this.
The independent scene does breed this.
Everyone is congratulating you and reaffirming that what you're doing must be right.
So you continue.
You fall deeper into that vicious cycle.
And indie scenes across many art forms are breeding grounds for this kind of behavior.
We're told it's necessary to succeed.
You know, how will we get people to give us money for our work if they don't know who we are?
We get fame confused.
Fame does not come before virtue.
Fame does not get bestowed before success.
There's a really good quote by this person called Daniel Borstein about it.
And he says,
The celebrity is a person who is known for their well-knownness.
They are neither good nor bad.
Great, nor petty.
They are the human pseudo-event.
And we like to think that as artists we're complicated,
you know, we're deep.
But we're really not.
We're the kids screaming for more attention.
We're driven by feelings of inadequacy,
desire for relevance.
We're rewarded for never maturing.
And we're paid to indulge in our habits.
And myself, I was very guilty of this.
I trembled over others to reach the top.
Lots of, I guess you could call allies and enemies
or acquaintances and colleagues.
But friends, real friends, not so many.
Some of us are friends, yes.
Some of us are very good friends,
some of you in this room.
But to many people, you're an asset,
a utility to help them reach the top.
It's labeled as business or hustling.
But when people use these terms in a non-business sense, when they apply them to, you know,
friends getting together, it highlights their intentions.
It highlights their goals and values.
More than anything, it highlights how they see themselves.
Why do they do this?
Well, they're addicted too.
They need that head of validation because they're not going to get it from themselves.
They need to move up the ladder to achieve what they're truly after.
And what they're after is that attention.
And I did this too. I'm very guilty of that.
And I've probably done this a lot worse than many others have.
So in the fall of 2014, Fane was finished.
And I sacrificed so much for this.
And in the end, like, despite everything we achieved,
despite achieving virtually everything I'd set out to do,
I still felt empty. It still meant nothing.
My whole life had been leading up to what I thought would bring me happiness, but it
just didn't.
I felt worse than ever, in fact.
I kind of just lost my mind.
I lost some of the closest people around me.
I neglected friendships and deserted family members when they needed me because I needed
to get that fixed for myself.
I neglected all of my relationships, but really, before all of that, I deserted myself.
I changed, you know, not for the better.
I became something I never wanted to become and in doing that I just ended up losing or
giving up everything else around me.
I sacrificed what makes me who I am.
And there are times I wish I could take it back.
I wish I'd treated and valued those around me better than I did.
I wish I had the strength and...
insight to see what I was doing to myself and those around me.
So with Jack and Jimmy by my side I kind of soon followed what was a year long downward spiral of
self destruction. It was fueled by denial, anger, resentment, regret, and an unhealthy
dose of alcohol. I drank literally every day.
It's not an exaggeration.
From shipping until the end of 2015, I drank literally every single day.
And I blamed everyone.
Everyone else but me.
I blamed my parents for not staying together.
I blamed my friends for needing me as much as they did.
I blamed my teammates for not living up to my unrealistic expectations.
I blame those that had my back for not noticing what was really going on.
I wish I saw my family more.
Was it all worth it?
It wasn't.
Did everything achieve or satisfy what I needed to achieve?
Fuck no, it didn't.
Didn't achieve what I needed because what was I really seeking to achieve?
You know, you can say it was the awards or the respect, but like I said, it's the validation,
the attention.
Things that no matter how much you receive will never be enough.
The issue with satisfaction, sorry, the issue was that satisfaction was not tied to my internal
sense of values anymore, but to external validation and attention.
And it's really easy for us to fall into that trap as creators.
Because that's the only objective measurement we really have.
So, will I change anything?
Of course.
You know, I sacrificed myself.
What I held dear.
The things that got me to where I was, my values for success, I threw away my sense
of self so that the public image of Joshua Boggs would appear greater than it really
was.
And it worked for a little while.
I felt good in the beginning.
I was getting more gratification by being associated with particular people and using
them to further my own means as well.
It's really bad saying, I knew exactly what I was doing.
If you saw my previous talk at all, you maybe would have known that I'm quite good at reading social systems and people inside them.
So, with all that said, you know, how did I get out?
How did I turn it around?
Well, as I began to lose myself, my insight in myself, my understanding of who I was changed dramatically.
Lots of running away from my problems, leaving cities and a lot of drinking helped, for a
little while at least.
But a year later I'm kind of happy to finally say that I have found some sense of happiness
in my life.
I've never really sought happiness, so I've only ever strived for success.
But that pursuit had destroyed me and I was still unsatisfied.
Particular people who stood by me helped me a lot.
A lot of acceptance of what I've done wrong and lots of therapy have brought a greater
understanding about myself.
And it's really hard to accept help, particularly with mental issues, because your mind is the
problem.
And as creators, it's really hard for us to understand that, because we trust those
instincts so passionately, right?
They are what make us great at what we do.
But it also lies to us.
Schopenhauer once said, an artist never is happy, but spends their whole life in striving
after something which they think will make them so.
They seldom attain their goal, and when they do, it is only to be disappointed.
They are mostly shipwrecked in the end, and come into harbour with mast and rigging gone.
I remember when I was at EA, right, there was someone there who was leaving, who I really
looked up to.
I asked them why they were leaving, like why were they giving up on their dream, they were
leaving the games industry altogether.
And they said something that I find I think more and more about, and it's, they said the
difference between dreams and reality is that a dream can't really be lived, right?
If it can be lived, it's too narrow, and if it can't, it shouldn't be a goal.
Rather than dream, you should wake up and build a life that really fulfills you.
And a dream is just an illusion.
Don't ever tell people you are living the dream.
All it proves is that your dreams are shallow.
Being a superstar or an indie sensation doesn't mean a goddamn thing when you have nothing left.
So, like I said, after being in the darkest and lowest point of my life for a year, I sought help.
No person is an island and if my issues are stemming due to my need for approval of others,
I'm also going to need the help of others to get out too.
I'm going to state right now also that if you're going through this yourself, please
seek help.
If you notice someone on your team or a friend going down this path whose goal is set to
becoming famous or acclaimed, please point them towards this talk or get them help.
Tell them that those awards don't mean anything.
Because if it's unreasonable to judge someone poorly based off of their lack of achievements,
it stands to reason that you shouldn't also judge someone highly based off their achievements,
right?
And when you embrace this idea, goals kind of become meaningless.
So rather than set goals, set what I like to call an un-goal.
And an un-goal is really just a goal that's not really a goal.
It's more of a value.
Goals are a way to measure our achievements, measure our values.
Our values stick with us and represent us as people,
but the only way we can really measure that as creators is by achieving goals.
The problem is, however, that it's very easy to replace your values with your goals.
You hear about this all the time, only in a different language.
You hear about selling out, losing yourself, corrupt.
Achieving goals doesn't prove or disprove your value as a person.
That is to say, it doesn't really measure your value or your worth as a person.
Values can't be achieved or ticked off, they can only be lived.
Really, we all just want to be remembered for our values.
I don't want to be remembered for my achievements anymore.
I want to be respected as a person and I want to be
a loving and caring person to those around me.
I don't want to make games for fame or attention or anything so short-lived.
I want to make games to share a part of myself with everyone.
to speak and listen to humanity and the generations to come who will be here when we're not.
So one thing I've kind of learned in therapy recently was different to the deathbed experiment.
The deathbed experiment was focused a lot on your own bubble, your own internal measurements,
on goals and achievements. Other people and the meaningful relationships in your life
are never really considered.
The funeral experiment is just slightly different.
It just asks, what will your loved ones say about you at your funeral?
And it's different because the funeral experiment is based on character.
It asks what lasting mark you will leave on those around you.
Did you make anyone's life better?
Did you help people?
Are you a good person?
It asks how you will really be remembered.
Interestingly, this happened to me kind of out of the blue.
Um...
So just in case you don't know, um...
Kojima at some point at the end of 2014
name-framed his game of the year.
And for me,
it meant a lot.
Um...
This was the one person who
kind of, like, inspired me,
you know, as a kid to make games.
To try and push things forward.
to be authentic in what I create, and whose dedication and focus shape the values that
would become me as a person.
So to have that sort of connection and have your career come full circle in that way,
it was something that I finally felt hopeful about.
It reminded me of my core values again.
Made me finally not want to kill myself, really.
It was more important than any kind of laurel or any award nomination.
I wouldn't give it up for anything.
So, should you really chase your dreams?
It's kind of a trick question.
What are your dreams really?
If we really look inside ourselves as independent creators or artists,
no matter whether you're independent or not, really.
I'm going to wager that our dreams are to be very similar to things that I saw.
We want respect. We want validation and acknowledgement from people.
Which is really kind of just other words for fame. The desire to be remembered.
However, to achieve those goals you need to become a more public figure.
And by doing so that changes you from someone with a private set of values to a public persona.
Suddenly everyone feels they have the right to comment or critique or praise your decisions
and achievements.
This changes your goals, it changes you.
Feels good to have that attention and so by extension your goals no longer match your
internal values.
When you achieve those goals no satisfaction is gained anymore.
It's just a head of validation and ticking something off an arbitrary list.
So was it all worth it?
And again, no. It wasn't worth it at all.
Did I achieve everything I sought after?
Initially, I did.
But did it make me happy?
Just not at all.
Because ticking a goal off your list will never bring you real satisfaction.
Would you still seek it if social media wasn't as big as it was?
I'm betting the desire wouldn't be so large if we rewinded time ten years.
Which leaves us with that one question again.
Why do we seek it out?
And again my answer to that is for fame and attention.
Social relevance and respect among those pairs that we look up to.
And I don't know if I'll ever properly be able to forgive myself for feeling that way
and for what I kind of sacrificed for being so resentful and hateful of other people
who were really just there to support me.
I don't know if I'll ever really reclaim that youthful hope again.
But maybe all isn't lost.
Maybe I can make it worth it if...
Maybe I can make it mean something if there's some way to warn others.
To...
Really give meaning to what I'd lost.
So, was it all worth it?
Well, if it helps anyone here today, I say it is. Thank you.
I don't know if we have time for questions.
Two minutes. If anyone asks questions.
Otherwise, we don't need to.
I'm wondering if your experience or your addiction affected how you saw other independent
developers.
If you saw them more as competition or as idols, you know, when other people are getting
awards and things like that.
Yes, the question was how did that addiction affect how I saw other people, right?
And yeah, it definitely did taint things.
Not necessarily like, you know, they won something and I didn't, but more just you look up to
them and you sort of are trying to constantly do better to try and be remembered and that
does cause a sort of negative influence on you.
So yes, it does.
Hi, you said that if you are going through this too, that you should get help and I was wondering if you could elaborate, like maybe, if you mean like therapy and if so, a specific kind of therapy?
I can't really like give out medical advice or anything, but, and everyone's kind of different, so, just, I mean even if you just start by telling people around you, you know, what you're going through and
That's one of the great things about this community is, like I would never give this talk anywhere else.
I give it here because I know that we're all a community and we can all help each other.
So it's not necessarily like any specific kind of therapy, it's just being able to actually voice that and have other people support you.
Thank you.
When you said you kind of lost your sense of self and your values, how did you reconnect
with yourself and kind of figure, find yourself again?
Yeah, I think stopping drinking is a good one.
Yeah, I mean, alcohol, like for some people, makes them like further depressed and it definitely
did that to me.
But I think it was just a lot of like accepting.
What I had done helped a lot in that.
And I did seek therapy, which has only just kind of now slowly made me feel like I can
go on again.
I don't really have a question, but more just wanted to say thank you for giving this talk.
I really applaud you for being able to use the platform that you achieved through Framed
to talk about this, which I think is something that's universal to everyone who has a natural
drive and ambition.
So I can imagine that this was tough to do and thank you so much for speaking about this.
Thank you.
Thanks a lot.
I think that's it.
Sorry.