All right, so while the final few file in,
thank you all for coming at this ungodly hour.
I've been at this thing for five days, and I'm tired.
I guess most of you are too.
Before I get started, just a quick show of hands.
Who here is working on their own game or on an indie game?
All right, excellent.
That's most of you, and that's sort of the audience
for this thing, as am I.
I am an indie.
I'll get back to that in a second.
All right, let's get started.
If you're an indie, you may have seen this,
but you don't want to end up with it.
It's still so good.
Like just the timing and the pacing of it is perfect,
and it's so sad, and you want to avoid that.
We all want to avoid that.
And I mean, if you want to avoid that, what you have to do
is you have to sell your game.
That's basically the heart of it.
If you want to make money, you have to sell your game.
But if you're an indie or a small team,
it's not really about selling your game.
It's much more about selling yourself.
You are usually your own marketing team,
and you're a key part of the game and its story
and its development story.
So you need to figure out how to sell yourself.
But it's not only just selling yourself.
It's actually selling yourself to strangers,
people that don't know you and don't know your game
and probably don't care.
So that's pretty scary.
So hi, I'm Martin.
I'm going to spend the next couple minutes diving
into all of that.
Before I do that, though, a little bit of context.
I'm a German indie.
I've been making games since the early days of Quake 1,
doing some modding.
I've been in the industry since 2008.
I've been working on indie since 2012.
And I've been working on my current project,
Noir Prophet, which I'll use for a bunch of examples.
I've been working on it since 2012.
Back then it looked like, since 2014, back then it
looked like this, then like this, and now like this.
So 2014 to now, that's almost four years.
So that's a lot of time for conferences.
and a lot of exhibitions.
What I want to do is, in the next couple of minutes,
I want to help you find your strangers and talk to them.
So that said, you have a game.
That's a big pile of work.
That's hard to do.
But what do you do next?
You want to get it out to people.
You can do social media marketing,
all this kind of thing.
But if you want to really meet them,
the first thing that comes to mind is, yeah, let's get a booth.
And booths are awesome.
There's a lot of opportunities for indies to get on a booth.
There's a lot of joint booths, like the Indie Mega
booth or the Indie Arena booth.
There's joint showcases like the Day of the Death, which
is here at GDC, or like Dutch Courage.
And these are all really great.
They have huge advantages in the sense
that because you're constantly physically present on site,
you have a lot of exposure.
Also, because they usually use joint affairs,
it gives it a sense of credibility,
like you're part of this larger thing.
And also, another really important advantage
from going to these things is you
get to do networking with all the devs around you.
You're in the trenches together, spending a lot of time
just crunching and standing there next to each other.
And that's a really valuable thing.
But you're here.
You've read the session description.
Sorry, German.
So all of the things are going to be jumbled.
You know I'm not going to talk about booths.
But I want to talk about the downsides of having a booth.
And I mean.
The obvious one is, it's going to be expensive.
These things cost upwards of 1,000K
for a small kind of thing in sort of a joint booth,
and runs you to 3 to 5K for a bigger area.
Obviously, longer events usually cost more,
and shorter events may cost a little bit less,
but it's gonna be expensive.
It's gonna take some money.
That's the obvious one.
But also, if you're a small team in India,
God forbid, like me, you're doing this solo,
going to a conference or to an exhibition.
Manning a booth for three days, five days,
it's really, really exhausting.
It's hard work.
You stand there for eight hours, 10 hours,
on your feet, talking all day,
shouting over the speakers that are next door.
By the end of this, you're gonna feel like an old man.
I feel like an old man.
You will feel like an old person.
Your knees hurt, your legs hurt, your feet hurt,
your hips hurt, your throat sore.
It's really hard.
And also, booths aren't really for every game.
Some games benefit more from booths than others,
especially multiplayer games that sort of have visuals
that attract people more easily.
If you have a very slow game,
it'll be hard to pull in people.
I have a card game, Noir Prophet is a card game.
So what I have to do is I have to pull people to the booth
and go like, oh, do you like card games?
Come on, take a look,
because the game isn't as flashy and visual
that it's just being played,
attracts people that much.
So, expensive, exhausting, and not for everybody.
Then I found myself draining the budget
and draining my energy levels,
but I still wanted to get my game into the hands of people.
I had made some serious changes.
I just wanted to have people play, so what can you do?
I mean, you can just have no booth.
It may look a little bit lonely, but it's a lot of work.
All right, so what's the benefits of doing that?
I mean, the obvious one is it's cheaper.
You don't have to pay for the booth.
You don't have to pay for like roll-up banners,
or like, I don't know, custom t-shirts,
though that you may still want to do.
But the important part is it's flexible.
You don't have to do 10 hours a day.
You don't have to do eight hours a day.
You don't have to stand in one place all the time.
And that's really the key to this thing.
You can do as much as you want,
and you can do it where you want.
And doing it where you want means
you can go to where your players are.
Wait, oh no, I'm looking at the wrong thing.
And if you look at this one.
So you can go to where your players are.
This is one of my terrible selfies at Gamescom.
I don't know why, but most of the selfies
have this very serious face.
I think, I guess I have resting bitch face.
I'm trying to get better.
I've started Instagramming and sort of upping my selfie game.
So, no more profit is a digital card game.
I'm at Gamescom.
Where the hell are my players?
The good thing about these really big events are
the players sort themselves just for your convenience.
So I mentioned it's a card game.
So my players are probably people that play other card games.
So what do you do?
You go to big booth of similar games
and you talk to the people there.
So what I did is another bitch face selfie.
It's hard to tell because the lighting is all terrible,
but that's Hearthstone.
And you meet people there that are standing in line,
and they'll probably stand there for 30 minutes, an hour,
depending on how long the line is.
And they don't really have anything to do.
Like, they're bored.
They would like to be entertained.
They would like to see something,
like to shorten their waiting time.
And that's, they welcome you.
Like, they're really looking forward to somebody
to entertain them.
So that's what I did.
I went to Gamescom.
I talked to people in the queues for card games
and talked to them about my game.
And that's, that worked.
And that's what I'm gonna talk about.
So you can show off your game without a booth.
You do not need to spend thousands of dollars
in getting this huge setup.
It has its advantages, but sometimes it's
not what you want to do.
So let's get into the details.
OK, so I've sort of split this apart into three things.
First one is the goals, the sort of things
you should think about before you get started,
the preparation, the sort of things
you should do before you hit the show floor,
and the approach, what you do once you're there.
break for a drink.
So, the goals.
It basically boils down to, why do you want to do this?
So you don't have a booth,
but you still want to show your game.
And it's still going to cost you.
Like, this isn't going to be for free.
You still have to travel,
you have to get the ticket for the event,
you have to pay for accommodation.
It's gonna cost you time, energy, and money.
This is all stuff you could invest in your game.
So figuring out why you want to do this
helps you sort of,
understand why you do this investment.
It'll also help you be more prepared.
Once you're on-site, there's a limited amount of time
you have on-site, and you want to make as much of that
as possible.
And if you have sort of multiple goals,
it helps you to prioritize, so you know
which ones you can go first while you're still energized.
This is going to be a sort of strenuous, draining experience.
You're going to talk to people all the time.
For some, that's easier to do than for others,
but it still requires energy.
I'm going to come back to energy a couple times, I think.
So I'm going to go over a bunch of example goals.
I've seen myself and heard from others.
That's not an exhaustive list.
If you have any you want to talk about,
please do come up to the mic afterwards.
The first one is sort of obvious.
We want all.
We want exposure.
We want people and players to see our game.
So press is a good multiplier.
And that's a good idea.
There's a bunch of things you should
consider when you want to target press when you're at the event.
First off, it's probably a good idea to reach out beforehand.
If you've been to the talk prior to this,
reaching out to people beforehand will make them remember you
and sort of feel like they're more familiar to you.
However, if you're just a small studio,
you're very unlikely to get a lot of feedback
from, like, big-name sort of news outlets.
Still, you should try.
Also, for press, really large events are really good
because there's going to be more press,
more different people to meet.
And also, these large events usually have sort of...
press days or specific press areas
that you can hang out at.
When you meet press, it's also really important
that you have something they can remember you by.
They go to these shows to see a lot of games,
and yours is just one of a lot of them.
So try and give them something that they can remember you.
Also, you should definitely have a press kit in place.
There's a lot of solutions for press kits,
sort of like do press kit or differently.
And making a press kit is sort of its own talk.
Just know that it's.
easier than it looks, but you may want to consider
investing more energy in making a sort of custom thing,
because it may make your game stand out a little bit more.
But again, it's more work.
But in the end, when you want to go and meet press,
keep in mind press are there for stories.
You want stories about games and game development.
So you have something interesting to tell
about how your game was being built,
how you relate to your game.
Why are you making this?
That is interesting to the people in the press audience.
All right.
Another kind of people you might want to meet are influencers, streamers, YouTubers, all
this kind of new, the new way to sell games.
And again, sort of like press, you want to reach out beforehand.
Again, like press, if you're small and they're big, you're probably not going to get a reply.
But it's good to know sort of which kind of influencers play similar games similar to
yours and which ones will be at the event.
So you can then at the time of the event sort of see if you can reach out.
For influencers, it's really important that you bring something playable.
They want to play games.
They want to see games.
They want to see a pitch deck or anything.
And also, if you can, if you're far enough along,
bring keys to share.
A, it'll make them maybe play the game for you and stream it
or take a video of it.
But it also gives them something they can
give to their followers.
They have something to share with other people.
Because in the end, influencers want
content for their viewers.
All right.
Another goal to go, which was sort of my chief goal when I
went to Gamescom, is playtesting.
Conferences are really good to get a lot of people that
are in your target audience to play your game in quick
succession and see them play it.
A booth is really good for this because you'll get a
consistent stream of players.
But on the other hand, in my experience, after about two
days of this, you've gotten so much feedback that you just
want to step back, work on the game, and then get in another
couple days instead of being there for a long time and keep
hearing the same things over and over again.
And if you don't have a booth, it allows you to be more
flexible in that regard.
If you want to do place testing, it makes sense to be aware of what you want to test.
Do you want to specifically look at the UI or are there some things in your combat system you want to look at?
Having that in mind is useful.
Also, in that regard, if you have something you're not sure about, bring multiple builds.
I had an earlier showing, I had different versions of an armor system.
I wasn't really sure which one was easy to understand, which one was sort of fun to play with.
So I just brought multiple builds and switched them out over time.
Just watched people interact with them.
Also, you should have a conference-specific build.
I'll go into the details on that later,
but it makes sense to have special words and set aside.
And in the end, remember, players want to be entertained.
The game should look and play well and look decent,
even if it's short.
It doesn't have to be like a 30-minute experience.
You probably won't even have time for that.
But whatever you're going to show them should feel like a game.
shouldn't be like gray boxes.
All right, another goal, making money, yeah.
And no, that just doesn't work.
If you think about how much a conference is gonna cost you,
and depending how much your game is gonna cost,
you're gonna have to sell upwards of 10 copies a day,
and that's a lot.
You know, if the conference is sort of 10 hours,
that means selling one copy an hour.
And I don't think that's doable.
You have to consider conferences being an investment.
They're not about making money,
they're more about making friends.
It's not business context,
this is people that want to be invested in you
and the things you do.
So what you have to do instead,
instead of trying to sell people on your game,
you have to get them interested in what you do.
Try to get them to stay in touch.
If you find somebody who,
oh, that's interesting, that's cool,
I like these kinds of games,
try and in some way have them follow you,
have them sort of subscribe to your newsletter.
Newsletters are great.
by trying to hold on to them.
And if they stick around long enough,
they may convert into fans,
because the people you meet at that point,
they're just casual acquaintances.
And getting sort of, you know,
getting your hook in them in some way
that they're not lost to you is really important.
All right.
So that's a bunch of goals.
Another time for a drink.
Next step, preparation.
What to do before you actually hit the show.
What you should do before you hit the show
is you should know your game.
You need to know what's unique about your game
and your game story.
I've seen the talk from Tom Francis,
creator of Gunpoint and Heat Signature, earlier this week.
He had this great quote,
ask yourself about different parts of your game.
Can this be a bit bland, or will the game suck?
If you find the part that can't be bland,
that's probably a really important part of the game.
Maybe something that makes it unique.
I mean, these two games,
that's Slime Rancher and Death Trash.
they're very different, and they'll have,
as a result of that, will have very different messaging,
different sort of handouts, different way you play it,
talk to people, pitch it to people,
and for nowhere profit, I tried to figure out what that is,
and what it is, it's a single-player card game,
it's not free-to-play, it's not multiplayer,
it's not collectible, and that sort of makes it unique,
but at the same time, it's also a challenge.
When people see card game, they think CCG,
they think trading cards, they think multiplayer.
So that's always something I need to communicate clearly.
This unique thing is also a challenge for me to overcome.
It's also a roguelike deck-building game.
These aren't as unique as they used to be anymore.
We have Slay the Spire, Monster Slayer,
and the Hearthstone Dungeon Run,
which sort of all go into the same niche.
And it's sort of a mixture of Indian culture,
science fiction, and post-apocalypse,
which we always try to really communicate
in very simple images, like this character here.
He's got this sort of science fiction arm and gun.
The beard and the clothing clearly communicate.
sort of Indian culture.
And hopefully, some of the post-apocalypse
also shines through in the kid bashing
of sort of the gear he has.
All right, so if you know what your game sort of is,
at its heart, what makes it special,
next thing is making handouts.
I said.
You want people to have something that they can
remember you by.
Giving them something physical is very good for this.
This is the key idea of merch.
People play so many games, they see so many things at a
show, you want them to remember yours.
And one really important thing is, never do flyers.
They don't work.
The issue with flyers is they're sort of this big size
and they tempt you to add too much text.
And text is boring.
If you ever had a text-heavy game,
I have a text-heavy game, and you see players play a game,
they just click through the text.
The same happens with a flyer.
You look at it, you trash it.
Also, flyers are often sort of very light and cheap
and sort of crumble.
And if somebody hands you a flyer, what do you do?
You fold it neatly and put it in your pocket?
No, you probably just sort of go squish it in there.
Or if you have like a bag, you just throw it in there,
and at the end of the show,
it's gonna be crumpled mess at the bottom.
You pull out everything, you see this thing,
and you go like, ugh.
So don't do that.
Don't do flyers.
Instead, make something more high quality.
Make postcards, stickers, buttons, anything.
Also, focus on artwork over text.
If you have something that looks pretty,
people will want to grab it.
Don't forget to put your URL or the game's name on it.
That'll help.
So that's really important.
Have something cool you can give to people.
Like, oh, that's my game.
There you go.
Also.
if you do a lot of, you'll do a lot of pitching,
going to people, telling them about your game.
It's good if you prepared visual material.
This can be actually physical things you then can give them.
If you have like, if you make like postcards
and have different type things of your game on them,
or you could like have a tablet and have like images on it.
But it'll help people, you know,
follow the words you're using
and it'll make them remember your game more easily
because when they see your screenshot later,
they go, oh, I've seen that somewhere and that'll help.
Also, if you have time, money, and or a team, do something fun.
I've seen people do a reward wheel,
go do high score competitions, do costumes.
All these sort of things can help.
But again, it sort of ties back to messaging.
You need to know what your game is to figure out
what makes sense for you.
For No Web Profit, what I did, it's a card game.
So I made cards.
These are sort of business card-sized cards.
And they focus very much on the artwork
and had some little bits of the story and the world on it,
because that's one of the things that makes it unique.
what really worked well is that they're different.
There's different artwork on there.
And it always allowed me to play with people
and go like, oh, which one do you want?
And you have this interaction suddenly.
It's not just you have this thing,
but it becomes this, okay, which one do you wanna select?
Or maybe people play for a long time,
and I'm like, all right, you can have two.
And it sort of becomes more interesting.
And that works for me because I'm making a collectible,
or non-collectible card game, but a card game,
where there's lots of different cards.
So it sort of ties back together.
All right.
messaging, handouts, and then preparing your game build.
That's really important.
That's probably the most important thing.
And right away, make sure it runs on a mobile device.
Even if it is not a mobile game, if you can,
get it on a tablet.
If you can't get it on a tablet, use a sort of
convertible laptop.
But you'll be running around.
You'll need to show this to people.
You don't want to lug a lot of gear around and sort of
carry lots of things.
No More Profit is a desktop-focused game,
but I have a tablet build because it's really good
for conferences.
The second thing about your build is
you will have a very short play time.
If you go up to people in the queue and ask them to play,
you'll have five to 10 minutes.
If you can, target your game to be this short,
even if it's normally longer.
Because then there's this awkward moment
if the game is very long and people play
for like five, 10 minutes and they sort of,
like the queue starts moving again and they wanna leave,
but they sort of have to abandon the game
and give it back to you.
an uncomfortable experience for them.
So if you can give them an easy answer,
they've played a bunch, they're done,
you reward them visually, or maybe with,
like, oh, you finished, you get a sticker.
That's a lot better ending experience than just,
all right, I just, here, please.
Also, you cannot rely on audio.
It's gonna be loud, and there's gonna be lots of people around,
and people don't want to put on headphones.
You know, here, hold this tablet,
I'm just gonna put my headphones on you.
That just doesn't work.
And also, I mean, that's true for all games,
but doubly here, as self-explanatory as possible.
If you have a booth, you can print out your controller
scheme and put it on the booth so people can look at it
or whatever.
If you're doing this on the go, people
are not going to look at anything.
I mean, I thought about doing something like printing it
on a shirt, because that'd be funny.
But you want to give this thing to people
and have them play immediately.
And I've mentioned earlier, having a specific conference
build is a plus.
It is useful for making a short experience, rewarding people,
making it easier.
Because people don't know the game,
they want to have a good experience.
Maybe you're just going to tone down
the difficulty a little bit.
Always triggers the tutorial, resets automatically
after a while.
Maybe you want to put your pitch material in the game
so you don't have to leave the game and go back to the game
if you have images in there.
So there are a bunch of things you can do.
It makes sense early on to put this in your build.
And maybe just have some pool, some simple flag
you can turn on and turn off.
to get your conference build always up to date
and always sort of carry that forward.
Because it's going to come in handy a bunch of times.
And the last one is, you're going
to talk to a lot of people, and a lot of people
are going to watch you because you're
sort of operating in this queue.
If you can make people laugh, that's a real good plus.
It'll make approaching more people
easy because, oh, they're having fun.
And then you come to them, and they're
interested in what you're doing.
This may be sort of hard if you have a serious game,
like Nowhere Prophet, which is this post-apocalyptic
experience thing.
But what you can do is you have, if you're sort of early,
you can have temp graphics and have them be funny.
So what I did is I had these mustache-carrying dudes.
They're obviously temp.
Like, I don't need to explain to people
that these are not the final graphics, but they're fun.
Like, whenever they appeared, people had a good time.
So it's possible to add some levity,
even if it's sort of a serious game.
You have to decide if that's something you wanna do.
All right, so that's a quick overview of the preparation.
Let's get to the approach.
But before we do that,
Take a deep breath.
Because once you're going to hit the show floor,
you need all the energy you can have.
You need to be excited.
But first, you need to find your people.
What you can do is you can look for people,
for games that have a similar genre, similar mechanics,
or a similar setting.
So if you make a shooter, just look for people
that play other shooters.
If you have a card game, look for similar card games.
If you have a post-apocalyptic game,
I can never say this right.
Post-apocalyptic.
If you make a post-apocalyptic game,
look for similar games.
And then you approach.
And approaching these people is not as hard as it sounds.
Again, you sort of have to be in the right mood, I think.
I'm slightly extroverted, but still,
it always costs some energy, which why.
You need to be really refreshed when you get there.
And then be friendly.
That's what it comes down to.
Hi, I have a game.
Do you want to see the game?
Be excited about your game.
If you're not excited, you will not be able to get anybody
involved.
They don't care then.
But also, be excited about the game you're at, because
you're at somebody else's booth.
And people are there for that game.
So if I'm at the Hearthstone booth.
I've played Hearthstone for way too long.
Research.
But then I was excited and I could talk to people
about Hearthstone and sort of lead from that to my game.
So, hey, you like Hearthstone?
I'm working on a card game.
And something about Hearthstone that really bugged me
is that you sort of have to grind for cards
and sort of makes the deck building very restrictive.
So I made a single-player card game that fixes that.
Are you interested?
And that sort of worked really well for me
to tie in sort of my game to the game I'm at.
As mentioned, be friendly.
Be doubly friendly because you're at somebody else's booth.
You're not trying to,
got into any trouble, you know.
You're just a guest, as everybody else.
If somebody asks you to leave, stop it then.
You probably just do,
there's gonna be enough players around.
So, that's the approach.
To get people to play, just ask them if they wanna play.
Hand them the thing, let them play, five to 10 minutes.
And after you're done, keep it simple.
Ask them for one thing only.
Hey, thank you for playing, please.
follow me on Twitter or check out the game,
Wishlist on Steam, whatever it is,
give them one thing to do and give them something
to sort of remind them where to do it.
What I tried to do in the beginning
is to ask for newsletter subscriptions,
because I like newsletters,
and I had this clipboard with me,
and I wanted to write all the emails on there,
and that did not work at all,
because it made me look like the pollster,
like one of the guys you see in the mall
who asks you political questions,
and nobody likes those guys.
went in the bag real quickly.
But try to give them something to do.
All right.
And those, again, as I said earlier in making friends,
if any of them are really interested,
try and hold onto them.
Maybe ask them if they wanna be better testers.
Maybe they can get a key if they test for a while.
Whatever you're gonna do,
try and grab them and hold onto them.
So that's the queue.
You can approach the queue.
You can make the queue play.
You'll have five to 10 minutes of play time.
But if that's not long enough, you
may want to look at the stragglers.
These are the people that are around the booth you're at,
say around Hearthstone, but they're not standing in line.
They're just waiting or watching the screens.
And these people have time for longer play sessions.
They're not moving and going to get somewhere specific.
So you can approach them, hey, Hearthstone, my game.
Let them play if they're interested.
You have a longer session, and you have more time
for questions afterwards.
And usually, because it's sort of a more relaxed environment,
it also works a lot better to sort of get them to subscribe
or get them to do something on the spot,
instead of giving them something to do afterwards.
Also, it sort of seems to be easier to give people
the headphones here, because they're not moving.
They're usually sort of standing somewhere specific.
But that sort of depends on how you run it, I guess.
All right, press.
So we're on the go.
We have everything mobile.
We can talk to press.
On the big events, you can look for the press badges.
Here at GDC, there's this little media stripe.
For Gamescom, they have a sort of, like, slightly pink badge.
If you know what it looks like, you can spot it.
So if you see somebody in front of a press,
you can just go, hi, I'm making a card game.
Are you interested in card games?
And then sort of give them the pitch.
Here, again, stay friendly, stay professional.
You don't have to, if they're like, no, I'm in a hurry,
or no, I don't care, just...
All right, I'll be, we're sort of on the time.
All right, so be friendly, be respectful,
and try and get their contact details.
Try to give them something,
but they may have gotten so many cards,
so many, seen so many games,
they may not be doing the follow-up.
So if you get their contact details,
you're in charge of the follow-up,
and that's more valuable.
Influences are sort of hard to spot
because they don't have special badges,
but if you know who's there and,
what they look like, you can reach out on social media
and go like, hey, I'm around.
I can come to where you are and show you my game.
That's really useful.
Again, they want to play something,
so give them something to play.
And if you can, give them something, maybe some merch.
You've got a few t-shirts, you can hand to them,
they can raffle off whatever you want to do.
But that's all the goals I've got so far.
So once you've done this, you've talked to players,
you let them play, you talk to press,
you talk to influencers, you're done.
Not quite.
You still have the wrap-up to do.
As mentioned, you need to follow up with your contacts.
Say, hi, it was great meeting you.
Let's stay in touch.
Here's a build of the game.
Maybe press people a key, whatever it's going to be.
If you have people subscribe to a newsletter,
send out a newsletter and say, hey, welcome new fans.
Maybe you've taken some good pictures of the event
and the fans you played.
You can put that in there.
That'll make people more likely to share.
Or you do something like this and make a talk about it.
All right, so to wrap it up, because I sort of have to race through this,
find out where you're going and prepare accordingly.
Make sure your game and all your materials are good to go on the fly.
Have your cards in a pocket and know which pocket they're in.
Have the cards you get in another pocket so you don't go like,
ugh, wait, where's everything?
And approach, know where your audience goes, and be excited.
That helps.
Just loving your game and being excited sort of infects people.
So, and that's it, I'm at the end,
and I'm gonna finish with one clear call to action.
Follow me on Twitter.