Morning guys. How many of you have read the Shank Postmortem at the Game Developer Magazine?
I'm trying not to repeat too much of that. I think it's available to everybody. So you guys can read that.
I really tried to get this talk around things that I didn't get to talk to about or things that I found out after I'd written that postmortem.
So for people who don't know me very well or have seen the work that we've done...
It's interesting that we've gone basically more and more violent over time.
We started with eats, and it was family-friendly.
And then Sugar Rush was a game, it was teen, and then we did the mature thing.
So I'm not really sure what we're going to go to next, but I think it's going to be fun.
We're pretty good at stabbing people now, I think.
People seem to resonate with that for us.
It's good.
You know, I was presenting this, preparing this slide, and people kept asking me what
Shank looked like when we first started.
And you know, I thought, you know, it pretty much always looked the same.
And then I realized that there was this one test that I did with Jeff over a weekend when
we were first thinking about what Shank was going to be.
And so we built this thing.
And this is actually what Shank looked like right from the beginning.
uh... actually if i can just get the uh... this will work i want to show you
guys the actual
uh... demo here
try real quick and see if i can get there
uh...
like right up here
maybe i'll do it right at the end
but uh... it was all done in flash
and uh... we did it over a weekend and you can move around
basically all the moves were the same you could kind of get a feel of how
things were going
And that's what gave us confidence to move forward.
And then a few weeks later, we had a new character design,
and it was basically Shank.
And it was basically the same from then on.
And in fact, so much so that what you saw here
is in early January.
What you saw here was also in January.
And then the next thing I'm gonna show you
was in early March, so two months later.
You can see there's a double jump in there.
Some of the little differences that we had.
Basically, it looked like...
So in any case, that was, you know, when I look back at it, I'm like, what did we do for the next year?
But, you know, it was a lot of engine work, there's a lot of tweaks, you know, the animation was different over time,
we fixed a lot of bugs, we put it on three platforms, all sorts of things.
But it's still pretty amazing that we got to that point in two months, and it basically stayed the same.
I don't think I've ever worked on a game where it basically, from a visual standpoint and a feel standpoint, stayed the same.
after two months of development.
Of course, Monaco is going to follow me, so whatever I did.
So, some other really important things that happened to us is Pax 2009.
A lot of you guys have heard about that.
I wanted to show the picture of what really was there.
We were talking to a lot of publishers at the time,
trying to get a deal done for Shank,
because we really needed funding to finish the game.
because we're a team of six and growing,
and we were doing other side jobs at the same time,
we really wanted to close the fan this thing.
And the publishers were telling us to not show Shank,
and I think you guys have all heard this before,
this kind of thing, where they're like,
oh, hey, don't show your game out,
because that will hinder our efforts to promote your game.
Of course, in my experience.
they're kind of a multiplier on your own efforts, so if you put in zero, then they multiply on your zero.
And you just get zero.
And that happened to us previously on Eats, so we're like, no, you know, we're just going to show the game.
We haven't even signed anything yet, so it's ours to show.
By the same time, we couldn't announce what platforms it was going to be on.
Again, a lot of you guys have run into that.
So we just kind of made this box from staples.
and spray painted it and covered it up and it was,
you know, stuck whatever controllers in there that we could,
including Atari, hey, maybe it'll go on the Atari,
maybe it'll go on the Dreamcast, that'd be pretty sweet.
And actually it was a big hit because of that,
well, partly because of that.
People really enjoyed that kind of story.
So talking about some of the technically hard things.
uh... right there on the right you can see our very first playstation image
that we that was actually rendering anything that resembles uh... shank
uh... so i took a picture of that
and you can see the prettiness that it was
uh...
we shipped uh...
on the playstation 3 simul ship with the xbox
uh... but we didn't start
porting until february
about mid february
and then we shipped in june
So we had no code on the PlayStation and then we shipped in June.
So that was pretty fun. It worked out well for us.
Another thing was 2GB downloads. I don't think I'd do that again.
There was 1.4GB of movies in that game.
So the rest of it was the game. 600MB game.
And fragmentation, I didn't... I had no idea that...
I mean, like, logically thinking, of course, all the hard drives were fragment,
but I didn't think it was going to be a problem.
uh... we actually had problems up to
where uh... we have a magnitude of difference so one person would take
ten seconds to load the level and another person would take a minute to load the level
and it was literally that bad
uh... and
none of these certification caught that all our internal testing, EA's testing
Microsoft's testing, our external testing, none of it caught it
because they were all using fresh uh... xboxes
so you know if you're going to do an xbox you test the fragmentation thing
So that's what we learned and we had to fix that post-launch.
It also took us a week and a half to fix it and a month to deploy the thing.
So that's another really annoying thing.
But it was a really bad experience for the people who had it.
We also almost went broke while making Shank.
It was enough that we had to do temporary optional wage increases.
uh... we paid back we paid all the wages back with interest
uh... so that was pretty awesome actually
uh... and uh... it was kind of around uh...
that was in january 2010 when that happened
we also had a shareholder loan to uh... to tide things over
uh... a bank loan against my house
and jeff's house
uh...
and uh... you know the reason one of the big reasons why we did it was because
we felt
Not only did we want to get the best deal for ourselves,
but when we were negotiating the publishing deal,
things just didn't feel right.
It really felt like we were getting squeezed.
And I felt like even if I took the deal and it worked out for us,
it wouldn't bode well for the next person who came in after me.
And so, the deal that we were looking at just wasn't really right.
We would have survived and that's about it.
So that's why we stepped away and we said no because not only did I think that it wasn't a great idea for us,
but more importantly I really felt like we have a responsibility, all of us have a responsibility in our actions on how it affects the industry.
And so, you know, with some contingencies in mind of what would happen if shit really went down,
you know, that's when we took the bank loans and reduced the assets and everything and we just said no to...
to the publisher deal and went with EA instead, that had a much more fair deal. And I really
do think that that affects the industry, and everybody who does that affects the industry
in quite a significant manner, in fact. And so, you know, we're pretty proud that we were
able to do that.
There's other random things that had happened in there. We built the levels in...
In PAX East last year, we had this one great level.
And it was the Butcher level, if you guys have played it.
And it was just really polished.
It worked out really well.
And then we also had the first level.
And we showed this to the press.
And they were like, oh, this is great.
And they're like, when is it coming out?
I'm like, summer.
It's going to come out in the summer.
I'm shipping in like three months.
But that was actually all the content we had.
We showed them everything.
So after that, between March and June,
we built the rest of the game, which was 13 more levels.
So we had two levels and then we built 13 in three months.
And dishwashers, halfway through the development we had a flood as well.
That was fantastic.
I was actually on vacation at the time, the first vacation in some time, and I was in Hawaii actually.
And then I got a call and they're like, your office is flooded.
What do you want me to do about it?
I'm not even there.
And this picture here is actually the aftermath.
So the water was much higher than this before someone actually ended up taking a picture.
What happened was the next-door neighbor's dishwasher had exploded.
And what's really interesting is I think we were protected or something.
I mean, we were just really, really lucky.
Because first of all, our servers were in the other room that didn't get flooded.
So that was awesome.
And then the second thing is...
If you look, maybe, of course you can't see them because we lifted all the computers,
but the computers are actually on the floor.
And the power supplies are on the bottom of the computer.
And then the water level went like three, four inches or something.
That's what I heard anyway.
Again, I wasn't there, but all the computers miraculously still work today.
And I honestly don't understand.
Maybe it was, you know, we were trying to figure out what happened.
Maybe there was like enough dust stuck in there that would protect it or something.
So, you know, thankfully we don't clean anything.
All right.
I'm not sure.
Anyway, so somehow we were, you know, there was an angel or something,
because otherwise that would have been some big disaster.
I mean, at least our servers weren't affected anyway.
So it was good.
Some other stuff here cinematics is one of the big big problems that we had because we had such big cash flow issues
you know all the
cinematic team right at the end. This is a mouth chart for scissor and
And you see you know
This is some of our storyboards and you see it just kind of gets more and more rough as time goes on
It's the last one. It's like what the hell is that you know?
And and so you know they were really meticulous at first you know directing everything and doing the proper storyboards
And then at the end, it was just like, OK, we have to animate now.
So here's some scribble, and then you go off and do it.
Some post-launch data that I wasn't able to put out.
30% of the people completed the game.
It took people around three or four hours for the first play through.
And then they had the co-op mode and stuff like that.
So that obviously played into whether or not
you complete the game.
Only 1% of people beat the hard mode, 1.9, or 1.6, rather.
Yeah, our conversion rate is pretty good, 26%.
And I think in my next game, I'm going
to have a smaller download size.
Well, at least not 1.4 gigs of movies anyway.
Actually, even that was, as we were developing it,
the movies just kept peaking up.
And I would compress it some more
and do other tricks to push it down.
And then the animators would go, hey, look, more cinematics.
And then push it up.
And then I had to push it down.
It just kind of bobbled along.
And then we just finally squeaked by at 1.9 gigs
kind of deal.
The last point is aggressive versus defensive players is another really interesting thing that we learned after launch,
which kind of shows that we didn't do enough testing before launch,
was that there's aggressive players and defensive players,
because I would get people saying,
the controls are just the most amazing things ever, this is just so sweet.
And then other people are like, I'm stuck, I don't know why I can't move.
And we realized it was because it was a different style of player.
So if you were really offensive and you wanted to kill people and stab things,
which is what we wanted you to do, it would feel really good
because all the transitions were working really well.
And you could just get into the groove of it really well.
But if you wanted to run and you wanted to just get out of the fight,
that was not something that we anticipated, really.
So that's when the controls got sticky, when it's like, you know, I do a move and I want to run away.
That didn't work out so well, and we didn't realize that.
But, you know, it was definitely a data point for us for the future on things to think about, you know, just the different play styles.
Another thing is, you know, everybody asks me how the relationship between us and EA was.
And, you know, I always catch that with context, which is that, you know, it works really well for us, and sometimes it can work really well.
And sometimes, obviously, it doesn't work so well.
So I've got some stuff going on here.
And I wanted to start with the less good and then go to the
good, because, well, usually it's the good and the bad.
But people are interested in about the less good.
So we had a deadline that was two months before we really
had to ship.
And that was some internal thing from EA that they really,
really wanted us to get it out on a certain time for other
financial reasons that had nothing to do
with the actual game.
So
You know, that was maybe a month, actually,
before we had to ship.
But anyway, that extra month would
have been put to good use in terms of testing and tweaking.
So that was unfortunate.
And I think they understand that that was unfortunate.
And I don't think they'd do that with us again anyway.
And old-style PR is something that I'm really passionate
about, is that the PR.
side of things in the old ways when they're doing the box product stuff.
You know, they set up these time slots that the media can meet with you.
And it's like, you know, listen to us talk as opposed to, you know, talk to the media.
And I really think that it's important for us to talk to the media
and actually have a conversation and have everybody understand where you're coming from.
And obviously as an indie, that's one of our strengths.
But just as digital download continues to go, that, I think,
is the way that it's going to go, as opposed to this press
release thing.
I mean, press releases are horrible.
I mean, I just never really want to do a press release,
and I'm always against it, pretty much.
But sometimes I get coaxed into it.
And we did a press release where Marian Krawczyk, it was
announced that Marian was our writer.
And she
actually wrote God of War as well and then she wrote Shank.
And she had written Shank like way back when we started,
with us, right in the beginning.
And then when we did the press release of it and it said,
you know, Marian Krozek signed to do Shank, right?
And the media rightfully so said, why are you hiring a writer
at the end of the project?
Why are you doing that?
And the reason is because the press release was a one-way
communication.
There's no way to talk back and say, or no way
to have a discussion and say, actually, no, no, no.
We actually had her on right from the beginning as she was involved, but instead, you know,
the news just spread out that, you know, this game Shank, after signing with EA, decided
that they need a high-profile story writer, which totally wasn't the case.
So anyway, it's a big rant that can probably go on for quite some time with APR, but kind
of preaching to the choir here, too.
Consumer expectations, you know, signing with a publisher, suddenly you're an EA game.
and that brings with it all sorts of other things.
It's just, you know, they have different expectations
of what the game might be or might have
or the features it might have and the length it might be
and all that kind of thing.
And we definitely felt that from everybody.
And that means it's just something you have
to keep in mind.
It's just a thing that's there.
And of course, there's a possibly reduced upside
if you're not self-funding it, but I mean, the fact is
that we wouldn't have shipped Shank without.
some funding. So, you know, it's not really something that's on my mind.
I mean, the fact is that we ended up keeping, we kept the IP, we kept the creative freedom,
here's the good stuff. You know, they really trusted us to do what we wanted to do, and
we just went and did it. And, you know, part of the reason that that was possible was because
we had created Shank so far already. I mean, in two months it was basically the same game
as The End.
And so nobody was going to come in and say, I want a different game than that.
Although, back in the day when I pitched Eats, we got like, hey, can you make it into a Super
Monkey Ball game?
And things like that.
Maybe they did want Shank to be, I don't know, Machete or something.
So we had other great things as true support.
I mean, I felt like it was actually a supportive team as opposed to most of the time,
I mean, I've been working with publishers for a long time.
So a lot of times it can get to the point where the publisher
has become a cost center for you rather than a support
network for you.
And for us, this specific time, it was definitely a
support network for us.
Because I guess the stars aligned.
I mean, it was just a really great fit.
Multi-platform was absolutely huge.
You know, it's very, very difficult, if not impossible, to do a multi-platform simultaneous
ship without a publisher.
They actually did do marketing, which is pretty cool.
And they actually spent money on marketing, which is a novelty.
You know, reduced risk and less platform requirements.
I mean, I didn't have to localize Schenck because, you know, we knew that it wasn't
really going to make much of a difference in sales.
So we didn't localize it.
And right up to the last moment, we still changed
tweaking text to make it a little bit better.
And we wouldn't have been able to do that if we were not with
a publisher.
So all good things.
And of course, everyone asks, how did we do?
Well, in the first 24 hours, we sold more than Eats
Chowdown in its lifetime.
So that's pretty awesome.
It was reported and I'm not privy to talk about the actual sales numbers, so here it is.
XBLA reported 41,000 units in the first week, which is respectable and profitable for everyone.
But the main thing there is that multi-platform was key to our profitability.
It really was a difference for Schenck specifically,
it was the difference between profitable and not profitable.
uh... so you know it's it was a really great thing to see
uh... and uh... and on steam
you know uh...
i think everybody here loves steam it just it just works so well
uh... and it just uh... it's got a really long tail and it just keeps on going
as well
uh...
so as an overview uh...
the uh...
we had prototyping for three months we did tools forever so that we could
actually build those thirteen levels
in three months
The demo that you saw in two months was really cobbled together with old tools and things
like that, and we couldn't have finished the game with that.
There was six months of just madness.
You know, one of the great things, though, is that the engineers actually did such a
great job during the first nine months of tools making is they never had to, I mean,
I think they worked three weekends throughout the whole project.
So that was pretty amazing.
And even in the weekends, it's like one day out of it.
It was really the designers and the artists
that got the crunch of it because of the content crunch.
We're also working on another project at the same time
that we're doing Shank, and that really went awry
trying to do two projects with not enough people.
And that was definitely one of the hardest times in my life.
You know, listening to the Meat Mortem
and talking about their stress levels and things like that.
For people who know me,
it's actually pretty hard to stress me out.
But that was probably one of the most stressful times,
and having to go in the office and just work it out
and not show how stressed I was to the rest of the staff,
because that affects everybody.
If you're stressed, you're just gonna
permeate that with everybody.
So when everybody left, and it was just me and Marcus,
who's my high school buddy who started the company with me,
he'd stay late with me to finish things
until like 1 or 2 a.m.
And I tell him, you know, I just don't know how we're going to get this done.
How is this going to work?
And, you know, we just kind of fought through it, really, and took a look at the risk.
Yeah, it was a pretty tough time.
It was around April of last year.
And I wanted to finish off with some of the thoughts of the future,
which I've been thinking about a lot, you know.
There's a whole wall of text here, so I'm just going to talk about it here.
The best breakout hits on Xbox Live and PSN, they made $10 million, which for us is like,
holy crap, that's a lot of money.
But when you're talking about the lower number of games, the best games make $10 million
or $20 million, whatever it is.
And the publishers look at that, and they look at their investment into it, and the
whole economy looks at this.
And it's like, the number's just not really adding up.
all that much and the ceiling is pretty low.
But there's so much potential there that could work.
And I think the platforms really need to...
Well, we've been talking about this forever,
and they've been talking about it forever,
to improve the platform time over time,
which is create new ways to micro-transactions
or subscription or better ways to find games.
And they need more and more things.
That's what they need.
and you need to continually improve that platform,
you know, like Steam and iOS have.
And I think that that's how you're going to be able to
create this proper ecosystem.
And, you know, I think that one of the flaws there,
actually, is the king-making.
You know, the Summer Arcade frenzy is, you know,
I mean, if I got in Summer Arcade, great,
I'm not going to complain.
It is king-making, that's what it is, right?
It's a huge boost, but everything around it.
kind of falls to the side and you gotta do whatever you can to kind of pull yourself
back up a little bit.
And I think that it's definitely a double-edged sword.
It's a dangerous thing to rely so much on king making, on all these promotions where
it's all focused on this two-week period.
You really need to be able to spread out so that everybody can win.
And we've been talking about it forever.
All of us have been talking to Microsoft and PlayStation, and
they've been talking back and saying, yes, we know we need
more, we need recommendation systems.
Literally about five years ago, they were talking to us
about recommendation systems and other ways to find games.
Instead of top-selling game of all time, top-selling last
week, last month, last 35 days, whatever, just more ways for
people to.
for games to organically get found is the way that we're going to be able to actually have a proper system
where people can take risks and also have a much longer tail.
I mean, Eats, when it shipped, I think it made like $20,000 or something when it shipped.
And over time, that's when we really started making the money.
So we were able to take that kind of risk.
We're saying, OK, we're going to launch this game and over a long period of time we can make money.
But actually on the consoles, it's not so much.
It falls off a lot faster.
you know, unless you're one of the top.
And so you really need to be able to find new ways
of being able to make money on it.
And, you know, free-to-play micro-selections, that's one.
You know, Steam style, you know,
all the recommendation systems,
all the different ways to get people back.
You know, instead of deal a week, it's like deal a day,
you know, all that kind of thing.
You know, it's all important things.
uh... and you know that the main thing there is just the abundance mentality
you know it's not it's it's not trying to squeeze down it's it's like
is
steam understands that if your game is out on more platforms will actually sell
more on steam
not less
so you know this exclusivity thing
doesn't actually help
that i mean it helps hardware sales and i guess that's the motivation
between uh... for it
uh... but if they if they want you know games to sell
exclusivity isn't going to sell it in my opinion
uh... and uh... and codes you know free codes just so easy right at the other day
asked for twenty five thousand free codes on steam
five minutes later here you go here's a twenty five thousand free codes of eats
uh... and uh...
uh... you know it's
it's just such a slow process when you're working
uh... in the console
anyway that's exactly twenty five minutes so i guess i'm
uh... but i hope that was helpful