Good afternoon, my name is Vanessa Hemovitch,
and I am an associate professor of psychology
at DigiPen Institute of Technology.
And my research and the classes that I teach
focus on cognitive science, UX, UI,
and a lot of ways that psychology dovetails
with game design.
And I'm really looking forward to giving this talk today
and the role of schemas as a driving force, as we'll see,
with perception, information processing,
and decision making.
So for today, I'm just gonna sort of outline
kind of where we're headed.
And the idea of how is cognition relevant to game design
is something that we're gonna look at here.
And I wish I had three hours to do a masterclass,
but unfortunately I only have about 20, 25 minutes.
So I'm just gonna sort of boil this down
and schemas have a very complicated relationship
with human behavior.
They are easily formed, easily activated, and never really turn off.
And today we're going to explore the nature and the relevance of schemas to player behavior
and how and why they function to drive player perceptions and how they guide decision making
and things like player choice.
So what is a schema?
This is a good place for us to start.
And one example of this is obviously what you see here.
this cute little puppy dog.
And in research, a schema is defined
as an organized mental structure or representation of stimuli.
And schemas really do work to streamline our information
processing and categorize objects to help
them relate to one another.
General categorizations like this can more or less be considered universal.
This is a picture of a dog, not of an airplane,
and schemas tend to reside in our long-term memory.
That said, one more complicated aspect of schemas is their subjective nature.
So if I had everyone in the audience close their eyes
and imagine the concept of a dog,
we would see a lot of variety in this room.
I might picture a German shepherd,
and you might think of Snoopy or something like that.
So in terms of looking at schemas in action,
what we can see here is that when we first learn,
often when we're young, what a dog is,
a schema is formed, and this is called assimilation.
And this is the process of fitting information
that contains the features we associate
that defines this stimulus.
So for example, a dog typically has two ears, a tail,
four legs, and tends to bark.
And when we are out and about in the real world,
we see these stimuli.
And we carry forward what we've assimilated in long-term memory with us.
Is this a dog? Does it match the known criteria?
In this case, the answer would be yes.
So over time, what we do is we learn that life can get complicated,
and schemas evolve and develop into more specific
and hopefully more accurate mental representations.
And this is referred to as accommodation.
And it allows mental frameworks to adapt and progressively change
from simple concepts to more complicated representational concepts.
like this. So we learned that schemas or dogs in this case contain a bit of variety and
our mental frameworks adapt. And by the way, we are doing this our entire lives. This is
not just something that children go through as they learn and grow.
experience invoke and change their schemas, so do artists and programmers,
players do as well. Really nobody is immune. So in cognitive science what we
do is we sort of work through schemas and activate them in different ways and
one is through what's called conceptually driven schemas and this is
known as top-down processing.
So here we see Homer deliberately invoking his mental framework of bacon,
which of course is delicious and I hope you're all not thinking about bacon
and can instead stay with me here as I continue to talk about schemas
and not talk about bacon.
And strategy is another good example of this as well.
So with top-down processing in a game, let's say like Rocket League,
What happens is what's called endogenous thinking.
And players learn strategy quickly.
And they learn best practices and procedures
to use these strategies, use this knowledge
to inform how to play the game.
For example, you should not really, in a game like Rocket League, send more than one teammate
into the initial strike.
You'll want to also maybe think about dividing the field and only watch the risk in terms
of chasing the ball.
Don't bunch up and keep the ball centered.
Maybe if you're going for a more aggressive strategy.
Personally, I find that the best offense is a good defense, and if you disagree with me,
I look forward to meeting you in the arena.
Gimas are also activated sometimes purely
from a sensory level, or when the environment delivers
a stimulus sort of at our feet.
And this is more of a what's called
data-driven type of processing.
And here Homer is sort of minding his own business,
and he happens upon the cola machine.
He might not have been thinking about
this attitude object before, but he definitely is now,
and it may even change or alter his behavior.
And for those in this room who have maybe experience playing Fortnite or other battle royale games,
what tends to happen is sometimes the environment is so intense that player strategy just goes right out the window.
I'm going to drop into this zone.
No, there's 30 other players that are here.
Now what do I do?
Now where do I go?
And here the environment is telling the player what's going on.
And what they might get into is a little bit different
than what they might have expected.
And they need to prepare themselves for what's coming.
So sometimes players have to adapt their strategy
based on how the game is going.
And schemas are what shoulder this burden for us.
Schemas allow us to shift between top-down processing
and bottom-up processing and meet the demands of the game.
So mentally, there's an app for that
and it's called a schema.
So in other games and I'm using destiny here as an example.
We oftentimes refer to on strategy-based schemas
for planning and the more that you are aware of these schemas,
the better you're going to play.
But that doesn't mean that players won't also be interested
if something does sort of pop up in front of them
like a golden treasure chest or a loot crate.
And there are things that will...
inform the player that they're close at the environmental level. It could be a sound cue that they're getting close to something that might be
interesting or worth checking out. So one question that I always pose to my students is, is it possible for
schemas in terms of top-down and bottom-up processing to coexist and truly be simultaneous?
And if we think about it, the answer is yes.
It is possible.
Knowing strategy and the schemas around that is a good thing.
Being open to the demands of the environment
and sort of knowing that we should react
to what the game throws at us is also a good thing.
So you may start with one strategy,
the game throws something else at you,
and schemas allow us to adapt and shift
between these different types of combinations
of mental processing.
So, games are not only able to do this,
they are notorious for doing this.
In the case of what we have here, Robo Recall,
there are plenty of game examples
where devs absolutely throw a wrench in the plans
of the best laid strategies that players have.
The player understands where to go,
the checkpoint is here, the game has informed them,
it could be a narrator, a narration, it could be an NPC.
and they already know where they have to go.
Unfortunately, enemy agents arrive on the scene,
they're probably blocking the path,
and the player's forced to sort of accommodate
and use that environmental input in a way moving forward.
And this is schema accommodation.
I have a plan, but the game world did something else.
So this is one thing that I wanted to kind of highlight
with this presentation.
Another one is how do we predict
what players are going to attend to?
People are complicated, and so are their perceptions.
But the good news is that science has repeatedly shown us
that we can, to a large extent,
predict certain aspects of human behavior.
And one way is to invoke schemas
that will guide information processing
through what's called conceptual fluency.
And in terms of understanding player perceptions
and predicting those perceptions,
conceptual fluency is one of those things
that's all about invoking schema consistency.
and designing game elements that rely sometimes pretty heavily
on how to navigate the game world and wrestle with stimuli
and adapt their strategies.
So players have a long history, as you can see,
with certain icons for schemas, and we build game icons
around those perceptions that can
and should be easily recognized.
And when we do recognize them, what happens is it aligns
with what we know and what we expect, and it's automatic.
Information processing is easy, and it feels good.
And really this is now sort of getting into the domain of UX versus UI,
which I don't have time to talk about today.
But I wanted to just sort of introduce this concept here,
because we are going to circle back to it.
So let's consider an example of how, let's say,
a typical player would interact with something like a game menu.
And the new game is generally listed at the top of the menu
with exit at the bottom.
And that's a schema that I think every single person in this room probably has.
And when those puzzle pieces click together with what I know and what I experience, this
generates conceptual fluency.
Here is another example from the Witcher series and you can see again we have a relative match.
That new game is listed at the top and exit or quit is at the bottom.
Here is another example where
things are aligning.
And in all three instances, the mental rule is in place.
And we have a schema match.
Information processing is easy, everything is as expected,
and cognitive load is relatively light.
However, what sometimes happens
is schemas don't always match to their environment.
Here suddenly there is a mismatch with this rendering,
and easy and automatic thinking is momentarily disrupted.
And as the player is asked to accommodate
to this new arrangement,
that violates some of their prior expectancies.
And cognitively we have to work just a little bit harder,
just a little bit.
This creates what psychologists call conceptual disfluency,
and conceptual disfluency leads to something
called attentional blink.
So when schemas are violated, mentally we often have to pause.
Orange juice and chocolate chip cookies is not in my wheelhouse.
My students say, go on, you should just try it.
I'm not having it.
I'm not going to do it.
It's too much for me.
I don't have time to tell you what's wrong with this combination,
but it's not a good one for me.
And when the disfluency is too strong, what happens is we reject it.
Here's another example of my students.
They send me emails, and they say, just go for it.
And again, I'm not having it.
it's feel free to do as you see fit I don't want to hear about it. So with
conceptual disfluency is another example again from my students this is something
called Cage of Thrones which is just a Google click away and most of the major
characters from Game of Thrones are photoshopped with the head of Nicolas
Cage on instead.
And to each their own.
The thing about Cage of Thrones that's interesting is that
Nicolas Cage doesn't really belong in Game of Thrones at all.
And it creates a very profound attentional blink.
And this, what's especially interesting is that these characters are so iconic
that if you put your hand sort of over the head of this character,
you could probably identify who it is.
And audiences don't even need to see their faces.
This hairstyle alone is enough of a cue to invoke a mental representation of a certain character,
and we see Nicolas Cage's face instead. And by the way, to be clear, Cage of Thrones is an equal
opportunity Photoshop endeavor, and no woman, man, or child who has a leading role in this series is
particularly safe. I just happened to pick two characters here that are popular, and there are
plenty more.
And it's perfectly fine to laugh when there is conceptual disfluency,
but the point to remember is that there's a schema violation,
and we do recover from them.
And they can be interesting,
but what happens that I hope that you would focus on
is that there's a shift from automatic processing
to a more controlled type of cognitive processing.
So getting back to games, as an example, oh I'm sorry,
with Mario is that some of you may recall in Mario Odyssey
there was a bit of a slight wardrobe change.
I'm not sure if I can say the word nipple gate,
but I'm saying it.
Chest Goombas was also another reference point for this.
Poor Mario. I mean Mario deserves to have nipples, doesn't he?
He's an iconic character and this look generally had one of two reactions
and players did respond in a certain way that sort of violated their expectancies
of the traditional norm of this franchise.
And attentional blink shifts our thinking.
oftentimes to a more deliberate and systematic type of thinking.
And controlled analytical evaluation oftentimes will require consideration.
we can move from automatic processing to something else.
Now, science also shows us that we can predict human attention.
So it should be no surprise that there
are ways to study knowledge formation through schemas.
And again, it is our schemas that really do wield the power
for us to do this through something
called cognitive mapping.
And these are schemas that players create, often very
quickly, and revolve around their preferences
or perceptions across spatial environments.
They guide and inform player decision making and information processing.
And they can be automatic.
Sometimes they do require a little bit more deliberate or controlled thinking.
And in the case here of Titanfall,
this is a bit of an older image now, but still relevant,
players are using their schemas
to navigate their game spaces
to help them understand streamlined thinking,
where they are, where they need to go,
and what might be in their way.
So for a game like this,
I understand that I can jump or parkour my way
from point A to point B, and through this exact route,
that's how I'm going to get there.
If we wanted to give somebody in this building directions to the movie theater,
you would go down the escalator.
We would invoke route mapping.
You take a left outside the door, you cross the street,
and I'm totally making that up.
I don't know my way around this city at all.
But you get the general idea that we could give somebody directions
through this type of schema processing.
Now, another way that we see players sort of wrestle with information is through a topographical
map maybe in the mind's eye, even abstractly about where they are in terms of distance
and landmarks and territories.
So if I'm at ground zero in the case of this game, Fallout, how far am I from Diamond City?
And players ask themselves these questions internally all the time.
How long will it take me to get there?
And game maps help players to solidify these working schemas
about their environment.
So through survey mapping, sometimes it really is advantageous to,
or even critically necessary, to hand players that topographical map.
Just please be aware that the research is starting to show
that some players have preferences,
and they prefer to learn through route mapping,
while others have a tendency to sort of lean more towards survey mapping
in terms of understanding their environment.
It's a lot like some people are more kinesthetic learners,
some are more audio and visual,
and the data is starting to show that this also seems to be the case
for processing information at the game level
through these types of maps.
Now, in either case, there's a clear benefit to encourage players
to map their environment
and generate strong spatial frameworks around their schemas.
So, in the case of Overwatch, where is the choke point?
Is that going to be the best place to put my team?
How many can fit over there?
Are we too exposed?
Where's the best vantage point?
And cognitive maps really do align with environmental data.
And something like Google Maps, they update regularly
based on player experience, time, and knowledge.
So we are accommodating our schemas
pretty much our entire life.
In games there have been a few examples where player mapping is not really
supported.
This is one reason why something like Mapstalgia
came along and I encourage you all to check out this website. It's fascinating.
This is where players reconstruct mental maps
of games that they played entirely from memory.
And I think some people cheat a little bit here and there, but
the level of detail is pretty impressive
and it also demonstrates the longevity of
these mapping schemas that we have.
And especially when they're tied to strong emotion,
in this case nostalgia,
the ability to draw upon that prior knowledge
is fairly strong and it's also easy.
I particularly encourage you to check out
the Resident Evil map that's in Mapstalgia
because it is absolutely fantastic
and the level of detail is really, really good.
So going back to examples where games sometimes don't support this mapping
procedure. For me personally, when I'm playing Dungeon Master,
it can be a little bit more difficult to do because the player could create a
mapping schema, but it's not really supported there.
The walls all look the same.
The corridors left and right are very similar and mapping schemas can form,
but it's not easy today. We seem a little bit more.
able and willing to help players with their mental map schemas early on.
In fact, now our players expect it, and they expect it to be done well.
And this isn't a terrible idea, but we have to be very careful with our mapping
not to push it too quickly with players. We need to, in the case of route mapping,
give them enough time to get their hands dirty in the environment and explore,
because that's how something like route mapping occurs. And if we just throw them
instant teleportation or the epic ride too early...
that can be potential missed opportunities for them to really sort of get down and dirty
with the game environment and assimilate these schemas about space and ability to travel
and how long of a distance is between point A and point B.
Now, one of the last topics that I just have barely enough time to highlight here in the
interest of time is, again, the predictive utility of schemas for knowledge formation.
So as an example here, I have six chairs.
And this is a concept known as category judgments.
We engage in stimulus recognition when comparing what is known with what we encounter.
And we make these category judgments all the time, all day.
This is one reason why our brains get so tired.
And here is a very simple stimulus with the example of a chair.
So I think just about everyone in this room can agree that there are six chairs on the screen.
This is not some psychological trick. Sometimes my students think that I'm trying to pull one
over on them. But we have a schema for office chair and rocking chair. We also have preferences.
My personal preference is the chair on the bottom row in the middle. I love those chairs.
They're so ergonomic and they're great.
I'm thinking you can probably guess which chair is the favorite of my students,
and I will give you a hint.
It's in the top row and on the far left,
and that is one repeatedly that they enjoy sitting in.
Now, we might be surprised to find that top right,
top left chair in a game like The Stanley Parable.
Well, it's The Stanley Parable, so maybe that's a bad example.
But we have these models for recognition
based on the schemas that we find appropriate for them.
And these category judgments can really
be useful in terms of knowledge prediction.
So again, getting back to games.
One way that these, uh-oh.
Okay, so one way that these manifest is through
what are called template or feature matching schemas.
And in Minecraft, players develop a very efficient
working model or mental rule of thumb
that you need exactly three stone blocks
and two wood sticks.
And with template or feature matching,
typically it's a cookie cutter recipe
that only a certain combination of objects
will get you to sort of the end game here
for what you need to do in the game.
Skyrim is another example of this with the golden clock
where the task for players to complete is based on a template
and the game hints at what will match.
And if there is a match, the content unlocks.
And again, only this combination will do it
or the number or correct order of things.
In games like Riven, a personal favorite of mine, or even Monster Hunter or any game that
sort of throws a wanted poster at players invokes a very specific cognitive schema based on
distinct features and what players will do and we can predict this pretty robustly.
is they will compare the schema in their mind
with what is sort of thrown at them in the game.
Is it a match, yes or no?
And if the answer is no, we can predict
to a fairly strong degree that they will ignore it
or even outright avoid that stimulus.
And these schemas are activated so, so quickly.
It's almost impossible to see.
And we can study it through brain imaging,
but the point is, is that these schemas
really do propel behavior forward.
or backwards.
I don't want to approach that thing.
Or maybe, in fact, I do.
Now, these types of ways that we work
through different environmental stimuli can also
manifest through what are called recognition
by component schemas.
So schemas help us find the basic building blocks
of the things that we encounter in the everyday world.
And I'm all kinds of confident that if I didn't have the reference points on the far left,
that you could sort of disentangle that messy stimulus or stimuli that are listed on the
right.
And the world is messy.
Game environments are messy.
They're challenging.
They're complicated.
And through these schemas, we have the ability to sort of break things down to their base levels
and repair them in our mind's eye.
And it's a little bit more cognitively taxing, but we can do it.
And it is, in fact, quite possible to do so.
So, with that in mind, we are able to, when we encounter things in a game,
see, let's say, for example, these two models here.
And these two objects we can understand through sort of our prior knowledge.
These are the basic building blocks of the Halo Rings.
a train that is not feeling so good in Fallout.
In fact, a good horror game,
and Limbo is a nice example here,
will often take advantage of players' schemas,
especially in this way.
And we don't have to show our entire hand.
And that's the beauty of using these schemas
to really inform game design.
Because a partial cue is enough,
and schemas will fill in the box for us.
They will take over.
And particularly in reference to monsters,
players don't even need to see
the
the entire object in order to understand the danger that's involved, as you see here.
Devs, artists, and designers often allude to this, and they're invoking this type of
recognition by component schema without really knowing what to call it.
And we can do this with sound, we can do this with light, it doesn't have to be a purely
visual stimulus.
We can use these to sort of invoke activation thresholds and imply through a sound cue that
gets stronger.
You're getting very close to the loot crate,
and we don't have to show them the entire thing.
A change in light will sort of guide players one way.
You're nearing the end of the maze,
but you're not quite there yet.
And while schemas are very good
for encouraging certain player behaviors,
they're also very, very efficient
for other things as well, and one of them
is to help them establish characters
or even entire storylines.
So one way that this manifests, excuse me,
is through what are called configural models.
And through these schema models,
As you can see in the case of Assassin's Creed.
As long as the deviation isn't too far, and I'm thinking now of poor Mario again.
The idea of the mental model in the case of Assassin's Creed with this protagonist is
that sort of every game, every new game in the series, there's a little bit of a change,
but it's relatively the same.
There's always the cape and cowl and there's some type of gauntlet and there's usually
boots involved.
So these characters are iconic and we accept that they change over time as the series changes
over time.
But Batman can never have a red cape like Superman,
and neither one of them is really allowed to ever wear overalls.
Unless Superman is back at home in Smallville,
I guess that wouldn't be a total deal breaker.
But when deviations steer us too far
from the established prototype,
players oftentimes will say, no, that's enough.
It's orange juice and chocolate chip cookies.
I'm not gonna do it.
And it is rejected as a concept.
In the case of Elite Dangerous,
clearly what we have here are configural models
that help to communicate to the player
that there are different achievements.
And they still look.
simple enough to the achievement prototype,
but clearly these are different.
And the overall concept is still easily understood
and not too much of a challenge mentally.
A more complicated example is what you see here
with Overwatch and other games as well.
These configurable models may need
a little bit more explanation.
But at the end of the day, the achievement schema model
that players have assimilated,
it still sort of is with them in their backpack.
And it maintains fairly good consistency over time
as the achievements increase.
The design changes a little bit, but players are still able
to accommodate these changes and really sort of go with it.
Again, in the interest of time,
there's a lot of other things that I could say,
but I sort of need to wrap this up here.
I hope that I've been able to share just a few ideas
about how schemas do manifest themselves in games,
and I'm gonna leave you with a few key points here.
One is that schemas are very, very important
to help us understand what it is that players are doing
and predict.
how they are going to work with the information that we throw at them.
Onboarding, attentional focus, this is obviously a huge domain to explore,
but I hope that you would consider them from the perception of schemas,
because schemas really do play a very important role,
and it is okay to violate those schemas.
In fact, it's pretty fun to do it and twist players' expectations and again, I'm thinking
of the Stanley Parable, it's just on my mind today, but we have to be very careful with
this because what can happen is an over-reliance on different types of thinking and they are
more systemic, deliberate, and more controlled types.
of thinking. Sometimes we want players to be on autopilot because that's a really fun
way to throw a wrench in their plans. And if we are violating their schemas too often
or too hard, that can really cause a problem. A flow is an automatic cognitive process and
schemas are very much within that realm of flow and help players to achieve flow.
There's a few golden rules with flow
that some of you may know.
We need clear and immediate feedback,
minimal distractions and so on.
But in terms of schemas, I'll just present
sort of one final point here.
If you want to virtually guarantee
the absence of flow in your game,
it's really easy to do.
All you need to do is place your players
under heavy cognitive load,
because what happens is that is demanding
that the player activate schemas
to sort of keep up and change and accommodate.
And the point that schemas help players the most
is when they are trying to reduce cognitive load.
And if we invoke them too hard,
the task becomes too difficult.
And we want players to be boosted in their ability
to sort of work with new content.
Too much stop and think will also get
in the way of that process.
And automatic schema activation
is absolutely one of the keys to flow.
Experience also seems to matter, and we can think about chess,
where controlled thinking and strategy is super important.
And sometimes players have to work at that level,
but as they become good, it becomes an automatic process.
But at the end of the day, loss of immersion
does happen when players stop, and they
have to ask themselves, what am I doing, and where am I going?
And controlled cognitive processing is not bad,
but when we are interrupted, when there is uncertainty,
when we don't know what's going on,
there's a change of shifting from controlled,
sorry, from automatic to more controlled types of thinking.
Controlled thinking is not bad,
it just is not the optimal condition
in which to invoke flow.
So I hope this talk has been informative.
I am really glad to see psychology
manifesting its way into games and games design.
kind of a bigger level. I think this summit is fantastic and if you aren't
on board with psychology it's fun and it's not scary and you should join us.
We have cookies. We probably don't have orange juice but there's plenty of
things that we can still explore. So I think we have just a few minutes if
there are any questions I'm happy to address those. We're going to get kicked
out in a minute or two. If there are no questions, thank you.
Yeah, first of all, that was an amazing talk.
Second of all,
something popped into my head when you were talking about route mapping versus survey mapping.
I wonder what your thoughts were on how The Legend of Zelda Breath of the Wild treats its map,
because it seems like there's a lot of both route mapping and survey mapping in that.
Yes.
And it does let you play around a little bit and get your hands dirty?
There are a lot of things to say about that particular game.
One is that it is an example that attempts to sort of hit
the mark for, I'll just say, both player types that tend to
really enjoy route mapping and then others that prefer
survey mapping.
And they're kind of throwing everything in the kitchen sink
at the player and letting the player decide, which I think
is fantastic.
I don't know how effortful that thought process was in
designing that concept, but it seems to be working.
But for some players, it doesn't.
really work at all. So, I say this to my students all the time, how on earth do I make a game that's going to make everybody happy?
And they seem to be hitting the mark enough and it seems to be working enough.
I look forward to the day when we
think of the different schema preferences
from the prototype stage, from the first stage. That partially answers your question.
Thanks.
And I'm happy to talk after, by the way.
Speaking of schema subversions like in Stanley Parable,
are you aware of any sort of research or work being done into seeing how games can work to help people challenge or rethink the schema that they have outside of the time that they play games?
You know, the schema about the world or themselves or society?
Beyond the game environment pro social gaming right there are a lot of pro social games right now being
Created and pro social research utilizing games. I don't think we're quite there yet, but we're getting very very close and
if you would like to become a cognitive psychologist and help us with this endeavor that would be fantastic because
These are the questions that are now being started to kind of revolve around the community and I certainly don't claim to know all of the research but
The pro-social side of gaming seems to be very high level right now, which is great
And you're talking about something that is distilled down
We will get there. We're just not quite there yet
Hi
When you create are creating a new system and say you find that it's sufficiently distant from existing mental schemas that it causes a lot
Of this dissonance and all these problems
Do you generally find assuming you can't stack it directly on top of those schemas?
that's better to get close and have those exceptions be a little bit outside the norm or to go a little further out and
Have the person have to create new models for that entire thing. That's a wonderful question
Dark souls comes to mind just off the top of my head. You're dead. You're dead. You're dead. You're dead. You're dead
Some people responded very well to that, others needed a bit more time to adjust.
Sure, Stanley Parable, we've completely violated expectancies. I think the important follow-up to
that is how we design after the fact, because sometimes we just go for the punch of,
this is totally not what you expected, and then what?
I think that's an important consideration to take into account.
I love a good schema violation.
It's better to maybe start a little bit smaller, but sometimes devs will come out swinging
and it can kind of go one of two ways.
Know your audience is important and good UX research will also help you get there, I will
say.
Excellent question.
Thank you.
Hi.
I'm too short.
So I'm worried that this is too similar to the last question,
but I was wondering, is there a way
to overwrite existing schemas without causing schema
discomfort or at least a minimum amount of schema discomfort?
And if so, how would you go about that?
I would like to think that hopefully I converted one or two people in this audience that psychology
is really cool and applies to games, so if I've won even one person over, I'm happy.
That's a fairly easy example.
To follow up on your question, reinforcement is really valuable, because if the player
is encouraged to think a different way, it's a little bit harder for us cognitively to
do it.
It places a little more cognitive load on us, but if the rewards are there.
and I don't mean a carrot on a stick,
it could be an intrinsic motivator,
it could be group-based,
that's a really efficient way to sort of encourage players
to keep a more open mind.
And that's a very large question,
but reinforcers come to mind
as kind of a big helping hand with that.
Thank you.
It's a great question.
Yeah.
So, first of all, thank you.
And I have two questions, which I think will have the same answer.
But one is, that was a lot of information really fast, and my hand hurts from trying
to take notes.
So, where can we go to learn more?
And also, I'm a consultant for companies that don't usually think about games, and so part
of what we do is go out and try and find...
evidence that we can use to back up our designs from ethnographic research to
other examples in the industry and so this is why they might have the same
answers. What would you recommend looking at to help justify using some
of these ideas?
Well, I do know or I would hope that because this is being recorded,
this talk should be made available in the vault,
that would be my hope.
The slides will also be made available as well.
If anybody can't wait,
I'm happy to e-mail you the PowerPoint slides at any point.
So that's certainly an option as well.
The second part of your question was?
Well, actually, you just answered that as well.
But the first part was actually where can we go to learn more,
like dig more into this?
Oh, well.
UX is gathering momentum, UI, research, psychology,
sort of these two fields are colliding, which is great.
We have the traditional academics who study schemas
that are just now starting to sort of transition
into applying this more to games.
So you're a little bit, we collectively are a little bit
ahead of the curve here, which is fantastic.
But in terms of a book, I will direct you
to Celia Hoden's wonderful book on.
Supposing we've already ordered.
That is a very, very good resource.
We need a million more books like it.
One just on schemas would be a very large volume.
So the research is getting there.
The academics are coming.
But right now, a good Google search
is probably your best bet.
Always feel free to email me.
I'm happy to give specific resources for more
specific types of questions.
And I can wade through that research.
I do that a lot for people who get in touch with me.
Thank you.
All right, I think we're going to get kicked out of here.
So feel free to come talk to me.
And thank you for coming.