Hey everybody, if you could turn off your cell phones
and make sure to fill out the forms afterwards,
that'd be great.
Everybody loving that ordering on the word order?
Does it bother anybody?
Yeah, that's kind of awful.
Right, cool.
All right, so my name's Nathan Fouts.
I'm from Mommy's Best Games,
and we're going to set this game in order.
So we're gonna look at ways to organize levels
and lots of mechanics,
and what can happen when you have a game
that's got a lot of stuff to keep track of,
and what you should be doing to manage all that.
But before we get into that,
We're gonna talk about some basics of difficulty curves,
level design mindsets and ways to think about level design,
and some examples of games with lots of mechanics,
and then some possible solutions.
So back in 2007, after working in AAA for a few years there,
I ended up going independent with Mommy's Best Games,
and we made a lot of shoot-'em-ups over the years there.
And we made Shoot 1 Up and that got us recognized
by Devolver Digital and we got to make a Serious Sam game
for them in 2D called Serious Sam Double D XXL.
And I created the idea of the gun stacker.
You do the same, gets to stack his guns
one on top of the other to shoot the bad guys.
That game had 40 weapons and over 20 levels
and it was already starting to get to be a big mess.
I love to use this promotional art,
I never get to use it, so it's silly.
There's a teacup stacker, I don't know.
So.
In 2013, I began working on what would be our biggest game yet called Pig Eat Ball.
It is a classically styled kind of arcade adventure game.
It has hundreds of levels, lots of bosses, a story.
It's non-procedural, all handmade.
And it had a whole bunch of stuff to keep track of.
And it's like 6 to 10 hours long.
So there's a lot of stuff going on.
So I was trying to figure out how are we going to keep track of all the mechanics,
how do I know what everything is in the game, how am I going to balance my difficulty curve there.
So in any game, this is a 2D game but it still applies to bigger 3D games,
how do you keep track of if someone changes a mechanic in the game,
changes one of the enemy types, if they add a new one and you want to insert it into the middle of your game.
you shouldn't be testing a 10 hour game
every time something changes, right?
So you should know where those enemies show up in the game.
So that's the kind of problems I wanted to get into
and I talked to other designers about solutions
over their years.
So before we get into all that,
we're gonna talk about some level design mindsets
and difficulty curves.
So if you wanted to plot out your difficulty curve,
you'd probably start with something where
the game gets harder when the player gets
further into the game.
and get a nice upward slope like that.
And if you're a masochist, maybe you're gonna make a game
get immediately hard and then stay just super hard
the whole time, like Super Meat Boy or something like that.
I like this idea of, I call it the heartbeat curve.
So it's a gentle slope, but it has periodic spikes
and dips in it.
We'll zoom in here on that.
And the idea is you start out with and introduce a mechanic and it's a super easy to play level.
The player can't really fail, they just get used to the idea.
Then you start to twist the mechanic and add little changes to it and slightly challenge
the player further along in the levels.
And then finally, there's a big spike in the difficulty.
It's not terrible, but it's there.
And the player gets a rush, and then they accomplish,
and they beat the mid-boss or the boss,
and it's a big spike there, and it feels good.
And then you start over, but it dips way down.
So the difference is really sharp,
and the player gets a big, full relief feeling,
and they feel like they really accomplished something cool.
And then you introduce a new mechanic,
and the whole process starts over there.
So that's my heartbeat curve. There's also a really good talk on the GDC Vault for free
about the game called Jelly Splash. They have a whole different take on the difficulty curve.
It's a mobile game. It's really popular. It's probably designed to teach you how to
just vacuum cash out of players' wallets. You should go look at it. It's really smart.
So when you're thinking about difficulty curves,
there's the concepts of puzzle difficulty
and skill difficulty.
So puzzle difficulty is the idea of how hard is it
for a player to figure out what to do,
and the skill difficulty is how hard is it
for them to execute it with their hands in the controls.
You could actually probably plot both these two
on two different types of difficulty curves for your game.
So now we're gonna shift into design mindsets.
Just some overviews of different ways
to think about level design.
So that's Bioshock there, of course,
and this is an idea of environmental storytelling.
It's kind of the idea of the player asking,
what happened here?
And then thinking of what happened there,
and there's a really good talk on the vault
called What Happened Here?
It's from 2010, you should check it out, it's excellent.
Another cool game that's really big with environmental storytelling was Hyper Light Drifter.
It's just the idea of the player looking and them telling the story without being explicitly told what the story is.
So kind of related to that, I like to think is set piece design with the Call of Duty series and others.
You kind of take like a basic gameplay, simple shooting guys and maybe not a lot of enemy types,
but you really dress it up with these huge environmental set pieces.
The Golden Gate Bridge and America Explodes, that kind of thing.
And it really adds a lot of flavor to what would be kind of normal kind of gameplay.
So another type is what I like to call transcendent level design.
I really like shoot-em-ups and bullet hells, there's like these curtains of bullets and
I talked to a player, he had a really good quote, he said, bullet hells are like that
moment when apparent chaos becomes perfect order in your mind.
It's just a different way of thinking and related to that is racing games.
You can even like Rez or Thumper or the Wipeout series.
And one of the games in the Wipeout series, Wipeout Fusion,
even had a mode called the Zone Mode,
where you have to loop the levels as long as you can,
getting faster and faster.
It's just a different way of kind of building your levels.
And the final design type is mechanics-driven or modular,
which is the one I'm gonna focus on today.
So that's Super Mario Galaxy there.
I mean, look at that.
There's just like so much going on, right?
You can interact with all of it.
There's the lily pad, the water,
the Bumblebee power-up, the 1-Up.
You're probably thinking about hopping on that flower
in the background, the purple thing, right?
It's all really cool stuff.
And there's a lot of games like that.
Super Monkey Ball has some cool,
a whole bunch of puzzles like that.
The Rayman series, the new stuff.
There's like those little fireflies to grab,
the lily pads to hop on.
Everything's interactable and it's really interesting.
So on my own game there, this is our upcoming game,
Piggy Ball, if you look there's bowling pins,
conveyor belts, cue sticks, there's a lot of stuff
going on, it looks really busy, but the player
gets introduced to these slowly, and this sort of game
just lends itself to lots of levels and lots of mechanics.
Because you want to introduce all these mechanics nicely.
Here's Marble Saga Kororinpa.
I mean look, there's scissors in the background,
they get a level, right, there's that diamond,
there's pinball bumpers.
Here's Ape Escape 2, there's that cool silver slope
your eye's drawn to, then there's little gold pickups,
crates, the apes, they all get their levels
and they all get slowly introduced in these huge games.
So I'm talking about introductions and not tutorials.
Tutorials sound awful, right?
You put that at the beginning of the game
and everybody hates it.
Hopefully you guys don't even have to do that.
You should be able to introduce mechanics slowly
and flesh out the mechanic
and give it its own nice little area
in the bigger level or its own little level.
This is Super Mario Galaxy 2.
This is the Flezzard level.
It's actually, it's far into the game. It's World 2, Area 2. It's a whole little mini-game of tilting the controller.
It just makes the game feel so much more polished if you give your mechanics some room to breathe
between all the other stuff you've got going on. Just do a nice introduction.
Ape Escape 2 is another favorite of mine.
Here's the super hoop mechanic.
So you spin the right thumb stick really fast,
and you can actually run up those sharp slopes.
So that silver slope on the other screenshot,
this whole level is the level
they introduced the super hoop mechanic in.
It's all this Spanish tile.
And so now it's a nice area to play in,
the whole level's built around it,
but from then, that point on,
anytime you see those slopes, you know what to do.
You're like, okay, great, I got this super hoop mechanic,
I'm gonna use it.
Which brings me back around to our own game,
that piggy ball that we're working on.
So the gameplay mechanic starts with,
what if Pac-Man could get fatter while you ate?
then it ends up kind of turning all the levels
into a bit of a puzzle.
I had to do an actual Pac-Man homage, of course,
but in this game you can barf on the ghosts
and eat their skin off.
It's cute gross, right?
It's not terrible.
Okay, so we start with that,
and you actually, so you still have to eat
all the balls in the level,
but now you can get stuck in the maze,
and there's a lot of barf in some parts,
but then we expand to that.
So I'm gonna walk you through a couple
of the cool mechanics we introduce in there.
So in World 2, there's an idea of the polarity cats,
and they are like lucky cats,
but there's a gold one and a black one.
If you break the gold one, you just smash it apart
and you can pass through that spot.
If you break the black one, it explodes and hurts you.
So we give the player a nice little level
to play around with.
The damage in this level doesn't affect the end goal,
so they're free to goof off with it.
And if you notice, what happens is
when you break any of the cats, they flip polarity.
Gold goes to black and vice versa.
We do that because then later on, of course,
we wanna introduce, we wanna get into
more interesting levels.
So this is like a looping level where they're on a track
and the cats are blocking off these balls
that you have to eat.
As you pass it around and you keep eating balls,
you're getting bigger and bigger and at some point,
you're gonna run into a spot that you might've screwed up
and caused a black cat to be in your way.
So that's more of like a puzzly level.
But again, we introduced it nicely before
so the player could get their mind around that.
In the game, there's these silly little creatures,
the pill bugs, and they cause you all kinds of grief.
There's all kinds of different types of them.
This is a glutton pill bug, and he loves to eat.
So, we basically make sure that you start out with a level you're sure to be able to beat,
even though it's strange and confusing.
You perturb the balls, they hit the conveyor belts, and the Glutton Bug gobbles them up.
Turns out he turns into a giant bowling ball, of sorts.
You know what the bowling ball is at this point in the game, but you've never seen him before.
But you know you can't get through bowling pins without something.
And there you go, you're able to solve it.
Later on, we get into really big, complicated levels,
but you know what all these mechanics are
as a player at this point.
The player's in the middle, the glutton bug's on the right,
and then we've got super crates on the left,
which you have to be fat enough to break.
There's spike walls, there's bowling pins,
there's jelly blocks, there's barf goblins.
All that makes sense once you play the game.
So you're trying to get into the glutton bug there,
but you can't reach him yet.
You're eating the jelly blocks and you're going really fast
and you make it to, oh, the barf goblins.
I can barf on those.
They love it, don't worry, it's fine, they love that.
So and then they fly away and you can get into
where they were blocking off some balls
and then you get bigger and you get into more
and more sections and the player can kind of like
red paper clip their way through the levels.
So all this is possible because of the level editor
in the game, which we do ship with the game.
I loved the Mario Maker, I thought it was great.
I thought it had a few little UI problems,
which I tried to address,
but we tried to make our level editor super nice.
There's our object palette, it's very inviting.
And basically, you're able to real easily
play around with, goof off,
with all these weird new mechanics we got in the game.
You can share your own levels with friends,
you can share them with the world,
daily feature levels, all that kind of cool stuff.
There's beer, I'm sure we'll have to rate that
or somehow for kids,
but there's consequences when you drink the beer,
so hopefully it'll be okay.
So we're gonna talk about how methods we've looked at
to organize all this stuff in the game.
Before we get to that though, let's assume together
that better tools are gonna help you make better games.
I'm sure somebody can make a house
without a hammer and a saw, but it wouldn't be great.
It'd be better with tools.
The same thing here, you're probably using Unity
or Unreal or something like that to help you along,
but consider that you might even wanna write
some own custom tools for your game,
even if you're a small studio.
So, one of the easiest thing we can all use is paper, right?
The cool part about paper is it's 2D.
So if you're making a 2D and you can rearrange things
and really easily balance things, that's great.
But it's hard to share, you can't share it
over the internet, it's not computer searchable,
it's not ideal, but I'm sure we've all started there.
I talked to Radu Marison.
He's working on an upcoming puzzle game called Simispheres,
and he used paper to balance his game.
He actually printed screenshots on his business cards
and were able to lay them out
and rearrange his levels that way.
The problem, of course, is when he adds new levels,
he's gotta reprint his cards again to keep going.
So he ended up digitizing that.
in a program that's free that you guys could use
called Inkscape, and he's got all his little slides
and levels there that he can rearrange now
and look for a better difficulty curve.
I like to know what's in my levels
because we've got so many levels going on,
I wanna see what's going on.
So early on I tried using Windows Search,
like that folder search function that we all have access to,
and it actually works.
It's not the best thing, but the way you gotta do it
basically is have a level format that's text-based,
You have objects that have a word that you can search on,
and then you just tell this index to build.
You have to rebuild the index on that folder.
It does work, but it can take hours
to really rebuild all that kind of stuff.
So then if you change levels,
you have to rebuild the index again.
So it's not ideal, but it's there and it's free
if you have Windows.
Now something I hope everyone's using,
if you have any number of things to keep track of at all,
is some sort of online docs or sheets method.
Of course, there's Google Docs and Google Sheets.
They're really powerful and really useful.
This is a screenshot of our,
just a little clip of our world
where we keep track of the world,
the level file names, the level titles,
the goals, and the meddling times
on getting gold and silver.
The problem with Google Docs is that you've got to update it.
And I don't know about you, but I get a little lazy.
And then I have another designer that lives in a
different state, and he's supposed to see what I'm doing
and vice versa.
He doesn't always update it.
It's critical.
You should still use this, but it has some problems in terms
of use.
So I talked to another designer,
I think he's here at the show, Austin Borden, at RareSoft.
They're making a big puzzle game on mobile
called King Rabbit.
It has 512 levels, and they use it to see
what kind of mechanics they're introducing for each world.
Real simple, real nice, but it definitely helps them out.
Now.
Unity Analytics, you probably are using something like that.
I talked to a different designer,
and he is using his own custom system for analytics
that sounds intimidating, but it's not that bad.
Stuart Denman is working on a new puzzle game
called Tiny Bubbles, where you were able to pop
the little bubbles to create this chain reaction
to solve the puzzle.
He still stores his analytics like most of us,
but instead of a funnel, which is kind of junk
in terms of seeing what's going on,
he plots his own map.
And he stores the number of times somebody quits the level,
and the number of times they had to replay it to beat it.
Look at that gorgeousness, take it in.
You can see exactly what's going on in his game.
The red are problems, or are they?
Take control of your difficulty curves.
Maybe he wants those spikes there,
but he knows that they're there now.
It's really cool to see.
Stewart's at the show as well.
His game's coming out in a little bit,
you should check it out there.
Now an older game, I talked to the guys that did
Where's My Water with Tim FitzRandolph,
and they used paper way back then,
but it served them pretty well.
They would print out screenshots
of the Where's My Water puzzles
and rearrange them as they needed to balance.
But they also did this really cool solution
where they had multiple designers working on hardware
on iPhones and iPads.
And the devices could look at a shared Dropbox folder
and they could hot change little level fixes
without going through the entire build process,
which is kind of a pain in the butt for mobile.
And multiple designers could work off of all this together.
That's something to think about.
He said it was a little janky, but it worked.
In our own game, Piggyball, we do have the level editor,
and we've now got an in-level editor searchability
for all the objects and mechanics we have in the game.
And you could search for that glutton pill bug now,
and it filters all the levels that contain that one object.
And then you could also filter by world,
by goal type, or anything like that.
So here's another one where you could actually filter
and combine the filters together to even see more
of where the levels line up together.
So I'm working with John Meister from Super Soul.
He's in Kentucky and I'm at Mommy's Best in Indiana.
And we're working together on the game
and he's the one that implemented a lot of these
cool features that I requested.
The other thing he changed was
we now have Google Sheets Export.
So the whole problem about being lazy about not updating your level data is now gone
because we get fresh level data as we build the levels.
And what's cool is you don't have to be in the game to see this.
Anyone can just get in on the team, can get on the Google Docs
and just check out and see what's in the levels.
and you can even look at this heat map
of objects in the levels.
The way they built that was through,
as the levels are loaded,
they would count up all the objects in the level
and the level data and then store it out to an XML
and then parse that.
It really wasn't that bad
and John Meister's here at the show as well.
I talked to another designer, Ian Stalker,
of the Escape Goat series.
He had this really cool grid arrangement tool.
His level where the players play through the game
to find levels, this is a little sketch,
it was a 2D grid as the player made their way
through the game.
So he made this extra little tool, it wasn't terrible,
where there's the live part kind of in the middle
and he could drag and drop levels into there
and rearrange that based on playtest feedback
to get a better feel for how players were having problems
or drop levels that weren't working.
But he had control over that really easily
rather than just having it hard-coded in or something.
I talked to another team, this little indie team,
making this game called Candy Crush Saga.
Jeremy King from King, he gave a talk a couple years ago
on how Candy Crush Saga was built.
And there's some really good nuggets
of information inside there.
They have an internal tool called the level library.
And they store the screenshots, the designer,
and the difficulty rated by the other designers
of that level.
And they can rearrange the levels as well.
But it gives them a little leg up
on what they think it's gonna be like
for players at the end.
They also use Google Docs.
They have a beat chart for where they're deciding
to introduce new mechanics there.
I'm not sure if Jamie's at the show there,
but he's a really nice guy and you can contact him
for any questions as well based on his talk there.
But I thought it was neat that even they
use this kind of thing.
Catherine Neal gave a really cool talk
called For When Spreadsheets and Flowcharts Aren't Enough.
It's actually talk about tools for game design,
not really production, but it was really interesting.
Well, and that's another one that's free on the vault.
You're probably asking like,
oh gosh, does my game even need this?
Well, I like to think of if you have more mechanics
or levels that you can count on two hands
and you've got at least two people on your team
in different areas, you should be keeping track of it
somehow, not scribble down on a piece of paper
so that everybody can be on the same page.
So we talked about the level design mindsets,
the difficulty curves and the heartbeat idea,
and about making custom tools themselves.
And right now, you could be using spreadsheets,
you could use Inkscape, I didn't talk about Trello,
but I'm sure a lot of you know about it,
but you could be using that to keep track of things
and it's nice to rearrange.
There's paper, there's even Windows Search.
But hopefully you guys are gonna think about
the idea of doing some custom tools for yourself,
even on your smaller teams and how it could help you out.
I'm Nathan Fouts from Mommy's Best Games. That little URL there in the middle links to all
the information in the talk site I covered. And Piggyball is on Fig. It's like Kickstarter, but
only for games. If you guys could back it, I'd be eternally grateful. And thank you.
And afterwards, all the level designers
are gonna go over to the Marquis in the lobby
and hang out for a little while if you wanna chat and talk.
And if anybody has a question, can do a question.
Yes.
Hello, so I was wondering if you could talk about
any mishaps that you had happen
with your mechanics and levels
before you had your organization methods set,
like any problems that came from not having these tools yet.
Right, yeah, so for any problems,
what did all these tools solve?
We've been working on Piggyball for five years.
It's a big action puzzle game.
I lost track of mechanics.
There was gameplay objects that I forgot
that I didn't even have or didn't even use,
and I found them.
That's a ridiculous example, but it's true.
The big thing you should be able to get out of this
is difficulty balancing.
Like I said, take control of your difficulty curve.
So that should help.
Hi, good talk by the way.
Thanks.
I'm a student right now for game design
and I was curious if you're just using
all these different methods for building your whole design
or are you actually making like say
a full game design document for your games
and then using these as add-on additions?
My method is ad hoc and so I do start with the game design
but then I get a lot of ideas from iteration with tools.
And I always say, you're gonna make an interesting game
out of different tools.
So whatever custom tools you'll have,
you'll end up with something different.
So for the media, they go together.
Like I can't imagine planning something and sticking to it.
100% all the way to the end, that sounds incredible.
So that's what I got, man.
It's a mixture.
Okay, thank you. Thanks.
Yeah, thanks for the talk, that was really interesting.
My question is, with so many different game mechanics,
and introducing those and the interactions between them,
when you're adding new mechanics and all the possibilities,
how do you explore those, the different possibilities,
and if new people join the team,
how do you convey them efficiently to the new members?
How do we introduce how do we decide what new mechanics are what and where they go?
Well first of all everybody that should joins a team that's on the production side should be playing the game
So that that should get them into something and then um
Where the new mechanics go it like it comes down to?
What kind of physical work the player is going to have to do like to understand that new mechanic?
So it's like breaking a thing like those polarity cats.
They're in world two because all you gotta do
is just break a thing.
And then your mind has to understand what they do.
But like that glutton bug, you have to feed it
and then think of where it goes and then take it there.
So I would say it's combined with that,
balancing your puzzle and skill difficulty.
For those two who are kind of magnified suddenly,
I think that mechanic should go further into the game
for what you're expecting out of the player.
Thank you.
Yep, thanks.
Cool, thanks guys.