Okay, I think we can start.
So, thank you very much for coming over.
Hello, everyone.
It is our real honor to be here
and talking with you about music of The Witcher 3.
So, who are we?
We have very complicated names.
Yeah, so my name is Marcin Przybyłowicz.
I'll try not to pronounce my name,
because that may be really difficult for you.
So let's just agree that I'm Marcin, not Marcin.
Marcin like marching, so that's easy to remember.
I'm music director and composer at CD Projekt RED.
I'm working on the Witcher series for over five years now.
Before that, I scored a number of mobile and indie games.
and this is Mikolaj.
Yes, I'm Mikolaj Strzelewski.
I go by Mik if it's easier, and if you have a problem
pronouncing my family name,
it basically sounds like strong whiskey.
So, yeah, I'm a freelance, as you see.
I have to read this.
I'm a freelance video game composer, and before The Witcher 3, I worked on the game that you
heard, The Vanishing of Ethan Carter, and I wrote a lot of TV before that, and the project
that was pivotal for me to move to video games was a trailer for Dark Souls 2.
So we want to show you our creative process behind composing and producing The Witcher 3 Wild Hunt soundtrack.
We want to analyze and show why it gained so much attention among critics and players,
and treat that as kind of post-mortem to our work.
And to tell you more about The Witcher, we would like to tell you more about where it
came from, about the franchise lineage and how it all affected our work.
It all started with, yeah, with The Witcher book hero in...
The first story was written in 1988 by a very prolific Polish fantasy writer, Andrzej Sapkowski.
In 1988 he wrote a story, which was then followed by two short volumes of stories and then a couple more books.
Just to remind you, witchers are professional monster slayers,
witchers are mutants with superhuman abilities,
and the most important one, most famous one, is Geralt.
Now, after the books, people in Poland decided to film,
to make a movie about The Witcher,
and I hope you will never see it,
because it's a terrible one, disastrous, I've heard.
I chose not to see it, and you should do the same,
in order not to spoil the view you have on Geralt.
But I heard, Marcin, sorry?
Yeah, I have this privilege, I would say, to see this movie actually.
We bought the tickets for cinematic premiere one time and the saddest part of that story is that right before screening of the movie they showed us trailer to Lords of the Rings.
Fellowship of the Ring and so basically we did watch kick-ass three minutes long trailer of awesome stuff
And then we were presented with almost two hours long movie with Robert Dragons
So you can imagine how sad we were after that
Actually the subtitle of this of this movie was The Witcher and Robert Dragon
So, after that, TV series, really?
I didn't know about TV series because I was already in America, but if it was one, then
it just shows that Polish people don't give up.
They fight even if they know they'll die.
But luckily they fought and the Witcher, the first video game, came to the surface in 2007.
Then there was 2011, which I believe Marcin had already his musical contribution in.
Yes, exactly.
And finally, happy year of 2015.
where The Witcher 3 Wild Hunt came about,
which we are here to talk about.
Now, as you see, The Witcher has already been present
in film, TV, books, comics.
and video games.
And the fan base of Witcher had already certain expectations
about what the soundtracks should sound like.
And we had to meet them.
We had to choose whether we're going to go the easy route
with generic music, which could have been done.
But we chose not to.
We chose to go a challenging route to take risks.
And it paid off.
In our case was similar to this of Batman, Superman, or other heroes that already existed in other media.
And we needed to decide what we're going to do with the music because of that.
So what did we do?
We decided to redefine musical style for The Witcher 3.
The following points that you see in the picture all affected our soundtrack.
The Witcher universe is heavily grounded in Slavic folklore.
Yes, a lot of characters, a lot of stories and substories
present in the game are directly taken from legends,
from that region.
It's a fantasy game, so that's, which is naturally,
which is a genre directly connected
to specific kind of music as well.
Games main feature, the long engaging story with its sub-stories as well, that also had
to be reflected in our soundtrack.
Nothing is good or bad in the game as well, even if something evil happens, even if there's
an evil character, there always seems to be some sort of justification of his or her actions
and therefore everything is kept in a grey zone.
Again, another element that had to be kept in mind while doing the music.
There is a lot of choices and a lot of consequences
that players are exposed to.
And there is the element of non-linearity.
Sorry, difficult word for me.
Which is connected with the fact that it's an open world.
You know, players can go wherever they want.
But everything had to be done under the linear.
music, under the umbrella of film-like music, which help tell the story.
We're going to continue on that later on.
And now Marcin will tell you more about the pre-production process.
Yeah, so once we know what we are up with, we are ready to actually start working on the game itself.
So first stage of production is obviously pre-production.
We had to figure out how to deal with issues and challenges that were ahead of us.
The most important thing was to do as much preparations as possible to basically save time,
and so production phase would be as easy as possible.
Obviously, not every time happens that a lot of planning translates to complete success
and something didn't work out quite good along the way.
We're going to address that issue also.
But basically all those sets of those words you can see here on the slide
basically can give you some impression of what we aimed for with planning our soundtrack.
So first of all we decided to mix Slavic folk with big contemporary sound.
Normally in fantasy games people expect big, broad orchestral sounds with choirs, percussion, strings, and so on.
Because the Witcher franchise is so heavily grounded in Slavic folklore, Slavic mythology,
that was kind of obvious for us we would have to also reflect that somehow in music.
So, Slavic folk.
Then, that was when we started working on Witcher 3, that was...
really important moment for us regarding technical stuff because we were just
finished with the Witcher 2. We decided to leave FMOD, Game Audio Middleware, to Wwise,
so that opened up quite new possibilities for us regarding how we would deal with game audio
systems and stuff like that. And that also goes to another thing that Miko already
talked about briefly. So our main
focus on soundtrack was to make music feel like it was composed for every single player separately.
So we wanted to achieve that effect that when someone plays the game,
he or she can feel that music was, you know, tailored just for him.
One thing to, one way to achieve that was to make sure that music would feel like basically a film, like a long story.
So linear in non-linear environment.
We need to remember that we're not only dealing with a video game, but that particular one was a very complex one.
That was open world RPG with nonlinear story, which
was branching on multiple levels.
So music system had to also address those issues
and handle the music itself in a way
that basically that could be done.
Another thing is obviously budgets and costs
of live recordings.
We knew we had a very big game ahead of us to score.
And doing this with the live orchestra
would cost tons of money.
And we knew we wouldn't probably get as much budget as we wanted to, so we had to think how to be clever about that,
and how to basically do what we aimed for, but, you know, make it cost less, right?
So, if the game was big...
amount of music was big.
Another question pops in, how to not kill ourselves
with that big amount of music?
So again, we would have to come up
with some clever approach to composition process,
then implementation, production phase, and so on.
One of the ways we decided to do that
was to have a greater use of leitmotifs
compared to our previous games.
And the next slide briefly shows you how much of those thematic work we actually did throughout the whole game.
Obviously, we have our main theme along with two other themes that are from previous games.
These are our legacy themes.
And apart from that, you can see we
have a bunch of specially composed custom made themes
just for The Witcher 3.
Those themes obviously served as a bridge
and help the vast amounts of music sound cohesive,
because that was one of the exactly challenges
and one of the most important things we wanted to maintain.
So OK, we know what we're going to do.
Now we have to answer the question,
how are we going to do it?
Since we are about to do some Slavic folk music,
we need to think, OK, how are we going to approach that?
We had a really big database of folk music from Poland, Ukraine, Hungary, Germany, Slovakia, Russia, you name it.
At some point, it struck us, actually, that maybe we shouldn't just treat it as a point of reference.
Maybe we should...
you know, reach out for some bands, some performers maybe,
and get in touch with them.
Invite them to cooperation, not to work for us,
but work with us and try to work on something
completely new and original.
Our choice was the band Percival,
and I'm sure most of you are already familiar with them.
Of course, other great musicians as well.
We're going to introduce them later on.
And...
about those things that didn't work out very well.
I need to admit that the beginning of our work
was quite difficult because it turned out that.
We didn't get along, actually, at the very beginning.
Why is that?
I'm a trained musician, trained composer, just like Mikołaj.
And it so happened that we were about to deal with people
who are self-taught.
What does it mean?
That means they do not know how to read musical notation.
That means they taught themselves
how to play instruments.
their playing techniques would be much different than, for example, playing techniques I was learning when I was at musical academy.
That meant also that they quite didn't understand what I was talking to them because I was using musical terminology.
To be honest, the first day of the recording session,
we were basically wasting money, burning money,
because time flies.
Time is money, and we didn't get any stuff recorded.
We just struggled.
We tried.
We discussed.
And one thing I discovered, they weren't even
able to record to click track, which
is pretty standard procedure when
you go to a recording studio and you are about to do music.
So at some point, we realized we have
to.
figure out a way to basically communicate with each other,
to find some common ground,
some common line of communication,
and follow that line.
So...
At some point I decided to just ditch this whole stuff I prepared, and I was prepared very, very well.
I presented them sheet music, mocaps, spreadsheets with themes written down, broken down to tempos, time signatures, key signatures.
I was really, really well prepared, and believe me, I wasted so much time on that to basically not suck during the process.
That all went to trash, and we had to figure out what to do.
So we thought, OK, so maybe.
If we cannot communicate with each other on language level,
maybe we can communicate on musical level.
So instead of just doing recording sessions,
maybe we should organize a jam session.
Let's improvise a bit.
So pick that instrument.
Pick that instrument.
Just play me four chords.
Just play me some riff on top of that.
Maybe we could try improvising some vocals on it.
And suddenly, magic happened.
they started to play and they started to play with the way I wanted them to play.
They started to be happy about it. I started to be happy about it because, you know, we were progressing.
I could say the rest is history because we end up having the quickest material after
what 7 or 8 days of recordings and that was 12 hours a day so you know pretty long time
and then we were able to actually take away this material, go to our studio, edit it and
work on it.
Once you know that story, maybe we can now talk you through the process of selection of instruments we pick.
Since the core of our soundtrack will be on solo performances, we picked our instruments very carefully.
We looked for unique sound, obviously, but also what we cared about was the history behind each instrument,
because we believe that if you pour a lot of soul into the music, people will hear it and basically love it.
So, the first one.
So this is baglama, or called saz, if you like.
This is basically the same instruments.
This is our primary plucked instruments
for the whole musical palette of the Witcher 3 soundtrack.
And the fun fact is that's not even Slavic instruments.
The country of origin is Turkey.
And you're going to see that we have a lot more examples
of that later on.
Second one also, as I could say, a signature instrument
to the Witcher sound.
Thanks for watching!
That one's also not Slavic.
That comes from Eastern Mediterranean, so Greece
and Turkey.
An interesting story behind it is
that Percival actually built that instrument themselves.
The design was based on original medieval iconography,
so they looked for proper wood, proper strings,
proper materials, and proper craftsmen, basically,
to make that instrument.
The next one is really interesting.
Thank you.
This is Hardigurdy and this is, to spice up things a little bit, this is the most Slavic instruments you can get.
That instrument comes from Eastern Europe, its origins are in Poland, Hungary, Belarus and Ukraine.
That particular one is very very special because it was custom built for Robert Jaworski,
folk virtuoso from Poland.
Regular Hardigurdy has three strings, that one has seven.
Thanks to that, the instrument has much broader scale compared to regular ones and also the sound of the Kerdigordi.
That one particular is much more darker, grittier and probably you could say more devilish.
If I may say something, it's worth noting that the name Kerdigordi was invented by a Swedish cook from a Muppet show.
LAUGHTER
Next one.
Yeah, Renaissance Fiddle, so as you can hear...
You can hear it very well for a reason.
Yeah, the quality of this recording is very crappy.
When I took that clip, I didn't know I would be presenting my stuff on GDC,
so you have to forgive me that.
But basically, this is another custom-built instrument just for Robert.
It's based on original Renaissance design and the special thing about it is that it has a pickup like a guitar or a bass guitar.
So you can basically plug a cable into it, amplify it with the speakers, apply some guitar effects and achieve really, really crazy sound.
And how does it sound? Well, I have a short clip for you.
Sorry.
Yeah.
Next one is also very special.
So basically, a piece of wood with a few strings attached to it with a big hole in it, and
you have another instrument.
It's a Bowet Gusli and the Polish name is Gęśle Gdańskie, another very difficult word for you, so don't bother with that.
I'm just mentioning that because basically this is a replica built especially for Robert,
based on archaeological remains found in Gdańsk, Poland, hence the name Gęśle Gdańskie, in 1940s.
Original designs, experts say...
was from 12th century, so probably that's the only instrument from 12th century built
with the original design, so that's also very special thing for us that we were able to
you know incorporate that instrument into our palette.
Another ones?
Yeah, so while Marcin recorded Percival in Warsaw, I took care of some recordings in Los Angeles and recorded some wonderful musicians.
One of them was Amir Yagmai. He's a multi-instrumentalist from Iran.
I should say, and he plays guitar, he plays violin,
he plays oud, he plays this wonderful instrument
which is called yali tambur.
It originates from Turkey and what it means
is basically it's Turkish guitar.
By adding yali in front of it,
it makes it Turkish bass guitar.
It can be bowed, it can be plucked,
it has a bright sound.
and the semitones are on the frets,
and the frets are movable.
Yeah, it sounds really cool.
I'll show you in a minute.
Now, this particular one doesn't have
any amazing story behind it.
However, the next one,
being a combination of a violin and a zombie,
it looks great.
It sounds more or less the way it looks.
It originates from India, it made its way to Nepal and Iran.
And this particular one was found by Amir's grandfather
50 years ago in some forgotten village in the south of Iran.
And it served as a decoration on a tavern wall.
Back then it was 100 years old, so you know.
Now it's even older than that.
Fun fact about it, that it's carved out of one piece of wood.
And as you see, it has two hollow chambers.
I'm going to show you the example of how
both of them sound.
There's a call and response coming.
The call comes from yali tambur being bowed.
I think it's a great sound.
And the response is coming from gai chak.
Yeah, it's gai chak, gay chak.
I'm not sure.
There's probably a wrong way to pronounce it.
But yeah.
Here it comes.
One more time?
Yeah.
You sure?
Okay.
♪ Do the L. ♪
All right, so those are the two instruments.
One more instrument that I want to tell you about is viola.
That's not any viola, because this one was made in 1610.
So actually, very close to when Gerald was alive.
It's McGuinea, which is the viola equivalent
of Stradivarius, and it was discovered
in a closet in Germany in bombed-down Dresden city,
and it was in pieces, torn.
I'm not sure how the player, Andrew Duckles, got hold of it, but he did.
And he restored it in Los Angeles. It took a year, it took a whole year to restore it.
A lot of money as well.
A guy named Michael Fisher restored it.
He had to find exact kind of wood that was originally in the instrument.
So it turned out to be, you know, like a Frankenstein.
Viola, it's very large back in 17 back in 17th century people didn't play viola like this
They play it on lap like a like a cello
vertically
It was much bigger now Andrew duckles is a big guy, and he can play it like this. He's a virtuoso
So but and it sounds amazing. I don't have an example here, but it's in the soundtrack
So yeah, that's that's Andrews viola there are more instruments
One more time.
Okay, more instruments, as you see, that we will not have time to talk about.
They were all live, recorded.
Thank you for that.
And you ruined that.
Yeah, this is to...
Okay, so to talk you briefly.
Bazooki, Lyra, vocals, violin, electric cello, acoustic cello.
And vocals, lots of them.
Yes, a lot of them.
So yeah, the stuff we recorded has influenced our approach to music composition and our implementation choices.
So one thing you need to be aware of if you are dealing with medieval or period instruments is that their natural tunings can basically set the tone for your work.
Most of our instruments were in D natural, so that was some clue for us what to do with them.
As you know already my story with Percival and recording sessions,
you already know that great amount of improvised performances happened along the way.
We did it a lot and because of that also partially we...
as you already also know, decided to focus our soundtrack
on more of those solo performances
instead of standard palette.
So if you take those choices,
you also have to deal with consequences.
Yeah, and the consequences are, yes,
five hours of D minor.
After that, it was really challenging to me
to compose any other key, even C major.
Even C major was a challenge.
But D minor is nice.
It has a nice topography.
It has a nice sound.
So.
Yeah, so that's one consequence of those recorded instruments.
Another one is improvise staff transport
into great tavern queues.
Now it's probably worth mentioning
that when Marcin was doing jam sessions with Percival,
I'm sure there was a lot of alcohol and cigarettes
involved.
But there are no photos to prove that, though.
But it's for a good reason.
It's for tavern queues.
So you know.
I have my own click truck.
So it worked.
He had to edit it, so, you know.
It's all to serve the art, right?
Yes, yes, yes.
worth the pain.
And yeah, those solo parts became
the core of the soundtrack.
And the songs.
Songs, Marcin will tell you more about them.
It turned out that songs happened
to be an important part of our soundtrack.
We had three brilliant vocalists from Percival,
and we used their talents a lot.
And I think the most
Bright and shiny example of how much love and care we took about songs is a Priscilla song case.
If you played The Witcher, you already know that at some point of the game,
Geralt is attending a pretty awkward concert for him,
because Priscilla is singing a song about his love to Yennefer.
Interesting musical story behind it is that this song has been translated to all seven languages we did.
So Polish, English, German, Russian, French, Japanese, and Brazilian Portuguese.
That was kind of a technical challenge for us to not only compose the beautiful song, beautiful ballad,
but also to make it work in all those seven languages, to translate that song,
to, you know, fit the number of syllables within the phrase,
to sync it perfectly with the lute track.
That took us some time to figure out how to do it.
And I think that's a good example to actually prove that
basically we care about songs very much.
Yes.
My turn.
So musical direction, don't focus on the game.
Do you?
Yes, good.
OK, it works.
set of mechanics under player's disposal.
What this complicated sentence means
is that some other games have implementation
down to almost every step of the player.
This approach, however, might not serve best
in terms of telling the story
and the overall narration of the game.
Well, yeah.
So if you take the music away from any medium
that it accompanies, it has its own emotions.
It has its own pacing.
And we really loved how the natural pacing of music
dances and intertwines with the pacing of the game,
how it kind of dictates it, rather than the other way
around.
And so, yes, we could have done the implementation.
in a more detailed way.
There are games that have the audio implementation done
more technically.
However, we chose not to do that.
We chose to let the music sing.
And that was a risk.
And I think it paid off well.
Like I said, the story and its pacing comes from music as well.
This approach also makes the music matter.
It gives its own voice and story to tell,
and it lets the emotions shine as well from the music,
not being interrupted by, you know, little...
little sync points that go to the sound engine.
And scoring with songs.
Yes, songs is just everything.
It's on top of everything.
This approach just makes the music even more important.
Yeah, as you probably know, we use a lot of songs throughout the whole game.
And obviously, one might ask the question,
OK, but what about the correlation between songs and spoken dialogue, for example?
We don't obviously want to draw the player's attention out of the dialogue because of, you know, some chick is saying some words with song, right?
So, we decided we would basically use songs in gameplay situations. What gameplay situations?
It turned out, once we started to test our game at our headquarters with the music,
that slaying monsters and casting spells feels much more awesome when you have kicking rock riffs
and wailing vocals basically, you know, supporting you.
You can actually feel like kick-ass monster slayers, so that was really a no-brainer for us
to decide that, okay, so our combat encounters...
would be scored with songs.
And no matter if the song would be sung in Polish, Ukrainian, Hungarian,
because we have all of those, really.
But that doesn't matter.
It's all about emotions and the way the song makes you feel about yourself
and feel you as Geralt, a monster slayer.
So that's why I think our songs shine.
in the soundtracks, shining in the game,
and are one of the ways we are actually
pushing the music towards the front of a player.
To summarize that part of the presentation,
we have a short video clip for you,
which I hope presents all of those thoughts
we presented for you.
So take a look and hear.
We knew someone special was to arrive.
We read beast entrails, saw the omens.
We would glimpse her likeness.
A mirage in a puddle.
She came from the lower swamp.
We knew not at first it was her the omens had spoken of.
A child of the Elder Blood, the sown seed that will burst into flame.
She's there, to our hands.
Elder Blood!
Mmm, the blood of the treacherous!
Do-do-do-do do-do-do-do-do-do, do-do-do-do-do-do-do, do-do-do-do-do-do-do-do, do-do-do-do-do-do-do-do-do.
Yes.
Not the kind of briar you would see on Fox TV.
OK, so we're going to tell you a few words about implementation.
So how-
did we make it all work. You already know we decided to pick Wwise, Game Audio Middleware,
to handle all the audio music stuff and within Wwise we decided to build our own adaptive music
system. The goal was simple, we wanted to have responsible fast adaptive music system that would
would work in non-linear quest structures.
Obviously, we use layers, parameters, and states,
but I guess that's obvious for all of you.
Here, the important thing regarding our system
is that it's based on two pillars.
First one is location-based exploration and combat music.
So whenever Geralt is visiting some place, the Novigrad,
some forest, swamps, whatever, that particular location
has its own.
Is that okay?
Yeah, I thought I finished for a second.
A set of exploration music and paired combat pieces with that.
Second pillar, also important,
is all the tailored music we did for quests.
So that means all the cutscenes music, dialogue,
quest-specific segments,
or some custom gameplay situations,
like, for example, when we have to chase someone
or stuff like that.
One of the aim...
that Mikolaj already briefly talked about when we designed our music system was not to sacrifice
music artistic value and essence to perfect implementation solutions
we decided to
at first be
at first try to
How do I say that?
think about narration of music and what kind of story music has to tell itself rather than just
you know thinking about it as a set of assets and just divide it mathematically.
This is one of the examples of one of the locations
in Prologue by Torchart.
And each of those green blocks represents one queue.
These are standard exploration and combat queues here,
as well as that tailored music I mentioned for quest events
and cut scenes.
And this is how they work together.
So even though we did try to.
maintain this artistic beauty of music and have the music its own voice, we try to do as
sophisticated system as possible and that little spider web is showing you how basically that
translates to technical side. Don't be confused about the visuals, this is F-mod and I just use
that to sketching because I like sketching in F-mod but we are still on Wwise, okay?
So to summarize briefly what we just told you.
Yes.
So how did our music turn out exactly?
Well, players seem to like it a lot.
But why?
One of the reasons, we believe, is pitch tuning imperfections.
As you heard in examples that we showed you,
a lot of music was quite out of tune.
For this particular project, it worked out very well.
But in general, imperfections are
what make music beautiful.
You can try to make the sound perfect down to the beat,
but we believe it would happen at a certain cost.
Very important sentence today is the second one.
Don't be afraid to experiment.
Go wild with ideas.
And this is what we want you to take away from this lecture
today.
We chose to go wild.
We chose to risk, and the risk paid back.
And vocals, as Marcin said, are very important.
Push the music towards the foreground.
And our formula is to.
It's a generally good formula to take something that people are accustomed to and on top of that introduce something that they don't expect.
That's good on every level, we think.
Yeah, a couple of closing thoughts for you.
We have read numerous amounts of reviews for our game,
and almost everyone highlighted music
as a strong part of the game.
That means a lot to us.
We read a lot of those, so that, I think,
also represents that.
correlation between pouring your soul into a project and
You know having the love back from the players as we described before
The Witcher 3 soundtrack has spawned lots of fan covers including YouTube celebrities like Maluk Ahor or Taylor Davis
I think that's another example of how our music turned out to be and how likable it turned out to be
We would like to encourage you, if there are composers out there in the room,
to do not be afraid of experiment and sometimes take controversial decisions,
because in the end, if you are really dedicated to your work and you love what you are doing,
that can really pay off and basically you can receive lots of love from people.
I know that the second to last sentence about staying true to yourself and loving your world
is the most cliché thing you will probably hear today, but it kind of summarizes our
journey through the Witcher soundtrack and basically tells everything you need to know
about our work.
And last but not least, don't be afraid of vocals, because I personally believe that
Today, nowadays, in video games, music, we could use vocals a lot more.
Let me just add to this cliché sentence that Marcin had.
When you work on a project for a long time,
you know, after a couple of weeks, it's easy to stop, to really stop loving it.
But the longer you maintain this loving attitude to your art,
to your, you know, musical childhood, the better it will turn out.
For everybody.
That's it, people.
That's it. Thank you.
Are there any questions?
Microphone.
Or shout very loudly.
Hi there, my name is Isabella Nessa.
I'm a composer and a sound designer.
And I have one quick question about your theming,
specifically with Song of the Sword Dancer and the Vagabond.
The melodic theme is the same in those,
but the rhythm is very different.
And did you pay very careful attention
to how you made it out the rhythmic displacement?
And did you have any ideas about how
you wanted that to affect the player experience?
Vagabond and second?
Song of the Sword Dancer.
Uh, okay. Oh, wow.
Oh.
Okay, I haven't expected that.
Yes, is the answer.
Yes, we had to experiment with rhythm a lot
because we were in the same key.
That's one reason.
You picked very different pieces
because the Vagabond is an exploration piece
and the song of the sword dancer is a shining example
of wailing vocals during combat, right?
God damn it, I don't even know how to respond to your question, really.
I'm confused.
They have the same melody, the theme is exactly the same between them.
Yes, that's because we tried to recycle the material.
That doesn't sound good.
It was very effective.
There was this slide about thematic work.
So that was important for us to basically use themes
as some sort of glue with the whole soundtrack
because of the distribution of regions
and musical influences we have among those.
So that was pretty obvious for us.
We had to, or we wanted to, use some pre-existing themes
or themes we composed throughout the whole game.
But regarding arrangement and rhythms,
I don't think there's that much of a theory
or ideology behind it.
I think it just happened by itself
during the process of composition,
and yeah, basically that's it.
Thank you.
Hi, you talked about how you tried to look into the history of each instrument in
order to work with it and create this sort of Slavic experience, but then you
described how all these instruments come from Italy and Greece and Turkey and Iran.
Were you surprised by how multicultural your instrumentation that you
use as kind of the core of this was?
Uh, but also the Slavic part came from the performances as well.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's also not only...
The instrument is obviously the important part of the process,
but if you just strip it out of the awesomeness,
it's just a tool, right?
Just the object you are using to create music.
So it's all about the way you use that instrument.
So when you, for example,
listen to traditional Turkish performances of kemençe,
so that little fiddle thing, right?
The kasha played, the red-haired girl.
It sounds very different compared to what we did with Kemenche in our soundtracks.
So it's how you use it, what kind of sound you produce out of that instrument, what kind of scales you use, for example.
So that, I think, also...
with our influences. Influences the way the music sounds in the end.
Okay, thank you.
that are all associated with that.
My question regards, when you're working with musicians,
like as you were saying, that come
from very different backgrounds.
They come from a sort of a self-taught or a by-ear route.
And you're trying to work with them.
You're working to develop certain types of motivic
material that you can then use.
You're coordinating with musicians in Poland,
musicians in Los Angeles, all of which
are kind of working in different spheres, I guess.
Like, how do you bring that all together?
for the final product, or did you find it,
or what kinds of difficulties did you find
as you were doing that?
Did we find difficulties?
Well, you did at the beginning, I didn't.
It was, you know, partially the improvisation
that was done on both continents,
and partially it was, you know, playing the themes
that were pre-composed already.
I don't know, Marcin, by the way,
how you made these guys from Percival
to play the themes if they didn't.
Did you sing?
La, la, la, la.
I was actually trained in singing.
So just don't ask me to sing.
OK.
No, I'm not.
And then we swap files.
And that's what made it cohesive.
Yeah, the bottom line was that with all those recording
sessions in LA, in Poland, the plan
was to build our own musical library we would use
to build our soundtrack around it.
So we ended up with hours of recordings.
We edited it up.
We chopped to, you know.
lakes, musical sequences, riffs, loops, drum patterns,
because we also did record chants,
but we forgot about it when we did presentation.
So.
Think about it as your new sample library you buy,
for example.
So that was our base set of sounds
we wanted to use in that project.
And whenever we felt that, for example, oh, that's
Bagrama part or that Yalitambur Lake or reef
would feel useful in that piece, we just used that.
So it was all about having additional firearms
under our sleeves, basically.
Cool, thanks.
Hey, guys.
Great talk and also amazing music in the game.
Thank you very much for giving me hours of enjoyment.
I have two quick questions.
And the first one is, what kind of direction
did you give the musicians to get the best results in terms
of, did you say this is a battle scene,
just be angry with your instruments?
What kinds of direction?
Or this is a romantic scene or this is a romantic piece.
What kind of direction did you give the musicians?
Well, I believe that, and I also work with my supervisors in the same way, that if you are well briefed, you're going to deliver the best possible work.
So my responsibility as music director was to brief them as much as possible and to provide them all the necessary information they had.
When we did recording session, we had already working game.
So we were able to present them some gameplay videos,
some concept art, renders, game art,
and also tons of scripts, spoken dialogue lines.
And just my imagination working with, for example,
saying them, OK, now we're going to play tavern piece.
So imagine that we're in this wooden medieval tavern.
There are lots of dwarves.
So you know the dwarves.
kicking each other's asses, for example.
There is some bum in the corner, drunk and sleeping.
There's some courtesan or prostitute, for example,
looking for customers.
So imagine that thing.
And we need to come up with some musical mood for that.
Also, you can put the players into certain moods
by telling them how to feel.
Like, you've got to make this more angry, feel more anger.
You cannot really.
put this on paper, you know, you describe a certain situation like, I'm sorry to say it, but maybe, you know, imagine like someone died in your family, you know.
So it's horrible, but this evokes extreme emotions, you know, which you want to catch.
One more thing that also worked in my case, that...
surroundings. So if you are in the studio environment, you have very limited options of adjusting your space, but
even
small things like for example
toning down the light can do wonders with
you know, adjusting them, toning them into right emotional mood you want to achieve. So
that can also work.
Wonderful and great job on that and getting the emotion out.
The second question is in the WISE implementation of your adaptive music system,
how long did that take and how many people did you have working on it?
It took us, I guess, half a year to finally figure out what do we want and what do we
need for The Witcher 3.
And regarding manpower, we did prototype the system with two guys, so audio programmer
and senior quest designer, my friend.
But all the implementation was done by me.
So just one man army.
Wow.
Good job.
Thank you very much.
Thanks.
Hello, thank you very much for the talk.
I had two quick questions as well.
The first one is about percussion,
because you talked a lot about your melodic instruments
and voices, but what about percussion?
Did you record them as well?
Did you record performances, or maybe more individual strokes,
and then put them in a contact instrument?
And how did you handle the fact that probably
some performances weren't really like very, very
regular in terms of tempo?
Percussion?
Yeah, for percussion.
Well, two ways, I guess.
When Percival was recorded, they were recorded in cues,
you know, like songs, so there was already
like a natural accompaniment from some sort of a drum
to the song, so both files would naturally go well together.
However, the majority of sounds would come from samples, I'm afraid.
OK.
Yeah.
Yeah, for that amount of music, you want to have flexibility,
which we didn't get from those recordings, I guess,
in terms of percussion instruments.
That's why they didn't brag about them, by the way.
Yeah.
And so that leads to my second question,
is that how did you manage to handle well
the mixing between all these recordings, which
have lots of imperfections, I would say,
and that's what makes them so great with more?
super produced elements that we usually use in our DAWs with virtual instruments.
So how did you manage to really mix that and come out with a successful music?
I think that begins with the very first stage.
So setting up the right microphones and picking up the right recording studio.
I was fortunate enough to have a brilliant recording engineer as my friend.
So the moment I knew I'm going to have several days recording session,
I just phoned him, asked if he's available.
Fortunately, he was.
I need to admit that he basically did most of the hard work, so proper microphone setup
was the very important process because I didn't even know their instruments.
could sound in their raw, unedited form that good.
So later on, when we took those recordings,
we had a very good source material we could work on.
So that was obviously much, much easier for us
to apply all those effects, compressors,
and all the stuff we are using during the process of mixing
and producing music.
The stuff was also mastered in Los Angeles, which helped.
Thank you very much.
Sure.
Hi, really quickly.
I remember you guys mentioned that the initial onset
of your success in this was allowing the musicians
to kind of have a jam session instead of going strictly
off of what you wrote.
I imagine that might create some mess
with intellectual property.
Is that something you guys had to deal with?
Or how did you deal with it?
Well, they sold it all to CD Projekt.
There you go.
Cool.
Okay, I guess that's it.
Thank you very much for listening.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.