I'm hoping I'm on. It sounds like I'm on.
Lovely to see you all. Thank you very, very much for making
the inexplicable and possibly ill-advised choice of
starting your GDC with the talk about death.
I appreciate it more than I can say, so thank you very much.
because that is what I'm here to talk about.
So I call this the gamification of death,
partly because I'm a little bit of a troll,
and partly because I couldn't think of anything better.
But I should probably say up front,
I'm talking here about gamification, not
air quotes gamification.
And I don't really want to get bogged down into that debate.
I think it's already unfolded quite interestingly
at various of the summits earlier this week.
But I think it is worth just making that distinction
between a process of trying to make something
into a meaningful game, into something that operates
in the way that we understand games work,
with risk and rewards and objects and constraints
and whatever particular definition you best like
as your definition of a game, and the other equally
interesting but different process
of using some of the language of games,
some of the furniture and paraphernalia
in terms of point structures and badges
to apply to other circumstances.
And both are interesting, but what I want to talk about today is the first one, is about
this process of trying to make something real into a real game.
So I'm going on the no air quotes front.
And the thing I was trying to make into a game was death.
And I and my team at Hide and Seek have spent on and off quite a lot of the last 18 months
working on a project about death.
uh, from which we learned a lot, uh, and I wanted to come and,
uh, share that with you guys here. And this being GDC, I
thought I should do that in the format of takeaways, because we
all love a takeaway. That means something quite different in the
UK, you know, it really skews our perspective of this whole
event. Um, but yeah, I wanted to share my takeaways from that
year and a half of working on, uh, A Game About Death. And so
these were my kind of top three takeaways. Uh,
was pretty much it.
It was a hard year and a half.
And I did tell you you were coming to a thing about death,
and I'm sorry that this is how your day starts.
And it may sound like a major overstatement, right?
Games about death, not that hard.
Games have a lot of death in them.
We've all seen and played, and some of us
have made probably really interesting projects, game
projects, proper game projects about death,
whether some of Eric Zimmerman's early game design challenge
sessions, or playing Passage, or The Path,
or whatever it is that you.
go to in your head when somebody says games about death.
So why did this drive me to the brink of my takeaway slide
when it seems quite straightforward?
So it's worth saying that this isn't really
a project about death.
It's a project about a death.
And that turns out to be a much harder thing.
So this was a project that was based around this film,
a film called Dreams of a Life.
And this film.
tells a story that I still struggle to tell,
about the discovery of the body of a woman named Joyce Vincent,
dead in her North London flat in 2005.
She was found by the bailiffs, who
had broken in because of a buildup of unpaid electricity
bills.
And they found not her, but her skeleton.
she'd been lying there for nearly three years. Despite the unpaid bills, the electricity
had remained on, so for that entire period, her television had been on. Um, broadcasting
BBC One for all of that time. Um, her neighbours didn't know her, no one had ever reported
her missing. Um, in the end, she was only identified, or formally identified,
by comparing her teeth against holiday photos that they found
in the flat in which she was smiling enough that they could
make that secure identification.
When she died, she was 37 years old.
And it's a story that I think everybody, or everybody I've
ever told it to, responds to very strongly.
it's unthinkable and horrible that somebody could fall through the cracks to that extent
and this was somebody who had friends, who had a successful career, who had family still
living, who had a father still alive at the time of her death and sisters.
It was briefly reported in the UK press, but the story sort of went nowhere because nobody
could find out anything about her.
She dropped so far from kind of...
the way that we normally keep people in our social lives that nobody had any stories to tell.
So Carol Morley, an acclaimed documentary filmmaker from the UK, just couldn't let the story go.
And so she spent the next five years trying to dig through what she could to try and find out.
both more about how Joyce had come to die but also how she lived and who she was and what we'd lost in
losing this woman that none of us knew or none of us knew had died. The film was primarily funded
by Film4 in the UK who you may know from Slumdog Millionaire and a bunch of other things that you
might like and they were really keen early on to make this a
uh
a commission that went beyond film.
They knew that there is not necessarily an infinite market
for people who go and see your house documentary,
particularly at the cinema.
There's often not opportunities for people to see that work
depending on where they live and where the film is screened.
So they wanted to commission something to sit beside it
that would be more accessible to a wider audience
and that would provide an opportunity
for people to explore their own reactions to the film.
and to Joyce's story. So they knew they wanted it to be digital and interactive,
which meant they basically knew they wanted it to be a game. So they came to us and said,
might you be the guys to do this? Now, if you, you may or may not know Hide and Seek,
if you do know Hide and Seek, that may seem like a weird thing, because quite a lot of what we do
is silly.
Quite a lot of what we do has comedy swans in it and involves people running around in streets and reinventing
clues so that it's got zombies in it and Monopoly so that it's about divorce
and doing film work but often film work for big entertainment
projects like Sherlock Holmes or Green Lantern as I'm sure you have clocked already. But another
half of our work that's maybe not so well known is with more serious and kind of
art house project. So Hinterland was a playable poem that we ran on the streets of Edinburgh
last year. We've made games with Tate Modern, integrating with all of the artwork in their
permanent collection, which in Tate Modern is a pretty eclectic and challenging bunch of stuff.
And we've done theatre projects and art projects with various kind of national theatres.
So...
Film 4 thought it would be a really great idea to involve us.
We thought it would be a really great idea to involve us,
because this is the kind of stuff we like doing.
And I thought it would be an especially good idea,
because I spent a lot of the last 10 years,
some of you have been on the receiving end of it,
talking about the potential of games,
talking about their ability to tackle any subject,
to stand shoulder to shoulder with any other art
and entertainment form,
and make things of worth and of weight.
So I thought this was a brilliant idea.
It really wasn't.
And it really wasn't because the minute
you start poking at this proposition,
you start to find all kinds of really difficult constraints
and challenges that affect how you approach the design.
So in kind of no particular order,
I thought I'd take you through a few of those
just so you could kind of see how the thing stuck together
in our head.
So aesthetics is a place to start.
This is a project that has to sit next to a film,
a feature film.
and not just any feature film, but a documentary.
And so very early on, we're asking
those sort of big principle questions of,
what do we think this looks like?
Is it going to feel right if it looks like a video game?
Is that going to sit well next to the film?
Is it going to feel right if it is illustrated?
Because while you have some fantastic animated
documentaries,
we had some questions about what happens when you put an animated game against a film documentary
and whether or not you kind of trigger any interesting questions about kind of hierarchy
of reality and truth in kind of those two things. And so we immediately found that we were kind of
being led in interesting directions about what our aesthetic approach to this thing might be.
And part of the reason that's so hard is, as any of you who've ever worked on a film
project know, is that timing is incredibly tricky.
That you're probably trying to make a thing that needs to be ready for when the film comes
out, that means you've got to start work before the film is finished.
And that's hard enough on a kind of blockbuster film where you can make a bunch of assumptions
about how the thing will come out.
you know, you've got hundreds of versions of the script,
assuming you can get hold of them,
to kind of see what's going to happen.
And you can maybe even get on set for some of the shoot,
or see some of the production design stuff coming through.
And those are experiences we've had before.
With Carol's film, this is a documentary
based almost entirely on interviews
with people from her life,
which meant that right up until the last minute,
new information was kind of emerging
and thinking about,
how the finished version might look. So when we started conversations with her, she had
not made any firm decisions about how the film would appear. We knew there would be some moments
of recreation of Joyce's life in it, but we didn't know at all what format they would take.
And so both you have no access to that information and you also probably have no access really to
the creative team working on the film. This is a low budget passion project for a documentary
maker. They are working.
18 hours a day in Dublin on this stuff, and don't necessarily have a whole lot of time
to work with you on the questions you have about how you want your game to look.
And that relationship with the film also gave us another interesting problem, which is
the incredibly arresting thing about this project is the story of Joyce and all of the
questions that her life and her death trigger.
And that's where you want to start.
But that's what the film is doing.
That's what Carol is doing.
She's the documentarian.
She's the person who spent five years immersing herself in
every detail that she can find and building relationships
with all of the people who did No Joyce who were willing to
contribute.
And for us to
present our own version of that story for us to make our own efforts to recreate Joyce's world
it seemed both like unnecessary duplication and also really a pretty substantial impertinence
right this isn't i make video games i'm not a documentarian i have no business rocking up to
this and three weeks later going hey we made a explorable replica of Joyce's flat that we invented
you know from not very much so although
you want to start there because that's clearly the kind of the center of gravity of this whole thing,
it becomes a very difficult place to be. And it becomes literally a very difficult place to be.
I mean, I think Film 4 had initially considered some approaches that included things like
recreating Joyce's flat as an apartment, as an explorable environment.
instantly
apparent that that's kind of a
macabre and inappropriate thing to do because because Joyce
was there, Joyce's body was there and either you have to include that
in that replica of what you do which is
macabre and difficult, you have to exclude it, which is sort of even worse.
And finding a way to put you there that didn't feel intrusive and inappropriate
was something that, you know, I think we very, very early on decided that we
didn't want to do. So,
although Joyce was this huge starting point,
we realized quite soon that she actually
wasn't going to feature very largely in the work
that we did at all, which leaves you in an interesting place.
All of this, it's worth saying, is happening against what
I think, to be fair, is probably the best-funded art house
transmedia digital game project ever, which is to say,
you know, this is not a AAA title, all right?
You're trying to do this within a very particular set
of constraints.
But do work that's going to stand up credibly next to something designed to be seen on the big screen.
But also because of the nature of that funding, you have a bunch of other really interesting questions and problems.
Joyce's story...
touches on some very difficult issues, touches on issues of suicide, touches on issues of
domestic violence. At the time when we started working on this, it wasn't clear whether or
not we were going to be dealing with issues of drug use. And obviously touches on this
central issue of people who go missing, of what that process is.
what it can mean about the people who do go missing and what it means for the people who are left behind.
And Film4 is pretty fearless about tackling all of that stuff.
They weren't looking to mark off any particular taboos for us.
But they have a very well-established set of compliance guidelines
and some very well-versed lawyers who have good guidelines and opinions
about how you might tackle these things,
about how you make sure that you don't include...
you know, trigger points for self-harm or where you have to think about putting in safety
nets and contact points for people who might be having suicidal thoughts.
And you very, I mean, these are very sobering conversations, very, very fast that you don't
necessarily have.
There's also a whole bunch of legal issues here about questions of...
libel I guess in terms of suggesting if there was kind of a any direct negligence that led up to
Joyce's death and the failure to discover her body. You know because these are all this only
happened a few years ago all the people involved in the story are still alive we're going to play
this thing.
And so you're very quickly aware that you're navigating in this kind of very complicated space.
And we got a lot of help from Film 4 in doing that.
We spent a lot of time talking to people like Missing People,
which is the big missing persons charity in the UK, to try and kind of get our heads around all of these issues.
Because the problem with a project like this is it's not just about keeping the lawyers happy.
It's really a lot about not being an asshole.
Because you hear the story, and everybody has their own
immediate reaction to it.
And I think quite a lot of people had a reaction.
I certainly had a reaction, where you go, oh, god, I
should ring my brother.
I've not spoken to my brother in like three months.
That's inexcusable.
I should fix that.
I should do that.
I should call my granny.
I should do this thing.
I should bang on my neighbor's door and introduce myself,
because I still don't know their names,
or whatever it is.
you very quickly start having ideas about how you might
structure a game experience that revolves around doing those
kind of things.
And possibly, revolves around doing those kind of things in
machine-readable ways.
So you start to have over-excited ideas about
scraping people's Facebook accounts for a whole bunch of
information about the size and richness of
their friendship group.
and looking at how often they contact people
and prompting them to get in touch with people
that they haven't contacted for a while
and all this kind of thing.
And then you realize that you have no business doing that.
You have no idea who these people are.
The machine-readable portions of their social lives
are only ever portions.
None of you have lives that are fully and wholly represented
in Facebook or on Twitter or whatever it is
that you tend to be.
There's people who are there,
there's people who are not there,
there's maybe people who.
are there who it looks like you never interact with but that's because you see them every day
or you IM them every day or you know whatever else is going on and trying to reconstruct.
a true reflection of somebody's degree of connectedness
from digitally scrapable sources.
Again, the minute you poke at it for more than two seconds
is clearly not a good idea.
Even if you remove the machine readable portion
and just say, how long is it since you called your mother?
you may have a really good reason for not having called your mother.
I have no business, my game has no business telling you that you ought to do that.
And what you find is you, you...
So you step away from that specificity,
and you try and find something that is gentler and more open to interpretation,
and then you end up with something that is so wishy-washy and so vague
that nobody cares.
It's like, hey, maybe you should think about a thing that you don't think about if you'd like.
It's not like, you know, that's not hooky.
That's not kind of what you want.
So that.
you know, that became really important to us. I think particularly when we talk to people like the Missing People charity,
you start to realize lots of things that I hadn't perhaps thought about before as much as I should, that, you know,
sometimes people go missing because they want to go missing. Sometimes people are isolated because they enjoy solitude.
They're happy working that way. Sometimes people like mediating nearly all of their friendships and social life digitally.
And that doesn't mean there's anything deficient in that. It doesn't mean there's anything deficient if you don't want to do anything.
digitally and you want to do everything down the pub in real life. It was very difficult
to find any firm ground of a thing that we felt we could say that didn't involve being
an asshole. And that led into another realization that really affected the development direction
of the project.
One of the saddest things at the heart of Joyce's story is she was found by accident.
No one knew she was there.
No one was looking.
Her neighbor had become a bit frustrated the previous year at the noise from the television
and had banged on the wall a bit, but when it hadn't worked, he'd given up.
And that felt incredibly important to me, that this reality, that...
this terrible thing had happened and we just didn't know and nobody did anything and nobody
was looking and there was no sense of quest, there was no sense of mission, it was a really
interesting thing to take into a game design context because so often that's our structure.
I mean arguably it's always our structure, but there's a thing you're trying to do, there's
a point you're trying to get to, there's a, you know, there's some kind of mission statement
or a goal objective.
And you know.
Obviously we didn't want to do crass ways to do that.
We would, I don't think we would have felt at all comfortable kind of making a game where
your job was to save Joyce or, you know, find her earlier or, you know, whatever that could
have been.
But even if you make it oblique, it just started to feel, um...
totally and thematically wrong. Putting you in a structure that was about going,
hey, you know, your job is to do this stuff and that will work,
just felt to be a structure that was everything that the film and Joyce's
story wasn't about. And it was probably about this point
that we started to get quite scared, because it's like, okay, so now
we can't even kind of have that structure.
So we're not going to use Joyce's narrative, we're not going to use...
that kind of conventional game mission structure.
And then the difficulty is, even when
you start looking on a systemic level, it's really difficult.
So a lot of, and certainly a lot of the work
we've done in gamifying with no air quotes things,
and a lot of what the other people have done,
is looking for those essential systems,
is looking at how you boil something down to something
revelatory and interesting about the kind of interplay of key elements within that system.
That's great because games thrive on those structures.
But I think this is interesting because we've talked here often enough about whether or not
it's a realistic goal that we'll ever be able to model the muddier elements of the human
condition in that kind of a way. And
Joyce's story just seemed like, you know, this incredible object lesson in how functionally impossible that is.
The systems, there are systems that sit under Joyce's story.
All kinds of systems. There's administrative and institutional systems.
It was clear that...
it became clear from Carol's research that there was some history of domestic violence
there and that had put her into a system which had provided her with safe housing but had
probably broken her connections with the places that she'd been living prior to that happening.
There is terrible administrative details that come to light.
She had gone into hospital a few months before she died
and had listed on her hospital admission sheet as her next of kin, her bank manager,
which is still one of those things that kind of wakes me up at night occasionally.
you know, and then there's all kinds of social and friends relationship, again, it's clear.
I do, if you, if you have a UK iTunes account, you can download Carol's film, it's not released
in the US yet, and it's, it's great, and it is also not as doleful as it sounds, it's
surprisingly life-affirming.
Um, but you, you can definitely map a bunch of, you know, friends there of a, you know,
this friend who was jealous, and this friend who had a secret crush, and this friend who
rejected her.
There's a whole bunch of professional stuff about where her career took her and financial concerns.
There's some kind of systems that underpin her upbringing and the questions of the history of race and racial prejudice in London.
And all of these things are so...
knottedly interconnected and produced these imperceptible, unpredictable, longitudinal,
contradictory changes and effects on each other that even if we could make any kind
of statement on how that had played out in Joyce's life, which we obviously can't, the
thing is just a mess.
The thing is not navigable as a system and you're left with this choice of...
of you can boil it down, but then you boil it down
to something that's reductive and misleading,
or you can leave it confusing.
And then it's just terrible game design,
because you have no idea why anything is happening,
or what's affecting what, or what kind of meaningful choices
you're making, or all the rest of it.
And reminder, this whole massive thing
is to be delivered as a super accessible film 4 project that's
going to attract a new audience to this thing.
So our goal was to make sure that people
who maybe even hadn't kind of converted to Facebook gaming yet would find something here
that they were comfortable dealing with audiences who weren't necessarily already gamers.
So while I started saying we were trying to make a game about death, we were really trying
to make this game.
Yes.
And we took a swing at that, right?
Because we'll give it a go.
That seemed like a thing that we might try to do.
So we...
We turned quite early to text.
Text seemed like a really interesting starting point
for a thing to solve some of those aesthetic problems,
to solve some of the budget problems,
to solve some of the tonal problems.
And we thought we could do something interesting
and hopefully.
meaningful for people by drawing on a bunch of interactive
fiction, traditions, looking a bit at text adventure design
and graphical text adventure design, and thinking about, oh,
we were so pleased when we came up with this,
thinking about if we could create this environment that
may or may not be graphically represented,
that you navigate it in the way that you navigate a text
adventure, broadly speaking.
So you're moving through a sequence of rooms or spaces.
And that would present you with.
Versions of the kinds of puzzles and challenges that you're maybe familiar with from text
adventures. So there are locked doors, there are characters perhaps you won't let you pass,
there are things to navigate. But rather than giving you the kind of tools that often those
games give you of, you know, candles and bits of rope and keys and all the rest of it, we
would ask you to draw those from your own life.
So there would be a room where to move on from that room you would need to leave something behind that was, you know, an object that was precious to you.
Or a door, probably wouldn't be a door that would only open if you would tell it the name of someone you never told you loved and you wished you had, or whatever it was, maybe a bit less terribly mawkish than that.
And then the process of puzzle solving would be the process of reuniting and restructuring those things and hopefully finding some interesting perspectives on, you know, on how those things work together.
So you would move through this space and, you know, in the end, make progress not by unlocking the blue key with the blue door, but in the end, by, you know, giving your.
grandmother's engagement ring to your high school crush or whatever unresolved thing
we had uncovered in the course of doing that.
And we thought that this whole thing might play out, the big reveal at the end would
be that in the choices that you'd made in navigating this space, you were actually navigating
on this map that told you something about yourself in terms of where you situated yourself
on that grid in terms of whether you were somebody who...
gravitated to crowds or liked to solitude or was somebody who was kind of more digitally or
physically native and then that might be a thing that we could kind of map and take out to the
world as a whole as kind of something that had arisen from this game.
There's a lot about that idea not to like.
You're probably sitting there cataloging a lot of those
things right now.
I mean, certainly, I don't think there's any kind of
great discovery at the end of that to find out whether you
like being alone or not, or whether or not you're on the
internet often.
I suspect you can probably self-diagnose on those counts
quite well.
And also, we started realizing that there were a bunch of
problems in
uh, giving you that kind of progression structure. That, um,
even within, uh, a game that has no overt winning, that has no
kind of great statement of purpose or sense of potential
failure, the minute you sense that your progress is being
gated or that one thing or another thing is going to happen
depending on what you do,
When we started paper prototyping this, we found that it totally colored people's responses to questions that we hoped they would feel able to respond to truthfully, honestly.
The thing that I really liked about this structure was there's this kind of confessional space that you form between the player and the game, and the game is an anonymous...
repository of these kind of confessions and information.
But the minute you know there's kind of two ways forward and you're being asked something,
you're second guessing the game.
You're wondering what you should say, what's going to happen to this, you become incredibly
self-conscious.
And we really struggled to kind of find a way beyond that.
Which took us to Sharj.
Um, this is the, the labyrinth in Chartres Cathedral in France.
We didn't actually get to go there.
There's a floor cloth replica in North London.
It's pretty good.
Um, it costs a fiver to get in.
That's the weird thing.
It's like going on a fairground ride.
You have to queue up and give a, give a lady your money at the front.
Um, so you guys will all know this.
I didn't know this because I hadn't been paying attention.
Labyrinths, mazes, very different things.
Mazes are puzzles.
They have choices.
You can get lost.
Labyrinths are only ever one continuous line.
There is no choice, there is no possibility to get lost, you just walk along and wiggle.
And that seems like a kind of interesting thing that you have a kind of more traditional
game experience, something with an implicit challenge and a possibility of failure and
a series of choices and you have something that's a classical linear structure.
should be boring, therefore, right? We're, we're GDC.
We're a bit snooty about linear. We like interactive.
We like choice. We like challenge. Walking one of
these things blew my mind. I don't know, has
anyone ever done it? Has anyone ever walked Labyrinth?
You guys are great. So I, maybe I just,
like,
I was having a bit of a day.
But this whole weird thing happens,
that all you do is you go in one end
and you walk to the middle.
And the middle is like five yards away.
And you know how far away five yards away is,
it's just over there.
You know how long it's gonna take you to walk there,
it's gonna take you five seconds.
You know the direction that you're gonna walk to get there
because it's just over there.
Except now suddenly you don't.
Now you have no idea how long it's gonna take you
to walk five yards.
You're walking along this path, you don't know where you are.
Your sense of space and time have effectively dissolved.
You meet somebody coming the other way, but you don't know if they're coming the other
way.
They might be going on the same journey as you, but they're just at a different point
today.
And if they're at a different point today, you don't know whether they're ahead of you
or behind you.
And so suddenly that made me feel,
and that's kind of before you get
to all of the kind of experiential choices
of just how you act within that space
and what you do with yourself.
So we got kind of excited about linear stuff
and thinking about whether we could use that
as a way to diffuse some of these questions
about how to get more...
pure responses from people in terms of the questions that we, the issues that we wanted
to think, them to think about and the questions we wanted to put to them.
But we did just keep hitting up against this problem, that the minute there was any sense
of completion or goal, we felt like we were losing people's ability to be honest.
So we played around with that for a bit, we played around a bit with the notion of...
not setting a win condition, but setting a big number of win conditions.
So kind of approaching this in a more simmy way.
So rather than saying, hey, there's this puzzle or structure or space that you have to get
to the end of.
see if you can get that right, go, OK, you can adopt a bunch
of different personas and move through this space
in different ways.
So try and make the right set of decisions
for somebody who's a loner.
It also gets us out of the being an asshole problem
where we're not telling people there's a right way to do it.
So successfully navigate this space as a loner.
Successfully do it as a parent.
Successfully do it as whatever those kind of personas
would end up have being.
That kind of worked a bit as a bit of game design, but it made us really sad because
it loses the player being the player.
What I really liked about the intensity of that relationship between the player and the
game was you were you.
I like making games where you are you.
And that seemed to kind of dilute that to a point where it wasn't interesting anymore.
Another option you have is make it so that the player defines the win conditions.
Go, hey, we're not going to be judgmental.
We're not going to tell you how to live your life.
we're gonna let you say what it is that you care about or you're aiming for.
Again, the problem is the minute you, um, overtly ask somebody that question,
even if it's in an automatic way,
they don't tell you what they think, they tell you what they think they're supposed to think,
and it's incredibly difficult to find a structure that lets people actually answer honestly in those circumstances.
And then we thought that maybe reflecting the, the...
insights that we've had about a kind of mission and quest structure
being inappropriate for Joyce's story, we would secretly not have a winning
condition. So we would set you up in a structure
where you thought you knew what you were doing,
you had a bunch of stuff to keep you busy that you were kind of chewing
through, and at the end of it we would go, oh no, but look while you were busy
doing all of that stuff, you really lost because there was this other thing going
on that we didn't tell you about, that you
didn't know about, that is sad.
And then I'm an asshole again, right?
That's terrible game design.
So there was this kind of,
I don't have sound for this,
but there should be like the sound of massive stone slabs
dropping onto bleak, rocky ground.
I'm just thinking, you know.
we really tried, but we couldn't find a game that, that, that fit within those things that we talked about.
And, and that really kind of shook me, because I've had long campaigned on the principle that
games, you know, really can do anything.
So, we did something clever.
We made a thing that wasn't a game.
And that thing is dreamsofyourlife.com if you want to go and have a look at it after
this.
And it worked!
Hooray!
Great news.
Everything.
Okay, we made a pretty good thing that isn't a game.
So we worked with an amazing novelist called A.L.
Kennedy, who if you don't know, you should check out, who turned out to be a secret expert
on all kinds of...
really interesting sort of Stanley Milgram experiments and Barnum statements and psychic
codes and stuff that turned out to be an incredibly useful way to try and structure the text of
what we wanted.
We worked with this amazing photographer, Lottie Davis, whose work you are seeing, who
helped us think about how we might find a way to photographically represent some of
the issues that we wanted to...
tackle. And we made something that's been pretty well received, that we're super proud of, and that
we think stands effectively next to the film. So I should be thrilled, right? I should be, this
session should have a different title. But I'm not, because it wasn't a game, and I really wanted
to make a game because I like making games, and I wanted to find a resolution to that.
And the thing is...
It's possible that all that happened was just those constraints that I took you through
were just too crazy.
They were just too nested, too many of them.
We just boxed ourselves into a corner.
The fact that we couldn't find a solution to it doesn't say anything about games.
It just says that we overcooked our design process.
But the thing that makes me less sure about that is...
This isn't the first time this has happened.
This is a process that is now becoming fairly familiar to me.
So we did an awesome, genuinely secret laboratory project
that I can't tell you about because I'm still NDA'd last
year that was working with a scientific institution that
was looking to improve its energy usage.
and go greener.
And one of the things that was preventing it from doing that
is they have these huge block of climate control rooms
in which they run experiments.
And they felt that they were probably using that really
inefficiently.
And was there a game that we could
make that would motivate and reward scientists
for doing a better job of combining experiments
and finding ways that they could share those rooms
and use them better?
We couldn't find one.
Because the minute you.
set a bunch of game objectives and game rewards on top of that system, you distract them or
divert them from the already completely important set of goals and constraints that they have
in the work that they do.
Can we make a really awesome tool that makes planning this stuff more fun, that is really
impactful in terms of improving their energy use, that draws on a whole bunch of stuff
I've learned as a game designer?
Absolutely.
But it wasn't a game.
look, it says so on everything. Science, okay, what about, if
it's not secret laboratories, what about, what about this? So
this is a thing we did last year as part of the Green Lantern,
um, campaign. Uh, which I really like, it was a nice thing. Um,
Green Lantern, you know, all about his green ring, space
battles, bad acting. Um, and we wanted to do something maybe a
bit more interesting with it than, than just do a bad org,
although.
we did a little cute org as well. Uh, so we hooked up with
these guys, this is the Milky Way Projector, you may know,
they're scientists who operate out of Oxford. They get real
people to look at, mm, uh, these are pictures from the NASA
Spitzer Space Telescope that haven't yet been classified.
Because there's billions of them and there's not enough grad
students. Um, and just get real people to look through them and
see what they can see.
And what we're looking at, at the moment, in the bit that we hooked up with, is the
birth of stars.
When stars are born, they explode.
There's a pressure wave that sends out a globe of gas and debris around the exploding star.
You take a photograph of that, you see it from the side.
What you see is a ring.
And in the photos, they colored them in green.
So suddenly, I have all of these photos of green rings
in space that NASA need people to look at just before the
Green Lantern really launches.
So I think that would be a nice thing to do.
So we hooked that into the stuff that we were doing.
But those guys who are really smart.
already know you can't put game objectives on top of this observation process, that the
minute you set people goals, the minute you say how many, how fast can you classify ten
things, how many green rings can you find, any of the kind of obvious structures that
you might go to to make a game of it, corrupts the results, changes the, loses the veracity
of what people do.
So they have a lovely slick system, there's a nice...
air quotes gamification process going on here in terms of giving you level rewards and giving
you a sense of progression, a sense of your place in the community, but it's absolutely
not a game.
And then the same thing happened with another secret music project I can't tell you about,
which was about looking at what we could do with gaming around listening habits.
And you, I mean it's interesting, this hits the same thing but at another element of the
same thing, which is...
There are games you make where the game places a value on the music that you listen to.
So either we do something that judges the music that you listen to and says,
well, this band is worth more than that band because they have a higher chart position,
or they've sold more records, or they have more likes on Facebook,
or however, or because we think they're better, or however we draw that data from.
Or we can do a thing that says the more you listen to this,
you know, so I don't know if any of you
played Song Summoner on your iPod back in 2007,
which is a lovely little Scroenix RPG where
your characters are built from songs on your iPod.
And the more you listen to that song,
the more kind of that character levels up.
That's a simplification.
But the key point is the more you
listen to that piece of music, the more powerful
you are in the game.
Music is this incredibly important thing in people's life.
The game doesn't know if you just got dumped or you just got a new job or you're going
on holiday.
I mean, I found playing those games where my listening habits are impactful in the game
that I'm playing just makes me hate music.
You just get up in the morning and go, oh, God, I've got to put that thing on repeat
for 10 listens, otherwise I won't get my, you know, spangle when I log in.
And I don't  I think there are things you could do.
I don't really want to do them because I think I'm ruining people's relationship with music
and
That's not a nice way to spend your life.
So what does this prove?
It might prove this.
And I'm aware that I've kind of taken a risk of standing up in a room full of game designers
and going, this is an impossible game design challenge, nobody can solve this.
And you guys already probably have notebooks full of ways to solve it.
So I might just be rubbish at it.
you know, I'll take that. If anybody has better ideas for what we could have done, I would love to
hear them, you know, I, I would love to see this problem solved, so, you know, by all means,
pepper me with those. Um, you know, but it is worth saying that I, I worked with a bunch of
smart people on this and we tried really hard and we, we came up blank and, and maybe that
tells us something important, which is, maybe this is just really hard. Um, maybe, you know,
it's okay that we, that, that...
in the time that we've been spent trying to bolt games into the real world in interesting
and important ways that we haven't completely cracked it yet.
But there's this other thing which is the scary thing which is maybe this just doesn't
work.
You know, the reason I love making games is I see them transform people in this incredible
way.
The great delight for me moving from working on digital games to also working on games
in the real world is you see face to face people do things they never would have thought
they could do.
you know, become kind of characters that you wouldn't otherwise have thought they were.
But it feels so much to me that the reason games manage to accomplish that has an awful
lot to do with the fact that the constraints that games set up are temporary and arbitrary.
That's what makes them so powerful.
And the minute you bolt those structures onto something that is real and enduring and ongoing,
there just is a tension. It is hard to do the things I can do in games that don't have to sustain that structure that moves against it.
So this is kind of where I hit that we may have a problem here.
Or certainly a problem that I didn't immediately know how to solve.
low point. I refer you back to my takeaway slides of going,
bollocks, what do I do now? And I have, um, I couldn't fit all
of this into an hour, so I have some terribly highfalutin kind
of, um, attempts at structures that I don't think do work that
anyone has ever done before, but may be useful in terms of when
you're approaching one of these projects, figuring out what it
is that you, um,
what kind of structures you might want to use.
But in the end, it isn't actually what I wanted to talk about today.
I don't think that's what's interesting about today.
What I wanted to do was come and be honest about a real project
that presented these kind of real challenges.
Because in the end, I don't feel nearly as bad about this as I expected to.
It is all okay.
I think mostly I've realized what's happened is that...
And this maybe says more about me than anything else.
I guess this was kind of previously my conception of games.
Games could go anywhere, games could do anything, games are unstoppable.
And that was what excited me about them.
I felt like there was this huge new potential that we were only just beginning to explore.
Now, I think games are more like that.
I don't know how many of you played Shadow of the Colossus, but aggros.
a much subtler and more sensitive creature than the horses in Skyrim.
He can't go everywhere.
He has his own idiosyncrasies.
He's wonderful.
I care far more about him in the end than I do about any of the Skyrim horses that I
rode over cliffs.
Sorry, Skyrim horses.
And I think that's great.
I think if we start to butt up against hard edges of things
that games can't do, that shouldn't
depress us about games.
That shouldn't make us feel that games have failed to make
a case for why they ought to be allowed to stand shoulder to
shoulder with anything and everything else.
But they should delight us that we're starting to get a
sense of what it is that makes them special, that we're
zeroing in on what it is that.
games can do that other things can't do.
And then you take another swing.
So this is, we're taking another swing.
This is South by Southwest.
This is the live game version of our game about the lady
who died in a flat, which we think might work,
which is another different approach.
Again, probably not a game, but I've
loved having a chance to take another swing at it,
to take what I learned from the last one
and come back and do this.
And you know what?
Um, also this.
here we are at GDC again and I think a lot of us have this experience that you slog away for a year at this project that whatever it is probably has you close to tears at times and you forget there's all these awesome people who can help and who are already doing this and who already know this stuff and I think it's been really nice being here having written this talk in the dark days of the end of last year to come here now and see everyone and start having conversations and start hearing about the other projects that we heard about
at the summits yesterday and that we'll hear about
in the rest of the week, that start to find
other solutions to these problems and start to show
ways in which we can refine our understanding of the theory
and prove out those assumptions in practice
in a way that kind of resolve all of that.
So, ha, got ya.
Not the bleakest session ever, I hope.
I wanted to leave, we've kind of got 10 minutes
for questions, because I kind of thought people
would want to shout at me and tell me that we'd missed
a really obvious thing we could have done that was great.
So we've kind of got 10 minutes.
I can talk more about anything you would like me to
or kind of more about structures that we use in this work.
So far away if you've got anything.
Thank you.
Hi, thank you for a great talk.
I, last fall, made a game that was kind of a documentary game
about some soldiers accused of war crimes.
And I faced a lot of sort of similar challenges
to what you faced.
I'm sure.
And ended up with something that I sort of didn't
feel comfortable calling a game.
Something that I'm sure also you faced that was a big
challenge was even convincing someone to try a thing like
that because when I would say that sentence a lot of people
would just immediately sort of like eyes glaze over back up
no that doesn't sound like something I want to do.
whether it's a game or not, when you have that sort of interactive thing exploring this like very serious issue that sounds like it's going to be a huge downer, what do you think are ways to get people to like take a chance on playing something like that?
So I'm honor bound to repeat the question so that it goes on the tape. The question of how you get people to approach games that are about this kind of super serious subject that aren't necessarily very appealing.
We tried to work in two things on that front for this. So the actual front door to this project is a Facebook quiz.
which is funny and social and lightweight,
but just starts to dig into kind of some of those
slightly darker questions.
Again, I can link anybody out to that who wants it.
And that has a little kind of link through at the end
that goes, oh, okay, so you seem really interesting.
You should come and have this conversation over here.
And I think the people who played that had a pretty positive experience with it, but
you just hit the problem then of how you market that thing and how you get that notice from
Facebook.
And the other thing is these photos that you've seen and that you'll see if you play the experience,
there's a time-lapse animation that spits out every day from the game.
I've given up not calling it a game.
What am I going to do?
So everybody who plays, everything they do every day,
the choices that they make and the routes that they take
through this thing are logged and then are used to recreate
a kind of unique edit of that thing.
It doesn't show anything personal that they said or
anything individual about them.
But we hoped would become a little kind of shareable thing
because it takes a minute and it's pretty to watch.
Again, that probably didn't have quite the impact that we were hoping to do, but I think
you're exactly right.
You've got to think about how you bring people to this kind of work, whether or not it ends
up being a game.
Before you'd resigned yourself to this not being a game at all, were there any other
games that you looked at for inspiration or that you thought had sort of blazed that trail
before?
And if so, what were they?
I mean, I think we were looking at all kinds of stuff.
I mean, we've ended up doing quite a lot of...
projects about death over the last year and a half.
So we contributed to the...
There's a big art center in London
that ran a festival of death this year,
and we did talks there on death in games.
And there's, I mean, pages,
pages and pages and pages of stuff.
And then also a whole range of things
that aren't necessarily about death,
but are about subtleties in this stuff.
So I don't think we're at all trailblazing.
I don't want to come off as thinking
that we're the first people who ever faced this stuff.
But I think often the projects that I knew and that I looked
at weren't.
if they were about death tended not to be, they're often very
personal but they weren't documentary and so that, that
kind of limited their usefulness because they often got to do
things that we couldn't get to do and I now can't give you a
really good list but um I can afterwards if you ask me, sorry.
Oh and I forgot to repeat the question which is did we look at
any other games, that was probably obvious from my answer.
We'll do left and then right. Uh yeah so I hesitate to use the
word appeal but it seems like a part of the appeal of this
project is that this was a real person and so you've, you've
kind of
morbid almost kind of fascination with it. Do you think you would have taken a different kind of
creative direction or found game mechanics that would have made more made it more gamey had it
been a fictional person that you created? Would you maybe not been so I guess reverent about it
and do you think it would have affected you know the outcome for better or worse? So question here
would it would it have been an easier project if the person had been fictional? Oh my word yes.
You know, I think, I mean, I think reverence is a fair word there.
I think there is maybe a fair comment that we were overly sensitive about these issues.
You know, this is the first project and unlike this, I think one of the things that you face as a documentarian is...
developing your own practice about how reverent you're going to be about how much you wear
kid gloves when you handle this stuff and we may be over worried about that. I think
because we also had this nested thing which it wasn't just what could we do with Joyce's
story but it was we also had to be respectful of what Carol was doing with her film and
we ended up at kind of two removes from that content.
Had it been our own fictional person, we would have had a lot more freedom, but we also would
have had a lot less impact, right? The thing that gets you in the gut about Joyce is it's true,
it happened. You can't walk past that block of flats in North London now without knowing
that unfolded there. So, easier, but maybe less powerful. Thank you.
So first of all, thank you for an amazing talk and for your capacity to sort of reveal the creative process
It's very informative. So awesome. Thank you in listening to what you were talking about. I am unclear where
Exactly you guys hit the wall. Can you talk about?
your expectations around agency and
or appeal because it felt to me as you were discussing that that maybe where you hit was having a
a particular expectation around that that may have conflicted with, like we were talking
about, the need for reverence.
where did we hit the wall and was it around the question of agency?
It's a fair proceed.
I mean yes, a lot. I think oddly, probably one of the things that hurt us on this project
was our background in designing
real world games.
That I've seen those be so transformative and I've absolutely seen those
be, I've experienced those being revelatory, where you find yourself
doing something or say something that you never would have thought you would
but is actually a truer
expression of who you are than if you'd had...
time the way you normally do in life to compose your reply and present the front
that you want to present and I was definitely chasing that I was really
hoping that I could do that but I couldn't find the bait-and-switch that
you need to do though which is I need to get you thinking that you're doing
something else and focus your agency and focus maybe the constraints or the time
pressure or the competition or whatever it is that's gonna
force you to reveal those things within this context and truthful structure.
And God, I wish we could have, because I think that could have been incredible.
But I think what we have accomplishes the emotional goal that I set for the project,
but through different means, through non-game means, and I would love to have got there through games.
I want to start by saying I think you might be selling yourself short a little bit.
It sounds like a really hard problem.
Thank you.
I wanted to ask, you mentioned a couple of times with the astronomy and with the music game.
that sort of adding a game mechanic
kind of screws up the experience.
And I wonder if that might be because
there's already a game mechanic there
and that game mechanic is sort of a part of life
and we just, we don't know what that is.
So the question is, is it hard to do these projects because there's already mechanics in place that then conflict with the game mechanics?
Yeah! I mean, I don't think they're necessarily game mechanics, they're just mechanics.
There are a whole bunch of systems that drive the choices that you make in relation to these things.
And I think I have like hand signals now for how I try and think about these things that, you know,
we're always chasing the game of, like, make this thing, make this thing into a game.
and that that transformative approach is not necessarily right and that sometimes
there's it's interesting looking at at kind of two feet this is oversimplified but kind of two
fields you've kind of got the um the subject to the narrative of the and the context of the thing
that you're working with and then you've kind of got it's
rules and objectives and interactions.
And often where these projects don't work well is when you try and stack everything
on top of those.
You're going to go and stay in that context and we'll work with those interactions and
objectives, and we'll try and put a game on top of that, and we'll just, and it doesn't
work very well.
And there are often much more.
successful approaches where you turn one of those through 90 degrees. You go, okay, so
we'll look at those objectives and actions and mechanics, but we'll actually just change
the context. We'll, you know, this is maybe a game about saving energy, but we'll tell
you that it's about parrots, or we'll tell you that it's about space aliens, or whatever.
And that's something you see quite often, and there's kind of a good reason for that.
That helps release that tension.
Or you do it the other way and go,
yeah, we will keep you in the context and the narrative of this topic,
but we'll change the things that you're worrying about.
We'll maybe invent completely new fictional ones
that aren't actually about any kind of real-world behavior change.
Or you kind of separate both.
And, I mean, this is a thing, you know, where I ended up with is,
with games, I can make a game that uses your listening habits
that I have a bunch of problems with.
or I can make a game that really uses your listening habits as window dressing,
you know, where they color what's going on, but they're not meaningful game tokens,
they're not really changing the system.
And that's not making a game of your music taste,
but it maybe is making a game with your music taste.
With is a word I've come to use a lot.
And that kind of...
side-by-side, looser relationship often feels like a way of dealing with that, that very real tension,
which is obvious the minute you say it, and again, there are so many people in here who do this
awesomely for a living, and I'm super aware that they know this stuff inside out, but
you know, I thought it might be interesting to kind of work through a specific example and see.
Thank you. Thank you for
Thank you for a beautiful talk.
It sounds like along the way, emotions arose,
as we would expect.
And I'm wondering to what degree at each stage along the way
you thought about what emotions you wanted to convey
and what techniques or devices you thought about using
to convey those emotions.
So the question of what emotions were we trying to instill in our players, I mean, again,
you worry about being a jerk and telling you what to feel.
But then you also hit this thing that, again, often in the game projects that I make, you
don't hit of kind of having to have an artist statement, kind of having to go, what am I
trying to do with this?
And I found that scary.
And I don't know how well I did.
But in the end, what it boiled down to for me was, and I think this project is a quite
nice expression for this, is that the thing that I felt...
I could truthfully say to everyone about Joyce's story is,
time passes faster than you realize
and things happen when you're not looking.
Which doesn't sound like much,
but it felt like an important and universal thing.
And so this whole project is about those two things.
It's about time passing faster than you realize
and things changing when you don't look.
and then I leave it up to you to decide how to feel about those phenomenons.
But without that, one of the reasons we, even once we decided not to make a game,
we were still lost in the weeds for a while until we doubled down on that,
on it needed a core, it needed something that we were willing to make an absolute statement about,
otherwise it was just airy-fairy float.
I felt like this photograph conveyed a lot of emotion that was suitable to the project,
for instance.
I mean, the work that went into this, I cannot begin to tell.
This was a three-day shoot that did a two-year time lapse.
So we had 11 stunt daffodils.
We poisoned and then baked those flowers
to make it look like they were dying.
That tree behind you is a tree that we
bust up from 200 miles away.
All of those leaves are hand-wired
because we shot this in February when there was nothing there.
We scouted, I think, 25 locations
to find a window that was kind of.
anonymous but believable and not too sad but could kind of decay and I hope you know I
mean that was just wonderful to hear that because I know a huge amount of that came
from Lottie and Allison and the team on that to try and convey that.
Thank you.
Okay so bear with me because my original question was technically asked so I had to modify it
in line.
For sure.
Okay so.
Drawing from the experience that you guys had with trying to work with Dream of a Life,
say you were to take from that experience and go towards a fictitious route, where you
did say it was easier to consider that, how would you exactly convey the impact of death?
I mean, the impact of death is kind of centered around what was done in life and what wasn't
done in life and what you were able to experience being taken away from you and never coming
back.
Or would you guys kind of go through the carnal instinct of survival?
Just death-sucking in general, like nobody wants to die.
I mean, I think...
So, how would we approach the project if we didn't have the documentary core to it?
I mean, we've been playing around with that a bit.
It's really interesting trying to push it out into the lives of the players as much as possible.
I'm not really interested in writing a big complex narrative about fictional characters, fictional death.
I'm interested in poking everybody out there and seeing what happens.
And I think, you know, we, for the Festival of Death, we were looking at kind of...
live action Conway game of life variations where your behavior
in that simulation was dependent on choices that you made that
were maybe reflective of your own life.
And I think we looked now, I'm remembering the answer to the
previous gentleman's question, you know, we were looking, I
just spent a whole year playing games about death, kind of, but
particularly kind of perma or relatively perma death games.
So kind of road like things where death is a really big
loss and something to fear and not just an instant respawn.
And I think there are all kinds of structures there, but I think...
I mean the other kind of really depressing note I could have ended on is that maybe games
are the worst place to try and tackle the question of death.
Because we have this weird relationship with death not ever being a real thing in games.
There's an indie game, I don't know if you've heard of it, I can't remember the name of
it for the life of me so anybody here totally help me out.
Someone will know.
It's an indie game where you download it to your PC and literally you just have one chance
at it.
One life to live, thank you.
Yeah, no, I mean, amazing.
I mean, yeah, if I could have come up with that,
then I wouldn't have been standing up here
looking like an idiot for the last hour.
So, I mean, I think that's fantastic work.
But I think it's interesting how abstracted that is.
I mean, it's what gives it its power,
but also how unplayable.
I mean, it's interesting.
I've never been brave enough.
Have you been brave enough?
I've never actually let it taken that risk.
I mean, so this is it.
So this is kind of where I am.
I think there's a ton of interesting stuff to do here and I think everybody here is in
the middle of doing it.
And I just like giving kind of progress updates.
Thank you.
Thank you for the amazing talk.
And we're out of time, so I have to stop, but grab me if you have anything more.
And thank you very much for coming.