We made it here.
OK, so I'm supposed to ask you guys to silence
any noisemakers you have and to tell you
that you're going to be getting an email to rate this session.
And am I supposed to ask them to move in, scooch in also?
Does that sound right?
Like, toward the center?
Do whatever you want.
You know?
Eh, that's what I do.
Back in 1981, doesn't seem like that long ago,
but I was in my apartment in Berkeley
and I was playing this game on my Apple II.
a dungeon adventure, first-person adventure.
And I'm just sitting there,
and I'm staring down these corridors.
They're not really corridors,
they're just white lines plotted
on this default black background,
but it was like I was there.
And I'm looking down this corridor,
looking, trying to figure out what's ahead,
like something's gonna jump out at me.
And I would spend long nights there
with my list of spells ready to go, typing them in.
Drawn from perspective, I can remember hardly sleeping for days up all night,
staring there, trying to figure out where I was going next.
There wasn't anything to see.
Basic sort of a game written in Pascal, higher level language, on an Apple II.
So it was really clunky and slow, but it was real for me.
That's my experience.
Seems unbelievable today when we think back on something like that.
In a gaming industry.
and a motion picture industry that's so wrapped up in computer-generated realism,
the graphics are so vivid today,
where graphical complexity, it seems to me, is sort of taking over things.
and is more central sometimes in the content behind it,
which back in these old times was all that the games really were about.
And you'd think that the graphical realism in movies and in games
would draw us in powerfully, but sometimes they don't today.
It's not always the case.
But it was out of those nights in my apartment back in 1981, 1982
that The Bard's Tale came to be,
because I saw a lot of possibility in this game in Wizardry.
in uh all right
I wanted to experience more as I was playing this game.
I'm looking down these corridors and I'm thinking,
I have so many ideas for things I want to do in this game
that I can't do.
And that's where Bard's Tale really came like.
I wanted people to surpass the limits.
I wanted to surpass the limits in the game.
I wanted to go through walls.
You know, I wanted to do more things
than were in the game.
And that started, my experiences in Wizardry
gave rise to this idea that I had
about something more powerful and more vivid.
People have written me over the last 30 years and tracked me down at different points and found me and said,
I want to tell you this game changed my life.
It's weird to hear that, you know, thinking about putting this together when I was a young guy.
Many people have told me that.
They didn't just tell me it was fun for them or whatever,
but there was something life-changing about the game for them.
And you've probably had that kind of experience at some point in your life
where you've seen a movie or read a book or something and it...
and it changed your life in some way,
where you didn't feel like you were just wasting your time
playing it or, you know, like how you watch tons of TV
and then later you think,
man, I just wasted all that time,
I feel horrible right now.
But sometimes there are experiences
that come from things like this that change us.
and you get something from it for yourself.
And we don't see it a lot.
And we have movies today that have these amazing effects
and no soul, and it leaves me with questions.
It probably leaves you with questions.
Like why couldn't Lucas replicate the success
of the first three movies in the next three
with all the extra money and technology
yet available to him?
What happened in there?
And even the ones that are being made today
sort of leave me cold.
It's not the same experience anymore.
Well, I'm going to take you on a little journey through my experience on Bard's Tale,
and part of my goal in this session is to give you a hint as to what I think one of the answers to that might be.
I don't want to oversimplify it, but I want to give you a clue and hopefully inspire a vision in your mind,
if you're a game designer or creator, maybe to avoid some of that and end up with something that's not just a game,
but something that's an experience that impacts people's lives,
which is something you have control over.
So first I'm going to cover some history about this and then I'm going to cover some philosophy,
some of my philosophy behind design and I'm going to even throw in a little bit of theology
but just a little bit.
So before I knew anything about coding, I was designing Dungeons and Dungeons and Dragons,
which is where Bard's Tale started.
It started, you know, sort of Game Top playing.
And I was in high school, and they tried to launch a Dungeons and Dragons club in high
school, and I showed up.
That's me, and I made the yearbook shot.
I show up, but it was being run by these nerds.
This was the problem.
And when I say that, please understand, I was a nerd.
but these guys have like paper mache armor on
crowns made from you know uh... construction paper and things like that
they weren't serious about the game
so i ended up uh... making the yearbook but i ended up leaving the leaving the
club after that
but but my name got around a little bit because of that and so i was walking
on the quad of our high school in these two guys walk up to me
in letterman jackets
and their their football players normally i was startled they walk up to
me because i was like one of these invisible guys in high school right that
that normally does like this would not talk to you
and they walked up and talk to me and they said hey we hear that you put
dungeons together
uh... we play dungeons and raggeds would you like to take us
through a dungeon
and i'm like sure
uh... i was uh... blown away and uh... these two guys their names were at one
was john perry and the other guys name was brian fargo
now brian you know it's funny cuz he talks about himself as being a nerd
sometimes back from this time is brian here
right now he did he make it to this uh...
uh... he's here but i he's busy this week
uh... he
he talks about himself being a nerd but you know something he was a super popular
kid
in uh... in high school he was a track star at our high school and he played
football
uh... but uh... but he played Dungeons and Dragons and uh... some of the other
guys on the football team did and so i ended up taking these guys through some
dungeons
at that time which was really awesome for me
because uh... i got invited to all these great parties that brian would throw at
his house at his parents house his parents through these outrageous parties
for high school students
and I ended up getting invited to those,
and it was, which was really awesome.
And it was one of the greatest things about Brian
is though he had this nerdy friend,
like he didn't care at all,
and just absolutely never,
Brian's never cared about what anybody thinks about anything
and it was one of the great things
that made him such a great friend.
And I ended up having the benefit of that
and getting to talk to some real girls,
which was the first time in my life that it ever happened.
But I was an artist. That was kind of my thing at this time.
And I drew these line art, kind of comic book style illustrations.
It was my hobby.
And what I would do is I'd illustrate these dungeons.
So I'd actually, all the major rooms that you'd go into,
I'd have a pretty elaborate illustration for it.
and the illustrations would contain clues and puzzle pieces to the adventure.
And I would write it kind of in a way it was more of a script, more like a book story.
It wasn't like a lot of the stuff that the campaigns of the creators of Dungeons & Dragons were coming out with at that time.
So these guys really liked the dungeons, you know, and they'd be studying the illustrations trying to figure out,
you know, how I was going to kill their guys or whatever.
and uh... you know but i i get a lot of magical items i didn't really follow the
rules for doing this thing correctly but uh... the guys always had a great time
playing my games and i get to hang out with these guys and we got to sergeant
pepperoni's pizza parlor
and they have stand-up arcade games in the back
and missile command asteroids
uh... space invaders these kind of things and uh... me and and brian and
some of these other guys and we play these games all the time and and that
really was the gaming industry at that point there was nothing else at that
stage
Those right about that time, Brian's parents bought him an Apple 2 computer.
And I remember going over to his house and walking in,
I'm looking at this thing and he's trying to explain to me what it is.
Because at first, it's, I don't get it.
And I'm starting to wrap my mind around it as he's talking about it.
And he's showing me this interface for basic programming.
And I'm like, wait a minute, can you play games on this?
And he says, yeah, actually, there's a couple games out.
And so I sit down, and he's showing me some basic
programming right there.
And so he and I end up developing a game together.
He and I were both coding it.
There in his parents' house, we started writing a game
called Labyrinth of Mardagon.
It was a text-based adventure written in BASIC.
And I drew the cover.
And we got it printed up at a good friend of mine's dad owned a civil engineering firm
and he's actually sitting here in the front row from high school.
And he printed up copies for us and Brian and I took this around, Paragon Gaming.
We took this around and distributed it at a bunch of computer stores in Orange County.
and actually thought we were doing real game development with this.
But it's a crackup.
He sent me that picture a number of years ago,
just thinking back on these days.
But this is where it all started, in my relationship
with Brian in high school and doing some gaming.
We had no idea how to do graphics at this point.
It was just completely beyond us.
But I was really interested, and I had a knack for development.
And just the way the computer worked,
it made perfect intuitive sense for me.
I've always kind of had both right and left brain things going on.
So I really got into it, and also creatively into it.
And so by the time I graduated from high school,
I could develop in 6502 assembly language.
and i was writing full video games uh... like platform games and ships moving
around and
things like that sound effects i'd i'd done that
so then i was up in northern california went up to berkeley to study
architecture
because i was trying to find some sensible career connected to my uh...
illustration
but i uh... i spent all my time programming
and writing games and that led me to late evenings playing wizardry and just
blowing off my classes
and as I was playing wizardry I kept thinking I could do something so much
better than this because for one I could write it in assembly language
and it would be uh... you know so much faster and more powerful than what I was
getting from wizardry
I mean you could actually see the lines plot like it was so slow
and I knew that I could at least you know do that instantly in writing it
So I wrote the code to do the front-facing 3D view that Wizardry had.
That was sort of my first move, where you take a matrix of numbers that represent places on this dungeon floor,
with numbers representing each of the doors and things like that,
and then it got translated into this first-person view, you know, drawn.
sort of in perspective, not really, but
but giving you that sense of actually standing there. I had that going where I
could walk around a dungeon.
That was the first thing that I did. So then I called Broderbund Software,
which was up also in the Bay Area, and I called and I said I wanted to come in
and show them a prototype for a game.
Now at this point I'm delivering pizzas in North Oakland, okay, so it was kind of an
interesting and sketchy thing for me to do. That's what I was doing.
So I was really kind of hoping maybe I could do some game development.
So I went up to Broderbund and I brought this prototype,
which just really was this movement piece,
and demoed it for a guy that turns out was the president of the company.
uh... it had no other game action on this prototype it was just this movement
thing and i'm just describing to this guy all my ideas for what this could be
so much greater than wizardry is and then when the three
and and and i was about a ten minute demo because you know it's just that
piece of it so it was very interesting
and the guys is looking at it with a blanket expression on his face i don't
remember his name
uh... but i he he was looking at will blank expression on his face
and then after my demos done i'd get a forty five minute lecture from him on
what a real game is
and what makes it fun and i find out i'm a stupid kid
uh... who doesn't know what he's doing and i get kicked out of the office
back to delivering pizzas
but i'm sitting in the back of a shakespeare class of this big lecture
hall at berkeley
bored out of my mind
i'm in the back row
and i'm looking reading the daily cal the school newspaper there's an ad in
there for video game programmers people who get they were looking for students
who develop in sixty five with two assembly language to do some video game
development i'm reading this out of my this is what i do
so i contact the guy and it turns out that a company that was in south san
francisco called has where was was
opening an office in berkeley cuz they were trying to find some developers
people who knew how to do the sort of thing there were a lot of people didn't
even knew how to do it
and they thought they could find some by the campus.
And I went in, I called the guy and I said,
do you have an Apple? I'll come in and demo.
I got an arcade game I can demo for you that's fully functional.
And he says, no, I don't even have an Apple here,
I have a VIC-20 or something.
And he says, I'm going to get an Apple in here.
I'll go, I'll bring my Apple in.
So I put it in a suitcase and I didn't have a car,
so I had to get on a bus and take a bus downtown.
Because I was mostly riding my bike back and forth from my, where I was living to school,
but I couldn't, you know, ride a bike with this, you know, I don't know, it was pretty
heavy all this stuff.
So I ended up going down and setting it up, plugging it into his monitor and demoing my
game for him and I got hired on the spot.
And I did that part-time for a semester and then I'm realizing I do not want to be an
architect, I want to do this, and so I bailed out on school and I ended up working there
full-time.
And I ended up doing a bunch of platform games for them, a lot of conversions, you know,
Donkey Kong for the Apple, and Super Zaxxon, and things like that for the Commodore 64.
But I had a concept for this game, and I already had this prototype built, so I said to him,
listen, could I do a wizardry game for the Commodore 64?
He goes, well, all the titles we're doing right now are cartridge titles.
We're not doing any floppy disk-based titles.
So if you could get it into a 16K cartridge,
then yes, we'd be interested in that.
Okay, 16K.
Like, your emails are bigger than that, right?
16K.
So I'm like, yeah, no problem.
So I started working on this thing,
and I did a product for them, which was called Mazemaster.
So this is sort of the next step in the evolution of Bard's Tale.
This was 16k and it was in fact a very stripped down, minimalistic version of what would later
become Bard's Tale with wireframe lines for the corridors and then a few party members
and some simple spell casting.
So I developed this, it was, you know, obviously graphically pretty primitive,
but notice how I made the window so much bigger than Wizardry's for the corridor,
as though that would matter.
But, you know, to me it was like, see, I'm even more, like, in that corridor now.
And, anyway, so this came out, and I was at CES after this was released,
and I'm standing in the HESware booth.
uh... you know my game my title all the titles around and i happen to be
standing there in the sales people don't know who i am
is a very weird company people that were running it did not know what they're
doing but i'm standing there in a sales person's and a distributor comes up
and walks right over my time is is what's this i'm really interested
and the distributor says now you do you you don't want to get that come over
coming to show you this you know arcade game we have
andy lee the distributor away and i'm like what is going on with these people
but that company was out of business like two years later
So I continued working there and then I ended up in Southern California again hanging out with my parents
Wondering what I was going to do next and I ended up getting a call from Brian Fargo who at that time had
broken off from another company he was working for that had a couple different
interests but one of the things they were doing was making games
and he had broken off and taken the programmers with them and started his
own company
Interplay Productions. So he said, hey, what are you up to? I go, well I'm, you
know, doing some work up in Northern California. I was actually doing a
project for a company in San Jose right then, but I was just independent
and he said, why don't you come down and work for me down here? And I said, okay.
So I ended up...
Moving back down, Southern California, which is where I was from originally,
takes me kind of away from the game industry, but
gave me this opportunity to be close to my folks again,
and also to work on some stuff with Brian.
But I had this on the back burner, I had the whole barge tail thing on the back burner.
and I really wanted to just get to that,
but I needed also, you know, make a living.
So I was doing some conversions for Brian,
and I don't remember what he had me working on at first,
but it was really boring.
Something like educational product of some kind,
and I was really bored out of my mind.
So I finally thought, you know something,
I really wanna work on my game.
So I'm going to partner with Brian in this, because he's my buddy.
So I said, OK, Brian, I've got a game concept,
and I've got a prototype built.
And it was further along at that point.
So there were actually, there was text,
there were some characters that were being printed.
And I'd done some work replacing these 3D wireframes with bitmaps.
I'm one day I was just staring at these wireframes and I'm realizing wait a minute
I'm looking at the graph paper these things fall in these you know discrete rectangles
I could just stitch together some bitmaps and probably get something more realistic looking
Which was what my interest was because I wanted to put I wanted to be in the corridor
You know and and to the degree that the interface wasn't real looking it was sort of not transparent
It wasn't allowing me to sort of enter into the adventure
So I thought if I can make it more realistic I can I can realize this goal that I had
And so that's what I did.
I ended up building this prototype,
and then I gave it to him,
and I showed it to him, and he was excited about it.
He says, yes, let's do this.
And he took it, and we actually had a CES right after that,
and he took it and showed it to Electronic Arts,
and they were fired up about it.
So then I ended up being able to work on my own product
at that point, and Bard's Tale began.
I don't know what to say about it.
So here's me at Interplay with the guys
that were part of the company at that time, that was it.
And we were in this little business complex in Irvine,
just like all of us in kind of about the 18 to 22, 23 range
starting Interplay off.
But it was a lot of fun.
It was a great time actually in my life hanging out.
And I was back down in Southern California,
which was great.
So I kept working all those years on a bigger concept for my game.
And one of the things I'd come up with as I was up in Berkeley
working on the prototype for this game was this idea of having seven different spellcasting classes.
I really like magic. I was really bored by melee combat.
Wasn't interesting to me.
And I didn't understand, I mean, why couldn't you cast spells and also hold a sword?
I mean, how hard can that really be?
And I'm picturing, you know, I'm picturing Lord of the Rings and Gandalf with the sword anyway.
I'm like, what's up with this? Why do we have to have this class differentiation?
Because I would expect to be able to do both things if it was me.
And that was the whole idea, was me being, you know, in the adventure.
That was my conception. That's the whole way I look at gaming.
So I think, no, I can learn how to swing a sword as I'm developing as a spellcaster.
So I ended up with this idea of seven different spellcasting classes,
seven different magical disciplines,
and I started generating lists of spells for those disciplines.
And I had this idea of mastering all of them,
so you could actually go from one class to another class
once you mastered it until you mastered all of them,
and then you'd become the archmage, the master of the seven magics.
And I was thinking, maybe I'll even call it that.
That was my idea at the time.
Um...
Melee was just a backup thing for me, you know, if your spell points run out, then you gotta, you know, use a sword or something like that.
So there was this enormously long list of spells at this point that I'd written down.
But the ideas behind the spells were suggesting ideas for the game, because I'm thinking, okay, one of the classes is conjuring.
So this person, you know, conjures things. So there was...
So I'm like, okay, so then you need a way to have conjured things in your party fighting for you.
So this whole concept of conjuring and then...
mind controlling and bringing things, I'd never heard of anything like this, but I'm thinking,
but of course, I would need that, so then I'd need monsters that were able to function
autonomously, but still be part of your party, so I'd need a slot
for them in your list of characters so that they could do that. So these were some
of the concepts that I was putting together, which I hadn't seen before
in a game, but they just intuitively came out of the ideas, just, and
my background and interest in all the different spellcasting classes.
And design's like that, you know, isn't it like that?
Where one idea leads you to another idea,
where you have a great idea and then you think of
a really amazing way to implement it in the game.
You don't necessarily jump to the perfect idea
from the beginning.
Sometimes you have to start with a kernel idea like that.
and then it just stimulates creativity.
It's like adding spells with duration.
So I had a light spell and I'm thinking,
okay, Wizardry's got no animation,
but I'm doing all this video game development,
I can make a flickering torch appear
when your light spell's going.
I think that would look cool.
But then I'm realizing I could make a lot of spells that last over time,
that have a certain function and are also represented graphically by some kind of icon.
Because now I've got a section of the screen where this, you know, torch thing is gonna appear,
so then what else am I gonna put over here?
So then I'm starting to think about other kinds of spells.
Like, what if there's a compass that actually appears and turns?
Then you're actually— it's not only, you know, serving a function,
but there's a reason for it being a graphical icon on the screen.
And then I'm thinking, what about other spells that just hang around and protect you and do things?
And I'm like, this is exactly what I need.
So I started developing a lot of ideas that just started rolling out that way
and becoming sort of core elements.
And then if you have a torch and you have a compass, then you've got to,
well, then I have to have a way to mess those up.
So then a room where your torch gets put out,
or a room that you walk into and you get spun around.
So if you don't have the compass,
then you're going to get lost.
Or then I thought, what about a room where your torch goes out
and you get spun around?
And then I got hate mail over that idea.
Anyway, every limitation in wizardry was like that.
How do I get beyond this?
I want to go through this wall.
I want to teleport.
You know, what is four spaces over?
I want to be there.
And magic is like that.
Magic is a way to extend yourself in ways
that shouldn't be possible.
It was the core of my thinking and my design, surpassing what you are, becoming something more,
was all about my design process.
Though I wasn't really thinking too hard about it at the point.
It was more like, hey, what do I want to do?
I want to be greater.
I want to be powerful.
I want to be immortal and unbeatable.
That was the idea.
And so I wanted a game where I could be.
and I wanted to develop a game where you could be.
That was the idea.
And I also had ideas about graphical complexity
and smooth movement and some of those things
that were coming out of this.
Clear differentiators from wizardry,
just really surpassing the limits.
and uh... uh... so after started in a play you know and uh... and started
working with brian
i realize i came to realize that seven mage classes wasn't gonna go
that that was a little over the top and then i i had this concept also for a
barred
and the reason that happened was again it was sort of this chain uh... reaction
of ideas
i i had we had background music running in some of these video conversions when
i was at house where no and a buddy of mine larry holland
was was a musician was really good at this
and uh... and had come up with a really good way using the screen interrupt on
an apple because that's really the only interrupt there was an apple to was the
screen
raster interrupt that would happen
and and for a tickling the uh...
the the the speaker a little bit at on these intervals
and causing certain tones to appear out of the speaker was really fascinating
uh... and so coming up with a way to do that so you could have
music running in the background on an apple to which which was very rare
seeing something like that
So I thought, I definitely want that effect in Bard's Tale,
but then I thought, well if I have music running, why not tie it to this idea of spells with a duration
and make the music itself part of, make it a spell effect,
that it's accompanying a spell effect the same way the icons are accompanying a spell effect,
and then maybe even making the tone of the music sound like the kind of spell that you're wanting to cast.
So, because I had a bard and he wasn't one of the seven spellcasters, it sort of obviated
the need for all these spellcaster classes, so I ended up cutting it back.
I can't remember if I was told to cut it back or if that was my idea, but I ended up cutting
it back to four classes, which meant I had a ton of extra spells I didn't need, so I
was able to pick the ones I really wanted.
And then the idea still, though, of mastering the four classes,
the archmage still was an idea that was in there,
and it became sort of the central idea in Bard's Tale 2,
and got its own spell, sort of a reward for exceeding all the limits of time and space, you know?
If you can get to that point, then you get even more power, sort of ultimate,
which is what I wanted.
Right? It's what we all want.
An existence without limits.
So as the project went along, there was a lot of tension on the bard character,
it turned out, which I wasn't expecting at first, I'm going to tell you.
But the idea of the music in the background, that was at that time,
because it was technologically difficult for the Apple,
it was actually easy for the Commodore 64, but difficult for the Apple,
it was unique.
So when people saw it, it was surprising to them that it was tied to gameplay.
But the idea to make it a central component and name the game after it was not my idea.
Electronic Arts had kind of pushed a consultant on us
who had a background in RPG game development, but not computer game development.
But he was sort of pushed on us with a bunch of ideas and his ideas were so horrible
I can't even tell you and I'd like to tell you a story about it but I'm not gonna have time to get through it.
But he did name the game, he originally named it Tales of the Scarlet Bard
and it was just so wordy that it eventually got chopped down to Bard's Tale
and he also named the city of Skara Brae.
And those are the actual only two things he named in the game
and really the only two good ideas he had, I felt, at the time and Brian felt the same way.
There were no cursed items. I don't put cursed items in my games because I don't like cursed items.
I like items that do something for you.
This is a game. This is the way I look at it. I make it fun.
Realism is only helpful to the degree that it draws you in.
If it pisses you off, then it becomes less transparent.
This is the way I looked at it.
So if there's something in the games that piss you off,
it's not that they didn't piss me off,
otherwise I would have taken them out.
And that's the way I look at it.
You want to make it fun and also, you know,
to keep it transparent.
I don't want people thinking about an interface
in a game that I'm building.
I want them to think of,
I want them to see themselves in the game.
But I want to build in limits in the game so that I can then give the player tools to surpass them.
So I make it so that once you cast spells, your spell points aren't restored while you're in the dungeon.
You have to leave the dungeon to get them restored.
Just so that I can then provide a magical item.
the mage's staff that allows you to regain your spell points while you're in the dungeon.
So I'm creating boundaries and limits so that I can create a way for you to surpass them
in the game because there's an experience that comes with that that I want people to
have.
And I also build the game, I build all the stuff I work on, on a familiar mythos,
which is the same thing Tolkien did when he wrote his books.
He built The Lord of the Rings on a mythos that was very familiar to the people of England of his time.
So a lot of the imagery in it really was very English, the way that he tied it in.
It wasn't some other totally different mythos, it was very familiar to them.
And I wanted to do that also, I wanted to leverage a lot of what he did.
And certain fantasy books that were favorites of mine at that point were formative in some
of the ideas that I put into it.
I don't build games on alternative religious mythos like Hindu gods because I feel like it's
It distances people from the content because that's not as familiar content for people.
It's ideas, it's creative, but it's not a connection.
I want to connect people to the content in some way that's familiar to them,
and then I surprise them with something on top of that.
I'm looking for bridges in what I build.
So I want to build a mythos that is familiar to people.
when I design things. Bard's Tale 2 also include time puzzles, which were, because I wanted
something more real-time involved. If I could have kept going with all this, it would have
ultimately become very real-time or all real-time, because I would feel like that would be more
representative of reality. So, somehow to combine both turn-based combat, which was
the only practical thing that way i could see the solvent at the time
with something real time was what i was trying to surreal time puzzles a real
time snares we have to actually react you can't just sit there monsters will
eventually appear and kill you
if you walk away make a sandwich or something like that
always how can this more closely simulate reality but not only to
irritate people but in a way to draw them into
And these kind of background processes were possible
because I was writing in assembly language,
unlike wizardry, which was written in Pascal.
so i was uh... out and i was just playing barstow for i want to say
something about that the barrows deep which is uh... is coming out later this
year and i just want to say uh... i'm really excited because i'm seeing a lot
of the same kind of elements and what the guys are doing on this project i'm
not directly involved in the project
i'm just a kind of experiencing at the same way all of you guys will
uh... but at the game in the puzzle elements of the kinds of things that i
would have seen
Bard's Tale eventually reaching if I've been working on it.
So I'm really excited about what they're doing.
And I'm also seeing a big connection to the Mage's Tale,
which is the VR adventure that they put together,
which I'm going to kind of conclude the talk mentioning briefly,
which I really enjoy.
And I'm seeing in these games a real continuity
between the stuff that was built originally.
Bard's Tale 2 was built on this character idea that was my focus, the Archmage.
Really kind of the idea I had from the beginning.
I wanted everything to be about this idea of mastering all these magics.
Because you don't just master the magics in Bard's Tale 2, you become something more.
More even than an Archmage, you become the Destiny Knight in that idea.
This idea of assembling pieces of a wand to achieve this ultimate existence in the game.
Here I've had all kinds of screens.
I didn't talk about those.
I want to debunk a couple of myths that have popped up over the years about Bard's Tale as part of this,
because there's some things said.
uh... rebecca heinemann has made a number of statements about uh... barge
tail in the history of barge tail over the years i i normally i was tell you
don't pay much attention to these things
but uh... they they have been appointed out to me especially recently knowing
that i'm gonna be here
so i'm not i'm a clear up a couple things
about that and I'll say something about Rebecca and with no offense intended about this, but
I need to set this straight. The idea that Bard's Tale 2 was originally going to be called
the Archmage's Tale is not true.
The Destiny Knight was always the idea I had.
It was really sort of an idea I had from the beginning.
Even when I was working on the Bard's Tale,
it was sort of behind the idea of Archmage.
But the Archmage itself, the name Archmage, was never the idea.
It was always going to be this ultimate hero class
that emerged out of that idea.
It was always going to be the Destiny Knight.
There was no one that was talking to me about the design of these games
or what I had to do or didn't have to do.
Brian gave me pretty much carte blanche on the game concept.
So I did what I wanted to do on it.
So if there's anything you don't like about the design of Bard's Tale 2,
which there are a number of things that have been told to me over the years
about how incredibly difficult it was to solve certain parts of the game,
then that's just my fault.
And maybe, you know, a little bit because we didn't playtest it
as extensively as we could for difficulty level.
uh... but it was never going to be called the archmages tale i've never
heard of that before when i was never discussed
i'm also aware that i would be it's been said that
there there was a that uh... rebecca said she had a discussion with me
at some point back then that
uh... and i was asked why i didn't
add female character options into Bard's Tale and allegedly my response was
that girls don't play these games.
So this has been said. I was just told about this.
Okay, that conversation never happened.
And let me just explain to you a little bit about this.
Rebecca was back then Bill Heineman and so Bill at that time, so I'm just speaking historically
now, Bill was a very colorful character in the office.
Bill was, he was almost like a sitcom character, you know, kind of like, I don't know if I'm
if you guys are, most of you are older, like a latke on taxi.
You know what I mean?
He was a comedic kind of guy that we all liked,
but he had a kind of extreme personality.
And he was in the back corner, we called him Burger Bill.
And he would start the week out by going to McDonald's
and buying a ton of burgers and then storing them in his desk
and just pulling them out through the week and eating them.
It was like that.
he he he would do a lot of really peculiar things that will what made us
laugh and
uh... he was uh... he wasn't and my understanding from brian at the time was
he was even put on on full-scale projects because
he he had difficulty completing them
and would it would do what brian would call shut down
which is sometimes when pressure was from he would just spontaneously like
take a nap like uh... read it as best and then we sneak in
turns monitor upside down and things like that
uh... to kind of mess with them a little bit we are
I really liked him, but I never had a serious conversation with Rebecca, who was at that
time Bill, at any point when we were there.
If I'd had a conversation about female characters, I would have been messing around with him
at the time and certainly not having a serious conversation.
It's funny.
I was looking around and I found some artwork of mine.
from that time frame, from a couple years actually before the Bard's Tale was done and I pulled it out.
And you know, I have almost as many illustrations that I was drawing of women
with swords and casting spells that I was drawing at that time as men.
So it's certainly not the case that I didn't envision women as characters
or as girls as playing games and wanting...
avatars that were in the game on that level or that I was insensitive to gender issues with respect to the game.
Gender issues are, and you know as I say this, I'm like at this moment
I can tell you that my daughter is right now almost certainly at home playing Fortnite right now. My kids are all gamers.
So this idea that I just don't picture that is just not true. I've never had that thought.
uh... that uh... women wouldn't be playing games like the kind of games
i've done and as i went out and eventually was would do signings and
things that there were girls that came up
uh... who had me autographed their games so
i never had the experience differently and uh... i wouldn't envision it that
way actually most of the things i work on even some of the things i'm working
on right now
which i'll mention that briefly at the end uh...
uh... it's true sort of gender irrelevant and that the things
i'm i'm all this i'm doing a couple i'm doing some voice interactive role
playing games for the amazon all exotherapy it's fully voice activated
free-to-play kind of things for amazon
i just had a kids game wizard of oz that it was a finalist in an amazon
competition
i've done a fully interactive uh... role-playing game voice activated role
playing game of combat
called Shadow Realm, which is also free to play on the Amazon Alexa.
So I've been doing this sort of thing, and you know, you can play the...
It's role-playing from any perspective. There's nothing gender-specific about it.
So I wouldn't think in those terms.
So this is kind of where I've come from and my background,
and I never had that conversation.
Another deal is the story about Brian and my falling out back in this time frame.
Brian and I had a big falling out right about the time that Barge Tale was being completed
into the development of Barge Tale 2.
Brian and I never had a formal agreement for Barge Tale and what my compensation was going to be.
I just talked to him about being partners in it. He said, sounds good.
And I had a certain thought in my mind about what that meant.
And he had a different thought in his mind.
so as bar still was getting wrapped up on finally like hey i'm what's the deal
on the money on this
and he said oh yeah yeah i'm gonna have my attorney draw something up and i'll
show it to you
so i eventually got handed about that time in agreement and i looked at it and
it wasn't what i was expecting
So I thought, okay, what do I do with this?
And I got advised to hire an attorney to do this.
Well, my parents had an attorney for their business.
They were going through some legal things.
So I got this guy to represent me in this,
and he jumped into this.
And from there, the entire process of negotiation
started going wrong, okay?
And if you've had any experience with attorneys,
you know that it's in their best interest for that to happen but i don't
know this i'm twenty two years old so and this guy's coming back he's meeting
with brian's attorneys coming back in the same
these guys are dragging this out there really being negative they're not gonna
work with us on this you know we're gonna end up in court
uh... they're missing all their deadlines
and i and i and i'm i'm still working on barge till two now
and i'm talking to brian and he's like i do this is not happening
but i'm talking to my attorneys like nope nope they're lying to you so i'm
like what's going on here and you know brian was my friend but i'm like i am
i'm really worried that i'm gonna get screwed
so as time was going i was developing barstow to this thing dragged on and we
were out of the year in back and forth on the contract but there were massive
delays were supposedly they weren't being responsive my attorneys telling me
and brian saying it's not it's not happening
so what happens is eventually we get it worked out
But apparently, I didn't turn over the source code in Bard's Tale 1 until we had the signed agreement.
Now, I don't specifically remember that, just to be honest with you.
I don't think it was that big a deal at the time.
It certainly wasn't to me.
But I can tell you that many times as a developer, I have withheld work product before I'm paid.
And I've had to do that at different points as a developer.
So it doesn't seem unusual that I would have done that here,
where I would have said, I'll hand it.
Because I think they needed the source code so that they could
start working on the PC version.
And I was probably saying, we need to wrap this agreement up
before I turn it over.
I'm just guessing, because I really don't remember.
But that wouldn't seem strange to me if I did that, because I
felt like I had a commitment for our
agreement to get wrapped up.
But it wasn't the case that anybody was being extorted for something that wasn't due or
something like that.
It would have only been that, not like some massive negative thing.
But I'm not sure exactly.
But there was nothing else about it.
And I can tell you that...
uh... rebecca at that point was so peripheral to everything help happening
at the at the company and completely peripheral to bard's tale
that she wouldn't have known anything about any of that except what brian
might have mentioned
at that point but really again at the margins of of the company and
and and not involved in barcelo at all until i left
and then uh... and then was involved in barstow three and after that point i
can't really say what her involvement was in the degree to which he was
involved but she had all my source code going into barstow three so
uh... they they're what they had a major running start at that point
anyway what happened was after this brian and my falling out i would i was
kind of uh... you know we worked out a deal we we i don't think either was
really like the deal we ended up with either of us was really thinking it was
what we expected but that's what it was
and then at about five years later
i get a call from my mom and she says
You're not going to believe what our attorney's done to us.
And I'm like, what are you talking about?
She says, we've been going through this two-year-long
negotiation process with this other company.
And our attorney's been telling us the whole way that
they've been dragging it out, and they're acting in bad
faith, and the other side's been telling us we're not
doing any of this stuff.
She goes, it turns out the attorney was lying the entire
way, like he's pathological.
And I'm like, Mom, this is the attorney that you referred me to for the whole barge tail thing.
And she's like, Oh yeah, he's crazy. And I'm like, Oh my gosh.
So I'm like, oh, all of a sudden I'm thinking back on everything that happened and realizing this guy
wrecked my relationship with Brian. I ended up writing a long letter to Brian at that point,
apologizing to him for this and saying, Man, I'm so sorry. I should have listened to you,
should have trusted you.
but this guy really had made me afraid.
And plus I was a kid, not a good communicator myself at that point.
So anyway, so Brian and I worked that out
and we've had a positive relationship ever since that point
and that resolved everything with us.
It was okay though because the break,
you know, I have no idea how many more titles
we'd have gone on and done together.
If that hadn't happened,
we probably would have done quite a few more.
But it was okay because I really wanted to go back to school
and I was already taking class,
I transferred my units down from Berkeley,
I was already taking classes at UCI in philosophy,
which is what I wanted to move into.
From designing systems to getting to the ideas
behind the systems, the ideas that motivate human behavior.
which led me into theology and then into a doctoral program in social ethics at USC,
where my research and writing was on ethics and technology.
So speaking of philosophy, let me say a couple things about philosophy,
which I've been hinting around about.
And this is really kind of where I want to take all this for you
in whatever my short time is left here.
But let me draw a picture for you.
Technology is rooted in our innate need to extend ourselves.
That's what all technology is about.
Our senses, our lives, our abilities to surpass limitations.
To become something more than we are as mere physical human beings.
That's how I view technology and the trajectory of technology.
It compresses space-time.
It allows us to be anywhere at any time,
to communicate with endless numbers of people,
to remove physical distance as a limitation.
to overcome all kinds of physical limitations.
That's why we use technology, to see beyond our natural vision and so on.
You can see the correspondence between magic and technology
if you think of technology in that way,
and consider it like that.
The idea behind them is the same,
and it's the thing that we yearn for
as human beings to exceed our limits,
and we build devices to make it possible.
Almost everything I've been saying about my approach to Barge Tale goes in that direction.
And my design's always been to offer people that kind of experience.
And I think that games and movies succeed and fail based on how well they deliver that kind of an experience.
really, whether they allow people to have the experience of exceeding their limits,
the experiences that are intrinsic to being human.
And this is one of them, this idea of becoming more than we are.
It's only one, but it's an important one.
And I can explain why I think it's a universal need based on a Christian worldview.
Now I'm not going to dive into theology, so if that doesn't sound good to you, you have
no fear.
Nor does it matter if you share that worldview or you think it's BS.
But there's a takeaway in this, which is interesting regardless in the process of game design and
what I've been telling you.
And as we look at so many movies, and maybe games,
I can't really say so much from that,
about storylines that don't meet our needs, that are failing,
that don't change our lives, that we forget almost
the moment we walk out of the theater, we feel like, wow,
I just wasted $18 and 2 and 1 1â„2 hours of my time.
There's something about all this that's
not obvious to designers today, whether they're game designers
or movie designers.
And there's been attention given to the fact that I named the cities in Bard's Tale 2 after biblical cities.
And that's come up and I've been asked about that at different points.
Kind of runs antithetical to my design philosophy, but I want to explain that.
As I was designing Bard's Tale 2, I came up with the main city name, Pangramain,
and then I had all these other cities that were going to be nodes in the game,
and I'm sitting there trying to think of names, cool names for the cities,
only I really had other stuff to work on.
I just started filling in the names of biblical cities that came to mind.
Because I'm thinking maybe some names of ancient cities like Scarabray,
but I don't know any except the ones that are in the New Testament.
So I started filling in those names. I left out two really obvious cities.
that would have been immediately recognizable and I used a bunch of the
others
and I knew someone was going, I thought someone was going to see that and point
it out and say you gotta take the Bible names out of this game
and come up with some fictitious names for cities but it never happened.
There were just placeholder names. Nobody ever noticed. Nobody ever commented on it.
Nobody ever said anything. I'm looking at the proofs for the
for the map. Nobody's ever saying anything to me. I'm kind of like really?
Nobody knows what these names represent.
It didn't seem like it.
Or maybe somebody did, but they thought it'd be funny to let it go by, I don't know.
So eventually I didn't.
It went through and then people later on figured it out.
And maybe like that response, not recognizing those cities,
maybe people are oblivious to the implications
of the Christian worldview with regard to game design,
of people wanting to become more than they are.
That's a central idea in the Christian worldview
of extending ourselves, of surpassing limits,
of becoming immortal and unbeatable.
This is at the core of the Christian worldview,
to reach a destiny
beyond what most people settle for.
Tolkien's world rested on that exact same worldview,
same assumptions I've made when I come to design,
not to explicitly put things in like these names
of the cities, but the ideas behind them
and what people want to be.
So even if you think, you know, you don't have a clue about, you know, this Christian thing,
his work was formative for a lot of what's happening at this conference. So,
it's worth thinking a little bit about something that was so central to his design.
But it's this assumption, this is Tolkien's assumption, is that you're intentionally
created, you're not an accident. If you're intentionally created, you were made to work
a certain way.
Like anything that's intentionally created you have a purpose and you have a certain kind of life built into you if that's true
That's what his assumption was if you live that life if you fulfill the thing
You're made to fulfill you have an experience of fulfillment
And if you do something different, you don't.
You have a train wreck on some level in your life.
That's his idea.
So Tolkien took that and created a mythos that had nothing explicitly to do with Christianity
but was based on those assumptions about who we are, what matters, and who we should become.
And every bit of Lord of the Rings rests on that idea, though there's nothing explicitly
in it.
If you look at the storyline, the characters don't directly relate to anything in our culture.
They don't make sense of our culture.
It's counter-cultural.
His characters are selfless.
They are sacrificial in the way they live.
They're not Western American individualist consumers.
That's not the characters of Lord of the Rings.
They are people that become what they should be, or people who intentionally...
diverge from what they should be.
That's his representation of evil in the book.
And I build games the same way, or at least that's my idea.
Nothing explicitly Christian,
except where I was kind of messing around
with those city names,
but offering people the things that the world view says
are at the center of being human.
And this idea of exceeding limits is one of those things.
We want it because we're intended for it.
And if you approach game design with that,
you have a hook automatically.
Whether you buy the worldview or not,
it is something that people yearn for.
Extending our senses.
It's what all of technology's about.
We wanna walk through walls.
We wanna cross infinite space
and be powerful beyond the circumstances of life.
That's why we love superhero movies.
We want to be immortal and unbeatable.
We want to be those things because we're intended
to have those things in our life.
That's the philosophy.
So here's the application for game design.
You can offer that experience virtually in a game.
just as you can, not as transparently. And by transparently I mean, with a movie theater,
there is that, there's not as much transparency. You don't project yourself into it the same
way that you do in a game, but you can offer it also in a movie, this experience of transcending
your limitations. So all I did in Bard's Tale was offer that to people in every way I possibly
could. It was one of the central ideas in the whole way I was approaching it.
and the whole ethos of the world was to deliver that kind of experience and make them fun
and also make them hard to acquire.
So this progress to becoming a destiny knight, something great, which is not something bizarre
or weird or sick or, you know, crazy, but something that you're supposed to be, that's
what I want to offer in a game.
You can offer people all kinds of unusual and bizarre things, but if you want to tap
into this sense that people have, you want to offer them the ability to become the best
of what they can be, this destiny, not an accident, it's something we want.
This idea that everything's an accident, nothing matters, and you're headed nowhere, that's not going to sell copies as you build it into a game.
Purpose, destiny, meaning, sacrifice. See, these things inspire people and pull them in.
You know, people want to grab the balrog and drag him into the abyss.
makes no sense of Western consumer culture,
why would you want to do that?
But people do want that.
And if you give them the opportunity to do that
in the context of a game,
maybe you'll be up here doing a post-mortem in 30 years.
Maybe.
Now, if you're hearing that idea, it might also be obvious that virtual reality is not
only an effective way to deliver the kind of experience I'm talking about, a transcendent
immersive experience, but it is the thing itself.
The medium's the message.
That's what virtual reality is.
It's inherently transcendent.
You inherently project yourself into the world that it creates.
It's as transparent almost as you can get, unless you mess it up with too much stuff.
And that's one of the ways in game design that we interfere with the transparency of the interface.
We make it too complicated.
The simpler it is, the more that people don't have to think about what they're doing,
the more you...
You draw them in and commit them to what's going on in the game.
And so VR is a technology that not only has the potential to engage people in this amazing way
and graphically interesting way, but to touch them at the core of who they are and what they need.
And I've been playing Mage's Tale this last, since it was released about six months ago or so.
All the elements I'm talking about are here.
I mean, this is to me really where Bard's Tale would have ended up.
That's the way I feel.
If I could have made anything or done anything, I think this is the kind of a game I would have ended up at.
Seamless. This chance for me to really be the Archmage.
Because if you're in the game, you are the Archmage.
Or at least you're taking a step in that direction as part of this game.
I can feel the game drawing me that.
Giving me this chance to be a hero as I'm standing there.
Or to be afraid, you know, as goblins are running up to me, you know, in the game.
Like I'm almost screaming the first time I'm playing the game.
uh... sitting in my apartment all those years ago staring down wireframe
corridors
you know wanting to be there and now i can
i've eight minutes
anything you want
uh... i'll make two questions if i can uh...
so
I recall years ago using sector editors to pump up the abilities of the characters in
Bard's Tale and I still could not finish the game.
I think it was probably the first time I ever cheated in a game and we cheated because we
couldn't do anything else.
Did you guys intentionally make it that difficult?
No, you know, well I think I did, because I think hard games are good games, but I never
intended the game to be so incredibly frustrating that people were pulling their hair out.
But you know how it is, if you're a developer, see I'm really much more a developer than
I'm a gamer.
I play it a little bit myself, but I know what I'm doing, right? I'm playing the game.
And we had play testers, and I wasn't getting feedback. Like, this game's way too hard. I didn't get that feedback.
So if I had, I would have changed it. That's all it was, I think. If I'd gotten the feedback...
I think I have a tendency to make things too hard, and I need to get feedback from people.
And I've had that experience. So the first time I did this Alexa game, I'm thinking,
these puzzles are so obvious, these riddles are so obvious, people are going to guess them right away.
And they don't. I'm getting emails from people like, you know, what is this thing?
And I'm having to give them clues to figure it out.
And I'm realizing, sometimes I think I may be jumping ahead a couple steps when I shouldn't.
So I think that was the problem. I think I thought this is going to be so fun for people.
And I made it unintentionally frustrating. And I just didn't get feedback.
It didn't make it any less enjoyable, I'll say that.
I was just wondering if that was an intentional issue or not.
No.
So the other question I would ask is, based on where
technology is today versus where it was when you were
starting out, you were saying that, hey, you went to your
friend's house, you saw the Apple II, you were able to,
and you had enough time that that had a
you know, long enough life cycle that you could see it, discover it, spend time learning
it and still be publishing games on it eight, nine years later. I don't think that's really
possible today, so what I'm wondering is from your perspective, you know, when you have
that, you see that opportunity or you have that idea, um...
What would you say you would recommend as far as like,
how do you balance or make the decision that,
hey, that's the thing I'm gonna make the investment in
in the hopes that it actually bears fruit
rather than, well, I'm gonna kind of sit on the fence
and hope that when it's time to hitch my wagon to that,
that there's still a market there.
Right. Yeah, it's a difficult thing. I had this problem. I waited too long on getting into PC development and stayed with 6502 development too long.
Yeah, I think it's really hard. I think it's a great career move to really think what's going next and how do I get myself up to speed on that.
Because, yeah, if you focus on the moment right now, the level of complexity to manage the kind of systems and engines and things that are out right now.
I think you'll always be catch up.
Never have the opportunity to come up with something
really leading edge and creative.
You need to think next step.
To me, next step is virtual reality.
I have no question that that's where
almost everything's gonna be.
I think the technology's gonna be
just exponentially increasing in time.
So if it was me and I was going back
into this kind of game development,
I'd be focused on that.
But I think you're absolutely right.
You have to almost think ahead,
like three steps ahead, or you get wiped out nowadays.
Completely different business nowadays than when I was in it.
No question.
Yes?
Hi.
I had a quick question as regards to the balance.
So earlier you were speaking about familiarity
of the mythos and how that is necessary.
I was wondering how you feel about the balance of that
versus the inclusivity or exclusivity that
might create to the folks who are just as
interested in that sort of thing.
But.
primarily want that experience of being better, but it's not, it doesn't look like them, it doesn't feel like them.
Well, yeah, I mean, that's a good point, because I want everybody to be drawn into my game.
So that would definitely be a consideration for me is,
yeah, am I keeping anybody from, like, feeling like I'm starting with an experience?
So maybe it's, it's, it's, it's, maybe it's shifting far enough away that it's not, like, identical to any one community.
But yeah, any sense that I'm keeping, any gender or perspective or ethnicity or community
or social economic bracket from enjoying my game, that would not be what I would want
to do.
I don't want to connect on a level that taps into those kind of differentiators.
So right, so it's fantasy enough that almost anybody could project themselves into it.
And I can think of a couple shows and things that have accomplished that.
So I would be sensitive to that, absolutely.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Yes.
What can you say about the burger Easter egg?
The burger what?
The burger Easter egg.
I'm sorry, the burger...
Burger Easter egg?
I don't know what that is.
Okay.
Sorry.
In one of the temples, it generates and spawns off a whole bunch of monsters.
Was that in my game?
I don't remember.
I'm sorry.
I've written 150 million lines of code since then, so forgive me.
Sorry.
Hi there, uh, yeah, first of all, thank you, because yeah, this was one of those games
that I felt was formative to me, but one of the things I was looking at is it feels to
me that there's somewhat cyclical ebb and flows over the, you know, twenty-something
years that I've been making games and kind of watching that, and...
When I was young, I played this game and Ultima 4 and found that there was a vast distance
between those two experiences and the stories they told and what's available now.
Do you find that it's kind of cyclical in that regard?
And when you look at games like that that are going into the marketplace, what are some
of the other themes that you thought would be interesting as those kind of come and go
in consumer interest?
Well, I can't say too much about the game industry.
Why am I talking into that?
I have a lovelier mic.
I can't say too much about the game industry specifically,
but I think that, like what I said,
I think that the emphasis on graphical realism
has skewed game design in a certain direction
and has drawn so much energy and interest
in a certain direction that I think that the elements
that made these games so powerful for people
are being neglected.
And a lot of people, again, don't know, like, how do I make a game interesting?
Let's just come up with a million things you can do in the game or something like that.
People aren't looking at it correctly.
Like, from the point, like, they should be thinking,
what experience do I want people to have and how do we give them that?
rather than how do I throw more graphics in or how do I give them more content or something like that.
It's not the amount and it's not the complexity.
It really is more the engagement.
And yeah, I think that that's just not in focus and I think it's more likely the issue nowadays.
And it's easy for people to make that mistake and I think that was Lucas's mistake, at least in part.
Uh, yep. Hi. Uh, first of all, thanks for making such a great game.
It sucked so many hours out of my childhood.
Uh, loved it. But, uh,
um, first of all, I didn't know that there were only male characters in Bard's Tale.
I didn't know a lot of my characters had female names, so, uh,
never knew that. Thanks for mentioning that.
But one thing I wanted to ask you was, what was it like back in the day when games were made by a programmer?
Compared to today, where we have teams around the world, and Agile, Scrum, Process Heavy, Test Development, like...
It was awesome. It was awesome.
being in sole control of the world is so awesome and fulfilling
and you know working with other people can be so frustrating
and uh... even today i'm kind of a lone wolf developer to tell you the truth
because uh... it i i i can get things done efficiently you know game
development was efficient back then and uh... because you know
but there wasn't there were there's too much
There's too much to do nowadays.
But back at that time, it was amazing and a great
experience.
And yeah, I'm drawing pictures.
I'm creating dungeon textures.
And I'm coming up with the storyline.
And I'm writing the code.
envisioning what version two is going to look like.
And it was a blast.
It was an amazing experience.
So I mean, I had help on the game.
I don't want to make it seem like I didn't.
I worked with artists and sound people.
But it wasn't like it is today, where there are huge teams.
It wasn't a cinematic production like it is today.
So I think that's one of the other factors that might make it harder to come up with a great game today,
is you've got so many different people that are involved.
And sometimes, you know, the best ideas are sort of that solitary inspiration
that may not make it through, you know, just by throwing... it's like a boy band, you know.
You can throw a lot of people together, it doesn't necessarily mean you're gonna end up with good music.
So sometimes it's just that one solo artist that pulls it off.
Yes.
Last one, I promise.
You spoke a lot about intentionality and the fact
that you made the game the way you wanted to feel.
And it was kind of like that sort of if we make it,
they will come type of experience.
And it is a great game.
I'm just wondering if you feel like with the industry becoming so big and so quickly, so rapidly,
if that ideology or that idea is being lost in a corporate sort of setting?
Or how do you, I'm just curious as to how you feel about where the direction that it is going.
Yeah, I think big companies kill all kinds of, you know, art.
So I think that's entirely a factor.
You know, there's so much money in this industry nowadays.
It just, it wasn't like that before.
So yeah, I think the pressures and tensions
are very different today.
And I think getting a good product out.
and getting something that's really life-changing
is a bigger challenge for companies.
They've gotta roll titles out,
they have to roll a certain number out,
they need to get a certain level of sales.
They get there thinking that's all about marketing
and a lot of times it's really no,
it's about impacting people with your product.
So, you know, same with the motion picture industry.
You know, that's why we see so many bad movies.
You don't just think, you sit there and just think,
wow, they put in so many millions of dollars and this is it?
You know, you think, what happened?
But it's that, it's an agenda, it's a corporate agenda and it can make getting artistic and really wonderful product out difficult.
Any suggestions as to something to say to those folks?
No, well, I mean, hopefully small indie game houses
have a working their way around that.
So I would think that'd be the solution to it.
So hopefully that's happening.
My son knows a lot more about the gaming industry nowadays
than I do.
But I'm hoping that that's sort of the way
that all this will be righted in the future.
All right, hey guys, thanks for coming.