Hello. I'm Scaff Elias. I'm here to talk about what video games can learn from collectible
card games. That's what CCG stands for. And first a little bit about who I am. I started
working on, in game design, on Magic the Gathering with Richard Garfield. We were classmates
at a university in Pennsylvania, in grad school there.
Eventually, over the years, I became senior vice president
at Watsi Hasbro throughout the years working on game design.
But sort of the unique perspective of the talk
is how business and design are intermixed
for this sort of certain class of games.
And first came to that realization in 1994,
I actually became the business and brand manager for Magic.
And so that was a large portion of my job there.
But I continued to work in design.
I co-designed or developed almost all of Wizards of the Coast's CCGs.
Not all of them, but the list is very long.
And a large part of what I did there was I designed the Protor,
the organized play system, the tournament system, leagues,
that both Magic and then eventually Pokemon used.
And there at Wizards after a while, because I was going back and forth
between design and business, it turned out that...
Really, I was, to borrow a phrase, if any of you know who the sports guy is, he's an ESPN columnist, the VP of common sense.
That's basically what I was doing at Wizards, and I was very overworked.
So in 2004, I left Wizards of the Coast, started a company called Three Donkeys with Richard Garfield.
And it's mainly a consulting company, and we've done a lot of computer game consulting.
And also design, we did an Xbox Live arcade game called Schizoid with a company called Torpex.
And we've also published Spectrum Answer, which is something like a collectible card
game.
You can go look at it online.
And also, we've been teaching courses at University of Washington, and I do a podcast with Richard
where a lot of the things I'll talk about here are sort of gone over in more detail.
That's at 3donkeys.com.
So the interesting thing is, by their nature, distributed object games...
mixed design and business in an inextricable way.
A lot of concerns that are sort of traditionally in one field
turn out to not be able to stay in that field.
But first, a little bit about collectible card games,
for those of you who don't know.
Magic the Gathering was the first collectible card game.
And sometimes inside the video game industry,
people don't understand how large some of these properties
were.
Magic was doing.
since 1994, so for a very long time, between $100 and $150 million wholesale.
And because of the way the distribution margins work there, the wholesale numbers,
that actually about translates to $375 million retail.
And actually, these numbers are sort of semi-publicly available,
and really they're probably about double what I'm printing here.
Pokemon, on the other hand, our best year there did about almost $2 billion at retail,
and it had several years pretty close to that.
And it's interesting, it hasn't quite gotten back to its peak, but more than 10 years later,
it's doing, you know, more than half that again.
And then Yu-Gi-Oh! is sort of the top seller all the time, and it had several years.
where it was making at retail over $3 billion a year.
Probably about three years in a row,
it came close to those numbers.
So they're actually very large properties.
And sort of the attitude that Richard and I take is,
you should look at all games, all the time, constantly,
because there's valuable lessons that you can learn,
that you can learn from them.
Especially any game that's as popular as these,
or major video games, or even basketball.
You know, you really,
Yeah, if that many people like something,
there's certainly some valuable lessons there.
So before we start, kind of a definition
that I want to use for distributed object games,
just because mainly the lessons from the collectible card games
apply to these sorts of things.
And one of these games sort of should
contain hundreds of semi-individually purchasable
objects.
that together constitute a large portion of the gameplay.
And semi-individually purchasable
is actually kind of important.
It means that I don't just pay one price.
I get a game with hundreds of objects
and then I use those throughout the course of the game.
That's certainly a multiple object game
but not necessarily distributed
where maybe the players don't own all of the objects
and they're purchasing them over time.
And these types of games are interesting.
They take a basic gameplay interaction,
a standard set of rules, and they use these objects
to change the gameplay in fundamental ways over time.
And that's interesting because they become
almost more of a hobby than a game,
or traditionally what you would think of as a hobby
compared to a game,
where they're taking enormous amounts of time.
People can be involved in them
for a very long period of time, several years,
for even an average customer.
And actually they spend a lot more money than they might with a standard game because they're putting money into it across a long time.
These types of games are very difficult to construct and enormously difficult to construct.
They're also enormously difficult to play.
Magic the Gathering is, except for basketball, the best game I've ever played.
And if I wanted to teach someone how to play and I knew they could only play it for one day, I wouldn't teach it to them.
it wouldn't be worth their time because of the amount of difficulty there is in getting
up to speed with these things. However, on the back end, they're extremely rewarding
for both the publisher and the player as well. You almost can't have one without the other
because you get to really have almost a lifelong involvement with these types of things if
they're done right.
or at the very least several years.
So you get a very big payoff for getting into the game
in the first place.
First, a few assumptions.
One thing is that I'm only gonna talk
about gameplay concerns, what gameplay lessons
can be learned from video games from CCGs.
There's a lot of other things they could learn as well,
but just for the scope of the talk,
we'll talk, we'll concentrate on those.
And also, what type of video games can learn lessons
from collectible card games.
So I'm going to make just a few assumptions here.
You can relax these assumptions, and there's
a whole other interesting series of talks.
I could talk for a semester on this sort of thing,
but just to try and narrow the focus.
The first one is a repeat purchase revenue model.
And as I mentioned before with the distributed object games,
not just that the objects get parceled out over time,
but that people are making purchases over time.
Essentially, you're creating an operating system.
and providing sort of new software for it constantly
throughout the course of your project.
It's very difficult for players and designers,
so it needs to be built very robustly
because if there is no long-term involvement,
it's a very dubious value proposition.
Again, both for the publisher and the player.
The fact that you don't have to purchase it all at once
is a huge benefit for the player.
They get to try it first before they decide how involved they want to be.
And then, hopefully, ideally, they're getting rewarded at virtually any level of money they decide to input into the game.
One thing about this is it requires actually a very large degree of sophistication in the audience.
It's very difficult to fool people for two years and several thousand dollars of their money.
This is something that's probably underrated, even for a game like Pokemon, where maybe only 20% of the people played, maybe only 10% played correctly,
those other players were extremely sophisticated about their purchases.
I shouldn't say players. Those other customers were extremely sophisticated about their purchases.
They knew more about Pokemon and what they were getting in their cards than, you know,
90% of the average video game player knows when he's actually buying a video game.
They knew the prices of the cards.
They knew what they were getting.
They knew the back history.
They were allowed to associate
with this enormous amount of story.
And the reason they had this degree of sophistication
is they were watching a television show
or playing the handheld game.
And so they had actually, in some sense,
put in hundreds and hundreds of hours
of research into the brand.
And by respecting that sophistication,
we were able to provide them with a much better product.
Another assumption, this is a very personal bias of mine, it's limited SKUs.
I've seen a lot of times this sort of analysis paralysis on a part of the customer, and so
I really like it when there's very few things for them to buy, and it does imply, since
you're selling hundreds of objects, that there's some sort of randomized selling going on.
It doesn't have to be fully random.
I mean, you can be creative in your product.
For instance, when people are purchasing new cards,
they could get a random set of them.
And then the next time they purchase,
they could get a random set that they don't already own.
You can change rarity levels.
You can do all sorts of things here.
It's not fully random.
But the limited SKUs apply some degree of randomness,
and that actually has some implications later on.
And another assumption is that you're planning for success.
you are expecting your product to be around for a long time,
let's say at least a year of people actively supporting it,
they're actively purchasing.
And also you're planning for a very, very wide range
of customers in terms of the amount of skill,
in terms of the amount of free time they have,
their psychographics, the amount of money they can spend.
And another thing when you have a game
that's lasting this long is since your customers
come in at different entry times, that's actually,
That's actually another very important consideration
when you're trying to build these games.
So what are the implications of these assumptions?
For these games, the purchase decision of the consumer
is not made once.
A one-time deal heavily influenced by the marketing guys
who have put a big spend behind your initial launch.
They're constant decisions.
Absolutely throughout the course of play,
at any time, someone's able to make a purchase.
Every single game is a sales pitch.
Every single game that you have that someone plays,
you should be thinking of, in a way,
as a sales pitch to that customer
because they can just turn right around
and make another purchase decision.
And also respecting all your customers pays off
because you will have an enormous amount of them.
And if you start cutting off sections of that market,
pretty quickly you'll see the effect in terms of revenue.
If every game is a sales pitch, this is one thing to learn from collectible card games,
the objects actually have to be pretty easily understood.
Your audience is pretty sophisticated.
They have put a lot of thought into the game.
And they will tend to, again, over time, put a lot of thought into their purchases.
Clarity is very important.
You really need for them to understand exactly the benefit
of their purchase.
There are other ways you can somehow obfuscate to them
what the real value of these objects is,
but let me just say the easiest way for them to,
the easiest way for you to have them see value
in what's going on is actually give them value.
And clarity in what they're getting
is a very important thing.
Which is to say.
So for instance, if you had objects in your game
that acted like black boxes,
and you were selling them Tamagotchi-like things,
maybe with some hidden characteristics,
the value of those purchases,
as it goes over time in your involvement,
is it's very hard to make a case for people over time
that they're actually getting something of value.
This is an important one.
It was really critical for us in producing these games that
lasted, I guess, Magic now is almost 20 years old,
18 years old.
For objects to have a clear benefit
across the different entry times and the different purchase
levels, as we sort of were talking about before.
The value of every purchase in terms of winning percentage ideally should only have logarithmically increasing value.
And the reason for this is sort of obvious.
If I came into the game five years ago and I keep buying cards and now you came into the game today
because you just turned 13 or 14 or whatever the low end of your age range is,
if these objects that I've purchased over time all have some sort of linear value,
there's no way you can catch up as a new player, a new customer.
That's sort of the most critical case.
And then, because you don't want to cut off
your new customers coming in.
And then additionally, even two people
that have entered the game at the exact same time,
just naturally, one of them probably
will spend more than the other.
You want your players to get a benefit
for spending extra money.
That is, after all, how you make your money.
But you don't want that benefit to be too high,
because if it is, it scares away other customers.
solution to this? Is this logarithmically increasing value? There's a lot of ways to
accomplish this. The easiest way is that you have some sort of slight extra benefit for
the combinatorial variety that you're able to get by purchasing a lot of objects. Each
object isn't necessarily that you purchase more powerful than the next one. Maybe they're
all of equal power, but by owning certain subsets and increasing subsets, you sort of
the natural tendency will be to have a curve like that.
And also, it may be useful to reduce
the amount of physical skill involved in your game.
When games have a lot of hand-eye coordination,
then you are much less in control.
It's just this extra variable.
in terms of the difference in your audience skill level
that you're not in control of.
And people can have very, very, very wide ranges
of hand-eye coordination,
especially if you're talking about a game
that appeals to a wide age range.
And this sort of thing is sort of important
because it's really difficult for a person
to see the benefit of,
let's say I'm making a first-person shooter.
and this gun is 10% better than the other gun.
Well, that may only matter if I'm playing against someone
who's in the exact same skill range that I am in.
And that might be a very small fragment of the audience.
Most likely, if you gave me a gun that's 10% better
than another gun, I'm just gonna get killed anyway.
So the value of that purchase is very, very minimal for me.
And similarly, if you're at the top of your game,
those sorts of purchases may not matter
in 99% of the contests that you're in.
This isn't a hard and fast rule, but it's just, it's sort of critical to realize that
you definitely reduce the value of incremental purchases for your customers in terms of their
win percentage, the wider part they are in skill.
Another really important lesson that we learned, and we actually, at one point when we were
doing magic, we were concerned about reducing randomness in the system.
And the more we tended to do that,
we did actually notice effects of sales essentially going
down.
For small audiences, a high degree of randomness
in your game is critical.
Now what's high, I mean I'm not saying that you should
be flipping coins, there needs to be skill there
for one object to make a difference over another one.
But higher than you would sort of normally think.
Because for a very small audience,
It is, you want people to be able to play against each other.
You want your bottom 10th percentile
to be able to play against your 80th percentile guy.
And without randomness, that's hard to do.
Some people think of randomness as the opposite of skill.
And that's not true.
You can perform a slight thought experiment
by considering, say, the game of chess.
We could take a game, let's call it rando chess.
where you play your game of chess,
and then at the end of it, you roll a six-sided die,
and if it's a six, the loser wins.
May not be the greatest game in the world,
but then you start to think about it,
and you say, well, is there less skill
in that game than there is in chess?
Well, no, not really.
Every little bit of skill that you had in chess,
you still have in that game.
Every opening you need to memorize,
all the games you need to study, they all still apply.
And even more to the point.
the exact ranking of chess players in terms of their skill in the world would be the same
if that were the game of chess. What are you losing? You're losing accuracy and skill testing.
That's the only thing you're losing. It might take more games of playing that for you to
determine what the proper rank order is, but it's still the same rank order. And still
every single skill applies, you still want to win.
So it's sort of instructive.
Obviously that's a terrible game
because the randomness that's been added to that game
is very overt and very unsatisfying
when the loser wins for the loser.
Although I'd still be plenty happy
if I beat Kasparov anyway,
because he might be pretty mad.
And so that's the sort of thing,
you shouldn't think of randomness as the enemy of skill.
It's just another completely separate
characteristic of the game.
And if that's blended into the game along the way,
even in a game of high skill,
you get the effect that you have in poker.
So, you know, you have a very wide set of people
that are able to play with each other
and get positive feedback along the way
of determining who the better person is.
If I play 10 games of chess against a better person,
and I'm winning zero of them,
and maybe once I came a little bit close,
that's a very unsatisfying experience.
I play those 10 games of poker
against someone who's better than me.
and I win three or four of them, whatever,
figure games as some set of hands,
or one hour blocks in a 10 hour session.
That's actually pretty interesting for me.
That keeps me involved.
If you ask a tournament level poker player
if they would want to remove that randomness from poker
and have it be more skill testing,
they would have a heart attack, right?
The whole reason they're able to make money long term
is because the game is fun.
for people who get feedback of exactly how close they are
to that better person, of course,
they have to pay for that privilege of finding that out.
The other value of randomness in your game
is that if you have an astute audience,
it's very helpful in maintaining the discussion
about the exact value, strategic value of the cards.
When you don't have anything muddying the feedback
for many, many games,
people can coalesce fairly rapidly
on what the exact best cards are,
what the exact best strategy is,
before you have a chance to update and change that
and keep the game fresh for people.
And that's a disaster.
You don't want that to happen,
because again, that's a disincentive to purchase
for people that have already bought
the elements of that strategy.
Another thing is if every game's a sales pitch,
how can you go about adding real value to the objects for your players?
And this is an interesting one. You're not trying to, through the course of this,
is sort of going to sound like, oh yeah, you're just trying to get as much money out of them as possible.
And that's true, but the best way to do that is to actually give them value for the money that they're giving you.
So it's not some sort of evil plot. It's, I want to give them something that they want to buy.
Adding real value to the objects is an interesting question.
One thing you can do is you can cash out the objects.
When we first started with these collectible card games,
as many of you know, there was a sort
of a thriving secondary market in the cards,
because, specifically because, they were purchased randomly
to begin with.
So you didn't have all the cards you wanted.
Some people, you would get a sort of a better overall value
if you're buying them randomly.
But if you really only wanted specific things.
you could just buy that one card.
The people at the company hated that for a long time
because we felt that we should be capturing that money.
We felt that, you know, somehow this was,
we were losing out.
But the nice part about it is,
is it gave players the feeling that they could cash out
if they wanted to of the purchases that they've made.
How many do cash out?
A very low percentage.
But.
that didn't matter.
There was the belief, and it was correct,
that if they wanted to cash out,
they would get some of their money back.
So the objects had a real value for the players.
It wasn't a completely, entirely sunk cost.
The other way is, oh, and so when we did Magic Online,
what we did there, and this, I guess,
it launched almost 10 years ago, pretty close.
So for a product like that.
When people were purchasing the digital objects, we were very worried that they wouldn't find value in them.
So there's a cash-out system there where you can convert your digital cards into paper cards.
You say, get rid of my digital card, we'll mail you the paper card.
There's some restrictions and constraints.
But essentially, we felt that was important when the game first started in order to give people real value for the objects they were purchasing, that they clearly understood.
I think that's less important in today's day and age.
People are much more used to buying digital objects.
Digital secondary markets are common.
But back then it was a really critical thing.
Tournaments.
Let people play tournaments of your game
if it's a competitive game.
And that gives people, again, real value
for the objects that they've bought.
Because they go, they go to a tournament,
they compete, they win.
There's social currency in winning.
There's real money in winning.
And so that, again, adds value to their purchases.
Fulfilling people's desire to collect.
Building community.
These are all sorts of things
that aren't quite tied into gameplay.
All very, very, very important.
When you have a product that's going to be like a hobby,
you need to think about these things.
Again.
returning value to their players for being loyal,
for being in the system for a year,
for making the purchases across time.
There's a lot of other things
that are sort of outside the scope of the talk
that you can do, but the point is to figure out
how you can provide that value to your players
for being loyal customers and feed that.
If every game's a sale pitch,
then the scary thought is that your customers
are your salesmen.
And that is pretty scary.
Intermixing, but in order to facilitate them
being your salesman, it's really nice
when you can intermix large populations of customers
because it gives people more opportunity to play
and more opportunity to play against
a very wide variety of people.
Again, here's randomness absolutely helps.
I mean, you look at tournament games played for money.
in the sort of in the paper realm and you have a 50-year tradition
of or more of chess being played for money
and it's nowhere near as successful as poker
and there's a big reason for that. The randomness and the allowing
a much larger group of people to play, much easier to find a poker game than a
poker
than a chess game, much more positive feedback for doing okay
is critical in that sort of
poker's tournament success.
because it allows you to have fun when you're playing against people that might have a better deck.
And here's another important thing.
If you're playing against someone in any of your game interactions,
you really do want, again, because you want your customers to find value in purchasing more objects,
you want them to run into somebody who has bought more objects,
who is beating them, and they think they're beating them because they bought those extra objects.
if there's no randomness or a low amount of randomness in the system,
they will not have fun throughout that process.
If there's enough randomness in the system, they will have fun because maybe they're losing,
maybe they're winning 45% of the time.
And that's actually really an important sort of number.
I mean, you really would love that to happen, and you would love people to think
that the extra purchase they make is going to be the one that puts them over the winning percentage.
If they're winning 0% of the time, they're going to have an awful, awful, awful time.
And they're going to think they need to make too many purchases that it's too far beyond them.
So this whole thing actually implies, this is something we struggled a lot with in the tournament formats for Magic and actually a little bit even Pokemon.
It implies limiting the potential number of formats you have to play.
You can play StarCraft in a million different ways on a million different maps.
And if you have a billion customers.
you're fine because all of those things will fill up.
You'll have plenty of people in each of those.
But except for the very top end games,
that's not a luxury that most games have.
You need to get in control of the number of formats
that people play your game.
And it's a really hard lesson
because every one of those games offers something fun
and offers a little bit different way to play.
And you want there to be different ways to play.
But you have to balance the consideration
of making sure there's a robust audience
in each one of those.
or else you start, again, to lose the value of players as salesmen,
and you lose sort of the value in any sort of social currency built up
in being accomplished in any one of those formats.
This is a really important lesson, especially for video games.
It's sort of a side digression.
It's not so much about the intermixing of business and game design,
but it's something that I think a lot of people don't realize.
And that's reconfiguration in these distributed object games is half the game.
Well, that means that losses are critical for two reasons.
One, to drive sales, because if I win every game I play, I'm not incentivized to buy anything extra.
But even worse from the customer's point of view, they've put in all this effort into learning this very,
very complex system where a large portion of the fun is the reconfiguration of their set of objects.
So if they're not losing.
they really actually don't get to access half of the game that you've designed for them.
In a strictly multiplayer game, losses are easy to come by. You look at your average
population, everyone's playing, half of them are losing, you know, half of the games are
losses for people.
So you might think it's trivial there in that case,
but it's actually a little bit trickier than that.
You want it to not just be, for instance,
you could achieve that if your bottom half of the players
lost every game and your top half of the players
won every game.
Again, as you can tell, a disaster situation,
very few people are actually accessing
that reconfiguration part of gameplay.
So what you want is you want the right amount
of win-loss ratio for people spread
across your whole population.
And it's something that you can,
there's a lot of statistical ways that you can measure this.
For instance, like in magic,
we used a variant of the ELO system that chess uses.
It essentially tells you what your win percent chance is
against someone else, like true skill ratings,
that sort of thing.
You really want to look at it across your population
and figure out if you're getting anything
too aberrant in that.
And once again,
Skill can be high, it can be extremely high, as high as it is in chess, but that doesn't mean that accuracy in skill testing does not have to follow from that.
You can have enough noise in the system through the randomness that you have as much skill as you want in the game,
and then you dial up that noise so that people can have fun playing people of higher skill,
and you're getting a much smoother feedback on your actual true skill position than you would if...
you are simply taking a measurement.
Let's play the fun game of who's the tallest.
And we line up, and OK, you win, and you lose.
And I think perhaps the more important implication
for most computer games is that the single player
version of your games actually has to entail a lot of losses.
And this is hard.
I mean, we submitted games over the years to major publishers
and would get consistent feedback.
that the single player game was too hard,
the campaign was too hard, you were losing too much.
And we tried to make this exact argument
that I'm making now of,
well you've got all these digital objects,
if they're winning all the time,
like the player should always win.
Well, if they should always win,
then there's no reason whatsoever
to have a distributed object game.
They're just, they're not accessing half the gameplay.
The fun in these games is in losing,
reconfiguring, going back, playing and winning.
And I don't know what loss percentage you're supposed to have, but it's pretty high.
I mean, even if you're losing 70% of the time, it's fine. It's a single-player campaign.
The win, sure, they should be able to win at the end of the campaign.
But along that way, you need to be, they need to be generating losses at a much higher rate
than you would normally sort of, most people from a game design sense, would consider,
especially a long time ago.
And again, if reconfiguration is half the game,
repeat play is critical.
You want to be able to play against that same person
with that same deck after you make a small tweak.
You want to be able to get the tactical part of the game
under control so that you can access
the strategic part of the game.
Keeping play times low is, I cannot stress how important,
for each individual interaction,
I can't stress how important that is
for these games to achieve their full value.
If you're playing a two hour game,
and then you go back and you reconfigure,
I mean, to play another two hour game,
there's a certain audience out there,
I'm sure, for games like that.
But in general, for most people, most players,
that's just too much.
That's just not a high enough percentage of the time
where the thing that makes your distributed object game
unique, where it sets it apart,
they're just not accessing that part of the game.
And repeat play is one of the biggest drivers
for players getting positive feedback,
because there's somebody that's really annoying
that's beating them, beating them, beating them.
They go back, pull another object out of their collection,
change their thing, and beat that person.
That's, I mean, there's no better feeling
that now you have this recurring villain,
or best friend, or whatever, and now you're beating him.
And we really struggled with this at Wizards.
We kept trying to, in R&D, move playtime down.
And if I were making a new game today,
it would have an even lower play time than Magic.
And now, design and business in these sorts of games
are intermixed in an interesting way.
Some examples.
When you change the rarity of an object,
you're not just changing it in a game design sense
to the frequency that it might appear for a player.
You're actually changing the price of the product.
you, at Wizards, we used to look at, you know,
well, if you're a competitive player,
roughly what percentage of the objects will you need to buy?
How much will you need to spend to be competitive?
And if some of those objects change in rarity
because you decided, oh, instead of one in 10
for this card to appear or object to appear,
it's gonna appear one in 12 times,
Now all of a sudden, you've actually made sort of what would normally be considered a major marketing decision.
It's not like I'm the head of marketing for a project and I decide to call down to R&D
and talk to some junior level designers and say,
should we put this out at $29.99 or $49.99?
And they say, I don't know, $49.99. Great, we'll go with that.
And that's actually the decision that's being made constantly in these types of games,
something no less powerful than that.
even when you change the power of an object.
I mean, rarity sometimes, maybe that's a little more major decision,
but when you change the power of an object,
oh, I've got a dragon of 42 power,
and I don't know, he's not quite good enough,
I'll make him 63 power.
And just tweak it out.
Again, it's this sort of seemingly very, very, very minor decision,
which ripples through the whole system.
Now all of a sudden, your average price for your game
for a competitive player could be, I don't know.
$30 a month instead of $20 a month.
And you've sort of completely unthinkingly
made that decision about how many sort of
top level cards are needed and what's required
to access play.
I cannot stress enough how important it is
to understand what your audience is.
At Wizards of the Coast we would sort of
break down our audience into various categories.
These are competitive people.
These are kind of casually competitive people.
These people over here don't care.
They like the art.
They love dragon pictures.
And you sort of look at all those people.
And when you make these decisions about small power
rarity changes, you are, again, changing
the price of the product for those people,
just as much as if you actually change the dollar sign.
And another thing is the release schedule.
Something as simple as changing the release schedule
has major implications for.
for not just the gameplay, but for,
well, I'll give you a specific example.
So these games, these combinatorial games
are very difficult to coalesce around
sort of proper strategy.
And the very top level players enjoy that
and like a fast rate of that.
But the, just one step below them.
if the rate's too high, if it's too fast,
they can't, they can never feel like they're
anything solid in their sort of efforts in the game.
So in 95 or so, this card came out called Necropotence.
Some of you might be players.
Necropotence is like the most hated card
in the history of Magic among sort of top players.
We had so many complaints because, as it turned out,
Necropotence was a really freaking good card.
And a whole set of decks, all Necropotence decks, a little bit different, different in
interesting ways, but still the professionals kept bitching about it.
That card dominated play, dominated play for a whole summer.
And it's going to ruin the game, you've got to ban the card, you've got to get rid of
it, it's terrible.
And an interesting thing happened, which was sales shot up, even though there weren't any
new releases during that time period.
It's largely anecdotal, but at the retail level feedback, it was like, oh yeah, it's
great.
People know what deck to play finally.
The average, the low-level customer, he knows what he's doing now because he knows that
if he builds a Necropotence deck, he may not win, but he's not coming with the worst deck.
He's whatever.
He's halfway there.
And this was enormous.
And the message boards took off.
Strategy articles took off.
And it was all because...
sort of the strategy had slowed down enough
that a large enough percentage of the population
was able to catch up, access this,
know what they were supposed to buy.
I know, I go make these cards, I make this deck,
I know I'm no longer an idiot.
I may not win, but I'm not a fool anymore.
And I'm not saying you want everything to stagnate,
of course you don't wanna lose the top end of players,
but you have to respect everybody
and changing release schedule as far as how rapidly
you're changing the strategy has very strong implications on
Again, the value of the incremental purchases for players at different levels of skill.
And don't cut your best salesman, which are these sort of rabid top-level players, don't
cut your best salesman off at the knees by limiting their time.
They should be bitching about not having enough new things to think about at the same time
they're posting articles saying this is clearly, clearly, clearly the best strategy in the
game.
That's right about the point where it's perfect and then move on.
Yeah, changing the price of the product changes your potential customers.
You, when you change the price of the product, either by, because you made the dragon have an extra whatever, three hit points, you, or if you make an actual change to the price, you change who your potential customers are.
And this is another thing where I think sort of more traditional marketing people might actually be more concerned about this sorts of thing,
where they'll say, well, I'm making a game for 10 year olds, so I'm going to put it out at a certain price point versus a game for mature audiences.
And it makes a big difference.
And so it's something to consider.
You need to actually really know who your customers are, who the customers are on the fringes.
and how sensitive they will be to price changes
in your products that you're doing all the time
by changing what mix of objects that they need to buy,
what rate they're expected to buy the objects at, et cetera.
One thing that we did, it's a lot less important
for digital games, I think,
is we were very big on the organized play.
Tournaments, leagues, that sort of thing
is a very powerful tool.
Sort of the interesting part about this
is that is it marketing?
or is it design?
When we started it, it was sort of traditional event marketing.
And I think that's sort of how many people would view it,
depending upon the company today.
And there, it was an intermixture.
It's design.
It was the only way we had to patch the game.
Games aren't just their rules.
They're not just the rules that come in the rule box.
It's how people play.
Every game, nobody plays by the rules,
or there's variations of the rules.
So by being able to pick that, you're
actually
effectively changing the rules that people are playing by.
It's a very powerful tool, and it's very similar,
like the way we thought of it, is to patching the game.
By patching the format, we actually
were sort of patching the game as per rules that we put out.
And it's a really interesting question,
because there's a lot involved here in the actual.
I would say more sort of event marketing mold,
like one thing that we ran up against,
especially with Pokemon, is keeping these play times short.
You've got kids, you've got six-year-old kids,
you've got seven-year-old kids,
so they're gonna come in to the game and they can't play.
They can't sit there for two hours and play.
I mean, that's at the low end,
most of them are 10 years old or whatever,
but even a 10-year-old,
he can't sit and play an hour and a half in a row.
It's just not gonna happen.
It's a terrible event.
It's terrible event marketing.
Doesn't work for anybody.
Doesn't work for the parents, the kids, a lot of crying.
There's a lot of crying at Pokemon tournaments.
And so then you have to start thinking about,
again, the design implications of that.
Lower your play time so that they can play.
Well, what does that mean?
Does that mean that I can't play best out of two out of three?
Maybe I can only play one game.
Maybe I need to change my mix of cards.
Maybe I need to start discarding defensive cards
so that the game moves faster.
Then of course, then that is this whole big cycle,
then that affects how much skill there is in the game
if you're playing just one game at a time
or best two out of three.
So you play two out of three, it's more skill testing,
you can develop more consistent winners,
a lot more social currency is being able to be built up
among the audience for winning at tournaments
because there's these consistent winners.
You feel like you might be able to get a prize,
you feel like improving skill at the game
or buying more objects will actually help you.
Or do you dial down toward the randomness end
so that the tournament will run more smoothly?
Well, the answer is somewhere in between.
You need to take all these things into consideration
based upon your audience.
And that probably happens just as much
with online play of these games.
Are people expected to play a one hour game at lunch?
Or is it a game for kids?
Is it 10 or 15 minutes?
Well, your design in the very little things you do
in those objects that come up.
are going to affect that play time.
If your tournaments are important,
then you really need to be concerned
much more about play time
than you were if they were not important.
And another thing is that organized play might be
sort of you think of the organism,
the rules as unimportant as I actually think they are
in most games are the skeleton.
If my game is let's flip coins and see who wins
or cut for high card,
you're not gonna have a pro tour.
It can't happen.
There's no way for you to get consistent winners on that.
So you do need a certain underlying structure,
rule structure, in order to build up certain types
of tournament structures, especially the competitive ones.
So, a couple extra concerns, long-term concerns.
How do you keep objects interesting in the long-term
over the course of several years, and why should you care?
Well, you should care because hopefully,
your players are playing, and I don't mean to say
that every game that has distributed objects
is going to last.
for, what, how long did I say Magic was?
18 years.
But it might last for a year across several releases.
That's sort of maybe a little,
that's not normal for a game.
So yeah, it definitely does matter.
We found that we couldn't just allow cards
to live forever in the environment
because when a new player came in,
they felt hopelessly outmatched
because you have thousands of cards that I don't have.
So we would rotate objects out.
That was part of what we did with the tournament formats.
And an interesting thing, in the long term,
you need to, in the medium term, you need to rotate objects out.
So no one is expected to have to make purchases
at too high a level.
And in the really long term, you want
to start rotating objects back in.
Because just as I was saying about the cash out value,
if the cards have no value after two years,
again, I should use objects instead of cards.
The objects have no value after two years.
That's bad.
But if they can always keep rotating back in,
there's always a chance of rotating back in.
That gives people hope.
And it actually does, in fact, increase the long-term value
of those cards.
Avoid complexity creep.
This is the, yeah.
This is possibly the worst magic card ever made.
The text you see here, I hope you can't read it because.
you'd be some sort of mutant if you could read all those words,
is about half the text of the card,
because there was another set of rulings
that was about this long of the actual text of the card.
I created this card, by the way.
And what a disaster.
And it's the easiest way to sort of, oh, I've
got to put out more objects and more objects and more objects.
Well.
Yeah, let's just add another line of text.
Let's have it be resistant to fire.
Let's have it, I don't know, increase your accuracy by 10%.
Let's, oh, let's also have you draw a card
and take the card away from it.
You just keep adding this list of things that these things do.
And then if that's the way that you're
trying to keep your design fresh across two years,
you're going to end up with stuff like this.
So you really do need to get in control of it.
I would set hard limits right in the beginning on how much,
how complex your stuff's going to be.
and avoid power creep. Here's another really bad card for magic. I didn't create this one.
Not that dumb. And if you have power creep, two things will happen. One, you won't be
able to rotate objects back in because they'll be awful. And that's a minor concern. The
major one is that you won't be in control of your game. You won't be in control of,
if the power keeps going up, you will not be in control of your play time.
Because now, maybe all of a sudden, the game is ending on turn four instead of turn ten.
You won't be controlled necessarily of the amount of randomness in your game.
For Magic, it's a very specific example.
You're drawing cards, something that ends on turn ten is going to be, in a way, inherently
less random than a game that ends on turn four, just because you're accessing more cards,
your distribution is more even.
But in all these games.
just a little bit extra, a little bit extra, a little bit extra.
I keep making my gun a little bit more powerful, a little bit more powerful, a little bit more
powerful so that people want to buy the next version, buy the next version, buy the next
version.
And then pretty soon, you'll end up, oh, everything's a one-shot kill.
Clipped his ankle, he's dead.
And so that's a real problem.
So you ideally, if you can handle it, over the long term, you would like the power of
your objects in year 18 to be the same as the power of your objects in year one.
And that won't happen.
But as long as you keep having that as a goal,
you'll cycle up and down.
And in conclusion, there's probably,
I would say there's two major lessons that I
would like to get across.
One is, there is no substitute for studying games, all games.
Any successful game, I don't care whether it's
basketball or poker.
the chess rating system, chess formats, any of these popular games, they have a valuable
lesson for the game you're working on.
It just, I can't, I cannot possibly understate this particular thing.
Probably you have a problem that's been solved by someone.
Maybe it was solved by someone making the golf tour back in 1925.
I don't know, maybe it was solved by someone last year who released a great RTS.
the answer is out there or at least something that's going to give you an idea for a problem that you have.
The other one is that your customer does not care what your org chart is at all.
So the fact that it's this person's job to set the price for a product
and it's this person's job to figure out what the power level is,
you people need to get together and really figure it out
because you're both working on the product all the customer cares is.
what that ends up to him in the long run.
And this is hard.
This is one of the hardest lessons for us at Wizards, because it's very painful when
people are stepping on each other's toes.
And you're going to have that both from the business people and from the marketing side.
But it's critical in these games to work it out, because there can be such an amazing
value proposition for the customer and the publisher if you're able to sort of throw
those divisions away and think of everything in terms of the...
and utility of the decision.
That's it.
Questions?
Use the microphone.
Oh, everyone, please fill out the cards.
There's a couple of different CCGs I've been involved in, Magic being one of them, the other one being Legend of the Five Rings.
One of the differences I noticed between the two is that in Legend of the Five Rings, the common most...
Sorry, could you speak more into the microphone? I can't quite hear you.
In... two games I've been involved in, Legend of the Five Rings and Magic.
And one of the differences between the two is in Legend of the Five Rings, the commons were...
of more variable power than they are in Magic.
Usually the commons in Magic are almost kind of throwaway cards
when you get to the higher level.
It's the uncommons and the rares that people tend to play with.
Do you have any thoughts about that?
One being the better design?
I guess my main answer to that is to disagree.
Magic, there's plenty, like if you look at,
it's varied over the years.
Certainly if you look at a tournament decks in Magic,
I think there's going to be as many common.
cards in those top-level decks as there are in the other rarities, or at least it'll be
close. Certainly when Magic first came out, lots of the most powerful cards were in common.
So the intention, at least, for Magic was, and I'm not saying that they did this, and
I know at certain times people have had different viewpoints, but the intention was to push
more complicated cards to rare, and to push cards that had more specialized effects that
may not occur as often to rare.
Now, certainly a lot of the powerful ones in the very beginning did end up there.
But I would say if you've noticed a consistent trend, it's unintentional.
Thank you.
Magic has different formats for the tournaments, and then Yu-Gi-Oh has the abandoned, restricted list.
Could you comment a little on the differences there that you see and the pluses and minuses?
Sorry, the question is, Yu-Gi-Oh has...
Abandoned restricted lists? Correct, yeah. And but only one format?
Well, it has abandoned restricted and then just limited and restricted, but the cards
from the very first set can still be used, whereas Magic has the formats that rotate
them out. Oh, right, I see. Yeah, well, we made a conscious effort, I didn't work on
Yu-Gi-Oh, we made a conscious effort to keep the expenditure for the player down.
Uh, and so what happened with Magic in the beginning is you could use all the cards with
a ban and restricted list.
And it became really, really hard because our print runs were so limited in the beginning
to get those older cards, they're much more expensive than, say, first run Yu-Gi-Oh cards.
So I don't know where they, I don't know how much it costs to put together a Yu-Gi-Oh deck,
but we looked at, the price was just becoming more and more prohibitive.
That's when we decided to start rotating out those older cards and we had to do it wholesale
because you get a television show, they print whatever.
100 billion cards literally to start. So their prices never got to the level that they were
of the original Magic cards. We had to cut those off. Now, maybe they're making a mistake
because it's still too expensive to collect. I don't know. I haven't really looked at the
chart. But that's the first thing I would do, would be sit down and look, you know,
at that. It'd be great if the older cards were free enough that everyone could just
use all their cards all the time. Thank you. Over here.
Sometimes when you make newer iterations of, like, say, Pokemon or Magic,
like, there were sometimes when you made a new card that just was better than a previous card.
How do you counter that later on?
Like, if you did it, if you did it intentionally, if it was accident, but later on,
you know, sometimes, like, people will have cards that are just not really worth anything
because they have the better version.
So how do you counter that later on?
Well...
That's gone back and forth over the years.
We had a rule at one time that no card was supposed to be strictly better than any other card in the whole set.
It was a good rule of thumb, but it didn't really work out.
So eventually we just started making cards better or worse because of where we wanted the end goal to be.
You will be forced into obsoleting certain cards when you make tens of thousands of different magic cards.
You'll be forced to do that. And the same thing if you're designing a computer game, same exact sort of thing.
If you have enough objects, some are just going to be strictly better than others, and you can't help it.
Would it be better to try to plan ahead of time to make sure that it doesn't happen, or does it really matter?
You know, is it better to just like, you know, to make sure, like, try to put, you know, a lot of effort into trying to not do that, or just let it happen?
Um, I think you should plan for it to not happen, but then when it does, don't be too
afraid and too resistant if you're actually going to end up in a better space.
Yes, certainly the ideal is that that doesn't happen.
I just, I don't think that's realistic.
Uh, so I, I do think sometimes you'll have to just say, yeah, you know, lightning bolt
should cost whatever.
R for two damage instead of R for three damage.
That kind of thing.
It just, yeah, you'll be forced into that.
Yes.
Over here.
Yes, if someone has an idea for a trading card game, what advice would you give them
to help flush it out?
I wouldn't launch a new trading card game unless it had a major license attached to
it today.
Okay.
At least I wouldn't put money into it.
If you want to launch it sort of on your own, and you know 10 years ago I would have had
different advice.
Now the way the market is, it's sort of difficult if you don't, if you aren't able to bring
a lot of initial customers in.
But if you wanted to, let's say, let's ask it a slight,
we'll question it a slightly different way.
If you want to make a really good trading card game,
I would sit down, I would play test it.
I would play test it with people that are not your friends.
I would play test it with strangers
and I would do that for at least a year.
And I would make changes on that with the thing with,
you know, we really sort of as nice
as you can get the cards to look.
I mean, that's what we did back in grad school.
You know, we had art, we photocopied it, cut it out.
these games are really, really, really hard to get right.
And there's a lot of group think that goes on
in your group of, in any group of friends.
And so, yeah, you know, put it out in front of people
that aren't your friends for about a year
and keep making changes.
And you'll end up with a much better product
at the end than you would.
Great, thank you.
Sure.
Yep.
You mentioned that in single player campaigns,
you needed to introduce very frequent failures
in order to motivate reconfiguration of the deck.
Yeah.
I'm wondering if you might think it would be possible to do something to motivate players
to reconfigure their decks proactively, so that they still get that rich reconfiguring
experience without the feeling of failing all the time.
You can do a little bit of that, because you can say, now you're going to fight the fire
guy, so they sort of go ahead and think they should put all the anti-fire things in.
And that's okay, it's just really difficult to...
There's two things about that.
Most of these systems, if they're gonna have
hundreds of objects, are sort of too complex
for people to be able to successfully do that
if it's a hard job.
And I'm not saying that there aren't people
that could do it, but if you really want to provide
a lot of value from the complexity of the system,
that's almost impossible.
And then secondarily, when you get to the end of that campaign, you, I guess, I don't know, I would question how smart I was if I didn't lose any of the things, if I didn't lose any battles, it's very difficult for me to get feedback on how well or poorly I did.
I think it's more the nature of the complexity of the system makes it.
I definitely understand, and in fact the game that we submitted that was rejected had a lot of that in it,
but I think you still needed to generate the losses in order to, yeah, in order to really do the hard thinking about your deck.
Thank you.
Yeah.
One of the advantages of going digital is that you can update cards at any time.
So you don't end up with a necropotence or a channel
fireball situation.
But at the same time, you saw that sales surged as a result
of players seeing which cards were needed.
Right.
So how do you?
So updating cards is a very hard thing, even online.
Just because it's possible to update does not mean that you
want to update them.
Because someone's purchased this card, they feel really
good about this purchase because that was a very
powerful object that they bought.
And then you decide later, oh, sorry, this is going to be the last question and then we'll go.
So then you decide later that that thing was too powerful.
Well, maybe I went out and bought that thing specifically because of its power.
Well, now you nerf it.
Well, how does that make me feel?
How does that make me feel the next time I think there's a really good object out there that I want to buy?
Am I going to spend money on it?
How about if I wait and see if you nerf it or not?
That's a decision you don't want to make. It's much better to constantly move forward if you can.
Sometimes there'll be something so broken that it's just destroying the game and you have to deal with it.
But aside from that, if you at all, if there's any way you possibly can,
don't take away what people have bought. It's a terrible thing.
Thank you.
All right. Sorry. No more time.