Thank you all for coming, and would you kindly please
silence your phones.
And if you would also be so kind as to remember
to fill out the surveys at the end,
they get a lot of valuable information from them.
Hi.
My name is Soupy, at least to 98% of the people
that I work with, to the other 2%, I'm Chris.
And this talk is about a way of prototyping gameplay
that we call action blocks and how
we use them to find the core of Titanfall 2's single player
campaign and to develop the levels.
A little bit about me.
I've been working in games for about 13 years.
I started making some.
World War II Call of Duty games, and then I worked on Modern Warfare,
and for the last eight years or so I've been working on the Titanfall games.
I'm a level designer. My focus is mostly on layout, and I've done both single-player
and multiplayer levels. And a little bit about the folks who made Titanfall.
So years and years ago, a group of guys
made a really fantastic game called
Medal of Honor Allied Assault.
I remember this playing, or I remember playing this
before I even thought I could make video games
as a profession and loving it.
And then some things happened, and some of those guys
made a new company called Infinity Ward,
where they made the Call of Duty franchise.
And then some things happened, and those guys,
some of those guys.
and me went to form Respawn Entertainment.
That is to say, there were a lot of talented people
who had worked together for a really long time.
And because of that, there was a lot of collective institutional knowledge
that created this well-oiled machine that had the skills and experience
at making a particular type of game.
But now we had to make a brand new game.
And this was exciting, and it was scary,
and we flailed around a bit, and we experimented with things.
And finally, inspired by different gameplay prototypes
and pitches and concept, we found the core of that game,
which was a first-person game with wall running
and double jumping and giant robots.
And it was pretty great.
We also wanted to make a single-player game.
One that was new and went with all of those new mechanics that we had.
And that was a bit harder, particularly because we fell into some bad habits.
Like pitching levels as a series of cool movie moments.
Because this assumed that we knew what the core gameplay was going to be,
but the movie moments didn't help create that gameplay on their own.
or long, meandering, brainstorming meetings
that were full of arguments and whiteboard vomit and tears.
And on top of that, in AAA, you have a whole bunch
of other departments that are just hungry beasts waiting
to be fed.
Still, we spent some time making a single-player campaign.
And some of that stuff was really, really cool.
But the gameplay never quite got there.
Because of that, because of production constraints,
we ended up cutting single player
so that we could focus on making multiplayer, which
ended up as Titanfall, this crazy mobility, giant robot,
MP game.
And we managed to sneak a little bit of single player flair
in there.
So when we finally got to make the sequel,
we had some of the same questions and problems.
We knew we wanted a single player campaign,
but we didn't know exactly how to get there.
We had a sense we were going to make a first person
platforming shooter, something that
used all of those things from Titanfall,
like our mobility and our Titans.
But we also needed to change our process a little bit
so that we didn't fall into the same familiar traps.
And that's when we had a design meeting,
and the design team was told, go do some action blocks.
Sorry about that.
So action blocks.
are kind of game jam style design sprints.
The point of them is to encourage creative play
and to get designers thinking about game play.
And they came with a few simple guidelines.
They needed to be quick and dirty.
I made this guy my blocky buddy titan.
Rather than finding a model and posing it
and doing all of that, this was quicker.
I got him into the game.
And that is to say, these should be short.
They should take days or a week.
Every once in a while, if something's a bit more complex,
it can take a little bit longer.
But we sort of had a hard limit on two weeks.
And that was the exception.
They should also be a single designer working alone.
Unless two designers work together
because they complemented each other,
like one designer doing layout and the other doing
script for a particular action block that needed that.
And most importantly, things needed to have a skill test
that could fit into a level.
So that could be platforming or resource management
or combat or puzzles, whatever,
but it had to be about gameplay.
And the designer was supposed to take that
and iterate on it, dive deeper.
And to that point, we were not allowed to do awesome moments.
You couldn't just put something in because it was cool.
unless you were able to turn it into a gameplay skill test.
Now when we were finding gameplay,
we were told that it was okay to be as abstract as we wanted.
It didn't need a theme, story, or setting
as we were just kind of exploring what was going to be fun.
But, context wasn't necessarily discouraged
if it helped get the idea across.
as long as it didn't suck up too much of that time
developing the gameplay.
And finally, it had to be playable.
Not perfect, but playable.
We weren't going to do on-rails demos.
We needed to solve the hard design problems
of making something fun for somebody else to play.
So that means pulling people in for hallway testing
and iterating on the idea.
And this was super important because
We were pushing into unfamiliar territory
and trying to explore gameplay that
was outside of our wheelhouse.
It was really necessary to make that playable
so that we could figure out what the hard problems to solve
were.
But it wasn't always possible.
See, sometimes you would hack controls,
or there would be particularly difficult bugs
in some of the more complicated action blocks.
If there's so much duct tape that it's not
safe to let somebody else drive.
It's OK for the designer to do that as long as they're still
working at solving the hard problems of how
we're going to get the gameplay across to a player.
And then at the end, we did our show and tell.
We'd gather the whole design team.
Sometimes people from other departments would wander by.
And we would do this every week and show all of the action
blocks that we had worked on, especially things
that didn't work.
Because if you just stick those in a file cabinet
and hide them away, other people are doomed to repeat them.
Sometimes the designers would explain what their thinking was or their process to help everybody understand it.
And if possible, when we were playing it, we would do
a little bit of hallway testing right there, have somebody play it who had never played it before.
And at the end, we'd discuss, we'd give some honest feedback and a lot of cheering for the really cool things.
But there was no decision and no action items.
Like this was.
really about getting everyone together, sharing ideas,
learning from them and getting inspired.
So now we just had to use them.
The design test, the first thing that we did was
to take the design team and say,
use your action blocks to try to figure out
what Titanfall 2 single player was gonna be.
And this was a very open-ended exploration.
In the end, we did come up with what the core of the game was.
After a week, we had a bunch of different ideas.
We had a maze, a chase, a few different takes
on platforming and mobility, an old school shooter,
some Titan Buddy combat, a new movement model.
And we were all excited about the potential for the game
that we could make.
We did this for another six weeks.
And we ended up with about 45 different action blocks,
each one exploring a new type of gameplay.
And we were really excited at this point.
See, these specific chunks of gameplay
cut through all of our grand prototyping
and our rambling debates.
They gave the team a shared, clear vision of the game
that we wanted to make.
So how did this work?
I'll go through the process a little bit.
I'm going to start with an example.
This was my first action block.
And I think it's representative of the process
and some of the results.
As a layout guy who's done a lot of Geo in my time,
I started with this question.
What interesting gameplay can I get with a Pilot and a Titan
by just using layout?
My answer was a maze.
Now, as a kid, I loved mazes.
I've kind of always loved mazes.
As an adult who played games, I kind of hated mazes.
Because every first-person game that I've played that had a maze,
I didn't enjoy.
But this was about the time that Maze Runner had come out.
And that changed the scale of what a maze could be.
And I got this idea.
What if, as the pilot, you got out of the maze,
you looked at it from above, and you solved it,
and then you got in the Titan and you went through the maze?
So you weren't hitting dead ends.
So I did some pen and paper stuff,
and then I got in the editor and started blocking things out,
and I made a nice, simple maze.
OK.
It really wasn't that simple.
I was frustrated when I played this and walked around.
So I started trying to work out the kinks,
trying to do the design thing of solving the problems.
And I separated out different pieces of the maze,
made them a little bit simpler.
Honestly, it was still over-designed and over-complicated.
I felt at the time like it was important to have a significant challenge that would really
force people to get out and solve the maze, but I have a lot of sympathy for the hallway
testers that I dragged into my office.
None of them enjoyed this.
They did exactly what I did every time I went through a maze, which is just kind of walk
through and bonk my head into the wall.
So I thought, oh, they just need the right incentive.
So the next version, I added deadly ground lasers.
Because pain is motivation.
It turns out this was also not a success.
Pain and complexity just kind of make something really annoying.
So there were a few people who did what I wanted,
but nobody enjoyed it.
And finally, I ended up learning the right lessons, which
were to simplify it down, keep some of the things
that I learned on the way about landmarks and even the damage.
but make it straightforward enough that people would go in,
solve the puzzle of understanding
the environmental exploration, go aha,
and then get through it and move on to the next thing.
We played this at the end of the week.
Somebody played it who had never seen it before,
and it was really enjoyable.
Everyone kind of gave it a thumbs up,
and we identified, because of action blocks like this,
a tone that fit in the game.
This particular one set up an idea that we could do light exploration
and environmental puzzles as long as they were on the relatively simple side.
And we ended up having a lot of action blocks like this.
All of these were examples that didn't directly make it into the game.
Like there's no maze in Titanfall 2, but the tone in the central idea
had a fairly direct influence on different parts of the game.
There is environmental exploration and light
environmental puzzles throughout.
And then some of these early action blocks
did even more than that.
So designer Sean Slaback had an idea.
He wanted to create an alternate use for the smart pistol.
Smart pistol was this auto-targeting gun
from Titanfall 1 that was either the best or the worst thing
in the world, depending on who you asked.
He made the gun lock on to switches
that would cause panels to flip down
and create a cool little wall running path.
The light context was a construction area,
but more importantly, it was fun.
Like the maze, this action block helped us understand
kind of what the core of the game was going to be,
that we wanted to have platforming
and that the platforming could be a little bit more dynamic.
Now, we didn't have any idea where this was going to fit into the game that early on,
so we filed it away.
Until eventually, that is not the right thing.
Until eventually, Diner Jason McCord was blocking out the level The Beacon,
and he needed a way for the player to traverse this big open area.
And he had a unique weapon for that level that locked on to switches,
and he had a construction theme.
This action block fit perfectly.
And so he used it to traverse that space.
And this wasn't the only one.
There we go.
From crane puzzles to titans throwing the player,
we had this good library of gameplay segments
that we could pull from and slot into designs
later on in development.
These were things that we knew were fun,
even if we didn't know exactly where we were going to use them.
But action blocks didn't just tell us what we should do.
They also helped us figure out what we shouldn't do.
So if you look at Titanfall 1, we had pilots and we had titans.
And there were kind of these four food groups of gameplay.
There were human versus human.
There was human versus titan.
There was titan versus human.
And then there was titan versus titan.
And we, when we started on single player,
we wanted to have all of that because they were all fun,
good parts of what the game was.
So during development, during this early development,
we used action blocks to explore each of them.
One of the things that we thought in particular
would be great were human and titan interactions.
To be a pilot fighting a giant enemy titan
or next to your giant big buddy titan on the ground.
We tried giving the player different special weapons.
We tried using disposable titans.
We'd had titans that would go into a shield state
and get repaired.
And some of it was genuinely cool,
but they also showed some very real challenges
with this kind of gameplay.
Fights were either too easy because your big buddy titan
destroyed all the enemies, or too hard
for the little pilot on the ground
when enemy titans were smushing you.
there were a lot of hard problems.
And at this point, we hadn't even figured out
the fundamentals yet.
We still needed to get human-sized and Titan-sized
combat good.
So we decided to just not figure that out this game.
Because of those early action blocks,
we knew that we didn't want to solve that hard problem that
would, if we had kept working on it through the whole project,
led to bloated production.
And
a lot of time where eventually we would have had to cut it.
The early action blocks let us narrow our focus and really not underestimate some very
hard problems in design.
And all of these action blocks set up different fences for the design of single player.
By saying that, by saying no to things like mix, tighten, and human combat
We were able to scope the combat experience
to solve the problems that we already
knew that we had to solve, like Titan on Titan,
human on human.
Then there were some very special action blocks.
Sometimes you get context and you get gameplay,
and it creates this defining moment in development.
Jake Keating had this idea.
What if the player could control time travel?
This is kind of a crazy idea, but he wanted to get in there and do it.
And he needed a context to make it work.
So he took this Titanfall 1 map that he had designed for multiplayer, and he made a quick
overgrown duplicate of it so that it looked like it was from a different time.
And this set up the temporal research facility.
Then he set up...
some script so that you would teleport between the two locations at the press of a button.
And after that he built a path through the environment using that to explore
different gameplay elements with his new ability.
It was awesome. The entire team just fell in love and he sold the idea beautifully.
We saw a great idea for a level, and much of it
worked so well that it just made it into the final game.
Things that he did early on when he action blocked combat
with his new ability translated really well.
And there were other cool platforming puzzles
that he did because that's what he thought would be fun that,
again, directly made it into the final level.
But this did something else for the team.
It also showed us what a level could be.
what the tempo and the sense of timing and pacing
and how all the different parts of mobility and puzzle
solving and combat, how they could fit together
into one space.
And this was really wonderful.
This was also the only action block
that made it directly into the final game
as an entire level like this.
There were other ones that had this kind of levelish action
block.
feel to them. And they helped us evolve what our sense for a level was going to be.
But they really weren't the defining aspect of this early action block time. It was all of the
action blocks together. The things that inspired us and the things that guide us and the things
that set up those fences. And even ones that didn't come close to making it in the final game
had very real impact on what the final game was.
when Moe Lavi made this awesome action block that was absolutely never going to ship.
So he wanted destructible environment.
And it was awesome. Like the titan walking through the buildings was great.
And there was gameplay in there. You'd play hide and seek with this giant robot who was smashing through buildings.
But it was way out of scope for the team and the production
schedule that we had.
There were code reasons, and design reasons,
and production reasons, and art reasons.
And it was just too much.
We weren't going to be able to do it.
But in a really unexpected way, it
was the inspiration for the level
that I worked on for most of the project, Into the Abyss.
Now, not only did Mo's action block inspire this level.
But action blocks also played a significant role
in shaping the level.
A little bit of background.
Into the Abyss is the third level in the campaign.
It's sort of a Mines of Moria.
It's a shortcut through a bad place to get to the other side.
It ended up being this crazy underground factory that
constructed military test chambers,
but it started with Titans crashing through walls.
Because after finishing that action block in that sort of six week sprint,
we actually started designing levels, or pitching levels is a better way of putting it.
One of our designers, David Shaver, wanted to do the destruction that he saw in that action block.
And he knew that we weren't going to be able to do it for the scope of the entire game,
but he thought, well, what if we limited it to military testing facilities
that were made out of plywood shacks?
And then you could destroy the town with robots and stuff.
And then you could replace the town again.
And it was literally a boom town, a town that goes boom.
So the pitch went on.
If you're going to replace this town that's being destroyed,
you also need this crazy automated factory that
keeps replacing the parts of the town.
And of course, as the player, you'd
have to go into that factory.
I heard this pitch, and I got it.
really excited. I thought that there was a lot of potential. And the factory that built towns,
it tingled something in my brain. And it made me think of this particular piece of concept from
Jung Park. I love this concept. I just thought this was beautiful and inspiring. And I thought,
well, this fits really well with those towns that Schaeber was pitching.
What if we tag team on the development of the level?
I had more Geo experience.
He had more scripting experience.
And we could both design it together and come up
with a pitch.
And he said, sure.
So we rolled up our sleeves and we got to work.
And this was diving deeper and trying to design a level.
It's coming up with and pitching the entire thing.
So trying to figure out what the story was,
what the characters were going to be,
and the setting, and the beats, and the cool moments,
and of course, the game play.
Often, the gameplay would be inspired by those early action blocks.
And we did cool platforming early on.
What if we were wall running on those grassy panels?
What would it be like to play in that factory?
Or we would expand on the town fighting idea.
Like what about the town collapsing around you?
We wanted to find the best gameplay though, before putting it into the final design.
So while art was diving deeper on a style for the level
and we were exploring layout and story stuff,
we also took those ideas and used action blocks
to drill down on the gameplay.
And we started with a little open-ended, context light,
context light action blocking.
The idea was to quickly play with ideas
and figure out what was going to be fun
and what was going to work in the space
and get a handle on what the fundamentals were.
So as an example, platforming in that factory.
So art was worth wasting no time.
Todd Su, the lead environment artist,
did this 3D sketch of what the giant underground factory could
look like, because this is the obvious place to put a factory.
It looked cool, so we figured, yeah, we should use that.
And I used this with those ideas of big grass panels
as a starting point to do some simple platforming action
blocks.
I blocked out a space that looked almost as good
as what Todd had done.
And I put some giant rectangular grass panels in them.
And over a few days, I played with static platforming.
And I started.
those panels moving across and then moving up and down,
using them as elevators, just trying different ideas.
And this created a library of gameplay ideas,
but also helped me solve some of the design problems.
How do I translate my skills at making mobility
in an open multiplayer environment to a linear path
that we're trying to guide a player down?
I figured out what worked and some of what didn't.
While I was doing this, Shaver had a different approach.
He wanted to play with hazards and riding along
those platforms.
So he thought of things that could knock you off
the platforms, or things that you had to jump over,
or things like these beautiful rollers of death
that had pretty simple and straightforward platforming
to get around.
Now, really didn't have a clear idea
of what these were going to be in the factory.
But they were fun, and that was the first thing.
And they also solved some problems
with first-person platforming, like letting the player know
that there was a big threat they needed to watch out for
and having simple platforming navigation so
that they weren't overwhelmed by what they had to do.
So we took this and filed it away in the library.
Now, how does all this make it into the final game?
Eventually, we started.
doing level design.
Shaver wrote the level design doc.
And this is a page from that section about the factory.
I actually took this doc and did the layout for the level,
or this chunk of the level, and started
with the grand reveal of the world foundry.
So I wanted to do the best grand reveal.
And I went and asked an artist, specifically Jose Zavala, who
was the.
environment artist that was working on the level.
And I said, OK, we have this big factory.
What's the best view to look at it from?
And he gave me this view, which had a problem,
because that's where I needed to get to.
The doc, of course, reads, the pilot crosses the chasm
on blank moving terrain panels.
So this line existed because of those old action blocks.
We didn't have to have the specific details of what
the platforming was going to be.
Figure that out when we're actually blocking out the level.
But because of them, I was confident
that I'd be able to make good platforming to cross the space.
So I added some platforms.
And then I got them moving.
And then I did a little bit of testing
and a little bit of tweaking.
and made some adjustments, and eventually it
was a fun little platforming that
got you across the section.
I also added a little bit of context in my block out.
But just enough to get across the space, the timing,
the important points, so that when art came in
and the scripter finally made it work, for real,
it could all come together.
So when we got to full production,
Chad Grenier, who scripted this.
section of level, he came in and he just made it amazing.
The timing was adjusted a little bit.
There were definitely slight adjustments to the positioning
as the robot arms were taken a bit more into consideration.
But fundamentally, it was building
on the platforming principles that we'd already established.
Now, we had another problem, which
was, how do we get our pilot from one platform where he's
just?
squished a bunch of bad guys to the next platform
where he's got to fight new ones.
Again, in the document, it said, the pilot
jumps on a grassy terrain panel and rides
to another assembly area.
Well, riding didn't seem quite interesting enough.
And we actually still needed the detail
of how the grass got added to the panel
somewhere in this design.
So I came up with this freaky farm equipment hybrid.
It looks like a machine that.
you know, adds grass to things.
Art agreed that we could probably make something work like that.
But then how does this translate into gameplay?
Well, that's where Shaver's action blocks came in.
See, his exact layout of action block platforming,
where you jump from one to the other, that didn't work in the space.
But the general lessons, the big hazard and simple platforming,
that actually worked really well.
So when I ended up blocking this out,
I got to a point where I made a simple platform
that you jump on and then you see
the giant rollers of death.
And that forces you into the one path,
which is a simple wall run.
You jump around the other side
and when you land on the platform, it's covered in grass.
We ended up making a lot of abstract
platforming action blocks.
And some of them, like those, made it in.
There were lots of them that didn't.
They didn't work or they didn't actually fit the gameplay that we needed,
but all of them guided the gameplay in the section.
They were lessons in how to design that kind of platforming gameplay.
It's kind of like how a good piece of concept art guides the visuals of a level
without actually giving you the level layout.
These action blocks guide the gameplay and give you a target to shoot for without necessarily saying this is exactly what you're doing.
But we did use them in a lot of other ways too.
More specifically, we wanted to try to use action blocks in a more focused and directed way.
So we would take an initial idea and then explore it with theme and context and try to figure out what was going to work.
In this case...
what are the details of a factory? So we started with some just factory reference.
How are cars built or houses? Because apparently there are factories that build houses.
And this inspired memories of I think one of the greatest science fiction movies of all time.
And this particular scene.
Well screw that!
How are we supposed to get through this?
I don't think she said screw.
So what about something like this for our crazy factory
assembly line?
I took that and decided, well, we need to make panels.
We need to make parts of these houses.
So let's block out an actual assembly line.
I started with it turned off.
static environment that was blocked,
but that you could go through and do some simple platforming
on.
You get to a control room, and you turn it on.
And rather than trying to make it work in that area,
I just teleported you to another area
where everything was already moving.
And then I started playing with a bit more context ideas,
like laser things.
And screw this.
These were terrible.
It was not fun at all.
But rather than, you know, redesigning that little chunk,
I just kind of went forward and I started doing things
that you could jump over, figuring out that, oh,
if you had a place where the player could stop and rest,
that worked better.
And, you know, adding these in a row and having fire,
like there were different gameplay things that worked.
And we got to some place where some
of these were really pretty fun.
Learned some good lessons.
And then I moved on to a different problem.
What about building the house?
Because this was another idea.
We thought, wouldn't it be cool
if you had the house built around you
while you were fighting on it?
So I made a really simple frame.
I put some enemies around you,
and while you were fighting them,
I just had the walls of the house start to drop in
and block up the fight.
It was fun.
Like, it was a fun little dynamic moment.
when I played through it.
And then when I had other people play through it,
I started to see some problems.
They didn't just stay on the platform
and wait for the walls to fall into place.
So the next version,
I added a little bit of cover in there,
those white walls that are now around the frame.
That drew people to them,
because cover always draws people.
And they stayed there,
so they were in roughly the right position
while the walls dropped in.
Now, sometimes people would ignore that completely
and then just run off to go fight the enemies.
So the next version, I ended up putting it over a giant pit.
And that kept the players on the platform
because they didn't feel as encouraged to run and jump off.
The walls kept them roughly where I wanted them.
And I still had some problems with players being squished.
So I ended up making the walls come in from the front.
But this was a pretty cool little moment.
And I'd solved some of the design problems
with making this kind of gameplay and space
work before we were in full production for the level.
Now, it turns out we had to make a decision.
The problem was, in the final level design,
considering production constraints,
we couldn't do both of these.
We had to pick one that was more fun and better.
But because we had the action blocks to look at.
it was easier to make that decision.
Getting the house built around you
was the more enjoyable, the cooler choice.
We didn't need to, on top of that,
there were a couple of extra bonuses
from doing those early action blocks.
We didn't need to discover the design lessons all over again
when we were in full production.
The cover was already on the platform.
I knew it needed to be over a big pit, which
worked really well in that giant underground space.
So.
I just put them in and blocked it out when it came to blocking out this section.
The other thing that we got out of those high context action blocks were good
reference for art and animation and script.
See the level block out when relatively quick and it saved a bunch of time to be
able to see to say this is what we're going for.
Now there was still a ton of work to do from a lot of valiant people to put all
of this.
together but we had already solved the hard gameplay problems so at least that wasn't getting
in the way and causing us to redo animations and change art and set up like different rigging
throughout the process. We didn't waste time with that. Unfortunately there are some things that
just don't work out. There are ideas that you just love and those ideas are almost too good to test.
And action blocks are so far the best way that I've found to test those exciting and kind of untested things
Figure out what could make them fun or that we just shouldn't do them
So one of the earliest things
As I mentioned a while ago now
It feels like was that we wanted to have the test chamber combat like that was a big part of what the level was
going to be
the town was going to
switch around you. So while you were in a fight, we wanted floors to drop out and buildings
to be raised and everything to change in this dynamic battlefield and give you alternate
ways of flanking. And it was going to be really cool. And it sounds really cool. Like all
the ideas we had when we were talking about it were great. And we spent weeks trying lots
of variations on this.
Simple rooms with just very clean flank paths where you could go underneath and you would drop stuff out
It was okay, but it didn't add anything to the fight when you could just shoot the guy who was across from you
We tried more complex interesting environments with bigger enemies and a chance to use your mobility underneath and it ended up being too
Challenging and there were still reward issues and on top of that once you get underneath you didn't understand what was going on up above you
Interactivity.
Shaver made these cool pistons that you
could shoot from underneath.
And you could shoot them while enemies were standing on them,
and it would drop guys down and kill them,
which seemed like it was going to be obviously great.
And it still wasn't worth it, even
when there were giant rollers that they fell into
and they died.
We didn't stop there.
There were so many more action blocks
trying to figure this out.
Buttons on the top that would drop panels.
Sometimes we did some puzzle game play in the arenas.
We tried all sorts of enemies, glass floor,
whole houses being built around you.
But there were really too many problems
and it never ended up being fun.
They were a little bit too random.
There wasn't enough reward.
It just didn't quite work out.
I'm sure that there is a solution
and that there is a really cool dynamic arena fight
that can happen somewhere.
but we did not figure out what it was going to be.
And so it didn't go into the final design.
We still got cool stuff out of this time.
We learned a lot.
And there were even things like this little section that,
again, a little too random when you were fighting in it,
but it ended up being a template for moving the town
into position.
And honestly.
It was really great that in the end,
it just ended up being this little intro to the town.
It's a cool scene and it feels good when it's happening.
But more importantly, we figured this out
before we were neck deep in production
trying to do that final push on the game
where everyone is in full swing
and you're trying to figure everything out,
not having to figure out
what that dynamic town gameplay was then
because we'd already decided not to do it.
was incredibly valuable.
So let me give you one final example in the process.
Much like the noble platypus, nature's Frankenstein monster,
there are lots of different ideas
and things that come up in development.
Design is busy designing, art is arting,
coders are codering.
And we're getting a lot of new things.
And throughout development,
action blocks are...
a nice way to experiment with those new things and then try them out and see if you can mush them
into the level that you're working on. So to step back a little bit, there was a time where we were
still convinced that we were going to make that dynamic town work and that it was going to be fun
gameplay. During this time, like I said, Art was still exploring the space. Well, I went down to
Jose and I asked, how could we make this happen?
without using magic floating platforms.
And to me, because I wanted those individual pieces
to come out, I thought, oh, let's do giant robot arms,
and they'll pull out some and replace it with others,
and we can do cool stuff.
So he begrudgingly obliged me and made this little mock-up.
But he had another idea.
He thought, well, what if we put all those long panels together
in a strip?
And then that strip is mounted into this big underground
cavern where it rides on rails, and that moves up to position.
I hated this.
It was so against the gameplay that we were at the time
trying to figure out.
It was a great idea for solving the mechanical problem,
but it didn't fit the arena that I thought we were going to make.
So I filed it away.
Now I'm going to jump to the side a little bit.
The tech that we had initially did not
support players interacting with moving geo.
We knew we wanted to and so code put it on the schedule and John Haggerty,
one of our programmers, made it work.
And it supported players navigating and wall running through stuff like this.
Now, I'm flying around it just to show you broadly all of the things
that Jason McCord took and experimented with once this feature came online.
He made this big abstract funhouse where we could just...
play, or he could just play with a bunch of different ideas,
and try things to figure out now that we had moving Geo,
what was actually going to be fun, a fun challenge
for the player to do.
At the end of this giant, crazy Plinko machine that he had,
you'd get to the top of it.
And when you landed here, under your feet,
the entire thing would start rotating.
And it would go from vertical to horizontal.
And this was just a great example of like what you can do with action blocks.
You don't even know like where it's going to go.
But it was really cool and it was really inspiring.
So again that got filed away a little bit jump to the side one more time.
Shaver and I were talking about the overall flow and layout of the level.
And we had a problem which is how do you get from the factory to the arena that the factory has built.
Now, we knew a few things at this point.
We knew we were going to have a factory,
and we knew that we were going to have
the house built around you.
We also knew that we were going to have an arena
and that it wasn't going to be dynamic.
And I was just sitting there and kind of thinking
about this one day when I had an idea.
That sort of clear, beautiful vision
where maybe you start in the house in the factory,
and that moves through the space.
And it gets turned on its side and stored in this sideways
town that you do platforming to get up.
And then that entire town flips directly
from McCord's funhouse.
But also, because Jose had done that particular type
of contextualization, that would be a good delivery system.
And then you'd get to the top, and you'd fight.
So action blocking this, I got into the editor.
And
I just started building a little town.
I instanced it and stuck it on its side
so that when I was in the test map,
I could fight around the town, walk around the town,
and then jump up there and try to do some platforming.
And I learned a couple of valuable lessons
about guiding the player and mobility
in that kind of an environment.
And then I just took the thing, and I cut it
into a bunch of different pieces.
And I took all of those pieces, and I did the brute force
like mash them.
riding down a hall and then onto the side
and I put a couple of rails on the side
to sort of imply where it was gonna go.
And then eventually made it playable.
This was kind of a bit risky as a total idea,
but it turned out that it worked pretty well.
And like the other action blocks that I did,
I learned a lot that guided us in making the final.
block out of the level.
I got a lot of confidence that I could make something
that would be fun, even though I'd have to make some changes
to make it work.
And I made a template for what the final section
was going to look like and what the gameplay beats could be.
Not one-to-one, things definitely changed
as we did the work, and Chad added a whole bunch of touches
to it when he was scripting it that made it better.
But personally, this was, I think,
one of my most successful action blocks.
And there were a lot of them throughout the entire project of Titanfall 2 that influenced
the final design of the game in so many different ways. We had other abstract action blocks from
all sorts of other designers. We had wall running on spinning concentric rings and
arbitrary wall hazards. We had level experiments like deadly sludge and poisonous gas.
We played around with core loop for mobility and combat
exploration, and the list kind of keeps going on and on.
Directly or indirectly, all of these
influenced the final design.
Now, this whole talk might imply that we actually
got the process right in Titanfall 2 development,
but it was genuinely a bit more messy
like game development always is.
And we made some mistakes in how we used action blocks.
I think I've tried to give a bit more of an idealized process
than what it was actually like.
But I'm going to try to help you avoid
some of the same pitfalls.
So one of the things that we fell into
was naturally just trying to make something perfect
and polished and finished.
But action blocks are supposed to be quick and dirty.
You're supposed to get to them.
and get them done and then move on, generate more ideas
once you've found the good gameplay.
And there is some friendly competition that goes on.
There's a little bit of action block envy,
especially when you see Jake's time travel action block.
It's a thing to watch out for only in that it
can lead to spiraling out of control
to the point where action blocks blow into this giant thing.
They have to be kept.
quick and dirty. There is definitely a problem where the action blocks can
create the impression that things are going to be easier than they are. It's a
lot simpler to move a few pieces together and make a house than it is to
art and rig and animate.
and deal with the collision on having a house in there.
And so things like that, as part of the process of designing
the levels, they just need to be called out.
And the real production cost has to come.
And it's easy to spend a lot of time doing action blocks that
imply a much bigger game than you actually have time to make.
We did that a little bit.
There's also a problem with
making action blocks that are a little too abstract,
unless you end up with a game that's a really abstract game.
Because at some point they need to be turned
into the real world equivalent.
Now this doesn't mean that you shouldn't
make abstract action blocks,
just that the part of the process where you decide
what the thing really is,
has to happen during the level design phase.
You don't wait till the end of the project and say,
hey art, make something that looks real here.
you figure it out while you're working on it.
And finally, action blocks are not level design.
I personally fell into this trap a lot,
where I would do both, not only a little bit of block out,
but a lot of block out, and then I would just kind of like
mash action blocks in, and it ends up
being an easy trap to fall into,
but it's really important that action blocks
in the gameplay prototyping are separate.
from the actual problems of solving game flow and level design,
and that they're not mashed together.
So we have actually formalized the process a little bit
because of some of those problems that we had with it.
We do use action blocks early on to find the gameplay foundation.
Sometimes we do them with no direction,
and sometimes we have light guidelines,
like play with titans a little bit.
We also use them to get 100% confidence in our level designs.
We try to find the most fun gameplay,
but also make sure that we've solved the hard gameplay
problems before we commit to them in the production process.
And then we continue to sprinkle them out through
as inspiration strikes.
And of course, the rest is just making games,
which is the easy part.
So I would really like to thank everybody at Respawn.
It is an incredible team of people to work with,
and especially the design team, who
I wish I could call out all of their individual contributions
to that whole process.
There are so many of them.
Additional special thanks beyond the people
I already mentioned to Carlos Pineda, who
helped me with the submission process for this.
And to Rick Grubel who captured almost I think all of the video footage you saw and really just
saved my bacon. And GDC for having me and Amy Hennig for mentoring me through this process.
And finally, my daughter for her artistic contributions and my family for their love
and support. I am Soupy. I twit relatively infrequently at Mr. Soupy. Thank you so much
for coming.
And I believe we do have time for questions.
There are mics.
Hey, I've got a question.
By the way, awesome talk.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
I've got a question about the production scheduling
of action blocking.
You mentioned at some point that the player interacting
with dynamic environment feature was not
in the beginning of the production or in pre-production.
I'm just wondering where, how do you reconcile the lack of gameplay features and systems
with building prototypes that require them?
And how do you, do you assume that you will get these systems later on or like where do
you, at which point do you do these action blocks basically or do you polish them later?
So let me see if I'm clear on this.
Your question is about when we do, when we commit to.
other things that we need to do for production of the game versus when do we do the action blocks
in the production schedule? Yeah, exactly. Okay, so we try to do the action blocks, the big action
blocks very early on to get a general idea for what we wanted and so for example we knew because
of those early action blocks that we liked platforming with moving geo but we also knew
that we kept getting stuck in the moving geo.
So, one of the earliest code schedules, because we knew that there was something good there,
one of the earliest code features was, okay, let's make that.
And we use that to sort of imply what we're going to do later.
And then as the project goes on, we tend to be just a bit more aware of what we have the
time to maybe add in as a code feature.
Versus you know what we should be prototyping with action blocks and we tend to be a little bit more selective about prototyping action blocks
It'll represent gameplay that we can actually make in the time that we have left
All right, thank you
So you stop action blocking like in the beginning and just don't come back to it later on you just use whatever was there
We'll use it what we do action when we do action blocks for levels throughout development
We'll use it more in the context of the tech and the features
that we know are going to be coming online
or that we have online.
So we still will do action blocks,
but they're more limited in scope
to what we can reasonably make.
OK, thank you.
You're welcome.
Hi, a bit of a similar question.
In your first round of action blocking,
it sounds like you had a leg up because you
were making number two.
So you already had your.
traversal mechanics and your metrics.
So how would you approach doing the first round
of Action Block if you're working on a new IP?
Yeah, so the question is how would you approach
doing Action Block on a new IP where we really didn't have,
where you don't really have anything?
I think I would take more of an approach
from like a game jam.
perspective so.
And that was a little bit similar like there were we did have experiences that were kind of like that during Titanfall one development and that's where some of our first game play John Haggerty would.
Made all the moving geo he made the first like wall running and double jumping stuff in source and some of that was just.
Coming up with the idea and then in a similar way making it work as quickly as you can.
The problem there, of course, is that you have so much more of a broader place.
And so I think there, it's important to have the step before then, which is to just do
a little bit of that talking about and pitching ideas and coming up with potential games that
you want to make so that you know what the first set of things you want to experiment
with are.
And then treating it a bit more like a game jam where it's, okay, what are we going to
figure out with this?
Okay.
Thank you.
Welcome.
So this is a bit of a follow-on question to contextualness,
but you mentioned the, like for instance,
the prototype that you were working with,
with the building house and everything,
and obviously that has quite a tie
into the environment that you're going through,
and I was wondering if you're mindful of the narrative
that you already have at that stage,
are you thinking about that specifically,
or are you trying to not think about that
and then shape that later?
I'm wondering where the narrative sort of flows
into the types of prototypes you're coming up with.
Are you asking about the narrative of the entire game,
or the narrative of like a specific level?
Well, you had a specific script for what the pilot does
and the environment they go through
at this particular stage, but was that,
it was loose enough that it could fit
into any particular environment, or?
No, that was actually more specific in that case
to the way that that level was being designed,
and some of that was because in this particular case,
we were doing the action blocks alongside
trying to come up with the level and the story
and the beats and what the tone was gonna be for the level.
In...
you know since then the way that we've tried to refine and formalize the
process is to do the action blocks kind of before
with only a rough rough sense for what the
beats are going to be so you know when you're doing the brainstorming come up
with the this is what i think the level is going to be
and then uh based on that go oh this would be an
interesting place to play this would be an interesting place to play and go in
and start doing more specific action blocking
around figuring out what that gameplay is going to be.
But the actual level design as it was described,
it was aware of what those action blocks were
and some of that prototyping
and all that kind of discussion that went on with it.
Cool, okay thanks.
Yep.
I was just wondering how you would apply action blocks
to something like an indie group
that had maybe up to five to 10 people
as opposed to a very large company
like Respawn Entertainment.
Hmm, how to apply action blocks to a smaller indie group.
I feel like the biggest difference is in what happens
after having done the prototyping phase
and how you transition from that to full production.
And in some ways taking that into account
when making the decisions about what to go forward with.
So with a bigger company like Respawn,
where we have fairly big animation and art department
and they're really good and you can kind of say,
all right, we need all of this.
It's a little bit easier to say,
these are all the pieces that we wanna have
and kind of try to do everything.
And I think, I would think with a smaller group,
you'd get the same benefit of.
finding out what the gameplay was that was going to work,
but then have to be a lot more diligent
about what in production you decided to focus on
and what you actually had the time to take from it.
Because, and I didn't even get close to this,
like I showed the grid of 45 action blocks,
like there were probably 200 by the time we shipped the game
and it was way more than we could actually,
we could make in the time that we had by a large amount.
And part of the process, which I don't think we respected as much on this project, was that step
of saying, here are a bunch of good ideas. Let's decide on only the ones that we have time to make.
And I think the big difference would just be would be in being how selective that would have to be,
and at what point you'd need to cut off and decide. Thank you. Welcome.
And I think we are now done. So thank you all very much.