I'm Mark Flurry, and today I'll be talking about
the game I made, Thumper.
Is there anything else?
Yes, please put your cell phones on silent or vibrate,
and I'll remind you again about the evaluation forms
at the end of the talk.
So thanks for coming, and I am part of a two-person team
called Drool, it's myself and Brian Gibson.
You might know Brian, he's the bassist for the band Lightning Bolt.
He lives in Providence, Rhode Island.
Woo!
All right, and he's an artist and musician.
And he did all of the art and music for Thumper.
I'm a programmer.
I've been living in Korea for the past five years, but I grew up in the United States.
And I did all the programming for Thumper.
And the game design of Thumper was a collaboration between the two of us.
So if you've never heard of the Thumper,
it's a simple action game.
You are a space beetle cruising
through a dark, psychedelic world at high speed.
It's a rhythm game, but our goal was always
to make it feel like a unique and intense experience
and different than other rhythm action games.
We like to call Thumper a rhythm violence game.
So if you've never seen it, for the benefit of those
who are not familiar with Thumper at all,
I'll just play the trailer that we released
when the game came out.
It's about a minute long, I just have to figure out
how to get it on that screen.
Let's kind of do a drag.
That's good enough.
Thank you, thank you.
So hopefully that gives you an idea of what the game is like.
So you're controlling that little space beetle character.
You play the whole game with one analog stick
and one button.
So a lot of it involves just beat matching
with that one button.
As you can see the little rhythmic cues coming at you.
There's also times where you have to turn, jump, and fly,
avoid obstacles, and defeat some bosses.
Thumper was released last October on PS4
and PlayStation VR and Steam at the same time.
And then a couple months later,
I added support, we added support for Steam VR and Oculus.
So you can play the whole game
either with a VR headset or without.
To give you an idea of our background,
this is before we started working on Thumper.
We started back in 2009.
And at that time, Brian already had years of experience
working at a game company as an effects artist.
But he had never done all the art for a game before.
He'd never art directed a game before.
And he ended up doing everything for Thumper.
Brian's a very talented musician,
but he had never composed electronic music before,
never done game audio,
never made sound effects for games before.
And he did all the audio for Thumper.
So for myself, I had about six years
of professional C++ game programming experience.
So I kind of knew what I was doing,
but most of my experience was limited
to things like menus and user interfaces.
Actually, very little gameplay programming,
very little serious graphics programming.
Like a lot of people, I was kind of pigeonholed at my job,
and I did a lot of the same thing.
I also had pretty limited understanding of 3D math or graphics.
I'd never written a line of shader code before starting Thumper.
I didn't really even know what a shader was.
So in that sense, I was kind of starting from scratch.
And also importantly, like, neither Brian
and I had never really designed a game before Thumper.
We'd worked on games and kind of contributed to design discussions,
but we were never actually, like, responsible for designing the whole thing.
So back in 2009, we set a set of initial goals for ourself.
Number one was make an engine.
And I think this was largely just a personal goal of mine.
I'd come to GDC, I'd been to the
Experimental Gameplay Workshop,
I'd seen what designer programmer hybrid types could do,
and I was really impressed by that.
And part of me just felt like I'd never be
a real game developer unless I made my own engine.
I don't think that's true, but this is just how I was thinking about it personally.
The other goal was, you know, let's make our own game.
I think this is what motivates probably just about everybody who's here at the Independent
Games Summit.
I know we felt that, like, working at a sort of a corporate game development company, we
would never really be able to do what we wanted and realize our artistic goals.
And then our goal was, you know, we kept saying like,
oh yeah, we'll release it within a year or two.
You know, we said that for the first few years
of the project, and this was the last generation of consoles
so we actually imagined Thumper as an Xbox 360 game.
And of course, back in 2009, high quality,
like VR was just a fantasy, and we never even dreamed
that Thumper would be a VR game.
So I entitled this talk Seven Years in Alpha
because we started seven years ago
and we set our goals so far beyond our abilities
at the time that we just got kind of lost
along the way many times and it felt like a real adventure.
If we really wanted to hit these goals,
we should have made a 2D game,
something much, much simpler and easier to make than Thumper.
So it was like climbing a personal Mount Everest for us.
You know, it was definitely an adventure.
And before I get into the meat of the talk,
I'll just show you what it actually took to make Thumper,
which was over seven years of development.
We built the custom engine.
This is over a hundred thousand lines of code.
We added support for VR.
We released simultaneously on Steam and PS4.
And we did all that with no external QA.
It was just kind of Brian and us,
and then with some help from friends at the end.
So this talk will mostly be a chronological review
of Thumper, the development.
I'll talk about key moments where I made some breakthroughs
and art design and technology behind the game.
I'll talk about how our understanding of Thumper evolved
as we made the game.
And I'll also talk about how we changed
and how we look at games changed,
because if you work so long on one project,
you're gonna be a different person at the end of it.
Finally, I'll say that this is my story of Thumper.
Brian might tell it a little bit differently.
So the beginning involves concept art,
and Brian actually started thinking about making a game
and coming up with concept art
before we even started working together.
And with his friend Matt Brinkman,
they came up with a lot of concepts
about how the game should look.
And strong art direction was always
a real strength of the project.
And you can see from these early sketches,
the kind of dark mood and vibe was already set.
And these are all pencil sketches that Matt Brinkman made.
And you can see that he was creating this world
out of like these little cubes.
Because the idea was that it would always be a rhythm game,
so it seemed natural to sort of divide the world
into these spatialized chunks where each cube represents
like one beat or one measure or something like that.
And another thing that we determined quite early on
was that the main character should be a beetle.
And this was an idea Matt had.
In a rhythm game, you want something,
we wanted the character to be kind of circular
so it's easy to tell where the center point is.
It needs to be low to the ground so you can see over it.
And we didn't want some generic thing
like a spaceship or a car.
And I think with those constraints,
Matt just immediately said, oh, it should be a beetle.
And that was one of the first decisions
we made in the project.
And in all of these sketches, there's so many ideas.
And he came up with these really psychedelic monster ideas,
these things that we never used, but are really cool.
And what I like looking about these now
is I think you could make a completely different game
with these concepts.
And Thumper turned out quite a bit different,
but it was still really important
in establishing the mood and the overall art direction
of the game.
Another big contribution Matt made was the design
of the main antagonist of the game.
So at the end of every level, there's this giant evil head
and the track that you're moving on
comes out of his mouth.
And that was an idea we had a long time ago.
We call him Crackhead.
And every level he becomes kind of more demented
and more disfigured looking.
And this is just early sketches Matt made.
And the central one actually looks a lot like
how he looks in the actual game.
So I'll move on to some early prototypes that we made.
I joined the project in 2009 and.
Brian hadn't established that much of a game design direction.
He had little images like this, which were, you know,
he kind of imagined Thumper as something where it was
like a single track, instead of a bunch
of different notes coming at you, there would just be one stream
of notes, but you would be on a grid, and you could turn,
and that would be kind of the interesting innovation of the game.
So you can see here, like, there's kind of a layout
where like you're following a path,
and you have to make these right angle turns.
He also made this rendering.
Let's see if I can play it.
It's really short, but I'll play it one more time.
So that already kind of established some of the mechanics
and kind of some of the look of the game.
And that's what I kind of used as my target
when I wanted to start making, actually programming.
So, like I say, I didn't really know how to do 3D graphics,
and the first thing I figured out how to do was draw lines.
So all the early Coder art prototypes
had this kind of vector style.
And even though this is Coder art, I think.
I looked back and I dug up these old prototypes
and I also looked back at the emails
we were sending each other at this time
just to see what we thought about these.
Because I look at them now and they look quite bad.
But what was cool is that we were really enthusiastic.
And so I sent this first prototype to Brian
and his reaction was, perfect, great job.
And a month later I figured out how to actually draw quads.
And to Brian that was like 10 Christmases in a row.
And then I figured out how to do texturing,
and these don't even have filtering or mipmaps,
but Brian was just excited about the fact
that there's textures.
And then I figured out how to do a skybox and load a model,
and Brian stayed enthusiastic.
So, and I think what's really important about that
is if you actually want to make your own engine,
you're gonna, most of the steps
will not even be that fun, right?
You'll do a lot of stuff where there's no visual outward.
outwardly visible result of the work you're doing.
So you better find some way to stay motivated
and stay enthusiastic during the whole process.
So we didn't have much tech experience,
programming experience, and we also didn't have
much experience as game designers.
So we started to ask ourselves some questions,
especially as we got years into this project,
which was, is what we're doing actually interesting?
And will it be interesting for hours, right?
And this is kind of the questions I think everyone asks themselves
when they're embarking on a big project.
And we didn't really know, but we just started experimenting.
So I have a few clips of some early prototypes.
Just bear with me.
Okay.
So you can see that it was the beat matching mechanic,
moving on a grid, and you can see like I was doing
these weird like double like 90 degree turns
just to like kind of show that you could move on a grid,
but we didn't really understand like what was cool
about moving on a grid or why it was important,
but we still thought that that was gonna be
what kind of differentiated Thumper from other rhythm games.
So we actually took it in some really weird directions.
Here's another movie.
So here you have a health.
And you have to hit these beats to keep your health
from falling to zero.
You have to do these really awkward and difficult loops
really fast.
Yeah, as you can see, it was really easy to mess up.
And it wasn't really clear how.
It wasn't really clear what was going to be interesting about a grid-based rhythm game,
but we stuck with it for a long time and then finally we decided, well, it feels the most
fun just to go really fast.
And then we just started to abandon this whole idea of a grid.
And here's a later prototype.
So that one had kind of the fun rhythm game thing
where it's really dense and you're getting really
in the zone, you can lock in.
But it didn't really have the feeling we wanted.
It started to just feel like every other rhythm game
where it just kind of looks like a UI coming at you,
not like you're going through a world, right?
It was so dense, the notes are so dense.
The turns didn't have any weight or impact to them.
And then we made another prototype here.
It's kind of the same thing, but now we're actually like bending the track and deforming it as you're moving on it.
So you'll see some of the turns kind of like appear and then go away.
So in that one, we tried to make it more interesting
by bending the track and making you react to that
as you're playing just simple beat matching gameplay.
That also turned out to be a dead end and we abandoned it.
And we didn't really figure out where we were going
until a lot of basic polish work happened.
And at this point in the project,
we knew that the game wasn't that great.
And we were showing it to a lot of different designers
and friends we had that we really respected
who had made great games.
And a lot of their advice really didn't match up
with what we were trying to do.
Like we had already gone down this path for years
and when Brian and I would talk about the game we were making
we both kind of convinced ourselves
that we knew what we were doing.
The game itself didn't communicate these ideas to anyone else.
And we had a better understanding of where we wanted to go, but no clear path to get there.
And this is kind of this experience of being in the wilderness.
That's why I feel like we were in this state for a really long time during the project.
It's a state that can breed a lot of anxiety.
And you can feel overwhelmed, but it can also be very exhilarating.
As long as you can kind of keep moving forward without needing external validation and trust
yourself then it can be a really cool place to be.
So around this point in the project in 2011, I moved to Korea, and I think that was, you know,
kind of a challenging time because we'd already spent a couple years on this thing. It wasn't very
fun yet. And we, you know, now that there would be a 14-hour time difference between us, there was,
you know, a real risk of kind of losing momentum.
So to switch gears for a second
and talk about something a little more technical,
like the way we tried to address this
was by adding a little feature to our editor in our engine.
So this is a screenshot of the Thumper editor.
There's a bunch of like little editor windows for different types of objects
and the one in the upper left is like a browser of all the objects.
And this is like the first level in the game and there's like hundreds
or thousands of objects in this file.
So if I'm working on something and Brian's asleep and I'm like, oh,
you didn't set the settings on this material correctly.
It would be kind of annoying to have to tell him the name of the material
and then he'd have to open this file and find it
and see what I was talking about.
So we added a system where any object in the editor,
you can kind of highlight it or click it, select it, and copy a URL,
which represents a unique address of that object.
And here, you can see what the URL looks like.
The first part, the DRL, is like a custom protocol
that you can register with Windows.
The second part is the path to that file,
and then the last part is the actual name of the object.
And how to implement this is detailed on my development blog
with the link down there,
or you can just ask me for it after the talk.
But this ended up being super useful,
and it was like one of the.
times when having a custom engine that we could really
optimize to our own workflow paid off.
And we extended it a lot too, where late in the game,
we made it so that you could actually copy URLs
at a specific point in a level.
And that made it very easy to say, oh, there's a bug
in level 2-5 on beat 16, and I could just email Brian a link
and open up the game.
He just clicks it in the email, it opens up the editor,
and then he's right there looking at it.
So to get back to the design problems
that we were working on,
we didn't really figure out what the game was
until we kind of figured out how the turns work.
So this is a screenshot of one of the last
kind of grid-based prototypes we made,
where we found that when you're going super fast,
it just seems physically awkward and weird
to hit a 90 degree turn.
So we kind of made the turns less than 90 degrees.
And then here we made it a little more polished,
but it just looks weird, right?
There's this weird discontinuity
between the rectangular sections.
So we were still thinking of everything
as these discrete kind of blocks of rhythmic time.
And for a long time, Brian kept complaining
about how this looked,
and he didn't like the way these looked.
And as the programmer, I was kind of like,
oh, you're just being an artist,
you're just worried about polish.
Like, let's figure out the real meat of the game.
Let's figure out the design problem.
And I don't really think that way
about game development anymore.
And this is what it looks like in the finished game,
where the turn is this smooth surface.
And I'll explain how we got there, it's really important.
And also I'll go step by step.
And I remember this very well,
because I did most of this work
when I was on a workcation in Hanoi.
If you're a programmer and you ever travel,
I recommend you bring an external keyboard and mouse
and elevate your laptop to an ergonomic position.
It's very important.
So here if you look at this track,
so if you think of this as the path
that the beetle moves down,
every little square is one beat.
And then basically I figured out
how we could deform the meshes
so that they seamlessly matched up.
It seems pretty simple when I do this,
but for me it was a couple weeks of work
figuring out how to do that.
In a vertex shader, I calculate a rotation matrix
for every single vertex and rotate it around one axis.
And then I make sure that it's seamless
and it matches the next mesh perfectly.
We also added this ability to make it
so we could dynamically scale the meshes
before deforming them.
So here you can see I've...
made the path thinner, and then I can also extend the path.
So if each block is still the same amount of musical time,
we can scale the paths and make the beetle go faster
and slower really easily.
And everything's still seamless.
We also made it so that you could pitch the path up,
and you could also add a twist.
So it's all three axes of rotation that you can apply.
Another really important thing is figuring out how to
properly deform the normal vectors on these meshes
so that the lighting looks good.
So you can see that the lighting's all smooth.
There's no weird discontinuities.
This is extra important because a big part
of Thumper's visual look are reflection maps.
And these are just simple cube maps
calculated from the eye position and a normal vector.
But with the normal vector properly deformed,
then the reflections look really nice.
And in order for this to work,
we had to really highly tessellate the meshes
so that they look pretty smoothly.
So like Thumper spends a lot of time every frame
just deforming vertices in a pixel shader
in a way that's probably not, I mean in a vertex shader,
in a way that's probably not very efficient,
but a lot of, I think games end up spending a lot of time
doing other things like they have real lighting
or more complicated rendering
or they just draw a lot of stuff.
Thumper doesn't draw a lot of stuff
and we just spend the time on this.
So, you know, once this kind of came together,
and here's the final image again, you can see that it's
like a seamless, smooth curve.
There's a reflection map on it that has kind
of a really nice iconic look.
And it seems like something that you could like hit really fast
and then kind of continue going.
And, you know, beat matching was kind of.
the first kind of core mechanic we settled on,
but I think turns and the feeling of the turns in Thumper
what really make it feel good
and what make the game actually fun to play.
And I think like most action games,
there's always kind of one fundamental interaction
that you play the game hours and hours for.
Like in a hockey game, it might be like checking the dude
or I don't know, shooting someone in the head,
stuff like that.
And you can also see that the track is sloped up.
And this was another advantage of this kind of dynamic system where
Basically the whole time you're playing thumper you're moving up until where you're actually doing like a giant circle through space
But that helps you see all the obstacles a lot clearer, and it's not something that most people notice, but it's actually really important
So we use the same technology in so many ways.
And it's a real credit to Brian's kind of artistic vision
that something that was designed just to fix
this one little visual discontinuity
became like the fundamental visual tool
that he used to make the whole game.
So this is what the checkpoint looks like.
And I just want to show an animated version of this.
Right, so you can see.
These are the checkpoints you go through in the game,
and it's using the same vertex shader,
except we're applying a scale over the length of it,
so it gets down to a little fine point at the bottom.
And then Brian also realized that,
rather than just deforming these simple little squares,
we could make more interesting meshes.
So this is a segment of something we called the zillipede.
And this thing was something we spent
like way too much time on.
for its actual impact on the game,
but basically here we're now like, you know,
modulating colors and scale and width
of a whole sequence of instance meshes.
And it creates this kind of like evil looking worm,
and it's all, and the path that the worm is following
is actually another sequence,
and he's just kind of being phased along it to animate him.
And you can see here in this video that.
It's actually just like an animation in the editor. You can like scrub the whole thing back and forth and
Like yeah, we probably spent like a couple weeks. Just making that possible
and then
Ultimately it showed up
In the game it just kind of as a background element in one of the boss battles
but
You know, we also did a bunch of other experiments
with this vertex shader.
We created a lot of different creatures
and I really wish we would have found a way
to put this guy in the game, but he got cut.
And so here, like, these are just some screenshots
from the game where the decorative tentacles
you see on the side are that same vertex shader
being animated.
This boss and the obstacles you have to jump over,
the same stuff.
It was also really important for making the tunnels
that you go through, because the tunnels are all seamless
and they're reflective, and it's the same thing,
where now the mesh that we're deforming
is just like a cylinder that you're going in the middle of,
and we just sequence it.
And then Brian just did all kinds of stuff with it,
like this, here's a boss character,
this kind of spiral graph starfish,
where it's the same thing, but now he's kind of using it
as a weird particle system with this radial symmetry.
So Thumper is a music game.
I should say something about the audio,
although I think it's unique in that it was a music game
that found itself through visual experimentation.
And Brian did all of the audio himself,
and he changed what the game sounded like
so many different times.
There were a lot of different musical influences,
and the way we approached it was always
by making the gameplay first and the visuals
and kind of just adapting the audio to fit that,
kind of the reverse of how I think
a lot of other music games are made.
I also want to mention that I used FMOD
as the only middleware in the whole engine
and it was great.
It's very indie-friendly pricing
and they have awesome support,
so I just want to say that I recommend FMOD.
And this is,
this is, let's see if I can get this pointer up here.
So this is how we actually author gameplay.
And it looks a lot like a step sequencer,
where up top here, he's placing things
like the beats you have to hit, the turns in the track.
He's making an upward slope along the whole thing.
And then down here, he's triggering little samples
that go along with the audio.
And I think that this tool is really fundamental.
We call it the sequence editor.
And it was really fundamental in how we made the game.
You know, when I first started working on
building the engine and tools, I kind of was,
you know, the only thing I knew was the engine
I used at my old job, or Unity,
and I was kind of trying to recreate those tools
and make really general purpose stuff.
And I found that it was always got the best results
when I made something really specific for our game,
something that really, like a tool that could do
one thing really, really well.
And that was a lesson I learned along the way.
So in 2004, I've been working on the game for a long time.
And I think because we had the turns working
and the game felt really well,
we felt confident enough now to submit it
to things like the IGF.
And it got a nomination for excellence in audio.
And I went back and listened to that build
that we submitted and it sounds terrible,
like really bad, like the mastering is off,
there's a lot of distortion.
And I really think that it was the visual elements
and the funness of the game that convinced people
to nominate it for audio.
Just the fact that it's a music game
kind of makes you eligible for that category.
So I think that's why we got that.
And that was really cool.
This was us two years ago in the IGF.
And I think the best thing we got out of that
was just meeting other game developers
who were interested in our game.
And that was super motivating
to continue and finish the game.
So I'm going to go and talk about one more really important visual element of the game,
which are the post-processing effects we use.
And again, this was something that I just considered polished,
and Brian kept bothering me about wanting to use post-processing effects,
and our engine didn't support it,
and I thought it was something we didn't have to worry about right away.
But to say something really obvious,
like everything in your game needs to be interesting,
or your game needs to be interesting,
and how you achieve that doesn't really matter.
I think certain games like Tetris would be interesting
if you, you know, with no visual polish,
but Thumber's a game that is all about visual polish.
And yeah, all that matters is the final result.
And so.
Another thing Brian said was that, you know,
like when you think about visual effects,
post-processing effects are something that affect
every single pixel on the screen.
So in that sense, they might be
the most important effect you have.
So here's an image of Thumper fully post-processed.
This is from the final game.
And this is it without any of the post-processing effects.
I mean, maybe it looks kind of cool,
but for me it lacks like, you know,
all the dynamic elements, all the mood,
all the tone that this image has.
So I just wanna go step by step and show what we did.
And all of these are really.
easy to implement, they just took a long time to kind of tune.
So first we apply a bloom, a very standard effect,
and then we desaturate the scene,
leaving the bloom fully saturated.
Then we apply a cubic distortion filter over the whole scene,
which really distorts quite a bit.
And it's really important for selling the sense of speed
in the game.
And you can see that it really distorts the player
character a lot.
He gets way longer.
And nobody really knows that he's
being distorted because he never really moves
from that position on the screen.
And we kind of like the way he looks longer like that,
so it didn't bother us.
And then we apply a levels over the whole scene.
And this is just basically modeled
on the Photoshop RGB output, black-white output value
filter.
This was something that Brian just wanted,
and this is the one that changes the most
when you play the game, and it really helps
make different parts of the game
have a different mood or feel.
And we apply a radial blur over the whole screen.
This also helps with the sense of speed.
And then we apply a vignette, which is a generic effect,
but this kind of makes the,
keeps the stuff in the periphery,
it makes it less distracting,
and it also brightens the center of it.
We use the overlay blend mode to bright the center
of the, center point of the screen.
Like, there's no real lighting in Thumper,
so this kind of is like a fake HDR or something.
And then last but not least, we apply another vignette,
which we call the noise vignette.
And this, you can see it here, it only affects the skybox.
And it brightens the skybox,
darkens the edges of the skybox.
And then it applies this high frequency noise.
And you have to kind of see it animated
and look really closely,
but there's a noise texture being played on the background.
This helps the foreground elements pop more.
Also, like, I don't understand color space theory yet.
That's something I'm gonna work on for the next game.
So there's,
some pretty bad banding artifacts in Thumper
because we're doing everything in linear color space
and this noise kind of helps mask some of that.
So it's important.
So to summarize the essential visual effects of Thumper,
we use this vertex bend shader
to create the smooth surfaces.
We use tons of reflection maps on everything
and we use really highly tuned post-processing effects.
What we don't have are any complex lighting.
Like we support diffuse and specular,
but really don't use it almost anywhere.
No normal maps, no real particle systems.
Anything that looks like a particle
was just some big hack that Brian did.
And the nice thing about that is, you know,
I didn't have to program all of this stuff.
And this was like a real benefit
of having this kind of minimal aesthetic
and working with a really talented artist like Brian.
So I think at this point, once we really had
the visual look at the game,
that really built our confidence.
And now when we show the game,
like people would play 10 minutes of it
and they would get excited.
Well, most people would.
And I think, you know, for me,
confidence as a game designer means
just like being able to stick to your guns, right?
Like you have a bunch of stuff
that you don't understand yet
or you don't know what you're gonna do
and just feel like eventually you'll figure it out.
And I think that's what having the post-boxing effects
and all the visual elements gave us with Thumper.
So I'm going to make a little segue and then like I also gained some confidence as a programmer
and what's really interesting is that I'm a much different programmer
and the way I approach programming is different.
Specifically, one big thing is I don't use object-orientated programming anymore.
And when I was starting Thumper, it was really the default way I thought about stuff.
My brain, the gears wouldn't start turning unless I started typing out a class definition.
Or started thinking about object interaction diagrams.
And it was how everyone programmed at my old job, and that's what I thought real programmers did.
And I don't want to get into an argument about this
or something, but it's just interesting to me
that I change that much.
And when you work on something for a long time,
you do change.
And if you're interested in this,
this is a talk by Brian Will on YouTube
that I recommend you check out.
And now what I think good code is, is much different.
So I have a file called avatar.cpp,
it's about 5,000 lines of code,
and almost 90% of the gameplay and input handling,
a lot of the complicated stuff that makes Stumper fun to play
is in this one file.
It's all done in a procedural programming style.
And this is also the fact that when you're on an indie game,
when you're making an indie game,
or when you're working by yourself,
you should probably not program the same way
as you do on a big team, if you wanna be more efficient.
Another example is all the rendering code
is in one giant file.
Supports all these different rendering backends
and probably some new ones soon.
And that's 90% of the graphics code is in this one file.
So now I'm gonna talk a little bit
about how we brought Thumper to VR.
So like I said, we never imagined that Thumper would be a VR game.
And my first experiences with VR were very negative.
I think I used an Oculus DK1 and I did like a roller coaster and skydiving
demo and just made me sick.
And you know, most people who saw Thumper just thought it would make them very
sick if they tried to play it in VR.
But we were very aware of all the hype and the marketing opportunities around VR.
I ended up going to GDC China and I attended this talk.
I think he also gave it at GDC Europe if you want to check it out.
I thought it was very interesting.
He talked about a lot of the physiological causes of motion sickness and in particular
with...
VR experiences, what makes a lot of people sick are changes in acceleration, right?
Like when you're moving or speeding up or slowing down, and
your body doesn't have that same feedback, and it creates vexation and
leads to motion sickness.
So I
realize that in Thumper, you're going super fast
all the time, but you're going at a constant speed
most of the time, especially because it's a rhythm game.
And when you're going through the turns,
they're so fast that they just kind of feel
like teleportations, you don't really feel
like you're actually turning
for any extended period of time.
So we got Sony to send us a PSVR kit,
and we just decided to try to bring Thumper to VR.
And this is my home office in Seoul,
and this is one of the few times in the past five years
where Brian and I actually got to work
in the same physical space.
He came to Korea for three days,
and we basically didn't leave this room
for those three days,
and we figured out almost all of the fundamental issues
bringing Thumper to VR during that time.
So one of the first challenges was how does Thumper work
with a different field of view.
Because when you have a 2D game, of course,
you can set the camera field of view to whatever you want.
And in 2D, we have a super wide field of view,
and that really helps things feel deeper,
and it's essential to the sense of speed in the game.
In VR, the field of view is constrained
by the lens in the VR headset.
If you don't know how it works,
basically you have to use the same FOV as the lens,
otherwise things are gonna look wrong or broken.
So here in VR, it's about 100 degrees in PSVR
and everything looks way closer to you.
And when we played the game like this,
it just felt kind of slow and not exciting.
And so this seemed like a really hard problem to solve,
but Brian instantly knew what to do,
and that was just to basically scale the path by two times,
and just scale everything further away from you.
So in VR, you're actually going twice as fast
as you are in non-VR,
and it seems like that would be insane,
but it feels like you're going basically the same speed.
So to compensate for the FOV,
we just push everything further out.
And this is something that works for Thumper,
but might not work for a lot of games.
Another big question was, you know, how big are you
in the world of Thumper when you put on the headset?
Like, if you look at this image, like there's a space beetle
and all this abstract stuff,
there's no real world analog to these things.
So, originally we had it where the beetle was this big thing
and you were this little tiny guy,
like he's like this big spaceship or something.
And in this sense, you felt really detached and distant.
So of course we did the opposite where we made it so the beetle's about the size of your head.
And this felt like you were just like flying headfirst down this like hell ride.
And it was really intense, like too intense. It felt like you're getting smacked in the face.
And it was almost a little nauseating. And we found that the sweet spot was to be about where
the beetle's shoulder width about 40 centimeters. And this felt like you were sliding down the track,
kind of like a slip and slide or like a playground. And this was really the sweet
spot of intensity and comfort.
And so I saw that, you know, the famous game designer Jeff Minter, who I've never met,
but I saw that he was developing a PSVR game, so I sent him a build of Thumper.
And then the next day he tweeted this.
And so I think this means that we got the scale correct, because he really feels like
he was, you know, immersed in there.
I guess he never mentions Thumper in this tweet, so maybe this is just the way he lives
his life.
Like I say, I don't know him.
But...
Anyway, and then another cool thing we could do in VR
was adjust the scale of the bosses.
So this is Crackhead in level one.
And you see that's about as big as he can be
before he starts going off the screen.
But in VR, we just make him four times bigger.
And that means that you have to kind of look up to see him
and he's looming and more ominous.
So that was a nice thing about the VR experience we could do.
So the stuff with all the VR, like the fact that it worked out was kind of this like incredibly fortunate
And lucky thing like we kind of chased the technology, right? We're like, oh, we've got a game. It's almost done
Here's this big marketing opportunity. Let's bring it to VR and it worked out
but I don't know that that would work out most of the time and
You know, like I say, most of what we did was really specific to Thumper.
And I don't know that it's applicable to other VR games.
I think that the big kind of takeaway here might be that, you know,
when there's a new technology, no one really knows what will make it interesting
or successful, like the engineers or the business people behind it have some ideas
for sure, but it's always kind of up to artists to like use it in new and unexpected ways.
So in the last part of the talk, I want to kind of just talk
about what it took to get Thumper over the finish line.
So the last six months of the project, you know,
we decided we're going to be a PSVR launch title.
And that was the first time
in the whole project we had a hard deadline.
And it was a really brutal experience.
But the first thing we had to get
through was optimization, right?
So the game was running on PS4.
It was our main target platform at.
about 60 frames per second,
kind of bouncing off 60 frames per second, right?
And then with PSVR, like now we're rendering the scene twice,
we're doing super sampling to make it look better,
and we're rendering at 90 frames per second.
So that's almost three times as many pixels per second.
And if you tried to do this, I think like raise the bar like this at the triple-a scale like you just couldn't do it
Right because I mean you probably have experienced engineers who made a bunch of decisions
About how art assets should be built and you had tons of content all built to those specifications
And if you did this with a commercial engine like Unity,
I think it's really easy to paint yourself into a corner
where you've made it the whole game
with one level of performance
and you don't have any ability to get really deep
and tinker or you don't have full control
over the way your data is used
and ultimately displayed on the screen.
So I think our advantage was that we had a custom engine
and that I'm not an experienced graphics programmer.
So I was kind of banking that I'd done
a bunch of stupid stuff that we could find
and improve upon.
And we had a lot of help too.
I mean, Sony was very useful.
Like, I met with Sony engineers
and they helped me better understand the PS4.
So actually getting the,
getting GPU performance to spec was not that hard.
We did the thing where you draw.
both eyes at the same time, like if there's a cube
in both eyes, you draw that cube for the left eye
and then immediately for the right eye.
It's kind of called multi-slice rendering.
All the major VR headsets recommend
you kind of render this way.
Also, because of this vertex shader,
I was already using tons of hardware instancing
where like, you know, we're drawing one mesh
many, many times, so you only send that mesh
to the GPU once and then you apply
different parameters to it.
using a shader, and that was a big win for Thumper.
And then we did a few specific things for the PS4,
but not that much.
Kind of the biggest thing I had to tackle
was CPU optimization.
I mean, Thumper all runs on one thread on the PS4,
so I didn't have time to build a multi-threaded engine,
so it was really just about getting that one thread
to be fast enough.
where basically everything happens.
And most of that, as is often the case,
had to do with memory access and allocation.
So I just want to explain what I did there with Thumper,
and it's a pretty simple thing that worked.
And it was heavily inspired by this blog post
by Nicholas Gray.
And this whole blog that he has,
it used to be called the BitSquid Engine,
but now it's called the Autodesk Engine.
And if you're interested in building your own engine,
I think this is a great resource to start.
So the main thing I do is I use custom allocators everywhere.
And so that means I override operator new like this.
So you can't use operator new.
It forces a higher level of discipline over all the code,
where all the code uses a custom allocator.
And then that forces you to think about,
how is the memory being used?
And is it being used efficiently?
I also require that all memory I allocate is deallocated,
so in the destructor of the allocators,
including when the program shuts down, they will assert.
And this is a really good way
to just find memory leaks right away.
And I didn't have to build any sophisticated
memory tracking tools or debugging tools.
This was sufficient.
And the reason is is because
Slumper's allocation pattern's quite simple.
When the game starts up, I just malloc.
Massive chunk of memory I take advantage of the fact that like, you know
The ps4 has about like eight gigabytes of memory and that's not close to how much thumper needs to run
Or probably most indie games need to run
And then so to start divvying up this big chunk of memory,
I use a stack allocator.
So when you see like the Druill logo,
like I'm basically loading over half the game
during those like 10 seconds.
And it's a stack allocator,
which is super easy to implement.
And then I allocate a bunch of little utility allocators
for certain things that are necessary
while the game's running like effects and animations.
Those are almost all pool allocators
and there's a couple other ones.
And then when I load a level,
I allocate from the other side of the stack.
So it's a double-ended stack allocator,
still really easy to implement.
And then when the level's unloaded,
it goes away and I can load a new level.
So I can do everything with this one big chunk of memory
and it avoids fragmentation problems.
And I just have this,
these are, I only use four types of allocators,
the big stack one, the pool, scratch, and frame.
And these are all really easy to implement.
I won't go into them.
And I think the thing I just wanna.
mentioned is that I think there's a kind of a,
when I was learning programming,
there was this kind of attitude that, you know,
memory management is super hard,
and it's really dangerous.
Like, you're gonna be spending all your time
chasing down memory leaks and stuff,
and that's not the case, I don't think.
And it's sad that it's not taught in a way like this.
Like, once I read this, that blog post by Nicholas,
I just like, a light went on, and I was like,
oh yeah, that's how you should use C++,
and that's how you should manage your memory.
And,
And, you know, if you think that using like a garbage collected language or using something
like Unity is saving you a lot of time, like, it might not actually be true.
And another big advantage of optimization,
or of art direction with regards to optimization
is that Brian was like totally into this minimal aesthetic.
And if you look at the game,
almost all the scenes in the game are,
there's one or two key visual elements.
Like there's like the boss or the tentacles or tunnel.
We never do all of them at once.
And that kind of, you know,
lowered the bar for what I had to deliver as the programmer.
And Brian was really good about defending
what was really critical about the look,
but also he was really good about cutting the fat too.
So we didn't really have to sacrifice much visual quality
to get the game running in VR.
And a nice side effect was that with PS4 Pro,
we can render in native 4K,
because we had done so much optimization.
So if you look at, it's easier to see on this chart,
like that's, you know, native 4K at 60 frames per second
is about 500 million pixels per second,
which is more, but the PS4 Pro has a GPU
that's about twice as powerful,
so it was well within what we could do.
And then we also were able to enhance the quality on PSVR
if you're running on PS4 Pro.
So during this whole optimization and bug fixing period,
we were still play testing the game.
And we were still really just,
everything was coming in super hot.
And I know that we had this 10 minute demo
that we showed many times that people really liked,
but there was the whole rest of the game.
It's a 10 hour game and how,
whether or not that whole thing's gonna hold up and be fun.
and be understandable for everyone is something,
a question that we didn't answer until really late.
And I think it was because of these people,
especially, that we were able to do it.
These are all people that I sent builds
and donated their time,
just because they were excited about the game.
And it was everything from just people telling me
that the game didn't run on their machine,
to people who played the game for hours and hours
and became experts and helped us add new expert mechanics.
So we're really grateful for that.
And like I mentioned earlier how,
you know, there's this feeling that like no one could
help us, right, like when we're in the wilderness.
But at the end of the project, these people saved us.
And like having like a community of other indie developers,
I think is one of the most valuable things you can have.
So like I said, we had no external QA.
And I think the way that we got away with that was that,
well, it's a pretty simple game,
but we also did tons and tons of game shows.
It stopped being fun after a while, but we did so many of these that,
like, the build was constantly being tested.
We were constantly finding usability and technical issues.
It was running on all this different hardware.
We also took advantage of the Sony kiosk demo program
where I made three different kiosk demos over the last year
of the project, and those all require a certification pass.
So I got some experience doing that.
We were also on the PSVR demo disk, which was another certification pass.
And it was a lot of extra work, but it ended up being worth it.
And then Sony also offered VR consultations,
where we would send them builds, and they would just point out
issues with the way we were doing VR.
So that was really useful.
I also want to just mention a couple partners that
helped us get over the finish line.
We did everything from the business side
and the marketing side ourselves.
And it was really hard for us to trust anyone.
I mean, I'm the kind of person that made my own engine,
so maybe that explains it.
But.
You know, like to release on PS4 in Japan, which we did at the same time as everything else,
Zach from Kakahashi Games was really helpful.
And he, his business model I think is what a lot of indie developers are looking for.
And I would recommend working for him if you want to bring a console game to Japan.
And also Chris Dwyer is a indie marketing specialist.
He's kind of like a one-man company,
and he actually reached out to us
and helped us with marketing and press outreach
during the last month of the project
when I was the most stressed out.
And he was really a lifesaver.
I think the nicest thing I can say about Chris
is that during that month he really felt like
part of the team, and I really trusted him.
So I think he doesn't have that much free time
because he's just a one-man company,
but I also highly recommend Chris.
So the game came out and, you know, it was a very weird experience, like this, you know,
thing that you've worked on for so long and suddenly it's out, it's done.
I'm still kind of processing how I feel about it, but more than any review score
or anything this user from NeoGAF posted this image
and I think this alone made it all worthwhile.
So I mean, I think this kind of summarized a lot of our goals with Thumper.
And it's cool to see stuff like this.
But of course, we weren't actually finished.
There's an immense pressure to sustain and maximize after so much work.
We immediately started working on Vi and Oculus support.
We added a new gameplay mode called Play Plus Mode.
We did support, bugs, customer service,
stuff everyone has to do, and I'm still working on stuff.
So it's really been, even though it came back out in October,
it's really been a full-time job since then.
And so yeah, if you wanna go on your own
and make your own engine, that's kind of
what you're getting yourself into.
So yeah, I have just maybe one more unrehearsed comment
about the whole project.
And I think what I will remember most fondly
about the whole project is not the kind of external validation
or the review scores or sales or anything like that.
It was that feeling of being in the wilderness with Brian
and having
that freedom and that privilege to be able to like, you know, just get totally lost and like not be conscious of,
you know, what other people are going to think about the, about the game or feel about my position in the industry or anything like that.
And, um,
That's a privilege that not enough people get,
and I think it's something that has to come from
an industry or society that makes that an important thing.
It's kind of like going to university or education,
or getting an education.
You can't do that on your own.
It takes a community of people.
So, yeah, I'd like to thank everyone who helped us along the way.
Thank my wife, who I couldn't have done it without.
So that's the end of the talk.
And we have some time for Q&A.
And this is my email address if you want to message me.
If there's any questions, there's some aisle microphones.
I recommend you use those.
So I have two related questions.
It's basically how were you full-time all seven years
and how did you fund the project?
Contract work or funding or?
Okay, yeah, I was full-time the last,
out of the seven years, the first two years
I had a day job working at a game developer
and I made it work on Thumper only,
like nights and weekends.
The next five years I was full-time.
So that included programming, marketing, biz dev, all that stuff.
And funding was mostly savings from my job that I worked for six years
and the support of my wife, whose job in Korea came with a housing stipend
and helped me have a low cost of living.
So that's how I did it.
So both the look and also some of your implementation notes about Thumper kind of remind me of the early 90s demo scene of massively optimizing graphics and tiny little packages.
Was that an influence on y'all at all?
I don't think it was a direct influence.
Although we like that stuff, I mean I think a lot of it's interesting.
I think like...
Some of the things we talked about were like,
we wanted it to be really psychedelic,
but we didn't want it to be like light feeling
or kind of wishy-washy.
We wanted like hard psych, you know, like we wanted,
and kind of like 2001, right, like the monolith,
like that image is like so simple and stripped down,
but it's like terrifying.
So I think, yeah, there were so many influences,
more than I can mention, but that was a big one.
All right, did you satisfy your curiosity
at building your own engine?
And second question would be,
would you use a commercial engine knowing all the job
that you need to do to actually have an engine?
Yeah, I mean, it satisfied a lot of my curiosity.
And I did have to always remind myself
that I don't wanna make engines for my life.
I don't want that to be my goal.
My goal is to make games.
So sometimes I felt like I went down this weird rabbit hole that wasn't necessary, but ultimately, yeah, it was worth it.
And I don't think I could ever stand using a commercial engine now, because even if it does 99% of what I want to do, the last 1% is really important to me.
Does this one work?
Yep.
I was wondering, I saw how you created the tracks
with pieces being put together,
but in the game, does your character,
does the beetle move in world space,
or does the track move around your center point
when you're moving?
The camera and the beetle are actually moving through space.
So there's actually a track out there that's being built
and it's moving along.
Yeah, yeah, it's being built out like 50 beats ahead of you,
and...
I mean, at one point we had it so that we could animate
everything, every frame, but we kind of dialed some of that
back just for performance reasons.
But yeah.
Cool.
Looks great.
Also, I made an observation that back when you had the 90
degree turns, and it's kind of like on a grid, and you're
picking up balls, it reminded me of the bonus stages in
Sonic the Hedgehog 3.
Oh, yeah?
OK, cool.
If you want to see a shipped version of that, check that
out.
OK, cool.
Thanks.
So I fully intend to watch the YouTube video you referred to, but can you summarize in
a nutshell what's wrong with object-oriented programming?
Yeah, um...
I'm not disagreeing, I'm curious.
No, sure.
I mean, well, this is just me, and I don't want to go too long on this, but yeah, I think
that...
Like that video says, like object-oriented programming has this goal of encapsulating things as a way to make
problems easier to solve. And I think that it forces you to do encapsulation like all the time, including really early on.
And the reality of how at least I program is that, you know, first I just kind of want to get see something working and
I want to
then like, you know, maybe then make it more beautiful or make it more performant or something.
And I just found that object-orientated programming just creates this meta-problem
that I'm spending all my time solving and not actually solving the actual problem I want to solve.
I also find it much easier to think of things often as data and...
functions and data as separate things,
especially when your goal as a game programmer
is to transform tons of data at once,
and trying to fit something into an object-oriented
programming model is not, for me, a very useful tool.
That's basically it, yeah.
Hey, so when you were making music for Fumper,
was the music more informing level design
or was it the other way around?
Like, did you start first with the track
that you wanted to make and then build the level around it?
Or was it more like you started with what you want to do
with the level and then sort of added the music to that?
Well, yeah, Brian made all the music,
but basically, I mean, it was so iterative
that like, you know, we're constantly changing the levels,
constantly trying new music.
So there's so much experimentation and back and forth, but.
broadly the overall goal was to like kind of make a fun action game and then add music that accompanied that so
We never like I mean, there's a soundtrack for thumper and some people enjoy it and that's cool
But like the goal is never to make like songs that would be catchy or memorable
It was more about to make like a game experience that that use sound
Thanks for the talk did you ever come close to quitting?
No, I don't think so.
I mean, and like I said, that's like a very privileged thing to say.
You know, it's kind of like, you know, I do what I want whenever I want.
You know, like, I didn't really give up because it was always something that was interesting.
And certainly, like, during the seven years.
that we were working on it, you get burned out,
and you do have to start thinking about
your own psychological well-being.
And like I say, there were parts where the uncertainty,
anxiety were kind of paralyzing.
And certainly towards the end of the project,
when I think about how hard it was,
and how dehumanizing and brutal the act of commercializing the game was.
There's certainly things that I hope I never do again.
Or I got making a game all by myself out of my system,
and I don't know that I want to do it the same way again.
I just wanted to ask, how did you do difficulty tuning?
Because I'm terrible at the game. I love it.
How did we do difficulty tuning?
I guess it was mostly just observing people.
You know, over, like, we kept making the game easier, basically,
because obviously we were, like, total experts and we had no concept
of how hard the game was by the end of it.
And so, you know, we did all these game shows where we would watch people
and then we just, you know, tried to make sure that, like,
95% of people at least could.
beat the first level or get through most of the first level.
And I think there's also, like,
Thumper's not that hard a game.
Well, maybe I'm biased, but it's not that punishing, right?
Like, you'll die and then you just go back
to the previous checkpoint and you get to practice
the same thing you just did.
And I think there's just something about rhythm games
that are particularly frustrating.
You know, you know what you have to do,
but you just can't do it.
And so that's why I think a lot of people,
they think it's a hard game.
Hey, thanks.
I was wondering how you dealt with cross-platform problems.
since you just used FMOD as your only middleware?
Oh yeah, so right, FMOD's awesome
because it worked out of the box
and that was something that just worked across everything.
But for cross-platform stuff,
right, so at first I wrote this really bad renderer in DX9
and that's what I was using for a long time.
And then once I had to port to PS4,
that port took a long time mostly
because I had to kind of...
make the engine cross-platform.
I had to build that level of indirection
or abstraction into the engine.
And I think that was another instance where like,
like naively I was like kind of anticipating this
from an object-orientated perspective
where I was like, oh, I'll make like a mesh
and then I'll have like a DX subclass of that mesh
or do the same thing materials.
And that's just through all that garbage out
and started just basically doing procedural programming
and slowly refactoring things out.
I don't know, nothing's that special.
I think every time I've added a new rendering back end,
the code's gotten better
because I just kind of understand things better.
Can I follow up?
Did you have a lot of support problems
with different graphics cards on PC and stuff?
Yeah, I mean, still dealing with them.
And it's always hard to know.
I don't know, do Unity games have all these problems?
I don't know, maybe it's just my game
because it's a custom engine.
But yeah, we kind of worked through them.
And like I say, customer service is actually
a really important skill if you're gonna make
a custom engine, because you've got to convince people
to trust that you're actually gonna fix it
and send you a system report.
And especially with the VR stuff,
it's still kind of like the Wild West
and there's so many different configurations.
And I think for 99% of people it works,
so that's pretty acceptable.
Thank you.
Thanks.
If there are no more questions,
then that might be the end of the talk.
Okay, thanks.