Hello, can you hear me?
Welcome to the State and Future of Board Games 2018 edition.
Oh wow, thank you.
Bit of housekeeping, I will get in trouble with the CAs
if I do not ask you to please fill in your surveys
at the end of the session.
We incorporate the feedback that we get from those surveys.
Tell us what you think, what you liked,
what you'd like to see more of.
Feedback like that has been incorporated
from last year into this year,
and will be again into next year.
It's like the circle of life.
from the Lion King, and I can be here in a year's time holding up a cub for you, if that
is what you request.
Please do not, please put your phones on silent or make them extremely quiet.
And we'll have a general sort of, oh, thanks, panelists, also you.
We'll go through a series of topics ourselves together, and then we'll open up to some questions
sort of halfway through the session.
and close off about five minutes from the end for a short thing that I also want to say.
Thank you all for coming at 5.30 in what I guess is now the evening.
My name is Paul Dean. I am one of the co-founders of Shut Up and Sit Down.
I hope by now on the way here you have all seen our large, very green this year, gaming area,
which is full of picnic tables. You can sit down and play a bunch of board games
that we think have been particularly exciting over the last year.
It's a lovely place.
to relax, do something non-digital, and also maybe accidentally network and discover that
you are sat next to the audio designer from Bungie or something like that.
It is an absolutely wonderful space.
I assume you all also know you're here because you love board games.
You know they have exploded.
Board game growth is now kind of exponential.
It is more than a billion dollar industry.
While it's kind of tapered off for video games on Kickstarter, board games on Kickstarter
have gone insane.
We have now...
It's...
3,500 board games were released last year,
up from 1,000 in 2000,
and about 2,500 in 2005.
It doesn't seem to be stopping.
With me to discuss this incredible phenomenon
is a series of panelists who can introduce themselves
better than I could introduce them.
So we're gonna start right here with...
Hi everyone, I'm Jonathan Yang.
I'm a game designer.
Somebody rude. It's a decent sized whoop.
I've designed a few games including Star Wars Imperial Assault, Doom the Board Game, and Bargain Quest.
Many of them have been with companies and some have been independent and on Kickstarter.
So, yeah.
Hi, I'm Tom Lehman. I'm the designer of Race for the Galaxy, many other board and card and dice games over the years.
I'm Andrew Fisher. I'm the board and card game manager at Fantasy Flight Games.
I've worked there for about seven years as a game designer.
I've worked on things like the Star Wars role-playing game,
the Rune Wars miniatures game, and most recently the Fallout board game.
Hello everyone, I'm Anna. I started in Facebook and social games when that was still a thing.
Then I moved into mobile games and now I'm working at a company that's making Dized.
It's an app that will help you learn board games so you don't have to read the rulebook.
Thank heavens.
I'm going to open with the same question I opened with last year, which is, we are at
a predominantly video games conference, so folks, what is exciting about being a board
games designer in 2018?
Why should we care about this?
Why should we all be here right now talking about board games?
You're referring to we as in video game designers?
All of us, all of these folks who have turned up.
Can we justify ourselves at this conference?
Clearly we can.
I mean...
Board games are cool, right?
And getting cooler, which is nice.
Everyone in games are in basically the same business,
creating engaging, interactive experiences.
And board games are just as valid a medium of doing so
and provide a good window into how to do exactly that.
A big advantage of board games is
that none of the mechanics are under the hood,
the way a lot of video games can hide things with programming
or physics, et cetera.
in board games you just have like a letter you've written to the player on how to enjoy a game
and the margin for error is much lower there and it is a great way for video game designers to learn
game design and for any kind of designer to get better. I also think one thing that's
getting really exciting with board games is kind of the merging of the digital side and the tabletop side.
My talks today was on just this topic.
My department makes a lot of app-integrated games,
is what we call them.
They're basically board games that also require an app.
So they're a game that requires both digital and physical
components to function.
On top of this, a lot of the talks I've gone to today
are about integrating apps into the process of learning games,
into creating digital versions of board games.
And so I think the lines are blurring
between the two different forms.
They'll only continue to blur further.
as we introduce technologies like VR and AR,
and they become more accessible and more saturated
in the market.
I think board games are going to get bigger and bigger.
I don't think they've even seen the Golden Age yet.
It's a great time to jump into them,
if anyone here is thinking about changing careers.
Well, there's a valid point there.
I mean, your company, if I'm correct, is recruiting.
People are recruiting right now.
Yes, we're recruiting Unity developers.
We haven't reached that yet.
It's worth it for a bit.
putting that out there.
But have we reached saturation?
I don't think so.
No, I don't think so either.
I don't think we've even seen the beginning of how big board games can get.
Right.
It doesn't seem to be going away.
There is a graph that we put up on Sharpensitdown's news on Monday where someone had plotted the
growth of board games and it just goes like that over the last, what, 20 years.
It's just absolutely insane.
Anna, you work on apps that help people to learn board games.
which has always been one of the barriers of entry.
And I generally like to ask the panel,
is the way that we're learning these games changing?
I remember board games as a kid being drier,
generally having larger manuals,
the way old video games used to be.
It's not like that anymore, is it?
We're getting better at this?
Well, I think that people are trying
lots and lots of different approaches.
There's not only the integration with digital.
But there's also experiments like Freedom and Freeze
had three games this year, which basically start with,
draw a card, do what it says, flee, fear, and so on.
And there, you're building and learning the game
as you start playing it.
And he's just doing that without any app or anything,
just building the game that way.
Legacy games also change things, because you're discovering,
perhaps, more of the game.
as you play, which we used to call this program learning
at one point, but now it provides a way where the players have a huge incentive
to actually learn the new rules
so they can figure out how the game state is evolving.
Yeah, so
the way games have evolved, the tutorials and the way to learn them have also
evolved with them, so we had
a huge upsurge of YouTube videos now that will teach you how to play a game.
But we're with our app where at least we're trying to go one step further and actually have
Someone there like a digital person at the table that will teach you how to play the game
I think board games will move more into that and I
But games will be designed that have tutorials built into them already
But there should be ways to play games that don't have that without a rulebook
So and touching briefly on
We're talking about games increasingly integrated with apps like
Mansion of Madness, 2nd edition, XCOM, things like that.
Is this the new future? Is it also the way forward?
That it's great to have an app that is the referee that does the shuffling for you?
There's an Imperial Assault app as well, right?
Surely this is the best way to play games now?
Just have someone else do all the legwork.
Well, it's really just another way to play games, right?
And it's not here to replace traditional board gaming.
I think these different forms are always going to exist.
But I do think that a future of using digital tools to help
even your traditional board games is definitely
going to be the case.
Look at the Dized app.
Look at YouTube channels that teach games and review games
like it.
all of your traditional games.
A lot of people are still, a lot of people
don't even read the rule books.
They go to How It's Played and other YouTube sites
and get it explained to them by somebody
who is much better at it than your friend Paul, who's just
struggling through the learn to play at the gaming table.
That's right, Paul.
Actual fact.
So I do think, well, I don't think app integrated games
and technology.
integrated into the games is necessarily going to replace tabletop games, I definitely think
that technology augmenting even your traditional tabletop games is here to stay.
They're not going to fuse and board games and video games won't merge into something
more powerful that kills all of us.
Some horrible gaming Voltron.
Okay, that's fine.
Well, there's certainly some resistance to always putting an app in a game because there
are people who say they spend the entire day.
looking at their screens, looking at their phones,
and when they want to play a board game,
they don't want to look at their phones.
So I think you're going to see a spectrum
where some people are all in favor of the apps,
all in favor of integrating apps into the gameplay,
and some people are going to be resistant to it.
And I think it's great, because the hobby is growing,
we have the capability to satisfy
many more different interests and gaming tastes
than we had 15 years ago.
And there will always be those purists, right?
The people who just want, you know,
I want my tabletop gaming to be viable
after the nuclear apocalypse,
where like I won't need any electricity,
I won't need any batteries or anything,
I can just play what I wanna play.
And you know, for them, we will continue to produce games
at as high a quality as we can manage.
And I think at the end of the day though,
a big thing to understand is that
all tabletop gaming has a pretty fundamental priority of the player, right?
And I always say this quote from Tim Fowers, but what we do is we make software that runs
on people, which is, at its core, even the app integrated stuff, right?
That stuff is, in some cases, not meant to replace the player, though sometimes it is.
It is meant to give the players a valuable experience that is interesting and lets them
not have to...
do things that aren't as exciting or aren't the game, like shuffling.
No, John, someday we're just going to have apps playing board games.
With each other?
Cut the human out of the equation, you know, just games playing games.
I mean, if the apps have money, someone will do it.
I have news for you about the someday, neural net AI can already do that.
I think there's some talks on that.
It's called Grimm.
Well, speaking of...
Grimmer things.
We all grew up with video games to some degree,
and we're used to video game piracy.
Increasingly, and I'm still trying
to put my head around this, and there's
been more and more news about this over the last year or so,
increasingly, board game piracy is a thing.
There are folks out there who will scan in a board game,
they're scanning all the cards, and they'll just
print a cheaper version of it and make that available
to purchase, perhaps overseas.
And to maybe a not so savvy customer,
if you're buying the.
discount budget copy version of the game or the original you may not know the difference and you may just think that you are
Saving a third or a half of the price
Apparently this has been happening for a while, but I've only recently become more aware of it
I wanted to ask any of you if you've been affected like directly or indirectly
By this and also how you would think you would address a problem like this
Well Rio Grand Games has had it with both race and Dominion
And they are working pretty aggressively with Amazon
to try to shut down the sellers of counterfeit.
And in fact, one of Rio Grande's employees
was testifying in court in New York a week ago about this.
So they're working on it.
I mean, you know Asmodee.
Well, yeah.
I mean, we haven't been greatly impacted by it.
This isn't a huge thing on our radar.
And honestly, we see.
less problems with printed piracy.
Often, you know, if all the files
of the game get online, it's still almost as expensive
as just going to the store and buying a nice copy for a customer to print
a copy and reproduce all of the components of the game.
One of the bigger things we tend to see is actually
digital reproductions of our games on different
websites or different, like, tabletop portals.
I mean, they're really useful to the players,
but, you know, these...
these are kind of pirated digital versions of our games.
And so that's what we see more often.
Really, I think our main approach to this
is to kind of try to, what are we missing for these players?
And a lot of this is the ability to actually get our content
to wherever they live.
And so I think one thing that we're looking to in the future
is like.
For example, all of our RPGs that we print, tabletop RPGs we make, are available on DriveThruRPG as PDFs.
And I think digital distribution of board games is something that we can look to in the future.
3D printing is becoming more and more viable as consumer tech.
And so these are things that we can look to as an industry as ways of basically selling to these consumers
who want to get everything digitally, basically, and appealing to them.
I mean, I think a big part of this situation is awareness, right?
Like, the issue isn't that some people...
So when some people buy pirated games or they buy counterfeit copies,
they aren't buying them just because they, you know, want to get...
just because they want to get a good deal.
Sometimes it's the only deal on the table for them, right?
Like, it's actually a similar situation in video games.
Like, I think CD Projekt Red...
was involved, like I was talking to some of them about how video games in their country
were very hard to come across, but you can buy counterfeit CDs fairly readily, and if
they didn't have those, they just wouldn't have video games.
And then we wouldn't have The Witcher, right?
We'd have the books, not the games.
And on that front, I personally don't really have a huge problem with cheaper reproductions
being made to service markets that we don't service in the first place.
My main problem is when, say, like regular consumers on Amazon who are like expecting,
you know, the normal quality game are making this uninformed decision and being duped by
counterfeit publishers.
And that is something that I think is definitely that we need to address and has to do with
supply lines and printing costs.
And it's a real issue since in China are, you know, I've been talking to factories.
And more and more factories are getting into the board game scene because it's so profitable and so cool.
And that means that there's more and more means to produce games as expensively or cheaply as you want.
And all you have to do is send them digital files and ask them to print it.
And they're not... Some factories don't even know.
They just assume, oh yeah, this is just the game that you made, right?
They don't know everything.
The Chinese factories may have never heard of Race for the Galaxy.
And so they're just being told, hey, can you print this game?
And here are my files.
And they're like, sure, here are the specs.
Here's how much it costs.
And then you can get a huge print run
of false Race for the Galaxy copies
and then sell them as your own, which sucks.
But I'm personally not sure what the solution to that would be.
It's just the magnitude of the problem.
So I mean, I was going to say, is this just not going to go
away?
Is this now going to be a feature of the industry
the way it's still kind of a feature of the video games
industry?
I mean, people still want to pirate things, right?
It's availability, right?
Like, music piracy dropped tremendously
the second most people could have access
to easily streamable content, right?
So if we reach a state where board games
are super readily available at reasonable prices,
which I don't know if we'll hit that state,
but if we do, then absolutely piracy
will probably drop off a cliff.
But until then, I think this is something
we might need to learn to.
Right, another strategy also is that
Some of my games were now producing Chinese editions,
already localized, working with Chinese printers to print,
and separate European editions with different artwork
and so on, so that we can sell two products
in two different markets with different margins.
This is something I've been working
with several publishers.
Question for you, actually.
Do you have different quality levels or different margins
for?
those print runs where it's like say if this community is slightly less wealthy
are you going to sell it at a lower price point in that
market? I don't believe there's any explicit setting
but if you are obviously working with different printers
then there may be different local standards as to what
you know how thick is the cards and so on.
Like, we as the publishers are working on a lower profit margin than American distributors.
Distribution still being one of the biggest challenges for the industry because I feel like most of us I've been living in Canada
I'm currently in the US and you live in Finland you folks live all summer in the US
Getting board games in Canada is surprisingly difficult sometimes especially because people just order them from America or drive to America because it's nearby
How is it getting board games in Finland?
It's okay.
Right.
I've been trying to get Fog of Love, but it's a Walmart exclusive, so it's very difficult
in Europe to get something like that.
I don't know.
A lot of board games are made here and made exclusively or sent to the United States,
and then shipping is really expensive to Europe, so I don't know.
It sounds to me like this is still one of the obstacles that the industry has created
for itself.
Is that fair to say?
Well, I think it's created by the medium.
Right. Just like, you know, they're physical games.
And so by nature, we have to print them and ship them to somewhere.
And so to get them all over the world to everybody that might want them,
you need a massive distribution network.
You know, Asmodee has has a pretty large one.
You know, they have studios, you know, all over the world now.
And they have a pretty large and extensive distribution network.
But they still, you know, struggle to get games everywhere they want it to be.
And certain countries like Australia see pretty large markups in price on these.
And so distribution, I think, is always going to be a challenge for physical product.
It's just a fact of the matter.
But like I said, I think digital distribution of stuff could help with that, help with accessibility.
Things like 3D printing and print and play and things like that can definitely help people
who aren't kind of as part of the main game network get access to these things.
And just on that point very quickly, is there anybody in here from Australia right now?
Can I ask you to yell out sort of how much you pay for the average board game? $80?
Wow. $80.
That still seems more than like $30 or $40.
Like even with the exchange rate, right?
Right, now one of the other things affecting is simply that the cost of shipping has gone up a lot over the last 10 years.
But then, I mean, I would immediately say why are we making things overseas and then already shipping them once and then...
It's so much cheaper to make them in China.
Even when you put them on boats and drag them halfway around the world, it's still cheaper?
I mean, most of your customers are going to be in the US if I've used their numbers or anything to look at.
You know, that's why Shucks is in America and not...
And in many cases, the parts are being done, but then the printing's done in Europe or the United States.
So you have some division there, so you're not shipping everything twice.
So the solution, maybe at some point, is if we can just print them all in a house.
That would be nice.
I can think of worse things to do.
We briefly mentioned legacy games before.
Are they here to stay?
It feels like...
doing we just had werewolf legacy announced risk legacy was now what six or seven years ago
pandemic legacy seafall it feels like this is the sort of the flavor of the moment sharp and sit down
has looked at a number of legacy games over the last year or two and liked some of them and not
being as excited as others i feel like this is a bubble that might burst or that these games work
really well sort of cooperatively but as soon as
it becomes a competitive complex thing like Seafall or Charterstone, it kind of falls over.
Is this just gonna, are we gonna get bored of these within a couple of years?
Personally, I like legacy games. I think, I've always thought of myself, not so much as a game
designer first, but as a storyteller. And legacy games increase our ability to tell stories.
As far as the cooperative, I think it's a natural extension of cooperative games.
to go the legacy route, and I'm sure that that will continue.
That's not a bus.
Competitive ones, and I can say that I've designed one,
but it hasn't been announced, are another beast.
And I had to go through a lot of trials and tribulations
along the way.
So I'm not so sure that they will continue,
but I suspect as we design more tools.
as we come up with more ways of dealing with the various issues,
that you'll see more of them that will be good.
Is the challenge being, if it's a cooperative game,
it's almost as if you're designing for one player,
you're designing for a group who are all in the same situation.
Is the challenge that things become imbalanced over a series of games
when it is player versus player and there are winners,
separate winners and losers?
Well, as was discussed by Mr. Honeycutt here in the last session,
you know, you have the runaway leader problem.
Yes. And how you deal with it, do you introduce a second meta-currency?
There's a number of different approaches that you can use.
I mean, I think that the surest way to put your foot in your mouth at one of these is to like
make a hard and fast declaration of what will happen. So I don't, I honestly don't know how,
whether legacy games are going to fizzle out or not, though I doubt that they'll disappear
entirely, right? They've done well enough, people like them.
I think one of my major concerns is honestly the, there are a couple of weaknesses within
the legacy format, which is the disposable nature of it, right?
A lot of players don't like the idea of a game that they can't continue playing all
the time, which is kind of a silly response when it's like I barely play the games I own
more than 12 times at a, you know.
And then sell them for nothing.
Right.
And then sell them for like, but then there's also, you know, this idea of once you've started
a legacy game with a group, you are committed and it's like you either have to try and reel
it back or.
start again and like it's hard to introduce new people more than once to a single legacy
item.
Uh, I think it's going to be a challenge and I'm really interested to see what techniques
the industry does to mix it up.
Uh, and I mean, I know Jr is going to, yeah, give him a mic up here, up the podium very
quickly.
You can be a special guest.
There you are.
Games designer, JR Honeycutt.
The only person up here in shorts.
Yep, I'm really very sorry about that.
I didn't mean to jump in.
You asked what Legacy games have done
to the environment of board games
and whether they're gonna stick around, right?
Whether or not Legacy games stick around,
I think the impact they've had on games
in the last two years, since the first quarter
of sales for Pandemic Legacy came out,
have been that it's pushing players,
or pushing designers who wouldn't normally include
deep narratives in games to include those deep narratives.
And I think you see it in Kickstarter,
there's both a push and a pull for designers
to start actually working deeply on maintaining
a real connection between the narrative mechanisms
of board games.
And it's making for better products, right?
And you're seeing it in the quality of games
in the last year or two years,
like Rise of Hellas is a game that wouldn't have existed
if legacy games hadn't enforced it.
And Subnecontinent has some influences there too, so.
All right, thanks.
And just quickly following from that, I wondered asking Anna and Andrew,
surely something app-supported is ideal for a legacy format,
if it does a lot of the work for us?
I don't think we've even seen the start of what legacy games can do,
and I think they're going to stick around for a long time to answer your previous question.
But I think app-supported legacy games are going to be great for players
who are hesitant about destroying their games or not being able to play them again,
and will introduce a whole new mechanic to games.
I also think that you'll see some fusion between app-driven legacy games and LARPs, which is
a whole different area.
I want the app legacy game that's like, and then break your iPad.
Yeah, yeah, color in on your iPad.
I think a lot of our existing app-integrated games that Fantasy Flight makes kind of have
a campaign aspect and have permanent choice across many, many plays.
We do that.
permanent aspect in the app, but at the same time, it's not really considered a legacy
game by players.
I think integral to the definition of legacy is the permanence, the physical permanence
of it.
You don't see anybody complaining about having to make permanent choices in our ongoing campaigns
in say like the Road to Legend app for Descent, or our Legends Alliance app for Imperial Assault.
That's just standard game campaigns.
I think there's that physical aspect of the disposability of it that gives that permanence to the decision.
And to throw my answer into the pot, and stick my foot in my mouth, as John said...
Your feet taste fantastic.
Yeah, that can't be true.
I think that legacy as a mechanic is a tool that we've added to our collective toolbox.
It is a, I think Mark Rosewater from Watt Wizards calls it a technology.
This is now a tool we have, and yeah, it's super hot right now, right?
But it's like deck building when Dominion first hit.
Deck building was huge!
You saw so many deck builders.
You definitely see fewer deck builders now.
Oh, and very different ones.
Yeah, and very different ones, but you definitely still see deck building mechanics, and they
often come as like an aspect, a portion.
of the game. You see very few dedicated deck builders anymore, but you see a lot of games that
have a deck building aspect. And so I think in similarly we'll see the same thing with legacies,
the legacy mechanic as it seems to have been termed. And I think we'll see it used in different
unique ways by designers as just a tool in the toolbox, even after it wanes in popularity.
Yeah, definitely. I think since board games is such a growing industry and more and more players
come into it, maybe players that have played computer games before,
are used to longer campaigns and playing over several, several sessions the same game,
Legacy is something that is going to stick around for those players.
Yeah, no, that's valid. Many of us video gamers are...
something in our DNA that makes us sort of genetically campaign kind of people.
And I don't know exactly where you draw the line between a legacy game and a campaign.
I will say on the, if we are to, for this conversation, refer to legacy as games that
involve a sort of emotional, like physical sacrifice as part of the experience, right?
Destroying components, permanently altering things.
It is actually really exciting when video games have started doing things like that.
Nier Automata and Doki Doki Literature Club both have game elements that involve permanently
altering the player's save file.
Nier Automata has a mechanic that allows you to actually remove your save file completely
for a specific purpose.
That is, I won't spoil, but that is a genuinely deep and emotional decision that you can make
which feels akin to burning a card in a Legacy game.
Or you know, a whole deck of them.
Video games, huh?
Video games, right?
I'm going to ask one or two quick more questions to our panel of experts.
In the meantime, if anyone has things they'd like to throw at us,
please start queuing up. There's a microphone over there.
Do not be scared of it.
We got a lot of different questions about a lot of different topics last year.
And I feel that the folks that we have this time,
we have a very good spectrum of experience.
Speaking briefly about video games,
I play Carcassonne now mostly on my phone.
There is now a very good Race for the Galaxy app.
Do any of you worry that this is going to take over the hobby,
or that we're going to lose our physical versions of some
of these games?
Are we going to just play these games online with each other
instead of in person?
There are games that, oh, you want to go?
I'm going to say no.
I think there's something magical about tactile games
and ripping cards for like, for example,
and playing with cubes and rolling dice
that an app can't really get rid of.
I will say there are games that I do feel are fundamentally improved after their transition
to an app.
Games like Nieroshima Hex, which is a good game, but I just find kind of exhausting to
play physically.
Just because of the way it's fiddly to deal with the components.
And when you don't have to constantly worry about managing all of those, then it helps
a lot.
Or Mansions of Madness is a good example of one that was improved by an app.
And there are games that go, it's a spectrum, so there are games that go all the way to
just being...
completely better by being entirely on an app and games that become completely different in an app like seven wonders is
You know a kind of like solid kind of mid weight game once it's on an app
It's super lightweight because there's no like you're not doing the experience of handing cards to each other
You're not experiencing like laying them out and like looking over your things
Everything is just kind of very snappy and your decision-making has changed completely to just one thing and there's no
physicality to it
And it was interesting to me because I didn't realize that there was so
That so much of the seven wonders experience is that communal playing with components
Like drafting cards by handing them to another person next to you that feels nice and is part of the thing
Well, you said it yourself at the beginning of this panel actually, which is that
we
the number of released board games each year is ballooning, right?
With 3,500, you said?
Something like 3,500 plus last year.
We're not running out of board games.
Honestly, this is an industry that is still rapidly growing
and rapidly integrating with the digital industry,
and so I don't think we have to be concerned about some kind of takeover.
I mean, we were worried when video games started happening,
and then, hey, we did okay.
Yeah, that's fair enough. Very quickly, Tom, I mean, Race for the Galaxy now is an app.
Do you feel it's lost that card physicality? Is something missing?
Well, I will say that the person who came up to me and told me how they play it on the
toilet every morning, that was something I had not expected.
And questions from the audience. You, sir, at the front of the line.
Hello. Hello. How do I follow that up? I was wondering
if the panel could...
give us a check-in on the state of diversity in board games,
both geographically and identity.
I know the answer generally is not good enough,
but if you can maybe signal boost or shout-outs
or let us know how that's going, what's happening.
First of all, I have a short thing about this
that I was gonna read or say at the end of the session,
but I'll say it in a moment.
But also...
It's coming out of the mouth of a white guy, so how about someone who isn't a white guy
would like to talk about how they feel in this industry right now?
Would that be okay?
I think the diversity is awful in board games right now.
Coming from video games and seeing all the indie devs here, the pronouns and stuff like
that, and then stepping into the board game industry two years ago, almost, it was kind
of shocking to see the lack of diversity happening at the moment.
I mean, the magnitude of the issue should not be understated, right?
Like this industry has been primarily servicing a very particular audience for a long time,
an audience that absolutely deserves good games, but it's not, it hasn't been inclusive
as a priority, right?
Which means that it caters specifically to its own audience and has a tough time spreading
that love around, if you will.
Luckily, there are some great designers and other people, including people right here,
who are working hard at increasing diversity, increasing representation in games, making
players more comfortable at events, and trying to just be ambassadors to other people.
Because this hobby will only improve with more viewpoints, with more perspectives.
If we keep having the same people making games, or making games for the same people, we'll
keep making the same games.
But the more people we bring in, the more perspectives we have,
the more interesting experiences we have.
And that's what everyone wants, honestly.
I just want to talk a bit more about the accessibility issue.
At least with our app, a thing that we're trying to do
is make board games more accessible to people.
So you don't have to read this huge rule book to play them.
You can just start and experience board games
and fall in love with them and become a designer.
And geographic accessibility is hard as well, because like,
As we've discussed, shipping is hard.
And so not just shipping, but also manufacturing a product
to serve different markets and different languages.
Like there are a lot of considerations
that have to be made for that.
And when it's a physical product, it's just difficult.
When it's an expensive physical product, it's even harder.
And it's like, what happens when you have so much stock
of this in this language?
And like, oh, you're making all of these decisions
and at any point it can go wrong.
And so a lot of publishers are really gun shy about that.
And so I feel like we as consumers need to be very enthusiastic and ask for these things
because that is kind of how the current capitalist interplay works.
So...
Hey, Anna, can I briefly ask, you have been an indie dev as well, you've been a video
games developer, so you've seen both sides of the thing.
How does it feel, like you have been to a couple of board game events now, to come back
to a video games con?
You're suggesting it's...
It's great.
It's really great here at GDC.
I mean, everyone's so exclusive...
Inclusive.
And there's just so much diversity and it's great seeing so many women and non-binary
people and you just don't see that at board game events.
I mean, the customers are women and non-binary people, but the people making content is just
white guys.
I'm going to say something about this, and this is what I was going to say at the end.
I read something really saddening last month.
retrospective about the impact of Gamergate, of which there is still a lot of fallout.
And it was about the amount of young women who had written to leading women in the industry
saying that they're not going to work in games because of what happened.
It's a very real casualty rate.
And those are careers, and those are games, and those are ideas that we never get to see,
because those people have decided that they don't want to put up with the BS of everything
that has happened.
And I still have many conversations with women peers and with people of color
about the difficulties and the obstacles that they still encounter in the industry like now.
A writer who's really dear to me passed away last month,
which is a lady called Ursula Le Guin, who was a science fiction titan.
For most of her career, she's a woman working in a man's world,
and she's all too aware of the imbalances, and she challenged them, she called them out.
This is something that she actually said at a convention.
kind of, I don't know, not a hundred miles away from something like this convention we're at now,
she said, I'd like to ask the men here to consider, idly, in some spare moment,
whether by any chance they have been building walls to keep the women out,
or to keep them in their place, and what they may have lost by doing so.
And that sounds really contemporary, doesn't it?
But that was actually said at a convention in 1975, and I hate that that just sounds
completely relevant today because it does.
It's a reminder that we've got to keep working hard, and that games, or science fiction,
or comics, all these industries that come on, let's face it folks, we're all adjacent
to each other.
We're all the same sorts of folks.
We still have this problem, and there's still so much that we have to do, and consciously
or unconsciously, it's folks like me who look like me, who are me.
who perpetuate this and it's on folks like me,
who look like me and who are me,
to address it and to fix it.
That's, that would have been a really good finisher.
But it is, it's, I'm just frustrated that she said that.
Like before I existed, she was in a room full of mostly men
saying like, dudes, come on, get with it.
Sorry, that was a bit of a digression.
The next question, hello, hi.
So I kind of have a question slash comment in respect to the digitization of board games,
the convenience that it brings, and also the piracy of it, specifically tabletop simulator.
You're able to go on the workshop and just download literally every board game for the
most part, the ones that people have been willing to create.
Do you guys see that as a problem?
It's increasing accessibility, but you're not making any money from it.
And have you considered digitizing in some way similar to that?
Or is there a possibility of partnering with Tabletop Simulator to form a contract?
Maybe not charging the users, but making money from what Tabletop Simulator gets in terms
of revenue by hosting your game on it in a more professional way.
At first, I mean, I think this is a really good point,
and it's only increasingly relevant,
because everybody I know has tabletop simulator.
But also, like how many of you folks have used it?
How many people here have played Surgeon Simulator?
Because for me, it's still an experience
where I'm trying to play a game, and I do this.
And that's me rolling my dice.
Yeah, it's certainly not the best,
but it's at least an opportunity to be able to play
with someone that's across the world.
It's kind of a cool thing.
It's tough, I'm not going to get away from the physical aspect of board games.
Well, yeah.
So, I mean, I'll talk a bit about this.
I'm going to disclaimer what I'm going to say first, just because, like, you know, I
am just a sole person.
I do not represent, you know, Fantasy Flight, Aspiday, or whatever, and like I can't speak
to, like, our corporate feeling on this, right?
But that being said, yeah, I played Tabletop Simulator.
Like I know tons of people who played Tabletop Simulator, right?
It's...
It's a great tool, and you're right, it is great for accessibility.
And putting games online like that is fantastic, but just as broadly across the industry, not
everybody can just sign with Tabletop Simulator and give rights away, right?
There's all sorts of different legal stipulations based on intellectual property, based on licenses,
based on quality assurance, you know, like, of, you know, the quality of the product that's
on Tabletop Simulator, and if it meets with a company's standards.
So, well, that model does work for some companies, it doesn't for others.
There's never going to be, I don't think, a world where every single board game company
all licenses with Tabletop Simulator and we have this one great digital portal for all
board games.
That being said, I think these kind of digitization projects are really awesome and really friendly
to fans.
I mean, like, but like, look at Race for the Galaxy, right?
By putting out a more controlled app experience,
they're able to offer an app that is way more functional
and way easier to use than Tabletop Simulator ever was,
right, and so some companies want to take approaches
like that instead.
Well, with Race and with quite a few of my games,
if it's a non-commercial enterprise,
I've done licenses with my games.
Yukata has to court the king.
Board game arena had a race for many years and gave us no money.
So I'm in general in favor of non-commercial licenses
to anyone who's not making money off of it to do it.
I think it's great.
More people playing my games.
I'm all for that.
Nice.
Thank you very much.
I have one very minor thing to say.
But for me, like.
It feels kind of awkward to say this, but I do strongly feel that no one is playing
Star Wars Imperial Assault just for the experience of the rules.
They're playing it partly for the miniatures and for the enjoyment of being in a room with
their friends, you know, rolling dice and having this physical experience, which you
mentioned earlier about why we won't lose to digital apps anytime soon.
And I feel similarly about the tabletop simulator.
I think it provides a great service, but I don't think it's really harmful.
One other final note on that.
In some cases for some games, and I suspect that may be true
for Imperial Assault, there's third party licensing rights
that may make it hard for a company to allow a game to do
it because their own contract to license the Star Wars, for
example, may preclude it.
So that's a obstacle that's really not at the game
publisher level.
it's at the IP licensing level.
And that's valid.
I still think the biggest obstacle is that I just do that and all the miniatures fall
over.
But, maybe I have poor taste and I'm a Luddite.
Maybe it'll get really good eventually if they keep updating it.
That's fair.
Hi.
So, I for a long time have thought that there's that spectrum between fully digital and fully
physical board games with all these cool hybrid in between.
And I know there's fantasy flight interactive now
but also what do you guys think in general about the idea of studios that do board games and
Video games that they come up with an idea and then they decide whether it's going to be physical or digital or a hybrid
Rather than being a company that just does one and then
Licenses out to another studio to do the the other right from a business point of view you have the problem at the moment the
Distribution networks are totally different
And so you have to assemble a different distribution network
if you're trying to get into the other industry either way.
So if distribution gets solved, then I
think you'll see a lot more companies that
are willing to move a project either way.
I had a discussion about this with a gentleman earlier today
about the fact that I don't consider the actual game
design that different implementation.
Very different but in terms of getting good gameplay. I don't consider them two different markets
No, that's fair enough
I was going to say on the design side as well anyone here know about fallout New Vegas being partly just paper prototyped
enormous fallout video game took a very long time a lot of people to make but it didn't have to have a few folks around
The table with bits of paper because it turns out that that's a valid way to design something
Yeah, I was doing a licensed game,
and I ended up playing a paper prototype of it
with executives from Warner Brothers Interactive
over Skype to show them where we were going long before we
had any video game up and running.
Yeah, I mean, coming from a video game background,
I think paper prototyping is super important.
Before you even touch a computer,
you should paper prototype your mechanics
to see if they even work.
saying that I don't think there are many board game companies that also have access to making their own video games.
They usually just focus on board games, and then they'll maybe license it out to some other video game company.
I think, like, probably Fantasy Flight is the only one that has.
You might just get to the coast retiring.
Anna, am I correct that the... what was the race to the North Pole, the first DICE game...
that was developed to partly be an app supported board game,
app game, was that developed deliberately
sort of in parallel?
Yes.
Actually the designer of the game is right here.
He's like sitting right over there.
I'm not letting anyone else up here, sorry.
We got more questions here.
This whole photograph, like keep talking
and nobody is talking.
It's different, like we learned something.
Oh yeah, I mean.
Hybrid game, yeah.
Or the Jackbox TV games.
Yeah, Jackbox TV.
Keep talking and nobody explodes for the recording.
Yes, that was mentioned.
Keep talking and nobody explodes,
which is as stressful as it sounds.
Yeah, I'd say that the production is definitely
different from a video game and a board game.
And one of the things that ends up
changing the most for the final product
is those production budgets and the production pipeline.
You can't always fit everything that you want into a video game in there, and you also can't
fit everything inside the game box that you want to fit in there.
And I would like to just open this question to any of you.
How would you feel, how do you feel that designing board games specifically has changed your
design methodology?
To say, I can only have so many cards, or I can only use so many different types of
pieces, and how has that influenced your designs?
I've got a weird answer for this one, actually.
So I did a game on Kickstarter, which is quite exciting.
And on Kickstarters, we have these things called stretch goals.
And when you do a stretch goal, you're like,
we promise that if we make this much money,
we'll add this component or this mechanic.
And often it's a physical component or mechanic.
And you can overpromise or you can make a decision
where you don't realize that producing this thing,
like say, poker cards are printed on a 54-card press form,
which means any increment of 54 cards is good.
But the second you go over that,
you have to make an entire new press form.
And so, like, we had a situation where we were like three cards over that we promised to backers,
and so we were paying for, you know, an extra dollar on the game's production cost, which is
like, was like 20% more for that particular element, which is, you know, these mistakes
can happen and they can sometimes end companies when they overpromise. And so that risk is
something that didn't exist when I was like at Fantasy Flight.
where we'd make a decision and be like, oh yeah, no, we can't have that many dice molds.
Change the mechanic and no one will know.
And it's fine.
Yeah, I do think what kind of games you work on and what kind of constraints you work on
wire your brain.
You see this all the time with designers.
Designers will work on one type of game for a while and then they'll move into a new genre of game
and they'll actually bring a lot of the knowledge they had from their other genre they're working on
into the new game.
and like you can kind of see it's like, oh, this game was designed by this person who
did this other kind of mechanic for a very long time and you totally can feel that in
the design.
I think similarly, constraints kind of train how people develop their skills over time.
But I mean, I think that's true in the digital space as well as the tabletop space.
I mean, like, you know, this is the limit on this is constantly raising, but you have
like render limits and all that kind of thing that so, you know.
People working on digital games have all sorts of constraints they're working under.
They're just a little different than the tabletop constraints of our printing budget.
I'm lucky enough that I do a lot of games for a publisher who says,
don't worry about the components, just get the game right.
What a dream.
Yeah.
Well, this can have some odd effects.
When we were doing Roll and we were well over 100 dice,
we went back to Jay Tummels and said,
do you really mean that?
And he said, no, no, get the game right.
Don't worry about it.
Then when he got the print quote,
there are a lot of dice in this game.
But he then worked a lot and tried different suppliers
until he could do it at reasonable quality and cost
and so on.
And he didn't place any constraints on us
about how we do the games.
So it's.
you know, an interesting thing because there are times when we know we're pushing the limits.
And it's like, well, Gay hasn't complained yet.
Okay, very well. I love the idea of somebody, speaking as someone who writes an awful lot,
the idea of a person saying just do whatever you like is, I love the idea of constraints. Someone
saying just do whatever is the least helpful thing in a creative industry. When people
put up barriers for you, I feel that gives you direction.
If somebody came to me and said no limits, I'd just be like, challenge accepted.
This is someone who has struggled against constraints.
So I think that innovation tends to come from having expectations defied.
And certainly as games have proliferated, more and more we're playing games that, as players, deliver different kinds of experiences.
So what I'd love to hear from each of you, and certainly from you as well, Paul, is just the last game that you played that really surprised you, good or bad, that sort of helped you.
you see something that maybe you hadn't quite seen before or thought of before?
I'm gonna just throw that to the wolves
while I think, so fill time for me. I think I've got an answer but folks, all of you, if you have an answer for this?
Well, you know what? I'm gonna go with a bad one, and I won't name the name, but I did play a game...
Oh, name and shame.
I will not... Come on, guys. Let's be professional.
But I did play a game recently that was mechanically brilliant.
had a lot of very good ideas and was, you know, overall, like, I really enjoyed playing
it.
But the wrapping of it, the sort of theme around it, was so incredibly uninteresting
to me.
It was like a game where, like, the mechanics were beautiful, but the aesthetics were this
very classical thing that I've seen a million times before.
You know, orcs, elves, it's, you know, it's...
I know what game this is.
Don't tell anyone.
He has a theory.
But and sort of that understanding of like, you know
Mechanics are important and very relevant and you can have the most brilliant mechanics in the world
But if you're you know, but if the other elements of the game don't sink to it and don't make those mechanics sing
It's an experience can fall flat or the experience can just kind of be soured even
and
you know as a designer that now makes me much more cognizant of the themes that I choose and like I know some designers are
just like
put whatever on it, you know, you hire the artists or whatever, but like now I'm making
very, you know, informed decisions about like how the art should look, how inclusive it
should be, that sort of thing is all decisions that should be made with thought and care.
So, um, I work with Wei Wah on the Roll series, and so he came up with something that'll be
in the next expansion.
that effectively models credit asset swaps.
When I saw all the things you could do with it,
give up some of your treasury limit, get a die,
sell this, do this, I mean, my brain exploded.
And the thought that you could get something that dry,
you know, I mean, credit asset swaps,
not exactly the most exciting term in the world,
and make it come alive and make it work in a game
that had already been designed,
so this is in an expansion, that blew my mind.
As far as games that don't work, I always have trouble playing lots of games because I'm very picky.
And when I play games, the hardest thing for me is I see what they could have been.
And that just eats away at me.
I don't have time to play board games anymore.
Because you're making them.
But whenever, I did play one recently and the thing I notice now about games is the rule books.
And this game blew my mind because I had a 50-page rulebook, and I did not have time for that.
Yep. Andrew, do you have one?
Yeah, so I think the last game that really surprised me was...
It's actually a series of games, the Exit series, for any of you who have played.
They're a series of one-play escape room games.
They kind of simulate the experience of playing an escape room with the different puzzles
and unlocking these different puzzles.
And I don't really want to...
Since they're one use, and once you know the riddle, they're done. I'm not going to spoil any
of them for you, but they each kind of break the rules
in ways you might not expect. And I found
those games definitely surprised me at the table in a really good way, in a really enjoyable way.
I encourage anyone who has a chance to go out and check out Exit or Unlock, or any
of the other kind of escape room type games. I think they do something really cool.
I think I saw a couple at the lounge.
Oh cool.
Yeah, there's a couple in there.
I will very quickly say, having just played it, Fog of Love maybe, because it is sort
of cooperative, but not in a game where you hide information and choices from each other
and define your own objectives.
Like that's insane for something that is supposed to be cooperative.
There is a video up on our site about it, please check it out.
We've got a couple of minutes left.
We can do I think at least two questions, maybe three?
Alright, hello.
Drawing a comparison to the video games where we don't really have to get it right the first time because we can easily distribute patches
I wonder if you could comment on
certain advantages possibly with having these in-app and integrations where you have the manual in the app or
Certain challenges you've had with physical ones where you can't really change it until you have an expansion or something
Printing a game and then finding errors before it's in consumers hands is the worst
You know, we see it all the time, obviously.
The digital games are awesome because of that,
like our app-integrated games being
able to patch things out.
But also, digital games have a lot more bugs
and have a lot more difficulties that come along with that.
And also, they require constant updating and patching
is almost expected for them.
So while it is awesome to finally
be able to kind of change our products after launch,
It also comes with just a ton of ongoing maintenance and work for that product line going forward.
One of the features of our app is that you can update your rulebook.
So you can have your rules there, all indexed and referenced, and you can update them if
you have a correction to make or a second edition that you're doing.
So that's one of the cool things we're doing.
It feels like a tiny little miracle, actually.
It's much harder with components, though.
Like, I mean, I've had nightmares, and it is like...
there is a deeply unbalanced character that I put into Star Wars Imperial Assault due to my own
failures that haunts me to this day. And you know, you can't, and like I know that there are
still copies out there that don't have the second edition version or that don't have competitive
players who went out and got the eroded cards that we printed and gave out at tournaments. And like
I've just like made the experience slightly worse for anyone who bought that version of the game
and it kills me. And
I mean, we do produce ways around it, right?
Like, FFG has done a lot of competitive physical games,
and we'll print cards that are answers to cards
that might have been a little too strong before,
or cards that very specifically synergize
with slightly weaker cards that existed in the past.
And that sort of design is often a very fun design challenge,
but it's kind of a result of our own human failings.
But yeah, I mean, and errata is hard
because most players don't look it up.
You know, most players assume that we got it right, unfortunately.
Never.
One more, I think, please.
Thank you.
It was a great talk.
Thank you very much.
As someone who has recently made a large print edition of a beloved game for my parents to
play, I was wondering if there's any particular focus in the industry to make visual accessibility
more of a thing, because our text is often very tiny.
Thoughts?
I mean, unfortunately, there is not a big push for that.
I would like there to be.
I think that it would be very important.
And I think the more people who make that request and who actually like send emails
to publishers, like, I think it would be very cool if you, you know, showed people whoever
published the original version of that game you made the updated version of, send them
like, hey, we made this.
And just let them know because companies only, you know, their main focus is what their consumers
are doing.
And if consumers aren't emailing them and letting them know what they feel,
they end up not thinking about it, which is unfortunate and thoughtless.
Right. I will say two things.
We've been trying to improve the color blindness in our games.
But also I find that many of the people who do the graphics of games are in their 20s
and they have excellent eyesight.
And I'm an old dude who wears glasses.
So I will complain myself about various features of games,
and the graphic person is like, hmm,
I didn't think that was a problem.
So there is some advantage for the old white dude still.
I was going to say, surely apps have an audio element.
Yeah, we are making sure that all our tutorials are
completely voiceovered so that you can just,
and in different languages as well,
so it's as accessible as possible to as many people
as possible.
I would quickly add, I don't know if any of you folks have heard of 64-ounce games.
They do braille overlays for things like cards and board games.
So if you're playing a game like, I don't know, the Resistance Avalon, which is a card
game, you deal cards out to people, they look at who they are and they go, I am this person
on this team.
If they're partially sighted or they cannot see at all, it's exactly the same for them
if they feel the role that they are, they can enjoy the game like other people.
I think some of these problems can be solved if we're just a bit more inventive, maybe.
I think we're pretty much out of time, aren't we?
Thank you all very much for coming.
Consider idly, please, in some spare moment
what it is that you think you can do to make gaming better,
and I'm addressing some of you more than others.
We got attacked a little bit online
for talking about this last year at this panel.
Probably get attacked online again,
and it will probably keep happening until we win.
Thank you, everyone.