What was that?
My apologies.
Many people think the character design is a job limited to character artists or senior
writers.
But this is not true anymore in the next generation open world RPG where players spend more than
99% of their time with a character inside a real-time gameplay.
Cinematics are just one way among many of character storytelling.
Final Fantasy XV is one of the good examples of this.
Rather than limit ourselves to character design,
we focused on the character experience design.
For this project, we chose to have CS, the character experience,
expressed by an AI.
Man, it's hot.
Then lose the jacket.
My name is Sun, the lead game designer of Final Fantasy XV,
in charge of bodies and photos in the AI system.
In this session, we will cover how we designed our main characters, CX,
and how we used animations, voices, and game design to achieve AIs that make you feel emotional.
No formal knowledge in any field is required, yet I am sure both beginners and experts will find this session truly enjoyable.
Welcome to CU Geyser.
Wow! This place is so romantic!
Then you get to enjoy it with us.
All three of us?
You are a lucky man.