Hey there, this is Jorge del Val. I'm a research engineer here at the SIT division at Electronic Codes.
As some of you might know, deep generative models are among some of the most popular areas of research in the deep learning community nowadays.
We have seen enormous success of techniques such as generative adversarial networks,
variational autoencoders, or autoregressive methods in either generating or morphing different kinds of content.
So we believe that this kind of techniques will have a profound impact on the way that we understand game development in the future.
So if you want to know more about how these techniques work on a fundamental level, about
some of the state-of-the-art results, or have a hint about how we can actually apply this
to game development nowadays, don't hesitate to come to my talk at GDC, the Machine Learning
Tutorial Day, Tuesday at 5.30.
So regards from Stockholm, and I'll see you in San Francisco.