Hi everyone, thank you so much for being here, because we, honestly, we should all be drinking beer at that time.
So I really appreciate you being here.
My name is Celia, I've been in this industry for about 10 years now.
I've been working at Ubisoft, LucasArts, and I've been at Epic Games for the past four years.
Before I start, I would like to warmly thank you from the bottom of my heart,
because this is the third part of a Gamers Brain Trilogy,
and I wouldn't be here without your feedback,
without your encouragement and your support.
So I'm really honored to be part of such an amazing community,
and that you find my shit interesting.
So thank you very much.
Alright, um, I'm going to do a quick explanation about cognitive psychology principles and
about UX, um, that I talked about in my previous talk, so I'm not going to explain any of this,
uh, but I just want to make sure that you have the basic understanding so we can be all on the
same page if you haven't seen these talks.
So what UX is about is all about making sure
that your user is going to experience the game
the way you, as a designer, as a developer, intended.
So you want the image of the system, the game,
to convey truthfully the experience you want to offer.
To do that, we explore how player perceives,
interacts with the game, and the satisfaction
and emotions elicited via this interaction.
So UX takes its roots in cognitive science.
in human factors and in human computer interaction.
UX principles rely on cognitive science knowledge.
So this is why you need to understand
how the brain processes information.
Today we're going to look into motivation more specifically,
and motivation is one of the variables
influencing information processing.
Um, disclaimer, this is highly simplified. The brain is not working like that. It's not in
separate buckets. Uh, but it's just a way, uh, for me to communicate about what we're talking
about. Uh, making games is very complex and so is the brain. Surprise.
All right, so the main purpose of this talk today
is to understand better the mechanisms of retention.
And the reason why we care for free-to-play games
is that to make money, you need to first retain players.
Paid up-front games also care about retention
because players who retain are more
likely to convince their friends to buy the game as well.
So retention at its core means engagement.
Also, if you're engaged in an activity as a player,
it's more pleasurable.
So not only is it good business practice for you,
but it's also a good UX practice for the player, or when.
Okay, so the part of UX that is more specifically
relevant to retention is what I now call engageability.
So I used to call this part game flow
because it's a familiar concept in game development.
However, it didn't quite encompass all what's important to engage players and retain them.
This is why I'm now using that weird term that some of my colleagues call bullshit,
looking at you Ben.
And it's fair because it sounds a bit pompous, but it has the advantage of expressing the
ability of a game to be engaging, just like usability is the ability of the game to be
used.
don't really like it, so maybe it's gonna be okay.
So usability and engageability are not working in silos.
They interact with each other.
Just like the brain, there's interaction everywhere,
but we're separating the buckets
to make it easier to talk about.
All right, so here's how I'm breaking down engageability.
These three pillars.
You have motivation, emotion, and game flow.
So please note that this is my mapping of how to make games more engaging.
It's based on academic research on one hand, and on my own game dev experience with various teams.
So motivation is at the origin of all human behavior, and ultimately engagement is all about motivation.
Emotion and game flow contribute to motivation.
Emotions serve motivation in the sense that they help us choose the right behavior.
So if you see something that scares you, you flee.
Game flow is a state of deep focus and immersion, which is a concept often used in games.
And it's also important for engagement.
Alright, a little warning here.
This talk is going, I'm going to cover a lot of shit
super fast in that talk.
The reason why I'm doing this is,
one, you're an expert audience,
and you should have a good understanding
about a lot of these concepts I'm gonna present here.
And two, even though rewards and motivation have very.
popular topics at GDC, it's pretty rare to see these topics tackled, um, having a bigger
picture in mind. And this is what I want to do today. I'm giving you the big picture, uh, and
I will dive more deeply into a few of these concepts for each pillars, uh, and more
specifically regarding motivation. But the idea really, I want you to have the big picture
rather than like look just at one thing. Um, but it's going to go fast and, uh, by the way,
these slides are going to be on my blog.
this weekend so you don't have to write down everything.
You're gonna have all these this weekend.
Alright, so motivation is that the origin of any behavior.
Without motivation, there is no action.
So it's pretty cool for the survival of organisms
needing movement to survive.
Therefore, it's key to understand
where human behavior come from
and by extension to understand what players,
what make players tick.
So I'm using a tree here because we often talk about meaningful choices when referring
to motivation, and games often have skill trees to offer meaningful choices to players.
So motivation is super interesting,
but the problem is that there are a lot
of motivational theories in psychology, and I mean a lot.
So this is a Wikipedia screenshot,
and this does not list them all, not even close.
So you need to understand this about motivational theories.
There are countless theories that have been proposed
to explain human motivation,
but a solid meta-analysis is still missing
to make sense of it all.
So remember there is no current consensus,
nor there is a unified theory of human motivation
that can account for all of our drives and behaviors
in a clear mapping.
So keep that in mind,
because we always talk about one or two
motivational theories,
but you have to keep in mind that there's a lot out there
and there's no consensus at all.
So here's what I propose.
This is an attempt to organize human motivation
in a simple mapping, therefore inaccurate
because science is complex, but to help game development
to, again, help to talk about these things.
So here are the four buckets.
You have implicit motivation and biological drives.
So, basically it's impulses.
You have personality and individual needs.
So you might have heard of one of the personality model which is ocean.
Then you have environmental shaped motivation and learned drives.
So basically, it's behaviorism.
And the last one that usually people talk about a lot
is intrinsic motivation and cognitive needs.
So intrinsic motivation is when you intrinsically
want to do something for its own sake
because it's inherently pleasurable to you.
Another disclaimer here, SDT is the motivational theory that is usually named here.
These are not really separate buckets, again, they are not independent from one another
and they are not hierarchical, contrary to what maybe you've heard of Maslow Pyramid,
it's called the hierarchy of needs and actually they are not hierarchical.
So, I wanted to very briefly introduce the top two, but very, very briefly again just
for you to have a clear mapping of it all.
But I'll move on to the two bottom for the sake of time, since these are more particularly
relevant to us.
Okay, so biological drives are very basic needs
that we share with other mammals.
For example, hunger, thirst, a need for sleep,
pain avoidance, and sex are powerful,
innate physiological motives
aimed to satisfy our biological drive.
There's other implicit motives
that also can influence our social behavior,
which is more relevant to us.
Three of these implicit drives
have been more particularly studied.
You have the power motive, it's one's motivation to dominate others.
You have the achievement motive, it's the motivation to improve on a task.
And you have the affiliation motive, it's the motivation for
close and harmonious social relationships.
So, depending on how strong these drives are within individuals, they will influence the
pleasure we feel from certain situations differently, which in turn will influence our behavior.
So not everyone is super excited at the idea of dominating others, for example.
So keep that in mind if you really truly appreciate to dominate and humiliate others, it might
not be the case for everyone.
Just a tip.
Alright, moving on to the next bucket,
I told you I would just describe it very briefly.
So generally when you talk about individual differences,
we mainly think about personality.
So Ocean or Big Five is about personality differences
measured against five traits.
You see these five traits here.
For example, some people who score high in extraversion
mean that they are more outgoing
than people who score low on that trait.
Ocean model, like all the personality model, has a lot of limitations.
First, it's not stable during your lifetime.
It means that the personality that you have at 17 years old is not going to be the same
personality that you have at 65, for example.
So it's not stable over time.
Also, it cannot accurately predict behavior.
So it's not because you understand the personality of someone
and you have a clear mapping of that personality
that you can predict what that person is going to do.
And lastly, it does not explain all of human personality.
However, it's the most robust model we currently have,
and it's certainly interesting to keep it in mind
to account for human motivation.
For example, an individual who scores high in openness
might be more motivated to accomplish a creative task
than a low score on that trait.
Nikki from Quantic Foundry is using this model
to account for gamers' preferences,
so you might have heard of that.
All right, moving on.
Okay, so this one is really interesting.
The reason is it's video games are,
it's a specific environment
that is shaping players' behavior.
So this learn drive bucket is really important for us.
And it's mainly about rewards and punishments.
So here you are.
I'm going to have to describe this a little bit.
It's a bit boring, but after that it's going to be better.
So, rest means from the environment, the game is the environment, after player's action,
the behavior, can either be positive or negative.
When it's positive, it means that we're adding, we're adding something.
The player receives a carrot or is hit by a stick.
When it's negative, it simply means that we subtract
something from the environment.
We subtract a stick, a stick or a carrot
is removed from players.
So depending on how this feedback from the environment
is perceived by players, the player's behavior
will either increase, be repeated,
they're gonna do the action again, or decrease, stop.
Here are some examples for the positive reward example.
You kill an enemy, you get a reward.
So it feels rewarding, therefore you are likely
to do that behavior again.
A negative reward example would be you equip a shield on you
and therefore you don't get one shot killed anymore
by an enemy, so we remove the pain of dying,
therefore you're likely to keep that shield again.
Um, a positive punishment would be you tower dive in a MOBA, you die. Uh, so if you
understood what happened here, you are likely not doing that behavior again. And a
negative punishment would be you commit toxic behavior in a MOBA. Uh, for example, you
get banned from the game. So we remove the game from you.
or you did not manage to retrieve your souls
and you lose them all.
By extension, a negative punishment could happen
if you collect, say, 100 flags in Assassin's Creed
and you don't get any meaningful reward for that.
So even though it's not really something
that will remove some player technically,
if an expected reward doesn't come,
it can be felt as a punishment.
So, yeah, I love Ubisoft, but that traumatized me
a little bit, getting these flags.
Okay, so this is just a mapping of these rewards and punishments.
Now you have different types of rewards.
Rewards can be given either continuously or intermittently.
So continuous rewards is when player action is always rewarded.
So that's really important for learning and for game feel, which we're going to talk a
little bit later.
Intermittent reward is when player action is sometimes rewarded.
So that's more important for sustained engagement.
So let's dig deeper in this kind, this one,
because it's very frequently used in game.
All right.
Rewards can be intermittent, either based on time,
it's called interval, or based on player action,
it's called ratio.
Both of these reward types can be given expectedly,
so at a fixed interval or ratio,
or unexpectedly, at a certain interval or ratio.
All right, let's use some examples from games,
because I understand it's getting a bit complicated.
Okay so this is an example of a fixed interval reward. So in a game like Fortnite when you have
daily rewards, like everyday you come back in the game you have a reward that's waiting for you.
That's a fixed interval reward. Another example would be in Clash of Clans.
when you're starting building something
or you're waiting for your reward,
you have a clear timer on it.
So you know that after that time,
you can come back and collect your reward.
So this is good to lure players back in the game.
But once they're here,
you need to have something else from them to do.
So either the multiple rewards happening,
so like in Clash of Clans,
or once you're in the game in Fortnite,
you have a quest that's waiting for you
or you have a message saying,
hey, your friend is playing,
do you wanna join him or her in that game?
Sometimes it can be a fixed interval
before removing a reward.
So this is an example you have in stores.
It could be, you can get that thing,
rent it, you pay for it,
but it's gonna be removed in whatever, in 24 hours.
So this is creating.
uh, I, you know that you're not, uh, gonna have the opportunity to have that, uh, reward
at all times, uh, so you, you don't want to see that window of opportunity, uh, closing,
so it brings you, motivates you to try to get that thing, uh, before it's gone. Okay.
So now a variable interval example would be the cherry bonus in Pac-Man for example.
It comes at a certain time but you don't know exactly when.
You know that it's going to be here at some point but you don't know when.
Same thing in MMOs when you know that a certain mob can spawn at a certain place
but you don't know exactly when. It's unpredictable.
So the reward appears over time unexpectedly.
And fixed ratio example.
So this is all about when the player is doing
a certain action, certain actions,
certain amount of actions.
So quests, for example, skill trees,
are example of fixed ratio.
You need to do a certain number of actions
before getting the reward or getting the next skill.
Progression bars are kind of fixed ratio.
It's not exactly fixed.
It's fixed because you have a certain number of points
that you need to collect in order to get at the next level.
But the rate at which you're getting these points
is not always predictable.
So it's sort of, but not entirely.
And the last one is variable ratio examples.
It's of course gambling.
Slot machines.
You want something valuable to you,
but you never know exactly when you're gonna get it.
So it's loot crates, card packs, chests in the world,
et cetera.
All right, so now that we've seen
all of these different types of rewards,
let's see how it can differently impact behavior,
how it can impact player action.
So.
You see that this is how, this is the response rate.
So this is all the actions that the player do.
If you look at the top left one, it's a fixed interval.
So you know that at some point you're gonna get the reward.
So you don't really do anything until you had that window
and then you know that the reward is here.
When the window is open, then you do the action
and as soon as you had the reward,
you stop doing that action until the next time.
So this is what these graphs are saying.
So if you look at this.
You look at all the fixed type and you see that the behavior pauses after you get the reward.
And if the reward stops coming, this is really when you have a fast response extinction.
If you look at all the variable wins, they are the most steady response rate
because you don't really know when it's going to happen.
Now if you look at the ratio one,
when the player needs to do something,
it's not just about time you have to do something,
it's creating a higher response rate.
And the highest response rate
and the most steady of all is very low ratio.
As you can see, these different types of reward
affect player behavior very differently.
So when researchers say that extrinsic rewards
can deter intrinsic motivation, yes.
But really, it depends on many things.
It depends on the type of reward,
it depends on the context, whether or not
the person was intrinsically motivated
to do the task without consideration
of any rewards to begin with.
If the reward is money, or if it's a verbal pat on the back,
is it an item that you receive, et cetera.
So it's really hard to anticipate what's going to happen
because it depends on so many variables.
Also, usually you see a decrease in intrinsic motivation
and behavior when a reward is introduced and then removed.
And that doesn't happen that often in games.
So I don't know if you were at the session
from Travis Day from Blizzard yesterday,
and he mentioned in his super interesting talk
that when players reach max level in WoW, for example,
then it seems that the rewards stop arriving
because you reach.
the highest uh XP level. The highest level. And so XP don't really matter anymore. But it's
not really that rewards stop arriving. Um there's still you know you still receive stuff for
doing uh what you're doing. Um but it's more that
you have reached an end goal already, the max level,
and you might not have another meaningful goal
to work towards.
So, hence the importance of community events
and new quests and content,
because you always want the player
to be looking forward something.
This is why rewards are highly related to goals,
and both must be meaningful to keep players engaged,
and a reward must be not an end goal,
but it should be a means for the next goal.
Okay, so, these are not mutually exclusive,
the list I'm gonna give right now,
and these are really broad guidelines.
In practice, like I said, there's a lot of subtleties
depending on the context, but consider all rewards
and punishment your game provide,
because everything in your game,
all the feedback that's happening in your game
are either gonna be perceived as a reward
or as a punishment.
Always give feedback to all player actions.
We're gonna talk about that in game feel.
But give consistent reward for most meaningful actions.
And remember that the more time and effort
it's taking for the player to accomplish a task,
the greater the reward is gonna be expected.
And an absence of these rewards
will likely be felt as punishments.
Also use rewards at intermittent intervals
for player habit formation and player strategy.
You can use rewards at fixed ratio
to create a sense of mastery.
You can use rewards at variable ratio
for some chests to create excitement.
and remember to mix it all.
So this is the reason why it's complicated
because there's so many different types
and so many different contexts and variables
that are at play here.
All right.
So the last bucket, we're gonna talk about
intrinsic motivation, about SDT,
so self-determination theory,
that you probably have heard a lot
because there's minimum two talks per GDC,
if not more than that, that talk about SDT
at some point or another.
So I'm pretty sure that you know what this is.
So you have competence, autonomy, and relatedness.
Intrinsic motivation is all about the need.
for these three things. So competence is about a sense of progression, a sense of being in control,
autonomy is a sense of volition, having meaningful choices and being able to express yourself.
And relatedness is a sense of meaningful social relationships,
either through cooperation or competition.
And when we talk about undermining effect of intrinsic reward,
it can take place when they thwart more and more of these three needs.
So this is why, for example, we give the illusion of control to gamblers,
so they can feel a sense of autonomy,
even though the outcome is ultimately completely random.
So the thing with SDT is it alone cannot account for all
human behavior.
You have to take behaviorism and individual needs and
drives into account.
Undermining effect of intrinsic reward on intrinsic
motivation depends on the context.
Some self-determination theories moved away from the intrinsic-extrinsic motivation dichotomy
and talk, um, now they talk instead about, they have a focus on distinction between autonomous and controlled motivation
which, uh, with different types of reward. So I'm going to talk about that right after.
Um, but ultimately it depends like how you perceive, how...
Ultimately what the reward is going to be,
if it's going to be more intrinsic, more extrinsic,
controlling or not controlling,
really depends on how the player is going to perceive it.
And the most important thing you need to remember
is goals and rewards must be meaningful to players.
So the autonomous versus control rewards.
So you can have different types of rewards
that are either controlling or felt as more autonomous.
Let's see the different types of rewards.
See, there's a lot of different types.
You have one, the non-contingent rewards.
So these rewards are not related
to any particular behavior from the player.
So you have a surprise gift just because
the player did not do anything to get a reward.
Now, you also have task contingent rewards.
These are the rewards that you get for doing something.
So either you get a reward for engage in an activity.
For example, you're in the world,
you just accepted a quest or whatever,
and you find stuff in the world
that's rewarding your engagement.
They can be rewarding completion.
You have to finish a mission to complete a mission
before getting a reward.
Or they can reward performance.
So you have to complete a mission,
but you get a different reward
depending on how well you completed the mission.
So this is an example with the stars.
You have to have a high performance
to get all the three stars.
Otherwise, you get less stars.
So the...
Performance contingent rewards that are given specifically for matching some standard of
excellence are likely to be experienced as the most controlling because you really have
to perform something at a certain level to get the reward.
However, since they also can act as a feedback on competence and give you a powerful sense
of mastery, the negative effect of the control can be counteracted by the expression of a
sense of progression, when there is such progression.
So, in the end, rewards that are task contingent but simply given for completing a task might
be felt as less controlling on one hand, but they also do not offer any perceived increase
of competence and could therefore ultimately be the worst kind of all as far as intrinsic
motivation is concerned.
So this is just an illustration that it's complicated
and not easily predictable.
There's a lot of stuff happening
and it's really not easy to have
a clear understanding of it all.
You need to have all these clear mapping in your head
and there's no just one recipe that you can apply everywhere.
So try to make sure that the incentives are not trying to,
well at least make sure that the player
doesn't feel controlled by these incentives.
Which is not easy to do, but anyway.
Swimming in rewards.
Again, Travis Day yesterday mentioned
that making players swim in rewards,
being generous with them and give them a lot of rewards
was increasing engagement.
Which I totally agree.
Like he was taking the example of Diablo III
and they were seeing that if they're giving more rewards,
players were actually more excited
and felt more rewarded and were engaging more.
I totally agree with that.
The problem is it's only if these rewards
have a meaningful value for players.
So I'm gonna take the example from Paragon here.
And you're gonna see what's happening
after the first match that you play.
So it's a batch against bots.
And you get a bunch of reward after your first game.
It looks like that.
All right, so you saw here that the rewards are flowing.
So the intent was to make the player feel rewarded.
But the problem is that the player at some point
is just dismissing all these rewards.
So it could actually be perceived as more punishing
or overwhelming than truly rewarding.
Because at that point, the player doesn't know
what all these rewards are for.
It doesn't have the need for looking into these rewards.
It doesn't understand the value of these rewards yet.
So it can be really tricky to do that.
You have to make sure that the rewards
are meaningful to the player,
because if you receive all these rewards,
it can be a bit, it can rise as anxiety,
because you can feel like, oh shit,
I have to learn all that stuff at some point,
and what it means, and what I can use them for.
So you have to be careful with that,
because giving a lot of rewards, it's cool,
only if players understand what they're for.
So show the lock, show the purpose, show the goal before giving them a key or giving them
rewards which are means to an end.
Okay, so just to wrap up this part because I know it's a big part and I apologize to go
through that very quickly but again I really want you to have a big picture of it. So
remember you have to give clear goals. So
yeah short term, mid term and long term, it's really important.
Offer non-controlling rewards that give feedback on player competence.
Goals and rewards must be meaningful,
which means that players must understand
their sense of purpose, value, and impact for the game.
And receiving a key reward should not be perceived
as an ending point, but as a starting point for a new goal.
So this is really important.
If you're receiving a reward and it's the end of it,
then you don't need to engage anymore.
The reward must be perceived that you get something
and with that you're gonna do something else.
So meaning can also be a sense of purpose
greater than the self.
And this is why being a part of guilds or factions,
it's really highly meaningful.
So in For Honor, for example, you have
a faction war that's persistent, cross-platform,
that's a conflict between knights, vikings, and samurai,
and you're part of one of these factions,
so whatever you do in the game,
it's not only just gonna impact you,
but it's gonna impact your faction,
so it's a meaning that's greater than just yourself.
Same thing in Pokemon, you have the different teams.
There's another game that maybe you played.
It's called Noby Noby Boy.
So in that game, the player controls the character
called Boy, and you have to stretch
his body on the planet.
And the player accumulates points by how much they stretch
Boy during gameplay.
And these points that the players earn at the end
can be submitted online to Girl, another character that
goes out of space.
The points submitted online by players.
to girl are added cumulatively across all players,
causing girl to stretch into the Milky Way.
So girl starts on Earth,
and the more players are doing their stuff
and winning in their own games, it's growing girl.
And it took, for example, seven years
for Toonobi players to make girl reach Pluto together.
So that, again, is another example
than whatever you do in the game
as a meaning that is greater than yourself.
All right, so you need to consider motivation as a whole,
with all its complexity, to maybe be able to anticipate
your player's behavior and projected engagement.
So please, if you hear a simplistic,
one-fits-all solution about motivation, be dubious.
Yes it might sound seducing to get a magic peel to solve all of your problems, but it doesn't
work that way and ultimately it could mislead you if you don't consider all the complexities of
human motivation. Yes I know it sucks, but it's the way it is. It's complicated. Okay, um,
So now I'm going to briefly talk about motivation and game flow.
As I said earlier, these both elements
are contributing to motivation.
So emotion serves motivation.
When you detect a danger, you feel an emotion, fear,
and that gets you to run away.
Like you know, I'm sure emotions are critical to learning and survival because they guide
us through our interaction with the environment as we seek pleasure and avoid pain.
But emotion is also influenced by cognition.
So top-down processing involving prior knowledge, expectation, and judgment, like appraisal
of a situation, is changing the way the emotions are going to feel.
That's why presentation is important.
If something looks good, that is a nice bottle of champagne,
you expect to have pleasure, and indeed you're going to get greater pleasure
by drinking from that bottle of champagne rather than drinking from one that doesn't look as good.
So this is how your cognition, your expectation, your prior knowledge
is going to impact what you feel about something.
It's going to impact your emotion.
Similarly, if you experience something frustrating
in a game, for example, such as losing a PvP match,
you might attribute your frustration
not to just the outcome of the match,
but to the whole experience, to the whole gameplay.
So you have to be careful with frustration to the players
because they can generalize what they feel,
but not to just the element that made them felt that way,
but to the whole experience.
And so that's the appraisal of a situation.
And the interesting thing is what we call reappraisal.
So appraisal can modify how we feel about a situation.
Helping players to reappraise their cognitive feelings
might also have some benefits.
So for example, instead of letting them feel bad
as they see in big red letters that their team has lost
and that they suck, you could instead emphasize
that they did better than the winning team in some metrics
or that despite losing, they have improved
on some of their personal metrics.
Overwatch is an example that is particularly good at that.
And whenever you finish a match, you see all...
whether you win or you lose.
I tried to lose before going to GDC and get the picture.
I couldn't lose.
But anyway, it's...
But you see the same screen.
You see all these badges that you get,
whether you win or you lose.
And it's telling you whether you beat your career average
on different metrics such as number of kills,
like here, elimination.
time stayed on the objective area, healing that you did, weapon accuracy, etc. So this is
helping you even if you lost and you feel bad, what makes you reappraise that negative
feelings to look at, oh, okay, it was not all bad. At least, you know, I did that stuff good
and oh, I'm getting better at this.
So think about ways to do that because in multiplayer games,
there's usually half of the players that feel miserable at the end of a match.
So if you find a way to make them reappraise their judgment of their negative feeling,
it's really all win.
Okay, so in games, in game design,
usually when we talk about emotion,
we talk about two things.
We talk about game feel,
so how it feels to interact with the game.
And when we talk about that,
we mainly talk about the three Cs,
so character,
control, camera, we talk about presence,
as the presence experience when players have the illusion that there's nothing
in between them and their virtual world when they perceive that there is
simply inside the game without mediation,
about physical reality, so it's all about
it means it seems real when you shoot on something because you
have particle effect or you have like some some visual effect and sound effect and it feels real.
So all of that contributes to the player to feel emotions when they play.
So it's a big bucket and that's the reason why I'm not going to really talk about it,
but it's really, really important.
The other one is all about bringing discoveries.
bringing surprises because this is going to impact the level of engagement and awareness.
The brain usually is, when we see something surprising, it's going to wake us all up because
it might be dangerous.
So just overall, this is helping awareness to have surprises.
It's not everything all the same.
So just to illustrate game feel a little bit,
this is why our direction, animation, music, sound
effects, all that is really, truly important
because it's going to make the game feel
good to interact with.
And so in Fortnite, what we do when you open card packs,
we actually, it doesn't look like card packs,
it looks like a piata, which is really
close to the environment, the game world.
And you don't just click on something.
You have a stick or a.
uh, sword in that case, to bid the f- shit out of it. Uh, so it's really compelling, uh, you really, you
really feel that you're gonna do something interesting. Um, I'm gonna show a vi- show you a
video of that, and you're gonna see that, uh, the- the eye of the piata, as, uh, of the llama is
actually following the mouse, and as soon as you click on the button to, uh, to, like, hit it, uh,
the eyes are retracting.
It's a lovely day for loot.
Have at it.
Oh, I am feeling lucky.
Hey, check out this nice loot.
Super loud. And so what you saw here is that it's sort of the red circle by the way, it's eye
tracking. That's where the players are looking at. It's really making this part of the game like a
toy within the game itself. So it's helping game feel.
Also, just like the lever and slot machines,
it gives you the illusion of control to open a pack.
So we would see players trying to hit the limelight
in a certain way because they might believe
that they're gonna get an upgrade if they do that.
They don't, but they believe they do,
and this is giving you the illusion of control,
which brings you some autonomy,
and it's good for intrinsic motivation.
Alright, here's another example of game feel.
So in Fortnite, it's an action building game
and you need to harvest a lot of stuff to build later on.
There's a lot of RPG mechanics in that game.
And so you spend a good amount of time
harvesting in the world,
especially if you're the outlander,
which is the hero that goes out to harvest everything.
And when you harvest, we actually have, again, a mini game when you harvest.
And you're going to see that you have a little blue target.
It's called a weak point.
And if you hit that weak point, it's actually harvesting faster the item.
And it's also, each time you hit one of these targets,
you hear a very nice, rewarding sound.
And it goes up in tone.
So it's been doo-doo-doo-doo.
We're not going to be able to hear it that well, but it looks like that.
The sound is not great because all these videos are coming from playtests, so it's pretty
compressed and the sound is not terrible.
But this is giving you an idea of when you harvest, you have the mini-game that's included
in there.
An example of surprise, so in Fortnite you wander around in the game, in the world,
and you sometimes find some chests and it's always pretty exciting.
But at some point in the game, it's fairly late in the game, this is what can happen.
Not a chest!
So the first time that happens to a player,
they're usually pretty surprised,
you know, they're like,
oh okay, what am I gonna get in loot?
They sometimes, you know, like,
take a sip on their, whatever stuff they're drinking,
and then there's, oh no, it's actually an anatomy,
and they need to do something about it.
That makes them feel that, actually,
they cannot take everything from Fortnite,
and so it's raising their awareness.
So, surprise like that only work once,
but you can do that across different stuff in the game.
All right, that's all for emotion,
I told you it would go fast.
Let's look at game flow.
Game flow is all about putting the player in the zone
where it's not too easy, not too difficult.
I'm sure you know that already,
so I'm not gonna describe this in detail,
but there are three components to game flow
that are really important.
So the first one is difficulty curve.
You want to make sure that the challenge is not too easy, not too difficult.
It's all about pacing as well.
You want the rhythm of the game not to be, the pressure not to be too strong,
and the stress not too strong, not too low.
And it's all about the learning curve.
So learning curve is really, really important.
It's all about onboarding.
You want to onboard the player in a meaningful way.
You want to distribute learning over time.
It's not too compacted, everything at the beginning.
I had a whole talk last year about onboarding,
so I'm not gonna talk too much about it,
but it's really, really critical.
And so you know, I'm pretty sure you've seen
that graph many times.
But one thing I want to emphasize here
is you don't have, like in the flow zone,
it's not a straight line.
Because if the challenge increases at the same time
as the player mastery is increasing as well,
it never feels that you're getting better.
Because if it's really growing in a straight line,
it's not working that well.
So you need to have some times when you feel extra challenged and sometimes that you feel like super powerful and you're destroying everybody
So that's the reason why it goes in waves and it's not a straight line. So you need to approach game flow like a
Wave you need to think about it as a sawtooth
difficulty progression, as game designers call it,
and to create situations where old ability
can be compared to new ability.
It makes a player realize that progress was made.
It makes them feel competent,
and it's really important for motivation.
Here's an example from Shadow of Mordor.
So you have these nasty Uruks, captains,
that are pretty difficult to beat at the beginning,
and actually most of the time,
they're the ones who will kill you.
but had all that nemesis system that you can remember.
You can see clearly who killed you.
It's not great for reprisal of feelings
because they're all like boasting that they killed you
and they're like, hey, you suck.
But on the other hand, at some point, you're getting super powerful and you can kill these
motherfuckers. And then it feels really, yeah, this is really how it felt when I played that
game. And it's really compelling because you remember how difficult it was to kill them. So
now clearly you've become super powerful. And at some point you can even control their
minds. So anyway.
You got that.
So you really need to give players a reference point
to make them feel their growth.
Because if it's growing always at the same level,
you're never gonna feel extra powerful at some point.
So you need to have that sawtooth challenge.
Pacing. Pacing is all about stress. You need stress. Stress is important. If there's no stress at all, it's not meaningful.
You're not willing to learn about anything. You're not willing to pay attention to anything if you don't have any stress.
So the problem is that if it's too stressful,
if a situation is too stressful,
you might be less efficient because you're losing your shit
because it's so overwhelming
and so it impacts your feel of competence.
So you need to find the nice balance,
all about balance in games,
not too stressful but not low on stress either.
To do that, for example, in Fortnite, the first time that you actually, after the introduction,
the first time that you can play the game, we place you in a situation where it's a little
bit stressful because enemies are just spawning right away.
So you don't have to, you know, you can't just like hang out like that.
Enemies are here.
However, they are behind a low wall, so they can't really get at you right away.
So you have a little bit of pressure, but it's not too much.
You see that?
No, you don't.
Yeah.
All right.
So you get the idea.
So you really need a little bit of pressure, but not too much.
Another example in this one, we're now going to talk about onboarding.
Okay, I'm going to talk a little bit about it, but not too much, I promise.
But it's really important because if you don't onboard the player well,
if the tutorials are not made properly,
then the player is not going to feel competent
because he's going to get his ass killed.
So you want to make sure that this matters way more than you think.
And, um...
When we look at the analytics in Paragon,
we show that the most impactful factors for churn
were related to actually lack of competence.
Like people dying from towers, for example,
or not equipping cards were the most impactful factors
correlated with churning early.
So we would see in playtests a lot of core players
that would tower dive.
So it looked like that.
Time for a good old DU front A
Time for a good old DU front A Take that toward the stop
Take that toward the stop
So I don't know if you know that, in a MOBA, you need to destroy towers, but the towers,
you're going to get aggro from the towers if you don't let minions get in first, or
if you're trying to destroy the tower to actually try to aim at some enemies while within the
radius of the tower, then you get the aggro to you. And this is something that would happen
over and over and over again. We had players that were core players that would do these
things because they didn't know exactly all these rules, the tower aggro rules.
So what we did later on is we had a tutorial level
where we teach a little bit about the towers
and tower agro, and once we did that,
we saw that retention got a little bit higher.
So it's really, really important,
and this is where the top five issues
that we saw in UX testing,
so it was all about understanding the game,
all about you being competent in the game.
These were actually, months before launch,
were identified as later on
as the most impactful factors for churning.
So keep that in mind, like it's really important to nail your tutorials.
Alright, yeah, that was the game flow part.
So this is all that we saw today, I'm going to wrap this up really quickly.
I'm going to try to at least.
So retention, engageability, is all about motivation,
which entails managing goals, so quests, events, and rewards.
But not only.
Motivation has a lot to do with moment-to-moment emotions.
So this is all about game feel and surprises.
It's also mostly about feeling competent
and feeling a sense of growing mastery.
So game flow, and especially onboarding,
is really paramount.
And for all these things, usability has actually a critical impact on all of the above.
Because it impacts the level of friction and the sense of being in control.
If you have too many usability issues, it's likely that players are not going to feel any sense of mastery.
If they don't understand the value of certain rewards,
they actually don't even see,
perceive that they're receiving a reward.
They don't see that there's a new goal,
or they don't understand why they need to do whatever,
it's certainly not gonna help their motivation.
So please do not neglect usability,
because usually a lot of problems are actually there.
It's not that there's motivation design missing,
it's that the players don't understand it.
So it's really critical to engagement too.
And if you, I don't know if you noticed,
but the commanding lady here is you always have to think
about what is the meaning for players?
Like really, truly there's one thing to remember
is always think about the meaning for the players.
Why would they care about your goals
that you're setting for them?
What would they care about that reward
that you're giving them?
Is there a purpose for them to get it?
Do they understand the value to get it?
So let me take one last example to illustrate this.
And it's also illustrating how to find out
what's going on in your game.
So when you identify an issue in your game,
for example, when you're designed for the loot,
all the nice math that you're doing,
it's actually not really perceived
the way you intended by the players
because when they say about how they felt about the loot,
if it was compelling or not compelling,
it's not necessarily working the way you intended.
So.
a few things can happen here. You have three main possibilities. Either something is
missing in the design. Uh one system has not been implemented yet so it's fucking
everything else. The balance is off etc. Um so this is when it's difficult because until
the system is here you can't really see how players react.
Or it could be here, but it's not yet balanced well.
The last possibility is the systems are all in well-balanced,
but they're not conveyed properly to the players.
So they cannot really perceive the true value of it.
And so when that happens, you need to figure out what's going on
and where is the problem coming from.
Do you remember when I was talking about the mini game when you harvest and you hit these little weak points?
Actually, I'm going to talk about that first. So in Fortnite we have a
One of the feedback that we get from players and they feel that it's too grindy
You have to harvest all in Fortnite, but they really have that strong feeling that it's taking too much to grind to get all the stuff etc
And if you look at just the signs and feedback,
when you harvest, you see that each time you hit something,
like a car for example,
you see that there's one material popping, it's metal.
So you get that you are getting metal from the car,
but this is the biggest thing that you see,
it's the closest to the reticle,
and you just see one piece of metal.
But in fact, you actually just, with one hit,
you're actually getting like 13 of these pieces.
So it might be that just the players are not truly understanding that each time they're
harvesting something they're getting way more than they actually perceive just because it's
not clear on the feedback on screen.
And we also had another problem for a long time with the weak points.
So,
when you saw the player like hitting the weak points and it was actually
rewarding, it actually took us a while to get there. At the very beginning the weak points looked like that. It was yellow.
And this is what we would see players do.
Not getting the point.
Don't care. Nope.
So what I initially thought was, okay,
it's probably just a usability problem.
It's not perceived as something you need to hit
because it looks like a feedback,
like yeah, you're destroying shit
and it's the same color, it's yellow.
It's usually the color that you show
like you're damaging something, it's yellow-orange.
So what we did is we changed the color of it.
We changed how it looked like to make it feel more like,
hey, you need to hit that stuff.
And so it changed and now it's blue.
It's way more in your face and this is what happened.
Still not hitting it.
And so this is like, what's going on?
It's right in your face.
It's blue.
Why don't you hit it?
And what we're asking players, we're just showing the little hit point, the weak point,
and we're asking them, what do you think that is?
And they were saying, well, it's just saying that I'm targeting that item when I'm harvesting.
And you're like, oh, OK.
So in the end, what the designers did, the team did,
is instead of having that waypoint from the get-go,
you would not actually have it at the very beginning.
You would have to unlock it in the skill tree.
At some point, you get a mission,
and you need to unlock this thing.
You see it in the skill tree.
You pay for it.
and then you do it with a sabre, and then you get it.
And this is only when that the players truly understood
the value of this thing, because they experienced
what it is to harvest before getting that thing.
We made it more meaningful to get that thing.
And so therefore, they immediately understood
what it was for.
We gave meaning.
to the weak point, and this is when we solve that problem.
So you always need to think about the purpose,
and you always need to give a reference point
to the players before giving something that is cool.
So the real challenge, usually in games,
is to find the real issue
before you can actually solve the problem.
So having a clear overall mapping of player engagement,
know all these ingredients, and have hypotheses
at the beginning, which you can test
as you develop the game, will help you identify
the real issues and fix them appropriately.
So we always think.
We always talk about players' motivation.
But what about game developers' motivation?
Intrinsic motivation is important for creativity.
Guess what happens when you are given a motivation recipe
that you have to follow?
When games end up being all the same,
so players can now see the matrix,
and everything is too predictable.
The brain likes some changes and surprises,
and so you don't have that emotion
if it's too predictable.
And the other thing is developers feel less volition
creating the game, therefore they don't put
their heart and soul in it.
So even if there was a secret sauce
or perfect recipe for game engagement, there isn't.
But even if it were existent, game development
is mostly a creative endeavor, so developers need
to find their own recipe to be motivated and ship quality.
So the ingredient approach works better for animation.
And so as UX practitioners, we are here,
we're only here to provide guidance.
We can provide game developers with a methodology,
like user research, and guidelines such as these UX pillars,
the ingredients that are important
for offering great user experience.
But in the end, it's gonna be up to you
to make your own recipe.
And that's it for today.
Thank you.
I talked a lot, but there's still five minutes for questions if you want to come up to the
mics.
Hi, Celia.
Hi.
Great talk.
I was wondering if you could talk a little bit about, how do I want to phrase this?
difficulty adjustment in a game that applies to like a wide audience. So an example would be like
an Uncharted, if I'm wandering around and I'm lost, it'll put like a little tip on the screen
and say you actually have to go over here. Um I'm just wondering like when a game apply applies to
a wide audience like how do you make that decision when you're developing the game like to actually
like improve the level design versus actually like pointing out stuff to the person that's struggling?
Yeah, that's a great question.
So overall, it's usually a good practice
to have contextual tips.
So you don't necessarily, depending
on how complex a certain behavior it
is for the player to learn, you can just get away with it,
not have a cool, big tutorial about it,
but just give a contextual tip so only the players who
are lost see it.
Or it could be you had a tutorial about it,
but at some point later in the game, you forget about it.
So having a contextual tip is helping.
So usually if it's done well, it is cool because feeling lost and not knowing where to go can be very frustrating
and so you feel that sense of autonomy and control, you know, feeling in control of the game.
On the other hand, if it's happening too early,
it can feel controlling.
So the problem is that everything in game
is all about balancing.
So you don't want players to be lost,
but you don't want them to feel controlled
by some pesky comments.
So it's all about.
If you can make it more subtle, try to draw their attention to something rather than just having a text, it could work as well.
It really depends on the context.
But if really they've been wondering for five minutes, it's better to give them a solution so they don't stay stuck, for sure.
Hi there. You talked about the motivation that having things like clans or teams like For Honor with...
I can't really hear you. What can you...
Sorry. You talked about the motivation that having things like clans can add to the game,
for using For Honor as an example, the Samurais and the Watchers and all that.
How do you manage the balance between the emotional connection to losing that battle
with providing that motivation for the player?
Yeah, it's all about trade-offs yet again.
So yeah, if you're in the clan, it's always losing.
It can be feel a bit hard.
So you have to make sure that you have ways
to help the player to, like I was talking about,
reappraise what's going on.
So them negative feelings, just like,
okay, your guild sucks, but hey,
you're the best of this guild.
So it could be either that, or making sure that
the team, if there's one that's really overpowered.
you give them more difficulty,
like you increase their difficulty or give them.
That's the reason why we have handicap in games like golf.
So everybody can be at a certain level.
It's not, you don't feel like you really,
you're really a loser or like games like Go,
you have a handicap, so it's balanced.
So we can think about doing stuff like that,
but there's always trade-offs for everything.
And like you say, we need to design for it
and to think about it.
Yeah.
I would like to ask you to give me the analysis of an example I give to my students.
When you play Shadow of the Colossus, when you kill the Colossus one after the other,
you understand that you are making something which is wrong.
There is a feeling of guilt that goes all around the games.
I would like to ask you to give me the analysis of an example I give to my students.
After a certain time, you understand that you are going to be punished for what you
are doing.
But if you want to know the story, the end of the story, you have no choice.
You have to kill the colossus.
So it's very strange motivation.
It's narrative motivation.
I give this to show the long-term motivation in the game can be purely narrative.
But how you put it in...
the analysis of the motivation of the player?
So it's a little bit different, because like you said,
it's really about narrative, and it's
about making you feel guilt, which
is the point of that game in that case.
So if it's the point of the game,
if it's the experience that you intend for players,
then it's fine.
You have to think about the trade-off,
but usually you feel that towards the end of the game.
It's also a paid up front game, so you don't necessarily need
retention as much as in free-to-play games.
And so there's another great example from Brenda Romero,
like she's, remember the game like Train,
and you have to make sure that you place as many people
as you can in the train and to make the space.
efficient, until you realize that the train is going to Auschwitz.
And that was the whole point of the game, to make you feel guilt.
And only games can make you feel emotions like that.
You don't necessarily feel guilt from watching a movie.
So if it's your intent...
You know that maybe the player is going to not feel super motivated to finish the game,
but you're playing with that feeling of guilt.
So when it's the point of the game, then go for it,
as long as you know the trade-offs you're making.
Now, if it's not the point of the game, you should avoid it,
especially if it's a free-to-play game.
Hi Celia, thank you for the talk.
It happens that I work on the math model of slot machines.
So it turns out slot machines, all the rewards come from the real money that is the payout.
So how can we apply all the theories of the rewards and events
when the payout and the hit rates are all fixed in the math model?
Yeah, it's a whole different beast.
And like I said, there's no real recipe.
It's hard for me to just give you an answer just like that.
It takes a lot of different variables.
Any tips on the whistles or the game flows?
Yeah, yeah. And that lady here maybe would have some tips for you.
Okay, thank you.
You're welcome.
Alright, one last question?
No, if there are no more questions.
Okay. Are you good?
I thought we had all the time, but the Game Audio Awards are...
What do you mean we have all the time? We want drinks now.
Right, exactly.
Thank you very much, everyone.