Thanks for coming.
Hi, I'm Kosuke Ibuki from Nintendo, producer of Mario Kart 8 Deluxe and ARMS.
So, I'm sure you all know Mario Kart, right?
As for ARMS, like you just saw in the video,
it's a competitive fighting game using fighters with extendable arms.
We created ARMS based on our experience with Mario Kart.
The genre of the game is different from racing and fighting,
but Mario Kart and ARMS are like siblings.
We used our experience with Mario Kart as the basis for the development of ARMS.
Though they're different genres, racing and fighting,
Mario Kart and ARMS are something like siblings.
Today, I'd like to take a look back at the creation process for ARMS and touch on how it was influenced by Mario Kart and how we used that previous experience.
And at the same time, I want to talk to you about Nintendo's game development culture that forms the backbone of both.
However, you may wonder if a Mario Kart developer can make a fighting game.
But Nintendo developers have had the experience of making a variety of games.
I myself have been involved in games like Zelda and Nintendogs,
not just Mario Kart.
I've been involved in a variety of genres,
so it's no wonder I make fighting games.
When you try a new genre, you will naturally use your past experience.
You may become unique because you know the other genre well.
Since I've worked on many different types of games,
it shouldn't be any stranger to try making a fighting game.
Naturally, when attempting a new genre, you have to rely on your past experience.
And, if you have a strong background in a different genre than the new one you're attempting,
that can mean you'll be able to make something unique.
However, other companies other than Nintendo make legendary fighting games like Street Fighter.
I think that even if we imitate it, it will only be a deteriorated game.
So if we make a fighting game,
it will be limited to when we find something unique that is different from others.
That said, games like the Legendary Street Fighter
are something companies other than Nintendo specialize in.
Even if we tried to imitate them,
the game we'd end up making wouldn't be anything unique.
So if we decide to make a fighting game,
it's only because we found some interesting idea or element
that'll make it different from other games.
Unique is something Nintendo values the most.
Miyamoto-san,
If I'm asked what makes Nintendo different from others,
if I can't answer, I have no future.
Nintendo places importance on being unique above all else.
If Miyamoto-san asks me,
what makes this different, and I don't have an answer,
I'm finished.
Nintendo always makes new games.
Making games is not easy.
Sometimes you feel like you're walking in a big maze,
and you often bump into walls.
so you might want to look for other ways.
At Nintendo, we're always prototyping new games.
Making games isn't easy, is it?
Sometimes it feels like you're walking around in a giant maze.
You run into walls a lot.
Sometimes you need to find another path.
There are very few new IPs that come out in the world.
Mario Kart is already 25 years old,
so it's quite an adult game.
But for me, ARMS is still like a newborn baby.
So, we have to take good care of it.
So, let's get started.
One day, I was having a light chat with the game designer, Jikumaru.
Can we make a fighting game from the perspective of the back?
I think this is a topic that has been repeated many times by developers around the world.
You may have talked about it once.
So, one day I was casually chatting with one of my game designers named Jikumaru-san,
and the topic came up,
can you make a fighting game with the camera behind the player?
It's probably a question that's come up among developers all over the world countless times.
Maybe you all have talked about it amongst yourselves as well.
That chat was how ARMS started.
Of course, I think we all understand why most fighting games use a side view.
It's because it's easier to understand the distance between you and your opponent.
You approach your opponent and punch in exchange for the risk of getting hit.
It's because it makes it easy to judge the distance from your opponent.
In exchange for the risk of being hit, you move in closer to hit them.
That's the most basic structure of a fighting game.
If you're using a behind-the-back perspective, it's hard to judge how far you are from your opponent.
Will my punch reach them? Will it come up short? It's hard to tell.
If the players are freely mobile on top of that, this lack of tactical precision will lead to a fight that just isn't worthwhile.
So let's veer off a little and talk about a game I know very well, Mario Kart.
Something appears in the distance, and you have to cut the steering wheel.
That's the basic structure of the game.
Even if you don't know the precise distance to the obstacle,
you can avoid it by using the time until you reach it.
Something appears in the distance, and you steer in relation to that.
That's the basic structure of the game.
Even if you don't know the distance between you and an obstacle,
as long as you steer around it in the time it takes you to reach it, you'll be fine.
So let's take a look at this again.
If, given enough time, attacks will always reach your opponent,
maybe we can structure a fighting game around the behind-the-back perspective.
That was the idea my game designer came up with.
The question of distance, whether your punch will reach the opponent or not,
instead becomes a question of whether your punch will hit or miss,
playing out over the entirety of the screen.
When you get an idea like this, you have to try prototyping it.
This is a video we made back at the prototype stage.
It still has some Japanese text in it, but let's take a look and I'll translate it.
So it's a competitive fighting game where you use these long reaching attacks
and you hold the controller using this thumbs up style grip.
You tilt the controllers forward and back to move forward and back,
left and right to move left and right,
L and R buttons to jump,
and then flick them to send out this stretching punch.
While the punch is extending, if you tilt the controllers that'll curve your punch.
Here you can see the hit point meters for you and your opponent.
If one of those reaches zero, then the match is over.
You can switch out your weapons on either side just before the match starts.
We also made mini-games using that same ARMS gameplay. ♪
So you might have noticed there was a bowling prototype
that didn't make it into the final game.
All prototypes don't make it into the final game.
With Nintendo prototypes, we don't care about the visuals.
If the boxes and balls are moving, we can check the game design.
So at Nintendo, we don't care about visuals when we're prototyping.
Blocks and balls in motion are enough to check out a game design idea.
This prototype was like boxing, where you fight your opponent in the distance,
or like shooting, where you aim at your opponent in the distance.
It looked cheap, but it was a very tactical battle.
So this prototype had elements of boxing, trading blows with a close-up opponent,
but it also felt like a shooter, where you aimed at a distant opponent.
It might look cheap, but even at this stage, you could have a tactical battle.
Players can punch one of their opponents, and then punch the other at any time.
The first punch was a straight punch, and the second was a curved punch.
A player could, after punching with one arm, unleash the other with opportune timing.
Maybe the first punch just goes straight as a decoy,
and then the second punch curves to where they're dodging.
We also thought that we could replace the elements that make up a fighting game
with elements that make it easier to understand and visualize.
On top of that, we took the basic elements of a fighting game
and tried to replace them with easy-to-understand visual elements.
For example, the defensive opening during an attack
can be expressed as the time when the arms are extending and contracting.
You can't guard while your arms are extended.
That's easy to understand, right?
Also, attack variations like weak and strong punches could instead be expressed as arm variations with light and heavy weapons.
Different combinations of weapons on the left and right arms could also create different strategies.
This idea of finding replacements for familiar gameplay elements
is very important when you're trying to design a new game.
We had two basic principles.
Make sure that the trajectory of the extending arms
is easy to visually distinguish,
and keep the number of things players have to learn
to a minimum.
With these in mind, development of ARMS began in earnest.
Also, this gameplay felt like a really good fit
with the then prototype stage, Joy-Con.
It felt unique, like it had a future.
In fighting games, there is no delay and the operation is very reliable.
It's been more than 10 years since the Wii Remote,
and the hardware has evolved, but we have also evolved in the software side.
Fighting games in general strive for controls that are as precise as possible.
Ten years have passed since the Wii Remote first came out,
and the hardware has certainly evolved,
but the software side, us in other words, has also evolved.
With our current technology, we can create a game that can be played by advanced players
with precise and motionless motion control.
It seemed to me that with our current technology,
more precise and accurate motion controls could be realized,
and we could make a game where advanced players could pursue highly technical play.
On the other hand, the Nintendo Switch is a game console that changes its appearance according to the player.
Like Mario Kart 8 Deluxe,
ARMS aims to make games that you can play
with any style, whether it's buttons,
motion, backrest, or mobile phone.
On the other hand, the Nintendo Switch is a game system
that can adjust itself to many different types of players.
As with Mario Kart 8 Deluxe, I wanted players to be able to play
how they want, to use button controls and motion controls,
play docked, or play handheld.
One thing to note about motion control,
and that you can play with just moving it around,
and that you can't beat advanced players with just that.
In other words, the game has a wide and deep opening.
This was a challenge that Mario Kart had been pursuing for a long time,
and ARMS also took on the challenge.
This is something I worry about with motion controls,
but we focused on making sure that the game could be played
with casual and precise motions,
but that also playing like that
wouldn't be enough to beat an advanced player.
In other words, the game's broadly accessible,
but it also has depth.
That's something we've been pursuing
all along with Mario Kart,
and ARMS has been a similar challenge.
We also aimed to make ARMS a game
where top players can play the same way
by using the same buttons and motions.
And with ARMS, we aim to have motion and button controls be equally viable in matches between top-level players.
Learning controls you're not familiar with is like practicing the piano.
It doesn't go well right away.
But once you get used to it, you find that you start reacting before you even think about what's happening.
And that feels really great.
You might find it hard to believe, but in reality we've seen players using motion controls reach the top of the world rankings.
So ARMS is a game where you can aim for the top, even with motion controls.
Next up, let's talk about ARMS character designs.
You may be wondering why their arms are so long.
So next, let's talk a bit about ARMS character designs.
And I'm sure you're probably wondering, why did ARMS extend?
Well, let me explain.
Like Splatoon, we also considered a lot of characters that fit into this game.
Just like with Splatoon, we tried a lot of different characters to find ones that would fit this game.
The designs you see here are just a few examples.
We looked at more than a hundred different designs, but we didn't have a clear way to pick the right one.
Yoshi licks his tongue, Link fights with hook shots,
and so on.
We even had ideas for existing characters,
like Yoshi fighting with his tongue,
or Link fighting with hook shots.
We also tested various body and head-body balances on the screen.
We tried out characters with lots of different silhouettes
and head-body balances on the screen.
But what I was trying at this time was a character that only had a long fist.
When I threw a punch, the action seemed to be small.
The small movement on the screen was also affected by the point of view from behind.
At this time, only their fists extended out,
and when they would throw a punch, the action just felt too small.
The behind-the-back perspective was part of it,
but the movement on screen was just too slight.
So, we decided to just go for it and have the entire arm extend out from the shoulder.
This was the breakthrough we needed.
Flicking the Joy-Con made it feel as though your own arm was actually extending out far away from you.
So normally you might just use normal human characters in a game like this,
but since having the characters' arms themselves extend fit the gameplay so well,
we decided to design the character and world entirely around that,
which I feel like is a very Nintendo-like way of doing things.
So in other words, the answer to the question,
why do arms fighters have extendable arms, is because Nintendo.
And then, a fighter with the ability to stretch his arms, Spring Man, was born.
His hair is a bun and he has a spring-like hair clip.
So that's how Spring Man, a fighter with this extending arm ability, was born.
And that's even his real hair, as springy as the spring itself.
Boing!
We decided to consider other fighters as well, as long as they can stretch.
Usually, they're compact and extend very well when they get punched.
For the other characters, we set about exploring a motif of different extendable things.
Things that could stay compact, but then stretch and extend when punching.
The first thing that we thought of was a ribbon, and ribbons called to mind the glamour and grace of a pop star.
And that became Ribbon Girl, a fighter who can perform multiple air jumps.
And we decided to get an actual singer to actually be our voice actress.
Next, the chain. I think the chain and ninja are a great match.
You may be familiar with the shuriken,
but there's also a ninja weapon called the chain-bending sword.
The next idea was chains, and to us, chains paired perfectly with a ninja.
I'm sure you're all familiar with shuriken, that weapon,
but there's also a chain-based ninja weapon called the chain-bending sword as well.
Ninjara. He became a popular fighter in the world.
And this became Ninjara, a character we've noticed is very popular with boys.
By the way, Jara is the Japanese word for the sound of a chain.
And by the way, Jara is the sound that chains make in Japanese.
Next, Houtai. When you think of Houtai, you think of Mila.
But if you just think of Mila, I don't think it's unique.
Next was Bandages, and Bandages led us to mummies, but a basic mummy wouldn't be unique.
So we made him a buffed-up, powerful mummy.
We called him Master Mummy, and in Nintendo's entire history,
this is probably one of the most muscled-up characters we've ever had.
Weight fighters can bear down on an opponent, which can really make you feel powerful.
This picture is made by the development team.
So you might be wondering what's this picture about.
This is a bowl of ramen that someone on the dev team made.
日本人は本当にラーメンが大好きで、ごく自然にラーメンをモチーフにしたファイターの案も出てきました。
We love ramen in Japan, so naturally ideas for a ramen-based fighter also came up.
ラーメン屋の看板娘で、カンフーの達人。ここまでは普通ですけど、左腕に彼女の特徴があります。
She's the daughter of ramen makers and a kung fu master. All of that's normal stuff, but her left arm is something special.
Min Min, and when she charges up an attack, her left arm grows in size.
She's the only fighter with asymmetrical arms, so we struggled with what weapons we should
give her.
You might think of snakes as jungle, but we wanted to create an extreme sports atmosphere.
And the result was Kid Cobra.
It has a quick body and a thick arm like a daija.
His quick movements and thick, snake-like arms make him stand out.
We also had staff with some more outlandish suggestions,
like a girl genius obsessed with extendable arms,
but since she doesn't have extendable arms of her own,
she builds a robot suit that does.
A mechanica.
Her envious attitude towards the extendable arms ability
was also something that led to more hints about how this world might actually work.
Here's a jelly-like artificial life form.
It's called a helix.
It not only extends the arms, but also the body.
called Helix. Not only his arms, but his entire body can stretch and shrink.
Some of our more passionate players say he's very cute.
One idea was an actress who fights not with her arms, but with her hair.
Her hair whips around violently,
but with her actual arms she poses with grace and aplomb.
And that graceful concept developed into...
Twin tail.
Twin tail. Her dazzling aura captivates her opponents.
This fighter has received a lot of feedback from fans around the world.
Based on the reactions from fans all over the world,
she's made a big impact on players.
The more we developed the robot as a support item,
the more unique it became.
It became a fighter that fights with a dog.
This was a robot that we initially designed as a support item,
which gradually gained so much personality of its own,
it ended up being its own fighter, in combination with a robot dog.
This is Bite and Bark. Sometimes Bark the dog helps you, so you might be luckier than the other fighters.
As a result of pursuing the difference in the individuality of the fighters, we have a lot of colorful fighters.
By working hard to make sure that each fighter's unique characteristics stand out,
we ended up with a very colorful group of fighters.
Rather than having the fighting be a literal fight, we decided to frame it as a competitive sport.
The world's similar to Earth, but it's a world where this extendable arms ability has become commonplace.
The Arms Grand Prix that the fighters participate in is a sports festival like the World Cup of Soccer or the Grand Slam of Tennis.
The sound policy has also been consolidated.
The ARMS Grand Prix that the fighters take part in is a huge sport event.
This world's equivalent of the World Cup or Tennis Grand Slams.
And this also solidified our direction for sound.
Using a camera from behind means that we can make the stage 3D.
We've been making the 3D stage on the Mario Kart for a long time.
Using a behind-the-back camera also let us focus on fleshing out the stages in three dimensions.
3D stages are something we've been building all along in Mario Kart.
But of course, stages as complicated as Mario Kart tracks would get in the way of a serious fight,
so we tried to limit ourselves to just one or two 3D accents per stage.
Spring Stadium is surrounded by trampolines, for example, and you can do a bounce on them to do a big jump.
Here in the Ribbon Ring, cubes will rise up from the floor.
You can get on top of them or hide behind them while fighting.
For the DNA Lab, making use of these six pillars will be the key to victory.
While the pillars are still standing, arms that curve, like the boomerang, will be useful.
This is the Sky Arena. The platform in the center is patterned around a sumo wrestling ring, or dohyo.
If you fall off of it, you'll end up pushed up against the ropes in an instant.
And here's the Sparring Ring. This kind of a sparse stage with nothing in it is naturally favored by serious gamers.
We put a lot of effort and thought into the characters' clothes and their home stages
to really get across the idea that this is a competitive sport in the ARMS world.
We used the experience of creating a lot of custom-made logo and mark on Mario Kart 8.
When we were working on Mario Kart 8,
we made a lot of different fictitious logos and brand name marks,
and we used that experience here as well.
We also paid a lot of attention to detail in the fighters' athletic bodies.
That part is a little different from Mario Kart.
I think we were able to create a colorful, pop world
where the fighters are fighting with all their might.
They're colorful and poppy, but you can also feel how serious these characters are.
I feel like we've done a good job of expressing their world.
Let's take a break from game design.
Now let's take a little break from game design talk.
We've seen a lot of fan art featuring ARMS characters popping up.
As developers, this makes us really happy and also inspires us.
We're preparing a comic book that will help you enjoy the ARMS world even more.
On another side note, we're working on a comic that will help people understand and enjoy the ARMS world even more.
It will introduce a lot of things that we weren't able to talk about in the game,
like the fact that this Spring Man is actually the third Spring Man.
I hope you'll enjoy it.
Let's get back to Game Talk.
ARMS has been constantly updating.
We've been constantly checking to see how fun it is to play.
We've released a number of updates for ARMS since it came out,
and the entire time we've been working on the game,
we've constantly been checking to make sure it's the kind of fun, competitive game
people will want to play over and over.
We've been constantly checking to make sure it's the kind of fun, competitive game
I think a lot about the balance between technique and luck in competitive games.
As you know, Mario Kart is all about luck.
No matter how good your driving technique is,
you can get hit by a shell or slip on a banana and lose.
As you well know, in Mario Kart, the luck element of what item am I going to get is huge.
No matter how good your driving technique is,
sometimes you'll get hit by a shell or slip on a banana peel and end up losing.
But on the other hand, sometimes you get a mushroom and pull a victory out of the last second.
You don't know what's going to happen. It's like life.
On the other hand, we imagined that the arms would be like tennis.
We could predict whether the opponent would move to the left or to the right,
so luck was a factor.
For arms, we had a tennis-like balance in mind.
You throw your punches while trying to predict whether your opponent will move right or left,
so there's some amount of luck involved.
However, it is a game where players who are basically more skilled win.
In real tennis, there are few perfect games, but most of the time strong people win.
Arms is the same.
I think it's a game that has fair rules, is competitive, and is close to general sports.
That said, essentially the more skilled player is going to end up winning.
In tennis as well, you might not see a lot of perfect games,
but generally I think the stronger player wins.
ARMS is the same as that.
The rules are fair, there's a high level of competition,
so I think it's very close to a natural sport.
I'm like everyone else,
and I don't like games where one-pattern tactics are effective.
I've been adjusting the game balance
to create an environment where various characters and ARMS are used.
Much, I imagine, like you, I don't really like games
where only one type of strategy is effective.
We aim for an environment where lots of different characters
and arms would be used, and have adjusted the game balance
along the way accordingly.
Since the number of body pairs for arms and fighters
vary by a vast number,
the development process
included the AI- reinforcement data
as well as battle data
to help people relate to each other.
The possible combinations of fighters and arms amounts to a huge number.
So while we were in development, rather than relying on fight data solely from human opponents,
we referred to data from AI matches as well.
After release, we adjusted the data based on user play data.
This table shows the world's top 3% user win rate.
Post-release, we've been making adjustments based on play data from actual users.
This chart shows win percentages by character for the top 3% of players.
I don't know how to look at it, so let's focus on Master Mami.
Master Mami is not good at Ribbon Girl and Menmen,
but she has Ninja and Kid Cobra as her camo.
But if it's 5% win rate, it's within the scope of the game.
So it might be a little hard to read, so let's focus in on Master Mummy.
If you take a look, you can see that he fares poorly against Ribbon Girl and Min Min,
but he does well against Kid Cobra and Ninjara.
That said, I think a difference in win percentage of up to 5% or so is allowable.
We don't just look at the user's overall data,
but also the data for the top 3% and regional data,
and we cut and analyze the data from various perspectives to make adjustments.
When we're balancing, we don't just simply look at all the data at once.
We'll break it down and look at it from different perspectives,
like the top 3% of players or just from specific regions.
Of course, we don't just look at the data.
We also conduct online battles to check the environment.
We also refer to reports from the Sugode staff at Nintendo of America and Europe.
And we don't just look at data.
Our own development staff will participate in online matches
to check out how things are going.
And we'll also get reports from top players
on the Nintendo of America and Nintendo of Europe staff.
To show off our players' skills,
we held an event called Online Sparring in Japan.
We invited top players to the online lobby
and played a match.
So the players could display their talents,
in Japan we held an event called Online Open Sparring.
We invited high-ranked players to an online lobby
and broadcast their matches.
This was the first time Nintendo had held an online tournament like this.
The Mechanics won, and the Japanese players were surprised.
Even though she was considered low tier at the time,
Mechanic ended up winning, which surprised a lot of Japanese players.
In Japan, we held the Arms Japan Grand Prix.
We had a preliminary tournament in four regions,
and the final tournament was held at the end.
Later, we held an official tournament called the Arms Japan Grand Prix.
We held four regional prelims, followed by a championship tournament.
We'll show you a little bit of the footage before the tournament.
You can see that there are kids, women, and other age groups participating.
Let's take a look at some video from right before that championship tournament.
You'll be able to see children, female gamers,
gamers of all generations who came to play.
And there's some Japanese text which I'll translate as well.
It's time.
to find out who the best arms player is.
The championship. ♪♪♪
Thank you.
The main characters in competitive games are always the players themselves.
I feel that we are growing ARMS together with the players, not just the development team.
I am grateful from the bottom of my heart.
It really feels to me that it's not just the dev team,
but everyone playing the game as well,
that are helping to build up ARMS together.
I'm sincerely grateful.
In January's EVO Japan,
all the best 8 fighters were different.
The game balance has improved.
At EVO Japan back in January,
everyone in the best 8 used different fighters.
So I'm feeling good about the game balance.
Many other players from outside Japan also came to the event.
We saw a different strategy from the Japanese players,
and every match was a surprise.
We announced this at Nintendo Direct the other day,
but we are also planning to hold an online tournament in the US at the end of this month.
As you might have seen in the Nintendo Direct the other day,
we're also planning an online tournament in North America for the end of the month.
On the other hand, ARMS is not just a game for advanced players.
We've also prepared mini-games like basketball to knock your opponent into the ring.
But of course, ARMS isn't just a game for top-level players.
It also has mini-games like hoops,
where you try to knock your opponent through a basketball hoop, for example.
To allow players to enjoy the game for a long time,
we added a feature to collect badges and an event mode called Party Jack.
We also added a special secret fighter.
Features we added later, like collectible badges and the party crash events,
also give the game longevity for more casual play.
We also added in a mysterious challenger for players to battle against.
We aimed to further expand the game's potential
by using the data and voices of the players.
The main focus of the discussion was the fighters.
Based on user data and feedback from users themselves,
we've worked to broaden the game's appeal.
Naturally, a big part of that was adding new fighters.
We hope that not only the fighters' skills,
but the game itself will be played for a long time.
Going forward, hopefully it's not just the fighters' arms,
but the lifespan of the game itself that can extend as well.
Speaking Japanese
Games are a tool for creating communication and interactions between family and friends.
This is something that longtime Mario Kart developer Konno-san has said to me many times over the years,
and it's become my linchpin for making games.
But, when I think about it now,
I think it fits into all the Nintendo games made around me.
Of course, there are fighting games like Mario Kart and Splatoon,
but also things like Animal Crossing and Nintendogs are communication tools.
In the Legend of Zelda, everyone is actively communicating about the strategy, right?
I think that designing a game so that there is a lot of communication
is like Nintendo's DNA.
And come to think of it, I feel like it's true of all the other Nintendo games being made around me as well.
It applies to competitive games like Mario Kart and Splatoon for sure,
but Animal Crossing and Nintendogs create opportunities to communicate as well.
Even with The Legend of Zelda, players often end up talking to each other about how to progress in the game.
Designing games that naturally give rise to lots of communication is something like the DNA of Nintendo games.
ARMS is one of those games.
We aim to create games that create communication.
regardless of language, region, or age,
people from all over the world can play ARMS,
interact, and communicate with each other.
And ARMS is the same.
We wanted to make a game that would create opportunities
for communication and interaction.
Something where, regardless of language, country, or age,
you could compete against people all around the world,
watch their matches, and share stories with them.
And if it's been used like that, then we've succeeded.
I used my experience developing Mario Kart to make ARMS.
Even though the genres were different, it worked out.
Good game design can be applied in lots of different ways.
I used my experience developing Mario Kart to make ARMS.
Even though the genres were different, it worked out.
Good game design can be applied in lots of different ways.
I'm sure you'll be taking advantage of your experience and making new challenges.
I'm looking forward to the games you'll make.
I'm sure all of you are going to take your own past experiences
and apply them to new challenges going forward.
And I personally look forward to seeing the new games you make.
Thank you very much.