Okay, I think I'm gonna get started soon.
Hello everyone, I'm Steve Lee.
This talk is called An Approach to Holistic Level Design.
Before I get started, I'd like to remind everyone to turn off
your phones and make sure you fill in your review forms
after the talk.
Especially if you've stayed in from the last talk, I think
you need to leave the room and make sure you get scanned so
that you can receive the notification
to review the talk.
Finally, if we're looking fairly forward,
in general it's cool if you can sit closer to the middle,
so it's easier for people to sit down
if they enter during the talk.
And also, yeah, there's no filming allowed
after like the first five minutes of the talk,
I've been told.
Okay.
So a little bit about me.
I've been a level designer in the industry
for about 10 years now, shipping these four games.
The first one in the list is an open world
action driving game.
But since then I've kind of deliberately made moves
towards first person games and games
with an increasingly kind of holistic approach
to level design in terms of how I see it.
that satisfy a particular set of values.
Particularly the last two, Bioshock,
and especially Dishonored 2,
which are games that belong to this genre
known as immersive sims, which I'll touch on a lot.
I'll kind of discuss a lot of ideas
kind of connected to that genre.
So one thing to bear in mind is that while I hope the ideas I talk about in this
presentation are kind of relevant to many kinds of games,
I should say that these three games are three of my favorites of all time and
they kind of,
you know, this talk is very much informed by their sensibilities.
OK, so what do I mean by a holistic level design?
The dictionary says, it will talk about how holistic
thinking is generally about seeing everything, every part
of a design in terms of how it affects the whole and how the
whole can be much greater than the sum of its parts.
My favorite summary of this idea is a quote from this
great book called 101 Things I Learned at Architecture
School.
which isn't a level design book,
but I recommend it to all level designers.
It's got a lot of stuff that has very strong parallels
to the creative process and that kind of thing.
The quote is about the nature of beauty,
and it goes like this.
Beauty is due more to the harmonious relationships
among the elements of a composition
than to the elements themselves.
And needless to say,
I think this is often very true of level design.
So speaking of the elements of the composition,
these are the 3 elements I'm going to talk about in games,
which are, well, referred to,
which are presentation, gameplay, and story.
If you just kind of categorize all the different parts of games
into these 3 main pillars.
And note here that by presentation,
I generally mean all the kind of audio visual output of the game,
and so like graphics and sound,
and everything the player sees,
but also like text and stuff like that,
and I'll get into why later.
Now these big 3 elements are all very important in their own right, all deserving of talks
dedicated to each of them, but this talk is specifically about how everything works together.
So I'm going to focus on topics that emerge from the relationships between these things
instead of the things themselves.
So to explain what I mean by this, between these pillars of gameplay and presentation,
I'm going to talk about these concepts of affordances and intentionality.
Between the way we present things in story emerges this idea we refer to as world building.
And finally, between gameplay and story emerges this idea of interactive narrative and all that kind of thing.
So this is a talk to kind of highlight and summarize these things
and give a few tips on what we can do to apply them in our level design.
So first up, affordances and intentionality.
2 concepts which emerged from this relationship between gameplay and the way we present things.
I'm going to talk about affordances first and then use that to lead into the concept
of intentionality because they're very strongly connected.
So affordances is this term that is generally considered to come from the world of industrial
design.
A great book to read about this is this one, The Design of Everyday Things by Don Norman.
And the classic example of affordances in action
is the design of door handles.
So if you look at this photo, you can see two doors.
And the one on the left should be pushed.
The one on the right should be pulled.
And the problem here is that the handles for both of these doors
look the same.
And also, they both look like they should be pulled.
So you can imagine how people will approach the door
on the left and intuitively pull it instead of pushing it
and look like a bit of a fool.
So here we can say that the affordances of these door handles on the left are very poorly designed because they're misleading.
By contrast, here are some much better door handles where the push panel on the left clearly affords being pushed in a way that kind of contrasts with the one that should be pulled.
And indeed, in this case, the affordances
are so clear and strong that you could remove the text
from these door handles and use them in any country,
and people would just intuitively use them correctly.
And that's the kind of goal of affordances,
is that it's about communicating
how things work intuitively.
We can talk about this as form-conveying function
to use kind of industrial design lingo.
And designing a font as well is a crucial part
of designing anything that is used by people.
And of course, this includes games and level design.
So what kind of a fonts are we talking about
when it comes to level design?
This is a screenshot from an early mission in Dishonored 2,
Edge of the World. Not my mission, I'll talk about mine later.
In a fully realized, immersive 3D game like Dishonored,
the most obvious affordances in first-person level design,
in particular, are visual, and they're conveyed through things
like layouts and lighting and all this kind of stuff,
all relative to the player's view as they move through the environment.
So, you know, some of the main affordances we're talking about
are like the presentation of the player's navigation options
in relation to their goals and the obstacles.
And, you know, we design layouts partly to present options
to the player about where they can go and what they can do.
And in the case of Dishonored,
we deliberately add a lot of verticality
to allow the players to reach higher viewpoints,
which, you know, afford a much better view of the situation.
And finally within the layer we have like you know a bunch of
specific interactive objects that we had and that afford
particular gameplay opportunities.
And this can be both was that the play could pick up and throw
to distract gots on those that we and could sneak a place and
peek through the key holes and that kind of thing to spy on
people and in this screenshot we have a street speaker that's
hanging above the streets and that the play can shoot down to
distract. Gots and that kind of thing.
We also employ this rule that every wall of lights,
which is the obstacle in the far end of the screenshot,
every wall of light is connected by a cable to its power source,
and so it affords following that cable and using a panel,
reaching the power panel to disable the wall of light.
And I mentioned that every wall of light follows the rule
because it's important that these kind of low-level
gameplay affordances like this are all consistent.
For example, it's important that we're very clear about
all kind of low-level interactions,
like whether a door is interactive or not,
or whether this glass can be broken or not,
and that kind of thing.
And this screenshot here above is about how at Arkane,
it's forbidden to use the same meshes
for a non-interactive door as an interactive one.
Because we really want to make it clear
so that players don't just kind of only find out
that it's a non-interactive one when they've walked up to it
and when they're trying to use it.
So we tried to establish a very clear visual language,
like non-interactive doors being physically blocked by things
that are always used in this world, in this district.
And you know, and on a high level, the fiction of the world,
like Dunwall and Karnica,
there's a reason why there's always kind of disease
and stuff like that, because it justifies buildings
being abandoned and closed down
and kind of justifies these level design requirements
that we can't have every door be interactive, right.
So yeah, we try to establish a clear visual language
and then stick to it so players can learn consistently
about how things work and then act with that information.
And as well as those kind of low level of funds this there are lots of kind of
broader high level ones to consider to such as
community communicates the play how broad the possibility space and how much
agency they have.
You know this is no there's no use in kind of
designing a big complex level full of different stuff
if players don't realize that it's not a number there while the play.
So this is a screenshot of the dust district which is my mission into some
of 2.
And I worked on this with level architect Christophe Lefort.
We knew that the mission kind of fundamentally
revolved around two factions and a choice
about helping one over the other.
So one of the first things we talked about
was reflecting this in the layout at a high level
and presenting the two factions at a very clear junction.
And hopefully this kind of not only makes it very clear
that there's a big choice to make
and that it's a fundamental part of this mission,
but also we hope that it allows the players
to look at the layout from this perspective
and kind of visualize and intuitively understand
how different this mission can be based on their choice.
Another heavy lift when it came to high level of finances and
exposing the size of the possibility space and that kind of thing
I was the briefing with Megan the start of the mission and the task of
dates that come afterwards.
At the end of the day the Dust District is quite a busy mission with a lot of
stuff in it that we
could potentially talk to the player about and let them understand.
But in the end we were very deliberate about
which information we convey to the player and which stuff we kind of hint at in a vague way
and which information we just don't give the player at all.
So in one category, there's the crucial stuff about the mission that the player needs to know.
Like, there's two factions, this is the choice you can make,
and we want to be explicit about the fact that it will change the future of Karnica
and change the endings and that kind of thing.
And kind of the second category is stuff that we talk about in vague terms and hint at,
kind of, you know, such as the fact that you can find a solution to the Jindosh Lok,
which is the thing you need to open to progress to the next mission.
You can find a solution without helping the factions, in fact, if you find out how.
And we just tell the player that that solution exists,
but we don't tell them where it is or even what it is.
And we leave that to players who want to explore.
And finally, we have a bunch of stuff about the mission
which we deliberately don't talk to players about at all.
You know, things like the fact that you can find
Corvo's old home in this mission, and things like that.
But also, there's this huge thing,
which is that you can skip the entire mission
by solving the Jindosh lock on your own.
And it was important to us that we didn't tell the player about this at all.
We actually kind of iterated on the dialogue in the briefing
and, you know, kind of tuned the text and the task updates
to make it, well, sorry, the information for the objectives and stuff.
We deliberately tried to hype it up as something that is really,
like, nobody's done it, like, nobody in Kanaka has ever solved this puzzle
to kind of, you know, make it seem like this big thing
that is like this impossible obstacle, you know.
But then at the same time, we positioned it near the start of the mission so players would
find it on their own and discover it on their own.
So it was important to us that we just didn't talk to the player about this at all and let
them discover it on their own.
So if you're making non-linear levels, it's really worth thinking about how and how much
you choose to be explicit about the size and the content of the level's possibility space.
We want players to understand the situations they're in,
but without giving so much away that we spoil surprises.
And we don't want to spoil the genuine experience
of exploration and discovery.
Unfortunately, we've dishonored by making levels
that are very non-linear and very dense.
We're in a cool position where we can promise a lot to the player
by being explicit about the mission,
but then hopefully deliver even more
to kind of surpass people's expectations
that we've established.
One final thing I wanted to talk about in relation to affordances is this kind of running joke or recurring idea that players don't look up in level design.
And the thing is that while players...
looking up has become kind of slightly trickiest since the big
kind of make mainstream make it me to us consoles and controllers
and you know we kind of know that this isn't true in the case of certain games
for example in dishonored you know plays the couple the time because they're in a
stealth situation
and the very mobile and we teach players that being in high ground is very safe
and it's very useful for like
surveying this the situation and second of example players look up in Titanfall
especially multiplayer
because they're always looking for opportunities to run on walls,
they're getting sniped at from rooftops,
and of course there are like 50-foot robots blowing things up.
So you're going to look up all the time in that game.
And kind of on a more moment to moment basis,
you know, players look up when they go up a staircase.
They look up if they're in a small room,
but there are cables hanging from the ceiling.
A pipe above the player gushing water onto the floor
would make them look up.
Maybe if they were in a dark room
and the only light source is above them,
they would naturally look up at the light source.
So the lesson here is that when players aren't looking up,
The problem isn't like players,
the players or the human nature or anything like that.
It's actually like affordances that have kind of emerged
without us knowing perhaps.
You know, and if the players aren't looking up,
it's either like maybe we can redesign
the way we present the situation they're in
to kind of teach them to look up.
Or perhaps we're fighting kind of higher level affordances
where the game, maybe the rest of the game
has taught them that this isn't a game
where you need to look up.
And people are kind of like just running
with that higher level affordance
from the rest of the game.
And so the reason I talk about phone says is because of how
they relate to the subject of the talk with topic which is
player intentionality
and because the phone says a crucial to facilitate this idea of
play intentionality.
It's a quick set.
This idea of intentionality in games seems to have been coined around 1997, I
think, partly by Doug Church who did a talk.
and an essay on gamma sutra called
Formal Abstract Design Tools,
which you can still read online,
and a book by Janet Murray called
Hamlet on the Holodeck,
which kind of explored this in terms of narrative,
an interactive narrative.
So, there's lots of fancier definitions
that you can Google of this,
but my version is that acting of intentionality
is making conscious choices
with specific goals and expectations in mind.
And this might sound like super basic,
like something we can take for granted
that players are just naturally doing all the time
when you play a game,
but it's often kind of not the case
and often because of kind of maybe slightly wonky choices
in the level design and that kind of thing.
So here's some examples of weak intentionality
that we've kind of probably all experienced at some point.
You know, being lost and trying to find something to do
or trying to figure out what's going on is, of course,
not really acting with a strong sense of intentionality,
just kind of wandering around aimlessly.
And kind of a mod doing something without knowing why you're doing it,
but only because either the game's UI has told you to do it
or because it seems like the only thing you can do
or because you think it's what the designer wants you to do.
or you know that that thing where you find a lever in a game and you pull the
lever because it's a lever in a video game and you're always supposed to pull
leaves in video games.
That's not acting with intentionality, that's kind of lame, right.
And finally like twitch reacting to sudden surprises is not really
you know if a monster jumps out at you from behind a door you've just opened
it's more of an instinctive response and not an intentional kind of
you know choice, you know.
So that doesn't really count as
intentionality as far as we're concerned.
And the thing is that enabling player intentionality
is at the heart of all immersive sim gameplay,
and the way that systems and level design is approached.
To us, this is the whole point of presenting these gameplay
challenges and stuff to the player.
So this is why in Dishonored, all of the gameplay mechanics
and abilities revolving around this idea of giving the player
unique and combinable powers, like blinking and bend time
and all this stuff, that encourages players
to come up with their own ways of solving problems
and overcoming obstacles.
Going back to the screenshot of the Edge of the World mission
in Dishonored 2.
All of these affordances that we were talking about are trying to present the player
information about their situation so that they can
understand their options in relation to their goals and formulate a plan
and then act with intentionality.
This concept of intentionality is so important at Arkane
that as a level designer,
if you suggest a gameplay challenge or an optional puzzle
that seems like it's kind of lacking intentionality
at any point of the way, the idea will just be rejected.
Like it's just bad level design as far as we're concerned.
And wherever possible, we probably slip up sometimes,
but wherever possible, we always want the player
to be acting with intentionality by default.
So to break the concept down a little,
these are the four things that I think players need in order
to act with intentionality.
First of all is choice, the presentation of a choice.
Second is motivation, having goals in mind.
The third one is information that they
garner from clear and consistent affordances.
And finally, you need time to process that information.
You can't pressure the player too much
in order to distract them from the information
that they need to have.
And with those in mind, here are some ways
of facilitating intentionality.
First of all, it's the clear and consistent advances
that I've talked about.
Second of all, it really helps if you present the player
with higher level and longer term goals,
instead of kind of drip feeding them lower level tasks,
like look over here, and walk in that room,
and press this button.
It's way cooler to just give them
a higher level objective, which they
can find their own solution to.
And of course this is how Dishonored always works.
The textbook Dishonored mission is,
you're at this part of the map
and somewhere on the other side of the map
is some bad guy you've got to kill
and it's up to you how you do it.
And it's up to you to explore
and find your own journey towards that goal.
Finally, there's this idea of player-driven pacing and player-initiated action.
It's generally...
Again, it relates to the idea that players need time
to take in the information and formulate a plan.
It's just way cooler if you can find ways of giving the player space
to act intentionally.
And with this in mind we can consider a kind of a 4 step
cycle of a kind of a game play cycle.
I'm not sure who originally came up with this to be honest,
it's been mentioned in other talks at GDC
like by Clint Hawking, Nels Anderson, Forrest Darling
have all talked about this.
But yeah, it can be useful to consider this loop as something
that the player continuously goes through as they play.
So if we start at the top with observing,
the player is taking in information
about their situation.
And then they use that information and combine it
with their goals and their motivations to form a plan.
Then they execute the plan.
And then perhaps there's a fourth step
where they react, perhaps instinctively,
to maybe the plan not going to as they thought it would,
or reacting to some emergent situations that arise from it.
And then they go back to observing, of course.
And there's just this constant cycle
of taking in information, formulating plans,
and acting with those plans in mind.
And of course, stealth gameplay is particularly good
at emphasizing this loop.
It's built into stealth games that the player starts
in a hidden state, where they then have time
to think and explore and analyze the situation,
and then formulate an intention before they reveal themselves.
And they have to start thinking in a more dynamic way.
And as I said before, in Dishonored,
we use a combination of player mobility and verticality
in our layouts to empower the player to reach safer,
higher places that give them more time
and a better perspective for their observation and planning
phases.
But a crucial point here is that you don't need to be making
a stealth game to kind of facilitate intentionality.
This is a screenshot of Doom 2 on the left, which I love
dearly, and Doom 3, which I was a little bit less keen on.
And
Dooms 3, the thing was partly because of its move
towards a scary horror game kind of vibe.
It had a lot of monsters kind of popping out of nowhere
and trying to eat your face and that kind of thing.
And often it would like teleport monsters behind you
after like doing something arbitrary,
like picking up some ammo or pulling a lever
or something like that.
And this kind of works for the horror vibe
that it was going for.
But the kind of flip side to this
is that this reliance on frequent surprises.
where the player has no way of knowing what's going on
until it's in their face,
it has a side effect of killing a lot of the player's ability
to act with intentionality.
And it's kind of reduced to very short-term twitchy responses
to things that they didn't expect.
Now, Doom 2 generally had some of these surprises too.
Sometimes you would open a door and a pinkie's in your face,
and that kind of thing.
But as well, it also offered way more situations
where the player was in a much bigger area
where they had time to consider the situation
and always choose which weapon they wanted to use
against these set of monsters I've seen.
And also in the screenshot on the left, which is from a classic level called Barrels of Fun,
it would even use setups where enemies were facing away from the player.
So it was almost like they managed to find ways to almost implement a kind of stealth-like approach to the game,
where you can see the situation before anyone even knows you're there.
A final point about intentionality is that it affects
how players perceive linearity in level design.
Generally, I would say if linearity feels bad,
part of the reason at least is often
because the intentionality is kind of lacking or a little weak.
I mentioned earlier that Half-Life 2
is one of my favorite games of all time.
One of the things that people often praise it for
is this idea that it does a really good job
of feeling a lot less linear than it really is.
And I think there's a lot of reasons for this, you know,
an engaging story with well-written characters
helps a lot.
But yeah, like I say, intentionality I think explains
some of this as well.
The thing is here is that Valve have play-tested
their levels so much and iterated on their affordances
so much that in general, they've managed to align
what the player wants to do with the thing
that they have to do.
And so even though the game is linear,
it rarely feels like you're doing things
without knowing why, or just because the game told you to.
On a similar note, Portal is even more linear than Half-Life 2.
And yet, generally speaking, very few people complained about it being linear.
It's because even though there's usually only one solution to progress,
being a puzzle game and all, the player is given the time and the freedom
and just the right information to constantly experiment with the Portal gun
with intentionality in order to solve that solution.
One way of looking at it, it might sound kind of goofy,
but I was thinking about how the more linear your game is,
the more you can kind of say that your job as a level designer
kind of has parallels with what the guys do in Inception,
in the sense that you're trying to present,
kind of design and present situations in such a way
that players will naturally learn and want to do the thing
that you want them to do,
but they will feel that it was their idea all along.
And if you get this right, generally speaking,
linearity stops being a problem.
But if you get it wrong, you know, the players kind of jolted out of the experience,
they're kind of conscious of the artificiality of the experience and they'll reject it.
You know, they won't be as engaged as a result.
So the overall point here is that, you know,
whether your game is linear or non-linear,
intentionality is pretty crucial and fundamental to the gameplay experience.
I have a little note to myself about taking a sip of water here,
so that's what I'll do.
Okay, so number two of the three big topics,
which emerges from this relationship between the way we present things and the
story,
is this idea of world building.
I mentioned
earlier on games like Half-Life and Bioshock and Dishonored, you know,
these are all games that are praised for this very rich,
vivid sense of place and world building.
And to be honest, a lot of this is kind of art direction stuff and high-level
story stuff, which
especially if you're in a big company you won't really have a hand in.
you know, playing with yourself.
But I think there's still a lot you can contribute
on a lower level in order to kind of add
to the world building.
So with this in mind, I'm gonna present
these kind of three little goals for world building,
which is to create a world that feels unique,
cohesive, and meaningful.
And with those tips, sorry, with those goals in mind,
are a few tips.
So number one is that I suggest that world building
must always be specific.
I mean this both in terms of like being detailed
in the kind of ideas you're presenting
and not just being vague ideas of like it's the future
and there's war and corporations.
Like if that's all you present,
then you might be establishing a genre,
but you're not really building a specific world.
And the other thing is that, yeah, like I said,
the idea must be the more specific to your world
that this idea is, like this particular game's world
and not like all sci-fi games or all noir games or whatever,
you know, the more you're building a particular thing
because, you know, people can only judge your world
based on the things that are unique about it.
Those are the things that will stand out the most.
And, you know, one thing is here,
it doesn't necessarily mean that everything
has to be completely original.
Harvey Smith, our creative director on Dishonored 2,
he talked a lot about, in interviews and stuff,
about, well, he used Kieran Jindosh as an example
of how he's kind of quite a well-used archetype
in this kind of game. He's kind of a crazy,
evil, genius scientist guy.
But by layering details and specificity
on top of this archetype,
he turns the character from someone
who could feel like a bit of a cliche
into someone who feels unique enough
to contribute to this world and the world-building.
So to run through those examples, our crazy evil scientist guy
happens to look like this weird love child of Nikola Tesla and Prince.
He builds robots and gives them his own voice, which is a bit weird.
And when he's tasked with securing an important building,
he does it with this super obscure puzzle, the Jindosh Lock,
as a way of reveling in his own intellect.
And finally, he lost his finger and thumb in an industrial accident,
and he has this bionic thumb that he can smoke like a pipe.
And these details might seem kind of trivial on their own,
but altogether they add enough specificity to the character
to make him stop feeling like just kind of a trope
or whatever and becomes unique enough
to contribute to the world building.
With that kind of stuff in mind, I tried to populate the Dust District, which is my mission,
with scenes that help build the world and tell stories that feel specific to the Dishonored
Universe and also to this particular district, which has its own unique story.
So just to run through them quickly, on the left is a scene about the inside the Black
Market, which is kind of a...
you know, video game shop where you can go in and talk to someone and spend your money
on nice items and things.
But I didn't want it to just be a pure gameplay thing, so I added this scene where howlers,
who are like the crime mafia-like style faction.
they're harassing the shopkeeper for protection money,
and supposedly claiming that they're protecting them
from the overseers, who wouldn't agree with the fact
that they're selling magical stuff,
like bone charms and stuff in their shop.
The scene in the middle is this scene
where overseers are executing civilians
for breaking their religious principles
and doing things that are considered impure and forbidden,
again, which is this kind of,
an idea that is quite specific to their ideology,
and is kind of fleshing out them as a faction.
And on the right, there's a scene where,
inside the Overseer Outpost,
where an Overseer is mercy killing a friend,
another Overseer, after he was mortally wounded
in a fight with Howlers.
And through the way it's done,
and the way they talk about it,
I hope that it reflects a special kind of discipline
and conviction that characterizes
the way the Overseers think.
And so all of these scenes are supposed to kind of
convey information that is specific to these factions
in this district and this game.
So yeah, in general world building should be as specific as we can make it.
The point number 2 is that we should always be world building.
Try not to see it as something where
you kind of
off the critical path you have a small little room with some world building
stuff and then you go back to the gameplay where you're shooting monsters.
If you can
try and approach every idea in your level.
as an opportunity to build the world.
Every NPC you place or you can talk to,
every objective or side quest,
every kind of piece of loot that you place in a meaningful position
can develop the world in some way.
So try and look at all of these things as opportunities.
I've got a couple of small examples of this.
in the in the district this this building on the right on the right one
in the red.
I wish this is just like a facade like an empty building with no interior they
couldn't go into
and and at some point I I realize that it would be really useful to open
up the building so you can go in and you know so
to present the play with more navigation options on this area.
And we could have easily made this just like another generic
abandoned apartment.
But instead, through the way we did the set dressing
and appropriate placement of loot,
and by adding a note for the player to read,
we tried to tell a story about someone who used to live here,
but got kicked out by the overseers
when they were moving into the territory
and invading on the area.
So it's just a small example of how
something that could have been just this generic empty room,
we used even that to tell a story.
And similarly with a room inside the overseer outpost,
you know, I knew that from a gameplay
and exploration point of view,
I wanted a room with juicy loot to pick up.
And again, we tried to find a way that is specific
to kind of not only justify it in the world,
but to build the world of it.
So we made it into a room where the overseers
are confiscating things that kind of break
their religious principles,
and so we chose to add like bone charms
and stuff like that in there to support this idea.
And the third point is about world building,
particularly in this kind of game, maybe,
maybe not for all kinds of games,
but it's good if your world building
says things about the people in the world.
World building is a form of storytelling,
and stories are always about people.
In film, there's a great example of this
in Children of Men, which I really recommend
if you haven't seen it,
in which the world building is always about people,
and what would become of us in a world
where hope is kind of fading away.
In practically every shot of this movie, the background and the mise-en-scene and all that stuff is speaking to us about
how this loss of hope would change our society.
You know, it would change the role of police, people's political values,
like attitudes to immigrants and that kind of thing, and even our attitudes to suicide in this case.
In games, the classic example is Bioshock,
where every part of its world is trying to tell
and support this idea of how a society might crumble
if people were relentlessly pursuing progress
in this Randian objectivist kind of way.
One little thing I really like in the game Metro 2033,
which is this kind of post-apocalyptic game,
is this decision to show a child playing with a toy car
inside the player's hub area with an adult watching over him.
It feels quite memorable and appropriate and meaningful in the context of this particular game
because it symbolizes how people in this world aren't just killing the monsters because monsters are bad,
but they're trying to save the future and build a future for their children.
And it supports the game's kind of recurring ideas and themes.
that are reflected throughout the game and in its branching endings and stuff
about how survival in this world is about
more than just like fighting and defeating enemies, but it's
also about holding on to like
our wisdom and compassion and empathy during kind of dark times.
So it's a simple idea, but it resonates with the particular themes of this
particular game and world.
And for me, in the case of Dishonored, in my head it's...
The world is generally about power relationships and corruption.
And this idea that everyone, depending on their place in society,
is either screwing somebody else over or being screwed over by somebody else.
And of course, it's the lower-class citizens who get screwed the most.
So, for example, in the Dust District,
which is kind of like this lower-class area near a mining district,
We added this kind of wooden, weird wooden kind of raised street structure
that people have built in response to the dust storms and environmental problems
that have been caused by the Duke.
And so they've kind of been figuratively pushed underground
by the problems caused by the people in power.
But also, they're kind of trapped, literally,
in the middle of this ideological fight
between the two factions.
And this street is placed in the middle of the map
in between those two HQs.
And so it's supposed to be something that,
you know, more than just looking cool,
it's meant to be a symbol of, you know,
something that is unique to the story of this district
and its people, and support the broader themes
and the tone of the Dishonored universe in general.
This idea that people are being victims
of the people above them, essentially.
So yeah, to summarize, three points.
Point number one was world building must be specific.
Point number two was always be world building
and don't just see it as a kind of extra thing.
And point number three was the importance
of saying things about people in your world
or relating to human ideas in general.
And the third part is, how am I doing with time?
Oh, not so bad.
But the third part is interactive narrative,
this idea that emerges from the relationship between.
into interactivity and story.
So one little disclaimer here is that this is a huge topic
that I should not be trying to tackle in 15 minutes,
but I'm gonna try and hone in on one or two particular ways
of approaching this topic that kind of resonate
with me personally and that I kind of think are a big deal.
I realized that everything, or most of the stuff I wanted to say related to this idea
of show and tell.
And specifically the fact that in the context of interactive narrative in particular, I
don't think this is a really good phrase for us to use as a guiding principle, and I think
we should be careful about it.
It's useful for a lot of aspects of level design,
like the world building stuff,
in the sense that it encourages people to think
about communicating stuff visually
and in the world in front of the player, which is cool.
And not just using cut scenes
and big blocks of text and stuff like that.
But my argument would be that specifically
in terms of like interactive narrative,
only showing and telling things is just not the full thing.
We need to do more than that.
And the reason why this phrase is kind of problematic
is because we've lifted it from passive mediums
like films and novels,
and which don't need to worry about interactivity at all.
So with that said, I think we can get somewhere
that's more useful to us if we look at
what this phrase means to those mediums
rather than focusing on the phrase itself.
So to explain what I mean by this,
in film, show, don't tell is generally about this idea
of telling the story using the unique strength of the medium.
which in the case of film is moving pictures and editing between them
in a way that creates drama and evokes ideas.
In literature, by contrast,
Show, Don't Tell is about the idea of writing in a way that evokes ideas and drama
in the reader's mind and imagination.
So instead of simply telling the reader things like,
John was very sad when he said goodbye,
or old abandoned playground had a really creepy atmosphere,
we need to write in a way that evokes these ideas
instead of just throws them in the reader's face.
So if we take those two key parts of those kind of ideas,
we have using the unique strength of the medium
and evoking drama and ideas in the audience's mind.
And personally, I think pretty much every game that is kind of
interesting from an interactive narrative point of view
does at least one of these things well.
Some games kind of naturally lean towards one or the other,
but yeah, it does one of them, I find.
And so first of all, a couple of, a few examples of using the unique strength of the medium.
To me, like, the idea of...
Well, of course, in interactive media,
interactivity is the unique strength of the medium.
And combining interactivity with narrative
naturally leads us towards this idea of empowering the player
to act with what I'll call narrative intentionality.
I talked about intentionality earlier,
but mostly in terms of gameplay and gameplay goals.
But here we're talking about the idea of giving the player
the information and the time and the opportunity
to make intentional choices, but with narrative goals in mind
and not just gameplay ones.
I also mentioned how Dishonored and Immersive Sims revolve
around intentionality.
And this kind of goes for narrative intentionality, too.
And this is on its case, especially like I'm so
and it's on his case narrative intentionality is kind of go
into the game the systems level in the sense that every NPC
in the game can be you know you can even sneak around them
or you can deal with them on leafly
or you can know them horribly of course
and we tell the players that this will change the story
in the world and certain scenes in the game
and the endings and the kind of thing.
And so what this does is it transforms
like a simple, what would be a simple gameplay choice
into an opportunity to act
and express narrative intentionality
every time you encounter an NPC.
That's the kind of thing we're into.
Going back to the Dust District,
one of the main things that appealed to me
about this particular mission
when I was kind of given the mission to work on
is that its premise revolves around this idea
of choosing a faction and making a choice
that will affect the endings of the game.
So the mission, the unique thing about the mission
is this act of narrative intentionality
kind of built into the whole premise of the mission.
And with that kind of thing in mind,
I mentioned in the world building section,
these three scenes that I tried to develop
the world with in some way.
But another kind of aspect of it is that
I deliberately designed them to kind of encourage
the player to act with narrative intentionality.
So two things about these scenes is that first of all,
they're not just scenes that you watch.
I'm not just showing and telling a story here.
These scenes are deliberately designed to be interrupted
and interacted with,
and they all have extra lines and scripting and stuff
beyond the main scene in order to react to certain choices
that the player can make.
And secondly, these scenes are there
to present interesting dramatic situations
which invite the player to interact
with narrative goals and values in mind
and not just gameplay ones.
you know, as far as I'm concerned,
whenever I can make a player make gameplay choices
that they're moving through a level
with narrative goals in mind and not gameplay ones,
it's kind of more interesting and, you know,
cooler and more immersive and that kind of thing.
And so, you know, any opportunity I can do,
take to do that, I kind of try and take it.
So that was about using the unique strength of the medium,
which is agency and how that leads to narrative intentionality.
If we take a look at the literature's take on this phrase,
we have this idea of evoking drama and ideas in the audience's mind.
And...
Yeah, I've got an example of this.
I've got three examples of this.
The first one is a kind of low-level, in-the-moment kind of thing.
It's a bit of a pet peeve of mine.
When...
like basically when something very dramatic and perilous is happening to
the player character, but in the game it's presented as a cut scene, so
control is taken away from the player just before it happens and so
while the character is thinking, oh my god, I'm in peril, the player is thinking,
oh, it's a cut scene, I can relax, I don't have to do anything and it's the
complete opposite of what the character is supposed to be thinking. So it's just
like, you know, I'm a big bit sensitive to this, it always drives me mad.
By contrast, this scene from Uncharted 2,
where you're navigating this collapsing building
when the helicopter's blowing it up,
is kind of a crazy, extreme, expensive example.
It's amazing.
But the cool thing here is that Nathan Drake
is kind of cropping his pants and thinking,
oh my God, what am I going to do?
And the player is hopefully figuratively cropping their pants
and thinking, oh my God, what am I going to do?
And so they've perfectly spent a lot of money and time
to align the player's thoughts with the character's thoughts
in this dramatic situation.
You know, it reminds me of this phrase by,
quote from Frank Capra, who's like a filmmaker from the 30s,
I think, who talked about how he made mistakes in drama.
I thought drama was when actors cried,
but drama is when the audience cries.
And of course, we can take that idea and apply it to games,
because we want the player's experience
to be these dramatic highs and lows,
and not just something they see on the screen.
And my second example of evoking ideas is this
classic pick up the can scene from Half-Life 2.
For anyone who hasn't played it, well, first of all,
shame on you, you should really play Half-Life 2.
It's really good.
But secondly, it's basically a tutorial for the player
for picking up and interacting with physics objects.
But what's cool is that the level designer
used it as an opportunity to allow players
to act with a narrative intentionality.
you know between the when you pick up the can the game tells you that you can
even put it in the in the trash can I can throw it at the combine guys head.
And this choice between obeying and rebelling is a narrative thing
that the player is going to consider when they go through this tutorial.
But an extra cool thing about this is that these two particular choices,
this idea of obeying and rebelling,
basically sum up the human condition of people in the world of City 17.
Every citizen here is struggling with this choice
of whether or not they should obey and conform or resist and rebel.
And so by being oppressed by the Combine directly
and making this choice yourselves,
the player relates to their plight, essentially,
and relates to them as people.
And so when you come up to this scene later in the game,
you don't just shoot the baddies
because they're baddies in a video game,
but you naturally side with the civilians
because you relate to them,
and you're naturally opposed to the Combine
based on a personal, interactive experience that came before.
So even though Half-Life 2's story and gameplay is pretty linear and stuff,
to me it still qualifies as solid, immersive, interactive storytelling
because it's very smart about emotionally involving the player
in the ideas and themes of the story.
My final example is,
it might be a surprise to immersive sim people
because generally immersive sim people aren't so keen on this game,
but I think this particular scene is amazing.
So near the start of the game,
It's establishing you as the main character, this father,
in a game about losing your child and desperately wanting to save them,
and doing anything to save them.
And you're out in the garden, play-fighting in this very melodramatic,
Star Wars kind of way,
and as with a lot of Heavy Rain, it's a sequence of quick-time events,
where you have a prompt to press the button on screen,
And based on whether or not you succeed or fail at this,
the game shows you a different animation, essentially.
Now, the interesting thing here is that.
if we follow our kind of gamer instincts
to just try and win the sequence,
we end up being a super douchey dad in the process.
And this scene, like I've watched a lot of play-throughs
of this on YouTube and stuff,
and it's really good at making players realize this
as they play and change the way they play
based on this kind of narrative desire
to play the role of a good dad.
And so it's cool because it's like, you know, the subject of this scene is quite grand in the sense that it's,
you know, it kind of reflects the fundamental nature of becoming a parent in the sense that
when you have a kid, you know, it's like, it changes your life in a way that means that
succeeding in your own kind of selfish terms is no longer the priority.
And that's what this whole scene is about, it conveys interactively.
So yeah, it's a great example of how we can take even
something that seems kind of basic and binary
and typically trivial as pressing a button in time,
but use it to kind of interactively evoke
some fairly big ideas about the story
and about life in general even.
And all of this is inside the player's mind
without explicitly telling them anything, which is awesome.
So to summarize, yeah, these are my three points
about interactive narrative.
Number one was striving to do more than just show and tell
wherever possible.
Number two was empowering the player
to act with narrative intentionality.
And or, depending on your kind of game,
you can try and think of ways to evoke drama and story
and ideas in the player's mind and not just on screen.
And so we've got a couple of minutes.
So yeah, to wrap up.
As a closing thought, I thought about this particular section of a book called
Understanding Comics by Scott McCloud, which is a super smart book that I
recommend to everyone.
It's kind of written to educate people and change people's perspective on
comics, but I think it has the effect of doing this, changing the way we look at
pretty much every medium.
And I really recommend it to everyone if you like this kind of thing.
And don't worry about reading the text on the panels here,
but in this section of the book,
he talks about how comics used to,
and perhaps still do, suffer from people assuming
that because comics are a medium made of pictures and words,
that you can just take a great artist and a great writer
and kind of just throw them together
and you've got a great comic.
And of course, in reality, if you just put nice words on nice pictures,
you only end up with something that's pretty like a shallow form of a comic
that doesn't really utilize the true magic of the medium.
And the experience of reading a great comic
doesn't just come from the combination of these two things,
but it's completely defined by this art form's particular set
of special relationships between words and pictures.
And of course, the whole point of this talk
is to talk about how level design is kind of the same thing,
or at least it's one way of looking at it.
I think we've all played games before
where these three elements, the gameplay and the story
and the graphics and the world or whatever,
they're all good individually,
but they don't seem to kind of gel so well.
They're not really working together.
And to me, when games and level design are at their peak,
it's all about how these things work together.
For those familiar with the genre
known as the Massive Sims that I talked about.
To me this approach and this set of ideas says a lot about,
to me explains a lot about what the immersive part of immersive sim really means.
To me these ideas aren't just extra nice little things to sprinkle on top of your gameplay and stuff
to add flavor to the player experience.
I'd go as far as saying that these kind of games,
with these kind of games and the kind of games
I'd like to see more of,
these things are the player experience.
You know, these three ideas
are what the player is thinking about all the time.
You know, so I would argue that the individual pillars of gameplay and graphics and story and all this stuff,
they're kind of just means to these ends, I would say.
Now, to be honest, I'm not really sure that everybody will agree with that, but I would hope that,
you know, if I can encourage anyone to take this kind of perspective of level design, I think it would be a cool thing.
And finally, on top of that, as level designers,
when we work with other disciplines,
you know, like artists and writers
and creative directors and stuff,
I think the more we can discuss
and establish these kinds of ideas
as shared goals between departments,
the better and more interesting
and the cooler our games will be.
And that's it.
Thanks for listening.
I hope it was interesting.