Hi everyone, welcome to The Secret Lives of NPCs.
My name is Georgia Simmons.
And I'm Jason Becker.
And we are the narrative co-directors of Ghost Pattern, which is a studio that's based in
Narm or Melbourne in Australia.
So to start, Wayward Strand was made on the lands of the Wurundjeri and Bunurong people of the Kulin Nation, and is set on Bunurong country, and we pay our respects to Wurundjeri and Bunurong elders past and present.
We also wanted to acknowledge that we're all meeting on the unceded lands of the
Ramaytush Ohlone people, and to pay our respects to the ancestors, elders, and relatives of the
Ramaytush community, we encourage you to visit that link, ramaytush.org, where you can find out
more about the community, as well as donate, and also to form relationships with First Nation
groups in your own communities as part of your game development process.
Our talk today focuses on our studio's debut title, Wayward Strand, which we'll tell you
a bit more about in a minute.
In particular, we'll be telling you about the process of developing our game's unique
real-time narrative structure.
In Wayward Strand, no matter where the player is, all NPCs are carrying out their own narratives
in their own time.
This abundance of characters and stories creates a rich world for the players to explore.
Yeah, um...
We hear over and over again from players that Wayward Strand feels transportative.
It doesn't feel like you're playing through a narrative.
It feels like you've been dropped into an alternative world.
We think a big part of that is how we designed and developed our NPCs, their relationships,
and each of their journeys through the game.
And that's why we wanted to talk about our process with that.
We'll begin by giving you a bit more context about the game itself, as well as the team who made it.
We'll talk about the values of our studio and how they shaped the game.
We'll talk a bit about the consultation we did to flesh out our characters.
Then we'll get into some technical and design details of the tools we used for plotting the simultaneous stories of the game.
In talking through that process, we'll explore a few snags we came across in terms of finding
narrative interest in the game.
We'll then talk about how we brought the narrative to life through the realization and
implementation of all aspects of the game.
And because this is an industry event and some of you are probably on the company dime,
we'll make sure we finish with some lessons that we learned along the way that we hope will be
useful for you as well.
So that's what to expect in what order, and it all looks very ordered and laid out, perhaps
a little too much so.
So we wanted to show you this.
Some of you may recognize this, it's a page from the book We're Going on a Bear Hunt by
Michael Rosen.
Now bears are living creatures and they should never be hunted, so just ignore the right-hand
side, focus on the left-hand side.
It says, we can't go over it, we can't go under it, oh no, we have to go through it.
If it seems like we know anything about developing a real-time narrative game now, just rest
assured that we didn't used to.
We used to know nothing.
This is a really challenging game to make.
We couldn't go over it.
There were no other games that were like it enough that we could just re-skin.
We couldn't go under it.
It's just not the kind of game that you can shortcut in any way.
We had to go through it to make this game.
We had to look way outside of games for inspiration.
We had to look to music and literature and who we were as people and our nation's history.
We had to write our dialogue like it was an immersive theater show and then record it
like it was a film.
And this meant that all the processes we'll talk about today were sort of
MacGyvered together with string and tape and optimism.
But the only way that we were able to do this was by going through it.
And we encourage you to do the same.
If you've got a narrative game idea and you're at the start of your dev journey,
don't wait until you know how to do it.
Just go through it.
Okay.
Here is the trailer for the game in question.
So you're excited after all?
As if.
Oh, well, my mistake.
Now, your job is to go to each of the patient's rooms and spend some time with them.
Got that?
Yep.
The name's Esther.
What's yours?
Um, Casey.
Very original.
Now, if you'll excuse me, I've got to go solve a mystery about a goat.
Uh, is this you?
Oh yes, that's me.
And the family.
Would you like some company?
Of course.
Be warned, I am writing up a storm at the moment.
You weren't in the wall?
We escaped. Anna and myself.
I'm doing work experience.
Deadly. Well, working up here is an experience, alright.
Now, as you know, my room happens to be beside the nurses' station.
You were listening in on them. Got the picture?
We are to have.
Something's fishy, if you ask me.
I exhort you all to follow her every command as we prepare for tomorrow.
You both know the drill here. Regardless of what's going on...
Patience first.
Doctor Bouchard?
What are you here for?
Time to turn me sunny side up?
You think I'm trying to kill you?
You've been picking foxglove and slipping it down the dumbwaiter.
Death by a thousand slurps.
Director.
Mr. Pettigrew?
I have seen that you talk.
I will speak with him about your case.
How are you finding your time on the ship?
I hear people talk about things, but I'm not sure what they're on about.
That sounds a bit like the life of an older person.
Nobody explains to us what's going on.
We just have to piece it together as best we can.
Wow, you all are so nice, thank you.
So Wayward Strand is, as I said, our debut title.
It's a narrative game set in regional Australia in 1978.
And you play, as you saw, as Casey, who's a 14-year-old girl
whose mother is the head nurse of a hospital,
which just happens to be on an airship that's suspended in the clouds
above your small regional town.
It's the summer holidays, and your mum can't find anyone
to look after you for a couple of days,
so you go with her up to the hospital.
And she gives you the job of spending time with the patients in the aged care ward, keeping
them company and helping them out with anything that they need.
So that's the setup for our real-time narrative game.
Three days as a teenager, talking to the residents of this floating hospital, getting to know
them, getting a brief glimpse into their lives.
The game's about a four-hour round trip and is fully voiced by a cast of 15 superb actors.
Many people contributed to the making of this game and we always like to highlight this.
We find that the best ideas are found in the space between us.
And as you'll hear throughout the talk, Jason and I are definitely not the authors of this game,
especially not when it comes to the details of the stories.
We're just the people who happen to write it down.
Of the 33 fine people you saw on the slide before,
the ones on screen now formed the core team.
So these are the people who were along for long sections of the development journey
or who directed significant parts of its development.
As you may have noticed on the other slide, our team does come from outside of games.
That's both in terms of who we are as non-binary people, women, people of color, neurodiverse
people, new parents, people from working class backgrounds, and it's also in terms of our
professional backgrounds.
Some of us have come to video games from theater, or music, or comics, or VTubing.
And what this means is that...
Although we all love to play video games, we know that video games are not made by us, about us, or for us all that often.
When people like us appear in games, it's often as NPCs.
With a few repeating lines of dialogue, a quest to give, and maybe a crush on the player character.
And this has a deep and conscious impact on the kinds of games that we feel compelled to make.
Wayward Strand is a game that strips back player agency and gives space and power to the NPCs.
The gameplay is geared towards listening and caring for them, rather than enacting your own
desires upon them. And this is deeply informed by who we are as a team and our lived experience.
So that's the team.
And this is us, the narrative team.
So my focus was squarely on narrative, including, uh, voiceover,
direction and casting.
And Jason does everything.
Except art.
So Jason comes from a lot of programming experience, but before this game had only ever really
dabbled in writing.
I come from a lot of writing experience, particularly in the theater, but had not even really dabbled
in video games.
I mean, I played Portal 2 on my MacBook with my trackpad, but nothing that could be considered
actually making a digital game.
Jason and I found very quickly, though, that we were a really good team.
The disparity of our professional backgrounds meant that we brought different strengths
to the team.
But we're also really deeply curious about each other's work, so we were able and open
to learn from each other throughout the process.
It's also worth saying that Russell, who was on that slide, who mainly worked on programming
throughout the game, was deeply involved in the ideation of the game.
So a lot of the character ideas and broad brush strokes, plots, come from him as well
as from Jason.
So our initial inspirations for Wayward Strand came from our personal relationships with
older people in our lives, stories that they've told or experiences that we shared with them.
And we thought that older people's lives were really interesting to explore and have players
think about, and to have represented within media, like outside of the cookie cutaway
that a lot of old people are represented as mentors or sources of knowledge.
Yeah, people that give you a sword or whatever.
Instead, we wanted to present them with full lives
in the present moment.
Yeah, so Wayward Strand takes place
across three in-game days,
and all characters more or less live out those three days
within view of the player.
This allowed us to tell stories
where the rhythms of daily life
are a critical element of the stories.
Unlike other media where a character has to have a cinematic moment of realization or
a moment of conflict that drives the story forward, we could represent how stories and
events take place more in real life.
So messily, fits and starts, woven amongst other things that are happening in your life
with important things sometimes taking place outside of the exciting cinematic moments.
Like a kind of funny example of this is for a long time,
we were aiming to get like toilets into the game
and have each of the characters schedules,
like bathroom schedule, interact with each of their stories.
So maybe a character misses hearing a critical thing
because they went to the toilet
or maybe somebody excuses yourself
when you're spending time with them
just because nature called.
But they could do that
without any big narrative consequence sometimes.
So it's a way to.
bring in the feel of like reality that's quite unique to this real time storytelling format.
Because if somebody is on the toilet in a movie, that's because maybe it's a comedy
or maybe they're about to be strangled by James Bond.
Shout out to objectively the best Bond movie, GoldenEye.
But yeah, exactly.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
But you're not going to have a heartfelt moment with a character happen just after they've
gone to the bathroom in a movie for no reason.
But we do have those heartfelt post-bathroom moments in real life.
And that just never gets reflected in media because you have this limited linear plane
on which to work and the juxtaposition.
It just has a different meaning when it's been placed there for you by a director or
a creator in a deliberate way as opposed to in this kind of semi-dynamic way that we have
where if that happened, it would just happen within the game.
It's not necessarily part of our plan.
So I'll talk a little now about our process of consultation for fleshing out our characters.
Our game has characters with a really broad range of lived experience.
So we have many aged characters, of course, many of whom are experiencing chronic illness,
as well as queer characters, a First Nations character, healthcare workers.
And given that the point of our game, as we've been mentioning, was to show the richness
of these characters' lives, it was important to us that we engage in consultation right
from the start, and that we honored these relationships through to the end of our development
journey.
One of the first teams that we started working with on consultation was the Bonorong Land Council.
And I'm going to focus on this consultation as a bit of a case study for how we engage in consultation.
This was a really special relationship that we maintained throughout the entire lifecycle of the development of the game.
The Bunurong Land Council, just for some context, is the traditional owner group representing
the First Peoples of the area of regional Victoria where Wayward Strand is set.
As soon as we agreed to make this game together, we got in touch with the Bunurong Land Council
and we went and had a first meeting with them.
We opened up questions about locations where the game could be set.
Any landmarks with cultural significance that we should be aware of, as well as what kinds
of Aboriginal characters we might be able to represent in the game.
And it was these early conversations that fueled the development of the character of
Ted, who you can see on screen, who is the much beloved teen cable car operator with
a secret ambition to write comic books.
From there we ended up consulting with a number of people from the Land Council in an ongoing
way, including Bunurong Elders.
And the bullet points that you see on screen are just some of the principles of how we
engaged in that consultation.
So the fact that we engaged from the start ensured that we never included anything in
the game without first knowing that it would be appropriate to do so.
This ongoing engagement also meant that our collaborators at the Land Council weren't
just correcting our ideas, but also conceiving of their own ideas and contributing to the
creative development of the game.
And they had real agency in terms of determining how their culture would be displayed on screen
and communicated to an audience.
There also never came a point where we ended that relationship or sort of said that we'd
kind of done enough consultation.
All the way through to voiceover casting and direction, we had input from the land council
about what that character should sound like.
And we ended up being fortunate enough to cast.
Shane Clayton, who's the son of a really well-respected Bunurong elder, and Shane himself was also
able to bring that fantastic cultural knowledge into the room.
And the last point on the slide says listening before Agenda.
It would be great to be able to say listening without Agenda, but in doing consultation
it's great to sort of be honest with your scope and there would be no point us pretending
that we weren't trying to develop a video game.
But whatever vision that we had for how it would turn out, that was always secondary
to our listening and our relationship and to hearing what the Boon Wurrung Land Council
and their various elders and representatives were saying to us and honoring that before,
honoring what we thought it should be like.
Yeah, the fact that we could be so responsive to the consultation over the course of development
does feel like an advantage of this unique storytelling structure, which we'll get into
the structure a bit more soon.
We weren't relying on certain interactions between characters as pillars of a single linear storyline,
and that meant that, you know, if we were making changes to particular bits of the game,
we could do them without, yeah, kind of taking some critical bit of the arc of the game and
then like knocking out that pillar or whatever.
We still had to consider knock-on effects of every change because every change would
have this ripple out to all the other storylines and characters and so forth.
But yeah, nothing was load-bearing in that way.
So these are some of the other people that we consulted with throughout the game.
Dementia Australia, the CEO, Kate Swoffer, lives with dementia herself and she was a
fantastic consultant on the game.
We also have Goldie, our art director's mum, happened to be a nurse in hospitals in the
70s, so she was a really great source of knowledge in terms of what that experience was like.
And we have a lot of team members as well who had lived experience that fed into the game,
whether that was about being raised by a single mum, or about their lived experience of gender,
or racialized identity, or class, or chronic illness. And of course, our wonderful actors
also brought so much authenticity to their characters, and we were able to keep making
some critical script changes through the recording process. A bit of a funny story about this is,
I don't know if we have any German speakers in the room,
But we have our character, Mr. Pruess, who you would have seen in the slides.
And at some point, really early on in the development, his story is that he had this wife who he was so devoted to,
and she's sadly passed away now, but he remembers her a lot.
And her name used to be... Alter?
And then I can see we've got a German speaker over here giving me the look I was expecting.
We got into recording with our actor who we were recording remotely from Austria.
And he came to that part in the script and he said,
Alter, this is, you know, why is he saying this about his beloved wife?
And we were like, oh, that's her name.
And he was like,
No. So, um, you might be able to verify for me, our actor told us that the meaning of this word, which we thought was just a name is like, it's kind of like calling your wife, like the old ball and chain or like, you know, the old bag or something.
It's like a really disrespectful, like thing to say about your wife.
So luckily we picked that up with him in the recording studio and we were able to change her name to Anna.
It's a much more standard Austrian or German name.
That was probably the most egregious mistake that we had, but our actors brought a lot
of other cultural knowledge or knowledge from their own lived experience to those characters.
So, in terms of the simultaneous stories that we told throughout the game, in many other
games your NPCs might have a few looped animations to make them look like they're doing stuff,
but they are ultimately kind of existing to wait for you.
So we asked ourselves the question, what would the player experience be like in a game where
no one waits for you, you have to keep up with them and listen to them and play in service
of them?
And this idea was largely inspired by immersive theatre.
And my background, as I mentioned, is in theatre, which is why I was asked to join the team,
to bring that knowledge to bear on the game.
So we needed to create stories, enough of them with enough detail,
that would populate a fully realized world,
characterized by overlapping dialogue and confluences of action.
And this is the question that we started with and that we still often get asked about the
game.
How do we guarantee a satisfying narrative journey if we can't guarantee the narrative
itself?
The first thing to say about this question is that satisfaction is a rather limiting
goal in terms of what we want our player to experience.
Our game's about a teenage girl.
She's on her summer holidays and her mum has dragged her along to spend time in an aged
care ward with a bunch of old people.
So satisfaction is not necessarily what she would be experiencing.
And so as nerve wracking as it was, we wanted to create an experience that left
room for boredom or frustration, or maybe even anger.
And this was reflected back to us in a lot of the reviews we got.
Many reviews contained a similar version of this sentiment, but Emily Spindler
from Games Hub captured it in a really great way, which we were really thrilled
to see when she said.
This. There were some small moments where I was unsure of what to do.
And while this did leave me wandering the halls aimlessly for a brief time,
it ultimately felt like this added to the overall feeling that you really are Casey,
wanting to help, but unsure how. And that's the exact feeling that we were trying to create, is like
We don't necessarily need for this to be this action-packed, rising action kind of experience.
We wanted the player to have moments of really deep, heartfelt connection, but then also moments
of boredom, or moments of not knowing what to do, or moments of trying to figure out how to be helpful.
I also want to talk about the narrative shape of the game.
So this is a page from Matthew Frederick's surprisingly insightful coffee table book
101 Things I Learned in Architecture School.
And this page that you see here reflects how in architecture, the organizing principle
for a building can be expressed in a simple geometric diagram.
In many creative writing courses, some of which some of you may have attended, it's
taught that there is exactly one story shape.
This tedious, ugly, boring, vaguely phallic, time-tested and data-backed hump, Freytag's
Pyramid.
The action rises, there's exactly one climax, sound familiar, and then everything is wrapped
up in a neat little bow.
I hope that in the year of our lord 2023 it's uncontroversial to say that this is like...
Kind of played out and tired and it works in the same way that a Honda works, i.e. just fine.
Do we want to make things that are just fine? What about this? See, now it's a star and that's
more fun. Let's make something fun. I really think that Wayward Strand's organizing principle,
if it was anything, would be this hairstyle. So Wayward Strand takes place over three days
and at the start and end of each day, you have a conversation with your mom, Ruth, who's the
head nurse.
So the shape of Wayward Strand is all of these strands that are running parallel, and just
like a little louse, you can jump from strand to strand, but then there are these gather
points, and we use these conversations with Ruth to gather the strands together and make
sense of those strands for the player.
Ultimately, though, there are infinite shapes that your story in your game can and should
take.
And it's so fun and freeing and a bit freaky to consider all the myriad ways you can break
away from silly little 19th century pyramids like this loser who tried to convince you
that they've been around since the time of the pharaohs.
Anyway, rant over.
We're now going to take you on a deep dive of our process of structuring and plotting
the game and bringing all those values and theories and principles that we've been speaking
about so far to life.
So if you unbraid that ponytail from before and stick all the strands of hair up on your wall,
I'm starting to regret this metaphor, it looks like this.
This is the wall of our Melbourne studio circa 2018.
And then if you put all of that under the microscope, it looks like this.
Our plotting document is a little too big to fit on one slide.
This is about 70% of it.
Linear time runs from left to right, and then each row is one of our characters.
And what you're looking at is all the different stuff that people are doing throughout the
game.
So if we zoom in further, say on this chunk, we can see the following.
These are all the things that are happening on or around
10.54 AM of day one of the game.
Even trying to get them all onto one slide like this, you still can't quite
make out all the text because there's just so much going on.
But if you really squint, you'll see that most of these events have a title
like Esther Forgotten or The Inspection.
These are the names of the different stories that run throughout the game.
And each story takes in a number of characters.
So Esther Forgotten centers around Esther and an experience of chronic pain that she's
having, but it also pulls in the nursing staff and the medical staff who are trying to treat
Esther's worsening condition.
Or the inspection is about the staff preparing for a visit from a VIP who's meant to be
arriving on day three.
You may also be able to make out in the tiny little text there that some of the scenes
are called incidental.
So as we plotted the game, we realized pretty quickly that we would need two
distinct kinds of scenes, scheduled scenes and incidental scenes.
So those scheduled scenes, they happen at the same time on the same day, regardless
of where you are and what you're doing.
Even if you can't like see them going on, they're happening in the background.
And incidental scenes are those scenes where if you happen to come across
someone in some downtime, you can sit with them and talk with them and
interact with them in a less time bound or plot oriented way.
So that was vital to situating the player within the world of the game.
You know, if all you were going to do in this game was sit around, listen to
conversations and like sort of very occasionally interject, then it felt
like there would be a distance between the player and their world, a distance
that was a little greater than what we were trying to achieve.
So we created these incidentals, these kind of hangout scenes, which mimic the fact that
in real life people have their own stuff that they're getting on with and that they need
to do.
But if you catch them in a moment of downtime, then you can kind of sit and hang out with
them and have a moment.
So yeah, creating Weird Strand and plotting it out was a very experimental process for us because
there aren't really very many narratives to draw from. Like there are games like The Last Express
which is helpful but feels more like the story ultimately revolves around the hero or what he
can uncover and then there's Sleep No More like an interactive theatre piece where you're wandering
around a hotel and kind of...
All a bunch of scenes are happening and you can wander into a scene as it's halfway through going on. But those stories are told in more of like a poetic and abstract way where we were going for representing the mundanity of everyday life.
For the characters, in developing the characters, we had some initial storylines and characters,
but we wanted to have them interact with each other regardless of if they had a storyline
reason to. So one of the tools we built into our development process was what we
called a character relationship matrix.
Um, which looked like this, uh, where we put every character on like the column and on the road and then in the cell for each, uh, character, like kind of intersection of characters.
Uh, that's how they respond to or feel about the other character.
A lot of the process for defining the narrative of the game was like this, like trying to
find ways of identifying what we were missing in our world, whether it was certain relationships
that we hadn't thought about or considered yet, or interactions between characters that
could happen that weren't yet plotted out.
Kind of like filling out all of the space where stuff could be but wasn't yet.
Something handy that came out of mapping the characters' relationships like this is that we could define very specifically how each character feels about each other.
Like in this example, Mr. Avery, Neil, is a writer of self-help books who, as we say in Australia, is a bit up himself, like thinks a lot of himself.
While Ida, his neighbor, is a lot more reserved and polite.
So from Ida's perspective, Neil is always interrupting her and bothering her, so she has a pretty negative feeling towards him.
While from Neil's perspective,
Ida's friendly and he's friendly, so they must be friends.
And this
Relationship Matrix, like it was simple, but it was also actually a really good prompt to
consider how to summarize how each character sees themselves. Whether they've got a positive
feeling towards themselves or a neutral or a negative feeling towards themselves. And all
of this stuff is like very high level and lacks a lot of the nuance that's in the game itself.
But it really helped particularly during the co-writing process, like keeping us all on the
same page. Yeah.
Uh oh, a bump in the road.
At one point after we developed the initial character plots and timelines,
we were trying to get publisher funding.
And so we wrote up some plot summaries for each of our characters to try to
get the publishers to understand what goes on in the game.
And then we stood back and looked at our plot summaries and panicked.
After reading over what we'd written, we had to ask ourselves, are our plots boring?
Here's an example of a plot that we planned for the game, centering on one of the patients,
Ida, who Jason was just talking about.
So it says, Ida has been knitting Hugo a scarf for his birthday on Sunday, a surprise gift.
Knitted into the pattern of the scarf is Hugo's family crest, which Ida sometimes sneaks into
Hugo's room to get a better look at.
When Hugo dies, Ida decides she must finish off the scarf in time for his birthday on
the third day of the game.
On day two, Casey can figure this out and get the crest from Hugo's room and give it to Ida.
Okay, like it's maybe an interesting start for something, but is it a whole plot?
But on reflection, we realized that our plots weren't very interesting when laid out in
this way because they were never designed to be consumed in that way.
They were never designed to be interesting when read from start to finish without interruption.
So to go back to the ponytail for a second, imagine that upon your head you have just
one hair growing out of the top of your head, and it's really long and it grows all the
way down your back.
But it's just the one hair.
That would look very different than this ponytail.
And our plots are the same.
They're designed to allow the player
to discover random bits and pieces
and braid things together and gather more and more strands
both on each playthrough and in any given subsequent playthroughs.
Writing out the plots in a linear fashion felt reductive
and didn't help us understand how the plot and characters
would feel to the player as the player was discovering
random bits and pieces.
Possibly out of sequence, possibly on multiple playthroughs.
Yeah.
Um, yeah, so we were feeling kind of, uh, again, more confident,
especially as we built out some like demos of the game and kind of
we're realizing that, oh yeah, you know, when you're actually
experiencing the game, these, these plots are working a lot
better than they do in that way.
Um, and then, uh, kind of, uh, another step that.
The first thing that happened in development is that we went to a workshop in early 2019 that started us on this path towards an additional lens on the game's narrative structure.
And it got us the idea to
Create what we called our dramatic narrative structures, which is up here.
Uh, these work similar to a schedule, like the schedules that
we've been working with so far.
But instead of the columns being hours of the day and the rows being like
each character, so that we could cross reference what the characters
are doing at whatever time we had one of these diagrams for each character.
And then, uh, we simplified the column.
So instead of them being like, you know, 10 AM, 11 AM, it was just like.
Morning, lunch, afternoon for each of the three days.
And then, yeah, we had one for each character in a bunch of rows, which I'll go through.
Oh yeah, but this is us at work on those.
And this, I guess, kind of shows how not only just coming up with all the ideas,
but building on them together was a very team approach.
Yeah, so each of the rows that were on this sheet, this is an example for Esther.
What about non-player characters?
Um, so there would be, it's a bit hard to read, sorry, but, um, there's Esther's
story is the top row, so that's just this character's key scenes.
Um.
Then there's Esther and Casey, so that's in those incidental scenes what can be going on between Esther and Casey during this window of time.
And then there's Esther's attitude, so how Esther's feeling during this period of time.
One other thing that you can see up there is it wasn't just morning, lunch, afternoon for the columns.
We also had an overnight column for the NPCs where we described what happens overnight between the days of the game for that character.
And then the player can discover that during the next day by chatting with the NPC or overhearing things.
And this is another just little thing that we did to make the world feel bigger.
Then just what the player can see within the game.
We had a different version of this dramatic narrative structure thing for Casey, the player character.
Because there's very little in the game that must happen for the player character, like in most of the game, you're really free to just wander around, listen into whatever, talk to whoever, like.
It was quite tricky, but we still found it quite handy to make one of these diagrams for the player character.
The additional columns there are like what we call bookend scenes at the start and end of each day that were like required scenes, but then within the day it's all up to the player.
And Casey's rows were...
Casey's attitude, so how Casey, representing the player, might be feeling during this time.
Is she curious or comfortable or frustrated? What is Casey's plot at this time?
Notes on any specific scenes that will always happen for Casey whenever that would happen,
but also generally what's happening between other characters and Casey during this window.
Is she meeting a bunch of people for the first time on day one morning?
Or is she trying to help people not being able to on day two afternoon?
And then there was the player motivations and goals.
And in this we're trying to guess at what a player would generally be trying to do
at that point in the game on their first playthrough.
And this was important because we wanted to give the player complete freedom and a sense that they're creating their own goals,
but we just wanted to make sure that generally whatever they would encounter would hopefully just feed towards whatever that goal might be at that time.
It was a lot of kind of like guesswork and hope.
Then there's the mechanics row. Are there limits on what the player can do in that time?
Is the action on the ship moving towards a particular place as well?
Like at lunchtime everybody goes to the cafeteria for lunch?
And are we going to try to build structural things into the script at this time?
Each character will recommend two other characters to talk to within the incidental scenes that you have with that character.
And then one interesting thing is that we also had colors and lighting on this, which isn't really related to the player's story exactly, but we just wanted to make sure that they wouldn't clash.
The weather on day two is really stormy, so we make sure that they're on scenes with the player.
that happened at that time that are really like happy or whatever.
Yeah, so with this dramatic narrative structure process, by zooming out a little and not worrying
about the specifics of every single scene, this allowed us to define for each character a more
meaningful arc or through line through the game as a team as we gathered around these like physical
butcher's papers or A2 prints.
This is an example of what Jodha was talking about earlier,
where a bunch of the core team are working together on this
and that it not only allowed us all to collaborate and come up with ideas and
solve problems, it also allowed us to share amongst the team
exactly what each character's storyline was
and the existing decisions and plans and thoughts.
And...
Yeah, we were also able to identify empty windows of time during this process,
or times where for a character they might have a bunch of functional scenes, but
there's nothing that really changes their attitude much during that time.
Yeah, it just really helped us expand out quite a lot what the player will come across
within a particular playthrough.
And also to take things that we had ideas about for a character and actually make sure that they're actually included within the game.
So Ted, our young Bunurong man, is a good example of all three of these.
He was a very well-defined character, but during this process we realized that sometimes he didn't have much to do, like he didn't have a very active role in a lot of the existing storylines.
And so we annotated on this quite a lot during this process on Ted's sheet.
And this is a zoom in on that sheet, which is semi-legible.
But yeah, a theme that came out of our discussions with the Boon Wurrung community was that members
of the community are constantly doing things for each other, helping each other. So Maize Wallen,
who's, you know, our composer and audio director,
So, we had the idea that Ted is doing something for a member of his community.
And then looking at the ideas here, I think we combined ideas 1 and 3 for what actually went into the game.
One of Ted's aunties is pregnant, and so she's looking for work, and then Ted's helping her find some work.
And then after confirming this approach with our Boon Wurrung consultation collaborators,
this turned into over a dozen additional scenes for Ted, both with Casey and with other characters.
And we also managed to bring in a bunch of other characters into this storyline that
were a bit bare during some of their time periods as well.
Yeah, another example is Tomie, the nonverbal patient in the hospital.
As we were trying to get into her mindset and understand her and her perspective,
Kalonica Quigley, Wayward's animation director,
brought up that it felt like we were relying too heavily on cliches about dementia from popular
culture as opposed to lived experience. And so that's where we organized the
consultation with Kate Swoffer, who Georgia mentioned before.
Yeah, with Kate, we just had this really lovely and kind of frank conversation about living
with dementia.
And from that, we were able to unpick some of the harmful stereotypes that we'd accidentally
built into Tomy's character, as well as getting just a really good insight into what living
with dementia is actually like, as opposed to what our assumptions were about it.
Yeah, just one little example of this is that Tomy is mostly non-verbal and Kate told us
that actually that's quite rare for somebody with dementia.
But often a person with dementia won't talk a lot or people will think they're non-verbal
because they're just fed up with communicating with people who don't take them seriously
or don't know how to communicate with them.
Yeah, and then we were able to express this in the game.
We were able to change it so that Tomy does eventually speak to another character
who speaks to her in her first language.
And then this is, you know, it isn't the player character that like figures this out and does it.
It's a different character because we didn't want Tomy as a character to be a puzzle to be solved for the player.
Like, because that would then take away from the feeling that Tomy is an active agent in her own life.
Yeah.
Yeah, and it was obviously it made the game a lot better, like it's all of this consultation,
but it also was just a really enriching process. Like having these conversations
was just really incredible and really lovely and the collaborators was super generous and
it just felt like it made us better people. Yeah.
So after all that, we had to actually write it.
Um, this is a tiny, this GIF is a tiny snapshot of our scene list document.
So this is what you get when you plot 15 fully realized non-player
characters across three real time days.
Um, and whilst we'd written some test scenes before, it wasn't until we knew
that we had the funding runway to complete the game, that we actually tried to get
the thing written from start to finish.
Um,
It was really difficult to actually write and finish off all of it, and I often remembered a tweet while we were doing it from Jake Elliott, one of the creators of Kentucky Route Zero, who advised to avoid creating homework for yourself during game development.
And I was like, oh yeah, okay, we've accidentally created like a thousand scenes of like complicated
interwoven subtext filled scenes of homework for ourselves.
That was great.
Yeah, good job us.
When we went to record voiceover, we printed the script physically for the first time and
it was 1500 pages.
So that was a moment of panic.
So actually writing the scenes meant that we were now testing out all of these grand
narrative theories that we'd been talking about earlier.
And sometimes our assumption about how a scene would work just didn't actually work when
written out in full, or it wasn't feasible from an animation perspective.
You know, for me as someone who's used to working with real flesh actors who are amazing,
I had to really get out of the habit of saying, Ida finds a piece of paper and folds up a
chatter box, or...
Esther jumps on top of her dresser and hisses like a banshee.
Sometimes getting a particular scene to work would require significant changes from our
plan.
For example, we used to have an intercom that was on the top level of the ship.
There's a chef in the game who's kind of down in the bowels of the ship.
And there are various places in the game where you can use the intercom to interact with him.
We used to have one on the top level, but most of the other characters interact with him through
this intercom that's in the mid-level of the ship. And we just couldn't guarantee,
either from a narrative perspective or a technical perspective,
that every time you press that button on the top floor...
He wouldn't already be interacting with someone in real time down below.
So we had to create this whole thing that, like a sort of subplot where the intercom on the top level is broken.
And then there's another scene where Devon kind of explains that to you after you've tried to use it.
So things like that would crop up all the time.
It was also during the scene writing process as well that we really ensured there was enough
Casey-specific content within each character's windows of availability so that we could ensure
the player never felt that a character had nothing to speak with them about unless that
was our explicit intention.
We do have characters in the game who actually don't want to interact with Casey or don't
have anything to say with Casey, but we needed to make sure every instance of that was intentional
and that Casey wouldn't ever rock up to a really friendly character's room and then
kind of like sit twiddling her thumbs.
The dramatic narrative structure diagrams that Jason mentioned earlier were super useful
throughout this time as well, because they could really determine the focus of each of
those dynamic incidental scenes, because now each of those scenes could exist to highlight
or underscore a character's attitude at that time, as well as relating to the scheduled
scenes.
So once we'd finally gotten into the writing of the scenes, we had to ensure that the two
of us worked together to keep the characters' voices consistent, despite having two writers
working on the scripts.
And I think we did this in three key ways.
It says there are major and minor stake in characters, so by this I mean that there's
no character in the game that was written 50% by me and 50% by Jason.
Because I think that would have probably led to a bit of an indecisive character voice.
There's also no character in the game that was written 100% by me or 100% by Jason,
because we felt like that would probably lead to each character having quite a unique voice,
but the tone across the game being inconsistent.
So instead, and this is actually something that we've sort of realized after the fact,
it wasn't really by design, but we sort of had each of us being kind of the majority
stakeholder for some of the characters, minority stakeholder for other characters.
So for example, I reckon I probably wrote most of Ida's scenes and most of Esther's
scenes.
I reckon Jason probably wrote most of Neil's scenes, most of Lily's scenes.
And the effect that this had is that one of us was able to set the tone and the other
one of us was able to read through what that person had done and kind of follow that tone.
Second thing, and this is a bit more kind of stock standard writing advice, we used people that we
knew and based the character voice on them. So Neil's voice is largely based on an old friend
of Jason's. A lot of Esther's turns of phrase come from my family. You know, I think we all,
or I hope that it's not just me, that plays out hypothetical conversations in our heads
with people that we know. And when you use those voices from your mind that come from
a stock of real memories, it just adds a lot of depth and flavor to the game.
And I think the final key to the consistency of our character voices is that we had two
writers but only one editor.
So Jason and I both wrote on the game, and other team members wrote a few scenes here
or there, but only Jason edited the scenes.
And this meant that although we both had input throughout the process, there was just the
one person going through and making sure that each character was consistent in their use
of language and consistent in the way that they came across.
For me, I knew we were onto a good thing in terms of the consistency of these characters
when we were in the recording studio one day and one of our actors had a question and I
was directing the performances.
They said, you know, why does my character say this or what am I feeling in this?
I turned to Jason who was in the room and I was like, oh, what was the thinking behind
this line?
And Jason said, you'll have to ask yourself.
I'd sort of lost track of the characters and they were sort of taking on their own life
so I had forgotten that I had actually written that scene.
But we were still revising the script throughout the recording process, as we've mentioned a little bit,
with the input from the actors, and the voiceover process was also such a time of discovery for us.
The actors often showed us things about our characters that we didn't know yet,
and putting our trust in our actors and forming a true collaboration with them really paid off
in terms of the depth of feeling that our game was able to achieve.
Yeah.
Um, so after we completed the VO recording process, uh, and that was a whole thing and
our audio team, uh, right up there right now, um, uh, doing a talk about the VO process.
Uh.
Which I think shows our team's commitment to simultaneous storytelling.
Anyway, after the VR, there was another stage of revision as we were implementing
like the scenes into Unity with the animations.
And at that point, like all of the VR was done, but we were able to still kind of
like break a scene apart or like, yeah, just change the way that the player goes
into it or all of that kind of stuff.
Make only some of it available depending on if certain options are set and that kind of thing.
And a lot of this just came out of like playtesting the game and kind of feeling out
like which scenes feel too long, which scenes would be better if Casey is like asking questions
to go into sections of it as opposed to just being like a longer set section and that kind of thing.
Yeah, so after seven years of development, we released Wayward Strand in September last
year.
How did it go?
Well it was definitely an experiment.
We were trying out a new narrative form in order to tell a story that reflected the values
we were trying to instill into the game.
The values of subtlety, of complicated narratives that don't fit into stereotypical structures,
and of representing characters that aren't often represented in games, especially as
active agents in their own lives.
And the feedback that we've heard in general has been great.
Like, yeah, very positive.
But the specific things that we're hearing about the game
tell us that we're going in the right direction.
That this style of storytelling allows us to present characters
in what feels like a brand new, like realer feeling way
compared to other styles of storytelling,
even within the medium of games.
Yeah.
All right, time for some takeaways.
There's some stuff that's not on this slide that I wanted to mention before I go through
these points as well.
Just shouting back to the earlier parts of the presentation, we really recommend that
your studio find some way to form some relationship with the traditional owners wherever you are.
That's more relevant in some parts of the world than in other parts of the world, but
it's been incredibly meaningful for us.
We've engaged in that consultation ongoing, we've paid for that consultation, and it's
been really, really a wonderful thing.
So we definitely encourage you to do that.
So we created a game in which stripping back player agency allowed for more dynamic, vibrant,
and alive NPCs, and a player experience that encouraged listening and reflection, which
is what we were going for.
We did it all by experiment.
We couldn't go over it, we couldn't go under it, we had to go through it, and we strongly
encourage you to do the same.
We started with strong values and we never compromised on those values.
This motivated us to make the game, but those values are also structural to the game.
They're the muscles that operate the machinery that we built.
And we proved our hypothesis that just like those individual strands of hair that would be very strange
if they were growing alone out the top of your head, like I was talking about before,
our simultaneous stories created an experience that was much more than the sum of its parts.
And speaking of the ponytail, ponytail is a real narrative structure that everyone now knows about.
Thank you so much for coming to our talk.
Thank you.
We're very proud of this game and we're very humbled by the response it's had.
We're here at GDC looking for long-term partnerships for our future projects.
So if you know anyone who you think might share our vision for
games, please put us in touch.
We'd love to see you to have a chat after the session, get your
feedback, answer any questions.
And if you see us around, say hi.
I do believe that we also have like approx five minutes
left for some questions.
So if anyone does have any questions, please feel free to step up to.
Is it these mics here, I believe?
Alright, I think you were first.
Alright.
So, amazing talk, really inspiring, really appreciated it.
Thank you.
I did have a question.
You mentioned how the simultaneous stories are more together than, you know, for some
of their parts and all that.
How do you in the game encourage the player to follow through these distractions so that
they do not experience the stories as a single strand, taking away the value as a whole?
That's a great question. I think that my take on that would just be that it would be really hard to follow the one story the whole way through.
And the reason that that is, is that any given character that you are speaking to, especially earlier on in the game, there'll always come a time where they have stuff that they need to do.
Like,
A nurse might come into the room and need to kind of assist them into their wheelchair
so they can go to lunch and they ask you to leave the room at that point.
A character might get tired and ask you to leave so they can have a nap.
They might even, you know, if you're talking to them about a specific thing, like there's
a thread through the game where Casey has an interest in the history of the airship.
You might be talking to someone and they'll say,
Oh, Mr. Proust knows about that. You should go talk to him.
And so both explicitly with the characters telling you to go do other stuff,
but also implicitly with them having to get on with their own lives,
it kind of, each narrative shunts you out of it pretty quickly and into other ones.
And it would be quite difficult to linger with the one character the whole time.
Perfect. Thank you.
No worries.
Hello, great talk, thank you.
I had a question about how in your game does the time move on and how did that imply the
way you built the narrative and the way you kept the player to engage with the narrative
and all of the edge case with a time-based narrative like you did.
Thank you. I just remembered that our facilitator said that I should repeat the questions back
before answering them for the purpose of recording. So the question was about how time moves on
in the game and how we deal with edge cases around the functioning of time and how that
time mechanic interacts with the narrative. I reckon this is a you question.
Yeah, so it was definitely super complicated.
And yeah, I guess we've got like, you know, a timer that moves forward at like, I think,
eight times speed, we changed it around a bunch of 16 times, six times,
but we ended up on eight times. And then all of the scenes that
A meant to play will play out when they're meant to play.
All of the incidental scenes have windows where they can play or not play.
And then we eventually built in a delaying system so that if a player is halfway through a
conversation with somebody, one of those incidentals and another one is meant,
as another scene is meant to play at that time, it'll just delay so that
The player can finish their conversation.
We initially wanted to not do that, and then the player was always getting interrupted
right when they were about to ask a question and it was really annoying.
So, yeah, that's just...
It was very complicated, is the short answer.
Yeah, whatever.
Yeah.
Thanks. My question piggybacks off the first one a little bit. Games that allow players to
pursue depth or breadth on a time limit often have a problem where people who dabble a little
and never go deep anywhere miss things. And I was curious to hear if you had sort of wrestled
with that question and if you had landed on an answer for how to deal with people who
got a little bit of a lot of experiences and never went super deep.
Yeah, cool. Yeah, so the question was, like, how did we deal with the fact that often in these games, players might just dabble in various storylines and get distracted and never really get like a like a full complete storyline on a particular playthrough. One part of that I think was like, Ruth and Casey, Casey's mom, the head nurse, they have like this relationship with each other, that
changes a lot over the course of the game, especially in those bookend scenes that are
at the start and end of each day. So that has its own arc to it and that comes to a resolution.
And so you kind of, I think even on a single playthrough, you get some kind of plot. But then
we just embraced the chaos as well. And yeah, it seemed to work surprisingly.