Hello, good morning.
Thank you all for coming.
I know it's quite early.
So my name is Ilkka.
I'm from a company called Supercell.
And I will talk today about the way
that we are organized, which we call the cell structure.
But before I begin, I want to emphasize that I'm not here
today to tell you or trying to convince you that this would
somehow be the right culture or the best culture.
Obviously it has worked out very well for us, but I believe, I'm a firm believer that every company should have their own unique culture, which is like, of course, designed that company in mind.
So instead my goal today and my sort of hope is that at least some of you guys would walk away from this room with maybe one or two new ideas how you can make your organization better and the culture better.
So I wanted to begin with a story about one of our games.
So I think it was almost exactly six years ago.
I remember it quite well.
We were in this meeting room with most of the Supercellians
at the time.
And we were talking about new game ideas.
So at that time, we had plans to release a couple of games
that year.
But we had no idea whether those games would be successful.
And at that point, none of our games had been successful.
So we felt that it would be good to have some game ideas
in our back pocket.
And one of the ideas that was presented,
there was a guy called Jon who presented his prototype, which
he called the Summoner.
And that game essentially was a real-time PVP game.
And I remember people really liking the prototype,
but then lots of concerns there.
expressed as well and I remember myself for example saying that you know I just love what you've done here, but but I just don't believe real-time
PvP games would work on mobile. I wish it was asynchronous or something along those lines then
and and so this is like six years ago, and I remember that like a
When if you fast forward a couple of months from that moment then actually we did get very lucky
but that our games Hayden and clash of clans actually became relatively successful and
and we had all of our developers tied to those two games
so then we actually didn't have time to pursue any of the ideas that were presented in that meeting.
But then a couple of years went by
and two other Supercell people, Niko and Vesa,
they needed a game idea and they sort of remembered this Summoner prototype that was presented at that time
and they sort of picked that up and they were inspired about it
and they created their own version of it and it still was a...
real-time PvP game on mobile.
And again, the sort of the same skepticism
was around the game.
But despite that, they kind of pushed further.
And I even remember this moment with those two
that we had a meeting and they came to me and said
that they feel like killing the game.
And I asked, like, so why is that?
And they said, well, it doesn't seem that that many people believe in it.
But then I asked, do you guys believe in it?
And they said, yes.
and then encouraged them to continue and thankfully then they did.
And then slowly but surely a group of enthusiasts started to form around this game.
But at some point the project ran into some difficulties
and then Niko decided that maybe somebody else should lead this project
and then there was this guy Lassi who was super super excited about what had been done.
the only issue was that he believed that the game should actually be like reworked completely
and maybe they should go back to square one and build it one more time
and on top of that the team had the idea that instead of the IP that had been planned for this game
code name Scroll, they should actually use the Clash of Clans IP
and you can just imagine like the amount of resistance from the people who had been originally involved
with that game and of course Clash of Clans at that time
was our most valuable IP, so it was a big call.
But, you know, Lassi and the team didn't really care about the resistance,
they just went on and decided to do exactly that.
And what's interesting to me is that
even still a few months before the beta,
there was quite a lot of people who thought that, you know,
just doing this pure real-time PvP game,
it's going to be like a really difficult thing to pull off on mobile.
But again...
and the team, they didn't care, and they just powered through
and released it on Vita.
And then that game is Clash Royale.
And obviously, it was pretty successful from the launch.
But then the story continues.
So fast forward again, maybe three, four months
from the launch.
And we actually start to face some issues with the community.
So they were not happy with how the game worked.
We had an issue.
but it was known as a trophy threshold, so it had to do with the progress of the players in the game.
Players weren't happy with that, and for a good reason, it wasn't a good experience
once you get to a certain point in the game.
And then what really pissed our players off was this thing
known as emotes in the game. So what you can do in the game is that
you can send emotes to your opponents
and lots of players were sort of using that to...
to basically irritate the losing player and that really drove some of the players completely mad.
And those complaints had been there from the very beginning
but the team, the original team always thought that, you know,
like this is part of the game, this is the soul of the game, it's a PvP game
so we are not going to change it.
But then Lassi wanted to do some other things and then a guy called Jonathan came
and he started to lead the team and there were some other changes.
Despite the fact that all the original creators thought that these emotes are an essential part of the game,
they decided to make a call to enable the players to mute these emotes.
And that, of course, like many of the original team members thought, was absolutely wrong.
But yet, they did it.
And because of that, and most of all because of some of the other changes that they had made to the progression of the game,
again, started to grow quite quickly.
next six months and it is still at a very good place today.
So I think this story as a whole is a really great example of how our organization works,
both in good and bad.
And it's a good example of our culture.
But I don't think it's a good example of our culture, I'm not telling it because the game
eventually was successful.
I'm telling it that, you know, this game came together despite...
the fact that lots of people in the organization disagreed what was about to be done.
Like starting from the CEO, many of the founders and many other
sort of people in the organization.
But yet somehow the game progressed and it was released and was...
We were lucky in a way that it was successful.
So today I will talk about this culture and really like
trying to tell you guys what...
We have found out what works well and then also what hasn't worked and what the challenges have been
and more than anything what we have learned throughout these years.
But before I actually get into the actual culture and how it works,
I want to tell a bit about what actually led to the creation of it.
So first of all, a bit about my background.
So unfortunately I'm not a game developer.
I haven't developed any of our games and none of them have been my ideas.
So I can't take any credit for the games.
And even if I have always loved games and I've been a big gamer,
I actually ended up being part of the game industry just by an accident.
So, and it's funny to think this, but originally, actually,
like for whatever reason, I wanted to be, when I went to the university,
I wanted to be an investment banker or management consultant.
And until today, I don't know why.
I'm sure I'm very happy it didn't happen eventually.
And the reason why it didn't happen is that I got really excited
about entrepreneurship at some point.
And then I was lucky enough that I bumped into this group of people and they wanted to found their own game company.
And it just happened to be a game company. It could have been any other company like from my point of view.
But these guys wanted to do games and they were all game developers.
But none of them were like interested in doing any kind of a...
Or handling any of the commercial or the business side of running a business.
And they couldn't afford to pay any salaries.
And I'm sure they didn't have any other applicants
for myself for the job.
So then I finally got the job and became
the CEO of the company.
And that company was called Sumea.
And this is like year 2000.
And funnily enough, we were actually doing,
or our plan was to do mobile games already at that time.
Eventually the company did okay and it actually was sold to a company called Digital Chocolate
which is actually from here, was from here based in San Mateo and my job was to run the
European operations of the company.
And you know, those times were quite different so the ones of you who are used to, or all
of us who are used to like dealing with the app stores, I mean this was a very different
time because the distribution was through like carriers.
and you had to do like these separate distribution deals with every single one of them
and it was quite interesting. I actually found this
photo from those times. As you can see, it's a very serious business
with a jacket and everything and just look at that phone like on my lap like
but the funniest thing about those days is that you were basically selling games to people
who didn't really care about games. Most of them they didn't. They didn't play the games
and it was just, you know, traditional sales work.
I can't say that I would miss those days too much.
But then after that, my job was to actually run the global studios organization
of Digital Chocolate and we had three studios and I guess around 200 people all together in those studios.
And so I come from, as I told you guys, I come from this quite analytical background.
Like I said, for some reason my dream job was to be something like management consultant.
And so...
originally took a very kind of, what I thought was a very analytical and thoughtful
approach to design the organization.
And by the way, since I've sort of created this organization myself,
I believe that I also have a right to kind of criticize it.
And you know, all of the funny things and mistakes that I'm going to talk about
and the flaws, I mean, those are all like my mistakes.
And the other thing is that even if some of this stuff will sound quite funny,
I mean keep in mind that everything was done like with the best intentions.
So already at that time our goal was to just simply to create the best games.
But anyway so my approach was that I wanted the company to be very well organized.
So like everybody belonged to their kind of own unit or box and everybody reported to somebody
and we had this like very well thought out matrix organization.
And we had process for every single thing you can imagine,
from creating new games to many other things.
And everything sort of looked really great on paper.
And most importantly, what the light bulb there indicates
is that who has the product vision,
like who ultimately decides what type of games the company does.
And the product vision was very much at the top.
So it was myself, it was the three head of the studios.
and some product managers and our small group essentially controlled what the company was doing.
And then like, what made it probably even worse is that then the organization grew
so we hired all these people and we opened these new studios.
Our approach to manage that growth was actually to like even further increase the control
so we added layers of management and we added the amount of...
added new processes to the company because we wanted to control it.
And I've thought a lot in the recent years, like, what sort of draw all of those things.
And it really was like this feeling that I guess ultimately I had to have that.
I wanted to feel like that I am in control of our destiny.
And having everything, all of these written plans and org charts and everything and process,
it kind of made me feel...
like that we would somehow be in control of our destiny.
That's probably the best explanation that I've come up with.
And we exercise this control through a couple of processes.
And I'm going to give you an example of two.
The first example is, which I think is relatively widely used
in the games industry, one form or another,
is this kind of green light process.
We call it the YDChalk, meaning that
why should Digital Chocolate build this product?
Essentially, it's a mini business plan for every game.
So basically starting with things
like what's the market opportunity like,
what's the size of opportunity, what does the competition look
like, how are our games different and or better,
what's the cost budget, what are the risks, so forth, so forth.
And from every single new game, this type of document,
probably like 10 pages, was required.
And to make it worse I had this idea which I thought was a good idea but resulted to be a very bad idea.
So my goal was that I wanted to make everybody in the company feel, all the departments feel that they are sort of a part of the process and they can create this sense of ownership.
So I required the game developers actually talk to heads of each and every department and sort of to get their sign-off or support for this new game idea.
So these people would talk to me.
head of the finance, head of the marketing, head of sales, head of operations
to kind of get their approval and you can sort of guess what it leads to.
Like in these meetings that they had about the Greenlight decisions
like there was no real discussion because the real discussion had been like before the meeting
and it was like super political process where
like the developers would do anything they could possibly can to get an approval from certain people.
And then, like, if there was no approval from a person,
then that game wouldn't, the idea wouldn't even appear in this meeting.
So the value of the meeting was close to zero.
And also, like, some other problems that it had was that, you know,
like, if you think about it, like, I mean, nobody has a crystal ball.
It's really hard to predict which games will be successful.
So then you could make the argument that, you know,
why would this group of people have that crystal ball,
and why should they be making the decisions?
And one could argue that who really knows the games and the players best, it's probably the game developers themselves.
Also, like this process, it's really favored sort of what I would call incremental innovation.
Like very, kind of products that are a little better than the existing ones.
And the reason is that for you to make a case like what type of product to build,
the easiest way to build your financial estimate was to look at what already exists in the market and say that okay,
we are better because of these games because X, Y and Z and therefore
the revenue estimate it's like a
you're gonna capture X percentage share of this market or something like that
and that was sort of an easiest way to sell this stuff to people who didn't come from games background so
for example a guy with a financial background, I mean that's the language
that that person understands
but what
the problem is that this type of process doesn't favor the truly innovative ideas
like if you really wanna build
something from scratch, you want to build something that doesn't exist yet.
You can't build a case like that around it.
And surprise, surprise, we really didn't have many of those type of games, like,
coming through the process.
And then the last sort of problem with the process was that just, you know,
it required lots of time from the developers.
So instead of them, like, writing prototypes and, you know,
building actual games very well, building pitches,
which, of course, isn't a very good use of time.
they could use that time to the products themselves instead.
So that would be one example of the process.
Another example is like at some point we introduced this like monthly review processes
and they were essentially like status reports from a game teams to the upper management
like what's going on.
And the purpose was like that we wanted to feel in control about
and make sure that these games are actually progressing as we had agreed and you know
still shooting towards a vision that we had agreed.
And what really made these meetings bad
was that they were also essentially go, no-go decision
points.
So they also were green light meetings as well,
meaning that it could be that your game gets discontinued
in this meeting.
And of course, you can imagine what happens.
Of course, the game teams would come to this meeting
very well prepared.
They had done all of this work the prior week
to prepare for the meeting.
they had created a lot of materials just for the purposes of this meeting.
And after the meeting, had the game continued,
they would just throw away all of that stuff and continue where they left off.
And at some point I think I figured out that
some teams, they literally used one week of every single month
just for the purposes of this meeting.
Of course, that doesn't make any sense.
Also, you can imagine the amount of frustration that these developers had
when they had to explain game stuff and game development stuff
to people who like...
weren't game developers at all.
Again, it was my fault.
I was the one who invited these finance and marketing and sales guys
to the meeting.
It's definitely not their fault, but of course they had questions
and it wasn't very productive.
And the last thing about this meeting that, again,
you can imagine it's a large group of people
and very easily leads to this kind of design-by-committee type of thinking.
So the ideas that would go through are the ideas that
doesn't get anybody irritated,
but then the overhand, you know...
aren't really that great or innovative either.
Because like most of the big innovative ideas, they are
things like, for example, Clash Royale that did something new
but then you don't really understand it before it's out there.
And there were other... and I could have like
picked some other pros as well, but these are probably the top two ones
on my list, which really didn't work out.
And the really, really interesting thing about all of this is, and all of these processes, as I said, they're put together with best intentions.
But the thing is that despite all of this, I mean, believe it or not, but we were actually able to put out some really great games.
So, uh, ones of you who were part of the mobile games industry back in those days might remember a game called Tower Blocks, which was a really big hit for us.
Later on, then Facebook just started their gaming platform.
We released a game called Millionaire City,
that got a huge amount of users, and there were others as well.
And at some point, I started to think,
what really is the common nominator
behind all of these games?
And the more I thought about it, the more I realized
that actually, first of all, all of these games,
they had a really great team behind them.
Then two.
they were released exactly at the right time.
So we got the timing right, which of course has mostly to do with luck.
But then thirdly, it also seemed to me that what explained the success
is that the less the management, like myself and some others,
the less the management had to do with the game,
the better were the chances of success.
And somehow these games, these hit games, they just happened.
Like, almost like accidents.
And I once actually joked to somebody that we were able to put out these hit games despite all of these processes that we had in place.
And that of course tells you something like how great these teams and the people there at the company.
And then I sort of finally got it and it's really embarrassing to almost talk about it because it took so so many years.
But I finally got that these processes, no matter how well thought out they are, they just do not...
translate into great games.
And then the thought process continued and I started to think that
if the success truly is only about the team and the timing
and the timing you can't really control because that's about luck
but what you can control is actually the team.
And if it really is about getting the best possible team together
And you know having an environment that really like doesn't slow these teams down
So there's like none of this management stuff like that
But it creates friction for the team if it's all about the team like what if what would happen if you would sort of build?
like a new type of company
But would only be about people and these teams and and having an environment there is no friction
And and what if actually like what what if we?
The people who would be sort of the superstars of the organization would be the game teams themselves and not sort of the founders or the management.
What would happen if it was actually the teams who owned the product vision.
And then at some point we had this idea that what would happen if we actually turned this organization chart upside down.
And actually like it would be the game teams themselves who kind of owned their game.
And that's what the light bulb again there indicates.
And then we kind of took this idea even further and thought that
we could actually think these teams as
as they're kind of almost like their own independent companies
inside the greater company.
And then at some point somebody suggested that since this is such a radical idea
I mean let's not call them teams, let's call them cells.
And then somebody asked that okay
like if that's the case like what is this whole thing called
and then somebody came up with the word supercell
and that's where the name of the company comes from.
But really the idea here is that there is no central process.
I mean, every team can be different.
And that enables us to hire from much broader base of people
because you don't have to be just one type of person to get hired.
And every team can have their own ways of working.
And we wanted to see that as a source of strength
rather than a source of weakness.
Well, at some point somebody asked that, OK, but
if it's all about the teams, like, what do you do then?
Like, what is the role of management in this type of case?
And we thought about it a lot and really
the answer seems to be that it's our job to put together the best possible teams
and it's our job to make sure that these teams have the best possible environment to work in.
And by best possible environment I don't mean a fancy office, for example.
I mean, I mean an environment where these teams can have the biggest possible impact
and there's no friction in the organization.
Also one of the things that we got excited about was this idea that if these teams make the decisions
it probably will increase the speed of execution
but also, because they don't need approvals
but it will also increase the quality of the decisions
because then the decisions get to be made.
as close to the player as possible.
Because it's obviously these guys who know the games best
and they probably also know their users or the players the best
so it just makes sense.
And these days I think that our organization, it works the best
when I make as few decisions as possible.
And we've sort of made it a goal that most of the decisions,
if not all of them, they should be made at the team level,
not at the management level.
And to describe that goal, I even like start to say to other people
that my goal is to be actually the least powerful CEO
and meaning that the less decisions I make, the better the organization works.
And sometimes this leads to some really interesting situations.
For example, when we work with some outside companies,
like for example with partners, platform partners for example,
it always takes them a while to realize that at Supercell
the most important meanings you can possibly have
they are with the game teams.
So for example, if they're meaning with me
in most cases it's a waste of their time
because at the end of the day it's not me
who's making these decisions.
And they usually don't believe it the first
or even the second time we tell that to them
but maybe after third or fourth time
and then they start to see how we work
suddenly they sort of get it.
Or there are things like...
Recently, when it was the International Day of the Girl,
I participated in this initiative called Girl's Takeover.
So the idea is that this, say, a teenage-age girl comes and takes over the job of the CEO
and makes all the decisions for one day.
And they asked me to participate, and because I thought it was a very important initiative,
of course I wanted to participate.
kind of a pre-warned them, all these girls, Sonja, that I'm happy to support you and we will do this,
but I just want to warn you that you might be actually quite disappointed,
because the fact is that I make very few decisions in this company.
But, you know, she took the chance anyway, and I think she did the right thing by touring the studio
and talking to the game teams, which is, like, always the most interesting part of my day.
But, you know, it is just interesting, like, how this type of...
way of organizing it, it changes how you also deal with some of the external parties.
One other idea that's very close to our culture is this idea of the power of a small team.
So at the previous company we had seen in our own eyes that how powerful this very small group of
people can be if they are just the right people and work well together. It almost seemed that
And it's counterintuitive, but the scarcity of resources, meaning the number of people,
it sort of, it leads to better prioritization, better focus, and then that in turn leads
to better quality.
And, you know, we saw it at the previous company time after time, and also we've seen it at
Supercell.
So quite often when things aren't working out for us, one of the de facto solutions
that we have is let's make the team a bit smaller.
and you know, let's try to put together the smallest possible team.
So it probably isn't a surprise that at Supercell we don't have any kind of green light process
but then the question is that gets often asked, how do you guys decide what games to build?
How do you sort of, quote, control it?
And actually like, the only thing that we sort of control
is the team and the team's composition and
and of course I have to be able to trust the lead of the team.
But after that, it's up to the team to develop the games they want
as long as they develop the games in the framework that we've agreed on.
I mean, our dream is to create these games that people will play for years
and that are targeted for a widest possible audience.
But that really is the framework, and within that framework
the team is free to do what they want and build the game that they want.
Also, we are known for...
for like killing a lot of our games.
So how do we do that then?
Well at Supercell I would say that two
entities have like
control. So one
is the game development team itself and then
the other one is players.
So and the team is in control
in full control during the
development phase. So when we still don't have any
hard data or
metrics it's the team and only the
team who can decide.
whether the game will continue or not continue and be killed.
But then, like when the game goes from the development phase to a soft launch phase or the beta phase
and we start to actually get some metrics on the players,
then the control shifts in a way from the team to the players
because then it really is up to the players
and of course we will be observing the metrics
and if they are good enough we will...
uh, launch the game globally.
And what's good enough?
Well, that's something that we always decide before the game goes to beta
and we tell the metrics to everybody in the company
just to make sure that we are honest to ourselves.
And after that it's actually quite simple.
Like if the game reaches the metric goals, we will release it to global
and if it doesn't, we'll kill it and we'll do something else.
Um, the...
This model has a couple of, couple of like
challenges that are important to understand.
The first challenge is an interesting one.
The thing is that lots of people do not believe that this is true.
Not even after they've joined, at least for the first month or so.
Many people outside the company believe that this is some kind of a PR trick,
so people like me would come to conferences like this
in the hope to talk about it and then attract talent to the company.
And it's just a PR thing, it doesn't really, isn't true.
But that's obviously not the case and it wouldn't make any sense
because people discover it very quickly when they would join us.
And it has happened to me like so often that, you know, somebody comes in...
is with Vassil for a couple of weeks
when I meet with somebody at the coffee machine
and that person goes,
hey Jelke, I have to convince you something
that I actually didn't believe
like this independence thing
when I joined, but now I've realized
that it actually is true.
The other thing that is a challenge for us
like outside looking in
there's this misconception about the model.
Lots of people think that...
Supercell is somehow this small happy family where anybody can do whatever they want and not care about the results.
And that really isn't true at all actually.
I mean what actually keeps this whole thing together and acts as a glue is our very high quality bar.
So as I just said, you know, our goal is to create these games that people will play for years and years and years.
And that's a very high bar as you guys know.
And then if you combine that with a completely transparent information sharing,
so every single team knows exactly how all the other teams are doing,
just because we share all the metrics to everybody in the company,
and also these teams have to give updates to the rest of the company quite regularly.
So it's very apparent how the other teams are doing.
So the combination of the high quality bar, and that is very transparent,
makes it sort of a high performance organization,
where people really want to like always...
get to the bar and even higher.
And you know, like I said, whatever doesn't meet the bar, it actually gets killed,
which of course is always a hard, hard decision.
And you know, in our organization, the fun part to talk about is always the independence.
I mean, of course everybody wants to be a part of an independent team,
a small team that can do what they want.
The harder part is to talk about the other side of the same coin,
which is responsibility.
And the way we think about it, that every single member of that team
they are responsible towards each other and to all the other super salients
and that's a very big responsibility
and it also means that in our culture we don't think that
the responsibility lies with the management
I mean if there's a problem we expect the teams themselves to do something about it
and not the management to interfere
And you know that actually results in a lot of like killing decisions.
So like, I mean, I believe it's actually easier for people to kill their work
if it's not working out, then they can, when they're in full control of that
by themselves and the decision is theirs.
So, for example, a guy called Jonathan,
I think he was here speaking like two years ago about a game called Smash Land,
which he was the lead of, a game that we dearly loved and
and he was telling the story here in the same conference
about how he, in a typical Finnish way,
even if Jonathan comes from New Zealand,
I think they had met in a sauna with a team,
and then they had, and the game was in Bida,
and it was almost reaching the Bida metrics,
but just almost, not quite.
And they had had this show of hands that, okay,
like how many of the people in the sauna
believe that this is the best game they will ever do?
And I think there was very little hunch.
And then they decided in that evening to kill the game.
And then I think Jonathan sent this email to everybody in the company informing.
And I remember that very well because I happened to be traveling here
and I was checking my emails in the morning and I said,
OK, they actually decided to kill this game.
And I felt really sad about it because,
one, I love the game myself.
I played it a lot and whenever I went home, I...
I played it a lot with my kids and said,
OK, I'm going to explain this to my kids.
Two, I felt really sad for the guys and for the team.
I know they had worked super, super hard for that game.
And then they had to kill it.
But then I also felt very proud.
Like, I mean, just think about it.
It's amazing that these people have poured their heart
and soul to this game that everybody in the company loves.
And it's very close to these metrics.
And yet they think that they can do better, and they kill it.
So I just felt proud about that.
Those guys and the team at that time.
And you know, we do kill a lot of games and we are known for that.
So, be it in our game number three and four,
so be it in Boom Beach and Clash Royale,
I believe we had developed ten games to relatively advanced state
and out of those ten we killed nine.
And the one that we didn't kill was Clash Royale.
And of course, like, killing games is definitely not fun and failing is not fun.
But still, like, we...
we've actually tried to take some inspiration from Pixar.
They often say that failure is an essential
and inevitable part of the creative process.
So, i.e., like without failure,
there wouldn't be any hit games either.
And, you know, if you're not failing,
it just means that you're not,
your bar isn't high enough
and you're not taking enough risk.
And that's how we try to think about it.
It doesn't make failing any easier,
but, you know, that's the kind of,
our way of thought about it.
Okay, I want to close by talking about some of the learnings that we had over the years
and some of the challenges.
So this will sound self-evident, but I still need to say it.
I mean, this model is exactly as good or as bad as the teams are.
It really is all about the teams.
And from this perspective, it's actually interesting.
Originally when we founded the company we didn't say that the best teams make the best games.
We say that the best people make the best games.
And it took us many years to actually realize that actually it's not about the people.
It really is about the teams.
And you know putting together great teams is super hard.
And to sort of use a sports analogy, what we realized over the years is that
the best team is not necessarily the one with the best individual players
but the team that plays best together.
And putting together such a team, it's not easy.
And I don't know if there's even...
Lots of people have tried to put some science around it.
But still, at least in our experience,
the only way to really know how a team is working
is just to put together the team
and see how they work together.
The other challenge is that, you know,
I talk a lot about how we love
the kind of small size of the teams.
And yes, there's a lot of great things about it.
Then you have a small team.
You don't really need any layers of hierarchy in the team.
You don't need process.
You know, everything can be planned on a whiteboard.
You need very little meetings, because everybody
can hear each other out.
They're working in the same room.
The size of our new games teams are like two to seven people.
Live games, maybe 10 to 17 people,
to give you guys an idea of how small these teams are.
And as I said, we believe that all of this
actually leads to better quality.
And it's way more fun.
to work in a smaller team.
But it also creates challenges.
One really interesting challenge that we actually didn't realize
early on is that it's actually like, for some people,
it can create a relatively stressful environment.
So the combination of having a very high quality bar,
and then this idea that there's like, no, it's only about you.
Because there are no pros.
It really is only about you and the team, of course.
And then that combined with the small team size.
So everybody basically is designing the game,
There are very little specialization in the team.
So that combination can become stressful.
And we've actually done quite a lot of work
to make that stress go away.
But that's a hard thing to do.
And then the other thing that is a challenge for us,
and I don't think we have been very good at solving this
so far, is how do we create content fast enough
for our players, given the small size of the team?
Another double-edged sword is this idea that you have very little visible structure.
And again, there's tons of things that we love about it.
But the challenge that comes is that it may seem chaotic, especially early on.
And we have learned quite a lot of lessons, for example, about onboarding.
Like, many years back, say four years back, it...
was probably like really difficult to join Supercell because you would just come in and
somebody might in the best case show where there's your seat and give you the laptop
and but then you know when you're on your own and and but then finally we realized that
we really have to invest in this and now we are like way way way better at that but you
know like in certain places you have to have structure and it's especially important for
the new people.
Sometimes people ask, I mean we still don't have any HR
So we do have recruiting and of course we have office people and admin people
But we don't have like HR people
And people ask that if people and the teams are so important to Supercell
Like why on earth don't you have HR person
Or somebody who's responsible for HR
And my response always is that well that is exactly because people are so important to us
So I don't believe that you can somehow outsource HR
to a third person.
I mean, if there are any kind of HR issues,
we want them to be dealt with between the lead
and that person themselves.
We don't want to have a third people involved there.
But it creates some challenges at times.
Also, as I'm sure you've already figured out,
it's almost impossible to reach consensus
in a culture like ours.
And many of our games, I would say most of our games, we have like four games,
have faced strong, I would call it almost like internal opposition,
or people who have just disagreed about the direction of the game
and have thought that we shouldn't even be building this game in the first place.
And just talk about Clash Royale and all the twists and turns.
The other example could be a game called Boom Beach, which was our game number three.
I still remember this meeting there.
myself and all the game leads, so every leader of a game team sat, including the lead of Boom Beach
and we had a very heated discussion about Boom Beach and people were not happy about it at the time
and then we again had a show of hands, how many people believe that this game should be killed
and every single person in that room, with the exception of a Boom Beach lead, wanted to kill that game
and then we had this really interesting discussion that okay
Like, all of us, except you,
like all of us, we want to kill this game and we don't believe in it.
But then again, like if we now kill it,
like at the same time, not only do we kill the game,
but we will also kill the culture.
Because I mean, after that, you know, we couldn't say
that Supercell is all about these small and independent teams
who like are our responsibility.
And if we make the decision to kill this game,
all of a sudden the responsibility is not with the team anymore
it shifts to us, because then it would have been us who make the call
and then we decided that out of these two options
we are here for the long term and culture is so important
so you guys should just do the game
and again thankfully they did and it's been a big hit for us
so we've tried to like...
And we borrowed this from Jeff Bezos from Amazon, this phrase that disagree and commit.
But, you know, like we tried to like enforce this idea that even if you disagree,
you can still sort of stand behind the decision.
And, you know, and the reason why you can stand behind the decision is that you trust the team
who has made that decision, even if you disagree.
So that's how we can think about it these days.
But still we have these heated discussions,
and I think they're a really good and essential part of the culture.
The last learning is this one.
It really is interesting, but this traditional approach,
and by traditional approach, I...
I'm talking about stuff like top, desire to do like top-down management,
desire to control stuff like from outside the team,
desire to create rules and processes
and all the stuff that I just talked about.
It's almost like gravity.
Like, you know, it sort of, it pulls you
like all the time like towards it and you have to like
almost fight back like every single day that it doesn't happen.
And it happens in all kinds of situations.
And the interesting thing is that fighting this, it gets harder and harder the more successful you are.
And for example in our case, the more successful we've become, because we've obviously been ridiculously lucky with our four games,
but the more successful these games have become, there's always some kind of pressure.
and natural kind of instinct to do even more stuff and grow the team sizes
and there are all kinds of opportunities that you say no, need to say no to
and we have to really like push ourselves to be always like saying no to all kinds of things
so that we could stay laser focused on the games.
Also, what's even harder is that, you know, it's easy to talk about this stuff when things are going well
but when things aren't going well, it's way harder.
Because there's this thing that comes to you, that this kind of pressure to get the control back from the teams and give it to some other people.
There will be people who will say that, okay, we'll come and we'll fix this for you.
And you know, lots of opinionated people, as I guess most of the great game developers are.
So there's really strong opinions.
And we really have to fight strongly against this idea that, for example, there are some...
some really, really great people in the organization
who have done great, great work, hit games before.
And if they feel strongly about the game,
that they are not part of who gets to decide.
And we've always taken the side of the team.
And we've tried to resist the temptation
to give control to some people outside the team.
But it's a discussion that we have surprisingly often.
And as I said, it gets even harder
when things aren't going that well.
Also, you really have to like...
be strong in this situation where the rest of the organization
like completely disagrees with the team
and then somehow you have to create an environment where
first of all, like
we believe that ideas get much better when they're challenged
so on one hand you really want to
facilitate that type of really honest, even brutally honest feedback
but at the same time you have to be very clear
that nobody, like nobody outside the team
has any authority over the game
it really is the team's decision
like whether you like it or not.
And you know, it's interesting like
this is the same case
with almost all of our games
and even Brawl Stars which is currently in Vita
it's the latest example so lots of people
at Supercell thought
didn't like the controls, they didn't like the art style
they maybe even didn't like the game genre
they don't believe that this type of like
twitchy action game even belongs to mobile
but yet, you know, the team
like really really
believes
believes in the game and of course it's in our culture to give them the possibility
to create the game, put it out and work with the players to make it a success.
And we really tried to create this environment where
you don't ever need to create the proposal about anything.
I mean, you can just do it.
And we just think that in our culture nobody
hopefully creates any kind of internal proposals about anything.
The minute somebody proposes to do a proposal
I say no, no, I don't need to see it
I mean here's my feedback and you just do it and prove that it works
And you know, sometimes it works, sometimes it doesn't
And if it doesn't, that's fine
And then like
The last thing I want to say about this is that
It also gets harder in case of mistakes
So say that there's a big failure or we do a big mistake
And you know, we do many failures
We do failures, we fail all the time
And that I think, as I said, it's an essential part of the creative process.
But then the natural human instinct in case of failures and mistakes is to
but okay, let's not do this again, let's create this rule
or process that will prevent this from happening again.
And we always have to remind ourselves that
hey, people, let's remember the foundation of a company.
Instead of rules...
we believe in trusting the people and their common sense.
And you know, like, the more we grow, actually,
the less rules we should have as a company.
But again, there's like this temptation always
to take that path.
So I want to close by saying two things, really.
The first one is that I want to emphasize
that despite everything that I just said, I mean,
Culture has not created our four hit games.
I mean, all the credit, it really does belong to the teams
behind these games, and culture has been an enabler at most.
And it really is all about the teams.
And for example, the story about Clash Royale
that I just told you, I mean, that would not have happened
without those people, those amazing people
who were part of that journey and contributed to the game.
And again,
the role of the culture is just to enable these people and enable these teams to do exactly that.
And then of course there's always that element of luck that is related to timing that's in the play.
The other thing I wanted to say is that
how I personally have started to think about culture is that it's almost like
how I'd like to think about our games.
I believe that our games should be getting better like every single month.
And as I said, our dream is that people will play our games after years, if not after decades.
And in a way, our games are never complete.
And in a very same way, I believe that culture is never complete either.
Like it can always evolve and it can and it should get better.
And I think we are a good example.
So our culture has evolved.
on many different respects and I do believe it is getting better and can and it has to get better over the years.
Okay, that was it. As I said in the beginning I hope you got some new ideas.
At least some of you got some new ideas out of this talk.
Thank you very much.
I think we have time for a few questions.
Hello.
Please.
Hi.
Hi again, Ilka.
I had the privilege of working with Ilka at Digital Chocolate.
He indeed gave his best to make it a good place.
I think at Supercell you have innovated team structures in a different way compared to
how we were operating at Digital Chocolate and you have seen excellent results.
Congratulations on that.
So my question is, at Digital Chocolate while you were making dozens of games, at Supercell
you made very few of them.
So why was the shift from many to few?
Well, I think like the thing that I've learned a very hard way over the years and I think many people like who've been part of these companies is the importance of focus.
I mean, games is such a competitive industry with so many smart people, so many smart companies that and you know, we are a small company.
So you can only do a very small, small amount of things if you want to do them at the best of your ability.
So just believe that it's about focus and, you know, focus and quality.
They just go hand in hand.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Hi.
Yes, so you talked a lot about the structure
in terms of the game designers and the developers.
What about the ancillary people that you might have?
Let's say the marketing teams or the technical infrastructure
teams, the IT and stuff.
So is that shared among the teams,
or is that also each team kind of has to deal with that?
That's a great question and that's exactly an area where I think our culture has evolved quite a bit.
So obviously like when we started there was six of us and five of the six were game developers
and again I was the only one who wasn't.
And you know like the whole idea started from like thinking about game developers only
but then like when the model like started to work out pretty well like then we thought that
why wouldn't we take this idea and apply it to some other teams as well.
But it really depends like on the...
area of business how it works well it's like and it is important for us still that the game teams
are at the at the center of the company and they sort of like set the pace for the company
because we want the company to be kind of led by the creative people but then like for example in
the case of marketing like i would say that that our marketing teams they operate very independently
of course and they're still trying to figure out like what's the best way for this team
to be independent enough but yet of course you need to link them somehow with the game teams
because the marketing needs to kind of communicate the vision of the game to the players so that it's
actually in line with what the game is about. So how do you kind of combine these two things and
we've done all kinds of different experiments and I think we're still learning. But I would say that
the goal always at Supercell is that we'd like to all of these teams to fall into this idea of like
independence and responsibility, but there are like differences how these teams have
implemented it depending on which areas of a business way they are.
Okay, thank you. I'm curious about the transition of the old structure to the new structure
and I guess the shift in mindset needed by everyone but especially in managers.
So how did you deal with that and what did you do when
people in management positions didn't want to lose control?
Well, of course this is a different company, of course some of the same people,
but I think it's a combination of just having more experience.
The interesting thing is that I've actually spent,
I've still spent most of my career in the previous company,
so Sumen Digital Chocolate Combined was ten years of my life,
and now Supercell I think we're getting closer to eight years now.
So I've been at less time at Supercell, but you know, like I believe that those years
have taught us so much how to do things and then maybe also like how not to do some things.
But you're right, like the mental shift that has to happen is that you have to like let
go.
You have to be like, you have to like completely trust these people and these teams.
That's how I say it.
It's an.
easy thing to talk about when things are going well and it's way harder when things aren't
going that well. But you know, I think there's like enough of a critical mass of people at
Supercell and definitely not just the management. We have a very small management team and we
don't even call it that way. But there's so many...
super salient at the company who like seen how this model can work and I think we
all the super salients do a great job of keeping each other like honest about it so if
and we often say that that if you see something at supercell that it's not in line with our
values and culture it's your responsibility to speak up and I trust me like people do speak up
if they see that something is wrong. Thank you. Yeah, hi.
being the least powerful CEO, that is your aim,
so what forms your day?
What is your day-to-day schedule?
What is your vision? What do you wish to do?
So what is it that I actually do?
That's funny, I actually was asked that question not long ago.
And I really had to think about it.
So what is it that I do?
So I try to spend most of my time in the people-related things.
I still interview every single new employee that comes to the company, no matter what
is the position.
So I spend time with recruitment, I do spend time with all the team leads.
And then, of course, everything that is somehow related to culture, at some point it will
end up on my desk, even though I firmly believe that, you know...
But it's not, it obviously isn't not my culture and it's not my responsibility,
it's everybody's culture and everybody is responsible for it.
But I, I, it's my job to sort of somehow like summarize it for everybody and
figure out what the culture is and, and kind of keep on like telling,
telling that message. And then there's like lots of like, not like very sort of
just boring administrative stuff. So like, for example,
like everything that is related to like everybody in the company, like stuff like.
you know compensations and all these things I mean thank God we don't do any
annual performance reviews or anything like
that you know those used to take too much of our time
like in the previous company added like no value whatsoever but so we don't do
that type of stuff
but you know like there are certain things like for example the compensation
review which is
you know very much like on my desk and which I think is important of course I
feel it's very important to
make sure that people are compensated fairly. It's a combination of
those type of things. Thank you.
Hi, Elka. Thank you for sharing the insight.
Actually, I've been working with a very big Chinese game developer.
And so this is more like a question, let's say, from our president.
So let's say we have a super independent, super elite team
who can make all the decision and execution.
And there is a way, like say, if we can do it here, we can do it anywhere.
So what do you think would be, you know...
the potential risk that the team might go like really independent, like over independent
somehow.
How I can convince our president to give us the power, you know, like being a sell.
That's a great question.
I mean, then it's a long time ago when we actually had to raise money and had to be
dealing with venture capitalists.
That actually was always the question.
doing that, like, why don't these guys just leave and set up their own companies?
And I told them that if they do that, I mean, if they feel like that, you know, that's the
best place for them to develop the best games. That is exactly what they should do.
And you know, the way I think about it is that it's just like we need to make sure that Supercell
is the best place for these people and for these teams to create the best games. And as long as we...
As long as we are successful in that, then everything else will take care of themselves.
And if you're not successful, then obviously these people will leave if the environment isn't great enough.
But we do talk about this quite a bit.
And really, ideally, I'd like to think...
The way I think about the supercell structure,
but ideally it would combine the best of two worlds.
So you can work in a very small...
independent almost like startup within a startup and you can do your own thing
but then of course you get sort of a job security and and some of the other
benefits that are part of being a bigger company and and and you can you just
have more resources I mean we can do the reason why I believe it's more fun to
work at Supercell today than it was say six years ago is that today we can just
you know do much bigger things just you know because of the resources that we
have available for us and we can run after much bigger dreams and
That's exciting for me.
Thank you.
Maybe we have time for one more.
Yay, can I ask?
So teams, very important, obviously.
Could you talk about how you form them?
How they change over time?
Do they change once a game goes live?
Like, how you manage the composition of them?
So it's really a group effort. So what we do is that, and a big part of my job is that I meet,
and let's limit the discussion to this game team. So I meet with the game leads, these are the people who lead the game teams, every single week.
And that's actually the only regular meeting that we have, by the way.
But we have this one hour meeting, and we just meet.
Usually like without any agenda and we just talk about the teams most of the time.
We don't make any decisions regarding the games.
We never talk about like...
I mean of course if somebody needs some advice they might raise up a question in that meeting.
But most of the time we talk about the teams and you know like maybe a team needs help in a certain area
and can somebody like move from this team to that team and you know those type of things.
And I wish there was like more science or a process to it.
I mean because that's the hardest part of our job is to...
create great teams and ultimately the only way to really figure it out is
whether a team is working is just to put it together and see how it works out and
then if it doesn't then you can make changes. Cool, thanks. Okay, thank you again.