Thank you for coming. First, I'd like to introduce our two speakers for today.
I am Shinya Kumazaki, Executive Director of HAL Laboratory.
I worked on Kirby Air Ride as an artist, served as director starting with Kirby Superstar
Ultra, and am now involved with the overall development of the Kirby series as general
director.
Our other speaker is expert director Tatsuya Kamiyama.
We have worked together since the development of Kirby's Return to Dream Land, and he has
since been the director on games like Kirby's Blowout Blast and Kirby and the Forgotten
Land.
Today, you're going to be hearing from the two of us.
We've been involved with this series for many years,
and I hope you enjoy our presentation.
In 2022, the Star Wall series will celebrate its 30th anniversary.
This is a game series with a long history, which was inherited by the predecessors.
We would like to pay tribute to the many developers who created and continued to develop this series.
We celebrated the 30th anniversary of the Kirby series in 2022.
This series has a great deal of history passed down from its early developers.
I'd like to express my respect for the developers who created the series and those who have carried on its legacy.
We decided to take on a new challenge.
To mark this milestone 30th anniversary, we decided to take on a new challenge.
This is the 3D Action Hoshino Kirby Discovery and 2D Action Hoshino Kirby Wii Deluxe.
First, I will talk about Hoshino Kirby Discovery.
That challenge was to develop our 3D action game, Kirby and the Forgotten Land,
and our 2D action game, Kirby's Return to Dream Land Deluxe.
I'd like to start with Kirby and the Forgotten Land.
Discovery was the first 3D action game.
There was a long road to completion.
But that didn't stop us from developing just one title.
Urbi and the Forgotten Land is the first fully 3D action game in the franchise,
and the road to its completion was a long one.
The process went beyond the development of a single title.
We accumulated experience little by little as we developed many different 3D games and modes.
As we dealt with the challenges presented by each game,
we also discussed how we could handle those challenges
if we were to create an action game in the main series.
We finally began development of a fully 3D mainline Kirby game
after the completion of Kirby Star Allies.
We had two themes at the beginning.
The series' theme was to re-examine Kirby.
We began with two themes.
Our theme for the series was taking a fresh look at Kirby.
The theme for the game was a 3D action game anyone can play.
We began our approach by taking a fresh look at Kirby.
I will now think about the personality of Kirby.
His body is as soft as a rubber ball, and he is flexible.
Whether he stretches or stretches, he is a very strange being.
I will think about how to make an intuitive 3D action using his Kirby-like personality.
We reconsidered Kirby's characteristics.
Kirby is a strange creature, soft like a rubber ball,
can take on a variety of shapes, and is totally fine
even if stretched or pulled.
We thought about how we could create an intuitive 3D action
game that took advantage of this uniqueness.
We thought about how we could create an intuitive 3D action game that took advantage of this uniqueness.
For example, if you capture a triangle, it transforms into a square.
We aim to capture objects that are easier to understand than mysterious triangles.
With that in mind, we took a more intuitive look at this shapeshifter's characteristics.
For example, by eating a triangular object, Kirby becomes triangular.
And the same goes for something square.
But rather than something mysterious and triangular, we wanted to use familiar objects.
By that, I mean objects that exist in real life, like road cones, lockers, or cars.
However, Kirby's not as good at swallowing real life objects.
Kirby's body takes the shape of the object Kirby tries to swallow thanks to a mysterious
power.
We used those shapes to push, fly, and roll.
We created intuitive actions that looked like they should.
We then used these shapes to enable Kirby to pierce, fly, and roll,
creating intuitive actions that behaved like they looked like they should.
A new 3D action that took advantage of Kirby's unique features.
And that was how we came up with the new 3D action system, Mouthful Mode, that utilized
Kirby's characteristics.
What's more, the setting for this game would be a new world
filled with the ruins of modern civilization,
where objects from the real world wouldn't feel out of place.
That's right. We didn't start with the visuals or the setting.
Instead, we started with the game design.
Both Mouthful Mode and The New World were conceived in order to create a new kind of 3D action that took advantage of Kirby's flexibility.
We wanted players to be comfortable running around in that new world.
Next, we'll hear from Director Kamiyama. He'll be speaking about the trial and error involved
in achieving our goal of making a 3D action game anyone can play.
I'm Kamiyama, and I'd like to introduce some specific examples from Kirby and the Forgotten Land to show what we did to create a 3D action game anyone can play. I hope you find this information useful.
The expectation for Kirby games is that they are fun to play, even for beginners.
We did a variety of things to achieve this, even in 3D action.
Actually, Kirby is not a good fit for 3D.
I think it's best to see what I mean.
First, let's take a look at Kirby's character design.
Honestly, Kirby isn't a good fit for 3D.
I think the fastest way to explain what I mean is to show you.
What do you think this Kirby is facing?
Which direction do you think Kirby is facing here?
The correct answer is this way.
When you rotate a sphere, you can't really tell that it's been rotated.
Kirby has a simple spherical design, so it's difficult to tell which way Kirby is facing
when seen from behind.
For Kirby's ranged attacks, it's a significant issue if the player even slightly misjudges the direction the character is facing.
Kirby sucks in the enemy and then spits them out.
If he misses, he has to find another enemy to suck in, which is a big stress.
Kirby attacks by inhaling enemies and spinning them out.
For this reason, if you miss, you need to look for another enemy to inhale, which is very frustrating.
We used homing to solve this.
While this is a common approach, we also added some twists to it.
Let's talk about these twists.
The first twist is a way to use a point-based system to determine the homing target.
The first category looked at is the direction the character is facing.
The closer the enemy is to that direction, the higher the point value.
When an enemy is dangerously close to Kirby, that enemy is assigned additional points.
When there is an important enemy like a boss, that enemy is assigned additional points too.
This way, for Everyone, the condition of the player can be evaluated by scoring, so the game can be a perfect homing.
This allows the homing system to choose the most appropriate target
by evaluating the player's situation via a point-based system.
We also paid attention to selectively ignoring certain targets when homing.
When homing is too strong, it robs the players of the fun of aiming.
We limited the height of the homing range so that the homing doesn't hit airborne enemies
when Kirby is on the ground.
This kind of homing failure feels acceptable when the reason is easy to understand, so
this minimizes frustration.
The problem is that it's hard to grasp the distance in the air, so we compensate it with strong homing.
However, it's especially difficult to get a handle on distance in the air,
so we supported this with strong homing.
If it's too obvious that the attack trajectory curves toward the target,
the player will not be motivated to aim.
We handled this by using a simple system that splits homing into two stages.
First, we use strong homing only during the first frame, immediately adjusting the projectile
to face in the right direction.
After that, we intentionally lower homing performance, making sure the trajectory does
not curve drastically.
This two-stage homing allowed us to make the player feel as if they had aimed at and successfully hit their target.
It's difficult to get a sense of distance in 3D space.
We solved this problem in Forgotten Land by introducing a unique system.
Before explaining our unique system, we wanted to ask the audience,
there's something wrong in this video. Can you tell what it is?
You can see what's wrong by changing the angle.
Actually, the attack didn't hit the enemy.
The attack is not actually hitting the enemy.
The attack didn't hit, but the enemy is reacting as though it took damage.
This is our unique system.
Like I said, it's difficult to get a sense of distance in 3D space,
and players would sometimes be frustrated at failing to hit,
even if it appeared to be a bullseye.
Therefore, we made attacks hit when it looked like they should hit.
That doesn't mean we simply made the hitbox bigger.
We extended the hit detection only for depth.
In 3D space, it is difficult to grasp the sense of distance in the direction of the object.
Therefore, we extended the hitbox along the perspective from the camera position
to compensate for the difference in the sense of sight and hitbox.
As I mentioned, in a 3D space, it's difficult to get a sense of depth.
Therefore, we extended the hitbox by parsing from the camera position
to correct the discrepancy between the visual feel and the actual hit.
In Discovery, we look at the position of the camera and correct the hitbox in real time.
In Kirby and the Forgotten Land, hit detection is corrected in real-time based on the camera position.
One particular pain point for 3D action games is the camera.
It greatly affects the gaming experience and takes a lot of resources to adjust properly.
In addition to this, there was another major hurdle for a Kirby game,
games that even beginners should be able to enjoy.
The player uses the left and right control sticks to control the character and camera simultaneously,
a control scheme that's difficult for beginners.
Unlike side-scrolling 2D action games,
you cannot move the camera to the desired location
unless you operate it properly.
It's also very difficult for them to be aware of the surrounding area.
Unlike side-scrolling 2D action games,
unless you control the camera properly,
you can sometimes miss the elements you need to get through the game.
As a solution to this problem,
we decided not to let the player operate the camera.
The level designer sets the optimal camera for the stage.
This is the movement of the camera.
The level designer sets the camera when designing the game.
This is how the set camera behaves.
The level designers specify the camera settings as they design the gameplay.
This controls the player's field of view to an extent,
and also allows us to leverage our know-how from 2D action games.
This video is an example of how the camera shifts from being centered on the character to include relevant objects.
With this sort of controlled camera, we can design the game so that relevant objects
naturally appear within the field of view, guaranteeing a smooth and comfortable gameplay
experience.
There were other issues that could also be resolved thanks to this kind of camera setup.
One of these was the issue of hovering.
Before we talk about this issue, let me first explain what hovering is.
As you can probably guess, hover is an ability that enables Kirby to fly wherever the player wants.
This is done in 3D space.
This is the most terrifying thing that has ever happened to a game developer.
This ability is used in 3D space. As a developer, can you think of a more terrifying ability?
If you allow the player to fly around freely by hovering, they'll want to keep going and going.
But in a game based on completing each level, there are restrictions on how far you can go.
If you don't understand the game unless you try, it will be stressful.
We used a camera to show the player's bad smell.
Not being able to tell whether you can get somewhere until you try
ruins the smooth gameplay experience and can stress out the player.
To resolve this issue, we again used the set camera to hint to the player where they can't go.
Even if you don't go all the way to the edge, you can get the idea that there isn't anything there.
The mechanism behind this camera setting is to first create walls surrounding the course that only the camera can hit.
This placement was mainly done automatically.
Next, we sent radial detection lines out from the focal point of the camera, within the area we want to show.
By having this detection occur ahead of where Kirby is, we can smoothly move the camera focus.
In addition, many artistic expressions became possible precisely because of this set camera.
The background was the main focus, and the camera layout
helped to express the world of Kirby.
We aimed to create a 3D action game that anyone could play.
In addition to the creation of Kirby and the Forgotten Land, during this landmark 30th
anniversary, we also developed something that can be considered the roots of the series,
a 2D Kirby title, Kirby's Return to Dream Land Deluxe.
Kirby's Return to Dream Land, released for the Wii, was born at a turning point in the
series, and this is a remake of that title.
Leading up to the original Wii game, Kirby's Return to Dreamland,
there were three experimental titles that were created, starting from the GameCube days.
It was the fourth iteration that finally saw the light of day.
This was the first mainline Kirby title for a console in 11 years.
During those 11 years, we continued to iterate on experimentation and development.
Because we were determined to not release a title until a certain level of quality was
met, we went through a long period of many growing pains.
And finally, the efforts of the entire staff bore fruit, and Kirby's return to Dream Land was complete.
It became a key title in the history of the series.
Now, I'd like to discuss some of the creative ingenuity that we have been able to accumulate through the history of 2D Kirby titles, using Kirby's Return to Dream Land Deluxe as an example.
KUSHINO KERBY aims to be a series that has approachable yet deep gameplay,
enjoyable to both beginners and veteran players.
To this end, we have accumulated a variety of inventive methods,
and these methods are all based on a certain concept.
That concept is, make Kirby the hero.
We want Kirby to be a heroic figure who fights valiantly to defeat his enemies.
In order for Kirby, and by extension the player, to become the hero, we feel it is essential to have controls that feel right.
What is a pleasant operation?
So what do I mean by controls that feel right?
It's not just a matter of matching character movement exactly to button input.
From that fuzzy input we know what the player might want to play
and of these, we move the Kirby as he or she wishes.
We will now explain how to jump as you wish,
using many different mechanisms.
What leads to feeling right is when a character moves exactly the way the player intended.
There are times when a player thinks they pressed the button at the right time,
but in reality, the input was a bit off.
From this sort of fuzzy input, we predict what the player intended Kirby to do
and have Kirby behave according to the player's intent.
I'd like to share with you a few of the many mechanisms that demonstrate this.
When you press the jump button in midair, you usually get a hovering effect.
If you press the jump button while in the air, Kirby would usually begin hovering.
However, if the button is pressed just before landing, you may get a situation where the player intended to jump but ends up hovering.
In these situations, we predict the player's intent and make it so Kirby jumps instead of strictly following the button input and hovering.
Even in situations where the player presses the button too late to jump over a pit,
we predict the player's intent and make Kirby jump even in midair.
Even the hit detection on Kirby's head during a jump has been adjusted so that it matches the player's intent.
This is a slow motion video of Kirby jumping during a dash.
At this rate, Kirby's body would come into contact with the enemy first, resulting in taking damage.
But, let's see what happens next.
Look at that! Kirby was able to defeat the enemy without taking damage.
Let's look at the video again with hit detection displayed.
When Kirby jumps during a dash, the hitbox actually extends a bit toward the direction of the movement.
We on the dev team call this Pompadour Detection.
Thanks to this Pompadour Detection, the player is able to jump as they intended.
In addition to these, there are numerous other features that have been implemented.
These are features that support the player behind the scenes, and are designed in such a way that they are not noticeable to the player.
All of this is for the purpose of making the player the hero.
These elements have been inherited and evolved over time
and continue to be improved upon.
Now, I will talk about graphics.
We faced the challenge of developing Kirby
while making it move as we wanted.
Next, let's talk about graphics.
In the early stages of development,
we also faced challenges in terms of graphics
as we attempted to move Kirby as the player intended.
As a result of aiming for a beautifully evolved graphic,
it became easier to lose track of the character.
In order to make Kirby move as we wanted,
we focused on the fact that the player is a hero
in terms of graphics.
As a result of our goal to beautifully evolve the graphics,
we realized that it became easier to lose track of the characters.
So, keeping our focus firmly on the idea of
the player is the hero, we considered numerous options.
And where we landed was the use of outlines.
The character's visibility was greatly improved,
allowing us to move Kirby as we pleased.
However, simply adding outlines would result in a visual that looks like a logo.
This resulted in a vast improvement in character visibility
and ultimately being able to control Kirby as the player intended.
But, simply adding outlines would result in a visual that looks like a logo.
We continued exploring ways to outline characters in ways that would really bring out their charm.
We tried using the inverted hull method for outlines,
but this resulted in small bits of noise where parts of the character overlapped.
To address this, we used depth value.
By applying gradation to parts of the outline where there were steep variations in depth value,
we were able to create an outline that allows for a sense of depth.
We focused on creating smooth, eye-catching outlines like those in TV anime,
and worked on each issue one by one.
This was the same for complex models besides Kirby.
With our eyes set on smooth and visible outlines, like those you would see in anime characters on TV,
we worked out these issues one by one.
We focused on creating more fun backgrounds and terrain graphics.
We thought that try and error was important
especially for terrain designs involving play.
So we used a decorative editing tool called Cinema
that we developed in-house.
We also worked on the graphics for the background and terrain
to make the game easier to play.
We thought trial and error was particularly important
in designing terrain as it ties into gameplay.
To facilitate this, we used an asset placement tool
called Cinema that we developed in-house.
The part where the designer felt it was difficult to play while moving the game
can be fixed and confirmed immediately in real time.
By using this cinema, we were able to create a world that made Kirby's imagination flow efficiently.
Designers were able to play the game, and if at any time the gameplay felt off or cumbersome,
they could edit and test it out in real time.
This allowed them to immediately fix any areas that hindered gameplay.
Using Cinema allowed us to efficiently create a world in which Kirby moves exactly as the player intended.
Next, I'd like to talk about the new modes added to the game.
In order to make this title an even more approachable yet deep game, we created two additional modes.
We wanted to take that idea and put it in the middle of the living room
so that everyone can enjoy it whenever they want.
A major feature in the original Wii game, Kirby's Return to Dream Land,
was its on-the-fly multiplayer functionality
that allowed family and friends to join in the adventure at any time.
We wanted to build on that concept and add a mode that could be played together,
anytime, sitting in the middle of the living room.
This is Y.Y. Mahoroland.
That mode was Merry Mago Land.
In Merry Mago Land, you'll find a variety of sub-games,
all playable at any time by up to four players.
However, we didn't want this to be
just a standalone bonus mode.
We wanted to make a mode that players can play between the action stages and Magoland at any time.
Allowing players to go back and forth between the action stages and Magoland at any time,
our goal was to create something that players would want to play between completing stages.
Which is why we wrapped that mode up into an amusement park called Merry Magoland.
In Theme Park, you can get items that can be used on stage,
such as masks and souvenirs.
You can play a sub-game while you're on the action stage,
and then use the souvenirs you get to conquer the stage again.
This is how the cycle works.
The more games the player plays at the amusement park,
the more dress-up masks and souvenirs they get,
which can be used in the main game stages.
Play a sub-game between completing main game stages,
then take your souvenirs with you back into another stage.
That's the kind of gameplay cycle we implemented.
We've made sure that the flow is comfortable,
and that you can go anywhere with just one button during the adventure.
With these advances, the bigger theme park mode has been completed.
Our goal with the flow of the game was ease.
We made it easy to go back and forth between modes mid-game with the press of a single button.
All these ideas went in together to complete this approachable amusement park mode.
Now that we've created this approachable amusement park, I'd like to talk about Magolor.
The theme for this section is creating a new character within a long-running series.
When we add characters to the world of Kirby, what's important for us is that the character has the essence that makes them a part of that world.
As you can tell from this sketch, Magolor was built using the fundamental design elements of the series.
We then carefully considered his abilities, role, and personality.
I want to protect him, but I'm also suspicious of him.
By wearing a hood, he has a mysterious design.
In this game, by wearing a part of his costume,
he can express a pinch, and other features of his costume are further used.
We gave him a hood to add a touch of mystery to the design.
In this game, we leveraged some of the unique characteristics of his outfit, such as parts
of it falling off to denote that he's in trouble.
And despite his voice being a synthesized one, he is still a voiced character, so he
hid his mouth to make it easier to create many conversational scenes.
Incidentally, he is voiced by the sound creator of this game, so on the inside, he's a veteran
composer in his 50s.
Some voices are made by other than Kirby.
A fair amount of voices other than Kirby's are done by other team members.
For example, like King Dedede.
Like, for example, King Dedede.
This is a concept diagram that we drew up when we were creating this game.
It shows the world.
Magolor comes from another world on a ship called the Lore Starcutter and lands on Kirby's
planet.
With that, he gradually starts to open up to Kirby and his friends.
As with the flow of this story, we hope to design him in such a way that despite being suddenly dropped into a series with a long history, he would fit right in.
This is the path he took to join the world of Kirby.
This is the design proposal for the Wii development.
This is how Magolor came to be in Kirby's world.
These are design proposals from the Wii-era development of Kirby's Return to Dream Land.
Many team members drew countless designs.
Ultimately, we arrived at the current design,
which preserves the spirit of the series while also adding new elements of individuality.
We also went through the same kind of trial and error for Kirby's Return to Dream Land Deluxe.
This is all concept art for Merry Magoland.
Our goal was to summarize the overall mode
through symbolic buildings and make it possible
to see all the doors to the many sub-games at a glance.
We are constantly incorporating new things
as we continue the series.
But we are finally able to create something
that will become the number one in Kirby's world
based on its role and personality.
As we continue the series, we are always incorporating new things.
But when we do, it's not until we consider their roles and characteristics
and brainstorm many design proposals
that something that will become a part of the world of Kirby is finally born.
In addition to the wide theme park mode I introduced,
we also created a mode that allows you to feel the depth.
In this game, in addition to the approachable amusement park mode that we introduced,
we also created a mode where players can really feel the sense of depth that we mentioned before.
That mode is the Magolor Epilogue.
The Magolor Epilogue becomes available after completing Story Mode and is a mode that offers a greater challenge.
I'll start with a brief overview of the game system for this mode.
In this mode, you collect magic points and use them to enhance your character's abilities.
The story is linked to the story of a lost mage who seeks his revival.
This increases the player's motivation for adventure and the sense of accomplishment.
However, this is only a superficial reason.
The main goal is to make a game that is more profound than Kirby Wii Deluxe
and a different kind of play experience from the original.
This game system is tied to a story in which Magolor has lost his powers and wants to get
them back.
This increases the player's motivation to go on this adventure and makes it easier for
them to buy into the premise.
However, that's really just a secondary reason.
Our main goal was to give Kirby's Return to Dream Land Deluxe more depth of play by providing
something different from the main game experience.
While we balance the game for experienced Kirby players, the highly flexible enhancement
system allows players to control the level of difficulty.
One of the elements that makes up this game system is the combo system.
The more combos you connect, the more reward points you get from defeating an enemy.
The word combo might make it sound like the game has a high threshold for entry,
but we worked to make the game both approachable and deep here, too.
We put in a little secret sauce to make combos fun.
Magolor's attacks use two different kinds of hit detection.
The combo detection only hits when the enemy has been hit once.
The red circle shows the hitbox for a regular attack, and the purple shows the area used for combo detection.
This combo detection area is only used for follow-up attacks when an enemy has already been hit once.
The game plays with a video that is not displayed in the combo detection.
As you can see, it's easy to hit the enemy you knock back.
This is an example of a small feature that supports the player.
Here we have two videos.
One with the hit detection displayed and one without.
As you can see, it makes it easier to land hits on enemies
even if they've already been knocked back.
This is another example of a subtle feature that supports the player behind the scenes.
There are also various other features that support the player from behind the scenes.
Even though the Magolor Epilogue mode is more challenging, we made sure to make the player
the hero of the mode.
Everyone can become a hero and become a strong enemy.
In Hoshinokawa Bui Deluxe, everyone, including your parents,
children, and friends, can become a hero.
This mode is also playable by up to four players at a time,
which means that everyone can become the hero and battle mighty enemies.
Kirby's Return to Dream Land Deluxe is a game where everyone can be the hero,
whether they be dads, moms, kids, or friends.
Hoshino Kirby Wii Deluxe is packed full of the creative ingenuity of 2D Kirby games,
cultivated through 30 years of history.
Kirby's Return to Dream Land Deluxe is packed full of the creative ingenuity of 2D Kirby
games, cultivated through 30 years of history.
And in Kirby's Forgotten Land, we challenged ourselves to create a uniquely Kirby 3D action game, approachable to all.
Whether 2D or 3D, everything from the technology and worldview to the design
was thought out with the goal of making each gaming experience awesome.
If I were to describe Kirby games in a single phrase, it would be one you've heard already.
Approachable yet deep.
And it's the concept we've kept front and center as we've continued to create Kirby games.
If I were to describe Kirby games in a single phrase, it would be one you've heard already.
Approachable yet deep.
And it's the concept we've kept front and center as we've continued to create Kirby games.
This is my 22nd year in Kirby development.
It has grown so much that it is still a series that has been played all over the world for over 30 years.
I am very impressed.
This year marks the 22nd year since my first involvement in Kirby development.
The series has continued to expand, and somehow it has become a series played around the world
with 30 years of history.
I cannot express how much that means to me.
Once again, I would like to express my gratitude to the developers who gave birth to this series
and continue to develop it, and to everybody who has ever played a Kirby game.
And I would be overjoyed if any of what we have shared today
helps you, the developers, in any small way.
We will, along with our team, continue to challenge ourselves to create games that are even more
approachable yet deep, no matter what genre they are.
Thank you so much for your time today!