Yeah!
What's up?
It's time!
Is my mic working?
Alright, good, it's working.
Real quick guys, that was Kyoko Higo.
Kyoko has been in the industry for a while.
She used to work at Squaresoft,
and then she co-founded Enhance.
And it's really thanks to her,
and all of our friends at 8Four.
that we even get any really cool Japanese talks at GDC here.
So, I mean, I just want to say thanks to you guys,
Kyoko, 844, for bringing us over here
and always bringing over all these cool,
legendary Japanese developers.
And with that said.
The time has come!
Yes!
We got some DMC fans.
Guys.
Alright.
My name is Matt Walker, I'm the producer on DMC5.
I've brought here today with me from Osaka, Japan,
the senior producer, Michiteru Okabe.
Hello.
Woo!
So how many people play Devil May Cry 5?
Nice!
All right.
Thank you.
And the main event, a legend in the game industry, a man.
who's been around since 1994.
He's directed games like Street Fighter Alpha,
Rival Schools, Capcom vs. SNK, my personal favorite,
Dragon's Dogma, and of course,
Devil May Cry 5, Hideaki Itsuno!
Thank you, thank you for coming.
Itsuno-san, let's rock.
Let's rock!
YUSUKE USTUNOMIYA Yes.
So, this is going to be a talk for game designers, so please bear with us.
Alright, you guys may feel differently after seeing that, but honestly, we did bring a proper GDC presentation here.
This is going to be based on game design. This is going to be for game designers.
We're going to talk about Itsuno-san's approach to designing games.
Alright.
We'll start with this theme,
game design by reverse engineering of emotions.
Oh, there's one thing.
Actually, there's one thing before we get into that.
We've reached 2 million sales.
Yeah!
Applause! Applause!
Thank you very much. Thank you very much.
We just really want to thank everybody for playing the game.
It's been a great honor.
Alright, let's go.
So Itsuno-san first wants to start with the idea of, okay, designing a game by trying to reverse engineer an emotion that you felt in your life.
What can you do to make people feel that way?
In other words, how can you get a player to feel that feeling that you felt?
And when we're talking about...
emotion here. We're talking about emotion, we're talking about being moved, we're talking about potentially creating a feeling
that will motivate the player to continue playing the game.
So the first important thing is do not mix up means and objectives.
We're going to start by assuming that we want to invoke emotion A in the user.
That's the objective. 日本語
And so then we want to consider what are the means,
what are the things that must be done to invoke emotion A. 日本語
What you want to be careful about is remember that there is one objective here, but there
could be multiple different means of achieving that objective.
Japanese translation
One thing that Isosan has really found throughout his years in developing games is that it's
really easy to get the two confused, and you end up getting so focused on a particular
means that you forget what the true objective was, and you end up spending a lot of time
trying to get a certain means implemented before realizing, actually, you know what?
This isn't what we're going for.
But what Ito-san usually tries to do is come up with both the objective and the means at the same time.
And by doing that, he can usually implement it in a way that is likely to succeed and actually be something that is implementable.
In order to achieve that, it is important for him to think of a means, or priority ordering,
that will work out and lead to success.
And then what you can do is you can think up
a lot of different kinds of means,
and you can kind of prioritize them
based on how easy they might be to implement,
how hard they might be to implement.
And with different priorities like that,
you can kind of decide what's going to be the best approach.
YUSUKE USTUNOMIYA-KONCHALAEWAGENA
So here we go.
We're going to say that we're going to assume here
that our objective this time is invoking a particular emotion
in the user.
As a game designer, you need to fill your library of emotions.
When you make a game, you want the user to feel this way.
It's natural for the creator to prepare a lot of emotions.
I mean, of course that makes sense, right? Because what we're trying to say is our objective here is to invoke an emotion.
It only makes sense that you want to have as many emotions as possible to draw upon.
So, get out there and experience everything you can.
For example, a traditional event, a popular event,
and also...
I want you to experience an event that you have never experienced before.
At the bottom, it says skydiving.
Ojiisan, Obasan no shito wa yannakute iidesu. Wakai shito ga yatte kurereba iidesu.
And we have skydiving on here, but if you're pretty old at this point, that's okay. You probably don't have to do that one.
I'm gonna leave that one for the young people if you want.
Wakai uchi ni shika daiken deken koto de ippaa aru to omoundesuyo.
Occhan, Obachan wa shiaanai desu kedo, wakai shito wa taiken shita koto no nai,
wakai uchi ni shika deken youna koto wo, wakai uchi ni ippai ko chokin shito ite kudasai.
So for all you young people then, get out there! Now is your chance!
Do everything you can.
And then remember, remember what you felt when you had that experience.
Keep that in memory, because that's what you're going to draw upon.
Now before that though, before you actually have the experience, Itsuno-san wants you
to think and visualize what you expect that experience to feel like before you actually have it.
And it's going to be that experience and that expectation that you're going to take and you're
going to reflect on, because the difference in
how different that was to actually feel versus what you expected to feel,
is going to be key to this process.
YUSUKE USTUNOMIYA And so the idea then is that
Let's say you expected something to be incredibly fun, really fun,
but then you actually did it, and it wasn't as fun.
It's this difference right here.
This difference here is going to be what you can use to draw upon.
On the flip side,
Let's say that you expected it to be this fun, but it was actually this fun.
I look like an idiot.
It's more fun. It's more fun than you expected it to be.
That's also going to be important for you too, because that was something that
you yourself, you didn't have the ability to envision how fun that was going to be
until you actually experienced it.
I have something to say about this.
I buy games.
I saw the magazine and heard about it on the internet,
and I thought it was a great game, so I bought it.
And this was when it was a shitty game.
So imagine that you bought a game.
You've read a lot about it, you've seen a lot about it,
it looks awesome.
And you're like, you know what, I'm going to buy this game,
and I'm going to have a ton of fun with it.
This is going to be sweet.
You bought it, and then it was crap.
This is a very lucky thing.
That's a good thing.
You are lucky for having that experience.
Got that.
I thought it was a great game, so I spent $69 on it.
I won because I thought I could win.
I had the $69 in my head.
But I couldn't win because I was solo.
So, your imagination won.
So imagine, you spent 69 bucks on this.
You're like, this is going to be awesome.
I can envision this is going to be sweet.
There's going to be all this cool stuff happening.
And it wasn't.
That's okay, because...
It's that expectation that you had, you're going to be able to draw on that expectation.
You're going to be able to use that.
You're going to be able to draw on that. By drawing on that, then, you're going to get more out of the game than you actually would have gotten from that $69 otherwise.
So, what Itsunzana is trying to say is...
Buy games, buy as many games as you can.
I forgot, with your own money.
But please, with your own money.
I would like to look back at my experiences
where I have had a big impact on my emotions.
So Iso-san is going to give a couple of examples of
experiences he's had that have provoked
different feelings that he's been able to draw upon.
Have a look.
So for instance, finishing a triathlon.
That's actually him.
That's him.
He finished that triathlon.
I didn't translate this, but having an expensive full-course dinner.
For anybody who's had fugu before, it's really good.
YUSUKE USTUNOMIYA If you've ever had a fugu dinner, you'll know that this is actually just the first portion of the dinner.
And for anyone else that hasn't, that's okay.
YUSUKE USTUNOMIYA But also, TV shows and movies that moved Itsuno-san when he was young.
I think that's what moved him the most.
So let's take a look at a couple of examples from TV shows or movies that have actually moved Itsuno-san.
Yoroshiku onegaishimasu.
Now, unfortunately, we weren't able to get the rights to use the actual footage from this,
but our art director, Koki Kinoshita, has done a great job of drawing up a couple little slides
to illustrate just what this scene is all about.
Now, the actual naming here is completely fictional and is in no way related to any brand, living or dead.
So we have this anime, this Japanese anime, where a super robot is just getting the crap
beat out of it.
This is the most famous robot in anime at this time.
This is the robot that everybody, all the little kids look up to.
YUSUKE USTUNOMIYA So he's getting the crap beat out of him,
and then his father, who's been missing, who's been missing, turns up out of nowhere and
brings out a new machine.
YUSUKE USTUNOMIYA A completely new robot that no one has ever
seen before.
YUSUKE USTUNOMIYA
Of course, of course, on top of a cliff.
And then this new super robot comes out and destroys each and every one of those enemies
that was beating the crap out of the hero in one fell swoop.
Speaking in Japanese.
So what little kids don't really know when they're watching this is that this is all
planned, right?
by bringing in the new robot as the old robot is basically dying off.
They're able to continue that new series,
and then the series that was originally playing,
well, that's going to kind of be retired anyways.
So it's this great marketing tactic.
But for Itsuno-san, when he was a little kid, he was like,
oh my god, this is amazing!
What's happening?
He was four years old at the time.
The title is different, and the A is different.
And this is also from a different series.
And again, any relation to any series or brand, Living or Dead,
is completely coincidental.
So this time, we have another robot show
where three different robots usually
fight together against a particular enemy.
And of course, Ito-san is watching this expecting that the three robots are going to beat the
crap out of the enemy, but no!
This enemy is so powerful, this enemy can destroy all three of them at once!
And then...
Again, this time a princess from space has come from out of nowhere and said,
don't worry, I have something that can save you.
We're going to link together.
And the three robots with the new robot combine into one giant robot.
And without lifting a finger, obliterates the enemy
that was giving them such a hard time.
This is the one from the TV show, the theater version,
that was shown during the summer break.
It was originally a robot that would appear
for the Christmas show at the end of the year,
but it was shown a little during the summer break.
This was also a big surprise for adults.
What's interesting about this one is usually the way these robot shows work then, is that
they show the kind of combined super form usually later in the year, usually somewhere
in about fall or so, so that they can really start to gear the kids up to buy all the cool
toys for Christmas.
But this was a little taste of that combination in a movie that came out over the summer.
When I saw this in the theater, I was so moved I almost cried.
Ito-san was so impressed by this, so moved by this, that he cried in the theater.
It was just that cool.
He was 32 at the time.
Ha ha ha.
So let's now take those emotions that he felt when watching those, let's analyze that,
and see if we can't use that in a game.
Which scene, which line, the character's personality,
did you have similar experiences and emotions?
Why is it cool? Is the pose cool? Is the voice cool?
Let's analyze all of this.
And so, when you're drawing upon a...
emotion like that. You want to think about everything, everything that is surrounding that situation.
What was happening? What was what had happened beforehand? What were you thinking? What was the
character thinking? What were the motivations for the character? Other stuff that I can't read from here.
What was missing? What was missing to make you feel moved?
If you don't have these elements, you won't be able to feel moved.
Think about it that way.
If you don't have these elements,
what was missing to make you feel moved?
If you have these elements, you can feel moved.
If you look for those elements,
And then what you can do then is you can try to replicate that situation, take all the
different elements that you found in that situation and then kind of one by one, take
one away, basically use the scientific method, take one away and then see does that affect
the experience?
Is that going to make the experience any less relevant or is it still relevant with that
taken away?
If you can understand the logic behind the emotions,
it will be easier to create similar emotions for the user.
You just need to recreate that logic in the game.
And then using that, then, you can basically figure out the logic
that triggered that emotion in you.
And then you can take that logic and apply that to your own game.
OK, let's move on.
感動した要素そのものとその感動を増幅させている要素を 混同しないようにしてください。 One of the important things is you're going to want to remember that as you're looking at all these different elements,
you don't want to confuse the elements that triggered the emotion
and the elements that simply amplify that emotion. まあ、例は書いてるんですけど。
and you can see some examples in the slide here.
But really the important part is that you'll want to distinguish between those two,
and then you can then take different elements and further amplify that feeling
once you've gotten that figured out.
Let's try it with Devil May Cry 5.
So here's something we need to be aware of.
SUGOI netabare ga... ...
...arimasu.
Ehh...
Moshi...
...mada...
...kono game wo kuria shite nai hito ga itara...
...minai...
...moshika mimi wo usagu toka...
...yatte kudasai.
But before that, please understand...
...we are going to spoil the crap out of this.
So, anybody that hasn't played the game yet...
...and wants to experience it for yourselves...
...now's a great time to maybe take out a podcast...
...listen to that, close your eyes...
...and just enjoy the ambience of the room.
I mean, really, this is the point of the presentation, but there's a huge difference in having seen this here and actually played the game and actually played and felt that experience of beating the enemy yourself and then seeing the cutscenes and whatnot.
I've heard a lot about the theme of Devil May Cry 5 in interviews and stuff, but I'd like to hear more about the photorealism and stuff.
I'm just lying, but this is the real theme.
Well, now to reveal a little something to you guys.
We've had all kinds of great interviews about the game,
and everybody always asks us,
what's the theme of Devil May Cry 5?
And we've said stuff like,
oh, you know, we're going for photorealism,
this, that, and the other thing.
Honestly, though, that's all a lie.
And we can finally say,
now that we're going to spoil the crap out of the game,
that the real theme is set back in Awakening.
Because there is a setback,
I wanted to do this in Devil May Cry 5.
It's because of the existence of that setback
that the awakening is relevant and so poignant.
This is the picture I wanted to show the most.
For Devil May Cry 5, basically, the whole scenario was written
specifically for this one moment in the game, right here.
Before we made the video, we rehearsed it.
We wanted to make this picture.
We wanted to make the user cry with emotion.
This particular photo, this is from the previews.
This is what we do before we actually start making the cut scenes.
But this basically shows that moment.
That moment where we said, okay,
this is going to be the moment where I want to move people.
I want to move them to tears.
Let's take a look.
Now let's take a look.
I don't have sound.
Let's see.
Oh no.
Oh God.
One more time.
Will it play?
Let us all pray.
I'm not letting you die!
This, this right here.
This ends right here.
Thank you.
Yeah!
You know, when you're doing this,
Long hair goes like, whoosh!
It's that moment when he's doing this and the hair slowly, very slowly floats back down.
That is the only reason that he has hair in that form.
Yes.
In a normal game, the main character is full powered up in the middle of the game.
So in terms of game design, then, usually what you would expect to do is you would have a character, and that character would probably have their full, their kind of full-powered state, somewhere a little over half the game.
So in terms of a Devil May Cry game, maybe about Mission 12 or so.
And then you'd be able to then play in that full-powered state until the end of the game.
Even for Itsuno-san, that makes perfect sense. That is fairly common.
But in Devil May Cry 5, we threw out the theory and we said,
no, we're going to achieve Nero's full-powered state at the very end of the game.
So we threw out the theory and we said,
OK, mission 20 is going to be where you're going to get into that state,
and people are going to go, oh my god, what is this?
This is nuts.
But then we got cocky.
We said, actually, you know what?
No, let's add even more stuff during the credits.
We wanted to convince the team that we were going to change the theory.
So in 2015, when we were preparing for the training camp,
we apologized to the team, saying,
I'm sorry, but I have something I want to do, but I want to change the theory.
And so as we were kind of coming up with a concept for the game,
this was in September 2015, we had this little retreat, Nisei Shima.
And that's where Isuno-san basically said to the team,
look, I know what we're supposed to do here.
We're usually supposed to get you in a full-powered state somewhere a little over half the game.
Please, just listen to me, just let me do this.
I want to do it this way.
This is actually a video from about three and a half years ago.
At this point, we were actually thinking about
We decided where and how to power up, and we haven't changed anything until it's complete.
By the way, this is a tip.
Gather all the main members of the team and say,
I'm going with this.
Do you have any opinions?
It's okay, I'm going with this.
And when you're busy at the end of the game,
you can shut the mouth of the person who complains
that you thought it was wrong.
Now, this is a pro tip from Isuno-san.
If you do something like this, we have a retreat,
and you have all the leads together,
and you say, okay, all right, we're going to do this, right?
We're going to do it this way, we're going to do it this way.
Then near the end of development,
when everybody really doesn't want to do that,
they know well.
I did tell him we could do it, so I guess we have no choice but to do it.
So, Nero. Let's look at Nero's setbacks in Waking of the Dead.
For Nero, we have he's lost his Devil Bringer at the beginning of the game,
he's been obliterated by Urizen while impaired,
and then he loses to Urizen even with Devil Breakers.
And then his awakening.
He loses one arm, but he gains two, so he gains a total of three.
But then his awakening.
Not only does he get his arm back, he grows two more.
And then the other things that we wrote there.
By the way, this is a picture that we shared with everyone
including the image of Nero with wings positive.
And this is actually the photo that we used then as we were kind of working through development
and sharing with the team.
This is what we're going for with Nero.
What is he going to do?
He's got these two arms!
Look at these things!
They're like wings!
Alright, now let's look at Dante then.
I...
can't...
get out!
Who dares interfere?
So maybe you guys remember, earlier we were talking about a TV show where a robot was getting the crap beat out of it, and then the new more powerful robot showed up.
Just this mysterious new hero comes out of nowhere.
So...
That really moved Itsunosan to tears and so he kind of hoped that by making this he'd
be able to move everybody that plays this game to tears in the same way.
In the actual game, after a mysterious hero appears,
you clear the mission and continue on.
You can bring the player's feelings to the next mission.
And this comes at the very end of the mission.
So at the very end of the mission, you beat that mission,
and then this cutscene plays.
And the idea there is that we've put you in a state where
you have no choice but to play the next mission.
You've got to know what's going on.
Yes, that's the theory in Dante's case.
He can easily defeat Yurizen.
He can also use Devil Trigger to defeat him.
He'll be in the FMA for a month.
Then, Kakusei.
The birth of the Demon Sword Dante.
The birth of the Shinmajin.
Yurizen's second form.
Yurizen's final form.
And then for his awakening, we have the birth of Devil Sword Dante.
The birth of Sin Majin Dante.
Then he obliterates Yuruzen's second form, and then his third form!
Okay, let's go to V now.
Let's go to V now.
In order to defeat his younger brother, he could only do one thing with the crumbling flesh and feelings.
He needed to separate man from devil with the strength of the Yamato.
And eventually, the man became a true devil.
This is my last request.
I told you we were going to spoil the crap out of this.
So what ends up happening then is V's awakening is the return of Vergil.
And to really play that up then, we have both V and Urizen in incredibly weakened states.
They are both near death.
V's setbacks then are that he's been thrown out as the unneeded portion of Vergil.
He doesn't have the power to fight for himself.
He needs these familiars to fight for him.
And his body is continuously falling apart.
But then the awakening is that he returns as Vergil.
And this is how we have our three different player characters, our three different heroes,
how they have their different setbacks and different awakenings implemented in this game.
The purpose of all of these projects is to
It's important to make clear what your goal is.
Here's one really important thing, though.
You want to have a clear objective for every scene, every event, every element in your game.
What is the goal?
This time, we're moving the user's emotions like this.
If you don't have a clear goal, you can't create a scene.
Think about what your goal is for this scene.
Without a clear objective, you can't create your scene.
You absolutely need that objective or else you're just kind of creating willy-nilly.
You need that objective to have a clear idea for what to do with that scene.
If you're working on a scene and you don't know what the purpose is,
ask the person who ordered the work,
what the purpose of the scene is.
So for any of you guys that are making something right now, maybe you're working on a scene, maybe you're working on something,
and maybe somebody's told you, like basically given you this as work, like make this scene, do this thing in this game.
If you're not clear on what that objective is, please go to that person and say,
hold on, hold on, what is the objective here? What are we trying to accomplish?
I haven't talked about the action part at all, but I think we should talk a little more about the action part.
So I mean I guess a lot of you guys probably know Ethan O'Suhan.
You know that he's a big action game director.
So I would assume that a lot of you guys came here
because you wanted to hear about action game design, right?
Right.
All right.
I'll do it.
Yes.
I'll do it about action.
Here's the action part.
This is what happens when you clear an action game after a lot of hard work.
Look.
Yes.
This is the feeling you want to go for when someone's playing your action game.
The way we see it, this has not changed at all in the last 30 years.
Action games have always been about this.
Everybody that is playing an action game, they are playing it so they can get this feeling.
What should we do to make the user feel this feeling of yes?
We should find a way to clear the game ourselves.
And we should practice to realize this way.
And I think it's important not to give up on this practice.
So you want the player to be able to figure out the trick to beating that particular enemy,
to winning that particular event themselves.
And then you want them to be able to brush up that technique and get better at it,
so that they can then finally beat that thing.
And the other important thing is, make sure that the players don't give up on themselves.
And this is kind of vague, so it might be hard to actually envision how to do this,
but this is the way we see it.
So, let's go. To find a way to win with your own strength means to see through the enemy's actions.
So that first trick...
Sorry, I'm going to keep going.
Sorry.
Figure out the trick to winning yourself then. Well, what does that involve?
Well, we think that one way that you can implement it, it involves observing the enemy's behavior.
And then you want to, as you can see here, provide a proper balance of risk and return for them as they're playing.
Make the player feel like they figured that pattern out on their own, without any help.
And you'll want to design your enemies in a way that the player can look at that enemy and instantaneously know,
okay, this is probably maybe envisioned.
this is probably how the enemy is going to act or behave.
I think we need to design a design that doesn't make a difference in the ethnic or national areas.
So you want to make sure that ideally, ideally, you can create that design
based on concepts that aren't influenced by differences in regions, cultures, whatever. Ideally.
Finding the enemy pattern by the user itself
leads to the feeling of, I'm great, right?
We do think that having the player be able to actually observe the enemy's behavior and
actually kind of figure that out on their own, that really does link to that feeling
of accomplishment when they've beaten that enemy.
Also in terms of enemy design, as we just talked about here,
if you have, say, you have an enemy that is powering up for an attack,
you know that attack is probably going to hit pretty hard.
So the player then will almost instinctively know to get the heck out of the way.
Speaking of enemy design,
it's natural for big guys to punch and attack with their fists,
but this is very important.
Or, as another example...
enemies with really, really big fists are probably going to punch hard.
That kind of thing.
I've had a design with a big blade on my elbow before.
I thought, you're not going to attack with your elbow,
but when I was told it was different, I was like, that's not right!
Well, we actually had one enemy at one point in one of Isono-san's games
where there was an enemy that had a really long blade.
coming off the elbow.
And he's like, oh, OK, OK.
So this enemy is going to go like this
and is going to attack like this, right?
And the game designer was like, no.
He was like, what are you talking about?
Of course, that's what he has to do.
All right.
JAPANESE SPEAKER 1.0
Now, some more examples from Devil May Cry 5 now.
We have a couple of different designs that we were looking at,
some thumbnails that we were looking at for a character called Riot,
an enemy called Riot.
We used this one.
For Riot, we ended up going with this one.
This is important because on the right side,
there is a circle with a picture of a rotating saw drawn on it.
This is important.
So we decided to use this design because we knew that the enemy would definitely roll, charge, and attack.
Now we ended up going with this one for this particular enemy that we're talking about.
The reason we did that is because the enemy is going to have this spinning, spinning like hedgehog-like attack.
A certain blue hedgehog perhaps.
And because they have that attack, this design clearly communicates to the player that
that's what they're going to do when they come at me.
Next, we used this red one.
And we have this other one called Fury. You can see this red guy here.
And the reason that we designed this one like this, you'll notice that he's standing up
straighter than the other ones. And the reason he does that is because
the player sees that and instantaneously they know that this one is going to act more intelligently than the other ones.
In Capcom, the red enemy is strong, and this one is red, so it's a symbol of strength.
It was called the Red Alimer during development.
We also have this thing in Capcom where basically whenever we have a really strong enemy, that enemy is probably going to be red.
Red seems to be the symbolism we like to go with that.
So during development, we called this guy the Red Alimer.
I didn't say much.
Okay.
So next, we need to practice the techniques to achieve the strategy.
We need to practice the operations.
We need to have intuitive operations.
Okay, so then how do players then brush up the technique that they need to succeed
while they can practice moves?
To do that, we need to be able to implement direct, responsive, and tactile control.
We've got to have proper tutorials as well so that the players...
are able to understand what they need to do.
YUSUKE USTUNOMIYA But then, we also need to be able to design the game in a way that they
can practice good judgment, that they've made the correct decision when they're fighting
against a particular enemy.
And one thing that we found is that success should be non-binary.
Even if players are having trouble with an enemy,
they should be able to tell if they're doing a little better
or not doing as well.
YOSHIMASA ENJI, SPEAKING JAPANESE Now, an example of that
is we have this move called Max Act.
So in Devil May Cry 5, there are three different ways
that you can succeed in actually pulling this move off.
YOSHIMASA ENJI, SPEAKING JAPANESE
So take a look at this first.
This is what happens.
He's about to play the video.
This is what happens when you hit that perfect frame.
You get a full charge on your weapon.
And then if you don't quite get the timing,
oh, you don't quite get the timing,
then you can see in the second one
there that you get basically one out of one charge out of three.
And then finally, if.
If you at least try it but you completely fail, you'll still get a tiny tiny bit of a charge.
Well, here's a fun fact. In Devil May Cry 4, we had the same move. We had this move called Max Act.
And it turns out basically there was one frame where you could hit that button and you would actually get that charge.
But we thought was basically, if it's that hard and there's absolutely no way to get any kind of benefit from it,
unless you hit that very specific frame, people just kind of gave up.
They just kind of stopped doing it because they could never really pull it off well.
In Devil May Cry 5, the number of frames for big success hasn't changed much,
but we've made it so that the wider range of mid-success and small success is possible.
When a user challenges something, the closer they get to success, the better feedback they get.
And so this is where we implemented some of that non-binary design.
We said, OK, for Devil May Cry 5, then,
let's make it so that there are these three different stages.
There's the perfect stage if you hit it with just the right frame,
and then gradually have more and more frames
where you're going to get less of a benefit,
but you're still going to get something out of trying it.
We're doing a few things to make sure that we don't give up on the challenge.
So what do we do then to try and make sure that people, players, don't give up on themselves as they're playing the game?
Well, for DMC5, we've changed the continue system.
So that's one way that we've kind of tried to do that.
We're going to go into a little bit more detail on that in a second.
Another thing is giving the battles a balance where players...
hopefully aren't just totally obliterating the enemy,
and vice versa, the enemies aren't totally obliterating a player.
That there's, that, hopefully they're having a pretty decent challenge,
and it's not too one-sided.
As we showed Dante earlier,
we're going to add the next part that we're curious about,
so that he doesn't give up.
And then another thing that we do then is, just like we showed you earlier with Dante,
try to lay out the game so that you have these key moments where players get to that moment
and then they want to find out on their own what is going to happen next.
We do high-end graphics simply because we want to see more of the game.
For Deadly May Cry 5, we tried our best to really make a game that looked as visually stunning as possible,
and we feel that that also kind of fed into that same idea of,
well, if it looks this good, people will kind of want to keep playing to see what comes next.
So now we'll talk a little bit about the continue system that we just mentioned.
In Dead Man Cry 5, you have a couple of different options when you die in battle.
You can use a gold orb if you want, and that'll bring you back.
But we also gave players the option to actually use red orbs this time.
And we very specifically made sure to, again,
take that non-binary approach with this design.
So that there were three different amounts of orbs
that you could spend, and then amounts of life and whatnot
that you could get back when you revive.
When a game is over, the user is the one who is most stressed.
So if you give a new, bigger stress,
the user will stop trying, so we took this approach.
We did this because we realized that players
feel the most stress.
when they get a game over.
And we don't want them to feel any more stress beyond that
because that is certainly going to be plenty of reason to quit playing the game.
So we give players the chance to choose themselves here.
They can say, OK, I'm going to bet on myself.
I think I can beat this enemy now with this much life left,
so I'm not spending any more orbs than I absolutely need to.
YUSUKE USTUNOMIYA And ideally what happens then is,
if they get a game over after that, well, it was their decision.
They bet on themselves and they lost that bet.
So they hopefully don't blame the game.
They blame themselves for not quite measuring up their own ability.
I think it's important to have the feeling of hitting your face, not the controller or game console.
That's all. Thank you very much.
While we're doing Q&A here, how are we doing on time?
Let's see here.
All right, we've got seven minutes or so.
We'll just keep using the room until people kick us out,
I guess.
And then if anybody has anything else,
or if anybody wants Ito-san to sign anything,
we could probably go out into the hallway.
In the meantime, during the Q&A, we
had this video that we made that we would show internally
for different events.
approval meetings, green light meetings, and that kind of stuff to kind of show how the game's going,
maybe a first party, and we thought it'd be really fun to kind of show that in the background here
as we're doing Q&A. So with that being said, Kyoko, you're better at interpreting than I am.
Okay, we have people lined up. Let's get to it. Okay, hello. When you are designing a system
and you have a certain objective that you want to achieve, but your system is too complicated
and takes too long to complete, how do you go about pairing that down to achieve your objective?
So the question then is, when we have a system that we're trying to implement, we expect that
we have a specific way that we want to implement it, and it turns out that it's not, it's going
to be too complex to actually implement it that way, how do we then pair it down the right way,
right? Actually, I mean more for the, it's too complex for the player, it will, and it's too
drawn out in gameplay. Okay.
So it's too complex for the player to turn on and out of gameplay.
So for the player then, we want to adjust this system.
Yes. How do we cut it down?
What is the purpose of the game?
The purpose and means are like a tree.
There are ways to achieve your goal.
I don't think it's a problem if the means become your goal.
But if you are conscious of the fact that it becomes a fine tree,
What do you want the player to do next?
How do you want them to feel?
What do you want them to do?
This is called reverse engineering.
If you go back to what the user thinks at that moment,
you can go back to a bigger goal and simply reverse the calculation.
Was it difficult?
It might have been difficult.
Good luck.
So, yeah, we were talking...
Oh, someone asked a question.
So yeah, we were talking earlier about the goals and the steps
and how to get to that.
And there's not always just one solution or one answer to it.
So what we do is we sort of map out the trees, the branches,
on how we can get there.
But like we said at the very top,
we use this sort of reverse engineering tactic
of thinking about how the user is going to experience
and what we want them to feel.
And when we see that big picture and we sort of land on or nail on that idea of
this is how we want them to feel and get to it, then it actually becomes a lot
more simpler and we're able to simplify it into the system.
Thank you.
Who's next?
We'll go left to right.
Okay.
All right, so a lot of things that we see with Delta Blade Cry as a series,
you know, Dragon's Dogma, is that these games have a lot of after content.
Like, you know, in three you could play as Vergil, in four you could play as Vergil,
you could play as Trish and Lady.
And as games get more expensive and high fidelity...
Has this posed problems in production? Because in 5, you know, we don't, like you had just mentioned, we don't see
Nero's devil trigger until the end of the game. But this makes your next playthrough on Son of Sparta potentially something completely different.
You have the devil bringer,
the entire game now. There's new enemies and what's surprising the most about this new boss moves.
And that there's this whole new level of the game. The essentially the entire experience is redesigned.
for a post 15 hour experience. So in this new industry, well not new industry, but you know
as games get more and more expensive, how did that affect your design philosophies or how did that
affect design in general? So the question then is how do we take into account the idea that we were
going to have all of this post game content, post game content, either way, basically that
we were going to have new stuff.
that the players would be able to do, new content that players would be able to experience
after you've beaten the game once, right?
Right.
Question in Japanese
So, in my case, all the content, even post-release, that's already planned out from the very,
very beginning.
And so it's already in the planning stages of the planning document.
And it comes down to what timing we're gonna be able to release it.
And there's sort of a cycle or pattern to that.
So it's all very much a calculated effort.
From the very beginning, we have a roadmap, and we kind of slot that in.
I even take into consideration, if we run out of time,
this is what's gonna happen.
That is even included in our planning from the very beginning.
And if I can elaborate on that a little bit, for DMC5,
I mean, this goes back specifically to that retreat
that we showed you guys the picture of.
It was at that retreat that we kind of laid out
the foundation for what this project was gonna be.
And also, DMC5 being a DMC game, there are expectations.
There are expectations that people are gonna be able
to have new experiences on their playthroughs
after the first playthrough.
So Itsuno-san totally had that in mind from the beginning
in terms of this is all the content
that needs to be in this game.
Right, thank you.
Cool.
Maybe one more until they kick us out, like Matt said.
OK, hi.
My question is about technique.
Devil May Cry games are really known for their really deep
combat systems.
And so my question is whether Itsuno-san
is aware of the ongoing conversation
around the changes from DMC4 with regards to DMC5 inertia?
And what he thinks about those unintended advanced player
techniques like guard flying?
OK, so you're curious to hear very specifically from Sun's opinion on the idea that inertia has been kind of changed since DMC4.
And we've changed it for what in DMC5 we do it a different way, right?
There's inertia doesn't necessarily show up in the same moves that you would expect.
So is he aware of that discussion that players are having on the Internet?
Yeah. And how like as a designer, you sort of approach those ideas of.
players finding these sort of edges of a system.
OK.
Japanese overlapping dialogue
check it and if it's interesting, we'll adopt it.
This is a tradition in Capcom games.
So even if we find bugs,
if it makes sense, and action-wise,
we feel like we can keep it in,
we'll be like, okay, well, this makes sense and it works,
so let's keep it in.
We go through a very thorough, obviously, quality control and check process,
but...
Amongst our, I think he meant dev team staff,
we have top, top players.
So we're very, very thorough with the checking.
But even with that, if we find something
that actually works, then we have done that,
not just in Devil May Cry,
but we have sort of a tradition at Capcom
that we'll wing it, we'll put it in there if it works.
And I'll elaborate on this one too.
Devil May Cry 1 is famous for really starting from a bug.
The idea that you could launch the enemy into the air
and then juggle them with these moves.
So we've had different instances like that
in Devil May Cry games and Capcom games throughout time.
For the momentum that you're talking about specifically,
our designers, obviously they play the heck out
of all the different Devil May Cry games
before we even start working on DMC5.
They very specifically implement these systems with a reason.
So you're talking about momentum, right?
You're talking about how Nero, for instance, Nero can have certain moves where he can keep
that momentum even after he does enemy step, right?
Well, our designers decided that they didn't want that to happen because they want to give
players, the players, more choice when doing that enemy step.
If you have that momentum and you do the enemy step,
OK, now you're forced to go in that direction.
But by taking that away, now the player can jump up.
They can jump straight.
They can jump back.
They can jump forward.
And they wanted to give players choice.
So that's specifically for this instance,
that's what we had in mind.
Done?
Yeah.
You're giving me the sign.
OK.
So yeah, we can go outside.
And again, if anybody wants to have Itsuno-san sign anything,
our lovely brand manager Charlene might have some pins for people.
Woo!
Thanks a lot.
Thank you.
Thank you all.
Hideaki Itsuno is back!