So this is the art of first-person animation.
My name is David Helsby.
I'm a senior animator at Bungie Studios,
and I've been there for about six years.
My game credits at Bungie are Halo Reach and now Destiny
and subsequent DLCs.
And yeah.
So I want to start out by asking you a question.
And that is, what makes a Bungie game feel like a Bungie game?
Well, a lot goes into creating the first person experience,
but first person is something that's
going to affect how the game plays and feels
on a moment-to-moment basis.
And many of you may not even notice it if it's done right.
So this talk is going to be split up into three parts.
So first we're going to talk about supporting
the goals of sandbox design.
Secondly, we're going to talk about making first-person content that feels good.
And what does feels good mean, really?
I'm going to talk about that later.
And finally, I'm going to talk to you about how to keep from killing yourself in the process of making a game.
And for all of you game developers out there, I'm sure you know what I'm talking about.
So, what is first-person animation?
Well, first-person animation is just the animation, it's the movement of your avatar from your
perspective as a player, including the player camera.
So all that motion you see, I mean, some designers have really told me that this is the most
important animation in a first-person shooter, and whether you believe that or not, doing
this content well is something that's definitely going to help the playability of the game,
and more importantly, the replayability of your game.
So.
Let's get started. Supporting the goals of sandbox design.
Now, design and art don't always see eye to eye.
Art wants to make an amazing player attack
that has like three seconds of anticipation,
while design wants an attack that hits one frame after the player hits the button.
Well, to build a new IP of Bungie,
I really needed to know how to best support
the goals of sandbox design and build enough trust
to try and push the artistic side of Destiny's first person
experience forward.
So we came up with a set of design directives
for first person we called Design Pillars.
So this is my first talk that I'm giving at GDC.
And when you're putting a talk like this together,
you want to sound really prepared
and you want to sound like you know what you're doing, right?
And so when I, in my first incarnation of this talk,
I was gonna say, yeah, you know,
we made these design pillars,
and we made them at the beginning of the project,
and then we just followed that,
and everything went super cool, right?
And I gave this, I gave this kind of a,
this first talk to one of our sandbox director,
and he's like, he's like, what are you doing?
He's like, tell the truth.
And I was like, alright.
So the truth is, we came up with these
these pillars of first-person design, like, after the project was finished.
I sat down with it, and I'm like, what do we really do here? What's important?
He's like, oh, okay, yeah, you know, we did this and this, and I'm like, alright, cool.
Now, for the next game, we'll know.
So, here are our pillars.
And you guys get them for free, you don't have to go through the pain we went through.
The first one is just immediate feedback from the player controller input.
And that just means like you hit a button and you get an action.
And if you think about it, your brain's already told you what you want to do.
So if you hit the button, you don't get an immediate response.
It feels wrong. It feels like there's a disconnect between you and the game.
So the minute that button gets pushed,
you want to start seeing motion on the screen, like immediately.
Secondly is the preservation of motion between actions.
It just means everything has to flow smoothly
from one motion to the other.
And we've gotten past the point where we can do a motion,
it comes back to an idle and hits a wall,
and then you do another motion.
You need to be able to design animations
that chain together effectively.
So the third one is the player should have visceral satisfaction from your animation.
Now this doesn't mean like, oh, make something cool, make a cool reload.
This means think about the player, think about each thing as a player experience.
And that means like, if I'm going to make like a really cool melee or reload,
I need design and sound and effects all on board,
because if we're all not working toward the same goal,
toward the same player experience, it's not going to be as good as it could be.
Four is, motion should serve to ground the player to the world.
Now, first person is really an interactive experience,
or an immersive experience.
So you should really feel like, you should feel physical.
You should feel like there's a body behind the camera.
And finally, this is one that I thought was really interesting and it didn't come on until very late.
At least, my true understanding of it, which is no speed bumps.
And that just means we don't want to take control away from the player or slow him down in the sandbox as much as possible.
And like, analogy of that is like, you're, you've got a really fast car. You've been given like a Ferrari.
The last thing you want to do is go for a speed bump.
You want to be on a straightaway. That car is meant to be driven fast, so drive it fast.
So, this is the last time I'm gonna assault you guys with a wall of text. I promise.
So, but I will be mentioning some of these things, you know, as the talk goes on.
But I boiled them down to like two main principles.
And one is support fast, fun, responsive gameplay.
And two, make it feel like a body, your body is behind the camera. Make it feel physical.
Now this is, this is the hard part, because trying to do both of these, both of these
things at the same time can sometimes...
seem impossible, but there's where the challenge and the fun comes in.
Sort of.
So,
let's move on to, now that we've talked about design principles and
what we want to do and how we want to do it, let's talk about
how to make first-person content that feels good.
What does feels good mean?
Well first, I mean we've gotten some information already.
We want to support first person that supports this fast, fun,
and responsive gameplay.
And we want to make it feel like there's
a body behind the camera, something that feels physical.
But like the last thing, the last piece of information
is, don't get in the way of the player's gameplay experience.
Don't get in the way of their fun.
Your content is not more important than the player's fun.
And that's one of the main things
to remember about making first person animation.
So, this is what Destiny looks like without any first-person animation.
And this is the same player presets, everything exactly the same,
except you're not getting the visual feedback from first-person.
And it feels like you're just kind of a floating camera inhabiting the world.
It doesn't feel like there's any person behind the screen.
So, we want to change that.
We want to start drawing you into our world.
So, the first thing we need to do before we even start animating is we need a character.
So let's just look at Bungie's player character.
Our player character is actually two characters in one.
The first one is the third person player,
which you see when your buddies are running around.
You see them in the open world.
Or you see yourself when you do like a super animation.
And then we have the first person player, which
is derived from the third person player.
And that's just your arms, a player camera, a support
object, and a weapon.
And this is the stuff that you're going to actually see
from your player view on your screen.
Well, when we put these together,
you have your actual player character.
So you have your first person arms and rig basically
sitting on top of the third person rig.
And we basically make all of the third person geometry
above the waist non-renderable from the first person camera.
And because of that.
If you ever wondered, like, this is what the first person character, what your player character
actually looks like.
That's why you can actually see the feet in a Bungie game, because you're actually viewing
the third person animation set.
So, now we got a character.
But where are we gonna animate it?
Like, we need to understand, like, how to, how to compose art on this kind of canvas,
which is your, your screen, your TV, or your monitor.
So let's talk about Bungie's screen space.
So this is a view of Destiny's first-person screen.
And it looks a lot like a lot of first-person
shooters out there.
And as you can see, we basically have a really good representation of what's called one-point perspective.
And that's basically these disappearing perspective lines all converging on one point in the screen.
So, and that's, in most first-person shooters, that's like directly in the middle of the screen.
But Bungie does something a little bit different, and we have since Halo 2.
we're actually lowering the reticle and by doing that we're actually giving you
this
uh...
like peripheral vision that are vision that you're just kind of wherever in the
peripheral of your vision
that uh...
that actually kind of opens up the world.
It makes the world seem larger and more expansive.
And for me, like, I, like, if I, even if I look out on you guys,
I see, like, this, this box that I can, that I,
where I can actually see stuff very clearly.
But then there's all this other information, like, on the top
and on the sides that I'm aware of,
but, but is not perfectly clear in my vision.
So, this actually makes it, I mean, for me, this,
this makes it feel like it's a little bit more of an immersive, um,
a real life view of how you would be viewing a world.
So, we have our screen space and we kind of know what it is and how to pose it on there.
So let's put a gun on there.
And basically like...
We'll go back to that one-point perspective again, and this may seem like a very rudimentary
thing to suggest, but taking a little extra time to actually pay attention to that one-point
perspective and find those disappearing lines and actually line up every single line on
your weapon.
or first-person character, so they converge toward that one-point perspective,
it makes it actually feel like, even though these two things are different,
like you have this world that's being rendered, and then you have this character that you're looking at,
it makes it feel like it's part of that world, as opposed to just window dressing that's sitting on top.
And by just taking that little extra step, it just makes it...
you're going to actually build a foundation for your first-person animation
that's just going to feel better, more immersive and right.
And I've done a lot of first-person animation where I didn't take this step.
And there was always something just kind of missing from it.
And this is what it was.
So now we're going to start animating in first-person.
And I thought it'd be interesting to actually show you
what, where, this space that you're actually animating in.
So this is a representation of first-person animation space.
And as you'll see, it's a very small box.
It's very distorted by an extreme field of view,
and nothing matters outside of that box.
Now that sounds actually pretty depressing.
But it's actually like, again, where
kind of the challenge comes in.
So now we've got this gun on screen.
We need to start adding something to it
to actually give it some life.
So let's talk about adding animated overlays
to your weapon.
So if we just got the gun on the screen,
this is what it's gonna look like.
These are just base animations.
So it's a little better than having no first person
on there at all, but still it just looks like
a piece of geometry sticking out of your screen.
It's like, it's not giving me any feeling of physicality
or connection to the world.
Well, this is a problem and I really wanted
to solve this for Destiny.
I kind of went looking for like where can I get information from
from our game to actually start plugging back into our
into our first-person animations and
it was really obvious like these
this third-person player was actually giving us all the information we really
needed. It was giving us pitch, it was giving us yaw, it was giving us this
directionality, speed, everything
that I might want to like actually
you know bring into first person to actually give it
that feeling of physicality to drive these overlay animations.
I made these animations, like these look poses,
these jump animation overlays,
and these lands. And I started plugging all these animations
into the first person. And this is what it looks like again,
just base animations only, just kind of the
gun just kind of static, sticking out of screen.
And now, we'll see the base animations with the animated overlays.
Now, it's starting to feel like a little bit more physical.
It's starting to feel reactive, and that's what I want.
I want, like every time you move that controller around,
every time you push that jump button, or land,
I want you to feel like you're actually in the game.
Like it's actually, you're actually behind that camera.
I want it to feel physical.
And now it's starting to get there.
And this, by the way, this...
This sounds simple, but like it's one of those things that
it just took forever.
Because it's getting all these animations to all work
together, sometimes all at once, and
blending them off and on.
It was just like a really painstaking process.
So now we're like half done.
So with like getting the first person character kind of
feeling right.
But now like we have to start animating things like actions,
like reloads and melees and all that stuff.
So.
Before we start animating, I always think about
what's the most important thing in terms of animation, especially in games.
For me, the first thing is posing
before anything else. The poses have to read and they have to
feel right. So I needed information
in that first-person game space as to
how to pose this stuff.
We already have some information that we've gotten from the screen space that I talked
about earlier.
We have this peripheral vision, which is this blue bar.
It's on the side and on the top.
And basically...
you don't want to pose or do any of your player actions or interaction in that space.
The reason is, it's a vision that you're aware of, but you're not actually focusing on it.
If there was something right here, I could actually turn to look at it.
But because we're in the first person shooter, you don't have the option to do that.
So you want to make sure that you don't pose things in that area.
The second thing...
which is even more important, is this red strip.
And I'm calling that the combat corridor.
And I call it that because that's where your enemies are
going to be coming from, usually right straight at you.
Or you're going to be coming at them.
You're going to be aiming your gun.
And you want to make sure that you don't block that, really
under most circumstances, just because, well, I'll give you
guys an example.
How many times have you been playing a first person shooter?
And you're doing pretty well.
You go to reload your gun and
all of a sudden you get killed, like out of nowhere.
Because you didn't see the guy in front of you,
because the reload was actually blocking your view.
Like, I hate that.
Everybody hates that.
You're like, you're actually, your content is actually
getting in the way of the player's fun,
or player's experience.
So.
What other information can we get from posing?
Well, something else that I learned is that the eye travels radially around that reticle,
like around that aiming reticle.
And that is actually the most important, you know, space on screen, which is to basically
like, it's basically where your eye is always looking.
That little circle right there, you're going to move your camera around, or your player
around so you can view things in that particular space.
and in that radius.
So how do you like actually support that radius
with your posing?
What can be done really overtly, like I did with this warlock melee.
Like the thumb and the forefinger are actually creating kind of like a frame for this
radius that we're looking around. And in this way, like
not only can you support, not only can you do like cool actions, but within those actions
you can actually frame
like what the player is actually looking at. So you're actually helping them look at this
really important part of the screen.
And this can be done in less overt ways,
like this knife melee.
or even this reload.
And it's just a way of like using your animation to focus the player's attention
to where they already really want to look.
So that's two. I like to do three, so
there's one more that I find is really important.
So in this grenade throw, and in a lot of our actions,
we'll have this moment where
you're actually like holding a part of the body on the screen.
just for a moment. Maybe like, you know, like seven to ten frames or something like that.
And this is a grenade throw. So if I was actually throwing something in real life, I would be
like throwing it and I would barely see my arm, like come through my field of vision
and then it would go off.
Because I have this body awareness, my brain has told my body what to do,
and I'm aware of where my arm is all the time,
I don't need to actually see it.
But in first person, really the only information that you have about your character,
this body behind the screen, is the visual information that we're giving.
So we kind of came up with the idea of just kind of like keeping that elbow on screen
just for a little bit longer because those poses are what is actually going to read to
the player.
Like, there's only maybe three poses that are three frames of animation where it's actually
going through the screen.
This elbow is actually what's going to read and tell you what you actually just did.
So, it's difficult to, like, continue to talk about animation without
actually going into a real example. So, I want to talk about an animation that
was really hard for me to get right, and one that ended up being really successful
that people ended up liking. So, I want to talk about animating in a knife melee.
So, this was like the knife melee that the hunter class in Destiny could use to
stab people, like, as a melee.
And this is what it looks like.
So, how do we do it?
Well, again, let's start with poses.
And right now, let's start with the key poses.
And for you non-animators out there, key poses
are those main poses or those main pieces of information
in an animation that kind of describes the action.
So I can get pretty much the entire timing of an action
and what that action is going to be by really defining
my key poses.
So where do we start?
Well, this is the idle pose.
And we don't want to start here, because you actually
already have an idle pose on screen.
So you don't need to spend these valuable frames actually
showing it again.
Where I would actually start, where I started with the knife
melee, was I started here.
And that pose, that idle pose that I showed you before, that
would actually, in my timeline, probably be on frame
negative two or something like that.
But this is the first frame of, or starting pose of the animation.
There's a lot of information here.
So, the first thing I'm doing is I'm pulling this gun off screen.
I want to have that gun completely off screen by the time I, you know,
by the time I've hit something.
And I want to do that because this animation is something that's going to be reused over all weapon sets.
And I'll talk to you a little bit more about why we did that later.
The second thing is I'm actually bringing up this knife in a line of action,
like to go to the anticipation of the animation.
So secondly, it's frame three.
This is the anticipation pose.
Now, it used to be that...
Bungie games, all melees hit on frame three.
And that's just like, because you can't,
that's how, three frames is what it takes
to really draw a line on screen from like,
to start from, to where you're going.
And actually like, it was thought of as like,
that is law at Bungie, like that's what you do.
Like, it's a three frame melee.
But we were able to kind of push this,
and push the physicality of this a little bit more.
It was two frames.
we were actually hitting on frame five. Those two frames, like, actually just gave it a
little bit more, more weight.
So, frame five, that's the hit pose.
So in this frame, we're actually going to hit right at the center of the targeting reticle.
By doing this, I'm actually breaking one of my own rules that I just talked to you about,
which is blocking that combat corridor.
But to really make a melee feel, in first person, really feel effective,
it has to actually hit through that reticle, that contact corridor.
And it actually has to almost stay there just for a little bit,
just to give people the idea that, or the communication that they actually hit there.
Next, you know, the knife mainly has a hit and then it has a pull free.
So that pull free is going to take about five frames including the overshoot and then it's
a moving hold for about seven frames.
And this is where I was talking to you guys about.
those poses that we keep on screen to kind of show you that extra bit of physicality
or that you've actually done something. This is that pose and for me like I feel like this is one
of the most important poses in the animation that you're going to do because it's probably
the pose that people are going to most recognize or see when they're doing the action.
And finally, like, frame 25. This is the, this is where it starts transitioning off-screen.
And basically, like, this is a, that, it's a moving hold to off-screen for about seven frames.
And for you animators out here, this is what this animation actually looks like on the timeline.
So.
Let's take a look at that all blocked out.
Now it looks pretty, it doesn't look great right now, but I've actually got all the information
that I need to like start building this into an animation that feels good in gameplay and
also like kind of feels right physically.
So that's, that's the polished version of this animation.
So there's one more piece to this.
One more thing that's going to actually kind of...
up your game and kind of make it feel a little bit, make this animation feel a little bit more
physical and a little bit more immersive. And that's, that's the player camera.
And the camera is, is one of those things that can actually be,
can be really cool. It can kind of add that extra bit of physicality or
it can be really destructive to your game. And, like,
I don't know if a lot of you, if a lot of you have played games that
have made you motion sick or, or you're, or you get motion sick, but like.
it's one of the reasons why you really have to be careful with camera animation
because
even if you're like, even if your cam motion is going to make only ten percent of the
population sick
if you're selling a million copies of your game
well you've just like, you've just lost a hundred thousand people that
will put your game down, never play it again and probably never play one of your
sequels. So
it's definitely something that you have to pay attention to.
Now this next clip I'm going to show you, if you guys have any motion sickness, you might want to look away.
But basically this is just a head-mounted camera, a GoPro on a guy's head, just running straight down a track, running in a straight line.
So this is actually where I started when I was kind of trying to figure out what the camera or what the eyes were doing, what the camera was doing.
And I was like, oh, okay. I'll just animate that.
But, you know, I actually tried, you know.
And I, you know, I had to walk around, like, all the time with this GoPro camera and try and figure out what things look like from a first-person view.
And...
I quickly realized that it wasn't, that's not actually how you see the world.
It's not, it's not right.
And it's, it's because we have, as, as human beings, an image stabilization system.
Like a lot of you probably know technology with cameras, with these new cameras that
have image stabilization.
Well, we have like a biological version, and that's called the vestibulosystem.
Feel free to correct me, I'm not a doctor, so if I've gotten it wrong you can tell me after the talk.
The vestibular system has two parts.
One is the vestibular-ocular reflex.
Now this is basically a fancy way to say, to basically say like,
if I'm looking at you guys out here, and I turn my head,
my eyes are going to turn in the opposite direction of that turn
to like keep my eyes focused on what I want to look at.
And this happens very fast, like it happens almost immediately,
to like stabilize an image that you're trying to look at.
But your eye actually gets that information from the inner ear.
So...
the inner ear is like kind of an accelerometer. It actually like as you
as you move around and tilt around it actually tells
your eye and your brain like what's actually happening.
So as I move around like it allows my eye to keep up and continue to
look at that thing that's it's interesting to me
that I'm looking at.
And like it can be, it's, if you look at this picture right here of Floyd Mayweather,
he's a really good example. He's doing, especially since we're talking about melees,
like he's punching this guy and he's, it's a really violent action, but his eyes are keeping up
with the turn of his head and body and he's continuing to look at his target, which is exactly where his,
where his glove is hitting. So, like a really simple way of thinking about this stuff is.
balance equals alignment.
And that's like that feeling,
it's basically like the balance of seeing motion
and feeling motion.
If those things are in alignment,
then you're healthy.
It feels right and you feel in alignment.
But if you feel emotion and don't see it,
or if you see emotion and don't feel it,
you're gonna get motion sickness.
And a lot of you have probably felt that, like, if you've ever been sitting in the backseat of a car
and you read, you're reading, a lot of you might have felt like that motion sickness.
And that's because your body is feeling the motion of the car, but you're not actually,
you don't have any visual reference of that.
So your eyes and your inner ear are actually out of balance there.
And it's the same, it's the inverse with games.
Like, if you're seeing a lot of motion on screen,
but your body's not feeling it,
then it's also gonna cause that motion sickness.
So, a good way to, so, like, what do I do with that?
Like, I know that now.
So I know that a lot of motion on camera
or the wrong motion on camera is gonna make me sick.
So I kinda wanted to see, like, what motion was right.
So.
If you rotate a camera, and I'm not talking about like if you're rotating your head, but if you actually rotate a camera around, it's going to create
these large motions in the world and on the horizon line and especially on objects far away.
So, and that can, and especially like camera roll in that way can be very disorienting. It's like a lot of motion, especially when you're talking about making motion for the, motion on top, on the, on the player camera
in like an open world.
So, camera translation is actually kind of the opposite.
It creates large motions up close,
and then it kind of trails off
as it goes off into the distance.
So, if you're looking at something up close,
like a player or an NPC or a combatant, or just anything,
you're gonna see that large motion,
but then in the world,
it's gonna kind of trail off after a little bit,
or it seems to.
So, I kind of decided that,
in making camera animation for these melees,
that I wanted to do it with mostly translation.
And we did do a little bit of, like, rotation on the camera to kind of mimic what was happening up close
with that translation and kind of, so we could see a little bit of movement in the distance, but then
because of some game optimization that we did kind of at the end of the project, like, those small
decimals of numbers got stripped out.
So, wah-wah, you know, next game.
So.
So I, I, I know, like, I know I want to use translation, but, like, I want more information
of how to use this translation. So, in most of the, in most actions, in most
violent actions, like, that, you know, that have intent, like, the head leads the action.
And that can actually be seen on the slow motion of this, this boxer hitting this guy.
So if we really slow this down.
This is pretty cool.
When the boxer's setting up, he's actually setting up
with his anticipation.
So as he sets up here, his head's gonna go to the left
and actually anticipate with it.
Then as he starts to throw it,
his head's actually going to lead that action or that hit.
It's gonna lead his arm.
And then as the boxer is about to make contact with his target,
and it's about to cross the center line of his body,
the head actually starts to kind of reverse that direction
and go in the opposite way.
And this is just because his body's trying to keep on balance.
And so it's just kind of like his head's moving, then his arm,
and then his head kind of starts to go in the other direction.
And then finally, like, as that head goes in the other direction, it kind of like, boof,
like does a little shake to kind of get back over the center of the body and maintain that
center of mass so he doesn't fall over.
So like, a lot of times, like, this happens really like imperceptibly.
You don't see it unless you look really close.
I had this really cool, um...
a video of Mike Tyson doing this, and it was totally apparent, but it was like VHS quality,
so I didn't figure you guys would want to see that.
So here it is one more time.
So now I'm going to show you the camera path that I kind of created with that same principle
on that knife melee.
So here's the slow motion version of that.
And as you can see, the player camera is going to actually lead the action into that hit
and then lead the action on the pull out.
And it might just be like by one frame, but it really makes a difference.
As you can see there, like basically I'm
creating a grid inside Maya within the first person view.
And I'm doing that because I want to just see what's happening in my first person view
while I do my camera animation.
And secondly, I actually showed you guys the finished animation of the knife melee first.
And that's because I actually want to finish that animation and finish those arcs before I even start getting into the player camera.
That's because I just want to concentrate on one thing at a time and I don't want the player
camera animation to actually be destructive to the
the animation itself. I just do that by basically
finishing the animation and then putting all of the
player control flags in camera space. So
as I move that camera around, like
the animation isn't affected.
And then at the very end I can start making slight
like offsets to the camera and the character.
So, from first person, this is what my final camera animation looks like.
And I'm not going crazy with it, it's just enough to make you feel like that head is leading the action and the body,
you feel that physicality of the knife hitting and then getting pulled out, and then that motion trailing off.
So let's see this motion through the development.
And finally, with camera animation.
Alright, so that was like a good representation of kind of how we develop like a motion for first person, like in, for Destiny.
But, like the final piece of this is,
how do you keep from killing yourself in the process?
So why is there a plate of delicious waffles on the screen?
Well, there's actually a story behind this.
When I was working on a previous title, Halo Reach,
I had a producer come to me and say,
yeah, so we've got this beta build at 6 o'clock in the morning that we're cutting, and...
the designers want to change the timing of the grenade throw.
I was like, okay. And he's like, so you need to do that
before this date, before six o'clock in the morning.
And I was like, okay, well it's seven o'clock at night.
I guess I can do that.
But unfortunately, like...
it, it, like, in this game that we're making,
each gun had its own unique grenade throw.
So it was like 22 guns in our,
in this, in this thing, so then,
then there was like three different grenade throws on the third person character.
So, I had to like change like 25 animations,
like before this date, before this, this,
this cutoff time of 6 AM where we're gonna send this beta in.
Like...
for some reason, he said,
he said, you know what,
I'm gonna make you a plate of waffles
if you do this for me.
And for some reason,
I thought that was a really good trade off.
But really the point of the whole story is
the waffles are not worth it.
The waffles are not worth it.
So this really affected me.
This was a really painful experience, and so I wanted to figure out, as we like move
forward into this, building this new IP, like how I could figure out like not to do this
anymore or not to have this happen to anybody else.
So there was about, there's three really cool things we came up with.
The first one is called an agnostic animation.
This is basically just a non-weapon specific animation.
And these are animations that we shared over all weapon sets.
And so basically the point is we made this animation,
we authored it on the rifle pose,
and then basically put the hand in kind of a neutral pose,
the gun went off screen, you do the grenade throw,
and then we use the ready animation to bring the weapon back up,
back so it can fire again.
So just to illustrate that, here's the rocket launcher animation set.
And there was a grenade throw.
It kind of popped a little bit.
Oh, well.
But basically, that grenade throw was used on everything.
It was used for whether you're holding a pistol, a rifle, a
machine gun, or a rocket launcher.
And by doing that, if a designer came to me then, he
said, yeah, I want you to change this animation.
And you've got this crazy deadline.
I'm like, sure.
It's one animation.
So instead of 25, which was great.
So, this is basically how it looked with the whole thing together.
Oh, well, I guess you don't get to see that, sorry.
Here it is.
And it actually worked. It blended pretty smoothly.
And I actually wasn't sure about that,
because I wanted to actually get that kind of opposing action,
where you would see that throw,
and you would see kind of that pull of the arm.
So I was really concerned that by not doing that,
we would kind of lose a little bit of physicality,
but it worked, and nobody complained.
So it didn't get in the way of the player experience.
So it was actually successful.
And it kept me from, you know, from many sleepless nights.
The second one was animation scaling.
Now, a lot of you animators out there, I'm sure,
like, you feel passionate about your work.
Like, you spend a lot of time on an animation.
You want it to be presented well.
Well, like, we didn't have the budget to, like,
just make animations at different speed.
Like, we needed to, like, we needed to, like,
not only, we were not only under a time crunch,
but we just didn't have the memory to make
all these different reloads, so.
So I made one reload, and they're like, yeah, we're
going to scale this up to, I don't know, 150%.
I was like, no.
That's my beautiful reload animation.
Don't do it.
Don't touch it.
They're like, that'll be fine.
I was like, oh my god, this is going to be terrible.
But you know what?
It was actually fine.
people actually liked it. They liked feeling that
that perk of
seeing an animation that actually, you know, happens a little bit faster. It
actually, like, added to their
visceral and... and visceral experience of the game and something they
enjoyed.
And I mean, let's face it.
A reload animation is a punishment
given to you by a designer.
So you fired your gun too many times.
You have to stop and reload this thing
and wait until you can fire again.
So as an animator, your whole job is to basically
make that as seamless and palatable as possible
by making this pretty animation.
Well, the actual act of speeding up that animation
ended up making it something that was even
better and more palatable.
Now this next one is something that may seem boring to you, but it was really exciting for me.
So I actually got brought into Bungie because, as a contractor, because the designers tried to, were going to change the FOV of the game.
And FOV is short for field of view. So if you have like a high field of view, like, you know, in the 70s or something like that, that means you have a wider aperture that you're actually being able to see the game.
That's good for first-person shooters because you want to be able to see as much as possible
while you're actually, you know, of what's happening around you.
A smaller number means a narrower field of view.
So they were adjusting this slightly.
But even a small adjustment to field of view can actually start to affect like...
how, like what's happening with your first-person content.
Like, they changed it a little bit,
and you can start seeing inside of meshes,
or things start to, you know, travel,
seem like they're getting smaller,
and seem a little bit weaker.
So, they brought me in to,
because they were changing it,
and they, they wanted me to basically
reposition all the animations,
so they look good again.
Well, I knew that...
if they did that like when we're trying to make this giant
new IP that it would be really painful because
their designers are always messing around with stuff
and making artists lives miserable.
No, I'm just kidding.
No, they're, I mean, they need to be able to iterate
and change things as much as we do as artists.
So we did something that was actually pretty cool.
So the world camera FOV was 72,
and the designers kind of were changing that back and forth
like through the entire development of Destiny.
But the FP arms and weapon FOV was 77.
And that remained locked from the beginning of the project
until the end.
Because we figured out exactly where
we wanted to frame that weapon and where it looked the best.
And then we didn't want to change that.
So by doing this, by actually splitting up
the FOV between these two elements,
we were able to keep our.
we were able to keep moving forward with what we wanted to do,
as opposed to doing all this busy work of readjusting our content
based on experiments by design.
And also, alternately, design was able to do this without being destructive to our work.
So it was actually an incredible time-saving thing that we did.
So, besides the obvious, what do we get by not killing ourselves?
Obviously, we don't kill ourselves, but we get time.
And as game developers, we're constantly fighting against the clock, trying to make our deadlines.
But as artists, like, what you really need as an artist to make something good is you need time for experimentation.
and iteration. And that's how you make a good product. And that's
that's what artists are really there for. Like that's, and that's how to effectively
use an artist is actually give them time to do this. So if you can actually plan for,
you know, things that are gonna help this within your pre-production and production
process, it's actually gonna help your end product make a, make something that people
are really gonna respond to because the artist has had time to really polish it and make
it as good as possible.
So.
What do we, what do we talk about today?
We talked about a lot of stuff.
We talked about design principles.
We talked about the idle and the overlay animations.
Posing in first person.
Talked about animating the knife.
The camera.
And finally, how to keep from killing yourself.
But like,
really the main takeaway from this, this talk is...
that details matter and it's worth waiting to get it right.
This was a quote from Steve Jobs that really resonated with me because
like first-person animation is something that you just see constantly in front of
you all the time and
like no matter like what your schedule says like
if you want your game to feel good like it has to, this is one
element you have to spend time on. I would say like
that's a you know
lots of different disciplines within games.
Details do matter. It's worth researching. It's worth spending a little time to
experiment and iterate on your content and make it feel as good as possible.
And do we have sound?
And finally, like, this is
this is what we got, like, by kind of, by doing that, by
by kind of focusing on those details.
No sound.
There's a lot of cool music.
Oh.
Oh, I was too late.
No worries. No worries.
I promise you, it's much better with the music.
So this is a lot of the first person animation that we ended up with in Destiny.
So thank you very much.
I really wanted, I'm thankful you guys came to hear my talk.
I really wanted to give this because, like even for me,
like this stuff really isn't taught anywhere.
And I wanted to like, unless you're like part of a studio
that actually like has a tradition of doing
this type of animation, it's really hard to learn.
So I hope you guys got something out of it.
And I'll take questions now if you guys like.
So you did the melee for the hunter.
Did you also do the throwing knife animation?
Yeah.
Can you talk about how you made this thin little projectile
feel like something physical?
Like I throw it, and I feel that thud when it connects.
That's magic, thank you.
Yeah.
Yeah, I can definitely talk about that.
Basically, everything kind of comes from life.
So I would spend a lot of time trying to do that motion,
seeing what it would feel like, and also
seeing what it would look like from my vision.
And so I would kind of start there, you know what I mean?
And obviously that timing is something that wouldn't work in game,
but it like gave me some reference to how to actually do it.
And then it was basically like working with the designer to, you know,
define that timing in a way that would actually continue to still feel good to the player.
And finally, like I would actually, I would animate that knife like leaving the hand and
actually like spinning and traveling through space.
And then when, so when I was working with the designer on this, he actually took that
path or that rotation.
And actually the knife itself, as you release it,
that's just a prop object.
So that prop actually, we disappear that prop,
and then that becomes an in-game object that actually,
or a projectile that goes toward the target.
And by just kind of balancing the timing and the posing and physicality of that,
with working with the designer to get that to feel as good as possible,
that's kind of how we did it.
And I think it's all about one of those first principles I talked about,
which is to work together with other disciplines to make it feel good.
You know what I mean?
You can't do it in a vacuum.
It has to be a team effort.
So does that answer your question?
the designer applying dynamic positioning for the rotation
to make it feel like it's always going to.
I guess the question is, like, did the designer add any dynamic rotation to the knife to kind of make it feel right?
To be honest, like, I'm not exactly sure.
Like, you know, there are certain points when you just, like, when you work together and you,
and then there are certain points where you hand off to somebody with a different skill set
and they kind of push it that extra mile.
So he, that was Danny Bulla, he did a great job.
helping get that one finished.
So, yeah, thank you.
I had a couple of quick questions about the knife melee.
The one you started it, like the first frame was already up and ready.
Where was the knife on the frame before?
Is the knife always present on the first person mesh?
On the...
Oh, actually we like spawn that knife like on that first frame.
Really?
Yeah, and I tried a bunch of different stuff.
Like I tried, I was like, well maybe we can use blending
to make like a smoother transition or...
Or maybe, you know, like I want to start the hand off screen so it would be a little bit more believable.
But what I really found was like, it's such a violent action that like bringing that knife, like popping that knife up on screen,
like it wasn't something that people could read, like visibly.
It's just like, oh, you know, what actually read was the idea of that arc.
Because it's only five frames from the, you know, point of the beginning of the animation to the hit.
So you have like...
an incredibly short amount of time and your eye actually can't usually
track motion that fast so it was just like boom
and you know people believed it so it was
good and that took a lot of experimentation I wasn't sure what was
gonna work
the second thing was just
probably real quick uh... that you stabbed and you actually held it for five
frames
I see that there's a big effect hiding
the contact
was there is that all there is or is there is the enemy actually playing a
reaction to anchor them
to that stab
All the enemies play like actual reactions to the stab as well as like effects, you know,
making it feel like it's impactful and like it's adding to that physicality.
But it's not pinned, right? It's not actually like...
No, no, not exactly, no.
And basically like we have like a,
you have a cone of effect, you know,
going away from the character.
And I was actually really worried about that one
because you're actually hitting this point,
but it actually worked because as you,
because it starts up at the ear right here,
as you come through it like this arm actually kind of
takes up that whole cone.
So when it hits it actually feels, it feels right.
And there's actually some adjustment of the player
where the player will actually kind of suck.
to the combatant a little bit if you're actually on target when you activate the knife melee.
Cool, thanks.
Yeah, thank you.
Hi.
So, two questions.
One, in terms of the animation for first person and third person, are those the same animations
or do they go through some adjustments?
And the second question is just scheduling.
So how long did you have per animation?
per animation? Yeah, like the melee, how long did you have to work on that? Oh, okay. A
day, a year? Yeah. The animations on the third person player were like, also like, we thought
of them as chunks, like the first person reload and the third person reload were basically
an assignment handed out to one person. So, like when I got this knife stab, like I was
responsible for the third person knife stab too.
and, uh, like, they're actually separate animations.
So we try to, um, make sure that the timing is exactly the same on those,
on, on usually, like, on those, all those key pose elements.
Um, but they're, but they're separate.
Um, and like, we usually do, like...
I think, like a first person animation takes a little bit longer to do.
Like I would say, you know, that knife stab on the third person character, which was basically
like from the waist up, because it's a replacement animation on top of like a navigation set
or an idle.
That would take maybe like a day.
like a first-person animation like that just to get it right and because
you know you're going back and forth with designers and you're putting it in
play tests like
I would say something like that like all together might take you know
like a week
to get right or even longer you know like
there are times when like those animations just kept
coming back it's like wow
uh... one frame less
one frame more
I was like oh god
so so yeah it's it's kind of
I would say, yeah, it takes a week, but it's really like, who knows?
You know what I mean?
It's like, I would say it takes as long as it takes to get right.
And producers don't like to hear that.
But that's kind of the truth.
So thank you.
Hi.
My question is about the FOVs.
I noticed that you used two different FOVs
for the first person weapon hands and world.
My worry is that if you have some animation,
like maybe a little bit longer melee attack animation,
because the enemy and the weapons
are rendered in two different FOVs,
their position on screen might be a bit off.
How do you deal with this problem,
or you feel it doesn't matter at all?
I mean it definitely does matter and there is that problem.
We were able to kind of, I think when designers brought it down to 72, the world FOV, we were
definitely looking at how that FOV was affecting the combatants and other players.
When you actually were to see melees or up close attacks, how that would actually affect
the combat.
And I feel like they kind of...
they hit that threshold of like, okay, we can't go anymore,
otherwise it's gonna start to break down.
So it was basically just kind of like,
look at it and see if it was believable,
and then do that.
There wasn't as much science to it as you might think.
It was just like, that looks right.
Okay, cool.
Let's move on.
So it's mostly like experimenting
for the just right FOV angle.
Yeah, definitely.
And that's like most of it, is just
kind of seeing what looks right, seeing what feels right,
and then just doing that.
OK, cool.
Thank you.
I had a question to ask about the animation blending stuff.
So in the overlay animations, you
were talking about first person blending animations
for the movement stuff.
So could you describe a little of how easy
it was for you to preview those blends, adjusting them?
Did you have control over them, basically?
Over the, um, the, of those animations and how they blended, or?
Yeah, that kind of stuff.
Um, I mean, I had some control, um, based on, like, kind of some blending numbers that
we were able to apply to specific animations.
Um, but yeah, you know, basically it was kind of like, you know, I, okay, you know, these
two animations don't play well together, so I'll have to blend this one off.
while this one blends on at a certain point.
Well, at least you had full control.
Wasn't it like a designer had to do it?
Yeah, yeah.
The designers are basically like, well, you just
make it feel right.
And so I would just sit at my desk constantly
looking at the look screens and looking at the jumps
and be like, OK, that's a little bit off,
or that's not playing well with this particular overlay.
And just make slight adjustments to the animation
or that.
or the blend or the ramping on and off of the animations.
Cool, thank you.
Yeah, thank you.
I just have a quick question.
When animating the first person player
inside that camera frustum,
with all the weird perspective and all that going on,
are there any tips or techniques you used
as far as preventing the mesh penetration
and clipping planes and all that kind of stuff?
Yeah, I mean I basically kind of like I mean I use that kind of
combat corridor and peripheral vision thing and basically like I try and stay in those safe zones from from the standpoint of
That point of view and then from like the standpoint of like how the depth of that that area
I just kind of try and keep in mind that
when I'm doing an action or putting anything on screen in first person that
the farther away I get an element away from the camera, the smaller it's going to be.
And when you get an element farther away from the camera and it gets smaller, it feels weaker.
And then if it gets closer, in fact when it gets too close, then it starts to feel claustrophobic.
So just trying to like kind of find the...
find it within their, or find the best kind of depth
is really important.
And I'd say like that's,
that's kind of the guide that I use.
So you used a combination of kind of exaggerated poses
and kind of more close poses in order to kind of
tweak the scale of the objects with the animation?
Yeah, I mean, and it's not like.
me like saying, oh yeah, you know, you should do it this way.
And in fact, all this stuff, it's like,
this is like, this is what I tried and what seemed to work,
you know, and even like the camera rotation,
it's like, well.
yeah, just be aware of like what that does and not saying not to do it.
But yeah, it's just, it's basically just kind of experimentation and
first-person, you know, if you interview first-person animators, they're still
left out there. It's, I mean, you know it's just all kind of about feel.
Like you, you put something in there, you experiment with it and
sometimes it feels right and sometimes it feels right in Maya.
or in your in 3D Studio Max and then you get it in game and it just completely falls apart
and I'm not even sure why sometimes, but that seems to be kind of the way.
So it's just basically I'd say just develop a workflow that where you're continually getting
content in game and actually testing it in game.
That's the best way to go.
Thank you.
So that grenade thing kind of sound like a nightmare when you came up on the what's that the green?
Refactoring all the grenade animation sound like a nightmare. So I was wondering if you could have maybe
Separated the two arms on different tracks
So you could have just done the throw on different timing and then give that to the designers like as they wanted it and then
spend more time to get what you actually wanted on the right hand with the weapons?
Is something like that, do you think it's possible?
Yeah, in fact, I was actually, like, I really wanted to do that.
I wanted to, like, actually separate the rig.
So, like, I could do something on the left hand,
and do something else on the right hand, or, you know,
and kind of mix and match and put those together.
That would have, like, saved a lot of time and effort.
But it also required a lot of engineering work,
and a lot of work that was outside my department.
It's just one of those things that we didn't, we just didn't get to, or we didn't get to early enough in the development process to actually make it effective.
But I mean, yeah, it's a brilliant idea and we definitely want to try stuff like that in the future.
The agnostic idea seemed like a good solution as well. It seemed to be cool to blend those two.
Yeah, thank you. Like I said, I wasn't sure if it was going to work.
Yeah, it was great. Thanks.
Thank you.
Anyone else?
Well, thank you very much for coming. I'll be around for a little bit if you guys want to ask me any more questions.
Thank you.