So I'm Austin, and I'm here to talk about this game called Stray Gods, which has not come out yet, which makes this a pre-release post-mortem.
And we'll see how that goes, how much of what I say turns out to have been bullshit by the time it ships.
And joining me, as you can see here with a lovely asterisk, is Mr. Troy Baker.
So just to address the elephant in the room here.
Hello everybody.
I am disappointed because I was very much looking forward to spending my very first GDC with you in such a great way to be able to have a conversation like this.
For me,
The notion of a post-mortem is probably very pedestrian and banal to you guys.
It became a very novel concept to me once I started participating in games like Bioshock Infinite or The Last of Us or Second Son and studios started bringing me in and go, we just want to kind of post-mortem with you and what is it that we could have done better and just we have some notes for you as well.
And it became a part of the process that I loved the most.
So being able to
talk to you guys about the things that we learned, the mistakes that we made, and some of the accomplishments and the discoveries that we made through this process is a conversation I'm very, very excited to have with you in any way possible.
I think that's his way of inviting you to send tweets and things after the fact and give your unvarnished opinion of what we have here to share.
So yeah, long and short of it is, as you're probably aware, he's quite
consistently busy, principally as an actor, and some pre-existing work scheduled some things at the last minute that he desperately tried to move, but scheduling complexities being what they are, he was unable
to make it so I said okay well I'll tell you what let's jump on a zoom call and I'm basically going to say hey what do you think about this and then just record his answer and show you all that so he can still be quite present because this project is one where it's a musical and I am the kind of music director and composer slash co-composer depending on the section of it
and Troy became our kind of voice director and so he and I worked really really closely together for years on this thing and I really thought even though I'm assuming in fact show me by a show of hands who here is a composer primarily or exclusively
Okay, so as I suspected, it would be most of you, although I thought it was going to be a more overwhelming majority, so that's nice.
I like that.
Also, what that probably means to me is that a lot of you are sitting here going, he's not here, and you're looking and figuring out a way to...
I will not take it personally.
He's very dreamy, I get it.
Point being that because the GDC obviously here, the audio track and the world of game audio in general,
I think composers and sound designers get quite a lot of focus in what we do, but it's really quite an unsung hero in terms of how to work with and collaborate with voice actors and voice talent and that sort of thing.
And because a musical calls for such a strong overlap between your actors and the music, and for obvious reasons, the whole premise of pitching this talk together was that
he could speak to the idea of directing and what a lot of his thoughts I thought translated so beautifully as almost a metaphor for the way composers can collaborate both with the musicians that we hire and work with and help bring our scores to life, but also the ways that we collaborate with the people that bring us on, you know, game directors and audio directors and people like that.
So a lot of what he says I think is actually quite universal even though it's specific to this.
So real quick, let me give some background
on what this thing is because, again, this hasn't come out yet.
So I'm going to hopefully not say too much that I'm just assuming you know what I'm talking about.
I'll remind myself, no one here has played this game.
No one has any clue what I'm talking about.
Of course, it's just general state that I have to contend with in my conversations with people.
So it's kind of a wonderful little GDC fairy tale because five years ago, GDC 2018, which as a side note, the idea that 2018 was five years ago, I'm still wrapping my brain around.
but pandemic created this weird time horizon that it's like, you know, interstellar with seven years passing for one and five seconds for the other.
I have a game developer friend who called me up and said,
When we meet at GDC in a few weeks, this would have been like February or something of 2018, he calls me and says, I want you to pitch me a game.
Instead of me design a game and then ask if you'd be willing to write the score, what if you threw an idea at me and we thought about making that game?
So I, of course, showed up to GDC with a list of, like, 46 game pitches.
And one of them was, you know what would be amazing is my big passion in game music is interactive music design.
I really, really love exploring ways for the music to not just simply accompany the gameplay, but to become an interwoven part of the gameplay.
So I said, imagine that, but the gameplay is, in some way or another, a musical.
And he goes, oh, wow, I hate that idea.
But weirdly, I have a friend who's looking for collaborators on the premise of making an interactive musical.
And he's from Australia, and he's here at GDC for one more hour, and then he's going to fly home.
So I scramble to find this guy.
I literally sprint across the city in slow motion with rain.
And that was this time, actually.
meet up, the guy's name is Liam Essler and he was starting a company called Summerfall Studios with the idea being, what if we made a musical?
And the astonishing fairytaleness of it was that he was looking to set up this company in collaboration with David Gaider and Ellie Young without knowing who would write the music or anything.
You would think that they would have had that figured out before going to set up the company and quitting their prior jobs and things like that.
And so you'd be shit out of luck for someone in my position.
But somehow we met at the exact right moment.
It was amazing.
We hit it off.
We had this amazing hour before he then had to rush to the airport, fly home to Melbourne.
And so it was like, OK, let's do this.
So of course, the first question is, well, how is this going to manifest?
Because game mechanics are as numerous as stars in the sky.
So how do you define the way that music might interact with it?
The co-founder of this company, David Gaider, was the lead writer for quite a bit of the Dragon Age franchise and basically left BioWare in order to make this game and start this new independent company.
And so one of the ideas, the kind of joking pitch was, you know, what if we took the dialogue system of a game like Bioware and then got rid of all the other parts of Dragon Age and made that the game?
So it's very, very narrative and dialogue driven.
And because he had spent so many years developing these just absolute crazy labyrinthine branching dialogue systems with huge amounts of narrative implications and not just
what's behind door A, B, C, choose a line and then it funnels you right back.
But it's like the story actually evolves in a very branching kind of way.
We thought, okay, that's a great sort of jumping off point.
The game, Stray Gods, as it's now called, was originally called Chorus, and another game came out called Chorus.
So now we're called Stray Gods.
And it's actually a way better name.
I love this title.
The long and short of it, just to give a really quick synopsis on the story.
is this character that you see in the middle wearing the kind of black leather jacket is named Grace.
That's her player character.
And at the beginning, Grace essentially is accused of a murder.
She witnesses a murder.
She witnesses a death.
that's presumably caused by murder, and then she's told, you're the suspect.
And it turns out that the people accusing her are the remnants of the pantheon of Greek gods, who as it turns out are real and alive and kind of living in a shadowy existence in the modern world.
and one of the things that happens as part of the death of this character is she realizes that this character is the last of the muses, Calliope, and Calliope's sort of magical power is the ability to draw the truth out of people
through song.
And so she inadvertently, by mistake, it certainly absorbs this power.
And then the gods basically say to her, OK, so you have one week to prove your innocence or we will kill you.
So the game is sort of effectively a murder mystery.
And so it's like, OK, great.
Love it.
This was David's story pitch.
And so it was like, well, we need to start working out how this is going to go.
So we made some initial concepts
What we did is kind of create like a paint over.
This was just, let's create like a simulated UI, some really basic animations and just kind of see how it feels.
So I wrote what is effectively a linear piece of music, this is all again several years ago, where I kind of predetermined the idea of a branch and we developed this sort of simple, you can see this sort of trait based
UI.
The classic Bioware model, of course, you think of Mass Effect or you think of Knights of the Old Republic where you've got, you know, your blue Jedi choice and your red Sith choice, or Renegade and Paragon, et cetera, et cetera, sort of good versus evil.
We wanted to instead lean into something that's a little bit more sort of subjective.
So our trait-based system, we kind of termed them the kick-ass, clever, and charming.
And the idea being that
because the songs tend to be about antagonistic encounters where you're trying to get information from somebody, you have different strategies with which to deal with them.
So you can be very in their face and very confrontational, which is the red one.
You can be very kind of empathic
and sort of emotionally sensitive, where you're trying to very genuinely see their point of view, which is the green one, and then the blue one is the more kind of cerebral, intellectual, sometimes that manifests as maybe it's even conniving, you're trying to outsmart them, that kind of thing.
And so the idea is that there is no actual right or wrong choice.
This is not solving puzzles.
This is essentially the essence of what role-playing originally was conceived of.
You are taking this existing character and then saying, how would I approach this?
Because what's great about all these traits is that they're intrinsically emotional, which makes it excellent for writing songs off of them.
So we had our little team assembled.
We had the basic of our concept.
That's David and Ellie and Liam.
That's my girlfriend, Angela, who was enjoying sushi with us.
And then we brought on Troy.
And then we have the superhuman Laura Bailey as Grace.
And so it's kind of this dream team.
And so to that end, I had Troy say a few words about this idea of casting and auditions and that sort of thing.
As an actor, there's a little bit of, you know, insight that I think that I could have into the process.
My goal is always
in whatever capacity I'm working in, I just want to try to be a problem solver.
And how can I position myself to be on the right side of the table with the right people, looking at the right problem in the right way.
And a lot of that is, just as an actor, I hate auditioning.
It's not fun.
It's typically very uninformed.
It's not a delightful process for
either party.
So what I found to be very substantially beneficial is if you can just develop relationships with people and understand
who they are as an actor, who they are as a person, and how they're going to fit into this delicate ecosystem that you're creating.
That's a much smarter way to do it.
Why do the same people continue to get hired?
Because they consistently prove that they can solve the problems, consistently.
So one of the problems with auditioning, and I'm not saying that people shouldn't audition, I'm just saying there's an alternative to it.
Part of the problem with auditioning is you have no idea, as the director or the producer, how many takes it took for you to get that performance.
It could have been take 5, it could have been take 500, you don't know.
But what you got, oh my gosh, the performance that we got out of it is great.
I mean, obviously, we're going to change it because we didn't tell them this thing about the character that's incredibly informative because we just wrote it yesterday.
But I'm sure they'll be able to take that adjustment.
Then you get the person in there, and you say, hey, you're not sad.
You're angry.
Or by the way, you're not from this planet.
You're actually from this.
And oh, you actually, you didn't have a brother.
You had a sister.
and you watch as the actor can't make that adjustment and now you're stuck with a problem.
So for me it's about find someone that regardless of what you throw at them they're going to be able to roll with those punches and deliver every time.
That's why you get Laura Bailey.
Laura can do that.
It doesn't matter what you throw at Laura.
It's just like she's just playing Fruit Ninja and she can just chop that up mid-stream.
For some people, the auditioning process can be very informative and you can learn about the character because someone comes in with a completely different idea and you're like, I never thought of it that way.
And some of the greatest casting choices ever have been because of people that do that.
They change the mind of the director
because of their performance.
If you can be that person, if you can be that director, if you can be that open, then by all means do that.
See as many people as you can.
Constantly iterate on your character.
You cast the character multiple times.
You cast them when you write it.
You cast them when you cast it.
You cast it when you shoot it.
There's just multiple iterations.
And this industry, as you guys know, is all about iteration and innovation.
But regardless of the medium, the challenge remains.
You have to cast this game, and you better cast well.
We had a unique challenge in the fact of our casting choices were so targeted, so specific, because of the character type, because of the genre, and because of the skill set that was required of our actors.
We need you to act, and we need you to sing.
And we also hope that you're pretty adept at being able to track multiple non-linear storylines across several months, if not years.
That presents an incredibly unique challenge.
Yeah, one of the recurring themes that I have here is that the cast we ended up with are just not of this world.
And everything you just said there
is not only true very much of this project, but I also, the reason why I put that clip for that long is I remember thinking this really seems to apply to, for example, the musicians that I hire on my scores, like, you know, Kristen Nagus is here, hopefully, especially the composers in the room should all be familiar with Kristen Nagus, woodwind player, oboist, who plays also every other instrument ever conceived.
this talk.
like all they care about is playing the oboe, but it's, it's, this is someone who thrives on, Oh, here's a new challenge.
Here's a new thing that we can do.
Tina Guo is someone I've worked with extensively.
Who's the same way.
Tom Straley is a guitarist.
And so I think that's one of those where, uh, finding someone that you can kind of go deep with as opposed to having a really broad Rolodex has, has always been my strategy as well.
I like, I always admired, you know, recently John Williams and Steven Spielberg celebrated 50 years of collaborating.
since 1973, and I look at that and I say, that's a relationship that has gone for depth versus breadth.
And I admire that, and I think this notion of just being a problem solver, like for a prospective musician wanting to record for composers, for example, framing yourself as someone who can help solve their problems, as opposed to, oh, I can just play the notes on the page, is the point he was making about actors and one that I find very
uh... apropos and likewise if you find yourself pitching yourself as a composer to an audio director or what not the more it's I'm someone who's here to help you solve the problem and make this easier and it's not just oh I'm some genius who writes all the best notes is you know gonna yield better long-term in my opinion uh...
So yes, as I mentioned, Troy became our director, and because this is a project that has quite a lot of dialogue and a lot of singing, we ended up tag teaming.
I learned an insane amount.
One of the biggest things that I learned from him that he himself had had to learn from other directors that he had worked with over the years
was that it's really easy to overshare and give a lot of information that's just fundamentally unneeded.
I've gotten that from the podium from conducting orchestras a lot of times where I'll, you know, I'll be working on a cue and I'll stop and I'll turn to them and I'll say, here's the thing, this is a scene where
You know, the main characters just found out that, you know, their family has all been frozen in carbonite and they may never see them again.
And it's going to be really, you know, it's going to be really difficult, but at the same time it inspires them to have this resolve to cope with it.
And so it's sort of simultaneously heartbreaking.
And ten minutes later the concertmasters say, so louder?
took me about 40 times of that happening before I learned to just say, okay, let's do it again, this time a little louder, because it's just, you became convinced that they need all this information, that somehow the bow is going to be really informed by this mental image of the, and it's just not the case.
But my assumption was, yeah, but that's because musicians are abstract.
Get in the room with the actors, now that stuff really matters.
And Troy's like, no, it doesn't.
He had a quote he mentioned where he says, all they need to ever know is what's at stake and what does the camera need.
Like in the case of performance capture or actual on camera, you could think of it as what does the microphone need.
That's it.
I have a little glimpse here.
When we did our initial little prototyping, I was, here's a little moment.
Gonna get through this no matter the odds I'll solve a crime, I'll be divine I guess I'll give this a whirl Give yourself that.
Cool?
Yeah.
So we're going for, uh, I can't think like that.
Yeeth.
Section 11 is bar 40.
At which point he discovered, I'm not paying attention, I'm just fucking filming.
So we made a little prototype, here's just a little taste.
This is not, every single note was completely thrown away and started over again because this prototype was just proof of concept to try to get money for the game basically.
But here's a little taste we did with Laura.
Okay, so it all began when the band held auditions.
No, no, no, no, wait.
Singing.
I didn't... Fine.
Alright, I know.
This might be hard to believe.
I'm not drunk or possessed.
Okay, a little naive.
But this happened.
I swear it happened.
My life was normal until Calliope.
So there's a less part of a longer thing, but just to give you a little taste of kind of, you know, how it was sounding.
And then of course, pretty much right after we did that, the pandemic hit.
Um, so it was like, okay, well now we have to rethink our strategy.
In fact, the funny thing was that the team is principally based in Melbourne, Australia, and we're in LA for us to really kind of get rolling and do some initial recordings.
And, um, it, if you all remember those first few days it was kind of hard to gauge if this was a real problem, um, because it just didn't seem like it can't possibly get, it can't scale to like a global, it just, nah, that's like movie shit.
And so they had, they had flights to go back to Australia and it was one of those where every day got
you may want to consider moving this flight earlier.
You may never go home if you delay and sure enough at one point they did finally move their flights and then the next day all the borders closed and it was, it was kind of dodged a bullet.
Um, it was, it was quite a time to be starting something, uh, this sort of huge in, in scope.
Anyway, uh, we showed our little proof of concept around and, uh, you know, yeah, you got some money.
Now we got to actually write this shit.
So I fundamentally am not a lyricist, as evidenced by the poetry you see before you.
And so I knew that I wanted to bring in, now apropos Troy's comments earlier about finding people that really can consistently inspire you and that make you better and you hopefully make them better.
I have had the great fortune of working on this photo on the left.
That's a band from Australia called Tripod.
And they are genius songwriters.
And so I had worked with them on Assassin's Creed Syndicate and a bunch of other projects where we were kind of co-writing stuff and they were writing lyrics to music I was writing.
and they're just they're amazing they're a comedy band go look them up on youtube they've been a band together for almost thirty years and just absolutely hilarious and brilliant and unlike most musical comedy where it's sort of very generic and bland music with witty lyrics they're actually really quite brilliant musicians so the songs are interesting and also hilarious and witty and interesting
I said, I want to bring these guys in.
And obviously, it helped that they live in the same city as the game's studio.
That sort of somehow made things easier for, I don't know why that matters, but it was nice.
And then the funny thing was, we started to look at the list of what we needed and realized, there's a lot of material here.
Because originally, it was going to be, OK, the four of us together will write each song.
And then it was, OK, so that's going to take about 46 years.
because you'll see, I'll get to it in a minute, but the complexity started to really exponentially go nuts.
So then it was, okay, then I'm going to work individually with each of them on multiple songs at once.
So the guy on the left is Scott.
Scott and I will work on a song.
The guy with the cap on is Jan.
Jan and I will work on a song.
Gatesy and I will work on a song as a third guy.
And even with that, it was like, this is still going to be pretty hard to finish in a reasonable amount of time.
There's just so much music that we're looking at.
And so Liam, the co-founder of the company and our studio director,
He just sent me a list of, he's like, here's some other sort of songwriters and weird, interesting indie musicians and stuff who I like, and it could be cool.
And one of them was this woman, Montaigne.
And I was listening, and it was like this really kind of quirky pop music that I thought was really well done.
She's got incredible vocal chops.
and we were saying, oh yeah, that should be cool, we should maybe track down her manager or something and reach out.
And then before we could do that, she cold calls us because she heard about the game and was just like, hey, I'm a nerdy gamer, this sounds awesome, do you need any help?
And it was like, holy shit, that's amazing.
Welcome aboard.
And then the hilarious thing was then we get started.
Of course, the pandemic was off and rolling.
And then she was like, oh, by the way, I got to go.
I got a gig I got to go do.
But I'll be back and we'll keep writing again in like a month or whatever.
Turns out she was Australia's Eurovision contestant.
So she had to go kind of do that for a minute and then come back.
She very generously returned to the land of normal people to help us on our game.
So one thing I want to explain about this is that I don't actually think of this as non-linear.
I started referring to it as multi-linear because it is, it's a branching narrative but it's not, it's not open ended in the way like an open world game or something that's
procedurally generated might be.
It's more just that there is a completely stupid amount of possibilities that we are arming the player with.
So that you have an enormous amount of agency, but it is fundamentally all bespoke content.
And so it's not linear, but non-linear didn't feel like the correct word.
And so
As part of the discovery of the distinction between those, I laid out a few rules for myself and also in talking to the team because the music had such an opportunity to inform the narrative.
It wasn't just that David wrote a story and said, okay, here's, you know,
situation
genius with keeping track of all the branches in his head.
I will never understand it.
Oh, well, if we change this, what that means is, like, there's 42 scenes later, there's this A, B choice, and if we change what you're talking, then the B is going to have to change, which I guess is fine, because there's this other scene, and then you just, like, work it out from memory in front of us over and over and over.
And I always go, is this written down anywhere?
Like, if you slip into a coma, are we just completely fucked?
And I think the answer to that might have been yes for quite a bit of the project.
But I didn't ask too much for the sake of my sanity.
So here were some of the rules that were laid out.
First off, the songs have to have narrative consequence.
This seems obvious, but it's really easy when you go into the normal rhythms of game design to just kind of, as the writer, as the creative director, to start laying down foundational points and just know, OK, there's going to be music that fills in the gaps.
in between, but it was like, no, no, no, no, the whole point of a musical is that if the narrative reaches a certain emotional threshold before words no longer count, it must be sung in order to really get the meaning across.
That means that that's when the actual important stuff is happening.
So we need to make sure that all those linchpin moments in your story where it seems like, you know, this is going to really make a difference to how the story turns out and who the character ends up being, blah, blah, blah, that needs to happen in song.
And in addition to the fact that these choices need to be something that the player is making, we're not feeding them.
These are not cutscenes.
The songs are the main gameplay.
It's not just that you're making a succession of choices in this kind of like concatenated series of one-offs.
The idea is that these choices have to compound.
So think of it as I have door A, B, and C, like I showed you the three colored traits.
I have door A, B, and C.
It's not that behind that is door D, E, and F. It's that behind A is D, E, and F. Behind B would be G, H, and I. And I'm very quickly going to lose the ability to keep this going.
But you get the idea.
It's each decision impacts the decisions that come after it.
And so it has a ripple effect.
It's like life in that way.
I can't just randomly walk back everything I do as much as we all wish we could do that on a regular basis.
And so the compounding of the choices was a crucial one.
And the last one, which again sounds very kind of pointless to assert, is that they have to sound like real songs.
But what I mean by that is that it's really easy to get lost in the weeds and say, OK, well, the character is going to sing this to whoever, like Grace is singing to X.
And so then X replies with this and then Grace can then sing with this and this and very quickly it's almost like you're writing dialogue and just setting it to melody and it's not a song.
Songs, even structurally avant-garde ones, typically will have some form of perceptible structure that is what makes us register it as a song and not just as a through composed, you know, an art song as we would call it in the classical world or something like that.
Although those also tend to have
perceptual structure.
So it's a terrible example and I'm a fraud.
But you get what I'm saying.
The most banal way to phrase it is verse chorus, pre-chorus, chorus returns.
These structural elements that we're all deeply familiar with as composers and songwriters need to be able to come back.
But you can imagine that if this is something that is crazy branching, how to also shoehorn it into that kind of structure became fundamentally our challenge.
So here's an example
This is like maybe the simplest song in the game.
It's really, really basic, but just to give a sense of kind of how some of the diagramming works.
And this one even, this is almost an incidental sort of transitional moment.
This isn't even like one of the full-on songs, but it gives you a little sense of, of
the way that things kind of, there's paths that are also different lengths, where sometimes you arrive at an ending, like if you go here, you know, 1 to 2 to 3A, 4 to 5, actually 1, 2, 3C, and 5 is actually quite short compared to some of the other possibilities, you know, 1, 2, 3A, 6, 7.
That's just a fundamentally longer song.
So it's interesting, because then different choices actually yield really different musical results, even just in terms of their length.
Some of the other kinds of interactivity that we had is some choices that you might make in a song determines which songs will even then populate the game after that, so that some of the interactivity is happening in this downstream way where, you know, you have three different characters that you're kind of interacting with and you choose one.
The two that you didn't
choose may have had their own musical numbers that are now completely removed from the game for this particular playthrough.
So I wanted there to be kind of, in other words, short and medium and long term interactive musical concepts at work so that the actual set list, as it were, was evolving as much as the actual songs in real time are.
And we do some things, for example, where the system is actually also measuring how many of a certain type of choice that you've made, and then will funnel you into a choice based on the average.
Like, OK, you chose red more often than the others.
So what you don't realize is the next thing you're hearing is part of the interactive system.
This isn't just through-line cinematic.
But you didn't choose it right now.
You chose it over the last five minutes based on the things that you've been doing in aggregate.
so that there's again this compounding that can occur.
So you end up sometimes with a really simple one like this and then sometimes they look more like this.
But you can kind of see from the label along the right, the way we tried to force it to have sort of the essence of what an actual sort of song's structure might look like.
It took, by the way, about two years to write all of these.
It was well over five hours worth of material.
And we ran an algorithm
in Unreal, and it turns out that there's like many tens of thousands of permutations.
So no one will ever actually play the game every possible way in the one lifetime.
I don't think that's even physically possible.
And that's the meaningful differences.
There's some differences where it's like, OK, well, you chose this, we chose that.
You'll get similar music, but the orchestration is slightly different between them.
I don't even count that.
That's too superficial to even include in the list.
If you include those, it's like hundreds of millions of permutations.
It's absolutely stupid.
Don't advise this.
This is basically a talk for me trying to steer you all into better choices in your life.
But you can see the color trait organization and you can see some of the concepts I was talking about where the player reaches these nodes, they make a choice, it will feed them, it will then feed you different choices based on the choices that you made before.
So that very often, like for example, you can see on the line labeled Chorus 2, where for the player, they think they are making
a choice of three, they have three options, they have a triumvirate before them and, but in reality there's actually nine because the system is going yeah but what did you do before?
So if you're like under this blue banner then you have red, green and blue under the nest of blue and if you had chosen red then you have red, green and blue under the nest of red.
All this has
wild musical implications, it sometimes means whole different genres of music within a song, and you're kind of swimming back and forth and changing.
And the idea is that all of this has to sound like a real song, and hopefully a good one, if we're lucky.
So, like I said, it took about two years, so yay, now we have all the songs, we gotta record this shit.
Turns out that's a whole thing as well.
So I had a quick thing here from Troy about onboarding our cast into this.
that actor walks in and it's this dance and the thing that I found is that you have about five minutes to
let them know who's in control, who's in charge.
Because if the director and the writer are not locked up, if there's any dissonance there, it's not that, well, the writer's going to have control, that's who I listen to, or the director's going to have control.
The actor will take control, because they don't trust either of you now.
Because there's not this harmony between a single voice that's speaking to them and saying the same thing.
So you have to walk in and go, we're here to tell you this story and show you how you fit into it.
And we're curious to see what you can bring to it.
So now you realize, what I'm trying to set up is that it's the three of us working together as opposed to we've given you a script, you give us lines, and we've got four hours to get out of here.
Yeah, I think another way to phrase that is the only possible way to get through it all was to really make sure to invite the cast to feel like real contributors, because we booked nearly a hundred sessions with the actors.
I mean, it was six months of recording.
And so, especially in the case of someone like Laura,
you got to spend a lot of time together, which means that you need her and everyone else to feel very bought in, that they really have a voice in this.
So one of the choices that I made was we wrote all the songs.
In fact, let me just jump to this.
I'm going to, in the interest of time, I think this is a little long.
I got plenty from Troy here.
Well, I'll save the point I was going to make when I play you audio in just a second.
An easy trap to fall into is, well, just hold their hands through it.
And that sounds like a lovely sentiment, and that sounds like a very supportive thing.
The problem with it is, the second that the actor becomes aware of the fact that you're holding their hand, the instant thing that that telegraphs is, yes, you're supporting them, but also you don't fully trust them.
And this process really required that we just let it go.
And we had done everything that we could on our side to write, to create a world that felt real and tangible even though it's very fantastical.
but also to cast these people and go, we know that you can do this.
We believe in you.
That's why you're in that booth.
So show us what you can do.
And if they feel our hand on their back the entire time, it can actually kind of be very counterproductive to letting them feel comfortable enough to do something that's really, really awkward, which is to sing.
It's one thing for an actor to come in and go, I've got this.
Now, when you're dealing with people like,
Yes, you know that you're dealing with f***ing talent and these guys knew exactly how to do it.
You're dealing with people who haven't necessarily been in this situation before.
You need to let them feel that they can do hard things and that they are up to the task.
So a lot of times we have to do this.
The problem is, if you're not holding their hand, if you're not over-communicating, there's a lot of information that we are having to communicate to our actors in order for them to understand where they're at in the scene, because it's not a very traditional way of doing this.
Most actors want to come in and go, okay, so where are we right now?
What has just happened?
What do I want?
All the basic questions that actors have been taught to ask either you or themselves.
The problem with our game is go, well, if the player has, and making sure that you could have already done this, but if you didn't, so now there's this
box of disconnected ideas that will come together as a very cohesive story, but in an actor's mind, they've got nothing to hold onto.
So what becomes very critical is that we concisely communicate information.
Yeah, it's always the same.
Just don't overshare.
And just try to boil it down.
It's part of the writing process as well.
There'd be so many times you get so lost in the weeds over a single line and then just realize, you know, this is going to go by like that.
Or maybe they'll never even hear it because they chose some other path.
And it's really easy to kind of shoot yourself in the foot with that.
In the interest of time, he kind of
talks here about basically you don't need to do a billion takes.
If it's not working, move on.
But I want to not run out of time here, and I also prefer to have a Q&A and have discussion.
It's way more fun.
But the point I was going to make a moment ago that sort of leaps off of his notion about giving them space was
we made the decision early on to approach this kind of like we were workshopping a broadway musical and so when writing the songs we would create essentially like rehearsal piano tracks or in some cases like the tripod guys they were recording the vocalist because
you can probably guess by the way I talk, I can't sing for shit.
And so I was like, let's make some scratch vocals with the real singers.
And they would find it easier to record to some rudimentary drum beat or something.
And so they would literally just take like a garage band, you know, Fruity Loops or something and just create something very generic just so that it helps them to sing.
And so the most elaborate that we would have in terms of these initial backing tracks were just, you know, simple piano chords
and then the maybe a drum, maybe a simple bass line.
The idea being that when we get in there with the actor, they actually really have a lot of say and, you know, not just sliding it up and down and re-pitching it in Pro Tools live in the studio with them in order to accommodate the strengths of their voice, but also to let that be part of the storytelling where, you know, Laura might say, you know, this is right in a range where I can sing it down here in the lower part of my voice and it has a very kind of grumbly quality
But if I sang it up an octave, much more of a head voice, it would take on this kind of quality.
And I think reading through the lyrics, it actually makes sense to have it up there.
But in bar seven, it's a little beyond what I can reach.
So can we, like, pull the whole thing down?
And so we would, like, say, yes, yes, love it.
The fact that you are discovering ways to kind of bring your own ideas into this and breathe life into it is amazing.
And it makes it...
so much more of a viable finished product because it's the product of all of our ideas and intuitions.
It's not just, you know, I wrote a thing, now please don't deviate, read my genius notes, and God help you if you change anything.
I'm not like that at all.
And again, part of the reason why I wanted to focus so much on this aspect of working with the performers is I think this can hold true for every musician collaboration we have.
I have it all the time with, you know, like I mentioned, the guitarist I love working with, Tom Straley.
He'll say things like, oh, I'm playing this part on a 12-string and I see what you wrote here and if I drop this note, that note, and that note, I can think of this way more organically.
And as a non-guitarist, I would say, I care about what sounds the best.
Here's the emotion I'm after.
Here's why I wrote those notes.
And he'd say, ah, what if we did this?
Or here's actually a different instrument that might achieve that better.
What do you think of this?
And my attitude is always,
the player, the listener, will never know about this conversation.
They only know how it makes them feel.
And so the thing that creates that feeling, I do not care how we get there.
Whatever gets us there.
So I will skip this.
So we can listen to this shit.
So here are some initial little sketches.
This is where I'm going to end up fighting PowerPoint slightly because it's very janky.
So this was, I would send this to Tripod.
Oh my God, it's going to get very loud.
It might be worth, Ru, if you could pull it down just a little bit.
That's fine.
That might be too much.
So we would do these Zoom calls to write these songs together, and I would often be kind of working stuff out on the piano, and then I would just record it and send it to them and say, you know, what do you think of this?
What do you think of that?
So here's one of those little sketches of, this is that song that I showed you with the crazy colorful branching a moment ago.
That was, this was some of the earliest ideas that I sent them for that.
So you can see it has a little bit of a kind of a sultry quality.
It's a little bit sort of swaying.
So there's one little taste.
So here was like, okay, let's refine it a little.
And then about halfway through this, there's a little fragment of a melody.
So you're keeping your guard up That'll help once you're out in the fray Lots of folks out to get you
They were very fancy with their panning to represent two characters in the scene.
So then it's like, okay, let's keep messing with that.
So you get the idea, sort of playing with it.
The idea is Grace is being taught about her superpower.
Freddie is her best friend.
So you know, kind of playing around with the idea.
So then it was like, okay, well what if
What if, you know, that becomes a recurring hook and that each player choice sort of presents you with something new in front of it.
Maybe that's how we make it feel like a song.
Can we start over?
Hi, my name is Grace.
This is Freddy and we're in a band.
What should we call you?
How about old-timey weirdo who's up in our face?
together.
Forgive me, this is going to sound horrible because I'm going to tab through all of those speakers.
It's fucking weird primitive PowerPoint.
So then let me show you some of the actual final mixes on how we end up with this.
So then we, you know, these little speakers correspond to where they are positioned on here.
So I'm not going to play all of it for you.
Like I said, some of these songs, to play the full song in every incarnation would literally take several hours because even just the raw guts of the way that these things can be added up is
Our average was about five or six to one.
So if it's a five minute song, there's 35, 40 minutes worth of material that is potentially being pulled from, which is how you end up with like five hours worth of musical numbers.
Please kill me.
So here's an example of how it starts off, where we introduce our little verse tune that I just played with you.
Grace, you know that you're lost now.
You've been given powers you don't understand.
I'm the guy who can help you.
All that you hear is at your command.
Wait.
No, it's okay, Freddy.
This is all me?
in
makes different choices and then we often again each song is structured a little differently depending on its role within the narrative.
The idea was to make sure that we have simultaneously downstream effects that you will carry with you but always there needs to be something that the player immediately registers as feedback to the choice that they made.
And so the way that I personally chose to address that is by saying that each trait choice will always have a very noticeable instrument in the mix that is only associated with that trait choice, so that you develop a kind of Pavlovian association between that color and that sound.
So the three that I chose is that the red, you will always hear a prominent
semi-distorted electric bass and the kind of supportive, you know, bass role.
The green, the empathic, I chose a harp, which often is very kind of ethereally treated as well.
It's not just straightforward.
And what I like about that is that those have a different role from one another.
They're both inherently accompanimental
instruments but they have very different ways that they can be accompanimental, obviously harp having a massive range.
And then the blue, the clever, I chose, I alternate back and forth between B flat and then bass clarinet, often in a very kind of
you know like borderline Dixieland kind of play style which is fun because that's a melodic instrument and so it's now about counter melody so that you you feel this twist even though it won't change necessarily in that exact moment what the verse and the chorus are it that's an aggregating a compounding change you'll feel the instrumentation shift instantly once you make make those choices that you never feel like
You're making a choice, but you don't really feel that you did something.
David Gaider, our creative director and the writer, had this brilliant catchphrase where he says, if the player clicks on a thing and they can't perceive what they did, he calls that doing card tricks in the dark.
And I always thought that was genius, because it's like, it is just not a good game design strategy.
So, we introduce our little birds.
You know, he obviously hinted at it in a very sort of quasi-spoken way.
And then we get our first little taste of it in that very first choice.
Not about to just trust you.
You barge in and take over the place.
I don't know what I must do, but here's what you can do.
Get out of my face!
I'm doing it right now.
You're a natural, girl.
You can also hear a fair bit of vocal production on her.
That's something that is consistently associated with the Red choice.
The idea is that it's a lot drier.
It's a lot punchier.
There's often kind of delays and saturation effects and things like a pop song in order so that Red, her voice sounds different when you click that choice throughout the game.
Every song, no matter the genre, no matter if it's a sweet and sentimental song or it's a big, you know, showstoppery kind of over the top one, whatever it is, there needs to be these consistent things that somehow have to be made to work.
In the case of the blue, for example, that tends to be a very kind of middle-of-the-road treatment with little occasional effects and things placed on her voice.
And then the green tends to be really lush reverb and really spacious.
And there's also orchestrational implications, you know, the red tends to be more percussive in nature.
et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
So if the player had, instead of choosing red, they chose this one.
How the hell did you find me?
Here's our little clarinet.
This is the weirdest night I've ever had.
And you say I have powers?
How could this possibly turn out bad?
Am I doing it now?
Brilliant.
So it's like a parallel reality version of the same phrase.
And then finally, our green choice.
Featuring The Harp.
So it's like, this is just, so obviously this one's very simple, because one of the ideas I also said to them is, I don't want it to just be, it's the same melody, but it's different lyrics each time.
That's the really obvious way to do this.
But because this is the first major song of the game where we're teaching the player to kind of clock what we're doing, we start off with it doing that.
Then the player reaches the next hub, and now they actually fully define what the hook of the song is going to be.
So you choose red.
And actually I'll, let me just say narratively, this scene, she's been accused by the gods of a murder and then sent back home.
And they're like, okay, good luck.
See you in a week.
Good luck.
You know, you can do it.
Hoping of course that she can't and that they get to execute her.
and in strides this character who basically is clearly one of the gods and is saying, you know, I can help you.
And the player has to choose, do I trust this guy?
He seems kind of shady, but he is actually one of the gods.
So, I mean, he certainly knows more than I do.
Is this a bargain I'm willing to kind of go with?
And of course, as you can imagine, you
you work out pros and cons as the song, and this is going to have ripple effects through the whole game.
And so the scene, and you're with your character's best friend, Freddy, and so the song kind of becomes this tug of war where the red choice is about like, both of you need to give me some space because
I just have to work this out.
Clearly, I don't think I can trust you and, you know, Freddie, I love you, but you can't empathize with the position I'm in fully, so I should probably just work this out on my own.
Whereas the blue choice is, you know, this guy, you know, he knows stuff that I don't know.
I should probably trust him, even if it feels a little funny, and I'm sorry to my best friend and loyal confidant.
And then the green choice is the, you know, sorry, you are shady as fuck, and I'm going to stick with my friend, you know, my ride or die, as it were.
And so you'll hear that reflected in these hooks, like this one, the red one, ends up being this is my time.
time to shine and this becomes the hook of the song that influences everything so that no matter what you choose from that point forward we're playing around with this hook
This was a drink I'd be drinking But someone is dead and I'm losing my head Like the goat said This is my time Time to shine This is my time Time to shine
She's getting a lot of pushback, of course.
In contrast, here is the green, the blue.
So this morning fades into the day.
He's telling you, you don't have time to sit on this.
Trust me.
And that comes back again in the interest of time I'm just going to power along here So here's where she's saying him, you are shady
So you get the idea.
So then what happens from that point forward is basically the song is going to kind of arrange itself in front of you almost like, you know, Iceman in the X-Men where
It's going to look at the decisions that you've made and start feeding you new decisions under the banner of the decisions that you've made.
So here's an example of how this can manifest later on in the song.
Grace, I'm worried that this guy has got to you.
This is obviously one of the blue choices.
What?
There's so much easier to explain, but all I want is to sing it again.
It's my time, time to shine.
So like, we initially heard that under the red banner, but now I'm choosing it under the green.
That's why you're hearing this clarinet with it, but that's our hook, so we're sticking with it.
Does that make sense?
You end up with these cross pollinations of the material.
It's gone and the day wastes away Grace, this is our place Is he gonna stay?
See, I don't think I have any choice I know where you belong Grace, the song grates But can you show me the way?
It's time to play So
So you get so you know, there's the taste of that and then finally here's the last So all three that I've just played Which means the player just clicked green but you can hear all three of the hooks are passing through this filter because
earlier this year.
For most of the development, green was blue and blue was green and yeah, I'm hopeless.
So anyway, point being, does that make sense what I'm describing?
I know I'm being a little bit succinct here because I'm running out of time and I didn't want to get caught off.
But that agency means that, you know, you end up making a choice and then everything is sort of going to compound on top of that.
Forgive me once again.
So yeah, hopefully, maybe it's not shit.
And I just wanted to really quickly address some of the challenges and possibly even failures of this, because part of the goal here in taking on this project is we said, well, what's something that feels like no one's ever really tried before?
And as Troy very succinctly put it, usually there's a reason.
And it turns out that this thing is quite a lift.
It's very expensive.
to
ratio of music that's recorded that a player will hear on any given playthrough, which is obscene.
And which also means that there's huge amounts of content that maybe you'll never, ever, ever hear.
Also, don't even get me started about how in God's name I'm going to do a soundtrack album for this.
But that's a whole other talk, I think.
And Troy, just basically, I'll summarize this because I want to take a couple questions before we get chased out of here.
But he basically was talking about, as well, given the number of people, the number of actors, this constant, he felt he had to relearn over and over this idea that this really, this needs to be our thing and if I come in prepared to direct it with a specific goal in mind and the actor brings something totally unexpected to the table,
to just say, you know what, actually you're right, let's go with that and to really lean into that because the end product is likely to be better.
So, anyway, enough of quote our shit.
You can wishlist the game on Steam now.
And yes, let's just get chased out of the room answering questions.
Go for it!
Yeah, as an actor and singer, this seems like a dream project.
I was already thinking in terms of those YouTubers that love to post cutscenes and how that's going to make their life absolutely miserable.
Is there going to be a feature in this game which will allow players to have their version of the song just so they can listen back to it because they might really like what they come up with?
Yeah, I think that's OBS.
Okay.
about
And that has not been met very well.
But no, so yeah, it's one of those where I have plans to release kind of like a barrage of albums that hopefully cover the bases as much as possible.
And then it is going to just end up being a, you know, you just kind of have to play the game to, you know, experience it different ways.
Which was, that was always the goal though.
And was there any specific visual novels or musicals that really inspired you guys in the process of that?
Oh, I mean, I'm a Sondheim junkie, you know, to me, to me, sort of like the king.
I'm also a big obsessor for Leonard Bernstein, but, but so, you know, Sunday in the Park with George and Sweeney Todd and actually, but funny enough, you know what, the number one thing that we talked about at the beginning was the Buffy musical, because first off, it's pretty genius, but also it's baked into the fabric of that musical that they know they're in a musical and they have to escape it to survive.
And that was kind of,
I thought that's an interesting kind of premise of sorts.
Let's sort of play with that.
The characters know they're in a song.
That's the idea.
So Buffy was a big inspiration.
Yes sir.
Thank you, that was a great talk.
I'm a narrative designer and occasional composer and I think over the last half hour you melted my brain.
My question is, I'm curious to know, because of those two hats I wear, what was the sort of interactivity during the writing process, because you said David had sort of come with a fairly put together concept, but what was the interactivity between the music and the musical, which of course you know you'd expect
I don't know, a torch song, and back one closer, 11 o'clock number, whatever, between that and the narrative side of things, and how did they talk to each other during the course of putting this together?
It's a great question.
Short version, it was a lot of back and forth.
It was a lot of, oh, you know, this is an interesting moment.
Let's expand this.
We can make this a full-on number.
This originally was just a passing comment, but there's really major narrative implications for this that I think we're overlooking.
What if we built this out?
Or, hey, we thought we'd stick a number here, but let's get to the point of this scene faster and whatever.
And like I said, David was really
of
is a complete insanity.
I mean the thing is analyzing every song you've done in the game and it's just it's absolute it took us it took us months and that was one where we would have to jump on a call with him every couple of days and go okay we want the player to do this and then we want to bring a reference back from this earlier song but I want to know is that even possible?
And he would go, oh, well, no, actually, because if you're talking to this person, it means you didn't talk to them in this earlier scene.
And the only reason this person's in the scene is because you did talk to them.
And so it was like, we had to constantly have him hold our hands to even know all the millions of branches to know what even should be on the menu.
And that was just, yeah, just constant slack.
Yes.
And a lot of Zoom calls.
Awesome.
Thank you.
Yeah.
My pleasure.
Hi there.
First off, I'm super excited.
I've been following this since the Fig campaign, so just love seeing this come to fruition.
I'm really curious, coming from the Dragon Age, Mass Effect style of storytelling, I know that a lot of people reach the moments for decision and they take a long time.
So when you're dealing with something like a musical where there's a time component to it and you're working with the music and the background trying to keep things in a general
song format
what is, in effect, your character class.
Because that unlocks a whole other thing I don't want to get into, but there's a whole idea of the first time the player has made this choice, we don't want to just assume that they've played other Bioware games or something and would just immediately understand what this is.
So this one actually goes into an instrumental infinite loop.
It's the only one in the entire game that does that.
Because otherwise, I said, the trade-off of the player constantly feeling like they're on a rail
is that it can feel like a musical number in a way that you fully sacrifice if you take that away.
Because my little mental image fantasy is if you're playing the game and I'm kind of over here like doing laundry and I'm not fully paying attention, I should think that you're just watching a musical.
It shouldn't occur to me that you're driving it because that then sounds like a real musical.
It just turns out that there's like tens of thousands of things you could have done.
And so
The way to achieve that, one of the potential sacrifices and possibly a weakness of the format we chose is that you have a time limit to make these choices and after trial and erroring a million different possibilities of how to contend with them, what if they just don't click on one?
We ended up basically going, it's just going to pick one at random.
Because if we don't pick one at random, it becomes, well, why did it choose, what's so important about that?
And it was very important to me that it never feel like there's a right and a wrong or a canonical answer versus a not.
It should really feel like, no, no, no, this is about role playing.
This is creating your story.
And so random felt like the best way to get to that than, OK, well, I secretly think the red one is the best version, so I'm going to make you do that if you do nothing.
It's like, no, no, no.
that's even less agency I thought.
To me it's not my favorite aspect but it felt like a necessary
compromise to make, because the infinite looping that you would run into if you wanted to try to not have that undermines the musicality of it so dramatically.
We tried it.
Again, we experimented on a lot of prototypes and things like that, but that's where we ended up on that.
It's a very savvy question, because you wouldn't believe the amount of hours we spent sort of sweating bullets over, what do we do with it?
This is a really interesting design challenge.
You end up with Jeopardy music at some point.
I think I'm out of time.
Is that what that means?
All right.
I'll just go hang out outside and we can address... Thank you all.
Blah, blah, blah.
Evaluation forms.
You know, be nice to each other.
Thank you.