Hi, my name is Patrick Walker, and I'm with the market research company, EDAR.
So EDAR collects a lot of video game data to help clients make better business decisions.
This is a really fun and exciting time for us in VR because we finally have VR data.
It was very hard when there wasn't consumer systems on the market to ask people what they thought about VR.
We've tried VR and we know that you don't really understand it until you've tried it.
And now we have about six months of great data, not only sales but also just consumer engagement, consumer attitudes towards the platform.
And that's what I'm going to be showing today.
That's also why the focus of my talk is going to be on VR rather than AR.
AR is very exciting.
I think a lot of people, including Tim Cook,
think that AR is eventually going to be bigger than VR.
But right now, we have more data on VR.
And that both makes for a more interesting presentation
and makes it a little bit easier to figure out where VR is going.
I'm going to be showing several data sets today.
Data from our Steam Pulse data set,
which shows Steam ownership, Steam engagement,
which is really great for understanding the Vive,
and then also data from our consumer tracker
and several consumer surveys.
And then also, with AR, one point, I don't really consider Pokemon Go AR.
We do have data on AR, and it mostly tells me that people turn off the AR functionality
so that they can save their battery.
So this is VR focused mostly.
You may have noticed VR is pretty big right now.
It's pretty hot.
This is a picture of the moment that I realized, OK,
I'm going to be speaking about VR from now on.
This was GDC 2016.
And I was giving a presentation just on the overall market,
walked into this hallway of people doing VR presentations,
and was like, hmm, I am talking about the wrong thing
right now.
Why are people so excited about VR?
Well, one reason is the amount of investment dollars
that are flooding in.
So year over year, we're seeing significant growth
in investment on VR.
This chart doesn't even include Magic Leap.
And Magic Leap has over a billion dollars
of funding on its own.
So we've hit over a billion dollars in 2016
of investment into VR AR.
Now.
There is also the fact that 2016 became when VR hype had to become VR reality.
And my favorite anecdote to explain this shift in thinking, or to think about this shift in thinking,
is the quotes from Facebook.
So in the tail end of 2014, Zuckerberg was talking about the Rift and their $2 billion investment.
And he said, oh, well, for that to be a successful platform
or a platform that matters, we're
going to have to move 50 to 100 million units, right?
Probably thinking about something like the PS4 install
base or Xbox One install base.
And then last year or this year, the CEO
is saying, well, if we can move 1 million units life to date,
then we'll be satisfied.
That'll be great.
That'll be fantastic.
A little bit of a coming down to Earth
in terms of the expectations for the platform, right?
So where are we now? What's the VR roadmap?
So this is the VR roadmap in November 2016.
What we're seeing is really there's two types of platforms being released.
There's the accessible platforms, the mobile platforms, able to move more units.
And then there's the more immersive platforms.
On the more immersive side, we've got the Oculus and Vive.
Accessible side, we've got Cardboard, Gear VR.
And now we've got the PlayStation VR coming in,
and that's pretty exciting because the install base
of the PlayStation 4, 47 million units end of year,
means we first have the first platform
that really has the potential to hit a little bit
of that sweet spot, right, where it's both accessible,
a lot of people in the ecosystem,
but also offering that deep immersion.
I also have some exciting platforms on the horizon.
We've got the Daydream coming out,
which will have a hand controller and Google really
investing into the ecosystem.
And then Microsoft has recently announced
that they're going to try to make some third party, lower
end, $200 systems over the next couple of years.
So what does this look like? Well in terms of headset price, you can see that relationship, or as they're more immersive, it increases.
Oculus is now $800 instead of $600, but it started out at $600.
Now when we look at our install base, so what's the worldwide install base estimated by the end of the year?
There's this inverse relationship, as you might expect.
For an $800 system, you're not going to have...
50 to 100 million units, you're probably going to have closer to a couple hundred thousand,
which is where we're at now.
You do see that in the middle, the nice position that the PSVR is in where they have both a
pretty high price point, but also the opportunity to move a million or two units, which is really
where when we look at the overall revenue number, a billion and a half this year, a
lot of that is being generated by the PSVR.
Because it's the first platform that really has that sweet spot met.
And it makes sense.
These are expensive systems.
And when we look at people and we ask them, what's the amount that you're willing to spend
on a VR headset, it's pretty low percentage when you get to the $700, $800 price point
where the Vive and the Oculus exist.
PSVR is a little bit better.
I put it at $450 because it's somewhere between $400 and $500 depending on whether you have
the camera.
and hand controls. And then when the full market starts to be interested or say
that they would be willing to buy that headset,
you're at a lower price point around where the Daydream and the Gear VR are.
It's just at that point, you know, we start to lose some of the
aversion and it's a less high-quality VR experience.
We also have an install-based situation where there's only 5 million GPUs that can really
even handle the high-end PC headsets.
So even if you attach 10%, you're still in that 250,000 to 500,000 unit range, which
is where we're going to be at around the end of the year.
Forty-five million PS4s is a much better install base to hit.
All right, so who are these early VR adopters?
What do they look like?
Well, for one thing, they spend a lot of money.
This is their spend on non-VR gaming.
We see that for a PC VR owner, it's
significantly higher than just a PC console gamer
and higher than someone who is interested in purchasing a VR
headset but has not purchased one yet.
Interestingly, they don't necessarily play more
than those who are interested.
The people who play the most are the ones
who can't afford a PC VR headset yet,
but they're excited about it,
and they're interested in purchasing.
That also is a much larger group,
something like 10x, 15x the size.
So there is a lot of excitement about VR,
it's just that the price points
make it a little bit difficult at this point.
They're also consumers with money.
So I'm going to say, make about $70,000 a year.
Most have gone to college.
72% male, which is higher than the typical 60-40 split
we see for console gaming.
As a general rule of thumb, mobile is close to 50-50, male-female split.
Console is usually 60-40.
This is about 70-30.
It's a very core gaming group in 20s.
And they're spending a lot on VR right now, which is cool.
You know, it's about, you know, of that 1.5 billion,
about 250 million is likely to be software.
For the number of people that are in the ecosystem, that's actually pretty good
because people are spending a lot of money.
They're also so far satisfied with the systems.
When we ask, you know, are you satisfied with the virtual reality headset that you purchased,
over 75% on both platforms say that they are.
So have critics.
Critics have been pretty high on these systems.
And when we look across five to six, seven top tech sites
and look at their reviews on the platforms,
on the VR headsets, we see an average review score
for the most part above 80, right?
Which is kind of that standard for a good game,
which a lot of even like compensation plans
are tied to in development studios.
And each headset has had pretty much its USP or the thing that was called out about it the most.
So for the Rift, the headset quality, the quality of the games, the length of games, the depth of the games was called out.
Vive had the plus of coming to the market with hand controls and the full room immersion,
which got called out in reviews a lot.
Oculus has now caught up with that and now has touch controls.
And then for PSVR, it was all about the price point, right?
This is a good enough experience.
This is a great VR experience and you don't have to pay as much for it.
And there's a lot of VR content that's already out there,
despite maybe that there's not a huge install base yet
for these systems.
So this is the Oculus Rift game releases by release date
and price point.
You can see the launch there with software released
at each $10 increment.
If you've released a software for one of these systems,
you're a dot on this chart.
There is the recent PSVR release.
Same strategy where at different $10 price points,
we have content released.
Now the openness of the Vive and the Valve platform has meant that there's a lot of content on that platform.
Generally at a lower price point, but it's already a fairly saturated ecosystem only six months in.
Which does mean that in order to stand out, you really need to develop high quality content.
These launches, when you look at them compared to traditional platform launches, have actually
had a lot more content than both the 8th gen consoles, but also then I think what was previously
the last really big accessory, the Move and the Kinect.
So these have had way more software released across the Oculus, PSVR, and Vive.
Now, when we look at must have, you know, the game that critics agree upon, saying that
everyone needs to have, that hasn't really happened yet, right?
If we say, all right, the must have game on console has an average review score over 85.
The only one we've seen is one PSVR title that's come out that did that.
So on these PC VR systems, with the install base
of a couple hundred thousand units,
there is a path to success of making a little bit
over a million dollars.
That was something like raw data,
where we're moving 30,000 units, $40 a piece,
making a million and a half million dollars.
I'd say that with the PSVR, where the install base would
be higher up, could make $3 to $7 million.
But.
The price points that have made this happen are around $40 and then around $20.
So the titles that are doing lower price points at $5, $10 are having trouble making as much
money if you think about it, when there's only 100,000 users out there, 200,000 users
out there, it really is difficult to move software based on price rather than quality.
At this point, the way to move software is really to keep the quality high, get a high
user score, and keep your price point up around $20 to $40.
Also I'll point out that this is average price.
So this is based on the average of daily Steam pricing.
So we're not seeing a whole lot of summer steam scale style,
just drastic price cutting down to $5, $10 to move units.
The software that is developing and making more money
is keeping the price point high over time.
Those are some of the top titles there.
I'll show them on the next slide.
That has more call outs, if you want
to take a picture of that one.
So one thing that does really matter, and I think it's interesting because I hate to
piggyback on bashing professional critics when Bethesda is doing a lot of that lately
with not giving them early copies, user score really matters.
So when you look at the correlation between Steam user score and revenue on the HTC Vive,
there's a really strong correlation.
I should point out that this is max revenue.
So this is taking the number of owners, which we have really good data on, and steam average
pricing and multiplying them times each other because of things like giveaways and discounts
and returns that's typically about 15 to 20 percent higher.
But it's a good number for just looking at these overall correlations.
Here's some of the titles that have done the best.
Your top 15 performers on SteamVR.
So Virtual Desktop, Hubbard-Jenner's Call of Starsi,
You to Drift, Raw Data.
What do we got there?
Audio Shield, Space Pirate Trainer,
Vanishing Realms, Silent Approach.
A lot of these titles are also the ones
that have been getting awards.
And what we see in these titles is a lot of immersion,
right, deep immersion.
In general, the titles that are getting the awards,
that are moving the needle, that people are talking about,
are more about the immersion
and making someone feel like they're being transported
than they are about traditional game quality.
Things like content length, progression systems,
what we traditionally see moving user scores and review scores.
When we ask people, why do you purchase VR content?
These user scores really seem to matter, right?
It's the top endorsed reason that people
say that they purchase these games.
Interestingly, price is lower down the list.
And I'll tell you what, we ask this question
across a lot of different platforms.
This is the only platform that price is lower down the list.
If we ask this on mobile, price is not only at the top of the list, it's almost a quarter
in percentage past the next one down, which is genre.
So when we ask this on mobile, it's price and genre.
Is it a game that I know, I know the content type, and what's the price?
And then it goes to word of mouth.
So here, on VR, word of mouth isn't as much because most people don't own these systems yet.
Professional reviews are not up there.
People are going to user reviews and they're looking in these communities to see what people are saying about the game.
Now, one thing that doesn't seem to matter to drive user score, which I think is important
when you're thinking about developing this type of content, is the relationship between
user score and play time.
We don't see that there's a strong correlation between what your user score is and the total
time that people are putting into this content, right?
The average number of minutes.
The outlier here, which I think is very interesting,
is virtual desktop, right?
Because that is a type of experience on VR
that works well for putting in a lot of hours.
We have the best data for SteamVR.
I do know anecdotally that if this was showing GearVR
and showing mobile apps, it's Netflix, right?
That's popping out and showing a ton of average time played.
It's in the functional use for VR.
But what is heavily correlated is retention,
how often you're coming back to an app.
So this is that same graph showing the max revenue
or showing the user score versus how often people have come
back, what percentage have come back in the past two weeks.
A lot of VR is about sharing it.
A lot of VR, I mean, we all remember the first time
we took VR and got into it.
We all also know that it's very rare
to put somebody in it for the first time
and their jaw not to drop, right?
One of the most fun things about VR
and what drives a lot of the system purchase
is showing it off to other people
and getting that magical aha moment.
And these experiences that are getting the highest user score,
people do feel a need to show them off every couple of weeks or several times a day.
This retention metric is actually comparable to AAA at this point.
So this is showing five games or six games.
They are games that came out in April of May of 2016
around the launch of the Oculus and the Vive.
These titles are a couple big AAAs and then popular games on Steam VR.
Several of these titles are bundled in, so they're the most owned games on the platform.
I think The Lab, which is Valve's demo, by far the most owned HTC Vive game on the market.
So we see that really the only VR experience that even comes close in terms of total playtime
to the AAA titles is a functional application, right, is virtual desktop.
But when we look and we say, all right, what about retention?
It's actually very consistent.
All these VR titles have been returned
to in the past two weeks about as often
as these big AAA titles.
So people are feeling a need to come back and check out
this content.
When we look at this overall usage patterns,
I think we can start to see what are the experiences that are going to be driving the growth on
the platform.
These are some stock images that I pulled from a great article on the LA Times.
So basically it was a pretty funny article that had some great stock images.
If you're looking for stock images that are ridiculous, that's a great link to find them.
So, but basically that there are two ways that VR content is being used.
One is the functional accessible way.
This is to connect with people.
Things like virtual desktop, Netflix, Altspace is a really great social application.
And then there's things that completely transport and immerse people.
So, we're talking about the lab, which is a set of immersive experiences, raw data,
which as a game is only four levels.
The progression systems aren't even that deep.
But it does a really great job of making
you feel like you're there.
And because of that, it's able to get a really high user
score and move a lot of units at $40 price point.
And then Tilt Brush, just a wonderfully immersive
experience of painting in virtual reality.
So what does this look like if we
want to go and say, what's going to happen over the next two
to three years?
What is going to be the roadmaps, the paths,
for these different use cases in VR?
Well, I think we're at VR 1.0.
And this is the Samsung Gear VR platform.
This has been the early adopters on Steam VR,
really pushing immersion.
There's going to be a bridge over the next year or so
where we're going to get a lot more people involved in VR
because of PlayStation VR and the amount of units
that it's going to put on the market.
The Daydream, right now, it's going to be a little bit limited initially because of
Google support for which phones it's on, but as that pushes out to more Android phones,
that's also going to start to bring more immersion on mobile VR and more use cases because I
think it will be more broadly developed for.
We're also going to get the touch controls.
And the thing that's exciting about that is Oculus has pumped $500 million
into custom content and proprietary content that's really going to move
the needle in terms of what we would think of as AAA console development.
for VR. Then we're going into 3.0, which is I think where we really start to see some
growth, right? What this is, is Apple and Facebook, whenever Apple decides that it's
time to enter the space, which will be when they don't need to worry about their stock
price taking a dive because VR is here and they can be assured that their hardware is
going to be great and sell a lot of units. But then also on PC VR, there's a lot of great
improvements that are coming over the next couple years that will increase
this immersion that I'm talking about.
The idea of going untethered is big. That's huge. The idea
of eye tracking is big. That lets you do
more rapid acceleration without making people sick.
And then Microsoft entering the space with AR and mixed reality applications
and more accessible VR
I think is big as well.
Alright, so what does this look like in terms of revenue growth?
Well, one thing that we all agree upon, including John Riccatello at Unity, is that it's likely
to be exponential, right?
And the thing about an exponential curve is that you don't really feel the growth until
the growth really happened, right?
You're kind of walking along on flat, and then it happens, and you look back and you're
like, wow, I'm really high.
But at the point before it happens, you never even really see that you're right at the precipice,
about to take a quick acceleration up.
So if we take what I'm talking about and we turn that into an actual VR forecast.
This is our numbers.
I think we're at about 1.5 billion right now.
Growth over the next year to about three,
two years to about eight.
And we have those waves pushing that right now.
We're in the phase of early adoption right now.
That's kind of what we'd say is VR 1.0.
2.0 is gonna be console VR.
Microsoft will likely push into that as well,
as it makes sense for helping them catch back up
in the console race.
But when it's really gonna take off is mobile VR.
The growth of the industry is all about scale and the platforms that have the opportunity
to scale.
And that really comes from mobile, right?
And I think that Apple moving in whenever they do will really push that to the next
level when we'll really start to see exponential growth.
I think that the key for developers is to...
realize what the upside is right now on which platforms.
So maybe I can make a million and a half on the PC VR
platforms, or I can get a first party deal, which is sweet.
Or there's a several million dollar opportunity, PSVR,
over the next.
ear until that install base really grows,
but then being prepared to see when mobile VR takes off
and thinking about what type of functional applications
can really move the needle there.
And that's likely to be social, right?
And thinking about how to connect people
with mobile VR applications.
OK, that is my talk.
And it is time for questions.
Thank you.
Slides are available.
I know I threw a lot of data out there.
I already see a question.
We'll go there first.
We also do free EDAR white papers.
Check those out.
Going to be doing one on VR with some of this data
and more of that consumer data over the next month.
So go there and go back there often.
Doing a mobile one as well.
And then there's an email for our EDAR solutions.
And we have several minutes for questions, I believe.
Yes.
I think I did hear the question though, am I including standalone VR?
Talking about snap-in VR on your phone?
Absolutely, yeah. And if I go back to that slide, that's already, if you talk about like
the number of units that are out there, that's already the biggest by far. In January, Google
announced that they'd moved over five million cardboards alone, right? I know that retail
deals are, there's several million units of Snap and VR is going to move through Walmart
this year at least. So, when we say we're probably at...
you know, somewhere between 5 and 10 million right now.
I think after holiday this year, we'll be higher than that.
I'm sure that we've all tried that, right?
That is at a point on the scale where accessibility is as high as it can be.
It's super easy.
It is going to be an early way that some come into VR.
Yeah, see there we have it.
So at a $20 price point, you're by far the most units that we're seeing.
It's just...
Without the ability to hook into the phone,
the applications of what you can do are limited.
And I don't see a breakout functional use case
happening on that platform before it
would happen on a synced in mobile platform.
Yeah.
Thanks for the question.
So first let me say just thank you for this presentation.
It's extremely informative for those of us making VR games.
So thank you a lot for that.
The question I had was just looking at your stats on the
number of PCs with VR capable GPUs.
You had about 5 million.
Can you talk a little bit about where that data came from?
I know that NVIDIA's claimed that they had, earlier this
year, it was 10 or 13 million VR capable GPUs.
Where does that?
So that comes from conversations with other people in the VR hardware space that I would
say are more of an expert on that than myself.
And I will say that I think, and it is based on a VR compatible GPU being like a Radeon
970 or above, or an AMD, the one below the 1060.
You mean the Radeon 280 and the AMD, or the NVIDIA 970?
Correct, NVIDIA 970 and the 280. Correct.
Does that take into account the recent announcement that Rift made about supporting the 960, which is a lower level?
I think what we're seeing too is the movement down where because they're getting the technology
better to support lower that I will say that this is a conservative number and I would
agree that.
Now, I will say that I don't think it's much higher than maybe 10 million at most, but
I will say that it could be closer to 10 million.
about geographies. First of all, great, great, great information here. Thank you. With smartphones
and internet penetration growing at massive levels in emerging markets, I haven't, first,
the big question is how about emerging markets with this mobile VR penetration and adoption
and if it's at some point correlated with the type of content that is going to be offered
there.
So the question is what about regions and what about global regions and what's the opportunity
there?
And this actually gets back to talking about kind of the mobile VR because there's something
that I didn't think to mention, which is, okay, so first of all, we do have good region
data for these SteamVR games and the HTC Vive, and it is overwhelmingly Western markets.
It's about 50% United States, then a big chunk, maybe 35% Europe, and then the whole rest
of the world is coming up with the rest of that, and almost none of it is in emerging
markets.
So when we look at the high end, as you would expect because these are expensive systems,
they're almost all Western developed markets.
Now, I think that there is a huge opportunity for growth
of getting people involved in VR and moving low-end VR headsets,
moving $20 VR headsets.
The problem is that there's not a lot of money
to be made in software right now.
There's not a lot of money to be made in premium software
on mobile anyway.
It's free to play.
And then it's just very difficult
to make these experiences.
on a model that will move revenue on for a snap in mobile headset.
So what I would say is, and when we look at that pie
of that a billion and a half,
not a lot of it is mobile app revenue.
Most of it is moved by those premium headsets.
So if you are gonna make a low-end VR headset
that can snap in a smartphone,
I think there's a huge opportunity in emerging markets.
I also think that's a very competitive space,
working with some clients in that space,
with razor-thin margins where you need really good
connections with big retailers.
But I think that as these better mobile solutions become more broadly available,
as has happened in mobile, the growth areas years from now will be as those emerging markets catch up.
Thank you.
Good question.
Okay, awesome.
Alright guys, no more chance for questions,
but thank you so much.
If you had one, catch me outside.