My name is Miloš. I'm coming from Nordeus,
a gaming studio based in Belgrade.
I'm here to tell you a bit more about
our giving back efforts to the community.
I will mention community a few times
during this half an hour, and when I say community,
I mean the community where we are
working and living as a company.
So, for us, that's Serbia.
I'm going to talk about different strategical things,
different technical things.
And I hope there will be a lot for you to take away
from this lecture.
Ask yourself, why should we, as game producers, game
developers, give back to our communities?
I have a few reasons why.
First one, that we need to figure out that our businesses are an integral part of our
communities.
If our communities are not developing, our businesses in one moment will have problems
with the resources.
When I say resources, what I mean, I mean knowledge, I mean people, I mean funding.
We need to figure out the ways how to develop our community
so our business can grow with it.
Second important thing is that you need to stand out.
In this moment, there is hundreds, thousands,
gazillion companies that are very similar to yours.
And if you want to attract the brightest
and most passionate people to work for you,
You need to find a way how to stand out.
And if you show your future employees that you're thinking
strategically and how to develop your community, that
you're thinking strategically a few years ahead about your
business, and that you're having a cause that is bigger
than your business in some sense, that is one of the best
ways how to differentiate.
Eventually, if you don't want to do it, your players will
ask you to do it.
With all these generations that are now here,
millennials, set, epsilon, all these generations,
for all these generations,
purpose is something that is very important.
There is many, many surveys that shows
that millennials, for example,
will rather buy products from companies
that have some kind of purpose,
comparing, of course, to ones that don't have.
So.
One way or another, if you don't want to do it,
in one moment your players will ask you to.
These kind of activities are awesome way
to create a different type of engagement for your people.
When I say people, I mean your colleagues
that work with you.
When I say different engagement,
different than their everyday work.
And of course, that will create different content
for external and internal communication that you can use.
And of course, awesome content that you can use
to tell everybody what you are working on.
So how we started.
We, when we were founded 2010,
we didn't know a lot about giving back.
But we knew that we want to do it.
So what we did,
We asked our colleagues, hey guys,
what is the thing that you're passionate about?
And it was babies.
So, yeah, awesome, awesome thing to be passionate about.
And what we did, we invested one million euros
in the construction of 15 maternity wards in Serbia.
Those 15 maternity wards are responsible
for 30% of all babies born in our country.
Huge thing.
If you want to compare it to US market,
it's like we invested $180 million into some cause.
A lot, a lot of money there.
I'll talk a lot about Serbia.
So for starters, let me give you a little bit of context
who we are as a Nordius and who we are as a country.
So as I said, we are founded in 2010.
We have three games published by now.
And one that we are mostly known for is Top Eleven,
Football Manager.
We have 200 million registered users.
And Top Eleven is one of the most successful games for
mobile platforms in sports category.
We also have Golden Boot and Heroic, which are out there
for a short period of time.
But we will see how they will develop.
We are cool.
of 170 people from 22 nationalities.
So very, very diverse group.
And as I said, we are based in Belgrade, Serbia.
So Serbia, not Siberia.
Siberia is in Russia, it's very cold there, bears, snow.
Probably half of Siberia is not even livable.
We're in Eastern Europe, in Balkans region.
Very beautiful region, small region,
but with very turbulent history.
We as a country have very thriving IT industry right now
and worldwide we are known for our tech talents.
Also, we are very known through history
for our scientists and our sportsmen.
So to test your knowledge,
Do you know who this guy is?
Tesla.
I cannot see anything, but I heard Tesla somewhere.
That's right, Nikola Tesla.
So this is the guy that this Tesla Automotive Company
was named by, and he's responsible
for all the electricity we have here.
So what he did, he created a system
to transport electricity in long distances.
Of course, he did many other amazing things,
but this is the one that he's mostly known for.
And he lived a lot of his,
like half of his life here in US.
Mihailo Pupin.
It's not a quiz because probably you wouldn't know who he is,
but he's a very cool guy.
Why?
He has a crater on the moon named by him.
And he was the one of the founders of NASA.
Also, he perfected the phone.
So, not mobile phone, the landline phone,
so our parents would be very happy with him.
But he did also some many amazing things
in different areas.
And do you know this guy?
Come on.
Yeah, maybe I heard greatest tennis player
of all time somewhere.
Yeah.
I think he is, maybe we can argue about it
and talk a little bit after,
but 70 and something titles speak a lot who he is.
So, small country with some amazing people out there
and tech talents thriving in the industry.
But let's get back to our babies.
So how we did this activity?
We supported the NGO that was working on this project.
We give them financial support,
and we support this activity
in different communication ways.
So we help them spread the word about it.
And mostly that was it,
because we couldn't use our expertise in this area
because we do not know anything about babies,
except they are cute, et cetera.
So, before we go more deeply into the reconstruction,
let me give you one other example from Serbia
of giving back activity.
This activity is from the banking sector,
so I have to use this very generic banking slide to show it.
And you're right, there is something missing here.
This guy is like the guy for the whole corporate PPTs
and you can find him everywhere.
But the text out there, it's something that is not generic,
so pay attention on it.
What this bank did in Serbia,
if you want to take a loan as an entrepreneur,
your company must be older than two years.
You're too risky for the banks
and they don't want to give you a loan.
What this bank did,
they created a support educational system
that gave you a consultancy before you asked for a loan,
somebody to help you to develop your business plan,
to understand how your business should look like
in the future.
And when you get your loan,
they gave you a mentorship in duration of one year,
where some entrepreneur from your industry
will help you to further develop your business.
So essentially, they created a product
and attached different giving back activities on it.
We have these two examples side by side.
Let's try to compare them and understand the differences.
So we can both agree that both of them are giving back.
Their activities for the community,
they are solving some problems out there,
so that's out there.
Can you help me with this?
In what ways were companies involved?
When you look at the activity that we did,
in what way were we involved as a Nordius
in this battle for maternity wards?
Finance.
Finance, you're true, you're right, you're true.
You're right.
So, and the bank?
Service?
Yeah, service, knowledge, people.
They use the expertise of their people
to create a value for the community.
How their people were involved, our people were involved in communication.
We were out there, we were talking about the things that we were doing, we were opening
maternity wards, we were trying to use our PR agencies to help to spread the word, etc.
And the bank, the bank used the expertise and knowledge of their people to really do
some work out there and help entrepreneurs directly.
How this impacted the businesses?
For us, when we thought about it,
we didn't thought about the business
when we made the decision to support
Battle for Maternity Wards.
It was a burning problem in Serbia.
We just wanted to solve it.
We want to help our community,
so we just went out there and did it.
And it's very hard to put a value
when you're helping babies.
You never know.
It's very hard to calculate it in your business.
But for the bank, they created a pipeline
for their future customers.
When you help entrepreneurs in early stage,
it's very, very probably they will stay with you
after they grew and become a stable business.
When it comes to external communication, a lot of people asked us why babies?
Where is the connection?
What's happening there?
Why are you as a gaming company helping babies?
And for the bank, it was something that was very logical to explain.
Since, hey, we are a bank, we are a financial institution, we are helping entrepreneurs
start their businesses.
Super logical.
So nobody asked them why, they just asked them to give them more information how we
can help.
So when we have those two examples side by side,
what do you think, which one of those
will have longer impact,
bigger impact in the long run?
Let's show up hands.
Who think the baby example?
And the bank?
So probably others.
You heartless people, you choose banks before babies.
But you're right.
bank will have the bigger impact.
Why?
Because their giving back activity
is integrated in their product.
And their product, when this activity will help them
grow as a business, so the impact,
when you're calculating it over the years, will grow.
Just imagine the situation where we, as a gaming company,
ran into some problems.
This activity will be the first one that should be cut.
Because that's how businesses work.
You have like expense,
it's not giving any value to a business,
cut it and move on.
So in that sense, the bank will create more impact.
Also, what is important,
this activity was a part of a bigger strategy.
It was just one of activities
that was aimed to create a value for the community.
So when we finished with our giving back,
with our Battle for Maternity Awards activity,
we wanted to figure out, okay,
how should we use more knowledge
and our expertise to help community out?
And what we did, we created a strategy
that has four different stakeholders in it.
First, stakeholders are employees.
We wanted to figure out the ways how we can help our employees
give back to the causes they care about.
So we want to create different internal events,
different fundraisers to help them to do it.
Other stakeholders are players.
We, as a gaming company, have a huge platform, our game,
or now our games, that will grow.
And those platforms and those players
have some causes that they're passionate about.
And we want to use our platforms as a way
to give them opportunity to give back.
Third is environment.
There is a huge talk about environment
and what kind of, like...
about the problems that we are in right now.
So we don't want to be a part of the problem.
We want to try and be part of the solution
and think about how we're using our resources
and what can we do better.
And fourth, which is most important for us
and probably most interesting for you, is community.
So when we were thinking about how to help out our community,
we figured out that there are three challenges out there.
First one is very low level of digitalization in Serbia.
So our systems are very outdated.
We are still waiting in lines, in post offices, banks.
We don't use modern tools in our everyday business
or administration.
And we wanted, as a company, to figure out how to help there.
Second thing is education.
We have an outdated higher education,
which is not creating talents that
are needed for this fourth industrial revolution.
We want to change that.
And third thing is, we as a gaming company,
we care about gaming ecosystem.
In Serbia, the gaming ecosystem is very underdeveloped,
and we wanted to set as our mission
to find a way how to help that ecosystem develop.
First thing that we did to go out
and solve all of these problems
is create an umbrella organization
with like-minded companies.
Why an umbrella organization?
We figured out that if you want to tackle the systemic problems,
like huge problems, you need to work very closely with the state.
You need to go and change the laws.
You need to work with ministries.
And we, as a company, we didn't have that power to do it.
So we created Digital Serbia Initiative
with 26 like-minded companies that are from different industries.
So we will have more.
We'll have more soft power to use
when we are dealing with different stakeholders on top.
We wanted to figure out how to solve problems in these areas.
First one is higher education.
Second one is legal framework.
Third, startup ecosystem.
And fourth, we want to figure out the ways
how we can help
Why their public understand the importance of digitalization and such.
So when we had an umbrella organization,
the second thing we wanted to do is create a physical space
from where we can run these changes.
So we created the Nordeus Hub.
Nordeus Hub is a co-working slash event space
where it's a physical space very close to our office.
And from there, we want to do different things
in the community.
We want to run different programs for talents.
We want to help talents develop even further
and help them to start creating value
for their community as early as possible.
Also, we want to help out the community-driven programs.
So we want to help communities,
programs that are coming from community
to have a space where they can do their programs
and help them increase their impact.
We want to help our people develop even further
so they can increase their impact on the community.
And fourth, we want to help Serbian Gaming Association
develop the gaming industry as much as possible.
We're helping them to do different events
in Nordius Hub, and also run different programs
in our Hub for Gaming community.
I'm going to tell you a little bit more about those programs.
So first is Game Making Boot Camp.
We figured out that our students in Serbia
are not getting into any touch with the gaming industry.
during their studies.
So if they're playing games, that's
the only way how they communicate.
Because in our curriculums, there
isn't anything that is connected to the gaming industry.
So we figured out that we have to show them
how gaming industry looks like from inside.
And we created a boot camp that will have different tracks for different type of students
to show them a bigger picture how the gaming industry looks.
We will have a track for artists, we will have tracks for game devs, we will have a
track for business development, game designers, etc.
And with the idea...
to put the gaming industry and career in gaming
as one of the first few choices for the students
when they think about what is my next step in the career.
Second program is Indie Game Incubator.
We want to develop a gaming industry in Belgrade, in Serbia.
And if we want to do that, we figured out
that we do not have a mechanism that is creating or supporting
new and upcoming gaming studios.
So what we did, we created an incubator program
which will last six months,
and it will consist from coworking space for six months.
We will also do assessment in the game studio
and give them mentors for different areas
where they need help the most.
And we will organize different workshops that are more,
they're like general business workshops,
that will help businesses understand the other roles
their business needs to have,
like HR, finance, accounting, law, et cetera.
We hope that this program will help us to produce
one, two, three.
game, new gaming studios in the future, and it will help us fuel the gaming industry.
This example, this is also one activity that we did,
but it's not connected to our community,
it's more connected to our community of our players.
But I wanted to mention it to you
just for you to understand how you can use your games
maybe to impact your players.
Do you maybe know what is this?
Have you heard about War Child Football Club?
No? Yeah.
It's a soccer club.
So, not football, soccer club.
And the World Child is an organization
that is helping children...
reintegrate into their societies after they survived
some kind of war or they lived near the war zone, et cetera.
War Child Football Club is the program they are running
in Central African Republic,
where they want to use football or soccer
as a tool to help those children
reintegrate into their society.
For us, we have a football game,
and it was an easy match to make.
You can see they have very funky jerseys.
And those jerseys, they're using those jerseys in real life
and they're awesome looking.
So what we figured out, what we can do,
we offered those jerseys in our in-game shop.
So you can buy those jerseys and their emblem
in our in-game shop and all the proceedings will go to them.
The response from the community was amazing.
The sales of this jersey surpassed the sales of jerseys
from some of the most famous soccer clubs,
football clubs in the world,
like Real Madrid, Paris Saint-Germain, and others.
For us, this is just scratching the surface.
It's a new turf, but I think there are studios out there
that are doing a great job with this,
and I think this is a territory where we can do
so many amazing things in the future.
So, let's summarize how we got there,
and how maybe you, when you go home,
can retrace our steps and maybe be here
even in a few years and talk about it.
First of all, try to start with anything, really.
Don't overthink it.
You go back home and think about
what is the cause that you are passionate about,
or what is the cause that your company is passionate about.
It's just, or your people that are passionate,
just go out there and solve it.
We did it with the Better for Maternity awards.
And in the end, it was something that created a huge value.
We solved a huge problem.
So it's just important to start somewhere.
But when you're doing that,
think about what are the problems out there
in the community that...
really you or your company have expertise and knowledge to solve it and that you are
of course passionate about it.
For us, those were higher education, digitalization, and gaming ecosystem.
When you figure out those challenges, try to figure out what are the knowledge, what
are the skills and expertise you have that you can use in solving those problems.
Look, money can be given by anybody.
But the expertise and knowledge we have as an industry,
it's quite unique.
For Serbia, it's certainly totally unique
because maybe there is one, two, three companies in Serbia
that created the product from scratch
and had a global success with it.
But for your communities, it's important to understand
what are your skills that you excel
and knowledges that you excel
and how you can transfer and create value for the community.
And of course, try to create a holistic strategy around it.
Try to understand who are the people
that you want to impact and try to understand
what are the ways that you can impact them.
We're just in the beginning of this adventure as a gaming industry.
The rest of the world and the rest of the industries went a few steps ahead,
but the important thing is that we are not pioneers,
so we can maybe use the knowledge and experience they had
to start a few steps ahead of them.
and try to do amazing things.
We have responsibility to try
because we're in the entertainment industry.
We are very high grossing industry.
And what is more important,
we are like touching so many lives out there.
So many people that are living in so many,
in many different communities with many different problems.
And we have a platform that we can use to harvest.
different skills, expertise, money, or whatever it is,
and try to solve some problems out there.
Thank you so much.
This was all for me.
It was an amazing experience being here and talking with you.
Please, if you have some questions, feel free to ask.
I think we'll have three, four minutes.
Anyhow, if we don't have more time to do it,
I will be in Overlook 2014 for 45 minutes.
So you can come over there and talk to me.
Also, these are my contacts, so feel free to reach out
and say hi or ask any questions you have.
Thank you so much.
How many people does it take?
And what's the size that you need to do something like this?
It really depends, but you need to...
Yeah, it really depends.
Right now, from Node.js perspective,
there is always 10, 20 people involved in some capacity.
And it differs because there is different activities,
so we need different skill set,
but you need to have one person that will...
lead the charge.
It doesn't have to be a full-time person, but it has to be somebody that will think
about how these activities are progressing, and the person that will talk with others,
with managers, with people in the company, to try to help them understand what is the
scope of the job and how they can be involved.
So out of the 15 to 20 people, none of those are full-time on this?
It's just a passion that they have?
Yeah.
It's a passion that they have, and also it's something that we...
We present this as part of their job and their time that they can use.
So it's something that we are very passionate about as a company, so we mindfully invest
time in it.
Thank you.
Please.
I wanted to ask you, what were the biggest challenges?
You talked about that you did a program for teaching game development, right?
Yep.
What were the biggest challenges to setting all that up?
For us, the biggest challenge was to understand the market out there,
because our gaming industry is very segmented in the sense that there is like
so many different gaming studios in different stages of development.
And to create a program that will give value for all of them, it's very hard.
And that was one of the biggest challenges.
I think that we will see, because this program is now
ongoing, what I can see the future problems could be
is maybe inflow of those new.
We need to spin a few rounds of this game making boot camp
so we will have more people interested in making games
in the future so we can help them.
And also, yeah, those are like briefly the problems,
but there are many challenges out there, yeah.
And just like a positive side note,
like how did the kids react?
Like did they love it?
No, they enjoyed so much.
They're constantly out there.
They're like, hey, how can we do this?
You know, they're like asking to have more time with us,
to be there, and a lot of those children
then ask what we can do next.
What are our next steps? How can we be involved more?
So I think the reaction was great.
That's awesome. Thank you.
Please.
Your indie game, Incubator, you mentioned.
Obviously, EuroStudio would have put in a lot of time
and effort and money into things like PR
and things like that for those.
I'm curious what sort of systems you
have for dealing with the revenue
that any of those games brought in,
whether it was a revenue sharing or a royalty-based thing
or what.
Thank you for your question.
We don't ask for anything.
We don't even do PR.
So for us, because it's a very unique situation in Serbia.
Nordeus is very popular there because it's like a startup child that everybody was looking for
and from like in our eight years we grew to be such a huge success in Serbia,
so everybody knows about us.
In that sense, we don't need to do any PR, we are very recognizable.
And on the other hand, this is our giving back activity.
We want to, what we want to do.
We are seeing the benefits in creating the industry that
will come much later when we have 10 or 15,
30 successful gaming studios that we can maybe,
that we can benefit from it in the future.
So for right now, we don't want to use any,
we don't want to ask for any money, any investment,
or anything.
We just want to be there to help them out, to start,
and to see how it will develop.
Okay, so there are other people that are in the indie game incubator then.
Are they like officially working for you or are they separate?
No, they are our colleagues that are using part of their time and their expertise to help in different areas.
Okay, and last question, is your studio retaining the intellectual property rights for anything they make or are they themselves?
No, no, no, no, everything, we don't take any credits, we don't take any royalties, nothing.
We're just there to help out.
Okay, thank you.
Thank you.
So, uh-huh, please.
Sorry, one more.
Was there anything specifically, politically, logistically, that caused a lot of friction on the way to getting the system set up?
From... those kind of frictions we have in this, like, higher scale solving of the problems,
in a sense, like dealing with the ministries in higher education, etc.
For incubator programs, those are all run by us.
And we have an expertise how to do them.
We have a space, so we have resources put into them.
In that sense, we didn't have a lot of big frictions.
But when we are dealing with changing the higher education
laws or trying to implement different game-connected
curriculums to the universities, it
can be very hard to push because those systems are very slow.
They're not reacting good to change.
So from that perspective, there are challenges.
Thank you.
Please.
This is all very awesome, definitely, you all think about this a lot, and I think that's
great.
I did have a question.
One of the pillars you mentioned was your players.
I was curious if you'd experimented at all with, I mean, having such a large player base
and mobilizing them directly in any ways, or communicating with them about these initiatives.
About the local initiatives that we are doing,
we didn't do anything around it.
So for us, the players are also the huge unexplored area
that we need to do.
The only activity that we did is this one,
and the one with one special day that we just
fundraise for them.
But it was nothing that, so the only activity that involved player like very directly was
the activity for World Child Football Club.
But I think there is like a huge potential there that we can tap into.
But the game studios that did amazing things around this is Riot.
They have a few different awesome initiatives, how they involved players with buying different
skins and et cetera.
So you can look them up and maybe there is something that can help you out.
Thank you.
Okay people, thank you so much.
I'll be in Overlook if you want to chat,
and thank you for being here.