My name is Becca Saltzman, um, and yeah, it's better to be friends, marketing ass, than the reality of game production.
Uh, I am the CEO and co-founder of Finji, which is, uh, both a publishing partner or a publisher and also an independent development team.
So we kind of run both.
We're kind of, we're very weird in the industry and we've been doing it for a while.
Um, my partner is Adam Saltzman, who is our creative director.
Um, he runs our development team.
Um, and if you recognize his name, um, online, his name is Adam Atomics.
We,
was Overland.
And we're based in Grand Rapids, Michigan, so we're also in a weird part of the world.
Um, so, so, so, so, so, so, so, so, so, so, so, so, so, so, so, so, so, so, so, so, so,
We make a bunch of games, um, I mentioned two already, Overland and Canabalt.
Um, we also publish games like Tunic, I was a teenage exo-colonist, Chicory, A Colorful Tale, and Night in the Woods, among a lot of others.
Um, our studio is roughly, I'm giving you some context so you understand how small we are, um, which is important at something like GDC.
Our studio is roughly divided in half.
um there are approximately 4 biz dev and marketing um community management and launch operations staff and then kind of everyone else is on either QA or development um and that's about like 12 people.
Um we also have a few like floaters as far as like contract workers who pop in and out on various mostly engineering tasks.
Um
We also work with a marketing studio out of the UK called ICO or ICO.
And they help roll out our PR and marketing plans.
And we've done this since 2021.
Our launches have kind of gotten too big for just the four of us.
I specifically run the biz side of Finji.
I'm also a core creative team member on both community and marketing initiatives that we produce.
And I'm also a member of the creative team on our internal development.
our game that we're making internally.
It's a really big job and I sometimes wonder what I got myself into when I go to work every morning.
I am also, and this is very important, I'm always the first to know when my studio and my games are being considered for high profile marketing events.
Those emails come to me directly and it's my job to ensure that our teams are prepared to support both external marketing initiatives and internal marketing plans.
And we have been involved in a lot of them.
So that's who I am, just some context.
And I have a question.
Oh, it is doing this.
Okay, so fun bug in PowerPoint, and I'm just gonna point this out so you understand why I'm going back and forth, is that it's supposed to say marketing.
and now it does.
So, if I go back and forth, I apologize.
I don't know what's going on with PowerPoint right now.
Um, so, the schedule problem.
We are just mining our own business.
We're like running our development, um, milestones.
We're like getting our dev teams all together and then marketing comes in and is like, marketing initiative!
You need to make a trailer in six weeks and you're like, yeah, F you!
Are you insane?
We can't do that.
And that's our schedule problem.
A team comes in, drops a massive project change onto your team without notice and you're left scrambling to figure out how to deliver the project and also make a game.
Because the, to deliver the project, the outcome requires that you pull development resources off the current milestones and this will often halt the bottle, or basically halt everything, bottleneck development in a pretty serious way.
And we've all done this.
Um, so are there any marketing folks here in the room?
Yeah!
Hi!
you're, you're team marketing uh everyone else is production and I know for a fact that right now you're like thinking in your head we hate each other so much because marketing comes in it's like I need this thing because we do.
It came in our email and production's like how dare you come and ask me for this asset.
We don't have time for this or the budget and both realities are valid.
It's just how it is and this talk is like well how,
can we never have that conversation where we hate each other and we're cursing at each other and we act like preschoolers in our own offices and roll our eyes and continue to have poor collaborative communication practices.
So I want you to know it doesn't have to be this way, at least not the way you experience it now.
You shouldn't have to delay marketing assets until a request comes in.
You can plan for these in your development schedule.
and it's going to do it again because PowerPoint hates me.
So external opportunities, this is the thing that we call all of these emails that come in, which is our polite way of saying thank you, Sony, for this external opportunity.
Thank you, Nintendo, I appreciate
that external opportunity.
Because as a marketing person, we also hate these e-mails and love them.
Because we know what it's going to do to everybody on the team to support it.
They're really big projects.
They're also really good for studios and for your team.
Anyone who can amplify your message, like, you should do that.
It's very noisy out there.
So these are self-directed or externally directed times, these external marketing opportunities.
When you are going to publicly participate in some kind of marketing event, we're at one right now.
There are a lot of teams right now that are also flying to PAX East.
My team is there right now.
There are teams who have been working for months and months to participate at these events with trailers, demos, and other assets.
And the events are great, but they're also a nightmare to support for any size of team.
So, because these events usually start outside, um, of the studio, they have the potential to seriously disrupt the development and schedule of the game.
Um, and I don't know about you, but I could do without the additional stress.
Um, the sprints, crunch, frustration, and burnout, um, and there should be another way forward.
So, I'm going to give you some context as kind of,
I'm trying to think of, the kind of external opportunities that we, just in the last five years, that I have supported with my studio.
And we'll see if this works.
So, a quick disclaimer, um, we've supported both PlayStation State of Play and PlayStation Indies.
Um, I've done a Nintendo Direct and a Nintendo Indie World, um, the Xbox E3 press conference, plus their Twitch events.
uh, the game awards, that's a fun one, and very weird.
Uh, Apple keynotes and product launches, um, also additional partner events, conventions, uh, old PSX, PlayStation experience for example, demo events, plus the online develop, uh, demo events, et cetera, uh, and more, and more, and more.
It's like endless, these are endless events.
Um, and as I mentioned, we are a very, very small studio.
and we are in these all the time, and it should destroy us.
So, the collaborative marketing process.
I'm gonna talk about the process that Finji uses to plan, prep, and produce marketing assets alongside our internal development schedules across our separate teams, of which there are many, because we do publish as well.
it went up.
Uh so first planning.
Uh we plan as early as possible and this seems really obvious um and I'll get to this in a second.
This is the type of marketing strategy that focuses on when a marketing team is considering how to use events around the industry as external megaphones and how those types of partnerships require deadlines that are externally enforced.
And we literally spend the bulk of our time in this phase.
Because as long as we plan
We are able to prepare all of our things in advance, and I'm going to explain how this is possible.
These are the things that we do to anticipate future marketing asks, and we are given possible outcomes in collaboration with our marketing teams.
to identify the marketing needs sort of externally with our business partners.
And then when we get to produce, we usually only spend about 10% of our time on this because we've done so much planning and prep work that everything is there, everything is ready for us to put together the asset and get it out as soon as possible.
In most cases, we're only at a polish phase when we finally get to this.
So, I mentioned this already.
Oh no, it's gonna do it again.
The thing we're gonna talk about the most today is how to plan for these things as early as possible.
And a lot of this is going to be about communications, the questions that you can ask, and the things that you can prepare and build into your development schedules.
Okay, so questions for production teams, and there's a lot of marketers here.
They're also for you as well.
So, we are going to talk about a lot of stuff.
Um, since we're all sitting here right now, I don't have a very good idea of what kind of studios you come from.
I don't know if you're a studio of one or a studio of a thousand.
So, these are going to be kind of high level things that you can take back and use to create a process within your studio.
Um, I'm going to do my best to define things that you may not know and point out things that you might want to research later.
Um,
I know that I'm speaking to both marketing and production professionals, um, and I know that some of this might be unknown territory between those two, um, like aspects of game development.
So, things are gonna be working together today.
Why is there a disconnect between the discipline schedules and priority?
How does this limit good collaborative communication?
How can external marketing asks affect development teams?
Uh, your anticip- anticipatory pipelines, um, what, how can you build those?
I love that.
I would like to talk to somebody about this bug.
How can you control for these timelines?
What kind of milestones and test, tasks can you build into your production schedules to address the needs of all of your team?
And what kind of, uh, anticip, anticipatory pipelines can you build?
Um, so, we're gonna plan as early as possible.
Do you know what information you need?
And the answer is, maybe.
So when I was asked to give this talk, I was in a group of production professionals, and someone I look up to said, it would be incredible if there was a talk at GDC that talked about how we can plan for the things for our marketing teams to ask.
Supporting those just kills our development schedules, and it's awful.
And I was like, damn, that's like my whole job.
It's my wheelhouse.
I can talk about this.
And when this came up, I was a few days from participating in our first Nintendo Directs.
This was last fall, which took months
of preparation for our team, completely over the timeline of when we were launching I Was a Teenage Exo-Colonist on PC, Storefriends, also PS4, 5, and Switch.
We were also optimizing and developing Tunet for PlayStation 4, 5, and Nintendo Switch, and also running patches on the original Xbox builds of the game.
We were really, really busy.
And Nintendo coming in and being like, how about a direct, which is like a really big event in our industry, was very scary.
but we planned for this across our small teams for years before we got to September 2022.
This was a possibility and an outcome that might have come up and we did a lot of work in advance for it.
So do you know what information you need to support a marketing initiative?
Possibly.
Do you know what questions you need to ask?
Do you know how to get that information?
And this is what we're going to be chatting about first.
So dev production.
There is a misunderstanding about timelines.
When we talked about marketing timelines and dev timelines, we are like in different universes.
Dev timelines, we're talking about weeks, months, years.
I love them.
They're so comfortable for me.
When we talk about marketing timelines,
The email I got this morning may not even exist tomorrow.
Whatever they asked for is no longer even a project.
It was on fire and now it's gone.
Our task and projects list just for this week will change completely often.
We don't have the luxury
of weeks and months and years, even though we really would like that to exist.
And when you're talking to each other as production, dev production and marketing, this is where the disconnect often happens.
Because we're like, well, why can't you just give this to me?
Marketing.
And dev is like, are you insane?
That doesn't exist.
It's not going to exist until next year because we're on different schedules.
So, we need to control for the unknown.
We need to integrate our marketing team into the development process, which is a lot of education and I'm not going to sugar coat that.
It is a lot of like, no, that's a misunderstanding.
Like, no, that's not how that actually works.
I love you very much, let's go out to lunch and talk about how the holistic process of the studio actually flows together.
But since your marketing team's goals may change at a moment's notice, it's easy to think, well, let's ignore them until they really need something.
which, I mean, been there, been ignored before, but the opposite is actually a healthier approach, because your marketing team is going to need the same assets no matter what.
I was talking to somebody earlier, I was like, can you imagine going up to a dev team and being like, I'm going to need a trailer, and the dev team is like, what?
A trailer?
I'm going to have to launch this game someday?
And the answer is yes.
you're gonna have to launch, these are things you're going to have to make, no matter what, it has to exist.
So the idea that this could possibly ever just drop into your scope is baffling.
So marketing, gotta remind them a little bit earlier.
So not just the trailer, but like you're gonna have to have key art, you're gonna have to have B-roll, you're gonna probably need a behind closed doors demo.
These are all things that are so normal to game marketing and we just throw them on the dev team kind of last minute.
So instead of ignoring them, we should be bringing the dev team in.
We should be educating them on the future assets that they're going to need and we're going to integrate them into your team so you can never be ambushed again, but on both sides.
So how do you integrate this?
How do you sort of take a marketing lead into a development process?
And what is the purpose and goal of this relationship?
So we have knowledge on the game design that's happening outside the game, and I'll explain that in one second.
We have knowledge on the game design that's happening inside the game.
Producers know what's happening inside the game, and marketing leads know what's happening outside the game.
and you can have a meeting about these two things.
I want to, not necessarily back up exactly, but I am going to tell you a little bit about marketing design in just one second.
You're going to want to structure the meetings that you have between these two types of design.
to get at the goals of your team and what ideas that you have and what timelines that they're planning for.
How do you want to talk about your project to the outside world?
And these are all going to feed back into what you should be working on internally.
So sitting down with your marketing team means that you can do the following.
Marketing can play the game and ask questions.
They can review design documents like story bibles, not to make the game more marketable, but to ask them what ideas they have about future marketing angles.
production can ask what types of marketing materials the marketing team would like to access.
And when they think, they might need those assets.
And then they can continue to circle with regular meetings closer and closer and closer, um, to launch, um, because development is going to continue and continue to hone in on like the exact marketing, the exact marketing message, um, outside of this.
Um,
outside of like internal from the studio.
The communication needs to happen outside.
So, the more you know.
uh we need to document the possibilities.
And this relationship requires a give and take from the design team and the marketing team.
So you're going to need to sort of dig down and talk about like how would these possible initiatives, these marketing initiatives, overlap future external deliverable schedules.
So, what does that mean?
These are words that I'm spouting at you.
Imagine that you're like I'm going to be in a state of play in, when do state of plays happen?
Out February?
October?
those two dates.
February, October, sometimes the middle of the year one.
I'm going to be in a state of play in October of this year.
Or I want to work towards that.
That's going to require a trailer.
It's going to require a blog post.
If a marketing team knows that they would like to make some kind of announcement like that, they would have that information probably at least, at least a year in advance.
That that's what they're going to be working towards.
And if you as a production team don't ask that question, when would you like to announce a thing, you cannot
develop something to support it.
So how do these possible initiatives fit into partner expectations?
So we partner with a lot of people, Xbox, PlayStation, Nintendo, Apple.
What expectations do they have about this?
Has the marketing team, who talks to these partners, expressed the goals to you, the dev team?
Because otherwise you're going to be making two different things.
And then how do these things that they're asking for impact development at a glance?
Can you see where you're going to fall short on the expectations that people outside of your development structure have?
So to answer these questions, you should be looking at your development schedule.
You need to ask, are you building the right parts of the game to support future marketing assets?
You should be able to answer that.
If marketing comes back and like, I'm pretty certain I'm going to need to put a boss fight in a trailer next year, and boss fights take a little while, you should probably be like, I need to push some stuff around.
like we're going to have to build a boss fight.
Um, if your publisher or partner wants to see, um, like a different angle working towards a marketing asset or they have an angle that they want to work towards, if you don't know what that is, you can't build for it.
Um, so yeah, there's, you need to be able to take your marketing team, um, that like there are two true things.
Like, here's an update and give good parameters and boundaries on what is settled content and what is not.
And then talk about external schedules and partner expectations that might change and morph on long development schedules.
And then you need to follow up again and again and again in all of your meetings.
So the more the dev team knows, in order to get your development team to
understand the things that you're going to be working for, you're going to need to communicate future marketing opportunities to the creative leadership.
So,
marketing teams, we're just going to sort of bounce outside of this for a second.
Marketing teams have, internally we call them a marketing beat schedule.
Other teams might call it something else where they might look at the two years in front of you and be like, I, based on the development schedule that's been expressed to me, we're going to probably want to announce a title here, we're going to need to do these certain things in between our next big beat, which might be a demo or another content drive.
and that's going to be sort of mapped out over the course of like a couple of years.
It's going to have like social media, it's going to have advertising, it's going to be a lot of stuff in a marketing beat schedule.
Anytime you have one of those things, a marketing team should be able to take that to your creative leadership and to the production schedule and sort of talk about the range and scope
of what's going on inside of that particular document.
Because marketing is able to see opportunities here and here and here.
And we need to be able to put together the most important and interesting parts of the game in order to support those particular marketing initiatives.
As part of that, as a production team, you're going to sort of, with the marketing team, identify the sort of parameters around this.
basing this on an evaluation of what is possible versus what is desirable.
So you're filling in the boundaries of the full scope of the development schedule sitting out in front of you.
And you're probably going to say, but Becca, my creative team is really difficult.
My marketing team is really difficult.
But as a producer, it's your job to be able to go into a meeting between a creative team and a marketing team.
identify the problems that marketing is saying that they need to solve, and the creative team the assets and the development that can solve them.
Like, it's your job to sort of put those two pieces together.
In order to communicate future marketing opportunities to the creative leadership
If the people who make the creative decisions don't know what the future expectations likely might be, you're not actually going to be able to make well-intentioned decisions to be able to support them.
which involves identifying the overlap between marketing and what you're building.
Because what you're building is so huge and what marketing is building is so huge and there's only a very small overlap in the middle of identifying the marketing needs from development.
And it's like, what part of the game that you're making fulfills this in the coolest way?
So, there's some examples of things that you can do kind of during this particular time.
If you've had the conversations, if you're able to identify the problems that the marketing team is intending to solve, there are lots of parts that you can plan for in advance.
So, for example,
you're gonna have to build a trailer, an announced trailer, title announced trailer.
Are you able to storyboard this in advance?
Are you able to sit down with your marketing team, identify the talking points that marketing team is going to have to prepare materials around.
It's going to be an action RPG with X amount of combat and this sort of main character fulfilling these genre requirements.
with the assets that you have and the development, like sort of vertical slice, the game that you have available, can you storyboard out what is possible in that exact moment and how does that adapt throughout the next possibly up to a year before you actually have to make that trailer?
You're already sitting on the plans before you have to go into actually developing that asset.
A thing that we do often is we build our vertical slices to also accommodate different types of demos.
Um, so when we go into pre-production and then early production, we're already sitting on at least 45 up to like 90 minutes of a game that we developed intentionally to support early marketing asks like a 15 minute show demo that we can cut very quickly out of it.
Um, it's all, all been highly polished or um,
uh gone through like all the VFX treatments um and we can also cut that into a longer sort of online steam demo.
That's early early assets and sometimes we have that done upwards of a year in advance.
Um we also do this because this can also be cut into a trailer as well.
We're sitting on at least 90 minutes of a game, we cut that into a trailer and then we are not asking for additional assets when that does come in.
So this is all done because this is all
these are all assets that are going to be needed and we can front load them and then sit on those for as long as possible.
Because they're going to be marketing needs that would ordinarily destroy our studio.
We didn't used to do this.
The first tunic trailer that came out at the E3 showcase in 20 some time in the past.
I don't know if years have passed since then, but it was
2018.
We didn't have any of this sitting around, and we had to do whole, like, boss designs for it, which is why the librarian looks very different than it does now in the final game.
That was designed in about four weeks before the trailers put together.
And it was a huge problem when we were going to launch the game, like, would somebody actually notice?
The answer is no.
So we prepare in advance.
This is sort of what came out of that particular experience, which was we had to stop Tunic development entirely in 2018 in order to build a trailer.
We have stopped doing that.
We prepare almost everything that we do in advance, and we schedule this into production itself.
If we know we have a trailer, everyone has a trailer.
Everyone in this room, you're making games, you have a trailer.
The thing that you should be thinking of right now is what the hell in the build that you're making can be used in a trailer.
What story are you trying to tell?
And your marketing team does know that information.
So another Finji example.
Tunic needed a new demo as we were sprinting towards launch to address an issue that we had with future players thinking that the game was more Zelda than Dark Souls.
Which if you saw early Tunic stuff, it was like a fox running around a dappled forest with a sword and wearing a tunic.
the name has nothing to do with that but uh wearing a little green shirt and like looks like a Zelda clone and we were very aware of it um but the game also has tricky combat and a lot of secrets it really isn't a puzzle game um but we knew this back in 2019 and 2020 that this was going to be a massive problem with launch um and we communicated this um specifically because we identified it in marketing we identified it across a lot of axes that this was
absolutely going to challenge the expectations that our players had when we did launch the game.
And on the development side, when we talked about this, they started to sketch out how a new marketing asset could be made to identify what was wrong with this.
And then we overlapped this specifically with the development schedule to make sure that it was going to be done in advance, that we had a demo that identified the fact that Tunic needed sort of a rework on making people understand that the game had pretty tricky combat.
The pieces of this were complete in September of 2020.
We did not launch this until June of 2021.
We built it into the production schedule.
We aligned it alongside TUNIT getting finished up.
We cut it and we sat on it for seven months waiting for the appropriate marketing
timeline to be basically given to us.
Xbox was running a demo event, we pulled the demo, sent it off to our porting studio, two weeks later we had a demo that had gone through certification.
That was all planned in advance and sort of sitting in the wings for as soon as somebody had it ready to go.
And yeah, we planned it, we prepared for it well in advance,
pulled the asset together and we already had the full marketing buy in from everybody, every stakeholder before it happened.
Because it did happen over the course of a year.
So where are you going to schedule this in production?
These are all obvious assets.
And that was, this was one of the hardest things when I was making this talk.
It's like this seems, these are obvious things that have obvious game
assets, like they have things that come out of the build.
You can't make a gameplay trailer without a game.
So why is it that when we come in and say we need a trailer, it's like a new idea that has happened before?
And it's because we don't have these conversations.
We're not coming in and saying in a year we're probably going to need a gameplay trailer.
Or we're saying nobody's listening and I can't do anything about that.
So what, I say that these are obvious assets, and then I realize that they're not, because what do marketing teams need?
What are some of the things?
There's probably gonna be a lot more, because there might be like, well I need all these like advertising assets, and I didn't include those, because most of them overlap with a bunch of this other stuff.
So we sometimes need show floor demos.
If you still travel to things like PAX or can handle doing those.
Or, I mean, they're here.
Like if you just walk out here on second and third floor, there's a bunch of show floor demos.
They're down at the day of the dive.
So it's a show floor demo.
Usually like a 15 minute demo that self restarts.
It's been locked off in some ways.
So if somebody wants to come up and steal it, they can't.
like that's a thing that has to come from the game itself.
We also need trailers, they come in a variety of lengths, 45, 60, 90 seconds or longer.
There's also screen shots, usually without UI, depending on who you're working with.
There's B-roll, we have online demos which have different constraints than a show floor demo, usually a little bit longer, because it's going to be on like a steam online event, or it can be replayed.
You also have the GIFs, social media assets,
We also have interviews.
I'm including this because this is a deliverable.
You have to do PR training.
You have to be up on talking points.
What does marketing, what did they identify has been a problem?
And you can talk to that.
Oops.
And then there's also store texts and blog posts.
All of these are the sort of things that you can prepare for.
You can do all of these things in advance.
We do our PR and marketing training like months in advance.
Sometimes we even do like practice interviews.
Um, because it's good to do if you're going to put devs out in front of people.
You should probably train them how to talk to people.
Because interviews are weird.
So what are you making now to support marketing?
So we have our marketing plan.
We have your game.
What part of your in-development game can double as your future marketing needs from development?
Internally, we're like, what can you make now that is cool enough for later?
And we do front load lots of cool stuff.
So I brought up this example earlier just because we literally rely on this all the time.
Vertical slice is a weird like sort of terminology here in the industry um because it can be everything, sometimes it's just like uh it's like your pretty corner, some people call it that.
Um it can be like 15 minutes, it can also be like a huge portion of your game, it can be like upwards of 3 hours.
However you define that, it's kind of up to you.
But in general, whenever we start a project and we get, I mean
currently, it's usually about two-ish years into something.
We usually have a very, very pretty, very, very set, very polished and ready to go vertical slice.
We always, always cut that up into two different things.
We have our show floor demo and we have our online demo.
And that usually is like about a 45 minute experience.
Meant to be replayed again and has good game loops.
The vertical slice is always also cut into a trailer, so it needs to include the full scope of the game.
So if you have a narrative and an action component and a boss battle, if you have a magical system and you have the things that are important, all of these things are present.
Because they get cut into the trailer, even though it's only going to be like a snippet of it,
it is a thing that you are going to want to include to tell a story.
Because every single one of the frames of your trailer will be screenshotted individually.
So people will be like, whoa, what is that?
It's a marketing tool.
So the more things you add, as far as gameplay, gives more conversations for your future players to talk about.
Those also, that same trailer gets cut up into your screenshots.
You can use the same asset to make your screenshots.
It also gets cut up, or it uses the key art.
as part of the start and finish of it.
All of our trailers get cut up into our social media GIFs.
We use the exact same asset for this, and that includes everything that goes up on social media.
This is one thing that we built early on in development, and it supports all of our initial launch assets.
There we go.
So responsive assets.
responsive assets is sort of like the term that I have for
So when development knows what marketing needs to address, the development can work on parts of the game that respond to that need.
That's what I refer to as responsive assets.
You're working together with the team who's tasked with communicating to the public about your game, and you are building a development process, understanding what might be needed in the future to address that asset, or to address that need.
If you aren't making a responsive asset, you're just making an asset that doesn't have a plan behind it.
If you're not talking to your marketing team, it's not responsive.
You're just making stuff.
And you have no concept or understanding of what people are saying or what people are needing, or possibly even the cultural implications of what you're putting out there.
There's also business development needs.
In the Tunic example, if we didn't manage our partner's expectations, we would have like sort of missed the boat on reviews and player expectations and support cues.
Specifically, if we didn't tell people that there was combat alongside Zelda, like we would not have managed those expectations, it would not have responded to the things we knew that were happening out in public.
and your marketing team kind of knows all of this stuff.
If they're asking the right questions, they know that there are problems.
They're out there listening to culture.
Their whole job is to design a place out in the world for your game to exist.
If you're not utilizing them and asking them the things that they're seeing, you're kind of missing the boat on being able to design and implement responsive assets.
and it's kind of on you to work with them to build the best version of this communication structure of understanding what they see and how that feeds back into your development process.
Because what we prepare is going to change how it's positioned sort of out in the world.
And it's just, it's going to feed back constantly.
So, I have a second example of sort of a weird responsive asset, um, and it's a very, very small piece of a Tunic trailer, um, and I didn't actually put it in here, uh, because you can, you can just check it online because it would take slightly too long to show it, but we needed to put together a launch trailer for Tunic that showed a lot more of the game than we had showed in the past.
Um, previously we'd only ever shown the forest and the caves and various assets that we had, but we needed to hint at sort of the larger bosses, the scarier parts, the combat, the secrets, the manual that was,
in some of the assets that were out there, but not in the way that they launched.
The trailer had a lot of things to communicate.
And the first trailer, the drafts that we had of it, went hard at all the things, but it felt really wrong.
Like, there was just something off about it, and we were pitching different ways to sort of fix the issues, and the problem was that the opening was wrong.
And the opening, what ended up in the final trailer, actually came out of marketing.
and the need was this, we needed a trailer that would remind the player who the main character of the fox is.
Everyone kind of recognized the fox.
So we had a trailer that would remind the player who the main character of the fox is.
So we
but the game had been in development for a very, very long time.
Things go in and out of like common knowledge and we needed to kind of acknowledge that directly to the player.
So what we did was we made a trailer that basically was like, this was like the sentence that came up in the conversation.
It was like, oh hey, it's the little fox.
I remember him.
Oh, he waved at me.
I played that demo once.
Oh shit!
That's a huge boss!
Like that's literally how we opened that trailer.
And that was like the marketing sentence.
Uh that was the marketing need that we had.
It's like we need to bring them back in.
We need to cheekily wave at them.
Which maybe we can pull off, maybe we can't.
And then like yeah and there's a big effin spider tank.
What's the spider tank's actual name?
I don't know.
I call it the spider tank.
The big stompy monster.
And he screams.
And then it goes into the hard trailer.
And it was like, look at all the places.
This is how big the scope of this game is.
It was one tiny asset, but it was an asset that responded to a need that we saw in the community.
So, part of this is we develop 90 percent assets.
And I've talked about this concept before at other GDC talks.
But if you have an understanding of the future deliverable and the constraints of this, you can prep your 90 percent assets.
This is so that when you get that request, you are at the polish phase already.
And you can only make a 90 percent asset if you know what your marketing team needs.
You need a trailer.
It needs to respond to a need.
You've
put the development pieces of that into your development schedule well in advance so you can build your marketing asset when it is convenient to you.
We rely on this 100 percent of the time because a 90 percent asset for a trailer is we are mastering a trailer.
We are putting on the uh branding, the mnemonics on the side.
We are porting a demo that already exists.
That is a 90 percent asset because we are able to do that on a timeline that doesn't hurt people.
It also allows for a more collaborative approach to marketing.
We're able to involve the development team in designing these assets in a way that is conducive to the talent and brilliant minds that are on your development teams.
Because they know the game and you know the market.
because we have to produce these things on better timelines.
I work with very small teams and every single one of these initiatives that we've been involved with could hurt people and have hurt people.
And your goal at the end of the day is to not burn out your brilliant collaborators that you work with.
Because you've planned and you have prepped and you've done the design work and you've started building the asset well before, it's due because we work in games and everyone has to deliver the same assets.
So, things that I mentioned, we master things in that last 10 percent.
We, um, sometimes have storyboards and placeholders, um, for a trailer and we put it into full production.
Because if you know the beats, you can pull the clips.
Um, and it kinda, it goes real fast if you know what you're building.
Um, for store assets, if you have your key art and your identity done in advance, it's easier to pull the store assets.
You can also take final screen shots from your current builds.
The tasks are easier to get full stakeholder buy in if you're already sitting on them and they've already been approved.
Because we polish when we have the final info.
It is possible because marketing asks change regularly, you might be like I'm developing a trailer and next week you're not because the event is gone, it has been cancelled.
If
you are always ready to participate.
It's not a big deal if it's canceled because you have not moved whole development schedules to support it.
You just change the final 10 percent.
Because it's so easier.
So, I'm going to talk a little bit about the
are so much easier if you do it that way.
Because for external opportunities, it's always going to be a timeline crunch.
There's no way out of it.
It just is.
They're going to hold on to that news and they're like, okay, we need a trailer in two weeks.
We want a sample of it in 12 days.
I've had worse than that.
I need B-roll.
in 36 hours in some format they've never seen before.
This is the crap that comes in and I'm trying to be positive about it but it's just how marketing requests work.
It's just what my email inbox looks like.
It's always going to be a timeline crunch.
So if it's going to be a damn timeline crunch, we have to fix our timeline because there's no, that piece is immovable.
So we have to do our things in advance.
We have to talk to our dev teams.
So, how am I doing on time?
I'm good, right?
Okay, good.
Uh, polish less ten percent.
I have three examples, um, that I just want to run through.
So, chicory trailer number two.
Uh, we launched this thing in February of 2021.
And I'm just going to, I'm just going to tell you when we actually did this asset.
because I think it's interesting.
We had our 90% asset done in spring of 2020.
We had a trailer literally done, it hadn't been mastered and it needed to be cut a little bit, slightly too long.
Done in spring of 2020, we just sat on it waiting.
We negotiated to put this in at least four different marketing events between spring of 2020 and when it finally was on like the PlayStation blog in 2021.
And we just held onto it.
until we found the right spot.
The tunic combat demo, same thing, with the 90 percent asset done in September of 2020.
We did not launch it until June of 2021.
Because we had this done, we were able to negotiate an IGN exclusive look at the PC demo.
If we had gone too far, we would never have been able to do that.
The IGN exclusive look, that code went out in February of 2021.
That's how early they had access to it.
And if we hadn't
Considered that that was a possibility, it would not have been possible.
Same thing with the TUNIC launch trailer.
We started planning and negotiating all of that in January of 2021.
We got Derek Liu, who's done a bunch of, like, GDC, like, he's awesome.
He had the builds of that by the summer, and he was already playing through the builds and pulling things.
And then we were working on storyboards through that whole fall.
This is just, we have to do it this way.
We have to build all this stuff in when we're actually doing the work for it.
And right now I'm doing the same thing on my two unannounced projects.
We are ramping up all of these early marketing assets to make sure that we don't just stop development.
Because we can't do that.
If we stop development, the game doesn't get made on time.
So the questions for your team, why is there a disconnect between your discipline schedules and priorities?
Part of it might be an attitude adjustment.
I mean, it was for us.
Like, if I go in, I'm like, I just need, like, one, don't say just.
But I need this thing, and I need it tomorrow.
It's like, yeah, well, put it on a damn schedule, man.
Like, that sucks.
You know these things are going to be made.
So how do we communicate better and have better timelines, even from marketing?
We know what we're going to need, so let's tell our production teams about it early.
and as production teams you know marketing's gonna need stuff so ask them what they need.
When do they think they're gonna need it?
And if they're like, I don't know, be like, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
Give me some sample timelines.
What do you think could happen?
Because you can work with that.
How does this limit team good, team collaborative communication?
Like, obviously you hate each other and that's like just kind of a miserable environment to work in.
How does your external marketing ask affect your development team's anticipatory pipelines?
You don't have them.
If you don't know what's coming, if you don't know what's possible, if you don't know what the marketing team is planning for, or what they're hoping for, what they're dreaming for, you can't build anything to help support it.
How can you control for timelines?
You can't control for external timelines.
You can only control for your internal timelines.
What kind of milestones and tasks will you build into your production schedules to address the needs of all of your team?
Find out what the needs are for all of your team.
And that has to include marketing.
They are designers.
They are designing how your team and how your game is going to be presented to the public.
And build the pipelines for that.
So plan as early as possible.
We spend all of our time in planning.
I don't have a game announced for quite a long time, and we are already building all the assets for it.
This was the same thing for all of our previous projects, because we learned from experience that we're going to hurt people otherwise.
We prepare way in advance.
As long as we have slightly too much information, as long as we focus on the things marketing thinks we might need on our development schedules, we build those things.
Then we're sitting on the assets before we need them.
then we produce some better timelines because we are already sitting on everything we need.
Because we ask the questions that need to be there.
And this is me.
Eventually that power point will show up.
And I think we do have a few minutes for questions.
And apologies for my power point.
It's been doing some wild things.
There's some slides out of order and I don't know why.
Because they weren't an hour ago.
Oh, sorry.
I will repeat this after you say it.
Great, thank you.
So we talked about production and marketing timelines aligning and I think it's really great.
First question is, do you have dashboards globally across the company that have those two timelines visible?
Okay, so we were just actually talking about this because my husband was giving me a bunch of
Oh yeah, Apollo, shut up.
So do we have global dashboards?
So we work in a small company and the answer is yes, but the small version, small company version of this.
We keep most of our information on Notion specifically for our company.
and it works slightly different depending on if it's an internal project or an external project.
So within marketing we do have sort of a like overall look at everything that's going on and then it's actually broken out so for external we usually keep this kind of over in
something that they can actually work with.
And then internal, on our internal project, they can see or see all of the pieces of it.
But yes, the important piece of that though is because it is flexible and it has to be adaptable, things move around a lot.
team.
I can't expect him, if I change something, to know that I changed it.
He's not going to get that updated.
so if I'm like radically moving lots of things around or some console just emails me and I'm adding a new important highlight for one of our projects it is super important for me to raise that red flag right away because it is going to radically change development and that will come up almost instantly into our every single Monday we do our
sort of creative team stand up, where we do high level discipline breakdowns in all of our creative teams.
And we actually have a whole section that is biz dev and marketing.
So anything that changes gets highlighted right there.
Usually kind of high, if it's really high up and it needs to change anything radically, it gets just higher priority.
But usually at the bottom, anything that I'm gonna bring into that meeting is four to 10 weeks in advance minimum.
because I bring it up immediately.
As soon as I know something, I come in like, I'm pretty certain I'm gonna have to do this.
Here is the breakdown of what I think I'm going to need.
What are we lacking from this?
And usually we have the majority of it sitting around.
But yeah, there's a lot of, nothing gets ignored.
As soon as there's a flag, we raise it.
Because otherwise it's never gonna get done.
You're just, yeah, you can't drop stuff like that into people's laps.
talk talk talk talk talk talk talk
Oh, I mean the rest of everything.
So what are the other timelines that should be fitting into this?
Like, we have our marketing and production timelines.
We should be talking, like, where is advertising fitting into this?
Like, where is our events and logistics fitting into this?
Like, how is the QA process also on top of this?
We rely on our QA to help us get sort of our final screenshots even at the end of a game.
Like, that's not all on marketing.
Because they know the,
by the time a game launches, our QA team knows the game better than anyone else on the planet, and they're like, I found something really cool, and they will be raising that flag.
Like, everything by the end of this, understand, in our QA stand-ups, we have a whole space for marketing initiatives and, like, biz dev things that need to be highlighted.
It has to, if you're going to have a collaborative communication process, it's holistic and they're working across all of our teams.
You have to be able to have everyone kind of on the same page to raise the important issues, to answer important questions and know when things are going to be due.
if you have a demo, an Xbox demo for example, going live, your QA team needs to know when the hell that needs to go into certification.
Because they're the ones that are overlapping with your porting studio or the engineering team internally who are doing that port.
Like, it has to be there.
Thank you.
Yeah, of course.
I'll be back in a minute.
whatever.
Hi, great talk, Rebecca.
First of all, is your studio based in Grand Rapids?
It is.
Small world.
I'm from Hastings, Michigan.
Oh, no kidding.
Yeah.
Great.
I'm from Fallerville, Michigan.
Can I say that out loud?
The wildest, smallest town in Michigan.
Great.
One question for you.
I'm working on a team that is just about to move into pre-production.
And we're just starting to set up some rituals with our marketing team and our production team to make sure that we're just aligned in our goals and that we're setting up milestones that reflect a shared vision instead of separate goals on separate tracks.
What sort of rituals did you find to be successful for your team to ensure solid, cohesive communication between the two groups?
Oh, that's a good question.
Okay, so one caveat, I run biz marketing and my husband runs creative, but we do work with external teams.
Adam and I have a really, just a really good communication process because he got so sick of me coming in with marketing things and because we obviously have a very close relationship, he was like, this effing sucks, we need to have a better process for this.
The main thing, one of the main things we did right away is like we, one, we never bash marketing.
We can be upset about the fact that we have to do something on a timeline.
We can be frustrated by the fact that somebody has external requests of us.
Um, but the people who are answering those emails and making those requests out of line to go after them.
Uh, and that sort of, like that alone builds a lot of trust.
So if somebody's like I need to do this
and it is on a tight timeline and I need you development team to help me with this.
It's like I understand that you have an external request because you're on a different timeline than I am on.
And like that baseline respect for each other's disciplines has gone a long way, thank you, a long way to sort of alleviate a lot of the issues.
And it is done by example.
But in doing so we've also included like in our marketing teams we talk about development.
in our development creative teams, we talk about marketing.
We raise the important things that each team is doing to make sure that people are understanding that we are on different schedules regularly, but also that we are working towards the same thing together.
Because marketing is designing how your game is going to land, and the game designers are designing the game.
And they don't have access to the end user the way a marketing team does.
Thank you so much.
Does that answer your question?
It does.
OK, cool.
Hi.
You almost answered my question.
Is you have any tip on how you deal with, I mean, when the development team is too much involved on the marketing decisions.
So it's not the same an in-game,
Yeah, no, I know this.
Or that a trailer is not the same.
Here, in-game, you want a lot of new screen data.
Marketing here, so the good thing of, you know, probably this year, the marketing, that everyone knows about marketing.
So we are so lucky that we receive advice from everyone.
So how do you deal with that, say, like you were saying, I have knowledge and I have numbers that you probably don't know.
How do you handle that?
How do you manage that?
Yeah, so the question is,
when somebody is kind of outside their lane, basically.
Like when you have a dev team who is like, I know more about the way a trailer should be than you do, or I know more about the, honestly, for the marketing team in here,
Be real careful going in and having opinions on mechanics.
Do you know more about that than the people who do this every day?
And the answer is yes, sometimes you do.
That is true.
You are often, you should be part of that conversation.
I had a really funny, sorry, real quick tangent.
A friend was giving a talk at GDC this week and their marketing team came in to try to change their stuff to have a bunch of talking points in it and it's just like, stay in your lane, you can't do that to a GDC talk.
the, where's your actual expertise at?
But, very specifically, how do we ensure that development doesn't change the actual, like, sort of design work and the needs from marketing team?
And this comes out in the planning process.
The second that we try to do this too fast, now we are in, we're in a situation where we cannot solve things with time and discussion, and we have to make a decision based on ego and, I don't know, fury.
talk.
The longer that you have to discuss this, to plan, to identify, to share research, the better able you are to build a thing that actually identifies the needs of the market, to be responsive of a thing.
you have more time to build your case.
And nobody's coming into something stressed and hot and mad because you've already imploded a development schedule.
Which is another reason why we do this early.
Because building something on a tight timeline is going to introduce those, they're just ego decisions.
I know best.
It's my game.
I know the lore better.
And it's sort of like when you get a pitch and it's all lore.
You're like, no, no, no, baby.
You're just too close.
You've got the blinders on.
You've got to take a step back and tell me what's actually cool about your game, because it's not that.
It's the same very human feeling, is to take a step back.
You probably don't know best.
And you do need to look at it with really calm, sensible eyes.
But yeah, time.
Time and planning.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
I think I have one question.
Can I do one more question?
OK.
Hi, Rebecca.
Thank you so much for the talk.
My background's in development, but I work in marketing now, so I feel very seen by this.
My question for you is, for our team, we've been focusing a lot on tool development for my marketing team for how we can capture the build or take some of the work off the dev team and do that.
And I wanted to know if you had any thoughts about how you've handled that at Fingy.
For tool development, well we're small enough they don't have a ton of it.
However, we do have a lot of discussions sort of at like a top level of we are going to have to support this thing and who is available to help support it.
Because there are people who are infinitely qualified especially for capturing builds.
or they have to like run things in unity or I'm going to have to run it on device so I'm like capture carding with the QA team to pull that because like my marketing team doesn't have a damn dev kit sitting around and I have to run this off of a PS5 in the office and that's off a capture card.
We plan this stuff so far in advance that like we don't
we put it into pockets and that's our way around these legitimate bottleneck
moments.
But we do have to get buy-in from everybody.
I can't just go into QA and be like, I need fill in the blank.
I can't have that.
It does need to be like this scheduled thing.
And because it's not their main job, it might be they spend a couple hours capturing something very exact.
Because we usually map out, we need this exact thing.
We would like it to look like this.
And can you provide a couple of options of this?
Can you go through this boss scene like three times?
and for them, they're like, hell yeah, I can definitely do that because I can do that boss scene with my eyes closed.
We also will use like internal to the build itself, we have a whole bunch of depending on what we're doing, we'll script out whole scenes of things.
If we have to capture it on device, we'll like push that into
the build for marketing itself, because it has to be run on device.
So like Fox Waving, for example, that was a scripted scene that Andrew put together that we pushed through and then captured off.
And we do a lot of that.
But we do have to, we spell out, we would like to do this.
We would like the camera to pan like this.
And we spec that out, scope it out, and then talk to our dev teams to see when in the schedule can that be available, and what debug menu can we access to be able to pull that.
but usually done pretty far in advance.
And oftentimes, especially in some of our past stuff, both chicory and tunic especially,
A lot of it was already being thought about, of like, it would look real cool like this, it would be cool if we could spin it like this.
And they were already asking those questions, kind of, of us for future marketing asks, because they knew, I'm going to have to make a trailer of this eventually, and I don't want to be ambushed with weird camera cuts or something.
Does that answer your question?
It does.
Thank you.
Yeah, of course.
Okay, I think that's all we have time for.
I can go over to wrap up if anyone wants to pick my brain about whatever.
I'm cool with that.
Um, and wrap up is windows on that side of the building.
Um, but yeah, thanks.