So animation.
Like what Mike said, it's more of a personal, what we're
going to do today is not we're not going to be talking about
how we do it in the books or how we even learned it.
We're going to talk about how we actually do it ourselves,
all the good habits and bad habits of animation.
And what makes animation, what makes an animator successful?
The goal for animation, all of us, we
We just want to make an audience believe.
We just want to go out there and fool somebody
into believing the performance that you're doing.
And when I was preparing for a beginning class
not too long ago, and I asked myself,
I was like, if I was starting animation
and I didn't know anything about it,
someone asked me, what's animation?
What do I need to know to get a job in animation?
And I said, well, you gotta learn
the 12 principles of animation.
you know, that's really boring.
That's by the book.
You know, I said, how would I do it?
It's changed now.
It's been, what, 60 years since the 12 Principles of Animation.
So I started jotting down notes.
How would I do it?
What are the things that I do?
And I've got about five pages of stuff.
I'm like, oh, man, this is rough.
I can't tell my students that.
So I started breaking it down into categories.
And eventually, I got four categories of animation
that I felt was what I would do as an animator.
And again, that's a very personal thing.
I'm sure everybody does it in a different way.
But that's how I do it.
So the four aspects of animation I
think everyone needs to know is to become
successful as an animator is, so the first one,
the creative aspect of animation.
And that's the easiest one.
Everyone knows this.
This is when you get the idea.
This is when you make your choice.
That's the creative part of animation.
Anything you can think of that gets you excited to go into
animating, the actual arc, when you're doing an arc, how
do you push exaggeration, how do you push your animation.
All this is part of the creative aspect of animation.
The second one is the logical aspect of animation.
How does it actually work?
So it's important to know if you're doing a lion walking,
for example.
Can you guys hear me?
If you're doing a lion walking, for example,
you can go in there and just make the lion walk
just because you have a cat.
And you're thinking about it, you're like, yeah,
I can push this and push that.
But you've got to know exactly how a lion walks,
because they are really lazy
and how they roll their paws when they're walking.
All that's part of the logical aspects of animation.
You need to know how things move.
That's the science behind animation.
The third one is the methodical aspect of animation.
So you get the creative side.
You get the logical side.
Now, how do you actually do it?
How do you actually sit down, open Maya, open Softimage,
open any software that you flash?
How do you actually do it?
And that's the tough part, I guess.
That's what everybody wants to do.
Because the creative side is probably the easiest one.
So that's the methodical side.
Then there's the critical side of animation.
That's probably the most frustrating part of animation,
because this is when you're done with everything,
and you need to look at your stuff critically
and tell yourself, is this the best you can do?
So I'll be talking about each of them
and giving you guys examples of where I've used them
and what I do as an animator.
So, there's no order to do these.
A lot of what I'm going to say is, you know,
you can actually crisscross that.
You can actually, a lot of that stuff, for example,
squash and stretch.
That's a creative part as well,
because no matter how you exaggerate it,
that's being creative.
How it actually works, the logical aspect,
is because of the weight, you know,
that's why it's going to squash,
because of gravity, all that's part of it.
And the methodical aspect is how do you actually do it?
A ball will squash, you...
artistically you'll squash the ball, but a human being, you can't squash the bones.
That doesn't work. So human squashing is different than a ball squashing.
So how do you actually do that? That's part of the methodical aspect.
So just a ball squash falls into three categories itself.
All right.
So there are no rules to this.
There's no secret.
There's no magical formula to how to succeed as an animator.
But as long as you follow all four and you try to be as good
as you can in all four of them.
How many of you guys are already professional animators
working in the industry right now?
All right, so you guys already know all that.
How many of you guys are aspiring animators who want to
be working?
Rick, get your hand.
How many of you guys don't really care about animation?
Awesome.
Cool.
So we're all good then.
All right.
So last year, I don't know if you guys were here.
Anybody was here last year?
Awesome.
So you guys remember when I talked about a performance from an actor that I really respect,
Marlon Brando, and I'm sure you guys know him.
You guys know Marlon Brando?
Yeah.
He's a cool actor.
So he...
He had a performance from the Godfather,
I think it was the first one,
and I was talking about a little bit how he,
you know, he's a method actor,
he's an actor who acts, you know,
who performs by instinct.
And today I'm gonna talk about a different actor
who I really, I really enjoy watching,
and I learned a lot from his performance as well,
but there's a debate out there
if he actually was a good actor or not.
You guys can, you know, you guys can.
talk about that as well. It's, um, I believe he would have been an amazing actor
if he had done more movies. Unfortunately he died after doing three films.
That's James Dean, James Dean, you know, known as the bad boy of Hollywood.
And watching him, honestly, he lacks maturity in his performance.
And you can tell that.
But he's an actor who was reacting to whoever was around him.
And that's something which is really important in animation.
It's not about just delivering a line.
And you see that a lot in animation today, even in professional animation.
A lot of amazing films out there,
there's not quite, there's no acting in there.
You're just performing, you're just delivering the line,
you're just hitting the notes.
So knowing how to react to another actor
is incredibly important.
And even though James Dean is not the best actor ever,
but he was an actor who was actually reacting
to the other actors.
And I'm gonna show you guys a scene
from Rebel Without a Cause.
Have you guys seen this film?
Anybody?
Yeah?
Good, good movie.
So this scene.
So, just so you guys know, this movie is about, a lot of it is about honor and not being a coward.
Because Jim, who's James Dean in there, his character, so his father, is known in the town to be a coward.
And he's trying to shed that away. He's trying to push that away. He's trying to be a bad, you know...
a cool guy, he's trying to be different from his dad,
and he's really embarrassed by this.
So this is a scene where he comes back
and he just had an accident,
and I think he killed a boy, I think, in that scene.
So he's coming back and his parents
disagree with what he wants to do.
So let's just watch this scene.
Got it.
All right, I got it, I'm almost there.
And there's no sound.
Yeah?
Oh, there should be something.
I think it's going to work.
No.
Let me try another video just to make sure.
Sorry about that, guys.
It's what?
Yeah, it's plugged in.
Is that just it?
Computers.
All right, let's see.
Really? Oh, yeah. No, wait.
Now it's on 100.
Nope. Help?
Help?
Anyone?
It's weird.
I don't know.
Let me just try another video here.
Everything's plugged in.
Nope.
Sorry guys. Any questions?
Yeah? I'm not as good as James Dean.
Oh yeah, go for it.
So the critical aspect, is that like how you can kind of see your own work and react to its plausibility?
Yeah, yeah. So the critical aspect is, I call it...
The question is, the critical aspect of animation, is it when you react to your own animation?
Yes. It's when you go away from your animation, you look at it with a fresh eye.
And that's, I mean, I'm going to talk about that more in detail later on.
It's everything that has to do about you analyzing your animation and see if it's actually the right choice that you made.
You know, that comes from your director, that comes from your supervisor, you know, yourself.
your peers, anything. Or is it the right thing to do for the actual game or movie? Is it
the right choice that you made? That tends to be the most annoying part of animation
because if it happens too late, you have to go back and, you know, change it all and redo
the whole thing.
I'm not tearing me loose again.
Well, this is news to me. Just why are we moving?
Oh, yeah.
Just why are we moving?
How do I help?
Awesome.
Yay.
Thank you.
Feel like Lois Lane right now.
All right, I'm just gonna move this back here.
All right, so let's watch this scene.
There's no sound in the beginning, don't worry.
It's all good.
Accept yourself.
Wait a minute.
You don't want me to go.
No.
No, I don't want you to go to the police.
There are other people. Why should you be the only one involved?
But I am involved. We are all involved.
Mom, a boy, a kid was killed tonight.
I don't see how I can get out of that by pretending that it didn't happen.
Well, you know that you did the wrong thing.
That's the main thing, isn't it?
That's nothing. That is absolutely nothing.
Dad, you told me. You said you want me to tell the truth. Now, didn't you say that?
You can't turn it off.
Well, he's not saying that.
He's saying, just don't volunteer.
Just tell a little white lie.
You'll learn when you're older, Jim.
Well, I don't think that I want to learn that way.
Sure, we go too far.
I mean, what do you guys think?
Eh?
OK.
So what's cool about this is, watch how he's, you know,
whenever he's performing, and he's
the change of emotion in him saying, you know, when he's explaining about that boy,
you can tell he's, you know, I mean, we're talking about a really old film here,
and his performance, when you compare him to actually the two parents,
I'm going to play it again, watch the two parents' reaction to him,
watch how they're actually waiting for their lines.
They're looking at him, there's no thinking process going on there,
but then watch his performance.
And like I said, you know, he lacks maturity there,
I mean, you can tell after a couple more movies after this,
he would probably be incredible as an actor.
But watch his change of emotion when he's about to describe that little boy,
how he uses his whole body to describe this.
He changes, you know, his whole pose is changing when he's doing this.
And then watch when he tells the dad,
Dad, you know, speak, you know, didn't you tell me to do this?
And then watch how he goes.
He just uses his whole body and just drops,
you can't turn it off.
He says you can't turn it off,
and then he does the gesture.
It's after he said it.
If we had that line animation,
you know, let's say we get the dialogue
and the audio goes, you can't turn it off,
I bet you all of us would go, you can't turn it off.
Right?
We'll animate on the line.
But the thing about this guy, he says, you can't turn it off.
and the body continues his thinking process.
And that's incredibly important in animation.
It's, you know, you find all the good stuff in animation
is when the body keeps the performance going
and not just you're delivering a line,
you're just saying it.
You gotta keep the thinking process going.
Let's just watch this moment again
and you'll see what I mean.
Mom!
Oh boy, a kid was killed tonight!
I don't see how I can get out of that by pretending that it didn't happen!
Well you know that you did the wrong thing.
That's the main thing, isn't it?
That's nothing.
That's...
That is absolutely nothing.
Dad, you told me, you said...
You...
You want me to tell the truth. Now, didn't you say that?
You can't turn it off.
Well, he's not saying that. He's saying, just don't volunteer!
Just tell a little white lie.
You'll learn when you're older, Jim.
Just look at the mom and the dad, how they are waiting.
They are theater actors.
And it's not bad, it's good.
But look at the difference between them.
I want to learn that way.
Well, it doesn't matter anyway, because we're moving.
You're not tearing me loose again.
Well, this is news to me, just why are we moving?
Oh, do I have to spell it out?
Well, I'm not going to use me as an excuse again.
I don't.
Every time you can't face yourself, you blame it on me.
That is not true.
You say it's because of me, you say it's because of the neighborhood?
No!
You use every other phony excuse!
Mom, I just once, I want to do something right!
And I don't want you to run away from me again!
Dad?
This is all going too fast for me, son.
You better give me something.
You better give me something fast.
Jimmy, you're very young.
A foolish decision not good wreck your...
I love that bit as well.
Dad, he doesn't even turn.
It's way more powerful when he doesn't turn to...
I mean, you don't have to always be acting to camera.
You know, you can spend some more time.
Let the audience believe in that character.
Let the audience really feel what the character is saying.
That's why this moment is way more powerful.
In 10 years, you'll never know this even happened.
Dad, answer her.
This is awesome.
He's completely dismissing, you know, his mom.
And just by lowering his head down,
Dad, answer her, you know, and then he just tenses up.
just so, so powerful.
Just watch this little section again.
I'm too fast for you Sam.
You better give me something.
You better give me something fast.
Jimmy, you're very young.
A foolish decision now could wreck your whole life.
In 10 years, you'll never know this even happened.
Dad, answer her.
Tell her.
10 years.
Dad, let me hear you answer her.
Look at the dad's performance. There's nothing.
Dad.
Dad, stand up for me.
What a great line.
If you guys have seen this movie, this moment is really, really, really incredible when he says,
Dad, stand up for me. That's everything. That's everything he's been wanting, you know,
that his dad stands up for him.
And in this moment, you know, just that slow look up, eye, you know, looking at his mom is just incredible.
Watch that movie if you get the chance.
You have some really, really nice stuff in there.
Cool. So that's this performance.
And we're going to watch another one with the same movie, James Dean.
And this is when he gets back home.
He returns home and his dad, something just happened.
And watch his reaction there.
Mom?
Hi, Jimbo.
You thought I was Mom?
Yeah.
Well, the curls out I was getting Mom some supper.
She doesn't feel too well.
What'd you do? Drop it?
Yeah.
She dropped it?
Let her clean it up before she sees it.
Let her see it.
What?
What can happen, she's...
Dad.
Don't. I mean, you shouldn't. Don't.
What are you...
It's awesome. I mean, he... he basically...
He's talking to his dad, he can't finish his lines,
you know, it's all in his body when he goes,
dad, stand, picks him up.
You know, he's basically saying, dad, stand up.
You know, that little breath he takes at the end,
he's not finishing any of his lines, you know.
So don't be a coward, you know, stand up for yourself.
Don't be scared, you know.
and he never finishes it. He lets his body do it.
Today in movies we see that. We describe everything that we're doing.
I mean right now, even in Dragons 2, there's some lines in there that's just
like, you don't need to explain this. We get it.
But, you know, I mean producers want to be as clear as possible to five-year-olds
and they want to make sure that even kids understand what the movie's saying.
Kids are not stupid, they're smarter than we are as adults.
We've got to give them credit and then the movie will last forever.
When I used to watch movies when I was a kid, I watched again 10 years later,
things I didn't get, it's awesome when you get it.
It's, oh, that's awesome, now this makes sense.
That's great that this whole discovery process, instead of just feeding me everything,
and then I watch the movie 10 years later and go, yeah, this movie's cheesy.
it doesn't stand anymore.
So that's the kind of performance
that we're looking for in animation.
If ever you're doing a demo reel and you're sending work.
Make sure you have these kinds of change of emotion
in your work.
You don't want to just move well.
Just your animation moving well is not what,
what right now the animation is going.
It probably will change again.
It probably will go back to what it used to be,
where it was more about the appeal of how it looks.
But now, performance is becoming so important,
especially in visual effects.
You know, with movies like Rise of the Apes
and Avatar and all that stuff.
So let's watch another performance by another actor who,
incredible actor, I'm sure you guys will agree,
Gary Oldman.
He's probably good in every single freaking movie that he does.
And I think last year, I probably showed a scene by him.
You know, from a scene that he...
This is a scene from Leon the Professional.
Have you guys seen this?
This is one of his early performances and he's playing this guy who's actually on drugs
and you'll see that he's very fidgety a lot, he's moving a lot in this performance.
But just watch his timing in there.
Just watch how his body just keeps the thinking process going.
I have a lot of respect for your business, Tony.
When you've killed for us in the past, we've always been satisfied.
And that's exactly why today is going to be very, very hard for me.
I hope you'll excuse my mood.
My man was killed right here, on your turf.
And the chinks tell me that the hitman was kind of the, uh...
Italian type so we figured that
Tony might know something wait
There's more
You're gonna love this a
Few hours later a
Little 12 year old girl comes into my office armed to the teeth
With a firm intention of sending me straight to the morgue and you know who came and got her in the middle of the afternoon
Right there in my building
the very
same Italian hitman.
I'm dying to meet him.
So, I mean, just that last bit when he's smiling,
I mean, we all know that a smile is when you're happy, but...
I mean, he wasn't happy there.
He was being sarcastic.
I mean, he was just making fun of the whole situation
of a hitman walking into a police station
and taking a girl and leaving and no one stopping that guy.
So his real emotion is that frame right there.
After all that smiles, he ends his emotions on this one.
It's amazing.
Whatever he's saying, whatever his facial is actually doing
is not what he's feeling.
But it's right after he's done is
when he goes into his real expression, right there,
where he's like, I'm going to kill this guy.
That's his real feelings.
So this shows us that you don't really
need to put the emotion right onto exactly what
the person is saying.
choose different moments to do it because you could be showing another kind of emotion that
that person is trying to show. You know, he's trying to scare the other guys, trying to show
that he's cool, and many other things that you could do. There's another bit in there that I
actually really enjoy is the section where he asks for the picture. Check this out.
My man is going to...
He grabs onto it, shows it nothing, doesn't say anything, puts it down, hits on the table,
basically saying, check this out.
So my man, so he basically said a lot of things.
without voicing it.
And that's something that I do a lot in animation.
Whenever I get my dialogue, let's say I have a dialogue
that's the guy saying, let's say, random,
hey man, how you doing, right?
This is my dialogue.
What I do is I always imagine what the character
is saying before and after.
put myself into that mood.
So if, let's say, my kid would say,
hey, how are you doing, but I'm upset,
I would walk around the room, get into that mode,
and just going.
I can't swear here, right? No.
I would go, crap, crap. Is that bad? No.
Crap, crap.
I would go, crap, crap, crap, crap, crap,
you know, getting the really worst words on that.
You know, it'd be crap, crap, crap.
And then I'd say the line.
And then I'd keep going, crap, crap, you know.
And it gets you into that mode
of being that character.
And it really helps me out.
You always add lines.
For example, if your character is saying something,
hey man.
How are you doing?
There's a break in the middle.
Don't ever leave this break empty.
Don't ever do that.
Just fill it up with stuff.
Say it.
Because even if you're shooting your reference
and you're looking for a performance to animate,
things you'll do while you're saying it,
you can still animate that without doing the lip sync.
Let's say you're saying, hey man, how are you doing?
Let's say you're tired.
You say, hey man, how are you doing?
So you voice it.
Hey, man, I'm so tired.
How you doing?
So me saying, I'm so tired, I just,
the way I move my head, now if I just take the dialogue out,
I go, hey, man, how you doing?
So that's a thinking character.
That's a character who's actually in the moment.
He's actually feeling it.
You voice it out.
Just voice it.
Just don't do the lip-sync in your animation.
But you're keeping the flow going.
A lot of animators I see today, they'll go, hey, man,
Little hold.
How you doing?
You know?
So you don't want to be doing this.
You want to really get into your performance.
And that's, we'll talk a little bit more
about that eventually.
So, let me see, what time is it?
Okay.
Just gonna move on to a different performance.
So this is one of the last video, I promise.
And we'll have, we'll move on to a different thing.
So this one is, I don't know if I showed this last year.
I love this movie.
Anatomy of a Murder.
Have you guys seen this?
Anybody?
Come on, guys.
All right, awesome.
So this is an incredible film.
I mean, George C. Scott, and I think he probably won the
Oscar for Best Supporting Actor in this scene.
Just watch his performance.
He's an actor where, honestly, in that movie, he, I love,
was it Jimmy Stewart?
Yeah, it was Jimmy Stewart, right?
Jimmy Stewart's great.
He's a good actor.
But watch him.
Hold on.
It's coming.
I'm quite concerned about the lost panties.
Would you describe this article of clothing to Corfi?
They were nylon and had lace up the sides.
There was a label in them of the place I got them.
The Smart Shop in Phoenix, Arizona.
What was the color of the panties?
I believe white.
You believe?
I have white and pink. They may have been pink.
You're not sure.
Haven't you checked your lingerie to see which pair of panties is missing?
No.
When your husband came home late from his work,
you had this little spat.
Were you already dressed to go out?
No.
When did you dress?
After dinner, when he was asleep.
It's been stated here that you were bare-legged in the bar. Is that true?
Yes.
In your anger at your husband and your haste to get out of the trailer,
perhaps you didn't put on any panties, I...
Objection! Witnesses already testified what you were wearing.
So this scene is why I think it's just really beautiful,
is the fact that the whole first part of that shot,
he's really drilling his questions,
he's really being firm on this, he's looking for something.
And you can tell he's searching for it,
he's really, he's asking that lady specific questions
because he's looking for an answer.
And right before he gets it,
Which is very subtle, you'll see there's a tiny little smile like he does.
His muscle basically flexes.
Watch this.
It's really tiny, see if I can actually find where it happens.
If you guys can see, let me know.
I think it happens somewhere...
It happens somewhere right there, and you'll see that's where he actually goes,
I got you now.
I had lace up the sides.
There was a label in them of the place I got them.
The smart shop in Phoenix, Arizona.
What was the color of the panties?
I believe white.
You believe?
I have white and pink.
They may have been pink.
You're not sure.
Haven't you checked your lingerie to see which pair of panties is missing?
No.
When your husband came over...
And now, was it there?
You guys see it?
It is somewhere in there.
The thing is, I'm looking at this dagger.
Let me go find it first, and then I'll show it to you guys.
Sorry, that's planning for you.
I'm not sure.
Alright, right there.
So right before, right there, you'll see,
right before he says it, there's a tiny little,
he needs to keep his cool.
I mean, he's the guy who's questioning the lady,
so he can't just start smiling too early.
I got them. The smart shop in Phoenix, Arizona.
What was the color on the paint?
Right before, his little flex right there of his muscles,
that little detail, and that stuff,
when you get into a close-up shot,
these are very important.
You've got to pay attention to all these little details.
And what I love is as soon as he knows he gets the lady, now it becomes almost like a dance.
Puts his pen in his pocket, he walks away, and you see when he's walking,
he just completely arches his, you know, he's just like almost like a lion, really, you know, proud.
Yeah, yeah, I got you now, he's walking. The way he grabs onto the, it's almost like a dance,
and so well balanced, the contrast in his body. I believe white. You believe?
I have white and pink. They may have been pink. You're not sure.
Haven't you checked your lingerie to see which pair of panties is missing?
No.
And I love his choices of saying,
you're not sure.
He does hit the note.
You know, stuff that we do all the time.
You're not sure.
But then, there's no note hitting again.
You know, he just, there's no accent anymore.
He just goes into performance.
When your husband came home late from his work,
you had this little spat.
He knows at this point he's already got the girl.
Were you already dressed to go out?
No.
When did you dress?
Look at the confidence in his pose.
After dinner, when he was asleep.
Yes.
So he stated here that you were bare-legged in the bar.
Is that true?
Yes.
In your anger at your husband and your haste to get out of the trailer, perhaps you didn't put on any panties, huh?
Objection! Witnesses already testified what you said.
I love that holding, where he's holding onto the jug there.
He just leaves it there as he's delivering the line.
Amazing secondary action. I mean, you guys...
This is exactly what we look for in animation, you know?
When do you move stuff that's not distracting?
It's all part of staging, right?
You can't have stuff moving all over the place.
The audience, they don't know where to look at.
You gotta make sure that you have a focus
where the audience's eyes will go.
For example, in a shot like this,
if he was just doing too many things at the same time,
you won't know where to look at.
Right now, this jug thing
becomes a secondary action completely.
You're not paying attention to it.
It's part of his performance.
You're always looking at the face.
And that kind of stuff is tough to do in animation, and I don't think he was actually thinking about all this.
He just performed it.
After dinner when he was asleep.
It's been stated here that you were bare-legged in the bar, is that true?
Yes.
In your anger at your husband and your hastiness...
He was... So he got into a pose, delivers the line.
You're not looking at that, you're looking at his performance.
Then he stops, puts it down, delivers the line again.
It's so well balanced and I don't know if he was actually planning this. He might have.
I don't think he was.
Perhaps you didn't put on any pantyhose either.
What's your action?
Anyway.
This performance is awesome.
Go watch this.
So this is all part of that creative aspect of animation,
you know, when you have to study.
You need to go find performance out there
that you really enjoy.
See why it's really good.
Find the things that you need to add in your own performance.
Because when you get a shot, you're
not going to go pick a movie and go, all right,
I need to study this and do my shot.
You're going to have to perform yourself or find someone else
that can perform for you.
So I'm going to show you guys a little chunk, like a couple little shots.
I won't show you anything that I showed last year just to make it a little different.
So when I was on... what's that movie called?
Rise of the Guardians. Anybody see it?
Come on. No wonder that movie flopped.
So, I'm going to spoil it for you guys, because it's your own fault.
So, we shot a lot of reference for Jack Frost, and Jack Frost was a very realistic character.
We don't know if that was the right choice to do, because I do believe we should have pushed him a little bit more than what we did.
We went a little too realistic, and the reason for that was because we felt his proportions were very tricky to push.
I don't think that was the right way to go, but we went very realistic with him.
So reference shooting was incredibly important.
We needed to get a real performance.
We didn't want to just hit accents,
you know, that would be too easy.
So, you know, I shot, I had this little sequence
where Jack Frost is, sorry,
where Jack Frost is, he just got his butt kicked by pitch
and he fell into a hole and he's waking up from that.
And so I shot reference.
of me waking up from just falling into a hole.
And so this is my, I did probably a whole,
maybe a whole four or five hours of shooting reference
of myself doing it.
And this is one of the performance.
Play.
So that watch down there, that's Tooth Fairy.
That's a little baby Tooth Fairy that was there.
And we just put a watch there to represent this.
So Jack is supposed to wake up, then notice the baby tooth,
and then go to that baby tooth.
So anyway, so that was the first performance that I did, and that was the best one I got.
So as soon as I showed it to a group of animators, they were all laughing.
I was like, what?
What's so funny about it? Because, dude, you look like an old man.
So I was like, alright, well, you know, I got to reshoot reference.
So I did maybe another couple hours of shooting reference.
I just couldn't get out of the whole old man thing.
Um, you know, that's who I am.
So I had to find someone else to do this for me.
You know, if you can't do it yourself, you know, if you have a shot where there's a character doing Kung Fu
and you don't know Kung Fu, well, you have to find somebody who can do it.
Or you find a video that does it.
So I had to find someone else that actually can, you know, has, you know, a young...
He's 10 years younger than me. No wonder he would be better.
So I got Jacob to do it for me, and he basically did,
we did about 15 takes, maybe about 20 minutes,
and I got about three takes that actually worked really well.
So this was the first take.
Yeah, much more energy, much better.
Second one as well.
And the third one.
Alright, so when I got these three, I was like,
alright, these are the good ones.
When you shoot your reference now,
you don't just take one reference and you copy it.
You don't want to do this.
You find a good reference, you find what you like about it,
and for the most part, there's never a perfect reference.
You'll never shoot reference and just get the one take
that rules them all, you'll never get that.
You'll get a few takes, you'll get one thing you like in one take, one thing you like in another.
And then you have to actually take it, break it into pieces, and then use things that you like.
For example, in that first one, I really like his head accent that he did when he notices a baby tooth.
In the second one, I really like the way he slides his butt back right there.
I really like that, that he didn't do in the first one.
I was like, oh I can use this.
In the third one, I really like the way he put his hand onto his forehead.
he doesn't quite touch the forehead,
and I think I pushed it more in my animation
to touch the forehead.
So I basically grabbed these little moments that I like
in all these performances and put it together.
And then, you know, I kept working on this.
So I didn't do, in this sequence,
I didn't do Baby Tooth.
I only did Jack Frost in this sequence.
And Baby Tooth was done by Joe Bowers.
So, as you can tell, you know, I use the hand, you know, to touch the forehead.
I use the energy of the body going forward.
Sorry.
All I can do is keep you cold.
So in that movie we were trying not to hit accents and we were trying our best and I think that was our mistake.
We went the other way. There's hitting accents which is bad and then there's not hitting at all.
We were trying to stay away from hitting too many accents.
And I think that was a big mistake because we were losing a lot of animation.
When you're animating, you want to animate. You want to just push things and move things around.
This movie we were too tame. We didn't do enough.
On dragons, I think it got a little better.
I think we were pushing things a little more.
But I still feel things look a little too realistic
from time to time.
That's why we have motion capture, right?
So we don't have to be doing realistic performance.
We need to, when we animate, let's animate.
So this little chunk is an example
of how we would take a performance, break it up.
And here's another example of this is a group of friends
and I get together.
We got together.
to shoot tons of reference.
And basically what we did is we just put the dialogue away.
Like I never shoot with dialogue in the background
because whenever you shoot dialogue in the background,
you pay attention.
You're waiting for your cues.
And I'm sure everyone, we all do that.
And I learned not to do that.
Whenever you're shooting reference, don't ever,
I'm going to pause it there.
Whenever you, this is really, really important.
Whenever you're shooting reference,
and I think I said that last year,
Don't ever put the dialogue playing in the background
and then you're trying to act to the dialogue,
to the audio.
Honestly, this will hurt your performance
way more than it helps.
Memorize your dialogue, remember it.
Get the intent of the audio.
Get the feeling around that audio.
If your character's saying, hey man, how you doing,
get into the feeling of, hey man, how you doing,
even if you're saying, hey dude, what's up?
It's the same intent.
The only thing that will be different is the lip sync, which you can do later.
But the performance, the body performance, will be the same, the same intent.
If someone is angry, if you're saying crap, you're saying poop, you're saying whatever you want,
it's the same anger that you're saying, so the intent is the same.
If you actually have the dialogue and the audio in the background,
you're paying too much attention to this.
I find animators shooting reference are waiting for the audio.
Oh, my time.
When you're waiting for the audio, you're not performing.
You're just, whoa, okay, I'm just gonna jump into it.
You're putting too much thought, you just be the character.
Don't let, remember the audio, get to know the character,
get to know the intent of the scene,
and then somebody's yawning, oh, that's bad.
All right, so this is a.
This is, you know, just us, you know, shooting reference.
Just, we spent all day doing this, you know,
all day shooting reference.
And this was a shot where Jack was telling the guardians,
you know, I don't need you guys, you know.
You guys don't, sorry, you guys don't want me, you know.
Why would you want me?
You guys are all about hard work and deadlines.
I'm more like a freestyle kind of a guy, you know.
So.
So after doing a whole day of this,
I realized that none of it was actually
what I was looking for.
Then I spent another day doing this.
And this shot I actually had about a week to do.
So we're talking five days.
And I spent about two or three days shooting reference.
So that leaves me with about two days to animate.
And a shot that long could easily take you a week,
but we were on very, very strict deadlines for that film.
So I eventually did a performance that I enjoyed more,
and then I cut it, cut pieces that I actually liked.
with what he was supposed to do.
So, you know, as you can tell, you know,
I just go in Premiere and just cut little bits and pieces
that I actually enjoy and just put it together
and then that's the performance that I'm gonna do.
So this shot, I honestly did it in one day,
block it out, show it to the director,
he had a big note, and then I had another day to finish it
and it went in the film.
So it's not a shot that I look now and I'm like,
oh wow, this shot is awesome, not even close.
I think this shot, you know, needs a,
now when I look back, it's like, oh God, this is terrible.
But it is what it is.
Wait, there's no sound?
Ah, there's no sound on that one.
Oh.
Deadlines, and I'm snowballs and fun times.
I'm not a guardian.
So this shot has a lot of problems with it, you know.
Looking at it in hindsight, and there's one problem
I'm gonna talk about, you know, later on during this talk.
So this is what it turned out to be, and...
Ah, I just closed it.
Terrible.
So...
This is an example of the creative aspects of animation
where you need to get, you don't need to copy
any of your performance, you actually get it together,
take the stuff that you like, and then do your animation.
So.
Now, Hitting Accent, I know I've been talking about how bad it is,
but I've had my finest moment of Hitting Accent, of bad animation.
And there's a lot of great movies out there, very popular movies,
movies that make a billion dollars recently,
that has not very good acting in it, so never let it go.
So let me show you guys.
I know I love these guys.
I love them.
They just don't get acting.
So this is my finest hour in acting Garfield 2.
And you know, I was learning animation at that time.
You know, don't blame me.
Play.
You do realize I'm a cat, don't you, sir?
Do you realize I'm a cat, don't you, sir?
Hey, great arcs.
I mean, great squash and stretch.
No freaking acting in there at all.
I'm just hitting accents, you know?
There's nothing in there.
It's just me going, hey, you do.
There's nothing.
Honestly, when I did this, I was like, yeah, I'm awesome.
I'm working on movies.
But do I get animation?
Not really.
It's only when I got to Weta is when I actually learned,
you know, learned animation.
I remember my first week at Weta,
I was doing a shot and I was all proud of it.
I was like, look guys, I can animate.
And all the guys were like, oh, you're so cute.
You think you can animate?
This guy just finished Lord of the Rings and King Kong.
They get it.
So, you know, it took me a while to understand,
you know, it's not just about the motion animation.
It's, you know, it's very, wow, it's already time.
All right.
I have three more aspects to talk about.
So, you know, it's important to get that
performance is not just moving on screen, you know.
It's more than just that.
All right, so how much time do I have?
20 minutes? Oh, awesome.
We've got five minutes each.
So, let's move on to the logical aspects of animation
and how things happen.
Sorry guys, I just need to find where I am.
Questions?
When you go back on your old work,
Yep.
Do you ever feel that you can learn more from it?
Like let's say you do do dragons too,
will you ever like go back to your old work in guardians
and be like, I could have done that better,
I could have done that better in reading it,
try it out and like note it down?
Oh dude, yeah, all the time man, all the time.
And honestly, we do that, that's what makes us better.
That's the whole critical part of it.
You know, you want to look at your work
and see what wasn't working and what works.
As an artist, you probably will figure out,
you know, after one year,
you look at stuff you've done before,
there's none of it that you actually really like.
And that's good.
You know, it's harsh because you tend to become someone
that you can't appreciate what you do,
but it's important.
It's good and bad, because it's important
because you always want to get better.
If you find an artist who goes,
I'm good, I'm awesome, I don't need to know anything else,
that person is not going in the right direction.
You always want to be critiquing your own work
and make sure that you're getting better from that.
So yeah, we always do that.
We can't go back to it, movies are already out in theaters, right?
But we try to in the next film to do that.
Like right now, Kung Fu Panda 3, we're learning from the second one,
and we're going to apply what we've learned in the second one to the third one.
Same for Dragons. Dragons was a little different because
the characters grew up, you know, they're different physically as well.
We had to approach it in a different way.
They were not little kids anymore.
They were teenagers at that point.
So already there, we had to change.
We were forced to change it.
But a movie like Kung Fu Panda, we're not forced,
because they're not growing up.
They're still the same characters.
But that's when we learn.
We learn from previous films what we did wrong,
what's working, what's not working.
So the logical aspects of animation,
Why do things happen? The science behind it is extremely important.
Before you can break the rules, you have to know what these rules are.
And that's logical aspects of animation.
That's the one we underestimate as animators or any artist.
We just start, I just want to do a character running around.
You just go into it. I just want to animate a character jumping.
You don't know how this character, what's the physics behind it, you actually do it.
And you just use whatever you already know.
You kinda know how a person jumps,
but you don't know exactly how the foot will twist
when they're jumping.
These little details, you can only see it
when you actually shoot reference and you see it happen.
So I was, again, we're gonna go back to Rise of the Guardians
because that's where I did a lot of that
adding stuff later on to it.
I was working on this shot where Jack
was flying for the first time.
And in this shot, he,
He just, he was learning, you know, he just woke up.
I don't know if you guys saw Rise of the Guardians.
He just woke up and he's running around
and he just gets taken by the wind and he's flying.
And he's a little out of control, you know.
He's not quite knowing what's happening.
He's not fully out of control, he's a little bit.
And when I got the shot, I just jumped right into it.
Creative aspect of animation.
I just went into it and just started animating it
without any kind of knowing.
I did a little bit of YouTube.
I went on YouTube and looked at people gliding, flying.
I was like, all right, that's good enough.
I can just jump into it.
And I did a pass at it, and it looks something like this.
Oh, oh!
Oh!
So that was my first pass at it.
And when you look at this, at this moment right there,
he's too much in control.
You know, he got to a place up there
that he's a little too, almost superman-ish.
You know, he's gliding a little too much.
He's a little too...
So when we all look at it, we're like,
no, it's missing a little bit of that out of control.
And I tried to go in there and do it on my own,
but it wasn't looking right.
So what I did is I had to go in
and shoot a bunch of reference.
And I just got it onto a stool, a broken stool,
and tried to put myself out of balance.
But I wasn't falling, right?
So to put myself out of balance,
I put the stool far away.
Then I tried to run to it, jump on it,
and try to get out of balance.
That's really dangerous to do, so just so you know.
I fell a couple times, I don't think I kept any of that.
I would just run, try to jump on it, get in bands,
just to find all that, and that's me really trying
to keep in bands, that stool was really broken.
Coulda hurt myself.
But all these little things, these little trying to
not fall, this is the mechanical,
this is the logical stuff that you don't think of
as the artist, as the artist you just want to have
nice arcs, but this little sharp motion,
this is stuff that when you see it, you go,
oh yeah, I gotta add this in there.
And this is the stuff that actually I went back
and added that again in my animation.
And eventually it looked like this.
Oh, sorry for the sound.
So you see I've added more of the arms,
you know, trying to catch himself,
and eventually it worked out really well.
I mean, not really well, but better.
So, yeah, so you can later on add stuff to your animation.
You can actually go the artistic way first.
Be creative, start putting stuff,
and then later on go and find stuff that's not working.
Don't be scared to do this.
Don't get attached to your work when you've done a shot.
Always remember, you can go back,
you can come back to it, add more stuff to it.
So, here's another example of that logical aspect,
but also,
Oh, people are leaving already.
I'm going to mix the logical aspect of animation
with the methodical aspect of animation.
How you think about it, how it works,
and how do you actually make it happen.
So, on Avatar, the first shot in production,
I don't know if you remember that, Keith,
was this shot.
This was the first shot in production.
And there's no sound, so that's good.
And we didn't have any motion capture for this
at that point, and it was just all key framed,
and we were learning, this is the first official shot,
and it was at that point just me and my animation director.
And we were focusing on the eyes in this shot.
We needed to make sure that Netiri's eyes
were feeling alive, because that's the biggest problem
in full CG feature animation,
is the fact that the eyes look dead.
And Andy Jones, who was my animation director,
he's also the animation director on Final Fantasy,
The Spirit Within, so he knows about Dead Eye.
And he knows really well.
So when he came to Avatar, he was like,
I have to make sure this doesn't happen again.
So we sat down and we tried to figure out
how do the eyes work.
And as we were learning this, you know, I would sit down and really focus on eye motion.
And we would do a lot of eye tests, and I realized that you can actually break the eye motion into three sections.
The first section is the actual looks that you do.
You actually, I want to look at over there, so I turn my eye and I look there.
I want to look over there.
These are the actual you yourself telling your brain, telling your eye where to look.
That's the first part.
The second part is eye darts.
When you look at something...
You never just look at the thing as a whole.
When you look at something, for example,
let's say you look at a tree.
I did a little 2D animation just to illustrate that.
When you look at a tree, for example,
right, you're looking at a tree,
heh, you like my little eye blink?
You're looking at the whole tree, but your eye will actually, from time to time, go to the top of the tree, look at the top of the tree, and then it will look at a branch on the tree, then it'll probably go down at another branch, back at the top of the tree, then it'll probably go to the root of the tree.
And then it will keep doing this, over and over and over, until you're building that picture in your mind.
That's what causes these eye darts.
So whatever you're looking at...
You never just look at the whole thing.
You guys know that probably.
You look at every bit and pieces on that person,
but that's what creates these eye darts.
So that's the second thing in the eye.
The third part, the third section of the eye is what we all miss.
And that's the thing that, honestly, it took me forever to try and figure that one out,
is eye keep alive.
How do you make, because you can get the eye dart,
you can get the eye looks,
What's missing in all those movies like Tintin and
Beowulf and all those movies, why the eyes feel dead,
is because they're missing that eye keep alive.
And that's extremely important.
So, as we were playing with it, by mistake,
we were finding something in between these eye dots
that was keeping the eye alive.
And we're like, wow, why is this working?
And we tried to do it, and it wasn't working anymore.
It was feeling like vibration.
And we're like, no, this is not the right thing to do.
So I spent weeks trying to figure it out,
how to make it work, like a formula,
to give all the other animators for them to figure it out.
And eventually I figured out, and that's the methodical aspect, how do you solve that problem,
is I realized that if you do, if you basically look at a tree,
and you do the eye darts, big eye darts, you use the same animation,
you squash it, you make it much smaller, and you make it way tinier in terms of the amplitude of it,
you get your Keep Alive.
So it's not random, but it is control random.
It's very important to actually not make it vibrate,
because that becomes really, really distracting.
So that's what we started doing.
We realized that if you do eye darts,
and you tone them down, you speed them up a little bit,
you get this really cool keep alive.
Because eye darts, it basically hits something,
stays there for a few frames, hits something else,
comes back down.
It's random, but it's also control.
You never want to go back to a place
and then come back to the same place.
That's when it becomes like a vibration.
You don't want that.
So when we figured that out, we're like,
oh man, this is awesome.
So this is something that we can start adding
in all our animation.
So I went back and added this in this shot.
And we were all happy, it was looking great.
And then as soon as it got rendered,
motion blur killed all the animation.
So as you can see, the eyes are still dead.
So it was a learning process.
We looked at it and went, oh man, motion blur.
Because when you put all this time in motion,
motion blur kills it.
So the next shot that I did,
I decided I'm gonna go crazy and put a lot more in it.
And you can see I put probably a little too much in this one.
So her eyes are moving a little too much in this one.
And I did spend a little too much time on this.
It still works, but if I redo this shot,
I probably won't put as much.
But we were learning, and this is all part
of that methodical aspect of animation.
Cool. So then when I got to DreamWorks, we all did it.
You know, we were all doing tests, you know, eye tests.
For example, I did a tooth fairy test, you know, with just my eyes and, you know,
showing how this method, how...
If you look at my eyes, you look at the animated one,
there's a difference every time my eye actually stops.
If you look at tooth fairy, her eyes keep moving even though my eyes stop.
Realistically, your eyes will stop.
But if you do this in animation, you get the dead eye feel.
That's the whole thing is animators go,
I've done exactly what my eyes are doing.
That's the problem.
In animation, you have to push it a little bit
because it looks dead.
A lot of stuff goes on top of your animation, just kills it.
So adding that little keep alive really
keeps your eye from feeling dead.
That make sense?
Yeah?
Cool.
So here's another example of that methodical aspect.
Let me just turn this one off. So many videos. Sorry guys, give me one second. Questions?
I don't remember. Keith, were they rigged? Yes, they were rigged.
So you're saying that I didn't animate that?
Alright, so,
Rise of the Apes, that's another one that I learned
a lot in terms of how to, oh, is it there?
So this is a shot, hopefully it will play in real time.
So in this shot, which was actually a really simple shot,
I thought it would be.
is when I got that shot, it was basically
Caesar coming back from, again,
there was no motion capture on this one.
A lot of the shots, a few of the shots that we had
on Rise of the Apes, the motion capture data
was just not working, so, but we had the video
of Andy Serkis doing the performance.
So we were able to, so we were able to actually,
you know, use his videos and match the videos
to actually get his, you know, his motion.
And when I got this, I was like, ah, easy,
I'll just copy whatever Andy did.
I said, I'm done.
I was like, that's a couple days of work and I got it.
So I did it, took Andy's performance,
copied it to my animation, I was like, done.
Then I looked and I was like, wait,
that looks like a guy in a monkey suit.
it just didn't look right.
And if his body felt too light,
I was like, something in this is not working.
So, you know, Andy's proportion,
he has human's proportion, not quite like Caesar,
you know, way bigger, you know, torso,
much bigger shoulders.
So when Andy's moving, he's, you know,
he was acting ape, you know,
he wasn't, he's not an ape, you know,
he can't quite do it.
But, you know, again, all credit, in terms of performance, this is all Andy's performance.
I mean, the look away, that's all his stuff, that I just pushed the timing, you know, to make it work.
All credit goes to him in terms of acting. I did not shoot any reference for this.
But, so...
I started watching chimps walk.
When they walk, they really move their bodies.
That's what we all do.
We all know that.
If we have to act, Abe will do this, right?
So we all do this.
So I decided, artistically, I'm just gonna grab this
and add this to that.
I just started doing this to it when he stands.
It looked too cartoony.
It just didn't work.
The more I was putting side to side,
the more cartoony it felt,
and I was fighting my creative side and my logical side.
I was just fighting to just get the right thing.
So, even though I was watching videos, like, I just couldn't get it.
So, we went to the zoo to actually do some reference shooting of chimps.
And one of the videos that we had, there was this alpha chimp that was,
there was a trainer feeding the alpha, feeding the chimps apples.
And the alpha chimp was there and he got an apple, he cut the apple,
and then this little baby chimp jumped and grabbed the apple and left.
He looked at the little baby chimp go, he looked back and he goes,
You know, he'll ask for another.
And that shot, we actually used it in Rise of the Apes.
We actually did that in there.
And so, the way he moved was amazing.
The way he shifted his weight,
he's, basically he did side to side,
and then he just stops and asks.
His weight did not keep going.
It just stopped, and he was so stiff and rigid.
And it's not something that I would do as an animator.
I was like, I don't know if I would do that.
It feels too rigid.
And I tried it in here.
Oh, it's choppy.
Getting in?
So if you look at when he walks in, he shifts to the...
Oh!
Terrible.
Oh, do I need to do that?
Okay.
Okay, that's going to be a...
Yeah.
It's hard. I can't see it.
Warmer?
Nope.
Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah.
Like it?
All right, here we go.
You know what? I'm gonna make this smaller because this is too big. Let's see.
Oh my God.
All right.
Anyways, you guys believe me, right?
Yeah.
This is not going to be easy.
I can't get to the bottom of it.
All right.
Let's watch this again.
Maybe hopefully this will work.
It's the slow computer.
Let's go.
It's right at the very beginning of it when he moves.
And he goes to the left, and then he
stops when he goes to the right.
Left, and he just stops.
So that harsh stop is what actually I learned
watching an ape doing it.
And I tried that in there, and really,
I got that really strong, powerful feel of an ape.
And so this is an example of how you have that battle
between the creative aspect where you just want to keep.
You just want to keep all that overlap going,
which looks really animated, looks great,
but does it fit in a movie like Rise of the Apes
where it's very realistic?
Because you have to think about it,
is not animation, different styles,
you have to mix.
You can't mix styles if it's a realistic film.
Whoa, five minutes left.
If you're realistic film, you have to do a different style
of animation.
All right, let's move on.
So methodical aspect of animation,
how do you actually do it?
So I talked about the eye, us learning how to do the eye
darts and stuff.
Another thing that I do actually is I never
show the eye performance.
Where is it?
Whenever I'm shooting my reference,
whenever I start my animation,
I always start it without the eyes
because eyes are distracting.
As an audience, that's what you look at.
You know, you always look at the eyes.
So, as an animator as well,
if you have the eyes on,
if you're actually looking at the eyes,
it's very distracting whenever you're animating.
So, for example, this is the same shot
with the face turned on
and there's no animation in the eyes.
Check this out.
Sorry, the sound is broken.
So I bet you everybody was looking at his eyes, right? At the facial.
No one was paying attention to the body and that's because the eyes are so distracting.
So when I'm animating, I actually turn off the eyes and it really, really helps me out.
All right, let's move on.
So, what else?
What else?
Methodical aspect, we can move on.
Critical aspects of animation.
So this is probably, like I said,
the most important aspect of animation.
You need to come back with a fresh eye.
And, you know, in a studio, you don't have that luxury.
You can't quite just take a break from your animation
and come back in a couple days.
You have to actually pay, really pay close attention
to taking, what was I saying?
Sorry, I just saw the two minutes and I just completely lost what I was going to say.
You're making me panic there.
So, what was I going to say?
Take breaks.
Take breaks, come back with a fresh eye.
What I do is sometimes I put a mirror in front of my animation.
It really helps me out.
Sometimes I flick my animation and most importantly, you ask your friends to come and look at your work,
you know, give you ideas, you know, helps you out.
Is there music that's going to play when I have to go?
Cool.
So I can keep going.
So, you know, here's an example of, you know, things that I talked about that Jack Frost shot.
where he, at the end there, whenever he floats down from the table...
Why I didn't like that shot was because the director, when he floats down, I asked the director,
do you want him to be floating down with magic or do you want him to fall down like a real boy?
He goes, I don't want him to fall down like a real boy, it's going to hurt him.
Falling from that top, it's going to hurt him.
Or, magically, I don't want this to be too magical.
So he didn't give me an answer, so I went back to my desk and I was like,
alright, I'll do halfway.
Never go halfway. Commit to an idea.
When you go halfway, it looks shit like this.
So, you know, make sure you commit to an idea.
You know, you go, it's either gonna fall or it's gonna float down.
You commit to it. You want this to be awesome.
I've got one minute left.
Here's another example.
This is a shot of Jake where we all had to do
tail animation on the avatar.
And this was a shot that I did tail animation
and I spent like about an hour on it.
I was like, ah, super, super easy.
And I sent it through and people were laughing about it.
They're like, Jalil, you can't swing the tail like this
all over the place because we haven't modeled
anything in between his legs.
So, you know, we can't show anything.
So I had to make sure that I hide
as soon as he turns around and you're gonna see
There!
I turn the tail and hide whatever is there,
so you don't see underneath, like...
So, all that stuff, you know, is stuff that, you know, that...
that you learn.
I need one more minute.
And so right now, a group of friends and I,
we're working on a game, I just need to plug this in there.
We're working on a game, and it's called Deadwood,
and again, this is another one where we had a cool idea,
and we were doing this little wooden guy,
and the performance was an idol
when he's just doing his fist like this.
And we blocked this in, and I was like,
yeah, this is gonna be great,
this is gonna work in the game, and we can totally do this.
But the problem is, the game's, the angle of the game,
It actually.
the angle of the game is actually from this angle.
So for the most part, you'll be seeing the character
in this angle.
He does turn around.
So you have to realize there's a lot of stuff
that you do that you can't actually,
you have to work with the angle of that character.
And so what we did is, you'll see eventually,
we have a better angle of that character where
I tried something a little broader, a little more,
a little bigger that actually works.
Almost done.
The animation's coming.
And it's right at the end of this.
All zombies killing, blah, blah, blah.
Here it is.
So we decided to go a little broader with the animation.
So from the back, you can actually see what he's doing.
The animations are great, but hey, it's
going to work for a little game like this.
Cool.
I think we are done.
So that's the four aspects of animation.
Really important.
All you guys, think about this whenever you're animating.
There's no rules to that.
You can add your own things if you want.
Find the principles of animation.
Fit them wherever you want.
But incredibly important.
Cool.
Thank you very much.