Hi everyone, welcome to the GDC Twitch channel.
My name is Brian Francis.
I am, as always, the invisible voice inside your head.
I am here today playing a game called Heaven's Vault.
It comes to you from the folks at Inkle,
based out of Cambridge.
You guys are in Cambridge, right?
That's right.
Yeah, we are.
OK, I'm going to actually need you.
I'm going to need to do something down here real quick.
John has unfortunately, you can't see John down there,
everyone, but we have both Joe and John.
Yeah, there we go.
I'm going to have to get a bit uncomfortable to play, so that's all.
Anyway, we are here today with some lovely folks in chat. I already see CliftonB out there.
I think I saw someone else but I refreshed the page and I lost their name.
Hi everyone in chat. We are here today, like I said, we're playing Heaven's Vault.
It is just releasing today. It is a narrative archaeology game where you can walk around,
have great interactive conversations with people, with great interesting characters.
The setting is probably my favorite part of the game. We'll get to that in a bit.
Right now we are looking for the friend of the Archeal, of another academic type who we're friends with.
So we're on a kind of a friend-goes-missing-ancient-mysteries kind of quest.
Which is how Indiana Jones starts, but this game takes a very different tack from Indiana Jones.
Alex, I need you to introduce yourself, even though a lot of folks probably know who you are.
Hey, what's up? My name is Alex Warrow.
I am a contributing editor at Gamasutra.com and I help out on GDC.
And most importantly, I skipped lunch to be here,
and I'm just now starting to regret it.
I told him not to.
But luckily...
I've been getting some rumblings in the background.
Yeah, no joke.
We have two very special guests here who can do most of the hard thinking for me.
Special guest, will you tell everyone who you are and what you do, please?
Hey, I'm Joe.
I'm a gameplay director at Inkle.
I'm John, I'm the narrative director here at Inglewood.
Welcome.
Brian, where are you?
I forget the planet name, gonna be honest.
We're in the middle of the cyclones.
Okay.
So this game takes place in a nebula, which is instead of moons in a nebula, instead of
navigating through what's kind of a traditional space setting, you, you, um, uh, yeah I know
they don't take this naturally, we're robots.
So instead of navigating through a space setting, you ride these rivers around the nebula.
And we have made our way to an unknown moon way back in the uncharted waters of this place.
We beam down to the planet's surface.
There's kind of, me and my robot pal are here looking for our friend.
We have a clue that led us here about this robe.
So, you know, lost civilization, mysteries to explore.
Unfortunately, forward in chat, I will point out,
reading games are often some of the hardest to stream
because I have to read and process information that I need to lose later
and talk to our illustrious guests.
So, for now, I am going to work on this gameplay and toss a question out to our guests.
Would you please introduce Heaven's Vault from your perspective?
I think you've been working on it since shortly after 80 Days wrapped up, right?
Yeah, that's right.
So, 80 Days shipped in 2014, back when the world was a normal and sane place.
And that did quite well for us.
And we thought, let's do something ambitious.
Let's see what we can do that isn't just like 81 days or 240 days.
Let's try and do something different and something special.
So we decided to do something graphical.
We decided to try and go to PlayStation, make something for consoles.
And we didn't really know what else we wanted to do.
And then we spent quite a while kind of landing on a concept that really
attracted us and kind of had enough.
And I think we ended up with a concept with quite a lot, quite a lot in it actually, in the end.
About four years of work in it.
It was supposed to be a sort of ambitious, you know, maybe year and a half project and four years later and, yeah.
We're now a studio of eight people, seven people, whereas we were a studio of two.
So it's been quite a long and complicating process getting to this point.
But.
It's done. It's actually done and it works.
And it's out there. People are playing it.
I find this very surprising still because it was...
It was quite...
It was a sort of idea that we thought might be possible.
And we weren't entirely sure that it was actually going to be
the sort of thing one could actually do.
We thought we were going to get halfway through it and then go,
Nah, this isn't working. We have to stop now.
So, yeah.
I know.
Yeah.
That's a bit of a surprise. I've got launch day surprise.
Yeah, ain't that always how it goes.
Real quick, before we jump in, I want to say now that we have a good quorum going here in chat,
if you have any questions for these two, please, by all means, drop them in chat.
Brian and I will relay them and it will be a big help.
Because like I said, Brian's got some mysteries to solve, so we need your good, smart questions,
preferably about game development, game design, and this game particularly.
Yeah, I mean this is launch day.
I mean, we were talking before the stream, it's late over there, it's about 10pm.
How are you guys feeling so far?
Literally just stepped in back into the office after going out for a launch dinner with the
whole team.
So that was nice.
Where did you go?
We went to a place called Al Kazbah, which is an Algerian restaurant.
Nice.
It's very personal.
Yeah.
It's a brand.
Definitely.
There's a location in the game, you can go to the moon where Leo is.
I grew up and there's a bar there run by a bartender
and that bar is modeled on,
I mean it's modeled on places in Morocco really,
but like it's modeled on this restaurant down the road
that we went to, as good as anywhere else,
like that's our closest local reference for that.
So I look very cool.
So, I think on brand place to go.
We already have a good question here in chat
and it kind of dovetails with what I want to get into,
which is,
You know, what's so striking about Heaven's Vault is the look and the spaces that you traverse.
This is, as far as I know, the first like really 3D navigatable sort of like game compared to you've ever made,
because the earlier games, they were all based on like choosing dialogue options and moving through interactive stories.
And there's a question here from Dainty Rhino who wants to know,
what's the purpose of these faded ghosts that appear whenever the character moves?
So the whole theme of the game is history and archaeology.
So we quite liked the idea that as an archaeologist,
while she's exploring these sites,
and maybe she's leaving her own footprint on the sites
as she explores them, because she's changing history herself.
So wherever she stands, whatever she does,
she leaves almost like a memory which fades
as she moves away again, as you saw just there.
So it's just to give that sense of history
sense of memories and creating a new history herself.
It's a funny thing, because we've been through a bunch of different takes on the animation
style over the course of the project. We've had a lot of different ideas and we've used a lot of
different variants of crossfading frames. And at one point we took those ghosts out completely
and we missed them. We just missed them. But the thing felt a little bit throwaway. It felt like
you were just... you know when you have a video game character and they're just...
buzzing around an environment.
They're just running from place to place
and they're just scooping everything up.
And they don't really exist in the world at all.
They're just kind of, like a mouse pointer
scrubbing across the screen.
And that's how we interact in 3D spaces,
and it wasn't quite heavy enough.
Like, you're supposed to be in this world.
So just that little thing that gets left behind
just gives you a note of,
you really were there.
and you can't, if you buzz around the level, then it looks like she's doing something crazy, which she is actually.
Every time we took it out, it kind of looked worse, so we kept putting it back in again.
Yeah, I mean those bits of feedback can be interesting that way.
I think to me, watching Brian play, it sort of resonates with the game's themes,
which seem to be this idea that spaces can be so many different things,
and they can be used in so many different ways by different people throughout time,
and people leave...
pathways right as they go about their lives and so you're seeing very in a very physical way and in a very like
uh, what seems like a resource
uh a lightweight compared to like, um
Something like in god of war where you can like actually see the characters footsteps through the snow and incredibly rich detailed
Like very expensive technology. Um, but here you have this like very simple reminder that where she is is like a place
In space as well as time. I think that's really interesting
um
Oh man, there's so many good questions here
If you guys have a second clifton b has a question here
that is sort of unrelated, but I think it's fascinating.
How much prep work do you do before you jump into Ink?
And what tools do you use in your process
for, I guess, sort of narrative design
and implementing storylines?
We should clarify for those at home,
Ink is Inkle's game writing tool.
I believe it's available for other devs to use
because it's open source?
Oh, yeah.
It's open source, yeah.
Okay.
The whole point of Ink is that it's incredibly editable.
So we do not do any planning.
or prototyping outside of ink.
When I, if I want to write a scene,
if I want to write some dialogue,
if I want to start getting to know the characters,
I just write some ink.
And then as the structure gets more complicated,
you start taking bits of that ink
and maybe putting it somewhere else
or packaging it up in another wrapper
so that it can become part of a scene
rather than just a standalone bit of dialogue.
But you're just throwing scripts around.
So it's actually very, very quick and easy to do.
So all of this stuff has evolved and evolved and evolved
from very basic.
prototype scripts, the original kind of first third of the game,
but you're just about at the end of the first third here,
the kind of opening plot section.
And that was originally knocked out as a script in ink in one afternoon.
Like these are the basic beats that they will go through during that tutorial
section.
And that's just evolved into plates to become this 3d world within
environmental conversations and all the kinds of things that you do within that
world's sort of step-by-step-by-step.
So.
Yeah, I get quite dogmatic about this. We don't do any kind of planning.
We do things when we need to do it.
So if I need to work out the flow of a scene, I'll get a piece of paper and a pen,
and I'll draw a flowchart to help my brain work.
But we don't do any formalized process.
We don't have any kind of spreadsheet construction process or anything.
It tends to be whatever the level needs.
I think a nice thing about Ink is the way it kind of adapts to what your needs are.
So if some people like to really plan in advance and create flowcharts for absolutely everything,
then they can, and then they can fill in the boxes in terms of writing little snippets.
We try to make tools that kind of fit your own workflow, basically.
writing workflow is super ad hoc.
I mean, that's...
that's really familiar.
So, I mean, bearing that in mind, like,
how did you approach the
sort of conception and narrative
design of this game as a whole? You know, like, what was
your... like, because I'm fascinated as I
watch Brian play and as I look forward to playing
myself, like, this seems...
It's very difficult to construct.
It's a bunch of interlocking puzzles and interesting conversations and choices.
How did you go about structuring it from the beginning?
Was it really just you just started going and then kind of made it as you went along?
Or did you have a formal structure for how you create these narratives and branch them?
The goal of what we wanted to repeat
kind of had a clear image of that.
We changed the way that you walk around, but basically you can walk around and...
John, could you lean forward and start that answer again?
You suddenly lost it. You got really quiet.
I just turned my volume way up.
Yes, so...
I think when we started the project we had a very clear sense of
what the player would be doing in the world.
They would be walking around and interacting with things,
and then talking about things as they interacted with them,
and then as you walked to the next place you would be walking as you...
Sorry, talking as you walk from point to point.
That was kind of our core loop idea,
was walk and talks and interaction plots.
And then actually working out how to author that in Ink
was about a year's worth of work.
Because finding a pattern which allowed you to author it
flexibly enough that you didn't have to,
that you could do whatever you needed to do,
but that wasn't so complicated that you had to
constantly look up how to do it,
or break it the whole time.
Finding a right sort of balance.
for scripting it, that was a really long and difficult iterative process.
So I think we kind of had initial scripts within a couple of months, I guess,
that did do that.
They did the walking around and the talking, but they were a real pain to author.
They were too fiddly.
They were very, very fragile.
And over the course of the project, we slowly worked out
things that we were doing a lot of that we could extract into other ways.
So.
For example, the way the conversation in the game works.
Originally, conversations were tied specifically to rooms and things we were looking at,
because that's the easiest thing to do, right?
You go to somewhere and you have a conversation about it.
And what we have now is a system where they're walking around in an environment
that the game is feeding conversation options in from a bank of conversation that it has all the time,
which is triggered by the knowledge model that it's tracking in the game.
So what you know and what you don't know.
says well these conversations are relevant, these ones aren't, and all of that is sculpted in ink.
All of that is crafted in ink.
And yeah, it took a long time to build that structure and make it work.
I can't remember what the question was now.
It was a really complicated engine to build, but I think what we started with
was a very clear idea that it ought to be possible to build this thing this way.
We just had to find a pattern that allowed...
the author, the human being writing it, not to get totally baffled by what they were doing.
That's the major limiting factor.
Right to the bottom level, because I mean right from the very early prototypes we had
this idea that we could use the same text engine to basically not just produce prose
as we did on 80 Days, but produce line by line.
lines are basically an interactive film script.
So each line is either a scene direction like
show this camera shot, play this sound,
play this kind of sequence or it's actual lines of dialogue.
And then the engine takes these line by line
and presents them in a visual way.
And that never changed.
We changed the high level structure quite a lot
in order to fit the
the continually evolving game design, but that general approach stayed consistent throughout
even from right at the beginning when it was basically, it was almost a 2D game with like
static comic book panels where you made dialogue choices in a kind of static 2D comic book
panel and then it went from panel to panel.
But fundamentally, you know, John was writing in the same way then as...
he did towards the end, it's just that the whole game has changed in between.
I guess when we're making this stuff we have a really, we have an ongoing discussion the
whole time of what's in the game and what's in the ink, and we see those as two quite
separate themes.
So the ink is, should be in control of all the narrative stuff and all the presentation
stuff and all the sequencing stuff and all the stuff that wants to be flexible depending
on what the player might or might not have done.
stuff that lets you, so that when you get to the end of the project you can redraft it,
so that when you get to the end of the project you can make this particular line of dialogue not
actually appear under that specific circumstance because that's the sort of thing that Ink's really
good at. And then the game side has to cover all the things which are systemic, which we don't want
to have to bother authoring specifically every time. So like when you're talking to another
human being it drops into a two-shot which sort of goes over the shoulder between each character.
And that's within the game code because you don't want the ink to have to worry about that.
The ink doesn't even want to have to tell the game that that's happening.
The game just goes, oh, two human beings are talking to each other.
Time for a two-shot.
Which is kind of exciting because you can just write a load of dialogue.
without any scene instructions at all,
and it will present it in an interesting way in the engine,
which is kind of a magical process.
What's really great about that is then I can take a dialogue sequence
which was written for one location
and pick it up and stick it in another location,
and it will just work.
And plenty of times in the game where you can have the same conversation
with the same character in five, six different places in the world,
just depending on how you happen to meet them,
it doesn't really matter from our point of view at all.
Yeah, that's super interesting.
That's so cool.
That's magic.
That sounds like magic.
I'm sorry.
The idea that you can write a scene and then have the engine sort of programmatically figure
out the shot, reverse shot of it, and then not worry about, like, from a direction perspective,
that's so cool.
Yeah.
Well, it's incredibly liberating as well.
And, like, obviously games like The Witcher do this.
You know, games like Assassin's Creed Odyssey do this.
They have programmatic two shots.
they use to cover or like programmatic anims that are kind of brought in just to keep scenes
alive when they haven't authored something specific to override it.
And ideally you never notice that they're doing that, but I'm absolutely sure that they
are doing that.
We have the advantage of not having, because we don't have voice acting, we don't have
continuous animation, we can cut between procedural stuff and scripted stuff incredibly fluidly
without it being particularly noticeable.
So we can really push that.
It's a quite absurd extremes.
So you can have the same...
Yeah, you can have the same conversations with the same people in wildly different contexts.
And the game...
I'm curious, and before we move on to Greg,
did this game's design and development influence the design and development of Ink?
And if so, how has the language changed as a result of your work on Heaven's Vault?
It's kind of stayed remarkably static. We've developed it over time, but most of the major advances that we made in ink
happened at the very start of this project. It's been like one or two extra features that we've added.
Yeah.
It's worth noting that a lot of the design of Heaven's Vault comes from the design of Sorcery,
despite the fact that they're very, very different games.
A lot of what we're doing in Heaven's Vault is just taking something we prototyped in Sorcery and pushing it really, really far.
So, of course, we had basic knowledge modeling and...
scenes dropped in contextually if they happen to be relevant right now.
Heaven's Vault evolved entirely after that.
It's obviously used in specific places, but there were a few features like...
Lists.
Lists, yeah.
Ink has a data structure called a list, which I think when you first pitched it I had no
idea how powerful it was going to be.
And you were like, well, it's sort of this and it's sort of that.
And it sort of does both of those.
And I was like, we don't need that.
And you were like, yeah, but we can do it.
And now, like, I build everything out of this thing.
Programming speakers, basically they're enums or flags.
But they're so much more powerful than that.
They're kind of also a bit like mathematical sets.
And the way we use it is for state tracking.
So whether it's your inventory or...
all of the things that you know about or whatever, and we just track kind of pools of these facts,
essentially. Chris Remo did a talk at GDC this year about the fact system that they had in
Firewatch. I only caught the second half of it, I need to catch up on the Vault, but
I was going to entertain listening to it because we have a fact tracking system in
Heaven's Vault which has something like three and a half thousand facts.
And every single line in the game is sort of saying,
do you know these facts, but you don't know these facts,
in which case this line is appropriate.
This is how the whole system works.
Oh, yeah.
That's a lot.
It's fine, actually.
It's very, very manageable,
because they're all contextual.
So you just look up ones that are relevant.
Yeah.
Definitely was a feature that we were building
originally using quite a hacky system,
kind of got wrapped into the language.
I don't know if we all remember, it's been a journey, but this question started sort of
out of a question about how you, how you sort of create the, how you, your process for writing
the narrative of this game.
Before we move on, I want to get the last part of CliftonB's question, because it was
kind of interesting.
They wanted to know, basically like they always have their narrative super solid before they
start implementing.
And they want to know, like, do you ever realize things you've missed after you've started
implementing a storyline in your editor?
How does that shape your game design?
Whether it's a game like this or a game like 80 Days,
like, how do you figure out what to incorporate in a game
even when you're, say, six months from ship
and you've already got most of the narrative written down?
Like...
Yeah, so the thing that the whole...
So this business of building a structure
where we write the ink and the game code processes it
was very difficult,
but the payoff for that is two weeks before we ship.
I was playing through the game and I found a scene that I didn't like.
I just didn't like it at all.
The dialogue was rubbish.
So I took half a day and I rewrote it entirely.
Every single line of it was changed.
The entire flow of that scene was changed.
And I just took the file, rewrote it, tested it, swapped it out, and then it was in the
game changed.
Like, we were already in beta testing at this point.
Like, we already, I think, had sent a code off of PlayStation's FQA process, you know.
Dangerous.
I didn't really like it.
in the process, but it isn't dangerous because actually it's very easy to test a scene in
isolation in ink and make sure that you're really very happy with it.
And actually there's no cost to it.
I don't need to talk to anyone else.
I don't need to talk to the environment people or the character people or the animation people
or anyone else.
Like, I can just go off and do that on my own and come back with it and say, yep, that's
better.
And we constantly do that.
So I think if Heaven's Vault has a good
story or it has good characters or have good moments. It's not because we planned things
cleverly in advance, it's because we planned something that was okay and we've got a really
good system for trading up. So every scene in this game has been traded up to make it stronger or
tighter or better. All the bits that we didn't need we cut and all the bits that could be
stronger we developed. And the freedom to do that as a writer...
Like film writers, script writers on films do this all the time.
They are constantly rewriting screenplays on the day of shooting.
That's normal in the film industry.
In the games industry, you're supposed to lock your script six months in advance
and still be happy with it by the time you ship.
And that's a hell of an art.
And yeah, breaking that assumption definitely comes with some compromises
in terms of the fidelity of what we can achieve, but the payoff in terms of the...
We're massively taking advantage of the fact that we're not fully voiced, we're not fully
animated.
So we're kind of...
we're able to pour all of our energy into refining the core storytelling.
It's a funny thing though, because people looking at it sometimes say,
oh well it would have been nice if it would be fully voiced.
But you go, you know what, actually, if it had been fully voiced,
it would have been a significantly worse script.
I also want to chime in on what fully voiced can mean for developers.
Or from the player's side, fully voiced often means like I'm often sitting, I can't read
the conversation at my own pace, I have to read it at the actor's pace.
And often there's some very, very great, you know, performances in there.
That like, I forget what I was playing. Oh yeah, it was Horizon Zero Dawn I was playing the other day and I was like resisting the urge to just keep
uh, to just keep um, skipping past cutscenes because I wanted to, you know, hear the drama of it, but
that's another thing that I don't think, I don't think, I don't hear it said aloud a lot, but like.
Yeah, we're always talking about this and um, I think you know there are solutions,
but the solutions are in the core game design. I kind of see that.
Like the voice that you have to listen to occupies a small part of your brain,
but then the rest of your brain is left unoccupied.
And if you can fill it with other related gameplay, like, you know,
Firewatch and games in that kind of genre, you know,
it works because you're able to explore while communicating and listening to the dialogue.
If you only had to just sit and listen to the dialogue and do nothing else,
it wouldn't be as playable.
And so yeah, you could do a fully voiced Heaven's Vault, that kind of style of game, but you'd have to find ways of
occupying the rest of the player's brain while the dialogue is going on.
I mean, I think there's a... I don't know that I even agree with that entirely. I think there's a question of scope as well.
Like, the amount of information you can communicate in text that you read in your head
is just a lot higher than the amount you can communicate when you're doing...
voice acted stuff and it depends on what kind of story you want to tell and what you want
to talk about.
But like, delivering exposition through spoken dialogue is one of the worst things in the
world.
Like, films try to avoid it as much as possible because it's just deathly dull.
You can do it in prose much more effortlessly because people just read it and they grok
it and it's gone.
and if you understand your medium, you can take advantage of that and you can do things with it.
And yeah, this idea that we should just be making the flashiest version of everything
so that didn't impact the content that you can deliver seems to me to be a bit wrong-headed.
That's the thing. As a writer, I'm very happy.
Their question is,
Have you met or contacted Jordan Mechner during the development process,
considering this has a Last Express vibes?
I haven't played Last Express myself, so I can't testify to that.
I wanted to ask you about the setting in general,
because there's a few key things beyond just sort of the
Asian, Middle East, Southeast Asian kind of vibe of the game.
It's also...
This very strange intertwining of a mystical and scientific world,
because you have robots that are dug up from the ground,
you have a nebula where people sail in it like the river.
This is cool. This is really cool.
And while I think it would be nice to hear if you did talk to Mr. Mechner,
I just want to know more about making this setting in a world where game developers
I feel like have to fight for interesting settings with every game,
or they risk feeling like a knockoff of some other game that's already existed.
So no, we've never spoken to Jordan Mechner.
But The Last Express is my favorite game of all time.
It's just an astonishingly good piece of writing.
And wonderful, wonderful concept.
It's funny how it's almost like luck that we ended up being similar to Last Express.
I know it's your favorite game.
In terms of the structure, I'm sure you took influence.
But in terms of the art style, it takes a lot of...
Well you could say it takes influence, we came from a totally different direction.
I think I remember a point when we were talking about this, and we tried this, and we tried
that, and we tried the other, and you were like, oh bloody hell, let's just do the last
experiment.
We ended up with this almost rotoscoped look.
So the setting, if you want to dive into how you cooked up the setting.
Yeah, the setting was...
hard actually. And when we started, we'd always worked on other IPs previously, so obviously
80 Days is an adaptation of an IP, and Sorcery is too, and Joe was very keen on making our
own IP, and I really didn't want to, because I knew it would be difficult.
Turns out it's a lot of work.
Yeah, turns out it's a lot of work. But I think the... it was a really long and torturous
process. I think we started with a few things that we were sure of.
So we wanted the nebula, the rivers in space was a core idea that we started with, which
came from kind of landscapes that you were interested in visually.
Yeah, because we're just thinking that like usually when space is represented in games
it's kind of like this black void of emptiness and like hard steel, hard sci-fi, and we loved
that idea that you could create a version of space which is more like one of these
beautiful nebulas that you see.
see the Hubble telescope, it's beautiful, colorful, rich, and dense.
As you said, more like natural landscape of rivers and mountains where the mountains are
like big cloud banks.
Yeah and that coupled into an image that comes from Egyptian mythology of the gods sailing
barges through the rivers of stars, which is how they describe the way that Ra travels
across the sky.
That felt like a cool association to play with, but not necessarily a concrete piece of world building.
It didn't really help very much.
I think there was about maybe even a year where I would just wake up in the morning, try to do some writing,
and think, why are there rivers in space?
Why are there rivers in space?
And I would ask people in the office, why are there rivers in space?
They would say, oh, it doesn't matter.
I'm like, no, I really think we need to know this.
And then at some point, I had an idea for why...
there are rivers in space, which I'm not going to share because it's a huge spoiler.
But from that, everything else followed.
And then most of the rest of the building, of the setting, was trying to stick to a couple
of basic ground rules.
So I was hugely inspired by the work of Ursula Le Guin and Jean-Wulf Dye.
Rest in peace, Mr. Wulf, because I think you just passed yesterday.
Yeah.
Wonderful writer.
But they both...
Le Guin's stuff is incredibly empathetic.
Yeah.
Thank you.
and I love that, and very based around humans and what humans do and how they shape things.
And Wolf's stuff is not particularly empathetic, but one thing that he does very well
is that he tends to have one core magic in his world that then manifests in multiple ways
that the people in the world don't realize are the same thing, which is a really neat trick for
building a sci-fi setting because it makes everything feel connected even though everything
is also disparate.
So you get a sense of wonder, but a sense that it all comes from the same,
it somehow was cut from the same cloth.
Hmm.
It bridges the line between magic and science in a way.
Yeah, exactly.
Because the problem with magic is that it's arbitrary.
The problem with your kind of Harry Potter is,
well, next week Harry Potter might get a spell to do something else
completely random that you didn't know existed in this world.
And like, well, why doesn't Dumbledore just ask to win the game spell
and then everything's fine?
Um, and that's a problem.
If you want to kind of make your world compelling, especially if the player doesn't understand it and explore it
But if you if you lay out the like lots of technological rules in the way that Star Trek does you end up with this
Incredibly complicated world. It's very inaccessible for people coming into it new. So ideally what we have is two rules
with interesting consequences and
So we try to do that. We try to make our world set up in a way that
that would follow.
Everything in the world comes from these two technological ideas that we had, which kind
of come out in lots of different interesting ways, and then that led us to natural places
in the narrative, and then you think, well, how can I express this narrative?
And it all kind of twists around itself, and you bring in things which are interesting,
and you cut them to the charm, and there was lots of research that kind of inspired various
themes and moments in the game, and then you have to work out why they make sense.
It was horrendous actually, it was really hard.
Of course, you don't just have to build a world in the present, you have to create 5,000 years of history.
I resisted that for so long! For so long I was like, it'll be fine, we'll just make stuff up, it won't matter.
And then I realised that I couldn't do it. I genuinely needed to know what happened in 3,500 years in order to write this location.
The signals are on the back wall there.
I am too.
Luckily, that's a very tiny... they're very tiny on that screen there.
Feel free to enhance our 720p broadcast to try and pick out a few pixels in the lower left-hand corner with our moderately okay encoding.
It's probably easier to just play the game, isn't it?
Yeah, it's...
It was a really long and...
difficult process. And I think one thing we've had,
we've seen a lot of reviews today and one thing that's been common across the reviews is people saying, you know,
they really like this world. It feels like a really fleshed out real world and that's
incredibly good to hear because it was really hard work.
But I think the thing that makes it hang together is just
we have tried to shade it back at all times and make sure that it does really genuinely make sense with itself. So
there's a lot of places where
in the game, there's like symbology that just works.
So at the beginning of the game,
you're introduced to this symbol called the Eagle and Sun,
which is the symbol of the empire
that was around in this nebula
before a cataclysm happened and it was destroyed.
And one of the questions that the game
never explicitly asks is what the hell is an eagle
and what the hell is a sun to the people in this nebula?
But I see answers to these questions
and they're in there and they make sense.
And like the fact that that tracks.
is not an accident, but it does make the world feel robust, even if no one ever talks about it.
Um, yeah.
Uh, John, I have a question as someone who's, I've done some work, you know, I've, I know that the
how the process of writing different kinds of games can go what?
It is very easy to fall down the trap of building out loads and loads of beautiful lore and knowledge and information about your game.
You are all lucky in that you have a game that wants to use that lore and knowledge,
but how, when you only have so much time to make a game that needs to pay for your meal, your family's meal, how do you...
properly categorize...
You can make an argument that, you know, all the writing work you do, even if it gets cut, is worth it,
because it helps you do something else, but
how do you make sure you're not, like, falling down a rabbit hole when you're in a space like that?
So, um...
I think it's actually the same as designing
interactive fiction in general,
possibly the same as designing games in general.
That you have to think as a player, and then you also have to think as a creator.
So you have to think...
as a writer and you also have to think as a reader.
So as a writer I say, well I've got my lore and I've got all these things that I'm interested in and they're all really cool.
But as a reader, I don't give a damn about your lore at all.
What I want is the characters, the adventures, the motivation, the mystery.
I want to know what's happening next.
And if your lore isn't relevant to that, I don't care about it.
And I shouldn't care about it.
And there will be readers who do, but they're not the important ones.
The important reader is the reader who just wants to be told a good story and then go home.
And the important...
player of your game, one who just wants to have fun. That's all they want to do. They just want to have something to do.
And by... you have to split between those two viewpoints all the time. Like, it's no good to go
away and write out a great big lore book and then be really proud of yourself because you've basically...
you've just entertained an audience of one and that's it. Like, you haven't done anything.
You've got to think about the performance the whole time. So I try to write as little lore as possible
all the time.
but be thinking about the way that scenes will play or what will actually happen in the game.
And then when I realize I don't know something, then I go back to the lore and I kind of
construct the lore that makes sense within that. And then I go back to the gameplay.
And flip-flopping between those two, you eventually reach a point where both are satisfied.
I think that's true of all of our designs, you know, like if we're designing the translation
game, we're thinking about, well, how does this work as a language, but how does this work as
a thing the player can solve?
And both of those things are fighting, and you're trying to find the tension, the balance between the two.
Because if you go too far one way, you end up with something incomprehensible, and you go too far the other way, you end up with something that's just trivial, and neither of those are interesting.
So I think that's the whole job.
Like, that's the whole job.
It's not... anyone can have ideas.
Like, really, actually, anyone can have ideas, and it's...
A question is how do you make ideas that you can play out in an interesting way?
Is that what we're doing?
That's what all of us are doing all of the time.
Yeah, no joke.
Before we move on, there's a question that dovetails very well with this, which is from
StatueSat.
They want to know how much background research on archaeology, history, etc. did you do
to help build these worlds?
That's a long look.
I don't know, I mean, you start with research, but you start with research that inspires you.
I'm not very good at researching for research's sake. I tend to like drop in and out of stuff.
So my starting point on this project was a 1960s book of archaeological,
of schlock archaeology called Citadels of Mystery, which goes through 12 archaeological sites and
comes up with some crazy theories about what they might be.
So it's like Machu Picchu was a test village in the mountains and it was built purely to
see if people could survive up there and they didn't.
This is not a very plausible theory but this is the theory in this book and it's brilliant
because it takes real archaeological evidence and it plays with it and it has fun and that
inspired me a lot and it's a superb book and I hugely enjoyed it and that was one of my
primary researches.
But to say that...
I just read this one book and wrote the game is also not true.
Like I know a ton of archaeologists. My dad is an anthropologist. I've met them all my life.
Yeah, like it when you end up bringing together a lot of sources that you didn't deliberately look
for because we chose to write this game for a reason, you know. And I think that goes
across the team as well. Like Tom used to talk a lot about religion.
Like that was something he was really interested in bringing to a sci-fi context and that's
definitely fed through into the game.
Right on.
There are more questions in the chat that are very, very good, but I have one that I
wanted to ask since the start, so I'm just going to throw it out there.
How tricky was it to put this into a 3D context?
This is your first 3D navigatable game.
Tell me a bit about how that went for you because it must have been...
tricky at best. Like, what engine and tools did you use to build these 3D worlds and like how did
you end up deciding how to build them as these kind of quasi-3D storybook spaces that they came
out as? So we built it in Unity and we basically started from the point of, as I said earlier,
we wanted to make a 2D comic book essentially, but a dynamic interactive comic book.
and what that would mean. And part of the reason we wanted to do that is because we loved
2D character illustration because 2D character illustration can be really expressive.
So we wanted to draw our characters from lots of different angles so that we could dynamically
compose these panels and we constructed our environments in 3D. They were initially
a lot simpler than the environment's theatre,
because we wanted to create the sense of a background
rather than construct entire worlds in 3D.
But as we created this,
and we created the main protagonist, Aaliyah,
and we drew her from 12 different angles, her core pose,
we just loved the overall effect
of moving the camera around in 3D,
because we created a...
a system that basically has a database of character frames and depending on the camera's
angle and certain tags that's been applied to her character, like whether she's in a
particular walk or a talk or some emotion, then it would pick a different overall body
frame and also paste a different facial expression over the top so we could get all of these
different effects.
And then yeah, the 3D basically...
came out of that as we were experimenting with what you could do.
Because we wanted it to initially just be 2D comic book panels,
but then seeing the effect of all of that happening in 3D,
we just thought it looked really cool.
Interesting. I imagine...
Did that change the way you did your sort of...
how you structured the pace and flow of the game?
How much of what you might call level design went into this game, and how did the decision
to go full 3D change the way you structured it, if at all?
I think it massively changed things, because as soon as you go full 3D, you get the ability
to poke around in all of the little tiny corners of the level, just like any other 3D game.
You've been through an evolution to get to that point, because at the beginning...
We had a very limited amount of interactivity,
in that it was kind of a visual choice-based narrative.
So the narrative was really driving it.
There was not so much exploration at all.
You could only interact with whatever it gave you choices for.
But as we opened it up,
like we were talking for a while
about having 3D environments,
but maybe you have a completely fixed camera angle,
a bit like a point-and-click adventure,
...from that particular camera perspective, you could poke around these corners...
...but it weren't fully interactive.
As soon as you can swing the camera all the way around...
...there is so much more scope for where you can go...
...what you should be able to interact with because it's right there.
That had an impact, right down into that!
script because then suddenly your branching narrative script needs to be able to cope
with the player who walks over to one side of the room and does one thing, walks over
to the other side of the room and does another thing, then walks back to the first side of
the room again, which is not a branching tree structure even slightly.
It's something completely different.
Because in sorcery, like when we have waypoints on the mini-maps, we can easily just say,
we don't want you to go back in that room, so we'll just remove the choice to go back
into that room.
And we can directly.
push the player in different directions.
Like, depending on how open or friendly we want it to be,
we can enable and disable choices to go in different directions,
but we're always in control.
Yeah, I mean, we do do that in Heaven's Lock.
We will quietly turn a door off over here if you're way over there,
but hopefully in a way that you never ever notice,
but you lose a lot of that focus.
So I think that you asked about level design,
and I think that's a really good point.
One of the things that really took me by surprise on the project was
there was a point when I realised we actually needed to do level design
and we needed to know what we were talking about with level design
which we hadn't originally intended to be a thing that we needed to know.
We were really lucky when we hired Laura Dilloway
who's our lead environment artist.
We've done some level design on LittleBigPlanetPSP amongst other titles
and she was working at PlayStation at the same time as Walt.
And so we ended up in a process where I would kind of write a scene and say,
this is what I think the characters are doing in this scene.
And this is roughly what I think the geometry needs to be like to make that work.
And then she'd take it and turn that into more of a level design space,
a space with better vistas and better lines of sight and things.
And then I would take it back and say, well, I think we need to put more time in here.
This bit's too quick, this bit's too slow, let's move around, that's too long.
And between us, we could kind of thresh out a 3D space in a way that the narrative was happy,
the 3D design of it was happy too.
And actually, that process was brilliant.
And I think one of the things that was really nice about it
is that being a team of seven people,
like, we just sat either side of a table,
so the iteration time was incredibly fast.
So we were just bashing geometry around between us
and coming up with these spaces
that kind of flowed in really interesting ways.
I think that, yeah, that's...
Something we hadn't expected to have to contend with, but actually it worked out really well.
But as level design go, it's a fairly simple problem compared to something, you know, like
a proper shooter game or an adventure game where you really have to think about all of those parts
and all of those sightlines all the time. You do get a little bit more freedom in the way that
the game is made. Yeah, that makes a lot of sense. We have about 10 minutes left, so if anyone has
questions, please get them in now or forever hold them. There is a really good one.
that will take us over into the archaeology system, if you have a minute,
because I want to know how that whole thing works.
And there's a good question here from devrsw, who wants to know,
did you experiment with other difficulty modes around the translation stuff?
I've been playing a lot, and I wish the game had fewer clues
for those of us that love a challenge.
Nope, just the right amount of clues, thank you, from someone who also loves a challenge.
You went through about 20 prototypes of the translation mechanic.
of all sorts of different mechanics and all sorts of different ways of solving that high-level design of decrypting hieroglyphs,
which is the kind of thing we wanted to hit.
And generally speaking, the window of good game design there is incredibly tight.
Because if you make something which is too easy, where the player can brute force it,
or they can just make random guesses, or they don't have to do any work,
or there's no insight, or there's no structure.
then there's actually nothing to do.
And we had a lot of early prototypes
where you just lobbed words into slots,
and then eventually Aliyah would say,
yeah, that's it.
And you'd go, okay, that was a complete waste of time.
But on the flip side of that,
it's extremely easy to make a problem,
which is far too hard.
And in fact, the system we have right now,
it's very, very easy for us to give you a translation,
which is impossible for you to do.
We just use the more complicated words in the language.
And there's a lot of work that went into the game.
to make sure that it never does that, or it very, very rarely does that,
so that you don't just get translations that you have no idea about.
Because then the player just disengages and says,
well, I don't know, that could be anything.
A bit like I used to do in French class, you know, I'd look at something and go,
bof.
And that was...
Bad memory, sorry.
...complex.
Yeah, so...
I think...
If people are feeling confident about playing the translation game, then that's nice.
And if people are feeling that they could do better with the translations in the game, then okay, fair enough.
But language has a problem, which is that it does get arbitrary quite fast.
Like, what a word happens to be is really just what it happens to be.
So it's quite difficult to make a challenging language puzzle in the sense that you might mean it.
Because...
actually the challenging becomes basically random or impossible very, very quickly.
And then it's not really fun at all.
We definitely rather err on the side of, you know, without explicitly telling you what
the words mean, just give you a great amount of clues to whether it's, you know, where
it's written, what the symbols look like.
or how a word relates to another word, whether there's similar symbols.
If from that you intuit something quite easily, then I kind of feel like...
That's a win.
That's a win, exactly.
Even if it feels slightly too easy, that's way better than the alternative.
I think the other thing that people need to realise is that it's a 12-hour game,
and by the end of the game there are long and complex and intricate words
that you'll be looking at with deep, constructional reasons behind them.
And the tutorial ramp is kind of gentle.
That's probably for the best.
So yeah, for people who want more challenges, I think there are plenty of challenges in
there, even if it's just look back through all of your translations and even for ones
where you know the words, can you work out why the word is the way it is?
Like, what is the construction there? How are the symbols put together to form that word?
Because there's a lot there to kind of decode.
I mean, I think for us, like, the...
You know, it was a very iterative process, and one where we...
We settled on the translation mechanic after about a year and a half of work.
And after we found it, and we really found it from experiments,
we dug it out of the dirt, and we're like, wow, this works.
And we tested it on so many people in so many contexts,
and it's held up for two years or something for us as being,
I'm pretty sure this is the one.
Like, I look at it, and I honestly don't know
how we could make it better at this point.
Because, like, yeah, it's remarkable.
Having seen the versions that didn't work,
it's remarkable how well this version works.
Whether you like it or not is up to you.
But, oh my God, the other ones were a lot worse.
Yeah, for sure. We're coming off to the end here. I always like to ask, and with this game more so than most,
how did you get the word out about this game to people that you thought would enjoy it most? It's
such a tricky game to sum up easily or to very quickly give someone a sense of what they will
be doing. So how have you gone about marketing and sort of trying to get this game in front of people?
Has it all been like YouTube, email, reviews? What's worked for you?
Yeah, well, yeah, I mean, you know, step one is we have a PR agent who helps us in terms of like,
she has a specific focus on adventure games and shows she has a good amount of contacts in that
space, which helps. The other thing that helps is you write a really good game that everybody likes
and then you email them saying, do you remember that game you liked? We've made another one.
And I think that's pretty, pretty fundamental, actually.
It's also taken us a long time to work out what the hook of the game is.
We've been excited since the beginning about all the tonal aspects of the game, like characters, the world, the mechanics,
but it took us a while to find out, purely through experimentation and talking to people,
that it was the translation mechanic which really piqued people's interest.
And so discovering that...
Getting that down and always making sure that when we talked about the game,
we made sure to mention we have an entire hieroglyphic language to decipher.
That just became the thing that we always mentioned.
Our one-line pitch for the game is an archaeological narrative adventure
with an entire hieroglyphic language to decipher.
Right, I've said that far too many times.
and go, oh yeah, okay, a hieroglyphic language.
But a lot of me wants to say, oh yeah,
with this incredible, massively adaptive narrative
that totally responds to everything you do
that's completely non-linear,
that lets you explore this massive,
where are you going?
Why have you come back?
Why have you gone?
And yeah, that's what carries the game.
That's what, if you enjoy the game,
that's probably what's making it good.
You need that initial hook to get people in.
That's one thing that's been nice about reading reviews today, actually, is that a lot of
them have gone, oh, there's this world and there's people and there's characters, there's
mysteries, and you go, yeah, all this stuff was there, you know?
It's not just the language puzzle game.
But I think that goes back to something that Mike Rose, who used to work for Garbage Pitcher,
said, which was, projects need a hook and a kicker.
And hook, and you have a kicker.
And our hook is the translation game.
And our kicker is...
the massively adaptive narrative with the interesting characters and all of that stuff.
And it can be really hard to package your game up that way because
the kicker is probably the thing you care about and the hook is probably the
thing that you're kind of done with as the developer. Like you've got over it
by the time you're making the game. But it is a really good way to think
about explaining your project to people. Like
the hook is what gets their interest and the kicker is what makes them stay.
And the great thing about that is you can...
You can be constantly experimenting with that.
Every time you explain what game you're working on to a person,
you try explaining it in a different way.
You see what makes their eyes light up.
And we've totally found that since we found that way of describing the game,
then it's just been a question of, like, what have we done?
We've done posts on Imgur, we've done Twitter stuff,
we've done interviews with the press, we've done demos, various things.
Some things have had traction, some things haven't had traction, but...
in general, that those concepts, that hook concept has been, has always worked.
It's always been there.
Like when we've had success, it's always been the same hook and the same kind of payoff.
Well, I hope it works out for you guys.
This game seems incredible.
I think we're just about done with our IHR.
Brian, did you have any burning questions you had to slip in here?
Chat, go ahead.
Toss some.
Toss.
We got a lot of love for the language system in chat.
I'll start that off.
Everyone from Kale Woodbridge to Supercon22,
thank you all for dropping by and sharing your love for Heaven's
Vault with these folks.
I guess for you guys.
I've been asking a lot of developers lately because a lot of developers I've talked to have been building their companies and the future of their game-making lives alongside their debut games.
You all are a few games in right now, you're not in the same place, you know how to build tools and recruit people and sort of do that.
There's a lot changing in...
Um, the world of game development right now in that there's a more pressure for games
The the making of the game to be as as much of an entertainment as much of the product I guess as the game itself
um
And while I wouldn't argue that every game developer has to jump on that bad wagon right away
Um, someone in here was asking in chat was asking about updates for the game
and where what have you been thinking about in the way that like these kind of
Story driven games can exist with with a world. That's that's expanding
into games that are more persistent, which thankfully a lot of those games are still narrative and story driven.
It's thankfully not narrative or no narrative. It's how is narrative presented.
That's a question. There's a question in there somewhere. There's a question mark.
Yeah, I feel like I'm a bit of a dinosaur on the design of persistent evolving games because I
look at something like Heaven's Vault and like it's crafted, it's got a beginning, it's got a
middle, it's got an end. The idea of adding anything to it terrifies me because like...
The narrative sticks together right now, and if I add something to it, I'm really not sure
if it would stick together anymore.
In a way, it actually is much more difficult than, say, 80 Days, because 80 Days is made
out of lots of little individual pieces that could sometimes call to each other and remember
certain facts between certain cities that you visit.
But Heaven's Vault is so just like...
It's supposed to be tight.
Everything relates to something in the core plot.
So I feel like if we were ever to do an update for Heaven's Vault, it would have to be a sequel.
Whereas I still kick myself on 80 Days that maybe we should have just released a lot less of the game
and made it a subscription game and then just New Cities and Journeys every month
because we totally could have done that.
New Seasons. New Seasons. Yep.
Maybe that would have been a really great model.
Or maybe we would have just hated it within weeks. I don't know.
Yeah, I think what I want to believe is that it's still possible for us to make games,
narrative games, that are so efficiently made that they sell enough, that they justify themselves,
that they don't need to be persistent games. We don't need to have people coming back every three
months and paying another $20 for the next bit. We don't need three million players. We can get
enough players who are happy with their $1, their one-time purchase, that we're good, we're fine.
That lets us make the kind of games that we actually want to make and craft the experiences we want to craft
without having to try and bend the narrative into a shape that it doesn't want to be.
Or make games that don't really end.
I hate it when narratives don't have proper endings. It really irritates me.
I can see that in most contexts, narratives are moving towards stories which don't end.
Because then you could make another one.
And like, Marvel are doing this right now extremely successfully.
And George R.R. Martin's got his own solution, which is to just not write the end.
Yeah.
Wow.
Working well for him.
But I don't want to have to do that.
That was the sickest burn I think we've ever experienced on this channel.
I hope he checks this game out.
I think he'd like it.
He seems like a nice guy.
For sure.
Yeah, before we go, I'll just let Supercon get the last comment in.
How you did 80 days was perfect.
The basic game was amazing and the updates for it made them even more happy.
You somehow made a great game even better and
Cable Woodbridge would like to say as a parent hooray for short finishable games
I will just add I guess like a keyword that stuck out to me there is efficient like having game making be efficient
Seems to be something that I think everyone is trying to figure out at all times
And I hope I hope I hope that that I hope that heavens vault has struck that balance for you
I cannot arbitrarily say if it has
In some ways it has, in some ways it really hasn't.
In that it took us four years.
It's certainly a lot more efficient than if we'd done it in other ways.
I think this is the thing, we have made a 12 to 20 hour game that's full on narrative all the time,
that doesn't have any downtime in it, and there's seven of us.
And it ramped up from two.
I still feel like that's relatively inefficient.
With that, I will start wishing everyone adieu.
Thank you all for joining us on the GDC Twitch channel.
This is a place where we try to talk about the art and business of making games, and often where they intersect, just like we discussed in this moment.
If you enjoyed this, we would love it if you clicked the follow button.
We would love it if you checked out Heaven's Vault, which is the game we're streaming today.
Because, you know, it's a cool game. We try to check out cool games on this channel.
And we try to always be talking with the developers and give you an opportunity to ask developers about how games get made.
Because we're also GDC, we encourage you to check out the rest of GDC.
We have the GDC Vault up open right now. You can go check out all the talks from GDC 2019.
We have a YouTube channel where those talks also wind up, so you can go check that out too.
And with that, John and Joseph, if they have any questions for you, where should they ask them?
Twitter is probably the place.
We also have a Discord server.
Oh yeah.
I don't know how you find the Discord server.
Go to Twitter and find it.
Oh yeah, it's secret.
So our Twitter is at Inkle Studios.
And you can find us there and yeah, please do take a look at Evans Vault, it's on PC and PS4.
As of today, mmm, mmm.
I think PC from day one is the best day to play them.
That's what I hear.
For sure.
Alright, with that, everyone have a good day.
You too, bye bye!
Bye!