Good morning.
Welcome to the Rules for Development of People.
You had a lot of other cool places and choices
to be here this morning.
In fact, in bed, sleeping is probably among them,
given that last night was St. Patrick's Day.
So I'm very glad that you all picked this room and this talk.
Thank you very much for being here.
I am super jazzed about the opportunity
to share with you some of the ideas
that we are thinking about around how Blizzard is trying
to be more deliberate about the development
and the betterment of their people.
I am super curious about all of you, though.
So if I could just get a show of hands.
Production.
How many produce?
OK.
Nice.
Art?
OK.
Just one.
Just you.
Nice.
Way to represent.
Design?
OK.
Well done.
All right.
And engineering?
OK.
Cool.
Businessy type folks?
OK.
And I know HR is in the house.
I got a little support team there.
Yeah, you.
You too.
Yeah, we rule.
And then how many of you are leads within your own studios?
OK, cool.
That would be helpful.
So I craft this.
All right, so I'm Julie Farbanek.
A little bit about me.
This is me in game.
Come say hi.
I'm in the goblin starting zone.
For whatever reason, when I first started at Blizzard,
Farbanek was really hard to say.
So, Fabernacle became really easy to say.
I don't know why.
So, that's me.
And a couple other things to share,
just so you know a little bit more about me.
The first thing I'll start out with is,
I feel like Buffy the Vampire Slayer
is one of the best television shows ever.
It's even superior than Firefly.
Yeah, I said it.
I said it.
And I mean it.
And in the wrap-up room, wherever that is,
I don't even know where that is.
I didn't ask.
We'll discuss the merits if you want to after this.
I am a self-described leadership development nerd.
I dig it.
I enjoy working with our leaders at Blizzard,
helping them be better.
I read lots of books on it.
I got my master's in organizational leadership.
It's my thing.
And you might notice some of that.
influence sprinkled throughout this talk, so just fair warning to you. I've been in
HR for 15 years and I've been lucky enough to have been at Blizzard
Entertainment for the past eight years. Eight this month.
Get my shield in two years.
And so when I started at Blizzard,
my focus was learning and development.
So I built a lot of training programs
and did a lot of teaching and worked
with a lot of teams across the studio
to help them kind of work better together.
And now I'm responsible for all the HR activities
for three of our franchises.
Diablo, right?
Yes.
Yeah.
Hearthstone?
Yeah, that's it, right?
And Overwatch.
So fantastic.
And so speaking of that, I have spent the last four years
embedded with the Overwatch team.
That means that I sit with the team,
but it is a lot more than geography.
I'm in the production stand-ups.
I'm in the production team meetings,
engineering leads meetings, art leads meetings.
I sit on our steering team, which as the term suggests,
it's our game director and our exec producer
and our art director and our tech director and business guy.
We all kind of.
work together to shape and steer the direction of the group.
And we talk about things like schedule a lot,
launch plans right now are a big topic of conversation,
build stability, just the health of the team.
And I share all of that with you just
so you have a sense of.
my experience and the perspective that I'm gonna bring
to this talk, and also to highlight that all the examples
that I wanna share with you are all things
that are happening inside the dev team.
These are not things like we're sending people off to go do,
they're magically different, and then they come back,
and no, and so I thought that was important to mention.
Okay, so what inspired the ideas behind this talk?
It's this quote from this really awesome book by Ed Catmull called Creativity, Inc.
If you have not read it, add it to your reading list.
It's – there are a lot of similarities between how Pixar approaches their creative process
and then how we make games, so it's fabulous.
And this quote, getting the right people
and the right chemistry is more important
than getting the right idea,
this really resonated with a lot of us at Blizzard
because we talk about that a lot.
We don't say it as articulately and eloquently
as Ed Catmull did.
We say things like, making games is easy
compared to making a team.
And I am not at all suggesting, by the way,
that making games is easy.
You know, it's really, really, really hard.
But when you compare it to building a team,
a team that has an abundance of trust,
that has healthy conflict, that has
a lot of passionate developers all rowing
the boat in the same direction, and that
right balance between the creative ideas and the ability to execute on those ideas,
that mixture, that's a really hard thing to find.
And I'm sure a lot of you can attest that if you've been on teams,
maybe where there's poor communication or weak leadership or minimal collaboration and teamwork,
you would say that yes, the absence of those core things
really hurts how the team functions,
and ultimately, what we believe at Blizzard,
ultimately hurts the quality of the game.
And so, because we think this way,
we're starting to hone in a little bit on some rules.
that help us focus our actions and dedicate time, energy, and attention to the betterment
of all the developers on our teams and the teams themselves.
So let's look at these rules.
Okay, so we'll go over these really quick because we're going to spend a lot of time
doing a deep dive into each one.
So the first one is intentional investment.
Our time, our money, our energy, our resources, these are finite things.
And so this rule is really helping us determine who and where to invest those things in to
get the biggest return.
Second rule of utilizing frameworks.
So, this just reminds us that we need to pick really proven methods that work in order to maximize those investments.
We'll talk more about that.
Prioritizing connection.
This is really at the heart of this list, because for us, it's about what makes work.
worthwhile and meaningful.
If you ask anyone at Blizzard,
or probably in your studios as well,
what do you love most about your job?
I guarantee you, or I would bet a lot of money,
that the first answer would be,
well, I just love making games.
And then followed closely by,
I love the people I work with.
I love the people I stand shoulder to shoulder with.
And this rule is all about us building upon that
and emphasizing and making it easy for our developers
to connect with each other, to kind of keep
building our brotherhood, our sisterhood, our tribe.
And lastly, collaborative learning.
This rule builds upon that and really is a reminder to us
to never underestimate the power of peer-to-peer learning
and feedback.
And we'll talk a lot about that.
Okay, so none of these rules exist to imply, I need to be clear, that Blizzard has it all figured out.
We so do not have it all figured out.
We are still trying and learning to do these things well and in ways that feel meaningful to our employees.
And so as we'll go through each rule, what I thought would be good is we'll talk about why it matters, of course,
and then give you some context and talk about some of the things that inspire our action towards those rules,
because I think that kind of context matters.
And then most importantly is to give you at least one solid, very practical example.
of how we are trying to bring that rule to life.
And the hope, by doing that, is that if you
think any of these ideas are cool
or might make a positive difference in your own studios,
take them.
Try them.
That's the whole point.
It's my favorite part about GDC is you come here
and hopefully get a little nugget of inspiration
and take that back and maybe make your.
you know, your games or your business or your teams better.
Oh, you know, I didn't say shut off your phones.
Yeah.
That was my bad.
I didn't lead with that.
Anyway, so let's dive in.
Intentional investment.
So intentional investment is first by design
because it is the most important thing.
Without it, we would be growing our people
by chance or by luck, and that is not an awesome strategy.
But what do I mean by investment?
I think it's important to be really clear about that.
And so how we think about it is probably how you'd find it in any dictionary, but it's important to say that investment for us is the time, energy, and resources spent in the hope of future benefits actualized.
So each day at work,
or outside of work, for that matter,
we are all constantly faced with choices
of where to invest our time or our energy or our money, right?
So going to dinner with your friends
is an investment in them, right, in that relationship.
Or coming to GDC is an investment
in your learning or your career.
Or based on last night, your alcohol consumption,
from what I saw.
the shenanigans.
But then at work, our investment choice
can be things like what part of the project
gets our focus right when we're trying
to get pulled in a lot of directions,
or even what meeting do I go to when I'm double booked.
And then with respect to the topic of this talk,
the choices are who are the people that you
are choosing to invest in.
And how is that effective?
Some things to think about.
I also want to just make sure we're talking about the word intentional.
I want to be intentional about our intentions.
And how we think about it for us, it's discipline,
it's focus, it's deliberateness, right?
Being very deliberate so that those,
I guess here's what I want to say.
Everyone can make investments that don't pay off, right?
That's kind of an easy thing to do.
But intentional investment for us is the thought process
of trying to make the smartest investment
so that we get the biggest return on that.
So that's our first rule.
So what are some of the things that inspire our action
towards it?
Well, first.
It's awesome, talented developers like this,
and all across our studio at Blizzard,
and insert any picture of your teams on here, right?
These people are worthy of your investment, right?
And your top performers in particular.
They will stop being top performers,
or they'll go be top performers somewhere else
if you don't make intentional investments in them.
The second source of inspiration behind intentional investment for us is very much a strengths
focus and rooted in some of the work that the Gallup organization has done and Marcus
Buckingham, another great read, it's called Now Discover Your Strengths.
I recommend it if you haven't read it.
And what Gallup suggested, which maybe a lot of you know about, but it's worth just being clear,
right, so they said that we spend way too much time focusing on our weaknesses and trying to make them better,
instead of...
identifying and capitalizing on the things that we're already good at, our strengths.
And they argue that if you can identify somebody's strengths and the things they are naturally
born and awesome at and really lean into that, you will get far superior performance than
if you would if you spent all that time trying to make their weaknesses better.
So a couple of examples to drive this home.
So let's look at a study that the Gallup organization did a number of years ago.
And they took 6,000 10th graders, some of which were identified as average readers.
So they were clocking in about 90 words per minute.
And then they had another group identified as above average readers, clocking in at about
300 or 350 words per minute.
And they took a whole 6,000 10th graders through one semester of a speed reading course.
What do we imagine?
that the improvement was for the average readers.
150 words per minute.
Pretty good. Very respectable. But what about our above-average readers?
What do we think they improved by?
It's insane. It's an insane amount.
2,900 words per minute.
So we look at this and we say, OK.
The average readers had respectable gains.
That's good.
But whoa, it pales in comparison to the gains made
for the above average readers.
And so for us, Gallup's work on strengths
really helps serve as a data point, I guess,
when we think about developing our people.
And it's starting to help us crack the code of where
to invest our valuable time or our energy.
or our money. But it's not just that. Let's look at Rudy. Rudy, movie going way back starring
Sean Astin. Anyone see it? Okay, so I'll explain for those of you that haven't. Sean Astin
is also Samwise in Lord of the Rings.
And because I love 80s movies, Mikey from the Goonies.
So that's also important to know.
All right, let's talk about Rudy.
So Rudy was a small guy in football player comparison.
He was shorter, he didn't weigh as much, he wasn't as fast.
But Rudy wanted nothing more than to play football
for the University of Notre Dame.
And he applies three times to Notre Dame and is rejected three times.
And on his fourth time, he finally gets in and he earns a spot on the team's practice squad.
So the practice squad is those folks that just practice, you know,
they're in the drills every day with the team.
But come Saturday, come game day, they do not run out on the field in the uniform.
They are watching that game from the stands or on the television.
All right, so there's Rudy practicing every day.
Finally, fast forward to the end of the season,
and Rudy finally gets to suit up.
So he's in his uniform.
He gets to run out with the team.
He's on the sidelines.
He's cheering.
And then he finally gets in the game and runs a play.
And he makes this awesome one single tackle.
And the crowd cheers, and the players carry him off the field.
And it's a really awesome moment.
So what I'm going to say might sound a little cold and uncaring, and I don't mean it to be.
But when we really look at that, and we see years of pain, of sweat, of sacrifice, blood, sweat, tears, for one single tackle.
That is not a really good ROI.
And so what Rudy's story makes us think about
is be careful of taking the path of most resistance.
And this is a really hard thing to do.
We have a culture of rooting for the underdog, right?
And it's really, really hard.
So it's something to think about.
And so we're here, the yeah but.
Because all of you are like, yeah, Julie,
I've heard the strength thing before, yada, yada, yada.
And there's this thing called reality, Julie.
And you're right.
You're absolutely right.
Because sometimes a person's strengths
does not match what's needed on the project or team.
And sometimes even strengths over done,
they become weaknesses, right?
That hard-charging producer,
oh, there's a lot of producers in the room.
Hard-charging producer that's really, really focused
and driven and gets stuff done,
also gets so tunnel vision on the objective,
sometimes they start running over people to get there,
as an example.
And we cannot ignore the dark side.
The dark side matters.
Weaknesses do matter when we're trying to make a game
and build teams.
So where have we landed on this at Blizzard?
I would love to tell you we have this awesome spell
that we just cast, and it fixes these things, but no.
Where we've landed on this is that people aren't binary,
and we can't solve for every problem.
So these are just the realities that we manage,
and we don't make them problems that we solve.
So let's look at an example, a Blizzard example.
And I thought it might be interesting to actually use
a look at strengths from a team perspective.
Hi.
Love that picture.
So before the inception of Overwatch,
the team was actively working on a bunch
of different game ideas, right?
Trying to kick around and just generally trying
to figure out what was next for us.
And as part of that process, our game director,
the very amazing and talented Jeffrey Kaplan,
was building out his development philosophy for the project along with the team.
And one of the pillars that came out of that, one of the bullet points that showed up on
that, was play to team strengths.
And that's how Overwatch was born.
Is specifically and intentionally...
investing in the strengths of the team that we had.
Decisions about where to put our time and our energy
and our resources with respect to the technical aspects
of the game, with respect to artistic actions.
Those were, in very large part, looking
about what the capabilities were of the team as a whole.
More specifically.
When we look at this iconic lineup,
and I know Kaplan has mentioned this a few times,
we actually see how some very key strengths
of various people really influence
the direction of the game.
And specifically with this hero lineup,
we see the strengths of two people in particular.
The first is a guy named Jeff Goodman,
who's one of our principal designers,
has been with Blizzard about 15 years,
and is probably one of the most talented
and gifted.
hero and ability designers to walk the planet, in our opinion.
And we also see the work and the strengths of another guy named Arnold Tsang,
who's our current assistant art director on the project.
And Arne's talent, Arne was put on this earth
And he is an amazing character concept artist.
And so when we look at this, the team really
made a big intentional investment
to really lean in on Jeff and Arne's strengths
to help build the core of this game.
And I am very biased.
But I believe that the decision to use a strengths-based,
like intentional investment approach has resulted
in the exponential payoff.
This is our equivalent of going
from 350 words per minute to 2,900 words per minute.
Next rule, utilizing frameworks.
Why does this matter?
Well, for us, we look at, of course,
how that term framework is defined.
And dictionary says, an essential supporting structure
from which to build things.
And this becomes really important
when we're talking about building
the capabilities of others.
When you build a house, right, you need that really solid foundation.
For us, that solid foundation is intentional investment.
And then that frame on top provides structure, provides the stability.
And that's really, really key.
A framework does this for us.
The second thing that we really like about utilizing framework
is it's just simpler and easier, right?
When you've got a group of people
following the same steps and the same thought process.
And third, and maybe most important,
is that for us, a framework gives us needed discipline,
right?
to have disciplined thought and disciplined action
when we think about this.
And so the framework that we've chosen
to approach really getting intentional about building
our teams and our people is based
on the work of the Center for Creative Leadership,
and it's the 70-20-10 Development Rule.
Is anyone familiar with that?
Well, yeah, you guys.
They're HR.
They know.
All right, so let's talk about that.
OK, so if a strengths focus helps us determine who or where
to invest in, the 70-20-10 development framework
is the how.
How do we go about making a very calculated investment
about that?
And so if I asked each of you, what's
the best learning experience that you've ever had,
the one that had the biggest impact?
I really doubt that you're going to tell me it was this training class that I went to
or this awesome GDC talk.
No, I don't think that would be.
What I think you would say is, oh, God, Julie, you know,
it was that time, I was on that project,
I didn't know what the hell I was doing,
I had to try all these new things,
stretched really beyond my capabilities.
That's the thing, that's the thing that I learned the most.
And this is at the root
of the 70-20-10 development framework.
The best learning, the stickiest learning,
happens when it's built into the work itself.
So if I need to get better at talking in front of the team
during team meetings, I am not going to do that by taking
a class, watching a TED Talk, reading a book about it.
Yes, those things are important, and they do provide
sources of inspiration and models of excellence.
But that is actually not how we.
learn things in a way that it actually takes root and sticks.
The best way that we're going to learn.
and build our public speaking muscles
is to find ways to talk in front of the team
as much as possible.
That's that 70%.
And the 20% in the middle can't be overlooked either, right?
That's the part where after that team meeting,
I get immediate feedback and coaching about how I just did,
ideally from my manager or a trusted peer.
And together, all these elements.
really create and establish an environment where deep learning and development can take
place.
Something though to emphasize, not a warning, but something to emphasize, 70-20-10 is not
a fixed ratio, right?
And in fact, for those of you that are leads in the team, we have found that not skimping
on the 20 percent.
is really, really crucial.
In fact, do more of that if you can,
because that has really led to be significant differences
in the acceleration of someone's development.
So some examples.
Let's look.
I mentioned I'm a leadership development nerd, which is good because Blizzard cares a lot
about building the capabilities of leads.
So all these examples are things that we do when we're trying to build leadership capabilities
in particular and how we try and fill each of these buckets.
Really critical, right, because when you think,
you all know this, but leads on your teams,
we think of them anyway as force multipliers.
They have the greatest chance to do the most good,
they touch the most people.
They also have the greatest chance to do the most damage
if it's not done well.
So we emphasize this a lot.
All right, so how do we try,
what are some of the things on our list
of how we build work development into the work itself?
So, one thing that we do a lot is we have these strike teams at Blizzard and the whole
purpose of bringing a strike team together is to make our games better.
And so it's comprised of a bunch of people from cross disciplines and cross teams and
their sole focus is to give feedback on a game that's not theirs.
And so we found a lot of learning leadership-wise when someone has been assigned to either participate
on one of these strike teams or lead it.
The scary thing, hosting internal peer talks, right?
But what we found is that one of the things
that can be really helpful in leadership development
is building someone's presence, right?
The ability to communicate ideas in a compelling way.
And so when we're thinking about that for someone,
we might ask them to prepare and deliver
an internal peer talk on some area of their expertise.
Fixing inherited problems, another awesome way
to build learning into the work itself
and to fill our 70% bucket, particularly when someone
has to go outside of their group to solve a problem, right?
So they might have to go across a discipline
or across another team in the company.
That can be a really effective way.
And scope and scale.
Right?
So maybe I was responsible for this part of the game,
and now I'm responsible for this part of the game.
Or I'm overseeing these functions,
and now you just gave me these functions.
So those kinds of things can also
help how we fill that 70% bucket. 20%.
I can't emphasize it enough.
This 20% bucket is all about support.
Why?
Because learning something new.
is inherently about failing, right?
And failing doesn't feel good.
And so providing a mechanism for people
to talk about those failures and to kick some things around
is really paramount in the learning process.
So examples for us that we use.
So one-on-ones, if there were a soapbox, I would get on it.
I would tell you all to do one-on-ones
if you don't already do them.
But I'm also being very purposeful
about meaningful and effective, those terms used.
Particularly in this case, if we're
thinking about helping to build somebody's leadership
capabilities.
Ideally, those one-on-ones you're having
are less about just the day-to-day tactics
of getting the work done and more about whatever
that thing is that this person's trying to learn.
and helping them talk through that and asking questions like,
what's going right?
What's getting in your way?
And what are you learning about leading?
Effective, meaningful one-on-ones.
Mentorships.
So we do not have a formal mentorship process at Blizzard.
But we do like the idea of intentionally,
there's that word again, pairing.
people together.
And we think about it in two ways.
The traditional, like, senior person
along with a less experienced person,
or we're also starting to play with peer-to-peer mentorships.
Always being very intentional.
So as example, if someone has to get better at their soft skills,
we will intentionally pair them with someone
who is already really good at that, really respected for that,
in the hopes that that kind of thing can yield good results.
Discipline lunches, we really like and try and encourage
and push leads talking to other leads
to learn about how things are going in their worlds.
And it's a good place to kind of, again, build that 20%.
And we also have these things called coaching labs,
which I will talk about in more depth
when we get to collaborative learning part.
and a 10%.
So we're lucky enough, we have this Blizzard Academy,
so there are lots of training classes that people can go to,
or grab books from our library,
or we'll just shoot out a really cool TED Talk
or a thought-provoking podcast.
Just those kinds of things will go to that internal peer talk
that we forced some other person to do, that kind of thing.
And an important note on all these just examples of lists
that I gave you is that we just think of them as a menu.
So depending on whatever that thing is
that we're trying to get somebody better at,
we just pick and choose what might work and kind of build
a plan for them from there.
So what does this all look like in practice?
Some more kind of practical examples
so you know how we're trying to bring this to life.
And we're going to look, again, because it's easy
because I'm with the team, I'm going
to tell you more about Overwatch,
and particularly our art leadership team.
So recently, we appointed several senior artists
into lead roles and everything that comes with that.
So now they are.
directing the work, managing the work, having one-on-ones in the leadership meetings, all
that good stuff. And that's how we're trying to fill that 70% bucket. 20% is, yes, we're
utilizing one-on-ones as a mechanism to provide them support as they're in these new roles
and
falling down and failing and learning and picking them up
and all that other good stuff.
And there's also something else that's kind of interesting
that I wanted to share with you that on the slide
says team coaching with art direction moments.
So let me tell you what that is.
So because this matters and because we really
want to build those guys and their leadership skills
and invest in them, every single week at Art Leads meeting,
we intentionally invest.
a dedicated amount of time. This is the brainchild of Billy Petrus, our amazing art director,
and Seth Spalding, our really talented art manager, and dedicating some time to talk
about
for lack of a better term, the art of art direction.
Our lone artist, he knows.
He knows what I mean.
Because that's really, really hard, right?
It's like learn how to art direct others and the vision
part.
And in particular, a recent example
that the group was talking about was how do you
claw some, pull someone away?
from this thing that they love doing.
They're noodling on it.
They're perfecting it, right?
And you know what?
It's not really making gameplay move forward,
or particularly in our case, things are moving too fast.
The player's not going to see it, right?
And so how to pull that.
And so that group spent time peer
to peer in those meetings.
talking about what they're trying, what they're failing at, what they're learning, or what's
working.
And every week we're trying to do that, and that again is kind of filling our 20% bucket.
And then 10%.
After we ship, we'll send them to a training class, but not until then.
We're busy.
And so the ability though of that art leadership team
to share, to be vulnerable, you know, to talk about things
that are not going well, that actually takes us
to our next rule of prioritizing connection.
And we lean a lot on this rule when we think about building
and strengthening healthy teams.
So we are social creatures.
We are wired to connect to others.
And this rule is how we intentionally
create opportunities for that connection.
And this matters a lot, because connection, at least how
we think about it, is how we build trust,
and in particular, try and get that alignment needed
to manage those conflicts when they do come up,
because they always come up.
And so what inspires some of our thinking behind this
is worth talking about.
And it's based on.
the work of Patrick Lencioni and the book
of Five Dysfunctions of a Team.
Another great read.
Recommend it.
And so really quick, an overview of what
Patrick's book is all about is the first dysfunction
on any team is the absence of trust, right?
So team members do not generally open or honest
with each other.
Impossible to build a healthy foundation of trust,
which leads to.
The second dysfunction, the fear of conflict.
So now I'm not, I don't trust you.
I don't feel comfortable talking about it.
So we don't really have any conflict, right?
It might be like veiled discussions
or very guarded comments.
And so because we're not engaging
in that kind of healthy debate,
a lack of commitment emerges, right, because there's no buy-in.
We haven't been able to have that conversation in a healthy way.
And when there's no buy-in across the teams,
you start to turn to the fourth dysfunction,
which is an avoidance of accountability, right?
It was okay when it left my desk.
Poof, throw it over the wall, like that kind of thing.
And then all of that leads to the fifth dysfunction,
the inattention to results.
And that's where you see really, really unhealthy stuff,
in particular people acting in their own interest,
to feed their own needs of whatever it is, ego
or recognition, instead of putting the needs
of the collective ahead.
So not fun, not a good place to be.
And so our rule of prioritizing connection.
starts at the bottom of this, because that's the foundation.
And so let's talk about that some more.
Because the absence of trust, I'm sure many of you
are like, yeah, Julie, that's super obvious.
Right?
Nothing, no surprising there.
But what Patrick Leccioni was not talking about
was what he called predictive-based trust.
That's the kind of trust that happens
when we've been working together a really long time,
and I know exactly what you're going to say,
and I know exactly what you're going to do
at any given situation.
Right?
Charlie Brown and Lucy.
That kind of trust happens everywhere.
Very easy to get.
What Patrick Lencioni was talking about
was vulnerability-based trust.
And that's the kind of trust that exists.
And you can hear people on teams say things like,
I don't know the answer to that.
I need help.
Or, hey, I'm really sorry.
I was out of line with what I said the other day.
And that's the focus.
of the emphasis on vulnerability-based trust,
and that's what helps.
I guess without it, what happens is things get very politicky,
right, and can turn into these horrible manipulations to win,
right, instead of the assumption of positive intent
and the pursuit of truth, the pursuit of what's
best for the game.
So to build.
healthy amounts of vulnerability-based trust.
Lencioni, in his book, says and suggests
the use of personal histories exercises.
OK.
So if you went back to your teams and you're like, hey,
I saw this cool talk.
And we're going to do some personal histories exercises.
I'm sure you'll get some eyes rolling.
But.
What if you came back and you said, hey, let's try Pikachu?
Everybody likes Pikachu.
It'll be good, right?
This is what we jokingly call, the technical term
is petchakuchas.
And petchakucha means chit-chat in Japanese.
And it's a presentation style that was developed in Japan.
in which 20 slides are shown for 20 seconds each,
so you have a six minute, 40 second presentation.
And it was meant to have really, really concise presentations
that were really fast paced.
And often, they were images only.
There was no text on it.
And I have to thank, actually, GDC four or five years ago
for this idea, because this is not Blizzard's idea.
throw up the pitchy-pitchy thing there.
I sat, a bunch of us went to a talk by a guy named Scott Crabtree.
If you've been to GDC for a long time, he used to do a lot of talks, and it was called
um...
This is your brain on game development.
You can check it out in the vault. It's really cool.
Anyway, but in that talk, he was working at Intel at the time,
and he talked about how their teams were doing petchacoochas.
A person would do their own petchacoocha,
and how it was starting to help with how those teams functioned
and how they operated.
And so because of that, that idea sparked,
and now petchacoochas are running rampant
across many, many teams at Blizzard.
And it's kind of cool.
So let me tell you what they look like.
So I fudged this out, right?
I don't want to embarrass David Gibson's Pecha Kucha,
who this is.
super talented animator on Overwatch.
But for us, petchacooches have morphed
into somebody's origin story.
And we are not hardcore about the 20 seconds
or the 20 slides, so petchacooches are generally
10 or 15 minutes long, sometimes more.
And it's where the person is talking about
maybe where they grew up, or how they grew up,
things that influenced them.
By the way, when you see your coworkers
with really bad haircuts or in their awkward teen years,
it's fantastic.
It's great.
But also you start to see what matters to them.
You see their family or their hobbies, their favorite games,
first job, worst job, all these kinds of things.
And we're seeing some really interesting results.
Even outside, yes, it's helping with the vulnerability-based trust building, but we're seeing some interesting
gains also.
And one of the first gains that we're seeing is it's starting to chip away a bit at tearing
down hierarchy.
you see your art director with his 80s mullet or your HR person.
who wore headgear all the time with her braces
because she thought it was cool.
You just can't help but think, OK, all right,
they're just like a big dork, just like I am.
And so it's starting to chip away at that.
The second thing, and maybe this one's the most powerful,
is that simply the act of doing them.
communicates a message that is really powerful beyond what is actually said in the Pecha
Kucha itself.
It communicates things like, these things matter, we care about relationships, we care
about connection, and that has been hugely important in terms of our teams and
how they feel about coming to work each day.
And the third thing that's been really fun
is that Blizzard has one of our core values
is embrace your inner geek.
It's one of my favorite core values.
And this is really helping bring that thing to life, right?
Because now you've got developers going,
oh, you know, I totally love that game, too.
Or, you know, dude, I had no idea you were in a punk rock
band, or I had no idea you brewed beer.
And we're starting to now have people
talking about shared passions when they might not normally
have done that.
And that's a win.
So we have found the same results
that Lencioni actually talks about in the book,
Five Dysfunctions of the Team, about doing those personal
history exercises.
And I'm going to quote this, because I want to get it right.
So I'm going to read it.
He said.
By describing these relatively innocuous attributes or experiences,
team members begin to relate to one another on a more personal basis
and see one another as human beings with life stories and interesting backgrounds.
This encourages greater empathy and understanding.
It's amazing how little some team members know about one another
and how just a small amount of information starts to break down barriers.
So it's a win.
All right, our final rule, collaborative learning.
So collaborative learning for us,
this rule takes those ideas of building trust and safety
and admitting mistakes and really builds upon them.
So how are we thinking about collaborative learning?
We think about it just as a situation when two or more people are coming together to attempt to learn something, right?
So they're leaning on each other's skills and experiences, and there's some level of dependence and accountability once you have that group.
And maybe you're thinking, Julie, you know, I was in college. I did a lot of these group projects, and they totally sucked.
And maybe that's just me, but I don't think you're wrong.
So let me just share how we're thinking about these at Blizzard
or how we think about collaborative learning at Blizzard.
So it's in five ways.
And the first is it's peer to peer.
When you are surrounded by really smart, thoughtful,
creative people, you want to hear what they have to say.
You want to know how they go about solving problems.
And it's very powerful to put peers together in that context.
Collaborative learning for us is informal,
meaning that the group decides what they're going to talk
about, how they're going to talk about it, the pace,
and all that stuff.
This is where it departs from those annoying college work
groups, right?
There's no one from top dictating what
they do or don't have to do.
Sharing strategies and wins is a significant part
of collaborative learning.
It's really critical.
It's that idea of replicating awesome, right?
What's working over there?
Wow, that's interesting.
Let me try it out in my world and see if that works.
And vice versa.
It's an area where it's expected, encouraged.
rewarded to share what's not working, mistakes that are being made, and what we're learning
from them.
And so at its core, it's really group problem solving.
It gives us diversity of thought, different perspective, different experience, always
leading to a better outcome or a better solution.
And so a good example of collaborative learning, actually,
that we already talked about a couple slides ago,
is what the art leadership team of Overwatch is doing.
Those art direction moments.
that they spend that little bit of time each week.
Informal, no one's driving what they talk about.
They're sharing wins and strategies.
They are sharing what's not working.
And they're working together to solve common problems.
So that's one example.
Here's another one.
So we have these things called coaching labs.
And we use these coaching labs in a leadership development
context.
So what that means is we put together small groups of leads,
no more than five or six, together
to talk about being a lead and all the challenges, fun,
that go with being a lead.
And so it's topics like, you know, you've got the really challenging employee,
or you've got that really tough conversation that you need to have that you're probably avoiding.
or managing up and all the things that go with it.
The list is pretty endless.
So we've got these coaching labs, small groups.
They're really static, by the way.
So we've got coaching labs.
I'll go back.
We have coaching labs that have been happening probably
for five or six years now.
So you can imagine the levels of trust,
vulnerability-based trust, that is developing
within those groups.
It's super powerful.
Frequency of these coaching labs matter only in that there
is some level of frequency.
For us, we do them every four to six weeks.
We do them over lunch, a 90-minute lunch.
And so the cost is really low, cost some pizzas
that we bring in.
And that's really important.
And then the makeup of the groups do matter.
Yes, they're all leads for our purposes.
And then we've got some coaching labs.
We're getting bigger now.
So we have some coaching labs.
that are all leads from the same team,
and we've found those to be really effective
when we're trying to build trust and alignment
across one unified group.
And then we also have coaching labs
that are from different teams and different disciplines.
And those have been super powerful as well,
in terms of a silo buster, right?
So you get more perspective from other things that
are happening across the studio, and more diversity of thought.
And those are really, really interesting and good.
And then the last thing for us, all of our coaching labs
have some rules of engagement.
And the group decides what that is.
The one universal rule that we have is Vegas rules apply.
What's said in here stays in here.
We don't talk about Fight Club.
And that's really important in terms of that safety piece,
again, reinforcing that vulnerability-based trust
that we talk about, all that good stuff.
And so I went to a bunch of my coaching labs
and asked them.
said, hey, I'm doing this talk.
Can you give me some quotes about what it means to you?
Because I thought that would be more powerful and better.
And so these are some of the ones
that the guys came back with.
My favorite is this is the last meeting I ever want to cancel.
That's the value that it's bringing.
And the other thing is this really funny, happy accident
that we didn't intend when we started Coaching Labs.
That last quote at the bottom saying there's
pressure to do something.
pressure to do the right thing in particular.
So I'll just share a little story that
kind of brings that to life.
So you can picture this coaching lab.
We're all in a conference room.
There's pizza in the middle.
We're mowing down some pizza.
And one of the leads starts talking
about this really challenging issue
that they have with one of their employees.
And so the group's starting to ask questions, right,
and get a lot of context, like try and understand.
And then you start to see things like, well,
have you thought about this?
Maybe you should try this.
Something similar happened to me, and I did this.
Maybe that could work for you.
And that lead is walking out of that meeting.
with some nuggets, some actual practical things
that they can do to make a positive difference
on their challenge or their situation.
And so at the end of this particular meeting,
this guy says, OK, you're right.
I've been avoiding this conversation.
I know I need to have it.
I've got to tell this person what I expect,
what's happening.
Yes.
And everyone's like, yeah, go.
Fast forward to our next coaching lab,
a couple of bites of pizzas in, everyone
turns to look at that lead.
Again, this is informal.
No one's driving any agenda.
And they're like, how'd it go?
And he goes, I didn't get around to it yet.
And everyone's like, flipping the table and teeth.
He knew what you had to do.
Next coaching lab, there's no way that lead is walking into that room without having that
conversation.
So it is forcing people to do the right thing and make good leadership calls.
All right, so let's summarize what we've talked about.
So our first rule of intentional investment,
hopefully some big takeaways are that using
a strengths-based approach can help
crack the code of where to invest your very valuable time,
energy, or resources.
And invest for the exponential payoff.
Lean into someone's strengths, you get the biggest return
on that investment.
And just be careful about taking the path of most resistance.
Utilizing frameworks, right?
So for us, and maybe for you, that's
helping build discipline, thought, and action.
We didn't talk about it too much,
but choose a framework that matches your culture, right?
That's really key.
And if you're intrigued by anything in the 70-20-10
development rule, follow it.
It does help.
It does make a difference.
And our third rule of prioritizing connection,
trust matters.
Vulnerability-based trust matters.
It matters a lot.
Invest accordingly.
Make it easy for your folks to connect with each other,
to build that level of trust.
And petchakooches are for the win.
And lastly, on collaborative learning,
learning is an in-social construct, right?
So utilize that.
Lean in on that.
Don't underestimate the power of putting really smart peers
together and seeing what they can accomplish.
And if you like the idea of a coding lab, I don't know.
Call it a manager club.
Call it whatever you want.
We're actually thinking, we haven't done it yet,
of potentially putting disciplines together
for something like that.
So maybe putting on a bunch of designers
and have them start talking about design challenges.
That could be interesting.
So take that idea if you like that.
And then I will close with just this one thought.
It's a quote by one of the greatest quote makers, Mark
Twain.
He had the best quotes.
So he says, everyone must choose between one of two pains,
the pain of discipline or the pain of regret.
In our crazy world of making games,
often it's not easy to be very deliberate about developing
your people.
Things are moving really fast, expectations are really high,
and there are really, really hard problems to solve.
And so taking that time to intentionally invest
your people, that's the pain of discipline.
Right? And I would love to say that Blizzard never experiences the pain of regret.
We do. If you were to ask me, you know, hey, are there people that, where were they,
are where they were last year in terms of their development?
I would say yes.
But we keep trying and we keep learning.
And these are some of the things that are at least starting
to make a positive difference in our world anyway.
And so I encourage you.
You know, you're gamers.
I challenge you.
I challenge you to choose the pain of discipline.
As you think about the energy and the investment
that you're putting into your people, make that choice.
Your games and your teams will be better for it.
Thank you.
Okay, well that happened.
I did that.
So yeah, email's there if you want to talk Buffy the Vampire Slayer or anything about
what we talked about today.
I guess we have questions too.
We have four minutes for questions.
I have a question.
Yes.
When you were talking about intentional investment,
and you gave the example of the two people who
were empowered to design the character screen for Overwatch,
what would you say the alternative approach
that you were discarding was?
Was it like design by committee?
What was the thing that you were doing instead?
Oh, good question.
So the question was, I have to repeat this.
So the question was, we made the decision
to intentionally lean on the strengths of a couple people
to build out the core of the game.
What were the alternatives?
So design by committee was maybe one of them.
We were just in a state where we needed
to come up with some ideas right away
for the survival of the team.
And that was how we were gonna get the exponential payoff.
So it was almost like we didn't have another choice.
That help?
Okay, cool.
OK.
Hi.
Yeah, I had a quick question about the Pecha Kucha practice.
Yes.
It was quite interesting to share.
Thanks for that.
I had a question.
Was that an initiative for new hires?
Or is it on a voluntary basis?
So how does that work?
OK, cool.
So the question is, for Pecha Kuchas, is it for new hires?
And is it voluntary?
Mm-hmm.
It's not involuntary, but there's definitely a group pressure to do them.
And it looks very differently.
So, for example, the Hearthstone team does it with their whole team.
Like, they'll take a chunk of their morning, like, stand-up.
and someone will do a pecha kucha on the team.
They're a bit smaller, and that makes more sense.
On some of the larger teams, it's discipline specific.
So like the engineering all hands,
one engineer will take turns once a month
to do it, or are all hands.
Diablo teams deciding to do it in their Monday morning
meetings, someone's turn will be to do a pecha kucha.
So it just varies by the team.
Okay, great. I had a second question quickly.
This group of problem solving and sharing strategies, WIIN,
is it as well done by initiative, by people, or is there a support from HR to initiate these groups of sharing?
Oh, okay. So the question is on the coaching labs, I guess, example.
Yes.
for collaborative learning, who drives it,
who puts those together.
So it started off and it's been traditionally
like HR driven.
So we have the model, we have HR people
embedded with each of our game teams.
So they'll usually drive it.
But just literally
two weeks ago, one of our
art managers says, hey I want to spin
up a coaching lab of my own.
And we were like, yeah, that's great.
So we don't really have
some hard core rules around it.
The more important thing is that it happens.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah.
Thanks.
Yeah, thank you.
Hey.
Hi, Julie.
Great talk.
One of the pitfalls that studios I'm at right now
and the previous studios has been Halo Theory,
promoting your best talent to leaders and managers.
Do you feel like coaching labs is the best way
to combat that?
Right now, I'm helping people get indirect mentors
instead of going to the direct manager for coaching
opportunities.
So, okay, so the, I'm repeating the question again.
So the question was, if I understood it right,
so in your studio, you're experiencing the,
hey, I'm an awesome artist, so now I'm a lead artist,
and that magically endows me
with all the leadership capabilities needed?
Right. Okay.
And are coaching labs for us combating that?
Do you feel like that's a great way to grow people and to get the soft skills to be leaders
and managers?
It's an and.
It's not the only thing, but it is proving helpful.
Maybe more so, I think the guys would say there's some value in like, I'm not struggling
by myself.
Like some of them joke and call it support groups.
It's really not that, but there is value in saying,
hey, I don't know what to do about this thing. I'm not equipped.
And there's other people in that room that are and that can help.
So yes, I'd say a yes to that answer.
Hi, Julie.
Thanks for the talk.
With regard to the petri kuches, what
if you have one or two people on your team
who are just not interested in sharing
anything about their personal life with the rest of the team?
Does that sort of break the flow,
or how would you get over that?
OK, so the question was, what if you have people on the team
that petri kuches are not their thing, right?
You do not want to get in front of the team
and expose anything like embarrassing headgear wearing
pictures.
So we just kick them off the team.
No, of course not.
We, it is not mandatory.
That is not something we want to force someone to do
that truly does not feel comfortable doing it.
And everyone gets it.
They don't, like, ostracize them
or it doesn't really break the flow.
We just choose somebody else to go next.
Cool, thanks.
Okay, you're welcome.
Okay, last question.
Are you cutting him off?
He's cutting me off.
Oh, okay.
Sorry.
We can do, go in the wrap up room.
Thank you everybody.
Appreciate it.