My name is Jeremy.
I'm a development manager at Riot Games.
I'm part of the champion team on League of Legends.
Now League is a multiplayer competitive game
where players select a champion
and then duke it out five v five.
Today what I'm gonna share with you
is how we create those champions,
the kinds of challenges that we face as a team,
as well as some of the learnings
that we've had along the way.
And I just want to acknowledge right at the start,
30 minutes is a super short amount of time
to accomplish that.
So I'm going to move pretty fast,
but I'm going to do my best to save some time for Q&A
at the end.
And I also want to propose that this
can be the start of this conversation.
I'll leave my contact info up at the end.
If you guys want to keep talking,
I'm more than happy to after this presentation.
All right, so like I said,
I'm a member of the champion team.
Here's a recent photograph of us.
And when I look at this photo,
I think two things immediately.
One, I'm a terrible photographer
who can't get everybody into the frame
and everyone's blinded by the sun that they're looking at.
But I kid you not, this was literally the best photo
that I had out of dozens to review.
So that's as good as I got.
The second one is, it really just sort of strikes me
how lucky I am to be able to present this information
that I'm about to share with you.
I'm really honored to be the one to give this presentation
because this is not my work alone.
This is a work of many people.
So I just want to acknowledge that.
I think what we lack in our photogenic ability as a team,
we make up for in other ways.
And one way in particular is our dedication to our mission.
On Champion Team, our mission is to engage
and excite players with champions that deliver
innovative and resonant experiences.
I think innovative is pretty explanatory,
but I'm gonna spend a minute or two talking about
what we mean by resonant champions in just a moment.
And you know, this mission has changed over the years.
We haven't had this forever.
The needs of players have evolved.
The needs of our organization have evolved.
And so our mission has as well.
But something that stayed very consistent at Riot
is our desire to have empowered teams.
Empowered not just from a creative perspective,
but that's super important.
also empowered from a process perspective.
Basically, we believe that the best people
to figure out how to achieve this mission
is the team itself.
So that's what I'm gonna focus on today.
How does our production process sort of support us
in getting to this mission?
I'm not really gonna get into our creative process much
or our design thinking.
I wanna let you know if that's something
that you're interested in.
There's a talk tomorrow morning with Greg Street.
I think it's in North Hall, 10 a.m.
Definitely check that out.
He's design lead on League of Legends.
If that's something you're interested in, go see his talk.
On League right now, we have 134 champions.
And for players of League, investing time
on one of these champions is really meaningful.
It's a competitive game.
You're playing to win.
And so.
We really want to make sure that when players are committing their time and resources into a champion,
that we're giving them a really resonant experience back.
And that means from the first game that they play on a champion to their 300th,
we want that champion to have a deep and meaningful and fun and interesting experience for you.
And unfortunately, there's just no formula
to creating innovative and resonant champions.
I wish that was this presentation,
where I could be like, and here's the formula,
presentation over.
Unfortunately, not the case.
Here's a few champions that really resonate with me,
and that I personally really like.
But we have found that even though there's no formula,
you know, there are some things that really do help support
us in achieving our mission.
That's what I'm gonna talk about.
First, I want to share some of the challenges
that we have as a team.
And I think that these are challenges
that are pretty universal to our industry
and really to any creative team.
So as I go through these,
ask yourself if you've heard these before.
The first challenge is, are we there yet?
This sort of question on a team that bubbles up
from time to time of, do we have what we need
in order to move forward?
Do we know what done really looks like?
How long should we be brainstorming?
How long should we be in production?
And what this illustrated for us was that
we were lacking some clearly defined deliverables as a team.
And the second challenge that we face is,
that'll never work.
So there are times when you do wanna hear that on a team.
Maybe you're trying to implement a new technical feature,
and so that's a great conversation to have,
if it's going to work or not.
There are times you don't want to have that conversation.
Maybe you're into brainstorming or in a really R&D mindset.
And what this illustrated to us is that, as a team,
we really wanted to be able to have a shared mindset.
Because one of our biggest challenges
is moving from an R&D mindset into a production or execution
mindset.
We're doing that constantly on Champion Team.
There are times when we have six champions in development
at once in different phases.
And so aligning on what we should be thinking about,
what kinds of conversations we should have,
was really important to us and a challenge
that we wanted to solve.
And finally, let's not do that again.
No matter how awesome a champion development process
we've had, there's always, I would say,
a dozen times at least where we do something
and we're like, man, can we not do that again?
We'd all sit down and we'd say, yeah,
we're not gonna do that again.
And inevitably, we would do it again.
And so what this illustrated to us
is that we lacked a sort of system
that helped us capture our current learnings
for our champions that would help us
for our future champions and really make sure
that we weren't making the same mistakes again.
we realized that these aren't the worst challenges
to have as a team, right?
But altogether, they were sort of sucking up
some creative energy on the team.
And that brings me to the first learning
that I want to share with you today,
which is, as a team, we discovered
that structure empowers creativity.
We are pretty wary of process on Champion Team,
and I think with good reason.
We don't want things to get in the way
of our creative process and being innovative.
But when the lack of structure starts sucking away
some of our energy from being creative
and into sort of like the process stuff,
that's where we sort of draw a line.
And so the question for us,
and this is where that asterisk comes in,
is really like how much structure and what kind?
Because what we found ultimately has worked best for us
as a team is defining a very basic framework
to operate from.
And this gives us like a foundation to stand on
so that we can focus our creative energy
on innovating on top of it.
So we realized we needed a framework.
And so we started to create one.
And here's how we did that.
As a team, we talked about what are the natural moments
in a champion's development life cycle.
There were some pretty natural sort of like beats
that we would go to, and we called these phases.
And then we asked ourselves, what are the right goals
to have during each of those phases?
And we wanted to create goals that felt crisp
and clear enough that we could say,
are we able to achieve this in order to move forward?
Finally, we created a list of all the components,
all the deliverables, all the things
that we're gonna go into achieving that goal.
And this is essentially our framework.
And if it looks simple, I'm glad it is super simple.
And that was one of our goals.
We wanted to make something that was easy to create,
easy to understand, and easy to update.
But as simple as it is, it's given us a ton of benefit.
And so I want to sort of highlight
what those benefits are.
The first for us is clarity.
We don't ask anymore as a team, are we there yet?
Because we know where we're at, and we
know what deliverables we still need to achieve,
and we know what our goals are.
The second benefit we've gotten from this is scalability.
As a team, we're now able to quickly align
on what mindset we're in and what phase of production
we're in, no matter which champion we're talking about.
And it's also helped us with our partner teams
outside of champion.
And I'll give you an example of what that looks
like in just a few minutes.
Finally, flexibility.
So because this is sort of a simple framework,
we're able to quickly update it, add deliverables,
remove deliverables when we're making a champion so that it
helps us for our future champions.
It's really the combination of all of these benefits
that's helped us become more creatively empowered as a team.
But it's also helped us become more autonomous,
which I think is like a nice side benefit.
You know, we're really able to hold ourselves accountable
to hitting these goals and to completing these deliverables
because we define them.
So here's what our framework looks like.
This is the Champion Framework,
and it's essentially a big list of everything we need,
when we need it, and why.
And I'm gonna take you through a case study
of one of our recent champions
that sort of walks us through
how we really use this framework.
And I have some examples of the deliverables
that we go after in each phase.
I'm not gonna talk about all the specifics.
In some of our phases, there are over 50 deliverables,
and it would just be too much detail
and really dry and take forever.
So, before we get into that case study,
I do wanna take you through the basics
of how we think about champions,
the sort of core of every champion.
Each champion has what we call DNA, which is the design,
the gameplay, narrative, the lore or personality,
and the art, the audiovisual experience.
And so the combination of all three of these elements
that create strong, resonant champions.
And when these are really, really unified,
when these elements really support each other,
we call that thematic cohesion.
And thematic cohesion is a really important ingredient
in achieving a champion that resonates with people.
Everything just sort of feels right,
from their gameplay, from their story, from their art.
And I said I wasn't gonna talk too much
about our creative process,
but I do wanna mention briefly that.
On our team, good ideas can come from any one of these angles.
We've had some great champion concepts start
with a gameplay mechanic pitch.
But we've also just as often have
started from an awesome sketch from an artist that
illustrates a champion we've never seen before.
Or from a short story from a writer
that takes us to a place in our universe we've never been.
And it's that kind of creative versatility
that's really important to us.
And so we needed a framework that had flexibility
as a core benefit.
All right, so I'd like to introduce to you
the case study that I'm gonna take you through.
This creepy, gorgeous fellow is Jin the Virtuoso.
He's one of our recent champions.
And I wanted to talk about Jin today
because he's a great example of being thematically cohesive.
And he's also resonant with players.
But also the framework that we built and that you just saw,
a lot of that was developed and informed
during Jin's development.
Before Jin was known as Jin, he had a code name internally.
And that code name was Deadeye.
So let's go all the way back to the beginning.
of our first phase that every champion goes through,
and we call this phase Discovery.
Here's some early sketches of what Deadeye look like
right at the beginning.
And our goal in Discovery is to create a pitch
that's clear and concise and gets the team really excited
about making this champion.
And the first thing we do in every champion's development,
our very first deliverable,
is called the Opportunity Space.
we found that it helps us creatively
to have some like guide rails up
as we're searching for that new, innovative champion DNA.
Having a specific place to start looking is really helpful.
And so the opportunity space we defined for Deadeye
was we knew we wanted to make a marksman champion.
This is a gameplay role.
We knew we wanted to deliver on a gameplay mechanic,
this fantasy of
long-range sniper, sharpshooter gameplay.
We have some champions that do this in League already,
but none that really excelled at it,
and so that felt like a good opportunity
for us to go after.
And third and finally, from a narrative perspective,
we wanted to make a champion
with a dark and sinister personality.
That's not something we had done in quite a while,
so we were excited about that.
And so through the discovery process,
the team is iterating and we're creating new ideas
and throwing out ideas.
And here's an example of one of the sketches
that we sort of aligned at at the end of the discovery phase.
And I wanna share with you the first pitch
that we had as a team.
Our pitch for Deadeye was, he's a mysterious, robotic,
bounty hunting, sniper, cowboy guy.
And I totally, in retrospect, see
how this is not a particularly clear nor concise pitch.
But our framework really helped us out here,
because it allowed us to say, hey, we all
are on the same page here in terms of our mindset
and what our goal is.
We know that we don't have to overwork this concept
right now.
We're all aligned that this is just our first draft,
and it did get us excited.
So we were able to move into our next phase of development,
which we call ideation.
And our goal in ideation is to take that concept,
refine it, but then also back it up
with an in-game prototype.
And we create these in-game prototypes
by sort of Frankensteining together old models
and abilities from previous champions
and visual effects and sound effects
and we cobble them together and we try to squint
and create a gameplay experience that we can say,
yes, this is fun, this is new, this is interesting.
We found there's just no substitute
for an in-game experience.
One of the ways that we really validate
and hold ourselves accountable to proving that
is that we have a deliverable in ideation
that we call pattern lock.
This is a design deliverable.
And pattern lock has a bunch of things in it,
but one of them that's really key
is this idea of identifying the strategic identity
of the champion.
Essentially, why would you bring Deadeye to a game
versus 133 other champions?
And we have to prove that out.
We also want to lock and understand deeply
three out of the five core abilities on that champion.
So we set a pretty high bar at this early stage
for making sure that we really understand
from a design perspective,
what's gonna make this champion fun, interesting.
A lot of our champions never make it out of ideation.
But Deadeye did.
And so we moved into our next phase,
which we call pre-production.
Pre-production is, I think, the hardest phase for us as a team.
And it's hard because we're sort of straddling
two different mindsets at the same time.
We're still in sort of an R&D phase in a lot of ways.
For example, you can see this blue proxy model.
This is a quick model that we create and put in the game
based on concept art that helps us get a sense of the silhouette
and the overall shape.
And we're making them taller and shorter
and changing all sorts of things to get the right feel.
But we're also in kind of a production and execution
point of view as well.
And you can see that in the middle concept image
where we're really trying to refine
explicit details on the costuming
and really lock down some decisions there.
And our goal here is to come out of pre-production
with a really clear pitch and plan
for how we're gonna build this character
in our next phase, which is production.
And because this phase is so difficult for us,
we have a lot of interim deliverables
that we've created along the way as a way of sort of helping.
And this helps us keep moving forward,
making sure we're on the right track.
And before we get into production, though,
I want to share with you our final pitch for Deadeye.
I literally copied this out of an old PowerPoint
that I found.
We have a log line, which is Deadeye
is a mysterious Ionian drifter.
We've got a mission statement.
We've got these things that we call pillars, three pillars.
These are creative touchstones that we
use on the team to help us understand what's in
and what's out on the champion.
The three pillars that we had for Deadeye
are artist and killer.
So this is the sense that like he sees beauty in death.
That's a core part of his character.
Deliberate action.
Deadeye is super precise and explicit and specific
with what he wants to do.
And we wanted to really sell that
and make sure that that came through in his gameplay.
Finally, the lie.
This helped us understand his motivation
and what kind of personality he has.
Why does he wear a mask?
What's underneath that mask?
And it's the combination of all of these deliverables
together that helps the team align
on what we're trying to make.
I think ultimately what we ended up making for Deadeye
or for Jin was a character that really excelled
at this idea of a deliberate artisan killer.
But we couldn't get to that level of specificity right away.
We have to build alignment and understanding.
And to do that, that takes a lot of work.
There's these deliverables here,
but there's many others as well.
And that brings me to the second learning that we've had
that I wanna share with you now.
which is that for us, our hardest work is before production.
And in a way, we have our framework, ironically,
to blame for this.
You know, we've front-loaded more and more of our work
and more of our deliverables before we get into production.
Over the years, we've learned that the later we make changes
and the later we do some things,
the costlier and more painful it becomes,
especially when we start building final assets.
And so because those changes become exponentially harder,
we've decided as a team that we want
to invest in tackling these things early.
Our average champion production schedule is nine months.
And that's just on average.
And so for a lot of our champions,
before we ever make a final asset,
it can be five months in previous phases.
And we found that that actually has a lot of value for us.
All right, so let's get into production.
Production is not easy.
I know that I said our hardest work was before this.
Production's an exciting time.
Everyone's working on different assets,
we're integrating them all together,
we're seeing how they feel,
and inevitably there's some changes that we wanna make.
But because we've done some due diligence before this,
we can usually roll with those changes
without impacting our overall schedule.
And ultimately, our goal for production
is to get the champion in a content-complete state
with enough polish that we can start videotaping
and creating video content to show players.
And we do this because we want to engage and excite
our players with new champion content.
But we also want to release this content
before the champion comes out so that players
can get an understanding of what's coming
and what are the abilities here.
I wanna share with you one of the new features
that we needed to build for Jin.
We needed to create a new UI HUD element.
A core part of Jin's gameplay is that he has four shots,
and then he needs to take a pause and reload.
We needed to be able to communicate this mechanic
to players in a really clear way.
Unfortunately, we don't have any interface designers
on the champion team, or anyone that was like,
really that skill set.
And so we had to partner with another team,
and this is where that scalability thing comes into play
that I was talking about earlier.
Our framework really helped create an easy partnership
with our other team, because we were able to say,
hey, here's where we're at with Jin,
here are the goals that we have,
here are the deliverables that we need along the way,
how can we partner with you
and add your deliverables into this process?
And it's awesome that this helps us work and align
with other teams as well.
And as a result, our newer champions
have more new features than ever before.
So we move into our next stage from production,
which is post-production.
This is when we released the champion.
And I think in order to really explain how this works,
I should tell you a little bit about how League of Legends
delivers new content to players.
So we try to release a new patch of content
every two weeks worldwide.
But before that patch goes wide,
we upload it to our PBE or public beta server.
And players can play the PBE server and give us feedback.
And so for us on Champion Team, releasing a champion
isn't like a singular moment in time.
It's actually the process of many weeks.
And we're taking feedback.
And one of our biggest goals is to release the champion
in a healthy, awesome state, and definitely in a balanced state.
And so I apologize.
Let's get up some of this content.
So we've created what we call a balance mitigation plan.
This plan has a bunch of different balance outcomes
and scenarios that can come to pass
and all of the things that we're gonna do to address those.
Now those balance concerns really often never come,
but we found that it has helped us do that exercise
that if something does happen,
we're able to quickly react to it.
And if you play League, you may challenge me
on Jin's balance currently, and I encourage you
to give that feedback directly to Greg Street tomorrow
if you go to his talk.
So after post-production, we're in our final phase.
This is called sustain.
And this is where Jhin currently is,
and all 134 of our champions live.
And we have some clear deliverables at this phase.
You know, we archive all of our development assets,
we set up some partnerships with our other teams
in League of Legends,
and how we're gonna support Jhin in the future.
And we hold project retrospectives with the team.
But overall, we're really still trying
to figure out a good goal and good deliverables here.
And that leads me to the final learning that I want
to share with you all today.
And that's our framework's never done,
and it always needs improvement.
And if you create something like this,
I'm betting yours will also be in this situation.
But ultimately, that's OK.
This framework is cheap to iterate on, cheap to create,
and it encourages that constant iteration.
And what we found as a team is that the more that we work on this,
the more we get benefits like scalability and clarity.
And it gives us a stronger and stronger foundation of which to stand on as a team,
which in turn has given us more and more of creative energy
to focus on delivering innovative and resonant champions to League of Legends players.
I want to thank you all so, so much for coming to this talk
and for your time.
Thank you.
That's my Twitter.
If you want to send me tips on how to take better team photos
or give me feedback or continue talking about this,
please feel free.
And I think we've got five minutes for Q&A.
So I apologize, I can't really see you, but go ahead.
Hello.
Hi.
So I have a question about your framework.
You mentioned the different phases.
And I wanted to know if they are time-boxed,
like you have a specific time to reach these phases,
or it's more like you iterate until.
you're ready to go to the next phase?
That's a good question.
So the question was, do we have a time box
on each of these phases?
And the answer is, kind of.
We have some best practices that we found over the years
of like, it should take us about this amount of time
in discovery and about this amount of time in ideation
and so forth.
But these are just guidelines.
We've had, I would say all of our champions
have broken some of those guidelines at some point.
And we just use that as a way of kind of gut checking ourselves
where we're at.
Thank you.
Question over here.
What's your rate of atrophy between these different phases?
Like you sort of said, a lot of champions
don't make it to the next step.
How much are getting lost along the way at each of those steps
roughly?
Yeah.
A lot.
So it's kind of hard to keep track of that data specifically.
I will say that we cycle and churn through stuff
in discovery pretty frequently.
And we have this concept that we call iceboxing.
So if a champion isn't moving forward and not getting
traction, we put it in the icebox,
which means we've got a kind of backlog collection of concepts
that we can pull from in the future.
But are you losing them later steps also?
Or once they reach a certain point,
do they always go all the way through?
It's pretty unusual that we lose a champion after ideation.
And the main reason for that is because we
have some really hardcore design deliverables in there,
like pattern lock.
Thanks.
Yeah, take care.
Hi there, thank you.
I just wanted to ask, regarding champion reworks,
do you happen to find yourself starting at earlier points
in the process, or do you tend to get a little bit
of a head start due to that?
Is that the question?
Oh, great.
OK.
So the question was about Champion Reworks,
and do we use the same framework?
So was that the question?
More or less, yeah.
So Champion Updates is actually a sister team, a partner team
to Champion.
They use a similar process, but not exactly this framework.
There are a lot of similarities for how we work on the teams,
but I don't want to try to give specifics on their process.
Thank you.
He might have already answered my question,
or you might have already just answered my question.
But so you guys don't handle the maintaining of the champions?
That's another team that does that?
So the question is, do we handle maintaining the champions
or not?
It depends on your definition of maintaining.
So we have a responsibility and a commitment
to players and to our organization
that we will continuously take care of our champions.
And so when bugs come up or certain issues,
the champion team is accountable for making
sure they're resolved.
There are other teams within the League of Legends organization
that look at things like visual game updates for their large
scale reworks, as well as specific balance passes.
We do things like roster updates.
Essentially, there's a lot of teams working on champions,
and we're just one of them.
Okay, and how do you handle scaling out?
So obviously the more champions you have,
the harder it gets to actually handle
all of these different things.
So how do you handle scaling out your team?
Do you just grow exponentially the more champions you have?
OK, so the question is, how do we scale?
Or what are the challenges around scaling as the more
champions that we have?
I think that that kind of gets at the heart of the challenges
that we have around our current sustain phase.
The more champions that we have, the more
we need to just double down on our commitment
to maintaining them.
We are still trying to figure that out.
Thank you.
Yeah, thank you.
I've noticed that some champions come out with these really elaborate videos and, you
know, comics and all that kind of things, and other champions kind of just come out.
Is that considered as part of the design process, to say, you know, this champion needs this
video to kind of explain their lore so you understand them, or is that kind of added
later in the process?
The question was, you know, how do, how does the sort of like supplementary and then sort
of promotional content work for releasing new champions?
It's, my response is, I feel like gonna be long-winded,
but I'm gonna try to just cut to the chase,
which is there's another partner team that we have,
Champion Publishing, that partners really early with us,
and like how can we best tell players
the story of who this champion is,
and is the most effective tool to do that a comic,
or is it a video, or is it an interactive website,
or Easter eggs, or stories?
We're always like trying to innovate
and think of new things to do there.
So the process starts really early,
and we partner with another team on that all the way.
All right, thank you.
Thanks.
All right, I think we're at time.
Thank you guys so much for coming today,
and please hit me up if you have any other questions.
Thank you.