Hi, welcome to the Classic Game Postmortem for Star Wars Galaxies.
I'm Raph Koster and I was the original creative director on the game.
And I'm Rich Fogle and I was the executive producer on the game.
We're going to take you through the story of a game that maybe was a bit
unlikely to end up getting a classic game postmortem, but here we go.
We're going to start out with some of the early days, the prehistory of the game.
and how it got launched and started.
So Rich, why don't you talk about that for a bit?
Yeah, so the original team who started on Star Wars Galaxies
was really working on privateer online and origin systems.
And we, at that time, Origin was working on a couple of MMOs.
And one of them we figured would be great to take the Wing
Commander franchise and do privateer online,
in which we started on and worked on for about a year
and a half to almost two years.
did a great demo, a great actually first playable
of what Privateer Online was all about.
And then Origin canceled it.
About that time, Richard Garriott was also
no longer employed.
And I actually had to call Raf on the phone in Australia
to tell him what was going on
because he's actually over there
doing some UO promotions at the time.
And so it was a very interesting,
tumultuous time at Origin.
And so at that time when we canceled the game,
well, we just started to look around
and we found a landing place at Barron
and the rest is history.
We formed the Austin Studio for Barron.
And one of the great things about it is
when we started working there, we didn't realize they were, we knew they had the Star Wars license,
but we didn't know that we're already working on the game. So when we got there and went up to San
Diego, we found out that they actually were working on the Star Wars game and had some things to show.
But one of the concepts was it was actually they're working on EQ2 at the same time,
and they wanted to share the technology and engine.
And so when we looked at it, we started to review it and see where they were on the project.
And we found that really, based on our opinion, there wasn't really much that we could use at that time.
And we felt like the engine wouldn't get us to what we really wanted to be and do in the time frame we had to do it in.
So next slide. So we started on the first thing we did is kind of like get our feet wet and get a feel for Star Wars.
And we love Wing vs. TIE.
And so we all kind of, we didn't have an office space at that time, there were about 12 of us.
And so we started working at J. Allen Brax, who was at that time an associate producer for us.
And he lent us their house, his house, and we started working on Wing vs. Tai game.
And we actually put it together in about six weeks, a first playable.
It was so impressive that LucasArts decided, even though we haven't started on the game officially yet, that they would love to us to sign up for an expansion, and that would be actually a JTL, Jump to Lightspeed, actually came out of this prototype that we did.
for the Star Wars game that we started working on.
And we actually was able to get some of our previous technology
that another group was working on that we purchased.
So we get a little leg up on the client, but it was actually a pretty fun game
that we started there at J.
Allen Braxhouse. Next. And.
When we went up to San Diego, like I said before,
there was a team up there working on it, we decided that, you know, let's.
Let's look at this and let's break the development up.
So we took the good.
They had a really good, strong art team on it.
And we said, let's keep that strong art team on it
because they've done a lot already.
And let's form the tech team from Austin.
And we decided to do it in both locations, both Austin
and San Diego, to build this game.
There were lots of cultural challenges for that that we had to deal with.
And that's something we can go into a little later.
One of the biggest things that they wanted us to do before we started was to make sure that was not going to cannibalize EverQuest.
So they wanted to make sure it was differentiated enough that no way anybody would probably go for EverQuest to playing Star Wars, or if they did, it would be a very small group of people.
And so we had a great background with Ultima Online on a skill based system where basically EverQuest was a Dooku mod, which was level based, class based type system.
and we weren't going to build that and we were actually going to use the template very similar
to what actually all the Warcraft used and we decided no we're actually going to do something
totally different and separate ourselves immediately from EverQuest. Next slide.
Take it from there. Yeah then came time to actually start making the game and the very
first thing that we ran into of course was what do we do about Jedi?
The game was set during the classic trilogy time period, in between the Empire Strikes Back and Return of the Jedi.
And the challenge with that is that Jedi in that time period are supposed to be incredibly rare.
They are incredibly powerful compared to everybody else.
But of course, if you put them in a game, then everybody will want to be one.
So we floated the idea. Could we make it so no players could be Jedi?
And we were told no, it was too important. Players needed to be Jedi.
we asked, could we change the time period to, let's say,
after Return of the Jedi, when, you know, thanks to Luke,
you know, there's more Jedi everywhere. We were told no, we couldn't do that.
Then there was a question, well, can we make them not be powerful?
And the answer to that was, well, that's not very Star Wars-y.
So we were stuck with this impossible dilemma where you needed to create an
Uber class that was somehow incredibly rare, even
though players had infinite time.
was in some ways almost the game's original sin
and something that ended up leading
to massive, massive problems later on.
We played around with the idea of having Jedi suffer
from permadeath when they lost,
but that was seen as also being kind of a challenge
with the audience.
So we settled on a system where players had to sample
a random set of the features in the game
and every player's set was different.
So hang on to that idea,
because it'll come back up later.
The game, you know, remember what it was like in 2003. We shipped on three CDs. We took up two
gigabytes of space. A cable connection today is thousands of times faster than the modems we were
designing for.
we were looking at making maps that were large, much larger than say Ultima Online or EverQuest.
You know, we were under a mandate to ship multiple planets, and so we ended up shipping actually
two and a half gigabytes worth of map data, and those maps are to scale, they're what you see.
And as you can see, that already exceeds the capacity of the CDs that we shipped on.
So we actually had to invent a whole bunch of fractal terrain technology in order to be able
to do this. What we did was we basically created a Photoshop-like tool that used layers where each
layer had procedural rules.
and these could be added on the fly.
And those 2 and 1 1 gigabytes worth of map data
ended up shrinking to about 30k per planet
as a plain old text file.
It was so much memory to store these maps
that we couldn't even afford to have the maps running
in full on the server.
We actually had to generate them as players
walked around on the server.
which actually led to massive issues with collision.
You know, you could shoot bolts through terrain that didn't exist,
all of that kind of thing. But it did unlock really, really cool
procedural placement of buildings at runtime while you were playing the game.
And the neat thing about this is this is actually
way before this technology in 2003 that we developed was way advanced
for its time.
You know, not, you haven't seen this until just recently, actually, this technology.
And so we had it then, and this is a great example.
This is kind of when we started with the terrain.
This is month one, and this is month four.
It is an amazing technology, and it allowed us not only to layer, like in Photoshop,
different aspects of the terrain, but we also are allowed to do, based on height map,
rivers flowing and things like that.
that was in the game as well. So very, some very, very cool technology that we are allowed to do.
Next slide.
Yeah, so of course, everything had to go through approval processes,
which slowed us down, right, a lot of extra dev work.
Exactly. And so basically I had to actually hire a producer just to handle the approval processes
for LucasArts and LucasFilm because not only did we have to go through LucasArts, our publisher,
we also had to go through LucasFilm to get them approved. And some things I had to go all the way
up to George Lucas himself to approve. We were lucky to have Hayden Blackman,
who is basically a walking encyclopedia of Star Wars knowledge over on the LucasArts side because
since he was, I forget his title, continuity coordinator, something like that,
on the Star Wars side, he was really able to do a lot of approving directly.
But the level of secrecy was over the top. We were being sent material from the movies that had not yet come out.
These were hand couriered on CDs, encrypted with every file name garbled.
The file extensions were changed so you couldn't double-click the file.
And there was a separate hand couriered paper copy of what file was what, so that you could find what you were looking for.
And this just led to really crazy development challenges.
Like you probably remember Mace Windu's purple lightsaber,
right, Samuel L. Jackson.
We had designed a lightsaber system
that relied on different colored crystals.
And one day, the message comes down, nope,
all the lightsabers everywhere in Star Wars
are changing to only be red and blue.
We said, but we've gone and designed the system.
Nope, you've got to redo it all.
it turned out that that was just because George Lucas was editing this battle and he wanted the
two sides to be clearly different from one another. So a few weeks later we were told,
never mind you can put it all back, all the lightsaber colors can come back in, it's okay
again. So stuff like that was an ongoing development challenge as we went to go get approvals.
This is you Rich.
One of the things that we learned a lot about this, again, we used a layering system,
is we had to recreate these on Tatooine, Mos Eisley, and other areas, and they had to be
pretty much exact, because again, this was very much tied to the movie, so anything that
was shot in the movies, we had to actually replicate.
for approval into the game.
So it was a very tedious task of looking at.
We had pictures to look at for reference.
We had a huge library of reference material
that we had to go through.
Hayden Blackman was also our guide for that as well,
because he was a subject matter expert that we used.
Not only was he our producer, but he was, as Raf said,
a subject matter expert on pretty much anything Star Wars.
It was great to have him there.
Yeah, we were pushing boundaries on a lot of things.
We put together a character customization system using morph targets that I think was the second video game ever to ship with something like this. The first was whichever Elder Scrolls game I remember.
being really upset that they beat us to market with it. And we supported just incredible levels
of character customization, including old and young, including really detailed things like
beards, makeup, tattoos, everything that people see today in character customization
in terms of modern AAA games, we were having to invent on the fly.
back then, because we were literally one of the very first games on Earth to do anything quite
like this, and to this level of detail, including things like depth of layered clothing, all of that.
And we ended up pushing it in directions pretty far, right?
And the reality is the character customization people look at Star Wars Galaxies as the,
really, the premier first one that really pushes the boundaries of that technology.
And we wanted to do that because we wanted to make sure everyone felt unique in the world,
and they could be what they wanted to be. We weren't limiting them to cookie cutter type
body types and faces and heads. And so that led to a lot of really cool customization in the game,
characters that you see running around. Yeah, it's funny because years later I actually met
J.K. Rowling and
she was asking me, so hey, so in this game, can I be an overweight dancing Wookie?
So it kind of became a signature of the game, right, that people knew that it had that level
of personal expression in it. One of the nice things about Swig was it had a dynamic POI system
in the game. What that allowed us to do
is if you had a group of people walking around on Tatooine, for instance, you could have a dynamic
system like a spacecraft crash in front of you, someone run out and give you something, then
suddenly stormtroopers come over the horizon after you and shoot you for what you have. And you give
it to an NPC to get a reward once you tell them, she tells you to give it to this NPC in this town.
This was an amazing system. And it was also based on the level you were.
the level of your group or your party.
Not only did dynamic system did that,
but it also allowed events to be done in the game,
where we had real-time people be able to run events
in real-time on all our servers, anytime,
anywhere within our structure.
So that was pretty cool.
Yeah, it also, of course, introduced
all kinds of challenges around changing the collision
and the nav mesh on the fly and all the rest.
So it definitely gave us some headaches.
headaches was one of the big things, right? Because throughout
all of this, we were really consciously trying to create
sort of a next generation MMO, something that broke the
template of just levels and classes. So we tried doing too
many new things.
We had crafting on equal footing with combat.
We had hairdressing in the game.
You know, 612 individual skill boxes.
We even modeled PTSD.
If you got hurt a whole bunch while you were out in combat,
you had to come back and hang out in a bar
and listen to musicians and watch dancers
and that kind of thing.
And people definitely made fun of us for that, right?
Like it introduced a level of both tedium
and also...
kind of social contact that was sort of different from other games, right? So we were really
pushing boundaries all over the place in a bunch of different directions. A great example of that
was actually with the economy, which to this day is one of the main things that people talk about
with Star Wars Galaxies. We didn't set the price of any goods in the game. Players set all of the
prices.
They harvested materials from the environment and these materials actually
appeared and disappeared and generated with different stats all the time.
which caused huge database problems, because not only were those stats different, but then anything
you made from them also came out with different stats, and it had four digits of precision. So
a few years later, there were literally billions of resource items, billions of types of materials
in the database, and enormous database bloat and performance problems. And many of those,
there was one unit left of that resource in the entire galaxy.
everything was supposed to break. Everything was crafted by players. This meant that when
the game started, they had to bootstrap up the economy from nothing. And it was really a very
complex system. If you go hang out on Reddit today and threads start about, hey, what's the
greatest crafting system of all time? A lot of players mentioned Galaxies because of this level
of depth. But boy, did it cause problems with the database. It really did.
So we've gone and built all of this technology, but can we actually ship the game, right?
The answer was no. No, we couldn't.
So the timeline that you see here is we started in 2000, and you can see how we went to E3 in 2001
and showed off a demo of the game at E3, which won
many awards, including almost a game best of show.
We lost it by one.
We did get PC best of show, I think it was.
What's that?
I think we got PC best of show.
We did get PC best of show.
Not game of show overall.
Right, and then we got the onliner game of show as well.
But we made a lot of promises here when we showed it off.
We also showed off the Krayt Dragon
as you came around the corner the first time
you ever seen it in the Star Wars game.
And we could see how our tools were progressing
and where we are when we opened up the game.
We literally had people running around and just texting
with text bubbles when we first opened up.
We didn't have much anything working.
Now, I think it was very fortunate that we decided,
when we originally did this game,
we knew we didn't have a lot of time
to build this game, a very short time frame.
So we knew that we had to do a procedural type
of systematic type of game.
game design and not everything handcrafted.
So we didn't want to get into a handcrafted treadmill
when we released the game.
So doing that means that we had a huge
open world sandbox game, luckily.
But we didn't have much content, I'd call it,
in the game to really hold the players
for a very, very long time because our tools,
our content tool pipeline, as you can see
in the two dots at the end,
came very close to each other before we launched. We had no choice. The launch was set. We were not
going to move that date. They only gave us another month. That was it. We asked for six.
That wasn't going to happen. We actually even had to bring up 60 people to help us
to try to get the content done. But it was very much a hopeless case. We knew when we launched
this game that we would be running behind.
and having to really play catch up in terms of getting the content out and fixing the bugs in the game.
Yeah, so this meant there we are running off on the end.
We've gotten an extra month, we have no real quests.
I think there's one quest chain in the entire game.
There is no quest system.
So we just had to randomly generate missions from mission terminals,
not even from NPCs, because we couldn't afford to write dialogue for NPCs.
So it was just mission terminals.
Worst of all, we ran out of time to implement all of that tracking for becoming a Jedi,
and we had to change the system. Instead of a random subset of all the activities in the game,
every player had an invisible list of five skills out of the 612 that they needed to learn,
and that was how they were going to unlock Jedi. That was a very fateful decision made at the end
of a, you know, 14 or 16 hour long crunch day that proved to have really bad repercussions later.
we had planned to have things like player-granted missions, and we were cutting whole skill trees
at this point because we were just really desperate for time. We knew we were running out
of it. And this entire time, of course, we had been talking with the community about what we
were making. And so one of the things that I had a lot of experience on in Mertain 59, and then went
to UO and work with Raph on UO, is
how to build community and how to talk to community
and how important that was in an online game.
So I took a lot of lessons I learned there
and I saw the way this was happening.
So I got the community involved in this game right away.
And so about six months after launch, we formed a special Jedi Council of key players that we felt
like in the community, invited them over to our offices, we paid for everything, and to come in
and be our council and help us, guide us to what the players really want to do. And this concept
was never done before in an online game. And so this council and how we interacted with the community
was really very important to us because we realized that we had a very rabid fan base.
We wanted to make sure that we knew the way the game was launched. We knew it was buggy.
We were going to do everything we can to fix it to help. We basically helped with engagement.
And the Jedi Council's job was to help us to figure out how to triage what to do next to
get this game into the shape that we want to and the players want it to be. So
On that, we also had a situation where we were threatened by the 504s because you couldn't play a stormtrooper in the game.
They threatened to go boycott our offices.
I wish they had.
And I wish they had, because that would have been great news. But I was terrified, oh God, we're going to get harassed now.
And there was a reason we couldn't do that, because it all had to do with the movies.
And we couldn't talk about it at all. We were told not to talk about it at all.
So at that time, no one knew stormtroopers were clones.
No one.
And so that was a really, really important secret
that George Lucas wants to make sure kept within his group.
And so that is the reason why you cannot play
a stormtrooper in the game.
Yeah.
We eventually calmed them down by saying,
well, you can get stormtrooper armor and wear it,
and you can take the side of the stormtroopers,
you just can't really be one.
Yeah.
Tell you why.
Oh, well.
An effect of all of this was that there was a lot of hype.
A lot of people got really, really excited.
That community was so big and so active,
it translated directly into day one sales.
But, you know, the coverage,
people are tipping Galaxies and Sims Online,
which was the other upcoming big MMO,
to be the two big MMOs.
Sims Online even landed on the cover
of Time Magazine or something.
Right. And so there was an enormous level of hype.
And in the office, we are freaking out because we know our timeline is so short.
Right. A release date hasn't been announced yet.
And we know that we're we're about to hit a wall.
And the one thing about that is, you know, when you when you when you launch a game
for the first time, or talk about it from a marketing campaign, not for launching the game
for a marketing campaign, when you really release for the first time.
I think one of the biggest lessons I've learned is we release way too early.
I think that if you ever, you know, one of the lessons I learned for all the online games I have
is only talk about it when there's a point of action to occur, like signing up for a beta or
whatever. And it should be very close to when you're about to go into beta test. And that should
be it. Because if you wait so long, people in their minds get set up to what their perception
of what the game is. And it's very hard to change reality. Because perception is reality.
And so what that led to is we knew we were heading headfirst into a very bad situation,
which when we launched the game, we asked for it, you know, like I said, six months to a year.
I didn't think that we would get a year, but I think maybe we could get six months,
but we got one month, which really kind of like put us in a very big bind for.
for release in this game, because you only get one launch.
If anything is you got to get out of this,
you only get one opening night.
And what that happens is if you don't make it
on the D1 the first day,
and it becomes a very bad experience for the player,
what'll happen is you have a curve
and that curve goes like this.
And if you launch poorly, that curve will go like this.
You'll never get that really big accelerant
of that upward trending curve ever, ever, ever again.
You only get one opening night.
Now, most people think in today's world, if you see MMOs or online games launch,
they two years later, they come back and say, oh, they actually are pretty good,
but they will never reach that high point of the initial launch ever that I've seen.
So it's hard for a team that worked and crunched so hard.
We did that game in two years and nine months.
That was with no technology at all.
We had to basically build everything from scratch.
That was an amazing amount of work in that very short period of time.
We all.
It's very discouraging for the team to see it launch the way it did.
And we paid for it because this is probably the only classic game
post-mortem you'll see that won Coaster of the Year.
The initial reception was not good.
I'm not sure there's much more to say about that.
No. Life went on, right?
I mean, it did. We had to still run the game.
Absolutely. And the one thing I'll have to say is we had some technology that we're using that
were very, very new to the way the database and stored and also with the company running EverQuest,
they never had that day one surge that this game had. And so what happened was, is their login
service melted on the amount of transactions per second that was happening and they could not scale
fast enough.
And it took several days for that instability
to get cleared up.
And then on top of that, we had a new way of storing data.
As Ralph said, because our objects are the way they are,
the database we bought was for a very high-end company that
very much enterprise-level software,
had never seen the transactions per second that
was coming in with our game.
They'd never seen that.
And so they started melting.
And we had to figure out that for about, I'd say,
two weeks of instability really did cost us.
a huge amount of players going into this game because the player experience just wasn't where
it needed to be. And yet what ended up happening was what people today call sort of a golden age
of Star Wars Galaxies. Everybody talks about this pre-CU period. Early on we actually had a
pretty robust analytics system.
and we actually have some numbers here to share about what life was like during this time period.
We were able to measure things like GDP growth in the game and where income was coming from and so
on, and even though the combat was terrible, the game balance was awful, and there was no content
in the game,
we found that the sandbox elements of the game were surprisingly popular and were working really,
really well. Really high numbers of people were participating in all of these peaceful ways to
play. And of these, probably one of the biggest and most forward-looking was player housing.
Yeah, so player housing was an amazing trial. We learned a lot from you. If anything that taught us
about player housing was was what you owe what to do and what not to do in player housing.
There were situations that people took player housing so serious and you are we weren't going
to screw this up in Star Wars galaxies. That I wasn't going to have happen I it was the housing
was so screwed up that I actually found a letter on my doorstoop that was not posted and said how
would you like your house broken into?
That was the first time I realized how fans can be.
It really scared me.
And I said, no, I'm not going to have that happen here again.
So we put a lot of effort into our housing system.
And because we were a factual terrain based,
we actually can level out and place buildings
on the terrain very effectively and efficiently.
And efficiently so much that sometimes it
hid entrance to the dungeon.
There are checks that were not put on specific places.
There were bugs, actually, that occurred that we needed to fix.
But most of all, the housing really worked well.
And it created cities within galaxies on planets.
And so it was a very, very cool.
And the customization, which I like to talk about,
which is our next slide, was something that
has never been done before.
There's nothing out there like that.
in my opinion, on player housing that was added, this is players customization that we showed you
here. They could customize this place, craft many items and put it in the house. And so what this
allowed is not only players to do that but guilds to express themselves. So guilds have their own
guild halls that they develop themselves.
And because we had different types of housing available and different types of blueprints,
so to speak, they could pick the ones they liked and big halls and things like that.
So guilds actually built their own places. And that was very, very cool and compelling
and engaging in our game. So the housing really, really took off. And it's something that's
remembered a lot in Star Wars Galaxies. Yeah. And it wasn't just house by house because
guilds and players got together to found cities. And we actually created a politician skill tree
that allowed the elected mayor of a town to set laws, taxation for their town,
decide who the police force was so they could eject people or kill people who were misbehaving.
you know, we had a whole bunch of individual servers.
There's an average of 125 player cities per server.
So that means every planet had about a dozen player cities.
We had only built three or four per planet.
And they went on and built a dozen more on every planet.
And these had theaters, and they had museums,
and they had malls, and they had all kinds of stuff.
And this is one of those things that
outside of the political structures in EVE Online maybe,
you know, it's hard to think of other examples
of this kind of empowerment being given to players.
It really was a signature element
and there are still countless websites out there
for player-run cities and galaxies,
even though the game has been shut down for a long time.
And the cool thing about it is because the practical train
and other things that we're allowed to do, again,
we had this way before No Man's Sky had this.
Yeah.
This is in 2003 that this came out.
So you can imagine how far ahead we were.
And we streamed terrain in real time, both server and client,
as the players went around.
So that was just unheard of too.
One of the neatest things, I think, that we had in our game
is the pet system.
The pet system was really, really cool.
You started out with a baby pet, a baby bantha, so to speak.
And there were baby banthas all around.
And you can.
and you could train it. And basically, it would learn, if you are hostile to it, it would be a
mean bantha. If you were nice to it and kind to it, and it will be a kind bantha. But it actually
learned from your behaviors of what type of personality would come up. And you could teach
it tricks. And so one of the big things about the pet system was very, very cool. You walk
into cities, you can see people all around with pets. And
It became a problem that we actually had to nerf because the pets became very powerful over time.
Again, if you're abusive to it, it would also be very tough, very aggressive animal.
So we actually had to nerf it a little bit so it didn't dominate the combat component of Star Wars Galaxies.
But the neat thing about it is it did allow players to do arenas, little battles between
the animals and bet on them and things like that. There was so many different aspects of the pet
system that people used and liked. And you see them in their houses, people walking around the
streets with them. It was a very, very cool part of our game. In fact, very unusual aspects of it
that made it, I think, one of the best pet systems in a game.
Yeah, another thing that we ended up pushing on,
you know, player versus player, free for all player killing
had just about, I mean, it cut UO's user base in half.
It was devastatingly bad.
And the consensus in the market was that safe worlds
was the way to go.
But of course, we had to model a galactic civil war
between the Empire and the rebels.
So we knew that PVP was going to have to be really important.
So we came up with this temporary enemy flagging system.
that let you join a side, but as a covert sympathizer.
So you could turn your flag on temporarily
and duck back out.
And, you know, the stats at the time showed
that only one to 3% of people would turn on a flag
permanently in games like EverQuest.
Sure enough.
less than 1% of our players actually went to full-time PVP.
But over a quarter of them ended up
participating in the Galactic Civil War
as long as it wasn't a permanent commitment.
Now, this may not seem shocking today, right?
But back then, the market couldn't sustain a title
like Rust or DayZ or games that were sandboxy
but free-for-all PVP on their own.
That gameplay had to be integrated into something larger.
And Galaxies opened the door along with games like DAOC
to show how you could have that kind of realm
versus realm combat.
And we definitely lifted a bunch from DAOC
in order to do that, of course.
And that PVP, in combination with the Proc Gen terrain
and the ability to build buildings,
meant that there could be entire bases spawning on the map,
being destroyed, the ability to put down turrets in them
and have really large-scale battles and faction warfare.
So it really did unlock this thing where at any moment you might be in a city and suddenly have
a huge battle that wrapped around you. And if you weren't interested, it couldn't hurt you,
but it definitely made the environment feel more exciting.
One of the cool things about that is, and I will tell you,
is watching the faction battles.
I mean, again, all the tools in the sandbox really worked well.
That was the cool part of the game, I will tell you.
And that's actually where all the players migrated to.
As we were trying to build our content,
they started building content, basically,
and actually entertaining themselves very, very quickly.
And probably the biggest way they did that was, of course,
with the stuff that people made the most fun of us for.
Yes. Like having dancing in the game at all. But it turned out
that dancing and musicianship and beauty pageants, and making
music videos and filming little soap operas. And bear in mind,
this was before YouTube existed. Right? There was just an
enormous amount of player player creativity that got unlocked by
this.
even though everybody was also simultaneously saying that's not very Star Wars.
Yeah, and they had things like Hot Pants, all sorts of music videos that they did that were
were extremely popular, by the way, not only with our fans, but outside of our fan base, actually.
The emphasis on crafting in the game also unlocked all of this social play.
You know, the player economy had bootstrapped up from nothing because there wasn't real loot.
But players during this time period bootstrapped it up
to the point where one third of all players were running a shop.
whether a bakeries and weaponsmiths and architects and whatever. So we hadn't put any NPC shopkeepers
in the game at all and there were 15,000 of them per server. Probably more than we would have put
in by hand had we been doing it. So the community during this time period was amazing and yet
we were still going to hit a wall.
Yeah, so I mean, basically, if you see this, it's, you know, we promised a Star Wars experience,
but we delivered a sandbox. And I think that when you think of Star Wars, you're talking about
fantasy of being a Jedi, or being on the other side, dark or light. And so that we did not provide
a very good game experience for player experience for and that really did hurt us.
I think later on they made a lot of fixes and a lot of changes towards that, but initially
not filling out that fantasy was really something that hurt us. And I think Raph could talk about
that right now. Go ahead, Raph. Yeah, it was super clear that in the first few months,
this here is basically a graph of how many players are quitting in the first month, second month,
third month, and so on across a variety of games.
and the blue line is Galaxies. And you can see that the early months, it actually held better.
But players started churning out at increasing rates the longer they had played the game
because there simply wasn't enough to do other than participate in the sandbox community.
What I'm saying here, content is king.
I always talk about heartbeat.
Heartbeat is the amount of content
you're able to deliver after live.
A lot of games, even games today,
have made that valuable mistake of being
on a content treadmill that is too difficult to tap into
and get content out to the players in a timely manner.
And when you do that, guess what happens?
People leave the game over time.
What is interesting to say is, if we
were to have that extra year, that extra six months,
we would have had a different situation in our game.
And I think we'd have time to clean up the bugs and get the content the way we wanted to get the content.
But you see, that didn't happen.
We had to play catch up.
And that was really, really difficult for us to do.
But one of the neat things about the survey is that 80 percent will return if we fixed it.
That was huge.
That's a huge positive note about what we did.
So, you know, people look back at this game, I think they remember the sandbox elements of the
game versus the fantasy elements of the game that they were filled. What happened was,
is people filled their fantasy of Star Wars and living in the Star Wars universe themselves.
So they became what they wanted to be in the Star Wars universe versus us dictating it to it.
Now, that's pretty cool. And I think that's probably why people really hold this game
to where it is today in their minds, because they were actually living their own fantasies
versus us creating one for them.
Yeah, in fact, our tagline for a while was the greatest story ever told in the Star Wars universe.
Yours, right? Remember that? I still like that tagline.
Yes.
We desperately tried adding content, but we don't even have the tools infrastructure to do it.
Right? Like, all of our work had gone into that system underpinning stuff, right?
It had not gone into making quest tools.
So it's just like pulling teeth to get simple things like a dungeon added to the game.
And this is still in the first six months of launch
that we're hitting these issues.
And we get told by marketing, you know what?
To do a new marketing push, we need Jedi in the game.
We want Jedi by Christmas.
And the decision is made to drop hints.
But if you remember, players just
needed to learn an arbitrary five skills out of the 612,
a random set for each of them.
As soon as we stopped dropping hints,
A few players said, oh, it's a skill, it's a skill, it's a skill.
And then they decided they knew the whole system
and set out to learn every single skill in the game,
one after the other.
Which meant the creature handlers started killing monsters.
The people who liked cooking started making spaceships.
The people who liked, you know, building houses
went on adventures and died to Krayt Dragons.
Everybody started playing the ways they didn't like.
because the idea of becoming a Jedi was so powerful. And the result was that our turn
rate went up more and we started losing players even faster.
One of the things that we did is a lot of us came from Wind Commander, so we knew about space flight,
we knew how to do space flight. One of the aspirational games that we were doing,
even with Privateer Aligned, was Sun Dog and Mule.
was the two taglines that we use as games of aspirational here.
SunDog gives us a presence of what it's like working on
multiple functions on a ship. So when we did the Millennium
Falcon experience in JTL, it was that you could be a pilot, you
could be a gunner, or you can be an engineer. And that's pretty
damn cool. And allows people to have multiple roles on a ship,
be and be able to switch them off. And so that
what I call Millennium Falcon Experience, was a cornerstone of JTL. But it was a very cool game
because you can fly Star Wars ships into combat and have fun doing it. JTL was a great expansion
in the sense that it allowed us, and I'd say 80% of the user base got it, but there was one
unfortunate thing. The unfortunate thing was it launched right when WoW launched.
Yeah, so wow brought the whole industry down, not just us, every
online game out there went down as soon as well went out. Wow was
like a huge succubus of players went over there and drove into
Wow. And it drove all our numbers down. But it didn't help
JTL JTL got us a very small bump.
Yeah, and it was such a good expansion, and yet it really suffered from this.
Now, Galaxies, of course, this is a graph of daily active users.
You can see where WoW hits the game. It actually hit all MMOs.
Galaxies suffered less than the level and class-based other MMOs that were out there at the time,
because the gameplay, the sandbox gameplay, wasn't on offer in WoW.
But it really was just a devastating, devastating blow.
And when combined with the increased churn ever since the Jedi holocrons,
it left the live team in a really challenging position and,
you know, trying to stop the bleeding.
And at this point, I had already moved off the team.
I'd been promoted up to Chief Creative Officer at Sony Online.
So I got to watch a lot of this from a distance
as the live team was working on, let's try a combat upgrade.
No, that didn't do enough.
Let's try modifying the grouping rules.
Let's adjust the PVP.
All in all, none of it was really moving the needle,
as you saw from the graph.
And so this fateful decision is made
to try a really big revamp.
that was known as the NGE.
At that particular time, I decided I did not want
to participate because I knew that you have a core loops
in the game that you built from scratch
and the players love and enjoy.
And if you change that core loop and make it more like WoW,
you will lose a large audience over time.
And I said, you can't do that in a game like this.
It's already been out.
You already have the inner and outer loops
already working in the game.
changing that would be devastating to your base and you'll never ever get it back.
And so I said, yep, I think that if you want to guys do that, that's not where I want to head.
And so at that time I did leave SOE and actually joined BioWare and formed BioWare Austin Studio.
Where ironically he ended up making another Star Wars MMO.
Yeah, I want to try it again.
My second thought.
So.
You know, I also didn't think this was a good idea.
Unfortunately, we were right.
It has gone down in history
as the most infamous video game patch ever made.
It made the New York Times.
All of that skill-based stuff was removed
in favor of classes.
The RPG combat came out in favor of action RPG
with clicky stuff.
You couldn't mix and match different skills
from different skill trees anymore.
Peaceful professions now became helpless in combat
because there were combat levels.
Jedi was a starter class,
and maybe the worst blow of all to a lot of people,
their pets, the pet system got turned off for a while
and all the pets were locked away in their data pad UI.
And you could see Fluffy locked in there and tap on them,
but you couldn't get them out anymore.
and players literally held funerals across the game for their pets.
It was just a disastrously bad reaction.
And it wasn't just the New York Times, it made the Washington Post,
it made the Christian Science Monitor.
And one of the weirdest things was suddenly seeing people say,
no wait, this was something different and unique.
We liked it after all.
And that was a bit of a, you know, I mean, we were wrestling with bad reviews and churn and all the rest, and yet we get reactions like this.
So that was an eye opening and shocking and really just depressing and distressing to the team. This was a very, very tough time period.
Yeah, go ahead. And if you look at the graph coming up.
Yeah.
It was.
I'm not sure there's much to say. It was brutal. We had projected out what the normal rate of
cancellation was. In the space of one month, we lost 25% of the active usables.
And it continued to bleed over time as well. Oh, yeah. It got worse over time. Players just
complained in droves. A refund had to be issued for the last expansion.
you know, there was a marketing push. We tried to get magazines to write nice things about the game.
They said, oh, it's worth a second look. Right? Well, that very same magazine,
Galaxies became the only game to win Coaster of the Year twice.
I, not exactly what you want on your resume, right? So, yeah, and it, oh.
Of course, the irony is that little review says no more do-overs, but that isn't what happened.
There was a do-over because there was a new era after that. Over the next six years,
the live team on Galaxy started to be composed of people who were players of Galaxy, who loved
the sandbox qualities, who loved what made it different and unique, the things that made it
not like WoW.
And over the next six years, they did this amazing job of putting all that sandbox stuff back in.
And we can only call out a couple of things that they did during that time period, partly because
neither of us were there, but we really want to give them props for the amazing job they did
in basically turning the game around and bringing it back to life.
They did some amazing things. They again...
The event system on there really helped
because they ran a lot of events.
We had real time.
We had people that we played as volunteers to run the events.
And they developed tools and added to the sandbox tool set
where players can actually do and create, as you see,
quests, a quest system.
And when they put that in, the live team put that in,
there were three main quests were created by players in one
month.
It was an amazing experience for the players.
Yeah, but despite all of their heroic efforts. December 15 2011, the game was nonetheless shut down the team was so devoted and dedicated that they.
launched atmospheric flight, the ability to take off with your X-Wing from the ground
and fly over the planets and from there go out into orbit and into space, kind of the Star Citizen
dream today. And they launched that even though the game was going to get shut down that month
because they just were that committed to delivering on the promise of what Star Wars galaxies could be.
And so they held this crazy giant party and people from all over the industry logged in.
Many of the game sites ran all-day live streams of the final days with all kinds of really weird
stuff happening, like giant Ewok battles in the middle of Mos Eisley and whatever, as players
just really cut loose and were given access to do whatever they wanted on the last final days.
And so it was a big farewell. But it wasn't the end. Because there was an afterlife.
The fans also worked on keeping it alive.
They started building emulators.
And today, there are dozens of Star Wars Galaxy's emulators
running.
These projects have been running on a volunteer basis
for years now.
And fans are not just keeping it alive, they're extending it.
Bespin just launched in Star Wars Galaxy's emulators
this month.
And to this day, across these fan run servers,
there's still thousands of active users.
If Galaxies were a title today, running on Steam,
it would have enough active users
to be in the top 100 online games on Steam, even now,
which is just a testament to the passion
and dedication of that community.
And, you know,
We know that, like I said, it had a very ridiculous short debt period, two years and nine months.
It had one of the worst launches ever, I'd have to say.
Terrible churn and almost no content.
And I will say it had the infamous patch of all time.
That's the NGE.
But still, people think of this game, even today, as an unbelievable masterpiece in their minds.
It's interesting.
It makes us...
I'm left with these weird feelings because it was so painful and so demoralizing.
And it's like its reputation has improved over time.
Because now people look back and say, look at the ambition, look at the things that were
tried.
It turns out people do want to, you know, be Uncle Owen and Aunt Beru. That used to be the
knock against it. And today, with the popularity of Animal Crossing and Stardew Valley and,
you know, all of these ways to play that are just living in an alternate world.
Somehow, the game that went from two coasters of the year,
Variety names it, you know,
number 10 best Star Wars game of all time.
And there's this massive cognitive dissonance, right?
Because the memory of the things that it did right,
it turns out that those ideas were really, really right.
They really were going to be the thing
that extended the game marketplace.
And a lot of those things wouldn't come to full fruition
until mobile gaming and casual gaming really,
blossomed, right? Today, people look back at the crafting system
and say that's the one to emulate. They look back and they
say lots of players want to live peaceful lives. You know, it
used to be that you had to mine everything by hand, the idea
that you could put down a mine and check back in later. That
was the basis of games like Farmville and all of the
Facebook games.
right? Some of these features that we put into Galaxies that were the oddball things
have turned out to have been incredibly important to the development of online games.
I mean, there's lots of things you think about Minecraft, where that came from, and all the
systems in Minecraft, you know, UO influenced, and I probably believe Star Wars Galaxies maybe
have influenced that as well, and Roblox today. It's an amazing amount of
stuff that we did back in 2003, we got laughed at, like dancing and musicians, the music position
skill in the game and things like that. But actually people have fond memories because,
like I said before, they created their own stories and lived in the Star Wars,
living in the Star Wars universe. And that was what made it special to them.
Yeah. And so one of my favorite stories, there is a musician named Porter Robinson.
and I'd urge all of you watching, you know, we avoided putting the music in here because we
don't want a YouTube takedown or anything, but go search for the song Goodbye to a World.
Porter is a really, really famous Grammy-nominated electronic musician, and his album Worlds is
considered a landmark in moving EDM in a more ambient, peaceful direction. And it turns out
that this landmark album
was inspired by his time as a player in Star Wars Galaxies and other MMOs that shut down.
And today, you know, whenever I hear that particular piece of music where this robot
voice is singing, I'll say goodbye soon. Even though it's the end of the world, you know,
don't blame yourself. It's not your fault. But, you know, in the end, this is about giving life
to a world that is your own.
And that's really what Galaxies was about in the end.
And so even though we can't play the song,
kind of like for you to all kind of play out this presentation,
go find that song and listen to the end
as the voice kind of dies off making weird modem noises.
Because that's the right way to play off Star Wars
Galaxies in the end as it heads off into its afterlife.
It really was a world for players.
a world of their own. Thank you. Thank you for joining us. We appreciate it.