Hello, this is the talk honoring the blade,
lethality and combat balance in Ghost of Tsushima.
This talk is going to talk a lot about how the Samurai fantasy impacted
our design decisions and our combat balance throughout the game.
But before we go into that, talk a little bit about myself.
My name is Theodore Fishman. I go by Ted.
I've been at Sucker Punch for 11 years.
I'm the lead combat designer there, and I've worked on systems
and combat design all the way through.
And of course, mostly on combat design on Ghost of Tsushima.
So before we get into the actual core design issues we ran into,
it's important to talk about the samurai fantasy.
Flash of steel, few quick strikes and the enemy is dead.
That is the fantasy of a samurai.
This is a trope instilled via samurai films, manga, anime, you name it.
We had to fulfill this trope.
But how does that translate into gameplay?
How do you balance a combat for a grounded game,
especially with character and player progression throughout the game?
where you can't have everything die too fast, but still feel lethal?
That is the core we needed to succeed at.
And we had features like standoffs,
and nailed that feeling of lethality and honoring that trope and fantasy.
But how combat is initiated was the main purpose of standoffs.
That didn't really go into the standard combat loop.
How do we bring this feeling of standoffs and match those expectations?
How do we honor the blade feeling lethal and sharp?
So let's kind of break down the core design problem.
We wanted satisfying player progression that included armor, charms, weapons, you name it.
And that had to be for 30 hours of gameplay.
For an open world game, players could go wherever they wanted,
they could go, you know, do content, whatever they wanted to.
So we need to have that be satisfying.
And
We had multiple difficulty modes, whether it be easy to hard and later lethal, which we added.
We also had to support a 2-4 player co-op mode for Bronze and up to Raid tier difficulties.
Plus, we had a variety of enemies to keep players interested and escalate challenge and difficulty throughout those enemies and feel it through the progression of the game.
And we're also an action game, you know, it has to feel fast paced, it has to be responsive,
you know, how do we get players to understand what's happening and read,
you know, like, oh, that felt meaningful, that felt like there was an impact on my decisions
and the choices I made for my builds, my armor, whatever it may be.
But the whole risk that's part of this is that things start to feel like sword sponges,
that HP inflation could, you know, spiral out of control.
specifically because of like, oh, I need to challenge a player and then this sword upgrade doesn't feel meaningful.
That could be a huge issue.
And this is one of the major issues we had to try to, you know, tackle.
So we had to escalate those challenges, we tried things, right?
So the first one was like, you know, standard RPG leveling, right?
Level differences, scale damage and damage to the player, damage to the enemy.
And also, you know, we showed health bars and show how the big difference of each sword strike didn't matter.
But this started to feel really gamey and frayed at the kind of realistic and grounded nature of our game.
And it also felt like your sword wasn't sharp.
And it only got kind of worse when we did the extreme case, you know, other RPGs do this, where you have skulls to show the difference between high and low hero to enemy levels.
It felt very artificial and we need to escalate in a different way.
What was even worse was that you can do this in an open world scenario
pretty easily if you just kind of travel outside the boundaries.
Originally, this was what we're looking for.
We're like, you know, you should do this mission and upgrade your armor
and your sword.
But this became kind of harmful to the fantasy.
And we've tried to go.
it, maybe literally, where we had a shield of HP around the like a low health of a
red health bar. So in this video we talk a little bit, show here a little bit
about like hey this orange barrier around the red health points keep them
like you know three to four hits to kill the guy but if you could break through
the shield.
We had weapon scaling and like to go through, you know, armor faster,
but it was really opaque and people had a hard time understanding
what was going on there.
And plus, even though it was done in other games, which is, you know,
a totally fine way to approach it,
it didn't feel like lethal or matching the fantasy we wanted for the samurai game.
So we tried it on multiple different things,
we did a lot of internal and external testing, and we wanted to see
what do players think, did this match their expectations and.
A lot of them was not what we wanted to hear.
Like, oh, it felt like I was hanging with a foam bat.
Is this a pool noodle?
I don't know.
But the worst case is it really harmed the character fantasy we were going for.
We wanted them to feel like a samurai, and this was not honoring that.
So what could we do to really make sure we honor that?
A crisp idea, like what contract do we have with the player?
This lethality contract, you know, what does it mean to be a samurai?
And we talked about the standoffs being core to that feeling of the blade is sharp.
How do we bring that to the rest of combat?
As I was saying earlier, sword combat must be lethal.
And there's other elements of combat, too.
You know, when headshots and assassinations also had to kill
and made sense to the players, like, oh, if I use an arrow
and hit them in the head, they should die.
We had to be a lot more cognizant of what it meant to players' expectations
of this fantasy.
And so we had to be a lot more harder on our limits of our HP,
you know, number of hits to kill without upgrades had to be within a shorter band.
And even for our difficulty scaling, we can say, no, no, no, we need to keep it lower.
We need to keep it so that doesn't inflate even on hard, et cetera.
There are other ways to do this,
which I'll talk about in a minute.
And there's no RPG enemy levels.
Part of this was HP inflation, but most of it was just harming the reality
of the game, like we've been we were presenting this as a grounded samurai game.
Those RPG levels just didn't fit.
And that sounds great.
You know, OK, I'll just strip it all away. No problem. Right.
Now, we need to have some way to provide challenge and escalation.
Have your, you know, armor and swords feel meaningful.
If they didn't, you know, how do we how do we make sure the players
keep engaged with, you know, reward loops or, you know,
the combat loop that we're trying to provide?
So, you know, we had to start reevaluating what we were doing and say,
well, maybe we need to push on other angles, specifically
talking about being more defensive for enemies to protect a low HP.
We're pushing down the.
number of hits to kill to like maybe four or five, maybe three in some cases.
But we need to have them to block and parry, you know, pretty standard stuff.
But we just had we may have gone a little bit too far.
We tried to say, OK, no, they have to be really on their toes
and have them block and parry the hero.
And they're like, oh, no, no, no, no.
It just was too far.
It was too, too frustrating for players.
But at the same time, though, you know, like.
them, but it became the predominant strategy. We needed to have a way to have the players
break through those defenses and still feel like a samurai in an awesome way.
So pushing on going on the offensive was a big part of this.
Like, you know, we added a stagger meter, a pretty standard portion of melee
combat games nowadays.
But we try to do it in a little bit different of a way.
Not all attacks did stagger damage.
Light attacks were faster and heavy attacks did that stagger damage.
But they also were the same amount.
We didn't want one attack to be overly used to the other.
We're like, oh, you only heavy attack because it just does more damage.
And it also really pushed us for helping an enemy variety, like that heavy shield guy in the upper right,
like he could slow you down so other enemies would come in, like that spear on the upper left.
is a huge element of our encounter design and how we actually got an enemy variety.
It's like a speed of stagger can change how you approach these enemies,
especially with the speed of heavy attacks.
But it also lets us start to expand what other things a player could do.
And that led us to open the door to stances.
If those who know how our stance system works, essentially you match.
a stance to a specific enemy type.
So that shieldman in the upper right, you use shield stance or water stance for our game.
And it, you know, breaks through to the defenses faster, but not additional damage.
As I said before, because speed of stagger was a huge element of our encounter composition and design,
enemy aggression and how fast people attack, if you could break them faster, that was a huge deal.
And to be clear, this is not a hard solve.
You know, unaligned attacks would get reversed or dodged,
but it wasn't the only... you didn't have to do it.
However, it was on Fantasy and on-brand.
It felt really cool to break through an enemy's defense using the right stance.
And it was definitely part of that Samurai Fantasy stances.
But the reason not to make it a hard solve is...
completely different order, they may not have the stance or they're like you know
maybe they're not skilled enough, whatever it may be, it's okay not to
require it. They could get around it and they still felt smart and like
got around his defenses and still killed him. That being said, this is a great
baseline. We had to go from, expand from here. We had to escalate challenge for
the enemies. How are we gonna do that?
Well
A lot of it was actually mirroring, like mirroring the lethality of the hero,
you know, less hits to kill to the other direction.
Enemies have to start to be more lethal.
And we had an injective variety, as I said earlier on the first slides.
You know, weapon usage, as I just said, and counter composition
played into that, that includes their aggression, their speed
and what movesets have to challenge them with new types of attacks,
including the unblockable and parable attacks.
But also, of course, increased enemy damage.
That's that lethality I'm referring to where they push back on you.
But at the same time, we still had to increase HP, but carefully.
You know, we had to have sword upgrades feel meaningful.
And a lot of that came down also to character art,
where you could see the difference, like, oh, he's more armored.
That justifies it some more.
But that doesn't mean we went out of control like a huge amount.
We had to really be mindful of this.
So a good example of those, the worst case scenario is you can encounter the far right guy before any upgrades.
This is the worst case scenario. We still would have like maybe 10 to 12 hits to kill on that guy. That could be bad.
But we had some other mechanisms in our world that actually really helped us out.
So in our actual world, we actually broke it down into kind of like prefectures.
Each area had a different tier of enemies.
So you can see on this map here all the different colors.
A little bit harder to look at a little bit, but the white areas are kind of like the intro
enemies and then you have like the orange, blue, red and green as they escalate through the island.
And so you start down here in the lower portion of the island and it's actually blocked off
to the upper part.
There's a choke point right at the start at the tip of the blue part of the south.
And that actually helped us say you can't encounter the green guys at the top.
You have to, you know, get past that story checkpoint. You have to get some upgrades.
So that mitigated the upper band it could get up into, which is what we're really trying to avoid.
And it also helped us a little bit with balance, trying to make sure that you didn't over level.
I'll talk about that more. We didn't completely solve that, but it did help us kind of say,
oh yeah, this is as far as you could go for now.
So.
With all that in mind, you know, like, what about, like, how do we present this information?
How do we show number of hits to kill?
Now, we showed this earlier with the UI.
There's a lot of layers in the early, obviously, debugging versions of this,
but it actually just really...
less being more. A big portion of our art direction was minimal UI.
And also it was into our benefit, the comment and speed for Ghost is actually
pretty fast and a lot can happen and all this UI flying everywhere actually made
it harder. Good news we got rid of the armor points which are in some of these
earlier ones.
But we still need to show progress against other stuff.
Like you can see the stagger bar, which is the purple in the upper left,
got turned into this kind of arced bar.
A little lighter weight, easier to see.
We needed to show progress,
but we also didn't really need to show hit points
because those hits that killed were low.
We have a low health indicator,
but it was just there to say, oh, you're almost there.
That was huge and important to us
to make sure that you still had showed progress for that,
but we didn't need to have all that information.
And surprisingly, players were more accepting of slightly more hits with less information.
It's for like the lower band. So if you're like five or six hits, you might not need to show
anything. Of course, if you're higher, we might have to show something which I'll talk about in
a bit. But essentially, we were kind of surprised that people were willing to accept more hits if
there was less UI to show it, especially when it's lower hit points.
So this kind of gets into this interesting question of design by feel or like how do we
data use data to confirm it. Well we have the kind of standard hits to kill chart a lot of games have
where it's like oh yeah this is the number of hits to kill a target based on these progression
values. We needed to kind of see what our design sense was and what expectations players had and
it's like okay well this is six hits to kill if you have these upgrades how does that feel
when we test that and so we kind of charted it all out.
But it's also kind of interesting what the bans are, you know, we don't, players could, as I said
before, go anywhere they want in an open world game. They could, you know, complete some content,
not others. How do we make it sure what is the acceptable range, if you will, between value?
Is it four to six hits at this point in the game? Do they have certain charms and upgrades?
These are all questions we all factored into our sheets.
including difficulty balancing, like to the hero, as I said earlier, for enemies,
we increase damage on different difficulties, but we never increase their HP or their stagger values
because stagger had similar implications to HP where if it was too high players would get frustrated
and like, oh this guy just feels like a wall.
But we can push all the other angles,
so I said damage output, aggression,
moveset timing for parry and dodge, huge part of that.
We charted those out in similar things
where you number hits to kill the hero
and matching those expectations for the higher difficulties.
Talking about higher difficulties,
we actually added another post-launch experiment
initially called lethal difficulty.
We really wanted to push something
that was not just harder.
It was something that felt maximally lethal.
before of like, slash slash, someone's dead, or you could be dead instantly.
It ended up being harder, and we, you know, we pushed a lot of the stuff to the extremes,
but you know, we actually increased the damage of the player to make sure that when you're
taking so much, you can die in two hits, that they would also go down in one to two hits.
That felt, felt right.
We were trying to do something different, but it did narrow our progression band, and
we're like, okay, we want to try this more kind of role-playing, more fantasy-fulfilling
difficulty mode.
But it's OK if that progression player doesn't feel as impactful necessarily,
because this was actually more successful than we thought it was going to be.
You know, it hit the fantasy the way you want to.
It felt like this untapped potential.
And people really started replaying portions of the content
more than we expected in a really great way.
And especially for the challenging encounters like our duels,
people are like, I want a no hit run and I want to make sure that I do it perfectly.
It was just so great to see the community engage with that
and also be part of that, say, oh, yeah, this is what I expected.
So with all those things in mind, like how do we confirm all those, you know,
the difficulty modes, the hits to kill?
How do we know we're in the right band, those ranges I talked about earlier?
Well, we had to have certain player models and play testing, as I said before,
I keep saying play testing all the time, because it's really important.
But.
It's, we needed to make sure that we hit those progression targets for each of the difficulties
and those player types. So we had three player types. We had the linear, average, and wide players,
how they played the game. It's trying to match, you know, how much of the open world content that
they had done. Linear is just going through the main story. Average is doing kind of a mixture
of a little bit of content, some aside stuff, and wide goes as wide as possible.
sword level, HP, like where they were when they did onsen, armor, etc.
And see where they landed.
And if that matched their expectation for that band of hits to kill.
In the upper right you can see a chart of five players who finished the game
and we can consider them the average band.
And what's really great about looking at that and seeing where they were
and how much content they had completed over time,
we can ask them questions.
but more like, oh yeah, did you feel like your upgrades mattered?
Did you feel like you were fulfilling the samurai fantasy in this way?
Did you feel kind of like that journey?
Which is really great because we target this specifically.
But there are parts where we had to bend the rules, you know, like not
this is not a one size fits all solution, you know,
maybe painfully obvious to you, but duels are boss fights.
And we thought, oh, we can apply the same kind of lethality
feeling to this experience. But.
You know, if it's over in seconds, you know, that's not what players wanted.
You know, we we are heavily inspired by Samurai films.
But even though those battles over in seconds, it didn't exactly match that.
So what players wanted was like a skill challenge.
They wanted a longer fight.
more defensive, more agile, and they wanted to make sure that it felt like it was a longer,
you know, longer experience. And kind of the same as Samurai Cinema, it's kind of a reversal of
expectations. So we kind of had to flip it around and say, okay, hits to kill have to be higher,
we have to add a health bar back, which actually kind of helped because it made it feel more like
an epic boss fight, which is the point.
And we had it kind of subdivided a little bit with, you know,
Clash of the Sword to say, okay, this is not too long.
Yeah, this is a lot more hits, but, you know,
each section feels appropriately length.
So kind of like players are like, okay, this doesn't feel like a slog.
So it was an interesting thing because we had to add the health bar,
not just because it feels epic,
but to understand when it hits a killer higher,
we had to add a health bar to say, oh, am I making progress?
As I said before in the UI slide,
we condensed it down to like, you know, maybe.
In this case, players wanted to know how far they were doing,
how they're doing, it's long enough.
However, you know, still there were some issues
with feeling too short or too long,
and we iterate a lot on this in development
if we get the right feeling for our duels.
Another element of where we had to bend the rules
was our multiplayer mode.
So Legends mode is a two to four player co-op experience.
And there's a lot of realities in multiplayer that we kind of had to kind of accept.
And that is four versus one or even two versus one target.
Enemies go down fast.
And if HP is too low, it's going to be like they can't get any attacks out.
They don't. That's the go to solution for everything.
It's not what we were.
We couldn't really do the same thing as before, especially too,
because we also had more of a gear scaling, kind of like power scaling,
gear power calculation that would scale a little bit
between incoming and outcoming damage.
Plus, some of the player abilities are more magical in nature and like, you know, big
area of effect attacks and damage.
We couldn't just do the same thing as before.
It gets even more applicable because supernatural enemies were a big part of this, you know,
the Oni.
And as a result, it was a situation where it felt like they're mini bosses
and they had their own abilities and magic and buffs like healing nearby enemies
or, you know, regenerating or whatever it may be.
And it was a situation where like, OK, we need a way to show this to the player.
We had to show UI again, especially because, as I said,
on the duel slide, the hits to kill is much higher.
We had to show that progress.
And it just it was a completely different expectation for our players.
And as I said before, especially with these Oni enemies,
we wanted them to live longer and be more of a threat to players.
So, some final problems.
This was a great push for us towards Samurai Fantasy,
but there were some issues we ran into.
One of them was over-leveling.
So, as I said before, the wide player,
the person we did it for our player models,
they went wider than expected in our...
never really mirrored the same thing.
So you could do almost all the content
in this lower portion of Tsushima, which is Zuhara,
they would do almost all of it.
And then they would just start steamrolling their way
through the rest of the content.
Well, part of this was actually acceptable for us
on the player journey, where, oh, I'm becoming the ghost,
I have new weapons, new ways to defeat enemies.
And it's like, okay,
it's okay to be a little bit overpowered.
Not perfect, there's a place
we could have done balancing here.
We tried to use that choke point, as I mentioned earlier,
to kind of like hit a cap.
But definitely we're like, OK, we thought we had a correct range,
but we were a little bit off there. Definitely a place to improve for.
Another part of this is damage reactions.
We talked a little bit about this in the armor point slide.
I know it was kind of confusing whether you're doing damage or not.
This still applied in places for us, like when you have sparks versus blood,
is what we said a lot like, oh, if blood comes out, they're taking damage.
Especially like we have a similar stuff from like
to find a game terminology like super armor.
Those will show sparks because they.
they're not being interrupted and they're going to come on through.
But sometimes players would have a hard time reading that,
especially because their combat speed was very fast.
That kind of combat feedback, even with sound effects and haptics and so forth,
we didn't quite nail that feeling.
It was not exactly what, you know, we didn't get a nail on a knockout out of the park.
But, as I said before, way bigger improvement over our previous iterations
on giving feedback to the player on damage reactions,
but definitely room for improvement.
So last thoughts and takeaways just for us and when working through this problem,
you know, core design decisions and tuning should really be as much as possible
support the character fantasy core system and core combat.
Stuff like this has a huge impact on the play experience
and making sure that you can target say, oh, no, no, no,
we don't want to ruin that or undermine it.
It's easy to get caught into the swirl saying, oh, this system will help here.
Or in my or another game, just like similar,
we might have to go back to the drawing board a little bit.
especially for us, I'm talking about for lethality, you know, that goes both ways,
that, you know, there's an expectation for that, and there's a lot of learnings for us on that angle.
And that enemy defensive behavior is critical, like the stagger, the blocking, the dodging.
You know, these are these are core combat mechanics are in a lot of games, too,
but really emphasizing that, especially for protecting low HP.
But in turn, of course, making sure player verbs and player attacks
and actions can counter and counter that gameplay.
You know, stances for us was a big part of that.
Make sure that was a solid part of the character fantasy, as I mentioned a second ago.
And trust your design intuition on what does it feel like?
This is a lot of portions of this are designed by feel.
And it's important to make sure that you understand that,
hey, this isn't like a perfect number that I need to get a
certain sense of how it's going to be. But of course, you got to
verify with playtesting. It's always good to playtest as much
as possible and verify without your own confirmation bias of
how you play it yourself a million times, which you should.
Difficulty balancing escalation and progression should not
require major HP inflation. It would be best to make sure you try to avoid it,
especially for, in our case, this character fantasy.
And a huge element is just making sure to push all the other knobs you've got.
Aggression, moveset, timing, damage output, all these are really, really, really core.
But if you're going to increase HP, which we had to as well,
do it carefully. Do it thoughtfully and with intention.
It is okay to do so like we did before with character art,
whether it be in our Legends mode or whatever it may be.
Those are all important elements to consider,
but do it in a way that you're mindful about it.
So I really hope you enjoyed our kind of a quick look
at how we tackle lethality within Ghost of Tsushima
and its impact on combat balance.
It was a rollercoaster and a ride,
but we felt like we hit land on a pretty good solution.
If you want to know more information at GDC 2021
about Ghost of Tsushima specifically,
There's another combat talk here at GDC from our studio head, Chris Zimmerman.
He goes into more of the depth about the mechanics of combat, more like how we built them exactly
and through the years of trying to work on this game.
And if you're interested in that, just make sure you check it out.
And yeah, it's a great talk.
And lastly, we're hiring. If you like combat things, and if you are looking to work in combat design, we are hiring a combat designer.
This is the kind of problems we try to tackle and what we try to do. And yeah, just apply below if you can, and otherwise, thank you for your time.