Hello, everyone.
Welcome to the first talk of the board game track.
And this is the first year that GDC is doing board games.
So thank you for being here.
I am Rob Davia, this is Matt Leacock,
and we are here to talk about Pandemic Legacy.
If that's not what you meant to hear,
you're in the wrong room.
Oh, sorry, I'm not supposed to wander past here
and stay on camera.
You're gonna fall off.
Okay.
Before we begin, I'm just wondering,
or we're just wondering, it's hard to see with the glare,
how many people have played at least some of Pandemic Legacy?
Whoa, okay, how many people played all of it?
All right, get on it, the rest of you.
Who has not played it?
Just so I know it's all the people who haven't,
but I just show hands.
Okay, we will not be largely and mostly spoiling anything
in Pandemic Legacy,
because it is a board game with spoilers.
We will talk elliptically about various things.
So if you've played,
you'll understand what we're talking about.
And if you haven't,
if you do choose to play and you get to it,
you'll say, oh, that's what they were talking about.
Anything else for you know, I think it's I think it's a perfect start.
So.
Here we are there's pandemic legacy this came out in October of 2015.
And represented a combination of 2 different things.
It's based on a legacy game I done in a pandemic that Matt did.
And here's what we're going to be doing today.
Right, so we're not going to read all this slide here, but
we will tell you we're going to start out with our origin
stories, which of course are the most interesting part of
any story.
And then the rest of the cliched titles that you see up above.
So, all right, a little background on us.
Here's our origin stories.
So I'm Matt Leacock.
I'm a former user experience designer.
I've been a designer of one type or another for most of my
professional career.
I worked in the Bay Area for about 16 years in Bay Area
companies like Yahoo and AOL, Netscape.
About two and a half years ago, I left that.
I left high tech full time to go full time
into board game design, and these are some of the games
that I've designed in the meantime.
That's largely due to the success of Pandemic.
So I know you raised your hands for Pandemic Legacy, but
how many of you played Pandemic, the base game?
OK, great.
So I'm not going to explain to you how this game works.
It's a cooperative game.
You fight disease and so on.
Yeah, I won't belabor that point too much.
And that never gets old, by the way.
I just love seeing that.
That's how you get to leave your job and do it full time.
Yeah.
I'm Rob Davio. I have been a professional board game designer since 1998,
when I tumbled into a job at Hasbro Parker Brothers Milton Bradley,
just in time to do all these great games for Star Wars Episode I.
Part of my job in May 1999 was going to go see The Phantom Menace with a notebook so I could write trivial pursuit questions.
And let me tell you, after seeing that five days in a row, the excitement of seeing Star Wars for work really wore off.
These are some of the games that I have done over the years.
I've done a lot of Risk games, did work on Betrayal at House on the Hill that I'm happy with.
There's other games on there, kids games and things that I haven't done.
I've done about 80 games maybe.
that have been published.
But in 2011, I did a game called Risk Legacy.
Who has played Risk Legacy here?
OK.
Some?
So I'll just give a little brief thing.
The whole point of a legacy game is that,
and I'm giving a whole talk tomorrow
to do a deep dive of legacy games in general,
but top level here is.
Two parts, some of the actions you take in one game
permanently carry over to future games.
So everyone's game starts out in the same place
and then heads in a different direction.
This involves stickers, this involves markers,
this involves the dramatic ripping up of cards,
which is done infrequently, but the thing everyone knows
because it's such a social taboo.
And the second part, as you can see from the envelopes
that are on the inside of that box up there,
new content is delivered when you play.
It's like having expansions in the box,
but instead of just opening it
whenever you open it narratively
for either achieving something.
So I had done this and Matt had done Pandemic.
And then in 2013, he got in touch with me
and asked if we wanted to do Pandemic Legacy.
Yeah, I have been working with Z-Man to that point.
We were trying to figure out how to develop out Pandemic
into kind of a franchise.
So we battled around a lot of ideas.
You know, maybe we could do Pandemic a dice game.
Maybe we could do Pandemic the card game.
And then we said, hey, how about Panamec the Legacy game?
And we just kind of laughed.
I was really intimidated by the idea.
I'm not sure if it was because I was working full time
or the whole idea of a Panamec Legacy
was just too overwhelming or intimidating,
but I never really seriously considered it at all
until maybe, I don't know, six months later,
I was sketching in a notebook
and jotting down different ideas for twists and turns
and how something like that might work.
And I was just hooked.
I needed to go a little bit below the surface
and proceeded to try to figure out
how to talk to Mr. Daviau here
and managed to get his contact information through Z-Man
and send him a quick note.
Rob, you might want to mention where you're at at the time.
So I sent you this note and basically saying,
hey, what do you think, pandemic legacy?
Is that gonna work for you?
Yeah, and I wrote back yes in like a hundred point type because I just started my own company and was looking for any sort of work.
Luckily, I said yes to this one.
Yeah, we've been working together ever since on Legacy Games.
No, and I and we had a lot of a lot of questions a lot of design questions
We're getting basically take you through over the next half hour or so half hour 40 minutes
Why did we made the decisions we did?
What worked which luckily was most of it? What didn't work? There were a few things that didn't
And some of the learnings that we had about how to make this project this big in the board game space.
But really when we sat down in September of 2013 and then when we did it again two years later to start season two, it's pretty much that.
It's a lot of unknowns. We both made board games.
And so we basically kind of just sat down and said like, well, what are some key things that make a legacy game?
Because at that point, there have been exactly one.
And so we sort of pulled it apart
and we realized that there were,
there are two things that make a good fit
to turn a traditional board game into a legacy game.
And those are this, a simple core engine,
pandemic.
It's a great game and it actually has a relatively simple core of rules.
A lot of people play it who don't play a lot of games.
It's cooperative, so you can help each other if someone doesn't get the rules.
And as Matt's done a number of expansions that shows that you can build and stretch
and move it in different directions, which means as we designed a legacy game
and if it starts with basically pandemic, we can move it to go to different places
with rules we knew that would work.
And it also has a robust theme, which is more.
my thing, which is, OK, it's a world and there's diseases and everything's going
wrong.
Cool, I get that.
Everyone's going to get that.
It sounds like a fun way to torture players as you go through this experience.
It wasn't like trying to make a Legacy game out of Bridge or something or Uno.
There's a world there.
There's a good underpinning for a story.
So that's the first thing.
Like if for a Legacy game it's like it needs to start out relatively simple and then
build on top of it, and have a story that builds on top.
And if you go back and forth,
because when we design, we will get stuck on the rules
and the mechanisms, and then we'll figure out
what the story is, or we'll figure out the story,
and then get stuck, and then go back and forth.
And really, when we design,
there's a lot of back and forth between the two.
So with Mr. Risk Roll a Lot of Dice,
Star Wars Trivial Pursuit Storyteller,
and Clean Euro Guy, we were hoping for this combination.
Smooth chocolate and peanut butter.
Delicious, right?
There was a very big fear
that we were gonna end up with that.
I just love how that glistens.
I have no idea.
Please get that slide off.
Matt has weirded out every time we practice.
Okay.
First question.
Yeah.
So I mean, the big question is, how do we do that?
How do we string 20 games in a row and make
them kind of work together?
There were a lot of unanswered questions about
how to structure it.
No one had done a cooperative legacy game before.
And so we looked at a number of different options.
This first option.
Well, the first option is doing what I did in Risk Legacy.
So in Risk Legacy, players play games.
And there's a number of envelopes with
triggers on them.
in the sense of it tells you when to open it.
And if you remember from the box or if you played,
it opens up and the box stays open like a pizza lid open
because that's supposed to remind you
of things that are available.
So if you're.
like playing and then you see it you're like I want to go for that.
I get into this in detail tomorrow I really underestimated what a draw that
was I was just like taunting them with Christmas presents right to to go for.
But what you end up with is you end up something where you have the players in
the middle in control and then each blue circle represents like a new story bit a
new twist or turn where new rules are brought in and sometimes you have to go
through a darker circle to get to the lighter circle and then when you're done
there's kind of like just an ending off to the side like oh hey you've opened
everything it's done.
And that worked in Risk, but Risk Legacy is very sandbox play.
It's very tongue-in-cheek almost.
I mean, it's like a comic book tropey stuff in there.
Like, you shouldn't play it and feel like, wow,
that's a really tightly written story.
It's not. Like, it was more trying to figure out how
to make the legacy idea work.
So, we thought with this that that could work,
and that was one option.
But after talking about it for a while, we wanted something
that was a little bit more.
like linear, like where one thing leads to another in a more logical story path.
Right, so one of the things we explored was branching.
We have a story path where certain players would branch
off into one fork, and other players would branch off into
another fork.
And we kept running into problems.
This is probably no surprise to a lot of you.
I mean, that first branch, for example, if you hit that and
you end early, you feel like you've broken your game.
You've only gotten half the value out of it.
And then us as content providers, as we're writing
all this stuff, the thought that a huge percentage of the
game is not going to be seen by a lot of the people.
And a lot of the packages would go unopened, didn't quite resonate well.
And we were having difficulty coming up with a story.
And the complexity of the product was kind of overwhelming.
So we abandoned this one pretty early.
Yeah, and then we stumbled upon what we thought was a pretty clever way of telling a story.
And we—it's that.
Yeah.
And that had a lot of promise in it.
And we felt we could do something with that model.
I don't know if anyone's tried that before.
Yeah.
By doing that, there's a lot of concern.
with these legacy games of it being consumable,
of it ending, of not seeing all the content,
of getting your money's worth.
And so by getting away from branching and by doing this,
we could allow people to see almost all of the content,
but in slightly different ways.
So group A might make certain decisions
that let them deviate from the path,
and then we kind of pull them back,
and it goes back and forth.
So it's one continual road where you take
this little meandering journey through it,
and then group two.
you know, would do that. So at the end when they talked about their experiences, they all basically had the same experience
but made different choices along the way.
So it felt a little different and that gave us a lot of narrative control to try to tell a story and also to figure
out when we were building rules,
okay, like A happens and then B happens and then C happens and but you know, there might be gaps in between
but it let us have more control when building it. And that turned into
Yeah, the trick then was trying to figure out how to
actually enroll that in the game.
How do you do that when typically you take the game
off the shelf, you play it, and then you put it back on
the shelf, and the next time you take it out again, it's
the same game.
How do we unveil this new material?
And we came up with this concept of a legacy deck.
which basically you go through from top to bottom.
You start on this big stop card, which is inspired by the SAT test,
you know, put your pencils down.
And then you just flip through the cards one at a time
and we could gradually unveil new rules and new characters
and so on and other surprises as the game progressed forward.
Yeah, it also leads to the very fun rule in the rule book saying
if you drop it on the floor.
Get someone who's not playing the game to put it back together in order which might be the first time that's been written in
a board game rulebook
So we had that and we're like, okay that that's gonna work
That's gonna deliver things in the order that we want them to but how many games how many games?
Do people want to commit to and this is an interesting sort of
like
Product proposition question rather than a game design question. It's like if we give you a hundred one-hour games boy
We're promising a lot of content and no one will finish
Like, it just will wear out its welcome.
If we give you six amazing games,
many people will finish and then complain
that they weren't enough.
So there was a big question.
When I had done Risk Legacy,
I had just randomly picked 15 games.
Well, not randomly, I gave it some thought.
That turned out to be a pretty good number.
It's enough that you feel like it's money's worth,
but not so much that you can't get people back together.
And so we started talking about 12 to 15.
Yeah, 15 seemed like a little too much to me.
Although that's what actually 15 is pretty much where
it netted out at the end.
But we were like, how about 12, which
led to the other cunning idea that 12 is a number that you
can put on a timeline.
So we added the.
basically divided it into months.
And then we thought, okay, there's a lot of things
you're not gonna know in this game.
There's a lot of things that are uncertain,
but you're going to know that February comes after January.
And you're gonna know that you're going to play
till December, so you have this comforting feeling
of there are going to be 12 experiences in the game.
They logically follow each other,
and it's not like you get to game eight
and we say, okay, now it's over.
right, you know when it ends from the very beginning and that gives you a little bit of
peace of mind because one of the things that we like to do is not give you peace of mind while
you're playing this and so we had to make sure there were certain areas where you knew that like
you knew what was happening like you had a lay of the land.
So one of the tricks then is how do you balance this? One of the things with Risk Legacy is it's
a competitive game so if one player starts to get far ahead the other players can kind of serve as
a check.
We were doing a cooperative game that changed over time.
And so the big fear that I had was that players would start
to lose, and then because they lost and the world got worse,
they would continue to lose at a faster rate.
You'd get this positive feedback loop, and things
would spiral out of control.
And then you'd throw the game out because
you're so frustrated.
So we needed to figure out ways to put negative feedback
loops into the game.
And the first one we worked on was
One that plays off of these event cards.
Pandemic and Pandemic Legacy ship with event cards.
And they're these special superpower cards you can play
out of phase.
And they're good for two reasons.
One, they give you a special power.
And the second thing is they kind of pad out the player
deck, which is the clock for the game.
And when the deck runs out, you lose the game.
So these are pretty valuable.
So we start the players off with a certain number of them.
And we decided that if players continue to win, we can pull
some of those back, basically give them a handicap.
And if they lose, we can give them more.
And we needed to come up with some sort of rationalization
or story reason for this.
And so we came up with the notion of funding.
Basically, if you win a game.
The powers that be determine, of course, that you're doing
so well that we're going to cut back your funding and you
get fewer cards.
But if you lose a game, this stuff needs to be contained,
and you get more budget.
So kind of a tongue-in-cheek way of basically modifying the
number of cards you get up and down.
Here's an example of a game calendar of people keeping
track of.
game after game and getting more cards as a result of losing or fewer as a result of winning.
What's funny is that actually came out of a playtest.
You can sit and we can talk to each other all day long and then you get into a playtest
and you come up with the idea that you never would have had playtesting.
And this was just an attempt to make my friends feel less bad.
They were playtesting and then they lost the game and they're like,
Oh, that's horrible. We were about to win and we lost.
you have more event cards, you have more funding.
Play again, please.
And they were like, that sounds great.
Consolation prize, yeah.
And then I get on my phone with Matt,
I'm like, okay, I think this worked.
Hold on, we just did something.
So that's work.
That became one of our main ways to keep everyone in the middle.
And the hope was that, you know, one group like this might be
between 0, 2, 4, and 6.
And then another group that wasn't as good might float
between like 6, 8, and 10, right?
That both of them are going up and down
within their comfort zone.
But they have two different comfort zones, so it scales
for different levels of play groups.
Another thing we learned, though, is that if you play
January and you lose, and then you play February and you lose,
and you play March and you lose, you might feel like
you're being dragged through the entire timeline, that you
can't really catch up.
You can't take advantage of what you've learned again.
So we actually broke each month into two pieces.
So if you win the game, you move on to the next month.
However, if you lose it, you get one more chance to play it again.
You can take advantage of all the learnings that you got through your mistakes.
So you've got this sort of like two-part month system, as it were, and that worked fairly
well.
If you lost, you got a consolation prize, you get additional funding, and you get one
more shot before moving on.
We didn't want to keep doing that, though.
If you kept losing and keep playing January over and over again, the game would quickly
become a grind and people would get really worn out and want to leave it on the shelf.
There was also the risk that because your funding goes up when you lose, and because
at the end of every game you get these two sort of permanent stickers or goodies that
make it easier, that we had to be really aware that it wasn't like, let's just tank six months
in a row and then become superheroes and then we can win.
like the back half of things so now that we've solved like
losing is okay and it's not going to lead to more losing with funding and
also
letting you repeat a month gives you a chance to like do better and maybe
get some more goodies because you played another game
we were in a position where maybe we had gone too far the other way
and now we weren't encouraging you to win
so that led to
these cards
yes it is when bonus cards essentially uh... positive incentives for winning
You shouldn't have to tell players that you should want to win.
But they're gamers, right?
They're going to look at it and go, hey, it's better to lose a few games in a row,
because then our funding will go up.
We'll get more event cards.
So we give them this carrot.
But then we quickly realized, well, if we tell them what the win bonus is,
they're going to min-max and go, oh, OK.
Well.
This bonus is not quite as good as the two event cards, so I
think we should still lose.
And then you feel bad, because you're kind of playing against
what the game's intent is.
So we solved that by putting a scratch material over it.
So now you really want to win, because you don't know what
you're going to miss if you don't.
And so that was our hidden carrot.
Yep, it's the fear of missing out.
If you lose, and you don't get to see it, and you rip it up,
and it goes away, and you never knew what happened, and
that's a really powerful incentive in legacy games, is
well, but I want to see what it is.
And so, yeah, and they're all a little different,
and they all can't be so good that, again,
it leads to winning leading to more winning,
but it has to be good enough that you felt
like you earned it when you scratched it off.
It's a lot of psychology that we discovered in this,
and we're gonna get into that, you know,
not in this next section, but the-
Second half of the talk, yeah?
Yeah, second half of the talk.
So now we had some of our sort of mechanisms in place.
It was going to be 12 to 24 games.
It was going to be an average of about 18.
And it turns out it's 15 to 18 games,
that you win more often than you lose.
It's not a 50-50 win ratio.
So you end up repeating a couple months.
And if you lose both parts of a month,
which happens to people,
it feels like a particular low point
or a downbeat as we'll get to in a second.
So now we had to go flip over to the other side
we talked about, which is,
well, how do we tell a story with it?
So we can just keep throwing like cards
and numbers and math and actions at you.
But ultimately we want to tell a story.
And when we were going back to prepare this,
we went and realized out of the entire game,
The entire plot of the game is told in 23 cards,
some of which aren't even filled.
So we had to basically find a way
to make a lot of things familiar
so that the story was something
that just kind of filled in the blanks.
Like here's the next thing you go, of course, right?
Of course that happened.
Of course that character shows up right now.
And that relies on some using a lot of familiarity
with genres.
And so we sat down and this movie was out
around the time we were working on it.
And we're like, yeah, that's kind of it.
It's kind of like a 70s movie, but redone into a modern movie.
And it's an action thriller.
And it's got a little bit of, you know,
it's got some action scenes and a little bit
of character building.
And then that led to our other huge insight,
which is movies have three acts.
Now I know we're blowing your mind with this timeline
and this three act structure, but stay with us.
It'll make sense.
First the linear plot, now the three act structure, yeah.
So we're kind of like, wow, we can really just kind of,
kind of literally craft this into three acts.
Act one, you do this.
Act two, you do this.
Act three, you do this.
Neither of us have ever studied screenwriting.
So what we're about to say may be horribly wrong
if you have said it.
Or terribly obvious.
Like it's one of the two.
But we basically, we read some books,
and we kind of thought about it.
And it did a little bit of light research.
And so we kind of said, wow, we've got act one, act two,
act three.
And then we had both read a book.
I'll let you talk.
Yeah, yeah.
Well, I had read Hamlet's Hit Points by Robin Laws.
And he goes into great detail about beats,
these moments that provide moments of uplift or down.
uh... down left uh...
uh... that modulate uh... people's emotions uh...
sir like this the moment by moment uh...
how a game, how a screenplay, how music, how any of these
things kind of play out.
And he came up with a whole vocabulary of these things.
Most of them are procedural.
An upbeat that's a procedural beat kind of moves your
protagonist toward his goal, and everybody feels better.
But then you can also have downbeats that move the
protagonist away from their goal.
There's dramatic ones, which are more of the protagonist's
internal struggle.
But there's other ones that are less.
less obvious or less obvious to me like things like building anticipation
gives you a downbeat because it creates a lot of tension in a game
and then you have reveals which are upbeats and a lot of this stuff mapped
really well into you know the hidden things in these
legacy games and then the reveals that you get later
and so we started playing with this vocabulary first at a very micro level
looking at all the different moment by moment
elements of a pandemic game per se so you've got things like
hey we discovered a cure that's a that's a great upbeater everybody's happy about
that
Or, oh, an epidemic came out, and things are getting really,
really bad, and you have a downbeat.
You can kind of telescope out and apply these things to the
act structure.
Right.
So the first thing we did is we just basically said, OK,
things have to suck at the end of Act I and Act II.
Basically, Luke's aunt and uncle have to die, and then
Obi-Wan has to die.
So we kind of basically wanted to have these moments.
So if you have played this game, and you have played
April and September, there you go.
I have had people come up to me at conventions who I don't know get uncomfortably close and just go September
Walk away I
Take it really as a badge of honor
which then means that we have to build you up
to have an upbeat beforehand,
and then this isn't an exact mapping,
but we spent a lot of time when we were discussing like,
well, this is kind of an upbeat or this is a downbeat,
or we just introduced like problem, problem, problem,
people are gonna get despondent,
so maybe we should back up and do problem,
partial solution problem.
How much do we introduce at the beginning of a game?
How much do you introduce at the end of a game?
Because if you finish February,
And the next thing you do is March.
Anything that happens after February and before March
is sort of in the same place, right?
It's gonna happen before your next game,
but if you do it at the end of February,
you're finishing up your game,
and we give you something then, it's like a cliffhanger.
that you're going to live with until you decide to start March.
And sometimes it's right away, where if we do it at the beginning of March,
you have no time to process it.
Like the game started, and you're sitting down to play,
and you're like, oh, here's some new information.
And it feels like you're off and running.
And it's a subtle difference, but sometimes we've
found with our playtest groups that moving them from one to the other
provokes different upbeats or downbeats.
Yeah, it was like taking the beats that were.
I looked at within a game and looking at how they could be applied to the connective tissue
that kind of glued the games together and it leads to a lot of that kind of like binge
play or the page turner effect where you get to the end of the chapter and you want to
move on to the next one.
Which is all well and good if we were doing like a screenwriting 101 class,
but we aren't, right?
It's like we were talking about that,
like about how do we get these things into a game itself?
And many months were spent and then we, you know,
realized pretty soon that we had an old friend.
Yeah, so how do you do this in a board game?
We were able to leverage the legacy deck for this.
Initially, it was just a way to parse out characters and
other components and new rules and so on.
But we were able to slice it in with story cards in addition
to the other components.
Yeah, so each game starts with, and this is going to be a
spoiler if you haven't played.
We're going to show you the top card of the deck.
I apologize.
There it is.
These things called mission briefings,
which lets us set the tone of what you have to do.
This is, there are 12 months, there are 12 of these,
so it's about half of the story content
just takes place at the beginning of each.
each month. And we tried to pack a lot into each one of these. Right. So, you know, the first
sentence is, hey, you're a veteran, like, you know, the drill, like, we want to reward you
because you've played pandemic. So we're all like, you get this. And then we're like, you know,
there's causing problems. We're just going to kind of frame it up here in case you're not paying
attention. Oh, that's not so good. What's that? Some, you know, mutate faster than usual is,
is not really that comfortable.
And then we have someone looking into that.
Like, I don't know what that means,
but that might be comforting.
It might not be comforting.
And, but don't panic, don't panic for now.
Keep it under control.
You've got this and like, okay, panic a little, right?
So one of them may mutate beyond our capability.
So in two or three sentences,
we kind of cheated and put an em dash.
So, but you know, we can communicated a lot of the tone
that we were trying to do.
And they were, they were fun to write these.
And if you've finished.
and you still have them, I encourage you to go back and read them again, knowing what you know.
So that was one of the ways that we could basically squeeze a lot of narrative into a short space.
And we were limited. I mean, we didn't want to have,
okay, let's start, and you've, card, read a card, read a card, read a card, read a, you're like, where did, you know,
a book in card form was not what we were going for.
Yeah, one of the themes here was just trying to do a lot
with a little.
So the game ships with a bunch of stickers.
These are psychological scars that you put on your
character.
And we don't have a lot of room on these,
because they're small.
They've got to go on the cards.
We have quite a few of them.
And there's localization to consider.
The character count expands when you go to other languages.
So how do you get this stuff across?
It turns out that just having a single keyword like
insomniac or fear of small planes is enough of a hook to
really get players role playing.
It provides so much more story hooks than just the raw
mechanism that's on the card.
So it doesn't take a whole lot to really
unlock story elements.
No, all of you who play these games want to tell a story.
So if we just say reduce your hand limit by one card,
you're like, okay, but if it's like,
why do you only have six cards or five cards in your hand?
It's like, cause I can't sleep.
And like we just had to give you that one thing so you could shout out something during the game
my favorite one was PTSD which is up in the corner, which
You lose an action if you start in the region where you got this and then you write down to the region was one
Of our first ideas, which is I can't go back to Africa. Why like I just can't go back
to Africa
Which leads into the psychology of what we were trying to do and that's
That's this next part that we're going to get into.
So we've talked a little bit about the structure
and we've talked a little bit about how we,
well, you know, arrange the story and then,
but let's get into the psychology
because it's very different in one of these games
because you're committing to kind of go on this journey
with us for 15 games.
And you don't know what's going to happen, but we did, right?
So we wanted to have like a lot of moments
that basically sort of scared you,
but ultimately didn't get too scared
or scared that you broke it.
I didn't get that a lot.
I think we broke it.
No, you didn't break it.
And this first method or trick is really obvious.
I mean, there's a lot of package content that you can't
see right away.
There's eight packages.
There's five dossiers, which are like little advent
calendars.
So it's almost like a bunch of Christmas presents wrapped
up in the box.
And that led to a lot of fear of missing out, basically, on
behalf of the players.
They want to keep playing so they see what's inside the
boxes, see what's behind the hidden doors.
That was a pretty powerful motivator for
people to keep playing.
And it's actually interesting psychologically,
because you want to keep playing so you
see what's in the packages.
But people won't open the package.
Like, well, I don't have time, and my friend's moving away.
I'll just open them up and see what happens.
Like, no.
No, you have to finish.
Except for you.
You did.
But that was for work.
Sorry.
So the next thing we did psychologically
was we wanted you to care about these people in this world.
and you care about things by giving them names.
When you name something, you own a piece of it
and now you care.
So the medic is fine.
You probably played lots of pandemic
where you're like, I'll be the medic.
But that medic has a name, he's Pedro.
And Pedro has feelings and he has a past
and he's got a friend named Wallace up there in the corner.
He's got some other things going on
that we've redacted for people who haven't played.
And you can see down below that Pedro might end up
with a couple scars.
He might end up not sleeping well.
He might become afraid of airplanes.
And the reason that we do this is
we want you to have these little stories.
We want you to have attachments.
And so as you play with these characters
and they go on their journey,
It's much more interesting, because people are more interesting than things.
And so, most people here are people, and so you understand how they work.
And so, like, by basically giving you these little moments to imprint and bond on things,
then, you know, and get attached to it, you cared more.
Want to do this one?
Yeah, why don't you take this one?
Okay.
So, going back to our old friend, the up and down beats.
I don't know if you noticed, but what we like to do in this game is, we like to give you
a downbeat which is, here's a new problem.
Like in January, we give you a problem.
And you're like, this is a bad problem, we don't like this problem that you gave us.
And then in February, you struggle with that new problem.
And it's a lot of work to try to fix it, and it's really distracting you.
So then at the end of February, or the beginning of March...
We give you a tool to make that problem easier.
And because you've just struggled with it for a month,
you're like, oh, that's good.
That's gonna help.
That power's gonna help.
That person's gonna help.
Okay, this is fantastic.
Oh.
they've just given us a new problem.
And so we constantly give you a problem,
let you struggle, give you some tools,
give you a new problem, let you struggle,
give you some tools, and just kind of repeat this process,
not quite so formulaically,
but basically over the course of the 12 months.
But as the problems mount, even though the tools mount,
you don't have enough time or resources to use all of them.
So you're in a position of like,
what do we use the tools for?
What do we not use the tools for?
And that's part of the...
legacy experience where group A might choose to spend a lot of time on positive mutations
so that they don't have to deal with diseases, where other people will use tools for other
spoilery things so they don't have to deal with those problems over there.
But either way, you don't have enough tools to make the game easier, just choosing which
things are easier for you and which things you have to work with.
But there was that upbeat, downbeat of problem, struggle, solution that we gave you.
We were able to pull off a lot of these psychological tricks,
I think, because the players trusted us.
And in order to build that trust, we designed in some
safety nets into the game.
This is box eight, or package eight, one of my favorite
things in the game.
When you open up the box, one of the first instructions you
read is to take this sticker that you see here off the
sticker sheet and put it on box eight.
We don't say why that's important.
We don't really spend a whole lot of time on it.
But it's the absolute first thing you see and the first
thing you're supposed to do.
So you know internally, hey, this is kind of important.
And if you read it, it says, open package 8 if you lose
four games in a row.
It's just one simple sentence, but it provided just
tremendous amounts of value to us.
As you can imagine, we had a lot of playtesters, and some
of them would lose a game and get a little frustrated.
Then they'd lose another one and get frustrated.
If they lost that third one, they were about ready to
consider their $70 purchase a complete waste of time, shred
the thing, be embarrassed, put it on the shelf, or say nasty
things about at least Rob on Twitter.
He gets all the mean tweets.
But we're able to get around that by just including this
the single sticker.
Basically, so now if you lose those three games, you're like,
OK, we lost three.
We suck.
But at least we didn't have to open up package eight.
It kind of sets its anchor at four, which is like, OK, four
is bad.
But also, you know, that, hey, you know, if we do lose four games, at least we get to
open the present.
You know, we get to open up the package and see what's in there.
And there are things in there that are going to help you.
So you open it up and there is a safety net.
There's some material in there that will help you get your game back on track and get you
back on the rails.
And so it's a very simple solution, but provided just a tremendous amount of value to the game.
Yeah, and I do see a lot of people when they write, you know, talks about this like we
struggled, we didn't do a good job, at the end we feel like we didn't do that well, but
we didn't open package eight.
So they feel good about it.
So as you can imagine, this is just a sheer joy to play, test, and balance.
And so we're going to talk a little bit about how we did
that, which is the following talk.
I just really like that pun.
I'm sorry.
It was very early, and it made me laugh too hard.
All right.
So this is something that Matt taught me.
So Matt will.
So I came out of user experience design in the
Valley, where we did a lot of usability testing.
And we started to do some ethnographic research at Yahoo
where we'd go into the field with cameras and record people
using our products.
Since then, everybody got these smartphones.
Everybody's got a camera phone in their pocket.
And I just started taking advantage of that.
So for the last, I don't know, three or four years, I've been
asking people who are blind testing to take out their
phones and just record themselves as they're playing
the game on their kitchen table.
And it's amazing the kinds of data and how valuable that
information is.
In addition to just.
I'm always surprised at how relaxed people are in this
environment, because they're using their own equipment.
They're in their own home.
I've got video of people smoking pot in front of me.
This was before it was legal.
On camera, recorded, sent to a stranger they don't know.
Just really relaxed.
So you get very naturalistic feedback on it.
And you get feedback that you wouldn't get from a
self-report form or just from analyzing the raw data.
So one of my favorite moments from this group was actually
watching them open up.
A big reveal at the end of Act One, in an early version of the game, where the thing
just landed like a ton of bricks.
It was just a dead, dead beat.
They looked at each other, they shook their heads, and you would never see that on a feedback
form, but they were just, you know, it did not work for them at all.
all, and we knew that we needed to rejigger the story.
This wasn't a mechanical thing.
This was a thematic thing.
And it's something that we just wouldn't have been able to
internalize and really empathize with if we hadn't
seen it on camera above the table.
So, yeah, so we just get a ton of feedback from that.
Yeah, so what we do is every time we have a version ready to go,
we find somewhere between two to four groups.
And those groups will play as many games as we have done.
So we might only have, like, January through March or January through July.
They record every game. Then they upload it as they play.
And then we watch them and we take notes.
And we have discovered that 1.6 speed is as fast as you can go
and still pay attention.
Sometimes I'll push it to 1.8, but I miss things.
Because we're looking at dozens or hundreds of hours
for each batch of playtesting.
Yeah, it was somewhere between 100 and 200 hours for season 1.
It was more for season 2.
And so that turns into the wonderful world of game design.
which is a giant spreadsheet of notes and anecdotes,
whether it says observation, which might lead,
if you see the green, a design idea, red is an issue,
the time code, because he'll watch maybe group A
and I'll watch group B and we record the timing,
so if I see a note on his, I can go to the video and do it.
We have redacted things out out of courtesy for people who haven't played,
but there's two things of interest to note.
One is, that's 730 notes from this particular round,
and you get things like this.
How do you exhibit abnormal thoughts?
This was a throwaway comment from one playtester.
So, the end of Act 1, there's something that's revealed,
and the card had said, you know,
duh, they're exhibiting abnormal thoughts.
He says, how do you exhibit abnormal thoughts?
I'm like...
That's a really good point.
So the final card says they're exhibiting abnormal behavior.
Never would have caught that, because I wrote it.
That made perfect sense.
Everyone read it, unless someone on the video
is like made this comment, and then it got recorded here.
And then we're like, yeah, yeah, that should be fixed.
So you find these tiny, tiny things.
Another thing I like to, just for myself, to keep myself honest is to note all the observations
and issues separately from the ideas.
As often I'll watch a group that I'll be sitting with and I'll have tons of ideas and I'll
write down all the ideas, but I won't, I'll just sweep all the issues under the rug.
I just want to make the game better, you know, cut to the chase, just put the good idea in.
But then you find out that the good idea is not so good
anymore, and you throw the idea out, and you've lost
track of the issue.
So just kind of like bracketing all this stuff,
bracketing the ideas over here and the observations and the
issues really helps keep us honest, I think, when we're
doing it.
So this catches many interesting things.
We're going to kind of show you something that was on the
editing room floor from season one.
So as you get to the middle of the game, those of you who
have played, we ask you to go search for things.
And it's a relatively simple little side journey that we wanted to do.
And the final game shipped with a simple little side mechanism by which to do it.
But we got so caught up in the design when we were first doing it, it's like,
people are going to want a whole new game to break out right here.
Like you're like, and so we designed.
This thing
This is one of I think three different probably more than we lost like a man trying to create like
You're at a game and another now obviously this isn't the final graphics where the ads idea cuz pandemic
You know takes place in world and that you go to cities and so we wanted like oh, we want you to search Paris
Well, so we're gonna zoom in and there's gonna be like a city block card
And now it's gonna be almost like a tactical mini game where you're moving and there's AI stuff moving. We were so delighted
It was kind of cool.
It was also just kind of stapled on the side of the game.
It didn't really make any sense at all.
Right.
You'd need like a whole other table, right,
to manage this and stuff.
So we noticed very early on that every time this was about June,
I think it comes out.
I just watched the players kind of deflate
when they had to pull this stuff out.
And then they're like reading it,
and then the whole thing comes to a stop for 20 minutes,
right, like right in the middle of a 45-minute game,
you have a 20-minute break, which is horrible.
So anyway, we kept simplifying and simplifying.
until we made it as simple as possible.
And then everyone's like, this is great, thank you.
But we had never shown that before.
It took us a while to find it.
And we were laughing last week when we pulled that out.
Like, yeah, that was a great idea.
So then after we get those 700 and some odd observations,
we have a lot of phone calls.
We live on opposite coasts, so we use video conferencing.
And we go through each one, and we talk about it.
And then we turn it into a punch list
that's smaller but still pretty big of things we want to do.
So.
Here's one list of all the changes we made coming out of
a play test.
It's deliberately so small that you can't read it here.
But when this talk is up later, you can go through and
see all the notes if you're so inclined.
Yeah, so all the issues and ideas get converted into
really prescriptive, very specific things that we can do
and we sign up for them and knock them off.
And yeah, do all the, I don't know.
I've got a little bit of an Agile background, so we're
able to, you know.
apply some of that.
It's easier for us, because it's just the two of us.
We can do it all in Drive.
But yeah, we can be pretty efficient this way.
But some stuff does get through.
This next.
This next card actually slipped through the cracks.
This is one card that looks pretty innocent, just as time
is running out.
And it's got some fairly simple instructions, though at
least they look simple to me and Rob and our copy editor.
So it turns out, though, humans have a real hard time
with cognition when it comes to a negative
paired with an or.
I don't know why, but just tons of posts on BoardGameGeek
about this one, not opening the wrong package, being
confused, and so on.
So we've reworded this in the second printing.
But you can't catch everything.
Yeah, what we meant.
Was if either six or seven was unopened, scratch this card.
Not that they both had to be unopened or both opened.
It made perfect sense.
Every time I read it now, I'm like, no, it
makes perfect sense.
But it does.
Yeah, I think if you're an engineer or you're into
grammar, then you're like, solid.
But this caused some problems because this was a big moment.
So having a lot of people scratch it when they shouldn't
or should when, or actually the big problem is people
didn't scratch it when they should have.
And this is supposed to get the game back on track.
If you are behind on some certain objectives
and you're entering act three
and we want those objectives to be solved,
we wanna catch you back up.
And so if you don't scratch it and you keep playing
and then you get to a point where like,
wait, we can't, we can't win.
And then you have to go back and find that card
and realize you should have scratched it.
So we cleaned up the language there.
Another valuable thing that you learn from doing the video
testing is just how well the actual
physical components work.
Does that sticker fit in the rules?
Can people find things in the rules?
Do the pieces actually fit on the board?
That sort of stuff, all the human factors kinds of things.
When we were designing this game, we had a legacy deck
that had stickers in it.
So as you played the game, you would find a card that had
stickers in it, you'd peel it off, real easy, real
straightforward.
But at the 11th hour, we found out that we actually couldn't
put sticker cards in the deck.
And we had a lot of them in there.
And this was sort of a panicky moment.
But we worked through it and came up with these dossiers.
The thing is, we were never able to test the dossiers.
And so a few things showed up after the game was printed
that became problems.
For example, if you have a dossier door numbered six and
a box numbered six, and you tell your players to open
number six.
you know, sometimes they might open the wrong thing.
This was encoded.
Not everybody makes this mistake, but some people did.
They jumped ahead and opened up package six
instead of door number six to their disappointment,
I guess would be the best way to say it.
Yeah, no, it's particularly frustrating
because we tell you to open door number six.
It's either the first or one of the first things to open,
so you're very excited about opening something
and you haven't seen any other context.
Package six is probably the last thing I want you to open
by mistake at that moment.
So it was particularly bad numbering at a particularly bad time.
The lesson here was that, you know, this kind of testing with video and actually the physical components can unearth some of this stuff.
We did a better job in season two in that everything's uniquely numbered, like the package numbers and the dossier numbers all have unique coding, so you can't possibly do that.
But, you know, again, it's because we were done the game when we came up with the dossiers.
This one's related.
If you pull a door off the dossier, you've got it in your
hand, you're very excited about the card, you don't
look back at the tear sheet that you just pulled it from.
Even if it's got a big yellow box that's screaming at you to
read it, lots of people don't do that.
So that's another thing that we would have unearthed, I
think, if we were doing a higher fidelity test.
So yeah, that's most of our talk.
Basically what happened was we did it, and it came out, and
it did well.
And, you know, yay, Hobbits.
And so, by and large, it did well.
A lot of our stuff that we tried to do, set out to do.
And so, we wanted to leave you quickly.
We got about 13 minutes with three quick takeaways,
which was you can evoke a story with highlights,
attachment to characters, and using some tropes like, oh,
the world's ending, or I'm the medic.
And.
Yeah, you can do a lot of this.
You can actually manipulate people's emotions
if they trust you.
And building that trust, you can use safety nets and anchors
and provide the appropriate incentives in order to do that.
And the last thing is, everyone thinks of the game
as what happens when you take your first turn
until the game is over, but this game's,
especially legacy games, are experiences.
So if you test above the table how people are reacting,
you get a lot more knowledge about the experience itself
rather than the gameplay itself.
And that's kind of it.
We have 13 minutes.
I want to get time to some questions.
So we'll just leave that up there for no particular reason
while we take questions.
So.
Why on earth did you make me destroy so many cards?
I trusted you.
Yes.
So that is always the big thing is destroying a card.
A card is a piece of cardboard.
You destroy cardboard all the time.
And it's imbued with meaning because we've been trained
not to destroy cards.
You can get by by not destroying them.
It's just our way of saying, you won't need this again.
It's going to get in the way.
It's going to cause clutter.
Ultimately, if you ripped up an entire deck of cards and just like a fit of rage or whatever you wanted to do you will
basically spent 50 cents worth of material and then you can recycle it and it's nothing I
It was an idea for Risk Legacy and I'm like,
will people dare to do this?
And it was really, really dramatic,
but I wanted people to be like, this is permanent,
this is a one-way trip, you're playing with real money.
It raises the stakes.
It raises the stakes, right?
You just put the chips on the board
and now you've got something to lose.
That's a little teaser for the next talk.
Thanks.
Hi, I just wanted to say thank you for this pretty amazing experience that I've had over
the last couple of months playing Pandemic Legacy.
It's been incredible.
But I have a question, it's more about the original Pandemic, if you don't mind.
Sure.
One of the most amazing mechanics I've seen in a long
time is the idea of when you have an epidemic, you pull a
card from the bottom to infect a new region.
Where did this idea come from?
I have to credit Tom Lehman for that.
We were doing a lot of playtesting at Alan Moon's
Gathering of Friends.
And we noticed that when the epidemic cards came out,
sometimes there was a lot of tension, and
sometimes there wasn't.
And it was only those moments where there weren't cities
with three infection cubes on there.
And so he suggested this very simple idea of taking a card
off the bottom.
It's off the bottom so you don't pull a card you've
already had.
And always an epidemic card is a problem
from that point forward.
So yeah.
Thanks.
Hi.
So a question for both about co-op games and alpha gamer
situations, especially we hear about it with pandemic a lot,
and I've been in those situations.
Does the legacy format help with that?
Did you consider that as part of the design as a possible
problem that this could alleviate?
I don't think it was something that either Rob or I actually set out to try to solve,
but I do think it helps that there's some blurriness, there's some fog there.
You don't know exactly the one way to win.
Because there's some uncertainty and there's lots of different ways to play the game, right?
Are you trying to optimize for the specific game you're playing tactically, or are you
more focused on the long-term effects that affect the board for the entire arc?
And because there's no one right answer, I think that mitigates it somewhat.
Yeah, I talk about this a little in my talk tomorrow about Legacy Games.
Legacy Games...
you avoid mastery, right?
Every, if you play a game enough time,
you feel like you know how to play
and then you're only being surprised by the variety
within like the shuffle of the cards
or someone else's actions.
But with the legacy game, every game is a brand new game.
And so you never quite are at that level of mastery.
So to some extent, it might mitigate the alpha gamer saying,
I played this 50 times, I know how to win
because they just got the same piece of new information
that you did.
So a bit.
Thank you.
These games sound amazing.
I wonder if you could speak a bit more
about your testing process.
Did you also have them do written responses
in addition to the videos?
And how did you compose those questions,
given that you were also going to see
their entire game on video?
I think we did virtually no self-report.
We did not.
Well, we had groups who sat down and did a focus
group for themselves on video for our benefit,
and that was really helpful.
But I don't think Rob or I actually can post any questions
for them to answer directly.
We did collect some data for win-loss and that sort of
thing, but most of it is on the tape.
I mean, if it was, we could look at the players and we
could see their emotions.
They didn't have to describe their emotions.
I mean, there are authorities on that, but sometimes
hindsight's not so great.
So we just kept going back to the tape, really.
And sometimes I think we go back to them and ask a
question.
Like you see-
Yeah, clarify the question.
Like, why did you do that?
Like, you watch this, and this was kind of a problem,
and why did you do this?
Did you not understand the rule?
And they'd be like, oh, right, and-
But no survey type kinds of things.
Like, did you enjoy that?
Or, you know, what was your favorite part
or anything like that?
It's all, yeah, just the tape.
It's a lot of video to watch.
We get a lot.
And we, you know, we can, yeah, we can watch who won.
Okay, first epidemic, second epidemic, finished the round.
Oh, they forgot this rule.
Like, it's, a lot of those notes
are just watching play by play.
the sort of things that you would have gotten from like a survey where we were looking for data.
Hey.
Hey. You guys made a good game. Thank you. But it's a game designed to be
played one time. So my question is, to what degree were you worried about people
being spoiled either through let's plays or just assholes
and not wanting to play the game anymore?
A bit.
Well, I don't know.
A bit, right?
There's always a concern.
With Risk Legacy, I was like, how much are people going to spoil it?
And then I discovered that the gaming community just went, oh, here's a game with spoilers.
Cool.
And then just didn't spoil it.
And I was like, whoa.
I mean, if you go looking, you could find it.
The publisher, Z-Man, was brilliant.
They turned it into an event by having it come out worldwide on the same day.
in every country to minimize, like the United States gets it first,
and then they write reviews, then you're reading about it,
and you're like, I would have bought it, but it spoiled it
in the review, and I didn't want to do that.
So Essen Game Fair in Germany is a big game fair in October,
and it came out the first day of that, but it was in New Zealand
and California, and I think Russia lagged a couple weeks.
But other than that, so yeah, that was the way to avoid that.
You don't play it once, you play it 18 times.
Fair enough.
Okay.
I also have a spoiler question related to spoilers as a concept.
What's the statute of limitations for you guys giving a talk where you're like, all
right, we're going crazy, we're talking about every beat of the game, when are, you know,
when are we going to get that full spoiler talk, if ever?
Tomorrow?
I don't know.
I, I'm.
Cause I mean, like we all know Darth Vader's Luke Skywalker's
father, like, sorry, sorry guys.
What?
So like, so, you know, but there's not,
you're so this, these are sort of the first games
with spoilers, board games with spoilers.
So, you know, what do you think that it's going to be?
More honest question is probably pretty soon.
And most people here like have played it.
And hopefully when we talked about act one twists
and act two twists, you know what we were talking about
but just to save it from the people who had heard about it.
and wanted to play it, but I'm guessing sometime in the next year I will talk about season
one much more honestly, and then season two, you know, we'll be out and we won't talk about
that.
When I do podcasts now, like, there's usually a point where like, okay, now you just, and
then I'll get into the spoilers, like give people a chance to not listen.
But it's still selling well and still reaching new people.
Like if it was out of print, I'd talk about it all day long because it didn't run its
course.
Thank you.
Did you make any special considerations when designing for the varying player counts, so
like the game can play a little differently at two players than at four, for example?
It's a pen.
I don't think we did actually.
I mean, at first it was gonna be a three to four player game
but then we realized it's a great couples game
because it's easy to feel the team.
It is a little easier with two players.
You can play it with two characters each if you want
but no, we just, we kept it simple.
So yeah, you can play right out of the box
just like you might play Pandemic with fewer characters.
So. Cool, thank you.
Part of the reason for that is Pandemic had been tested
with two to four and also we didn't feel like
giving ourselves any additional design challenges
by having.
different rules for the player count.
Yeah.
Multiplied over 15 games.
The complexity didn't really have the payoff.
OK.
So we got two more questions.
And we got four more minutes.
Before we take the questions, just
want to remind people to fill out your evaluations.
You can tell I was a teacher at one point.
Fill out your evaluations so that the GDC
has a sense of how this new board game talk
branch is going for future years.
Yes, I was wondering if you could speak to a moment about the your sort of difference in experience between balancing a competitive legacy
game and a cooperative legacy game in particular how that was
Balancing against for lack of a better term in AI versus balancing between actual other players. You should probably take that
Yeah, so in in risk legacy
I made the assumption which worked most of the time but not all the time if player a kept winning and they were getting bonuses
Which led to them winning more than players B through D would gang up on them and bring them back to the herd
And because the game goes in so many different directions,
I needed the players to act as policing agents.
Where that fell down is when groups are like, well,
it didn't feel right to pick on that person,
so they just kept winning.
And then the game would go off the rails.
So I knew that lesson coming in here.
But we really did have this fear,
and we spent time at the beginning talking about it,
of like, you're on the ground in the fetal position.
The game's just kicking you game after game.
Like, you know, like, you're just like, well, you're just.
And it turns out that that.
Funding worked and solved like 90% of our problems in that point.
And, you know, like allowing you to pick two things at the end of every game that would
help you in the next game, and if you lost the game, you get a free game to try it again,
gives you two more things than if you had won the game, if that makes sense, were just
about enough to kind of work.
But it was a lot of fingers crossed and then watching the playtest and never seeing it.
Or if it went off the rails, we knew why.
Thank you.
So really quickly, talk about materials, if you would.
All these play tests, hundreds of play tests.
Did corporate pay for all these stickers
and tearing up cards and everything?
And what would your advice be for the garage developer?
Trying to do nice things.
We both work out of our homes as garage developers.
No, we just built it ourselves.
Like when we have to send out four prototypes,
towards the end when you have the full kit,
we make like actual dossiers, my wife.
God bless her.
Hand cuts perforations into the dossiers.
I'm more of a scorer.
She's like an arts and crafts person.
They're very time consuming.
There are some tricks.
I mean, early on I would print out stickers
and put them on actual cards.
We used a lot, we got in a lot of pandemic sets
and actually used those card backs.
For season two, it was almost exclusively card sleeves
because they're much easier to change out.
There's a lot of print on demand services,
but we don't typically do that
because the iteration cycle's too long.
And yeah, a lot of money as well.
So I don't know.
It's 10.59.
And the two of you sort of came up.
What?
He was first.
OK, if you've got a five second question, we can give
you a five second answer.
Thanks for the talk, by the way.
Just had a question.
Did you guys consider doing stuff like cross-campaigning,
like two groups of players influencing the same board or
some stuff like that?
Yeah, we like a challenge.
I've thought about that.
People come up to me with like, okay, now that you've mastered this, how can we raise
the stakes?
It's entertaining.
But we haven't planned it.
So, okay.
Thank you.
Thanks.