Here we go!
Thank you all for gathering here today.
And since you're here, I imagine that maybe you've played this game, and that makes me very happy.
How many of you attended the Legend of Zelda panel this morning?
That's great.
Thank you very much.
The Zelda team is very happy.
Today, I will be sharing the thought process that went into the creation of Super Mario Bros.
Wonder.
I am also hoping developers across disciplines will become more interested in 2D games in the future.
Hello everyone, my name is Takashi Tezuka, and I was the producer on Super Mario Bros.
Wonder.
Since I joined Nintendo in 1984, I have been involved in the production of the first Super Mario Bros., the Legend of Zelda, the God of Triforce, Super Mario Yoshi Island, New Super Mario Bros., and Super Mario Maker.
Thank you.
I've been working at Nintendo since 1984.
I began work with the company doing graphic design for the original Super Mario Bros.
series, as well as the Legend of Zelda series.
I've worked on many titles over the years, including The Legend of Zelda A Link to the Past, New Super Mario Bros., Yoshi's Island, and Super Mario Maker, among others.
I'm excited to speak with you all today.
Hello, everyone.
I'm Shiro Mori, the director of Super Mario Bros.
Wonder.
Hello, everyone.
I am Shiro Omori, the director of Super Mario Bros.
Wonder.
After working as the main programmer on 2D Legend of Zelda and 2D Mario titles, I have been working as the director on 2D games featuring Mario, starting with New Super Mario Bros.
U Deluxe and many more.
I look forward to talking with you all today.
Here is today's overview.
Up first, Mr. Tezuka will be introducing the appeal of 2D game development and Mr. Tezuka's POV.
Today, I would like to introduce the appeal of developing a 2D game.
I'd like to first start with explaining why I thought to touch on this topic.
In a media interview last year, I was asked why they decided to release a 2D Mario game a few years ago.
During media interviews last year, I was asked, why is now the right time to release the first 2D Mario game in years?
I said that we had been busy making other side-scrolling Mario titles, like Super Mario Run and Super Mario Maker, and honestly, 11 years just went by.
It's true.
However, I was reminded of the fact that when we go for such a long time without the release of a new 2D game, people may think 3D Mario games have taken their place.
And while it's true that New Super Mario Bros.
and Super Mario Odyssey are both action games where you control Mario, the gameplay is not the same.
Each one has its own brand of fun, and I think everyone should enjoy them both.
Do you think that's too much to ask?
In many games, 3D expression has been adopted, but when it comes to making games, the methods are very different.
Even if the production period is the same for both games, where to put effort is different, and the fun of the creator is different.
We're in a time where many games use 3D presentation, but the methods of creating gameplay are quite different.
Even if the production time is the same, where we allocate our efforts is different, and so is the enjoyment we experience as creators.
What are the differences between these two?
Mr. Mori, what do you think, from your perspective as a creator?
I'm originally a programmer, so I'm coming at this from my experience of creating games from the ground up.
The first three things I create are the player, camera, and map.
This is the same for both 2D and 3D games.
In particular, it takes time for the 3D camera to create.
In 3D, you need to move the camera so that it doesn't get stuck in obstacles.
In 2D, you don't need to do that, so you can focus on creating the angle of play.
Among these three, building the camera for 3D games takes a lot of time.
That's because in 3D, you have to be able to move the camera without it getting caught on obstacles.
You don't have to worry about that for 2D games, though, so you can focus on what we call the core of play.
That's right.
When I first started making 3D games, I remembered that I had studied cameras, which I didn't have to think too much about.
One more thing.
How about game design?
That's right.
I remember studying about cameras when I first started working on 3D games, which was something I rarely had to think about before.
So how about game design?
Well, there's not a big difference in how it's done, but the merit of 2D games is that it's easier to experience the game's design as it was intended.
I think so too.
Let's think a little more about 2D games.
I asked the Super Mario Bros.
Wonder staff about the pros of 2D games.
Let me share two of the comments I received.
First,
Here's the first comment.
In 2D games, it's easy to create and present ideas that would in reality be impossible.
I have fun thinking of how to incorporate these types of ideas.
This was from a designer.
In my opinion, the world of games is all about imitating and exaggerating the real world.
In a realistic 3D space, it is hard to find a way to express a strange feeling.
In a 2D game, it is hard to find a way to express a strange feeling.
In my opinion, all game worlds are fabrications that imitate or exaggerate things in the real world.
Even those on-screen presentations that might not feel quite right in a 3D environment can feel surprisingly natural in 2D games.
And it's not easy to see when you're cheating.
For example, when Mario is mid-jump and you press a directional button in the opposite direction, his jump path changes.
In reality, that's not how physics works, but I think it feels very natural for the player.
The next comment is from a level designer.
2D games can incorporate the creator's intentions in an easy-to-understand manner.
Compared to 3D, it's easier to rebuild courses.
I think so too.
I'd like to go into more details about course design.
I once had a conversation with Mr. Miyamoto about whether or not anyone can create a 2D game.
Of course, you can't say anyone can do it, but if you have easy-to-use course editing tools and the right instincts, then it just might become possible.
In the case of 2D Mario, the course design itself has a significant impact on the value of the game.
Let's look at Super Mario Maker.
We created a system in which players freely design courses and post them.
Other people then download the courses, play them, and rate them.
What I want to focus on here is that everyone can use the course parts and enemies as they see fit.
So everyone is creating courses under the same conditions.
However, when we play the posted courses, and let's keep this here, some of them were not very good.
Good player controls, sound, graphics, exciting enemies and game design are all important, but whether they come alive or fall flat is dependent on the level designer.
When allocating development time and cost, it's very important to make course design easy.
This is because in 2D Mario games, you spend as much time possible adjusting courses until the end of development.
Changing the topic here a little, I'd like to talk about what goes through my mind when creating a Mario game.
With the passing of time, the expression of games has evolved, and we can make both pictures and sounds more realistic.
On the other hand, how does the reality of playing games evolve?
The presentation of games has evolved over time, and images and sounds can now be produced to look and sound more real.
But how is realism in gameplay evolving?
For example, does Mario feel pain when he hits an enemy?
I think it's important to feel real in the experience of playing.
That's why we've made the expression real.
I don't think we should expect a sense of accomplishment just by making the expression real.
If anything, I think it's important for the gameplay experience to feel real, but I don't think we should seek a sense of accomplishment based only on the realness of the presentation.
For example, we should think about whether there are ways to make the gameplay realistic even if the presentation itself is not.
Even if expressive character movements and sounds are produced, what's important is how we make use of them.
I recommend that art and sound leads, as well as the entire team, share what they were thinking when they were working.
For example, in Mario Wonder, when two walking children bump into each other, an attractive animation is created.
However, if you don't notice this animation and level up, you may not be able to see that attractive scene when you notice it.
For example, in Super Mario Bros.
Wonder, we created this cute animation for when two Koopa Troopa bump into each other while walking.
But if work on course design is done without anyone noticing it, it's possible we might not see this charming interaction happen very often.
When we think about level design, we think about what we should do to intentionally create a scene where the Koopa Troopas bump into each other, and the sound person in charge wants to create an SUV that fits that scene.
When thinking about course design, it would be ideal to consider how to create scenes where Koopa Troopa collide, so that the sound staff would then want to create the perfect sound effect for that happening.
I think that by influencing each person in charge, the expression will come to life.
If we don't do that, we won't be able to make use of the special effects we've created, and it will be a waste.
In this way, I believe that leads of different disciplines can influence each other's work in ways that infuse courses with life.
When teams don't do this, it's hard to make the most of the game spec, and that's what we call mottainai.
There's a word in Japanese, mottainai.
To put it simply, it means when you aren't able to make the most of something and you feel regret or frustration that it's gone to waste.
Is what you spent so much time creating and development working the way it's supposed to in the game?
For example, in Super Mario Bros.
Wonder, we implemented a badge system whereby player abilities could be freely swapped out.
This is because we wanted players to enjoy frequently changing their abilities and play the courses again and again using different badges.
Once you clear it, you can move on to the next one.
It would be a waste if you can't play anymore.
Clearing a course once, moving on, and then never coming back to it is an example of something being mottainai.
Additionally, players not swapping abilities using the badge system is another example of mottainai, and that's why we implemented a badge swap opportunity whenever a player gets KO'd.
And this wasn't a system implemented from the beginning of development, but rather something that came about while considering the concept of Mottainai.
Our entire team wants to fill Mario games with so many surprises that people are always excited to play.
And for Super Mario Bros.
Wonder, we came up with big changes as the way to create those surprises.
So why did we make big changes in our mantra?
The path we took until arriving at Wonder Effects, the various prototyping, the results of our experiments.
Next up, Mr. Mori will be unraveling all of this while sharing some real examples from Super Mario Bros.
Wonder.
From here, I will explain how Mori evolved traditional 2D titles and made them available in the current market.
I will take over from here.
I would like to introduce how we evolved a traditional 2D game to be compatible in the current market.
First up, new surprises, things we did and didn't adopt with Wonder Effects.
Super Mushroom
In the first Super Mario Bros., coins came out when you hit blocks, and you grew bigger when you got a Super Mushroom.
Everything about it was new and full of secrets and mysteries.
However, as 2D Mario has been played for many years, at some point all of this has become normal.
For that reason, this project began with the goal of creating a 2D Mario game full of new secrets and mysteries.
I think back to the first Super Mario Bros.
and the elements that represented secrets and mysteries to me back then.
Elements like entering the warp pipe and being able to explore the underground area, or hitting a block, seeing a vine come out, and climbing that vine to an area in the sky.
Therefore, in the latest game, I thought about creating a new version of these secrets and mysteries.
And I tried making something where when you hit a block, a special item comes out.
And if you take this item, you can go to another area.
When I showed that to Mr. Tezuka, he said, this isn't so different from how it's always been.
Can't you make it so instead of going to another area, the environment itself changes?
So I thought, well, if I'm going to change the environment anyway, I might as well go hard.
So, I made drastic changes that have never been seen in a Super Mario Bros.
title.
I made the warp pipes wiggle and the piranha plants break out in song.
And so, this is how the strange changes that happened to the course, the wonder effects for this game, came to be.
Here's what the prototype of the wiggling warp pipes looked like.
And here's the final version.
By the way, the badge I'm wearing on my chest is handmade by my daughter.
By the way, this badge of the warp pipe that I have on me right now was made by my daughter.
Thank you.
With the evolution of hardware, the scale of game development has increased, and so has the number of developers.
As hardware has evolved, the size of development teams has increased in proportion to the scale of game production.
And something we didn't focus on during the NES days, which was team management, is now an important job.
Getting lots of people working in the same direction to develop a game with as little waste as possible is without a doubt an important job.
However, there is something even more important.
Working with many people means we are also working with many abilities and approaches.
So, it's about how can we represent each person's individuality and strengths in production.
And team management should be developed for this purpose.
We are always workshopping team management.
Mr. Mori will talk about how he and his entire team work together to create wonder effects.
In order to make it full of secrets and mysteries, you need a lot of types of wonder.
Many types of wonder effects are needed to fill a game with secrets and mysteries.
We therefore held brainstorming sessions where the whole team shared their ideas for wonder effects.
It was up to everyone on the team to come up with ideas, regardless of job title or seniority.
Nintendo believes that everyone on the team is a game designer.
At first, we asked everyone to write any and all ideas on sticky notes, without any conditions.
After all, if you start with conditions, you stifle creative freedom.
At this stage, we collected around 2,000 ideas.
As we looked at the various ideas that came up, we were able to gradually narrow down what criteria made up good wonder effects.
Among these ideas, the ones we liked had a connection between pre-Wonder Effect and during Wonder Effect.
For example, if the player were to suddenly transform into Balloon Mario due to a wonder effect, that would feel unnatural.
However, by having balloon-esque enemies appear first, then having the player transform into Balloon Mario due to a wonder effect, the feeling of unnaturalness is removed.
Other features that we pinned as good wonder effects were having players suddenly be able to do something that they couldn't before, and having effects that could be explained simply in one short phrase.
With these figured out, we started to try out different ideas that met these criteria.
This testing phase was also conducted by everyone on the team.
Each testing team was comprised of one game designer, one artist, one programmer, and one sound engineer.
When necessary, we created new temporary design data and sound data.
Once the testing phase was over, all team members would play the prototype, then share their opinions.
In response to these opinions, team members would share and layer even more ideas, and this eventually led to the product version taking shape.
More than half of the prototypes did not make it to the final product, but these testing sessions had many effects, such as everyone gained development experience, everyone's motivation increased, and the team solidarity improved.
And more importantly than this, coming up with prototypes is just fun.
I will introduce two of the wonder effects that were adopted after the wonder effect testing sessions.
The first one is the wonder effect, the terrain tilts.
Here's a video of when this idea was prototyped.
And this prototype ultimately became this in the final version.
Here is the second wonder effect we adopted.
This is an idea that came from a programmer in his first year at the company.
At Nintendo, even first-year employees and programmers pitch in ideas, and if those ideas are good, of course they're adopted.
All he did is write, a wonder quiz starts, on a sticky note, without any other specific info.
Do you think we can call this a good idea?
When I saw this, I thought to myself, this idea has potential.
What I saw was the opportunity to create a unique wonder effect where Mario takes action to answer questions, a way to supplement the worldview of the game, and motivation for players to play multiple times to see all the questions.
Here's what the final product looks like.
When I first heard about this idea, I wondered, and it's kind of out of the blue, is this really okay?
The note, A Wonder Quiz Starts, was more the start of an idea than a full-fledged idea, and we expanded on what the people who saw it came up with until we landed on the final implementation.
I don't think this is an idea that I would have ever come up with.
And I believe this is what's interesting about creating play with other people.
Next, I will introduce two wonder effects that we did not adopt.
The first one is an idea from our sound director, Mr. Kondo.
His idea was, when a wonder effect activates, a live-action version of Mario with human proportions appears, starts progressing through the stage while humming the background music, and mimicking the various sound effects himself.
As an idea, it's very funny, but it's hard to see the connection between pre-Wonder Effect and during Wonder Effect, and it's hard to imagine the gameplay changing much by having Mario turn into a live-action human-proportioned version of himself.
There were a lot of ideas like this that didn't meet the criteria of what constitutes a viable wonder effect, and they were all closely examined as we figured out our approach.
While we couldn't use Mr. Kondo's idea as a wonder effect, we thought it could instead be used as a badge, a system where players can select their own special powers.
It was such an interesting idea, it would have been motainai to not use it.
And so, the Sound Off badge came to be.
Here's how it ended up in the final version.
I'm wearing it!
This badge makes you want to hear a lot of different voices, so I think it's good that you want to try a lot of different actions.
I think that the appeal of this badge is that it makes you want to try out various actions in order to hear all the sound effects.
Incidentally, the man behind the voice of the SoundOff badge is Mr. Kondo himself, the one who pitched this idea.
Here's the second example of a wonder effect that was not adopted.
There is an enemy called Nosher that eats blocks.
So the idea for this wonder effect was to transform yourself into a giant block Mario and advance while preventing your blocks from getting eaten.
We felt like it had a very strong and interesting visual appeal, so we tried prototyping it.
Here's a video from that time.
Although we did prototype it, this was ultimately not adopted as a wonder effect.
This is because the area of the blocks was large, and it was impossible to develop a strategy of how to avoid enemies, so it just turned into a game of making a mad dash for the end.
However, reducing the area of the blocks would have resulted in losing that visual appeal, so we decided to not use it.
We weren't planning to include wonder effects from the beginning.
Rather, it was created by considering and solving issues faced by 2D Mario games.
At first, there were no rules on what constituted a good wonder effect versus a not-so-good wonder effect.
Nobody knows what the new elements are going to be at the beginning of development.
I believe that the answer to this question is uncovered together as a team.
What makes development of a game like this so fun is the fact that we're creating something that nobody holds the answer to.
Now, let's take a quick look at the design of past Mario titles.
The original Super Mario Bros.
game was simply focused on clearing various courses, and if players didn't clear the castle course that appeared every four courses, it would be game over and they'd have to start over from the beginning.
We didn't have a system to save the game, so it wasn't a big deal for the players.
But by playing the same course over and over again, it was fun to gradually improve.
This is back when you couldn't save your play data, so there was no way around it.
However, playing the same course over and over and the joy of gradually improving combined with the tension these challenges brought contributed to a greater feeling of accomplishment when you finally cleared a difficult course.
This gameplay loop was a new system that utilized a similar flow seen in arcade games of the past.
After that, on Super Mario Bros.
3, we implemented a map system similar to that found in board games, and added new elements that weren't just about clearing courses.
Even so, we've always valued having easy-to-understand courses, where the course design is a straight road.
But the tastes of players have also changed over the years.
So what challenges exist for Mario now, and how did they affect our approach for Super Mario Bros.
Wonder?
Let's have Mr. Mori speak on this.
Okay, I'd like to talk about gameplay strategies and player choice.
Another challenge for 2D Mario games that came to mind was limited player choice.
Past 2D Mario games had a minimum number of branches on the world map, but options such as being able to choose a course from multiple courses or being able to skip courses you couldn't clear did not exist.
Also, there were various power-up transformations, such as Fire Mario, Raccoon Mario, and Cape Mario, but since they were tied to the course, as in, you could only use a specific transformation on a specific course, players were not able to choose their preferred power-up.
In order to resolve the issue of limited player choice, we created an area where players can freely explore the world map and progress in the game while selecting the courses they want to play.
We created an area where players can freely explore the world map and progress in the game while selecting the courses they want to play.
Because the player can move freely, they can look at the thumbnail of a course and play what catches their interest, start with courses with lower difficulty, or play the easier break time courses.
It is also possible for players to skip the courses that they don't enjoy playing and progress in the game.
We first decided on a structure where if you collect a certain number of wonder seeds, the key item, you can progress in the game.
Wonder Seeds can be obtained in various ways.
Clearing courses, clearing Wonder Effects in courses, or buying them at poplin shops, and so on.
I believe this leads to an increased level of freedom in gameplay strategies.
Badges are a system that allows players to add abilities of their choice.
Here, I will be introducing some of these badges.
Impressive!
These are some of the things we adopted to address the challenge of limited player choice.
I think it's better to have an image of how you want to play when you think about playing.
For example, what do you imagine when you play Mario with your family?
When thinking of gameplay, I think it's a good idea to have an image of how you want players to play.
For example, what scene do you picture for a family playing a Mario game?
How about when someone's playing with someone they don't know over the internet?
What kind of gameplay did you imagine, Mr. Mori?
When I played with my family, I imagined everyone smiling with unexpected wonders.
Also, when I played with someone I didn't know online, I wanted to say thank you.
I imagined a family playing local co-op together, and an unexpected wonder effect happening, and everyone laughing about it.
And for online play, when playing with a stranger, I really wanted to create gameplay that would naturally make you want to say thank you to the stranger.
That's sweet.
I'd like to hear from the programmer and game designer, Mr. Mori, what he thinks about online play in Super Mario.
So what should online play look like for a Super Mario title?
I'd like to hear what you have to say as a programmer and game designer.
Okay, let me talk about online play.
From the beginning of development, in order to help 2D Mario games evolve, one of the topics we wanted to address was making a Mario game that can be played and enjoyed online.
However, while playing online with people from all over the world is very fun, I think there are a few challenges.
For example, when it comes to competitive games, beginners may lose a lot and quit.
If it's a cooperative game, less experienced players may slow the game down, and there is always the risk of people with poor online etiquette causing trouble.
These issues have been mentioned before, even within Nintendo.
In fact, Mr. Iwata has said the following, We've been discussing things for a long time, such as how parents can safely give online play to their children, and how to create a world without harassment.
There are many ways to solve this problem, but in Mario Wonder, other players don't directly interfere with you.
They help you when you make a mistake, give you items, and only do good things for you.
While there are many ways to overcome this challenge, for Super Mario Bros.
Wonder, instead of making it so other players can directly affect your environment, we made it so they can only take actions that would benefit you, such as reviving you when you get KO'd or by sharing their items with you.
Here is a video illustrating this.
Other players have been implemented in the form of translucent live player shadows to make it clear that they cannot break blocks, defeat enemies, etc.
However, there were challenges with the live player shadows.
There was no guarantee that there would be players near you on the same course at any given time.
To solve this problem, we made it possible for players to play standees of themselves on courses.
For these standees, we made the specs so that players cannot revive themselves with standees they place themselves.
Therefore, standees are placed not for your own benefit, but rather to help other players.
You can also play standees to tell other players about hidden elements.
Many people are involved in game production and online play.
When people interact with one another, we believe that acting not for yourself but for the people around you is important.
We help people around us when they are in trouble.
When you have a team made up of people with that mindset, there is a good chance something good will come out of it.
This holds true in game development as well.
For Super Mario Bros.
Wonder, we wanted to create a kind world like that, where online play is where you act not for yourself, but for the people around you.
We've been discussing things such as how can parents safely give online play to their children, how can we create a world without harassment, and we think that online play this time has become one of the answers.
During the development of online play for Super Mario Bros.
Wonder, we settled on the theme of subtle connection.
I believe this is one of the answers to the question, what should online play look like for a game featuring Mario?
Now, there may be some people who think there's a secret method behind game creation at Nintendo.
But the truth is, there is no definitive way to make games.
Each project has different set of priorities, and it's really up to you.
In the case of Super Mario Bros.
Wonder, our method was the one Mr. Mori shared today.
Our approach was to create and test various ideas for wonder effects and other seeds of gameplay, while also thinking about the best way to implement them.
While we hadn't decided on anything when development first started, we did hit a point where we felt like we had enough ingredients and therefore were ready to start cooking.
Essentially, we were creating while running.
But to be honest, I think we were running while also carrying feelings of uncertainty.
However, while we were running, while we were trying out various ideas, a unique character was born.
In Super Mario Bros.
Wonder, we introduced this unique character, the Talking Flower.
These Talking Flowers are the only characters that are fully voiced.
We use a variety of effects, graphics, and sounds to increase the player's immersion in games.
In previous Mario games, we included a clapping sound effect that triggers when you collect all the coins in a specified area.
The fanfare that sounds when players reach a goal was implemented because we knew players wanted to be praised for their gameplay.
But I thought players would feel even more immersed in games if that praise came more often, even for smaller accomplishments.
The results of these thoughts was the talking flower.
The character's number one goal is to give out praise or sympathy to increase player motivation and make play more rewarding.
In other words, they were created to aid in gameplay, like other effects.
I believe that the talking flowers helped contribute to increasing player motivation and making the play feel more real.
Now, I know there's a lot more we want to talk about, but I guess I should address the future of 2D games.
Before I do that, however, can I ask you for your final remarks, Mr. Mori?
Super Mario Bros.
will be 40 years old next year.
It may be difficult for the series to evolve for a long time.
However, not only in Mario, but also in other games, each title has its own challenges, and by solving them, new games will be created.
By doing so, 2D games will continue to evolve.
Super Mario Brothers turns 40 next year.
You might think it's difficult to make such a long-running series evolve.
However, new play is created by facing and solving the challenges that come with 2D titles.
This, of course, is not limited to Super Mario Brothers titles.
By doing this, I believe 2D games will continue to evolve into the future.
Thank you, Mr. Mori.
We noted that there are many ways to create games, but the first thing we think deeply about is what will become the core of the game.
I get very worried about production if I can't imagine what's going to be the fun of the game before we start polishing the graphics, sounds, and on-screen presentation.
If we proceed without that understanding, I don't think anything becomes more interesting as we move forward.
This is why I think it's good to put a considerable amount of effort into finding the core of the game.
Considering the angle of the game and its gameplay, it is easy to verify 2D games from various perspectives.
In addition to thinking about the core of the game and gameplay, we also need to verify they work.
And for various reasons, that's easy to do with 2D games.
2D games have a simple structure which makes it easier to focus on creating gameplay.
I don't mean to imply that the time and effort ultimately required to create a game is different between 2D and 3D.
Both take about the same amount of time, but in the case of 2D Mario, it's easier to make adjustments to courses and add new elements through the end of development.
As Mr. Mori noted, while we move forward taking on the challenges inherent in this franchise, a variety of new technologies will be created, blended with traditional 2D presentation, and perhaps, gameplay itself will change.
Did today's presentation pique your interest in 2D game development?
Thank you.
If you remember Mario Wonder and want to play it again,
If you heard what we had to say, were reminded of Super Mario Bros.
Wonder, and felt inspired to play it again, well, I could go home happy.
Mr. Mori talked about how 2D games will continue to evolve.
Perhaps I'm the one most looking forward to that future.
Maybe somebody in this audience will create a new 2D game, and of course, we hope to continue creating new ways to play in the years to come.
And let me say one last thing.
Thinking about gameplay is super fun.
I'd like to express my appreciation to all the people involved in the development of Super Mario Bros.
Wonder and everyone who supported our presentation today.
And of course, I'd like to thank all of you for listening to the end.
Thank you.