Hello, thank you. I'm Allie Overton and I want to talk to you about common problems in game art and how we can solve them.
So this talk is going to cover some game art basics because it's for those of you that don't have a lot of experience with game art
and are introducing it to your games.
We're going to talk about critique, the way we can treat things instinctually, and some ways that we can do it traditional
and apply that to practical game critique.
Also going to talk about vocabulary, probably terms you've heard, but maybe that you haven't
thought about as well as you could have.
And we're going to go over some examples.
So let's start with an example of an example.
So you're looking at your game and you're noticing that your character isn't as visible
as you would like it to be against the background.
What tools do you have at your disposal to make your character more visible?
What is your player looking at instead of your character?
Things to think about.
Well, let's start with critique.
Critique is a tool for finding the strengths
and weaknesses of an image.
So in our instinctive way, we critique things
as we'll see an image and we'll immediately judge it.
You have an opinion the first second you see the picture.
And then you justify your opinion.
You might say something like,
hmm, this picture's no good because that I think is a cat
and that's not a cat's face.
This can be valid.
There's plenty of times when this does merit valid feedback,
but you might see an image like this one
and offer the feedback that it's too blue.
And so with that, you or your artist fix it.
Bam, it's green.
Problem solves.
Or is it really?
Maybe what you meant was there was more colors needed.
So it's important to know what you're looking for
when you're critiquing an image.
So in traditional critique, there's a four-step structure.
You start by describing it.
It's a literal description of content.
You look at an image and you say,
there's two people, one of them's holding a pitchfork,
they're in front of a building,
they're both looking pretty frowny,
and that sort of thing, very content-based.
And then you analyze.
If this is a piece of traditional art,
you might talk about how it was made with acrylic
and what type of tools they made.
If it's digital art, you might tell them that it's made in Photoshop and you can tell by the pixels.
No matter what type of art it is, you talk about the way that color is used, the way contrast is used.
And then you interpret.
This is the sort of thing that people like to joke about when they're critiquing art.
They're like, hmm, yes, the spider painting is fascinating, but what does it say?
And there is some element of what does it mean to interpreting, but it's more about what did the artist intend.
Maybe the splatter painting really was just to get out some anger.
Maybe this portrait is a portrait of two people, it's very realistic based on who they are.
Or maybe it's a commentary on small town life.
What do you think the intention of the artist was?
And then, now that you've collected all of this information, you can judge.
You know how it was made, you have an inkling of why it was made, and so you can determine if it was effective.
So in that portrait, was it an accurate portrait in the splatter painting? Do you think the artist feels better now?
So how does this apply to practical critique for game art?
Well, there's one key difference, but most of the fundamentals are the same, and that difference is that you get to define your own goals.
This is your game.
You know what you want to do with your art,
you know what sort of thing you're trying to get across.
There's a few goals that are very common in game art.
One of them is portraying information.
You often want your player to be able to tell
at a glance where danger is.
You might want to control their focus.
Similar to information, you want them to look at
something in particular, a face, a dialogue.
It's very hard to get players to actually look at dialogue.
And then there's emotion.
Some games, this doesn't really affect them too much,
but there's very genre-based games like horror and others
that trying to get across emotion with your art
is very important to them.
And then style.
Style can be a variable thing.
Maybe you are a solo programmer and your style
is going to be minimalist and simple
because that's within your skill level.
Or maybe you're working with an artist
who's incredibly talented and you want to show them off.
Maybe marketing is a goal of yours and you want art that supports marketing and might go viral on Twitter.
Whatever your goals are, now that you know them and you've established them, and they can vary from these and include these and others,
you can determine the effectiveness of your visuals.
So, in V's, they make their information very clear using bright colors and interesting shapes
so that you can immediately read that something is dangerous.
In Dream Daddy,
They use detail and color and our natural inclination
to look at faces to draw your eye to the character,
as well as a really large text box
to make people actually look at the text.
And then in Limbo, they have interesting silhouettes
and desaturated colors that make you feel
the spookiness factor even more.
And in Bastion, they intentionally have
a more elaborate style that is very memorable
and interesting, but not necessarily a requirement
for their gameplay.
So with that, where is this image succeeding?
What can we change about it?
And what tools do we have to improve it?
Well, art vocabulary, this is how we talk about the tools
that we have to influence our visuals.
And there's a bunch of common ones.
So let's start with color.
You've probably heard of it.
So when we talk about color,
we might say that something is blue
and we want it to be a blue thing.
But blue could be blue or blue or blue.
So it's proper to be more specific, it's much more helpful.
So we usually talk about value,
because value is one of the main ways
we can make contrast in a visual.
Value is the light and dark in an image,
the gradient from brightest white to darkest black.
And hue is next, it's ignoring saturation and value.
Hue is basically color as we're learning as a kid.
It's the rainbow, red, orange, yellow, green, blue, purple.
And then saturation is how gray or vibrant something is.
This is regardless of hue and value.
Some people think saturation is also influenced by value,
but they're completely separate from each other.
So contrast can be between any of these elements.
Value contrast, like I said, is one of the most effective ones,
but it can also be a contrast of hues or a contrast of saturation.
Chess is an example of contrast of value.
It's the lightest white versus the darkest black.
Checkers is an example of contrast of saturation.
Very red, very vibrant versus desaturated black.
And Chinese checkers is a contrast of hues,
where you have only differentiation between hues
and not in value or saturation.
So when we talk about color,
it's important to try and talk about
all of these elements individually.
It's more valuable to say I want a light, bright sky
than it is to say I want a blue sky on its own.
So composition, there's a whole lot of elements
to composition in art, but one of the ones
that applies to gameplay the most is density.
High-density visuals are chaotic, busy, and noisy.
Density is basically just how much stuff is on the screen.
So if there's a bunch of stuff,
there's a bunch of stuff you gotta pay attention to.
They can make your visuals feel
more closed in, they can make you feel frantic, but they can also make your player space seem
more alive and vivid and full. And density can be either in the amount of content or
in the detail of the content. So in Enter the Gungeon, the amount of content they have,
because it's a bullet hell, inherently is a more high density visual. They try to lower the density
of the visuals in the background to make it more clear. In Bastion, they actually increase the
density of the visuals to make it a more full.
and immersive environment to add more detail to the art style.
Low density is the opposite.
It's open, it's minimal, it's airy.
It's easy to follow your eye through the space
and see things clearly.
It can also have the risk of looking unfinished or unpolished,
especially if you're doing a very minimal game.
Thomas' Alone is a very minimal game
that avoids this problem because it uses texture and lighting.
to fill in the lack of density that the gameplay offers.
On the other hand, the mortician's shell
is fairly dense in terms of interactability on the screen,
whereas it's lower in detail, which
allows you to see what's going on more clearly.
And then there's style.
Style, we often talk about stylized versus realistic.
But we also end up talking about cartoony.
And cartoony is a bit of a trap word.
It means a lot of different things
to a lot of different people.
So it's important to be more specific,
break things down into their elements.
So talking about color again,
you might have very saturated colors
and these are really good for giving moods in a scene.
The long dark offers a much more wondrous feeling
for its colors.
Whereas games that have more realistic colors
give you
a more sense of weight to your choices and your actions.
You feel like the things that you do in the game
should have more real world repercussion.
Line is one of those aspects of cartooniness
that you might talk about,
but it's a very graphic sort of thing.
It helps delineate things from their backgrounds.
If you do it in a more realistic game, it's very notable.
And if you remove line from a visual
that you might say is more stylized,
it really emphasizes the mood of a piece,
pointing more towards hue.
and value choices than towards the overall stylization.
And then proportion.
With funny proportions, you can stylize them
to the point where a character's head
is as big as his body,
and that will make things more cheery and funny.
But on the other hand, if you have more realistic proportions
in an otherwise stylized style,
you end up having more immersion
into the mood of that character.
You think of them as more of an elaborate,
fully-fleshed human.
And then there's light and shadow.
Zelda covers a lot of these through its games.
You can have absolutely no delineation of light and shadow,
or you can have flat light and shadow,
or you can have large gradations of light and shadow.
Whatever of these elements, color, line, proportion,
light and shallow that you use,
they can be anything in stylized and realistic.
It can be very stylized color with very realistic shadow.
You can have...
line on extremely realistic things, but the most important thing is to be intentional about your
choices. Make sure that they all go together and are cohesive. In Pokémon Sun and Moon,
the character has a large head and it's about the same size as their torso, and because of the level
of stylization throughout the rest of the style, it makes a cohesive piece. But if you have a more
realistic game and you have a giant head...
It stands out a little bit weird.
Now, in Lara Croft's big head mode,
they did that intentionally.
But if you do it on accident, nobody's
going to take your game seriously.
So that was a lot.
But let's talk about some examples.
So that example we talked about before,
we can pretty quickly tell that it's not
a high-density environment.
So that's not a factor in controlling the focus.
There's no frequency of detail that's
distracting us from the player.
So we can go to our color things.
What in the color spectrum is affecting this?
Well, hue, there's a delineation of hue
between the character and the background,
so that's not the problem,
but the real thing is value.
If you take away the hues, the saturation,
and look at it in grayscale,
you can immediately tell that the character
doesn't stand out against the background.
So it's good to up the values,
make the character more of a high contrast focus,
and that'll pop out more against the background.
immediately it's a lot easier to see what's going on
and focus on where you want to, where you're on the player.
So that's that in value.
And if you compare it to the original,
it's a lot easier to see what's going on.
All right, so in this game, this is the sort of game
where you're trying to light up a whole grid of networks.
But right now you can see the lit parts very easily
because in the hierarchy of value.
they're very bright. They're the only thing that contrasts heavily with the background.
But in this sort of game, what matters is not just the lit parts, also the dark parts. It's important
to give each piece of information in your games the same level, if they matter the same amount.
So if we bring the dark parts up in value to match, it's a lot easier to get the information
you need, because you need both parts of the puzzle to solve it. Before...
it was not the same level in the hierarchy
and you couldn't focus on the information
you needed to solve the puzzle.
So here is it before, it's hard to focus on the dark parts
that you need that information to solve the puzzle.
Now it's a lot easier to balance it,
so you can add contrast and hue to solve that problem.
All right, so this is the sort of thing
that happens when you're like.
I want a really bright, colorful game.
And you're extremely literal about what color is
and your saturation is just max.
Trees are green, sun is yellow, heroes have red hair,
and it's all as bright as possible.
So just cool it with your saturation, basically.
You can do things to make your game interesting
without just making it as in your face as possible
in like an MS Paint drawing
you made when you were 13 years old.
So if you calm down your saturation, you can make more interesting, less literal color
choices.
A tree trunk can be purple, whatever.
It's more interesting and less literal, and it catches the eye as much, but it's not quite
as painful.
And if you still want to go even further, you can be even less literal, stylize your
colors even more, and do something a little weird, and people will find that very memorable,
but not painful.
And then so you can have something that people like.
at the end of the day.
So visual clarity.
This can happen when you're trying to reuse assets,
especially to minimize the amount of art labor you're doing.
Like you get something in the assets there
and you just recolor it.
You have a green ally and a red enemy.
But if you're colorblind,
these enemies look basically the same to you.
And there's ways to work around that.
Like value, contrast, works for everybody.
If you make adjustments to help with people
with visual impairments.
It helps everybody delineate things better,
not just people who are visually impaired.
So other options are to,
like see, you can immediately tell
that it's more different for everyone.
Other options are to include symbology,
not just in character design or faces,
but if you have a particle effect that's red
when it's good and green when it's bad,
add some sort of symbol like stars or angry Xs
to delineate symbolically what's good or bad.
so that everyone can tell what's going on more easily.
So you can see that this is much easier to see for everyone
whether or not you're colorblind.
All right, one of the challenges of 3D lighting
is when you put a light in your scene
and you realize everything is still too dark,
so just keep upping the intensity of the lighting.
This is fairly common,
and people are getting first into 3D art
or making 3D games.
So most...
engines and 3D renderers have an environmental light or a skybox which you can increase the
lighting value of so that you have a flat level of light. It makes your shadows less dark. It
decreases the overall contrast of your image and lets you do stuff more intentionally instead
of accidentally having black value shadows distracting from the art that you're trying
to pour across. And then once you do that you can use color.
And using a warm color can give you more of a narrative experience like candlelight,
instead of the intense high white that makes you feel like you're in an office.
And then you can also use color other ways to just affect the mood, make things feel magical,
make things feel silly or spiritual or just fun. This is it before, and this is it once you try to
do lighting more intentionally, instead of just trying to light it enough that everyone can see.
And some fancy backgrounds.
So you have a game, you put a fancy background in it,
and now nobody can stop looking at the background
and they're not paying attention to your player anymore.
So, it's another thing where there's value contrast problems.
There's more value contrast in the background
than there is in the player.
This is also a density thing.
There's a high density background
and a low density player.
But that's also a type of contrast.
A contrast of densities can also be valuable.
So that's not the worst part.
The worst part is.
the value contrast being more interesting in the background.
So if we drop down the value contrast,
make it more of a mid-tone, the player comes out.
But it's also good for the player itself
to be more high contrast because you want to be able
to do a lot of things with your backgrounds.
You want them to be able to be diverse.
If you make a high contrast player,
it can be more intentionally put
against a low contrast background
and you can have a wide variety of low contrast backgrounds.
You can also solve this problem by having a light player against a dark background,
but that gives you less options for the diversity of your backgrounds.
You can also do a dark player against a light background.
But that leads you to end up making the same choices in your environment art
for the rest of your gameplay.
So that's what it was like originally, and this is our revision.
You can immediately see that the player is a lot easier to pick out against the content.
All right, too cute is a thing that happens a lot in art.
People have a lot of opinions about what level of cuteness
they want in their games.
And there's a lot of elements to cuteness
that is kind of vague and confusing.
One immediately obvious one about this one
is that it's a very saturated green zombie
against a spooky background.
So if we drop down the saturation,
immediately the mood, the style that you're going for
comes across more effectively.
But there's also the other elements of stylization we talked about, one of which was proportion.
Big things, like weird proportions, big heads, big eyes, make things feel a lot more cute
very quickly.
So we shake down the head, more creepy.
And we can also shrink down the eyes once again.
So you have your green guy, who's not the creepiest he could be, and then you desaturate
him of just his proportions, and he gets a lot creepier very fast.
Less cute.
All right.
So there is a lot going on here and that's pretty typical for game visuals. Like you're trying to
get a bunch of stuff in, maybe it's not as cohesive as you planned, maybe you didn't make
a plan from the beginning, and you're kind of overwhelmed. So the thing to do, I think, first is
take away the gameplay aspect and focus on your backgrounds.
Just like before, this is a very high density background.
with a lot of value contrast.
If we lower the value contrast,
you can immediately put more stuff in the foreground
that will pop out more.
You can see this with the spider web,
but the spider web also doesn't need
to be a high contrast item.
It informs the gameplay
and it's an interesting storytelling element,
but it's not important to the gameplay.
So you can reduce that as well.
And now when you put things back on the screen,
it's a lot easier to see what's going on
and understand what's happening.
So...
Now that we've resolved the background problems, let's look at the characters.
There's actually a lot of good stuff happening with some of the characters in this. Each of the
butterflies has a unique pattern and a unique color, so no matter what color impairment you
might have, you can still tell based on the pattern that they're different, and they have
hue separation for each player to recognize them as well. But now that we've adjusted the background
to more of a medium tone,
the spider is a lot harder to see and pick out.
So we want to do a value adjustment on that spider
so that it pops out.
Make it darker, you can see it a lot better.
And we also made the eyes a different hue.
The hue contrast between the spider's eyes
and the environment is now greater,
so you can pick that out.
And in games that are static,
where you have static elements,
you can also do something like put a light
in the background to increase the contrast.
It's harder to do.
in open world games, but if you have a 2D game,
it's something that you can use.
All right, so if we bring back our bullets,
like I said earlier, bullet hells have a sort of
inherent density challenge.
So we need to do what we can to make it clearer.
So these bullets have a delineation strategy
that's super common in the memes the kids do,
which is you have a white object in a black outline
or a dark outline.
It's purple in this case.
But now that we've changed the values of the image,
now we have darker values.
We don't need a dark value around a white object
because the white object is already brightest.
And it confuses things like the hitbox
and where things would land if you were playing.
So it's better to make things bright.
You can see where the bounds of the bullets are a lot easier
and figure out what's going on more easily.
And you can have a color association
between the bullets that the boss produces
and the boss itself.
If we go to the player bullets, it's a lot easier to delineate the bullets from each other now already,
because the yellow is very different from what they are looking like.
But we'd like to give the player as much information as we can,
so why don't we color the bullets to match the player?
More information is always good. We want the players to know what's going on.
And then we want to delineate the bullets differently
between the players and the boss even more.
And you can do shape for that, just like I talked about
when I talked about color blindness.
But you might want to reserve unique shapes
for special weapons or power-ups.
So you can just use size to tell the player
that a bullet is friendly or an enemy.
If it's a small bullet, it's a friendly bullet.
and that makes it a lot easier to see what's going on.
There's less visual density,
there's more open space between things,
and you can figure out what's happening a lot more easily.
So this is what it looked like before,
and this is what it looks like now.
So we talked about critique, how we do it instinctively,
and a good way to think about it for actual game development.
We talked about color and composition and style,
and how those affect our game visuals.
And we applied it, so hopefully you can now apply these
to your own game visuals, but every game is different.
These solutions that I've used are optional solutions.
You can use a lot of different strategies
with the elements I've talked about
to solve gameplay problems and solve your goals
for your games and figure out what suits your game best.
Thank you, I'm Allie.
You can.
Thank you, Ali.
If you have a question for Ali,
please come to the mic in the middle of the aisle there.
I will get things started myself.
This is awesome stuff and a lot of info.
How do you communicate this stuff
when you're working with other, you know, within teams?
If someone gives you that,
it's too blue or something like that,
do you give them a whole, you know, half an hour type talk
or you just give them a small piece of this?
Well, I'm hoping I can just link them
to my talk in the future.
But usually you try to ask questions back.
So if somebody is like, it's too blue, you just ask, do you
mean it's too saturated?
Do you mean you want it to be a different color?
Just try to use the knowledge that you have to ask them and
lead them to the correct solution.
Any questions?
Hi, thank you for the great talk.
Thank you.
So I definitely paid attention to the Owl My Eyes slide
because I'm working on a very colorful platformer,
and I probably am gonna hurt some people's eyes.
So that was great, I need to think about that.
How would you think about styles,
very colorful, bright, saturated styles
that like Nintendo uses?
What kind of tools might they use
or might think about something like that
to be able to hit that kind of toy-like,
fun approach without hurting people's eyes?
So the question is how to use bright colors successfully
without hurting people's eyes.
Well, basically you are more aware of saturation.
As vivid as those sorts of games tend to seem,
they have various levels of saturation
that makes the colors more compatible.
You might have a red and a green on screen together as well,
but you won't put them on the same character
and that makes it a lot safer.
So you use the sort of density.
and minimalist space separation between elements.
So that if you have the highest of contrast colors,
they're not next to each other.
Like Mario is red and blue and Luigi is green and blue,
but neither of them are green and red,
which are the most hue and color saturation contrasts
that you could have.
Hi.
Have you ever dealt with highly complex machine models?
Like how would you...
So I work in a company that has very small team,
but we do very complex objects.
So have you ever had to deal with stuff like,
say a car, like taking apart or breaking it down?
Like they are very realistic,
but how would you kind of manage the styling of that?
In what way?
It's tough because we have to maintain product integrity,
but then we also have to do artistic.
I don't know if you guys have ever had to deal with that,
with like, hey, make this thing look cool,
but not too realistic.
Sorry, I just didn't know that's a vague question.
So you're asking how you can make detailed machine models
look stylized in an interesting way?
Yeah.
Well, it depends on what elements you're allowed to play
with based on your thing.
I'm working on a game where I make a lot of weird planes.
But they're not anywhere in the realm of realistic.
We just do a bunch of strange shapes
and play with color palettes to make them stick out
in unique ways.
So it depends on which parts of your game or visuals
you're allowed to play with.
If you can stylize your color, it's
always a really fun way to work with stuff
and make things more interesting.
OK, I actually have, I guess, a more specific question.
Have you ever had to deal with conflict with preference
over certain color palettes?
That's very common.
Color palettes are super opinion-based.
That's the sort of thing where you play test it
and see where it's effective.
Because no matter what situation you're in,
there are always people with different opinions.
And you think about your target audience
and what they are most likely to want to see.
Okay, thank you.
Thanks.
All right, I think that's.
That's going to wrap things up.
Please make sure you fill out your email surveys
to give Ali some feedback on her talk.
Thank you so much, Ali.