Hi guys, I'm Kate, I'm a physical therapist, and I'm here with some of the team from 1HP
to talk about the early research into health and performance in esports.
So to kick things off, we'll do a little bit of an introduction and then we'll dive right
into it.
So like I said, my name is Kate. I'm a physical therapist.
I've been a physical therapist for about six years now since 2015.
I've been working in eSports for about the same amount of time.
I'm the co-owner of a company called OneHP,
which is a company founded by physical therapists
and we provide health and performance services to players,
to teams, to schools, as well as helping non-endemic companies
understand the eSports healthcare landscape.
And we provide our expertise for everything from compression gear to new research initiatives.
We are also, every single one of us, absolute gaming fanatics.
Ask me about my Guild Wars 2 crafting level hack sometime.
I got my graduate degree from the University of Delaware.
number one PT program in the country.
I'm also the editor, co-editor of the Handbook of Esports Medicine,
which is the first clinical textbook in the field of esports health and performance.
I'm also an associate editor for the Annals of Esports Research,
which is the first ever North American-based esports research journal.
And I'm here with two of my colleagues, Elliot and John.
So Elliot, why don't I hand it off to you?
My name is Elliot Smithson, and first and foremost, I'm also a huge gamer, as Kate mentioned, played World of Warcraft for about 10 years, got into the Fortnite scene after that, but I've been playing games since I could hold a controller.
A little bit more relevant to my medical history, I finished my undergraduate degree from the
University of Central Florida in athletic training and sports medicine. Then I went
on to Marshall University and got a master's in the same degree. I finished my doctorate
of physical therapy in 2019 from University of St. Augustine with a heavy emphasis on
manual therapy techniques. I've been working in sports medicine and performing arts medicine
for the past 10 years in various facets.
Esports really caught my interest because of a blending of several passions of mine
for helping gamers actually optimize their not only performance,
but also their health and ability to continue doing what they love without pain.
It's a great pleasure for me to be here speaking to you guys today,
and I really hope you guys can take something away from this lesson
that we can all apply to our individual practices.
Hi everybody, I'm Dr. Jonathan Chung, DC.
I'm also a person's trainer.
I'm the chiropractor on the team. I'm from Canada as well, so the northern contingent of 1HP.
I did my undergrad in life sciences and a minor in economics from Queen's.
I also did my doctor of chiropractic at the Canadian Memorial Chiropractic College in Toronto.
I've been with 1HP for a while now, about a year.
It's been an awesome time. I've learned a ton, and I'm hoping that I can help the...
Listeners here learn some more stuff about esports research.
It's a very interesting topic and it's something that we need to be evidence-based practitioners, which we should all aspire to.
Right. So let's talk a little bit about why we need that research in the first place.
Um, because e-sports medicine is a fairly new field. And in fact, up until about, I don't know,
two years ago or so, we didn't even really have a name for this field of medicine. It was just,
we were healthcare workers who happened to do e-sports stuff. And we've in that time coined
the name e-sports healthcare or e-sports medicine. And when I say we, I don't just
mean the team at one HP. There are other physical therapists, there's physiatrists.
There's absolutely sports psych professionals working in this industry, but we're pretty
short on data right now, or at least published, peer-reviewed, replicable data.
The reason that we need that data?
Well, for one thing, there's a pretty large population of people that play eSports.
They've probably got specific needs.
We need to make sure we're knowing what they are so we can address them appropriately.
Two, we need to consider the financial consideration for teams and developers.
So looking at the way that the NFL, for example, or the WNBA has invested in research on their players,
that affects player longevity, player injury risk, player performance,
all of which has a financial tie into the league and to the
I guess the ownership there, it's similar in eSports.
And really, this is a field in a population
that is distinct enough to need its own data.
Sure, there's some similarities
between office workers and eSports competitors.
And sure, there's some similarities
between traditional sports and eSports competitors.
But they're still, in our opinion,
as people who've worked in this field
for six plus years now,
distinct enough to need their own research.
One of the questions we get asked a lot is,
are esports sports and are esports competitors athletes?
As though this determines whether or not
this research should be done on this population.
And honestly, our answer is who the heck cares
whether they're athletes or not,
and who the heck cares whether this is sports or not.
We don't decide that something's not worth studying,
understanding, or approaching with intention.
just because it is or isn't a traditional sport.
So we should give the same amount of consideration
to esports competitors that we do to sports competitors,
even if we're considering the specifics
of what they do in different ways.
And sure, we can draw from what we know in sports science
about competition, about psychology in particular,
about periodizing training schedules,
but we need to make sure that when we're doing this research,
we're not just thinking of esports
as a more sedentary version of traditional sports
because it's not.
So in the meantime, who can we borrow from?
Quite a few, really.
As I mentioned, we can absolutely look at office workers
and traditional athletes.
Office workers obviously use much of the same equipment
as a large population that plays eSports competitively.
Keyboards, mice, monitors.
Not so much using joysticks and controllers as much.
So they're leaving out our console players a little bit
with just comparing that office worker research.
We can also look, however, at folks like air traffic controllers, who do a cognitively demanding task, sitting in the same position for a really long period of time. That's applicable to eSports.
Looking at musicians, competing, performing in front of a large crowd, having some component of entertainment as well as skill at what you're doing.
In addition to them, maintaining a single static posture with really precise spine motor movement, definitely eSports.
And chess competitors, heavily cognitive, also involves stable static posture.
Doesn't so much require you to have perfect precision, but I suppose if you know you want to make sure you're not touching your knight when you mean to pick up your rook, I guess that requires some amount of precision here.
But even with our ability to borrow from the research that's been done in each of these regions,
esports is still separate and distinct from all these fields. Sure, we described overlaps,
but none of them are 100% this fits exactly. The Venn diagram is a perfect circle.
So to provide evidence-based care, we need evidence. We need our own evidence,
evidence that's specific to esports competitors.
So let's talk a little bit about the data that exists right now.
John, what do you got for us?
Well, we do have some research.
It's not like we are completely devoid, but we need more.
It's just not enough.
We have some anecdotal advice from osteopaths or people
who have some ideas on how to use acupuncture on gamers.
We have some specific pain presentation research.
So for example, low back.
But the very rare thing that we don't have a lot of
is...
causation of pain studies. And those are very important, as you
can imagine, because if we understand the pathology of a
condition, then we can be much more proactive about preventing
it or treating it. There's also some studies for gamers, we're
not just looking at studies that necessarily have to do with pain
specifically, I think there's a lot of different facets of the
medical literature that are being looked at here. Is that
correct, John?
Yeah, exactly. We are like Kate mentioned pulling from other fields. So the causation
of pain study I talked about where we're looking at the speed and force of keyboard operation
that was done on symptomatic and asymptomatic office workers.
The other important part of esports is the performance aspect, which does have some research on it, and looking at some of the emotions and some of the differences between a pro player and a casual player are also really illuminating for us when we're trying to determine how to treat this population.
It's really, really interesting right now, being in the esports research field because there's just so many things we need.
Yeah.
If we can get some of those really, really interesting topics in, we're going to talk
about that a little bit, but we can do some really, really awesome things in this space.
Yeah, and so there's a reason that there's three musculoskeletal medicine professionals on this
call. There aren't too many of us who work in esports. I mentioned there's a couple. There's
a couple more than even just work at 1HP, but the number of folks who are really experienced
and experts in this particular field is limited.
And I don't even call myself an expert, I'm just reasonably experienced at this point.
We have experience, we have some degree of expertise, but we don't have data. And without
data, we can't provide this kind of education to medical professionals who aren't as in the
know about gaming, who aren't gamers themselves, potentially. So we end up with this awkward gap
between players and the professionals that they go to. You know, we've had plenty of players come
to us and say, yeah.
Oh yeah, you know, I went to my doctor and because I had wrist pain and he told me to put on a brace and just rest for a while and that's not really an option for folks who eSports is their job, their career, they make money off of this, they need to be able to do it and they need something more proactive than just rest and brace, which doesn't really work anyway for most tendon issues.
So part of the reason why we need this data obviously is for medical professionals to do
better by the eSports community. But part of the reason we need the research too is so that eSports
competitors take their health and their performance seriously and recognize that they're being taken
seriously. It's kind of a mark of respect to be doing this kind of research that yeah this field
is serious enough that it deserves its own time and attention.
So we're going to go into a little bit of some of the studies that are out there right now. This is by no means a comprehensive review. This is just a look at kind of some of the samples of the work that's available currently.
We'll make some recommendations about what we think could additionally be done, and then talk a little bit more about the overall research landscape.
Exactly.
So, this study was basically talking about what we were just discussing.
You need to treat eSports players like real patients.
They deserve care.
They deserve good care.
They deserve evidence-based care.
They also mentioned, like we've been harping on, we need more research too.
We want to be the most evidence-based we can and really push that side of things
because that's where healthcare is going.
The interesting part about the study was it is an editorial, but it has a very powerful message.
And I...
John, just for folks who aren't in like the research field, what's, let's describe what an editorial is too.
It's more of an opinion piece. So we're not really running an RCT, we're not doing a randomized control trial, we're not so much looking at subjects, but we're looking at...
What a need might be in this particular case and discussing it so that there's more information
on the topic and starting that dialogue. I will also say from a very pragmatic
perspective, people writing editorials and getting them published in research journals
is a really great way to convince your academic institutions that, oh, we should fund grant money
for this particular research project where you want to test gamers on things. That's one of
the utilities of editorials for sure.
Definitely.
It's definitely a hallmark of early research.
Yeah, this was a good paper.
I enjoyed it.
And one thing they brought up, which is interesting, is that esports is getting bigger, which means
that competitions are getting bigger, prize pools are getting bigger, and there's a lot
of pressure on the line when you're competing at the International for a million dollars
or more.
You can imagine that for some players that's a lot.
But if we can get ahead of that and look at some of those risk factors and be proactive,
then you won't have people retiring early.
They'll have long, fulfilling careers.
And that's what we want for every gamer.
Resident Dota Nerd, I do have to note that the last time a team competed for only a million
at The International was like at least 6 years ago at this point. Prize pool for
2019 was like what, 23 million I think overall. That's nuts.
Yeah. That's nuts.
More pressure, though. Right?
Sorry, I gotta defend my dota. No, no, please. Fact check me. I like it.
But yes, we know that there's a lot of pressure.
We know that there's a lot of competition.
We know that things are getting,
and more and more sports teams are buying
into the e-sports world.
But we still don't have that much data
on how to optimize play and practice in e-sports.
Exactly.
This next study was also very interesting. It was a scoping meta-review, which is when you're looking at research for people who aren't as familiar, you're looking at other reviews. So you're taking a wide bird's eye view of what might be out there in the research. And surprise, surprise, we need more.
Surprise, surprise, there's not much.
Surprise.
There's going to be a theme here, guys.
It's, yeah, yeah.
Can you tell that we structured the presentation
in a certain way to maybe push a certain agenda?
But the interesting thing is that some of those hallmarks
of gaming and eSports that we assumed were inviolable
are perhaps not quite so much.
So...
One thing a lot of people assume is that esports can make you more sedentary and predisposes you to weight gain.
But in one of the reviews that this scoping review looked at, it was non-significant findings.
social aspects of gaming. Yes, it can be a little isolating at times, but it can also expand your
friend group online. And I'm sure that many of us who have been stuck at home for a certain period
of time, I'm sure you can understand that seeing someone virtually and spending time with them,
it's not the same as being in person, but it's still a very powerful and a very nice experience.
And gaming is one of the things that facilitates that. It lets us connect with each other,
which to me is one of the most beautiful things about it.
Elliot, did you have any thoughts?
Yeah, I think that there is some research out there that kind of looks at just what you were talking about, the socialization aspect of gaming.
I believe there's a study looking at World of Warcraft players and how they
are actually able to fight off kind of the symptoms
or the pitfalls of gaming, internet gaming disorder,
better than some of their counterparts that play solo games.
So I really think that speaks to the fact that
social gaming really does have some positive impacts
on people's ability to
Have better mental health.
So more studies like this that are specific
for gamers' mental health, I think are really, really critical.
And we're going to talk about a couple.
I think it's also really key that we're looking at not just the, you know,
how do we make sure that eSports is competitive?
How do we make sure that eSports competitors are healthy
and performing at their best?
But also looking at the general overall landscape of, I guess,
the community that surrounds that whole eSports competition sphere.
So looking at.
Does playing this particular game competitively
have any impact on your fine motor control?
Does it have any impact on your ability
to regulate your emotions?
Does playing a team game versus playing a solo game
have an increased or a decreased effect
on your ability to control your emotions?
How does team communication play into that,
you know, that feeling of tilt,
that feeling of being stressed out and anxious
and frustrated at a game?
These are all really great questions
that we don't have a whole lot of answers for.
There's definitely more research
on the psychological side of non-competitive gaming
and kind of the social health there,
but there's not nearly as much on the communication,
teamwork, and performance side of e-sports
as associated with mental health,
as associated with mental skills,
like emotional regulation, like executive function.
Exactly. So one of the things that this scoping review shows us is there's not all that much. We need more.
Yes, exactly.
This one was pretty great though, and I know John, you're pretty excited to talk about this one.
Because this was one of the first ones that discussed like gamer health specifically.
It's to be clear, not just esports.
But there really, again, there's not too many studies that are differentiating
gaming from esports, like competitive gaming right now.
So we did have to fold in some of the non-competitive gaming studies here.
Yeah, exactly.
So this was a really, really awesome...
And they looked at trying to optimize three things, which is you want to build awareness of common MSK problems and health hazards.
They want to promote health in the gaming space, and then some recommendations for performance.
I love this framework. You want to treat gamers holistically.
It's not just pain, but you also want to care about performance.
You play games to have fun and to compete.
And especially in eSports, the competition side is paramount, so performance has to be
considered in this situation.
One thing that I didn't love about the study was they did mention carpal tunnel quite a
few times, and Kate will explain why that perhaps is not ideal a little bit later on.
They did a great job but ergonomics, it gives you some
some baselines. So just to run through for anybody who doesn't
know, generally, ergonomics are a way for you to hold yourself
for a long period of time without a ton of strain on your
muscles to, ideally decrease pain, but
Ergonomics aren't everything.
It's also, are you taking breaks?
Are you hydrating enough?
Are you sleeping enough?
Is your nutrition on point?
Is your mental health solid?
All those things contribute to your pain perception
and your overall health as well.
And we also know that actually changing your posture
is the best.
Kate's smiling very widely right now
because she loves talking about this.
We have a catchphrase.
People think about their chair as like, ah, I'm sitting in my chair for so many hours
while gaming.
My chair must be the most important part of my posture and my ergonomics.
I did not coin this phrase.
I stole it from a designer for Herman Miller, but the phrase is, your best posture is your
next posture, which is to say moving around consistently is better than any one posture
could ever be.
You've probably seen me fidgeting around in my chair during this presentation, and we're
only 20 minutes in at this point.
I strongly recommend everybody who's tuning in right now do a little bit of shifting around,
do a little bit of stretch. This is a great stretch break opportunity.
But that's something that we really want to make sure as we're doing this research, we're
incorporating, we're not reinventing the wheel, so to speak.
So yes, we want our own eSports specific research, but we also want to take what we already know
from really analogous lifestyles, office workers, chess players, air traffic controllers, who
do have to sit for long periods, and incorporating what we know there about consistent movement,
and rather than like going and testing.
Are gamers better at playing if they maintain the same position or are they better at playing
if they change positions often? We know the answer. It's going to be the second one. We
don't need to do that study. You can if you really want to and somebody's going to fund it,
but perhaps we should put our, you know, research efforts in some more specific regions.
Perhaps, perhaps.
And there's also the performance aspect of ergonomics too.
Your muscles have an optimal length-tension relationship where they can react the fastest,
they can be the strongest, and ergonomics is part of that.
It puts you in the position so that your muscles can work the most effectively.
Making that connection for some of our gamers we've worked with,
it makes a big difference because suddenly it's not just,
oh, do this and I won't hurt as much,
it's also do this and I'll click more heads,
do this and I'll play better.
That's important.
And if we're able to put the numbers in front of people, say, look, if you do this healthy thing, you will perform better if we have the data and the research to back that up, we can point them to a study and say, yes, we can prove that this helps.
That makes all the difference in the world because the gaming population and eSports in particular is justifiably skeptical of non endemic folks, let alone medical folks coming in and wanting them to make changes to what they're doing.
So if we're able to say, yeah, we can prove that this will make you play better,
then absolutely. That's so much better than just saying, I'm an expert and you should listen to me.
We have to give a why. Here's why you should listen. Here's the proof.
I think that is a really interesting paradigm coming in as non-endemic people in the space,
or even if you have some gaming experience, unless you've played at a professional level,
there is a lot of skepticism about your ability to make meaningful changes to the habits and
behaviors of these players, because the mentality really is, hey, I made it this far on my own,
when everybody else doubted me. They're coming from a lot of, oftentimes,
I'm going to go ahead and start the presentation.
So, I think we're seeing a lot of resistance from friends and families
that like have questioned like their journey to professional gaming.
I think we're seeing less and less of that as these things become more
accepted.
There are organizations dedicated to.
Educating parents on.
How e-sports is actually a profitable profession and can build these
make their dreams come true, it's really important that we are able to actually provide the research
that shows that this can be done in a safe and healthy way and how to really demonstrate the
benefits. And we'll talk a little bit more about that later, the benefits of gaming on kind of what
we can take away as a society as a whole.
But anyway, we're going to transition, speaking of performance, into kind of a more sports psychology, mental health, kind of intertwined with physiology type study here.
So this was a really interesting study that looked at both psychological factors and physiological factors.
So that kind of means more body response to stress and specifically pregame stress.
And while we took a look at this study and we kind of concluded that it was fairly obvious information,
what they ended up doing or finding was that professional players have greater psychological stress responses than non-professional players before a match.
And I think that...
go without saying in a lot of our minds, like of course that the pro player with money on the line is going to have more stress than the amateur player who's just playing kind of for fun or for bragging rights.
It's really important that we start laying the foundation
for all of the work to be done on top of this.
So now you can take a study like this
and then cite this in other studies,
given that this is already a known factor.
Like, yes, we know that the psychological factors
of stress are gonna be greater in professional players.
So now you can start building the case out
for hundreds of other studies on top of this.
So foundational work like this, while it may seem very, very simple and very, very rudimentary,
is still wildly important in developing the field for everyone that comes after.
So I think... Sorry, go ahead, Kate.
I mean, it's obviously important for researchers and professionals.
But again, this is also really important to gamers, to teams, to competitors.
Because, sure, they'll take a look at this and say,
like, yeah, no, of course I'm more stressed when I'm playing, you know,
in the finals of the International than I was when I was playing in the AD2L,
Amateur Dota 2 League in the US.
But sometimes research needs to quantify or prove obvious things that everybody in the industry knows so that one, we can communicate this to outside people and so that two, we can find the ways to address it.
Because if we can't establish in the research, this is a thing we need to address.
Then how do we test what's the most effective way to address it.
We've quantified something we've only theorized about previously, which means we can address it more consistently.
And we can say, yes, absolutely, we need folks who have sports psychology backgrounds, who have performance psychology backgrounds.
We've provided concrete evidence here that competing at a high level is not the same as just casually playing.
So that's important data for the players, that's important data for the teams, that's important data for anybody who wants to talk about, like,
How are they making a million dollars playing video games?
I play video games.
I should have gone into eSports.
No, you're not actually any good of it, Jan.
I'm also not any good at it, which is why I'm not a professional eSports player.
We are spitting the facts.
But like, so studies like this, well to those of us who've ever had any exposure whatsoever
to eSports are like, no duh, of course this is the result. This is really, really important
to making sure that we're providing the best possible care to players because we're able
to say yes, we've established without a shadow of a doubt, this is peer-revealable
Replicable data that says, yeah, this exists, and we need to address it as a result.
Exactly. It's validating. And that's the important part. And it's not just for us,
but for anyone who might be new to the space who thinks, like Kate just said,
it's just video games. How could it be stressful? It is. When there's millions of dollars on the
line, I think anybody would be a little stressed.
And I like that they in this study not only looked at the psychological factors and psychological research can sometimes get a bad rap for not being expressly objective, but they actually looked at the cortisol levels in these players.
So cortisol is a stress response hormone. So they really went in and did the blood work and looked at the actual cortisol response and noticed that it was higher.
So it's not just something that you can say is, quote unquote, in your head.
But there is an actual physiological response to this, which I think is just a really cool blending of both the psychological and the physiological.
Yep.
You can't entirely disassociate the two, they kind of have to work together.
And I really think that that is something that once the entire eSports industry understands we will see a major explosion in progress, as far as performance goes and.
I've been really interested to see, actually, that a lot of the places where teams have been
interested in investing more long-term so far has been in that psychological side of things,
which I think is fantastic because that is such a key component of things. But as this and other
studies will show, we do have to address both sides of it. We can't just address the body or
the mind. We need to address the two in conjunction in order to improve not just health but performance.
Right, this goes back to the our esports and athlete athletes discussion, where it's oftentimes brushed off that the whole athletic component because it's not perceived to be much movement involved but as we know from working in this.
And as you can see from the musculoskeletal pain patterns
that we're about to talk about,
there is a lot of movement going on here.
If you're using your body to do something,
you should be addressing that just as much as the mind,
but it is interesting how much emphasis is placed
on the psychological in esports.
But...
I'm segueing myself here into the next slide.
Self-assessment.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
There was a study done on Danish esports athletes,
and this was a survey.
So again, this is kind of a hallmark of early research.
A survey is not necessarily the best way
to get hard, objective data,
and we're not testing anything here.
So you're not comparing one group to another
like the previous study actually did.
You are just looking at responses of these athletes.
So you may not be getting the highest quality of metrics from this,
but it is definitely worth looking at and then actually taking these findings
and then progressing them into more of kind of a randomized control trial study.
But anyway, they had 188 responses, which is pretty good for esports, to be honest.
It really is, honestly.
And they were pretty representative of the population.
And 42 percent report reported having some kind of musculoskeletal pain,
which is absolutely huge.
If 50 percent of your population is complaining of something,
it is definitely worth exploring.
Yeah, you address it.
If half the people we're working with are hurting.
Yeah.
And yeah, and as musculoskeletal professionals, as physical therapists,
we we have this.
This study is a little bit closer to our hearts,
but that doesn't mean to say it's more important than any of the other factors
that we've been considering here.
But a lot of the pain sites that people were reporting,
31% of people reporting back pain.
So whether or not they were differentiating between upper back, lower back.
I'm not entirely sure in this study, but back pain seemed to be the biggest, the site of pain for these players.
And that I think is massively groundbreaking for perceptions of the community.
I think every time that someone non-endemic to esports has...
I'm going to get into that. There's a slide about that. Don't worry.
Carpal tunnel is an issue in the hand.
And that's not even the biggest issue that we see
when we pull gamers at large.
Most of the pain is in the back.
So even just foundational studies like this
can be so meaningful just to be able to point to this
and be like, no, it's actually back pain.
Neck pain is huge.
Shoulder problems can develop.
There's a lot of hip.
and kind of glute pain that go along with gaming as well.
Nerve symptoms that can be triggered by tight muscles.
There's a lot more to this than wrist pain.
I actually pulled up the supplemental research on this
where they kind of list out the percentages of players here
that are experiencing different region or pain in different regions of the body.
So it goes back at 31%, neck at 11%, shoulder at 11%, headaches at 8%, forearm at 7%, wrist at 6%, hand and fingers at 5%.
That is...
That's huge, like to understand that, no, it's not really all wrist and hand pain.
You've got other areas of the body that need exploring here.
And that's going to change kind of the way that we approach studying this population
and molding future studies.
So I hope I've kind of delivered the point here
of how important these foundational studies are.
And how simple it is to come up with a concept and just run with it as far as the study goes, because chances are you are doing something meaningful, whether you think it's a very specific topic or a very simple topic.
And we'll get a little bit into kind of more action steps later and how we can go about formulating some of these study topics, but I think that's huge.
That one of the one of the things that we can run into with a survey study, which this one was.
Is we're not getting necessarily objective data that we've measured, we're getting someone's
perception of what's going on. Which we can absolutely build out surveys that make things
less subjective, more objective. We can build in questions that kind of back check each other in
order to establish internal consistency within a survey. But survey studies like this are a
really great place to start for two reasons. One, they're pretty darn inexpensive and when
nobody wants to fund your research you need an inexpensive study to start with.
And two, the result of this study, you can then take it, especially if you get it published,
and say, look, we have published data that establishes back pain is a serious problem
for eSports competitors. We want to research that further. Then you can actually get grant
money for that stuff.
So kind of within kind of the progression of research, yes, we'd love to be testing a whole bunch of things that we've observed either anecdotally or from our experience.
But survey studies like this basically quantify that observed experience, and then let researchers actually study it in a way that's consistent and objective and reliable over time.
So for all that survey studies can get a bad rap. They're really really valuable for as Elliot said the kind of foundation laying for building the research for a field.
And it's really important, though, to consider, here's what a survey study is good for,
establishing do people have pain of some sort. And it's really important to note that in this
particular study, they didn't pathologize any of the pain, which is to say, they didn't say
they're reporting then that they have sciatica, or yes, they've confirmed that they have
thoracic outlet syndrome. They're describing where they have pain. They have not ascribed
a diagnosis to that pain.
Which is accurate, fair, and reasonable in a survey study.
Because in order to diagnose somebody with something, there's usually a diagnostic criteria you have to go through.
So if you were diagnosing, say, sciatic nerve issues,
you'd probably want to look at their range of motion in their back.
You'd want to look at their hamstring flexibility.
You'd want to test the mobility of the sciatic nerve.
You'd do certain clinical tests, like a slump test, for example.
to put that sciatic nerve under tension and see does that replicate the symptoms. You'd also want to rule out other things so you might go in and palpate kind of the gluteal tuberosity which is the butt bone basically seeing is there is there tenderness here that way I would associate with like a hamstring tendinopathy.
You might check out and see, is there weakness or tightness in the glute muscles that I might
think that there's a muscle compensating that's putting pressure on this nerve.
And so all of those things go into creating a diagnosis. A survey can't replicate that,
but a survey can give you general information about pain.
Now why am I going on and on about how a survey can't diagnose?
I'm going to come back to yours, I promise, but this was just a bit of a segue to miss.
All right, fine.
So there was a survey study that looked at carpal tunnel syndrome symptoms in e-sports competitors.
Which, not unreasonable, they do specify it's about symptoms.
But the danger of a kind of study like this where you're ascribing the results of a survey,
a player describing where their pain is located, to a diagnosis is you haven't actually confirmed
they have that diagnosis and you can, by publishing that research, create a misconception about
how common carpal tunnel is or isn't.
Now, this is not published research. This is my anecdotal
experience as a physical therapist who's been doing this
for six years. I have in my time, treating gamers, treated
exactly one case of carpal tunnel syndrome. And it was in
somebody who developed a carpal tunnel syndrome from a manual
labor job. And they also happened to play games, which is
where their symptoms presented the most. So the games brought
out the pain, they didn't cause the pain. So there's, there's
Saying that you have symptoms associated with carpal tunnel syndrome does not mean you have
carpal tunnel syndrome. Some of the symptoms that are associated with carpal tunnel syndrome
are associated with other conditions like tendinopathy, like other median nerve issues,
like something like cubital tunnel syndrome, double crush syndrome, a cervical radiculopathy,
a thoracic outlet syndrome, all of which are words that just sound like jargon if you're
not in the medical industry.
But it's basically the gist of it is it's very, very difficult to diagnose any of those things without being hands on with a person, and it's absolutely impossible to diagnose somebody with those conditions over a survey.
So it's really important as we're starting to develop the research and the foundations for this field that we a contextualize our research and make it really clear that we're looking at.
A player reported pain as opposed to ascribing a diagnosis to it.
And two, it's really important that the folks who are doing research have familiarity both
with research and with gaming. There's got to be a blend of both. This can't be a one thing
or the other, which again we'll get into a little bit later on once I let Elliot talk about performance.
Yeah. Yeah. Where was I?
All right, so this study about performance was actually interestingly put together.
I've never seen a study kind of done like this, but it was kind of a two part study.
So in the first part of the study, what they did was they developed this kind of litany of abilities that they think that pro gamers should have or.
Um, be able to be proficient at. Um, so they kind of broke this down into several categories here.
Psychic or mental abilities, including personality. Social abilities. Um, the condition category. So
those are things like, uh, physical fitness, endurance, speed, flexibility. Um, constitution.
So these are things like, um, sounds like a D and D statute.
Yep. Yeah, yeah, I really feel like they were very heavily inspired by.
Kind of RPG style stats, yeah.
But anyway, constitution is things like your age,
like your nutrition, sleep,
things like kind of baseline factors
and then media competency.
So those are like things like your ability to network
socially through internet media, like Reddit and Twitter
and like kind of finding information about the game
and stuff like that.
So these competencies, they then turned into a survey,
and then they sent the survey out
to a bunch of different gamers.
I think 1,835 players they sent the survey to.
So basically what they were looking at was,
do these individual competencies change
based on the game that you're playing?
And again, this is another study where it's like,
Yeah, obviously it's going to.
But it is good to have data like this in order
to continue building that case up.
But yeah, they ended up finding that the different games do
have different skills that are more
important or perceived important for these players.
So while kind of oddly put together,
I think they did come out with some good information that
can be used by.
Both people in our profession as well as game developers, as well as sports psychologists, nutritionists, all of these different fields can I think maybe pull at least something from this study just to kind of look at what the perceptions of large games actual population are.
Yeah, and something that could potentially come out of a study like this is testing what skills
are actually most important via an objective measure compared to what players perceive as
most important. And if there's a mismatch, they're determining why is there a mismatch?
How do we help them understand which is actually the most relevant skill for what they're doing?
Those are absolutely things that can then be built off of a study like this.
The really great thing about research is it builds more research, it builds more understanding,
it lets us as professionals provide better care, and it lets players play better if we
help them implement this research.
So we've got some proposed best practices for research when it comes to researchers
specifically, and we want to dig into that a little bit for sure.
The first one is I kind of mentioned that we wanted, we didn't just want non-endemic folks
to come in and do research on games without having any experience as gamers. That's not
to say that you need to be an avid gamer in order to do games research, but you need to at least be
familiar enough to kind of, I guess, respect the culture, have some degree of cultural competency
around esports.
This is not an us versus them venture.
This is not the gaming industry versus academia.
This is and should be a venture that incorporates the knowledge
and the experience of folks who are endemic to e-sports,
the players, the coaches, the staff.
And then the research qualifications of non endemic academic folks, combining those two things together, gives us studies that are relevant, that are well designed, and that actually have bearing on the on the eSports world so they don't just have.
Theoretical research use. They've got practical, actionable use in the field that is being studied, which research should do. Research should provide, you know, at least some amount of benefit to the folks who are being studied.
And kind of on that note, I think it's really important when it comes to research to incorporate subjects into publications. And what do I mean by that?
Well, in pain science research recently, there's been this push to have, as co-authors on papers,
patients who are describing patient experience of pain, especially when you're talking about
like the provider understanding of a patient's pain or the patient experience of pain,
to have actual patients helping to write the papers. Now, does that mean that every patient
has all kinds of, you know, research background and experience? No, absolutely not. That's why
they're a co-author, not a sole author.
But we know that expertise is not confined to academia.
There are experts in their field, and we should absolutely make sure
that the knowledge of those experts is well distributed and well transmitted,
because otherwise we're just doing research on something
that the industry already knows.
And then that cements that kind of.
Well, there are these outside folks who don't know anything who came in and tested a thing that we could have told them if they bothered asking us.
So then there becomes kind of this this headbutting thing. Whereas, if you come in and you partner with folks who are already in the gaming community already in the eSports world, players, coaches, staff, us.
Then you're making sure that you draw on what's already there so that you can build what isn't.
It can't just be a thing that academia does to gaming, it has to be a thing we do with gaming.
It's very recognizable when it is the former.
It's very, very clear.
You see E-S and it's an immediate giveaway that these people have not talked to any players.
I will acknowledge some degree of possible okayness with that.
It's a paper in another language and it just got translated in the translation engine put e-sports
by the fact that the AP style guide says e-sports, single word, no hyphen, no capitalize this.
All right, so also important to consider when it comes to research, who pays for it?
So this is the question that everybody really is asking at the end of the day.
Um, and I think before we answer who's going to pay for this, I think we should answer why they
should pay for it. Um, so I really think that there's a lot of applicability of esports to
other fields. So esports is interesting because although we have established or tried to
establish that it is not just a mental function, it is kind of the pinnacle of mental functioning.
competitively. There really isn't a whole lot of other kind of ways that we interface both
in kind of the neuromotor control facets of intellectual, that's not the right word,
it's difficult to find another field that
quantifies all of these mental skills
that we see represented in e-sports
in a competitive setting,
as well as we see in the competitive gaming world.
So that being said,
there is application to other fields
within kind of that sphere of like mental function.
So cognition is the ability to think essentially.
And there are studies out there that show that gaming,
actually does improve your ability to think critically, rationally, logically, strategically,
all of these things that we value in society and in both children growing up as well as
aging adults.
So I really think that it is.
In the same way that when we send someone to the moon, we advance technology here on earth, it is worth looking at these
These facets of cognition and fine motor skills and how we can prevent deterioration in patients with Alzheimer's by studying how to push the boundaries with competitive gaming.
And so who exactly would be interested in advancing this kind of line of knowledge?
I think both academic institutions as well as medical organizations are very interested
in kind of understanding how to push the limits in this way, as well as the government,
for various reasons, whether it be developing practice guidelines for our medical health
systems, either for military involvement.
All of these institutions, I think, can have a vested interest in kind of pushing that line of knowledge into
understanding how the brain works at the highest levels.
Right. And so here we're talking about some of the more traditional structures of research funding, academic institutions, which publication, publication, publication, medical organizations, we provide care, of course, we're invested in the outcomes of our patients, and government organizations, both in terms of general for the public good. But also definitely there's when it comes to eSports, there are military applications for the kind of stuff we study in gaming.
But we are not at an academic conference, or at a medical conference, or at a government conference.
We're at the Game Developers Conference, so...
Why should developers care?
So, the first part of the answer to this is, not all of them have to.
Which is to say...
Yes, developers care about the players who play their games to some extent and in some way.
We're talking specifically here about kind of the larger esports kind of organizations. We're
talking about the developers who create games specifically to be played competitively as an
esport.
And those are, in our opinion, the kinds of developers who are probably going to care the most about this kind of research.
Now that's not to say that smaller indie studios won't care.
Especially if, say, you're developing a game that incorporates aspects of mental health.
Then sure, absolutely, you're probably interested in and maybe even invested in the kind of research that comes out about mental health in games.
But if we're looking at health and performance in esports, then the developers who create games that are esports are probably going to be the most interested here.
So why should those developers specifically care?
Why should the gaming and eSports industry care about this?
Well, when it comes to a purely pragmatic financial perspective,
having longer player careers, having career longevity
because players aren't injured and they're playing at a high level,
there's financial value there.
People want to watch people play at the highest level.
People want to follow their favorite players.
And a lot of fans follow players more than they follow just teams.
Leagues want to have players who are able to play consistently over time, because that gets people tuning in to watch it, which gets ad revenue, which gets your company money.
But in kind of a more public good sense, investing in this kind of research creates a more stable, more sustainable industry.
And sure, eSports really started with so much grassroots work.
eSports really started with community organization, especially in the fighting games community, for example.
It still does rely very heavily on a lot of grassroots organization.
But if we want to create the kind of stability that we wished we'd had when we were first getting started in all of this,
if we want to create some reliability, some degree of security, some degree of infrastructure,
that doesn't mean we have to become stodgy, and it doesn't mean we have to create the exact same thing that's already been done elsewhere that we don't particularly like.
We have the opportunity to create a new health infrastructure in esports, and a new performance and health model for our players.
But we have to put the time and effort into it.
Because otherwise we're just going to have to borrow from everybody else because that's the easier and less expensive way to do it.
If we want a community that is ours, if we want an infrastructure that is ours and works best for us, we need to take the time and money to invest into it.
Other reasons that developers could potentially care about this really great way of correcting
misconceptions about gaming is providing research that says no you are wrong they're not basement
dwellers who just you know eat Doritos and drink Mountain Dew and no not just anybody could be a
top tier eSports competitor the kind of folks who win you know eight million dollars at the
international really are exceptional on par with you know making it into the NFL in terms of the
elite tier of the thing that they do.
This also allows developers to tap into new markets, as we alluded to.
Having research that shows kind of the health benefits of competitive e-sports,
as well as the ways in which e-sports can be integrated into an overall healthy lifestyle,
absolutely improves parental support. Parents being the ones who have the money to buy the
games that their kids play. It's a pretty important market to be tapping into.
So this kind of research absolutely should be funded by traditional institutions,
absolutely should be studied by traditional academic, medical, and government organizations.
That being said, it's absolutely research that the industry should be interested and
invested in, because it helps us create this more sustainable playing field for esports
to continue to be a viable option to design games to be played in, for players to participate
in, and for support staff to then design the structures that keep all of that up and functioning.
It can't just be a thing that non-endemics care about, because if non-endemics are the only ones who care about this research,
and non-endemics are the only ones who are going to do it,
then we're going to end up with a whole bunch of people who don't know all that much about gaming,
not drawing on the serious expertise that's already here,
that we could absolutely rely on for real value when it comes to research.
So, when it comes to research, what do we need?
Best practice guidelines.
Yes, what are those?
Exactly.
There's a reason I put three exclamation marks here,
because having some standardized care across the industry will do so much good.
There's some very cool research out on tendons,
and not everyone knows that isometrics can be really pain relieving.
being that disrupted to a training schedule.
And there's just so much cool stuff out there that if we can standardize it and
and help other practitioners understand what the best way to treat someone is,
we can make a humongous difference.
And think about the scale of how many gamers are in the world.
There's millions, billions of them.
And do they not deserve care any more than the millions
and billions of people who play basketball?
That's not true.
They both need help.
It's not a you take away from one and then you take away from the other.
We can help both.
Exactly. So prevalence data is basically in a population how often something occurs. And so having the understanding of how many
People may have a certain condition, whether it be low back pain, wrist pain, finger pain,
can help us a lot with understanding, okay, where do we need to invest the most time and energy?
As we just learned with Elliot, we have a lot of low back pain. Maybe instead of focusing so much
on fingers and hands, we should focus more on low backs with gamers, right? And understanding
the physical demands of gaming also really, really helps us
understand how to be proactive with injuries as opposed to reactive.
And as many of you might imagine, using a mouse and keyboard is very different
from using an Xbox controller or PS5 controller.
And then even then, you play Valorant, very different from playing Dota.
And even if you play Dota, if you're solo carry versus support,
that's very different inputs. Those have very, very...
We know that these are different, but we don't know exactly how.
And we don't know the distribution of pain that comes from these differences is actually relevant.
So like the studies that looked at all these back pain issues, I don't think it was organized by actual game.
So like understanding very specifically to the population you're working with is so important.
Yeah, like a great example of Smash Brothers, we've seen more folks who play Fox having,
you know, tendon pain across the back of their hand than folks who say mean peach.
Now, we can't prove that because we haven't done any research on it, but anecdotally, we're like,
yeah, this absolutely makes sense. And so being able to quantify that, as John referenced,
allows us to create more consistent care guidelines that are more specific and less
general. Because right now, the general guideline that gets given out...
by folks who don't know gaming well is rest and brace. Without really looking into, okay,
what game do you play? What input device do you use? How long are you playing for? What character
do you main within the game that you play if your game is one that has a main character that you
might play?
Okay, what are the most common inputs you use on your input device?
Are you wave dashing a lot as a Smash Fox player?
Are you in Dota playing invoker and having to do all of the, you know,
really complicated invoking combinations?
Or are you like me playing Vengeful Spirit and just pressing A?
Look, stuns are good, okay?
But all of this information is really helpful and really valuable for understanding what areas are
most under strain and what areas should we be starting to prevent strain in. What can we do
for players to help them not get injured in the first place? Because we really run into a lot of
players who don't want to see a healthcare professional because they don't think the
healthcare professional is going to know what to do to help them. Which, you know what? Fair,
based on our track record so far. That's a reasonable opinion to have.
But if we could have a few less, you know, highs and hacks in the world,
you know, having to retire due to medical injury that really could have been prevented,
then we end up with more top tier players.
We as spectators get to enjoy it a heck of a lot more.
The industry stays more sustainable and people leave because they want to leave,
not because they're forced out by a medical condition that absolutely could have been
prevented if we just had the data and the professionals who were in the right place
to help provide that care.
Exactly. We want to help healthcare providers help people better. And that's the whole point
of all this research in this entire presentation is that we can do better. We do, I think at 1HP
we do a great job, but we can help a lot more people. And ultimately at the end of the day,
we're all just trying to elevate the entire ecosystem of esports and the culture of gaming.
So I really think that that's a great kind of final note to end on here.
We have a bit of a motto at 1HP, and our motto is play more, hurt less.
And we want that to be an option for players.
We want people to be able to play.
We want that to be a part of a healthy lifestyle.
We want esports competitors to be competing at their best, playing more.
But without hurting and in order to make that happen, we need the research to develop this industry to develop this field of esports medicine.
And that's the way that we provide the best possible care to players so that they can play more and hurt less.
for joining us for this, guys. I think we've kept it to almost 60 minutes on the dot. We've
been pretty impressed by it, I've got to be honest. We've been in chat answering questions
this whole time. This is a little weird because we're pre-recording this. But if you ever
have any future questions for us, you can always reach out to us on Twitter, which I
believe will be posted here.
We're more than happy to answer questions at any time, because we really want to make
sure that this is something that sticks around, that this research really continues to grow.
Yes.
Absolutely. Thank you, everybody.
Thank you so much.