My name is Frank Sepaldi. I kind of lead two lives, I think. There's sort of a commercial
aspect and a charity aspect. Both of them have kind of similar color schemes to their logos,
now that I'm looking at it. So I produce and direct games at a studio called Digital Eclipse,
and we're mainly known for making
re-releases of classic games, usually in compilation form.
We like to think of ourselves as attempting
to be the sort of criterion collection of games
to sort of contextualize titles and add bonus features, things
like that.
I also run a charity called the Video Game History Foundation.
Gamehistory.org.
Don't look right now.
And I will talk a little bit more about that later.
Question I know that's on everyone's mind right now,
what's up with my forehead?
I have a cat and that's Tony.
That's Tony in his very, very expensive bed with the heating pad we put in for his comfort
decided this morning of my talk to attack my forehead.
So...
That's why.
All right, just a brief summary.
Here's kind of what we're talking about today.
I'm going to give you, I did a talk three years ago,
and I'll recap that real quick for you,
because this is a quasi-sequel to it.
I'm going to tell you about who it is
that actually plays and buys classic games.
I think we've identified the sort of three targets of that.
The duties of the classic game publisher,
meaning like in the commercial industry,
what is it we should be providing this audience?
I'm going to tell you a little dirty secret.
Doctors hate them.
You might not know, or you might if you work with me.
Some inspiring words, some terrifying words, and then some hopeful words.
So three years ago I gave a talk called It's Just Emulation.
Like I said, this is kind of the sequel.
If you haven't seen it on the vault and you're watching this right now on the vault, maybe
go watch that instead.
If you're in the room, don't leave.
I'll recap it real quick.
The gist of it, essentially, is that old movies, old comics,
old books, old everything, music, for the most part,
if it has even minor commercial potential, is available.
You can buy it legally.
When it comes to games, that's really dire.
This is a similar slide to the last one.
Just very, very few of our notable video games from the past are available commercially.
I illustrated this with a comparison if you were there or if you watched it on the vault
by comparing Disney's DuckTales for the Nintendo Entertainment System to a John Candy movie
called Uncle Buck.
Uncle Buck is available on like 30,000 digital services from startups you've never heard of and all the ones you have also
It's even on
video game console
Services right like like on the PlayStation in the Xbox you could buy Uncle Buck
Disney's Ducktales had, at the time, been out of print since 1989.
And I think it's because we largely demonized as an industry the notion of emulation.
Back in 1997, when emulation kind of became a viable technology on the internet, the industry
basically freaked out and went after it legally.
Nintendo put some text on their website calling it the greatest threat to date to the intellectual
property of video game developers.
You know, a few, like Kinectix got taken to court by Sony.
Unsuccessfully, I might add.
No video game emulator challenged in court has ever been ruled illegal.
Emulation's fine.
But despite that, to this day, that's a screencap from Nintendo.com that's still there.
But because we demonized it instead of embracing it, I argued that emulation...
Instead of becoming the tool that we used as an industry,
because it is the best tool for keeping older games in print
in a cost effective and accurate way,
instead of embracing that, we demonized it.
And because of that, I think two things happened.
I think old games kind of became
the domain of the pirates, right?
So people started thinking of games
the way we thought of MP3s in the Napster days, right?
Where it's like music's just free now, who cares?
And...
We also, I think, by not getting ahead of it and getting these games back in print through
emulation, I think for a lot of games it's kind of too late now.
I think a lot of the legal rights are just never going to be cleared up for a lot of
games.
And while, yeah, it is a means of piracy, like I said, it's just the best tool we have.
I liken it to film even, right?
So film…
When a company wants to re-release a film,
they basically just have to digitize it the once.
And once you have a digital copy of a film,
you just convert it to different video codecs.
We've all heard that term in this room, codecs, right?
But we don't seem to understand that there
is an equivalent of that with video games.
And ultimately, I don't really see
the difference between a video codec and a game emulator.
And if we were to think of it that way,
perhaps we could stop the bleeding.
We could get things back in print.
Like I said, I think the damage has largely been done, but I do think we can stop the
bleeding a little bit if we embrace the emulator loudly and proudly.
Emulation's the king.
I recommended at the time that we start taking open source emulation as an industry a little
more seriously.
I pointed out that MAME, which used to stand for Multiple Arcade Machine Emulator, I forget
what it stands for now, but it is essentially a video codec for video game machines.
And I suggest that we start taking that a little more seriously, especially now that it is open source and most of its components are available to use commercially.
What I didn't mention at the time was that while we're at it, maybe we should be contributing back to this fantastic resource instead of just taking from it.
We all caught up? Good? Getting your chronogens? Let's go three years in the future to today.
What's been happening these last three years since that talk?
Hey, someone did it!
A company actually did embrace open source emulation.
This is Sony's PlayStation Classic.
It uses an emulator called PCSX,
specifically the re-armed branch of it.
To me, this is huge.
It meant Sony was admitting that an emulator
written by the community was good enough, right?
Like this is Sony saying, hey, this is good enough
that this has the godfather blessing, right?
This is a real PlayStation game, this open source emulator.
So yay, good, right? Well, it didn't really work out that well.
The product had a lot of issues, which is a shame.
It's just that this particular emulator I don't think was the right tool for this job.
And they also, I don't think, like...
fixed it, you know, because it didn't entirely support all of these games and they also made
some weird decisions in terms of like putting PAL games on an NTSC console, stuff like that.
So that kind of sucked because it, on the one hand, it was, you know, yay, we're acknowledging
this community of authors is doing work that is good enough to sell, but at the same time
where it sort of took a hit, I think, because of public perception of this product.
Nintendo sold you Super Mario Bros. again, and again.
Actually three times in the last three years.
Oh my god, Sonic Mania.
You guys play Sonic Mania?
Oh my god, that game blew me away.
doesn't directly have anything to do with emulation,
but it would not have been possible without emulation.
The core team of this game actually
got their start modifying original Sonic the Hedgehog
games using, you know.
emulators and easily available ROM files for these original games. That's how they reverse
engineered the system and that's how they basically were able to copy Yuji Naka's
Sonic engine and make new things with it is because they had access to these open tools
and to the ROMs themselves. They could stumble into those and learn and get inspired.
Amazing! I don't think that's likely to happen anymore because easy access to ROM files was
also taken away from us recently, the last three years, actually just a few months ago.
You guys probably saw this story, right? Like Nintendo successfully won a suit against
Love ROMs and it caused this ripple effect on the internet where a lot of...
I have a question already, sure.
But it looks like it, the quote,
quains does not mean they'll actually hurt it.
It's more like sending it in two.
Okay, so the statement from the audience was that it was more of an intimidation message.
Yeah, I think that's true. Like, they didn't actually win $12 million from these guys.
It was settled out of court. But the point being that this caused a really unfortunate ripple
effect where, yeah, a lot of the commercially viable product you can't find online anymore,
which is fine, of course. Yeah, that's your property. You know, go after that. But...
It also meant that every other video game ever made that had nothing to do with Nintendo
is kind of hard to find now, so that was really unfortunate.
Nintendo's Boogeyman Tex is still up there.
In fact, we're about to celebrate the 20-year anniversary of...
Any day now.
We couldn't substantiate it quite to the exact date because the Wayback Machine didn't scrape
down.
you know, daily back then or anything.
But actually, I noticed something
when I took the screen cap.
So this is 20 years ago.
The introduction of video game emulators
represents the greatest threat to date, blah, blah, blah.
Everything's terrible.
Sometime around 2006, they actually, oh,
I don't have it here.
But sometimes around 2006, they added the text,
emulators used to play illegal copies of Nintendo games.
So they actually added that text right around when they
launched an emulator service.
So that's cute.
This is kind of an interesting thing.
This hasn't come out yet, but this is AntStream.
This is a company that's building, you know, like a, basically like the notion of a video
codec that you deploy to, right?
This is a platform for classic games, sort of your Netflix for games play.
I think these guys are out of the UK.
You can tell because Speedball 2 is the game up front.
And as for me, actually, something I said three years ago was that I felt that the only
path toward accuracy, toward doing these games justice, was to do a one-to-one copy of a
game, right?
That it should be warts and all exactly as it was.
and some products over the last three years have caused me to start rethinking that.
Do you guys know this? Wonder Boy the Dragon's Trap? This is by Lizard Cube. This was a
remastering of Wonder Boy 3 the Dragon's Trap on the Master System.
And it did a really good job of translating that old game and giving it modern flourishes,
you know, beyond the HD graphics and stuff like that.
I think an even better example, no comment on the game itself, but Night Trap 25th Anniversary
and all that.
But, yeah.
I'll leave it at that.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Bye.
added so many quality of life features that it is like undeniably a better game than you
could have played on the Sega CD or whatever back in the day.
It's not only better now, I think it might even be reflecting artistic intent of the
original more than the original did.
So I've been thinking a lot about that lately.
As for Digital Eclipse, we released a few more products, including bringing DuckTales
back in print.
That was actually complete coincidence
that that was the game that I chose three years ago
and that it ended up being our next project.
So you're welcome.
Thank you, one person who clapped for DuckTales.
We also expanded our scope at Digital Eclipse quite a bit,
and we started working on these deluxe anniversary packages.
So Street Fighter 30th was a collection
focused on the original mainline Street Fighter arcade games.
SNK 40th came out last year.
It's what I like to call a playable documentary
about what I think was a strange and wonderful little developer
called SNK in the 1980s.
This is sort of a snapshot of what
they were before the Neo Geo system was
introduced in the 1990s.
And they pivoted.
that way entirely. We're going to get back to that later. But these last three years,
we started thinking a lot about who buys this stuff, right? Who is the consumer of a classic
game re-release? And I think we can basically narrow it down to three main groups. Of course,
we're missing some here. You have your casual player, right? This is someone who...
you know, just sees the game on the store and is like, oh,
cool, Metal Slug or whatever, right?
Like, this is someone who probably has a kid.
I don't know.
And this is just sort of the impulse purchase,
slight nostalgia kind of person, right?
Your next tier up is your sort of collector type, right?
This is someone who probably identifies as a retro gamer,
right?
Like, probably still has shelves full of old cartridge
games and stuff.
And they kind of almost, in a lot of ways,
I think.
vote with their dollar toward the idea of old games being around.
So that's sort of the second tier market.
Your third market's kind of strange.
This is your really hardcore market.
So this is the kind of consumer that is...
Thank you for laughing.
I thought it was funny too.
This is your consumer who just knows way too much about this stuff, and it just wants more right?
It's like no, I already have access to these games
I know how to use maim if you're just selling me the ROM again like I'm not giving you eight bucks for this arcade game
That I've barely heard of I can just play it for free, and it's it's just as good as your emulator
I probably is actually main, but we'll get to that
So you know these three audiences, I think
I think one and two can graduate forward, right?
I think that a casual type can become a retro gamer,
can become a hardcore weirdo,
but I don't think there's a backwards.
And I also think that groups one and two, no matter what,
are capped by their personal nostalgia, right?
For things that they grew up with.
Whereas I think number three,
I think is a much more sustainable audience.
I think that's an audience that you can grow.
I think that's an audience that you can educate
on wanting this kind of product.
And that's the kind of hardcore audience
that we targeted Digital Eclipse.
And I think that's what we should all be targeting.
in this industry because it applies to every possible consumer.
But let me tell you about group number three, the hardcore.
The hardcore play hard. All right.
Like like we can do so many things
without the industry interacting with us at all.
I mean, we can download.
Every game ever, right?
Like it's super easy to just go download a mame set
and you have all of arcade history in front of you playable.
We have emulators on our computers.
We can, if we want a really terrible experience,
we can have, you know, touch screen,
like PlayStation emulators on our phones and stuff.
we don't even need emulation, right?
We're in an era now where we can use our original hardware
and we can load entire system libraries
on one single cartridge and just Tannel Surf
every Sega Genesis game ever made easily.
And while we're in that original hardware,
we're like enhancing it, right?
This is the MSU-1 core.
It's a demonstration of it on the Super Nintendo.
This is actually, this is Arthur Bew,
basically created a hardware add-on for the Super Nintendo
to add full motion video and CD quality audio,
stuff like that.
So people have made the definitive Chrono Trigger
that has the PlayStation features
without the load times and stuff like that.
Oh, we're playing on like.
beautiful RGB professional monitors from the 80s
and the most perfect display possible.
People, because of this hobby, are figuring out
how to hack old consumer CRTs to get the best picture out
of them.
No one's died yet, but my god, please be careful.
We're like building arcade machines and we have been since the 90s that has everything on it.
You know, there's even like new hardware being created to play these games in an accurate way
in HD. This is the Mega SG, which actually mine just shipped this morning. That's how
new this is. I just got the alert this morning. This is a, a, a
Basically, it's Sega Genesis natively inside,
spitting out 1080p clean picture.
And they do this through what's called an FPGA,
a Field Programmable Gate Array.
Is that right?
Yeah.
And the idea being that it's not even software emulation
at this point.
It is a chip that reconfigures itself to be a Sega,
so it's just hyper-accurate.
And we're even getting into open source now.
This is a build of what's called the Mr. Project.
Has anyone heard of this?
Yeah, yeah, I see a couple enthusiasts for the mister.
So this is like an open source FPGA retro console using off the shelf parts that are
like fairly affordable.
So you know, we don't, we don't need, we don't even need, we don't need emulators, we don't
even need the original consoles.
We have, we can build hardware that replicates the hardware.
without anyone, right?
And we don't even need the commercial games.
We can translate games that no one bothered to translate,
and in these cases, damn well should have,
and we can play through them.
We don't need to wait for,
we don't need to yell at Reggie Fils-Aimé
to translate Mother 3, just do it, who cares, right?
Not even translations, we're modifying games, right?
Like TecmoBowl.org, these guys for 12 years
have been upgrading Tecmo Bowl.
Uh, not only have they been upgrading the NFL rosters, they're like adding new NFL teams
as they're created.
They're like adding new NFL rules.
They are maintaining Tecmo Bowl.
We don't need whatever Tecmo is right now.
I don't even know if Tecmo exists.
But you know, we don't need the industry to like do things like that.
We're doing it on our own.
Uh, the middle picture, like we're.
We're basically correcting mistakes of the past even, like remastering in a sense.
So like when Donkey Kong Country was ported to the Game Boy Advance, you remember the
thing didn't have any backlight on it, right?
So people had to alter the color palette so you could actually see the damn thing.
But you know, because we don't play on the actual thing anymore, people are fixing the
games, right?
To run on modern platforms.
They're modifying the games to add or replace content.
This is Rollchon, which replaces Mega Man with his sister in the game, which is super
cool.
Yes, I tried to get that in Mega Man Legacy Collection, but the author didn't reply to
me.
I think they didn't believe me.
But we don't even need human-authored stuff anymore.
We're building randomizers that modify and change
the game in a perfectly playable way every time.
And this is getting huge.
We are building the tools now also to start
reverse engineering games.
and figuring out how they work and tinkering with them.
So this is a disassembly of the original Super Mario Brothers
with commented code, which is awesome.
And people are like taking that and porting that to C
and are and are figuring out how these games work
and the mysteries behind them.
And they're finding.
bugs in like Super Mario Brothers and fixing them because it turns out there was like a
copy paste error that caused the spiny balls to behave in a way that they weren't meant
to and we're discovering that with all these emulator tools.
And again, this is not something the industry provides.
We can't replicate a lot of this in the commercial industry.
I can't make anything look as good as one of those CRT monitors as my beautiful Sony
PVM 2530.
That's how I roll, by the way.
We can't we can't eliminate input lag.
OK, that that's the thing that will be chasing that forever.
It's in the world of software emulation versus these original pieces
of hardware running on a CRT.
There's nothing preventing your your button press
from from immediately reflecting on the screen.
But but with modern hardware, that's just inherent.
We can't defy the laws of physics, so we can't give you an experience like that.
We can't clear up the legal issues for most games.
Like we're never going to see like
Home Alone on the Super Nintendo, like, ever again, right? Like, based on the Tim Allen show.
Like, that's just never gonna happen. I don't know why that one.
We can't provide infinite variety. We can't give you every game ever made, right? We can't do it
for literally free, you know? Like, so, well, what can we do, right? I think there's a lot we can do.
I think we can curate these experiences that we're giving to people.
I think this is actually maybe the most important.
Because we're the commercial industry, because we're working with the rights holders, we
can theoretically provide behind-the-scenes access to help contextualize these things.
Or, you know, we can talk to the original authors to sort of ask them their intent and
restore the games to their liking.
We can put out titles that no one's seen before.
Previously on Released Works, Nintendo did that with Star Fox 2, which was so cool.
They put it on their SNES Classic.
We can offer new play modes for the games.
I mean, they're already doing that, too, but we can sort of author them,
you know, with perhaps the original creators. Right.
We can offer thoughtful improvements to the games.
We can we can do all kinds of stuff that people can't necessarily
do in the community as a commercial industry.
And.
We should be.
Like, we're getting paid for this, right?
Like, this is our jobs.
We should be providing a better experience
than people can get for free if they happen
to be pirates or whatever.
And a lot of companies, not just us,
are doing things like this to enhance their experiences,
like M2.
M2's out of Japan.
Oh my god, I have a crush on M2.
These guys are amazing.
The list of cool stuff they've done is really long.
The most recent one is Phantasy Star.
I forget what they called it,
but it was the Phantasy Star remake on the Switch.
And this release just did an amazing job
of modernizing this game.
This is a classic RPG with random encounters on the map.
So they, because we don't play like that anymore,
you know, we don't,
have one cartridge that we play for a month and like, you know, like they reduce the random
encounter rate and they increase the experience you get. So you play it a lot less, but you're
getting the exact same experience, just less of it. They, they modernized it without actually
modifying. They just tweaked it, right? They let you speed the game up because the walking
speed was a little bit slow. They added this auto mapping feature and these stupid first
person dungeons that no one likes anymore. Well, they have their fans, I guess, just
not me.
Um...
But, you know, and what I like about this is that I am a Fantasy Star fan.
I've played through Fantasy Star actually multiple times.
I've worked on one of the translation patches for it actually.
But I know as a Fantasy Star fan, having played through this, that to me they didn't really
change the game.
You know what I mean?
Like, they in a way I think translated it.
Like they translated it for modern audiences and I thought that was really cool.
I mentioned Wonder Boy the Dragon's Trap earlier.
Something I really liked about it, other than, you know, kind of did the same stuff as Phantasy
Star where Lizardcube updated the game to be a little more accessible to modern players.
They upped the frame rate from 30 to 60, which means I'll never go back to the original.
But what I like that they did is that typically when you get like an HD remaster of a game,
I think the notion is like, no, those old graphics, those are done.
This is what it's supposed to look like, right?
And I hate that.
But what LizardCube did instead was like almost an artistic remix, like a reimagining, not
a remastering of the graphics.
And I thought that was great.
Double Fine does really cool stuff with the LucasArts adventure games.
I think these projects are phenomenal because the teams have actual direct access to a lot of the
core staff who worked on these games, including Tim Schafer, who runs a studio, was the director
of Full Throttle. But even the art directors and things like that, they have a lot of direct access
so they can ask, what were these ambiguous pixels supposed to be and get an answer and can draw the
art appropriately. Excuse me one second.
I just spilled water down my chin.
That was great.
Our latest was SNK 40th.
Unlike these guys above, we don't really
get the opportunity to focus on one game at a time,
but we tend to make packages.
This one in particular, like I said,
was a snapshot of what this company was in the 80s,
instead of a remastering of a game.
So we approached things a little bit differently than M2 or Lizard
Cube or Double Fine.
So our goals with the project.
Unlike Mega Man, Street Fighter, Disney, these weren't IP that had an instant commercial
appeal.
So, it was kind of our job, I thought, to sort of make people care about this stuff,
which isn't impossible because SNK does have really hardcore fans.
They just tend to be fans of the 90s and more current SNK content, not the 80s stuff.
But this gave us an opportunity to say, hey, SNK fans, here's the roots of this company.
We also, it was our duty, we thought to sort of alter the gameplay of some of these games
to modernize it in a way that was more understandable and to reinterpret the controls, which I'll
get to in a minute.
But first I got a video up here somewhere.
There we go.
All right.
So this is a demonstration of what we're kind of known for our extra material in these games,
right? We do a little bit more in the games. We kind of give you the original packaging artwork
and things like that. And in SNK's case,
They made like 60 games in the 80s.
We'd still be working on this project if we did all 60 games.
So we kind of curated the collection.
But but I wanted to at least show what all the other games were. Right.
So this is actually a complete list of every game that SNK game
that SNK had done in the 80s.
And for each one of these,
if if art exists, we put it in there like it literally exists in the world.
You can, of course, do your zooming and stuff and and and and go in on there.
We got the screen test of the games, but each one of these also has a little bit of a history
lesson and it kind of comes across as like...
an interactive art book about the history of SNK.
And this was our way of capturing that
because a lot of this history has just never been talked
about even by SNK.
A lot of these guys are not getting any younger.
And so we wanted to sort of educate the consumer
on what this company was and give you
the definitive package, like here was SNK in the 80s.
So that was our approach with the museum content.
But we also added a feature that...
Oh wait, that is the same video.
That is not what we want to do.
Excuse me a moment, folks.
Okay, so this is sort of the game selection menu.
So another thing we did with this collection is that for all the titles in here, like POW,
for example, we included all the regional versions of it.
And we included the home console version as well, if there was one, which I think is really
important actually, because it...
tells you a little bit more about that game to know how they approached a home version of it.
Like in SNK's case, most of their home versions actually added features that the arcade games
didn't have, made them a little more RPG-like even. And even internally, this was a little
bit of a struggle because I think that a lot of companies are like, oh, why would you do the
inferior version of the game, right? But for us, it's like, no, we're historians, right? We're
trying to explain what your company was and we should include all of that stuff.
Luckily, they went for it.
But a feature that we added...
I don't think it's crazy to say that people like watching people play video games.
Have we proven that out yet?
So we wanted to make these games as accessible as we could.
We didn't want to just throw you in an 80s arcade and say, good luck, kid, right?
Like we wanted you to be able to access this content without being good at old video games.
And so if you want, you can just watch the games.
So this is a playthrough, it's actually a fairly tool-assisted playthrough of me being
more awesome than I actually am at playing these games.
But like a movie, you can scrub through it, right?
And you can go in there, you can pause, you can frame advance, you can frame rewind.
It's all pixel perfect because this isn't a video, it's actually a button playback of
the movie.
So every frame, or maybe three frames, we're capturing basically a save state and then
the button presses that come after it, and that's how we're able to scrub through it
like that.
Um...
And because we did it that way,
you don't have to just watch it forever.
You don't have to be passive.
You can actually just start playing
because that's just a save state, right?
So, to us, this was a way of letting you
just flip through the game like it was a book
and access whatever content you want to.
And that was a fairly low-tech-ish way.
I say low-tech and Adam, the programmer,
is probably screaming if he's watching this.
But, you know, it was our way of letting you access these parts of the game without having
to heavily modify a binary file, right?
But I think what was maybe the most important thing we did was reinterpreting some of the
original arcade controls so that they made sense, not just to a modern player, but to
a modern player on a modern controller.
This is a rotary joystick.
It's called the loop lever.
SNK was known for this in the 80s.
So just imagine this on an arcade machine.
You tilt it like normal to move.
It's a joystick, right?
But you actually rotate the stick to aim.
So, you know, here's Ikari Warriors, for example.
There's only two buttons in the game.
And you would, and they were nice enough
to do a left and right hand configuration,
which is kind of cool.
But you would tilt to move your character around and you would twist to aim your gun
and fire at people.
And so playing Ikari Warriors, you know, is supposed to kind of look like this, right?
Like you're able to sort of muscle memory your way in the original arcade game to be
able to, you know, fire three o'clock and then point straight back up.
Typically when this game has been re-released in the past, the way that that's been accomplished
is to sort of map rotate clockwise and rotate counterclockwise to buttons and it just doesn't
work that well.
It doesn't feel like Ikari Warriors anymore and I actually think that the reason that
fans don't talk about these games is because the only access we have had to them traditionally
is through means like MAME where they don't play the way they're supposed to so they're
not fun.
So for our game, it may sound simple on paper,
but we made it essentially a twin-stick shooter.
So we're emulating the game just as it is on one layer,
but there's an abstraction layer above it.
So for example, if the player points straight down
on the R stick, our abstraction layer
will tell the game, hey, change your game state
so that the player is pointing straight down.
There's no point straight down function
in the original game, which is why
we had to sort of interrupt the game.
to tell it that.
So essentially, we, I think, made Ikari Warriors
playable for the first time since its arcade origins.
So that makes sense, right?
Easy to do.
Hydrate's actually a good idea.
If you guys need to hydrate, I think I do.
All right, simple enough.
What about the sequels?
Ikari Warriors 3, The Rescue.
Not a very good game.
But it's not our job as historians to judge.
It's our historians to report accurately.
OK, so that's another rotary stick game, another rotary one.
So moving kind of looks like this.
You can aim where you want as you move
and keep pointing in that direction.
You've got a punch button.
and you got a kick button, right?
And then again, it's a rotary game.
And what the game encouraged you to do
were like roundhouse kicks, right?
So using our existing setup, yeah, it kind of works.
It doesn't feel that great, but you know,
you kick and you rotate the R stick
and you can do a roundhouse.
In the arcade, much easier, right?
Because you have one finger over here
and you have a hand on the joystick.
So it's just a simple motion.
But wait, there's three buttons, right?
So we no longer have our, uh, are just two buttons on the back.
We have a jump button and with the jump button, you can jump kick.
So, uh, again, this doesn't work.
So, okay.
Um,
And what we did here was we basically combined the pointing with the R-stick with the moving
and then put the three buttons on the face so that he now points where you walk like
you would expect in most games.
So that works pretty well.
And because of that, you can actually now do the main move that the game expects you
to do, which is a jumping roundhouse kick, right?
Which of course you couldn't do.
uh, actually, sorry, I skipped ahead, um, which you couldn't do, uh, if you had thumbs
on two sticks and had to, like, press two buttons at the same, like, it just doesn't
work.
Um, game had another move, backhand, right, and that one is actually a jump punch.
So, uh, jump punch on this controller, I didn't like the thumb movement.
that was required to do that.
I like the player to be able to just rest their thumb
on kick and jump.
And in the arcade game, again, we're thinking about
how is the player playing this in the arcade game?
If you think back to the way it was laid out,
you'd have your hand on the joystick
and you'd have three fingers on three buttons,
so you could instantly do any of that.
You can't do that if your thumb's just resting
on jump and kick, so we added a backhand button.
We just combined punch and jump into one button, so.
Hooray, right?
We solved all the problems.
Oh, turns out that actually strafing is like a valid thing
to do in this game, and we just took that away
by combining the aiming and the moving into one stick.
So this doesn't work anymore, right?
But we don't want to take away the ability to jump kick,
because that's actually the main move in the game.
So what we went back and did was added an optional aim, right?
So as you're tilting the left stick,
he's moving and pointing in the way you're going.
And if you happen to hit the R stick,
he's then pointing wherever you're pointing that one.
And then if you let go of the R stick,
he just snaps back into the position
that he was with the L stick.
Can you guys see the problem here already?
Like if you're shooting this gun, right?
Like now your thumb is on the R-stick
and how are you gonna point that
and like curve your finger to shoot, right?
So, okay, well we just added punch again.
Like it's another button
so you could easily shoot the gun.
Wait, no, there's actually a secondary fire, which is throw your weapon.
So let's just do backhand again.
Like it looks really complicated, but I'd like to think it works.
And that's just the level of thinking that I think you have to do
to interpret these arcade games to play on controllers.
They were never meant to play on.
And if you were to play this game on MAME, you know, you could theoretically
maybe get close to that setup on MAME.
Or you can even on MAME, like, people
have made new rotary controllers you can hook up to MAME,
which is cool.
But unless you know that's how the game functioned,
unless you know that, you don't know
to configure the game that way, right?
And it's not MAME's job to sort of interpret.
It's MAME's job to sort of be a binary equation, right?
And so last time around, three years ago,
I said we should maybe start using.
MAME, because it's a solid emulator.
It's got a lot of systems supported, it's open source.
I don't think anyone's done that yet,
that actually includes us.
We haven't used MAME, the emulator, yet.
But here's the thing, we're all using MAME.
Every emulator author.
in the commercial industry is using MAME.
And I don't mean the executable emulator.
I mean the MAME project.
MAME is a documentation project.
They document how these games and systems worked
and put that information in an accessible place
for people to reference.
We're not doing this every time we do one of these collections.
You know, we're not getting the original PCBs and like tracing the circuits and like,
you know, like figuring out what the chips were and getting their specs and looking that up.
And, you know, I mean, there's a little bit of that, but, but where we start is the MAME GitHub,
right? Like, of course we would, why would we look at the physical object to figure that out
when someone's already done that? We've all done that. And the reason we do that is it's simple.
I mean, I'd like to think of MAME as the Wikipedia.
of game hardware reference, right? Like that's just how it is. And other emulators too, of course.
I'm kind of shorthanding MAME. There's plenty of documentation and amazing work outside of MAME,
of course. But we've all been using it and we all have been from the beginning.
And I think we should stop doing this nudge wink thing we've
been doing in this industry forever when it comes to stuff
like this, when it comes to MAME or other forms of easily
available hardware documentation.
This is volunteer work that we've
been exploiting for decades, and like in secrecy,
like we're ashamed of it.
But I don't.
I don't see where the shame is in referencing the MAME project.
This is, you know, it's, again, it's the Wikipedia, we're not ashamed of referencing Wikipedia.
Why are we ashamed of looking at open source emulation as reference?
I think we should be proud and boastful and we should be thanking MAME in the credits
and I'm calling everyone out, including myself when I say that.
Alright, Wikipedia of hardware reference.
That should be your starting point, not your primary source.
When I was an editor at websites, if a journalist was just citing Wikipedia as a reference,
I'm going to kick that back and say, no, do your research.
So same thing with MAME.
It's only as good as the contributions that have been made to it.
I mean, sometimes it's wrong.
So we actually found quite a few things that were wrong when we accessed the original boards
for the games in SNK 40th.
I really should probably report this stuff to someone over there.
But I mean, here it is now.
These are some of the things we found.
And yeah, in this case, yeah, we're
hooking up the original board in our makeshift lab in the back.
But I mean, we don't always have boards.
You know, like, really, we might be provided ROM files from the client, but, you know,
how likely do you think it is that 20 plus arcade games we had English and US boards
sent us?
It's not possible in this project.
So we have to sort of rely on things like YouTube videos of actual cabinets, which is
okay to do and it should be done.
Like if you're doing one of these projects and you don't have the original hardware,
you should at least seek out video of the original hardware.
It often exists, sometimes it doesn't.
But it's not just that MAME is quote-unquote wrong and accurate sometimes.
Sometimes when it's right, it's not necessarily right.
So this is Street Smart.
It's a fighting game from SNK.
On the left are the actual RGB values that the game spits out internally.
And so MAME being a sort of like, you know, binary interpretation of the game says, okay,
that's the colors of the game.
I mean, look at that.
Do we really think the game is supposed to look like that?
I think that, I don't know, maybe the artist had a busted monitor or something, but clearly
the game is not supposed to look like that.
So we adjusted the RGB curve to compensate for that and to reflect what I think would
have happened in a real life scenario, which would be an arcade operator boosting the gamma
to try to make up for this very, very dark game they just got in.
And this kind of goes to what I was saying earlier, the game code...
is binary. But game playing is human and subjective, and I think that as authors of this kind of
work we should be empathetic, I guess would be the word, toward how a player would actually
have played this game, and what the author's artistic intent was, right? And the sort of
environment that the game would have been in, and the context that's needed to understand
it even. And, you know, like the rotary dial stuff, it's like, do we need to actually reinterpret
it and re-translate?
in a human accessible way rather than a binary way how to actually play these games.
And it's that sort of human interaction that drives everything we do.
I like to say that we don't make games necessarily or game compilations.
We make documentaries you play with a controller or if you prefer we make like coffee table
books you play on a video game platform.
And...
you know, of course the games are playable because it's about games.
It's on a gameplay platform.
So the games to me are like feature two.
But this notion of capturing that history and giving you the fan
this this hardcore product to to to really experience and appreciate this.
That's the product.
But we've barely started as an industry.
There's so much more we could be doing.
I mean, I'm just blue skying here, right?
But like, just think about it like we have.
complete access to what's on the screen, what's being shown and played at you, and the player
can manipulate things with the controller.
What can we do with that?
We can step backward and forward through the development process and show you early versions
of it and let you see why decisions were made.
We can...
I don't know, put the game source code in there, let you tweak it and compile it in
the game and like, like see what what adjusting it would do.
Right. We can we can, you know, like you earlier, we can improve the hardware
that the games ran on to compensate for some of its flaws.
Actually, M2 has done that beautifully with the 3D releases on the 3DS.
We can make a game about the making of the game, right?
Like we can make like a visual novel or an RPG about making these games.
There's this really wonderful book called Understanding Comics.
Do you guys know this book?
Yeah, Understanding Comics is a comic book that explains the art of comic books as a comic book,
and it works beautifully to illustrate why comics work.
work. So what's understanding games in these terms, right? I don't know, we could slow down
time and like annotate game functions as they happen to help you understand what you're seeing
here.
We can let people mess with our virtual machines themselves,
like let them turn off graphic layers
to see what's behind there, which they're already doing
in the amateur emulator world,
but we can unlock that for them
in a consumer-facing way, right?
We can give them tile viewers and asset viewers
to look at how the game was made.
We can make new cuts of these games
that combine the best features of each SKU
into a master version.
But put the original in there if you do that.
But I mean, the possibilities are endless, right?
We're just starting to think about how to do all these things using these source materials
to bring this stuff back.
But we can't do any of that stuff if that stuff is lost.
Usually when we talk about game preservation, I think the notion that people have is taking
the binary data, making sure it's online or safe or accessible.
And usually what I say to that is like, no, the pirates took care of it.
We're fine.
You can download this stuff.
But, you know, we...
That's not actually reality.
We've already actually lost even binary data
for some important games.
This is a photograph of an advertisement
of SNK's very first game, the Mikan Kit series.
These were brick-breaking games in the late 70s.
Actually, 1978.
This is the game that SNK 40th anniversary
got the 40-year anniversary from.
We don't have it.
No one has it.
They're not available.
They're not in Maine.
We don't even know how many they made.
They made between three and six.
We don't know.
And we don't even have people to ask anymore
that were around back then.
So even with this commercial support
of making this historical interactive document
to preserve what this company was and its roots,
we don't have its actual roots.
They seem to be gone.
We actually had to send someone on a special mission to the, I believe it's pronounced,
Diet Library in Tokyo, because they had an extensive archive of literature, including
trade magazines for the coin-op industry.
Ads like this is just all we have now for the Micon Kids series.
We don't even have player testament as to how these games played, what the features
were.
What does that ship do?
We don't know.
We don't know what the ship does in this game and all we can do is sort of extract as much
Detail as we can and try to preserve that while we can
And it's just like we got at least these photo guys like it's like the yet. There's like a Sasquatch
You know what I mean? It's like that shouldn't
B for video games, like looking at these mysterious things.
We actually managed to find one of the three to six Micon kit
boards for us to look at.
And it was through, actually, an arcade rental company
in rural Japan called Takai Shokai.
One of our developers, Brandon Sheffield,
had to travel like eight hours on public transit
to go to this place.
And he's been running this arcade business
since the 70s, and he happened to have one of the Micon kits.
So he was able to hook it up for us and Brandon was able to play the game to fill in some
details for our museum feature.
Unfortunately it was too late in the product for us to actually dump the ROMs with him
and put it in the product, but at least we know where one is.
Maybe if more people buy the game we can do a patch or something.
But it's not just these ancient, like, crusty arcanoid clones.
Like, Yosaku is a game that even Take-san doesn't have.
And this is a tree chopping game that...
From all accounts, it was actually really popular in Japan in the 70s, and in fact,
when you look up the game now, the results you typically get are an unauthorized clone
of this original game that was made for a home console, but the original—and it was
super popular, that clone—but the original game that was cloned, we can't find it.
Like, we've heard rumors that sometimes this arcade here
might swap it in for one of the machines once in a while,
but we tried.
We have communications to the Game Preservation Society
in Japan, we know a lot of the collectors out there.
We can't find Yosaku.
Yosaku might actually be gone, and if it exists still,
it's probably not digitized,
it's probably literally rotting on a board
and dying right now.
But it's not just the games themselves, even the material.
surrounding the games is becoming incredibly difficult to find, again, even on a commercial
project where we're paid to do it and have access to people.
We can't find some of this stuff.
Luckily, we were really fortunate to find a guy, Yoshino-san.
Yoshino-san worked at SNK in the 80s and was like a super fanboy for the company.
He actually got his start, I think, because he wrote a fanzine about SNK in like, 84.
So they hired him to be the communications guy.
So he made his fanzine official.
Because he was such a fan, he kept a lot of this stuff.
And for these two games in particular, World Wars and Mahjong Classroom...
This is the only physical thing we have for these games.
We have the game ROMs.
Well, actually, not for Mojave Classroom.
That game's not dumb.
But for World Wars, we have the game ROMs and stuff.
But this is the first time.
This is the only thing we know of that has the logo
and what passes for its key art.
And we were just so fortunate not only to find him,
but that SNK is a company that not only acknowledges
its past employees and allows us to talk to them,
but actually.
paid him. Like, SNK paid Yoshino-san, as a consultant, to work with us, to answer our
questions, to actually scan his materials, which, I mean, like, that should be a standing
ovation, but we're running low on time. Thank you again, SNK. And it's not just the materials,
it's the memories, right? So this is a game called Tangram Q. It's a simplistic-looking
Tangram game.
You know, like making the shape out of the shapes is Tangrams, right?
There's another one that's lost. We couldn't find the ROM. We couldn't find a board anywhere.
But it turns out we didn't know this until we had access to Yoshino-san. The game wasn't released, right? So like that's
information that doesn't... like you can't Google Tangram. I mean, maybe you can now, but you couldn't Google Tangram Q to find out,
oh, it doesn't exist. We don't have to hunt for it. Like it didn't come out.
Like we didn't know that until we happened to have access to that one guy.
And you know, game preservation is kind of like that right now.
Um, even on past products, uh, like going back to Disney afternoon collection that
we did, uh, Capcom and Disney didn't have a ton of material for the games and,
and this, this beautiful box art that was produced for these games.
Uh, Capcom doesn't have it.
Disney doesn't have it.
Or if they did, they, I don't know, they might have it.
They, they weren't very communicative.
Um, the only reason that we have this stuff is because I personally happen to have connections
to the like video game art collector world.
And I happen to be friends with this guy, Bronte, is what he goes by in Canada, who
happens to have purchased out the files of a marketing company that closed because he
cares about this stuff.
And that's the only reason we have this art.
And that's, that's, to me, that's scary.
But scariest to me of all is source, right?
How many of you guys here work on games?
Raise your hands.
OK, keep your hands up.
How many of I asked you?
OK, so keep your hands up if you worked on a game that shipped
five or more years ago, let's say.
Franz, I know you did.
OK, games five or more years ago.
How many of you feel right now, if I asked you to,
you can get that source and compile that game?
Okay, few of you.
The few of you that are left,
how confident are you that 20 years from now,
someone could not only locate that,
but they could compile it and build it and it's right?
Literally none of you.
Literally zero people, right?
And OK, let's make that even scarier.
Digital Eclipse, the current incarnation,
we've done these four products.
50-ish classic arcade games.
Out of those 50, how many would you
suppose we had source access to?
Zero is the correct answer.
Did I tell you that?
Zero.
I'm not shaming companies when I say
that it's just the reality.
We didn't hold onto a lot of this source code.
And that's terrifying.
So, I'm speaking at a developers conference,
ask developers what we can do.
I'm gonna sort of bring back some wisdom from GDC's past.
These are my pals, Lane Nooney and Jason Scott.
I'm gonna let you figure out the order of operations here,
but you're gonna steal from work
and you're gonna put it in a box.
You can do the box at work or you can do it at home.
I don't care, just do both of those things.
But don't forget that that material has to go somewhere,
because if it's in your house forever
and you get hit by a bus, just put it somewhere.
There's a lot of places to put your stuff.
This list is nowhere near complete, obviously,
but these, for my money, are the best potential homes
for video game material.
So the Strong Museum of Play in Rochester, New York.
What I love about them is that they have a library in-house.
They have full-time librarians.
and they are actively collecting
video game development material.
So for example, Jordan Mechner,
who did Karateka, Prince of Persia, Last Express,
he donated all of his materials to The Strong.
And as a researcher, you can, and I have,
you can make an appointment with the library
and they'll bring out Jordan's material
and you can go through his design notes
and the video that he shot to rotoscope things.
Like you can access those materials and it's wonderful.
I really recommend that as an option.
The National Video Game Museum, Frisco, Texas.
They don't have a library yet, but these guys have been collecting this sort of ephemeral material
longer than anybody, like since the 90s.
And they've been, they're in what they call their sort of 1.0 phase of the museum right now,
which is more of a public-facing display.
But their expansion plans, should they raise enough money,
include opening a library.
So that's going to be a really viable option
when that happens.
The Internet Archive, if you don't give a damn,
if you're like, I don't care who has this,
just put it out there, that's your option right there.
Just pop it on the Internet Archive.
If you own the intellectual property, cool,
just put it there.
If you don't own it, I'm not a cop.
Put it on the internet.
Put it on the internet archive.
If you don't want to deal with it yourself,
find Jason Scott, who will do it for you.
And he'll do free PR to promote how amazing you are for putting
this material online.
Library of Congress is one we never talk about.
But they do have a video game archive in Culpeper, Virginia,
kind of remote, not the normal archive.
It's where their films are.
And they, believe it or not, could be a viable option.
They do seek material like this,
but they don't do a lot of outreach about it.
And I mean, this is the Library of Congress.
Their job is to take things, keep it safe.
And I've talked to them about it,
and they're like, yeah, we'll take source code.
We'll keep it safe.
I don't know that they necessarily have the infrastructure
to maintain source code or anything like that,
but I think that's something we could work toward.
I mean, I don't know, let's use our federal dollars
for a source repo.
Why not?
And finally, there's us, the Video Game History Foundation.
This is my baby.
So we're the newest of the bunch.
We just celebrated our two-year anniversary this week, I think.
So we're a 501c3.
We're just across the bridge in Emeryville, just down the street
from Pixar.
We are actually going to open a library there this year.
I haven't announced that.
I guess I just did.
But we're going to open by appointment.
I can't be a librarian 9 to 5.
But we're going to have a video game history reference
library.
I think it might be the first dedicated one.
That's all it's for.
So we're doing that.
If I'm wrong, if there's another video game
library for referencing this stuff, let me know.
I've got to visit.
I like to say we fill in the gaps with the other institutions.
Like we don't have to maintain a public museum.
I don't have to use my money for rent on a large space or conservation
of really crazy rare materials, things like that.
So we can be really flexible with our time and money.
But I think.
One of our best functions in the world
is to sort of provide an impartial voice
if you have materials like this.
So if you have your video game development material,
you don't know exactly where you want it to go,
but you want it to go somewhere,
I'll go through your options with you
and I'll tell you the pros and cons of each.
They're mostly pros,
but you know, I'll help you find the right home.
But I think our best place in the world is I want to work toward source material
being an educational resource.
I think the industry sees this stuff as a trade secret.
I think it's an educational tool.
I don't think there's a better way to understand a video game than to go back
to its source and to study it, maybe even rebuild it, right?
I want to live in a world where historians like me don't have to like reverse
engineer binaries.
This is stupid.
Like, if that source exists, why am I going out of my way
to circumvent that when the real thing exists?
It's kind of a new concept, I think.
Source code is an educational resource,
at least for games.
I don't think the traditional library system
really has language for that or tools yet,
but it's something we're trying to figure out.
But we're making it up as we go.
It's all brand new, figuring it out as we go.
But maybe we should figure it out together.
So if you're interested.
Let's get in touch, let's figure this out.
Let's figure out how to get our source material safe
and accessible and figure out where your comfort level is
on access, things like that.
Let's figure this out
because it's only gonna get harder as we go.
And that's it.
Thank you, GDC.
I think I have time for literally one question,
and there's one person at a mic.
But before we get to that, I think two doors down,
is that right?
Yeah, two doors down, there's a sort of congregating meeting
area where I will be.
So let's go hang out there and solve all these problems
immediately today.
Yes, sir.
Do you know Showtime, Eric Chung?
He's the guy who preserves a bunch of arcade games,
and he's part of the main community.
He has extensive network with the arcade network and game preservation.
And he's also the founder and CEO of XR Arcadia, a new arcade platform
that will be available worldwide and hope.
And what do you think of the new arcade platform?
Is it worth preserving its history?
No, no, of course it is.
So the question was, do I know Eric Showtime?
He's in Japan, and he's an arcade board collector.
He has extensive connections to other arcade collectors.
He can find things.
Yeah, I know Eric.
Not personally, but I know a lot of him.
And do I think his new venture is worth preserving?
Yes, of course.
So yes.
I think that's...can we do one more?
Yeah, one more. Yes.
I'll make this as quick as I can.
We're at the point where we have official remasters
of games. What do we have to do to get to
remixing?
Ooh, okay. So the question was, we have official
remasters of games. What do we need
to do to get to official remixing?
What, something that Sega did that I really love
is that they did a collection of Sega Genesis stuff
on Steam and they actually allow users
to submit modifications to Sega Genesis ROMs,
which is really cool.
So like there's already a sense of,
you know, it's not Sega making remix games, right?
But they're blessing remix games
as being allowed on their platform.
I'd argue we're already there.
I think that Wonder Boy the Dragon's Trap is a remix.
Uh, I think, I think the, at least artistically like the, the actual art,
uh, it is a remix of the art.
Um, but what I'm really interested in, and I brought this up very briefly
earlier, I'm interested in remixing different versions of the game into
like the definitive version of something.
So like the example I like to use is Zelda 2.
So Zelda 2 originally was a disc game. It was on the Famicom disc system
So it used the enhanced audio capabilities of that system
When it was brought to cartridge, you know, we don't have that enhanced audio chip anymore
So they couldn't include that but they added a new quality of life features
They had to do tiles so that the dungeons varied more so like there's no definitive Zelda 2
I would love us to start mixing things to make the actual definitive versions of these games
We're actually out of time, we're over,
but two doors down, I'm gonna go hang out there.
Thank you guys so much, this was great.