Hello, everybody.
Good morning.
Welcome to the GDC.
This is a lecture about digital pixelization
in the 22nd century.
And actually, I just want to let you
know that you are in the right room.
This is the NBA Jam post-mortem.
And I'll be heading the surgery.
No radio playing, gambling, spinning during the procedures.
And if you'd like to turn off your cell phones.
Imagine, if you will, 2001 Space Odyssey music playing behind.
That's what I had in my mind.
Let's go back to a simpler time, the 90s, a decade defined by profound change,
world changing events, the dissolution of the Soviet Union.
Yes. The cloning of the first mammal.
Baaaaaa!
It was a big moment, I remember that.
But, meanwhile, the Hubble telescope goes into orbit.
The Gulf War.
But meanwhile, in Chicago, at Midway Games,
a new era was being ushered in.
A renaissance in the gaming industry would explode onto the scene,
shattering records and coin up earnings.
and sales. The game was a turning point. It was revolutionary. It was Mortal Kombat. Wait, what?
Hold on. I know what you're thinking. I kind of thought the same thing, too.
But then, like, shortly after that, maybe two months tops at best, the real game changer.
Where are you at, Boone? Yeah, the real game changer came along.
Welcome to NBA Jam, Boomshakalaka!
The game changer the world was waiting for had come at last.
The savior of the coin-op business.
And maybe the killer of the pinball game, but that's another story.
NBA Jam would go on to become the highest earning coin-op game of all time.
That's pretty amazing.
And I was one of the highest paid performers at that time, $600 I believe.
for a game that would earn a lot of money.
Yeah, it was a new era,
and that's why we're all here in the room right now.
It was 25 years ago today
that Mark J. Turmell gave fan gamers a new game to play.
And all you gamer geeks that know codes,
MJT0322 is his birthday.
The man with the biggest head on the planet,
cause he invented the big heads.
It's 6'6", hailing from Michigan, one of the original Detroit bad boys,
the man in the middle of the gaming industry, Mr. Zeus himself, MJT. It's his birthday.
Give him a big round of applause. The 6'6'' legend. High five. All right. It's his birthday.
How fitting is that? And now, co-creator.
at six foot four. He was the guy well you know maybe 5'10, 5'11. He wore shoes six feet we'll
call six feet Sal DeVita. You may remember him he was also one of the actors in Mortal Kombat.
There's all the great visuals the genius Sal DeVita. Mark Sabell we're glad you guys got up
early. I know there's been a lot of partying. Thanks for being here we're gonna have some fun
and let's
Get the surgery in the postmortem.
Let's start here.
Thanks, guys.
All right.
Thank you, Tim Kitsrow.
Tim is a rare talent.
Tim, Sal, and I not only did NBA Jam, but then we went on to do NFL Blitz.
And Tim was amazing on both products.
It was totally unnecessary, Mark, but a whole lot of fun to hear.
and so it's been great working with these guys over the years.
It's an honor to be here today talking to my brethren in the games business.
A lot of you are probably too young to even remember NBA Jam or to have played it, but
many probably did immerse themselves in it a time or two.
It's an honor to be representing the team, not just these guys, but the team that put
the game together.
It was really kind of a magical time back at Midway there in the 90s.
So, let's flash back to 1993.
Because again, some of you probably don't remember this,
but 25 years ago, the game was introduced.
We did it at an NBA All-Star game.
It was in Utah.
A lot of the players came over, you know, they shuffled over,
took a look at this game.
They all got a copy of the coin-op game,
$3,500, $3,900 piece of equipment.
But they were mad.
Every single one of them I talked to
was mad because either they weren't in the game,
because I had selected the wrong players,
or they didn't like their stats.
So it started right then and there.
You know, you hear that over the years
where these athletes are unhappy with their stats.
But 1993, and this slide right here,
the upper right corner really tells the whole story here. $2,468.
That's one week of earnings at one of our locations.
Every arcade around the country, of course what they do
is they track their revenue on a per game basis.
They're trying to shuffle in new games,
get rid of the games that aren't making money.
Hey Mark, give them a frame of reference.
Like what did the average game make?
It's there on the screen.
So the number two game is, you know, virtual racing.
But so $2,468 was just such a stunning number
because as a $3,500 or $3,900 price point
for these coin-op machines, well, the operator,
the owner of that device,
can pay it off in a couple of weeks and then it's pure gravy from from there
forward.
What it all added up to with the number of coin op units we sent out there
and that the actually averaging around seven hundred dollars
it comes out to a billion dollars in that first twelve months.
That's four billion quarters.
I mean, it's crazy.
We talk nowadays about microtransactions
and these games are crushing it here and there,
the Candy Crushes, the Clash of Clans.
Well, here's a game that really kind of set the tone
for microtransactions when you think back on it.
At the same time, Jurassic Park was the breakout film,
became the number one film of all time
at about $350 million grossing.
That was unheard of at the time.
And so it really kind of puts it in perspective.
The game just really blew up.
Of course, then there was a lot of anticipation.
I'm a little off today.
A little late.
It blew up.
That created a lot of anticipation for the home versions.
And so we were on the cover of these magazines.
You can see here, Ed Boon, I don't know if you noticed
that first line that says,
better than Mortal Kombat?
Question mark?
Leave it alone.
But, yeah, but no, we were really excited
just to see the kind of the anticipation and the coverage,
gaming guides and so forth.
And indeed, we actually delivered.
The home version came out.
It was a faithful conversion of the coin-operated game.
And we sold millions of cartridges that year of NBA Jam.
It was a Bitcoin of its day.
Yeah.
People couldn't believe it.
Yeah, it was a crazy time.
But so that's stepping back to 93.
What we're really here to try to cover
are some of the stories, some of how it actually came to exist,
and some of the problems and challenges and kind
of goofy things that happened.
So that's what we're going to do today, is kind of talk
through some of those stories.
And then we're going to have a little Q&A
if anybody has questions toward the end.
Both Tim and Sal will interject as we go forward here.
But it's not going to be like behind the music VH1 where everybody had drug problems and rehabs.
It's a really happy story. It's post-mortem, but it's a happy story.
I have that slide.
You have a problem?
I do. I have that slide.
Oh, you have the slide.
We were mostly done.
No.
But I do have to acknowledge the team right off the bat.
Again, we're up here.
I'm honored to represent.
But here on the lower left-hand picture, Tony Goski.
He's still killing it, I'm sure, on the Mortal Kombat
franchise there in Chicago.
John Carlton is the lower left, an artist.
I'm up top.
Sal's there in the middle.
Jamie Rivett.
kind of brooding in the back there with the black hair.
I still have the honor of working with him on a daily basis at Zynga today.
He did the Smash TV conversions for the consumer side.
Smash TV was my first coin-op game.
So he's been killing it for decades.
John Hay in the lower right-hand corner is the audio guy,
we always used to say, the sound guy.
wrote a lot of the music and was in the studio with Tim
to come up with all those phrases.
And then in the, yep.
And upper right, John Newcomer standing there.
He's still in the business today.
And then I put Sean Liptack here
because he wasn't in any of the other photos.
He was kind of our brainiac engineer,
did a lot of really cool things.
So wanted to acknowledge the team.
And of course, Tim Kitsiro right there in the studio.
He's on fire.
And at lower right, the hairdos of the time, we didn't talk about that, the Robert Plant
and the Bono?
Bono?
Wrestling?
Wrestling.
Who wore it best?
You decide.
Right, right.
Yeah, some good hair back in those days.
How it began.
So it's really, when you think about Midway in that era,
you're familiar with NARC.
That was this new hardware platform
that Eugene Jarvis had developed there in Chicago.
They crafted a game that had some digitized imagery in it.
There was a.
a red Porsche and you know there were characters walking around, you were trying to take out
drug dealers.
It was really the first violent game even.
There were a lot of body parts, you know, you'd blow people up with, you know, bazookas.
But the rest of the industry too was starting to dabble in
digitizing, of taking, you know, there was claymation on this Primal Rage game.
You know, people were starting to try to get these images off of VHS tapes or Hi8 tapes
and put them onto the screen. And so we were all internally kind of, you know, geeking out on that.
My art partner on Smash TV and Total Carnage was John Tobias, an amazing artist.
I have the honor to work with him actually now on a daily basis as well at Zynga.
But...
He was incredible at drawing and painting,
but he wanted to do digitized graphics.
He branched off and joined up with Ed
to create Mortal Kombat.
And then I branched off to dabble in digitized graphics
to do NBA Jam.
Didn't start out, though, as an NBA licensed product.
We knew we wanted to get characters.
Basketball, I'm a big fan.
It was something that could leverage that tech.
I went out onto the streets to try to find
some talent to shoot.
So I was cruising around YMCA's and.
you know, in kind of the inner parts of the city,
trying to look for some talent.
Found some guys, you know, paid them some money
to come into a studio and said,
hey, we want to shoot you to do this.
We'll pay you this hourly rate.
So we got some talent to come in,
and you can see actually a little couple of snippets here
of the,
of those early sessions, we had the camera rolling on a track and the characters.
We painted the wall blue.
We put blue uniforms on the players.
We saw this on TV, on the weather report.
I'll let Sal talk about that later to explain the strategy behind blue on blue.
Really smart.
Yeah.
Yeah, we'll get to that.
Don't get me started.
Blue demons.
Yeah.
So about halfway through the project,
the president of the company, Neil Nicastro, he came in
and he said, why not try to get an NBA license?
It didn't really even occur to me
that that would be in the realm of possibility.
That had never happened before.
We're just a small coin-op company, it felt like.
But we put together a video.
This is a short little piece of the video
that we sent off to the NBA.
Yeah, the real video is like 10 minutes long, or 5 minutes long.
Williams Electronics is currently developing an arcade-based, 4-player video basketball game.
One which employs lifelike digitized graphics.
If granted an NBA license, we would elevate this game beyond any computer sports simulation ever done.
Allowing players to choose their favorite team, and see and hear the names of recognizable players would be fantastic.
The 6 foot high NBA logo on the side of the cabinet would undoubtedly attract much attention
and generate even more excitement.
Thank you for viewing this work in progress and for considering our request.
So it was a little bit longer, this video.
We sent that off and we kind of waited anxiously
to hear how they'd respond.
I didn't expect them to accept it.
And sure enough, we got a phone call back
that they had rejected.
Rejected!
Rejected.
And so we.
Get that stuff out of here.
I can't go all day.
But I was surprised at the reason they rejected us.
They basically said, we don't want our NBA logo
in these seedy arcade locations.
And we were like, you know, well, yeah, I've seen a few seedy arcades,
but that's not the normal arcade experience.
But their reference point was Times Square in New York City.
Because that's where their offices were and at that time there in the 80s Times Square was very
You know grungy a lot of you know
Prostitution a lot of drugs and a lot of that was happening at these 24-hour and if you're a corporate NBA guy
Where are you hanging out?
Right and so they didn't want order in there
But so they said, hey, you know, we don't want our NBA logo.
I don't want my wife to know where I'm going.
Six feet tall.
Or our fans.
Yep.
Plastered there in those locations.
And so we were taken aback, but we said, oh, we can solve this.
And so we went and we created a new video
that went to bowling alleys and family entertainment centers.
And Mormon churches.
Yeah, we have more of the normal location
for coin-operated games.
And it worked.
They got that, they said, okay, we understand, and they worked out a deal that was very reasonable.
I think we were only paying them about $100, $150 a game on that $3,500 price point.
So it was a pretty good deal to get that NBA license.
That brought up of course then the problem.
We're halfway through development.
You saw kind of the state of the game,
you know, players running around,
you know, it shot a lot of footage.
But it brought up all these issues of, okay, players,
and how do we leverage all that?
How do we get this content?
This, you know, small, too small to read,
but I'm highlighting here a couple of things.
One, we were asking for source material,
like, you know, can you take photos of the players?
Back in those days, there were no...
NBA photos they took in preseason camp.
We referenced down here at the bottom, it says,
what do you think about the name NBA Jam or NBA Showtime?
We eventually used both names, of course.
So it's the opening letter there in August of 92
with kind of what our requests were, including the players.
And the players, again, there was no internet.
There was no DirecTV NBA League Pass package.
It was just me and John Hay, the sound guy,
kind of looking at, we were fans, but we had to look at the...
you know the newspaper and you know try to figure out your favorites yeah picking
our favorites you know who would look good out there on the screen you know
we're uh... we're making those choices i've got a lot of heat over the years
with some of the selections uh... some of the players
you know weren't worthy of being in the the final two
But, yeah, it's part of the lore.
And you would have cut Chicago out altogether if you could have done that, right?
Yeah, well, that's true.
Yeah, no Chicago.
I don't even reference that in the deck here, but some of you who are, you know...
aficionados of these secret codes. I did have cheat codes in against the Bulls
when they played the Pistons because I was a big Pistons fan so it was my only
way with Jordan rising it was my only way to kind of level the playing field.
He was working with Chuck Daly in the Jordan rules. So underhanded. Right, right.
But so that that brought us to okay now we need these players. We've got to have a broadcast look
We need a broadcast announcer. We need to be you know up our game
and so that
That was the next problem, and that's where we really
you know, got Sal involved to try to solve that problem.
And so I'll let you, you know, talk about a couple of these
things on the tech side.
Sure, yeah, actually, so getting all the,
the challenge of getting all the.
the players in the game and making it look broadcast and whatever, that was huge.
Our team, two guys, three guys, Tony as well, we were like scratching our heads.
How do we get all the players in the game?
And how do we make it look like TV?
Well, luckily, we had an advantage with our hardware.
Our hardware was amazing.
It gave us the ability to...
Most hardware for video games at the time had like 16 colors of just a few palettes
they could put on the screen at any one time or 32 or something like that.
but we had the ability to put 256 palettes of 256 colors,
which if we were creative enough could make,
you know, pretty much make it look like
unlimited colors on the screen.
So it gave us the ability to get all these beautiful,
like flesh tones and all these beautiful highlights
and so, and also when the videos were shot,
you know, all the details in the skin came out
to an extent, except for, you know, how it was shot.
So.
So, to get the characters in the game, we thought we had an advantage by shooting them
against the blue screen, the digitized footage, because it would automatically cut them out
from the background, and then we'd have footage to, we'd have those frames to choose to put
them in the game.
And actually, there's a little video here that shows the process of that.
And here, I'll just go through that real quick.
Everyone who has seen this work in progress agrees we have a hit on our hands.
First, basketball players are videotaped in a studio
performing hundreds of moves.
Then artists digitize this footage
into individual frames, which are stored and played back
in sequence or animated to create a video basketball
player capable of performing on command.
Artists are also creating every other element
of the basketball experience, including the court.
That's enough of that. So that's all you need to know about that. So it looks really clean. It's
like, oh cool, all the characters just pulled right out of the background. But unfortunately,
like Mark mentioned, we had shot the characters against a blue screen that wasn't really lit
well, like where it could be easily chroma keyed away. So that was our first challenge.
The second challenge was we shot it on videotape, which meant the quality was pretty blurry and all
the edges of the characters just bled into the background.
So we had to go in and then also we shot with blue jerseys, uniforms, which against a blue screen.
So the chroma key didn't quite work for that either.
So we had to hand cut out every frame of animation on every character for every single animation.
We'd go through and pixel by pixel.
And so part of our hardware tools were a suite of custom tools that allowed us to step frame
by frame, pixel by pixel, put on our headphones, you know, zone out, and for months just cut
out every frame of animation.
And that, and then we had to go through and tint all the edges because all the blue screen
in the background just bled right into them, right across.
So it would pretty much shape out every character of every, on every, every different character.
And then we had different.
skin tone characters.
So we had to unify all their skin tones
so that we could use every animation for every character.
So we had to tint all the skin all together
to like a medium tone, so it could be easily
with a palette, the index colors of palette that we had,
which meant that we, I'm not gonna go into detail,
but you could change that to be any shade that you want
for skin, and then jersey,
and we could change out the jersey colors.
So by doing that, our hardware allowed us to have flexibility and freedom with that.
But then the real challenge was the heads, the NBA characters themselves.
How were we going to get every NBA character in the game?
We just shot the few guys that we shot and that was daunting to strip out and to get
into the game.
So we had to come up with a system for how we could actually get their faces in there and we came up with one based on
Tech from previous games. It was like an object attach point
Something you'd use for like, you know holding guns or weapons or picking something up and moving it around
It's like a little we call them animation points
But it's like a little point that you stick on every single frame you stick on to the part of the body that you want
The object to attach to and we said hey, why don't we use that for maybe putting heads on the guys?
So we oops we lopped off
the heads of the animations and then we had to come up with a way of attaching the head that we wanted.
But the characters are moving around, they're like all buzzing around, so we had to assign
a head angle, and you can see it there, for every frame of animation depending on which way the
character was facing. So that was truly daunting. Luckily, you know, we had a talented group of guys
that could extract the heads from
things like magazines, slides, there was no internet.
So we had to go to the store and like,
okay, let's look through these, you know, these mags.
Oh, cool, there's a head angle here that we could use for,
you know, a large one or whatever.
Yeah, and so we'd watch the shows, the games,
and we'd record them on videotape.
I'm like, oh, there's one right there.
And so we'd take that tape and bring it to work,
and then we'd, you know, scan it and whatever.
So it was a nightmare to do.
And then we had to hand touch stuff.
And then we got savvy in the end where we noticed that,
oh, you know what, from the back,
you know, these guys kind of look the same
and these guys kind of look the same
and these guys totally cheated on a lot of that stuff.
It might have been easier to just invent the internet.
We should have totally done that, looking back now.
Actually, Tony Goski, again, he's an amazing artist
on the Mortal Kombat team, and he started
just hand-doing these things.
He'd say, nah, you know what, let me just paint this guy.
It was faster for him to create it than to digitize it.
Yeah, he's a freak, though.
So we had, our tools allowed us a lot of flexibility
and help on that.
So, all right, back to you, Mark.
Great, thanks.
And when you say a guy's a freak, he's a freak.
When you guys, I mean, you guys do.
A lot of stories that I could go into on this game, a lot of interesting things.
We're going to touch on a bunch here in the next 10-15 minutes.
But a lot of it is tech related, a lot of it is kind of the CPU assistance related.
I've gotten a lot of heat over the years for the cheating that happens in NBA Jam or even
NFL Blitz.
But a lot of games do it.
And we had systems in place to neuter that or to remove it.
But talking about a couple of the tech challenges.
It might sound rather mundane, but it was a big technical
hurdle for us.
Shooting a pass to your teammate.
Initially we had the teammate stop and turn and accept the pass,
but of course your opponent would come up and knock you down while the ball is in flight.
So we realized we had to keep the player running at his trajectory.
So we locked him in and let him run, and then he would reach back and catch it.
counted the number of ticks before the ball would get to him and we'd start the proper
animation at the right time. But then of course that carried him into the sideline. We didn't
want to ever let a player step out of bounds or pass out of bounds. That was a fail. So he had to
get to the sideline and then he had to glance off and continue to run down the sideline.
And so then the ball at pass time had to take that all into account
And so it was quite a challenge we iterated on that for and really this is about the decisions that had to get made to
Emulate what somebody would want to be doing or what somebody would expect to happen while you're playing the game
We want to eliminate frustration from our game and that's something that the other games had
That's why like when you did a pass in other games
They would literally stop and wait for the ball to come to them
Or the ball would just hit you in the body and attach to you.
Right.
We wanted to rotate and make this variety of catches.
Make it look more real.
And then, again, anticipate what you're trying to do.
And so as responsive and as seamless of a gameplay flow
as possible is what we're trying to achieve.
And lots of decisions were made and good code written
to do that.
It was a can of worms.
Because, again, imagine that you're shooting a pass.
Well, you know the player's running in this direction, so I'm going to shoot it like this.
But he's really going to glance off the wall halfway through his run and be down there,
so I really need to rotate and shoot it in this way.
Take into account where he'd be after he glances off the wall and travels a little bit in that
amount of time.
And then, so maybe now that opens up behind the back pass or, you know, so there are a
lot of, it was a big can of worms.
So that was one topic.
Leap to Rim for Dunks.
We at Midway, we created this system called Leap At.
And you're probably most familiar with NFL Blitz,
where when you're running at an opponent,
you hit the tackle button.
And it's like a missile, a heat-seeking missile.
It rotates and it gets to the victim in X number of ticks.
Well, that same concept is the leap at
for the wrist to the rim.
And so a player would go up for a dunk
and we knew we had to reach the rim
and based on how many ticks I would establish
for that point of connection
would dictate how high.
the player would go. If I said, well get there in two seconds, well it's going to have to go way up
and then come way down. If it's one second then it's a little bit more normal. Which is ironically
how the big dunks happen because like you just by mistake you'd put in some number that was too big
and the guy would shoot up in the air it's like, whoa that was really cool.
Yeah, yeah, I mean, I spent, you know, weeks and weeks and weeks just on animations.
That was my, you know, kind of my main focus once we got all this art was crafting all of it together
and creating the dunks and even combining a portion of one dunk, a spin, a spin dunk from
this angle would actually work from this angle if I combined it with this. And so it was like
this big puzzle piece that we were able to put together.
So the dunks became very modular.
Every part of a dunk could then flow
into a different part of another dunk.
And we got really creative with that.
And that's what gave us a lot of a win.
Yeah.
And the high dunks were a little bit controversial.
Some people were like, no, no, that's too crazy.
We're trying to make a simulation here.
But we tried to find a balance.
Eugene Jarvis.
you know, who was my mentor and somebody that has made,
you know, obviously a big dent in this business.
He would come in, I would show him a dunk,
and he'd say, yeah, that's pretty cool,
but why don't you go a little bit higher?
You know, and, you know, I joke with Ed, you know,
I'm sure he said the same thing to Ed over the years,
like, yeah, that's cool,
but how about a little bit more blood?
You know, and he did the same thing with Smash TV,
and with Mutoid Man, all these things.
So he had a really interesting take on things,
but...
So that was the leap at, shattering backboard.
We didn't think we'd get away with it,
but the NBA allowed it.
They soon shut that down.
The next year, they actually eliminated all the NBA games
from doing such a thing.
Beyond Fire Mode and Burger King,
Jamie Rivette, who I mentioned, he's an Australian fellow.
I work with him still today, did the Smash TV conversion.
We would walk to Burger King.
For those that know me, I'm like pretty much all business all the time.
I'm always talking about the task at hand and the game that we're working on in off hours.
And so we're walking to lunch.
It's kind of annoying sometimes.
Yeah.
But I'm so we're walking and just you know talking about you know, what do we need this game isn't quite there and and
He came up. He said well, what if we went into an on-fire mode?
What if you got stronger somehow and so over the course of the Burger King lunch?
We plotted out the the whole three in a row heating up
being able to goaltend as one of the benefits.
And so in that one lunch, it all kind of coalesced together.
We came back, we told Sal about it,
and he was like, absolutely not.
That's the stupidest idea I've ever heard.
Dumbest thing I've ever heard in my entire life.
And he said, I'm not gonna give you any art for any fire.
All right, calm down, calm down.
So I was more in towards the purist side.
You know, I wanted to maintain, OK, this isn't a fantasy game.
This is still basketball.
I didn't mind exaggerated stuff.
But then we're like, it kind of kept on going one more step.
But what if we put, you know, what if we put bunny shoes on the guy
and it made him run faster?
That did look good though.
So I was just trying to maintain some sense of still television style.
Right.
So but because he refused to give me any art.
Correct.
I actually used the Smash TV explosion art.
And we put that in the game and started piecing it together, you know, behind the ball.
And then Sal, I don't know, within a day or hour said, OK, OK, OK, this might be good.
Yeah.
It took some desensitization of all that stuff for me to finally go.
Yeah, okay. I thought Burger King, the flame broiled burger was going to be the thing.
Right, that's what it was. I haven't heard that story before.
Yeah. CPU assistance, I'll touch on this down here. Not very subtle. This is the thing I've
taken a lot of heat for over the years.
This bottom table actually kind of tells it all.
The basic system was every player did have a base
percentage, whether it was for stealing, shooting two
pointers, three pointers, blocking a shot, because
sometimes your hand would touch it, but we would ignore
the collision or just kind of flash the ball.
And then this table below was basically a modifier to that
base value for whatever the topic was.
and you can see them in the middle, there's a zero.
Zero is when the score was tied.
If the score is tied, then do no modification to your base number.
But if you are losing, then it would slide to the left. I'm down by one point, two point.
So we went all the way down by ten points. You can see a twenty-five percent.
uh... you know additional add-on to the already twenty five percent that was
there for say in this example
a three-point shooting
and conversely if you were
uh... winning
up by one two three four those number of points
then it would modify and so you could get down to the point where hey I'm a
great three-point shooter
but I just nullified you completely because you're up by 15 points.
And so that basic system was running amok through the entire game.
We had probably, I'd say, 40 different locations.
where I would insert this kind of logic
for deflecting passes, rebounding,
you know, goal-tending, shooting, layups,
dunks, doinked dunks.
Everything had percentages that boiled back and forth
based on the score.
Yeah, and we played the game every day,
like multiple times a day.
This is when we could actually do that.
And it was, and every day,
whatever would frustrate us,
we would talk about and try to smooth it out
and clean it out and come up with rules for it.
And we'd even argue, you can't just do that,
you can't just do this, you can't just have a big head
on everybody, whatever it is, but we'd talk about that
and figure out, okay, what's the right balance?
Yeah, the best part of that story that just jogged my memory
is because I was doing all these number modifications
and we were a big gambling crowd inside work.
People would come over and wanna play a game for cash,
for vending machine products, whatever it was.
And I knew like, you know, what the numbers were.
It's like, why are you trying to play me?
It's like, so I was, I was, John Hay,
you know, probably still owes me money,
but you know, took hundreds of dollars
from this poor sound guy, right?
John Hay, I hope you're out there somewhere.
So that's CPU assistance, a little story.
Magic in the game.
A lot of little things were magical,
but a couple of things that are noteworthy
is of course the codes.
Codes were of course happening on some of the consumer titles.
It was a growing phenomenon.
But both Mortal Kombat and Jam really kind of took it over the top.
This is all small print, but an example of the codes,
we had a CPU assistance off,
so it would turn off all that CPU slider bullshit.
All that cheating, yeah.
Another thing here that's interesting,
I'm at Zynga, I've been at Zynga now for almost seven years,
and we kind of live and breathe data and numbers.
Making a great game in today's world takes not only good gut instincts, good sensibility,
but it also takes understanding your consumer and being able to respond to that.
And even back here 25 years ago, the panel on the right here is an example.
of some of the data we were tracking at each of these locations.
A coin-op game has battery-backed up CMOS RAM.
And so even when the machine is unplugged, turned off, it can still retain that data.
And we could go into these machines, and we had a secret code, a secret backdoor.
I can still do it on coin-op machines around the country.
and pull up the diagnostics, pull up the CMOS, you know, backed up, battery backed up RAM,
and look at some of the data. Things like how many times they go to the second period,
how many times to the third period, how many people are buying a full game up front,
what are the most popular teams, what's the score differential.
Which controller actually were you most likely to win from?
Which controller, right, to see if there was bias there.
Right.
But a lot of stats were kept and a lot of decisions were made on this
because of course we wanted to optimize and have players get all the way to the end.
It was 50 cents per period, so $2 for a full game.
If we had a player leaving after one period, you know, it was a lost opportunity.
And that is the genesis of that CPU assistance system
because we found that when players were ahead by 10 points
at the end of the first period, they quit.
If they were behind by 10 points, they quit.
But if it's a tight game, they're like,
okay, I see what you got.
You think you can take me?
I'll come back.
And so that's really the genesis of trying to keep it.
And you see it in driving games,
the rubber banding that happens.
But I could have been a little bit more subtle.
But no, also, that was also the genesis of the winning team.
If it's a four-player game, the winning team
stays on for free.
Because we wanted to encourage four-player games.
Yeah, in a four-player game, the winning team
gets to stay on the machine for free,
much like a fighting game in the day.
This is a horrific story, but it's a great story.
When you put out a coin-operated game,
we put it out at maybe the 80%, 90% completion point
into a few locations.
And then we go at, you know.
10pm we plug in the EPROMs and we stand back and we watch.
We turn it on and we watch.
Two local arcades.
Local arcades.
Local arcades in our area.
Yeah.
And so one of the first test locations we had the game set up and you'll probably recognize
these panels.
The bottom left there is a typical four player control panel where there's four sticks.
three buttons, and we kind of angle things a little bit to give you a little bit of elbow
room.
But on the image in the upper right, you can see the whole unit where there's a coin door
down below, typical arcade game.
When you plug your token or your quarter into those slots, it would go to a kitty.
The machine has X credits.
two, four, five, you'd put in your coins
and it would just be racking up credits.
Then when you hit your start button
on one of those four stations,
that is when the money comes from the kitty
and you are controlling that station.
Right.
And so we were watching and this kid came up and he looked at the game, he said,
oh, this is kind of interesting. He took his money out.
He started putting quarters into the token and he had a jacket on.
It was wintertime and he tapped the player two start button.
Boom, boom, boom, boom. And he bought into it.
So that's the controller that was unlocked for him.
Yeah, you can see the button here. And he took his coat off, set it down.
But then he lined back up on the machine. He lined up on station number three.
And the way, of course, we coded the game,
there were timeouts.
So when you're trying to pick your team,
his cursor was just sitting there, not picking anybody,
but it auto picks.
And then at jump ball time, the players jump up,
and there's AI, and the action begins.
His stick is doing nothing.
He's moving it around.
Right, he's moving his stick.
Yeah, he's moving it.
He's like, yeah.
And the player, whenever player two would get the ball,
he would just stand there, and he'd be dribbling the ball.
And then.
And the CPU would go and steal the ball from him.
Right.
A drone would steal it from him.
And so we were embarrassed.
We were like, oh man.
And, you know, one of our kind of rules of thumb was not interrupt players and don't
tell them who we are.
Right.
Like going back into the past.
Yeah.
But.
So I walked up and I said, hey, just so you know,
you're actually on player two.
See these?
It says insert coin there on station three.
You're on these controls.
And he's like, oh, OK, sorry, thanks.
And he shifted over.
And I went back to Sazam.
Man, that's embarrassing.
How are we going to fix this?
And we kept watching.
And about 45 seconds later, he's playing.
And he stops.
And he shifts back over to player three.
Because it was a better experience for him. He had more fun playing a dead controller than controlling his character.
And so
So we were like, oh my god, and okay
So we went back to work that night and we invented this concept of bozo boxes
Where and you've probably seen it when you hit the start button and you get into the game a box comes up on your
You know quadrant of the screen that's this one India
You are Scotty Pippin, you are red, you only control Scotty Pippin.
So we remedied it and we put the color on the shoes, you are red.
And we also changed the AI because the AI was juking and jiving.
The AI was too good, it was too aggressive, it was pretty much playing for you.
If you let it, it would pretty much play for you.
So we had to make changes there.
So I'm going to hurry through up here.
You may not have heard of this one.
There was actually a hidden tank game in NBA Jam.
Sean Liptack, that brainiac engineer I was telling you
about, was kind of geeking out on 3D, learning 3D.
So he put together on this 2D engine a 3D little engine.
This was a tank that was gliding by.
You could hit the shoot button, and a little square bullet
would go out.
Bom, bom, bom, bom.
And you could blow up these tanks that were gliding around,
and you could kind of rotate with your stick
around this little world.
And I kind of thought, well, what are we going to do with that?
You're wasting your time.
We really need to be fixing this other bug over here.
But you know I relented and he kept it in and he said yeah
I just want to be able to show people here in the studio
How to activate it so he put in some combination push the stick up. Oh, there's you know swirl and
We accidentally launched with that feature
In the in the attract mode yes
So in the attract without putting money in because the whole idea was if you put money in and wanted to get to it
We'd let you do it sure spend your quarter on looking at a tank game
Yeah, so we started getting letters from distributors that,
you know, hey, what's going on?
People can play this game for free.
But luckily, the game wasn't that engaging.
And it would time out after like 60 seconds.
So it didn't really cause a problem on revenue.
Secret players, big topic.
You can see here we actually snuck in some Mortal Kombat characters.
The NBA ended up having us pull those characters back out at some point.
No good!
But there's some good footage out there online where Raiden has some electricity
and there were some effects.
Ed approved it at the time, but he was wincing, I think, when he approved it.
And, you know, Bill Clinton, a lot of people ask me about Bill Clinton.
That was really an Acclaim thing.
Acclaim had the home rights to our games, and they called and asked if they could put
a couple more characters in, and so we said sure.
I put the secret agent man up there because it's the best headline ever for me being a big NBA fan.
This was from Slam Magazine and you know the story of Mark Tramiel, the NBA's greatest player.
Dan here is the byline on that. One of my favorite articles ever.
Ken Griffey Jr. down there sent us photos, wanted to be in the game. Gary Payton wasn't
in the original roster. These guys are sending their photos with headshots.
Well first he sent us, first he just sent us a picture of his head, like you know, out at the beach somewhere, whatever he was doing.
It's like, okay, if you want to be serious about this, we sent him our sheet, that little sheet that we showed you earlier of all the different angles.
And then he looked at that, he's like, yeah, okay, yeah.
Alright, yeah.
He sends us back exactly every picture, perfect.
And I'm like, okay.
This is the best slide in the game, in my opinion.
We were always trying to get reactions out of people
at Midway, whether it be the blood and guts of our games
or the over-the-top dunks, the screaming, the announcing.
Well, here's a letter from a distributor
after NBA Jam came out.
And you can see that.
Your programmers have created a monster.
I think that programmer creative freedom has gone too far.
We thought it was a compliment at first.
It's like, oh yeah, thank you.
And it's because, this is the letter on the left, he references these notes that people
were putting on the side of the cabinet that had the secret codes.
Kids were selling the codes for $5, $10.
and uh... this is before the internet and so it's tough to learn these things
and uh... so he thought that was you know bad and here the games making you
know a couple thousand dollars a week i wish i knew that i could've been selling
codes right
make more money for me
That's a feather in my cap right there.
Playboy bunnies.
When, of course, we got the NBA license,
we wanted to have cheerleaders in the game.
We actually called up Playboy and we asked for models.
And we had, they sent over a couple of models
and they were current in that era.
you know, in the magazines and we shot, you know, a few scenes for them.
It was tactful.
Tactful scenes.
This guy, hey, Hef, yeah, Mark Tremel, send over a few Playboy buddies.
Yeah, we're on California between Belmont and Addison.
What world do you live in?
Yeah, it just, it made sense.
Slick and hash downtown.
At the time, that was the 80s.
Where do you find models in Chicago?
Right, right.
But...
We made a mistake with all these codes.
So many kids, so many people were calling
and asking about these codes.
And we communicated that the cheerleaders were in the game.
And so everybody was trying to find the cheerleaders.
We didn't know how to say no to people.
So they would ask us, are there codes for the cheerleaders?
Can you unlock the cheerleaders?
We're like, yeah, yeah, you can, yeah.
Right, so kids are calling Playboy to find out,
they're getting a hold of these girls at home.
Now it didn't help that we mocked up a false image
of a cheerleader actually, I did that in Deluxe Paint,
I think, yeah, we'll do this someday.
Yeah, so somebody asked, and I said,
Sal, you gotta, let's put a chick on the screen, Duncan.
Great idea.
Yeah, and so.
Jeffrey, you're supposed to be in bed.
Who were you on the phone with?
I'm going to have some Playboy codes.
All right.
What?
Yep.
But, yeah, so there's a...
Hold on, I want to...
We eventually did put the cheerleaders in the game, yeah, because, you know, we could
update EPROMs, because we took some heat for it.
Same thing had happened with the pleasure domes on Smash TV.
That's a different story.
So almost wrapping up here, you know, what the fuck happened to Jam?
It's actually a sordid story.
We were working with a claim and a claim wanted the license for themselves, no doubt, and
the head of licensing from a claim had shifted to the NBA and was in charge of licensing
there at the NBA.
The nail in the coffin!
Yeah, exactly.
And one day, we got a phone call from the NBA.
And they said, hey, what are you going
to do with the NBA license?
Are you going to stay the same?
Or what's your plan?
And of course, our natural reaction was, oh, no.
We're going to innovate.
We're going to do great new things.
We're going to go bigger and better.
Because we wanted to keep making NBA games.
And they took that commentary as like, oh, they
don't want to do NBA Jam anymore.
and so they gave it to a claim so a claim
garnered the rights when our contract expired
uh... for the rights to NBA Jam and they just drove it into the ground
uh... here you can see an example of College Slam it's a screen down below
you know centers and forward guards they they made that they made
this NBA Jam Extreme, you know, taking dunking from half court, doing all sorts of stupid
things and really ruined that brand.
They still gave us the NBA license though.
So while they handed over the NBA Jam name license to Acclaim right after they said,
but you can still have...
They placated it.
Yeah, you can still have an NBA license.
Here you go.
We did NBA Hang Time next.
It was, that game actually holds up really well.
It's more fun than Jam.
It was better.
And then we eventually did NBA Showtime 3D
after we had done Blitz.
So that's a little story on that.
But the legacy lives on.
I was driving through LA just here a few weeks ago.
Boom, shock lock on a window.
I go in, here's a NBA Jam jacket.
They're selling, you can see the Team Select.
For each of the different teams that were in that original game, you can buy that.
And they even had a Mark Tramiel, Duncan Funk, you can see there, as a secret character t-shirt that you can buy.
And up in the upper right, you can see a Boom Shakalaka.
Some of the teams in the NBA have grabbed Tim Kitzerow.
and said, hey, can you come in and do something special
for our NBA Jam Day, putting the new current players
into that mindset.
And Tim, you are Mr. Boomshakalaka.
It's amazing.
He has really almost single-handedly kept
the energy over the last several years.
I've got to pay rent.
I've got to do something.
And yeah.
I went with the claim. I was a whore. I took the money. Then I came back for hang tights.
I hate those new gray guys. I'm glad you took the license.
I had to put this in here, rib Tim a little bit. I was going through all my paperwork.
I found the original contract with Tim there in 1989.
$600 we paid Tim for all of that commentary.
Yeah, it's been amazing.
So, and he's gotten a lot of great, you know, I think publicity and gags.
Here you can see he's with Fox Sports.
Tim and I did a NBA Jam Day at the Staples Center here just in January, where everybody
who went into the stadium received an NBA Jam t-shirt.
Limited edition, but they're worth something now because Blake Griffin left a week later.
Right, that's right.
Right.
Blake and DeAndre, the Boomshakalaka brothers.
Yeah, so you can see Tim and I, we pumped up the crowd and, you know, he's just been great at
kind of keeping the brand alive, so thank you for that. Started my career, thank you. Yeah, yeah.
And with that, we wanted to open it up if there were any questions,
you know, relevant to JAM or even beyond JAM.
We'd be more than happy to address those.
There are microphones here to the sides if anybody wants to
partake in that.
Hi.
You kind of glanced on it in the presentation, the
overtime is dollars.
Yes.
And the scale of if you're tied, then you don't mess with the stats.
I missed a dunk when the score was tied on the buzzer.
Well, remember I said there were about 40 spots.
I remember you mentioned that, John.
Yeah, so...
Snowgun!
Running!
Yeah, yeah.
If you're down by three, you know, with five seconds left, you know, you're going to make
the shot, you know, more often.
So there were other special rules, but if you did the CPU assistance off secret code,
it nullified even those.
Yeah, it was Shaquille O'Neal that was a little pissed off.
Yeah, John, I can imagine.
A free throw I would have gotten.
I'm sorry about that.
My actual question, was that a midway thing?
Was that something you were told to do?
No, that was just, you know, my instinct.
You were evil.
I think I can start to heal now. Thank you.
Nothing personal, just business.
Thank you guys so much for the panel, also for the game, the games, huge fan.
Is there a kill switch or some sort of weird way that the versions of the game with, for example, Michael Jordan,
would just somehow find their way to the rest of the world?
I say that mostly from a historical preservation perspective,
because there are a lot of people who really do want to have that sort of stuff for future generations.
Thanks.
Yeah, there are EPROMs out there of NBA GM with Michael Jordan.
He was in the original game.
I know Gary Payton has said recently, he's got it.
He's shown it.
I have EPROMs.
I don't have a cabinet anymore.
So I can't plug the EPROMs in to confirm they're still working.
But it's on my list of things to do
is to actually plug those in somewhere and test them out.
And then I will be more than happy to release them.
Yeah, I understand.
Yeah.
You and Arcade.
Ma'am.
Hey, so thank you very much for the talk.
Extremely entertaining.
I'm curious, since we're talking a bit about preservation here,
there are several revisions of NBA Jam in MAME,
including revisions of TE with the now-deleted Mortal Kombat
characters and all the other goofy things.
And you mentioned the tank game.
And I'm pretty sure the ROMs for that version of the game are still in there,
but is it possible to release the actual code to access that?
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, we can do that.
I'll give you my business card at the end of this.
Awesome.
I will reach out to Sean and get that to you.
Wonderful, thank you.
Yeah, yeah.
Sell them, make some money.
So I played the game a ton in college,
and it actually got me interested in the NBA.
And I was wondering if you ever heard from the NBA
if the game itself had any impact on their business.
It is.
It's a great thing.
It seems crazy to state that NBA Jam.
had an impact on the success of the NBA, but there's no question it did.
Not just from the anecdotal comments we've had, but from the NBA themselves
have said that a lot of players were not fans of the NBA,
but the millions played the game and then they became engaged.
I hear it all the time, so no question.
On that point too, Russell Wilson's a good example.
He's a huge fan of NBA Jam and he lived in North Carolina,
but he was a Sonics fan and he wanted to play as a Sonics guy
because he loved their uniform.
He said, I was a bigger basketball fan and knew
about players and teams he said I would never have known about.
And so that's really everybody's experience.
There was only a couple games on a week and it was the big market,
the Celtics-Lakers, so it was a way to introduce those smaller
market teams and players that you would have never heard of.
Yeah.
Hey guys, I've been working with Jarvis for the last 15 years at Raw and I've seen you guys around at stuff, but
Just in that line a lot of my friends like John Hay and Petro and stuff appeared in all your games and stuff
Are there any guys?
That have not been revealed that have like really secret like yeah joystick combinations and stuff in addition with the initials that yeah
Nobody knows I've gotten a lot over the years and and actually everything was exposed
So there's no codes unexposed that I'm aware of.
There's codes.
I would know.
Yeah.
Well, you know, one interesting thing real quick.
Have you ever heard the story
about the haunted NBA Jam machines?
Oh yeah.
Petrovich.
Yeah.
This is the truth.
Yeah, Drozd Petrovich died,
I think it was in a car accident or something.
Tragic.
Yeah, he was a starter, he was in the game,
he was on the nets.
And after he died, we were walking through the factory.
We were just even sitting in our offices.
Yeah.
The coin-op game started saying, Petrovich, Tim's call.
Oh, that was good.
And every once in a while, it would just
say, Petrovich, in the attract mode, with the audio off.
It was crazy.
A weird bug, right?
Hi, again, thank you so much for just sharing all these experiences.
When you introduced the injured stat, how much did that really affect players during games?
The injured stat had no bearing.
Okay.
And I bring this up because for many of us who did play at home,
and as we all got to be very good...
instead of two on two, we played one on one on one on one.
And to try to see whoever had the highest injured stat
then essentially pays everybody else.
Right.
Yeah.
Yeah, we would do similar to use that to highlight
who was weak at avoidance.
An injury stat is when you would get knocked down.
And so we would kind of laugh like, oh, you can't even
swirl around these guys effectively.
Right.
Cool.
Thank you.
Hi, thanks.
Just a quick question, what did happen with Michael Jordan?
Was it like licensing?
Well, they offered him $600 and he turned it down.
Well, Michael Jordan, he pulled out of all NBA licensing, because all the players just
split the licensing money equally.
And so he thought, hey, I can cut my own deals and get a better thing.
And of course, he did an EA game.
Probably didn't really pan out that well for him, although maybe Nike, you know, he was
able to do something instead of Converse or something.
But he eventually did get hit one of those NBA jams with the Jordan E-Proms
because Gary Payton and he were really tight.
And Gary Payton is really the one who reached out to get himself in the game,
Griffey in the game, and Jordan in the game so that Jordan would have a copy.
Shaq actually bought two copies when it came out.
And this is a funny story.
He took one of the coin-ops, had it at home,
and the other one went on their team airplane.
As they traveled around the country on road trips,
they would take it out of the plane
and they would wheel it into his suite,
and the players would gamble.
He's told me this.
They would gamble all night.
They wouldn't go out to clubs and other stuff.
They stayed in there gambling on NBA Jam.
So in a way we saved the world a little bit.
Right, right.
Yeah.
Well, thank you so much.
One more?
I just wanted to say thank you guys
for letting me be my brother virtually,
as well as in real life in basketball.
So that was something I really enjoyed doing.
Just not so much on the shoulda, coulda, woulda.
Was there anything you guys could have done to keep?
the game at Midway or was there things that you were like,
man, I wish I really would have done that,
just for some other people that might be in the same situation?
Yeah, it was really just the relationship.
If we'd had maybe a better relationship with
the licensing management people there at the NBA,
we could have made the opportunity extend,
and we would not have driven it into the ground as they did.
So yeah, that's great.
So this is a great birthday present for me, a great opportunity.
Thanks everybody.