Thanks a lot for the creators of Killer Queen Arcade,
my friends Nick Mikros and Josh DeBonis.
And also special thank yous to fellow KQ players and fans,
Dylan Higgins, Charles Pratt, Josh Eklo, Tiana Tan,
Joe Pollard, Christopher Pressinger,
Eric Clarkson for helping me put together this talk.
And of course, thank you to the rest of the KQ community.
You guys are amazing.
So, who am I?
I am currently the producer at Funktronic Labs
in LA Game Studio.
But more importantly, for this talk,
I was previously the COO of Bumble Bear Games
from 2015 to 2017.
And today, I will be talking about Killer Queen Arcade
and how we built a competitive community that spans the entire country as an indie
and what you can learn from what we've done.
This isn't a post-mortem on the game or the community,
but rather a breakdown of a lot of the things that Bumble Bear has done
that I think that can be helpful for other competitive gaming communities to learn from, indie or not.
So, Killer Queen Arcade, for those of you who don't know,
is a five-on-five arcade game created by Josh DeBonis
and Nick Micros in 2013.
Two teams of five players compete against each other
to be the first to accomplish one of three
different victory conditions on a map.
An economic victory by collecting 12 berries
scattered around a map and bringing them back
to your hive one at a time.
A military victory by killing the opposing queen
three times in a single game.
or a snail victory by riding a snail
into your own team's goal.
There's a video here that I've linked
that goes into a lot more detail about the game itself.
There's a lot of other mechanics to the game.
For example, there is a queen character
who is different than the other four players.
Workers can become warriors.
There's a speed gate.
So I highly encourage you to watch that video later
if you get the chance.
In roughly half a decade, Killer Queen Arcade has gone from a niche New York arcade game
for hipsters to a niche national arcade game for hipsters.
Today there are over 30 arcade machines available for public play in over 20 states, not counting
the many privately owned cabs that are owned by individuals and corporations.
Every year since 2016, Bumble Bear Games
has organized the National Killer Queen Arcade World
Championship, which is hosted in a different city every year,
bringing in players from around the country
to play to see who is the best team.
In 2016 in Austin, Texas, we had 150 players
come to form over 30 teams.
And last year in 2018, we had Bumble Bash 3,
which was in Portland, Oregon, with 300 players and 60 teams.
And recently, it was just announced that for 2019,
we are going to be in Chattanooga, Tennessee.
So how does Killer Queen build communities?
And more importantly, how can you apply this
to your own game and to your own communities?
So game design builds community.
Killer Queen is designed to bring people together
at its core.
To even play the game,
you need to physically be near a machine.
You have to play together to win as a team.
You can't win by yourself.
Well, you can, but it's pretty hard to.
Local multiplayer means that you have to stand next to your teammates,
and you also have to be in the same space with your competitors too.
And since you're all in the same place together doing the same thing,
you are by definition part of the same community.
The game itself takes all five minutes to learn the basic rules,
but it requires a lot of practice to work together effectively
in order to play competitively.
We also have messaging in the game
that tells players to meet thy neighbors.
This message occurs at the end of the match
and encourages players to meet with each other,
give high fives, congratulatory handshakes,
talk about that match they just played,
or even switch players to start a new game.
It's also possible to add custom messages on the screen
to talk about things like upcoming tournaments,
free plays, meetups, and so forth.
So what can you learn from this?
Think about how the design of your game
or the nature of your game itself
facilitates building a community or building teams.
Have a built-in messaging system
can give subtle messages to players
on how to behave while playing your game,
as well as informing players about the larger community.
If you're looking for other models
of local competitive communities,
look at collectible car games and fighting game communities
or rec leagues like dodgeball and softball.
See how they build their communities
and see what they do to keep players engaged
outside of playing the game.
Streaming and casting help build community.
A lot of the KQ events will stream their games online
to let people watch from wherever they are.
The KQ Arcade cabinet has a separate HDMI port
built into the back of the cab.
You can use either plug into a streaming PC
to put the video online through Twitch
or your streaming platform of your choice,
or you can put it to a TV or a projector.
You can also split that HDMI signal
to put out to multiple streams,
multiple projectors, and so forth.
For bigger tournaments such as Bumble Bash,
we'll also use apps like Restream.io,
which will allow us to show a single stream
on multiple platforms,
or splice multiple machine feeds into one stream.
As you can see in the image over here,
the community has created custom overlays
that show the feed of the game,
a player cam, commentator cam,
as well as showing numbers of sets being won.
I think this one has kill and death ratios
at the bottom also.
This is another example of the one that we had at Bumble Bash in Portland.
In addition, we also have an API that sends out event data,
such as kills, deaths, and berries collected.
Some scenes have taken that data
and created their own stat displays.
So this is an example of one website that has stat tracking
as well as logging event data
based on where you are on the map.
This uses a Raspberry Pi that gets plugged into the cab
and then sends this data to a website.
This website is actually live right now
if you go to bmorekq.com.
Shout outs to the Baltimore KQ community
for putting this together.
So yeah, build in streaming tools
and make it easy to do things like organize tournaments
and show information about your game
and broadcast all of it so that it could be seen
in the best light online and help raise your game's profile.
Spectators can digest what's going on
with the help of color commentators and stat displays
so they can get into your game
without having to actually play the game or even be there.
If you can't provide the tools yourself,
see if you can open up your data for the community
to help you with displaying it.
provide instructions for folks on how to use all of this stuff.
A lot of your fans may not be very technical,
but if you have very clear instructions,
they may be able to figure it out themselves.
Down here is a link to a GitHub repo.
If you want to see an example of the API being used,
this is an app called KQStats.
This was done by Kevin Snyder, as well as a few other folks,
so thank you for doing that.
Events help build communities.
Bumble Bear hosts its national tournament with a trophy
and a custom marquee that it gives
to the winner of a tournament.
Local scenes also host their regular events also.
Because these arcade machines are already in public venues,
we try to partner with them to host events.
So you'll see KQ tournaments and events in bars,
bowling alleys, family fun centers, arcades, barcades,
and even in board game shops.
For tournament play, two commonly used apps
that are used to help organize and manage the tournaments
are SmashGG and Challenge.
We can use these apps to help players register ahead of time,
set up pools and brackets, and post results in real time
online for players to look at.
In addition to doing competitive events,
another kind of event to get players
interested in playing the game without explicitly focusing
on competitive play.
is to do theme competitions or fundraisers
for organizations such as Extra Life.
Despite the fact that KQ is a competitive team game,
scenes have created less competitive events,
such as scrambles, where teams are drawn from a hat,
social nights, draft nights,
where queens take turns picking players,
and we have our own version of Battle Royale called Bub G.
Silly things like theme or costume events
like a winter formal create a much more informal environment
and lets people focus on having fun
with and around the game.
So yeah, events build a community, not the other way around.
Organize events as soon as you can.
The first Killer Queen National Tournament was in 2016,
but there were tournaments and meetups held
by the community long before that.
If you feel that your community wants one,
then create one, or if you can't for whatever reason,
help them out in any way you can.
The event itself doesn't have to be a tournament.
It can be a playtest, a mixer, a meetup.
Just do it often and do it frequently.
Don't worry about failure or an event being bad.
You're not trying to plan a fire festival.
You're just giving players a chance.
You're just giving players a chance to play together
in a somewhat organized fashion.
If you do make mistakes, just learn from them
and do better next time.
I'll talk a little bit more about online events
in another slide.
But creating online tournaments
and having everyone meet in a Discord
is a great way to do an event without the need
of having everyone to be in the same place.
One interesting point about planning events is the importance of consistency.
In New York, there is an event every single Friday at NYU in Brooklyn called 5v5 Fridays.
It's hosted by one of the professors, Charles J. Pratt.
He noticed that by being consistently every single Friday,
players can always just show up whenever they have a free Friday
as opposed to having to plan for the event that only happens once a month,
which lessens the hassle of having to come to play the game.
You'll have regulars that come there every week,
but you'll also have access to people
who may show up every two weeks,
or maybe only just once a month.
If you have an individual player-based game,
but you wanna have folks competing in events like teams,
there are ways to organize that too.
At Bumble Bash 3, we created an Olympic-style
scoring system called the Dang System
that gave points per player.
At the end of the tournament, we grouped players by region
and added the points together of the top 17 players
of each region to determine the winner.
The winning city got an arcade machine.
Engaging with the community builds community.
Bumble Bear travels across the country to KQ events
to talk to players and fans and play with them.
Bumble Bear will also bring with them new maps,
new game modes to test out,
and answer questions about Killer Queen.
Every year there's also a state of Killer Queen announcement
where they talk about the upcoming roadmap and plans.
And when I talk about engaging with the community,
Nick and Josh really, really engage with the community.
So this was recently at the South Florida,
there was a Kale Green event there.
That's Nick in the, I think, hot tub being fed a steak.
So yeah.
Travel to events to promote the game.
Make yourselves accessible to the community
for direct conversations and feedback,
and engage only as much as you're comfortable.
Attending community events legitimizes those events
in the player's eyes and encourages people to attend
and builds goodwill.
You should also do regular testing with your community.
Try out ideas.
Keep good ones, throw away the rest.
And even with your bad ideas,
let your fans have fun with it,
and you never know what would happen.
We tried game modes all the time.
For a long time, there was a mode in Killer Queen
that had scorpions, which having scorpions
and bears and bees, I thought was a terrible idea,
but people liked it and whatever.
Keep the game fresh, it keeps the game fresh
and people keep talking about it.
Turn these tests into an event.
If you can't travel to other scenes, play online.
Host and play with your fans and players once a week.
do an AMA, blog, you can even do things like having regular tests where the highest scoring
player that week or month gets to challenge the designers and developers.
And whatever you do, put it online and stream it.
If there's one thing that you should take away from this talk,
it should be that aside from designing a very compelling and engaging game,
Bumble Bear's accessibility and engagement with its very, very active community
is a key factor to the success of Killer Queen.
Being part of your community gives you the opportunity to get insight
about what the community wants to see.
as well as instills confidence that the developers
will be able to shape the game into something
that people will want to play.
And even if Bumble Bear can't do it themselves,
sometimes creating the opportunity for the community
to help fill in those gaps can be still just as effective.
Having said that, I don't want you to walk away
from this talk thinking that Bumble Bear knocks it out
of the park every single time.
At one point, we came up with the idea
of establishing a membership-based
National Killer Queen League.
You pay a fee, you get some cool stuff out of it,
and you help fund an organization dedicated
to managing a competitive National Killer Queen League.
I'm not gonna get into the details of what it all entailed,
but long story short, it was not well received
by the community for various reasons.
This is one of the posts that was on the Facebook page
in response.
This was a situation where we got insight
that the community wanted something,
but we didn't create what they actually needed,
and we executed very poorly.
And as a result, the community told us how they felt.
So we realized the idea wasn't quite the right fit,
so we wound up shelving it.
So merch and fan art built communities.
Merch is merch.
People like to buy merch to support the things they love.
Originally, Bumble Beer had an Amazon store,
but we decided to create our own storefront.
We had issues with people making cheaper,
counterfeit versions of our stuff
and selling it on our product pages.
So it was just easier for us to take our merchandise
completely off Amazon and just do our own thing.
If you don't want to deal with your own inventory and stuff, and I don't blame you, there are
companies that you can partner with, such as Fangamer or Sanshi.
In addition to Bumble Bear created merch,
Bumble Bear encourages the community
to create their own merch,
and express themselves in the universe of Killer Queen.
It gives the fans a chance to contribute
to something that they already love.
And our fans make some really amazing things.
From picture frames, t-shirts, posters.
I'm actually wearing a fan created shirt.
This was done by one of the Chicago players,
Michael Sparza.
And yeah, we have one rule for fan merch.
Don't directly rip off the art from the game.
It should be transformative.
Reinterpret the art in your own way.
So all these three things were created by our fans
for either events or for teams.
The calendar in the middle was actually
a fundraising project for Girls Who Code.
Bumbleblair also makes our source assets available
for fans to use, which I didn't think was a crazy thing
until I told people and they thought I was crazy.
If you dig around the press kit,
you will find player sprites,
as well as some quality versions of our logo.
And a lot of people will use these assets
for the basis of fan art,
or for graphics to use for their posters, t-shirts,
and all sorts of other things.
The image on the right over here
is an example of someone using one of our sprites
and customizing it for their posters.
All these other images here are fan art
and event posters that the community has made.
And you'll be very surprised that, you know,
your fans may be able to make art better than you.
In addition to encouraging folks to create and sell
fan-created merchandise, Bumble Bear takes it a step further
and will actually sell a community,
or approved community-created merch on its own online store
for a cut of the sale plus cost of shipping and handling.
Those posters over here are created by,
also I think a Chicago player, John Doon.
and they're gorgeous and they're available
on the store right now if you wanna buy them.
We'll also do the same thing at events like Bumble Bash
where we have a merch table where fans can sell
their stuff there for a percentage cut.
By keeping things to a merch table at events,
you can see all the kinds of cool things
that people are making and it keeps all the merch
selling in one area at a venue.
The only other note I have is that you should be careful about tax laws,
as you're conducting business in some states, and they may consider that vending,
and therefore you have to deduct or collect sales tax for it.
I'm not a lawyer, I'm not an accountant, I'm just letting you know ahead of time.
So yeah, there are caveats to making your own merch,
but like I said, there are companies that can do it for you.
Either way, it's definitely something you should do.
Encourage people to create fan art,
do competitions, do contests with it.
And if you're as crazy as Bumble Bear,
sell merch actually created by your friends,
or by your fans.
And if you're worried about things like rip-offs and stuff like that,
in my time at Bumble Bear, I found it very effective to tell people
to have to make their art more transformative.
It challenges them to make something better without saying no,
and in the end, they're likely going to make something cool
and something that you may not have thought about yourself.
Sponsors can help build communities.
In order for competitive communities to thrive,
they need competitive events.
A healthy community has frequent events
and you're gonna need to pay for all of that
and sometimes tournament entrance fees alone
may not be enough.
Bumble Bear encourages people to host their own tournaments
and to find their own sponsorships for these events.
In general, Bumble Bear's opening to letting folks
arrange their own events as long as it doesn't appear
to look like it is an event endorsed or sponsored directly
by Bumble Bear or Killer Queen Arcade.
Killer Queen Arcade has also gotten to the point now
we have been lucky enough to have the attention
of some of the largest sponsors
and marketing brands like Red Bull.
It is through a lot of hard work from people
within our community and within Bumble Bear
that has raised KQ's profile to this level.
Because the game's located in a lot of bars, beer sponsors are a great sponsorship source for us.
These are two events, one in Portland and one in Minneapolis,
both sponsored by beer companies.
I think Surly Brewing sponsors Minneapolis,
and Not Your Father's Root Beer sponsors Killer Queen Events in Portland.
Before you actually pitch a sponsor for an event,
here's some things you probably want to think about.
How much control do you want to have
over the portrayal of your game?
How do you think the community will react?
Is that something that's actually important for you?
Are you now sanctioning official events yourself?
And can there only be one event?
What does that mean for non-sanctioned events?
Are you, the game's creators,
the only ones able to seek out sponsorships now?
And what does an agreement look like
between you and the sponsor?
I added this image here just because there's a lot of text,
but just as an example, this is Richie's Plank Experience,
which is a VR thing, and one of the cool things
that they do is that they also will do sponsored versions
of their VR experience.
So I think this one's Fear Factor,
the Richie's Plank Experience,
and I thought that was really cool.
So once you've thought about that,
you'll want to look for sponsors
that are most appropriate to your community.
In addition to beer companies,
there's a wide variety of gaming adjacent companies
that are willing to sponsor game events.
Food and beverage, which can include anything
from snack distributors to local restaurants.
Venues can help you also get a discount on rental costs.
There are also a lot of people companies.
There are companies that target people
in the tech or tech-related field
or always looking for marketing opportunities.
Gaming hardware brands.
and lifestyle brands that want to sell clothes and consumables and apparel to your players.
If you partner with a bar or venue, oftentimes they'll have their own food and beverage marketing
reps who are usually pretty interested and open to helping sponsor different events for
that venue.
In terms of the kinds of sponsorship opportunities available, there are a lot of options.
Asking for money is one of the more difficult ones, but asking for merchandise and swag
for use at the event or for giving away as prizes are much easier.
I'm not going to read through this list.
It's pretty self-explanatory.
You're at GDC.
Just take a look around at the many different sponsors we have here at GDC and see how they
make their presence known.
From the lanyards they're wearing to the free t-shirts to the hats that you get, or you'll
probably get sometime this week.
When pitching a sponsor, be sure to know the following.
Your audience, attendee, demographic, and size.
Where will this be broadcasted or streamed,
and what's the size and demographics of that?
What else are people gonna be doing at this event?
What's your social media reach?
How will you be promoting your sponsors at the event?
Any solid data that you might have for previous events
and similar events or even surveys
that you do with your community.
And most importantly, what are sponsors
going to be able to get out of your event?
You wanna let them know that they're gonna gain
something positive out of the entire experience.
That players and spectators alike
will be able to take something positive
from having that brand associated with your game.
I say sponsorships can help people or can help communities
because sometimes it can backfire.
Maybe your brand isn't the kind of brand
that likes to look like it's sold out.
Maybe it does.
And for those of you who don't know,
this is from when Street Fighter V
tried to do sponsored content skins
and this didn't go over very well.
Social media builds communities.
These are just some of the many Facebook pages
our community has created for Killer Queen,
and they're all divided by region.
Facebook pages and groups allow fans
to organize their lives outside of the game,
and they function as a way for players
to organize themselves in real life.
It also helps the community support each other and stay connected when they're not playing
your game.
BumbleBear itself did not create any of these Facebook pages, but we are a part of most
of these.
It's another great way for us to engage our community, and it's always good to know what
your community is talking about, even if it's memes most of the time.
So yeah, build your social media,
very important to build communities.
I'm not gonna talk about this too much.
There was a really cool talk yesterday about Discord.
It's 2019, if you don't have a Slack, a Discord,
or a Facebook page, and you're making a game,
you're behind.
Champions help build communities.
Find your super fans as you build your communities
and enable them to be your champions.
For Killer Queen, these were the ones
who helped organize the first local tournaments
in different cities.
They were the ones that created all the cool merch
that streamed our game, that did commentary,
that got new players into the game.
We even created an award for this,
the Charles J. Pratt Community Service Award,
which was won in the first year by Charles J. Pratt.
But reward your champions.
If you have an upcoming game, give them keys to give away.
Give them assets if they ask for them to make art and merch.
Ask for their feedback.
Ask for them to help organize an event,
and ask them to help you promote your game to new fans.
Another thing that we did at Bumble Bear was that we had a small committee of fans that
we talked to about upcoming events and ideas.
If you have an idea you want to do with the community, it's always good to have a small
group of people to test it with first before you go forward with something.
They can help embrace an idea or an event, they can help hype up the community, and in
general they just help make good ideas great.
Partnering with a streamer or YouTube was something
that we always wanted to do,
but given the nature of our game,
this makes it kind of difficult.
Luckily, most of you aren't making arcade games,
so that shouldn't be an excuse for you guys.
Or for you all.
Other communities can help build your community.
Killer Queen attracts all sorts of players
looking for competition.
We have folks from the fighting game community,
speed runners, recreational league, dodge ball,
softball players, who are just attractive to competition
and the competitiveness of KQ.
It would be smart to engage or partner with other communities
to cross-promote events and games.
At Bumble Bash, we will actually host games
made by other indies.
So the image here is a game called Death Ball Arcade
by Tony Halber, who's the one playing it.
It's worth looking into other competitive gaming communities and think about the opportunity
for collaboration on events or promotion.
In this situation, I think a rising tide lifts all boats.
Formalized communication builds communities.
Clear communication builds trust,
prevents confusion and uncertainty about your game.
State of the game announcements,
public roadmaps, and blogs are all very important.
This is the Trello board for Killer Queen Black,
which is the upcoming Killer Queen title
coming out for the PC and Switch.
please buy it when it comes out.
They did a pretty good job of showing their work
with a public Trello, showing release notes,
upcoming development, outstanding work, and so forth.
With all forms of formal communication,
keep it simple, straightforward, and consistent,
so it's not a pain in the butt to maintain.
And if things change, be sure to update it.
Also, try not to update or make any major changes
on your game before a tournament,
otherwise you're gonna piss off your fans.
I thought this was an original idea,
and then somebody showed me this on Saturday,
that Fortnite actually has this too,
and then obviously Epic has their own Trello board,
so it's a popular idea, and it's easy, you can do it.
So final thoughts.
I can't stress the importance of working with your community
and enabling them to do cool stuff with your game
when you're an indie.
They can surprise you with what they're capable of doing,
and they are literally the lifeblood of your game.
Oh good, I blacked everything out.
Here's an example of where things could have gone south.
We had a cab owner who just wasn't feeling the game,
and so they were talking about getting rid of the cabinet.
But through the efforts of our community,
hosting events like fundraisers, meetups,
we organized our events ourselves there,
or just showing up and giving the game some love,
that cab has never left the venue
and still continues to generate money
for the owner to this day by way of quarters
and food and beverage when the players come to play.
So yeah, if you're indie, be nimble with your community
and be personable and authentic to your game.
To an extent, you can respond to and work
with your communities in ways that the bigger studios can't.
The community can be very forgiving of your mistakes
if you show the effort of trying to make the game better.
Be clever about how you do things
and don't take no for an answer.
Move fast because the big boys can't
and don't let anything hold you back.
If you're a larger company and studio and watching this talk, engage with your community
and empower them and celebrate them.
Learn about what they really want and really need because you may have more noise to deal
with with a larger community than us as an indie.
Experiment with your game and listen to the community and build goodwill.
If you're scared of backlash and negative feedback from things going wrong, run ideas
by a subset of your community and see how they react.
Do the fun things that indies like us could only wish we could do with money and open
up a little bit.
If you wanna know more about Killer Queen,
we have our Twitter link, the Facebook link,
and our website here.
This Saturday, we are doing Killer Queen San Francisco
over at Brewcate SF.
So please check it out there.
Otherwise, look up your local scenes
for Killer Queen Machine and come join the community
and play this dumb bee game with us.
Oh, in exchange for me using Nick in the pool,
I had to put up a picture of Nolan Bushnell for some reason.
But yeah, I guess we have time for maybe two questions.
So if anyone has any questions, please step up.
If not, thank you very much.