I know it's one of the last sessions of the day, so thank you for turning up.
You've come to a talk about Rubik's Cubes at a game developers conference, so congratulations.
In 1982, there's an estimated 100 million to 1 billion Rubik's Cubes in the world, including
counterfeits.
And it's easy to see why. They're very interesting to look at.
They are fun to hold and to twist. It's immediately obvious what the goal is.
It's immediately obvious what the tools at your disposal to reach that goal.
But it's also incredibly, incredibly hard to solve.
And by the end of 1982, everyone who wanted to buy a Rubik's Cube had bought one,
and they had all figured out that they couldn't solve it.
So they went on people's bookshelves,
and the sales dried up almost overnight.
But today, people meet in hotel convention centers
all over the world to see who can solve it fastest.
It's a real hobby with a global governing body
and a vibrant and growing player base.
So how did it go from a dead toy to what it is today?
I'm Andrew.
I've been a developer since 2004, but for the purposes of this talk, my credentials
are that I can solve a Rubik's Cube in 26.4 seconds.
We're going to talk a little bit today about what speedcubing is.
And then most of the talk we're going to spend on how it became a thing all on its own without
any kind of corporate body pushing it as a thing.
So first of all, if we want to talk about speedcubing, we need to talk a little bit
about how to solve a Rubik's Cube.
I don't want to...
I don't want to spoil the joy for any of you if you choose to leave here and try and discover
how to solve the Rubik's Cube for yourself.
But I do want to cover some of the basic fundamentals for how we're going to solve it.
Let's get my little laser pointer.
So the first thing most people do when they try and solve the Rubik's Cube and what everyone
did in the 80s was get one face, all the stickers matching on one face, think they're making
one sixth of the progress towards solving the cube and then discover that doing the
next face is actually incredibly hard.
and the problem that they hit upon was that they were solving the stickers rather than
solving the pieces.
So there are three different types of pieces on a Rubik's Cube, they're called cubelets.
There are three different types of cubelets.
There are these centerpieces here, and you can see there's three we can see, the yellow,
the orange, and the green.
There are the edge pieces that have two stickers, like these ones, and there are corner pieces
that have three stickers.
Now, when we manipulate the cube, all we can do is turn the face of the cube.
And when we turn the face of a cube, one of the faces, we see the centerpiece stays still.
All these pieces around here stay still.
and then these pieces around the edge move.
And the same on this face.
Like if we turn this face, this orange centerpiece will stay absolutely still,
these pieces will move,
and then these pieces all around the edge will stay still.
So there's not actually any way, any manipulation you can make to this cube
that will move those centerpieces.
They're fixed relative to each other.
Green will always be next to orange, will always be next to yellow.
And so the only thing we actually have to do to solve the cube
is get these edge pieces and these corner pieces in the right place.
In each one, they already have an identified place they should be.
So if we look at this edge piece here, it has two stickers.
It has green and it has yellow.
So it must go between the green center and the yellow center.
So it must go exactly here.
There's only one piece that can go in that slot,
and there's only one slot for that piece to go into.
Same with the corner piece.
It has three stickers, we can see it's got green and orange,
so it must go between these green and orange centers.
We see it's also got white, but this is the yellow face,
so we can intuit that white must be on the bottom here,
and this corner piece must go here into this slot.
And then we're simply going to solve it layer by layer.
So when you solve the first layer of a cube, it looks a bit like this.
You can see those, because we've solved pieces instead of stickers,
you can see those sides of the cube.
at that satisfying T shape to them.
And most people, given enough time, can intuit how to do this step on their own.
The second stage is to move the middle pieces down into the...
the edge pieces down into the middle layer.
And you can see there's only four of them that have to go in to complete that.
Two-thirds of the cube are completed.
And most people, given more time, can complete this second step.
The last step is to correctly position and orientate all of the pieces in the last layer,
which is incredibly difficult and has loads of edge cases and you have no scratch space
to do it into.
So if I were you and you were interested in getting a Rubik's Cube, I would try and intuit
these first two steps and especially if you're interested more in speedcubing than anything
else than the puzzle nature of it, then I would just skip the third step and look up
a solution.
But speedcubers aren't intuiting how to solve the cube every time they do a speed solve.
I'm not doing that.
I couldn't do that in 30 seconds.
We're using several tools in order to get us to that step.
And one of the first tools we're using is algorithms.
So we're breaking the solve down into many individual steps.
You've already seen some of them, first layer, middle layer, last layer.
But then you can break it down even further.
And so you recognize the current step you're on,
you know the step you want to be on next,
and then you will have memorized the exact moves,
the exact turns that get you from this sub-step
to the next sub-step, and that's called an algorithm.
And it uses this notation you can see
along the bottom of the slide here,
which is just telling you exactly which face to turn
and how far to turn it.
And this algorithm we're looking at is taking that middle piece down and to the right.
So when you have a piece on the top layer that you know needs to go down and to the
right, you just execute these steps and it will be down and to the right and the rest
of the cube won't be disturbed.
So algorithms.
You have to learn.
A beginner probably needs to know half a dozen algorithms in order to finish the cube.
The best speedcubers in the world will probably know hundreds of algorithms if not thousands
of algorithms.
And it's just about practice, repetition, like ingraining it in your memory.
And then the next step is executing those algorithms really fast.
This is called turns per second, or TPS.
The best cubers will have upwards of ten, their solves will have upwards of ten turns
in every second.
And that's a matter of manipulating the cube in such a way that you don't have to re-grip
and let go and move your hands, because that's the slowest thing you can do when you're
manipulating the cube.
is to turn it around in your hands.
Try and get your hand on the top to turn the top.
So, speedcubers use their fingers and their thumbs
and every digit to manipulate the cube on all the faces
without having to re-grip.
And again, practice, muscle memory, repetition.
And we're aiming to reach this point of ultimacity
or over-learning where you know
what you're executing so well
that it can kind of just do it by itself.
Just the way when you're driving a car,
you can...
You can turn left without having to think about slowing down and using the gears and indicating and moving the steering wheel.
You just turn left and carry on with your conversation while you're doing it.
So we're over learning and getting this level of automicity so we can do this next step, which is look ahead.
In Lookahead, the idea is that as you're executing an algorithm and moving to the next step,
you can already be looking at the cube and trying to figure out what the step after that
is going to be and what the next algorithm is going to be.
So you can queue it up and as soon as you finish executing one algorithm, you go straight
into the next algorithm.
In this GIF, there is a very slight pause where this speed solver, who does like a 10-second
solve, this speed solver has a break-stand look-ahead just there.
They didn't do enough look-ahead, they have to stop, waste time, and look at the cube
without doing like this.
The cube is completely static for like a second while they figure out what the next state
or what the next algorithm is going to be.
With good look-ahead, that would never happen.
Every solve would just be a constant flow of moves.
So that's how you solve really fast.
So how do you solve really fast in competition?
This is Felix Zemdeg, who's probably,
well, definitely the greatest living speedcuber
we have at the moment.
This is him setting the world record in 2018.
This isn't actually the current world record.
The current world record is held by Yuxin Du of China,
who set a record of 3.47 seconds.
He can solve the Rubik's Cube faster
than I can say 3.47 seconds.
But unfortunately there's no good video of that one, so you've got this 4.22 record instead.
So every competition is run exactly the same.
The first step is your Rubik's Cube is taken away, a random scramble is applied to it,
it's brought back to you hidden under a cup, you can see the cup to the right of this GIF
when it starts.
It's brought to you under a cup, and then the cup is lifted.
and you're given 15 seconds to pick up and look at the cube.
And the best speakers now will be plotting their first 10 or 15 moves out
as they're looking at this step.
Then you put the cube down again.
You put your hands on the timing buttons,
which Felix is going to do now.
Take your hands off.
Now the timer has started.
Solve it as fast as you can.
Get it back on the mat.
Put your hands back on the buttons.
The second you get your hand back on the button, the timer stops.
And that is your time.
You do that five times with five different scrambles.
And when you've finished, we take your best scramble
and your worst scramble, we throw away those times
and you take the mean average of the remaining time
and that is your average of five.
And the competition is simply
who has the best average of five.
So you put that all together
and you have what I think is a sport.
Bennett Foddy in his GDC talk in 2014 talked about the three characteristics that he thinks makes a game a sport and he talked about
Integrity which is there's no easy way to cheat and there's no easy way to buy your way to the top
and if you don't know the scramble, there's no easy way to glitch your cube into the correct state fast and
You can buy the best speedcube in the world
It will cost you the price of a triple-a console game and it won't take you from a one minute solve to a ten seconds
So it has integrity
The second is stakes, and that doesn't necessarily mean big winner's checks, although that helps,
but it means is there an easy way where I can compare my performance to someone else's
performance and know who won.
Because we have the average of five score and your personal best, that's very, very
easy.
So we have stakes.
And the last one is performance, and that's the idea of I know how to do, I know what
I need to do, but not how to do it.
And also this aspect of...
how someone's 30 seconds solve will look very different to another person's 30 seconds solve.
There's this aspect of performance coming through and personality coming through in the way they solve the cube.
So you put all those things together and it is,
by FODE standards, a sport. And it's a growing sport.
This is stats from the World Governing Body of Speedcubing showing the number of competitions and
the number of countries going up year on year. This isn't just
an American thing or Chinese thing. This is worldwide.
And also the number of players going up.
Last year, in-person competitions, over 40,000 players.
And you can imagine there's probably people
who count themselves as part of the hobby,
as part of the pastime,
who don't go to in-person competitions.
That includes me.
So maybe 10 times that number, maybe 15 times that number.
We can say maybe top estimate,
maybe there's a million speedcubers in the world,
which is pretty impressive.
So that's the state of speedcubing today.
So how did we get there?
And I'm gonna break this down in terms of different puzzles
that speedcubing had to solve as a community.
And the first one is organization.
So there were people all around the world
through the 80s and the 90s
who were interested in speed solving
and were speed solving,
but they were doing it in small local communities.
And there was no global organization.
And that changed in the late 90s and early 2000s.
That changed, it started organizing on a global scale.
And the short answer of how that happened
is just the internet.
But once people started talking in IRC and in forums,
then this notion of trying to run a world championship
started growing, and trying to organize the sport as a sport
rather than just a hobby.
And it happened for the first time in 2003.
They held the first of the modern Rubik's World
Championships, Speedcubing World Championships.
And it was run by this man on the right, Dan Gosby.
And there were a fair number of teething troubles to do
with running this event.
And
There was a fair amount of backlash, which is probably, in hindsight, entirely overblown,
but still, Dan Gosby took this criticism rather personally,
and he left the scene immediately after organizing this event.
And this is an interesting inflection point in the history of speedcubing,
because his style of world championship is very different to the world championship that we have today.
It's very different to that average of five format that I've already shown you.
He was much more interested in a much more confrontational...
It's a television sport where there were mind games and it was much more like wrestling
where you could even know if you weren't technically the best solver you could still win because
you could get inside someone else's head.
And that's very different to what we have these days so it's interesting to think about
what the sport would be like if he had stayed around.
So the next year, two people from the different sides of the world came together
and decided they needed some kind of umbrella organization
to help regulate the sport and organize events.
And that was Tyson Mow on the left, who was part of the Californian speedcubing scene,
and Ron Van Bucum on the right, who was part of the Netherlands scene.
And they formed the WCA, the World Cube Association, in 2003.
In 2004, sorry.
And the next year they held their first WCA World Championship, which is weirdly hard
to find good photos of, so you've got the really low-res rubbish stuff.
And it was a success, people enjoyed it.
It wasn't perfect, there were problems, but generally people had a good reaction to it,
and then we were off to the races.
Ever since, there was a World Championship every two years.
So what did WCA do that, what did they bring to the table
that helps improve the sport and the community?
And I think there was a couple of factors here.
The first is this aspect of consistency.
So the Average of Five format that I've told you about
is exactly the same at your local meetup.
at your nationals and at the world championships.
So it's very easy for you to attend any one of those levels
and then move up or down the scale.
It's very accessible to you to do that.
And it's also very easy for the organizers
because they've already run countless events
of the exact same format.
The only thing that changes is how many people are entering.
They also have a very accessible format.
So last year, Ralph Costa et al.
published some work on trust spectrums,
which they wanted to use to categorize
MMO and online communities.
But I think applies here as well.
So Ralph Costa would categorize this as,
speedcubing as a game with lots of parallel play,
which means I can solve my Rubik's cubes
and you can solve your Rubik's cubes
and we don't really impact on each other.
There are no what they called roles in this sport,
which means I don't need to wait for someone to solve a 4x4 if I want to solve a 3x3.
And they were independent resources.
I can take as long or as slow as I want to solve my cubes,
and you can take as long as you want, and we don't impact each other.
And when you put all those together,
they would categorize this sport as a low trust game, which sounds...
divisive, but it's not. What it means is it's very, very accessible.
It's very easy for someone to come along and join the sport, and it's very easy for people to start up their own
their own events, because they don't need some minimum bar of quality player or some minimum quantity of people in order for it to happen.
And I think that's vital. When you have,
when you're starting with a puzzle that already has such a large learning curve,
having a sport associated with it that actually has a really shallow learning curve helps balance that out.
The WCA also has what they call the delegate system.
And this means that any event anywhere in the world can be an official WCA event and
can have official world records and official national records set at it as long as it has
a WCA delegate in attendance.
And that is someone who's trained in the WCA regulations as well as how to run a WCA event.
Now the interesting thing is that any WCA delegate...
Excuse me.
can train another WCA delegate.
So Ron Van Buchen, who you saw a few slides ago,
used to fill his suitcase up with Rubik's Cubes,
fly to some far-flung corner of the world
where he knew there were some people
interested in running events,
train them as delegates, leave them with the cubes,
and then within a year or two,
that country was full of delegates
trained to run events, and they were having
like half a dozen events a year.
So it helps it spread almost like a virus.
And then finally, it's a very non-confrontational sport,
as opposed to, like, Dan Gosby's model
of a more wrestling-style sport.
In fact, which is actually to its detriment
in terms of a spectator sport,
because if you're watching two people,
and in the World Championships,
they have the top two cubers on the stage,
and they'll solve in turns.
So one will do their first solve,
the other one will do their first solve,
the first one will do its second solve, and so on.
But it's actually really hard for you as a spectator to work out who's in the lead right now,
because you have to do all that mental arithmetic of throwing away the best and the worst and doing an average.
So really all it comes down to is there's no strategic decision to make.
Just make your next solve really fast. That's the only option.
And that makes it very collegiate, it makes it very friendly, because all you're focused
on is doing well and solving fast.
And if someone beats you in an event, it doesn't really matter as long as you're pushing your
personal best forward.
And so everyone's really happy for everyone else as long as everyone's making progress.
And it makes it a very friendly sport to be part of.
So now we've got organization.
What we need now is innovation so we can have more exciting, interesting things to do in
a sport.
And the major factor standing in the way of that at one point was the Rubik's Cube itself,
the brand, the company behind it produced these cubes that are very good toys, but they're
not good speed cubes.
They're slow, they're inconsistent, they take ages to break in, they're very awkward to
use.
And I mentioned that the 2005, the WCA World Championships weren't perfect, and one of
the things that wasn't perfect about it was that you had to use official brand, freshly
unboxed Rubik's Cubes as part of the competition.
And this was both unfair because people were getting, some people were getting cubes that
were relatively easy to turn and some were getting ones that were hard to turn, but also
unfair because...
Licensed Rubik's Cubes vary from country to country.
People coming from Japan, very used to a different color scheme,
color scheme layout.
And you can imagine that can make it very awkward to solve fast if
white is no longer opposite yellow.
And Tyson Marrow now says this was a mistake.
He says, it's not the Nike 100 meters in the Olympics.
It doesn't matter what trainers you're wearing.
What matters is your time investment
and your skill level and your talent.
And so from that point onwards,
the WCA have been very happy to take
Rubik's brand sponsorship money,
but you can use any cube you want in the competition.
And so people started popping up, wanting to design better speedcubes for speedcubers.
But they were still having trouble.
If you remember, at the beginning of the talk, I said there was a billion cubes in the world,
including counterfeits.
And Seven Towns, which is the company that owns the Rubik's Cube brand, still has this
hangover from the 80s of being very...
very, very protective of Rubik's Cube and of counterfeit Rubik's Cubes.
And they'll use things like patents and trademarks to try and stop people
selling what they think are counterfeit products.
Unfortunately, speedcube designers often got caught in the crossfire of that.
And so there was a stage in the mid-2010s where it's like good speedcubes were being
sold flat-packed like this to try and avoid any implication that this was like an official Rubik's product.
That eased up in the mid 2010s, and I'd love to do a whole talk about the patent-like cases
and trademark cases and stuff, but I don't think that's a GDC talk that people would
be interested in.
But it eased up, and now these days there's a tremendous variety of different speedcubes
and innovative designs in the market on making faster speedcubes.
Things like having springs inside your cube that can make it more forgiving of bad turns,
having magnets which make it more stable, having...
Customization is the thing this last 12 months, of being able to set up the cube exactly how
you want it, to make it your cube.
But we're still not quite sustainable.
So we've got innovation,
but we haven't got sustainability yet.
And this is because, like we said,
there's maybe a million speedcubers in the world,
but you can only really sell them one piece of plastic.
And these pieces of plastic aren't that expensive.
So to make it a sustainable business for the designers,
what they need to do is sell you more plastic.
And they can't sell you the Rubik's Cube because you already have a 3x3.
So what they're going to do is manufacture different types of cubes
and sell you those things instead.
And that worked great, like that worked out great for speedcubers because...
One thing they can never, they can always be pushing their times down and doing better
and practicing more, but one thing they can never ever do is solve three by three for
the first time again.
And so getting these new puzzles, these new experiences is something they're very interested
in and they're very happy to purchase these things.
And so collecting as part of the hobby started, became a thing.
And there's two main types of collecting.
The first one is collecting as novelty, the idea of trying to have that first 3x3 experience again.
And you can have that either as maybe adding more layers or more dimensions to your puzzle.
So both of these kind of use 3x3 algorithms in a weird way.
Or you can have something that's fundamentally different to the Rubik's Cube.
This one on the left is called the square one,
because it doesn't matter how many 3x3 algorithms you know,
when you unbox it, you're back to square one.
And there's also collection as aesthetic, the idea of collecting things that are interesting
or rare or novel.
And you've got things here, these are called shape mods, which are, these are both essentially
Rubik's cubes.
They're both 3x3s, except they've jumbled everything around.
Where's my little laser pointer?
So, this is actually the corner piece on the fissure cube,
and this is the edge piece.
So everything's slightly twisted.
This is the ghost cube,
which has every single piece has a unique shape.
And see you're solving based on shape rather than position.
But it's still a 3x3.
And then there's things like this,
which is the Oscar van Deveter sphere gear,
which is really interesting to look at,
really interesting to turn, but trivially easy to solve.
No one's buying that because they want the experience
of solving the puzzle.
They're buying it because they think
it looks cool on their shelf.
So now we've got all the pillars I think we need
for a sustainable sport, but no one joins your sport
because they've heard that you've got
good sustainable pillars.
And so we need to get people in and I think there's two reasons why people
get interested in join speedcubing. And the first one is definitely a novelty, a nostalgia factor.
Because we talked about the beginning how everyone got burnt out on the Rubik's Cube in 82 and they
couldn't solve it, but they didn't throw them away, they put them on their bookshelves. And so I can
remember my parents' Rubik's Cube on their bookshelf, people younger than me can probably
remember their grandparents' Rubik's Cube. And...
We don't have that burnout from the original fad.
And so for us, picking up a Rubik's Cube has got a huge dollop of nostalgia
of the family home from when they were young.
And I sent out some surveys to big speedcubing sites online
to try and get some idea of how people got into speedcubing.
I got some comments to back that up.
But I think it's a really important part of the hobby itself, this nostalgia factor.
And the other factor I think is important is this virality that comes with it as well.
So this is a screenshot of a video of Colin Burns breaking the world record in 2015.
And this is interesting because he was the first American to hold the world record for
about a decade.
Which means this clip went sort of viral on local news on the...
And now...
Here's some funny news at the end of the show.
We got lots of interest in Speedcubing spiked after this
because people saw this stuff on the news.
But I think it's not just patriotism
that got this onto the news.
I think that helped.
But also I just think it's intrinsically interesting
to watch someone solve a Rubik's Cube.
It's a demonstration of their time investment
and their skill level.
And as humans, we just find that interesting to watch.
And I've got comments to back that up as well.
I like that middle one.
I think it's interesting that the YouTube algorithm has figured out that we, as humans, find it interesting to watch this.
But it's not just that it's interesting to watch.
It's actually really rewarding as a cuber to teach someone else to cube.
Because it's not like Smash Brothers where if I teach you to play Smash Brothers and eventually you beat me, I lose out.
In speedcubing, if I teach you to speedcube and you surpass me, that doesn't matter. It doesn't matter to me because we've got that collegiate,
non-confrontational aspect to the sport. As long as I'm pushing my personal best forward, it's fine.
And in that aspect, I think it's very similar to video game speed running,
in that it's interesting to watch because this is investment,
like you're watching someone else's time investment.
I think speed running is very welcoming of new people to the sport.
So, to wrap up, I think when you've got a nostalgic, satisfying, yet complex toy
with sustainable, innovative designers and businesses,
based on an accessible and welcoming competition,
all tied together with a governing body
that puts players before corporate interests,
then you end up with a sport where before,
there was a dead toy.
And I'll leave you with this.
In 2018, a rogue, big money,
non-WCA World Championship was announced.
And when Red Bull is trying to muscle in on your sport,
you must be doing something right.
Thank you very much.
Don't forget to fill out your forms, high-five your CAs on the way out because they're awesome, and if anyone's got any questions
Hi, oh hello, yeah one fun question. What's your best time?
26.4 seconds
Congratulations.
That was on the plane over here by the way.
Wow.
The real question is, I was a little bit confused because earlier you said that like,
there's no, for one reason for something to be considered as a sport,
is that you shouldn't have any advantage, like,
Based on your equipment or anything, but then you mentioned that like people are making their own stuff now with magnets and other sort of stuff.
And like in sports it's important for there to be like, you know, whatever like regulation size balls and stuff like that. So like
I was a bit confused with that. So like with like with the world competitions, like how do you I guess kind of regulate like what kind of
speed cubes can be used?
So the position of the WCA at the moment is that
It doesn't matter.
There's no...
There hasn't yet been a technology that's deemed unfair.
It's not like the swimsuits in the Olympics a couple of years ago.
There's nothing that's been deemed terribly unfair.
It's just about making the cubes more reliable, easier to use, more satisfying to use.
Interestingly, Erno Rubrik himself, the inventor of the Rubik's Cube, takes the opposite position.
He thinks all cubes should be standardized and it should just be about skill.
But yeah, at the moment, we haven't reached the point where anyone's taken offense at any particular design.
Maybe that will come.
Hi, I'm interested in the organization, the WCA sort of
history.
And as a community of game developers here, I think a lot
of people are making games and hoping that they may take on
sort of like a community and like a competitive
scene of their own.
How important do you think it was that that organization
wasn't run by Rubik's?
Or was that sort of grassroots part of it an
essential component?
I think so in this case, I think so, because that original Rubik's Cube was just so inherently
bad as a speed cube, and still is bad as a speed cube.
In fact, I have a bunch down here if people want to come and play with them, but I have
a brand Rubik's Cube and you can compare it to my good speed cube and see what you think
the differences are.
But yes, it's the tension between making it accessible
to people just exploring the puzzle,
to children who are just playing with the puzzle,
which is what the Rubik's brand wants to be,
and then also making it really fast,
which makes it unstable and makes it hard to use.
And that's improved a little bit with magnets recently,
but still they're very loose feeling cubes
compared to the Rubik's cube.
So for this, yes, for this particular domain, yes.
And I think probably,
You can see it in speedrunning as well.
In speedrunning, they don't look at the original intention of the game designers.
It's just about how do I get to this end as fast as possible?
I'm going to glitch my way through it. I'm going to break my way through it.
So it's giving... I think it's really important to give the players the control of what they're doing
and let them try and find their best way of doing it. Does that make sense?
Yeah, totally. Thank you.
So, I can totally understand why making the sport non-confrontational is a good thing,
but I'm curious to know what confrontational Rubik's Cubing looks like.
How do you make Rubik's Cube confrontational?
So the Red Bull World Championships actually does that.
The Red Bull World Championships is a face-off between two people,
and there's various different events they have.
It's not just solving, we call it racing,
where you both try and solve a Rubik's Cube,
and the first one to solve wins a point.
There are various other events as well, but it's, yeah, it's face-to-face,
like getting up in each other's grill and, like, making it
so when you do something good, someone else loses out.
And I think that's really important for spectator, it makes it a much better spectator sport.
And I think they'll reach a point where speedcubing reaches a ceiling and they need to start looking at
making the top level sport more interesting to spectators.
But we haven't reached that yet because it's not grown big enough yet.
I think there's probably 10x more growth left in the sport.
Thank you.
I'm just curious, in competition, does each competitor have the same randomization of their cube?
And how do you know, if that's not true, then how do you know if somebody didn't just get a simpler solve?
So, everyone gets... it's a bit technical, but every hour there's a set list of random scrambles.
So they're guaranteed to be good random scrambles.
And then those are applied
by the people called the scramblers
that scramble the cubes for you.
So, and that changes every hour.
So the idea is you can't get a scramble
and then go and tell your mates
and then they are prepared for what the scramble will be.
So what was the question again?
You were asking about scrambles.
I guess I was drawing a parallel in my mind
to duplicate bridge, where you do play
a series of different hands, but each partner
is kind of playing a hand which every other team has played.
And so in some sense, it's a fair version of bridge,
because everybody is given the same resources
to be able to play.
Oh yeah, the average of five thing is designed to help with that,
because you do get very beneficial scrambles sometimes.
There's a thing called a PLL skip, which is like gold dust in cubing.
If you get a PLL skip, which is like skipping a whole step,
like one of the most expensive steps of solving the cube,
and it just randomly happens to come out solved,
and you don't have to do it.
Getting PLL skip is a really key part of getting a good fast time.
And so they take that five and throw away the best time and the worst time in order to try and get around
Like accidentally giving people like some people a PLL skip scramble and some people don't get a PLL skip scramble
Okay, thank you very much come to the front and play with the cubes if you want to play with the cubes
But have a good rest of your Monday