I'm Nick Popovich. Thank you very much for showing up today.
If I see any familiar faces and I'm not waving,
it's because there's lights in my eyes right now
and I can't see anyone's faces, so I apologize.
Let's kick things off with who I am.
I'm the co-founder and CEO of Monami Park,
the game director of Slime Rancher.
Hopefully some of you have played it.
There's me on Twitter.
I like to talk about game design a lot on Twitter,
so if you're interested in the contents of this talk,
some of it actually came from there, so there you have it.
And I'd also like to first put out a disclaimer
that this talk is not about how to make a great game.
You need one of those for the contents of this talk to matter.
and that this stuff might not be a fit for your game,
and that's totally okay,
because I don't have all the answers,
no one at GDC does,
and this is not the one true way
of getting your game out there
and getting people to notice it.
But I do think that some of this stuff
will help your game succeed.
That's why I'm up here today talking about it.
And what are we talking about?
The three major topics of today are sell it with a gif,
staying relevant, and a place to call home.
The TLDR version though is that this talk is about
getting people to notice your game,
to buy it, and play it repeatedly.
That is the goal of what I'm about to do here.
So talk about your game, notice it,
buy it, play it repeatedly.
But first, let's have some rad game facts, shall we?
First rad game fact, thousands of games
are released every year.
Second rad game fact, yes, seriously, thousands.
I highly recommend that you subscribe
to the ICO or I-C-O newsletter.
Just Google it and you will see all of the Steam games
that are released every week.
Last week, it was 156 games just before GDC
and that's one week, so that's what you're up against.
And also some of them even have marketing budgets
and you might not, so uh-oh.
And finally, you're competing with all of them,
every single one of them, whether they're good or not,
big or small.
And this is such a bummer that RadFox has decided
that he's gonna return to his home planet.
Okay, but why?
Why are you actually competing with all these games
despite the size of your game, your genre, et cetera?
Why is a AAA release that comes out tomorrow
actually taking customers away from you?
and that is because of time and attention.
And if you've been paying attention at GDC,
you may have heard more than a few people
talk about this at this point.
Time and attention is the focus of this talk,
and it's the core of why I make the games that I do
and put them out there in the way that I do,
and that's what we're talking about today.
So we're gonna get right into a takeaway, right off the bat.
that your game is what customers buy from you,
but time is what you buy from them.
Don't forget that.
It's not enough just to sell a game to someone
because you're still taking something from them,
and that is time.
So earlier I'd said everyone else's games were your competition.
It doesn't end there.
I'm sorry that I'm starting with such a bummer at the beginning of the talk.
I promise it gets better.
But your actual competition is everyone else's games, as we just established, and that includes
Fortnite.
It's also Netflix and YouTube and Twitter and sad political news.
All of that stuff takes up time and attention and you need that if anyone's going to pay
attention to your game, to buy it and to play it.
But don't worry, you are not the only one.
Netflix says that Fortnite is bigger competition than HBO and Hulu.
That's not just Netflix throwing some shade at their competition, it's time and attention.
Also major game publishers are feeling the impact of peaking attention.
There is only so much going around.
And there's also stuff like this, which is that they're starting to put little trailers
before a normal trailer, and it's because they know that you've got to see explosions
like right away, or else you're going to stop paying attention or scrub to 30% of the way
through, which is what most people do with your video.
So that's concerning.
And we're gonna really quickly take a look
at the average day of an adult in the U.S. in 2018.
It was four hours on phone and tablet.
So if you make mobile games, you have an advantage here.
Four hours of live TV, that's not playing video games.
That's either watching sports online or on cable
or just watching cable.
6.8 hours of sleeping, 8 plus hours of work on weekdays,
and you check your phone a bunch of times a day.
And that doesn't even factor in eating, commuting,
other life things, bathing yourself, all of that.
So what we're left with is two free hours
during the weekdays for new information,
and 10 on the weekends, and of course,
that doesn't count any of the other stuff
that you're gonna do on the weekends.
So, like I said, starting with a bit of a bummer,
but context is necessary for the rest of this.
And so we're going to move on to our first major topic
and leave the rad 90s to sell it with a GIF.
Okay.
First of all, GIFs are good.
They communicate things very quickly,
they're a form of artistic expression,
and they're very mobile-friendly and easily shareable,
especially on Twitter.
And speaking of Twitter, did you know that 31%
or Twitter users are 31% more likely to remember content
versus other online platforms?
Use stuff like this to your advantage.
Find that stuff out.
But this part of the talk is not about
best social media practices.
So instead, we're gonna jump right away
to another takeaway.
And that is, can your game design fit inside a GIF?
Oh, so what do I mean by that?
Can you present your core gameplay loop in a GIF?
That is the thing that the player is doing
over and over and over, usually it lasts about two minutes.
Can you show that in a span of five or six seconds?
Can you show the killer app of your game in a GIF?
And that is the feature or the must-have or must-see thing
that is going to drive people to buy your game
or to check it out or at least want to know more.
This might be because you can't show your core gameplay loop,
but you can show that one powerful moment.
If you were Jurassic Park the movie, this is the T-Rex.
The T-Rex is not the focal point of the story,
but it sure as hell put people in seats to see that movie.
It can't just be explosions unless your game
is really about that and that's at its core
because we've seen explosions before.
In the case of Jurassic Park,
we hadn't seen a T-Rex like that before.
So what do you have as a killer app?
Can you teach someone to play your game in a GIF?
This one's amazing.
If you can manage to pull that off,
it doesn't have to be every single step of the way,
but if you can give someone the gist
of what it is to play your game,
and they can understand it,
and they can start picturing themselves playing your game,
you have just won an enormous battle.
You've walked right through a 1,000 foot firewall,
and you're onto the next step
of engaging with your customer.
Basically though, what it comes down to is,
can I get your game in a GIF?
Can I see it and can I get it?
I might have questions, questions are fine,
but does it answer something?
Does it answer something material?
That's what you want to be able to execute on in a GIF.
We set out to do this with Slime Rancher.
We were inspired by what I saw with Spelunky,
how it was able to really clearly communicate itself
in the form of a GIF.
And so we knew we had to do that.
The landscape was rapidly changing
when we were developing it.
And you may have heard this term before.
It was coined in Stranger in a Strange Land,
and it's called Grok.
People in game development use it a lot,
often grokking a game.
and it is to understand something intuitively or by empathy.
You are establishing an emotional rapport with something.
And often times we use it in game design when we say,
player has grokked your game,
they're really into it, they really get it,
they're in a position where they can evangelize it,
and they're willing to put up with some bullshit basically
in order to get more of that experience because they bought into it.
But here I'm applying this concept to before someone actually plays the game.
Now, obviously they're not going to grok your game via a gif in the same way that they would
had they spent hours and hours of playing it and achieved that level of groking.
But there is a shade of that, a grok light, if you will, where someone has bought into
it based on what you've put out there for people to consume.
And so really it comes down to what do you want the player to feel?
And I think this is an important question as an aside to ask that about every aspect
of your game design, everything that you're putting out there.
But this isn't just about emotional context in the narrative of your game, this is about
Do you want the player to feel frustrated at various points in the experience?
Do you want them to have an overwhelming sense of freedom?
Every decision that you make, every feature that you put in your game,
you should be thinking about what is the emotional context on the part of the player here?
What do I want them to feel?
Well, why would you stop with your game design?
Why wouldn't you think about how that relates to how it shows to people
on social media in the form of a GIF?
People make gifts of their gameplay all the time.
They make trailers.
But are you asking yourself,
what is it that I'm looking for the person looking at this
to feel in response to it?
Because that might change what you decide to show.
And maybe it might change the kind of game
that you're making if you can't answer that question.
So, always ask that question.
You should always have something that you're trying to say.
And if you don't, you're just another game.
You're just another entry in a genre, if you're not saying anything different.
So the reason this is important is, as we've previously established, everyone is distracted
all the time.
The 90s segment taught us that.
And we have a finite amount of time and energy
to care about new things, your game included.
So the more time and energy is required, the harder the sell.
And I don't even just mean a game sale.
I mean to care about what I just saw
and maybe want to know more,
or to pay attention the next time I see that.
So basically reduce time to grok as much as possible.
So if you were selling burgers, for example,
to use a non-video game example,
and you just set up a stall, and you were making burgers,
you didn't put up a sign, you didn't put up a menu,
you didn't put up anything,
it's gonna be really hard to sell those burgers
until you put up a sign that says, burgers for sale.
Now I have context.
I know what it is that you're trying to sell.
But if you could then provide a picture of your delicious
burger that you're trying to sell and some reviews, you're
answering questions that people might have.
Even if it's just in their head, you are giving them
knowledge, and that's what's going to lead to either
wanting to know more or a sale.
So let's look at some games that do this very, very well.
And since I just mentioned Spelunky, I'll start there.
Spelunky, here's a GIF of it, shows you everything you need to know about this game in the form
of a GIF.
If you were my dad, you might look at Spelunky and say, this looks like Indiana Jones meets
Mario.
What is it?
But Spelunky shows you that it's a bunch of systems that are overlapping that generate
experiences.
This is just one GIF.
Any number of GIFs of Spelunky are going to show you different outcomes.
You may be looking at the same level, even though they're generated,
and seeing those different outcomes. And so as a player I'm looking at this now
and I'm thinking about all the different permutations of things that can happen.
It also does a really wonderful job of having fun by failing
and it shows you that in a GIF because the sequences that are occurring here
are comical.
I think this is pretty funny here.
I think the player dies about six different ways here,
and I think that's really great.
So it does a great job of showing that off.
Another one is Superhot, and this is a great example
because it's showing you a very, very simple concept,
which is time only moves when you do,
and then demonstrating how a variety
of different scenarios can play out using that
as your main power in the game.
It also does a great example of showing that there's a huge difference between complex design and complex ideas.
You want to generally avoid complex ideas when you're trying to sell your game.
A perfect analog to this is in terms of simple idea but complex execution would be portal.
I think that's probably the master class in this where you can very, very simply see in the form of a GIF.
to different portals and seeing what that means to you as the player
and then your mind just starts racing with all the different things that you can do.
If you, much like Superhot or Portal,
can get a player to start thinking about how they might play
your game, it's a huge advantage that you have.
I would actually relate this to how I used to
learn about games when I was...
A kid 9,000 years ago and opening up Nintendo Power and that's all we had.
We had screenshots to go by and really bad descriptions of those screenshots.
So you would make up in your head what this game could possibly be about and you got yourself
excited with lies that you were telling yourself.
And that's okay.
you might start thinking about the different scenarios in Superhot or the different weapons
that you might have, and that might not actually be in the game, but that's okay, because you're
getting your potential customers' imaginations excited. And those are the kind of things that
you want to be able to do with your game. So if you want to make games that people get quickly,
avoid complex ideas, but allow for complex design or execution on those simpler ideas.
Speaking of a simple idea, Rocket League, it's cars that play soccer.
But if I just told you that and you had never heard of Rocket League before, it was probably
a very awkward version of soccer that you're imagining.
Little did you know it's like rocket-powered matchbox cars that are also part ninja.
And I think there is not a lot in Rocket League
in terms of the moment to moment gameplay.
It's some cars and a ball and two goal zones.
But you can see that there's a number of different ways
that that can play out and it's exciting
and it gets right to the point and it's a huge hit.
something a little less elegant, Human Fall Flat.
I really love this one,
because it's a kind of very different approach.
It's showing you awkwardness and silliness,
and comedy is great for GIFs.
It makes it very shareable.
But there needs to be room for extrapolation.
If you just show a joke,
if your game is the Wile E. Coyote,
you know, getting the dynamite blown up in his face,
it's a great joke.
But if there's no way that I can understand
how that relates to your game,
or how that might create interesting scenarios,
I'm left with nothing other than a great joke
that I share just like I share a bunch of other stuff online.
So with Human Fall Flat.
in part because I understand video games and that's a protagonist, I know that,
it's telling me that mundane things are being done stupidly in this game.
And especially if I buy into it and watch a couple other GIFs or check out a trailer,
I get that immediately. I've done mundane things before because I'm a normal human being,
and doing them stupidly and without consequence sounds really exciting to me. So I'll bite.
Next, Subnautica does a great job of showing you a single
breathtaking moment, it's killer app,
which is diving below the surface of the sea
and seeing a massive, mysterious,
underwater world for me to explore.
It has a huge advantage in that there just are not
a lot of underwater games, so it stands out in that regard.
It's also beautiful and it adds that mystery element to it.
I want to know more, I want to see more.
So Subnautica came out when there were a bunch of other survival games, but none of them
were underwater.
A lot of them you were rubbing rocks together and stuff in a muddy forest somewhere.
Subnautica was different.
It was gorgeous and beautiful and bright and I think that contributed hugely to its success,
all of which is communicated in an image or a GIF.
Next is Factorio.
I love this one.
I think it gets you very excited to play the game, and it's showing you scale of things
that you can do in it.
You can see machines that are working together with one another, and I don't know what the
goal of the game is, but I bet you it's to do big stuff and continue to do more and more
of it, and that's very exciting, and I want to build stuff like that.
But there's a few key points about what Factorio decided to do,
which is that it shows known machinery, like oil derricks and spaceships.
I think that's really important,
because the game might take place on a planet that you've never heard of,
and the point of the game might be...
that you're building this to defend yourself against, you know, bug people or something like that.
But it's showing me things that I can understand, and I can relate to what I'm seeing there.
And so it acts as a sort of inroad to me understanding more about this game.
If everything were just alien machinery, I wouldn't get it as well as I do with what you're seeing here.
For example, if Rocket League was not cars playing soccer...
but it was UFO-like things hitting a Nova Cube through space or something like that,
and it was still soccer, it would be much less grokkable for people,
because I don't know anything about that.
So I kind of get that we're playing soccer here,
but if you can give me something that I understand,
that path to having more knowledge is a lot more open for me as a potential customer.
Next is They Are Billions, which does an amazing job of showing you scale and quantity.
It's very awe-inspiring, I think, to see the hordes of things that are attacking this city.
I immediately want to know what that's all about.
It doesn't tell me in this GIF who I am, but I imagine I'm not the zombie things.
I imagine I'm the, you know, homes and castles and everything that seems like they are trying
to protect themselves.
So I have an idea right away about what this game is about, and it's showing me the killer
app, which is...
billions of zombies coming at once.
It's also not a giant 3D experience.
It's something that you might even be able to see on iPad.
And yet it does a wonderful job of having
an awe-inspiring scale moment.
You know, it doesn't need to have a giant 3D T-Rex.
It's showing lots of little characters running out of city.
And immediately you get this gut feeling like,
that's not good.
I should probably protect against that.
Slime Rancher similarly shows quantity.
We think that's one of our secret sauces, is that much like they are billions, in Slime
Rancher you're seeing hordes and hordes of slimes bumping into one another at any given
moment.
It's a physics nightmare under the hood.
But you don't normally see that in a game, so even if you're a person who doesn't understand
game technology or you're just a little kid.
You haven't seen something like that happen before as regularly in front of you, and so
it just feels different.
An RTS that has billions of things coming at you feels different.
So you're winning a battle.
However,
If you can do the giant T-Rex,
you should absolutely do the giant T-Rex.
If you have the budget for it,
I'm probably talking to the like four
triple A people in the room right now,
but if you have the budget for it, show it.
But I do wanna add that there is a wrinkle
to what Monster Hunter does.
I think it does it particularly well.
That is, I think they flip the script
and they focus on the monsters, not the player.
So Monster Hunter trailers
and anything that they're sharing online
typically is not showing you crafting systems
or anything like that.
That's all ancillary to the big show, which is giant monsters doing cool stuff.
And their marketing narrative is very, very consistent in that regard.
So any time I pick up some Monster Hunter marketing, a GIF that is being shared online,
it's a very consistent message.
I am a little, strong, brave, probably stupid warrior in this case, fighting enormous monsters,
and they seem very overwhelming, and that narrative is very, very consistent.
And you know I do include this.
I'm up here, so I'm gonna talk about Slime Rancher some more.
If you saw my previous talk,
we thought about this from the very beginning.
The action comes at the screen.
It's bright and cheery and very easy to parse,
especially if you're just scrolling through
on something like Twitter.
And it has lots of physics,
and I already covered as to why
we feel like that's important.
Probably a better segue to this, to make it more powerful, would have been from Monster Hunter,
but I'm going to go to one last one, which is Baba is You.
I think this game is great.
It's a recent release, and I mean no disrespect to it,
but on the surface, an indie pixel art turn-based puzzle game
is probably not something that a mainstream gamer audience is going to care about.
However...
This game perfectly teaches you how to play it in a GIF.
This does it right here.
And I think it's a very, it is an otherwise sort of very
complicated game to understand, but it teaches itself very,
very beautifully.
And you immediately start thinking about all the
different permutations of this.
And I think it contributes hugely to its success.
It has a very strange name, has a very strange rule set,
and yet it teaches people how to play a game.
It's currently doing very, very well on Steam, last I checked.
I'm sure it'll do very well on Switch as well.
But I just want to play devil's advocate here and say that plenty of best-selling games
don't do this.
So I'm going to keep saying this throughout the talk.
If your game doesn't do the things that I'm talking about, it's fine.
You're going to do other things.
But in summary, your customers have finite time
and are highly distracted.
So make a game that customers don't
have to work to understand.
Make a game that sells itself in the span of a GIF.
Doing so will actually affect your design.
If you set out to do this from the beginning,
it will affect your game design because you'll
have to be lean and focused in order to do this.
Customers need knowledge.
It makes it easier for them.
And as Johnny Utah famously said, knowledge equals sales.
All right, so let's move on to the next topic,
which is staying relevant.
And I'll just say right now
that this is the most difficult and expensive part
of the three things that I'm talking about today.
So what is staying relevant?
It is having new content to play over time,
remaining community relevant to play over time,
remaining streamer or YouTube relevant over time,
with a goal to continuing to sell over time.
Some of you are probably already doing this with your games.
And that's great.
This will just be a refresher.
Maybe I'll have something new to offer here.
But the takeaway right away is that I believe that your game needs a pulse to survive.
Games with a beating heart have a far better chance of staying on the charts.
And very rarely does anyone these days release a game and just walk away from it.
And six months later, it's still a bestseller.
Those instances are extremely rare.
I wouldn't bank on that.
Unless you're Nintendo, they can manage to do that.
So how do we keep the pulse?
The two major ones are content updates for your game
and having a multiplayer sharing feature in your game.
Both of those together,
and that's the most powerful cocktail.
But there's also content creation from your community
if you've released a tool set and you foster that
and players are able to make their own content, that's huge.
There's community scene and competition.
This pretty much requires multiplayer to work,
but you can be very, very clever about that.
And then porting to other platforms.
This might seem like it's not a means
of staying relevant over time,
and certainly maybe not as powerful
as some of the other ones,
but it is, on its own, a very useful tool,
especially if you are releasing special
or deluxe editions of your game
as you port it to new platforms over time.
Basically, try to treat every port that you do as a new launch of your game.
Try and have some opportunity to scream about it again when you port it.
Don't just say it's now available on this platform.
Thank you.
Good night.
Then there's community engagement.
This one really is necessary to work,
really requires some of the other ones
in order to be best.
Very rarely can you just release a game
and engage with your community
and that's gonna keep you relevant
for six months to a year.
But it does work very, very well
in concert with content updates, multiplayer,
and especially a community and scene competition.
But why do you do this? It sounds expensive, it sounds like a lot of work.
Well, it's because long-term support of your game is becoming expected.
I'm sure you've read one or two Steam reviews that say things like,
dead game, negative review. As unfair as that is, it happens.
Supporting a released game is easier and less risky than building a new one.
Obviously you need to already have some traction.
If you have shipped your game and it didn't work out, continuing to support it might not
be for you.
and just remember that concurrency is king.
And that is not just about making an online PVP game,
so obviously you need concurrency in order for it to work.
I'm talking about at any given moment.
the total number of people playing your game in this moment, by the day, or by the week,
is really important and really relevant to your success, even if you have, like we did,
a single-player offline game. And the reason for that is it's relative. You don't need to
target 10,000 concurrent users in order for it to be material to your success. You need to target
a relatively small number of people that can grow into a bigger one.
And that will then lead to sales because it is a tiny little zeitgeist that can grow into a bigger one.
And since I just mentioned it, how does this lead to sales?
Well, viral mechanisms on Steam, PS4, and Xbox.
This is one of the principal ways that we sell on Slime Rancher.
We don't spend money on marketing.
We rely on this, which is we support the game over time.
and people play it over time, including existing players
who have stuck with us, that's really important,
because all the while, they are blasting
to their friends list on these platforms
that they're currently playing Slime Rancher.
And if you're the new release for today,
and you have some of your friends are playing that game,
you're gonna hear about it,
it's gonna pop up in their friends list,
you're like, any other game that's been released.
And I might pay attention to it, I might not.
And if that's your only chance that you're going to encapsulate that little weak launch moment,
or weak launch moment, and that's it, you just drove right past a billboard and you just crossed
your fingers that maybe people paid attention. But if you keep beating that drum and releasing
new content over time and people keep blasting to their friends lists that they are currently
playing your game, eventually, like a billboard that you drive past to work every day, they see it.
and now they're finally paid attention to it, now they maybe remember the name,
and now they're associating with this game that their friends seem to play a lot of,
and finally it just sort of worms their way into their head, and they're familiar enough with it
that they have that little bit of knowledge, and it could lead to the next step,
which might be a sale, it might be wanting to know more,
and reaching out to their friends, or...
at least looking at the game page, but it is a step.
It's very important, and you earn those
by doing long-term support.
Wishlist conversions and gifting from sales is another one.
There is a constant churn of your wishlist
that as long as you're doing things right
and you have a game that people want to play,
you will just get a constant churn
of people converting on your Steam wishlist.
into sales over time though.
And a lot of that comes up when Steam broadcasts
to customers that a game from your wishlist is on sale.
Well, if they vaguely remember it, don't remember it,
or something like that,
that it's gonna be a much harder sell.
If it's that game that they have now passed the billboard
many a time and their friends are still playing it,
maybe now is the time.
But maybe it's not.
And that's my third point, that sometimes people are just busy and distracted and maybe
they're not going to buy your game now.
We establish that everyone's very distracted, we don't have a lot of time going around.
It doesn't mean that they hate your game or they're never going to buy it.
I think sometimes we fall into this trap of thinking, I'm going to release my game.
And all the people that are going to either buy it or not are going to do so, and that's
it.
You've got to keep working it.
And I've backed things on Kickstarter that I've never even played.
That's the situation that we're dealing with.
Don't just be another entry in someone's Steam library.
So, the other final point is just joining the bandwagon and discussion.
This is why concurrency is powerful.
It's because then there are people talking about your game, and if you can get people
talking and sharing things like a GIF on social media, then we're all part of this discussion.
It's a much easier sell if the customer thinks that there is momentum behind it.
And some of that you can kind of generate on your own
by just pushing that out there,
let's say in the form of GIFs on Twitter,
or by supporting your game
and having people blast it to their friends
that they're playing your next content update,
playing it, playing it, playing it.
You're generating your own buzz
in people's friends' networks.
So in summary, I hope you noticed, by the way,
that the tomatoes have been growing slowly over time.
We put some effort into that.
Your game is a garden, nurture it.
Stay relevant by doing the things
that give your game a pulse.
And keeping a pulse keeps you selling your game.
And you can enjoy delicious tomatoes.
Final section for the talk is a place to call home.
And so we're gonna kick things off,
instead of a takeaway, with a question.
Have you ever sat down to play a game and not chosen a specific one because you can't
recall where you left off, the game is stressful or difficult and you were looking to relax,
you know that you will need to find a group like a multiplayer game, or you remembered
that you were stuck on something?
I'm sure many of us have done that, and that is as a result of friction.
All of that stuff is friction.
And so now we're gonna get right away into a takeaway,
which is that friction kills.
Friction being a killer is well-known in game design.
We often think about this, though,
in terms of game systems and game experience.
So it is after the player is playing the game.
If they encounter things that are bad
or that impede their progress or are confusing,
anything that keeps them from playing your game
and keeps them from enjoying it
that you are likely responsible for, that is friction.
But I'm talking about the idea of friction being friction itself.
So not to get too out there, but it's the idea that friction exists in the game that
is creating friction from anyone playing your game.
And so the solution to this is to give your game
a place to call home.
So what is home?
Home, by my definition, is any environment,
mode, or activity in a game that allows for relaxed,
low-consequence play, but still issues
meaningful rewards or progress.
I don't think this is talked about nearly enough in games, and I think this is really important,
and so that's why I devoted a whole section to it.
This is not a literal home base in your game.
This is often the kind of the cozy aspect of your game.
And it doesn't mean because you're making
Animal Crossing or Stardew Valley
and you've made a cozy game.
There can be cozy moments in very stressful games
and very big action oriented games.
And as long as it conforms to this definition here,
that would be this game's home.
And so I'll give you some examples.
In Destiny, it's running patrols and bounties.
So this is an activity that is available to you at any time.
I'm sure everyone's familiar with what this is,
but just in case you're not,
you're allowed to drop on a planet,
you're not doing any one specific mission.
You're kind of wandering an open world and things will happen in front of you and you
can choose to engage with those things.
And you also have a little quest list of things that you can be doing.
The rest of Destiny content is PvP and high stakes missions and raids.
And it's all a higher tier of play, a higher form of commitment to playing Destiny for
that evening.
So you are able to, in Destiny, by running patrols and bounties, to wait for friends
to come online or finish the activities that they're currently engaged in.
And you're not staring at a matchmaking screen when you're doing that.
You're wandering around doing your own thing.
And you might be waiting for a raid group, but this acts as a first tier of play commitment
to those other tiers that I mentioned before.
And it's important to note that even legendaries can drop when you're wandering around here.
One of the best rewards in the game.
Diablo 3 does a fantastic job of this, where
go in a direction, and you'll be rewarded equally for whatever it is that you're doing.
So it just feels good. It's like Mac and Cheese the video game.
Fortnite, PvP game, I'm terrible at it.
I get killed right away, but there is a battle pass
and that has objectives that allow me
to get meaningful rewards and do things
other than trying to be one out of a hundred.
So this, I think, was one of Fortnite's brilliant moves,
is they realized we have a game
where we put 100 people in the room
and 99 of them are losers.
And you might not think about it that way.
You might be very, very happy getting in the top 10%.
I'm happy if I can kill one person in it.
But it has these things that I can pursue on my own
whenever I want to, and hey.
a bunch of times it's just doing the thing,
it's just playing the game and I can decide
to go somewhere, do something, or have a different objective
that isn't being the best out of 100 people.
Mario Odyssey is obviously a pretty relaxed experience,
but there are definitely bigger challenges in it,
and it isn't really just about sheer difficulty
that we're talking about, but it's version of home
is collecting moons from past levels.
And the reason for this is, like I said, you don't sit down with Mario Odyssey and think
this is going to be like Counter-Strike levels of stress.
But going to a new world, having a new world open up to a player, like when you leave,
I don't know if I'm remembering correctly, but leave the desert and go to the city.
That is a source of anxiety to some degree.
I mean, you might be totally fine with it,
but there's a big unknown.
You now are gonna have a bunch of new objectives
thrown at you.
Anytime like a zone opens up in a world,
it's a mixture of excitement and anxiety for the player.
And so going back to levels and places in a world
that you are very, very familiar with
and doing it kind of on your own terms
and knowing that you don't have to maybe finish
the whole level, you just have to get the moon
that was halfway through it,
and it is overall contributing to your progress
and your ability to go to newer places in the world later,
that's huge.
Because if it were just about forward momentum,
you are gonna have players that get stuck eventually.
Next, MMO, Daily Quests, love them or hate them.
They're a great way of getting people just to sit down
and actually log into the game
and immediately have something meaningful that they can do
because at any given time,
most people don't have a lot of friends online
that they can play the same game with.
A lot of times, playing games with your friends is...
different people are playing different games or we're in the same game, much like I was
talking about with Destiny, we're just doing different things and chatting.
So dailies give you that entry into a giant, complicated world with a lot of moving parts,
but it gives you a focused daily thing that you can sit down and grind out and you get
rewards for it.
In the case of Spider-Man, I like this one because its version of home, which is swinging
around the city looking for things to do and perhaps encountering things happening randomly
in front of you, is also the best feeling thing in the game.
You might like its combat or its story or whatever, but you're wrong.
Swinging through the city is the best part of any Spider-Man game ever.
And it's great that in this game, that is how you get around and find new things and engage with higher tiers of play commitment.
But swinging feels good all the time, and that's huge for Spider-Man.
Spider-Man's having a great year.
It's just, it's huge.
Next, Minecraft and games like it
basically are just pure home,
gathering for projects and building them.
Everything that you can collect contributes
to grander visions and projects.
So in Minecraft, you might be looking for diamonds,
but if you're collecting other resources,
eventually you might use them.
That's huge.
It always feels like wandering
equals some form of forward momentum.
So, again, you might not be making Minecraft, you might not be making a game like Minecraft,
but think about how Minecraft achieved that and maybe you could do something like that.
Breath of the Wild is just almost another pure home experience
other than when you're doing dungeons and kind of the higher level challenges in the game.
But Wandering Over the Next Horizon, it's always offering you something.
And unlike a game like Skyrim, which allows you to wander over the next horizon
and encounter whatever, Shrines in Zelda are great
because I personally, I'm not usually wild about doing them,
but they are something in the environment.
that I can either bookmark or do right away,
and it's going to give me overall further progress for my character.
That's very material, whereas...
When I wander into a cave in Skyrim, for example,
there might be loot, there might be spiders,
there might be bears and spiders.
I don't know what I'm getting.
And that on its own is powerful,
but being able to spot things in the world
and go that is going to contribute
to my overall progression just by the virtue
of my doing it and engaging with it, that's great.
Agility orbs and crackdown are another one.
Slime rancher, also tending to your ranch, wandering.
You know, home is kind of my thing,
so I wanted this game to have this from the very beginning.
I always kind of think of the games I make
as like little gardens of play
and not a series of challenges.
And so this comes very naturally to the experiences
that I want to create.
The next game I make, I guarantee you
there will be some version of home within it.
But finally.
sort of playing devil's advocate again a little bit.
It's also sort of a design talk,
so you had to say Dark Souls at some point
or the lightning bolt would hit me and I'd die.
So Dark Souls doesn't really have home,
but I wanted to bring this up because,
you know, you might not have an opportunity
to introduce home in the way that I've defined it
in your game, but.
Dark Souls does have a kind of version of home.
It's kind of like a campground that you visit on your journey that you leave behind.
And that is, you know, Dark Souls can be very challenging and punitive.
When you collect a bunch of souls, you die, you lose all those souls.
So...
You know, that first level of anxiety is I have a bunch of souls and I just lost them.
Now we bring that anxiety up to another level, which is all of those souls that you have are
sitting over there by that giant dragon. You have one shot to get it. So now the anxiety has peaked
for the player at this point.
We are nowhere near home at this point.
Home is a distant memory and it's burning
and you can smell the smoke.
But if you die then, if it's catastrophic failure,
what do you get?
You've basically cashed out.
Now you have zero souls and you're back at the hub.
And that's a huge freeing moment for the player
because now I can go anywhere I want.
and do anything, and unlike before, there are zero consequences to my actions.
So I can decide to try that boss again and know I can maybe experiment with a new tactic this time.
I can go and find loot hidden away in dangerous places that I permanently get to keep.
Or I could just explore and do whatever. I could try something wild.
and then eventually I'm going to accrue a bunch of souls and I'm back to that anxious moment again.
But it's key that Dark Souls routinely, because that dragon's going to keep killing you,
is offering you this moment of reprieve.
And it doesn't matter if you're making a really challenging or obtuse experience or something.
If you can find ways where you basically release that steam valve every once in a while for the player,
it's going to be hugely beneficial for your experience.
So let's get into why players respond to home.
I think I've already kind of touched on this a little bit,
but games are recreational
and home basically allows you to relax.
We're accustomed to visiting platforms
and exploring for content like Steam, Netflix, and Twitter.
You might call this a bit of a stretch.
I kind of agree, but I think there's some truth to it.
A lot of our experiences these days are visiting platforms.
that offer a wealth of content that we dig a little bit
and we go further and further, further tiers of engagement
with these platforms.
So you might be deciding, am I going to play games,
or watch a movie, or watch sports tonight?
You choose movies.
So now you choose between your service providers for those.
You choose Netflix.
Now you're browsing.
through the content that you could consume.
You decide to act on one.
Maybe you watch it.
Maybe you go for the next episode.
You have continued to engage further and further and further.
So one, why not let your game be just as easy to engage with
and why not let the game itself
offer that experience to someone?
Because it is really easy for me.
If the dragon crushes me, and then I lose a level if I've had zero souls and dark souls,
for me to shut it off, pull out my phone, or watch Netflix because I'm done with this shit
for the night, I'm tired of failing. So offer home, and I firmly believe that it'll allow players to
engage with your game more easily, make that decision to sit down with it.
There's always some amount of anxiety around PVP,
team play, spending currencies, ranked play,
I think I've already covered this.
So home gives you a starting point
and a go-to during play sessions.
So home is what gets people in the door,
but it's also that comfy couch that you can return to
in between higher tiers of commitment within the game.
But why is Home good for your business?
So selling a copy of your game just isn't enough.
Having people play your game,
and play your game repeatedly,
as I've covered earlier, is key.
Home does this.
So players playing your game over time will increase sales.
Home gets players into your game.
And Home increases overall playtime
because of lack of friction.
Now you might be saying, just wait a dang minute.
Isn't some of the stuff in this talk the kind of strategy that is used by games as a service?
And I would say yes, and that's okay.
Copying business practices that work is okay.
Even if you're not really in that business, it's okay.
Steal the good stuff.
I could learn something about selling my game
from that successful burger stand
that I talked about earlier.
Copy it.
Why not?
Why not just try and fit in the mold
of what everyone else is doing?
If you do that, you're another game now.
To kind of bring it all together with Slime Rancher,
it was a single-player offline indie game.
It was released over three years ago.
The original dev team was three people.
Very, very humble beginnings.
And it is also not a typical games-as-service genre,
not by any stretch.
Single-player offline indie game
about ranching slimes and farming.
It's far away from that.
But that didn't stop us from releasing 18 significant content updates so far, with another
one on the way.
It has weekly and holiday activities and community contests, and those activities are just generated
within the game.
We took a page from Animal Crossing, basically.
Animal Crossing is not, at least the older ones, weren't an internet-connected game,
and yet it had daily stuff.
It felt alive.
We just copied that.
It's still being ported to new platforms, we make a big deal out of it every time we
do that.
It has maintained strong revenue since its release in December 2018, which was our best
month ever for what was then almost a three-year-old game.
And I basically want to say that I'm practicing what I preach here.
It sells itself in a gif, it has maintained relevancy by nurturing the game since its
release, and it has copious amounts of home in it.
That is usually one of the number one things, they're not using home, but the number one
things that our reviewers point out.
is that they can relax when they play it, it feels cozy.
And again, you do not have to have a bright, warm,
and fuzzy game for this to work.
You just have to elicit those feelings.
Again, what do you want your players to feel?
Do it.
But it also does other things not covered in this talk.
And it also doesn't do lots of things
that make other games successful, maybe including yours.
And so remember,
that the stuff in this talk will help your game succeed,
but it is not the only path to success.
So I say, instead, take the stuff from this talk
and everyone else's talks that makes sense to you
and your game and make your own path to success.
And good luck with that.
So he's back. Thank you very much. I want to thank Ray and Kara who helped me put this talk together, and everyone at Monami Park.
I believe there is some time I can take some questions.
I really love the talk, so it's a good follow-up to what you did last year, too, a couple years ago.
Kind of reflecting, you said that December was your best month revenue-wise,
what would you tell yourself beginning Slime Rancher?
I know that you probably tell yourself a lot, but what's maybe a couple of key lessons
having gone through that whole process now, especially from this perspective?
So the question is, what would I tell myself three years ago
from when we were in December of last year and at the peak revenue?
Yeah, so we had set out to sell 100,000 copies of the game.
That was our goal.
And I think this is important, that obviously we
sold way more than that.
But we weren't thinking in terms of let's just
see what will happen.
We tried to make a game that we thought we could
sell 100,000 copies of.
And we had a plan for what we would do if that happened.
And I think that is very relevant to what I was talking about with concurrency.
We weren't aiming for let's see what happens.
We wanted that 100,000 because we knew that was the momentum necessary to maybe get us more.
And it turns out that was very much the case.
But, you know, I think...
Yeah, I don't know if I totally answered your question there.
Obviously, I would be very excited.
But I think I might be slightly discouraged
at how much hard work was necessary to get to that moment.
Working at the long-term support, nurturing the game,
it's a very, very difficult thing to do.
And we just had to stick at it.
You can't get bored and want to make your next game.
You just have to keep selling.
So, next one.
So a question about how to make an effective GIF for telling your game.
If your game is based around mechanics which are not represented visually very well,
like a sound game or an audio game,
or something that involves creation of intangible things,
can you think of a way to kind of work that into a GIF?
Well, GIF is a visual medium with no audio.
So as I said in the beginning in the disclaimer,
this just might not be for you.
But certainly, that's a very unorthodox experience.
So immediately, that's a firewall
that you have to be able to somehow get
people to walk through.
And so it's really on you to think.
what is the shortest path through that.
And yeah, I think a lot of this,
because in relation to a GIF, it's visual.
There isn't a whole lot that we can do with just pure audio.
Perhaps there's, you know, Twitter, like I said,
is very good for delivering that visual information
very quickly.
Find a platform that delivers audio information
very quickly, but you're definitely up against it
because even movies on Twitter and that will have
subtitles on it because they know people just aren't listening to audio.
So you have your challenges ahead of you, I'm sorry.
Okay.
Yes.
Sorry.
Fantastic talk.
Thank you.
I'm going to force my whole team to watch it.
It's exactly what we need right now.
Specifically about the GIFs, I was
wondering if you could talk a little more
about the creation of them.
Literally, what tools you're using?
Are you recording actual gameplay?
And then how long it takes you to edit it and put it together?
And just the production of the GIF,
what's the effort and tooling you're using to do it?
So the question is, best practices for making GIFs,
how you do it.
Fortunately, I have someone who does that.
Early on, what we did was we added a feature in Slime
Rancher.
A lot of people don't know that this exists.
But on PC, hitting G generates a GIF of the last, I think
it's five seconds of gameplay.
There are third-party solutions to that as well.
I think it took Mike, the other co-founder of Monami Park,
Mike.
probably half a day to put it in.
It has generated a ton of community GIFs, which are great,
but also it allowed us to very quickly
create those moments early on
when it was just two or three of us that worked online.
They were probably totally unoptimized
and Kara, our communications manager at Monami Park
would probably never put those things online,
but when you're small and lean, scrappy,
that was a great solution.
She could probably do a talk on best practices
in terms of recording footage and that,
but there are a number of people who are really,
really good at making GIFs,
and they will share those processes with you.
I don't know if you've, I totally forget the name,
but there is someone who makes like amazing
Devil May Cry GIFs, and they're not Capcom.
Definitely check that out,
because they're gorgeous and perfectly formatted.
So, but early on, I totally recommend.
put a make gift button in your game, it will save you a ton of agony later.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
Hi. So you touched on a little bit with the first question saying how you went into this saying you wanted to sell a certain amount of games.
You also touched on earlier on about games as a service and how Sly Mantra is, as you say, a game as a service.
Did you go into that, even early on, like the first year where you were developing, to make it a game as a service?
Or did you go in thinking it was going to be a one-shot and then you wanted to move on to the next project?
Okay, so the question was, did we walk into it thinking we were going to use the games
as a service model?
I actually covered this in a talk from a couple years ago, but in brief.
We knew we were going to Early Access, and we also didn't want to do the Early Access
version where it's like, here's a bunch of bug fixes, see you in six months, and maybe
we'll have some content, because I think people get very angry about that.
So, as soon as there was a response to it, we got our stuff together and leveraged, I
used to make MMOs, and so did Mike, the other co-founder of Monami Park.
We immediately leveraged basically our MMO experience.
Games as a Service was definitely taking off at that point, it was just a natural fit.
I got an amazing education at Three Rings as to how to make and run an online game,
so I had that experience.
So, definitely seek out things like that, learn, like I was saying, steal other people's
business practices.
There is things that WoW does that is applicable to your, perhaps, very, very small game.
And so, yeah, we immediately conformed our early access experience to be more games as
a service.
We...
had our patches that were completing early access as content updates and we made trailers for them and gave them key art
and we got people very excited about just normal early access updates.
But there was always a hero element to every patch.
So we would never, like I said, just do, here's some bug fixes and we
change the bridge model
and the backpack now in Slime Rancher looks a little bit different.
we had something that we can put on a piece of key art
that was exciting, ideally a character,
to get people excited about this content update.
And then really, it just sort of worked that way.
Because early access is launching your game, period.
I've said that before and stand by that.
So, thank you.
Thank you so much.
Hey, Nick.
Hi.
Thanks for the talk.
So on the topic of home, do you always
design for your personal sense of home,
or do you ever try to create a generic sense of home?
And if so, how do you go about finding that generic, broad
sense of home?
So the question is, do I design for my own personal taste
of home or a broad one?
I think it's a bit of both, which is probably not
what you were looking to hear.
But you can't avoid putting your own personal taste
and preferences into experiences.
But in terms of the generic sense of it,
I think there's some very easy things to do,
which is just basically sticking to the definition
that I put out there.
features that aren't punitive, relaxed play,
getting someone to stay for as long as they want to.
That is something that I really value,
is I really hate it in games
where it tells me mission complete.
I know this is definitely a personal preference,
but I don't want anyone telling me
when the experience is over.
I want to like...
Like, can destiny go up to orbit when I feel like it?
So for me, that's a huge part of my personal taste,
is just, it's freedom, it's not taking control away
from the player, I like that, that's my jam.
First of all, I'm going to thank you for the talk.
And I have a question regarding the topic of nurturing the game.
So I want to ask, what do you think is the optimal frequency of pushing out significant updates?
Because there's a risk that players do not like the new updates,
and there's a risk that the player has not fully digested the previous updates.
So what do you think is the optimal frequency to push this significant feature?
So the question is what is the appropriate cadence of content updates when you're nurturing your game?
So you've committed to long-term support. You're gonna release content updates over time
Again, I think that varies by game
One of the ways that you can figure that out is you look at your tail. So you release your game
even if you release it in early access,
you're gonna get the bump, and it's great to be up here.
And then eventually it goes down,
and if all you've decided to do is release your game
and walk away from it, now you're here.
You've exited the peak and you're in the valley
probably forever until you put your game on sale,
and then just like a roller coaster,
that bump is never gonna be as big as that first one.
That's actually how roller coasters work,
which is super cool, and I didn't know that
until relatively recently.
Anyway, so look at that and release your content update, see what it does to the bump.
And then you have to determine for yourself how deep and how wide do you want that valley
to be.
But if you've done an effective update, you can get a data point where you say, you know
what?
we must have filled that valley full of dirt in the last update because the valley is now
higher than the valley used to be and that's the critical bit of information. If what you did
makes your bottoming out higher than your previous bottoming out and looks like it's
going to stay that way, you have done something effective to build value into that game. If what
you get is an exact replica of what you had before, maybe that's fine because the peak
equals the effort at least that you put into it.
And the reason breaking even there is a victory
is because you've built now value into that game
for the new customer.
When we're working on Slime Rancher,
we think about what are our current players gonna want
and what's gonna get them to keep playing the game.
but we're constantly thinking about the newest customer.
And so sometimes we add a feature
where we realize our existing players
chew through it very quickly,
and it's because they only focused on doing that one thing,
and that's unfortunate.
But then other times, with that same example,
they are able to, a new player is able to experience that
and other things whenever they want.
So, yeah.
Okay, I'll just take one last question, is that okay?
Yeah.
Oh, OK.
I'm sorry.
I think we're wrapping up.
I'll take your question after.
So I'll hang outside if anyone else has any other questions.
Thanks again.