Hi, I'm Nils Sørensen. I'm the music composer and one of the game designers at Bedtime Digital Games,
an indie game company based in Denmark.
I recently did the sound effects, music and songs for the game Figment.
Figment is set in a world full of music, where the characters actually sing to each other, like in a stage musical.
I'm the plague, you fear of disease!
I come with wharf and rotten teeth!
These aisles are...
Also, the sound sources in the environment seamlessly blend with the background music,
such as trumpets that play along to the music and raindrops that fall on the beat.
Composing an interactive musical, Lessons Learned from Creating Figment,
will be a dive into the practical approaches used to create Figment's interactive soundtrack and musical sound effects.
The talk will also deal with how motifs and musical themes help tell the game's story and tie together the universe.
And how musical numbers help build characters through different song genres and lyrics.
If you are interested in all things music and games, come catch the talk on Thursday, 5.30pm.
See y'all!