Hi, everyone. Welcome to live chat with the creators of BugSnacks.
One of my favorite games that I've gotten a hold of recently.
So I'm super excited to be able to do this.
And we get to do Q&A from the audience later in the session.
I'm really excited about that as well.
Hi, my name is Adam Salzman.
I'm the co-founder and director here at Fingy.
I'm in our offices, which I'm the only one here
because we're all still in the middle of that thing.
We're a developer and publisher.
We've worked on games like Overland,
Night in the Woods, and Chicory.
And I've been on the GDC advisory board
for about 10 years or something now.
So I'm just pumped to be here and talk to these gentlemen.
The first of which is Kevin Zoon from Young Horses.
Hi, I'm Kevin Zoon.
Thanks for having me here.
As said, I'm the creative director at Young Horses
on Octodad Deadliest Catch and Bugsnax.
My primary responsibilities day to day include level design,
quest design and writing, and on rare lucky occasions, some small art.
I work pretty closely with my colleague, John, who will introduce himself now.
Hi, I'm John Murphy.
I am one of the co-founders and the studio head at Young Horses.
We're an independent studio based in Chicago.
And I'm here because for Bugsnax, I did a lot of the sort of like systems
and gameplay design, designing Bugsnax and the tools and traps
he used to capture them and feed them to your friends.
And this is great because this is,
I think what I wanted to talk about most for this game
is how the gameplay and the story are connected.
Because I think that's one of the things
that a lot of developers struggle with,
either coming from a story background,
how do we do gameplay stuff,
if we're coming from a gameplay background?
Oh no, how do we get a story in here?
And in Bugsnax, these things are married
in a way that's really beautiful and often disturbing.
So,
Also, yeah, another reminder, there's a questions tab down there in the Swapcard app in the chat section.
You can ask questions and chat moderators can help get those things queued up and we're going to save
time at the end of this to answer those questions, which I'm looking forward to very much.
So, but I wanted to start with a question kind of about the early days and about the earliest stages
of this project, which is a project that you guys have been working on for a very
pretty long time in game-making terms.
So Bugsnax in many ways, I think is a game
about people who are trying to solve
uncomfortable internal problems
with comfortable external solutions.
And it started out like most games,
which is a clone of Pokemon Snap,
but you can eat all the Pokemon.
So I was curious if you could share some of the early turning, like early turning points for the system design, and also some of the early kind of hooks for how story might be connected to those things.
And whoever wants to start is totally fine with me.
Zoom, why don't you start, you have, you've been looking back through the archives you have a little bit of a better memory of the progression of these various early prototypes.
That's true. I made it my mission early on to just keep a record of every like kind of major
phase of the project and I have builds on my computer of like old versions of Bugsnax.
And you're right Adam that the very beginning it was a Pokemon Snap like it was on rails.
You threw your traps out into the world to catch Bugsnax while being in no control of yourself.
And you would bring them back to the town.
which would be later named Snacksburg, in order to feed them to these grumpuses.
And John, you can speak more on the actual systems at play when that happened, but
even like from the earliest pitches of the game, we knew bug snacks were
parasites and that they were very bad for you and that you should not eat them.
And if I were going to summarize kind of a lot of the development of the narrative and systems behind the game, it would be knowing that bug snacks are bad for you and everyone wants them is kind of the driving force of all the themes in the game.
Yeah, so, and we needed to figure out like, kind of like what happened after you, you fed grumpuses like early prototypes.
We're kind of like you're in this food truck, you go back to this town, you feed bug snacks,
and then why what happens?
So one early prototype that didn't really answer the why, but was was fun was just you
feed a grumpus a bug snack, and their nose turns into a pickle or something.
It's like, okay, that's...
there's something fundamentally nice about that,
but we had not yet like tied that to any narrative stuff.
And then separate from that,
there was an early prototype where this town,
you're trying to get the town to sort of like,
the townsfolk to work together
and to sort of build up the town.
And so I'm kind of obsessed with both like,
personality and human interactions, and also with building simulations.
So we tried to do an early idea of, okay, the different bug snacks will change different aspects
of the grumps' personalities, and different personalities will get
get along differently. So it's like, oh, we're going to feed this this person a bunch of
bananas and this person a bunch of pickles, and then they will collaborate better to be able to,
I don't know, build the town hall.
John, I would love to chime in on the specifics of the personality system.
Oh, yes, please.
Yeah. Just to note that, like, at the time, we had decided that it would be best if
the personality traits had no bearing on the real world.
And so the personalities the grumpuses had that interacted were things like
gormless, flatulent, ticklish, just like nonsense.
And it's like, hey, ticklish people get along really well with gormless people.
That's how it works.
That sounds super fun to try to surface through UI in order to like engage the player.
That must have been a super smooth and, uh,
Oh yeah, everything was super transparent and everyone understood everything that was
happening in this rough prototype.
For anybody who's following along with the subtitles or other languages, we're being
profoundly sarcastic right now.
This is a nightmare scenario for a game developer.
One of those early prototypes we were talking about had a...
an indicator where if you clicked on an individual Grumpus node,
because they were just sort of running around as little circles,
it would show you their connection to every other Grumpus in town
and whether they disliked or liked them.
So it just opened a spider web of relationships
that was impossible to read.
Yeah, great, great, awesome.
So it sounds like, I think it's funny that you guys landed
on the idea of like...
the, they have snacks, they get physically transformed because I think even though the
personalities and simulations components didn't move forward for possibly in retrospect obvious
reasons, kind of the idea, I think it's funny that like coming from an initial idea of these
things are bad, it was the funny but kind of horrifying idea of physical transformation
that really stuck.
But then you had to compensate, I guess you had to find
other things to go.
And actually my original follow-up question
was pretty specifically like,
I think it's interesting that in a lot of ways,
the transformation of the bug snacks ended up being
something that was used narratively a lot
and actually isn't used in terms of giving people stats.
And I feel like that's the normal place
you would go with the design.
And it sounds like that is also where you started like,
oh, strawberries give you plus four.
gormless or something.
And so that's how their gameplay meaningful,
but in fact, it's actually,
it's really meaningful that they have a pickle for a nose.
Yeah, that is an interesting point that we had started
with a much more systematized understanding
of Bugsnax effect on the characters.
And one of the reasons that we moved away from it
in addition to it being kind of a snarl of UI
was also that...
like it felt very distant and manipulative to work on the
characters in such a statistical way. And in answering the
question, why you care about this, like, why do you care
about these creatures and what's happening to their town? It
gets harder to answer that question in a meaningful way
when you see them as objects that can be just sort of changed
to your liking. And so
almost on accident, because almost everything we do is on
accident, we find that it's more meaningful in this case, for a
narrative reason, to accept that the Bugsnax are not useful in a
mechanical way, if that makes sense, but that they have
meaning to them, in terms of their desires and their
personalities.
And especially as it evolves in the story that bug snacks are
not great for you. The fact that they're also useless to you is
important.
Right, right. And how early would you say that was so you've
got you've gotten from, okay, like, are you still in a food
truck? Are you still kind of Pokemon snapping around
collecting things at this point?
If you're talking about that version, with the like town
manipulation?
Yeah, or figuring out like, so there's a point where you
figured out like, oh, the player is a, this godlike scientist
who is single handedly transforming all the people in
the town in a cold and manipulative way. And actually,
we're not into that. I'm curious where systems are at at that
point, too.
So it, our idea back at the time, was that it was kind of a
There was a core loop where you would go out in your food truck to catch the bug
snacks in the Pokemon snap first person rails game,
and you would bring them back to the town to do your feeding
and your attempt to get them to cooperate.
We had also and John, feel free to chime in on this,
had a separate side system where you would peel bug snacks apart
in order to make them more edible
as like a physics toy that was deeply horrifying.
Yeah, so in addition to deciding that having the systemic manipulation be directed at the grumpuses
and how that made it harder to see them as characters that you care about, even though
we're capturing and feeding, even though the bug snacks are parasites and you're feeding them
to these grumpuses, the
the ripping them apart was also too far.
Yes, it definitely came off as sadistic and upsetting to do, even if that's like how
making food exists in this world. It didn't come off right.
Yeah, it seems like a kind of a fine line or a balancing act almost.
I feel like if you want to, like, I think I guess this is a
tricky thing that I'm going to be poking at throughout this. But
I think it's a it's a game about things that are kind of
uncomfortable, but you do want people to sit and play it and
have fun. So like, how do you walk that?
tightrope, I think is a tricky question. I mean, all the time
and especially here. So yeah, like devouring bug snacks,
having your body transformed in horrible and surprising ways.
Great. But peeling apart the bug snacks. Oh, that's, that's over
the line. I think that's an interesting balance. Feedback.
Was that just internal guidance? Was that I'm curious, like, how
you guys navigated some of that balance?
It was definitely internal at that point.
Because to answer like the when of this, like we spent about a good year,
the first year of the project building this particular version of Bugsnax.
And it was about at that year mark that we kind of took stock of what it was
and what we were dissatisfied with
and like started making major changes.
Like I don't think we had necessarily shown it to very many people
outside of ourselves at that point.
Not until it had become a lot more like the game it is today.
But like, for sure,
like finding that line was a part of that development process.
And, you know, at the time discovered that swallowing them whole, fine.
No one has a problem with this.
Right, right.
But there was a very interesting result from doing that also is
that we had not allowed the bug snacks to be cute. At the time,
particularly, they were actually very scary and upsetting
looking as well, because they were much more bug like back
then. And in part, that was like a reaction to the fact that
they were prepared like food.
that the cuter they are, the worse that system becomes to
interact with.
Right, you've got pressure there automatically kind of from I
assume, like from a player, but also as someone who would have
to sit and work on the game for a long time. It's like, oh,
you're where this is where you do the horrible thing to the
horrible creatures. We definitely can't make these
creatures that cute. But I guess like, so now, if you don't have
to peel them apart piece by piece, and like,
uh masticate them in detail um now that's kind of maybe that's opened some doors design-wise for
like oh we can actually we can do some other stuff with these creatures now yeah and and because you
know one of our goals is to make games that are you know both accessible and like charming having
a a banana with like realistic looking grasshopper legs that you're pulling off is
is uh it's not that that's fair um but john it was i think it was you who
insisted that they all have googly eyes oh yeah that was that was definitely uh
uh yeah that that was a thing that i uh felt strongly about that it was it was a
there was a bit of a fight uh it was a bit of a fight but it's retroactively a great choice
I of course agree.
The finding the little dish out in one of the in the little
laboratory on the beach that's just full of extra eyes really
ended up being for all the all the upsetting things that were
removed from this game. That one in I found very, very
upsetting. So I was curious to I think one of the things that
One of the things that ends up being, or was very memorable for me at least, about the
game is the...
I guess it was this quest system of going out and finding all the people and bringing them together to make a village.
It's not a preexisting place that you're just tweaking.
And so you're a year into the game.
There's been kind of a set plan about let's get it to a certain point
and then we'll maybe we'll evaluate, we'll see how's this
extremely realistic, horrifying insect food peeling game
where you manipulate the village.
Let's check in and see how that's going.
And then there's kind of like, okay,
parts of this are really cool.
Parts of this aren't working quite like we hoped.
Is that a point where you start thinking more
about who specifically is in the village?
Is that a point where you start thinking about,
okay, are we pulling the player off of rails
or does that come later still?
That all, yeah, that was around that time when we when we found
that the way it was wasn't really working. We made just a
series of very drastic changes to all the designs. One of the
biggest things that we tried to accomplish back then was that
the there was a deep separation between the part where you're in
town and the part where you're out hunting bug snacks. And we
wanted those to be more connected.
And so that kind of brought about like, um, also that we didn't like that the
game was on rails.
So the feedback was like, all right, so take it off the rails.
Let us wander these environments freely.
Uh, same premise, drawing traps out in order to catch the bugs next.
But, uh, that was actually surprisingly easy to do, uh, that change.
Well, yeah, I mean that, that opened up a lot of possibilities because it turns
out if you're trying to like.
lay down traps or do like elaborate uh interacting contraptions while you're moving away from them
it doesn't that doesn't really work right like like pokemon snap works because you're kind of
just doing one thing you're pointing and clicking uh so yeah that allowed us to and and we slowly
like
developed this goal of having the pacing of the game be like relatively slow and
I don't know how successful we were at this but there was always a push to have it be
observational and planning oriented rather than sort of like reactive and action-y.
Yeah, I feel like it did land in a place where there's there's
kind of a kind of hunter gatherer kind of like, stop and
wait for this thing to happen kind of vibe to it as opposed to
like, here's arcade shooter moments. But I guess I'm curious
where that impulse came from. Because I think for for game
designer that that feels like another risk to take on is like,
Oh, what if in parts of the game, you don't do anything?
So I, like, did that come from,
and obviously it's worked very well.
So I'm curious, did that come from a,
like, was that just an innate desire
for kind of an interactive experience type of thing?
Or was that sort of like a story thing?
Like, you know, you're,
we want people to be in a mindset
where they're stopping and looking around them
and that's useful for X, Y, and Z.
I think that one was definitely something I pushed for as far as like a more contemplative pace.
Because I like I at the time was pushing us in the direction toward mystery.
As far as like exploration and mystery as far as your kind of tone and expectation going into the game.
And I thought that contrary to the on the rails game, which was very twitchy and reactive,
that if you're allowed to explore freely, it would be good to be more deliberate about
the things you do.
I, one of the, I remember now one of my biggest desires back then, and I had the same desire
with the characters too, was I wanted individual bug snacks to matter to you.
um that I didn't want it to be that you were just scooping them up in big handfuls and like
didn't notice or care what was going in your bag like you were uh net fishing right um I wanted
you to like have to look at and care about bug snacks because we're gonna put a lot of effort
into these damn things so you better appreciate their designs. Yeah and there was always kind of
a uh I was
always like not intentionally pushing but I was always like kind of pushing against that as I was
designing and building the various like contraptions like there was an early
version where you you like kind of attached the different tools and traps to each other
so I was like oh you got your your strabby and it's in its hamster ball that you can control
and then you take like a cannon
that shoots nets and you attach it to the top and you've got this like wobbly net cannon
ball that you're rolling around and like shooting it at at bug snacks and it's like oh this is fun
but it it quickly makes all of the bug snacks kind of be the same and there's some of those
tools and traps end up being
sort of pacing. Another thing that was beneficial I think of going this route is that we're
coming from making Octodad which because of the sort of like weird controls it was kind
of a level playing field for people who like aren't familiar with just like standard gamer
controls. So the fact that we were coming from that to making more of like a
a real video game that like a first person has somewhat standard video game controls having it be
yeah more slower more forgiving in terms of timing and things like that hopefully
made it more accessible to to people who would otherwise be intimidated by the that sort of
that sort of game.
Yeah, that makes a lot of sense to me trying to keep the keep the floor low for, you know, people who want a mystery story experience, and there's this other activity that you can do, maybe that doesn't have to be exclusionary based on like how good you are at.
Bayonetta or something like that. That makes a ton of sense
to me. I really I think it's it's really marvelous that
there's this. I guess like, I'm curious. I've got a bunch more
stuff I want to ask about, but there's something in here about
taking like deliberate steps to have
this kind of marriage between the tone of the gameplay and the tone of the story where
you wanted there's like an increasing interest in telling a story that has a mystery at its heart
and having gameplay that also is a little bit more contemplative and observational.
and trying to deliberately have those things fit together.
And I'm curious if that was something
that kind of came about step-by-step,
or if that was sort of like a,
no, it's mystery story, mystery gameplay.
I don't want to be in a article
about ludonarrative dissonance or something.
Or is this, or was this really just an intuitive,
like, it's a game about looking for clues and, you know,
you're foraging, why not look for clues there too?
Great question, because like the gameplay story connection is hard to get right sometimes,
but I think similar to my feelings about the contemplation of the gameplay,
like my desire for the characters was I also wanted them to be small and specific.
where I wanted you to care deeply about individual characters.
And that was a problem I had with the more zoomed out,
like town management version of the game.
But and so in that sense, like kind of as I continue to ask the question,
why do you care about this?
Like. Kind of.
Answering it by getting deeper and deeper into the situation at hand.
But so to answer about where story and gameplay meet,
I think that a lot of my process is to write about the game
that you're playing.
And so like, because I think that so much of the way
the quests are designed, the way the narrative is designed
are ways to encourage you to go explore the island
and
to get you to look around the world by doing specific things and to go meet new characters.
And so typically, the moment to moment of the game, I am just kind of responding to what the
player wants to be doing at the time. And like, letting things unfold based on what you've just
done recently, if that makes sense.
Yeah, is that where you is that where you start to get this idea of like,
everybody who lives in the village has kind of like, been in a big tantrum, and
they've gone and locked themselves in their rooms, and you're trying to get
everybody to come down and have dinner. I, the player now suddenly is less than
like a mad scientist role and a little bit more in like, sort of a therapist
role or something. Is that when that started to come in?
It actually took a little bit longer for that.
Uh, like I think it was a couple of years later, John, let me know if that's right.
That, um, we didn't figure out until then that the player was a journalist.
Like for a long time, there was an open-ended question as to who you were
and why you were doing any of this.
No, I think, yeah, I think that's right.
But the, the, the idea of, I think as soon as you have, like, here's this like
strange world where.
these characters um or have sort of discovered it or it's like unfamiliar and there is is um
and there is this this mystery I think like it almost sort of like naturally follows
that uh the sort of like or maybe it doesn't naturally follow and it's just because
Jurassic Park is so formative and you know probably makes up like five percent of my brain
this like oh there's like this explorer if you're not the center and I don't know why but I think
it's just more okay so if you want to have it be a mystery you can't sort of be the central
hero because and so this this idea of like oh there's this intrepid explorer who you're
following and you're trying to figure out what happened in this in this place um I think that
that showed up pretty early. And then I think sort of connected to this is also some of those earlier
town management prototypes because one of the things that we looked at early on was
Viva Pinata, this sort of thing of like slowly building up a community and then like
new characters sort of wander in as it becomes a nicer place or more, you know,
gradually you build it up and it's more active.
And, you know, by the end, it's just like flourishing little community
that was that was there
from the beginning, even before there were like.
of bringing a community together much more compelling.
Yeah, it's funny. I've been thinking I've been I feel like I experienced the game a lot as kind of like a, a noir Pokemon thing. But in a lot of ways, it's almost like, if, like, it's like an Animal Crossing Godzilla movie or something, where, like, there's, you know, because you
always have a, you know, there's always a monster movie trope of like, you need to, there's needs to be a reason for somebody to be there.
And they're trying to find out what's going on because the viewer wants to find out what's going on.
And so you often, you so often have, you know, a junior scientist or a journalist or something in the picture.
But I feel like they very rarely end up stepping into the role of kind of like a therapist for a monster community that then like brings everybody together.
And I'm curious, like, how, at what point, it sounds like pretty early, there was a notion about, like, there's a goal of cooperation as opposed to, like, a goal of being, like, adversarial or, you know, kind of victorious.
And it was that just like a...
Is that a personal interest? Is that something that came from
previous games? Is that? Because I think that's something that's
kind of rare and a little bit non obvious in terms of, you
know, setting out to have a goal. Usually the goal is, you
know, have the most be the best, vanquish your foes, etc, etc.
That's fair. Because certainly, like in a creature collecting
game, especially it is about having them all and like beating
everyone.
But like, you know, this, uh, one of our primary desires as a studio is to, um,
make games that are unique and are not kind of relying on the existing tropes
too heavily, as far as like combat and platforming, we want to come up with.
Our own particular ways of doing things, which is a nightmare sometimes, but also.
I think produces unique results. And so like I just like as a company I think we trended away
from anything that involved fighting. And so like naturally Bugsnax was never going to involve
like a combat component with the snacks. And I think maybe that's part of it then.
And because like this idea that Bugsnax are
parasites and bad and you know there's also the even though we we never really
uh it took a while to to figure out the each grumpus has their own thing that their own special
void that bugsnax are trying to to fill um the like consumption isn't bad
racking up points, capturing and feeding everything being like not that I feel like that's just like a
there's some sort of intuitive understanding maybe just on our team in general that like oh yeah it's
like yeah I don't know I think it's it's like it's it's uh common knowledge enough that there's
something wrong with focusing on
just mindless consumption, that we're not going to like do something that doesn't examine that, I guess.
Yeah, I guess to me, it's that we.
Like just for early on, uh, looking at the premise of our own story and thinking
about the implications of it.
Like, even if we didn't set out necessarily with that theme in mind, we
looked at it and said, that's the theme of that already.
Like, and we would, you know, it would be, uh, unwise of us not to
explore that aspect of it.
The parts that are kind of dark and upsetting about needing to catch them all.
Yeah, I think I think also the moving when the emphasis is on
we can't, we're not going to treat the grumpuses like, like
robots that we're manipulating, and we don't want to make it all
about. I mean, it's still there, but the all about catching them
all, then that sort of leads us to, okay, I guess this is about
the grumpuses.
and their actual stories.
So I think it's kind of almost like a process of elimination
of removing some of these things that didn't work
until we ended up on the focus that did work.
Yeah, there's almost like a,
once you've ruled out everything that's impossible,
whatever's left, no matter how improbable,
that's what you have to go with or something.
That's a good process.
It does sound scary to me as a game developer also.
But I'm really glad that you guys stuck with it.
One thing I wanted to touch on before, well, a couple more
things, I guess.
And don't forget, for anybody who's tuning in,
feel free to leave questions for us
that we can hit up toward the end of this session.
But I was curious about also the
Because there are things, I guess we've been talking a lot about like all the ways that
Bugsnax is like kind of breaking the mold or doing something unconventional within games,
but there's a lot of things that I think are very conventional but are still very effective,
like the idea that you get upgrades and new equipment that help you explore the world.
But I think those things ended up also being kind of connected to the story and to the characters
and to especially this kind of like sort of,
a tantrum based diaspora, the characters across the island.
But I think it's, I think it kind of like ties it together.
And yeah, I was curious if there were anything
about this process of like, oh, we're gonna,
we're gonna sprinkle these people.
It's the people around the island
and you're gonna go find them
and they're gonna be focal to how you explore these regions.
And then we're gonna connect,
and then we can connect kind of like conventional
markers of progress to those things.
Um, it was an interesting process and I know John and I talked about this the
other day that, um, kind of the way it all shook out was that we had developed.
900 bug snacks in isolation, the 13 characters, eight biomes and like six or seven traps and tools
all just kind of on their own. And then that process was looking at the map and then just
shuffling everything around like mad. Like we had a bunch of big meetings where we're like,
what bug snacks go on the beach? What makes the most sense?
Is it fruit? Is it all fruit? Like, what belongs in the mountain? What belongs in the desert?
What character would most want to live here? Like, what order do you want to get the tools
in by difficulty? And who makes the most sense to have it? Right? And it took us a long time
of moving things around and having very large disagreements about the kinds of foods that exist.
that we just kind of shook through this process of like,
all right, what kind of if we move all these pieces together
at the same time, what puzzle fits and what will kind of give
you the best, like sort of pathway through the game?
Yeah, we definitely didn't have any sort of like, genius game
designer master plan. Right.
Because we hadn't really built a systemic sort of game like this before,
I think the only way that we could have managed to do any of this was to
build all these little building blocks. And I think, yeah, so the two games that I was most
inspired by in doing the systems, the gameplay stuff, were
And it's funny that these are both like big AAA things that are impossible to achieve anything nearly like it,
but Horizon and Breath of the Wild.
So with Breath of the Wild being like, oh, this is amazing that this thing where all these,
you can do all these amazing creative things with these like little things that were clearly like built kind of in isolation.
Um...
So it was like both necessary and like the way that we're inspired to build things that it's like, okay, let's just build this, this, this particular bug stack, and then figure out where it goes like, oh, it's fun to have something that picks stuff up and brings it to its nest.
or it's like, oh, this is kind of nice to have a bug snack that burrows.
And you got to figure out how to get it out or a bug snack that's really fast
and you need some way to stop it.
And then back and forth between
going back and forth and sort of shaping the tools and the bug snacks and
against each other.
And then that felt like
a little bit separate from the character and the level design.
I think because that's.
I guess that because Zune was responsible for the story and the quests and the levels
and I was responsible more for the bug snacks and the tools,
there's like a little bit more separation between those two things.
But then within those, they were sort of cycling and influencing each other.
Yeah. And I can speak even a little bit more specifically on character placement
and how that kind of works dynamically that.
like oftentimes the quests were designed around the bug interactions that were going on inside
the level. Like I create a quest to be like, hey John made a really cool thing, I want to make a
quest where you have to do it, otherwise players won't look at it. But also when we place the
characters in the world based on where we think they would go, so much then of the story was
written around where they had ended up.
where like there are a lot of details that could have gone very differently if we had made a
different decision about where they went. So an example like a big example is like the fact that
Wambus and Triffany were put in different levels despite being married like because Wambus made
most sense in the garden grove because he's got his farm there and I thought it would be good
to introduce him early because he can teach you about sauce.
And that's like, we're like, you need to know about sauce as soon as possible.
It's extremely integral to the way the game is played.
So Wampus goes there to teach you about sauce.
Uh, Befica was there to teach you about the journal.
So they both needed to be in that level.
And we only ever wanted there to be two grumpuses introduced in a level at most.
So it's like, well, it can't be with his wife, but also Triffany cares
most about bones and skeletons.
She should be in the desert where the ruins are.
And then the story about the fact that they went to different areas because of their career differences is then written about that.
Right. Like the fact that we put them somewhere else.
I guess that's interesting. So there's a little bit of like, it
sounds like the there's a part of the process that I've heard
described as occasionally as like scatter and gather, where
it's like, okay, we're gonna go off, do a bunch of cool stuff,
and we're gonna bring it together and see what sticks,
see what doesn't. But also, it sounds like maybe there was a
certain amount of
I guess I think it's interesting because I think there's a lot of there's a lot of conventional wisdom about really digging into your story early and seriously to make sure that your story and your gameplay fit together.
But I think you ended up it sounds to me almost like you ended up in a scenario where you had like.
characters in story were almost like a pressure relief valve for the way that you needed to
spread out your gameplay elements in a way. You were able to have some like wiggle room, like,
oh, we've got, you know, we've left space, there's connections between the characters,
and those things are maybe malleable in a way that, you know, the systemic interactions might not be.
Yeah, I agree with that because it's my feeling right now in this moment that like,
oh, I'm confident enough in the way the characters were written that they could have been any,
you could have been introduced to them in any order and an interesting story would have happened.
And maybe it's my experience as like a role-playing game master that I am used to
improv-ing a story based on what the players do.
Right, right.
But where I feel like, Oh, I think the scenario and the setup are strong and
the details of it can go any given way.
Uh, we, cause like early on, we had the outline of the story about the big beats
about what would happen to the town over time.
Like we know they're going to come together and have a shitty party.
Uh, cause Phil was not good at this.
We know they're going to get together and like, they're going
to, they're going to see the monster.
But how that actually played out could have been very different if we had made different choices.
And I don't think I would have been dissatisfied with that.
That's really interesting. All right, so I'm gonna ask you guys to do a different GDC talk later
about this kind of dungeon master mindset to like making these kind of
Modular is very much the wrong word, I think, but these flexible elements that can be sequenced in
different ways and kind of remain kind of potent and interesting. Because that actually happens
structurally in this game also, like I think there's a deliberate kind of opening up toward
the end of the game where you start to be able to branch out and experience the stories kind of
in different orders a little bit too.
Yeah, it's basically like once we're done teaching you new tools is when the player is allowed to
just go wherever because you're like, oh, you've got everything you need, you should be okay to
explore now. Yeah, yeah. So before I turn over and start scooping up some questions from the
audience here, which we've got a bunch, my last question, I think, is kind of like,
Oh, how do you put this exactly? It's not exactly why bother. But
it's it's sort of a little bit that right, like on some level,
like, you know, an arcade game where you
you know, shoot critters and then feed them to people and there's like a town simulation like
that still totally sounds like a game to me but it also sounds like there was like a kind of like
an intuitive dissatisfaction with that as kind of like a creative undertaking for a group of people
and I was curious if y'all had any final thoughts on that.
piece of the project.
Because to me, from the outside at least,
that seems like something that's fundamental
to digging into something that has these ambitions
with a team the size that you have
and exploring the subject matter that it explores.
I can answer first if you want, John.
Yeah, go for it.
My feelings are that I think it could have worked as a game
and that we just weren't able to make it at the time.
Like it maybe it was too high scope for us.
Maybe there were too many unanswered questions at the time
where it wasn't exactly going in the direction we thought.
But I do agree that it
it could be a viable idea.
So maybe it was too, because it's funny, because I feel like where, where the game ended up is something that strikes me as very ambitious, but maybe the, what it was shaping up to be initially was even more ambitious in some ways.
That is accurate.
Right, because we were, you know, there, there've been these ideas floating around of like trying to make storytelling more dynamic and
uh improvisational right with like oh here's characters that maybe their personalities
aren't changed by what by what food bugs they eat but where like a character's attitude towards
or your interactions with other characters influence how they're going to
maybe haven't totally achieved yet. So like that, that like,
systemic sandboxy sort of sort of thing, like, could someday by
someone be accomplished in a way where those characters feel
real and, and, and compelling. But
We couldn't do it this time.
Well, I think to me it's such a funny way to describe it because I think you did end up with a game that it has these really strong, interesting systemic elements and you have these characters that are really believable and relatable and that's done really specifically through thoughtful combination of like traditional storytelling techniques and kind of traditional scatter and gather prototyping techniques.
And I just think it worked. I think it worked really well.
Oh, thank you.
I'm glad you guys stuck with it, even though it sounds kind of scary to me.
I guess that's how I always feel about games.
And I'm not going to draw any tenuous metaphors between like
not knowing the player's role in the game, why they were there
or why they were doing what they were doing for a long time.
And us as developers often sitting with our projects,
also not knowing who we are or what we're doing for a long time.
I mean, there were long periods.
of it's easy to just kind of be stuck meandering around not knowing like I definitely was lost
in for about a year in there uh trying you know like I'm fiddling with all these toys and trying
to massage them against each other but I don't know what I'm doing at all um and I think that
didn't mirror like figuring out who the player is and like really solidifying
was about uh directly at some point it kind of like shifted from the gameplay and system stuff
shaping and influencing the the the story and characters and it just slowly I guess as we got
to know and and care about the characters and like the the themes and story that we like had no idea
like it wasn't there at the beginning and as we got closer
to the end of development and things started to focus in it shifted over to to that and that made
it clearer.
Yeah, it's interesting because that's something that I feel like we see a lot on our side as as developers also is this
thinking like, because like, you're talking about this game like, oh, yeah, we knew up front, bug snacks, they're bugs,
they're snacks, secretly, they're bad. And it's all about, you know, how the characters deal with that. But like, and
that feels like knowing all the important things in a way.
And it's like, I feel like a lot of development often is figuring out,
oh, that was any, we didn't, that's nowhere near enough.
That's like, that's not enough to hang a thing off of.
That's not enough to make decisions about and like digging into it,
which I think you and the whole studio just did such a wonderful job of doing.
So we're under 10 minutes left.
We're actually technically under nine minutes left.
I want to get to some of the questions that came in from the audience.
Is this a good time to do that?
Sure, yeah.
Right.
So top voted question is specifically about the snacks.
What was the design philosophy behind the snacks?
Did you have rules for what could or couldn't be a snacks?
We talked about this a little tiny bit
at the start about how one thing the snacks can't be
is viscerally horrifying and then something
that you physically.
tear apart with your hands as a player, but were there other guidelines that settled into place over the course of development?
Well, I know at one point we had a spreadsheet where we were like
trying to get, we wanted a large variety of foods. We also wanted to like represent a lot of different
bug, you know,
very loose definition of bugs, so insects and other, you know, other arthropods, basically.
And sometimes just invertebrates.
And I feel like there's one other dimension that we are trying to balance other than food and
and snack. I mean on top of that there's like oh we need sometimes like oh we just need a care
we need a bug that flies in this level and we don't know what we know the biome and we know
the behavior like what what food what bug.
I'll also add one of our guidelines for what doesn't count as a snack,
because we have many things that shouldn't be snacks but are,
but the real and true limit was it cannot just be an animal carcass.
Oh, sure.
Like, well, because there were a couple times where like, oh, like a baked salmon.
It's like, no, don't just make it a fish.
Right, right. Like, like, because if it's already a different animal and you can see
that it's an animal, how is it also a bug? That was kind of the question.
Yeah, I feel like like, anytime it comes close, like I have fun
memories of some of the sometimes the endgame script sort
of like engaging with that, like Ribble Pete, I think has a
little bit of special dialogue about like, oh, these bones
aren't crunchy like bones at all. And which again, deeply
disturbing observation to me.
Soft all the way through.
Yeah, that's horrible.
I love to sprinkle the underlying horror of the world into just random dialogue.
Yeah, we we, you know, as as like
fun and accessible as we want the game to be,
we got to maintain that a little bit of that horror edge.
I think it ends up being it's I think it ends up being one of the things
that makes the the basic moment to moment gameplay feel a little bit tense
sometimes, but I think it also ended up being great building blocks
for the ending of the game, which we could do a whole separate.
one hour session about probably.
But I want to move on to next question.
This question is also from Megan Tankersley,
which is, was the size of the island driven by scope?
You have a lot of the basic biomes there.
And also, were there environments
that you really wanted to include but weren't able to?
You talked a little bit about this
being kind of a scatter and gather, like go off
and.
make some environments and we'll staple them together later kind of approach. But yeah,
if you wanted to get into that a little bit more, that would be great.
Yeah, I feel like we just didn't we just sort of pick eight as the number of levels?
You're like two levels per biome was our thought.
Yeah, and one thing that comes to mind is that we
tried to do like or thought about doing twists on the sort of standard biomes it's like oh we're
gonna do like a black sand beach instead of a regular beach but tried a few different versions
of that and it's like this just it doesn't look right. Yeah it just looks like dirt. Yeah so we
eventually you know we're doing enough weird stuff that this is one of
let's not try to reinvent the wheel with this that goes for like UI and a bunch of other things too
but but um for the the level the biomes are like let's just stick with the classics.
We could do lava level we can do ice level it's fine.
Uh yeah that's interesting I think the um I know uh I I'm just remembering several
several discussions that we've had um on our design teams about like where
how, how fun is it for because you can make something different
for the sake of being different, you can make something different
because you want to because you've already seen it a lot of
times in games, but like, is it actually fun for it to be
different? Is it actually fun for it to be stink? Like, is
that part of the fun of going to the area is? Well, I've never
seen this kind of beach before. And is that done through the
color of the sand? Or is that done through this beach is
populated by terrifying food parasites with very cute eyes?
And the part of the question about the size of the island,
I think that kind of comes from the thing
that Zune was talking about earlier
about wanting to care about the bug snacks
and not just have it be you're scooping up
a ton of bug snacks.
Like my MMO poisoned brain always wanted everything
to be bigger and just way more bug snacks.
But like, there's like a cozy sort of,
familiar with this kind of comfortable, in some ways,
size place that I think ended up fitting
the tone of the game better,
as well as supporting that feeling of like,
oh, there's only a couple of this bug snack
in this world at any given time,
and they feel a little bit more special,
and then the size of the space just...
Yeah.
And part of that related to that kind of the sizes that I tended to go with were built around the fact that Bugsnax are very small, like a big Horizon Zero Dawn giant open world makes sense when your monsters are the size that they are.
But for us, because Bugsnax is so little, and you need to be able to like watch and catch them, like if the environment is turbo huge, like they get lost in it.
And we don't have the optimization to put 100 of them in a jungle and be okay.
But yeah, so small and dense, I think, was the guiding line on that.
I feel like it works. One of the reasons I think it works so well, too, is you have this,
you want to...
all for all the reasons you were talking about before wanting to put the player in
a in scenarios where they can wait and watch and grab something kind of implies
in a lot probably not. For me, it wouldn't have been obvious. But I feel
like in retrospect, it sort of implies like, oh, you need to be able to know
where to go do that. You need to feel confident that you can like, go up here
up the ramp across the thing.
past this like very, what appears to me to be like a really carefully placed landmark,
over to this area because I know this is where they're going to be and I can hang out here and I can wait and watch and I can do, you know, the main thing that I do.
We've got just one minute left. So this is a bit of a.
That is not enough time to address this very good question but did you have a favorite villager, in terms of getting to make them and find out who they were.
Yeah, that's well and also I guess just in general, how did you feel about how players reacted to the characters that live in the in the village?
The answer is, yes, I do have a favorite. Well, I guess there's a difference between favorite to write and favorite to like understand and explore. Because my favorite character to write is Chandler. Because I could just
Chandler is my favorite character just because I identify with
Maybe you borrowed some of John's personality traits.
But to explore, I feel like I had a really interesting time.
I don't know, I had an interesting time exploring all
of them. That's what I that's what I liked about that process.
So I can't really pick one of them for the exploration. But
wait, what was the second half of that question?
It was how did you feel about players' reactions, but we're also out of time.
So if you have a one-word answer, that'll be great.
Thumbs up, thumbs down.
Surprised mostly.
Awesome.
Anything, John?
No, I'm good.
Thank you both so much. I think we're gonna wrap it up here. We
went only a tiny bit over time, which for me is a effing miracle.
Thanks, y'all for tuning in and listening to us chatter about
this game. If you haven't gotten to spend time with it yet
somehow. Apologies for spoilers and I strongly encourage you to
go check it out. It's beautiful. And I think I'm gonna wrap it up
right there. Thank you.
Thanks. Thank you.