Hi, everybody.
My name is Brandon Sheffield.
I kind of helped coordinate this panel and bring it here.
So I'm glad you're all here to see this super rare opportunity
because these guys aren't usually
the ones talking about Sonic.
And it's really great to hear their perspective
on the beginnings of this series that has sold millions
and is one of the biggest franchises in the world.
and how this started from nothing to become the giant monolith that it is today.
So they're going to do their own intros, but we have Yasuhara-san,
who did all the maps and game design,
and we have Oshima-san, who did all of the visual designs and other things.
So after this, after they go through their sessions,
I'll ask them a couple of...
questions and we'll have a little fun treat at the end of it and then we'll open up the floor a little bit.
And I know that a lot of people are probably going to want to get signatures and things like that.
We're probably going to have to take that outside to the wrap-up room.
I'm just going to let you know that in advance.
And so let's just go ahead and get started Yasuhara-san.
Oh, okay.
Wow, thank you for coming.
So I'm really glad to have such kind of the very rare
opportunity to share our experiences to make
the characters, the game characters.
So thank you for coming.
So I appreciate it.
And first of all, so this one.
OK.
So my name is Hirokazu Yasuhara.
I've worked on the game industry more than 30 years.
Oh, I'm speaking English.
I should speak Japanese.
Sorry.
I'll speak Japanese.
It doesn't matter.
OK, next.
Mr. Oshima.
I'm Oshima.
Hi, everyone. I'm Oshima.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
So today's session, we're going to have to sort of stick to these three big topics, but I promise there's a lot to cover.
So, the beginnings and the origins of Sonic, anecdotes about the game, and of course, the result, what happened once we created Sonic.
Okay, let's start.
So, the beginnings.
Well, in the early 1990s,
Sega was, well,
So as you can see here, in 1990, Sega wanted a next generation character that could stand
up to the NES and Mario.
We were not able to compete in the 8-bit console consumer market with it, so we had to come
up with something.
YUKKE HIRAHARA But I think it's fair to say that Sega did
not value characters and their worth very highly in terms of how marketable they could
be.
Instead, they kind of treated characters as something that was created, used, and then disposed.
So the thinking was sort of shifting a little bit.
The company was wanting something that could be representative of the company.
Let it be iconic and have a longer sort of lifespan.
And so then the question is, why a hedgehog then?
So a character that can deal damage by curling up like a ball.
roll around at a very fast pace.
Yeah, as you can see at the very bottom,
old guy with a mustache, the one that became the Eggman, that was even one of
the ideas as well.
So people from the company
made a guy who had a mustache,
and hedgehogs, and also a character with a dog.
I was going to New York to play,
and I took a poll at Central Park with a placard.
And the hedgehog was the most popular.
And the second place was the bearded old man.
So, I thought, this is just a joke.
I think the fact that they chose Sonic, regardless of race, was a big factor.
So there's actually a really, I don't know, a nostalgic story or episode here.
I planned a trip to New York while this discussion was going on internally.
And so the company and we were talking and they said,
you know what, we definitely want to see something
like an old guy with a mustache as an idea.
We also want to see something that's sort of spiky,
a hedgehog or even a porcupine.
And then we also want to see a dog-like or dog character.
And so I drew these on a board
and I am in the middle of Central Park.
This is a true story.
And I'm showing people these three boards randomly,
taking a survey.
And the result was is that the hedgehog
was the most popular,
people really pointed at it and liked it.
Second was actually Eggman.
And then third was the dog.
And so I was like, wow, this is a...
you know, kind of surprising or a pleasant surprise.
And so I was asking myself, I wonder why it is?
And the conclusion to me, without, you know, having nailed like one single
answer, to me what was more convincing was that by a lot of people
choosing the hedgehog, that meant that it will transcend race and just different
types of
people, gender, everything. And so I brought back that result with me and reported it back to the company.
Yes, that's right.
So, speaking of character design,
I've always thought that good characters are made with simple lines.
So as you can see here, character composed of lines so simple you could draw it as part of a sing-along song, like when we had the song playing.
You know, we feel like a great character can be easily sort of sketched or drawn with just a simple sort of few lines here and there.
For example, if a child were to...
Is this my place?
Yes, go ahead.
Ok.
So, anyway, it goes like this.
So I think that was my part, so I'm going to take over from here.
But Yasuhara-san is always sort of like bugging me from the side like this,
and wanting to talk about these things, but let me talk a little bit about the process here.
I didn't want Sonic to be a character with a lot of individuality.
I was aiming for a character that was easy to relate to.
I just wanted to have a character that was easy to relate to,
and that had the blue hedgehog as its characteristic.
I didn't want to make a character that was easy to relate to,
and that was just like, wow, that's amazing.
I was really looking for a character that was easy to relate to.
So, as you can see here, we said we wanted a character kids could draw, just simple.
But first and foremost, in creating this character, we didn't want it to be so foreign and like
almost too pronounced where it was not familiar.
We wanted that level of familiarity and even a level of kind of comfort.
that you would be able to kind of have, you know, a quick sort of relationship,
like build a relationship, be an affectionate character for you. So the point was to make it
into a character that feels familiar. You've maybe seen a figure or a silhouette or someone
or a character or an animal that looks like what became Sonic. But there are points that
we wanted to focus on and those are the connected eyes.
and him being blue. And then obviously we thought okay we haven't seen anything like this.
And then we added the pupils and then balanced it in a way that felt right so that there was at
least some level of kind of uniqueness and individuality. So all throughout this process
Yasara-san is like no but it needs to be simple enough so that anyone can draw it. I want like
little kids to be able to mimic and draw our character.
So, because I was thinking that way, I was like, OK, I want it to be simple enough and
draw.
So you see, obviously, the end result on the left-hand side, but the simple drawing that
I drew looked like that.
So that's the version that I used with any of the sketches, if I was sort of, you know,
doing some map design or anything, that's the version of Sonic that I consistently used.
Watashi mo kono karakutÄ wo sugo kini tte, nihon no torisetsu ni kono karakutÄ o banban nosete imasu.
Yeah, it's cute, so I fell in love with it too.
And we didn't let it go to waste.
We used it a lot in the owner's manual, the instruction manual
that came in the Japanese version of the games.
Yes.
Next, let's talk about the characters.
To make it a SEGA character,
you have to know that it's SEGA the moment you see it.
So, although this statement here may sound very as a matter of fact,
but the biggest challenge for us, because we didn't have those characters that had a long lifespan,
the challenge was that we needed to overcome, you know,
what needs to be done to create a character that represents Sega, the company, the brand.
We needed a character that could represent all of Sega.
So this character really had to kind of carry the entire weight on its shoulder and say,
okay, yes, I am Sega, like I can define what Sega is by seeing this character.
YUSUKE USTUNOMIYA What I mean by that is, for example, why is Sonic blue?
For me, it's because the Sega logo is blue.
Again, as a matter of fact, but we didn't have to really...
take a look at any other colors. Why is Sonic blue? Because that was Sega's brand color.
And then here we have listed some of the merits of having a fictional animal character.
as the character that represents the brand.
There's always some, you know, there's not always
pluses and sort of upsides, but we found a few that made sense for us here.
The moment you see it, anyone can tell.
And to promote it, even if you don't know the company, you know the character.
Yeah, and so we wanted, like I said earlier, there needs to be a little bit of that unique
originality, but still be somewhat familiar.
I think the important thing for us was that it represented the company, and even if someone
didn't remember the company name, that they would quickly associate the character with
that company.
And then another factor was that we can turn this character basically into a business of its own.
So for example, merchandise, etc.
So there were three sort of pillars that we went by in coming up with
what is in line with Sega's, what we call, high concepts.
So those three are here, that it's cool, that it has a kind of challenger spirit,
and that there's history or background to the character.
We created a mind map, and the image of Sega came up with a lot of keywords.
And so as you can see here, we call it a mind map of Sega.
All these key words that sort of express or describe
our brand values and philosophies.
And so obviously, we picked the right word that's in red,
cool.
And based on that, we went to work.
And, you know, cool is a nice word, but how do you define cool?
Like, everyone's definition of cool could be pretty different.
Cool is not about shape or appearance.
It's about attitude.
So cool can be something that is more on the surface, visual, visually sort of I guess
expressive or expressing or just cool character design.
But that wasn't the cool that we were looking for.
And so there were all these factors on the right hand side.
It was more about the attitude of coolness and bringing that somehow into the character
design.
So another thing that we, in addition to this, is that a substantive sort of coolness, it
says here is that I wanted it to be
what would you call it, that you wouldn't be, I guess, sort of afraid or sort of fearful,
or it wouldn't kind of lose its coolness. And so when it's looking at you, or when the fans
or the users are looking at the facial expression of Sonic, that it would be kind of, you know,
have a stare or like a cool attitude.
That's a trademark. So that's something that I really wanted to show through its kind of stare, I guess.
So I wanted the characteristic of Sonic to really come out or stand out from that sort of attitude that we were trying to create.
The second one is that Sega is a challenger or has that challenger spirit.
At that time, when Q10 was first announced,
people started to say that eco-boom, ecology and the environment are important.
So there's, I guess, some elements and atmosphere, as it says here, that was kind of happening in the early 90s.
And, yeah, not just restricted to our industry or tech or software, but even in the worlds of fashion and kind of like eco-friendly,
and eco-friendly, environmentally sort of like, I guess, conscious sort of fields of businesses,
there was all this movement going on.
So how that's, I guess, tied back into what we were doing as game companies and game creators,
it was.
I can say that it was kind of an era where we began to think about our environment a little bit more.
And that sort of idea, as a result, was kind of rooted into this slide you see here.
So in our game world, we use the idea of nature versus environmental development.
And the third element is that we talked about we wanted to have the character to have its
own history or background.
For us, this kind of history is not in the original character, so we had to do something.
So if you look at these other, I guess, series or very well-known character sets or families,
you know, these characters have their own world, they have their own story, they have
their own background.
In the meantime, we don't have anything, we're just trying to come up with a character here.
So we thought about having or giving the character its own history.
On the other hand, as a company, there was history.
Sega was a company that imported American jukeboxes and pinball machines.
And while it may not be a direct connection from what I just said, there is an element
of American culture and importing parts of these businesses, and so that led to Oshima-san's
interest that he had.
at that time, airplane nose art, emblems and leather jackets.
So then we used that as a base for coming up with this story and trying to develop a
convincing enough or a colorful enough kind of story as to how we can land this character to
have this story.
that's connected to something that Oshima-san is really into.
And then that's when I came in and actually wrote the story for him.
At first, it was me.
No, no, no.
I didn't write it by myself.
Of course not.
So what I wrote is something like this.
There was a pilot named Harinezumi, and he was riding a nose art with a picture of a hedgehog.
His wife drew a picture of a hedgehog.
He was wearing a jacket with a hedgehog character embroidered on it.
So I don't think I need to translate it, but this is basically the gist of the story that
I came up with, and the slide earlier was really like put into an actual like scenario
form to make it legit before presenting it to the company.
Here it is.
So yeah, Sonic, for one, the story in there is that it's connected to this background story
of the author. The premise is that she actually wrote the story that you see in Sonic 1.
So it's all kind of connected.
So this, yeah, this was drawn by Oshima-san.
It brings back a lot of memories for us.
And that's why, I think now that you know a little bit about the story that we wrote,
for coming up with Sonic, the emblem on this leather jacket or the flight jacket,
it really goes well with the story that we developed and I think you can, you know,
instantly sort of recognize that feel as well.
This is exactly the art or the illustration that I drew at that time.
as is.
So, yeah, we're going to talk a little bit about the game now.
Yeah, with the new technology, obviously we were moving on to 16-bit games.
Yeah.
And what that allowed us to do, not just us, but the generation at that time, it pushed
us into so many different directions.
as you see here, the smoother geography,
tricks to convey the feeling of speed,
much faster sensation of speed,
and then lots of larger objects and moving objects.
This is not something that anyone can do,
but a genius programmer called Yuji Naka
is doing it by creating a way to really hit the back of the hardware.
So we can now say looking back that that was the technology that became available, but it wasn't that
everyone, all the game developers at that time was able to really take full advantage of what was
about to become available. We truly think that Naka-san was front and center in trying to figure
out how can we best utilize the technology that we have now and try to get all this, try to extract.
the end result from the hardware that we have sitting right in front of us.
So I think it was a very special moment for us to see that really come to life.
So based on that, these are just some examples that we came up with.
It's like, now we can do this. Let's see what it looks like, how it feels like.
So these are just some examples that we brought.
from those days.
So we tried these out.
It was an iterative process, obviously,
but we wanted to see how far we can take it.
At the time, Mario was a game that you could practice and get better at.
Sonic was more like a Sega's experience game.
We wanted to make an amusement theme park.
The biggest difference that I can say, differentiating I guess factor between Mario and how you played
games based on Mario as a character versus Sonic, is that Mario had, or games that they
made were more of...
you play and play repeatedly and you get better. It was skill based but also exploring the world
world in that manner. Whereas with us it was almost like Sonic was taking you but also you
were in throwing an environment where it felt more of like an amusement park scenario. So you're
enjoying what is around you in the environment and Sonic is helping you sort of experience that.
So again, these are some design notes from back in the days.
It was a very simple kind of flow.
So first what I would do is I would have these rough quick sketches about level design.
and then I would share it with our programmer and our artist.
We would then discuss, you know, going back and forth, how we can do this, how we can
prioritize some of these ideas and concepts and make it work.
So I actually didn't really have like proper game design documents.
So the one with X's, just to prove that not every idea works or can be worked on right away,
the one with the X's on the right hand side, we wanted to, but we knew we just either couldn't
or it just wasn't possible at that time, so we were going to deprioritize them for a much later time.
Well, in the end, everything fit in and they had us use it.
But in the end, we were actually able to bring them back onto the table and make it work.
So here's another example, an actual sort of level map and how we drew them and assembled them.
So due to obviously the memory restrictions.
of the hardware, I can only use sets of 64 parts or panels for each of the zones,
and then I would build three unique levels with those parts.
But as you can see, you know, the blue frame part that says background,
I wouldn't be able to use all of it because of the part on top that you see there.
There you go, yeah, now highlighting the top level, the tunnel.
And then I would end up using two more for the tunnel.
And the enemy is the same.
Same with the enemy designs, they seem like just rough ideas, sketched, but it was a very similar process.
I would just make rough quick notes, and then draw these sketches, how they looked, how they act,
what kind of enemies, and then just have a discussion with the team.
He drew it for me.
Yes.
I will talk about the animation of the player.
I will draw with dots.
Before that, I will draw a lot of pictures like this on the sketchbook.
I have to make the movement in a small pattern.
I will draw it on the sketchbook.
So I'm going to talk just a little bit about the animations for the player character.
Pretty simple, but before reproducing my ideas using pixels, what I would do is,
in my sketchbook, I would draw these that you see here.
But...
knowing that the animations needed to work in a pretty sort of small volume,
I would just iterate and draw a lot up front before reproducing them in pixels.
I'm Eggman, but I'm not an animator.
So with Eggman or any of the really other non-player characters, it was the same situation or the same flow
I did not have any experience as an animator,
nor did I do any studies in animation.
So really I had to spend a lot of time watching anime
or watching film and kind of scrubbing back and forth
and seeing how it's done.
And so all of that learning,
I wanted to first lay it out in sketch form
before producing them and moving forward in pixels.
So these are some of the actual examples that I drew at that time.
So, this is the dancing, or dance animation, that I was really kind of committed and strongly
wanting to put in the game.
I thought it was a nailed thing, and sadly though, it didn't make it into the game.
It just didn't fit.
you know, capacity-wise into the game. So, unfortunately, we never got to see the dance animation.
The fabled dance animation that no one ever got to see in the game.
Sonic was made for the winter of 1991.
The reason for this is that SNES, Super Famicom,
was going to be released, so we decided to hit that.
Super NES was $199 with Mario,
and Genesis was $149 with Sonic.
So here we have really a high-level summary of some of the marketing efforts and campaigns
that were happening at that time.
I don't know if any of you in the audience remember 1991 in this manner.
Oh, you do? Oh, good. Small amount though, I think. But basically, yeah, the Super NES
was going for $199 with Super Mario World bundled in it, and then for Sega, it was bundled
with the Genesis and Sonic 1 was bundled at a $50 sort of lower price point. And so we
considered that was kind of like the holiday sales war of 1991.
So the result is... ... ... ... ... ...
... ... ... ... ... So all of our...this to us means that all of our...
blood, sweat, and tears, and everything that we put into building Sonic as a character, but really
putting Sega out there, having that brand recognition, and being able to beat
Nintendo, Super NES, and the Mario bundle meant a whole lot. It was something that we had hoped
and wished for and worked hard towards, and it actually happened.
Japanese interpretation So, here's a summary of our experience and
learnings, but I think they can be applied to a lot of different things.
The first thing is...
there's always going to be ways to compete with what you think are unbeatable opponents.
And the second one is making technology your ally.
I think new technology will be a very useful weapon for us to fight against the old generation.
And what I mean by that is, you know, anyone can go out and try to make use of new technology,
but more than that, I think it's a tool that can be used to sort of beat out an opponent
that had always had the number one position up until that point.
It's more difficult for companies or people in that position to make that change happen.
new technology kind of becomes a weapon or a tool for those who want to go up for that challenge.
And the third one is gathering allies, like getting a band together.
We created this game by talking to each other about a lot of things.
So, us, you know, we were a team, but individually we were very, I guess, opinionated and spoke our minds,
and those moments, you know, you're speaking about what your ideas are, but we came together as a band.
It was like a band, someone would play a phrase, and someone would add something to it,
and then we would work on it one after another.
So in a way we were individually having these solo performances or solo acts,
but once I projected my solo part, then someone else reacted to that, and then another person reacted to that.
And there's infinite sort of possibilities if you look at it that way.
Something that you can't imagine just by yourself will happen if you have other people come together.
that are kind of having similar tastes and ideas and minds.
So yeah, not just in games, but whatever you are pursuing or working on,
I would strongly encourage that you guys come together as a band,
start singing one phrase and then another person may step into it and add to that.
It'll be something that will result in an unimaginable sort of ideas and results.
Of course, Naka-san, but also the staff and the business,
I think Sonic was born thanks to the power of the staff.
I feel that it is important to bring together good friends
because the power of everyone is so great.
To add and maybe reiterate, you know, it's just us two speaking today, but obviously with Naka-san being a part of the team, it was, and not just Naka-san, other staff who made things happen, not just on the development side, also on the business and sort of sales side.
Because we all got together as one big team, one big band, I think the energy was exponentially sort of...
larger than what one person could have done or even a small amount of people could have done at that time.
So that energy and power that we had at that time was so strong and stronger than ever that we had
experienced before and I think that really helped to attain and actually achieve our goals.
That's it. Thank you.
That was great. You should follow them both on Twitter if you don't already.
They post a lot of good Sonic stuff. I'm gonna quickly get into some questions.
It was really hard not to jump in in the middle. So first, was there any sense that you were working in a dream team at the time?
We think of it now, but...
The Hime no Kyogen.
Yes, but,
Mr. Naka was the best,
the most,
the number one programmer in the department.
A genius programmer.
He was a genius programmer,
so my goal was to work with him.
So, in that sense,
when I teamed up with Mr. Naka,
So, I don't know if Dream Team is the label or name that I was even thinking of.
Rather than that way of thinking, you know, Naka-san at that time was already a genius
programmer.
He was basically our number one guy, an important figure at the company.
all this time my goal was to somehow figure out a way to work with him and to team up and if that
happens then I know that something really good will come out of it. So that's really the only
kind of thought and goal I had in mind at that time.
If you team up with Mr. Naka, you can gain strength within the club.
And not only do I get to work with Naka-san, but what comes with that structure is that
you have other talented people who will end up contributing or are already contributing
with what's going on in conjunction with what Naka-san is working on.
And that's where Yas Hara-san...
comes into kind of the picture for me because from a design point of view he was already doing
great work so it was a win-win for me I get to work with someone that I wanted to work with
all this time and then comes all these other talented people on the team.
At that time I was working with Mark Cerny.
He's a genius programmer, so I was totally satisfied.
You can't look down on him.
But I thought it was interesting and I wanted to make a character game.
So, hearing that is nice, but I was also working with someone who I considered another genius, which was Mark Cerny.
He popped in earlier a little bit.
He's on a whole different level, a whole other level.
So I thought I was already surrounded by all these geniuses.
And then I hear about Oshima-san being able to work with Naka-san.
So I actually wanted to kind of work more a little bit on the character design side of things.
So I guess the end result is that it was a really good team that came together at that time.
And how much did Yuji Naka's practice of getting the most out of the Mega Drive influence the game design and the game's creation?
He made everything for us.
He made everything, so he made anything we wanted.
It was like a dream.
We were able to work with a programmer like that.
So the truth is, is that he rarely said like he would take on any kind of ideas and wishes.
he'll be like, okay, I'll make that happen.
And that in itself was like a super ideal,
almost dreamlike scenario because he's like,
okay, I'll see what I can do and I'll make it happen.
So that was the environment that we were in at that time.
Little follow up to Oshima-san.
You once told me that when making Sega,
when making Sonic CD, during the time transitions,
they had to put in a loading screen.
but you wanted it originally to be continuous and you told me Naka-san could have done it.
I just want to...
I wanted to do it in a seamless way, but Naka-san definitely did it.
Right?
I can't say.
I'd rather not comment.
Okay.
If you read Gama Sutra, you will see that he did that.
Can you talk about the creation of the music for a bit?
I want to know how you got involved with discussions with
Masato Nakamura, who was from Dreams Come True,
a famous Japanese pop band. So I heard that he was just given static screenshots
of the game
and then he composed his music on keyboards and sent it in on a demo tape.
I've only met her once.
But just by looking at her, I feel that she's a child.
That's what I think, especially as a Japanese person.
But she's also very popular with women,
and I thought, she's definitely not a child.
I tried my best to explain that to her.
So the truth is, is that I only met Nakamura-san once this entire time, or as we were working
on this song and asking him to create the song.
There are a few things that I guess we were very careful of.
If we had just sent or shared an image of the character,
we feared that he would take it as more of a,
let's say like a child or a kid cartoon,
you know, a younger age demographic targeted game or IP.
So we wanted to make sure that that was not
the first impression that we gave or he took.
and that we wanted this character to appeal to a wider range of audience, even including
females and you know a higher age range, adult females. So that's one thing that we did for sure
and then also because he was part of Dreams Come True, which is a very popular Japanese band,
we had this kind of exchange or promise that by him working on
creating a song for Sonic that it wouldn't devalue the popularity of his band,
just because, oh, he's now out making songs for game characters or games.
So that was kind of the exchange that we had,
and that's kind of as far as my relationship or communication goes
in trying to convince him to work on a song.
Yes, he did compose it on a keyboard away from Sega and send it in on a cassette tape.
And then they interpreted it there into the FM synthesis.
And what was the process of creating the dot art in the game?
You had some specific programs and hardware?
Yes, the dot art.
The digitizer was in a wooden box about this size.
I would click it with a light pen.
And then I would zoom in and out using this monitor.
I think the action speaks louder than words.
But it was a touch screen, right?
Yeah, they called it a digitizer and it was like this pretty giant kind of box.
And so I would be basically clicking, touching here.
and then there was a monitor on the side, so I would have to kind of test check what is going on here,
looking at it, and then just one by one, it was a very tedious sort of process.
So here's a fun thing that we came up with for you.
The both of them are going to draw their...
They're going to draw their individual interpretations of Sonic right now.
Yeah.
I don't know if we can get a, I don't know, hands, but where do you think I start with?
Yeah, what part of the character do you think I start with?
I'll ask, do you think he starts with the head?
Or the shoes?
The body?
Or the eyes?
Well, eyes is right.
While he draws, I will ask Yasuhara-san,
can you quickly describe your...
the main points of your game design philosophy, because it has become so solid in recent years.
YUSUKE USTUNOMIYA So maybe I guess on a pretty high level,
but my game design philosophies, one of them is I'm constantly looking at things or I guess
triggered by things, what attracts our human maybe eyes or just humans in general. So,
you know, whether it's in just an everyday environment or moving objects, it's like,
what are we attracted to? What is appealing to us? That's what I'm always thinking of.
Yeah, he has a talk that you can see from Digital Dragons in Poland, where he really outlines...
Ah!
We should save this.
Yeah.
Save this, then you know.
Yeah, save that.
But you can watch his talk, and it goes through each step of his philosophy for game design
through a Unity tutorial that he made.
And it just starts from like, here's a bouncing thing.
Now make it red.
Now make it move.
Now change the physics.
So there are three bouncing things,
and they're doing something weird.
And if you drop something into the situation,
everything changes.
It's really like, it's great.
This pen is a little weird.
So now it's Yasuhara's turn to do it.
Let's see.
So in the meantime, I will ask Oshima-san.
Oshima-san?
Huh?
I don't have much time.
I've got to be quick.
Yay!
Yeah.
Oshima-san, which anime or animation were most influential on your animation creation?
It looks very Disney.
It's the one that influenced me the most.
Yeah, it's very Disney.
It's Disney, right?
Yasuhara-san, what is that?
What is it?
It's Lupin the Third.
Oh, Lupin the Third.
Yeah.
Lupin the Third.
That makes sense.
Yeah.
Good buddies.
Okay, we have time for like two questions maybe, so if you line up to those mics, we
can take them.
All right, you're first.
You stood right up.
Great panel, thank you very much for your time.
Real quick, what lessons did you take
from the mascot kind of characters
that came specifically from Sega, Alex Kidd and the like?
I can't imagine you're working in a vacuum
before coming forward and saying,
all right, we're trying essentially again.
And that might not have been your attitude
from where you're coming from,
but just curious about that part of the generation process.
Thank you.
I like Alex Kidd.
I was like a little, it was hard to hear.
So the question was, what influence did you take from
existing SEGA IP characters like Alex Kidd, if anything.
Yeah, the Flickies.
The Flickies are in Sonic, and they took some influence from that.
Yeah, they took some influence from that, but...
They're like, really, nothing in particular from the previous characters that Sega had at that time.
This was like really from scratch.
It was like a white, you know, board ready for us.
So far as I know, it was like, let's redefine Sega.
Right.
Okay, we'll go to this side.
Yeah.
Hello, I'll ask for the panel.
Just really quickly, how do you feel that while Sonic was popular worldwide, it completely exploded in America?
And
in Japan was popular but not as much. Do you feel that you may need it to, or looking back,
do you feel that you could change something or maybe you did something different?
I don't know. Basically, I made them for the United States.
I tried to make the taste similar to the American taste.
I watched cartoons.
To be honest, it was different from the Japanese taste.
So our target from the beginning was to actually create this character that would appeal to the
North American audience. So that was already part of the process. We weren't looking at
trying to appeal to the entire world. On top of that, I had mentioned in our presentation that
Oshima-san was very into like the airplane nose art, something that had a lot to do with
U.S.-based, American-based kind of culture at that time, or of that era.
I think it was natural for us to have come up with something that would appeal to the North American audience rather than the Japanese audience.
Thank you.
I cannot leave this room today without mentioning that I think the biggest, I guess, factor is that Sega of America,
I think the biggest factor is that Sega of America,
We're so confident in what we're about to do and what we're about to embark on.
And so the fact that they were they were they trusted us and believed in us and our work,
I think was something that kind of validated was validation for us.
But then they took that and really worked it, you know, into their strategy.
So that probably had a lot to do with how popular Sonic became out here.
Thank you.
Okay, so it's 4.30, we gotta wrap this up,
but thank you all so much for coming,
and we'll try to go to the wrap-up room.