Welcome everyone to the 1500 Slot Machines Walk Into a Bar
talk, Adventures in Quantity Over Quality.
A couple notes before we get started.
Please silence your phones.
Also, you may have heard that there is a.
event given next door by Microsoft with some servers that need some extreme cooling, so
it's extremely cold in here.
That's untrue.
We told them to turn the heat way down because the heat's going to get way up in this talk.
Am I right?
Yeah.
Yes.
So my name is Alex Schwartz and I founded and ran Alchemy Labs, the folks behind mobile games, Smuggle Truck, Jack Lumber, Discourse.
We also made Job Simulator and Rick and Morty VR.
We were acquired by Google a little over a year ago and I left recently to found an unannounced new venture.
And I am Zaiba.
I run Pop Cannibal, makers of such gems as Adult Swim's
Girls Like Robots, the IGF-nominated Elegy
for a Dead World, and Boat Building crowdfunding success
Make Sail, now in early access.
So let me first start off by, you
may have read the description.
You may have come to this talk thinking, what's going on here?
Let me tell you what we did.
In 2013, as a joke slash experiment, the two of us
built a robot.
that builds slot machine games, a lot of slot machine games.
And this robot went on a journey to automate
the process of creating, re-skinning, theming,
and launching those slot machines on the Android Google
Play Store.
We eventually created 1,500 slot machines.
Way beyond our expectations, we received over a million
installs of these slot machines and made actual money.
So, let's talk about this.
So, we are going to tell our tale today in four parts.
First, Alex is going to describe the seed of our discontent,
which blossomed into this enterprise.
Second, you will ride with us as we roll this snowball downhill,
collecting mass and speed.
Until third, we realize this may not be a joke.
And finally, we will enrich your lives with conclusions
that can only be arrived at by people
who have breathed the rarefied air
from heights such as we have achieved.
So let's go back to 2013.
Just a quick heads up.
If you're watching the slides during the talk,
at the bottom in the footer, every once in a while,
we'll have actual slot machines that were created and released
and downloaded with real stats displayed next to them.
So keep an eye out for those gems like 3D Puffin slots
with 42,000 downloads.
So 2013.
Here's a picture of Zybon and myself, just two indie game
developers with Hulk hands.
And we were working together in a co-working space,
making video games.
And at the time, we had actually just launched
premium mobile titles.
And we're kind of coming across subpar sales
and discontent with the whole market.
2013 was a different time.
And we felt like we were doing everything right based
on what we knew about the mobile market at that time,
everything within our power to succeed.
So by that, I mean we were hitting all these kind of like,
we're doing it right.
check boxes on mobile, we were working with big brand name publishers, which was Sega,
Adults and Games.
We were winning awards.
We were getting good reviews.
And none of that seemed to actually make a difference in making our money back and being
able to make enough money to make the next game.
So at this point, we're pretty much concluding that the mobile space is dying, at least for
premium games.
And we weren't feeling too happy about that,
and sharing that unhappiness with our other indie friends
and seeing that, hey, this is not really a great market.
And we were looking through the App Store
and realizing how kind of scummy and gross some parts of it
can really be.
And there's clones everywhere.
There's garbage reskins, low effort shovelware,
and casino phone bill.
I have no idea.
What is this gummy bear?
card game? I have no idea. Jackpots all around. And so we thought, you know, this garbage,
how do we do better? How do we do gross better? How do we hit rock bottom and find that spot?
So Global Game Jam was coming up and it was at MIT and we're feeling so burnt out on mobile
and we just thought, you know, let's just build something really, really out there.
So I did most of the tech on this project.
I'll admit to that.
So at this point, we want to make a terrible game.
I didn't know if I was capable of that,
but I was going to try really hard.
Then we need to clone it over and over.
So this involves pictures and sounds and assets.
And it just sounds exhausting.
And how even do slot machines work?
Nah.
Let's not bother with any of that.
Sorry.
There we go.
We just bought one off the asset store. $15.
So that's right.
Our whole talk, our whole enterprise,
is all based on a $15 game that we did not even make ourselves.
It was just this generic machine.
You pull the handle, you get noises and spinny things
and coins sometimes.
I don't know.
I don't actually really know much about how
these slot machines work.
Don't judge us too harshly, though,
because we did put in effort to make it our own.
We stuck advertising on it.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Playhaven adds to be specific, and Alex
will tell you later how they eventually felt about that.
So this is going great, but we only have one game.
And I needed infinite games, which
required further and deeper customization.
So we swap the name, curling slots becomes cantaloupe slots.
Curling stone becomes a cantaloupe.
Are you feeling that yet?
This is, OK, wait, there's more.
So we also added in an about blurb for every slot.
It's this flavor text.
It just really brings the feel of the theme to you.
In this example here, we have hair slots, which
Did you know hair is a protein filament?
These are practically educational games at this point.
And the piece de resistance.
Every slot gets a custom-themed song.
So we use text-to-speech for the vocals,
and then we deftly match that in with our fat beats.
Are you ready for this?
Let's do it.
["CANTALOUPE"]
Cantaloupe.
Oh.
So then we just swamped those assets about 1,000 times
by hand.
Of course not.
We wrote a Unity editor script that would just take one word,
and then it would use Google to download the text
to speech for our hot track.
It would go to Wikipedia to pull in a blurb for the about page.
Sometimes we'd end up with a disambiguation page
because it's like GDC also means General Dental
Council and other stuff.
I didn't really care because sacrifices to quality
weren't just made, they were sought after.
We use Google's image search API to find the images
until we hit a rate limit.
We use Bing's image API to find some images.
Thank you, Bing.
So at this point, we can just type themes into Unity,
and it pulls in all these images.
It makes the app, and this is amazing.
But that does not cover publishing these
in the Google Play Store.
The Google Play Store, it wants screenshots.
It has these check boxes and blurbs and more screenshots
and dropdowns.
And Google, you are asking too much of me.
Are you trying to ruin my entire day?
Oh, privacy policy, yeah.
So the screenshots and the icons are not a real problem.
We just go into Unity, we move the camera around,
we throw up a sassy frame.
Bam.
That's quality.
But for the actual Android developer page, enter Selenium.
So Selenium is this super potent web automation tool
that lets you record, customize, and play back
these web browser interactions.
So we connected that into our Unity editor script,
and we got it to open up Chrome, log in as our Google account,
create a new Android app, fill in all these text boxes,
screenshots, blurbs, more nasty, nasty checkboxes, upload the APK
and it's live.
So, at this point, we have reduced the gap between conceiving of a game and having it
live in the marketplace to typing in one word and pressing enter.
So, you might be wondering...
What?
Now what?
Well, some stats for you.
First two months, we launched 126 games, had 32,000 downloads.
Some old classics, such as Richard III slots.
71 downloads in the US, great.
Got the Harlem Shake slots.
2013, remember.
It was cool then.
Sure it was.
So you know.
This thing's chugging along.
We launched some games.
We had our fun.
So we did what any self-respecting game
developers did is we walked away and forgot about it.
And we actually came back many months later
after the holidays.
A lot of times app stores have kind of a bump
during the holidays.
We're like, oh, I wonder what happened.
And we saw the downloads went way up.
But then we checked our Playhaven ad network back end.
And, you know, we were surprised as you.
We first saw that in January and throughout the holidays,
we were making $210 a day on ads.
Not only that, we saw that the ECPM
for those interstitial ads was at $59.
And so, you know, I think we promptly Googled what is an
ECPM and that's way too high.
We also saw
And I'm, you know, I'm no scientist,
but 27% click through on the ad?
There's no way that humans click on ads
anywhere above somewhere around 1%.
So, we needed to step back and think,
what have we done?
What's happening here?
What the fuck is going on?
And after thinking for a bit,
we have to kind of step back and think about the basics.
What are video games, and why do people show ads in games?
So the typical mobile model for ads,
which I'll dub the retention model, is, as I see it,
you make something of a quality game for the intention
of having human beings have fun in said game
so that they will stay inside of the app.
And if they're playing for longer,
you could show them more ads, right?
And this is in one game.
Now.
What if you took this model and you turned it completely on its head?
Ladies and gentlemen, I present to you the signal-to-noise anti-retention model.
You have an obscenely low-quality game, thousands of them in fact,
that are found via hyper-specific keyword searches.
If you really love unicorns, we've got like nine slots for you. It's great.
Then you get the game and you're instantly bored, disappointed.
dismayed, disgusted.
And then, bam, we show you an ad.
But not just any ad, a perfect ad.
This ad looks so damn good.
The idea that a real game, a real game of quality
is just out of reach.
That with a single click, you could be onto.
Greener pastures.
The contrast in quality between where you are in this garbage pile
and where you could be is so high that of course you click.
You click to escape.
You click for a better future.
And maybe that's why our games are making a lot of money.
I don't know.
So, it's just a theory.
So clearly, you know, chugging along.
Thanks, Shutterstock.
The next thing is, well, clearly we have to put more time into this, obviously.
So next step, got to incorporate.
Signal to noise LLC, you're welcome.
We are the noise.
And yeah.
OK, so technically, what we had was good, but my life was not yet all just
champagne and three Musketeers bars.
I had two major problems.
One, we had to sit there and type in.
Theme after theme, wait for the process, type in another theme.
Imagine sitting at a computer for up to 20 minutes a day
just so you could publish a half a dozen games.
No.
Second problem, we discovered Google had a max 15 app a day
upload limit.
I mean, come on.
It's like they're not even trying
to support our workflow.
It's time to re-architect.
So I wrote a web service and a website, Middleman.
We call it The Goose.
Golden goose.
And it's a PHP MySQL server with this HTML front end,
and it takes keywords, and then it
lets me pick from several of Bing's finest images,
and I can tweak the blurb if I'm feeling artsy.
And it lets us build up a long queue.
We can just pile 100 different ideas into this.
Most importantly, I stole Unity's documentation style
sheets for this site, so at a distance,
my activities look very legit to my office mates.
Please note, there's only one language.
Yeah.
So we put these hundreds of apps into the goose,
and then back in Unity, it doesn't have to talk
to all these crazy different APIs,
it just talks to the goose.
It says, hey goose, give me an egg,
which describes one of these apps,
and then it builds its 15 of the day,
and now it publishes it,
and we can now do this from a web browser.
Anywhere in the world, we are just typing in our ideas
and willing these slots into the world.
But what I don't like is that I have to leave a Unity license open
in a machine running that's capable of building all these.
And it ties up my license, and I have other side hustles
that I need to be getting on with, and I'm not trying to break any terms of service.
So, the next idea is how do we free up Unity license?
We realize we only need Unity to build the slots, not to publish them.
So, we have the website where we just throw a hundred ideas in.
We go to Unity and then we just build hundreds of slot machines all at the same time,
but instead of publishing them, we just shove them back up into the goose.
And moving on to the next step.
we built a standalone game that does the publishing.
It says, hey, Goose, do you have anything that needs published?
It opens a Chrome, does its thing, and publishes.
So now any cheap computer can be a publishing terminal.
And so you can think of this very much like Steady at Home.
There's this central repository of important work
that any computer can now process
to advance the state of mankind.
What you're explicitly seeing here is that every time Marcus Phoenix from Gears of War gets hit in the head by an image from Bing,
a slot machine is born into the world.
So with this, we could keep a stream of 15 games a day being published as long as we had this queue of them ready to go in a garbage laptop waiting to do its bit.
On a good day, we did absolutely nothing.
So you might be wondering...
What resulted of this next adventure?
10 people still playing Lobster Slots.
I don't know why.
One year in, we had launched 750 games
with over 200,000 downloads across those games.
So a couple quick stats.
We've got bowling slots.
That's simple.
Simple bowling game with 8,000 downloads.
We've got Dolphin Slots, which is killing it.
17,000 downloads just for Dolphin Slots.
It's very America and Malaysia.
And we've got now hundreds of apps on the store.
We're bound to get some takedowns, or arbitrary
takedowns from Google, right?
First, we saw apparently side boob is no longer OK.
Which that image alone, if I were to show it to you
with no other context, no one would know that that is,
that's side boob.
Once you add the text, maybe.
We're starting to get bug reports from users in emails.
So that means that someone's so engaged
and so upset about their diaper slots having crashed
that they opened up Gmail, screenshotted,
sent it to us and had a whole thing about it.
We're getting user reviews back.
These are actual user reviews, I swear to you.
Why are people enjoying any of this?
I don't understand.
OK, some fair, fair content.
This person really wants to rate it lower than one star.
That's fine.
But this person really loves dolphins,
and they were very satisfied.
This person also loves dolphins.
And you know what?
I think we served them well.
So at this point.
the robots arrived.
And this is in the form of automated email outreach.
So let me clarify.
Our automated B2C casino app company
is now starting to attract automated B2B outreach.
So here's a good screenshot.
App Eggs was very interested in promoting 3D cabbage slots.
I could see why.
This baby's headed straight for the top.
But we're also getting a couple other pieces of outreach
from that company.
And, you know, we both run actual companies,
and we get a lot of spam,
and our bullshit detector's really high,
and a lot of, you could tell, like,
hey, they're not actually talking to me,
that's just a robot that said this.
And when I get those at the real company that I run,
I feel like, man, I don't deserve getting all this spam.
But here I kind of feel like
we deserved, absolutely deserved getting all this spam.
And, you know, that's fine.
OK, so third push.
Already on a good day, we are doing nothing.
But we still have to occasionally shovel keywords
back into the goose.
So it's time to optimize.
Question is, what makes great garbage?
Why are dolphin slots hot and hot tamales not?
Well, when we started making these slot machines,
we were just kind of randomly coming up with these themes
willy-nilly.
It's kind of like Kaiser Sosay.
We're looking around the room.
We're making microphone slots, handsome co-presenter slots,
beautiful audience slots, whatever we want.
We're just throwing them out there.
But it occurs to us that most people are probably
getting to our apps by searching for something
they actually wanted and just stumbling over us instead.
So how can we figure out what it is they're searching for so they are sidetracked by us more often?
Well, we couldn't find any actual search lists for the App Store, but there does exist Google Trends,
which is just a global list of what people are searching for on Google.
So here's a shot of Google Trends last week.
The stuff in red are sort of the problematic things.
It's a bit of a copyright.
landmine. So once you filter out all the celebrities and sex offenders and litigious institutions,
what you're left with are mostly current events, and often they're actually very weird current
events, which of course we used. This led to an early favorite of ours, deer antler
spray slots.
This was at the time, there was some sort of NFL doping scandal where people were
spraying themselves with deer antler derivatives. I don't know, I'm not a reporter,
I don't have a responsibility to actually carry this story to you, I just made the slot machine.
So this one has a particular spot in our hearts,
but surprisingly it actually failed to garner an audience.
If Google Trends isn't working for us, there's not enough of them, and people aren't into it,
what can we do to automate this more?
How can we think less?
Word lists.
So I downloaded several large lists of words.
And you may also have noticed that we have a bit of a formula to our slot.
So let me give you a tour of that.
First, 3D, because 3D is hot.
It's the future.
Also, it's really good for the alphabetical optimization.
It's right there on the top of your phone.
And then an adjective, any old adjective will do.
I have a very long list of them, and they're not all great.
And after that, we put in a subject.
Every country got a slot machine.
And slots, note it is, because with this audience,
there are some questions.
And free, so you know what an incredible value this is.
Then we made a button in the goose
where I could just click.
try again over and over, and it would just iterate through this,
shuffle them together, go through the APIs and stuff.
And this is how we came up with genius such as Viceroy Butterfly
and tremendous face pain slots.
I did love that one.
Which culminated in the creation of a masterpiece.
By far my favorite slot.
Maybe the greatest slot of our generation.
Something so specific that one pure soul out there
might see it and think, wow.
They really know me, they know my needs,
and they know my generation.
And I present to you, 3D inexperienced great horned owl
slots free.
I mean, I was training a great horned owl recently,
and I had some difficulty with their owl related drills.
And I thought, oh man, I should go to this slot for comfort.
But yeah, maybe it is slightly too specific or too targeted.
So at this point we thought, we need a professional.
We need to bring on a contractor who can help us decipher all this data and optimize.
Yeah, let's do it.
If you recall from our presentation, description on GDC,
we said that we involved an MIT statistician.
I regret to inform you that we forgot what university they were from and that was incorrect.
They were actually a Harvard psychology PhD.
I regret that small error.
So she came back to us with some real scientific looking data.
And I won't bore you with the statistics.
But I will call out one of my favorite parts
in the middle, which was that in the spirit of automation,
she employed Amazon Mechanical Turk
to do all the mundane tagging and sorting of the slots, which
for those who are not familiar, Mechanical Turk
is a farm of human beings who complete tasks
that robots cannot yet get to the level of automating, which
is just.
Perfect. Our consultant on her own without inquiring with us outsourced monotonous work
to essentially a human-robot farm so that we could better automate creating robots.
Anyway, the final slide of the presentation was the most important one. What are the takeaways?
What have we learned about all this data? We learned that sex is great, people hate
other people, and they hate objects, but
They love dogs, specifically dogs.
So you're welcome, everyone.
This is the hot, juicy data that you could use in your games
moving forward.
So yeah, we're giving it away for free, which is incredible.
We also, after seeing all this, are
wondering about all the inputs.
And there's so many things we could test against.
One thought was, what if we did a side experiment
to see and try to answer the question?
does quality actually play a role in all of this?
So we thought, let's just rewrite the entire slot
machine from scratch and make a really good slot machine
and see how it compares to our really bad slot machine.
But we clearly were not incentivized to do that.
So we used some of the money that
was coming in to outsource the entire process to Romania.
And you know what? We reached out and found a fine Romanian developer who...
Well, we reached out to him under a pseudonym, Ron,
and paid them hourly to mock up art, design, program a new slot machine temple from scratch.
You can see this looks very complicated. I have no idea what it does.
No idea.
Apparently you can bet on 15 separate lines,
and there's all these kinds of knobs and buttons that people who play slot machines like.
So we did that.
And it got built, and it's beautiful,
and it had audio and all these things.
And we never ended up launching it,
because we were too busy creating the low quality ones.
But I regret that part of the story.
So at this point, we have lots of questions and opportunities
of what to do next.
And what do you do at your company
when you need to make high-level decisions?
Company retreat.
So just like our original slot machine,
we did not set up this retreat ourselves,
we used somebody else's shit.
It was time, coincidentally, for the annual Indie Cabin.
So every year for almost a decade, East Coast Indies,
we pull in about 10 to 20 game developers in a cabin
in Vermont or New Hampshire and we work and play for a week.
So this particular cabin, we show up,
we have this growing awareness that we've kind of
been torching our friends with our hilarious slot stories
and how easy it is to make money for years now.
We came with a pile of booze, sort of as a bribe or apology to forgive our exuberance,
and as a stunning counterpoint to demonstrate our inability to stop celebrating ourselves,
we showed up wearing deer antler spray t-shirts.
By the way, we created one extra, and this is the last and final shirt that exists in the world for deer antler spray slots.
It's a medium. Raise your hand if you would like it, and we will throw it directly into that pile of hands somewhere.
Thank you.
Oh, yeah, we have the picture of that.
That's it.
For all you who didn't get one, this
is what you're missing out on.
It's really comfy, too.
All right, so at this point, we are literally
drunk on our own power here.
It was excellent.
I regret nothing.
But this is when a lot of the negatives and the opportunity
costs start to come into focus for us.
So let me paint a picture of this pivotal point.
So this cabin we've rented is actually
an off-season sex therapy retreat.
that was last rented by strong and vigorous people.
So Alex and I are in a room with beautiful tapestries
of barely abstracted genitalia and a shattered bed.
And we are there.
This is, you know, this is where you hold your business meetings.
We are there with a friend who is a perennial advisor
and investor in the indie sphere.
And he's telling us.
This really isn't a joke.
Looking at your growth curves and what's happening,
and if you actually paid more serious attention to this,
you could pull in real investors.
You could maybe sell your company, sell your data,
or just go further yourselves and maybe make piles of money,
but you'd have to take it seriously.
So we're looking down that road,
and the question is, are the people down that road still us?
Would this be our first steps
to wild success as a business person,
or?
Is it going to convince us to cross lines we maybe didn't want to cross and we become super villains?
Should we really go all in on this crap factory?
So this is the point at which a number of mounting issues and back-to-back kind of surprise issues
arose, all adding to the overall friction of this enterprise that we're trying to do on the side.
So keep in mind, first off, this is several hundred hours of work so far.
The entire enterprise is a fragile scaffolding with so many points of failure,
it's incredible and hard to even explain.
So the whole process end-to-end relied on so many...
external services, over a dozen, all remaining functional
every day for this to keep going.
There's servers, databases, text-to-speech,
the developer back end remaining consistent,
Bing, Wikipedia, Unity updates, ad network stuff.
In fact, if a new language or country
is added to Google Play, or a checkbox
gets moved 10 pixels to the right,
the entire thing falls apart.
And that's not to mention when Unity updates
and you need to fix things, and Android SDK updates
that are required for the Play Store.
hosting issues that come up.
And so, in addition to all of that pain,
there's now competing interests in our lives as developers
doing real things outside of the side hustle.
VR is just beginning to take off as the Oculus DK1 Kickstarter happened
and Alchemy was jumping on that and focusing there.
LG was getting some great attention, I believe.
My sensitive poetry writing game is in the experimental gameplay workshop.
I'm an artist.
And right around this time, this is all happening very, very
quickly after the advisor meeting,
is we were contacted by our ad provider, Playhaven.
And they said, hey, can we have a meeting?
And we were like, why are we so nervous about this?
Is it because we did something wrong?
Did we do something wrong?
We tried not to.
And so we had this call, and I'll describe it to you.
They said, we're seeing some.
Fairly erratic data coming from your side of the world.
You did not break any terms of service.
We'll be very clear.
We did not break any terms of service.
You're not doing anything wrong per se.
You're just inconvenient to us.
And they said we're not interested in continuing
to serve ads in your games, plural.
And also, by the way, you have the worst users somehow.
No one who comes from your apps wants to spend any money.
And I think there's another way to think about that,
which is you're welcome for segmenting your users so finely,
and you should be able to capitalize off of that.
But you know what?
Fine, we're off to ChartBoost immediately.
No worries.
And you know what?
That relationship turned out quite well.
We even received this little digital postcard from them
after a few months, so how sweet.
Thanks, ChartBoost.
At the same time, Google, anyone who's a Google developer
knows that you just get emails about the store
and what's changing and new terms of service updates.
And they send out these periodic emails.
And they seem to start kind of mentioning
some common topics, which are about repetitious apps
and duplicate content, and then specifically,
unique functionality being maintained within the ecosystem.
And so it sounds increasingly like.
They're talking directly to us.
Um...
And we're wondering, you know, okay,
we need to actually make that decision now
as, like, where are we going, what are we doing.
Uh, so you might be wondering...
what happened next.
Uh, this thing is
making real money.
Some.
There's some obvious issues to deal with,
but they're not insurmountable.
We could fix them.
It requires serious dedication,
pulling back from the main things that we're doing.
So what did we do?
We walked away again.
That was our big decision?
Yes.
Lazily stop touching the entire thing.
Inaction was absolutely the decision that we took.
And I think the weight and the responsibility
of all the things that we could not,
that we still could not automate away from ourselves.
was what ultimately drove us from not wanting to continue.
Don't get us wrong, don't get me wrong,
we left the keys in the car and the car running.
You know, we didn't shut it down,
we just let it die slowly over many years.
So, you know, we watched the empire slowly crumble
and just focused on making real video games.
But the enterprise lasted way longer
than we thought it would.
So when you log into Google Play Now,
It alerts you at the top, very helpfully, that, hey,
one of your apps needs attention.
That is the understatement of the century.
There it is, a ghost town, hundreds of apps all removed,
the ghost town of its previous grandeur.
Of course, installs dwindled over time down to zero.
But it lasted years past the mission it was constructed for,
much like some other proud robots out there.
And I think it's worth going over a couple fun facts
about the ashes of our empire.
First, the Middle East loves puffins.
Useful.
The US loves Obama 62 times more than Malaysia.
And India is super into sexy librarian slots.
We see you, India.
And so here we are, present day.
And I think it's worth reflecting on the journey
about what we built, why we built it,
and how it changed the world.
So clearly you're thinking,
well what's the legality of all this?
I will answer that.
We're always within the legal lines to our knowledge.
Our auto-generation algorithm did occasionally
stumble upon some trademarks.
Sure, if we ever got a takedown.
from Google, we would of course comply.
For example, the time that we stumbled upon someone
who had a very aggressive trademark for Bible slots.
You know, we received the takedown,
of course we removed it.
We want to let the Bible slots person continue on their way.
They worked hard for that.
Yeah. So if it's legal, sure.
But is it ethical?
Zaiba?
So first question, did we harm players?
We never took their money. That was a big line for us.
It's gambling. Some people have problems with that.
I'm not really educated in that area and I don't want to be involved in these problems.
We only took money from ad providers and I don't feel bad about that.
And in fact, I think that puts us a cut above a lot
of other slot machines.
And we're actually creating a safer place for players
to come and enjoy this kind of entertainment.
Similarly, we never took anybody's data.
Have you ever seen an app as low quality as ours
and felt safe that it's not stealing your data?
We were a real cut above in being a steward
of our players' money and privacy.
Of course, you saw we had quite a few good reviews.
Not all, but some people were happy with this.
We were bringing joy into the world.
And as a tangent, if you remember,
that is actually against our business model.
If we really wanted to go further,
we would have brought more disgust into the world.
But the virtuous beings we are could not
bring ourselves to do that, and we couldn't help but make
people happy.
Did we harm game developers?
I love you all, I wouldn't want to do that to you.
So we had the same tools as everybody else.
We didn't have some secret back end.
We just used them a little differently, possibly more
aggressively than the rest of you.
But we generally played by the same rules.
We drove the speed of traffic.
If you look particularly at the Android store,
it is a pile of unlicensed Star Wars things
and weird clones of your games.
We did none of that.
And as Alex alluded to earlier, you know, when Playhaven dropped us
because they didn't like our users coming out of there,
what we had done is we had taken chaos and created order.
We had filtered people through into a group.
And if they couldn't figure out how to use that knowledge we presented them,
that's their loss.
But I say we made this ecosystem better by doing that.
Did we harm platform holders?
We never knowingly broke the terms of service.
We didn't argue any of the takedowns.
I will still contend that Tasteful Sideboob Slots
deserves its shining moment in the sun,
but I'm not going to engage in that email thread
with anybody at Google.
They don't have to worry about that.
And I think we exposed some insufficiencies, generally.
when terms of service have to change,
it's because some sort of catastrophe happened.
Somebody really gamed something, did something bad,
there was a leak.
But we were, I think, a really gentle partner
in this period of discovery about what they did
and did not want on the store.
Kind of like, if you have a rash on your arm,
a doctor may draw a line around it
just so you can see if it's growing
outside of that line or not.
But we were respectful of that line.
We were like a very manageable rash
that just.
It helps to remind you that you should wash your arms more often.
Here's a shot of what our actual impact looked like on the store
on an average day when we were operating roughly at capacity.
So here we are, we're all the way down on like page 6 of specifically top new free casino.
Everything outlined in red is ours.
And yeah, if you go down to 7, 8, 9, 10, they're probably very similar.
There's a lot of us there, but we're not right at the top.
And I mean, imagine we were not on this page at all.
Number one fan.
Marijuana light might have been half a page higher and I hope they can forgive us
But I don't think we did too much damage there. So what I'm really getting at is
Every hour we spent on this was an hour
We didn't spend competing with the rest of you for a feature on Android or Apple or Steam
We didn't spend our runway funding on a four-year passion project that nobody but us wants,
underpaying contractors and promising rev share,
filling every subreddit and Twitter thread with our GIFs,
and elbowing to get cozy with platform holders.
We just quietly put out crap.
If...
If you spend four years making a game that nobody wants,
and I spend four seconds,
who squandered more of their precious life?
Who used more of the world's resources
and who took everybody's attention and time?
We are the good guys.
You all are animals.
Yeah.
Okay, so...
That last bit was half disingenuous, and we can argue about that later.
I don't really believe all that, though I'm afraid some of it is true.
So let me leave you with a bit more of a sincere lesson, which is that
This whole project was an itch that felt so good to scratch.
We conceived of this improbable idea,
and we used our talents to make it come true,
and we received rewards.
And we thumbed our noses at the mobile market of 2013
that broke our hearts.
We got to share these joys with dozens of our friends,
and it culminated in this overblown spectacle right here.
And the itches scratched, and now we are done.
We have not put out a new slot machine in well over a year.
They are all gone from the store,
because all that is left would be maintaining this machinery
and turning the crank to poop out more slot machines.
And you probably realize by now, I do not care about slot machines.
So we have moved on.
And if there is a business lesson in that,
I would say scratch that crazy itch and try your dream idea there.
Be prepared to walk away, even if it is successful,
because it may just be the attempt that made you happy
and not the result.
Well said, Zaiba.
I think it's worth going over some final stats
to close this out.
How many downloads did you actually receive in total?
It was 1.6 million downloads of slot games
over the course of the history of the company.
What was the number one slot?
I'm sure everyone wants to know.
What was it?
3D Sexy Skin Slots, free, 200,000 downloads.
And how much money did you guys make
over the course of all this?
About 50 grand off of ads.
That is what happened.
Of course, it is worth saying, oh yeah, sorry,
click through, 50, we did it.
What is the weirdest stat that you came up with?
The Sexy Skin Slots, which is number one,
huge in Iran.
We see you, Iran.
And I think we need something special to play us out.
So here we go.
So we would love to take questions now.
But before that.
Just one more thing.
Okay, so I lied a bit.
We have revived enough of the machinery just for today and today only that if you email
slots at signal-to-noise-apps.com with your idea in the subject line, it will reply to
you with a custom slot machine.
Today only, you get a slot, you get a slot, etc.
Thank you very much.
Please fill out your surveys and don't say
we never gave you anything.
Questions?
Hi, I'm Simon Rakestraw.
I work at a company that makes real actual slot machines
in casinos in Las Vegas.
For us, it costs literally tens of thousands of dollars
to get a new game approved.
So is there any takeaway that I could get from this?
So the question is, I'm doing this for real,
and it's expensive.
Like theoretically, let's say the app store
had a publishing cost.
How would this work?
I mean, how much work are you doing?
Can you do less?
Well...
We still spend a lot less time than like actual games.
It's still like a couple of months.
Have some pride.
These are all actual games.
I don't know what's going into your budget to do all that, but if you just try harder
to make worse things, you'll have some metrics to see which path is going to lead you to
victory.
Okay, metrics.
Thanks.
Yeah.
Remember, it's dogs and sex and not people or objects.
Hi, I'm Evan.
I'm also a slot game developer.
I did not expect this talk to be what it was actually about.
Have either of you considered a career in comedy?
Slots pays better.
I have nothing to add.
Hey there.
My name is Daniel.
I'm a business consultant.
And on Monday, I spent my day watching mostly mobile talks.
And they were quite depressing, the way
that people are monetizing games.
And I got to say that this is way better
than all of that stuff.
Thank you.
I think the depression cycle is like a 360 loop.
And if you go too far, it becomes back positive.
It's like yin and yang.
You know, one becomes the other.
And I'm wondering with.
kind of somewhere the trends that you're
seeing in the mobile market and automation
through artificial intelligence.
Do you see this becoming a growing problem
with game developers in the market?
This type of thing, being exploited?
Repeat the question.
Do we see what we're doing in automation
becoming a growing problem in the mobile market?
Yeah.
I've been so far removed from the mobile market
for many years because personally.
As someone who focuses on weird new innovation
in experimental hardware and new markets,
mobile is a more mature market where you need user acquisition
and you need much bigger budgets,
so it's not really well-suited for me.
Will machine learning change the entire ecosystem of mobile?
I think it will for targeted user acquisition.
I think that will get more and more honed,
but you're still relying on an ecosystem of quality.
So I don't know that machine learning is going to help
with the creation of higher quality art.
If there are a way to optimize for that,
that would be very interesting.
But it seems very far removed from the end goal of getting it
onto mobile and making money through ads off of that art.
So I don't see a, I mean, spam.
Spam will get more until it gets better.
Yeah, this is all just terrifying.
And it's not just mobile.
It's everywhere.
Everything is going to be susceptible to bold new methods
of creating things in volume.
And we're just on a wave of that.
It's going to happen.
Let's all enjoy that.
Well, I think that leads to curation just becoming
more and more important.
Every app ecosystem, and so the whole free Wild West
of, well, whatever gets downloads
is going to be the top thing that you open and see,
I think.
Maybe we're starting to realize that that's not the greatest
method of creating a good user experience for players.
So more curation.
Which is not where a lot of the markets are going, anyway.
I mean, it's not what the platform holders are doing.
That is not what platforms are doing.
So maybe automated curation.
Maybe.
And then you subscribe to things,
and they'll just make automated purchase for you.
Like Humble Monthly, that's just them.
Maybe they have algorithms deciding what's in there,
and you've just stolen their money,
and it's automating the purchasing.
It's automating the advertising.
It's automating putting it in the stores.
We don't have to do anything anymore,
and we're great consumers.
We don't even have to play the things that we automatically
bought.
Yeah.
It's actually interesting you mentioned automating curation,
because another side project they did over a weekend
a few years ago was when Steam Curator program was announced.
built a website called Steam Curator Curator,
so you can curate which curators you want to look at.
So I think there's a couple levels deeper
that we could go there, and I think that's a ripe opportunity.
Oh, thanks, guys.
This was a great way to start my day.
OK, so I'm a huge Slots fan.
Are you drunk right now?
Maybe.
No, I was going to ask both of you if you could speak to,
apart from all of this, related to mobile,
if you have a mobile game in the last year
that has really stood out to you,
just to give a moment of curation.
Oh, wow.
Check my phone.
Polytopia is incredible.
That's what it's called, right?
Polytopia?
Yeah.
No one went, woo.
Am I the only one who likes Polytopia?
Is that a thing?
Did I make that game up?
Did I imagine this in a dream?
It's like that little Civ-like game.
It's incredible.
Go play it.
A real recommendation?
I would say anything that Zach Gage makes.
I've been playing Pocket Pool on my phone for months now.
It's absolutely incredible.
Yes, Cinco Paus.
That's a good one.
Anyways, how many times did Google
break your automation for publishing?
Well, one too many, at least.
The question was, how many times did Google
break our automation?
Repeatedly, because it was probably
in the somewhere in the low double digits.
I would say we had to go in and fix it,
because things like a new country comes in
or a country would change its policy about gambling.
So we actually had to be aware of Korea's no longer
allowing gambling apps.
We had to go in and add a privacy policy to everything.
And then we had to actually, there
were changes where we would have to actually add a privacy
policy link to every app.
So we wrote the infrastructure for updating every app,
not just publishing, which is a whole different set of APIs.
And once, if you update to just add the app at all,
they're going to require you to catch up.
to all the not required updates before.
So they introduced new screenshot sizes,
which was fine until you actually updated your app.
Now you have to also do new screenshots.
I had to find these images from it.
It was a hot mess.
There was actually a lot more weird moving bits
than we talked about, because this isn't a tech talk.
So I feel like you've found this gem of the anti-retention model.
Do you ever feel like there's some new way
that you've wanted to wield it in the future?
or any ideas in the past that you've had?
What more can be done with the anti-retention model?
Yeah, that's the question.
I mean, like escapism as a business model?
I think it's travel agencies.
No, what do we?
I feel like Microsoft's doing that right now
with the refrigeration and chasing people out
of the room somehow.
If they can benefit from that, if we
can apply that to other spheres of our life, like talks,
and somehow profit from scaring people away from things,
we'll keep an eye on that.
Yeah, I don't know that anti-retention scales
across multiple people trying to do it.
I haven't thought about that.
Is that a one-takes-all type of model?
I think we have a lot to think about,
as a society and as a group here.
We're gonna need another retreat.
Yeah.
Yeah, it seems like the only way
you could make this more legitimate
is to add a blockchain.
Yeah.
I had like a slide that came after this that says,
what about blockchain?
And then I deleted it.
But I would have shown it right then.
So I would posit that anti-retention is actually
just curation, because you're sending people somewhere.
Well, hopefully after the curation process
and then you get the thing, you enjoy it.
Oh, fair enough.
So I had a real question as well.
Did you actually do any source control for these things you were generating?
Or was it sort of a once-off and they're all gone?
Or is there a GitHub with these things somewhere?
The question is, is there a pile of slot machines somewhere?
Yes.
It's a big pile.
I managed to get...
I don't know if Dreamhost is regretting their unlimited space offer right now on the hosting.
A lot of slot machines.
Thanks, guys.
This was extraordinarily entertaining.
Just a quick thing.
I don't know if there are people from Google Play in this room
and or watching this on the GDC vault later in the future,
but I hope there are.
And on the off chance that there are,
what would you tell them they should do to fix this shit?
Alright, thanks guys.
Later.
Peace.
Alex, what's your what is your message to Google?
Do you know anybody at Google?
As an ex-Googler.
There was a point in here that I don't think was drilled home
as hard as it could have been, which was, you know,
you got into arm rashes and the idea was
if people are sneaking by with garbage, the thing that we did was
to put a huge neon sign with an arrow pointing at ourselves
and the garbage next to us, illuminating the entire underbelly
of dark, weird App Store shit.
And so.
the idea that if you do it at scale,
clearly they're going to notice, and clearly they're
going to change the terms of service slowly to ice you out.
Hopefully others went down with us in the wake of that.
Like we provided the perfect targeted spot
to drop the missile.
So hopefully that helped get rid of duplicate apps
that were also in the area.
But I mean, that's the like.
billion dollar question is in an open market,
how do you prevent bad things?
And actually, I think that's the wrong question.
It's like the bad things should be there,
but they should just be so invisible
that it has no consequence to someone
who took their phone out, opened.
Google Play and then saw things of value that were great.
And to me, that is curation.
But curation, like the argument that everyone makes
is we're a group of semi-homogenous people
in one part of the world.
How could we be the tastemakers for the entirety
of all cultures and all people of all backgrounds?
We can't just say, these are the best things
because we believe that.
We have to figure out what is best to you individually
in this targeted curation.
Somehow I think it revolves around curation, but it revolves around a way better version of curation that is different for each person
Yeah, I mean you guys mentioned earlier very early in your talk
I mean this obviously is an extreme example, but early in your talk you mentioned that the Google Play and
App stores in general are filled with clones right like not this extreme
But nevertheless filled with clones, and I think it all ties together, and I was hopefully there's a message here anyway. Thank you
And if I could suggest to Google that they employ their own small team inside
whose task is to grief them themselves.
I think it might seriously work.
They could, you know, they'd...
I mean, it's the equivalent of security...
White hat, right.
Yeah, so like in machine learning, you have these adversarial networks.
I don't know much about machine learning, but I'm saying
they should just do it themselves.
They should do what we did to themselves.
See how they like it.
Hey, first time Caller long time fan.
So, is this and are we currently in Frog Fractions 3?
So if I could repeat the question,
it was how did you two gentlemen get
both so handsome and so clever?
I think that's what was whispered
with a grovelly, velvety, soft voice.
Is this Frog Fractions 3?
That's the question.
Just email slots at signaltonoiseapps.com
with the subject frog fractions 3,
and it will come back to you, and you've got it.
As many frog fractions games as you want right now
on your phone.
This is the rabbit hole, everyone.
Go, go, go.
We have, I think, time.
CAs, we have time for, what, we have three minutes?
Couple minutes.
Hi. If you would have taken on this project without scruples,
and I don't know how much data you collected, if any,
but do you have any idea how much money you could have made
if you allowed your users to play with the real money?
What if we'd gone full force, no scruples,
collected money from users,
what do you think the outcome would be?
Like real money gambling, wagering, et cetera.
Some of you here who actually make slot machines, you tell us, I guess.
I don't know if you if you took what we could talk about that later,
if you if someone who has a slot machine that does those things
and then we multiply them by the number of times we put out these slot machines,
we may be able to come up with a number.
I don't know if I want to see it.
Yeah, it'd be interesting to see that.
That's thanks.
Oh, that was another thing.
When we started, we actually would
have had to take money from users.
We would have to put in more personally identifying
information to Google about what we were doing,
and we didn't want to do that at first.
Yeah.
And we'll take one more.
I'm curious if you tracked how many times people pulled
Vuleva on average, total?
Oh, so I have the answer to that.
It is definitely did not.
Actually, but yeah, I think we're in the same page
We forgot to even add save data at all to the app and I think one of those reports
We only saw it while we're putting together the slide deck years later
It said when I close the app and I open it back up all my data is gone
And I looked at sideburn. I said did we add saving I?
Don't know and we're like I don't I don't know and it's really not important to the philosophy
No, so you don't know this actually I did implement stats for tracking every time
slot machine was pulled. I don't remember on what stat platform and I haven't looked at it in years. It's somewhere out there
It's gonna be huge. I don't know. We'll do a whole talk on just that number next year
Thank you fantastic question I learned a lot from it