Hello, welcome to Sewing, a Musical Patchwork,
the Music of Sackboy, A Big Adventure.
I'm Jay Waters.
I'm the game's audio director based over at Sumo Sheffield.
Hi, I'm Joe Thwaites.
I'm principal composer and music producer from PlayStation's
Creative Arts team.
And I'm James Marshall, music supervisor on this project,
also from the Creative Arts team.
We've been really pleased to see such amazing feedback since the release of Sackboy,
a great deal of that with regards to the music.
Today, we'll hopefully give you an insight into some of the decisions and methods
behind the soundtrack, provide a little look under the hood,
and also touch on how we used a diverse roster of tracks
to help set the tone throughout the various worlds.
I'm going to provide a deeper look into the practical approaches we took,
including the creative and technical challenges with implementing music in-game
and composing a theme for the game.
And we'll also look at how the overall brief led to new ways of using licensed and bespoke music,
ultimately tying together many threads to make a cohesive experience for the players.
Starting with a look back at the previous titles in the franchise,
We examined what the core components of the soundtracks were,
many of them centred around the concept of play, create, share,
and its support for user-generated content.
What this meant was that interactive music needed to have a simple system
that could be easily implemented by players in their own creations.
It also meant that licensed music generally remained a linear experience.
And as Jay mentioned, the franchise is well known for the play, create, share concept,
but we wanted to focus solely on play and that allowed us to keep the balance of licensed and composed music,
but meant we had a greater chance of a curated approach when it came to selecting the music itself.
So without these limitations, moving forward meant we were able to explore a much more narrative led soundtrack,
focusing more on thematic materials such as world themes, characters and story beats.
We also had a much bigger game to think about, with the level count hitting over 90 in total.
We also had a change from composed levels, where a composer would look just after a specific level
or section of the game, to composer curators, where a composer's sound would actually influence
the whole of that music of that world.
And we also wanted to move away from just dropping in licensed tracks wholesale and take a more
detailed deep implementation approach where each track fit a level aligning the licensed music
with the detail we can obtain from a composed score. When we first began talking to the folks
at Creative Arts Team we took with us a deck of audio goals. This particular slide served as an
ideal jumping off point.
Obviously this touches on more than just music here, but it gives a good idea of some of the
higher level ambitions we had for the franchise. First and foremost we wanted to support the art
direction as best we could, the concept of which was a crafted world imagined by a child.
Fantastic Meets the Familiar was the general strap line with worlds set within real world
environments and playing host to imaginary locations crafted by a child at play.
Through the sound, we wanted to support this by utilizing tangible objects
and accessible source material combined with added layers of imagination.
We also wanted to look at ways in which we could somehow marry the sound design
more closely with the music.
We wanted to bring a certain harmony to the game's worlds.
We were looking to do this by taking a music first approach to sound design.
This meaning that any tonal or potentially musical elements
of the sound effects we wanted to treat more as musical instruments.
We'll touch a bit more on this a little later.
Unsurprisingly, we really wanted to push towards assembling a really groundbreaking soundtrack.
We wanted to investigate ways in which we could revolutionise implementation of licensed music.
And we wanted to further push the franchise's trademark eclectic mix by expanding it in all directions.
And finally, we wanted to look at ways in which we could further innovate development of the franchise's identity.
paying close attention to attention to its subtlety, nuance and attention to detail,
its immersive world full of charm, joy and humour,
as well as its unique juxtaposition of concepts.
Following this up, we presented them with a wish list
detailing some of the musical content we wanted to explore.
Starting off, major artists, something that will be fairly new territory for the game,
and aligning with the drive towards a more AAA game experience.
This time we really wanted to raise the bar in terms of securing more mainstream and recognisable artists.
And artist exclusives, an area we experimented with on LBP3, and we're keen to develop further in this game,
working in close collaboration with established artists in the composition of bespoke music.
Classics. We also saw great potential in the use of more vintage material and were keen to experiment with interactive implementation where possible.
Similarly, with covers, we had a number of ideas for expanding the use of covers, selecting original arrangements of classic songs or commissioning somewhat more unique approaches.
Quite befitting of the game's general aesthetic, we were keen to explore interesting and effective use of mashup tracks,
in particular the prospect of using existing level music in interesting new combinations.
We also wanted to push further to discover more niche artists and performers,
something for which the franchise is now synonymous.
And above all, we just wanted to have some fun,
striving for opportunities that might raise a smile or two from the player.
So from the start of the project, we had a rough outline of the overall structure of the game.
We had a set of distinct worlds, which you can see on this slide here,
each with their own art style, gameplay mechanics, narrative hooks.
We had a general outline of the types of levels that would be in each world as well,
from ride-ons to more exploratory, more open levels, side-scrollers, things like that.
The team had already been working on prototypes for the music levels,
which we're going to touch on later,
so we knew we had to include those across the game
with one per world where we could manage it.
Jay also mentioned the covers,
and this was another thing that we wanted to include
throughout the game, but again on a one-per-world basis or so.
With both of these, we knew we had to strike a balance
that would keep the player surprised
without oversaturating the concepts.
Too many, and they'd become predictable.
Too few, and they'd come across as a gimmick.
The whole game then had to have through lines,
so Joe is going to touch on that later when talking about thematic material.
But we also had things such as cut scenes and a world map,
which did the heavy lifting of taking these worlds with their disparate sound palettes
and making them feel naturally cohesive across the project.
So let's have a look at some of these levels and worlds themselves.
So the worlds were fairly archetypal when it came to design.
You had a water world, a world set in space, but we knew with the esoteric nature of the franchise
we could take things in a different direction. This first world, which you can see concept art
for here, is set across a Tibetan-esque mountaintop.
The art design itself incorporates eastern elements, so it was a logical step to look for music which did the same.
Anderlea, a lot of alternative and psychedelic music, shares that similar kind of sound palette,
and these were the types of songs many fans associated with the franchise.
You can hear in this particular track certain instrumentation which fit this brief.
And by having it as the first set of music encountered,
with its bright, inviting, and lively beat,
not only did it thematically fit the design,
it also acted as a reassuring familiarity for longtime fans of the series.
Moving to the colossal canopy, our Amazon-esque world.
So you can hear here with this great track by Brian D'Oliveira,
it's incorporating tribal drums, organic instrumentation, you've got a very, very
subtle element of ethnotronica in there, which was another thing that we looked at when we
looked at this particular world. And given that there were a lot of elements from South America,
we brought those inspirations in to give it a real kind of carnival vibe as well.
Moving to the Undersea World,
and this very jazzy cover of Grieg reinterpreted by Jim Fowler.
The Kingdom of Krablantus was a world featuring lots and lots of
antique furniture in the background and these lush textures.
And this particular set dressing inspired us to look at older styles of music,
so classical, jazz, swing, and then often putting our own contemporary spin on things.
And you can hear that with this new interpretation of a classical piece.
We then also went in completely the opposite direction at the interstellar junction.
And you can hear with this track, it's synths, synths and more synths.
This was one of our checkboxes ticked with an artist exclusive
by the Glitch Shop producer Opio.
And this aesthetic went throughout the space world
where it was electronic music.
almost a history of electronic music as you went through the world itself,
with synths, beats, breaks, and a slightly darker edge
as things are heating up for Sackboy as he makes his way through his adventure.
And then lastly...
the final world, the center of QWAF World, with its previous...
designs of all the assets from previous worlds mixed together in a chaotic maelstrom by the
antagonist Vex. So we looked at that for inspiration and in this remix from 2Metalo
you can hear it's not only playfully malevolent but it also takes eight or so tracks previously
used throughout the game and makes a mashup again ticking a box that we wanted to achieve.
to create this delightfully demonic but very very funky mashup. And we were always considering the
level design when it came to the music and always looking for opportunities where music and visuals
would inform each other. But how did we select the songs for those levels? It all began
with a massive playlist of around 100 or so songs,
an extensive collection of anything we could think
would possibly work for a world.
It was more of a wishlist than anyone could feed in
with what they wanted to possibly hear in the game.
And then as the levels were blocked out,
we placed them in their earliest form to gauge the general vibe.
This allowed us to create a smaller subset of songs with about 20 to 30.
And it was here where we looked at what the general vibe of the level was.
Was it going to be fast-paced, a bit more chaotic, or something more laid back?
Did it have a set trajectory, like on rails levels?
Or was it a bit more free form, allowing the player to explore at their own will?
The former was easier to anticipate how a track might play out as the general time between A and B
was going to be pretty much similar throughout the level. But levels that were more freeform
and had a hub area required a different approach as players could spend a lot of time in one area
or they could go in random order between different sections of the level. So this allowed us to gauge
whether the level was going to be more suited for a composed or a licensed track.
If a license track looked like it would work, we'd find those which tick the correct boxes.
Did it have the necessary files that we might be able to use? Was it likely to be in budget?
Once we had these, we would go out for approval on those particular tracks, and then approvals
would come back depending on the request, which would give us around one or two songs
that we could consider for the level. If it looked like the license track would work,
implementation would start.
If it looked like it would be more of a composed level, we'd start a brief, discuss it with the
composer and begin that process. We did have one thing that helped us throughout the project. One
challenge that we encountered earlier on is that music's extremely subjective and the particular
process here involved a lot of stakeholders. As the importance of music grew throughout
the project and developed, we created this flowchart in a bid to slightly substantiate
the music choices as a way for us to make sure any songs that we considered met the criteria we needed for the game.
This particular portion of the chart served as an initial check and was there to remove subjectivity.
Given that Sackboy, with the type of game it is, there were a lot of songs that fit the vibe,
but maybe they didn't tick the other boxes. So we'd look at the flowchart. If there was someone
who was particularly attached to a song, we'd consult with the flowchart, refer back to it,
and if it didn't tick the boxes, unfortunately, the song would be set aside. When it came to
implementing, Joe's going to pick up on how that was used in terms of getting those songs in the
game.
James. As we mentioned, because of the heritage of the game, we knew that we wanted to incorporate
licensed music and we also knew that we wanted to embed the music into the game
in a way that was seamless and helped score each player's experience.
So regardless of whether the track was composed or licensed, once we had the track that fitted the theme and the tone of the level, we needed to make sure a number of things.
One, the track had enough variation to maintain interest for the duration of the level.
We'd often find a track that would fit perfectly to the brief, but we soon realised that it didn't really move from one or two chord progressions.
And within those chord progressions, if you take away the lyrics and the...
of the vocals, it's not really going to go anywhere, so we need to go back to the drawing board.
We also need to make sure that we had enough stems for the track so that we could rearrange
and embellish the track to best fit it into the level. We had some great tracks that we
couldn't use because we didn't have access to the stems, or it's an old track and the
stems themselves didn't actually exist.
And then we also needed to make sure that we had the rights to use it in the game how we wanted to use it.
So the rights holders needed to be on board and give us permission to break the track up into the stems and use it in our implementation system.
So once we had the track and its stems, we would begin our initial implementation.
The goal here was to have a system where we could add the component parts of the track
and the game would reconstruct these elements at runtime.
It wouldn't matter if it was a licensed track or a composed track,
they'd both be implemented in the same way.
So we wanted each track to feel unique and change depending on the player's route or play style through the level.
But most importantly, we wanted to connect with the narrative of the game and really help propel Sackboy's journey through the various levels in the game.
So to do this, we had some general high-level systems and also some bespoke systems for individual levels to keep the music fresh and interesting throughout.
So the basic system comprised of four implementation techniques, which many of you will be familiar with.
Horizontal re-sequencing, which is this idea of splitting the track into multiple loopable chunks and then moving through them as you move through the game.
Vertical layering, which is this idea of splitting each track into multiple layers
that can be added and removed at runtime.
So, you know, splitting it into drums, bass, vocals,
and then bringing in the drums or the bass at certain points in the game.
Stingers and embellishments, which were short musical elements that would be triggered by
gameplay events, these kind of more instant things. If you get a pickup or something like
that you get stinger or embellishments being kind of additional little bits of music that
we add on to kind of license tracks.
And finally, runtime processing, which was this idea of using filters and effects that manipulate the music at runtime, depending on what the player's doing.
And I'm going to show a quick demo of each of those and how we use them in Sackboy.
So the first thing we did was to split each track into these loopable sections.
Each section needed to maintain interest if the player stuck around in an area for a long period of time,
so we'd spend...
a lot of time with these tracks, extending them and doing multiple arrangements and variations
for each of the sections of the music so that if Sackboy stays in one space,
the music doesn't get boring and it kind of keeps evolving and changing.
Generally in the game the music moves on to the next section of the track as you move through the
checkpoints in a level. So you can hear in this video as Sackboy moves over each of the checkpoints
the next kind of section of music will be queued up.
And it'll be queued up in different ways depending on how quickly we want to transition.
So it might be queued up on the next bar, it might be queued up on the end of that section,
or the end of that melody, or it might be queued up immediately if it needs to happen quickly.
And that really depended on how it was going to be used in the game.
And in this video you'll see a couple of different examples.
The first couple of checkpoints, it kind of lines it up.
to be the end of the section.
So whenever that section finishes,
it kind of naturally moves on.
But then the final one that you'll see
when you get shot out of the flower cannon,
it moves on quite a bit quicker
because it needs to, the music opens up at that point
and changes kind of more dramatically.
But I'll show you what I mean in this video.
Let's start that.
So we've now moved into the first loop and this will stick around in this kind of verse
version and it'll go through different arrangements of this verse whilst you stick around in this area.
So we've moved to the second checkpoint and now we bring in the chorus.
The third checkpoint lines up the next part of the music, which goes into the bridge.
And that was the transition that happened a lot quicker because we're kind of opening up the music now into this kind of more
environmental, opium, kind of ambient version.
That last clip was just a good example of how using this horizontal resequencing we can really
end with a bang on these tracks so they kind of sync up to the landing on the scoreboard and
yeah it makes a real difference for those kind of moments when you really want to
finish and change the music up and yeah for the endings it works really nicely.
So the horizontal re-sequencing helped create momentum as you move through the levels, but we
also wanted multiple layers vertically to react to gameplay events whilst you are in each of those
areas. So we split all of our music into roughly the same sections that could be manipulated at
runtime.
These were generally categorized as drums, bass, lead, accompaniment, and vocals.
Obviously it depends on the kind of content of the track if we could split it into those groups,
and sometimes those groups varied a little bit. But yeah, what that allowed us to do was bring
in these different elements depending on what was going on in the game.
So the previous video showed how this would help with arrangements where we could drop out a lead
line if the player stayed in one area, but we also hooked off some of the game mechanics such as
we would drop out the drums if Sackboy stands idle for a period of time.
or bringing in lyrics at key moments of gameplay,
which in this clip I'll show in a moment,
there's a really nice moment where you open these gates
and there's some lyrics that you appropriately sing
open those gates,
and it works really nicely with that moment.
And also in this video, we've got a clip showing how we use layers to build towards progression of objectives.
So as you move towards a boss door and you get closer to a boss door, we bring in more and more layers of a track.
And then as you move further away, those layers dissipate and fall away.
So it's more intense as you get close to the boss door. So let's take a look at this video.
You can see the Y's overlay there showing the different layers that are playing at
the moment.
And then the drums kick back in when Sackboy starts moving again.
I'm not sure if this is a good idea, but I'm going to try to make it work.
I'm going to try to make it work.
This was our cover of Mars done by Opieo.
You can hear as you move away the layers drop out and as you move closer they come back in.
Using the layers really allowed us to build seamlessly into that moment and really build
up to the boss door and when you go through it kind of having that as a real moment,
which we wouldn't be able to do with just the horizontal re-sequencing.
So some events in the game happen immediately and we wanted the music to reward the player with
a flourish or an embellishment. So on top of the horizontal re-sequencing stuff and the vertical
layering, we also used musical stingers and embellishments to react quickly to gameplay
events such as picking up items or helping to smooth over transitions.
So in this video, there's a couple of examples of moments where a Sackboy does something in the gameplay,
and it's rewarded with a small stinger.
And I should note that all of the stingers are taken from the music itself in that level,
so you'll hear that they're kind of created by the sounds of the track itself,
and that really sits them in that kind of musical world.
But it meant we ended up with hundreds and hundreds of stingers throughout the game.
Let's have a look at that video.
This final example here is an example of using a stinger to help smooth over a transition.
So you get a stinger when you go into the flower cannon.
And it just makes more of a moment of that transition and helps kind of,
yeah, smooth over any rough edges, which is a really great way of using them.
And as well as actual edits and embellishments of the musical content, we also looked at applying
real-time effects to really embed the music into the world. The main example of this is probably
when you enter the bonus rooms in the game. The bonus rooms are the kind of side rooms from the
main level where you go in and find bonus content for the level. And in this case you normally go
through a zipped door.
And what we do is we worldize the music and position it in 3D on the doorway.
And we filter it depending on if the doorway is open or closed.
So if the doorway is open, we allow more through.
And when it's closed, we filter more out.
And then when you return back to the main level,
you get the full track in all its glory again.
Yeah, and it creates this really nice feeling of kind of
being away from the level and leaving the music behind.
And we also use filters to make music more dynamic in other places and we do it to adapt to
gameplay events such as when you go in those flower cannons doing a low pass filter on the music
and similarly when Sackboy loses a life we do kind of a filter sweep and the music kind of
dissipates away and this just creates a really nice dynamic flow of the music which really
embeds it into the world. So I've got a video a couple of examples of that.
Good to see you again, fellow explorer.
You won't believe it, but I finally found him.
Yeah, Big Moe, the real-
Ow!
Yeah, that's what a bite from Moe would feel like.
Here, why don't you hang on to this?
Think it's one of his eggs, but you can handle yourself.
Be lucky, sack boy.
This one's an example of how we approach something that was specific to a level.
Oi, sack boy! Don't go bruising me nanas!
There are stock and trade, imagination food. Export them all over Craftworld!
So these techniques kind of acted as a foundation to which we built on top of,
and we did kind of more of the level-specific stuff.
But on top of that, we did some really cool stuff with sound,
and I'll pass over to Jay to talk about that stuff.
So as we hinted at earlier, we also wanted to explore how we could push
musical interactivity into other areas of the sound.
Quite a large number of the sound effects are rich in tonal elements,
especially those associated with UI or player messaging.
As a result, we began thinking of ways in which we could implement these sounds
a little more elegantly in such a way that they become more intrinsic
to the musical experience.
It's ultimately led to the development of what we ended up referring to
as a harmony system and rhythm manager.
The harmony system enabled sound designers to create sound effects
that could adapt to the key signature of the accompanying music track.
The rhythm manager was more of a suite of tools
that enabled us to synchronize sound, gameplay events,
and animations to bar beats or custom markers
within the score.
And we'll touch on this a little more shortly.
So technically, the harmony system is quite simple.
In each level, the key signature is
defined by a set state component in Unreal Blueprint.
When a sound is triggered, the corresponding wise event
plays a combination of layers.
With any tonal elements arranged in switch containers,
basic one shots would generally tune to the root or tonic,
whereas more complex arrangements
might trigger an interval, arpeggio, or a short melody
by the use of sequence containers.
Here's a quick example in Wwise.
This particular event is the collection sound effect
for void energy, which is a rare collectible that players
can use to unlock levels in the Knitted Knight trials.
This is what it sounds like.
And you can see how the sound is comprised of multiple layers
with the riser, snare hit and sting elements being consistent across keys.
However, both the bass drop and bass rise elements are tuned
with the component source sounds held within corresponding switch containers
and subsequently set by the key state.
And here that sound is in game along with a few other examples of the musical sound effects.
One thing that was really important to us from the beginning of this project was bringing the game together with a theme.
We knew that each world and individual level was going to be unique, so we wanted to have a thread that really pulled it all together
and made it feel like a cohesive experience.
So early on we looked at writing a couple of short melodies that would go on to become
Sackboy's theme.
As the theme was going to be integrated throughout the game, we wanted something that was super simple and that could be utilised in any style.
So the main hook needed to be able to work as a fanfare to highlight important moments in the game,
but it also needed to set over all the different styles of the space world and the Amazon world and the Himalayan world,
and how it was going to work in all these different styles.
So we ended up writing three key melodies which came together to create Sackboy's theme.
We have a melody that represents Sackboy as a hero, we have a melody that represents Loom,
which is Sackboy's hometown, and we have a melody that represents the call to adventure,
which we'd use in a lot of the cutscenes when Scarlet would kind of help Sackboy onto the next thing.
So I thought it'd be good to share a little tour of the development of one of those themes.
We're going to look at Sackboy's Hero theme and how it started with a super simple piano melody.
Then we did a kind of a scratch guitar demo of how it's going to sound with kind of mandolins and guitars and stuff, which kind of.
was a bit of a foundation of Sackboy's sound.
And then the MIDI demo shows kind of the accompanying stuff that we built around that.
And then finally, the final version of it with the recorded instruments.
We did some kind of, we did some choir recordings at Air Studio,
and we also did some string recordings at Air Studio as well.
And that's all mixed in in the final version.
So let's have a look at that.
Don't forget to remember to measure between 0.5 and 6.5.
Most notably, the theme plays a big part in the cutscenes, which are the key moments where the narrative moves forward.
And our cutscene composer, Nick Foster, did an absolutely outstanding job of integrating the different themes into the different cutscenes.
But on top of this, we also shared the theme with each of our world composers and world map composer to integrate into their level compositions.
And this is when everything really started to tie together, when you start hearing it in all the different worlds and it starts popping up all over the place.
We then took the step even further and we also embellished some of the license tracks that we did.
We added kind of additional layers on top of some of the license tracks to feature the theme.
And finally, we also put the theme as a stinger,
which is attached to the main collectible in the game,
which are the dream robs.
And to do this, we actually ended up
writing a specific stinger for every level in the game
so that when you collect those dream
robs in the different levels, it plays
in the same key, tempo, time signature, and kind of groove
and instrumentation of that level.
So it really sits in with the world.
I'm just going to show a quick video showing a handful of the places where you can see the theme pop up in some of the different variations of it.
The world maps were a great opportunity for the themes to kind of just flow in on the
winds and kind of dissipate and appear and disappear when needed.
Oi, sack boy! Don't go bruising me nanas!
There are stock and trade. Imagination food.
That track there was a really good example of embellishing a licensed track with the theme.
So the brass band was recorded once we'd secured the track,
and then it was embedded on top of it to really work with the level.
So you can see the theme pops up in a ton of places as you play through.
Sometimes it's very subtle, sometimes less subtle, but what it does is it creates this
unified language that really helps pull the whole game together under one umbrella.
What's probably a fitting note to end on is what is essentially the culmination of most of the ambitions and technical approaches discussed so far.
Music levels, as they were generally referred to, are a small selection of special levels in which the music plays a much bigger part in the experience.
Used as a showcase for some of the game's bigger hits,
music levels were designed in reverse, with the accompanying track being used to inform level design.
And subsequently providing a rhythm and structure around which the whole level moves and dances.
And of course, these were all the products of the aforementioned rhythm manager,
which provided all disciplines with access to bar beat and custom marker callbacks.
So.
You've seen how we, what our goals were across the game, but what were specifically our goals
for these levels. So we knew we wanted to elevate and expand upon the franchise's use
of licensed music. It is a franchise known for licensed music,
and we knew we wanted to take that one step further and really kind of...
level up the use. We knew that we wanted to broaden the audience via more recognizable and well-known songs.
The game and the franchise, they're well known for using slightly more left field, slightly more
esoteric choices, so incorporating chart-topping hits, we had to do it in a way that was going to
be special. We knew we wanted to present the songs respectfully and unembellished. These were very
recognizable tracks and we wanted people.
to hear them as if they'd hear them listening in their car radio or, you know, just in their daily
life. We didn't want to make them unrecognizable. We wanted to keep them within the brief of the
game and the worlds if we could as well. And while there were very loose rules around where they sat,
we did try and fit them in either to a narrative beat or within the general theme of the world.
And as they were going to be memorable musical moments.
We still didn't want to confine the player's intentions, so we wanted to keep it as free
form as possible and allow the players to explore without forcing them through a level
at the pace of the song. That was probably one of the bigger challenges
and Jay's going to touch on how we had a look at that next.
So the concept of music levels began as part of some wider prototyping by Level Design.
At the time, we were building simple gray box levels, designing basic motifs to single shot drum hits and basic loops.
Upon seeing the potential, we soon progressed to prototyping with licensed music,
trying out a number of different genres to get a better idea of what worked.
Entering production, we had a clearer vision on what we wanted to achieve.
These moments needed to be more of an experience rather than just another level.
They needed to unite art, animation, music, sound and gameplay.
And the ambition was that the end result would be worthy of a well choreographed music video.
Another goal we all agreed on was that these levels should never feel on rails.
We wanted to give players the freedom to move at their own pace,
while we do the work behind the scenes to ensure the experience remains seamless and consistent.
Now one of the main challenges from a music point of view was concerning how we could
preserve the integrity of the original tracks, as James has just mentioned.
These were all well-known songs, complete with vocals,
so it was important that their arrangements were never
pulled too far away from what the audience would
be familiar with.
We approached this by treating them more as a 12-inch remix.
In a similar way to the process described by Joe earlier,
we implemented in such a way that they
retained an organic feel through variation in the layering.
Basically, this meant that the songs
would transition to instrumental arrangements
in between sections if the player hung around
in a particular area for too long.
For example, ensuring that verses and choruses never repeated unnaturally.
We also made heavy use of WISER's entry and exit cues to ensure the
transitions themselves felt natural.
For example, when the vocals would lead into a chorus or drums could feature
preceding fills or succeeding crash tails.
Thanks Jay. So you'd seen earlier how we went about selecting the songs throughout the rest
of the game but these were a specific set of songs that had their own challenges and finding
the songs for them was going to be tricky. So we needed them to be internationally recognizable,
that was pretty much a given. But we also needed them to have a set rhythm that continued
throughout the song because the level designers
Full credit to them, made some fantastic levels,
but having that set beat throughout
gave them something to build to.
As such, they also needed a standard structure,
so you couldn't really have a nine-minute epic,
prog, kind of solo or anything like that.
It needed something where the level designers
could very, very, you know, go in, construct something,
test things out, make sure it worked.
As such, you also needed a tempo within certain limits.
If it was too slow, the level really wouldn't stand out as doing anything too fast, and it's going to be very, very chaotic.
And as we mentioned, we didn't want it to feel on rails, but we did try and look for moments where the song could be choreographed slightly more than it is elsewhere.
And bridges and transitions were the perfect places where this could happen.
So we were always on the lookout for interesting bridges and transitions where you could see something.
choreographing and syncing up to the song at those moments.
As with every other song in the game, they needed usable stems, and this was
often a hurdle for some of the older catalog. And as
Jay mentioned, these are the songs complete with vocals, and for a family
friendly game, we needed them to be lyrically suitable for the rating.
You'd think most songs out there would work,
but there are plenty out there actually that would either require an edit
or just couldn't work or get past the rating that we required.
Even down to level design, there were criteria and they actually had a ratings chart where they would
rate the song based on things like progression or a steady beat or even the fact that a lyrical phrase
moved across sections. If that happens, it was very tricky to make it implement without
kind of making the song sound like a poor edit or just it not working at all. And then finally,
we needed the songs to be approved and you could get the perfect song and then find that
it wasn't going to be in budget or the artist wasn't keen on doing it.
So that was the final hurdle, but while there were challenges there were also rewards.
So we'll have a look at those here.
So we know that with the challenges we had these very specific set of conditions.
We also knew that it was a possibility that the levels could become too busy or distracting.
Making a synchronized level, and full credit to the level creation teams,
they did strike a balance between these beautiful, very, very choreographed levels
without making it too busy so you can't see the player character.
As mentioned, we did have the whole question between player freedom and choreography,
as Jay wanted, and we agreed. We didn't want these levels to be on rails,
so we wanted to give the player freedom.
But that came at the expense occasionally of choreography,
so it was great that we could strike a balance where the songs did both.
We also within the team didn't want it to distract too much
from the other music in the game.
We refer to them as music levels, but for us, every level in the game is musical.
And while these are definitely standout moments,
we didn't want these particular songs to make the rest look
like they weren't implemented as quite as curated.
And as with any licensed music, there are limitations around promotion and streaming.
However, there were great rewards for this. These are some of the most standout moments
within the game. Often, you know, these are the levels that players will mention
when you ask about the game.
We had the potential to also use actual master recordings and bring a new lease of life to
songs that have been everywhere.
And this was something that we saw a real benefit for, both for us and for the licensors
too, whereby these are songs that you'll hear on the radio, they've been used in adverts,
they've been used in films.
But now there are definitely people out there who are starting to really see,
you know, Sackboy, the game as a place where they know these songs from.
And bringing new life to catalogue and legacy hits is something absolutely fantastic.
They were definitely the combination of our learnings across the game as well,
not only in terms of music implementation and licensing,
but also in combination with art design and level creation.
We knew that while they're not necessarily emotional in terms of sadness or you know
narrative beats, they are emotional peaks of the game. Players very often describe euphoric moods
when playing through these levels and you'll always see people with a smile on their face
as they play through. Fundamentally they were also something musically new for a franchise
that is known already for its music.
And this was an absolute thing that we wanted to achieve with this game, where
we did something different, we did something unexpected. And that feeds into one of the
final rewards, which was the crystallization of what we described as the surprise ethos.
These are well-known songs and...
Hearing them elsewhere maybe isn't a surprise, but we wanted it to be a surprise for people
playing the game. That could either be just simply from the inclusion of these AAA,
massive international recognizable hits, or it could be in the way that they're used.
In always eliciting a smile or a reaction, there are people who possibly
weren't expecting these songs in the game.
Doing that, and it's something that we looked at across the rest of the game as well, the music is
always there to delight and surprise, and so we really feel we achieved that. And so we'll show
you a very brief clip of the first music level you encounter in the game, and I'm going to point
out a couple of bits as we go through.
So in the starting area it's looping the intro and it's positioned in 3D on the radio.
Here's the player doing some coordinated dancing, although Sackboy can emote as a dance as well.
And the song is always naturally moving through the song.
One of the ways that level design were able to create a choreography without making the level
itself on rails is through these enemies that move in time to specific parts of the song.
And here's one of the more choreographed sections.
So in summary, we started by examining the legacy of the franchise.
We developed methods and processes that enabled us to innovate
both creatively and technically.
And we expanded the soundtrack in multiple directions
in a bid to broaden the appeal.
We pushed the thematic content to pull together the varied soundtrack
and we did a deeper dive into the implementation that really allowed us to create a narrative
journey through the game, pushing into new areas but also maintaining that feeling of
the franchise that had come before. And we brought together the wildly
disparate threads of licensed music by paying attention to the level design
and working in harmony with art, level creation and our own guidelines for each of the game's worlds.
These were punctuated by high points of set piece musical moments
that were the most visible combination of these different game development threads.
And surprised was at the heart of our approach to Sackboy as well.
It was a constant throughout the game designed to keep the music fresh
and create a range of memorable moments.
This was no small feat, and it was therefore a huge collaborative effort.
So thanks to all the composers, licensors and musicians involved.
As well as all the awesome audio teams at Sumo Sheffield and the creative arts team.
Thanks for listening.