Game aims squarely at me because it is narrative and turn-based tile strategy all in one.
So as I begin, we're watching some pre-recorded footage here. Feel free to ask questions for
John and Tom while we're talking. We're here to talk about making Pendragon, so please be sure to
square your questions that way. And yeah, we're just gonna have a conversation about
making these games, but I should let them introduce themselves. John, Tom, how are you doing?
We're good! I mean launch day is always a bit crazy.
I'm suffering a little bit from having pressed the refresh button on Twitter
just a few thousand too many times today, but otherwise I'm good.
It's been really nice actually as we've launched a lot of games.
Inkle's been going about 10 years now and this is the first time that we've
launched a game that we actually had finished like two weeks ago.
Like normally you kind of sprint to the final line but this one we
because we knew the game is so complicated and so...
like weirdly put together that we really were very scared about getting it solid and tested.
So we started testing ages ago and then we finished testing and then for the last few
weeks we've been going, should we add this? Nah, let's not add that. It's been quite relaxed
actually for some in some ways but launch day is always launch day. It's always nerve-wracking.
So we're okay. We're okay. Yeah and uh John we've had you on the stream before. Tom you're new to
the stream. Would you mind introducing yourself?
Hi, yeah, I'm Tom. I am, uh, John, what's my job title?
Um, uh, you're senior designer developer now.
I, it's all the words.
I make things with John Inkle.
And yeah, everything John was saying, like, we took today off, in fact,
because apparently we're that confident or stupid.
But nothing seems to have gone wrong, which is really nice.
And yeah, such a change of pace to normally how games get released.
Yeah.
Sorry everyone who has caught me looking down my phone. I had to tweet out that we're live. We you know
It's it's alive. It's live television. This is where we make our mistakes for you to see a quick shout out to father
Let in chat. Thank you for joining us today father. We'd love to have you
John and Tom, let's get to it.
Pendragon, like I said, narrative game, turn-based strategy, and it's cool.
It's neat.
You're seeing me discover how cool and neat it is right now where I'm navigating a conversation
by doing turn-based strategy things.
Can you tell me how this game started and what were Inkle's design goals after the interesting
game that was interesting and ambitious, Heaven's Vault?
Yeah.
So...
The chronology doesn't quite work like that.
The game, Pentagram was already quite heavily designed
by the time we released Heaven's Vault.
So, but the two are kind of connected.
Basically while we were working on Heaven's Vault,
which is like a big 3D game, lots of cameras,
lots of like fucking around with 3D and stuff like that.
When we wanted to not be working on Heaven's Vault,
when we needed a break, especially Tom,
Tom was building a,
turn-based strategy prototype board game, mostly just because it was the most unlike
Kevin's vault thing he could possibly do with his spare time while still making a game.
That's about right, isn't it, Tom?
It's about right, yeah.
Yeah, and so we were messing around with that and kind of over lunch breaks and like when we
went to the pub in the evenings and we'd just sort of try out the rules of this game and sort of
play it.
And after about maybe two years of fiddling around with that prototype,
we ended up with a really good, really strong two-player game
that was a little bit like chess or a little bit like checkers.
And it was played with counters on a 5x5 board,
and you could have made it out of wood and sold it in a shop.
And we kind of thought, well, we can't do anything with that
because we make narrative games,
and you can't possibly stick a narrative on a game like that, can you?
But then once you have a feeling like that, once you have a question like, well, you can't possibly do that, can you?
You start to think, well, or can you?
That's kind of how Pendragon happened, I think, with like after the end of Heaven's Vault,
we had this sense that we didn't really know what to do next.
We didn't want to make Heaven's Vault 2.
We had this prototype knocking around.
So I think we kind of thought, well, let's just see how far we can take this idea of
putting a narrative onto an abstract strategy board game and making it work.
Because it won't work, it's gonna fall apart, it's gonna go wrong, this is a ridiculous idea, it can't be done.
And then we carried on doing it and like, yeah, now we've released it and it appears to work.
So we've gone to the other end of it, but...
Tom, do you want to tell any of your experience aside from, you know, fiddling?
It's cool to see a game that you fiddle with in your spare time become, you know, a full game.
Yeah, I mean it's honestly the dream, at least it's certainly my dream, to have like a boss be like,
oh let's make that game you've been playing with. But yeah, it goes back a really long way. It
actually goes back to when I first joined the company and we were porting 80 Days to Steam,
and that's when, at least according to my notes that I've been keeping, it goes back to 2015,
and I remember showing it to Joe, because I think...
John, you were off having your second kid, so Joe actually played it a lot more at the time.
And then when Joe went off to have his kid, that's when you started playing it with me.
And that's when you started throwing these dangerous ideas of adding a story to it.
And I started getting all scared.
And you proposed that you would add the AI to the game,
because I couldn't play it against myself, so I had to test it over lunch.
You said, I'll ride the AI.
and then I might also add a story or something? I was like yeah sure that sounds like a good idea.
I made a Fausti impact with you which was I agreed to write you in AI
on the condition that I could also write a narrative layer for it and you were like yeah
sure that sounds like a fair trade. Slowly over the next two years the narrative layer took your
beautiful balanced symmetric game and ripped it to pieces.
Yeah, let's talk, uh, we're actually, the game is demonstrating something interesting, which is, so unlike, this, this strategy game has a little bit of chess in it, which is, uh, your units can only move certain directions depending on, uh, uh, certain tiles, and capturing is just a matter of, like, this isn't, like, XCOM, this isn't Fire Emblem, there's no fancy stats, it's just move, capture.
So it's very chess-like to me.
While units mostly move diagonally, they cannot capture other pieces, while they must be adjacent to them.
So it creates this interesting back-and-forth that gets more complex later on.
Tom, I suppose since this is your baby, like, what made you go,
Oh! Yeah, chess! That's a game that is already solved.
I'm gonna make strategy chess with, and then enter Arthurian.
Um, so...
It's sort of a bugbear of mine. I really, really like tactics games,
and I started playing Fire Emblem and Advance Wars on Game Boy when I was a kid,
and I always really loved those kind of games, but I'm not a PC gamer,
and so I sort of missed out on XCOM and that kind of thing,
and whenever I tried learning them, I just couldn't,
because there's too many buttons and rules and menus and stuff.
And so this was kind of...
Me trying to take what I really loved about tactics games and boil it down into something without any context menus
without
Like resources or numbers. I want to just basically make it really minimal which you know also means you can make it on your own
Fairly easily. I thought be a really fun design challenge
And it actually turns out that that's really hard because it tends to be all of the menus and stuff
that, you know, gives these games the complexity they need to be interesting for like 20 hours.
And obviously chess solved this. You can play a lot of chess. And so I ended up sort of going
down the same route just because that seems to be the route if you want to make a tactics game that is...
very replayer, low-income infinite, you kind of have to find ways to give all of your actions
as much nuance to them as possible. Like, this action isn't just something minor, it actually
changes the state in this sort of fairly important way. So you have, you can really puzzle over each
move. Right on, yeah. Oh, John, go for it. Go for it, John. I was just going to say, I remember one
of your goals.
was that idea that you wanted people on every move to be stopping and thinking,
oh this is an interesting situation and I really want to treat it as a puzzle.
I think we tried a lot of iterations of rules over the years but I remember that was always
the metric, that was like the pillar of the strategy game was, am I puzzling? Am I getting
an interesting decision to puzzle over during this game or am I just working for a pattern?
So I had a really interesting interview with another reviewer last week who turned out it
was quite a chess boss.
And he was saying that he felt the game wasn't like chess,
because when you play chess at a high level, you just execute patterns.
Like you do, oh, this is the Sicilian defense, and this is the whatever gambit.
And chess players look at these patterns and just apply the patterns to each other.
And he was saying one of the things he liked about Pendragon was there weren't any patterns.
Like you genuinely had to actually think about what you were doing on every move.
And I said, well, there probably are patterns,
you just haven't found out what they are yet.
Yeah.
But, you know, it was kind of a nice thing, actually,
to try and make something that had the responsiveness of...
Not chess played at a high level, but chess played at a sort of low level, where you do interesting moves,
but you don't actually know how to play chess properly.
And I thought that was quite a nice thing to end up with. It's like chess, but fun.
That's actually... Man, we aren't even talking about the interesting procedural story things that happen here,
and we're off to some great design questions.
I agree with the... I have just such an inverse reaction to that...
to that reviewer's talk about chess, which is that...
I think of chess and I think of it more like, you know, the strategy games I enjoy, which is I'm looking at...
But that's because I'm a bad chess player.
Um, I play other strategy games where I'm like a much better player, and even then I'm still more like,
reactive, like, okay, I'm here, I have these abilities, like,
like, that's where I thrive as a player.
Um, so what did you sort of learn about, like, I don't know, like...
you know, taking sort of the core part of chess, which is moving pieces around,
throwing out the pattern part that, you know, identifiable patterns and like
help making it so that players could make these decisions. You can see me negotiating
decisions around these bears as we speak. So I'm kind of curious like what your thoughts
were for making sure that like, you know, it was never a solved problem, I guess.
How did you avoid making a solved game? He said knowing many developers would happily make solved
games.
I think when we were originally building the abstract board game,
like it was a five by five grid and the team started in either corner.
And we played that game a lot and we enjoyed it.
And it was interesting.
But I think it probably was a solved game or a solvable game.
I think, Tom, you were much, much better at it than I ever got to be.
But I think you had a sense that that game.
that game was finite, you could get to a point where you could just master it and then it
wouldn't be interesting anymore.
Yeah, right.
And as soon as that happened, I'd say, right, it doesn't work, we need to change a rule
because I've solved it.
And then you'd go, no, no, no, you haven't solved it.
Look, I'll beat you and then you'd lose.
And this happened a lot, maybe like 30, 40 times or something like that.
I remember there was this one time when I was like, I've got this strategy and I'm pretty
sure I can just completely ruin the game.
But at the time...
you could infinitely create new knights.
There wasn't a limit on it, and there wasn't a variable that said, you know,
it costs this many to spawn. And so I said, look, here's what I'm
gonna do. I'm gonna spawn a knight, I'm gonna move him, and then I'm gonna spawn
another guy, I'm gonna move him. I just built this wall,
and it completely broke the game. And like, none of us have really thought to
play like that, because it sounds really boring, and it's fun to move your pieces across.
And that's kind of a prime example of how we added a rule to the game.
We played it, broke it, and then said,
right, this doesn't work.
In this case, I think we went straight for adding a variable, like Admiral,
which really helped, actually, straight away.
I think we called it Spawn Monkey for the longest time, and I don't know why, but we did.
Let's be clear, you called it Spawn Monkey.
I, as a writer, wouldn't dream of calling it Spawn Monkey, but never mind.
Um, well, while I could let you two, uh, insult each other and slag each other in the chat all I want,
let's talk about, um, there's a procedural narrative component here.
So as you can see, uh, if you're watching the gameplay footage,
um, Guinevere, my chosen character, has an ability called push forwards,
uh, which she picked up when I made a decision back there in the meta, in the meta layer,
uh, out in the game world.
Or maybe I got it earlier because I still love Arthur.
And this is an ability that I could see normally manifesting a character having through, you know, a leveling tree, a talent tree.
It's just simple as, like, she can move further. She spends energy to move further. Sure. Simple.
But these abilities pop up in Pendragon. This is what makes it unique.
Because of narrative choices you make and narrative choices aren't just dialogue trees there how you get through missions
How do you do murder these spiders like lots of interesting things will happen in this hour because?
Not just how I made decisions
Narratively, but how I made decisions strategically which I think is really cool
So would you two mind talking about that layer of gameplay and how like abilities came out of story and that sort of thing?
It's interesting to think about how we designed that like I think
So we were talking about how the 5x5 game felt quite solved,
and we started to solve that partly by adding rules,
but also by adding variation to the board, right?
And changing the shape of the board.
And we found that adding just one of those hummock squares,
where you can go in any direction,
completely shifted the balance of the strategies and the patterns.
So that was really useful.
But then another idea we kind of naturally had was,
well, you know, what if we have pieces with extra abilities?
We have heroes and they have some kind of special ability.
And can we find some special abilities that don't just destroy the game straight away,
but are fun to use? And eventually that got tied into the resolve mechanic.
But we didn't really have a sense of how to pace those out.
Like, when should we unlock it? We didn't want to do experience points.
We didn't want to do another resource that you collect.
We thought about you gain 10 for clearing a level,
and you gain 5 for killing an enemy, and when you get 30, you get one.
But it just felt really arbitrary. It just felt really random.
It wouldn't be very satisfying.
And then I think...
the particular solution we hit on actually came, I was re-watching the Lord of the Rings films and
uh there's the bit where the, I've forgotten her name, but the lady in armor like the the king of
the undead guy says you know no man can kill me and she rips off her helmet and says I am no man
and then plunges a sword into him and and kills him. Yes. And I thought oh I love that thing of
heroic figures having like
a call to arms or having a kind of motto or having or doing a big speech on the battlefield where
they say for god and king henry and then everyone suddenly is buffed up and can do stuff and that
idea really resonated for me because it kind of connected the the mythological tone but also the
strategy board game so at that point oh right okay basically they should do a special move when
they're able to shout a rallying cry yeah and
That brought me to think, well, okay, what gives you a rallying cry?
And like, well, it's you declaring your love for someone, it's you're losing,
you've lost your lover on the battlefield.
And that just felt so rewarding and so good that we had to explore it.
And like, yeah, it's quite weird in a way, because it means that you have,
you don't really know what's going to happen in terms of what moves you'll get or what moves,
or how the moves will change over time.
But the one thing I really like is when you've got a move that's really good and you're really enjoying using it
and it's connected to something like, you know, I found my love
and then your love gets murdered by a spider on the battlefield and you lose that move
and it changes to, you know, I will avenge my fallen love
and you get something else because you lost something
because the character did lose something.
That's just lovely.
Like that kind of, where the change in the narrative causes the gameplay to change in a way that you might not actually like
that isn't technically an upgrade.
But it's right. And that felt to me really strong and really interesting.
And I'm kind of every time the system can do that, can make something happen,
which is not great, but feels appropriate.
Yeah. And I think, yeah, no, we found something interesting there.
Before our nerd crit gets slammed too hard, it is AoN who shouts that, and I also double-checked that if you saw me go off my phone,
because I really wanted to make sure I didn't have AoN and Arwen mixed up, because I am a nerd and nerds are pedantic.
But yeah, I love that example, Jon.
Tom, did you have any thoughts about, from a design perspective, how these narrative abilities manifest and how they make your game better? Your perfect chess?
Yeah, so John was always like, oh, I want to add this thing.
And from the story side, it's going to change the gameplay.
And every time he said that, I'd be like, oh, no,
he's going to break the game.
And I kept throwing down these rules like, OK, yeah, fine.
They can get abilities, but we have to test all the abilities
really carefully because they don't want to break anything.
And they all need to be perfectly
balanced with each other.
And actually, in the end, a lot of that
turned out not to be true for the reasons John was saying.
It's.
So long as they are narratively appropriate, it's actually really interesting when you get a move that is...
actually quite overpowered or maybe it's underpowered because the thing that caused it is
embarrassing or sad or just sort of fits the tone. And there's also sort of moves that feel
like they've been meaningfully upgraded or downgraded and you just don't get that sense
if everything is sort of perfectly balanced, which was kind of always my instinct for this
game is to keep everything very pure and elegant. And I feel that that's this really nice tension
in the game with sort of...
Yeah, the way that the gameplay and the story interact.
It doesn't ever fight, but it creates, yeah, this tension all of the time.
My writing-loving brain really wants to dive into more of the, like,
writing Arthurian legend, blah, blah, blah,
but I also want to linger here in game design world for a minute longer.
You know, we've sort of talked about abilities,
we've talked about movement and traversal and adding things to the game,
but how do you, like, how...
In a game where like the game has to generate scenarios for the player like this one's really interesting the one we're in right now
Because this isn't a clear friend or foe situation with where we're going
Um, although these rats apparently move diagonally and attack diagonally. Um, which is just video games. Um, uh
What is the secret sauce to making interesting encounters so that the computer can go,
oh, I'm going to grab this, and this will be the right time for the player to encounter this thing,
even though I am a dumb computer and I will only do what I am told to do, and I have no agency.
For now.
Yeah, that was really hard, actually. So, um, internally there's...
I totted them up on Twitter just the night before release and I think there's something like 20 different heuristic or analytic or algorithmic or AI systems in the game that determine and control what the game is doing or what the game is going to give to the player, like in terms of the board layout or where the resources are spread.
And one of those systems is the one that decides what...
what scene you're going to encounter.
So very broadly, the game has template scenes that you can get into.
So this one that you're playing at the moment is the meeting the archer
in the woods scene.
And that's quite a specific one because it's always the archer.
But they might be quite generic ones as well.
Like, you know, go to a village that's got a problem with some animals
and like the animals can change and the villagers can change whatever.
and that system looks at what you've done and looks at what you're about to do and looks at
where you are through the game and looks at it looks at a whole bunch of stuff and it doesn't
generate a level i shouldn't really reveal this because i feel like it's secret sauce but like
um it doesn't decide what scene you're going to get until the absolute last possible moment
and then it's all just balanced to try and make sure that the adventure is
interesting, like that's its goal. There are lots of systems in the game which are fair or which are
kind of, you know, based on difficulty sliders, but this particular one is purely for narrative
interest. And I remember just about a day before we shipped the demo, which was like one, it was
five levels long, it was a run through five levels long, and it did a tutorial and then it did another
level and then at the end of it, it tended to give you a hero, a new hero in a castle. You get to the
castle, you meet them.
And it was this really limp ending to a demo, because it felt like, oh, everything's going fine here.
So I wrote a version of the scene where you go to the castle and the hero's supposed to be there, but they're not.
And there's a Mordred knight there instead, who says, oh yes, Sir Kay was here, and I killed him.
And that was such a good ending for the demo, because it was like, dun dun dun!
Um...
And that kind of...
totally like non-design focused pacing but much more narrative pacing of just sort of playing it
and feeling like well have we had enough tension recently have we had enough drama recently well
okay what what lever can we poke or what variable can we tweak to try and make it a bit more inclined
to give you something exciting now because you're sort of at the right kind of time for that um
and that took ages
to get right, but it was kind of just another kind of balancing really, in the same way
that we balance the AI, we balance the board generators.
It was just another system that wanted to stick its elbow in and muck around with the
game experience.
I felt we got that right.
Tom, do you want to throw in anything at all?
Yeah, it's really complicated.
It's like this one...
I mean like...
I'm allegedly the programmer on the game, but I'm fairly certain that the ink script,
which is sort of John's side of things, which is supposed to be for the story,
but actually has ended up being just this massive amount of logic control.
Everything, like so much AI has ended up being piled onto the ink.
And while a lot of gameplay stuff is kind of like, okay, we're gonna build a feature and then it's in and then that's just a box and then you can stack the boxes on top of each other, this thing was just constantly improving for like the whole year and a half of development.
Gotcha. Let's talk about failure. Failure will come much later in the stream because thankfully I'm sort of savvy.
This is a game where failure...
Actually, no, we're gonna get some mild failure,
I think, in a few minutes.
Sorry, pre-recorded footage.
I hate sounding like a prophet.
But failure is a weird thing in games
because it's, failure in a shooter means,
oh, okay, I can try again
and I can do a Twitch skill a little bit better.
In a procedural game, failure might go,
oh, well, come on, you gave me this
when my health was low.
Come on, why didn't the RNG go Twitch this way?
But because you have a game where we talked about failure sometimes means interesting things change in the narrative and the abilities like
This is a this is a specific
Like it feels like you need a specific vision for how players fail in order to make this game fun
Is that accurate and if I'm wrong, tell me why?
No, that's absolutely accurate
And it's something that we thought about a lot and actually has been a kind of common recurring theme throughout all the stuff that we've done
at Inkle
that we're always interested in creating a story that has a beginning and a middle and an end.
And the problem with failure, and it is a drastically serious problem from a narrative
point of view, is that the minute that the player fails and tries again, the narrative dies
completely until the player has got to and surpassed whatever point it was where they were getting stuck.
And there is only one solution to that in current games,
which is the time loop solution, where you go,
oh, well, we just do the whole level again,
and that's that part of the narrative.
And it's fine, but not every game can be a time loop game.
Yeah.
So what we've tried to do, and we tried to do it in...
We sort of dabbled with it in Sorcery,
but we definitely do it in 80 Days,
and we do it in Heaven's Vault, too,
is this idea of failing forwards.
Mm-hmm.
So in Heaven's Vault, you can miss.
I'm running away right now. This is failure.
Yeah, right. Exactly. Exactly.
So, like, in Heaven's Vault you can completely miss huge amounts of, like, the content and the clues that might be in a particular location.
And the narrative will work to cope to make sure that that just becomes the way that your story went,
rather than where you need to backtrack and pick up that key that was in that chest, like in most adventure games.
In 80 Days, of course, there's no way to die, really, and if you go over 80 Days, it's not a problem.
So for this game, we knew we wanted the idea that you could fail, but that it would push you forwards and it would push your narrative forwards.
But then you have that question of, well, how do you do that if when you get killed, you get killed?
Which obviously led to us bringing in the flee button, which was pretty controversial, you know, within the team.
And I know Tom was convinced for a long time that no one would ever press.
a flee button because it was like having a button that literally said I am a loser when you press it.
He may not be wrong, it still may be true.
Well it may be, but like even, well the weird thing is even when it's strategically absolutely
the correct thing to do, like you know you're massively overwhelmed, you don't have the support
structure to do it, you could throw all your knights at this problem and kill them all,
or you could flee and save your entire party. That's a reasonable thing to do strategically,
but in game world it feels...
completely unpalatable and I thought that was a really interesting friction actually to kind of
bring the player up against this idea that they feel that they're supposed to win every encounter
but the game is a tragedy about being overwhelmed by forces much stronger than you, like you ought
to flee, like you ought to flee because everything's going wrong, you ought to flee because you found
a level that's too hard, you ought to read the board and decide you can't win this one and go
and do another one and those were all interesting and they come with other narrative consequences
attached to them.
Yeah, this is about to get very interesting in gameplay for what you're talking about
with where Gwynevere winds up, because this is a can't flee level because I've already
fled.
Right, okay, yeah, so some of the levels, so that kind of went backwards and forwards
what the balance of that was, but yeah, there are some levels where you can't flee to create
pinch points where you can die early, because in the end we decided it was nice, it was
nice to have that as an option.
But then there's also the other kind of...
uh way of avoiding failure which is the rage mechanic which i i don't know if
that's going to happen in your oh it's gonna oh it's gonna happen
yeah right and that again was just it was it was kind of thinking about well
what's fun like because we do want the game to
be fun as well and so if you're overwhelmed and you get trapped in a
corner and then your character just flips out and completely loses their rag
and turns into an unstoppable terminator with you know a cost associated with
that
that felt really interesting and it felt really enjoyable to play and it was just a lovely narrative moment.
Everybody remembers the first time their character goes into rage mode.
So it just,
it was really interesting to me that this idea of saying we are not going to let you simply die
opened up an enormous number of design questions and design ideas and design and narrative opportunities that we simply wouldn't have even thought about
if we just said, yeah, when you die, you die and then you restart.
you know, or you can restart any level at any time, which was a button we had.
Well, I mean, we still have it in the debug build for the game,
but like that was going to be a button the player could press, you know, just go again.
And now it's rage time.
So here we'll get to show off that mechanic right now.
Right. You can lose a raid if you don't manage to murder everyone
in within the kind of time limit.
He's got like an energy bar which goes down.
But you also are very, very overpowered when you're in rage mode.
That really is just about.
And hey, that applies for real life too.
Ayyy.
Yeah, exactly.
Tom, do you want to throw in on failure, making failure interesting, before I move on to my next question?
Yeah, I guess it's, I mean, I think Jon sort of said it all, but I feel like it's almost
an Inkle philosophy at this point. Every time I pitch a new game design to Jon, he says,
yeah, okay, what happens if you die? And I never have a good answer. And something Jon
says a lot, and I think it's definitely true in this, is...
It's about surprising the player, so when they think they've lost,
you can give them an extra life that they didn't know they had.
And that's sort of what Rage Mode is here. It's like,
ah, you really thought you'd lost, but now we're going to give you one more chance.
And you obviously can't keep giving that to the player.
They can't keep failing forward all the way to the end.
But it's a sort of get out of jail free card you didn't know you had.
And I feel that's a lesson that's applicable to a lot of games, actually.
You can kind of hide a little extra continue in there.
I like that.
In fact, for the longest time, we had, heroes could have zero health and they'd still be
alive and this is kind of that philosophy extended and we took that one out in the end
because it was sort of too against game convention where, you know, if you have one heart.
and you lose it, you expect to die.
What we had before that was if you have one heart and you lose it,
well, now you have no hearts, you're not dead, you just have no hearts,
and then it would take another hit to die.
And John really, really liked this, and I kept pushing back,
and in the end, I think it was just because players kept reporting it as a bug
that we took it out, but it would have fit the philosophy,
and it would have, I think if players had understood it,
it would have felt good for the same reason that Rage Mode felt good,
which is just that they thought they'd lost.
and then they kind of get this moment of hope.
Yeah, sadly I think we've been too conditioned by red bars in video games in general.
Um, we are a stupid lot.
Um, okay.
Uh, now I finally get to be the story nerd that I love being.
Uh, this is an Arthurian game.
Um, Arthurian legend and Arthurian lore is...
Interesting, uh, because by- even the game kind of reflects this. It's a little bit whatever you want it to be.
Do you want the happy story? Well, it's about Arthur finding the stone, or finding the- pulling the sword out of the-
No, wait. Lady in the Lake. Right, Arthur is Lady in the Lake. Um, uh...
If you want that, that's how you get Excalibur, that's the hero story.
If you want the comedy version, you get Monty Python and the Holy Grail.
If you want the tragic version, you have the various Merlin miniseries which have
made their way to TV. Like the whole story of Arthur, and I'm speaking as an American,
so I'm literally like this is the most outside perspective, well not the most outside perspective,
but it's a very outside perspective on...
on something that seems very...
Like, everyone has opinions about this, you know?
And instead of telling sort of one linear story about Arthurian legend,
you've told a lot of different stories at once that, like, you know...
And I'm curious how, once that, where that came into the game
and how that influenced the narrative and design direction.
Yeah, so, I mean, I've always...
I've always been an Arthurian.
nerd. I loved Arthurian Legends as a kid. My favorite book is an Arthurian retelling. So I
kind of had that context and I think when we were first kind of thinking about narrative frameworks,
the idea of making it knights in armor battling out just sort of fitted the flow of the game.
A few people have described it as being a bit like a dance. You kind of dance around the board and
strike when you can and it feels a bit like swordplay. It feels a bit like that kind of
a swashbuckling feel, especially when they're trading insults while they're moving around.
So that tone of being knights with big swords thwacking each other really heavily and really
hard felt right for the pace of the game that we'd built.
In terms of the narrative more widely though, I think it was quite a struggle for a while
to work out how to make it work, because as you say, the Arthurian legend is a lot of
different stuff and it covers an enormous amount of time.
But we knew that we wanted something very focused on combat, because that's the core mechanic,
very focused on traversing across the space, across Britain.
So it could have been the quest for the Holy Grail, but it just feels quite nerdy in a way, and not actually that compelling.
And I don't know when it was that we had this idea of setting it after the end of the Arthurian myth,
and that felt tonally right to me.
that the goal of the game is not even to save Arthur or to build Camelot, it's just to literally
witness him die.
And that felt like, it had the right sense of, well you're going to die, everyone is
going to die, the question is only where do you die and how do you die and how well do
you die.
And that had all that kind of chivalric sort of honour against the darkness, like hope
when...
hope is unreasonable, which I think speaks to me as a tonal thing, but it also makes the gameplay
feel kind of tense and taut and fraught with danger and it ties into that mechanic that we have that
which I don't think we've mentioned, which is just that anyone on the board can be killed at any time
and the narrative will deal with that. You know, nobody is ever safe at all and if you want to
murder all your key people then you can and you will sometimes, whether you want to or not.
But it also tied very strongly into the political angle as well,
that I think when we were getting inspired about this game,
I realised that one of the reasons that I wanted to do Arthur was...
the what was happening in British politics at the time which is still
happening and it's very much comparable I think to what's happening in American
politics as well where you have a new class of
leaders who are so committed to lying to us and to
and to hurting the population that they're supposed to be protecting they
are so happy to do that and they do on a daily
basis you know in America the the COVID situation is unbearable the
police brutality situation is unbearable Britain is not quite that bad but we are
not doing very well either
And that sense of a leadership that has abdicated its moral responsibility to its people is at the
core of the end of the Arthurian narrative as well. Arthur is this noble just king who is
thrown off the throne by his son who's just rubbish, who's just this power-hungry brat
who doesn't want anything apart from just to hurt his dad and to screw stuff up.
and Arthur goes to face him even though he knows he can't win against this, he can't,
he doesn't have a chance but he has to, and that's always spoke to me as a kind of,
you know, as an honourable and noble sacrifice in that kind of romantic vision.
The book that I liked as a kid, which is called The Once and Future King, was written
very much about the rise of Nazism in the 30s, but as a King Arthur story, but that it's that same tone and that
same tone applies now and that sense of
we can be good people and we should be good people.
And what do you do when the people in charge and the people who have all of the power
have absolutely no moral compass at all and you have to fight even though you can't possibly win? And that
that felt to me like a story that
that I was happy to tell, that I wanted to tell, that I was angry enough to tell,
and that needs to be out right now.
And that got me through the writing process.
Because I think if I was just writing some Arthurian legend, you're right,
it would be like, well, here's a giant and here's like a quest for a stone
and here's a magic screaming rock.
And it would all be very arbitrary and very random.
And I think the reason that the game...
Sorry, I've gone all serious, but...
The reason that the game hangs together thematically is because underneath all that Arthurian stuff and the thwacking and the board game and all of that is this consistent, angry, passionate, moral core.
And that's something that as a writer, I believe that we should always have.
And I think games often don't bother to have because they're scared of being political or they're worried that they're going to tell people what to think, which is absolutely not the point. It's not about telling people what to think.
It's about getting people to feel something consistently and be involved with that feeling.
And that was so important to me, that that really tied it together.
So for me, it's because Arthur is actually such a deep symbol in the British psyche and
also in the American, I think, by extension, of what our leaders are supposed to be like,
what government is supposed to be like, what the country is supposed to be like.
We're supposed to live in a world of round tables and nights.
And we like to believe that we do.
but we often don't.
And I think that, yeah, that really was the motor
behind the storytelling for me.
And I, yeah, and I hope some of that comes across to people.
I really do, because I think it's terribly important.
I think it comes across in this one run we did, like as you watch the whole arc of it.
Tom, I keep just going, I keep throwing out a question, John answers, and then I go, Tom,
do you want to weigh in?
But that's all I can do.
Tom, do you want to weigh in on your thoughts about turning your beautiful board solve chess
game into something Arthurian and messy?
No, everything he said.
The theme fit really well.
I think we all realized that.
We tried some other themes a little bit.
Ages and ages ago, we were thinking how it could be a court case and it was two lawyers fighting
I don't even know how that was supposed to work
and there's
Like we flip-flopped on a lot of things. Um, like really early on before we started really developing it full-time
But I think this was something we were really consistent on. Yeah
Um, uh, yeah, there's one neat- oh, I think we're actually about to come across it.
Um, there's one neat feature in this game, which is the Tales game.
I completely forgot to mention this at the top, but, uh, we low-key have to do some disclosure.
Um, this is a GDC Twitch stream, but we also, you know, this is also tied to Gamasutra,
and Gamasutra editor Chris Kerr is one of the people who submitted a story for your, uh, campfire.
feature where the characters hang out and talk about the fire.
Chris Kerr is a great writer and I'm so glad that he got something in.
The one we'll see in the stream is actually really fun.
We'll see it, I guess it's not this encounter but maybe the next one.
What were your
thoughts on that and roping good writers in to write little tales for you?
That's a neat story, what was all that about?
I'm so happy we did that and that was a complete stroke of luck really.
So we had this mechanic of people sitting around the campfire in the game
for a while and it was really just a way of gaining an extra health point and
they would sort of run some conversation between their characters
and I felt like they didn't have quite enough to talk about and obviously at a
campfire what you do is you tell a story so I thought okay maybe sometimes they
could tell a story and I wrote a story and I thought I'll write some more of
those later I just I don't feel inspired right now.
Then lockdown happened, coronavirus, COVID lockdown happened.
And there was kind of this mood in the air of lots of people stuck at
home and not quite knowing what they were doing.
And it kind of, I thought what I really, what we really want to do, I had this
sudden urge to try and make some space for some people
to do something nice and do something like
fun and interesting and take their minds off this thing.
We didn't have an enormous budget for this game, I couldn't hire extra writers in any way,
no one would have been able to understand the way the game was written internally because it's such
a mess. Like, you know, there was no way to hire co-writers for the game, but here was this
this one aspect, these campfire killers, which was not only perfect for packaging up and giving
to people who had no idea how the rest of the game worked and didn't need to know,
but also would really benefit from getting, you know, different
voices. So I pitched it to Joe, Joe Humphrey, the co-founder of Inkle, and said, you know,
can we spend a bit of money and get some writers? And he said, well, we can try, but like, do you
think they're going to be any good? And we sort of thought, well, we really have no idea. We just
have to try. And I remember we put the call out for writers, and it was quite widely promoted,
actually, which was really nice. I felt it captured the mood of the moment quite well,
just this sense of people, look, here's a nice thing to do. Do it if you can, if you feel like it.
And I remember the very first story that we got sent back was from one of, it's in the game,
and it's called The Man Who Couldn't Fart. And the note that came with it said,
despite the title, this is a serious story, I hope you enjoy it. And I thought, oh god, here we go,
you know, this is what I've let myself in for. And I read The Man Who Couldn't Fart, and I was,
I'll be honest, I was blown away. It's an amazingly good story, it's got a really
quality moral, it's geniusly delivered.
And I just thought, oh wow, this is gonna work.
This is actually gonna work.
And over the next, I think it was two,
maybe three weeks of submission period,
we got something like 500 entries.
So I was just constantly reading these tales.
My family would come downstairs in the morning
and I'd be sitting there on my laptop
going, I've read another 15 of these things.
And like just churning through and churning through.
And here we go, here's the-
And the kind of averages worked out, if you might.
Oh, which one is it?
Um, the story of failure.
The lonely knight and...
A knight who fails at his quest.
Oh, it's, um, Baldwin and the Chalice.
Yes.
Yeah.
Um, and...
Yeah, the averages kind of worked out,
you like, might, you might expect
maybe 10% of the stories were not great.
Um, and then 10% of them were absolutely
dishing, and then there was a middle ground
where we had to find the ones that...
for our game and our characters and our universe.
But it was a really enjoyable process.
And kind of bringing those together,
I was just delighted, actually.
I was delighted with how it went.
And they still just make me so happy
when I find them in the game.
And I feel like they're kind of the heart and soul
of the game, is this idea of.
voices and stories and stories mattering and uh yeah i love all of that stuff i really do i love
this little story um we started a little late i think i'm still gonna cruise us in for a i'm gonna
cruise us in for a landing soon um uh you know best best best to get out while you're still
welcome is one of my philosophies in life maybe maybe that's why uh i'm not a rich man but i
don't know wow that got really too weird and deep okay that's what covid let me tell you as an
interviewer
has made interviewing so weird because you're trying to have a conversation
acting like everything's normal.
And then midway through, you just sort of like have to admit it's not.
And I'm so thankful that you two have discussed that covid and locking down
has influenced your work as designers because it saved me
sort of assessing the generic question, how are you doing?
How is your lockdown going?
And in the UK, you have a totally different lockdown situation over here.
Like apparently I hear it's illegal to drive halfway across the country
to test your eyesight over there.
Well they keep changing their mind about whether that's legal or not, but I think it basically
boils down to it depends on who your father is.
Oh boy.
Oh that's this country too.
Oh no.
Anyway, so if you have questions for John and Tom, let's get them in.
I guess...
Oh man, do I have any questions left? I think I do.
Hopefully chat is willing to throw in something intelligent, uh, because I try to be an intelligent person.
But like I said, this is... the masks, like, the mask of professionalism slips more often when you're...
when you're just like, oh shit, this interview wraps up and I have to go sit in my apartment
some more and then my day wraps up and I sit in my apartment playing video games like Pendragon.
I guess, oh, oh okay, I have one.
It's shown up in the stream already so we're past it.
There's a line that repeats which is where Guinevere says this...
This plot, this field reminds me of where Arthur chose to build Camelot.
And it fires twice in this playthrough, and on the second one,
Guinevere talks about something different that followed the first one.
And I feel like this is a huge challenge for procedural narrative.
It's why sometimes, like, I start off procedural narrative games,
and then I bounce, is at a point where I'm like,
okay, I'm running through some of the same basic beats before,
and it doesn't feel, it feels stiff.
It feels like a machine is spitting words out at me.
And I think it's for better and for worse that good games and bad games I've played have encountered this.
I love Blaseball, but this sort of might be why I bounced off Blaseball when I tried it.
I don't know if you two know what Blaseball is, but I don't either, so that's okay.
Um, uh, um, but yeah, like, what do you think, like, you know, for a company that keeps doing procedural narrative,
what do you think is sort of the sauce behind making sure that your computer, which is taking inputs and spitting outputs...
you know, ones that you've carefully strung together, but still,
you know, how do you make sure that stories feel like stories and not
inputs and outputs, I guess? Like, that's my last question for the
both of you.
Yeah, that's quite a big question. So I think repetition is a
particularly bad thing, because we're so good at
noticing it as people.
And Dragon actually contains a whole bunch of systems to prevent repetition from one game to the next game.
Like, actually, it remembers quite a lot of what you see.
It remembers everything you see during the game.
That's just what the Ink Engine does.
But actually, it remembers most of what you've seen during all your previous games as well,
to try and mix things up and try and find new routes through the content and avenues that you haven't seen before.
There's a limit to how much of that we can do because...
like we can't record every word.
Obviously, this is a game you might play 200 times.
But it's definitely something we've worked really, really hard
to try and avoid.
But a lot of it is actually a balancing problem.
You need a decent amount of content,
and you need the content to be able to vary itself,
which is something that the Ink Engine is very good at.
So, you know, a single sentence can...
turn out different ways depending on who's saying it and how they're feeling and just
random numbers as well. But I think also it's about kind of what we try to do is we try to
lay down a bedrock of things that the game can say which are very self-varying but will work
and then to pick out as much specific context as we can. So the way that the system works,
I think I wrote a Garner Sutra article about this actually, but the way the system works is that it
looks for...
very specific matches for the current context and then dropped back to generic ones that can't find
any. So if you have a move where it's Guinevere and she is attacking a creature and the creature
has just attacked one of her own pieces, there might be a specific line of dialogue for that
exact context which will fire under very random, rare circumstances because it's so specific.
So that doesn't need much variation but if it turns out that it can't find any of those and
it'll drop back something more generic which is just the usual kind of...
Guinevere runs across the ground and wallops something with her sword, of which you will have seen the same line of content
50, 100 times, just tweaked and varied by the context.
But yeah, it's an enormous problem, and I think Pendragon is an attempt to tackle it much more than we ever have
before. 80 Days does a little bit of this stuff in some places, and Heaven's Vault does too,
but Pendragon pretty much is entirely built out of
content which is actually repeating itself all the time, but attempting to disguise that
as much as possible. And largely getting away with it, I think. But yeah.
Tom, do you have any...
There are always going to be some repetitions along the way.
Do you have any thoughts?
I actually have a question for John also, because John is the master of story. I just
make like code things happen. I'm curious to know whether...
it was easier to give the ink solid pieces of state that you could work off with this game,
which is obviously really state-based, or something that's more woolly and story-based,
like Heaven's Vault or something, where there's no fixed positions of things,
there's just you're in a world and there's stuff around.
Yeah, this was a lot easier.
Like, the bedrock of Heaven's Vault is the knowledge map,
which is kind of all the things that Aaliyah can be thinking or realise
during the course of the game.
And that is impossible to really write down,
so the only way to make the dialogue work is to have that knowledge map
entirely in your head while you're writing it.
So at the time that was okay, but now when I look back at it,
I have no idea what's going on.
Oh John, I lost you. Tom, did you lose John?
Game side thing.
John, we lost you there for a second.
Am I back?
Yes, you're back.
Well,
in PedDragon anyway, there's a game side
thing which Tom wrote which works
out what the current move looks
like and assigns tags to it.
And that's a lovely piece of robust
analytical code. It just looks at the board
and looks at the squares and looks at the threats.
and then there's the ink side can just read off that completely and that separation between
the kind of game analysis and then the ink just running with it that made it a lot easier to do
I think that there was a clear a really clear distinction whereas Heaven's Vault everything
is very muddy um so yeah not that I ever want to make a game like Pendragon again because it was
really very difficult I thought I don't know what do you think Dom was it hard?
Ah, it was hard in some ways and easy in others. I think maybe, I don't know, I think because
it's so much, um, I don't have a word for it, bucket of stuff approach where it's just everything
is contextual or at least so much is, it probably took it longer to come to life. I remember first
showing it to Joe when he came down first, showing him what we've been doing for a while.
and sort of having seen it in this state where like every time it would load a level it would
just say something completely random and you showed it to Joe and like he had this perfectly
normal playthrough and just everything just worked out and like after just piling stuff
into the bucket after like a few months all of a sudden oh no it can just sort of produce
like really robust content and like yeah the more you pile away the better that system gets.
Yeah, I do love the bucket of content approach actually for exactly that.
That when you get to the point where it starts to produce halfway sensible output,
then everything you do from there, every extra bit of content you add is just adding value
somewhere. And you don't know where it's going to come out or when it's going to come out,
but when it does, it's always like really, it's a real pleasure to see it when it does.
I remember that joke. Yeah, I have enjoyed that actually.
Right on, I think it's time to start wrapping up. I'll give a quick shoutout to Chaotic94 in chat, who just says,
love all the talks on YouTube, keep up the good work.
Uh, as a pitch for our friends at Inkle, there are some talks on the GDC YouTube channel from, uh,
from folks at Inkle about the making of games like Heaven's Vault, 80 Days, and so on.
Um, one of my favorites, it's not Joe Tomer.
or John here, but Meg Giants talk about NPCs in 80 days and how you can empower your NPCs to tell
better stories in games. One of my favorite talks and one of my inspirations for some of the writing
I've done outside of, you know, I love it. I love thinking about game worlds in terms of the
characters you meet in them. So with that, John and Tom, if they have more questions for you about
Pendragon, where can they ask them? And also, where can they buy Pendragon? I might as well
let you pitch the game.
So, Pendragon is available now with a 10% discount all week on this weird little shop called Steam that you might have heard of,
and also on this lovely shop called GOG which you might also have heard of,
and also on the Mac App Store if you're unfortunate enough to ever use the Mac App Store.
I'm joking, it's wonderful.
And yeah, you can get it there.
And if you want to talk to us, we're at Inkle Studios on...
We also have a Discord channel, but you can find that from Twitter probably.
Also, it's in the game. You can access... I thought this was really smart.
You can hit escape and you can click join Discord, which I think more devs are doing.
Oh, there you go. So you need to buy the game so you can join our discord. You can ask about the game
There you go
Okay with that, uh before everyone on my team gets horrifically murdered
I'm going to end this looking like i'm a smart strategic person and bid you all adieu
We're actually uh for fans of gdc. It's gonna be an interesting week for us tomorrow
We have a stream with uh, the ceo of proletariat. They make spell break. Um, uh later this week
We've got some cool things coming down the pipe about what is happening next gdc is going to be
next
Next year?
Question mark?
We've announced July things, but I don't... it's all weird.
It's... it's...
I mean, we're... no, that's announced.
That's confirmed, to be clear.
But also, like, we're still figuring out how to make GDC happen in...
in these uncertain times.
So we're doing that.
We're trying to bring more lessons for you.
We're bringing more great interviews with developers.
We're excited to keep,
we're excited that as the world enters a weird space,
people want to keep making games.
And we want to keep talking to them about making games
and learning what they've learned, et cetera, et cetera.
That's always going to be,
it's so thrilling to see that that like holds up
even when everything gets weird.
And I'm just grateful that John and Tom are willing to talk about like how a weird world influences
Making and releasing games it's gonna be a weird like man you two are it's gonna be weird for all your colleagues in a year
So when they release their games and they're like, yeah, we finished this in lockdown
That influenced some stuff
Anyway with that odd note, I will end this stream and wish everyone a good day. Thank you for let for hanging out
Thank you chaotic 94 other folks and have a good day. Bye
Bye.