Why do this talk?
So I think this was probably the best illustration I could find.
Suppose that two 30-year-old recent MBAs, a man and a woman,
receive job offers for $100,000 a year.
By negotiating, the man raises his offer to $111,000,
while the woman accepts the $100,000.
Because that's pretty good money, right?
Even if both receive identical 3% raises for the rest of the careers, by the time they retire at 65,
the difference between their annual salaries will have widened to over $30,000.
The man who negotiated will also earn more than the woman during every one of the 35 years in
which they work. If he invests that extra income,
into an account earning 5%, that initial $11,000,
the product of a single one-time negotiation,
turns into $1.6 million by the time he's 65 years old.
So in short, an absolute goddamn fucking shit ton of money.
Thank you, Cindy Gallop.
And we want you to get your absolute goddamn fucking shit
ton of money, both men and women.
And I get it.
This shit is intimidating.
Getting past that initial hurdle
and actually going to the table and negotiating
and not just taking what you're offered, that's hard.
So as part of this, we've assembled a panel
of amazing speakers, or two amazing speakers in my ass.
So Robin here is gonna be talking through more
of the kind of emotional hurdles behind
getting up to doing salary negotiations.
I'm going to talk through some of the tools, tips, resources,
and just kind of prep work that you want to do getting into negotiations.
And then Elizabeth's going to bring it home with the other side of the table,
the perspective of the hiring manager.
So without further ado, I'm going to hand you over to Robin.
Hello. Thanks, Sarah.
All right, I would love to get a sense of who is in the room with us today.
So if you'll indulge me, could you raise your hand if you are currently looking
for or working in the first job in the game industry?
Wow. Oh, that's so exciting.
Give me a round of applause.
That's really, really exciting to see you guys here.
Raise your hand if you've ever tried to negotiate a job offer before.
Okay, good, good, good.
Keep your hand up if you successfully negotiate a job offer.
What are you guys doing here?
Go see something else.
I'm kidding, you can stay.
Raise your hand if you were just thankful
to get a job offer at all,
and so you just didn't negotiate.
Yeah, all right, all right.
Those are my people, all right.
Hi, my name is Robin.
I lead product strategy at Code Combat,
where we make a game that teaches computer science.
We are in half a million.
We are played by over half a million players in the US alone,
and we are in over 15,000 schools.
And I've been in this industry for over 12 years.
I started my career as a news editor,
and eventually I moved into game production and design,
where I shipped dozens of web and mobile games.
Most recently, I ended up in user experience design,
which led me to join Code Combat, where I negotiated
a promotion to product manager.
And now I lead strategy for one of the best coding
games that's out there.
Thanks.
I'm getting slides.
All right.
Why is negotiation terrifying?
Let's talk about feelings for a little bit.
Let's imagine for a second being in that space.
So you found a job posting that you got really excited about.
You thought you met the requirements, right?
And you got a response from your application saying,
hey, we'd love to talk to you.
We think you might be a really good fit for this role.
So maybe you do some phone interviews.
Maybe you got brought onto an on-site.
You spent a lot of time getting real excited about this job.
You're really eager to hear back.
And then.
Yeah, you see this, this call or the female comes in.
Whoo, that is good.
I mean, I have a job right now, and I'm still
excited to see this, right?
We'd love to extend to you an offer to join our team.
It feels amazing.
Every bone in your body, every fiber of your being is like,
yes, let's friggin' do this, right?
And this is the last thing you want to do after all that
is to negotiate, right?
You want nothing to do with that conversation.
Maybe you weren't prepared, or maybe you
haven't researched the salary ranges.
Maybe you have no idea what to do next.
Because what if you ask and something bad happens, right?
Like, what if you ask and?
you appear ungrateful or unreasonable.
All of those feels are terrifying,
and that's the reason I want to call that out.
There's a lot to recognize about the emotional components
of negotiation, and I want to talk about all those feelings
that we get.
But I also want to call out that I
think all these things are swirling
around one big unspoken thing, specifically
in the game industry.
And it is.
that like why is it truly truly terrifying to make that ask when you're in the game industry?
Because this is my dream job, right? How many raise your hand if you have thought this to
yourself as you've like gone through a job interview process, right? This could be it.
This could be my dream job. So here's the secret. Our industry traffics in dream jobs.
You've heard this from friends before, right?
You are so lucky to be working in the game industry.
Wow, that must be so cool.
And you've thought this to yourself before, right?
You know what?
Things are really stressful.
I'm working 70, 80 hours a week, but you know, I'm so lucky
to be working in the game industry.
I should be grateful.
People would kill for this job.
And you've heard it from your peers, the hourly rates
that they settle for to work on the biggest franchises.
And I think we use the idea of a dream job
to use it as a bludgeon as a manner of all labor
complaints, compensation complaints,
and any career development that you really want.
Because the message that we receive at the end of the day
is, sure, you can have your dream job
of working in the game industry, but only conditionally, right?
I think the industry is really poor for these dynamics, these stories that we have to give
up control, we have to give up agency in order to have dream jobs.
I think they stunt us, I think they burn us out.
And I think that this is the same dynamic that leads us to say yes to the first offer
that comes our way that causes us to believe that we shouldn't risk it.
We have to replace this belief in the dream job, right?
I think it's born from a place of fear, the fear of losing our chance to work at our like our favorite studio working on
our favorite franchises. I think we end up manifesting these fears and self-limiting beliefs
and it makes us feel like we can't negotiate because it's risking too much, right?
We have to acknowledge that these are the kinds of fears that are in place when we get to that moment when you see a
job offer land in your email inbox.
And I think we have to acknowledge that it's preventing us from shifting our mindset.
And so I want to talk specifically about three self-limiting beliefs that prevent us from
negotiating and how we need to change the way we approach them.
So self-limiting belief number one, I'm asking for too much.
Who's felt this when they were thinking about negotiating?
Super common feeling.
I think this one comes from the stories that we've
heard from other game developers getting shortchanged
or having to settle for less.
That may be true for them, but that doesn't
have to be true for you.
I think this feeling of asking for too much,
I think it comes from, oh, they must know more
about industry salary ranges than me,
or they must be offering me what I deserve.
Or maybe that's the way the pay scale
is at this particular studio.
there must be a reason the offer is where it is so if I can negotiate I'll
be seen as asking for too much. This is a huge self-limiting belief right because
we often gauge our self-worth on what other people tell us our worth is. So the
mind shift that we need to make here is I know my worth.
You have to know your market worth, right,
which is what Tara will cover in the strategies talk.
But I think you also really need to internalize this idea
that you are worthy, you guys are worthy of working
at a place that acknowledges and validates the values
and the skills that you're bringing.
I think we need to notice when this feeling comes up
of I'm not enough and realize that it's coming
from this kind of like unfounded fear, right?
It's not a reality and we can shift this mindset
and let go of judging our value
by what other people tell us it is.
And in this case, it may be that starting job offer.
So I think we need to shift our thinking to, I know my worth.
I deserve to earn a salary that is commiserate with the value
that I'll be creating for this company.
All right, self-limiting belief number two,
I'm not good enough.
Who's felt this before?
I feel this every day.
I think this one is especially rough,
especially when we worked so hard
to get to this dream job because in a lot of ways,
Maybe we didn't believe we could actually get the stream job to begin with right? This is imposter syndrome like 101
This is imposter syndrome in its most insidious form and it's a sense that like maybe I'm not
You know experienced enough to ask for a better offer or to negotiate because like yikes maybe I tricked them into hiring me
And I really should just be grateful that, you know, and just like get away with it.
And so, you know, I shouldn't make any noise because what if they realize that and you
know, they realize that I'm not actually supposed to have this job.
I should just lay low, not give them any chance to realize the mistake that they've made here.
So that's one of the huge problem.
Instead, we got to think about this.
I earned this offer.
This is the shift that I want us to make.
I already got this offer, right?
They made the decision already to hire you.
You crushed that interview.
You showed up and you showed them all the things
that you're gonna be bringing to this job,
your enthusiasm, your skills, your dedication,
your commitment to this game.
And if we can shift from feeling like I'm not good enough
and starting to let go of that imposter syndrome,
that self-belief, we can move towards actually
I already earned this offer. I can make sure it's truly what I want here.
So I think that this is an important shift to make because I think it starts
making sure that we're not only, you know, negotiating in service of getting the salary
that we want from a starting salary standpoint, but it's recognizing that you actually deserve
to be on this team, right? You've earned this offer and you deserve to work at this place.
And that's really important for this next one.
which is self-limiting belief number three.
They're hiring somewhere else.
They're gonna hire somebody else.
If I negotiate, they're gonna hire somebody else.
And this one is hard because you've already gotten
to this point where you have this job offer.
And this one's not just a mindset, right?
It's a rarity, but it's a reality.
We hear just enough that it kind of scares us
from asking because maybe this is the time that we're
going to get this happening to us.
So there's a lot here that strategy-wise
that Tara and Elizabeth will cover
about how to structure an ask so that you'll set yourself up
for success here.
But if you're letting your fear limit
trying to negotiate in the first place,
I think we're perpetuating a cycle that allows companies to continue this behavior on other
people. I think that this is like really, really damaging in that way. And I think that the
mindset shift that we need to make is that I can break this cycle, right? This is the mindset shift
we need.
Be the one to break the cycle.
Make it difficult for this company
to have to shoulder the burden of going
through the extra work of hiring another person
to potentially have to continue their search, right?
Again, you deserve to work in this game industry.
You have earned an offer.
And now you have an opportunity to break a cycle
that we know is being used to prevent other folks from getting
what they deserve.
Make sure that the next person that comes along
will be able to negotiate as well.
Break that cycle.
So the reason it's hard to negotiate is because we're led to believe this is our one shot at our dream job, right?
That's why all those fears are amplified. That's the notion that this is our chance.
Like this is how we're gonna make it.
But it's actually the same reason that we have to negotiate because if we don't negotiate, it's not actually our dream job.
I think we have to be willing to ask for what we deserve in service of making our dream jobs a reality.
And here's the real secret, negotiation begets negotiation.
I have a single slide with an image in this entire talk,
and that's how important this is.
If you give a mouse a cookie, they will ask for a glass of milk.
If you start your job with salary negotiation, you are setting yourself up
to be able to advocate for the things that will actually make this job
a dream job for you.
You're going to be able to advocate for the coworkers around you.
You're going to be able to ask for the support that you need.
You're going to be able to ask for that promotion
once you realize you've earned it right.
That's actually the creation of a dream job.
It doesn't happen when you accept the offer.
And it's not just about the starting salary or the benefits.
I think we gotta let go of this idea that the dream job is shaped in a package somehow.
We receive it and then we have to pretend that we have to hold on to it, right?
I think that when you realize that the dream job is something that you shape versus something
that is given to you, that's when you start to make the shift, right?
Negotiation begets negotiation.
Be the mouse.
Be the mouse that asks for the cookie.
This is your negotiation mantra.
I know my worth.
I earned this offer.
I can break the cycle.
You've got this.
Make the ask.
Shape your dream job.
We believe in you, and you have got this, folks.
So my portion of the talk is going to be focused a little more on finding the resources and the tools that are going to help you feel
prepared for your negotiations. So briefly, my name is Tara J. Branigan. I'm the community lead at 5CA. We're a
customer support outsourcer in the Netherlands.
I'm pretty much on Twitter 24-7, so if you ever have any questions, or you just want to reach out,
that's the best place to get me.
I've worked at a whole bunch of different game companies and non-game companies all around the globe.
And this is pretty much me on any given day.
I am an anxiety-filled mess about 24-7,
I'd say, not when I'm sleeping,
but also while I am sleeping.
I overthink everything constantly,
and I mean shit that I did back in elementary school
still recycles.
So for me, it's really important to have a foundation
of facts and figures and tools at my disposal,
because those are the things.
that calm me down and make me feel like I'm standing on firm ground.
In short, I like to be prepared.
And welcome to that being stuck in your head for the rest of the time here.
So, what's in your toolbox?
What are the things that you know going into salary negotiations?
What are the scripts that you've practiced?
Do you know what this job is worth?
When you're starting out, your toolbox might look a little more like this.
And that's okay, because as with anything,
you build on this over time. And I'm gonna say, I don't have all the answers.
I don't even have half the answers, but getting started is one of the hardest
things to do. So for me, one of the first steps is to
research and to ask. So there are tools out there, and I'll
I'll say like, treat things like Glassdoor and Payscale.
you know
You know, this is kind of the sad fact, and Robin talked about this a bit, is that
you have to kind of count on some game industry tax here, and that can be anything from 5 to 20%.
Community management, I use this one specifically because community managers in gamedev,
we're all getting screwed. Like, that's the nicest way I can put it. If you compare the
community manager salary for the average community manager in San Francisco at a given tech company,
versus, say, those two anonymous game dev salaries
both from the UK and the US,
you'll notice a substantial difference.
And part of that is, you know, understanding that
and pushing back against it,
because it doesn't actually change
until we start to push for our own value.
And if you have friends who have been in those roles
who will tell you their salary in a trustworthy environment,
do it. I'll tell you straight up,
when I started at PopCap some...
I don't even know how many years ago at this point.
That was like seven years ago.
I was making $75,000 as a community manager with one year experience.
It's gone down.
Fun thing about the state of California, so Californians.
you actually have access to an amazing law.
So this new law, AB 168, bars employers from asking about your salary history,
either past or current.
On top of that, if you ask them,
they must provide you with the salary ban for the role.
I highly recommend asking that.
And this applies to all job seekers.
It doesn't matter if you're entry-level or CEO,
you are able to take advantage of this.
Do it.
So for me, one of the things that was really useful, and I'll recommend to anybody,
after this talk, if you haven't already done it, go check out Tara Wheeler's
Minute Zero in the Gender Pay Gap. It's a free article. It's up on Medium. It's bloody brilliant.
She also did the Women in Tech book that actually goes into this in more in-depth,
but if you want to just get started right away, go for this. She outlines a lot of great scripts
that address some of the common problems in doing salary negotiations. So
Here's this is just one example. That's a great place to start.
I understand that you can't go outside of your salary band.
So let's work on finding other ways to get your offer.
I can't say that word. I'm sorry
with my others, because I love this company
and I really want to find a way to work here.
And this opens up the opportunity to look at things outside of salary as well.
Would you like to work from home a day each week?
That's worth a certain amount.
For me, I would absolutely sacrifice a little bit of money
to be able to work from home a day or two.
And you don't have to use these scripts one-to-one.
You don't have to practice these rote memorization.
That's actually going to come off a little robotic.
It's taking this idea and adapting it to your own way of communicating.
A special note as somebody who has moved abroad, make sure to look at the cost of living comparison
because it's not a one-to-one.
You know, $75,000 in Seattle, you're not going to get 75,000 euros in Stuttgart, Deutschland.
The thing to pay attention to, like this is just numbeo.com,
and these are not like directly,
you know, it's not going to give you exact costs,
but it's going to give you a nice rough idea
of what the differential is.
The big one to pay attention here is rent price,
because that's going to be a large portion
of your monthly income.
In the case of Stuttgart and Seattle.
Rent prices are 97% higher in Seattle, so that helps frame what you should be asking for
if offered a job in Stuttgart. So negotiations. Sometimes we kind of think of those like this,
right? Really hostile, you're trying to win, it's about beating the other person, right?
Well, not according to the FBI, actually. So Chris Voss was one of the top negotiators with the FBI.
He wrote this brilliant book, I recommend all of you check it out.
Even if you're not going into salary negotiations, this is great for day-to-day living.
It's called Never Split the Difference.
Negotiating as if your life depended on it.
And this is the sort of guy that they called in where, you know,
somebody's been taken hostage, they're going to kill him in seven days.
They're asking for $300,000.
What do we do?
This is not a situation where they're shouting.
Most of his.
Recommendations are actually about learning how to harness your voice,
learning the difference between an upward tone and a downward tone.
One suggests that there's more to be said and the other says this is the end of
the conversation. Learning how to mirror words selectively.
So this, I actually love doing this once I learned how to do this.
is mirroring words selectively is when somebody says something,
pick the last one to three words that they said and say,
it sounds like what you're saying is blah, blah, blah.
This is wonderful because one, it makes the other person feel like you are
genuinely listening to them and you genuinely understand them.
Two, it is a great stalling tactic for when you're frantically trying to figure
out the next thing to say because that actually doesn't take much mental
bandwidth.
Chris focuses a ton on empathy.
So a large part of negotiation is actually
about understanding the wants, needs,
and limitations of the other party.
It's not about a fight, it's not about who's going to win.
It's about learning how to find
where the win-win situation is.
And I can't get into all of this
because we only have so much time,
but I just want to say like the summary of this
is this is more about understanding other people,
the constraints that they are in,
listening to them as a human being, and finding a situation that works for both of you.
Again, it's not a battle. Your target is a win-win. A situation in which one person feels
cheated either direction is a bad way to enter a job. You do not want to enter a new role feeling
like you got screwed out of money. It will eat at you every single day. You will start to resent
your dream job.
And conversely, if an employer feels like you just went too far and they caved,
they're also not going to feel great about that situation.
So one of the things that always makes me feel good, and to be fair, I don't actually use this
in the negotiation. I'm not sure if you can even see that,
but I'll post a version of this up on the website later.
is I go through the process of writing out basically my hit list of like,
what is my goal? What is my current salary? What is the salary I want to get to? What are
the constraints around that? You know, is healthcare different in that state, that country?
A summary, why I'm great. Like, this makes me feel really good going into negotiations. It's
just a reminder that like, no, actually I am, you know, I earned.
I earned my place to get to the negotiation stage.
What they want, do I fit that?
Yes, I do.
So let's keep going along here.
Some calibrated questions.
Those are questions that are gonna pull out more information
about the role, their constraints, their limitations.
Realistically, a lot of negotiation
is just asking questions and genuinely listening.
And sometimes it's just saying like, well, you know, I'm the sole breadwinner of my family at this point in time.
That's probably not going to change for the next six months.
How am I supposed to make this offer work in the city?
And just posing that as a question and saying that nicely and openly,
people will naturally go into a mode of troubleshooting like, oh, OK, well, maybe we can do this.
Or, you know, would it be helpful if we gave your partner relocation assistance and job assistance?
These are all benefits that can be negotiated for as part of this process.
And again, I don't take this with me into the negotiation unless I'm able to do it by Skype,
and then I will totally have it open in another window for reference.
But I just look at this beforehand. It gives me a little more confidence on the next step.
And this is something that says a lot about me.
But sometimes it can be really useful to remember that it's not just about you.
When something's just about me, I'm really prone to just downplaying it,
like, oh, well, you know, it's not that big a deal.
It's just me. It's just me.
Which I mean, that's a whole separate, separate talk about self-care
that we will get into.
But for me, it can be really beneficial to just remember, like, look, me
negotiating means that it should be easier for the next woman
in the same situation in this company.
And I gotta say, there's nothing that made me more confident about negotiating
than being on the other side of the table.
So as a hiring manager, I learned very quickly what the wiggle room is,
what's acceptable, what's not acceptable.
And I'm not going to go in depth in that because that's all of Elizabeth's talk.
So without further ado.
Hi, everybody.
Before I get into my talk, I just
also want to put in a plug for the book,
Never Split the Difference.
It's really amazing.
I actually bought a copy for my studio,
and it gets a lot of circulation.
It's not just useful for salary negotiations,
but really any kind of trying to get to a consensus
that you will have to do in your work.
That said, hi, I'm Elizabeth Stampat.
I'm the studio creative director at Future Games of London.
We are an Ubisoft studio, and I just
want to let you know that we've just started pushing
a huge hiring campaign.
Every single one of our studios all over the world
is hiring right now.
So if you would like to get some experience with salary
negotiation, I strongly urge you to check out our hiring booth.
Before I was the creative director at FGAL, I was the game design department lead at Saibo Games,
and I was also one of the lead designers on Plants vs. Zombies 2 at PopCap.
I've been deeply involved in hiring in almost every job I've had over the last seven years,
whether in an independent company or in studios owned by larger companies.
And to my detriment, it took me a while to realize something important, which was the
ways in which I was getting hired were also the ways in which I was hiring other people.
The constraints that I was under as a hiring manager were often the constraints that people
trying to hire me were under as well.
I have friends with stories about how they tried to negotiate salary or benefits or something
else and instead of countering, the company did actually pull their offer.
If this has happened to you nine times out of ten, it's not because you said or did anything
inappropriate.
But sometimes there are just requests that hiring managers can't fulfill.
And if you haven't phrased those requests correctly,
it's easy for a studio to believe that employing you wouldn't work out,
even if you would have actually been fine taking the original offer.
So, if you've ever sat at your computer
staring at an offer letter and wondering what the hiring manager was thinking
when they were drafting its contents,
let me let you in on the secret.
First of all, we really want you to take the job.
Do you know how expensive hiring is?
A studio may be paying internal recruiters,
contracting with external recruiters,
paying to place job ads on job boards,
and a million other small things that all cost money.
Even small studios usually have someone whose job it is
to just go through LinkedIn while they're on the clock.
Sometimes it's an HR representative,
but often it's just the hiring manager themselves
when they get fed up about the role sitting empty.
But there's also the expense of just having the empty desk.
Sure, the company's not paying a salary right then,
but if there's somebody in the office who's given notice,
every day without their replacement
is a day when there's no handover,
when some precious amount of institutional knowledge
is risking getting lost.
Or if there is actually a desk already sitting empty,
that's another day with somebody who has differing skills and responsibilities
having to cover them, adding additional stress and taking away from that person's original workload.
Maybe they can't have anyone cover that role at all, and the role just isn't getting done.
Maybe it's holding up the timeline of a project.
Maybe that means that a publisher is breathing down their neck.
So sure, there might be someone else waiting in the wings to accept if you turn the job down,
but while you're deliberating on whether this job is right for you,
that runner-up may be out interviewing for their dream role.
And regardless, we already decided that person is the runner-up. We want you.
And if there's not a runner-up, that means we have to spend even more on recruitment,
starting over from scratch, pushing the timeline down the road by weeks or months, which is
a pretty shitty worst-case scenario.
We're not trying to insult anyone with a lowball offer.
Nothing about offering you a job is trying to make you feel bad.
We're just crossing our fingers that you take it,
and doing everything in our power to try to make the offer compelling.
We're trying to get to yes with you as quickly and efficiently as possible.
But we're not in control of everything,
especially if you're applying to a studio
owned by a larger company.
There are salary bands in play
that sometimes we just can't go out of.
I know this is a lot of people
trying to get into their first job in the industry,
so quick show of hands, who knows what a salary band is?
OK, great.
I'll do a really quick definition.
Basically, it means that the company as a whole
sets a salary range for each particular title
that the company has.
And they don't allow people to go outside of that band.
Sometimes we can get wiggle room there
by changing the title in order to get a little bit more
salary.
But in order to do that, we have to justify that title
change for the role.
And the parent company may not authorize
changing that resource.
At a previous company, I once had a role sit open for months because the salary band we
were required to stay within wasn't compelling to the people who had the skills that we needed,
and it was difficult to get our parent company to change the role title on offer to something
with a better salary.
Likewise, special requests are often a great way to get value when you can't get more of
a salary, but some requests are harder than others to grant.
Things that are visible to the rest of the studio, like regular work from home days or
extra vacation days.
are often suggestions that are made in articles and that kind of thing.
But unless the office already has a standing work from home policy
or a flexible vacation allowance,
studios can be really concerned that offering special treatment
could set a precedent and annoy veteran employees.
Maybe a company could afford to give you an extra week of vacation time,
but if they have to multiply that by 50 or 100 employees,
that gets hairy real fast.
We also don't want to hire you.
We want to retain you.
If you tell us that it is vitally important
that you make 20% more than we offered you,
and that takes it outside of the salary band,
or that you need to work from home two days a week
in order to be happy and successful,
but the policy is one day a week,
then yeah, we might pull the offer.
Why?
Because we believe you.
If you decide in the moment to settle for a salary 20% less than what you told us you need,
that means your interest is going to be peaked by every single recruiter who contacts you on
LinkedIn. You'll rate your job satisfaction lower on every annual company review.
And you might get raises, and believe me, if you're doing your best,
we will advocate as hard as we can to get you those raises.
But every time we do, we'll both know that you still believe you're worth more than you're
getting.
which means you have a higher likelihood of quitting,
which means that we lose the training and energy put into you,
and we have to go through the expense of hiring all over again.
We want you to be happy right from the jump, and if we think we can't give you
what you need to be happy, there's no moving forward.
I know, this sounds really depressing.
Everyone else is telling you to negotiate and it sounds like I'm just up here giving
you the company line.
But really, I want you to know the lay of the land before we start talking about how
you can make this information work for you.
First of all, there is a salary band, not a salary.
This isn't true for every studio, but if you're applying someplace really large,
or at a company that owns multiple studios, it's almost certainly true in order to keep
things equal and fair. So, when you feel it's appropriate, you can utter these magic words.
I know it's a bit early, but I'm in discussions with a few other studios and I just wanted to
make sure we're aligned. I understand that compensation is more than salary,
but what is your range for this role?
If they ask you what you're currently making, and you're not in California,
say that you're just trying to ensure salary is competitive for the current market.
After all, it's not like they're competing against your old studio to hire you.
There's a chance that when you try to negotiate that first offer you're made,
you may be told that that's the top of their range.
That could be possible.
If you hear that, it's because one of many things
could be going on.
Maybe you made your salary history and expectations clear,
and they knew it would be a stretch to compete if they
didn't start as high as possible.
Maybe you're more qualified than the other applicants,
so they're really afraid of losing you,
so they wanted to come out really strong from the gate.
Or maybe they're being foolish and risking
a relationship that should be built on trust by lying to you.
Look, most of the time, there is absolutely no reason for the first offer to be the best offer.
Not just because it's not financially responsible for the studio,
but it also could mean that there's less room for raises early on in your tenure,
because you're already at the top of that salary band.
But the main issue is this.
We live in a society where most people expect to be able to negotiate their salary offer.
Consistently offering the top of your range is a great way to lose candidates who assume you're just being stingy.
Recruiters in HR read the exact same hiring advice as everyone else.
If the candidate is never supposed to accept the first offer, the company has to leave some breathing room.
How much breathing room?
Not a ton, but usually enough to make a difference. If you're talking about a salaried role, I would not go more than 5k.
The tricky part is estimating where you are inside of a salary band.
It's rare that a company would automatically offer at the lowest part of their range, but
it's also really rare that they would agree to offer a candidate that they did offer at
the lowest part of their range, the highest possible part of the salary band.
You might be able to negotiate more in special circumstances, but if you're trying to be
safe, I would stick around 5K.
Also, if you can't get the salary you're looking for,
negotiate benefits that are unique to your specific situation.
If studios are rightly concerned with equality,
it may be difficult to get more of the things
that are standardized throughout all employees.
But when you're starting at a new company,
that's a great time to bring up ideas for unique benefits
that wouldn't necessarily apply to everyone in the first place.
If you're relocating for a job, it could be much easier to negotiate a higher relocation
package than a higher salary.
When I first got my first job in Europe, I was terrified of getting stranded because
international relocation is a nightmare and I was uprooting my entire family just to take
a chance on this company.
I used my unique situation to negotiate a clause in my contract where if I left the
company for any reason in the first 12 months, they would then relocate me back to the city
of my choice in the United States, all expenses paid.
So when I lost my job after 11 months, knowing that I could get my family home if I didn't
find a job that worked for me in Europe was a massive relief.
I also have friends who have negotiated successfully
for personal development days, basically
being able to go to conferences on their own dime
without taking vacation time to go.
This is a great tactic to take if you're
new to the game industry, because you can really
spin that as wanting to get even more experience and even
more knowledge as quickly as possible.
Fewer friends have been able to get guaranteed paid access
to certain conferences every year,
but it never hurts to ask if you can make
a really compelling argument.
Basically, when you're asking for these unique perks,
imagine a co-worker who gets paid exactly what you get paid
coming to HR and saying,
why does this person get so much more than I get
when I've been with the company so much longer?
Give the HR person a really compelling argument to make.
Look, job hunting is basically like online dating.
When you start out, you're doing everything possible on your Tinder or your OkCupid profile
to seem broadly appealing.
But once you're tired and jaded, your profile just becomes a list of shit you're not willing
to put up with any longer in order to weed out people early.
Don't be hostile or aggressive because you might put off people you could click with.
Instead, just be friendly and honest about what you're looking for.
I had a fantastic interview with a company whose work was incredibly exciting to me.
They flew me to a totally different country, put me up in an amazing hotel, took me out
to dinner the night before my interview, and then I spent the entire day of interviews
being really excited and energized by all of the interviews and discussions.
And then in the very last minutes of the very last interview with the head of the company at 6 at 6 p.m
He asked me what my salary expectations were
I said I didn't know what the cost of living was in that country
But I was more than happy to offer my last two salaries for reference
Yeah, a few days later. I got a very lovely email saying that there was no way they could afford me
But if anything changed to please let them know
I'm actually really glad that I had that experience.
I keep in touch with a lot of the people that I met on that interview,
and it was a really lovely trip.
But if either of us had brought up salary earlier in the process,
it would have saved them some money and me some jet lag.
If you know that you have particular needs or expectations,
it's worth figuring out a way to bring those things up
politely and casually early in the process
in order to make sure that you're on the same page.
Otherwise, you could end up on a really long,
awkward first date, I mean interview,
without a way to make an excuse and leave.
In conclusion, it's worth remembering
that all of the advice about acting like
you're on the same team
works because at the end of the day, you really are all on the same team.
No one wants a new employee who feels resentful or cheated or insulted by the hiring process.
But there can be a lot of external circumstances and constraints that can make it feel otherwise.
The only thing that can fight the stress of salary negotiations on both sides is transparency.
Thank you.
Just one quick note.
So we have actually put up a website, fragupayme.com.
There are not a huge amount of resources up there right now,
and kind of a call to action for all of you
is if you find some that you really, really like,
please send them to me on Twitter
and I will add them to that page.
This is also all three of us on Twitter,
so we're gonna open up for Q&A.
Please wait for a mic to come to you, and yeah.
Hi, so I am currently about six months into my first major job in the industry.
And at some point in time, I'm hoping to.
talk about promotions or salary raises, things like that.
How do some of the things all three of you were discussing
apply when you are at a company and happy there,
but maybe approaching your one year
or working on your second project with them?
Thank you.
The number one piece of advice I would give you
is every time that you do something that tangibly helps
the company, or every time that you get an email saying, hey,
great work on this project, save it.
Put it in a Google document.
And that way, the big question that I would have if you came to me and you were like,
I think it's time for me to get a raise, I would 100% be in your boat.
But I would need things that I could bring to my boss to say, look, we really need to
we really need to make this guy's pay a little bit better.
Here's all of the great stuff that he's done for us this year.
I'd also make sure that you have a good relationship with your manager ongoing, right?
So make sure that you and your manager are on the same page about what it takes for you to get a promotion, right?
So what are the things you need to show? What are the metrics you need to increase?
What are the ways in which you're going to prove to your manager that you're actually meeting what their expectations for promotion are?
And then once you get around that time, I'd use a lot of these same strategies about like doing some market research, putting a case together, and then making a proposal like, hey, like,
here I'm like I know we're talking about my promotion we're about to kind of come
up on it I want to get a sense of like where we are in terms of compensation
right and so just kind of open that up and be transparent so that
it's very clear that you expect a raise as part of that promotion.
Just a special note for folks who work on social media,
community management, et cetera.
The second you join a job, put a file somewhere
that lists the number of likes, comments,
typical engagement rate, all of the channels.
Over time, as you add channels, note when you do that.
Basically, in a year, you want to be able to show
this is exactly what I did.
And anybody who works in social media,
you know that numbers aren't everything,
but they are a really solid indicator
for these conversations.
Hi, a lot of this was framed around negotiating after you get an offer.
But unfortunately, in my experience, salary usually comes up way sooner.
I've often been asked about salary before I even know
what the requirements of the job are, the responsibilities.
I've been asked on web forums.
Do you have any good tips on deflecting that until the time is right
to actually negotiate, especially with someone who actually has power?
Just just like ninjitsu it back at them, right?
The thing that all.
that all job ads say is salary commensurate with experience, right?
So if you have to fill out one of those forms, just put in TBD, or if you're in a conversation,
say, you know, that's a really interesting question. For me, it really depends on the
whole package, but this is a really great time to dig into a little bit more of the
responsibilities of this role and what your benefits package is like. Or just say, you know,
that's a really good question. What is the salary band that you're offering?
Yeah, go check out that article by Tara Wheeler.
She's got scripts for exactly that question.
I have used them successfully over and over again to get them to go first.
And they have always named a number higher than I would have.
I I have a friend and she's in a she's in a complicated situation.
She knows that when you first get a job, that's when you have the most leverage because they don't have any information from you and
you haven't said yes, so they want to hire you and retain you.
But the challenge is is that she is an assistant art director and
the art director who is in charge of her is
left the company. And so now her title has changed, but they haven't had any talks about
how her pay will change. And now she believes that she's getting severely underpaid. Perhaps
that person got double what she is currently making. And it's also a complicated situation
because when she first joined, she was the only woman in her entire department.
And even now, there aren't that many women.
And so she's struggling to figure out how she can negotiate and advocate
for herself, even though she's already at the company and is very thankful
for the job while navigating the interesting perception of women
negotiating versus men.
So I would give your friend basically three pieces of advice.
The first one, to network and make friends with other art directors at other companies
in the same city.
Get them to tell her what their salaries are.
The second thing is after about six months is a really great time to say, you know, I've really proven myself in this role.
I think it's time to talk about are you rehiring for this role?
Was this an interim thing or am I being promoted to this role? In which case I've done my research
and this is the general salary it seems like is normal for this role in the in the city.
What do you think? Is my research correct on this?
One particular thing I'd add there, especially for any time when you are kind of at a company and it's not clear,
it's a promotion, it's that you're taking over another responsibility,
make sure that you don't hinge your salary negotiation on a percentage based on your existing one.
Because if you're taking a new role, new responsibility, it's not based on, oh, you know, we, every promotion is 10% or
whatever it might be. Make sure you start over, reset the expectation based on market value.
I would also say just briefly, your friend should set some time frame in her mind, at which point this is no longer
acceptable.
and be looking for other roles because I almost guarantee she will find more money outside of the company.
Unfortunately, that's my experience.
During the negotiation process from an HMR perspective, are there any
questions that are basically red flags and or vice versa? Are there any
questions where you're like, oh wow, this person, that's a very good question, we
really want them? I don't have any specific questions, but I will say when
it's clear that somebody has done...
zero investigation.
So I've had candidates, especially abroad,
that did zero investigation into local cost of living.
And literally were asking for more money
than directors at the company made.
You know, it's a really hard place to start.
One thing that actually the three of us
were talking about before the panel started
is especially because there are so many people here
that are sort of looking for their first role
in the game industry.
A lot of times people will go in and they'll read very generic salary negotiation tactics online
that are actually much more sort of tailored to people who are in the middle of their career.
So if somebody was coming, for example, right out of school...
and decided to ask for a whole bunch more than what we offered them.
And my first question would be why.
And there could be a very good reason for that.
Maybe they have experience that would actually make them really valuable.
But oftentimes the response is,
well, you know, for my unique skills and my unique experience.
to which I would say, okay, what are those?
Especially if you just came from school,
unless you've done some really special,
really unique things while you were there,
you don't necessarily have unique skills or experience yet.
So part of it is knowing that you are making an argument
to hire you specifically,
and you should have really concrete examples
of why you specifically are worth what you're asking for.
I think specifically for kind of early career folks, something that I always find really
powerful is acknowledgement and confidence in the skills that you're bringing, but also
really open mind to what you could be learning there, right?
So saying things like, oh, you know, I'm excited to bring my skills here.
And I'm really excited to learn from this team that has worked on this game or on this
product for a while.
That open mindedness and that ability to learn is something that I know we screened for a
lot in our early candidates.
Hi. For those of us who are not as early in our careers,
if you're in a very niche discipline, which I am, I'm in narrative design.
And especially as you go up the ranks, I've been in the industry for like 13 years
now, and there's not that much information out there,
especially when you like know your market worth.
There's very, very little data that I can find from Glassdoor or whatever.
What kind of resources can you recommend for that sort of very niche?
It's all about networking.
You got to know the people in your industry and you got to be
willing to get intimate with them to be able to share your
salaries, which is scary, right?
I think that's, I'm the, I'm the emotions person.
It's very scary because if you ask your friend who's also
working in narrative what your salary is, what you might hear
is that it's a salary that's much higher than yours, right?
So that opens you up to a lot of vulnerability.
But I think that is the way forward, especially in those
niche industries.
It's like you need that you can get this information from peers
around you too.
And one of the great things specifically for narrative,
it's sort of like art this way, is that you have an incredibly unique portfolio.
You have something that nobody else has that's applying for that job, which is your body of work.
So it's especially with 13 years in the career, in your career,
you should go into that being like, you know who I am.
And if they're like, well, why are you worth so much more than we were going to offer you?
You should feel comfortable saying, well, did you read my samples?
Like, own your career. The fact that you have that kind of longevity
is something really unique and special, and that makes you more marketable.
What would be your advice to someone who is...
a number of transferable skills who wants to move into the field.
In some ways you have a lot of skills but you don't have the skills in this specific field.
So I would think that some sort of mentoring or something to catch up, right?
What's your advice on how I approach that?
I think you kind of answered it for yourself a little bit there is getting those mentors,
finding, you know, one or two individuals who are doing the thing that you want to do
that will help coach you, you know, and mentorship is not this strict program where you, you know,
have to have this meeting and then this meeting, this meeting, then it's done.
A mentorship is like any other relationship. They may not have all of the answers,
which is why it's good to have a couple people with their perspectives that can help coach you.
Yeah, but as long as you're outside of the field,
how do you get that mentor?
So this is a question near to my heart,
because I was actually 29 when I got into the game industry.
My only previous non-freelance experience
was working at the Sears Portrait Studio for $7.95 an hour
before I got my first salaried position in the game industry.
And I met my mentor on Twitter.
really a mentor when you boil everything else down,
is somebody who's interested in what you have to offer
and who believes in you.
So strike up conversations with people
who are sort of in that sweet spot,
in that area of the industry that you would like to go in.
I've even helped out an artist
who was looking to transfer out of medicine
just because she cold emailed
a bunch of women in the industry
and I was the only one who responded.
A mentor doesn't even necessarily have to be somebody who is in your exact discipline.
It's really just somebody who wants to help you succeed and is willing to put in a little bit of time to ensure that you do.
Hi.
When it comes to going from one job to another and obviously you're hoping your new job pays better than your previous one,
if the company that you're interviewing with is aware of your salary history,
and you're also aware that your current salary is
on the low end of their salary band.
How far is too far or what's your limit
when it comes to your salary requirements
trying to get to the higher end of their salary?
So obviously the first tactic is to try not to let the new company know about your new salary ban.
So that's tactic one.
But if they do know, I would try to reframe the conversation the same way that you would
if you were taking a different job at the same company.
It's like, yes, this is, acknowledge what I'm currently making, the current salary ban.
I'd like to talk about the responsibilities for this job,
this new job that I'm applying for and getting an offer for, right?
Just be like, just reframe, be like, I know I was doing this thing over here
and I was making this money.
I'm doing this new thing now and here are my expectations.
Let's start from scratch, right?
Let's start from market value discussion.
I think Tara would probably agree with me from the hiring manager standpoint in that
I've never chosen a candidate because they were the cheapest.
It's never like, oh, and we're going to get this guy for a steal, you know?
So if people already want you.
they're open to whatever they were, whatever number they originally had in their head.
And so if you get to the offer standpoint, and they try to offer you something closer to what
your salary was, you can just level with them and be like, you know, I felt like I was really
underpaid at my last job. And one of the reasons that I'm looking now is because I really hope to
end up someplace that values me. And so this is a chance for us to figure out if if this is the
place for me, because I really do want to feel valued.
That's a specific thing I want to point out is that you definitely don't want to get into a situation where you're saying is I want to be paid more.
What you need to say is I want to work at a place that acknowledges the value that I'm bringing.
And I'll say kind of Elizabeth, oh my God, to Elizabeth's point, sometimes I, as the hiring manager, was literally sitting there going, oh, why did you not ask for more?
And this like this is intimidating as hell.
So I understand why people don't want to do it.
But if you can have that as a conversation one on one
with the hiring manager as a conversation,
they will have a little more wiggle room.
So I had a situation where somebody asked for 2000 more.
I easily would have given them more if we'd had it as a conversation.
But with HRCC in that conversation,
I am now limited to what I can do.
I managed to bump it just a little bit to round it to an even number, but I couldn't, you know, have that conversation like
You know, thank you
This is the last question, but we'll probably stick around for a couple minutes if you have additional so now some pressure for me
Which is the value of the fancy titles, right?
Because some position, I'm in the field of game design,
and then at some point you start like,
but then you're like product manager,
and there's like game leads, head of product,
head of design, director of design, creative director,
and it's difficult to map from one company to the other.
Maybe some guy is head of design, but...
has less responsibilities than a senior game designer in another company.
So I find it very difficult to understand which is the value of that and also in wondering
which is the value for the hiring manager.
You got to look at the responsibilities they list out.
And as part of your job interview process,
ask them specifically, OK, I'm going
to be responsible for this.
OK, I'm going to lead this team.
I'm going to manage these people.
And then when you bring in the data that you're looking at,
you'll be like, OK, this studio lead here
is kind of like a creative director here,
but they have the similar responsibilities,
and therefore, you can look at that information.
Yeah, I once took a $40,000 pay cut
to go from a senior game designer
to a senior game design strategist.
I think, yeah, it's the fanciest title I've ever had.
Was not worth the pay cut.
But honestly, you've got to think about titles
like when you're as a hiring manager,
they're like clickbait titles.
Like they really are.
It's something that makes me go, ooh,
this person was head of production at a Google studio?
You know what I mean?
But ultimately what we actually give a shit about is everything you list under that is your responsibilities
I got so much more
traction from
Responsibilities where I was listed as a senior game designer than I ever got from the responsibilities listed when I was a senior game design strategist
so
don't so you can get kind of screwed over if the work that you're doing is so far beyond what your
actual title is but anyone who actually reads your resume is not going to care about the title itself
good thank you all thank you so much