Okay, it's 3 p.m. now, so I guess we'll just go ahead and get started.
So welcome to Level Design with Impossible Geometry.
Oh, and before we continue, if you have cell phones or sound-making devices,
it'd be great if you could turn them off now.
So my talk is level design with impossible geometry. My name is
William Cheer. I am an independent game developer based
in Chicago. A bit about myself. My background is in physics.
That's what I studied in school. And as a student I worked
briefly at the national institute of nuclear physics in
Italy.
in a linear accelerator lab just outside of Padua,
which is close to Venice.
That's a picture of me.
That's actually not what my office looked like.
I was just in front of a computer,
but that's not as exciting.
After school, I actually, instead of going to physics,
I went into installation art and did that
for about four years.
So they were primarily large-scale installations
made out of balloons commissioned by art centers
and science museums.
And I did that for about four years
and basically became typecast as the balloon guy.
which I didn't want to do.
And I actually didn't play games before I
started my current project.
And I was looking for another medium.
I tried glassblowing and metalworking.
And none of them really worked out well.
And games, because I knew some programming,
I knew a bit of design, I thought
it'd be a really good medium.
So I started on a project to learn Unity.
I thought it would take three months.
It's been 3 and 1â„2 years, and here I am.
So the project is called Manifold Garden.
What is Manifold Garden? It is a game. It's a first-person
exploration puzzle game. It has unusual physics, impossible
geometry, and crazy architecture.
These are screenshots from the game.
So the game, I see it as a, those are kind of like the key
features, and I see the game as a metaphor for the last 400
years of physics.
Because at the beginning of the game, you are learning how
gravity works.
It's different from gravity in the normal world.
And by the end of it, you get an understanding of the shape
of the universe.
inside a room working with rear gravity to, oh, this is how the
space folds upon itself. So the key features of the game,
there's a lot of stuff going on in the game, but the two key
features I'm going to focus on for the purpose of this talk are
the traversal mechanic, which is gravity shifting, and the
geometry, which is 3D world wrapping. So let's talk about
the gravity shifting mechanic.
I'm sure many of you have seen this film inception and this is
a scene in the film that takes place in the dream world and
they take Paris and fold it upon itself, fold it in half. And
then later we see these two characters start walking up the
wall. And when I saw this scene, I immediately had a ton of
questions. I was like, okay, let's say Leo is carrying his
wallet and he drops it.
does it fall in the direction of the surface he's currently
walking on now, which is the blue arrow, or does it fall in
the direction of the surface he was previously on? How does his
wallet know which gravity field it now belongs to? And what if
I'm standing on the previous surface he was on and I take
his wallet, does it still fall in the direction of the blue
arrow or does it transfer onto my gravity field? The film,
unfortunately, doesn't...
address these issues, these very important issues, but that's
where I thought a game would be a very great medium to explore
this. Now, inception takes a lot of visuals from M.C. Escher's
work and that scene specifically is based on relativity. And
originally Manifold Garden was called relativity. So let me
tell you a bit about how
that gravity shifting mechanic works in the game. So we're
going to start with a 2D example. Basically, say we've
got four surfaces. Each one of them has a different color,
blue, red, green, yellow. And all objects in the world belong
to one of these four colors and they fall in the direction of
the wall. So a blue object falls in the direction of the blue
wall. A red object falls up in the direction of the red wall.
Green falls to the right. Yellow falls to the left. Or the other
way around. I'm looking at my computer screen. So
Now, not all of these gravity fields are on at the same time.
And which one is on depends on the player orientation.
So right now, the player is oriented this way.
The blue gravity field is on, and all the other gravities
are off.
So those objects are frozen.
And then the player can walk up to the yellow wall,
then the yellow gravity is on, and all the other ones
are frozen.
and so on and so forth.
This is, now the game is in first person,
so this is what it looked like.
You can see the characters walking forward,
they switch gravity, and whichever direction is down,
that surface becomes colored.
So the color helps the player orient,
and it also lets them know which gravity field they're in.
so that's the traversal mechanic. Now we're going to
talk about the geometry which is 3D world wrapping. So
eventually you start off in the game inside and eventually you
make it outside. And when you fall off, instead of fading the
screen to black or killing the player and respawning them, the
world actually just repeats itself infinitely. So you could
be, you could just keep falling forever. You do have air
control. So this is what it looks like in one of the levels
and here's another level where this is happening.
And we'll come back to this.
But first, the title, Level Design with Impossible
Geometry.
What is impossible geometry?
So for the purpose of this talk, we're just going to say
impossible geometry is any weird geometry that we don't
see in real life.
It is very hard to generalize.
And also, this talk is not supposed to be the guide to
working with impossible geometry.
the stuff I'm talking about, they deal very specifically
with the way the mechanics are implemented in manifold garden.
So I just want to give you guys a taste of what it's like
working with it, some of the problems and challenges I face
and some of the techniques that I found to be useful. But you
might, you know, your mileage may vary. One thing I want to
clear up is that impossible geometry is not non-Euclidean
geometry. I see non-Euclidean geometry kind of thrown around a
lot every time people see anything weird. And that's not
always the case.
So what is Euclidean geometry?
Euclidean geometry is just flat space.
So that's kind of space as we perceive it on the human scale.
Some of the properties are that the shortest distance between
two points is a line.
The sum of all angles in a triangle is 180.
And parallel lines don't intersect.
And non-Euclidean geometry is just everything else.
So you can have hyperbolic elliptic,
but it's also not that unusual.
So the surface of a sphere is actually non-Euclidean.
And if you were to draw a triangle
on the surface of a sphere,
you would find that the angles don't add up to be 180.
And a good example of this is the surface of the Earth.
Now, if you were to draw a triangle on the floor right now,
the angles would add up to be 180.
But if you were to draw a triangle the size of a continent,
then the non-Euclidean properties start to show.
So now we're going to transition to start talking about world
wrapping and we'll start with 2D world wrapping. So you guys
probably all know asteroids, right? You're shooting asteroids
with a spaceship and when you get to the bottom side of the
screen, you're teleported to the top side and if you hit the
right side, then you're teleported to the left.
So this is actually a two-tour, so it's on the surface of this
and I'm going to come back and explain what I mean by this in
a bit. Here's an example. We see the spaceship go up, comes
back down from below. So now what we want to do is we
actually want to make that path seamless. So we want to connect
the top and the bottom and the right and the left. So what
we're going to do here is we'll start up and we'll take the top
and the bottom sides and we'll glue them together.
And then what we'll do is we'll take the right and the left sides and we'll glue them together.
So here on the right, you can see that's happening.
So first we're gonna glue the top and the right side
so that we form a connected loop.
So you can see now why the ship is looping
in that direction, and then we'll glue it
in the left and the right side.
So now we get the shape, basically a donut,
and the ship is on the surface of it.
So we can see that it consists of two loops
in two different directions,
and that's how you get 2D world wrapping.
But we need to go deeper.
We're going to talk about 3D world wrapping.
So I explained here how by connecting the top and the
bottom sides, and the left and the right sides, this 2D
surface is really the same as this 2-torus.
But how do we work with a 3-torus?
So to start with a 3-torus, it's 3D, so we're actually
going to start with a box instead of a surface.
And in this case, what we're going to do is we're going to
take the top and the bottom faces, and we're going to glue
them together.
and we're gonna take the left and the right faces
and we'll glue them together.
And then we'll take the front and the back faces
How do we visualize this?
I don't know, it's actually, it's very hard
because it's in 4D.
But one good analogy I found is that in 2D world wrapping,
you are a 2D character stuck on the 2D surface
of a 3D donut, and in 3D world wrapping,
you are a 3D character on the 3D surface of a 4D donut.
So while it's hard to visualize the structure,
the 4D donut, we can visualize what it's like
to be inside the surface.
So let's say the Earth, we have the Earth,
and it's in flat Euclidean geometry.
This is what it would look like.
Now if we were to put it,
we've already added 3D world wrapping to this,
this is what it's gonna look like,
because the light rays are gonna loop back around.
So you'll see repetitions of the Earth,
they're all the same ones, continued infinitely.
And here's a version with the grid,
so you can see the partitions.
Now this is a screenshot from the game. You can see this is what it looks like.
Here is another version where the distance between the instances is zero.
So it just looks like one continuous building.
And here's what it looks like when you're falling through it in motion.
So you can see that the level just keeps repeating itself.
Now this leads to some very interesting physical
properties. For example, let's take a box and we'll drop it
off the ledge. Now you'll actually see that box come down
from above because it loops back around. And the box is now
simultaneously beneath you and above you. A lot of games have
waterfalls. This is my drawing of a waterfall. The direction
it goes forward and then it falls off. In our game, in
Manifold Garden, there actually isn't waterfalls. There's water
loops because that water comes back down from above.
Here's a screenshot of a water loop in action.
So you can see it basically forms one continuous strip.
Now a really fantastic book if you're interested
in this subject is The Shape of Space by Jeffrey R Weeks.
I actually have a copy of it, so if after the talk
you want to come and check it out.
It's written, it's like an advanced book,
but written for the layperson, and it really talks
about how to visualize this stuff.
He also has a website, geometrygames.org,
which has a bunch of small games to help you visualize
this kind of geometry.
There's kind of 2D examples and 3D examples as well.
OK, so how did 3D wall wrapping get added to Manifold Garden?
Originally, the game was all about the gravity shifting
mechanic.
It all took place indoors, and all you did was change gravity
and put boxes on buttons and solve puzzles.
the problem though was it's very hard in first person games
to get a sense of depth and people were having a hard time
seeing when they dropped the box where it was going to land. So
they said why don't you add shadows to the box. So I said
okay, I added a directional light so that you can, you know,
there are shadows. And then people were asking, well, where
is the light coming from? So I said okay, I'll add windows to,
you know, provide an explanation for the source of the light. And
as a result of the window, people were able to see the
outside.
This wasn't intentional on my part. I just built a bunch of
rooms together in one scene. However, everybody was very
excited about what was going on outside and they were asking,
hey, can I go outside? And originally I didn't want the
player to because it would add all this complexity, but
everybody kept asking for it, so I allowed them to go outside.
This was also at a time when I introduced the edge detection
shader.
Now this of course introduced the problem of players falling
off the world. And the one thing I did not want to do was I
didn't want to add invisible colliders. Because there are
some games that have it and it's very frustrating. You want to
explore and it's constantly preventing you from going to
places. And I also wanted everything you can see in the
world that you can get to. Because I remember playing Sky
Rim and one of the most magical moments in that game is when you
see a mountain in the distance and then later on you're
actually on that mountain. So...
So I couldn't put anything in the sky, because that meant I'd
have to create additional content.
And I got this problem of a very blank sky, which is very
boring, and I added a skybox, and it just looked absolutely
terrible.
However, at some point I realized that by introducing
3D world wrapping, I've sort of solved all those problems,
because now I can have things in the sky, and it's not new
content, and I can allow the player to get there.
And yeah, it's not new content, because it's the
same thing.
So it solves the blank sky problem.
It ensures that everything you can see is still a place that
you can get to.
And it's also just a much more interesting level in general.
So these are some of the early screenshots of the game when I
introduced world wrapping.
And this is one of the earliest
implementations in motion.
It is very slow here, but you can see.
in this case you've got the button, you press it, it drops
a box, and then you jump off the ledge. And what you'll notice
in this implementation is that the distance between instances
is very large. It's very clear where one instance begins and
where another ends. This fall is going to take quite a while,
but basically it repeats. So we're going to continue on. Let's
just watch it through. Okay, we've landed.
Now, when I introduced world wrapping, it created a lot of
unexpected solutions to previous problems, which is very nice.
This is an image by M.C. Escher, a cubic space division.
And the original inspiration for the game was I wanted to
make a game based on M.C. Escher's works, and I wanted to
put this level in the game.
Now, here's an implementation of it in July 2013.
So this was before world wrapping got added.
World wrapping got added about a year and a half into the development.
Now when I made this level without world wrapping it was actually very painful to play so
the game, the level basically consisted of all these lattices that repeated
and you
went in and you just had to find an exit. So very simple.
But the problem was, it was very hard to orient yourself
because everything, basically all parts of the level
looked the same, and also if you fell off
the lattice structure, you landed on the floor.
And there was a floor because it took place in a room.
And then it was just like very tedious walk
to get back up to a lattice.
Another problem was that in order to make the level look
interesting it had to have a certain scale. But any increase
in scale resulted in an increase in navigational complexity. So
I played it a bit and it just really wasn't fun and I got rid
of it. After I introduced war wrapping all those problems went
away. So this is December 2015.
And now you can see the, so one of those boxes is one instance
of it, and you can go to any of those instances.
It doesn't matter.
So in this case, what happens is it removes,
you do not need to orient yourself.
There is no way, there is literally,
it is literally impossible for the player to get lost
because it doesn't matter which direction you go in,
you are stepping away and also towards the objective.
And it also means that I can increase the scale of it.
In this case, it's basically infinite.
And it doesn't add any navigational complexity.
In fact, it removes a lot of navigational complexity.
And it's also, again, just a much more interesting level
for the player to experience, because this is not something
you see often in games.
Here's another example of something that I wanted to put
in the game before, but couldn't.
These are Indian step wells.
And I saw these, and I thought, well, wouldn't it be amazing
if these just went on forever?
Once I introduced world wrapping, this was impossible.
So in this space, you can keep going down these stairs
or climbing up.
There is an achievement if you get to the bottom.
But.
So what is something that's very interesting about this
is that instead of having the world wrapping happen
on a grid, it is actually offset.
So this is the basic unit that's repeated.
So we have a set of stairs.
Now, if we just have normal world wrapping where
If you go down, if you drop from the bottom right,
you'll come back up down from the bottom left
because we have everything on a grid.
In this infinite step wheel world,
when you drop down from the bottom right,
you actually come back from the upper left.
And the reason why that's happening is because
instead of putting everything on a grid,
we've offset them slightly.
Because when you're going down these stairs,
you're not actually going straight down,
you're going down and forward.
And this is what it looks like when you're climbing up.
And then you can, because of the gravity rotation mechanic,
you can also choose to just fall down the level from the side.
Now, of course, adding roll wrapping
also introduced a lot of new problems.
One of the problems is gating.
Basically, when the player is outside,
the entire level pretty much opens up.
You can go anywhere.
And everyone would say, isn't there,
can't the player just skip all these levels
and get to the end?
And yeah.
So this is, let's talk about the 2D example.
So in this level we want the player to get to the star.
And what we'll do, this is too easy,
so we'll put a wall here.
And now maybe the player's gotta go get a key
to open the lock, or they have to learn double jump.
When you introduce wall wrapping, though, that wall is no longer a barrier because the player can jump to the right and land back on the other side, or they can jump down and come back down from above.
And the reason why that's happening is because of the repetitions.
and now I actually got, so this caused a problem with pacing
for a long time until I played Skyrim, and in Skyrim,
when you are outside, you can get to anywhere on the map,
but then once you go inside a dungeon,
it becomes a very linear experience,
so the game is open exploration and linear adventuring.
And I actually took that for my game,
so when you are outside in the space,
I allow you to go anywhere.
I just sort of embrace that.
But then there are these islands with puzzles,
and once you get there, then it's a linear path.
And once you're indoor, you can't whirlwrap,
so that removes the problem of players skipping areas.
Another problem you'll find is that height and direction
basically become meaningless
once you introduce weird geometry.
A lot of games will have something like a tower, right?
And you might get a mission that's
meet me at the base of the tower.
So let's go back to our 2D example.
If I were to ask you where the star is, you'd say it's near
the base of the tower to the left.
Once you introduce war wrapping, though, that
direction doesn't really make sense because the star is also
to the right of the tower.
And now what if we started to decrease the distance between
the instances so that they start touching each other. So now in
this case, base of the tower doesn't make sense because this
tower does not have a base. It's disconnected. This is one
implementation of it in manifold garden. And here you can see
this is literally a building without a base.
So once you introduce war wrapping, a lot of things,
you know, words like northeast, southwest,
up, down, left, right, that we use for directions,
they get tossed out the window.
Now what I found is you want to embrace the problems.
So you want to design with the geometry
instead of against it.
For example, what works really well is
designing your levels to be radial,
thinking of something as inside and then outside
and allowing the players to get there
between these two places from any directions
instead of...
This is much better than having something that's just a single
direction. I just put directional as a word for this.
Now what I want to talk about now is a number of techniques
that I found to have worked well. And these fall under two
categories.
The first is macro, which has to deal with the big picture,
the way you organize your level.
And the second is micro, the second group of techniques
is micro, which deal more with moment to moment,
not necessarily when the player is stopping to think,
but when they're moving through levels,
how can you help them, how can you help guide them?
So in macro, you want to have an iconic party.
The word party is the layout of a building.
I got that from Robert Yang's
level design histories talk last year,
which I highly recommend.
And you want to have logic to your level.
and with micro you want to have intentional architecture and
you want to utilize patterns and architectural elements. So let's
talk about the first macro technique, iconic parties. So
these are some examples of architectural parties. You've
got the layout. This is kind of roughly what the building looks
like. When you're designing a game based on M.C. Escher's work
it's very tempting to kind of overwhelm the player with a lot
of staircases and tunnels and weird stuff. And I think that
works very well in a print because you kind of want to, you
know, look at it in detail and discover things you didn't see
before.
However, this does not work well in a level.
So this is my very first attempt
at the opening level of the world.
And you can see I was just putting staircases
and tunnels everywhere.
And it looks and feels very MCS-sure.
This is another example.
But if you were to draw,
if you were to ask me what the party of this level is,
well, this is what it is.
It's very messy.
There's no clear structure to it.
This is the same level now.
And you can see in this case what we have
is a central tower surrounded by four islands.
And what's really great about this shape
is you can see that from any direction.
And also with the world wrapping,
you can see the repetitions of it in the distance.
So I don't have a mini map in the world.
However, because you can see the repetition of the world,
from where you are, you can, by looking at the other instances,
you can figure out what the current shape,
what the current structure of your world is.
And so it helps if you have a very clear design instead
of just a mess.
So a comparison of how the levels changed.
And these are examples of levels with very clear parity.
Like you can see this one, and right away
you see that these are stairs that continue on forever.
I see very clearly now this is just the lattice structure.
And you don't have to be simple.
You can get more complex, but you always want to have
this very clear overall design that the player can see
and recognize very clearly.
Now the second macro technique is you want to have
logic to your level.
Now the opening level of the game consists of a series
of four rooms indoors to teach the player the mechanics
and then they go outside.
And when I was play testing, there are people that are
really good at puzzle games, and there are people that are
not so good at puzzle games.
And the people that are good at it would finish those four
levels in about 10 minutes.
And others might struggle and take about 30 to 40 minutes.
However, when they got outside, and the outside
consisted of two rooms that they had to find, there was no
consistency in how long it took people to
find those two rooms.
Some people would blast through the first four puzzles,
and then they'd get outside and stumble for 30 minutes
until they found a room.
And some people might struggle for 40 minutes.
with the indoor puzzles and then they get outside and come across the room right away.
And this is because there was no logic to the way those two rooms were placed.
They were basically random.
So, it was basically a matter of luck in which how you found these.
And they were also a lot of like based on sight lines.
So, for example, you know, this is what you saw when you first came out
and there's a door at the very end.
and you basically had to get the box and go to the door.
And if you didn't do that, if you kind of turned around
or jumped off or changed gravity, you lost sight of it
and there was no way to figure out,
use logic to figure out how to get back.
With the current level now,
there is a very clear sense of logic.
You have this tower and then the puzzles,
there are four islands with puzzles in them.
And so you go to one, you solve it,
and you turn on a laser beam and then you can come back.
So the way the level is laid out,
once you solve one puzzle,
you can figure out where the next ones are.
So as you can see, this is kind of the center tower,
and just from where the laser beams are pointed,
you can deduce, okay, in this case,
I finished the blue and the red islands,
and there are these two other ones that are still missing.
So having a logic to your level is very important. Now we're
going to talk about the micro techniques which are not
dealing with the big picture but with moment to moment as the
player is navigating through the world how can you help to guide
them to the right places. Okay. So we're going to go back to
this opening level and one of the last things I changed is
this one piece of architecture at the very edge of the island.
So it used to be just this block and I changed it to a bunch of
stairs and with a platform at the end.
And the idea for this was because you're on that central
tower and I need you to get to the blue island where the
puzzle is, in this case the star. And in order to do that,
I needed the player to rotate gravity to get there. You had
to jump. So you can see this is it with the block. And the
problem with this was it was not very clear what it was doing.
So this is the thinking. I was thinking you'd walk up to this
block.
and you would rotate onto it, change gravity, and then you
jump off onto the island below. If you played Assassin's Creed,
it's sort of like those little things where you jump off into
the pile of hay. However, what happened was a lot of people
just kind of walk up to this and look around and then walk away.
And the problem is that this piece of architecture does not
communicate its intention. It's just this block. It's not
telling you what to do with it.
However, what I did was I changed it to a set of stairs
with this platform at the end, and now everybody,
like it becomes very clear, oh, I see the stairs,
I'm supposed to walk up them,
and then when you walk up the stairs,
then you rotate to the platform,
and then right away you see the island below.
So the difference between the block and the stairs
is that this tells you how to use it, how to walk on it.
The second micro technique is you want to utilize
patterns in architecture.
So this is what hallways used to look like in the game.
And this had a lot of problems.
Basically, because you can change gravity, we have
hallways that also bend upwards.
The problem is, in a lot of first-person games, a lot of
people don't tend to look up.
So players would come to this, and then they'd turn around
thinking it was a dead end.
So that was one problem.
And another problem was, if you started going backwards,
the hallway looked exactly the same.
And that happens a lot because of the gravity changing
mechanic.
It's very easy to get turned around.
So a lot of people would backtrack
through an entire hallway until they
got to the room they were in previously,
and then be like, wait a minute.
This is not where I wanted to go.
So when I started adding windows in the game,
I would put windows and hallway to be equal in length,
directly opposite one another.
And I showed this level to Brandon Chung,
who is the creator of 30 Flights of Loving,
and also talked about wayfinding in levels.
last year here and I recommend that talk highly as well.
And he suggested taking one of the windows
and sliding it down, offsetting it so that it's like this.
So you can see it, you know,
it touches the end of the hallway.
And this immediately solved a ton of problems.
So now when you open the door
and you're looking down a hallway,
you see the brightest thing on the screen is the window,
right, and the window offers a vista to the outside world,
which is much more interesting than the blank walls.
So it actually makes traversal through hallways
feel a lot faster.
and it attracts people towards the end.
And then the window kind of guides your eyes
into the direction of the bend.
And this solves the problem of hallways that bend upwards
because now players' eyes are guided to look up.
And it also solves the problem of players going backwards
because now when you're going backwards,
the hallway looks very different.
You're no longer seeing this window of light at the end.
So just the way the hallways are designed,
you can figure out the direction you're supposed to go.
And I actually, you know,
sometimes in games they'll want to vary corners and hallways.
And I actually have this in every single hallway because
having the player get lost inside hallways is not
something that I want to do. So in summary, you want to
embrace the geometry. Don't work against it. If you start
using impossible geometry you're going to find unexpected
solutions to previous problems. You will need to rethink a lot
of things like gating.
You'll need to rethink direction, northeast, southwest,
up, down, left, right, those all go out the window.
Utilize a very clear layout for your level.
The shape of it should be easily recognizable.
You want to create logic in your level
so the players can figure out where they need to go next
by looking at the architecture.
and you also want to have intentional architecture.
Everything you put in the game needs to tell the player
how to use it, and use established patterns
that the players can rely on
to figure out where they need to go.
And a lot of people will play the first level
of Battle for Garden and say, you know,
I thought this game was going to be very confusing,
but it actually turned out to be not bad.
So we've been sitting here talking about
impossible geometry.
I just want to leave you with one thing,
which is you mustn't be afraid to dream a little bigger.
So all of that has kind of helped me to make manifold
garden what it is. And I just want to say manifold garden is
playable here at GDC. It's actually just outside in the day
of the devs area. So if you want to check it out or watch other
people play and see how they work their way through the
level. And finally, my name is William cheer. Here's all my
contact information. Feel free to come up and ask questions now
if we have time. Yeah, I think we have a little bit of time. If
anybody has questions, you can come up to the mic.
Thank you.
So the question is whether I did any paper prototyping.
And I did initially do paper prototyping for the puzzles.
But then when it came to designing the levels,
I'm not a very good drawer.
And so even to do a 2D drawing is very difficult for me.
And all these levels have to be designed in 3D.
So I just build them inside the game
and then walk through them and play test them
and figure out where the issues are.
So I haven't done paper prototyping.
And
years.
Yes.
Oh, yeah.
Hey there.
Who else worked on your team?
Did you work by yourself?
And how did other people get involved in the later stages when you were sort of defining
an art style?
So I worked on the game alone for about two and a half years and then I got backed by
Indie Fund.
about a year ago, and I brought on a programmer, David, who's
actually in the audience. David worked on the game part-time
last year and joined full-time at the beginning of this year.
And the art style actually was just a lot of iterating over
time. There was never a clear direction. I wanted it to be
inspired by architecture, so architectural drawings were an
influence, but were an inspiration. But a lot of it is
just kind of tiny things added up over time to get to where it
is at now.
Thank you.
Hi, thanks for this. So there's like a recurring trend in games that are based on like some
twist of mathematics, which is that they're really, really hard to pitch. You know, like
whenever you talk about a four-dimensional game, of which there are many, I'm making one,
you're like, oh, the four-dimensional game, like that other one, like MediaCorey or so on. So
I'm wondering how you deal with that when you actually talk to people about it. And the other
thing is, what would make it easier for you in a game engine to do what you did?
So the question is how to pitch a game that has a weird
geometry, weird twist.
I actually, so.
Yeah, I've been working on the game for about three and a half years now and a lot of that is just talking to a lot of people.
In 2014, I went to about 14 different game conventions.
And the way I would used to talk about the game is I'd say,
okay, you know, there are six gravity fields and each one is based on a different surface normal,
and when you're going this, it's red, and you can just see people gloss over, you know,
and when you mention surface normal, they're like, I'm done.
But then I started to say, okay, have you seen Inception?
And you know that scene where they full Paris in half
and they start walking,
but then immediately people are like, oh yeah,
you know, I know that.
And so I think it's about like communicating,
giving people clear visual imagery
to help them imagine more of the consequences of that
as opposed to explaining the math.
Hi, you just said that you don't draw much, but I had a question concerning how do you
go about designing your architectures? How do you... what's your process to establish all this
architectural language that you have now in the game? And we saw the evolution, like we saw the
previous prototypes, very blocky, simple cubes and stuff, and now it's very much more on it.
Sure. I was wondering how you go about creating those.
uh... the two biggest architects who've influenced the game are Tadao Ando, he's a
japanese architect who works a lot with concrete so that helps with kind of the
the layout of the levels
and then and frank Lloyd Wright who kind of helps fill in a lot of the ornaments
and the ornaments are there
because i don't have textures
and so if you're moving through flat, like a big chunk of flat space and you don't
have textures, players can't see stuff changing on the screen so it feels very
slow
but once you start adding kind of these variations in height
um...
that really helps speed things up.
I think their earlier question was about engines,
how engines can help.
I think providing, you know, the biggest problem that we have
are now dealing with rendering.
So I think having kind of low level stuff in the pipeline
that's opened up that we can tweak is most helpful.
But just in terms of 3D and scripting,
those are pretty standard.
OK, just one more question.
Hi.
So yeah, you just said something about rendering
causing an issue.
I wanted to ask, you guys are instantiating everything,
right?
They're all instances?
Yes.
So how exactly were you guys getting
around the rendering issues?
Well, we've actually rewritten that system.
And I'm probably not the best person to answer that.
But we
We do have a 3x3x3 and sometimes 5x5x5 grid of the same level
repeated. We actually do not have one standard system. It
sort of depends on the geometry of the level. We have hijacked
the play pipeline in Unity now so when I hit play it actually
creates another level and merges all the meshes and deletes all
the unnecessary stuff and creates an optimized version of
that.
But yeah, David is in the audience, and feel free to ask
him technical questions.
Yeah, so thank you all very much, and fill out the
evaluation if there is one.