I am Toshiyuki Kamei from Capcom Japan, here to talk a little bit about Street Fighter with you guys.
I am focusing specifically on Street Fighter V with some other stuff thrown in there.
So I'm John, I'm just going to be interpreting, don't mind me.
So let's go.
First is the agenda.
All right, this is our agenda for today.
The first is about art direction, which is easy to see and easy to understand.
We want to really talk about the most important thing,
which is making the art easy to understand and follow.
The second is about art direction, which is about creative ideas and creating individuality.
After that, we want to talk a little bit about how we gave the art a real personality.
Of course, making the game easy to understand, very legible, very important,
but it's also Street Fighter, so it needs some style.
We're going to talk about a few of the techniques that we used to really give the impression of,
oh, this is Street Fighter.
And then we've got a conclusion, so yeah, let's jump right in.
So I've been a technical artist in the games industry for about 16 years.
And was the art director on both Street Fighter 4 and Street Fighter 5.
What I'd like to tell you today is...
So, we're going to talk a little bit about our philosophy.
What were we thinking when we made a lot of decisions around the art for Street Fighter
and also how we made those decisions and the learning that we've used, decades of learning along the way.
Street Fighter IV has become a huge esport.
It's an event.
Ever since Street Fighter IV, this
has been a wonderful thing for the series.
Speaking Japanese
Since time immemorial, people have been enjoying Street Fighter at these huge events like EVO, Togeki,
but now with the advent of real-time streaming,
this kind of feeling of enjoying Street Fighter in a tournament,
we're able to share it in real-time with everybody all over the world.
We can now comment in real-time,
so we can now share the winnings and emotions of tournaments around the world.
It's really great to just be able to bring that emotion that you get when you come to these tournaments to everyone in real time all over the world.
That's also been one of the things that's helped us grow the popularity of fighting games in general too.
This is one of the things that we thought about a lot when we were building Street Fighter V from the early days
and it informed everything from the art on down.
For a fighting game, it's very, very important if we're going to spread the audience,
if we're going to share this with new people,
that it be very easy to follow the battle and understand what's going on.
Even if you watch it, you can get absorbed in the battle.
That's the ideal.
Today, we'll introduce some of the know-how that Capcom has developed.
First, we'll start with the art direction for ease of viewing and understanding.
All right, section one.
Here's how we made the art easy to follow and understand.
Street Fighter characters are all muscular.
Their body silhouettes are often clear and distinct.
So it's pretty obvious, but Street Fighter characters,
super muscular, and the character outlines
very, very clear, well-defined, and unique.
Why are Street Fighter characters so muscular?
I'm often asked that question.
I always get the question,
why the heck are Street Fighter characters so muscular?
It's a fighting game, so it looks strong.
If you get hit by this guy, it looks painful.
If you get hit by this thick arm, you'll die.
There's a reason for that.
So that first impression is super important.
So when I want people to think,
oh gosh, if I get hit by this guy, I'm going to die.
This guy is super strong.
That's the first impression that I want to bring out
when I show a Street Fighter character.
Also, the facial expressions are exaggerated.
If you want to laugh, you'll laugh a lot.
If you get attacked, you'll look really painful.
In the facial expressions, another area where we tend to exaggerate an awful lot.
You know, if a character is laughing, it's the biggest laugh in the world.
If they get punched, it really looks like it hurts.
The art of fighting games, especially the characters,
is the best way for the player to understand the game's situation in an instant.
Really, the art, especially the character art,
is the number one vehicle that we use to give players information
frame by frame about what's going on in the battle.
Players have to make decisions as they're playing every frame, so this is very important.
Really thinking about how we can give the player the information they need, you know,
basically 60 times every second.
So if you don't express it in a natural way, you won't be able to convey the information in an instant.
And what that means is we found that rather than using very realistic art,
this exaggeration really helps communicate information quickly.
So again, a quick explanation of the game loop.
So first, every frame, we display for the player what's going on in the battle.
They make a decision based on that information.
Reflect their decision back into the game.
In a fighting game, you need to be able to create a loop in a short frame.
That's why understanding and conveying the story is so important.
So when we create fighting game art, we need to pay attention to the player's feedback.
Art is the only thing that can give the player feedback on the game's situation in an instant.
Let's look at a few examples, first around character silhouettes.
Of course, as we said, Street Fighter characters are super muscular with very strong and unique silhouettes and outlines.
The easiest way to understand and convey this is to give feedback to the player and audience about what the character is doing and what kind of pose they are doing during the battle.
And these outlines are giving the player feedback on what's happening in the game, every frame,
from this kind of far battle camera perspective.
We judge whether the standards of clarity and transparency are clear from the camera during battle.
And really, when we decide whether we've achieved our goals of this legibility,
we have to decide that all through this battle camera, which you see the whole game from.
I really thought long and hard about the body and the poses of all these characters.
And really, this is true, this was true back then and it's true now.
And the 2D sprite era has informed everything up until this point.
And as you can see, these are really, really dynamic, very, very well-defined, and very exaggerated character outlines.
In the battle camera angle, the character is shown in a very small way, but with this much movement, you can tell what the character is doing in a moment.
The viewpoint of a fighting game, no matter what, you're kind of pulled back away from the characters.
They're a bit small on the screen, but by kind of deforming and exaggerating their shapes,
we can actually convey a lot of information very quickly.
For example, Yun, the character on the far right,
you can see that his arm is quite pronounced.
Let's take a closer look at Yun.
So, when you hold out his arm, you can see there's a lot of deformation going on.
Six pixels to show the thinnest part of his wrist.
But then the thumb, that hump of his thumb is an extra four pixels.
And the musculature on his forearm, that's another two pixels.
Now this is very exaggerated.
When you pull the camera, you can see how the player is extending his arm,
and you can tell if his hand is a Gu or Pa by the silhouette.
By using this exaggeration, you can really convey a lot of information to the player very quickly,
like how their arm is extended, what orientation it's in,
whether they are making a fist, whether their hand's open.
We analyze the know-how from past .air and internal data.
And how we show this on screen, it all comes from rules that were laid down from time immemorial.
This is one example of an internal document that was created that has a lot of these rules written down,
A Strange Guide for Artists.
This document was created around the time of Street Fighter Alpha series and Darkstalkers was being made.
And it's been used ever since then to help teach artists some of the rules that we use to create our art.
This was created by some of the world-class artists at Capcom back in the time,
and it was edited by none other than Yasuda Akira, or Akiman, as you know.
It's kind of hard to tell, but that's actually Dimitri on the cover from Darkstalkers.
Yeah, again, it's a pretty old document, but again, still very valuable today for us.
So the content inside its figure drawing is very similar to the style of Andrew Loomis.
And what it explains is a lot of shortcuts and rules about how we take that musculature
and a character's frame and make a sprite out of it.
It's got a lot of great know-how, like if you exaggerate this part of the musculature,
it looks really cool.
Or if you actually make this part slimmer, it can actually help be a little more efficient
in the visual language.
A lot of different rules.
20 years old, but the information is still important.
So even though this is over 20 years old, having that information about what's important, what's not important, and how you can use that to create your characters, it's still used today?
Here's one example from Street Fighter V.
When you look at an arm from the front, the rule is the upper arm should be thinner than the lower arm.
But when looking at it from the side, that same arm should look narrow in the forearm and wider for the upper arm.
By following this one rule, you can actually convey a lot of information about how the
player is extending their arm, whether they're doing a straight punch, an uppercut, in just
a really short amount of time.
And when you compare this to an actual photograph,
it's obvious that it's much easier
to understand the position and what's going on with the arm
in just a second.
Actually, during the prototyping phase of Street Fighter V,
it was a time when photorealistic graphics
were very popular.
We actually prototyped and tried out a different style,
like this.
But one of the things we learned very quickly was that the realistic proportions in this model actually made the game a lot harder to play.
And it was really easy to go away from this style and make the decision to keep that more exaggerated style for the game.
Let's talk about how we decide how tall our characters look.
The character relative height is very important during the battle.
So if you know our character's bios, you've got Ryu, he's 175cm tall,
and M. Bison, 182cm tall, with a difference of only 7cm.
In most games, the relative height of the models is decided in a digital content creation tool,
using a grid to kind of set out those proportions and heights.
But that's not how we do it on Street Fighter.
What we do is,
We basically sit the characters next to each other, get them posed, and decide that more by feel.
And as you can see, M. Bison looks a bit larger than you. He kind of looks like he's looking down on him.
But if you look at their actual models in our content creation tool, the models themselves are pretty much the same height.
What we do is we put Ryu in his ready pose and we compare the other characters to him and decide how they should look and feel in the battle scene.
In the 2D era, there's even times when M. Bison
actually looks like he's over 2 meters tall.
So, deciding a character's height based on their battle impression
has been a popular method in fighting games for a long time.
So this is something, again, we've done ever since the 2D era,
kind of deciding those different relative character heights
just in the battle pose by feel.
Now let's talk a little bit about character animation.
There's a lot of information that we have to put into the character's animation
to relate battle information to the player.
First off is the fighting style of the character.
That needs to be easily understood through the posing, the animation.
So this is a medium kick, and as you know Ryu uses karate.
And then weight and rhythm, this is really the core important part of the animation.
It needs to be consistent with the fighting style, be very cool,
and also give the player the right information about what's going on.
And this really just comes down to the pure quality of the animation.
Last thing is the actual functioning of the game, what's going on.
The animation is what changes the collision of the game and the player's frame by frame.
So that pose and that outline and how it moves and being able to follow that frame by frame is again one of the most important things.
There's a lot of different techniques we use.
And we talk to the game designers
about the hundreds of different scenarios
where they need to get information of the player.
Like for instance, if the game designer
knows that there's going to be a sweep motion
and the player should be able to read that in, say,
three or four frames, that's the discussion we have
and it's used when we create the animation.
This is actually an animation from Street Fighter 4, Zangief.
I'll show you a quick video that will illustrate some of the different things we do to exaggerate.
There we go. Looks like we're dropping some frames, but you get the idea.
First, let's look at it from a battle camera angle.
So this is a very close camera angle to what you see during battle,
but when you look at it from the front,
you can see that Zangief is walking sideways at you.
Obviously, this animation would be completely wrong
for a game where you can view the character from 360 degrees.
But for fighting games, this is exactly what we need.
This one.
When you look at it from the front,
you can see that the pose is correct.
The left is the fighting game style animation,
and the right is the normal animation
that corrects the pose when viewed from the front.
So here, these two images you see,
we've got a normal animation.
This is if you were looking at the character from 360 degrees,
this is how you would animate.
But for fighting games, as you can see,
it's kind of tilted sideways.
Looking at it from the front, it's true, but from the side,
the waist rotation is also constricted, and it's hard to see the silhouette.
The information about the body is not transmitted.
This happens a lot because when you're creating animation, you're looking at the model from 360 degrees, so it's an easy pitfall.
And when that happens, the thing we say a lot is, do the 5 degree turn.
If you turn your waist and body 5 degrees in the direction of the battle camera, it's a great sign for a fighting game.
What we find is if you kind of take the character from their hips and their whole body
and just turn them five degrees towards the camera,
just that simple thing will just help get a lot of that information you need into the animation.
I'll show a few examples.
So first we've got M. Bison here as you can see.
This is his kind of battle camera view looking at his opponent.
But when you see him from the front, you can see his whole body is kind of at a 45 degree angle.
Next we got Zangief. Looks like he's ready to suck his opponent in,
but he's completely looking off to the other side when you look at him from the front.
Next we got Rainbow Mika. She's got a drop kick going right to her opponent's face,
but actually her whole body is slanted sideways.
In a fighting game, when you look at the camera work during a battle that shows more than 90% of the battle,
it's important that the player can see the information in the body.
So we really prioritize just that battle camera.
You're seeing over 90% of the game from that perspective.
So all of the information that the player needs
about what the character's doing, how they're posed,
needs to come from that perspective.
ANIMATION DESCRIPTION
We talk a lot about the animations,
but at the end of the day, the final decisions
are always made from that perspective.
ANIMATION DESCRIPTION
Talk a little bit about critical arts, super combos, those cinematic moves that Street Fighter is known for.
Basically, the important thing we've thought about for a long time is,
can you explain this in one phrase?
Let's take a look at this quick video, no sound, but hopefully you guys have seen this a few times.
We've got Rashid, his critical art.
Laura.
And Rainbow Mika again.
It's good timing. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Nice.
So what's the common point here?
I couldn't play the video to the end, but for example,
this technique you just saw,
wouldn't you want to say something like Aladin or Genie?
So when you look at Rashid's critical art,
don't you think the words like Aladdin or a Genie,
don't those words come to mind?
Next, this technique,
wouldn't you want to say something like electric whirling or Sonic the Hedgehog?
In Laura's case, it looks like electricity.
It looks like she's Sonic the Hedgehog going around the screen.
I guess Ken's being turned into a butt sandwich here.
And here's a classic one, Ryu's super uppercut looks like he's breaking his opponent's jaw.
And this is really, really important for us.
If you can't describe these critical arts in a single simple phrase, that's no good.
This is a traditional element of the Street Fighter series.
And this is true, again, since the very beginning with special moves and other things like that.
For example, have you ever talked about this 20 years ago?
When you first started playing Street Fighter, maybe your friends didn't.
Did you ever have these kind of conversations?
Dosuko yuute jimen to suihei ni sumo otori ga zutsuki sunnen.
It's like a sumo wrestler flying across the screen with a headbutt while yelling dog pie.
Yoga yuute kuchi kara hii hakunen.
It's this Indian guy who says yoga and breathes fire.
Kore wa tanin ni mo tsutaeyasui gengo ga dekiru youso ya ugoki wo itoteki ni toriireteru tteyuu koto desu.
And that's something again that we really try to make moves, animations that are easy to express with a single phrase.
When I watch a tournament and I want to tell my fans how I feel,
I watch Street Fighter's new character,
a character like Genie, and it's easier to tell them.
The fans are interested in what it is.
Going back to talking about Street Fighter as something that people enjoy in tournament settings,
if you want to tell someone about that, if you want to have them understand why Street Fighter is so cool,
it's very important that it's easy to relate these cool things
and easy for them to imagine them with a simple phrase that gets them interested.
We're going to talk a little bit about stages, and again, it goes back to the 2D era.
This is probably the easiest example to show, a screenshot from Street Fighter Alpha.
So this is still the 2D era, so there's no true concept of depth in the image,
but we did control the color saturation very closely to give that impression.
You can see from this image that the characters are very vivid colors,
but the background is a little muted to create a mood.
So it's pretty clear where the difference here is.
The characters use really bright, vibrant, saturated colors,
while all the background colors are very muted and toned down.
The characters use the darkest colors to the brightest colors.
On the other hand, the backgrounds have a narrow range of colors.
For the characters, we use the entire full range of colors,
but for the stages, we have pretty strict rules about
kind of shortening that range and only using a narrower range.
This is the main color used.
The background has 0, 0, 0 black,
and 2, 5, 5, 2, 5, 5, 2, 5, 5, white.
You can see that it's not used at all.
And you can see just by these histograms,
we never use a pure 000 white or 255, 255, 255 black
on the backgrounds.
YOSHIMASA ENJI, JR.:
And this, again, it's just another example
of one of the many rules that were created back in the day
when we were creating this series that we still use today.
In this game, to adjust the histogram of the background and character,
we improved the color grading of Unreal Engine 4.
We call it multi-color grading.
This image is with multi-color grading turned on, and this is off.
So you can see the difference between multi-color grading turned on and off.
Off is more correct in terms of lighting,
but in a fighting game that is a two-frame game, the visibility is very low.
So the off image, it's much more accurate in terms of lighting,
but when you're talking about, again, the battle happening within the moment of a few frames,
it's not as easy to get the understanding and the information of what's going on.
So what we did was we upgraded the color grading system
to be able to use multiple lookup tables at a time for the scene.
We use four lookup tables for four different areas of the screen so we can separate foreground,
background, and also left and right depending on the stage.
And then we can use these tables to boost all the elements that
are in the foreground, including the characters, and kind of
mute the background elements.
YOSHIMASA ENJI, SPEAKING JAPANESE
We also have different tables for left and right.
So what that allows us to do is to give a different effect
to, say, a stage that's kind of half indoors and half outdoors.
YOSHIMASA ENJI, SPEAKING JAPANESE
So this is just those lookup tables kind of highlighted with red in the foreground, green in the background.
And of course we can kind of decide how this blends just by tuning the parameters in the tables.
And what this allows us to do is just basically follow those same rules to make the characters pop out and make the backgrounds look great.
Now let's talk a little bit about a field of view technique we use.
So of course from a 3D camera's perspective, a model will be a bit distorted,
look a little bit different in the center of the screen and on the edge of the screen.
It's hard to see the collision, and as a fighting game, it's a factor that can cause problems.
So this is really bad for fighting games
because that will actually affect the collision
and how the collision looks to the player.
So we needed to find a way to fix this.
YOSHIMASA ENJI, JPNE2 TRANSLATOR So again, this is just
an example of how you would look in the middle of the screen
and on the edge of the screen.
YOSHIMASA ENJI, JPNE2 TRANSLATOR So to address this,
we created a vertex shader that we call fixed projection.
Fixed projection eliminates the horizontal angle of the character.
This does not actually weaken the angle of the camera.
It artificially adjusts the vertex of the character in the opposite direction of the angle of the camera.
We're using the vertex information on the character model to actually kind of negate that field of view.
So this image is the image without fixed projection applied.
And this is the shader applied to its full extent.
And you can see that that sideways distortion is completely eliminated.
This fixed projection 1.0 is very similar to an orthographic view head-on in a content creation tool.
However, if you completely erase the angle of the picture, the three-dimensional effect of the character will be lost, so I blend it with a value of 0.5, which is just the right value in the product version.
We find if we applied it all the way it does make the character lose a lot of depth information as well.
So we played with it a little bit and came up with a value of about 0.5.
This is kind of the nice balance point where we still had a lot of depth information for the character,
but we didn't have the issues of kind of distorted collision.
The shader allowed us to keep a nice robust wide field of view to let the stages breathe and be really impressive,
but also kind of do what we needed to do in controlling that distortion on the characters for the purposes of the battle.
Now, let's move on to the second chapter, Art Direction.
All right, let's talk a little bit about the actual style and look of the art in Street Fighter V.
So again, very early on, in terms of the rendering style,
we decided on this non-photorealistic, or NPR, style at a very early stage.
Two reasons why we chose that.
The first reason is that Street Fighter is a series that has a wonderful artistic history,
and we wanted to make sure that Street Fighter V continued that tradition in its in-game art.
The second reason is really consistency in the image.
We talked a lot about the need to exaggerate and deform the models for the purposes of
legibility during battle.
Well, a very realistic rendering style just doesn't match up with that, so this helps
keep the image consistent.
And this is kind of the final result, two keywords like rich lighting and a painterly accent.
To achieve this,
we use three different techniques.
Those three we talked a little bit about are the brush strokes, those painterly accents,
how we emphasized the edges of the image, and how we played with color and controlled it.
First, we talked about this painterly style, how we achieved it.
So again, this is a good concept image that conveys what we wanted the final image to look like
with this very strong brush stroke kind of feel.
So we did this by applying filters directly to the normal map on the model.
We used the normal map because it allowed us to use the environment's lighting to really bring out that texture in the model.
And this is the same technique we used on Street Fighter 4,
actually, some differences.
On Street Fighter 4, we used a default Photoshop filter
to add some of this information right into the normal maps.
But we had an issue trying that with Street Fighter 5.
In the previous game, Street Fighter IV, the resolution of the normal map was increased,
so it was difficult to filter.
To solve this problem, we converted the normal map of tangent space to the normal map of object space.
To alleviate this, we took the normal map and converted it from tangent space into object space.
As you can see, in tangent space, there is no color difference because purple is spread all over the map,
but in object space, there are many colors, so it's easy to filter.
And we did this because object space affords us a much wider range of colors that we can play with when we're applying the filter.
Let's take a look at the production procedure.
So let's look at our process here.
So we've got the original normal map.
We convert that from tangent space into object space.
That object space, that's where we kind of play
with the filters, add different levels of effect
on different parts of the model,
reconvert that back to tangent space,
and then check the results in Unreal Editor 4.
Thank you.
Oh, no problem, yeah.
In 4.0, we used Photoshop's standard filter to reproduce the touch,
but in 5.0, we increased the resolution of the texture,
so we can now reproduce the touch in more detail.
We are using the third-party plugin SnapArt,
which allows us to reproduce the touch of watercolors and other brushes.
We actually used Snap Art 4 for a lot of the really great artistic effects.
They've got really nice, you know, everything from oil painting, watercolors, a lot of different styles.
It was really great for the team because there was just a lot of freedom to play with the parameters
and get a really, really different effect for every character, even within the same model.
For example, there's some parts of the characters where we want this effect to be very subtle,
and other parts of the characters where we go ahead and put it up strong all the way.
For example, this picture is easy to understand.
When you draw a picture,
The face of the character is drawn with a delicate touch and high density,
and is drawn with a rough touch as it moves away from the face.
This also really draws the player's attention when they're looking at the models to the areas of the model that have the highest and most important information.
We create models by selecting fine strands, from rough to fine strands, when we are compositing them in NM.
So we were able to choose what level of accent we wanted to put on each model
based on what part of the model was important and what exactly we were trying to emphasize.
So with this accent off, there's not a lot of detail in the musculature,
and it's a little bit flat.
but adding that accent really gives it a nice painterly look.
And this again, it just gets really close to our goal
of making the image look like it was just painted on
with some rough brushstrokes.
And this is what Nash looks like.
Let's talk a little bit about edge filter.
YOSHIMASA ENJI, SPEAKING JAPANESE So we used a full screen post processing
effect to achieve our edge filter highlight.
YOSHIMASA ENJI, SPEAKING JAPANESE Basically this post effect applies a specific
color to areas of the image that have very high contrast.
This is an image with the edge filter off.
It not only is really, really great for defining,
helping define that really strong silhouette,
but also that painterly effect we just talked about.
There's on and off.
You can see the difference.
This is a compound technique that further enhances the touch of the normal map.
It also works as a character outline,
which contributes to the improvement of visibility.
So again, this really helps us strengthen that character outline
and make it even clearer for the player,
but also it helps boost that painterly effect
that we're getting with our normal textures, normal map textures.
Next, we have the joint light.
Third, talk a little bit about how we apply indirect lighting to our character models.
So indirect light, it's a really, really important piece
if we're going to achieve this kind of very painterly effect.
It really lets us make something that's really nice and strong
by using these highlighted colors.
We wanted to give the artists the freedom to be able to add these highlights and effects to the characters wherever they wanted.
How we achieved that, we basically controlled the indirect lighting in a couple of different ways here.
The indirect lighting is the very, very last part of the lighting pass that we do on the final rendered image.
After creating a three-dimensional effect with the basic lighting, we add color to the shadows and reflections.
So after we do a pre-lighting pass and get the characters dimensions, get their volume on the screen,
we do a basic indirect lighting pass to emphasize the shadows and other parts of the model.
And these second two images make it really apparent how we use that indirect lighting.
Also, there are two types of indirect lighting, one is UE4's Indirect Lighting Catch.
The other is Light Middleware's In-Light, which is in real-time.
And then we used Enlighten for adding real-time lighting effects to the final image.
You can see that the effect of Enlighten is quite influential in the creation of the image.
And that really, as you can see, allowed us to play with the image
and really dial in exactly what we wanted to do for each model and each stage.
By using these two joint technology, we were able to intentionally add the shadows and stars to the characters.
And it was really great, the artists were able to achieve a lot of different looks in a lot of different contexts.
I talked a lot with the lighting artists about exactly how they wanted the lighting in each stage to be reflected on the characters.
I still have a lot to tell you, but I don't have much time left, so I'll sum up what I've talked about today.
So this is just a few examples of the many, many different things that we did to give Street Fighter its look.
A lot of different stuff that I would love to talk to you guys about, but we only have time to introduce a few of them.
So again, art is a singular element that we can use to convey all the information that the player needs to play the game correctly.
Of course, it's very important to make our characters look cool, look cute, but if you can't understand and read the battle, it's all for nothing.
And again, like I said, I think that art is really the only vehicle that we have to convey that information to the player as quickly as it needs to be conveyed.
Once we're able to achieve that, then we can think about, OK, how do we give this art the personality that Street Fighter deserves?
This talk is really about the role of art. What does it do? How does it function in fighting games?
But as you guys are working on your projects, I'd love for you to think about that.
What is the function? What role does the art play?
So that was kind of the reason for this talk and I hope you guys were able to take something from it.
Thank you so much for listening.
And I believe we do have a little time for some questions.
Hi, great talk. I was wondering, I mean you've made a lot of emphasis about
deforming the characters so that they look good in battle. However,
differently from 2D, in 3D with all the camera angles and really detailed...
but like framing of the characters,
those deformities can come across as a little off.
So, for example, when you did in Street Fighter V,
the story mode, a lot of the characters,
for example, Karen was walking around
and she had a huge hand.
So in that regard, did you have any special considerations
for cinematic animations?
Kind of separate from the battle, the battle model.
So the question is, what considerations did you take
for the player models and character models
in cinematics versus battle?
If there are differences.
So when we do cinematic, we make the hand a little smaller
to maintain the head and body.
Yeah, we do kind of soften some of the exaggeration
in the cinematic mode.
So we do kind of tone it down a little bit.
Just a little bit.
Yeah, just a little bit, but there's still the character,
so we leave a lot of it.
All right, thank you.
Thank you.
Thank you very much for the talk. I was wondering if there's anything special to be said about the cast shadows of the fighters?
Anything special to be said about the cast shadows of the characters?
Ah, the shadows?
Cheat or tips and tricks.
Ah, so you mean the shadows of the characters?
Did you have any tips or tips about the shadows?
I'm worried about that.
When it comes to shadows,
if you use black,
it doesn't look good.
So I try to use some special colors
so that it doesn't look black
on all stages.
I try to use all the colors.
One thing we do is we make sure that shadows are never
100% black.
That's something that we found, if we do that,
you start losing information.
So by using indirect lighting, we
make sure that the shadows have some kind of color information
and that it's properly saturated so that the image is consistent.
Thank you.
Good afternoon. I have a question concerning character silhouettes in regards to both Fang
and Nicali. I'm just curious, because of all the very crisp silhouettes that have always
existed in Street Fighter, there's a feeling that with Fang and Nicali, especially when
Nicali's in V-Trigger and his hair goes crazy, that their silhouettes get much harder to
define and to track. And I'm wondering if that was kind of an intentional choice to
make them a little bit harder to fight.
A question about Fang and Nicali's character silhouettes,
how there's maybe a little bit less defined than some of the other characters.
As for the Necalli, he appears a bit ambiguous in this film, but I really tried to make it look erotic for you guys.
About the fans, you can see the Chinese character and how he wears a Kimono.
I have tried to focus on that and make it clear that he is Chinese.
Sorry, one second.
The thing about those 2 characters, you know, I don't really feel like they're any less well-defined.
It's more about how we did it. Like for instance, in Fang's case, you know, he's got his clothing,
the kind of not, it's very exaggerated kind of Chinese style, right?
But the same kind of information that we can get from that musculature,
we use by, you know, just showing that through the clothing.
Nicali, very muscular and things like that.
How can you make the V-trigger of Nekari easier to understand?
The V-trigger?
Yes, the Nekari.
The easier to understand?
Yes, that's right.
The easier to understand when you use the V-trigger is because the hair is an obstacle.
So I emphasized that it doesn't have to be three-dimensional,
but that it looks like an effect and that it doesn't matter if you hit the target.
As it as it regards to the Kali and the V trigger specifically,
you know, the hair is what really goes crazy.
You know, that's where we kind of focused all of that really
nice visual expression.
But the actual body where, you know, the collision comes out
and everything's moving fast, you know,
we still follow the same rules.
So I think we hopefully were able to do it.
Thank you for your time.
Thank you very much.
First of all, thank you for the talk.
It's very amazing.
My question is about character creation.
It's more about who decides about the fighting style.
It's more design or art?
So basically, who decided the character's fighting style?
Yeah.
Yep. So again, the question was who kind of makes the final decision about the characters and their fighting styles.
And at the end of the day, that's the game director, who is Nakayama-san.
But of course, it's not just his decision, it's a team decision, and Kamei is very involved in kind of deciding,
OK, well, once we have, you know, if it's a karate man or, you know, someone who's using Brazilian jiu-jitsu,
how is that going to look? That's something that they work up together.
As a tradition for Street Fighter, the characters are shuffled between countries and martial arts.
So we made the base based on that in FFV.
Countries and?
Countries and martial arts.
Yeah, you know, Street Fighter, it's all about the country and the fighting style.
And those are kind of matched together.
So that's how we start thinking about the character.
Like, okay, this is going to be a character from some country.
And okay, what's their fighting style?
And then what do they look like?
That's kind of how it comes together.
Japan, karate, Ryu.
Spain, ninja, Vega.
Yeah, sure.
Cool, thank you.
Thank you very much.
Thank you for the talk.
I also had a question about character creation.
When adding a new character into the world,
you're introducing a new silhouette
into the whole cast of characters.
So do you have characters that you check against?
And then the second part of my question is,
I noticed that the newer characters
are more elaborately designed than the original set.
And so is that an intentional choice
to sort of introduce adding newer,
more interesting silhouettes?
OK, so the question is for the new characters,
when you add a new character, how do you compare their silhouettes?
Make sure they're unique.
And then why are the later characters seem a little bit more rich or?
Elaborate.
OK.
SPEAKER 1 IN JAPANESE
Do you think there is a difference between the current characters and the new characters?
The new characters' silhouettes are basically the same as the existing characters.
Yeah, we definitely, for the first part of your question, we certainly kind of compare all the character silhouettes to new character silhouettes to existing ones and make sure they're not confusing.
If you make it the same silhouette as the old character,
the old character will die and you won't be able to appear again.
That's the disadvantage.
Yeah, and that means, you know, it's very important to do that because
say we make a new character that looks very similar to an older character
and then later we want to bring them back,
it makes it very difficult to bring that old character back
and, you know, just makes them both weaker.
And the other one, V-Trigger...
Oh, not V-Trigger...
The new character is more...
Elevator.
Yes, that's right.
The new character has a unique movement and ability.
In Street Fighter V, there is a system called V-Trigger.
Based on that, when we were making the character,
we used a new power, a power we've never seen before.
That's how it came about.
And probably the biggest reason why the characters look more
elaborate this time around is because of the V Trigger system
in Street Fighter V. So the V Trigger system is based around
really wild, crazy, and very, very different techniques based
on the character.
And so that was a chance for us to kind of really boost some
of the cool things that they do with Nicali's hair and
things like that.
Thank you.
Hi.
Thanks.
Evening.
Great talk.
So my question is, with 4 and 5, it's a very strong departure from the sprite styles of the earlier Street Fighter games.
And I was wondering if that change was dictated from above, from your director, or if it came from the art department?
And regardless of which way that went, how you went about kind of mitigating...
or embracing responses to the shift from 2D Street Fighter into 3D Street Fighter?
Responses in terms of the reaction from fans and things like that?
From fans and from within the studio as well.
Okay. So the question is, who made that decision to do the shift from 2D to 3D,
and then how we handled the reaction?
We moved from 3D to 4D, and then from 2D to 3D.
First of all...
The decision was made after the art was done?
Or was it the headquarters that told you to make it 3D?
It was Ono.
Ah, that was Ono.
Make it 3D.
Also,
the reaction to the fans,
I don't want to say control,
but how did you react?
What do you think?
I don't know anything about it,
but I think it's something that the producer
has to think about.
the fans would react.
You know, we honestly weren't thinking too much about that
in the art department.
It was really all about figuring out
how to create Street Fighter in 3D.
And we were lucky enough to have a team of great producers
like Ono and some wonderful folks managing the community
that helped us kind of bring everyone along for that journey.
We try to just focus on the art as much as we can.
Thank you.
Hi, yeah, thank you for your talk. I was wondering are we done
No more, I think I'm getting the
Sorry about that
Last one last one last one so much be quick. I promise
I was just wondering on that book that you were showing earlier with all the like guides and rules for the muscles
Like is there a copy of that somewhere or is that just internal?
Did you find any copies of the materials you discovered at that research institute?
I was also asked this question in Japan but no.
We should be able to publish them in a blog called Shadow Loo Research Center.
You should check it out.
There's a lot of stuff from those documents,
and I believe over 200 characters.
I think I've already introduced more than 2,000 characters.
Oh, that's right.
The whole thing isn't up there.
There's a lot of information from that document
and other documents.
Also, Nakayama has over 200 characters,
Street Fighter characters that he's worked with these guys on,
that you can check out.
So I highly recommend you look at the Shadaloo blog.
And this was another question he got when giving this presentation, a different presentation in Japan.
So when he returns back to Japan, he's going to let people know how interested everyone is in these old documents and see if we can release them publicly.
Send them messages on Facebook, tell them how much you want to see these internal documents.
Cool, thank you very much. What was that website called again?
The Shadowloo blog.
Shadowloo.
What was the name of the blog?
In Japanese, it's called the Shadowloo Laboratory.
And I apologize, I can't remember if that's the same name in English or not,
but if you look up Nakayama Shadowloo Blog,
it's going to come up.
Sorry about that.
No, thank you so much.
Cheers. Thank you so much, guys.