Alright, let's start. I guess, yes? Okay, let's go. Yeah! Alright, so, um, I'm Dave, uh,
creative director on Dead by Daylight. Thank you so much for being here today. Um,
This is what we're gonna talk about today.
So a little bit of introduction on our studio.
Origin story of the game, how it was made,
preparing for the release, the live operation.
There's a lot to talk about,
so I had to take some very specific subject,
but I think they're key to the success of Dead by Daylight.
So, I mean, let's start.
So I wanted to present the studio I work for,
Behavior Digital.
It's part of the story.
It's important.
You have to know that Behavior Interactive has been
operating for 25 years.
And our usual business model is to do work for hire.
So we develop the game of others, others' ideas.
And this is great.
We can work with big publishers, big studios, and
learn a lot from them.
But we also add our own stories that we wanted to tell.
So four years ago, we started a studio within the studio
called Behavior Digital.
And the goal would be to develop and publish our own titles,
our own stories.
And we had this vision.
Remarkable games we would play our way.
Remarkable as in having a unique appeal
that we would play because they would be for us.
We would be the market.
So hardcore, mature game.
And our way, because we would have creative independence,
so we would choose our own solution,
how we would build this game, or these games.
So our first project, we had very specific goals.
We knew we wanted to do an ore game,
because we're really passionate about this genre.
It would be an asymmetrical multiplayer game.
That was the unique aspect to the game.
It would be long-lasting.
We would aim to keep this game growing and alive
for as long as we could.
and it would introduce a behavior digital to the world, to players.
So, a lot of big goals for a first project.
And Dead by Daylight is exactly that project.
So, I just want to know if you can raise your hand
if you played Dead by Daylight or if you watched Dead by Daylight.
Okay, that's great. Thanks.
So, just for the benefit of people of the future that might be looking at the video,
I'm still going to explain really quickly what the game is, so that we're all on the same page.
Survivor gameplay, right?
So it's a asymmetrical multiplayer game,
4v1 in a procedural world.
You can play the survivor role or the killer role.
The survivor goal is you spawn into that procedural map,
he needs to find five generators, repair them,
that will power an exit gate.
They go and activate that gate
and escape to live another day.
The killer objective is simple, find the survivor,
hit them twice to put them on the ground,
pick them up, and bring them to a sacrificial hook
where they're gonna bleed out and be sacrificed
to a giant monster that lives in the sky,
which we call the entity.
Simple.
We released the game on June 14th, 2016 on Steam
with this offering, so we had three killers at the time,
four survivors, all with their unique perks,
a lot of different items with different upgrades.
There were two mode, one ranked and one offline
called Kill Your Friends.
12 maps across three teams, all procedurally generated.
And this is where we are today.
We've added a lot of content to the game.
We, a lot of players have tried the experience.
We've added, yeah, new killers, new survivors,
a lot of new maps and themes,
and also iconic characters now are guests to our universe.
This is pretty cool.
And what is really special of the game is that
in this space, it's pretty rare to see community
and player engagement such as this.
Players are staying, they play our game for a long time.
So yeah, it's really special.
So we did this game, we had ambition that it would work.
Obviously we had ambition for the game.
But we were the first surprise of how it exploded.
in popularity on release.
So today we wanted to talk about the good things we did
to achieve this, some of the mistakes we did too,
because we did quite a few,
and our learnings and experience on this project.
First let's start with the origin of the project.
So we were thinking about doing this game for a long time,
almost a decade.
We did a lot of pitch at that time,
and we had issues getting partners.
It was, we heard a lot of different things.
Auror would not sell, it's too risky to build,
or the tech wasn't there necessarily
to do this type of game.
But...
Over all these years, every time we could,
we would still use these mechanics that we wanted to do.
Like, for example, in Naughty Bear,
there is an asymmetrical multiplayer mode in there.
A tree, normal bear versus naughty bear,
the killer bear, using bear traps to trap them.
So like, it feels similar, right?
It's pretty close to what Day by Daylight is.
But one day.
we've decided to start this project
and we tasked a designer to start doing
a lot of different prototypes
to test this asymmetrical aura gameplay.
So this is stage one, we call it the pretotype,
it's actually prototypes before the real prototype
where a lot of different ideas were tested in Unity.
At that time it was a 1v1 local multiplayer.
I'm gonna explain the photo real quick.
Actually, what you see here is a giant piece of cardboard
that we still have in the office,
which is used to separate a giant TV screen
to simulate the multiplayer aspect of the game.
Very analog.
The demo was absolutely on balance,
the killer was super powerful
and it was just one survivor with lives
to simulate the four players aspect.
And we were already trying different procedural scenarios
or random scenarios for the maps.
And really quickly out of this prototype,
we could find, we found the one, the one that was fun.
So we could identify the core loops
of the survivor and the killer really, really quickly.
So this prototype was so fun and promising that we decided
to create a pitch to actually start this project for real.
What is great at Behaviour is that there's no red tape.
We can actually go in and see the executive and try to get
their pitch.
faith to build this kind of project.
So what you're seeing here is actually part of the original
slides that we use for the Greenlight process.
Dead by Daylight was a working title, but it stuck.
So the goal of this Greenlight demo was to recreate the
pretotype, but in a five-player multiplayer.
So it would be networked at that point.
The fantasy, still the same as we have in the game right now.
Slasher has the feeling of power,
survivor is having fun being scared.
We had very strong inspiration.
I kept this slide to show it today
because what's really cool about it
is that we actually have a lot of these killers
in the game right now.
And three big goals.
We wanted to show that fear could be real.
We didn't want any UI or mechanics that would show that
your character is scared.
We wanted to prove that the player would be scared and
would make mistakes because he's stressed.
We wanted also to prove a visceral combat system, something very binary.
The killer finds you and hits you, you're dead, you're done.
And we wanted to prove that this game would be long-lasting,
that it would be ever-changing,
that every time you play, you would have a different experience.
So we got permission to create this stage two prototype.
The company add Fate into the product.
So we continued in Unity to build this real prototype that
is networked.
So this one was 4v1 networked.
It was a more balanced experience of what the final
game would be like.
And we're still using random maps.
The idea where we succeed with this demo
was to prove that the fear and tension
would be real and fun.
We solidified the core and we could focus on the core
and cut everything that was secondary right now
and assess the risk.
Oops.
And it worked.
This demo was built, we played it a lot,
and we passed the internal green light
so that we could get to the next stage
and actually make it happen.
The process was so good that we now have a division
within the studio called Yugo, which only does this.
So they build prototype after prototype all day.
We test them, and when we find a gem,
something that's really fun, they can become actual games.
So here the lesson is a very basic one,
but a very important one.
Find the fun fast and stick to it.
As you can see, the first prototype already showed
what the final game would be like,
and we really stuck with it.
So stage three, we actually start production.
We switch engine, we go to Unreal,
and we start building a team.
So the photo you see here is more of a,
A recent team, it's the biggest team we have yet.
But when we started, it was quite small.
We were about 20 on the team.
Each.
member of the team was handpicked to make sure that everybody had the same goal and were passionate about the same subject
that they really wanted to build that game and this was key because
one of the best tool we use during production are
regular playtests, constant playtesting of the game. Every time we change something all the team would play and try the game
and what was amazing for us and that we
tried to keep
is that when team members would stop to play the game
and go get a coffee, instead of talking about features
or bug or a specific mechanic, they would talk about
the stories, the emergent scenarios that happen
during the match.
This was really, really interesting and something
that we wanted to keep until the game was actually released.
It's also in that time that we discovered a new goal.
One time we showed the game to the whole company
during an event, an Halloween event.
So players would play the game
and we had this giant screen in the cafeteria.
we discover and created a new goal is that our game was not only fun to play
but also really fun to watch.
And this became a key into the development of Dead by Daylight and its success.
So get the right people for your project, absolutely
important, and take care of them.
Just as a reminder, we really wanted to have a long lasting
game, and really the hard work really starts when you
complete your game and release it.
So don't burn the team.
Take care of them.
Actually, at Behaviour, on that specific project, we did
very, very little overtime.
We're quite proud of it.
And it's perfect, because as soon as you get live.
people are still fresh and want to continue to work.
Alright, so we're in production,
there's a lot of things I could talk about,
but I would never have the time in an hour,
so I selected two important features
that I think are interesting to talk about today,
that support the longevity of the game.
Sorry, my mouth is super dry, give me a second.
Alright, so first one is procedural maps.
We use a tile-based system to generate all the maps.
So the tiles have different assets on them, different gameplay.
So we adjunct them together, so every time it's different.
And we use also random spawners to have the survivor spawn in the unknown.
And our intention with that was to...
create billions of different scenarios
so that every time you play it feels really different
and you don't know what to expect.
So it creates uncertainty,
but it is also a very sustainable way to create new maps
because you don't have to end craft them.
So our idea was really,
players are gonna have million of different maps,
it's gonna be amazing.
But we found out really quickly that the players
testing our game would really have a feeling that
there's just one map.
The chaos that we put into the random generator was not
appreciated to its fullest.
Like they couldn't really explain where they were or
what the difference was between all the maps or all
the permutation.
So we went back to the drawing board
and found some rules to use to fix this problem.
So first off, we would build about five maps
within each team.
So we created that concept of teams.
So you have here, Macmillan Estate,
Coldwind Farm, Otoeven Wreckers,
the first teams that we created.
They have very different mood and lighting,
so they're recognizable.
Second rule is that every map would be.
would have a specific name and a specific building
that would be static.
So usually found in the middle of the map,
they're really recognizable.
And you know as soon as you see the name of the map
where you are and what to expect on that front.
The other thing that we made sure
is that we use a landmark asset
that were used usually in corner of the map
to be used as navigational point
and also recognizable that you can actually
know where you are and recognize them.
So this fixed our problem and added something really
interesting.
So as soon as the map is loading and you see the name
of the map, the player would be able, even though that
there's a lot of random component, they would be able
to start preparing their strategy because they knew
that something specific would be in there.
Also, the people watching the game could also start
hypothesis of what the player should be doing to win.
So that was really interesting.
We gave the players and the watchers a language
to be able to talk about the experience too.
This awesome thing happened to me
on the second floor of this asylum
is something that couldn't be made before
because the random aspect, there were no anchors.
So lesson learned here is that you need,
well, we needed to create expectation and anchors
in the procedural world.
Going fully random and fully chaotic is not something that is really pleasant or that you will feel good in your game.
Next big component I want to talk about
that we did during production is load out and progression.
So our goal, our intent was to create a lot of,
you know, bulk of items, add-ons, offerings,
and all of these things that you can
customize your character with.
So we had items that gives you secondary reaction
in the game, such as.
a toolkit for example that repairs generator faster,
add-ons, two add-ons to add to these tool to customize them.
Each character would have four perks
that would also change their abilities,
and the offering is the wild card
that actually changes how the match is gonna be played
and how the procedural aspect of the map could be tweaked.
And we thought that the more we would put in the game,
we would allow player to experiment, that would be fun.
So every time.
you go into a match, you put these components,
it changes the map, it adds chaos,
it adds different stories, and it adds uncertainty.
The other thing that we did is this infinite progression
through the blood web.
So this is a procedural skill tree,
and all of the nodes, the component that you can buy
to evolve your character are also.
procedurally chosen.
So you, every time you evolve your character,
you don't know exactly what it's gonna be
and you need to choose how to build your character.
So again, this was to create a near infinite progression
so that players could play for a long time.
The first, really, the big problem that happened,
so at first it was really good.
I mean, it was appreciated that there was a lot of content,
but experimentation stopped quite quickly.
In a competitive game,
players want to win.
So obviously there's gonna be a meta build,
the build that is judged perfect for survivors and killers.
It's gonna be on the web,
and then players will want to have this specific thing.
And our procedural skill tree, the blood web,
would become more frustrating than anything
because you really wanted to be able to achieve
this specific loadout,
and it was really difficult to get there.
Also, it stopped.
completely experimentation, like this is what you would see.
So the way we changed our approach with that now
is that instead of doing bulk of different items
to release when we do an update,
we focus on less things but that are more meaningful
and that shakes the meta so that the players
actually start to experiment and adapt again to a new meta.
Another problem with a bulk of items like that
is that it adds exponential weight on your team.
So an example of this is the moon offering.
So these are a set of four offerings that changes the
lighting of a map.
So you can change the moonlight so that the level is
brighter or darker.
And every time we create a new map,
the artistic team need to do a basic lighting pass
for the normal experience, and then make sure
that the combination of all the different moon offering
that the players can play will have a great lighting too.
And then we also add a perk that would also affect
the lighting of that specific character.
So there's all these permutations to,
it's a lot of work just to have a perfect lighting
for all of these things.
So our solution for that, I mean it was a great gimmick of an idea at first, it was cool,
but since it's not used that much and adds so much problem to the team,
we decided to retire these items.
That's fine too, so they just disappeared, they don't appear on the blood web anymore,
players cannot play them anymore.
So the lesson here is, don't be afraid, be courageous.
You might have released with something awesome,
but the game evolves in a way that you don't need it anymore
and that you should change so that the game
becomes interesting again, and that's fine.
All right, so fast forward to end of production.
We have a great game in our hands.
We know that it's fun to watch, it's fun to play.
But nobody knows about our studio,
nobody knows about our game,
so we started thinking about building a community
and iPlayers.
So I wanna, in this section,
go quickly over the different tools that we use
to get that community built up.
So for us, we started on Steam.
Obviously, this is where we released the game.
So the Steam forum is where we wanted to start
talking with the players.
And at that time, we had a partner, Starbreeze,
who have a game you might know about, Payday 2.
And at that time, they had one of the biggest
community on Steam.
They had about three million members in their community.
So the deal we did with their player is,
come join our community.
and you will unlock three awesome masks in Payday
teamed on Dead by Daylight.
So a lot of players came in the community.
Obviously a lot of them were there for just the free shit,
but we had a way to talk to them.
So now every time we did an announcement
on our community page, they would receive this message.
And quite a few of them were converted.
I mean, they wanted to know more
and started to follow the project.
Another big thing we did is our first event.
We went to PAX to talk about our game.
And this was a first for the company.
We didn't know really what to expect.
We shipped five PCs, and most importantly,
the dev team to go there and talk about the project.
We had a super cool, nondescript black box of boot
with only the title.
And the most important thing was the giant TV screen
all around the booth.
We knew our game was fun to watch,
so players would come here and test the game
and play a real match and then people around
would be able to look at what was happening
and have fun just watching the game.
The first day was selling the game,
you know, one person at a time, super difficult.
But people were intrigued, they were looking around.
It's the second day that was awesome for us
and a revelation really because there was a lot,
a lot of people just packed around the boot
and we didn't need to explain the game anymore.
The crowd was able to explain to newcomers
what was going on.
The concept is easy to grasp and easy to explain
and it's awesome for this kind of events.
And most importantly, at the end of the event,
we had a lot of content creators, streamers, YouTuber,
that came to see us to tell us
that they were hyped about the project.
They couldn't wait to get their hands on it
to be able to stream it.
They understood the power of this product
as a really entertaining game to watch.
It was actually so important, this factor,
that when we came back.
We really had the choice in production before release,
we had the choice to create one extra mode
that we needed to choose.
Do you want to do an offline mode, kill your friend mode,
or the survivor friend, the social group
that you form survivor with your friends?
And we chose kill your friends
because of the content creator.
We wanted to give them a platform that's safe and offline
so that they could create their videos and have fun.
And it served us really well.
I mean, the streamers really pushed visibility on the
beta-lite on release.
Another tool we use is that we started at that time doing
the weekly Devstream, which is something we still do.
We're going to do our 100th episode soon.
And we started to talk with the community on Twitch.
So people would come and interact directly with us
in the Twitch chat to be able to
ask questions about the game.
and we would show them some gameplay,
show them how it works, answer these questions.
And it's at that time that a lot of questions
would come back, and it was clear that we needed,
as a team, to start and take commitment
and do promises for the future of the game.
So it was time for...
big promises.
So doing promises to the community is scary,
but you really need to do it to start building trust
with that community.
And for us, I'm gonna expose you what the three
big promises we did were.
They were quite easy to do because they're a part
of our values as a team.
No pay to win.
It's something that was asked out of our community.
It's something that a lot of them lived in other projects.
And they wanted us to make commitment that there wouldn't
be any pay to win.
And it's something that
I mean, that we've put some systems in the game to make sure that perks, abilities would
be available to everybody, even though we sold DLC.
We actually just announced today that we're adding a new system or a new way to unlock
characters in the game.
So all of our original characters will now be unlockable with playtime.
So that's how we fulfilled this promise.
We actually did pay to lose.
The first DLC we released was a customization pack,
really flashy, themed on the 80s.
And of course, if you're a flashy character
in a game where you need to hide,
it's pay to lose, right?
Our second promise is no fracturing the community,
and how we did this is every map we released
was going to be free and accessible to everybody.
That was super important to us.
And last one, we'll be as generous as we can.
Since the release of the game, there's two full DLC content
drop that we did completely for free, because we
could at that time.
So that's it.
And also some charity case to give back to the community,
something we did with the streamers.
We created specific items for them, and then sold them, and
all the money went to charity.
super appreciated by the community.
So the lesson here is start building your community
as soon as you can.
Be transparent, be available.
You can't wait till the game is out, obviously,
so as soon as you can.
Interacting with them is super valuable.
And if everything is going all right,
you'll have a community.
So for us, we wanted as a team to be really involved
with the community.
We didn't want the company to be the person
interacting with the community.
So all of us on the team, we did go into the forums
and answered directly and interacted with the members
of the community, answering their questions, their concerns,
and having fun with them, creating characters,
talking about the lore, and this was truly amazing.
Since then, we've added or we transformed some people
into dedicated community manager,
because it's a lot of work
and we have to do other things, obviously.
So let's talk a bit about community.
Let's start with the bad.
Let's get this out of the way.
I actually saw a couple of conference this week
about exactly this problem.
It's something that every one of us need to tackle,
especially in the online multiplayer
with subject like killing, like our game.
you're gonna get your personal life invaded.
Like if you have your personal Facebook or Twitter
and you're having fun on there,
fans are gonna find you,
they're gonna ask you questions.
Some of them are really toxic as well.
And it's dangerous to start and work 24-7 really
because you have your phone
and you want to interact with them.
And because the game is worldwide, it never stops.
This is something you need to be careful about.
When toxicity becomes really, really high, some of them, I
mean, will also get to threats targeting you directly.
And my point here is that, I mean, these things, it
shouldn't happen, but they happen.
And you need to be ready to support team members that are
going to live these kind of scenarios so that they feel
supported and protected.
But the good of having community tremendously outweighs the bad.
It's great for motivation, interacting with the community,
seeing what they build, the arts and craft, they write stories,
they contribute, and make the game much better.
I add only one slide to show you the kind of thing
that our community is doing.
They create their own chapters, the Shia Surprise.
It's awesome, I wanna build that eventually.
Tattoos of our main character, it's crazy.
I mean, cosplay obviously.
Videos, I mean, they're all over
and they make the game richer.
Lesson, ear is one of the most important one.
When you release a game that's going to be live,
you...
create a relationship between you and your community.
And you need to give them this ownership.
It's gonna make the game richer.
It's gonna make the game better.
So it's as much as theirs as it is yours.
You should embrace that.
All right, so stage four, we release the game.
We're now live.
We have the biggest team yet.
I wanna talk a bit about the early days,
what we did in the first month.
about on the live operation of the game.
So continuous monitoring, communication with the community,
super important, fixing bugs aggressively,
and starting work on our major updates.
So here is a, it's quite small, it's the first things that we
released during the first month.
So we've listened to the community demands, and one of
the features that was asked the most was the survive with
friends feature.
So that mode that we had to cut before release.
So a way to be able to play with your friends.
So obviously, because it was a top demand,
we wanted to show that we had a commitment to that game
and to them, so we started working on that.
Other thing we did is that we monitored
the different languages in the community,
and we found out that we had a big community in China
and a big one in Russia as well,
but they didn't have their language supported in the game.
So they had to deal with English.
we added these language in the first month as well,
which was really, really appreciated.
We also released free content, maps, outfits,
just to show that these are the type of things
that we would give away, and again,
to show commitment that we would support this game.
It's not because your community is asking
to change a game that you should do everything, though.
There are some small rules that we kept
that we never touch.
I just want to do the first two example.
I think that since release, every single day, someone asks for voice in the game.
I want to be able to talk to other players.
I want to be able to scream in the game with a mic.
And for us, we knew that this would break completely the immersion, so we've always
said no to this feature, and even today we don't have it.
One other thing that was asked a lot was the ability to,
actually goes the other way,
the ability to change the survivor third person perspective
to go into first person,
to have a better immersion and be more scared,
basically as a survivor.
And we've always pushed back
because survivors are supposed to work as a team,
and if you make your experience harder
by going first person,
you might make the other survivor experience kind of sucky.
So we've decided not to go there.
There are some small rules we broke, though,
in the first month.
Killer speed is an interesting one.
When we developed the game,
the chase economy,
the speed of the killer and of the survivor
was sacrosanct values
that we decided that we would never change.
But then the first killer that we released post-launch
is our nurse.
She teleports, she goes through wall.
So we add to balance her by lowering her speed.
So this is something we broke in the first month.
Survive with friends, like I explained,
in our vision, original vision,
we wanted players to experience the game
alone with strangers.
This is like the uncertainty makes the game better that way.
But, I mean, something that was requested a lot,
so we decided to break that rule
and let survivors play together with friends.
And last one, last example, new killer powers.
We were supposed, when we originally designed the game,
that every killer that we would release post-launch
was going to be stat change and little tweaks
to create these new killers.
So we start with a trapper and we change this
a little bit, things here and there.
But we decided to go another way,
which is much better in my opinion,
whereas we basically created complete new powers
for these killers.
So lesson here, be confident, not stubborn.
I mean, it's fine changing your game.
You still need to be true to your vision,
but the community is gonna ask for something in your games
and it's also fine to change it.
It's gonna make something better.
So there's two types of things
that we do during live operation.
Pretty basic stuff.
We add new content and we do some services.
So this is an example of a content drop
that we do in Dead by Daylight.
We call them chapters.
It's a format that we use that is always the same.
So when we release a content drop,
we have a killer, we have a survivor,
and we have a new map that's accessible to everyone.
Survivor comes with new perks,
and the killer is the most important of all,
comes with new fiction, a new lore,
and a new power that redefines the gameplay of the game.
So, here are some examples.
When we create these new characters,
we really try to break the game in a good way.
So, the nurse teleports, changes the chase completely,
so breaks the game in a good way.
Really interesting.
Players need to adapt.
The Entryist, which released one year after the launch.
is our first character with a range attack.
So again, changes the dynamic completely
because all of the others would have normal melee.
So again, need to adapt to this new gameplay.
The pig, which is the last killer we released,
adds a new objective to the survivor completely.
So she adds a reverse bear trap.
So she's from the Saw franchise.
She adds the reverse bear trap on the head of the survivor.
and they can't escape even though they repaired the five generators
and they have the exit gate open.
They have to find the jigsaw box and find the correct key
to get this thing off their head.
So it adds a new core loop to the experience.
So again, need to adapt drastically to this new character.
So what is cool about having a format like that
is that it creates a solid pipeline for your team.
So having the same kind of format
every time you create a DLC, the team.
knows exactly what they have to do and what to expect.
It is also very clear for players.
When we announce a chapter,
they know exactly what is going to be in there.
And it adds to, well, everyone experience.
In our case, adding a new killer with new gameplay
means that you can play this killer
and have a new experience,
but you can also, as a survivor,
encounter this new character.
So it's like we're adding a new boss fight to the game.
Limitations though, redefining the whole gameplay
every time we do a content drop is difficult for a small team.
It takes a lot of dedication and bandwidth,
so it takes away a little bit of focus
of supporting what's already in the game.
It adds complexity to the players.
We're actually reaching critical mass at the moment.
By adding all of these new gameplay components
every time we release a killer, it
deepens the gap between veterans and new players.
So to fight this problem, we just have to do a lot more
on-boarding about these characters, add more ints,
and teach our players these new gameplays
so that they don't get confused.
Now, services.
So this is the first year of all the updates we did.
There's a lot of stuff, a lot of service.
So service, just so that we're on the same page,
there are free updates, just make the game better.
And I just wanted to go quickly over some of the ones
that served us better.
It's good to put names on them.
Base features.
So we had to cut a lot of things
to focus on the core of the game,
so that it would be solid.
Releasing a game on PC, there's obviously things
that the player will expect day one.
In our case, for example, we didn't have remapping.
We couldn't customize the control.
This is something that players expected day one.
So these services are really nice.
You should do them early as possible.
If you can just add these features,
make your community happy,
so that it feels like a more complete game.
Onboarding, we do it regularly,
just like I explained with the chapter,
to support a new player, to explain new mechanics.
We actually released the game with two videos,
that was our tutorial,
and they became outdated really, really quickly.
So we had to get rid of the videos,
and we changed that to a manual,
so text-based explanation and tutorial,
and that was much easier to update.
So it's a much better choice for a long-term onboarding.
Quality of life are updates that lowers frictions
within the game.
One example that we lived recently,
we had issues sometime with our matchmaking,
sometime people would be with players that would be laggy,
and they had no way to know their ping.
So they would...
go out of the game and use a third party software to be able to know the ping of the players.
And we didn't want that, we didn't want players to get out of the game for that.
So we've added this feature to the game, lowers friction, makes the experience better for all the players.
And these guys are based on community needs.
So when community is asking, requesting for something like that, we make it happen.
Safety, not glamorous, but something that we have to do
always, so every day, making sure that the game is a safe
environment.
We've added a lot of features, actually, since release.
Report function, so a way to report players.
Ban function, and also making sure that the new cheats and
the new cheat engine are addressed, so that there's no
cheating in the game.
Events is one of the most interesting ones, something
that we started last year, actually.
So Halloween, a winter event, the anniversary, they're great
to create excitement around the event for a week or a
weekend, and they're a great way to test
special gameplay as well.
and they are great to lower the toxicity for a moment.
Every time we do events with Objective
that are usually community-based,
we see that within the game, the toxicity is lowered,
it brings the community members together,
so that's really interesting.
And last one but not least, balance,
something we do regularly as well,
so to balance issues and to shape meta.
So I'll go back with more on balance a little bit later.
So lesson here is really to
if you're aiming to have a live game
that you're gonna update regularly,
you need to focus on the foundation
of your game at the beginning.
It's okay to cut a lot of secondary system
because you'll have time afterwards.
If the players buy in and wanna be part
of the experience of your game,
then the rest can come later
and you can do that indefinitely.
All right, let's go to balance now.
So, balancing a game is difficult.
I think we can all agree, balancing an asymmetrical
multiplayer is really difficult.
And I really wanted to go quickly how or what we use
to balance the game.
So we use three sources, gut instincts, data analytics,
and community feedback.
All important.
Quick note about gut instincts, when you're creating
something new, we're, I mean.
We had no clue doing the symmetrical multiplayer horror game.
Doing new characters, that changes the game completely.
Working in design, you don't have players,
you don't have analytics, you don't have anything to use.
So you know your game, your team knows the game,
so a team debate and going with your instinct
is the normal way to go at that point.
Data analytics is really interesting for us, for the team.
It was the first project where we actually used analytics.
One of the best addition, that's Julien by the way.
Hello, hello Julien, you can say hi.
He's a really fun guy, a data analyst
that we added to the game, to the project, sorry.
He's a PhD evolutionary biology.
So this guy is.
awesome addition, E will crunch through our data,
but also can make link to the psychology of our players.
So E works with our designer to find
what we can change in the feature or what we can balance to
address some specific personality-based
problem.
Data analytic is not optional.
Now we make sure that everything we design,
everything we add, it's a part of the scope.
We think about what we'll need as analytics
and it's always thought in the future.
Be mindful of the hooks.
When we, before release, we weren't sure
what we needed as hooks into analytics.
So we've added.
hooks everywhere, analytics about everything.
And this is a problem, it's something that you won't
be able to use.
If you get data about everything, it's gonna bloat
your data, it will be super expensive, and you won't
be able to analyze this data.
We had to scrap most of it, actually, and make it lighter.
So, not enough is a problem, too much is also a problem.
You just need to design and be mindful of what you need.
And the last point, data versus perception,
is really important.
Data analytics is really strong,
but when the community thinks that there's a problem,
it doesn't matter how strong is your data.
They won't believe you.
Like, the perception is much stronger.
And that's why it can't be the only tool
you use to balance the game.
So another tool that we use.
is a Discord group.
So we formed that last year with an elite group
of our players.
So we found players that had more than 1,000 hours
in the game, that were really invested,
that could play the game really well,
and that add constructive feedback about these features.
And we invited them into the Discord group
where our designers, some engineers.
and community manager interact with them directly.
We actually talk with them pretty much every day
to talk about a balance path that we want to do,
a new feature, to get their feedback.
They really represent the community
and what the community thinks.
They're also under NDA, so it's possible for us
to create specific builds just for them,
and we can play with them.
And they are so invested in the game
that they're much better than anyone in the team.
so their feedback is super valuable.
So just Trulison learned about balance.
First of all, don't react to first reactions.
We found out that every time we release new content,
it takes at least two weeks for the players to adapt.
The data analytics that you receive
in these first two weeks is rubbish, you can't use it,
and their reaction is also not real.
They need that time to adapt
and understand what has changed in the game.
Leave no one behind.
When we do a balance pass for a problem that is for the
higher ranks, for example, we always need to make sure that
this change will not affect in a bad way the
lower ranks players.
So we need to be inclusive.
And communicate a lot.
When we do changes like that, we usually communicate before
we do the change to get the feedback.
We communicate when we do the patch,
and we communicate a lot afterwards
to make sure that there's no wrong interpretation
of the changes.
Right, so patches.
Last segment.
So, obviously, if you're gonna do a lot of services
and a lot of the content,
you're gonna do a lot of patches.
And we have a crazy cadence where we would do patches
and not fix every two weeks about.
So, we did about five million, give or take,
different patches, and I think that we did
all the mistakes possible when doing patches.
So, I prepared a blitz of different mistakes,
so we'll go quickly through them.
Huge patch to download with no player-facing changes.
Patches are too far apart.
Patches are too close together.
IPing a patch that never comes.
Iping a patch that doesn't deliver.
Forget to communicate about an awesome patch.
Nobody knows about it.
Patching without patch notes.
Leaving space to interpretation in the patch notes.
Forgetting to mention the change in the patch notes.
Forgetting to remove the mention of a change
that was reverted in the patch notes.
Patching on a Friday because of limited support
during the weekend, that's bad, you know about that one.
Patching on a Thursday because one day is not enough.
Patching on a Wednesday because two days is not enough.
Patching on a Thursday because the last four patches
were awesome and surely this one will be too.
Horrible mistake.
Patching just before the holidays against limited support.
Patching because it's time.
Horrible.
Patching a bug fix which heavily impacts the game balance.
Patching a balance pass on a character
that released yesterday.
Nah, that can't happen.
Patching with data we don't want to reveal just yet,
so we did a couple of leaks.
Patching PC way before patching on console,
they're gonna be mad about it.
And patching console one hour before patching on PC.
They're gonna be super pissed about it.
So some best practices, I don't want to go through
all of them, but some important ones,
if this wasn't clear enough, patch early in the week
so that you can outfix.
Have an emergency plan.
So we put a pipeline for this, which is great.
So if something happens during a weekend or an evening,
the team members can know who to contact
so that the problem is fixed as soon as possible.
And PTB, so public test build, super easy on Steam.
Whenever possible, you can create this specific build,
give to the player before it's actually released.
They will test it, they will be able to comment.
If you have the analytics in there, it's super useful
to see if your patch is gonna be okay.
And you can even do a survey to make sure
that you get the feedback you want from your community.
So lesson here, probably the lesson of lesson
for our project.
You can fail, it's fine.
We did a lot of mistake, it's fine.
Acknowledge, learn out of them,
become better, and then repeat.
So as a summary, I want to expose what I feel
are the big points that made our project successful.
One, create a remarkable game
with unique flavors and emotions.
Two, consistently redefine the game
with new content and updates.
Three, work end-in-end with the community,
give them ownership.
Four, be available to your players,
be transparent, honest, and generous.
Five, be passionate and stay true to your vision.
And thank you.
OK, so we have a bit of time here, if you want to ask
questions, and then we can go somewhere else.
I think there's a wrap up section that we
can use afterwards.
Matt is also with me, so if you have questions for him,
please go to the mic if you have some.
All right, easy peasy.
So you talked a little bit about responding to the meta.
Has there been anything you've seen where you created an item
or a perk, and you expected it would be used in one certain
way, and then as soon as you saw the way players were
actually using it, you were like, that wasn't what that
was for, that wasn't our intention with that change?
Absolutely.
For sure.
I don't have an example that comes to mind.
Do you have one?
The party starters?
That was use, that was use okay, I guess.
I don't know, yes.
I mean, or we didn't expect to be that important.
That is one that happened.
For example, borrowed time or decisive strike.
We knew they were going to be important.
You know, second chance perk or huge.
But that they would cause so much pain to the killers,
that was a surprise.
Um, yeah.
So doing licensed character are super interesting creatively actually because you know
They they're already established and making their power fit into our game is sometime a big challenge when we started working on Freddy
You know which exist in another world only in your nightmares like okay?
This is gonna be it's gonna be a challenge and these limitation are actually super fun
Original character where we can go you know anywhere is also is also a lot of fun
But yeah licensed character with this challenges is it's quite cool
I mean, it's not a problem.
It's really a fun thing to have.
One last question.
How many killer ideas did you come up with did you not use?
Wow.
We have a dump of character in our documentation.
And we might have.
30-ish, just waiting there.
So they might come up in the future.
They're not necessarily cut,
but sometimes it's just a matter of time,
like this one is too complicated for now, so, or, yeah.
It's one that's definitely cut, yeah.
Oh yeah, the flying one.
Well, maybe one day, I don't know.
Yeah, we did have a killer in the prototype
that was flying, so of course it's kinda OP in that case.
Yeah, we got rid of that one.
Yes.
I just had a question about how you worked together with the Payday 2 team to do that
kind of cross-promotion with the masks.
Did you have any kind of information exchange?
Did you learn stuff from them on Payday 2?
Do you still speak?
Yeah, for sure.
I mean, our relationship with Starbreeze when we started this project, we learned a lot
of them, out of them.
I mean, how to build up that community, that's, I mean, for sure.
Do you have anything to add to that question, Matt?
No.
I thought the collaboration was, especially at the beginning,
it was sort of invisible to us.
Like, they did the masks, and they showed us afterwards.
And I'm like, yeah, OK.
That's sort of what they like to do,
because they didn't really know the game.
But they trusted us to do the game.
And they sort of left us to do it.
Yeah.
And they were just super supportive.
But they didn't want to touch it.
Yeah.
But it was good because they said, you will do the push to
push the visibility of this project.
You will have to work hard for it.
And we wanted to do this.
It's our game, and we wanted to be involved in our community
and build it up.
So it was guidance, and then we did all the hard work,
really.
Just had one kind of follow-up question.
Did you find that you had a lot of overlap from players that
were, you said you had a pretty good conversion of players
who tried Dead by Daylight that came from the Payday 2
audience?
I think so.
I don't have any stats.
But I mean, at first, building that community and having
people in our beta, a lot came from the Payday community.
That's for sure.
The first 10,000.
Right.
So he said the first 10,000.
At least, give it a go.
No.
Great, thanks.
No problem.
Anyone else?
OK.
Thank you so much.