Good afternoon folks, my name is Brian Francis.
I'm a community manager for GDC.
I'm a contributing editor at gamasutra.com,
which is a website with a name.
If you need to refer to me in the third person,
I use the pronouns he, him.
Today I'm delighted to be joined by Funomina CEO,
Robin Hunneke.
Robin, would you like to introduce yourself real quick?
Hi, I'm Robin Hunneke, I'm the CEO of Phenomena.
We're a 22 person company downtown San Francisco
until we became completely remote.
So I'm here today to talk to people about what that means.
I thought I'd give people a little bit of an introduction, just describe kind of where we are,
so that you know the kind of context that I'm in. I've worked with teams as large as 180. My
current team is 22 people. That's three functional teams, so teams of about five to seven typically
is where we start with on any game that we make inside of Phenomena.
And we were already two days a week remote when the pandemic hit.
And we went to full remote in advance of the pandemic.
So we've been fully remote for almost four and a half months now.
I apologize for mispronouncing a number of things there.
Everybody does it.
But with that in mind, I would like to quickly give a call out for folks to start asking their
questions for Robin because we are here to talk about the art and business of working from home.
But while you put your questions in chat,
I'm going to go ahead with kind of an explainer for our mindset
about doing this AMA.
I'm going to level with you.
We're here because shit is weird.
Shit is weird.
We are not in Moscone Center.
My cat is right behind me.
And I'm using a light from my miniature painting kit
to make sure I don't look like a goblin
that I would be painting.
When a once-in-a-century global pandemic hits, your job and your life get upended even if,
like me, or Robin's team sometimes, you're already working from home.
This is true at game development studios all over the world, and as CEO of Phenomena,
you've, Robin, been at the front line of wrangling the challenges that come with
moving studio-based teams to remote work. Like I said, we're going to take your questions.
And to help us get the right questions in,
we would like to ask you to please use the questions section
in the swap card to submit them,
and then go ahead and upvote the questions
that you want to see asked,
because we will use that to help figure out
what needs to be talked about.
I can only encourage you to please ask those questions,
please click liberally.
Otherwise, I will start asking Robin about
Tins made using art from 1980s Mexico anti-drug propaganda.
Or I will introduce you to my cat,
which I know people want, and I know she wants that,
but we're here to answer your questions.
That's right.
Shout out to Victor Rosales in chat,
saying hi from Tokyo.
We can go ahead and get started with the first question
from our good friend, Jason Della Rocca.
All right, Jason.
Jason, thanks for running GDC Pitch.
Jason wants to know what your go-to cocktail recipe is for this.
Of course he does.
Perfect start. Perfect. No, this is quarantine rules.
I actually started making my own limoncello during the quarantine
because I have a lemon tree behind my house in Santa Cruz.
And so I have a quarantini that is made out of limoncello that I made from my lemons,
which is basically vodka and lemon peels that you soak for a really long time.
And then I love to do it with the raw bitter cherry juice from Whole Foods,
a little bit of ice, and a splash of Campari with a slice of lime. It's actually pretty great.
For my part, I'm just missing an old-fashioned, but if you want more mixology lessons, we do have a mixologist, I think, tonight at the...
It's the one thing I truly miss.
Yeah, you can learn how to make your own cocktails from home, too, for your home game development studios.
Okay, serious questions now.
Michael Stephan would like to know, what are your favorite remote tools and how do you get your team to actually use them, especially if you're a less formal indie team?
Right, so one of the things that we have found over the years with Phenomena is that you can use
literally anything as long as it tracks data and can be edited by multiple people, right? So you
can do everything from just a Google spreadsheet or when we were in person, you know, a wall with
sticky notes all the way down to something really advanced like DevTrack or Asana where you're
building out a full waterfall and then trying to follow everything.
It's really actually up to the discretion of the producers on our teams.
So some of our teams use Asana, some of them use Google Docs and spreadsheets for burndowns that
they prefer to maintain on their own. Some people use Mondays.com and I personally use a task
tracker myself in addition to whatever I use on the team called OmniFocus and I started using that
at the beginning of this last month.
Because I started to find that I was getting a little bit scattered in terms of just trying to check in on slack and check in on all these other things.
And I needed a place myself where I could dump everything that was coming into my brain.
I've been making games long enough now that sometimes I forget stuff, so I have to write it down.
In terms of getting people to use it, because Phenomena was a two day a week remote studio and we had no meeting Tuesday, Thursdays.
We already had to be using this kind of software
to coordinate action on the days
when people are gonna be cranking and working from home.
And I think that the most comfortable way
to introduce a piece of software,
whether it's a Slack kind of channel or a Hangout space,
is to have a central place
where you communicate with everyone
and then do a reminder before you're gonna be using it.
So, hey everybody, we're gonna be checking in in this space.
Hey everybody, I'm going to need you to check your Mondays today.
I'm going to be working on it in an hour before this hour is up.
Could you please check in and make sure that you've made your Monday correct?
We also use a piece of software called 15 five now, which was suggested to me
by my friend Chelsea, who works at iron galaxy.
And that's actually a really helpful tool.
You check in on your own kind of goals for the week, and then there's actually
some questions that you can answer that the team can create a conversation around.
Like for example.
What are some roles that you wish we had at the company?
Or what was the best thing that happened to you this week or whatever?
So I think it's really about setting up a reminder and having that conversation
ahead of time so that people get used to using it.
And then every week at the team meeting, you can remind people,
oh, hey, your 15.5 is due today.
Last week, our, you know, our submission rate was 84 percent
and our average was 3.5 out of five because we had kind of a bummer week
in the news or whatever.
Right on, Chelsea Blasco would like to know,
how do you establish good boundaries from working from home?
Real quick folks, I did grab Chelsea's question,
but I need to grab the rest of the questions
from our chat section in order to manage
the number of good questions you're asking.
Please make sure to ask them there.
So yeah.
So Chelsea's question was,
remind me again, it was boundaries?
Yeah, how do you establish good boundaries
for working from home?
Right, so one of the things that we're really talking
about a lot lately is flexibility.
And that includes the flexibility
to be able to shut your camera off.
So not everybody wants to be like showing everyone the world their home.
So some people use video backgrounds, but some people just don't feel
comfortable having 10 people staring at them for an hour at a time.
And if you're doing that kind of work all day, especially if you're a producer,
it can be very helpful to, for example, take your one on ones
from a phone where you don't have video.
And so really normalizing the idea that the video is a performance
and that not everybody wants to perform all the time.
The other thing that we've been really trying to do is to make people feel less compelled to attend meetings,
but to give them the opportunity to attend if they want to.
So create a shared space for a project,
and schedule meetings of two to three people, say, in that space,
and then tell the rest of the team, this is the block of meetings we're having this week.
If you want to just hang out and listen and not be present,
you can turn on your audio, not turn on your camera,
and you can be kind of in the room while the designers are talking about something,
or in the room.
So it allows you to have kind of a soft boundary, which you used to have at your desk, and you no longer have now when your TV is on, or your camera.
And then the other thing is just really to make it okay to have no meeting days. We just implemented a Flex Friday program.
At the beginning of August, based on the 15 fives that we were getting, thanks Chelsea.
I think that one of the things that's happening is people's allostatic load is really high right now.
Would you be able to define allostatic?
Yes, yeah actually I have a link for it which I could probably put in the chat.
Essentially, where is the chat here?
There it is, chat.
I'll send it to you and then you can send it out.
Managing your allostatic load is about thinking about the amount of stress you have on a day to day basis.
And one of the things that's happening in this pandemic right now is that especially people that have a lot of people at home with them, for example, people that have kids have constant interruptions and stress related to homeschooling, taking care of their families and stuff like this.
And so the normal load that someone's processing
in their workday is really high.
And then on top of that, there's social stress
and political stress and a lot of the stuff
that we've seen since the protests have began.
So it's like really important to understand
that everybody's kind of pegged,
which means that you need some time to relax.
And so Flex Fridays we've implemented,
which will be on Fridays, not only are there no meetings,
there are no one-on-ones, there are no check-ins.
And if you wanna take that day to crank,
And catch up on something because your load was too high on a different day during the week.
That's totally fine.
If you want to just take a long weekend, no one's going to ask.
So we're going to be measuring our throughput and see if everybody does what I expect,
which is better with a flexible Friday three-day weekend.
And then who knows, you might even move to a four-day weekend.
We'll see.
Roger that. For the historical record, I guess we should note that we were talking about referring to the Black Lives Matter protests when Chelsea was referring to that. If we just say the protests, they won't know.
Yeah, the George Floyd murder protests.
Yes, thank you. Thank you.
Derek Clark would like to ask, we are all having to adapt and do things differently. What have you found that has stayed the same from onsite development through the transition to remote work?
So one of the things that we've been doing for a long time
is we've been doing it all hands.
And because we had some remote workers in Europe and stuff,
we actually ended up getting into the habit
of doing a show and tell on Fridays.
And that's been actually really fantastic.
Lately, we've been actually building something in Roblox.
And so we've been playing it on Friday afternoons
after the all hands, and that's been really great.
There's just nothing better than playing your game together.
And so if you have a kind of game that you can play together
and be on camera and comment on it,
it's just still so great to do a play test with the team.
That's been fantastic.
And then the other thing is that we actually we've tried to keep the kitchen hangouts normal.
So in the morning before people would come into work, they get some coffee, talk a little bit,
share snacks, tips, talk about movies and games they're playing, stuff like that.
So we have a kitchen hangout space that we still use. And that's actually been very helpful as well.
Oh, neat. Man, I think we should still, our team should still buy one.
A bunch of questions. We have a good news. We have a lot of questions in chat.
Mixed news. The upvoting is a bit, there's a lot of questions and not much upvoting,
so I'd like to encourage folks to just pick the questions you like so that we can figure out what
you need to know. Otherwise, I have to pick. And what I'm going to pick is Sean McPherson's
question, which is, hi there. I have heard that employees who are hired for a remote position can
sometimes be disregarded or blamed.
for something simply because they aren't in the office.
Now that we're all working remotely,
how could one avoid these situations
and create a friendly and trusting relationship
between team members?
Thank you.
Great question, Sean.
Yeah, that is a great question.
Because we're relatively small and we work in small teams,
that kind of a situation doesn't typically happen
at Phenomena, but I have seen it happen on larger teams.
And I guess if I was gonna run my producer brain
through that problem, what I would say is that in general,
the best thing to do on a team is to educate everyone
about how not to start fires.
So if you have a problem with somebody, if someone said something in a meeting or
they didn't deliver on a task and you're feeling frustrated, it's really,
really important to take the time out of your day to have that little difficult
conversation. It's a tiny one, but it's important to do it up front because if
you don't do it up front, then it builds and it grows and it creates more
tension. And you tend to sort of see what you're upset about. So you tend to
gather a little evidence against that other person and pretty soon you're,
you're in a beef. So I would say that the best way to make sure that that
doesn't happen is to check for it.
So, you know, when you're doing one-on-ones with people to sort of check in and say,
hey, have you anything come up this week that you need to discuss with anyone else?
Any snags in your workflow?
Anything I can help you with in terms of making things go smoothly?
So if you're producing a group like that, just make sure that you're encouraging
those conversations and those one-on-ones.
It's really hard to encourage one-on-ones right now because people really are meeting out.
So the other thing to do is to keep your meeting load low so that casual conversations can occur.
And people can chat with one another when they need to.
Tony Evans would like to know, what are your strategies for preventing remote team members
from burning out?
So this is actually something that we've been thinking about a lot and one of the reasons
that we're doing the Flex Fridays.
I'm especially concerned with the election coming up and fall coming into play, kids
having to go back to school.
We have a lot of parents at Phenomena who are really, really on the fence about what
to do moving forward.
Even in different parts of the Bay Area, there's different messaging depending on what age your child is and stuff.
So the reason that we started the Flex Fridays is really to encourage people to take that extra day.
We generally schedule for four hours of concrete, deliverable work a day,
because you have at least two hours of meetings, plus you have to have lunch, and then you still have your commute.
But that commute time, that lunch time, are getting eaten up by many people's children and families.
And so still like four hour work week,
keeping a four hour work week really,
or work day really solid would still be hard for some people.
So also being flexible about how much work
you're scheduling someone for,
that really requires a focused head.
Engineers in particular can sometimes double down
on engineering tasks because it feels like control.
And so monitoring your engineers and making sure
that they're checking in with their families
and not just burying their heads in their computers
is also really important.
Camille Mawinski would like to ask,
how do you handle communication with part-time team members?
Some of them might be working very irregular hours.
So this is actually a really good question
for people that also have international teams.
Actually being able to respect people's time on and time off
of something like a Slack or email,
having a lot more conversations in organized fashion
and not trying to ping people all the time is really good.
And scheduling a regular check-in at least every week
is also very helpful.
So worst case scenario, if you start the week with a check-in,
you'll be able to remember something that came up last week
that you didn't get a chance to talk about because times didn't coordinate.
I think one of the hardest things to do is to be working with a team remotely
or a collaborator remotely who's in a very different time zone.
And the standard practices are always about making sure that you understand
what their on hours are and what their off hours are,
and making it a priority to be sensitive to those requests based on their calendaring.
Next question comes from Yusung Chung.
Hey Robin, we worked together a long time ago at EA.
She's still there.
Yeah, this is you.
I have a couple of questions.
One, how do you measure velocity and productivity hit creative work at home?
Two, it's getting very hard to keep people socializing with each other.
There are just a lot of things that naturally come up when people are in a casual setting.
Accidental creativity is one, for example.
Do you have anything special to encourage non-agenda driven conversations
among the people you work with?
Yeah, so actually we have a policy that actually comes from the Google study
about the Aerosol project, about how to have the world's best meetings and best
teams. I read that stuff pretty actively.
And the other thing that we do is we have we've built the company philosophy
around the idea of a deliberately developmental organization.
So I can actually send you the original article.
We can put that out in the chat.
That I read about this particular sort of idea. It's from the Harvard Business Review.
And the idea is that you want people to be able to bring their full selves to work.
As you know, especially when you work in a larger organization, you can feel like you kind of have two versions of you.
There's the version of you that you bring to the office that's like doing everything perfectly and just OK or just fine.
And then there's the part of you like you get in your car and you're like, oh, you know,
like I'm going through a breakup or my kids are really struggling at school or my mom has cancer or whatever it is.
And so when we founded Phenomena, we wanted to use the deliberately developmental organizational strategies to create a safe space for people to really truly be themselves.
There's actually a book about it, which I'll also share with you. It's called An Everyone Place, or An Everyone Culture, sorry, Becoming a Deliberately Development Place.
Developmental organization. And the idea is that what you want to do is start your meetings with real talk about what's going on in your lives and not be embarrassed if you're having a bad day to say like, Hey, everybody, I'm really struggling. So, for example, a few weeks ago, my brother actually came down with COVID. And I had a meeting that I had to attend. And I started the meeting by saying, Listen, I'm sorry, I'm gonna turn my camera off because I'm not in a really great place. My brother's not well, I'm really worried about my brother and my family.
So I'm going to be quiet in this meeting.
If you really need something from me, I'll be here,
but I'm just going to be taking some time to myself.
Being able to say that kind of stuff
really does help people feel comfortable sharing
and socializing outside of the sort of work scenario.
And if you do it a little bit every time
you meet at the beginning and at the end,
then eventually it becomes part of the culture.
I think the other thing is to really understand
that sometimes people just don't really feel social,
and that's OK.
Right now, it's very hard.
We actually started.
The pandemic with a like a costume theme for our Friday all hands or people would wear hats and it was really fun for a while and then it got to the point where it's just kind of felt like we were trying too hard to be OK with what is really actually turning into being like a very difficult and mismanaged situation on the federal level.
And so we stopped pretending we don't dress up for meetings anymore and occasionally we may.
But I think the idea is to not force it and to try and be really honest.
It does mean that the producers are going to do more emotional labor.
There is going to be more chit chat about difficult stuff,
which means your producers need more free time to kind of offload that stuff.
But they should be used to doing that work on their own anyway,
because that's the job.
Wow, I'm so sorry to hear that your brother is better, actually.
He got better. Yeah. And no one else is infected.
So it was a miracle. Yeah.
My nephew. Yeah.
Okay, I was like, this is maybe very sad.
Yeah.
Camille, you're welcome.
I really try to do my best from pronouncing folks' names,
which is why I felt bad about messing up Robin's earlier.
More questions.
Megan Brin has a great one.
How do you create an environment where younger or newer folks
feel more comfortable speaking up or pointing out issues,
especially now that you just can't chat in person?
Yeah, so we're actually in the process of doing a real deep dive on this issue.
The way that we founded Phenomena, the reason that Martin and I decided to use
the deliberately developmental framework was because we wanted to hire young
people with less experience and then develop them towards what's called their
edge. So the idea is that you're really confident about the things that you're
good at, but you're also confident about the things that you're not good at.
And you say, like, I'm not so good at listening or I'm not so good at
turn-taking or I'm not so good at following up on requests, whatever it is
that you need to be working on.
And then you work with your producer and the people around you to make sure that you're making your edge better.
So, one of the best things that you can do to make young people feel safe and heard is to make everybody, obviously, in the process of learning.
There's no such thing as a person in a developmental organization who doesn't have an edge or who isn't learning or isn't improving because we all are always learning.
So, I think that it's getting rid of the auteur culture or this idea that there's people that know how to do it and people that don't.
I mean, especially now in this pandemic, nobody knows what's happening.
And nobody knows how to do it right.
This is like, we're all learning together.
So really embracing that is important.
Um, I also think that, um, there are ways to set up conversations where people can
feel safer talking to say a consultant.
So for example, we have a community action program that we're putting together
where we've set aside $10,000 to donate to local actions around black lives
matter and the George Floyd disaster.
And thinking about how to make policing and life more safe here for Black people in the Bay Area.
However, in order to adjudicate that conversation, we probably need to bring in someone who's an expert and none of us are.
And so having the conversation with people about who could we bring in to educate ourselves, we had a fantastic person come in
just about six months before the pandemic to educate the whole team about trans language, using people's
Correct pronouns, how to recognize those pronouns and how to engage with a trans person in your community, because we wanted our employees to feel safe and inclusive at the same time we wanted them to get some education because some of them hadn't necessarily grown up around trans people and needed some help. And so I think it's often about bringing in experts and having conversations as a group, so that everyone at all levels of the organization and all all sort of philosophies and walks of life can develop a sense of affinity around a shared goal which is
For us, it's making an inclusive org.
We have eight minutes left in the conversation.
I would like to invite everyone who's watching to submit some more questions.
Please be sure to use the questions section when you do so, so that folks can upvote the questions.
Although, you know, we're going down the queue here.
Just because a question is getting less votes doesn't mean it's not going to get asked.
For instance, oh God, that sounds like a weird call out.
Anyway, Matt Warner would like to know,
what's the best way to get in contact
with developers and decision makers?
They're finding it hard to do through PAX East and GDC,
which is just kind of like speaks to how,
yeah, and hey, yeah, we work for GDC.
We got disrupted real hard this year.
Even if we're trying to stay on topic
about working in your company,
a lot of work got done at these spaces and these events.
How do you view as a team grappled with these events
changing their venues?
So obviously, you know, I really miss being at events.
I miss seeing friends like Chelsea and having a beer and talking about
what's been going on in the industry.
But I think what we've been doing
to create connections with other developers and to stay in touch with our friends.
Is doing a lot of remote zooms, you know, drink ups and meetups, and actually movie nights is another one that's really great or gaming with each other. If you're trying to break in, it's actually it is really critical that you figure out a way to create a conversation with developers, and it is really hard. I've actually been talking a little bit with Megan Scavio. She and I helped run an event called Amplifying
I'm thinking a little bit about some kind of event that we could start or run that would effectively act in the same fashion as the GDC conference associate kind of experience, but it's very, very difficult.
And actually, I think that this is a question for the organizations that run events like PAX and GDC.
As the PAX dev ambassador, I'll bring it to the PAX staff because I know that PAX will be online this year.
Maybe there'll be some ways that we can do some AMAs with developers for fans.
I'm going to tweak Victor Rizal's question here.
Their team uses Slack and Zoom and they're feeling a loss of communication.
What are other companies doing to improve the lack of face-to-face communication,
even while balancing what you said a couple minutes ago about the option to go camera-less during meetings?
So one thing you can do is try to do more social events that are opt-in, that are at
times that people that have kids can participate and that don't require alcohol.
So there's just a lot of stuff that you have to work around given the way things are working
right now.
The other thing is to just do a phone call, just a one-on-one phone call with another
member of the team and check in.
If you have been social distancing and are safe.
And don't have any symptoms, you can also, if you can, travel to see another teammate.
So, I have a couple of teammates that I'm in a pod with that I travel to see on a regular basis.
And that's just basically to show up, see them, be with them in a park or a public space.
Maybe we both bring a beer, we have a beer, we talk.
But try to get a little bit of face time with people.
If you do happen to be developing in the same city,
you'd be surprised.
Like it can look really fine on the camera.
And then actually when the person shuts off the camera,
they can feel incredibly isolated and alone.
And some people really need face time
and seeing other people physically
in order to feel connected.
I'm not that way, but I know people who are,
and it's actually a very difficult time.
So I think actually, if you can safely check in.
And do a distance hangout or a picnic sometimes.
That's also even just with one other person on your team, that can be very helpful.
And then my favorite thing is to send chocolate or flowers.
Someone from my team sent me chocolate yesterday and I was so happy.
With about four minutes, 20, nice, left on the clock.
We're going to try and get as many questions as we can.
So, Robin, we may need to shorten the answers.
DT, Bandla Moody would like to know,
could game development move to a remote model
even after the pandemic ends, completely remote?
Absolutely, although I really do miss the office.
We've actually decided to de-res
and actually wait until the pandemic is over
to figure out what in-person work would look like
if we decided to do it again.
The other thing is that with the constraints
that we're seeing, traveling
and not driving your car all the time,
Being something that's sort of restricted is actually really good for the environment.
So I'm actually not so positive on the idea of us all having to start flying all over the world again in order to do our business.
It's kind of a, it's a toss up for me.
Yeah. Sean McPherson asks, you mentioned including keeping the office kitchen around because of the social importance of it.
Are there other activities that are great and effective this time for team building, building morale and lifting spirits?
Yeah, so you can have Office Olympics.
That's something that our office coordinator, Jamie, put together.
She'll just organize different types of tests and games that we can play
against each other.
The last one, I believe, was a typing test to see who could type the fastest,
most accurately.
And a lot of these are just run in the Slack channel that are in at the company.
The other thing that I saw recently was someone had a ship party
and they actually shipped meals and tequila mix and all this crazy stuff
to their people so that they could have a big party together.
Double Fine also did.
A really great personalized tequila bottle for their 20th anniversary, which is fantastic.
So sending people things in their homes and then getting on camera together is actually
kind of fun.
I even attended a magic show like that with a pitchfork, so that was pretty great.
Maggie LaRouche would like to know, working remote seems to have increased the amount
of meetings across the board.
What are the best practices that were introduced to reduce them so your team can focus and
deliver on their 20-hour-a-week goals?
Yeah, so actually the no meeting days are really, really essential.
Having very short meetings is also essential.
Having an agenda ahead of the meeting, obviously really helpful.
If you want to have time in a meeting to brainstorm, timeboxing that time.
And then Google actually has a short meetings option in its menu.
If you're using Google Calendar, you can click the short meetings and it'll end your meetings
five or ten minutes earlier so that you don't end up in a back-to-back meeting
cycle with no bathroom breaks, which is a really, really bad place to be.
Oh shoot, that's how I got on this call.
Okay, a couple minutes left.
We're going to ask a couple more questions before we do.
When you're done here, please click on the session evaluation.
It's going to pop up either in this session.
You can click on it again to see it or
it'll come up through your notifications.
If you give feedback on this session,
whether it's good or bad,
we'll be able to improve these sessions in the future.
We never did it in AMAs before.
This is new. We like it.
We did a couple, but now we're doing a lot.
This question, I'm going to try and get
at least one other question besides this one in,
but Anisha Deshmani would like to know,
I would love any ideas on onboarding teammates who are new to a project or company.
It's so much harder to do when there aren't people around to absorb information from.
Yeah, so we have a wiki that we've been building out. Jamie's been helping with that as well.
And I think that building an internal wiki that shows what it's like to be part of the team and
then keeping that conversation really going is important because it gives someone something to
latch on to. Having someone that they can follow through a day, so be on a bunch of different calls
with the producer as they manage different parts of the project is also helpful.
And then finally inviting them to present or give conversation in a more relaxed forum.
So we have tech talks that we do.
People volunteer to do tech talks.
We also have culture talks that sometimes happen over lunch hour.
People talk about the food from their cultures where they grew up and stuff.
So just creating events where they can contribute something personal is very helpful.
In the long run, my favorite thing to make people feel involved is what we call the thumbs-up award.
We give it away every Friday.
If you get the thumbs-up, your job the next week is to give it to someone who did something that made you feel great.
It can be anything. It doesn't have to be specifically to the development.
But as the thumbs-up goes around, it actually helps you see who is doing nice things for other people,
and that helps people feel encouraged to do nice things,
and it gets people involved in the cycle of being a friend at the office, which is important.
We are running a slightly bit out of time, but I'm going to get one more question.
Robin, real quick, if they have more questions from you, where should they ask them?
Go ahead and ask me on Twitter.
I'll go ahead and answer your DMs or your tweets as much as I can.
I'll start a thread now.
And what's your Twitter handle again?
It's just my last name, at H-U-N-I-C-K-E, Hunnecke.
At Hunnecke.
OK, I have a question that I've been thinking about actually since the Ukrainian protests
that led to the ouster of the president over there in like 2015 or so.
What are your thoughts about what happens when a team member is suddenly in an area
that's seeing something like the George Floyd protests or the uprising, and they either want to participate,
they're struggling, whether the struggle to go out over COVID.
Like, if a person is in a physical part of the world that is suddenly in a kind of upheaval,
whether it affects them, whether they want to participate and be a good citizen,
what are your thoughts about accommodating that, even though they're trying to, like, you know,
Work, earn money from you, for instance. Oh, absolutely. Like everyone at Phenomena,
the minute that the protests became apparently necessary and we needed to actually start
really, really pushing on this issue here in the Bay Area, everybody at the office on at the Friday
meetup, I just sort of said, hey, listen, if you're going to be participating in protests,
just stay safe. Please let us know where you are. If you need a buddy, if you have any questions,
people are going to be posting in the channel. We created a channel specifically related.
To black lives matter and some of the protests that were happening in Oakland in particular.
Martin, my co founder lives just next to City Hall and I live just next to City Hall in San Francisco.
So, you know, I mean, I think it does affect you.
And the idea with being able to be honest about who you are at work is that this never comes up as a surprise.
A phenomena when bad shit happens, we could talk about it.
And it's very important for everyone to recognize that bad shit is going to be happening for a while.
So we need to be OK with being less productive and more caring towards one another.
If we don't do that, we'll never get through anything.
So it's essential.
That's the right message to end this AMA session on, I think.
Robin, thank you so much for joining us.
Everyone in chat, thank you so much for asking questions.
Stick around, we have more AMAs going on tomorrow.
We have more great sessions tonight.
And I hope you all have a safe and lovely Wednesday.
It's Wednesday, right?
I don't remember the time anymore.
Bye, everyone.