So my name is Teresa Derringer, and I'm
going to be talking to you guys today
about indie development and the economy of favors,
and some of the risks, challenges, and rewards
of participating in this economy.
So I've got my contact details up here.
Feel free to take a note if you want
to get in touch with me after the presentation.
They're also going to be on the last slide.
So I am an indie developer.
I've been doing this for about three years, and I've most recently made a game called
Cannon Brawl.
And this is something that I've just shipped on Linux, PC, and Mac on Steam.
It's something that I worked on with one other person, Pete Angstadt, who's right there.
And together the two of us formed a tiny indie team called Turtle Sandbox.
So this is a 2D artillery game.
It's an RTS, kind of worms meet StarCraft.
It's a lot of fun, you should play it.
And during development of this game,
my picture of what indie development is
has fundamentally shifted.
So my background is in AAA.
I've worked on a lot of games
at a couple different companies, mostly AMAXIS.
And some of these games include Zumbinis, which was not at Maxis,
The Godfather, The Sims, Spore, some expansions for Spore,
Dark Spore, and most recently SimCity.
I'll actually talk about one more thing there.
So when I was at Maxis, I was sort of a juggler of all trades.
I had a lot of roles. I started as a tester,
I became a community manager, I was a producer,
and by the time I left, I was doing programming and graphic design on the online team.
So it really was a natural fit for me to go indie.
And while I was making all these big games at these companies,
I actually got a chance to make something really small
by myself.
So on Spore, we released the Spore API
so that players could make their own games using
any subset of the over 200 million creations that
were uploaded by players into the Sporepedia.
And when we released this API, I wanted
to create an example application to just show,
here's something that you can do with these creations.
So this is Psych Explore.
And what it would do is show a bunch
of creations on the screen.
They all have a common tag word.
And the player just has to guess what that tag word is.
And while the style of this game is grounded in the visual language
that was established by the UI team on Spore,
and the creations came from the community,
it was the first game I felt like I had a lot of ownership over,
and I just made the whole thing by myself.
It gave me a lot of creative freedom.
It was the impetus for me to break out and go indie.
So when I embarked on this indie adventure,
I thought it was going to be like this.
I thought I would be a Lone Ranger.
And when you think of the word Indie, some phrases are evoked, like
self-made, self-reliant, and pulling yourself up by your bootstraps.
But as I've been an Indie developer, I think that this common model of Indie development as a solo venture has become less and less valid.
The word Indie is short for independent, but I think that's a misnomer,
because right now Indie development is actually more interdependent.
So I thought this is what was going to happen.
I thought I was going to be going into my home office
or my bedroom with my pajamas and emerging a year later
with this beautiful opus of personal magnitude.
And I think I thought that
because there's this pervasive hero narrative out there
about the lone dev against the world
who is single-handedly crafting a beautiful masterpiece
and they were never relying on any connections.
This idea has been romanticized by the press.
If you hear a story about this, you'll probably hear
about a garage involved somewhere in the anecdote.
And it's very easy to digest, it's popular,
but it's not representative of what indie development is.
So why is indie development interdependent right now?
I would argue it's because the bar has been raised.
And the bar has been raised because indie game consumption
has gone mainstream.
So, you guys might have heard a game called Minecraft.
Pretty much everyone I know who has kids,
those kids are playing Minecraft right now.
And they're games like Braid,
that really sort of broke out indie games
from being these sort of niche consumer gems
into the mainstream.
Because they're mainstream, the demand is higher than ever.
And so that means that the developer community
has risen to meet that demand.
And more and more games have been churned out,
which actually just makes it harder and harder
to stand out from the crowd.
So here's an example from IGN.
This is their website.
And they show the top games of 2014.
And amongst the AAA games that are shown here,
you'll see indie games like Shovel Knight and Transistor.
These games have massively different budgets.
But that's not immediately obvious to the consumer.
This really blurs the line between what is seen as an indie game and what is seen as
AAA, and it drives the pressure to deliver up higher than ever.
As indie developers, we're competing with AAA companies who have teams of people at
their disposal to get things done.
And if indie developers try to do all of these things themselves, they'll flail.
What's happening, in my opinion, is that tribes are forming
to create layers of support, which
help them to accomplish the same tasks that AAA teams are
doing with massive internal organizations.
Some of the tribes here in California
include places like West Indies in the Bay Area.
There's Glitch City down in LA.
There's Game Nest, which just popped up in San Francisco.
There's also Hacker Dojo, which is not necessarily
gaming-specific.
But.
does support Indies in the tech space.
So this is what I'm talking about
when I say the economy of favors.
It's a quid pro quo exchange of services
to help Indies be competitive against AAAs.
So if you're an Indie developer,
you probably went Indie because you're good
at one of these four core disciplines,
programming, art, audio, maybe, or design, definitely.
But there are a lot of other disciplines that you have to tackle in order to bring a game successfully to market.
These things are like legal, financing, marketing, events, there's a zillion.
And actually a lot of indie developers have gone indie to avoid some of these peripheral disciplines.
The irony is that they become personally saddled with them, even though they may not be very good at them.
So these tribes are forming to establish pools of shared resources.
that can help indie developers tackle some of these peripherals.
So one example that I've seen where this is happening is I go to this group called West
Indies and there's a guy Tim Conkling from Antihero.
And he said that what he does with his tribe, he didn't use that word, is that they do a
weekly standup.
And that's not just with indie developers that are on his team or working on his game.
That's people who are working on other games.
but it fosters an accountability
and it fosters a productiveness
that can be really helpful to them, keeps them motivated.
So he's really stepping into this production manager role,
which is not something that indies usually have the luxury
of hiring a production manager
because you just don't necessarily have the budget.
And in that way, he's kind of helping share resources
and establishing this tribe.
So at a high level,
I would say that the benefits of these tribes is that they carry each other to the top.
You want your fellow tribe members to succeed because success begets success.
If you have a fellow tribe member who has a really successful game, you may have access
to better workspaces yourself just by your connections with them.
You may have more legitimacy with the press, etc.
So how do you find out about these tribes?
It's true that some of them are secretive and very exclusive,
but there's some points of entry that I can suggest.
So show your game at conventions.
We're at GDC.
There's PAX.
There's Indicade.
There's GamerX.
There's a lot more.
This is going to be one of the highest concentrations of talented developers that you're going to have access to.
There are limited slots to show your game at these conventions,
but I think you can sort of leverage the economy of favors to have a little bit more success.
So one thing I've done is I've sort of...
Sometimes if I don't get my game shown at a convention,
I'll email the organizers and ask if I can fill in
for someone who is a no-show or a cancellation.
And it sort of switches from I'm asking them for something
to I'm offering them something.
And I've never actually had that not work out.
When you're at these conventions,
I think one other thing that's kind of counterintuitive
is that you funnel traffic from people
who are done playing your game
to another game that's similar to yours.
They might seem like your competitor.
And the reason I think that's a good idea is that,
in general, it builds excitement for your genre.
But also, it extends to goodwill to a developer
who's probably tackling,
they're probably the one person in the world
who's tackling the same problems that you're tackling.
And so if you can build a relationship with them,
you can be helping each other in the future.
So one example of how to be a little bit scrappy
at a convention that I've done is,
I went to Indie Press Day at GDC a few years ago.
And I went early, and I stayed late, and I cleaned up.
And they didn't ask me to do that.
But because I did that, I was able to establish a rapport
with the organizer of this event,
who then invited me to show in the future,
who then invited me to host the Twitch stream
that was on the front page of Twitch on Monday at IGN.
So it was a great opportunity for me to plug my game.
So that's sort of that favors paying off.
Another place that you can find out about these tribes
are at shared workspaces.
So, these can be tribes in and of themselves.
At these shared workspaces, you can exchange feedback,
and really importantly, you can sort of
fill the role of QA testers,
because indie developers don't have QA teams.
But it's something you can do for each other,
as QA each other's games.
These shared workspaces act as watering holes
where people can exchange information
about things like contests, conventions, press events,
because Indie development really relies
on this word of mouth underground to get things going.
So it's really important to plug into that.
So some of the shared spaces I know about in San Francisco
are at Double Fine, there's Hacker Dojo,
there's Indie Open House at IGN,
and Game Nest recently opened in the city.
So if you find these tribes, how do you get your foot in the door?
I think the best thing you can do is establish yourself as a fixture.
So participate in game jams.
So there's a global game jam that just happened.
Ludum Dare is a quarterly game jam.
Some of these game jams are at physical spaces.
So this is a game that I made.
It's called Mathgrams for the SIFTIO, and this was here in San Francisco.
I also do Ludum Dare.
This is Beneath the Surface 29,
and I made this game called Platform Hero.
And this is an app I made for the Pebble.
It's yoga.
It was part of the Facebook Wearables Hackathon.
The important thing is just to show up
and show what you're excited about working on
because you'll meet people who are gonna be excited
about those same things and you'll be able to connect.
Something a little bit more grassroots that I've done
is establish a game night.
I do this at my house once a month.
These are Jell-O shots.
They're D20s that I made for game night.
And I wasn't really expecting this to pay off in my life the way it has,
but I basically collect interdisciplinary people from across the industry.
So some of the people who come to this include lawyers, press people,
some of them are other game developers.
And it's a great way to mix people who might not necessarily mix on their own,
especially as an indie, where you're not meeting these people
from all across disciplines on a regular basis.
It also gives me something a little bit more personal to connect with people
after meeting them at a convention.
So I don't just have to say,
hey, let's connect on LinkedIn.
I think that this establishes a little bit more meaningful relationship.
If you're not into board games,
some other things you can do are host a Kleenex test
to exchange sort of fresh eyes, perspectives on your games.
my buddy Justin put together a press event.
And so he got a lot of the different indie developers
in his area into one space.
And when you have that big momentum,
you can start attracting press.
But you can do things just as informal as Ultimate Frisbee.
I play Ultimate Frisbee with some of my other
indie developer friends, and I have a cooking club.
So there are more and more people
in indie development than ever before.
And so these tribes are popping up more and more.
And part of that is because there has been an exodus from AAA.
The reason I think that is, is because AAA games have exploded budgets.
They're so huge, they cannot afford to take the same risks,
because they just have to make a game that they know is going to sell.
And this has created a space for indies to occupy on the creative fringes.
This has been really attractive to a lot of people who have become disillusioned with AAA development.
And so there's been this injection of people with a lot of expertise coming from AAA,
which is driving up the talent in the indie game space.
This is something you can take advantage of by participating in these tribes,
but it's something you'll have to fight against if you don't.
In the last 10 years, there's been an explosion in digital distribution
with things like Steam, the PlayStation Store, Xbox Marketplace.
Local tribes of Indies are actually competing for a global market which is not saturated.
So never before have two kids from San Francisco been able to bring a game to market in Russia,
and I say that because for some reason we always have dedicated communities in Russia.
And the games that we're making are creative products. They're generative.
Games are not a finite resource. So it's not like we're oil miners,
and if someone else takes more of the oil, there's less for me.
In many industries, when you aid a rival, you make them stronger.
And they can take more of the pie.
But in our case, our product is not a finite resource.
And the pie is huge.
So while AAA companies need to sell millions of copies
to support their development studios,
indies only need to sell a fraction of a fraction
of that amount to be viable.
And I would say that this lack of competition between local indies relative to the global markets
disrupts typical models of scarcity and supply and demand,
and actually pushes us towards collaboration,
because the benefits of collaboration outweigh the costs and competition.
A kind of tribal economics takes over, and I think of this metaphor as a barn raising.
So, you can raise your own barn yourself, but it's probably inefficient.
It would be better if other people help you out.
And the incentive for those other people to help you
is that when they need to raise their barn,
you'll probably be willing to pitch in.
So for indies, our biggest risk is discoverability.
But there's so many games that are coming out,
it's really hard to get noticed.
And I've noticed that in the tribes I participate in,
people will rally around one person's launch
and just get on social media and get out there
and hype that game.
And the reason that people are doing that
is they know that when they're gonna launch their own game,
they'll have that.
word of mouth that they can rely on.
So asking for help can feel really bad.
It can feel like a burden.
People don't go indie because they want help
from other people.
I've become convinced it's always good to ask for help
because it lets people know what you're excited
about working on and it opens the dialogue for exchange.
So one little random example where asking for help paid off big time for me
was I was at this event in San Francisco called the Showdown at the Foundry.
It's a place you can have a beer, play some eSports, play some board games.
I missed my last train and I asked one of the organizers
if he would be willing to give me a ride, which he did because he's a nice guy.
On the ride, I was able to talk about my game, Cannon Brawl,
and develop a little bit of a rapport with him.
which led him to inviting me to show my game in the future.
And that wasn't just cool because I got to participate in his event
and have my game on a big screen and get to talk to a lot of players
and sell a lot of copies of my game.
It was also cool because they do events like the Extra Life Kickoff,
where I got to participate in charity
that also helped me get to the front page of Twitch again
and get some really popular and talented streamers who are on...
Twitch and YouTube, including LolReneNe, GassyMexican, and Iamspoon,
to bring their talent and entertainment value to talking about my game.
But favors don't have to be freebies, they don't have to be like really random events like that.
You can also do things like revenue share with people to avoid having to raise advanced capital based on trust.
For example, at my shared office, there's this guy, he's pretty great, his name is Todd.
And when I needed to bring CannonBrawl to more platforms, because I had a relationship with Todd from that shared workspace,
he was willing to port to Linux and Mac, and it was great, I didn't have to raise advanced capital.
When you're exchanging these favors,
oftentimes it's not a zero-sum game.
They're mutual benefits.
So for example, if you're approaching a press person
to try and get some coverage for your game,
you're offering them content to write about.
And more importantly, if you're approaching someone
who's maybe a Let's Play host or a Twitch streamer,
you're giving them an opportunity
to springboard off of your success.
So there are people like Northern Lion,
who does Let's Plays, and he found Binding of Isaac.
And that game really catapulted him into the limelight.
Now he makes his living off of his streams.
So one example of a mutually beneficial exchange,
another kind of random one.
I go to a lot of board game conventions,
because I really like board games,
in case you guys haven't noticed.
So I went to this game convention called Kublai Khan,
and I met a lot of people there who were super duper nice.
But they were complaining about their hotel,
so I offered next time if they wanted
to couch surf at my place, they could.
One person who took me up on the offer
happened to be a lawyer,
and so when it was time for me to trademark my game,
I tapped him and asked him if he would help me
with legal stuff, and I could avoid paying
some really expensive lawyer fees.
And he did, it was great, I got my trademark.
And also in the future, I've had a lot of people approach me about how I did legal work for Cannonbrawl,
and I make sure to reference that person who was super nice to me.
So I think a few things are happening when there's a transaction of favors.
First of all, the task gets done, and that's the most important thing.
But second of all, the passion for your project spreads as people take ownership over its success.
And thirdly, it makes people happy to help, which just fosters relationships.
It's also important to ask for favors
in places you might not necessarily think.
I think a lot of people think of their community
as something they have a responsibility to foster,
but they don't necessarily tap it for talent.
But one thing that I did with Cannonball,
as it's a super intense RTS that's very reliant
on the balance, is we have some of our top players
like Chess Kitten come on Skypes with us.
And they break down the things that they think we need to fix.
And they have a level of expertise
that we can't have access to on the development side,
coming from the players.
You can also get players to post about content ideas.
Like, we have a thread where people
post about the buildings that they want to see.
And these are things that we've built in the game.
And they've been some of our most popular buildings,
because the buildings are kind of the units in our game.
So there are a couple of unintuitive characteristics
of the ebb and flow of the economy of favors
that I've noticed.
First of all, the asynchronicity.
It's not turn-based.
It's not like I'm gonna help you
and then you're gonna help me and back and forth forever.
So new indies are absorbing favors at a higher rate
and their capacity to give back might be limited
by their time, reach, and their experience.
There's also an asymmetry.
It's really unpredictable
who's going to be returning favors.
It's a gamble, and so just help 100 people out
because you never know who's gonna pay off
in a big, pay back in a big way.
For example, last year I came to GDC
and I saw a talk at Lost Levels
where I met Murray Lancashire
who talked about explosion effects.
I invited him to come back to my office
like I invite a lot of people to come just to do dev jam.
But he ended up doing a critique
of the explosions in my game
that helped me bring up the polish to a better level.
It's really valuable.
So a lot of these things I've been talking about are a little bit crunchy granola,
sort of kumbaya, like let's all help each other,
but there are some real risks when you're participating in this economy of favors.
First of all, there are finite resources.
So while games are not a finite resource,
there are things like iTunes Features, Humble Bundle Inclusion,
or the Steam Top Ten list.
I mean, there's ten slots on the Steam Top Ten list that's pretty finite,
and we're all competing for them globally.
You can mitigate risks with this by doing things, for example,
staggering release dates with your tribe members
so you're not stomping on each other.
Also, work-life balance.
You might not notice, but this is a Venn diagram.
So it's really hard to maintain a work-life balance
if you're engaging in this because you're doing business
with your friends.
I had one thing happen to me that was sort of unfortunate.
My game launched right around the time of Gamergate.
And what happened was I had press people I had reached out to
who had actually committed to doing reviews at major publications about my game.
But after Gamergate they said,
you know, I think we're too close, I'm not going to review your game.
And I get it, as an indie, your game is an expression of yourself
and it can feel very personal.
But it also felt like a damned if you do, damned if you don't situation
because either they don't know about you or they think you're too close.
So that can be tricky.
Also, you'll have to relax control.
When you're engaging in favor exchange
with people who don't have equity in your company
and are not getting paid,
you can't expect the same kind of work.
You're not making the same choices
that you would make if you had a million dollar budget.
But part of that scrappy charm
that's part of an indie game can come from that.
And the final risk I wanna touch on
is the risk of homogeneity.
So I keep saying the word tribes.
It's a really positive word,
but tribes are also clicks, and clicks can be clicky.
There's a real threat of gildification.
So if you're on the outside,
you feel like you're looking in, you can't get anywhere.
Also, I think as game developers,
we have a responsibility to represent a broad spectrum
of perspectives in the games that we're making.
So just be mindful to be inclusive with your tribes.
And I see that the future of indie development
is going to get more and more
into this interdependent dynamic,
because as there's an injection of veteran wisdom
and capital with things like Indie Fund,
it's gonna raise the bar on what indies can accomplish,
but it also encourages interreliance,
because it's, again, raising that pressure
on what an indie can deliver.
So that puts more tension on the pressure
between interdependent and independent game development.
So today I've shared some of my resources with you guys,
and I hope that one day you will return the favor
or help someone else and establish
an exchange of favors with them.
Well, that is my talk.
Does anyone have questions?
Yes.
Thank you.
This mic, try again.
Hello?
Okay.
If you have a close friend who makes a bad game and asks you to promote it, what do you
do?
Oh, man, that's a tough one.
Um.
I don't know.
Well, I think you can always scale how much you do promote.
Like, I think it's really important to be genuine.
You don't want to promote something that you're not excited about
because you're going to sort of burn bridges with your personal connections,
the people who pay attention to you.
But in the interest of goodwill, I think it's good to,
unless it's something you're absolutely against,
like maybe it's got something horrible like racism or sexism involved,
I think you could lift a finger and do something,
but maybe not go completely all out.
Thanks.
Yes?
Hello, I just, a lot of the things you mentioned are, San Francisco's a great area because
you'll have a lot of these resources like the venues and things like that.
Yeah.
Do you have any suggestions for people who are in communities that don't really have
those kind of like shared workspaces or eSports bars and stuff like that?
Yeah, at San Francisco we are pretty lucky to have a lot, a lot of this going on.
I think it is really valuable for people like yourself who want to get involved in something
like that to start it.
This stuff is all really grassroots.
There aren't big organizations who are forming it.
It's all people like you who are saying, oh, there's a need for this in my community.
I'm going to step up and do it.
I know it can seem daunting because it can seem like, look, I'm not here to build a tribe.
I'm here to make a game.
But I really do think that the payoff is going to make it worth it to yourself and to the people in your area.
Thank you.
Yes.
Your greatest dream happens in your game is like the next Angry Birds or something, and it makes a lot of money.
And you had a lot of volunteers working on your game.
There's gonna be questions of ownership and.
rev share. I mean as soon as big money gets in the mix, how do you plan on that? I mean
what's the best way to protect yourself and your intellectual property from, you know,
legal claims later if you have a huge hit?
I think that while indie developers are probably not super savvy legally,
establishing a business model and having a basic contract with anyone you're working with on that
who's going to be making money is really important.
and that way it can help you distinguish between who's going to make money and and who's not and
and be really up front with people like when I'm talking about these exchanges of favor like
there I'm not talking about any kind of like
unclear situation as to whether someone's going to make money or not, because I think
that could be really immoral.
So yeah, just be really upfront about it.
I think that if someone hasn't agreed to give you money, you shouldn't expect money for
the things you do.
And, like, you know, in writing.
Yes?
Hi.
Great talk.
Thank you.
Up until which point do you think that...
you can say, okay, this person is someone I trust.
How do you measure that?
How do you realize it?
Okay, I can trust this person with my sweat and blood,
you know, like I can trust them with my project,
so okay, here is,
because it's not just something of asking for a favor,
because you're actually giving them
a lot of what you have been doing,
and encouraging them to do something with that.
So to which point can you say,
these guys are my friends?
Right. That's a good question. So I think that when you're forming a company as an indie,
figuring out who's actually an employee is a culling process where you're going to figure
out who do I super duper trust because this is, you know, this is basically my money because my
time is my money in the project we're working on. I think there are situations where
you're not gonna have enough knowledge in advance
when someone's offering to help you.
I did have a scenario where someone offered to do some promotional video work for Canon Brawl
and I said, great, you know, that sounds awesome, thank you.
And the videos were not something that I would necessarily want to put out there professionally,
but because I hadn't made any promises and I had just been encouraging,
I think it was okay to dial back the level of, sort of, publicity that I was willing to give those videos.
So I think you can do things like that where if there's an unknown as to how much you can
trust someone, just either be up front about it and say, we'll see how this goes, and if
it's great material, I'll use it.
Give yourself a way to exit, don't corner yourself in, if that makes sense to people.
Thank you.
Yes, go ahead.
Great topic.
Thank you.
Thanks for your presentation.
Did, for people who are starting their first startups,
is there any books or resources that you'd suggest
for things that we might not think about
or not know that we don't know?
I don't know of any particular books,
and I think the reason for that is
partially because it's such a new thing,
at least as far as the volume of people in the indie space.
So really, your best resources
are gonna be other indie developers,
or other startup developers.
Okay, and how about on this subject
of gift sharing, economy-based?
I just had someone actually, I just had someone recommend some material to me, but I haven't
read it and it was, um, you know what, I'll try and put it in my slide notes afterwards.
So if you want to download, cause I'm not, I don't want to say the wrong name right now.
All good.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Well, that's basically it.
So thank you guys so much for attending.