Hi folks.
Okay, my name's Stuart McDonald.
This is my first ever GDC talk.
In fact, it's my third GDC.
So I make apologies for the Scottish accent.
I'll try and keep it toned down as much as possible.
So building a visual threshold.
We often employ common or visual tropes
and pop culture elements into our games.
But the question is, why do we employ these visual elements?
And what useful effect does it,
that they can have on the audience?
So this talk is about this considered use of visual trope
and how it can help become a useful tool
for the art director in several ways.
So first I'll go through my bio and where I'm from.
The largest part of my career, after I was an architect,
for several years. I taught in architecture school too.
So I moved into environment art. I was at Rockstar for
nearly nine years and worked on several of the GTA titles.
I was an environment artist responsible for the countryside on San Andreas
and then moved on to GTA 4 and finally I was lead environment artist on GTA 5
for roughly half of the production.
After 8 or 9 years of making GTA, I decided I wanted to try something else.
So, after the initial creation of the world for GTA V,
my team was responsible for all the landscape outside of the main city.
So, it was quite a big project to start with.
After that, I decided I wanted to move to somewhere colder and darker than Scotland.
So, I moved to Finland.
where I was with Remedy Entertainment, you know them for Alan Wake and Max Payne.
So I worked on Alan Wake's American Nightmare initially,
and then we moved on to a new project and a new IP, Quantum Break,
where I started work as Art Director.
The interesting thing was it was a...
promotion for me, so I was a new art director on a new IP,
on a new platform, with an engine with new technologies,
so it was something of a challenge.
But there was some really interesting visual challenges
with this project.
In pre-production we had things like the,
how does time look, give it some physicality.
And that's something I'll cover later,
because this relates back to the use of common visual tropes.
And then lastly, with the quantum break completed,
Only one more year to go, I moved on to try some,
I handed some mobile development.
Again, it's a new thing for me,
and it's new worlds and new IP to develop.
So coming from a world building point of view,
it was going to be an interesting challenge.
So I moved to Play Raven.
So a visual threshold.
What is a visual threshold?
As I said, most of my career has been involved
with building worlds.
And I wanted to talk about something I would consider
when creating these new places.
not only for finding inspiration for the new elements of the design,
but also for introducing the world to the audience.
It's the point of where they actually get their visual comprehension
when they arrive in the world.
So it's a collective set of methods and visual guidance
designed to assist the effort and investment the audience has to take
when they become oriented and immersed in the world
with the visual design rules that you've created.
So it's like Alice through the Looking Glass, or Oz when Dorothy steps through that door.
The audience has to spend some time working out how the world works.
One caveat I would say though, I've actually been involved mostly with real world projects,
which really helps with audience engagement and comprehension.
But all of them have required some degree of investment in player immersion and narrative
exposition.
Remedy in particular strive for narrative,
cinematic, storytelling action games.
So there's always a strong emphasis
on establishing atmosphere and tone,
which you have to spend some time building
before you get into the real meat of the game.
But that said, all game worlds require
some visual orientation for the player.
So when it comes to world building and immersion,
how do we actually construct these accessible
visual thresholds for the audience?
One way, with the help of the arrival in your world,
is to employ visual stereotypes or visual tropes.
Visual stereotypes are quite powerful if used carefully,
as a stereotype is a container for preconception.
And that's not necessarily a bad thing,
because the use of a pop culture or common element
that taps into audiences' preconceptions
can actually be leveraged positively,
especially for those projects where we hope
to reach out to a large audience, like a AAA title.
For example, this is a 1973 movie, Westworld.
I mean, hopefully a lot of you have seen this.
And the movie is a future resort of sorts,
where visitors actually arrive in this mock historical world
that's been created for them to live out their fantasies.
I mean, it's basically a simulation.
It's a theme park.
And the actors are androids and go on to kill everyone.
I mean, that's the storyline.
It's a place where visitors step out of the real world
and are presented with familiar visual tropes
in order to live out these fantasies.
So it's a really good analogy for a video game.
I mean, we do the same thing.
We create these worlds, we carefully craft them,
and we can use visual tropes
in order to assist the player's expectations
when they arrive in the world.
But that said, I'd say a visual stereotype isn't a cliche.
And it's not always clear the difference between the two.
I mean, if you look at the description of a cliche,
it's an expression, idea, or element of an artistic work
which has become overused to the point of losing
its original meaning or effect.
And that would be a visual element
that's taken on a life of its own.
And what it would do is it'd actually weaken
the structure of your visual design for your world.
And it's something you have to be careful with,
but it's definitely something that is different
from the visual stereotype.
Visual stereotype is more of a functional trope
that we can use.
The simple test really is to keep in mind when adding these elements is to ask yourself,
does this support the visual design rule set that you've created for your world?
It's a fuzzy and subjected boundary between cliche and visual stereotype,
but we have to rely on our internal compass as artists to see what is supportive or not.
And they can be interchangeable too.
I mean, one pop culture element in one title
will help support the game world design,
whereas it might actually hinder
and fight against the design in another title.
So use that question, always check your work.
Especially when After Spring
want to bring something new into the world,
you need to have a clearly defined visual rule set for them
to do this check with.
But some gameplay cliches have actually become so ingrained in our culture and our medium
that they've become convention.
So these things are dangerous and require too much time to challenge within a project.
So I mean, it's okay, red barrels explode, health boxes heal you, that's fine.
Move on and leave them alone.
So in games we have a complex world to communicate.
And the use of visual stereotype can communicate
the foundations of these settings,
and they help free up the audience's time and energy
to focus on the introduction of new elements,
and then your more unique properties of your world.
I mean, this is a loose diagram,
but if you imagine all the parts of a game
that you need to explain to the player,
as buckets that you've got to fill.
If you think of the amount of initial exposition
available with the audience is limited,
Then you have setting player motivations, character introductions, and gameplay mechanics to teach the player.
And to get to the point of player comprehension and immersion within the game can be quite difficult with a limited amount of time.
You have, you know, well it depends on the game if it's mobile, you've got seconds almost before the players had enough.
And then in a AAA game you've got a few minutes really to really start to embed them in.
So if you can't really follow those buckets,
then there's going to be a problem with the player understanding some of the elements of the game.
In fact, we're not like the real world, so a lot of the time we have to devote
a lot of the player education to gameplay.
I mean, it's something you don't consider in architecture or film.
I mean, we don't have to teach somebody moving into a new building
how to use the door and work up the stairs,
or how someone how to watch a screen for a film.
So, education of how to actually function in a world
is going to take a lot of the time.
So, whatever the distribution of audience focus
at the beginning of your game,
the use of the visual stereotypes can actually help fill some of these areas
by allowing them to be partially filled by the preconceptions
they bring to the game world.
and also that brings anticipation.
It allows you to spend more time and focus
on communicating the more unique aspects of your design.
For example, if the player orientates themselves
to the world and setting in a quick and efficient manner,
we can devote more time to the introduction
and build more interactive plot details within our world.
With that extra focus and energy, with the audience, we can start to resolve some of the excessive exposition that we can sometimes use in games.
For instance, the 1950s B-movies have this particular staged exposition,
scenes where...
It's set up for the player, it's almost like a stage set
where the actors are actually facing the audience
and explaining every detail of the world,
even though the characters within that world
would actually understand all these rules.
So it's something we need to try and avoid in games.
Cinema and its audience have largely moved on
from this technique for exposition.
And as our medium matures, we're seeing more improved approaches
that take advantage of a game's unique interactive features
and methods for interactive storytelling,
such as Gone Home or Firewatch.
They've done particularly good jobs of building environmental storytelling in the world.
But looking to movies, a great example of this production design ethos
and world storytelling is with Mad Max.
There's a much deeper world and culture than is initially explained to the audience.
In fact, if it had been an older film, you would probably imagine a wall of text
or some early scene to describe what had happened to the world.
But there isn't.
The viewer is presented with visual information
and left to deduct the roles and relationships of the various elements.
They make up the world's backstory and current state.
Even if the viewer doesn't wish.
to invest the time to focus on, understand those rule sets,
present it to them, they can still enjoy the story for what it is.
And then in a re-watch, they'll gradually build more into that.
As one example, it's a dystopian future,
but with the modern cars of the world, it's just collapsed.
I mean, you don't see a souped up Prius driving along.
It's obvious there's a clear style choice there,
but the classic car customization imagery employed
is a familiar pop culture element
that stands for the hands-on personalization
and near worship of the classic automobile.
So it would stand well with the audience
and gives them some grounding.
the audience can understand how vehicles would exist like that in this world.
Movies often employ visual stereotype as convention
to support exposition on a broad scale,
to settle the audience into a theme or genre.
Often referred to as cliché,
but usually that has a negative connotation.
I feel it's often a disservice to some of these common visual elements.
It helps movies which have a limited time with its audience to efficiently and effectively
communicate the setting of place and historical time.
Classic example is in westerns with the use of Monument Valley.
It's been popularised by John Ford in over 50 films,
western themed films,
have been filmed in a location to the point it's ingrained in cinema
and stands as a symbol of the Wild West.
It's also been used as a classic visual stereotype in modern films
attempting to immediately grasp that western theme.
So if you were to make a Western game, of course your audience would likely expect to see this setting depicted in your game world.
And it also helps to borrow the history of cinema that have used Western genre.
Another example is you wouldn't expect this to be a setting for a romantic comedy.
But The Cabin in the Woods is a classic horror visual stereotype.
And it's not necessarily a bad thing.
as the preconceptions it carries with it
builds audience anticipation
that something terrible will happen.
And that anticipation is part of the emotional currency
that the genre traditionally uses to trade for scares.
I mean, the setting kickstarts the momentum
and sawtooth emotional path
of the ever-increasing tension and release
that the genre employs.
Moving on to games.
At the extreme end of this pacing issue, a need for rapid visual comprehension and exposition
is mobile games.
And with the title we've been developing at PlayRaven, it seems that unlike AAA, any
investment in visual introduction to your world for more than a handful of seconds could
result in players losing interest and potentially abandoning the game altogether and looking
elsewhere.
So Play Raven's Winter State is a vehicle combat strategy game
and it's set in the US East Coast after a frozen ecological apocalypse.
If you can imagine it, I would describe it as Mad Max meets the day after tomorrow.
And it's set on the East Coast with a bit of Frontier West vibe thrown in for good measure.
So to create this world, we brought in a consultant writer,
and together we created a really rich backstory
of a new society and culture that has grown
since the elements froze this world.
However, there's a problem communicating much of this,
as establishing the setting alone needs to be rapid.
And as it isn't your typical mobile game,
I knew we would have to rely on
the use of already established imagery.
in order to get a quick message across to the player
and use those preconceptions and anticipation
to get them into the game world.
So looking to movie tradition for inspiration and reference,
it made sense to echo Hollywood's longstanding obsession
with destroying the Statue of Liberty.
The statue's been commonly used icon in Hollywood
for representing the collapse of the US or the world
in an apocalyptic event.
from Planet of the Apes' famous final scene
to Flying Liberty's head in Cloverfield.
It's a powerful statement of disaster
and something a broad audience will likely have seen
and recognized its use in associations.
This was great.
It gave us place and event in a single recognizable motif
and gave us some storytelling shorthand
for a limited attention span audience.
So we started to develop that in early key art concept art.
And then finally, for the loading screen of the game,
the first thing the player sees,
it immediately sets up that setting in one shot
upon loading the app.
So it's an example of employing a film trope
as a visual stereotype.
It's functional, and it helps with a project
on a critically short time for exposition.
Next I'll come to my work on the pre-production
and visual development for Quantum Break.
I'm no longer attached to the project,
and it launches in three weeks time on April the 5th.
Remedy kindly agreed for me to be able to discuss
some of the pre-production phase of the project.
So once the premise of the game and theme had been drawn up,
we started rolling into pre-production.
And there was a few standout visual design questions
we had to answer to do with the game's theme.
Especially as we knew we had the opportunity
to define unique visual elements.
For those of you that don't know,
it's a third-person action-adventure game,
and its plot is a time-travel story
where time is breaking down,
and it's up to you, as Jack Joyce,
to try and save the world from ending.
So the main premise required us to show
both the player's time-based powers
and the effects of an ongoing temporal disaster
throughout the game.
And that presented us with one of the most
difficult challenges, which was to answer the question,
what does time look like?
I mean, you can't actually see time, you only see its effects.
So some of the easy decisions like setting the game in fall, it was an easy visual metaphor
which stands for changing time and one obvious example.
But for the VFX, we had to work a lot harder.
Since we're creating a game about time manipulation, we had to invent a visual and physical presence
for time itself within the game.
to create something tangible to show that time is clearly breaking or behaving abnormally
at certain points of the game.
The first thing we did was to look at how other art forms handle the representations of time.
And it's what you'd call casting the net wide, looking beyond your industry for inspiration,
especially on such a tricky theme.
We gathered reference from other art forms such as sculpture, painting, photography and video art.
to pull a set of visual elements that would form the ingredients for our version of time within the game.
Of particular interest was futurist painting and sculpture, slit-scan photography, and some video art.
From this research and reference gathering, we found the broken, multi-state imagery the most compelling.
The first element of our ingredients for time we developed was this prismatic fractured look.
It would echo, shear and distort the image on screen.
Time was breaking and fracturing in the story.
The main events for this breakdown manifest itself are what's termed stutters within the world.
They were the world events that would freeze, skip and repeat time,
with only a few characters able to move and exist within this dangerous and unstable state.
So as a visual metaphor for the moments of broken time,
the prismatics could distort and break the world view
in a disturbing and violent way,
and further help emphasize this threat and spectacle.
However, one issue was that if we employed
purely the prismatics in the world,
it would feel exactly the same,
with the image sheared and distorted,
and it would confuse the audience.
It would at best be confused,
and at worst, it would actually think it was a rendering bug.
So now the world would freeze when these broken time events or powers would hit.
But unless there was an obvious moving object,
it wouldn't make such a difference in the world state.
It was hard to communicate that shift.
So we needed a clear transition and shift in the visual perception of the time.
Only the main character and others could obviously freely exist in this state,
but they also had to do something with the shift in players' vision,
because their powers allowed them to perceive and live in this state.
So we followed another period of research
into the visual reference gathering.
We found something that might work.
So we used IR photography.
IR photography has this very brittle,
very brittle, frozen feel to the world.
And it's also a very strong perceptual change.
I mean, the sky turns this indigo color,
and trees go pink.
I mean, it's some really crazy looking photographs
and the frozen elements, like people frozen in time,
would have this porcelain look to them.
So in order to do this frozen, desaturated world,
we realized we'd have to actually push the lighting,
put more color into the actual real world when time's running.
So that drove contrast and impact in the shift
for a lot of the game by using warmer palettes
in the materials and lighting.
And then we shifted to the grade for Frozen Time.
I mean, it was a simple color grade shift,
but it made the light feel harsher as well,
way up to some of the high-level bloom, so...
It made the world feel slightly overlit, like time had slowed light itself,
so it was this heavy, desaturated, overly bright, harsh environment.
So we had a clearer state change for time now.
However, there was one more thing.
We had addressed the need for an overall change in the visual state of the world.
And we had the prismatics, but it still didn't feel like frozen time.
The grade in the prismatic effects still weren't easily comprehensible,
visual tell for time.
We needed an additional visual ingredient to add some familiarity to the recipe
and help the audience comprehend the altered reality and give them a visual grounding and visual anchor.
We needed a visual stereotype, one that the audience would understand as time-related.
Again, a period of research and reference gathering.
And one of the commonly seen visuals for slowed or stopped time that we settled on was long exposure photography.
It's a really attractive visual tell,
because when capturing bright light
and moving light sources like headlights or sparks.
Also the photography for star-streaked night skies
I found particularly compelling.
So we'd found this visual stereotype
that we could use to support the recipe for broken time.
And I say broken time here because it allowed us freedom
for a broader palette of visual reference.
Long exposure photography isn't really frozen time.
Except for the act of capturing the actual image, it slowed time.
So being able to pull in various examples of abnormally behaving time was less restricting.
Outdoor areas, again with a warmer colour palette and lighting.
They were especially effective with this long exposure photography sky,
where time is stopped but also blended.
We can mix in the long exposure night sky elements,
because even though it's day, when the time breaks down,
we can obviously mix day and night together.
So it gave the world a dramatic and obvious shift in reality.
We added the star streaks into the sky dome.
We also used contrails from aircraft,
as well as other light streaks that we would put in later.
We introduced this visual element into the recipe,
and it gave the audience the recognizable visual anchor,
but also helped highlight and reinforce
the look of the prismatic fracturing.
Bullet trails, sparks, and moving light sources
all created this linear sculpture in time,
and helped give us firefights and the stutters
and time powers a clearly different vibe.
This is the example, again, of using the application
of a visual stereotype to help reinforce
and provide a visual anchor for a new
and unique element in the world.
In addition to these elements, the technical art director also devised two further additions
into the ingredients for Broken Time.
One of them was flakes that evaporate off the surface of the world, and also an audio-driven
distortion effect.
These helped add more violence and instability to the scene they gave.
Well initially, when we were actually looking into the reference, there was one particular
video that I remember being the most compelling for me, which was actually a video of someone
filming an oncoming surf wave from above the water surface.
And there was all this noise and violence approaching.
And then you get this sudden world shift when the camera's swallowed by the water.
Suddenly the audio scape changes and also the movement becomes much more slowed and
has a different feel.
So that's how we devised these distortion effects
that were audio driven.
And these helped to communicate that violence
and instability to the scene.
And also this oncoming natural event almost
when they trigger.
These brought it all together in a visual ecosystem
for the moments of broken time.
And it really helped communicate with the world
freezing, skipping, and repeating.
The rendering team and the technical art direction
came together to create what is one of the standout
visual elements of the game.
And I feel it's a good example of art and tech working together.
I mean, it was a technical solution in terms of the rendering,
but it was also something visual that we really wanted to communicate.
The next use for visual stereotype in the game was Palette.
The main antagonist in Quantum Break was Monarch Solutions.
It's a corporation with heavy investment in science and research.
We wanted them to feel real and familiar,
but also give a believable corporate identity to them.
Again, through our visual research,
we ended up being really settled in particular
with the 1970s NASA brand guidelines.
It had this palette that felt like iconic science or sci-fi,
the burnt orange, gray, and white.
With this reference for the palette,
the in-game company was aimed at using a similar take
in this classic color palette.
You've seen this palette before,
repeated in sci-fi film from 2001
through to the recent The Martian.
We believed that we could still create something
with a unique presence in the world,
but it would feel more real with a palette
that would lay a foundation in the player's mind
of a corporation with its strengths
in science and research.
With the general palette theme set
and a need for a visual rule set and plausible logo design,
I hired a graphic design company
who had designed branding for various real world companies.
And together we devised a simple brand guide,
which we could then use as a springboard
to inform the branding of Monarch throughout the game
and also the live action.
Before passing the design to the graphic designers,
the logo had actually involved in the prismatic motif
of the time effects in the game too.
You can see the sharp prismatic shape language
and a few aspects of the corporation's design philosophy
from the architecture through to the logo design.
The brand guiding guidelines were then used as a foundation
for the team to work on uniform design.
Elements of the logo were used in addition
to the color palette and the corporate logo
and type style with progression in palette
and differing roles and the threat of enemy characters.
Also vehicle livery permutations and prop branding
were also a big part of the application.
Much like a real world corporation,
the presence was stamped in all their equipment
and props by color or complete branding design.
The colour schemes for Monarch interior design and signage used the palette too,
which was reserved for Monarch,
so their areas would have a much colder scientific vibe
in contrast to the warmer, natural tones of the older buildings
and structures in the city of Riverport.
I also have to say a big thank you to the rendering team at Remedy,
because they actually rose to the architectural challenge I set
for the architecture of Monarch.
It was a clean, modern, angular style.
I actually coined the term prismatic futurism
to describe the look.
It was something of a challenge for the rendering team,
as it would require an advanced lighting solution.
They excelled with the global illumination they created,
with the ambient occlusion and reflection rendering
they developed allowed me to build such architecture.
One further advantage of the color scheme
was we could tune the grading.
for broken time, mentioned previously,
to push warmer color tones belonging to the corporation.
That really helped the readability in combat.
So again, it was a case of considering
something of a pop culture
or visually stereotypical element
to add familiarity to the overall new creation in the world.
And then using external expertise
to attempt to create something of a credible entity.
It isn't only the visual threshold for the audience we need to concern ourselves with though.
We also need to think of how to introduce and communicate the world design vision
to the team internally too.
Use of visual stereotype and visual metaphor and distilled visual guidance
can also help communicate the visual direction of a project
into something easy to follow and comprehensible by a large team.
Using a visual metaphor or visual stereotype internally
helps to simplify the comprehension
of complex tasks for the team.
With ball building in particular,
we need to often create something
that captures the spirit of a place.
How we distill down and communicate its essence
to the viewer effectively and efficiently
without extra any visual information or detail.
For example, cities and urban environments
have a lot of visual noise.
And distilling that visual information
into the layout for the game
can be a daunting task for an art team.
Game worlds usually use far more condensed versions
of the real world.
And using a visual metaphor for your team
can actually help the approach
to the world's location and scale.
Trick I've used before for crafting
the world reference from the real world
is to think of your world interpreted
as a souvenir snow globe.
What would the distilled version of that snow globe contain?
What's important to the character of the place?
And how does the scale and relative positioning work?
It's basically a visual metaphor for thinking
and seeing like a tourist.
It's a foreign perspective of a place
that can help shape the bigger brushstrokes
that define a place without the over familiarity
of the native inhabitant,
which in this case is the creating artist.
Similar to a tourist visiting a place for the first time,
if you imagine the player as the tourist,
your player has initially this foreign view
to your game's environments.
And if you think of it as a single globe,
you have the global landmarks and key areas.
And the scale and position of these landmarks
are quite flexible, if based on a real place.
But it's also scalable too.
If the overall city and world is a single globe,
how do you think of the next level of granularity
within the world?
Each district or area of your map has its own globe too.
So with regional landmarks and significant elements
of that help orientate the viewer.
And so on down to neighborhoods or even blocks.
Of course, that relies on a lot of research
and a lot of reference trips to the actual place
if you're setting it in a real world.
Visiting the real place gives you a better feel for what's important buildings and structures
to your essence of the place.
But the principle can be applied to fictitious places too.
For example, Quantum Breaks, city of Riverport, doesn't exist.
It's an East Coast US location.
So when laying out the world, we created an imaginary history for the area, crafted to
create the vibe of an East Coast university town with an industrial heritage.
It has no direct analogue, but it has its own snow globe.
It's a world that's planned and laid out
based on its own pseudo-historical landmarks
and their relative locations.
Of course, laying out the world is more than just this.
There's other requirements,
such as for landmarks and orientation,
such as narrative or player progression,
fostering a sense of discovery or feeling of wonder,
and also hierarchy of routes and travelees.
Oh, and one more thing about the plausibility of a place,
it comes to graphic design.
When you're designing these urban places,
you need to remember that the world is full of hand-painted,
oddly-designed signage, and your world's more richer
for paying attention to how the texture and flavor that adds.
I'm not saying this is necessarily an example,
but the world is full of bad graphic design,
and you need to be careful of not losing the feeling
of a place by over-designing the world's graphics.
A simple term can also be employed to communicate the visual concept to the team.
For Quantum Break, we had this very heavy science feel to the look of technology.
And so we captured a lot of imagery of research science and coupled with Monarch's purposeful,
aggressive underlying intention.
So we termed the
the name, apologies to the company,
but we turned the name Militarized NASA as a term
for such a civil company,
but it helped fix this viewpoint in the artist's head
of somewhere that employed science and research
with a purposeful intent.
It led the team to gather and use reference
of various heavy science projects from around the world
as inspiration for the technology within the game.
It helped guide the visual design and aspire to feel more grounded and real,
from props to the more exotic enemy and location designs.
We tried to reference and echo how real experimental technology was constructed.
Doing this lent a solid, clearly manufactured look,
yet with some of the fragility and complexity of real-world experimental technology.
So where this guidance ends up is often in the style guide or art bible.
And one caveat I would have to say is,
from my experiences with the style guide,
is it can be a real rabbit hole for the art director.
It can grow in size and complexity over pre-production
to the point you're managing one or several large documents
on projects' visuals.
And something I learned was at the end of pre-production,
I almost put that to one side.
That's not what I actually showed the team.
I created a series of one sheets
that was quick to look through
and used carefully chosen visual stereotypes
or visual tropes, just one image and one single line
that captured that part of the visual design.
It was really easy for the team to read.
The team won't read visual style guides
if they're too small or too large.
You have to create something really concise for them.
So we've covered the use of visual stereotype
in both world building, key visual element design,
and also internally as a communication tool.
The last thing I feel I should cover
is the flip side of that.
So from the use of using visual,
support of visual elements,
what are the ones that can potentially inhibit
the world design intention?
We see the use of archetypal tropes
and cliche in our industry often.
but it's worth covering why their use can be detrimental
to the art direction and impact on player experience
and crafted game world.
For this, the best example is to look at
as a contained example of design
within a world of characters.
A character's an important element
in the building and visual storytelling of a world.
For a start, it's interactive.
You have a much broader range of expressing your design
and narrative.
with interaction and animation
than the static game world can lend.
So therefore, it's an opportunity you shouldn't waste
when trying to tell the visual story of your world
and communicate the narrative of your game.
Take The Heavy, for instance.
The 1987 movie Predator has a lot to answer for.
It's left us with a visual legacy of almost 30 years
of one of the most commonly utilized
archetypes of game design.
Don't get me wrong, this isn't a comment on the use of the archetype per se,
but it's great for adding variety to gameplay.
I love, and also love Predator. Jesse Ventura's Blaine is a memorable character.
But I feel the character's looks have gone on to burden us with years of repeating 80s action hero visuals in games.
Especially those where there's a world and narrative to communicate.
You can see the visual trope employed in part or whole when it comes to the use of gameplay archetype in many games.
From the bear sleeves to the chaingun, it's one of these things that you see often.
But for projects where you're attempting to create a wholly immersive world with a compelling narrative, the use of such imagery breaks the fourth wall.
The characters are reminding your audience you are playing a game.
It's comparable to the 80s action movie posters,
where often the actor's name was larger
than the actual movie title itself.
The character's playing is overshadowed
by the actor's own persona,
so the character becomes throwaway,
and the star feels somehow a separate element
to the world they're performing in.
And something to consider,
especially with the onset of virtual reality,
this is going to be compounded
with the arrival of a truly immersive experience
that VR can offer.
That said, I understand the use of visual tropes or archetypes can have its place and use.
There are situations when the use of visual cliché is part of the art direction,
using the preconceptions of the viewer to the game's advantage.
The obvious example, Team Fortress 2, where the visual tropes are a function of expression of character class within the game.
And of course, one counter-argument.
is that players need this visual cliché to recognise the archetype and its role within the game.
As I said, the issue fails to express the visual design of the world it lives in,
and also wastes potential interactive storytelling opportunities.
But as something of a sweeping analogy,
if you imagine car design not having evolved
since the 1950s, and any car design,
new car design requiring to have tail fins
to be recognizable as a car, it's ridiculous.
Cars today have the functionality,
have functionally defined.
visual foundation, four wheels, lights, grill and so on.
I mean, it's not changed in years.
But the design has still evolved.
We can still recognize these vehicles today as cars,
but even though they lack some of the visual design elements
of 60 years ago.
Not that I'm saying all parts of this archetype are cliche.
I mean, size and scale, and also the setup
of introducing the heavy to our world
is something we still need to have.
But again, one thing you could do is to check your visual design against the world's rule set.
Assess the design.
Does this support and strengthen the visual design of the world?
If you have any doubts, then reassess if you have the best design possible within the restrictions of functionality,
technical requirements and production time you have.
If there is an issue...
How would you decide how to handle the addition of an element that possibly breaks or challenges
the visual model of your world, especially potentially late in production?
Should it be dropped to keep the elegance of the world design?
There's always a risk of diluting the player immersion if they remain, but that's a really
extreme step and something you might not be in the power to decide.
It would depend on your title's aspirations, so a step like that needs discussion and appraisal.
Of course, a better solution, since the game development is such a complex, fluid and collaborative process,
is to have a robust enough design rule set for your world, and a mythology to support and change, for change and expansion.
Because generally, with game development, it pays off to plan change for some extent.
It does seem an inevitability sometimes.
So if when building a world with a compelling and appealing visual design rule set, what
are the good examples?
What examples of the heavy archetype do I think have an artistic success story?
And does this support and strengthen the visual design rule set of the world test?
Well an obvious example that sprung to mind is Bioshock.
Art deco styled underwater city of Rapture has become a classic setting and a great example
of world building.
Of course, it's the Big Daddy.
It's an iconic heavy, and it sits well in this underworld city,
and clearly builds a strong foundation on visual references related to its setting.
And it isn't overly reliant on game character stereotypes,
or recycling the more traditional heavy visual tropes.
Another game that strives to have coherent visual design in all its elements,
and a personal favourite, is Dishonored.
The game doesn't necessarily have a heavy in its traditional sense,
but the tall boys would probably satisfy that tougher imposing enemy slot.
The visual design and expression of verticality, behaviour and gameplay
works in unison to create something interesting and different.
It's a good example of visual game design and art
working in unison to create something unique.
Of course...
Irrational had a knack of creating other interesting heavy class enemies, such as the motorized
patriots.
The classic chain gun is actually there, but it helps reinforce the irony of a George Washington
statue toting such a weapon.
So to summarize, the visual threshold is your audience's gateway into your world and narrative.
Crafting an accessible visual threshold to your world
requires a few things.
And example, potentially leveraging a pop culture
visual element to ease the players into your world.
Or even mixing them with a more unique visual elements
to provide visual reference point.
It should be accessible and understandable.
That's where careful and considered use
of visual stereotype can be a tool
to help build the visual threshold for the audience
and avoid the comprehension or exposition traps that exist.
Manage your audience's energies for comprehension
towards your new identifiable elements,
and leverage the preconceptions of the audience
with visual stereotype.
It all comes in that crucial pre-production stage,
where you have a plan to use these visual tropes
strategically to give you the room
to explore your more memorable and unique elements.
Thirdly, reassess all additions
through the lens of the world design rule set,
as the project evolves and shifts into development.
I feel the most crucial part of world building
is consistency of vision.
So when adding new elements,
check they belong to this visual rule set
and ask that question.
Your world will be always stronger for it.
Hopefully this talk has provided you with some thoughts
on making game art accessible,
but finding ways to add and support
the unique flavor they can have too.
If it can help add to the art direction toolset
for world building, or consideration on how to support
visual comprehension of your neuro elements,
then that's great, it's helped.
Thank you. . . . . . . .
. . . . . . Any questions?
Hi, quick question.
As you were talking about the quantum break process,
as you were sort of coming up with these different ideas of ways
to represent time, how did that process take place?
Was that a series of meetings that happened in like a month?
Or was this you picked a couple things, ran with it for a while,
and then picked another?
It actually ran for a month.
for months. There was a lot of visual reference gathering, like I said, and we actually wanted,
we deliberately steered clear of previous game visuals. We actually wanted to pursue how other
art forms, I mean other art forms have handled the effects of time like cubism and futurism.
So we knew there was references there that we could actually use
and actually bring to into games because
There are things that haven't been seen before.
So we wanted to create something unique.
I mean, it's easy if you look at other games,
sometimes it's easy to be influenced by those.
And we wanted to try and steer clear of that.
So we created a board, basically,
and a room and gathered reference.
And then eventually we filtered it down
and we created like a,
almost like a memory tree of sections
of what the elements of that research was
that we wanted to actually combine together.
So yeah, it's a long process.
Okay, all right, thank you.
So my name's Ryan, I'm from Abertay University, Dundee.
Nice to see a familiar voice.
See a familiar voice, hear a familiar voice.
So when you're gonna write this book.
It's a really great topic, and I think it would be really great to have a book on something like this.
So, I'm trying to think of questions to ask in place of the students I would have,
and the big one I was really interested in was that visual research process that you go through.
I was wondering at what level that happens.
Is it, would it be your whole art team, or just, obviously, maybe just at the lead sort of positions?
The level of visual research.
Well, the whole team, I mean, the thing is with art direction, you don't want to be an auteur as such.
You don't go walk yourself in a room and then come out and go,
I have a vision, everyone must now follow this.
Well, that would be my dream.
Yeah, but I don't think it would really get your team on board as well as in bringing them into the process.
So, like I said, this room, I mean, this is where,
that was actually the room where me and some of the other teams sat, the technical art director as well.
We had this huge board with obviously all the visual research gathered,
but we'd go around and talk to the team and we'd actually have meetings with the team as well
and give them updates on how that's going and they would be involved in it too.
They could send visual research that they had found.
If they found a good example, they would send that and we'd discuss it with them on a daily basis.
It's an evolving process, really.
But I mean all the team have a stake or investment to some some extent
So it's more of a collaborative method. I think it should be because then
Everyone becomes on gets on board with the visual design of the game and it takes a long time and eventually when you get
get that
get that idea and the visual design is fixed in all the artist's heads, then you don't need to
manage them so much. It's more of a case of discussing and guiding them. They can actually
go ahead and the environment artists were on the same areas. They had ownership of the same
areas a long time and they knew exactly what they were creating. It was ingrained in their brain,
the visual design. So that's the best way to do it, I think. Yeah, great work. Thanks very much.
Thank you.
Hi.
Personally, my experience has been a lot of marketing
in games, which is obviously very closely linked
to the visual design.
And my question was specifically about targeting
and the target audience and interest-focused targeting.
Does that ever kind of come into play for you
when you consider color palettes and visual styles?
interest, focus on demographics or...
Say you're targeting fans of a certain genre or
fans who are interested in this type of game or
brand or experience in this game. Yeah, I mean, I think that did influence
say the colour palette styling for the corporation
in Quantum Break. I mean, it's a science fiction game, so
it has that.
that interest group, I guess, people that were more into the science fiction or action cinema,
then they're going to see some recognition there. I think that actually comes more in mobile.
Mobile is so focused on demographics in a way that it seems a bit more aggressive and focused
on who you're appealing to and what your target group is. So it does seem to be more designed
that way. With AAA, it seems to be...
it's more of a general plan you have.
And you know roughly who you're building the game for,
but it's much more complex,
so we can't really change a whole visual aspect
of the game that much.
It has to be cohesive.
Interesting, thank you.
Hi, my name's Wayne.
What she was talking about did bring up my own question of,
when you speak of threshold, how do you know,
this might not exactly be the same definition as yours,
but how do you know whether you've crossed a line?
where you might have lost your audience even though you've created something visually amazing.
It's a little hard to explain, it just popped into my head.
Yeah, no, it's how do you know when you've crossed that visual threshold?
Well...
It is a fuzzy and very subjective line.
I mean, some people will become immersed in the game a lot quicker than others.
So it's something you get through playtesting, really.
I mean, it's something that they do especially in mobile,
but I mean, we do that as well later on in the game.
And also, I mean, there's a lot of discussion and...
playing internally as well and covering that with the creative director and the creative
heads of the game will actually get feedback on that so it's a lot of discussion.
How many times, well I don't know if you have an example, how many times have you gone back
to a drawing board then?
Yeah, it happens a few times. Actually, the idea for the time visuals was actually very early.
We seemed to settle down on a look we really wanted to pursue very early.
And it took a long time to develop. It would be great to actually have the technical art
director here to explain the details behind it, but I mean there's a lot of new rendering
elements designed into the engine, so it took a long time to develop. But we knew we were going
very early.
And like I said, that went on to inform the architecture for the corporations.
They were inspired by the look of broken time.
So, that actually helped to form a visual umbrella over the whole project.
Cool, thank you.
Hey, I was just wondering, how do you know when you have a design that just needs a little bit of tweaks?
Or if you're like, oh, I just need to scrap this whole idea.
as a whole if you know that makes sense or how do you know when there's a design that needs
some tweaking as opposed to like if you have like an idea and you like the direction it's going but
you're like okay it needs something though but what if you add too much to it
and it takes away from the original idea instead of like,
oh, I could have just tweaked it a little bit.
Like, how is...
I don't know if that even makes any sense, but...
Well, I mean, I used to be an architect,
and it's more of, you have to design,
you have to work from a brief, in a way.
It should be a design brief.
And that's where your game designers help as well,
because they have an intention.
Like the Heavy, for instance...
You don't need someone to tell you he has to have a minigun and huge muscly arms, and you know yeah that
What you want is something to see I want him to seem unconcerned
and arrogant over the players firepower and
You can give a brief to the to the artist and then that gives you some framework to work with so then you know when
You start to extend beyond that so it's all about building like that framework in a direction to go to
Yeah, it's about communication. Yeah, okay
Thanks
Hi, thanks for the great talk.
Right now, I'm dealing with an environment that's
sort of very anchored in cliche.
And first of all, it's a desert, so you
have extremely cliche elements at work,
like pyramids and sphinxes or what have you.
So I guess what I've been dealing with right now
is introducing elements that will sort of expand it
into more of an interesting.
it's almost a less cliche thing,
without making it seem visually incongruent.
So I guess what I'm asking is,
do you have any experiences with that sort of thing
where your cliches and your visual stereotypes
that inform the player are covered,
and now you sort of want to diversify it a little bit,
and how do you deal with that
without becoming visually incongruent
and sort of confusing and lame?
So when you've got a...
an environment steeped in visual stereotype and trope, then how do you introduce unique elements
without disorientating or standing out too much to the player?
It was kind of like a flip side of the time powers that we talked about, where actually it was mostly 90% unique element and 10% visual trope.
You have to try and find something that would...
Well, it still needs to sit within that world, so there must be a visual design rule set for that world.
I mean, how do people exist in this world?
There'll be guidelines then for how this world functions.
So if you can find a unique visual element that still...
It's like the visual stereotype check, does this support and strengthen the visual design
rule set of the world?
You need to do that with the unique elements as well.
You need to make sure they're balanced and make some kind of logical sense in terms of
the visual rule set for the world.
So obviously you're not going to put like a...
You might not want to put a shiny stainless steel cap on the top of the pyramid because it doesn't look right.
But I mean, it's a unique element, but it's breaking that visual rule set.
So it's research again, referencing research.
It's what the artists always have to do.
It's their underlying foundation of their work.
So you need to look at a lot of stuff outside the games.
Okay, and just quickly, I guess part of it also is like,
in a team environment, wanting to give time to ideas,
but some ideas being sort of clearly unfit
or just a little off the wall.
So I mean, how do you manage in a team environment,
choosing wisely in what you're going to put
more visual research into, I guess?
How do you know?
Yeah, yeah, well.
Is it just an instinct thing for you, or?
It's an instinct and experience to some extent, but there's also a lot of discussion.
I mean, if everyone is sitting in a meeting and there's a lot of ideas thrown in early on in pre-production,
then you just have to try and distill down and discuss what works together in combination.
And again, some concepts might just not gel with the other set that you're starting to build.
Again, it's shining that mirror of world design,
real set on everything.
I mean, it's the same thing when you're laying out a world
for GTA or somewhere, you don't want to put in something
just that doesn't belong in the real world,
it just doesn't work.
So it's a lot of discussion.
Okay, thank you very much.
No problem, thanks.
Last question, I think.
Hi, have you ever been a part of a team that maybe was a little anxious to start production before having all the style guides and visual target?
Well, yeah, that's a team anxious to start
before the style guide and pre-production's completed.
That's normal, though, because you don't want
all your artists and your team sitting around
waiting on you.
Again, it's that auteur thing.
You don't want to come in and go, right,
here's the art bible.
As you're going through pre-production,
you'll gradually get work that they can start
to progress with.
I mean, you don't have to have the entire team
waiting for this final vision.
Like in Riverport, for Point of Break, we knew we were going to have docks, say, that are part of industrial heritage,
so guys can start going and getting visual reference for that, and actually can start building props and some of the other elements that we know.
We know what a barrel looks like, we don't have to wait for the visual design guide on the prop work.
That's like a movie set prop work.
You have this store that you have to fill with props really before you start building the rest of the world.
So there's always work that can be done that would contribute to the final production that can be done early.
It's not like everything waits for that day.
Day one of production, here's the visual style guide. Right, everyone start.
It's a staggered thing and it gradually progressed into production.
Thank you.
I think that's Liz.