Hey, I'm Diana and I'm from Mytona.
We are game developers and publishers.
I'm sure you know that Japan is one of the most lucrative markets in mobile gaming
and any developer or publisher would like to see themselves in the top grossing chart of this amazing country.
Wouldn't like to have a piece of delicious pie, right?
But when we take a look in the top grossing chart list,
we see that the majority of games have really cute and anime style.
Back in the days, when we were entering this specific market,
We did a lot of research on how to make culturalization, localization, and we didn't have any practical example, unfortunately.
So, I have really good news for you guys.
After long months of developing the process, we made a full culturalization for our game Seekers' Notes Hidden Mystery.
And I'll be really happy to share with you this unique experience from start to launch.
And more importantly, I'll be sharing with you the AB test results.
So, please come and join me at my talk.