So that talk is about Forerunner.
And as you know, Forerunner is about knight, viking,
and samurais.
And in the team, we have that ritual,
thanks to an old guy that is, every time we
meet new persons, we like to know who they are.
So before starting, I'm going to ask you a quick question.
It's who among you think they are samurai like that guy?
Not that many.
Who thinks are knights?
Yeah, we're a few.
It's because we're the good guy who always wins.
It's OK.
So I think all the rest is Vikings, right?
You are Vikings, all of them.
Usually you're louder than that.
That's OK.
OK, so who are we, except he's a samurai and I'm a knight?
So my name is Romain Campos-Oyola.
I'm a currently creative director on For Honor.
During production, I was game director.
And it's been 12 years now that I'm at Ubisoft.
And I'm the one on top.
And I'm Damien Quiquen, I'm the game director on Forner,
and I worked previously on the multiplayer of Assassin's Creed
as the game director as well.
I will let Romain do the first part of the presentation,
then jump back.
Thank you.
So why this talk?
Why this talk today?
What are we to say?
Well, before the start, before the launch of the game,
we were at that game.
We had a really successful open beta, second biggest open beta in Ubisoft history.
We were at the game being played at Clueless Gamer just before the Super Bowl.
So it was huge.
It was cool.
We had an amazing first day, had a big team party, went drunk.
And a month and a half later, wake up, big hangover.
And that's the story.
And we're like, what?
What happened?
Really?
So why is that?
What happened there?
Even if we have so many years of experience and all that
stuff around.
The thing is, we knew how to ship games.
Even multiplayer games, et cetera, as you see, worked on
the multiplayer of Assassin's Creed.
I worked on Ghost Recon.
We knew what it meant to ship a multiplayer game.
But we did not knew what it meant to be a platform and not
only ship a platform.
but also support it after launch.
And looking back at that last year,
we can say that we learned it the real, real hard way.
So quickly, the first chapter, I'm
going to tell you just quickly what Forerunner is,
in case you don't know.
Then I'm going to go into what we did well before launch.
Because hopefully, we did a couple of things right
that were really, really helpful just after launch,
when the shit hit the fan.
Then I'm going to handle the speech to Damien that's going to explain to you when she hit
the fan what went wrong and in order to fix it, how we reshaped the team and the way we
built the game.
And then he's going to finish on what it means for us to be a platform in terms of retention
and sustainability.
So first, what is Forerunner?
So Forerunner is a new IP.
It's made at Ubisoft Montreal, mainly.
And it's a PVP multiplayer game, and it's about sword,
and knight vikings, and samurai fighting.
The world fears us.
We are the favorite of the gods.
We plunder new lands.
We raid.
And we grow strong.
We live for battle, ready to die in glory.
Cast away from our land, we are rebuilding.
Our hearts are strong, our devotion absolute,
and our skill is beyond question.
We will be remembered.
We are the guardians of our people.
We stand strong.
When we defend the weak, we are immortal.
So that's the game.
That's the most important part for us.
since the beginning is that Forerunner was meant
to be a game as a service.
It was meant to be an offer that will continue to grow
and that we will continue to support after launch.
What does it mean?
It means that, what does it change for us?
Previously, when we were working for a game during three,
five years, then we shipped that game, and it's done.
And we go to the next one.
Yes, we continue, we deliver the DLC, maybe one or two patch.
But mainly, the team.
and most of the people switch to the next project.
Now it's not the same thing for us.
It's like opening an amusement park.
The first day of the release, it's
actually the day where everything starts.
And so now when you work on Forerunner,
you don't work on what's coming next.
You're not working on the next project.
You are still working on the same project,
making it grow, adding content, new character.
fixing, improving the game, listening to the community,
and just making it grow and be bigger for the years to come.
And that has been a major shift for us
in terms of the way we build the game.
So before launch, where did we start?
So that was our launch.
We had a massive open beta, more than one million players
on the first day.
That's comparable to an Assassin's Creed
that we released in February.
And we are a fighting game.
We are number four all-time NPD in terms of fighting game.
And so far, we've reached a little bit over 7.5 million
players.
So before launching, what did we learn?
First, we did a lot of life periods.
We started one year and a half before launching the game.
And we learned a couple of stuff on that part.
It helped us.
shape the team, and shape our process in order to be ready for the big day.
And remember, we are a new IP.
Nobody knew us.
And that was a really, really powerful tool to start to build a community.
So let's start with live periods.
So we did our first live period just after our reveal at E3, one year and a half.
before launching the game.
And basically, when we do live period on the project,
we either do them for production purpose
in order to test elements, see how things behave,
or we do them for a marketing reason.
That first one was really for production purpose.
So it was just to test.
the core gameplay of the game.
Before that, we were doing some play tests and so on.
We had the non-sat E3.
We had like 2,000 or 3,000 people playing the game.
But we wanted to see with real players
how that core premise of the game,
because we have a new experience, how does it behave.
So that's why only one target, PC, small audience, NDA,
so non-disclosure agreement.
You can't speak about anything there.
short period of time, just three days,
because we don't want to test the tail,
the long tail of the experience.
We just want to test the accessibility,
the immediate fun.
Then, second one, like eight months after,
again, production-oriented,
and it's to test and validate
the core progression loops of the game.
How the characters progress over time,
the foundation of the economic system in the game.
So again, small target, NDA, et cetera.
But then we take that same build with a few tweaks,
and we turn it into our first marketing live period.
It's our first closed alpha.
For us, it's our first load test.
But it's a tool that is used by the marketing
in order to start to push the game to audience.
And for the first time, we don't have any NDA.
You can stream whatever content you see in that build.
And you're going to see after, that was really important.
And then we use that same build, and we
go with new territories, Russia, Japan.
And again, purely marketing purpose,
just to get known on those territories.
Then our first closed beta.
Here, we are giving the whole game.
That's for the first time at Ubisoft.
All the characters.
All the game modes, everything is in that build.
And the goal of that build, it's balancing and polish.
And of course, it's under NDA.
But then we are doing a closed beta and an open beta.
And here the goal is to be ready for launch.
It's to drive the momentum, drive the pre-order,
in order to have the biggest launch as we can.
So here the main message is not that we
did the law of life periods.
The main thing is that each life period is different.
And you need to think of them as different tools
with different objectives, and so different KPI to track.
Second thing is, how did this life period help us?
What did it change for us?
For that, I'm going to take the example of fight balancing
in Fortnum.
So early on.
The process was based on team culture.
We were doing play tests to validate accessibility,
but the real balancing was mainly on two things.
First, every Friday, and that's still true today in the team,
we have a play session.
So everybody stop working, download the build,
play the game.
And then we grab beers and we discuss.
And that's true for the whole team.
Even still today, that is still true.
And the other thing that we were doing,
it's we have regular team tournaments.
Every time we have a big milestone,
we grab all the team, and during one day, everybody plays.
We have big breakfast in the morning,
then we bring food in the afternoon, et cetera.
And we celebrate the game, and everybody played the game.
Here, the goal, it's not only team building.
Also, it was helping us to see how the game was played
when people were playing it to win.
And remember, those guys are good former players.
I mean, some were working on the game since one, two, three years.
So they knew it.
They knew how to play it.
Then we have our first private pre-alpha.
And after just two days, some of our best guys
got there, got pretty rough time against players,
like really rough.
That picture was taken at my desk.
And all the people that you can see.
are people that lost against that player.
And the guy playing that actually managed to beat him
was one of our lead testers and one of our best players.
So we're like, oh, that's cool.
People are getting really good at our game.
It's awesome.
Yeah, but we might have a small issue.
Because we are clearly not the best player of that game.
So what do we do?
And also for us, the problem is even more difficult.
Because remember, we're not only a 1v1 game.
We are also balancing for 4v4.
So one of the first things we started to do
is collect data.
Data everywhere, woo!
But how and why?
First, we are collecting data for 1v1.
So we are creating the fight matrix
and comparing all the matchups in order
to have an idea of the power of each character
in a dual scenario.
Also, we were doing the same thing in 4v4.
So we were collecting the win rates.
But also, for the pick rate, and we
were tracking the pick rates over time.
And here, it's interesting because when
you see a character having a huge bump,
so yes, when it's released, there is a huge bump.
But then, when the character has a bump, there's two reasons.
Either we release a cool outfit, and everybody
thinks its character looks really cool.
And usually, it's not that.
It's because people think the character is the flavor of the month and is maybe too strong.
And so we need to take a look, a more deeper look at how that character is played.
And for that, we are tracking in detail amongst all the players, and then we can add filter
on skill, et cetera, what type of moves, what move is being used, and how much each move
is contributing to the overall damage dealt by that character.
And here for us, what is interesting,
what we're looking for, it's that type of moves.
Moves that are not used a lot, but deals a ton of damage.
And why is that interesting?
It's because that move is really safe.
It's really hard to block for the opponent,
so it's always landing.
So that's why it's dealing damage.
So either it's by design, or you might have a problem.
But also, doing live period helped us understand
the type of tools that we would need in order
to operate the game.
And basically, we developed two things,
what we call Live Updates and Cloud Server Updates.
So Live Updates, it's normal patch, if I can say.
The detail is that it's only data.
There's no code involved.
That means that there is no first-party submission
console.
So we can push that patch really fast.
The second one is the Cloud Server Update.
And here, we only update data on our side.
And the same thing.
Of course, no first party submission.
And it's even faster to deploy.
And those are the two main tools that we are now using in
order to balance the game.
Live updates for game mode and fighters.
Cloud server updates for economy and progression.
And so we went from first live period, that character is way
too strong, we can patch him next time we're
live in eight months.
To today, when we have issues with a character,
next week, the thing is fixed.
Here again, the important thing is
we were able to do that because we started early.
At first, we didn't add an architecture
where everything was data-driven for the character.
But that's where we figured it.
And that's where we figured that we needed that agility in order
to be able to support the game after a while.
Last thing, community.
So again, new IP, nobody knew us.
So what was our strategy?
Our strategy was to be end on, to convince with the game,
and to convince a core, and then have that core grow,
and infect other people, and eventually lead to consumer.
So that's the All-Splash strategy.
And we started that at the announcement.
E3 2015.
ends on stage, four players versus four players,
live on stage, then on the booth, you could play the game.
And just after that, for people that were not
able to go at E3, but were invested in the game,
they were able to play from home with our first closed pre-alpha.
And what was good for the community here
is that they had the experience, and done.
and they were able to be part of something bigger early on.
And they were able to discuss with us
and feel that their feedback was actually building the game.
And for us, that was really useful
because we were having those discussions with those guys.
Then, 2016, the goal was to build on that core
and not only bring the press on board,
but also bring all the friends of those guys.
So first, since we were doing constant live periods.
We always add new content.
So when you would go into a show to see Forerunner,
there was always something new, a new character,
a new game mode, a new map, always something new to see.
And also, we were doing the live periods.
So just as an example, our first closed alpha,
it was more than 300 times bigger than Gamescom.
At Gamescom, you have 10,000 players playing the game
for 20 minutes.
So that's an average of 200k minutes.
Whereas that first Close Alpha, it was 237k players.
But more importantly, remember, we
said there was no NDA on that Close Alpha.
So with that Close Alpha, we generated more than 65 million
views on Twitch and YouTube.
That's a much bigger reach than any Gamescom or trade show
that you can do.
And also to reach the friends of the community of those early
deliver in the game.
We were doing a referral program.
So basically, when you were invited into a live period
of For Honor, even if it wasn't the NDA,
you could bring five of your friends with you.
And eventually, more than 50% of the people
that played in a live period, even during the open beta,
were people that got invited by their friends.
The last part.
2017 reached the consumers through the open beta, of course,
and continuing to build on the momentum of Twitch and YouTube and the streamers and so on.
So, what did we learn? How did we get there?
The main thing is we started early.
And because that's early starts and starting to operate the game before launch,
because we're not a AAA, we can't do early access and this kind of thing.
We were able not only to adapt our tools,
but also to build a community of players
that would prove to be very valuable after that.
And then, as I mentioned, we launched the game.
And everything went, eh, I was going to tell you about that.
Thank you, Romain.
You always give me the easy tasks, the easy things to do.
So what went wrong on Forerunner?
So as Romain said.
We built an amusement park thanks to all those life
periods and were really happy.
We had pretty good reviews at the launch,
so team was really happy.
Everything was going well.
Then after a few days, a few weeks,
we saw that we had some issues in our amusement park.
What were those?
So we had connectivity issues in our 4v4 game modes.
So Dominion, for example, that is the most popular game
mode on the game.
We had balancing issues, even with all the things
we learned before launch.
And we had also some economics and progression values
that we had to adapt that weren't working as intended.
And it's something that clearly impacted
the whole momentum of the game.
So we saw the sales dropping after a few weeks,
even if we had an amazing launch.
Usually, press was pretty negative at that time.
and was using anything to do bad press.
And the community was really frustrated
at the point of threatening to do a blackout event
where nobody would play the game during that day
to tell us how frustrated they were about the game.
So basically, this super nice ice flat
we've built during two years and a half,
well, oil burns and everything went bad.
in just a few days.
So how did that happen?
And what did we learn from it?
So first, and this one is a very obvious sentence, I can tell, but you will see how it makes
sense in our case.
So you don't know what you don't know.
So there is an unpredictability factor on what is going on.
You need to be ready to adapt your whole production process as soon as you're live because everything
changes.
And the communication needs are not the same anymore
when you're live.
So everything we've built before launch
wasn't really working after launch.
So you don't know what you don't know.
Before launch, your players and the feedback
you receive on your game are mostly
focused on novelty, on discovery of your game,
on the cool factor of your game.
And they're not really focused on what is wrong,
or at least they don't give it to you with the right intensity.
While after launch, the context is really changing.
And small problems might become bigger.
And in fact, they will.
And I will tell you a very good example for us.
The connectivity, of course.
So do you really think we spent five or six years on a game,
built a new core gameplay, an amazing 4v4 fighting game
to have connectivity issues at launch?
Of course not.
That's why we started super early on our life period,
because we wanted to be ready at launch.
And our approach was, when we started building the game
many years ago, was to say, we'll
go through a peer-to-peer network model,
but a different type of peer-to-peer network model,
what we call the mesh peer-to-peer network model.
So it means that each player is speaking to each player,
sending information to each player.
And you don't have a host, so you
don't have an intermediary.
So this helped us to have the lowest latency possible,
which is what you want to have in a fighting game.
And on top of that, For Honor was
built around having a deterministic simulation.
So I won't go too technical, but the idea
here is that there is no randomness in a game session.
Whatever you do as a player will always have the same outcome.
So it meant that we only had to send the inputs of the player.
We didn't have to send their location, their animation,
or things like that that you usually
do with other type of systems.
Here we just had to send the input,
so it meant a lower bandwidth usage.
So we're like, yes, we found the secret formula,
and that's how we will do a reactive mini-gameplay.
And we're like, OK, we have one year and a half.
to test it, to see if it works, to polish it,
and to make it right.
So we started one year and a half before.
We didn't fight some issues on connectivity,
things like that, but things that we
were fixing along the way.
So we were clearly seeing that the connectivity was getting
better between each life period.
And we're like, OK, it's like when the game crashes
and things like that, things we can handle,
things we can fix.
We fix it.
When we launch, in fact,
Just before we launched in the open beta,
connectivity is pretty good.
We launched, and after that, we start
seeing a decrease of stability in our matches
and connectivity quality in the 4v4 game mode.
And we don't have a clue, or clueless, or like,
we don't know what's going on.
And to start understanding what's going on,
we need to put some new tracking in place in the game,
and then we dig.
And we discover issues, we discover bugs, and we fix them.
And we fix more than 100 bugs within the first weeks,
within the first month.
And the more we fix things, each time we say, OK,
that's the bug that's making everything bad.
As soon as we fix it, everything will be good again.
And the more we fix those, the more we discover other issues
and things like that.
And the more we see that the rates of improvement
we go through will never reach the quality we
want to reach with the game.
And we have kind of a glass ceiling.
where we never managed to have the connectivity we want to have.
And this is because the choice we made, where with Mesh Peer-to-Peer, the weakest link impacts
everybody in the game session.
And I won't go into the details of how it works and all.
In fact, we did it a few days ago at Amazon game session, but basically that's the issue.
So in the end, we had to change the online architecture of Honor.
while we were alive.
And we moved to the dedicated servers with Amazon Game Lift.
So when I say small problems might become bigger
or will become bigger, in our case,
it meant changing the whole online infrastructure
of the game.
So it's like eight months of work,
full team dedicated to only do that.
So it was huge for us.
So really pay attention to those.
Then, second thing we learned is that you
need to be ready to adapt your whole production process.
Because as soon as you're live, your velocity
is not the same anymore.
Why?
Because you have constant emergencies,
things that are burning on the live,
things that are not working on the game.
The team gets constantly interrupted
by things that are more urgent that weren't
existing the day before.
You have way more frequent milestones.
Because as Roman said, patch balancing, it's next week.
Another live update will be three weeks after, et cetera.
So you're constantly shipping new things.
So the team gets always interrupted.
And then you have all these branches, management.
And on top of that, what we thought candidly is that, oh,
now the game is out.
You have less things to test.
So QA should be easier to manage.
And in fact, the more you go, the more things you do,
and the more new things might impact old things,
and the more also the QA is exploding,
and the more QA is taking more time to test everything
every time you want to ship something.
So in the end, it's impacting directly the team,
their morale and their fatigue, because by doing the same job
as they were doing before, they have worse results,
they are less efficient than before.
So it's really something that you need to take into account.
And the other side of the coin is that before launch,
we're only focused on doing one thing, which was doing the game
and shipping the game.
Yes, we did live play, et cetera,
but everything was stored, making the games,
and shipping it.
Well, when you are live, you still
do the same thing, which is, for example, the season pass
content.
But on top of that, you have all the live operations,
as I just described.
And also, you have to take into account what the players want
the game to go.
So in our case, it meant a lot of bugs, a lot of updates,
more than 5,000 new content.
On the season pass, it was six new heroes, six new maps,
which is half of what we shipped the game with.
So on top of that, to build that, one new game mode,
new game mode variations, and also many, many improvements
based on player feedback, events, things like that.
So a huge amount of work.
And one of the examples that I.
can take here is the balancing.
So what did it meant to improve the balancing
on the live operation side while taking player feedback
into account?
So as I said, balancing was one of the core focus of the team
after we shipped, because that was
one of the biggest discussion we have with our community.
So we're still doing live operations
as we did before launching the game that we called Public
Tests.
And we identified those as very cool, great tools,
but to identify early exploits and bugs,
but not that good to balance really well our game.
And that's where we were like, OK, we
had this discussion with some of our players
before launching the game, and we
need to have an ongoing conversation with them.
And that's where we started to do
what we call community workshop.
where we invite some key players of the game,
so some players of the games, on site
at the Ubisoft Montreal studio,
and we spend a whole week with them
where they play new content
that will ship a few months after.
And here, this allowed us to have super early
qualitative feedback, and to have that dialogue with them,
and to understand what was working
and what was not working,
but on top of all, why,
and what was their usage of the game.
And then we put in place a private Discord channel
with the same players and some others
to always be able to continue the discussion.
So we were still inviting them every three months,
but we could still continue the discussion in between.
Here, the important element, if I can interrupt you,
is that our design team is.
on that discord. All of our game designers are on that discord and they are constantly
exchanging with those guys because they have the same level of knowledge of where we are
at a certain point, what character we're developing, etc. And so when you have a question in terms
of balancing or if we add two friends on that move, etc., we can have that discussion in
real time with any player in our community. And that is a powerful tool for us at the
moment. And that's for the balancing for the top players. But then you have another side
of the community that are...
playing more casually with your game.
And we were having the feedback from those
for community channels.
And here, it's more to identify the player frustrations,
the broad sortiment, et cetera, and to also take that
into account into our balancing.
Because if you only balance the game for the top players,
that might not work for everybody else.
And that's where it led us to this extra step
that we call a RIFT, Rapid Iterative Fight Test.
And those are private builds that we do within a few days
and that we ship to our player so that they can play at home
and they can test whatever we want or need them to test.
And this was super helpful also to continue the discussion
and to identify other problematics
and to iterate faster.
So production velocity is not the same in live.
And.
On top of that, you have to produce a wider variety
of content that are on different timelines.
So you have to ship stuff next week.
You have to build stuff that will be shipped in three
months, et cetera.
So you know that your team will be impacted by that.
And you need to preserve your team, because the live part
will be super rough.
And what we did, not right away, but by learning that,
what we did after a few months.
was we were removing one of the big pressure to the team,
where we decided, OK, we still have deadlines internally.
But now, for everything that is new feature, new improvement,
the community is not aware about,
we're not giving any public deadline.
We can still discuss with the community and say it exists.
But we're not giving a public deadline.
Those will be shipped when it's ready.
So remove pressure for the team.
And we also decided to save some time.
to give some time within the plannings
just to manage emergencies.
So we were giving a bigger buffer of time,
basically, to ship the same content
so that we could handle emergencies or things
that were going wrong.
Last part is the communication.
So before you launch the game, your players are your fans,
your early adopters.
But as soon as they pay for your game,
the mindset is changing.
They become your customers.
And on top of that, as I just said,
we're removing public deadline.
So how could we make that Oistplatz strategy green again?
How could we convince again our players?
Because one of the thing that was super curious
after a few weeks after launching the game
is that the team was crunching as hell.
They shipped the game, they were tired,
but they were still crunching to fix the issues, day and night.
And you were going on Reddit or on the forums,
and the only thing you were reading is, team is on vacation,
they left the game, Ubisoft made their money, fuckers,
blah, blah, blah.
And so you're like, what's going on?
We're working.
a lot and they don't see that.
And that's where we decided to switch our communication
strategy, say, OK, we need to be way more transparent.
We need to tell them what we're doing, what's going on here.
And we need also to show them early progress.
So even if things are not ready, even if things are not
ready to be shown, we need to share more with our players.
And here we decided to go back to the core,
to the core community, to go back to the roots.
and start a discussion with them.
And that's where we put in place what we call the Warriors Den.
It's a weekly live stream we do on Twitch,
on all the channels, YouTube, et cetera,
where every week, Roman, me, some other key people
of the team, we go in front of a camera
and we answer live player requests, questions,
things that.
they care about. We acknowledge the problem, say, yeah, we're aware of that bug, the team is on it.
We explain our strategy, where we want to go. Sometimes we say, yes, we agree with you,
that would be cool to do that, but we won't be doing it for the next X month because that's our
priorities, that's our focus. And so we explain them our approach, basically, and where we want
to go with the game. And we also have a direct exchange with our community.
Because we don't have any more public deadline,
that's also a good way how we use public test,
is to show progress of what we're working on,
the big feature we were working on,
while also being able to iterate with the players
on those big things.
And on top of that, we had the community workshop,
as I told before.
And we have also part of the team that is available online.
So we have people where it's their job, but us as well, Romain, me, etc,
we're reachable through Twitter.
And we spend one to two hours per day to do some community support stuff,
to answer our players, etc.
Basically to be reachable and to have always that contact with their reality.
And then it's something.
Again, we tried to spread.
So we were trying to reach out to the inactive players,
so players who left after launch because things were as good
as they were supposed to.
Same thing for the press.
And that's where we started doing new seasons
with new content, doing big streams,
also having extra reward weekends.
And I will show you some of those and in-game events.
We're in the end to find new ways to acquire new players
with Free Weekends, which is a strategy that a lot
of multiplayer games are using.
And we released, I think it's last week, so very recently,
the starter edition, which is a lower entry price point
of our game so that more players can come in and have fun
with us.
And so with all of those efforts,
we went from a blackout, a community that
wanted to do a blackout.
to a community that has to do a whiteout.
I don't know if that word exists.
But at least they wanted to celebrate the efforts, et
cetera, and they wanted to all play together the same day
and be happy about where the game was going.
So after several months of work, we
released the dedicated servers a few weeks ago.
So now connectivity on 4v4 game modes is under control.
Same thing for the balancing.
Balancing is in.
Continuous work, it will never be finished.
Always continuous discussion with our players.
It's true with all fighting games.
But it's something where we have now the good tools to react
and also to identify the problems.
And the progression in economy is
something we fixed throughout the first year
of the life period, thanks to our server updates.
So we're back on track.
The amusement park is working again.
But as I just said, to do all of that,
it took us almost a year.
And so how did we stay alive during that full year
with things that we knew that would take eight months
to be fixed?
First, we retained our players.
So we had more than one million players
every month of the game, even if we were not selling the game
during quite a big time.
So we kept our players into the game, and at the same time,
we stayed sustainable.
And what I mean by that is that to ship all of that content
were hundreds on the dev team.
And hundreds, when you don't say a lot of games,
well, to be game as a service, you
need to have extra revenue always coming
in to support the post-launch and to support the team working
on the post-launch.
And for our business model, and I won't go into too much details
because we don't have time, but basically the idea behind For Honor
was to say we want to have a balance sources of income.
So we want to have incomes from the season pass,
from the sales of the game, and also from monetization.
Always by keeping in mind that we wanted the players
to be happy about our model.
So we don't want it to feel as a constraint.
We wanted it to be something also that was cool for the players.
And so what have we done is that we put in place strong pillars and strong rules.
So some of them were, for example, everything, every content that is match-made is always
given for free.
So maps, modes, events, all of that, always given for free to the players.
Season pass, of course, something we sell.
But we don't sell the content of the season pass.
We sell the early access of that content.
Because everything that is in the season pass
is also unlockable after launch when you just play the game.
And the third pillar is having a single currency.
So everything, the same currency that you earn by playing
is the same currency that you can buy.
So you don't have a hard currency and a soft currency,
et cetera.
did we have those three pillars?
First, this way we never split our player base.
Whatever content you bought, you didn't bought,
you can always play with everyone within your game.
And there is no content that is behind the paywall
because you can unlock everything through the currency
you unlock just by playing the game.
And when I mean anything, it's new heroes, of course.
It's also all the RPG elements of our game, so loot,
crafting, things like that.
But it's also all the cool cosmetic things
we're shipping every week.
Like that outfit.
And it's true for exhibitions.
Very peaceful game and for emotes.
It's something we ship every week.
Every week we ship new content to the game.
It's something you can unlock just by playing
or if you want to support the game by investing more in it.
And so thanks to this aspect, we were sustainable.
And we could work on the game, fix the issues,
but also bring a lot of new things into the game.
So how did we kept the player inside the game?
So it's a two-side thing.
First part is we've created a routine.
So you have reasons to come back to the game every day.
because you have the daily orders,
and those are the main income for the currency of the game.
So it's something you want to do every day.
Even if it's just for 10 minutes,
you will come every day to get your steal.
Then every week, we had new content,
but we were also doing what we call community orders,
so small events where you also earn more rewards.
And then at each season, so every three months,
we're changing the meta of the game with new heroes,
new maps.
This is where we're also introducing new game modes,
new gear, new content, new progression content,
and things like that.
And all of that is wrapped around this idea
that we have inside our game.
That is the faction war.
So when you play For Honor, you need to select a faction.
And then everything you do inside the game,
so every matches, every duels, everything.
counts toward your faction and toward the win of your faction
throughout that season.
And this routine was also true outside of the game
by the online availability every day, by the weekly live streams
and blog posts, and also by the big streams
and reveal of new content for each new season.
And by doing that and by progressing
during that first year.
We also understood some things that, in fact, our job
was evolving from game developer to entertainers.
And that's a huge part today of our work on Forerunner,
is how can we entertain our community?
And what I mean by entertaining is by breaking that routine.
So it's by introducing surprises,
by changing something.
So new game modes are awesome.
For example, there is a game mode
that is called Dance of Death that we release like that.
We further announcing it.
was there only for a few days, then we removed it.
Then the committee asked us to keep it inside the game,
but that was not the purpose.
And it's something we reintroduce sometimes
where we feel it's a good time.
Then we have extra rewards weekends.
And the biggest example of that are seasonal events.
So I'll show you what is a seasonal event with a trailer
that you will see that is really different from the first
trailer that we show you.
Welcome to the feast of the otherworld, where ghoulish delights have been unfurled for your pleasure to devour.
In this frightening, ungodly hour, skeleton hordes are on their way, their gravest fury on display, for it is the creepiest time of year.
You guessed it, that's right, Halloween is here!
Howling werewolves to delight.
Blue flames burning from the King of Knights.
In this place you will find
Viking voodoo and their kind,
samurai demons and zombie...
of his lands. Make sure you tiptoe and watch your back, for the end of Skeleton March will
surely attack. So come along, join the feast, with the rest of the beasts of the world is
waiting for you. Boo!
So here, as you can see, it's a really different tone,
different marketing.
It's the team that has fun with their game.
And so what a game mode is, what an event is in Forerunner,
it's an exclusive game mode.
We altered the game as well, so we don't have skeleton.
We're more not a realistic, but a grounded world,
if I can say that.
So skeletons are not part of Forerunner's DNA at all.
But for an Halloween event, why not?
Let's have fun.
And we have also some exclusive content
that's only here for a week or two weeks
to also celebrate that event.
And what is cool with those, by making this entertainment,
is that players have fun, and it's something
we can clearly see in the data.
So for example, during Halloween event,
we have 20% more play time during that moment.
to just enjoy the new mood of the game.
And it's also something we discovered,
something that the team had a lot of fun to work on.
And when you have that routine of the life that is hard,
something hard, always a constant pressure, et cetera,
when they can put skeletons or silly things like that
in their game, they can have fun with their game
and enjoy that part also of the work.
And what is funny is that it's something that also
moved outside of the game.
So this idea of entertaining players
has also spread out to, for example, the Warriors' Den.
At the beginning, the Warriors' Den
was very informational, acknowledging problems.
Yes, yes, we love you.
Yes, we want to do a good game, et cetera, et cetera.
But then it become crazier.
We were disguising ourselves.
And it became a show on its own.
And now we know that we have some players that
come to the Warriors' Den.
not to have information on the game,
but just to have fun with us, which is also a key part of that.
And it's something that reached way more views
that we thought we would reach with that, because it
was something that was supposed only to be within us
and our core community.
So platform learning is to be a game as a service,
you need to constantly entertain your community.
And this comes with a mix of routine and a mix of surprises.
And to be able to do so, you need
to have extra revenue to support the team that
works on that content.
And so to close that talk, if I can go back
to what Romain was saying, is that at the beginning,
we knew how to ship games, but we didn't
knew how to be a platform.
And in fact, what it means is that being a game as a service,
it's like running a marathon.
But it's a different type of marathon.
It's a marathon where you remove the finish line.
So it can get really hard at one point.
So if we could go back in time and speak to ourself
before we launch the game, we'd say, yes, it's
cool to start early to identify the problem and all.
But pay attention to the small ones
because they might explode in your face after you launch.
You need to preserve your team now and not
when you launch the game.
by also doing no public deadline after launch
and also don't rush in new content.
So it's one of the things,
we couldn't went into details here,
but at the beginning, because things were going wrong,
we're rushing a lot of new content
and we're making new problems.
So also don't rush new content, don't panic,
preserve your team.
Work with your community, the soonest the better.
Be transparent, surely progress, we're here to help,
we're here to enjoy your game.
And on top of all, be patient, because victories
comes with a delay, so never give up.
Now Forno is in a much better state than before,
and so yes, it's worth it to fight for that.
So if you want to know more about what's going on next,
you still have the Wazen every week.
You can reach out to us.
And normally we did it pretty quick so we can have a huge amount of questions.
Thank you.
So if you have any questions, if you don't, we can go and grab a beer.
But if you do, we're here for that.
No questions?
Perfect.
Cool. Thank you.