Good morning, everyone. Good evening to our guests. Good afternoon. If you're on the East Coast, good somewhere?
I don't know, wherever you are in the world.
Welcome, welcome to the Game Developers
Conference
Twitch channel.
We are here. My name is Brian Francis. I'm usually much better at this.
I'm gonna wander around this room for a second while I introduce us, then I'll start playing. My name is Brian Francis.
I'm a contributing editor at Gamasutra. I'm the community manager for GDC.
and I am here today streaming Control.
Control did not come out this month, to the best of my knowledge, it came out last year.
But we are here playing Control today, for one very important reason,
which is this game, The Fine Folks at Remedy Entertainment,
have been nominated for several Game Developers' Choice Awards.
Those awards specifically are for best audio, best narrative, best technology...
Best in Visual Art and Game of the Year.
It's also picked up several honorable mentions.
I'll go ahead and drop the link to the full nominations in Twitch chat.
And in the lower left-hand corner to commemorate this nomination
are two developers from Remedy.
On the left we have Brooke Maggs, and on the right we have...
Oh god, oh no, this is it. I'm gonna miss the last name.
Mikhail Kestrinen. Mikhail, did I get that right?
I'm going to go ahead and actually adjust my audio over here so that I'm not the shooting's
not too loud.
The shooting is really good.
It really is best in audio.
Hi everyone.
I can see in chat that we've got Maniac536 and we've got Remedy Games hanging out.
Hi Remedy.
You're already here.
Yeah, we are here, like I said. We're commemorating the stream.
Also, we're taking the opportunity to catch up with Brook and Mikhail.
We didn't get to do this last year when the game came out.
We're going to talk about the making of Control.
There's already been a lot of great interviews and features about Control.
I totally suggest you Google around and check them out, but what we're doing today here
is we're taking some of my questions about the making of Control, and we are also taking
your questions about the making of Control.
So if you have anything in particular you want to know more about, go ahead and drop
your questions in Twitch chat and I will ask them.
For my part, however, I should start by letting Brooke and Mikhail introduce themselves.
Mikael, would you mind going first for me?
Right, yes. So my name is Mikael Kassorinen, and I'm the game director on Control.
And I've been at Remedy for, well, almost 20 years now.
I did a little tour in Sweden and went to other cities, but the majority of my career has been at Remedy.
I worked on Max Payne 2, Dawn of Wake, Quantum Break, and now Control is the latest one.
Right on. And Brooke, would you introduce yourself for me, please?
Yes, hello. My name is Brooke. I'm a narrative designer on Control,
and I moved here from Australia to work on this game, basically.
And it was my first AAA title. My background is in indie games and indie development,
and I was a freelancer as well before that.
So, yes, making this game has been an absolute pleasure.
Right on. As I work on some waste disposal here, I will acknowledge me...
You're doing a good job. You're cleaning up very well.
Ahti's gonna be very impressed.
Ahti? He asked me to take care of this, so I take care of it.
Yeah.
I worked on this side mission, actually, with the team.
It was a lot of fun, because we were thinking of things to do for Ahti as a cool side mission.
And we thought about...
Wouldn't it be funny if the director of the bureau had to, like, take out the trash?
I'm glad you're having a good time.
I think the director of any bureau should have to take the trash.
Humble oneself a little bit.
The identity of it was the key.
And then he has the task for you that maybe seems a bit more than just taking up the trash.
Getting rid of the rodents and so on.
The rodents.
We're actually going to be working on the plug in just a second.
For folks in check, Maniac has asked us to talk about some spoiler workings for Clickable.
I will let folks know we're only going to be here for an hour.
So, we're looking at, you know, basically the second hour of the game, second, third hour.
Spoiler-wise, I don't think we're hitting anything that I would consider a spoiler because I've finished the game.
And I know what's coming up.
But if you're sensitive about that, feel free to drop the visual, listen to audio, whatever you need.
Um, give a quick shoutout to Brian Otto, um, and Hannah1, who also are dropping by in chat.
Like I said, we're taking your guys' questions, feel free to drop them for us.
Um, and yeah.
Oh man, I think I had this problem when I first played it too, which is I don't know
where the last barrel is.
Don't tell me, I'll find it.
There it is.
Okay.
Um.
Uh, anyway, uh, what I need to do is I need to move on to the actual questions.
Uh, uh, Mikhail, uh, as game director of Control, uh, I would love to start by
picking your brain about Control's origins, um, and if you wouldn't mind
explaining how this game got started. And I'm gonna be blunt, like...
Control is a really unique game. It's got a really unique narrative, tone, vibe.
But it also has to balance some kind of, not totally conventional, but familiar action tropes.
So, would you mind explaining the origins of the game and when you started balancing this combination of
very out there concepts with conventional gameplay?
Yeah, it's a bit like... it has many...
aspects affecting that kind of the root of why we created a game like this.
We were coming off from a project where we wanted to have a kind of a
like a more accepting and normal world, a bit more casual experience and so on.
And we did Unwake before Quantum Break and we're kind of overall feeling like
the next game we want to do is going to be a bit more like brave and take more risks
and not be afraid of being a bit strange.
And that mentality existed already quite early on,
before we even had any idea of what we wanted to do next.
So there was this certain kind of atmosphere that existed already that fed into this.
And what was important to me personally was that we started to create a game where we focus more on the world than on the kind of, let's say, narrative-focused elements that we usually do.
So it's less about the singular character, more about what is this place, what is this kind of...
basic nature.
And me and Sam, Sam Lake, so we started the concept,
all of these different elements,
and that was the first decision kind of like,
let's not even worry that much about the plot,
let's not worry about the main character yet,
let's just talk about what is this world,
what is this place, what are the experiences that we want to have.
And from that, we came up with the Bureau,
the His, and the oldest house as a location, and so on.
And the background for all of that was that we wanted it to be
an experience that is unexpected, full of surprises,
and we embrace the strange side of the supernatural elements, and so on.
And we're not afraid of going all out.
And what we don't want to have is that we...
We kind of explain everything that's happening and actually quite the opposite, like we want to show things and leave the interpretation for the player.
And of course you need to, as a designer, you need to...
provide like elements that people can see and start to draw conclusions and so on.
So there was this kind of acceptance that let's not explain, let's not spoon feed and so on.
And once we kind of put those elements together and we started to see that okay
here's a compelling package of elements that there's this exploration into
strange phenomena and we revolve around that.
Brutalism was there almost right from the get-go, that it's an element that we want to have in the Oldest House.
And the side that we're not going to explain everything, let's just as a player dive into this world and leave it upon them to kind of understand what's happening.
And from there, we started to put the pieces together and start talking about, okay, what if, you know, you're kind of a director of this place.
And actually that was the first idea.
And then the second idea was that maybe you're an outsider.
Because we wanted to be bold with the strange ideas.
But if your character is already part of the world, then you don't have this view into this world that the player has.
So we wanted the main character to be someone who is an outsider to this world.
But at the same time, we wanted them to belong.
So, yeah, you become the director within the first five minutes of the story.
And a huge part of that was to give that lens into this world
through a character that can relate to you,
understand that they're kind of experiencing all of this at the same time as you are.
At the same time, that character is now a fundamental aspect, part of this world as well.
And getting to grips with all of that is a huge part of that journey that you take with Chessie.
And yeah, I mean, it took something like six months, roughly, to...
concept all of these bits together and it was pretty much just me and Sam talking,
have a lot of discussions and putting core ideas together.
And then came the time to actually start, you know, creating the assets,
creating demos and all of these elements that we needed to be able to
communicate further different ideas and so on.
And yeah, from there we kind of went into the standard
game development procedure and so on and that's how it came together.
Right on.
Uh, before I do want to jump to Brooke and invite you to talk about your
experience, but Mikhail, I'm going to ask one more question, which is, um,
obviously Remedy has a technology base and it has, uh, uh, some of.
format of game development that it's more familiar with as a company.
Um, how did you and your colleagues...
Oh, man, I have to get around.
Um, how did you and your colleagues figure out...
Okay, I can use this weapon.
Um...
Now I have to bring it back.
Uh, how did you all come up with, like, this kind...
A format for balancing, you know, the work you need to do, you know,
on making sure levels made sense,
on making sure that gameplay felt like something that players could still understand
in a weird world, while chasing that, um...
Uh...
chasing that sort of weird sensation.
I think that you guys were saying the word New Weird a lot when I was hearing the marketing
for this game.
Yeah, New Weird was basically a stance that we took into this world.
It is a literary genre, but at the same time it's not just about...
Hey, let's have a strange world is about the kind of holistic behavior of characters within it and
how these different concepts come together and this kind of avoidance of
explaining too much what's happening and leave a lot to interpretation.
It was a challenge to balance out these type of elements together with the game that we
want you to be able to understand quite quickly.
So that's why it was important that the core mechanics are seemingly simple, like telekinesis
for instance being a core element of what Jessie can do.
What I like about telekinesis is that...
It is visually simple. It is easy to explain.
Like, you conceptually get it. You understand what's happening.
And there is a sense of connection to the physical world.
So it's not like completely alien.
It's not like some force that enters the world that you don't understand.
We would have to explain and so on. There's none of that.
You kind of get it quite quickly, what's happening and how it works.
And that was crucial. I wanted it to be...
an approachable, relatable gameplay.
You can pick up the controller, start playing, and you can start having fun really quickly.
But then there's this other layer, where is the actual world itself, and that's filled with mystery and secrets,
and even contradictions, like sometimes you see a thing and you think it works in one way,
but then once you kind of dive further into it, you learn that, oh, it's not that simple, and so on.
So it was important for us to have these two layers, that there can be complexity
and this kind of depth to the world that can sometimes almost be impenetrable,
but playing the game should be fun, should be easy, should be intuitive.
And finding the right tone with the different missions, different side missions and all of that,
that was a lot of iteration because we wanted to really follow up thinking that
let's not explain everything, let's let the player pay attention and that they feel like they should be paying attention.
and kind of draw their own conclusions.
So it was a huge balancing act of like exercising restraint sometimes,
like, no, we don't need to tell that and tell that and tell that,
let's think those things out.
And it actually became stronger when we did these kind of decisions.
And what maybe was tough about it,
because as game designers, we want people to be able to jump in and get it.
quickly. So sometimes it's required like a specific attitude of like looking at the thing
and asking questions. I'll be telling too much. And that was I think a huge part of the process
and a lot of time went into that kind of iteration. Right on. I got a million more questions about
this kind of topic. But Brooke, I'm gonna throw the question ball to you for a minute.
Um, Brooke, uh, your role in the game as narrative designer, my understanding, uh, that you, that you
were able to join the game later on in the project. Um, I would like to know, uh, there's, there's,
it is a, it would be incorrect of me to say that games are, you know, plotted out at the start and
figured, you know, then, then just executed on way. What's, what is your narrative designer?
What is your goal coming into a project like this and, and working, figuring out story,
even though the game is already underway? Can you talk about that?
Yeah, that was, um.
It was really interesting and it was a bit of a challenge too, I guess, because it was
a brand new IP.
My first task really was to sink myself into the world and to understand all the concepts
that had been set up that we were just talking about and understand the ins and outs of them.
What are objects of power and what does the Bureau do?
You know, who is Jessie and why is she here?
And like, not only, and know the story and know the characters and know the world,
you know, that's been so lovingly built.
And then also understand what the tone is.
I think that's pretty key actually.
The mood, Control is a moody game and like it has a certain mood and tone to it that
comes from the new weird genre, which is not over explaining things.
which is elements of science fiction and fantasy, but never, you know,
straying into either genre, like completely.
So coming onto the project, I remember,
I actually remember having conversations with Sam about trying to understand
certain parts, especially when then I'd sort of understood what was going on.
And then I was, you know,
given some areas of the game to sort of cut my teeth on, I suppose.
And one of them was the motel sequences.
And I even, I went, I think I went to Sam and I went to you and I went to Stuart, our
world design director, who all these people collectively sort of came up with these ideas
and there was this legacy of ideas of what this was supposed to be and then what the
tone should be.
And then keeping that mood throughout development is a balancing act, as you say, because sometimes
you just have to play it and review it.
say well I think that's actually over-explaining the strangeness, you know, maybe we need to
dial that back or now we've gone too obtuse and people don't get it so we need to, you
know, spell things out a little bit more.
So for me it was, you know, an exercise in wrapping my head probably around the largest
narrative world for a game that I had taken on yet and then I guess embodying that information.
And I actually spent a lot of time, because we were in the heat of production,
as part of something I did when I first started, is I went to every room and introduced myself,
and said, what do you all do in this room, and how can narrative help you?
And I actually incidentally picked up these questions that people had about the world,
that were, you know, pretty nuanced kind of questions, you know,
so I didn't always know the answers, so I would collect them up.
go back to the narrative room, we would sort of talk about the answers and what that should
be and then I would sort of take them back to the team.
Because the team don't necessarily have the time to delve into every sort of nook and
cranny of the world that we in the narrative department have our great law documents going
on.
But sometimes they just need an answer quite quickly.
Being able to convey that narrative mood and that information to them quickly and succinctly
was a lot of what I was doing.
And then also after that I took on the side missions.
And so part of my job was to understand the intent behind them, to understand, you know,
what this one is meant to say, flesh out a character or it's meant to introduce an aspect
of the world.
And then I would go through, because a lot of it was in partial production,
so I would go through and see what was there,
and meet people who were working on it, and find out what their design intent was,
and sort of liaise between departments for the side missions and for the motels.
And we definitely honed them a lot, I would say, in that time.
So, yeah, that's...
I just want to say how amazing important that work was, because you were the glue between
different departments of audio levels and so on.
Finding also I think opportunity as well, like you know we were maybe even thinking of highlighting
certain things in certain quests and then you kind of saw this like hey what if you connect
this and we bring that up there and so on and that was that was wonderful and I think hugely
important to create this kind of a cohesive world that feels like connected and so on so yeah.
Thank you very much that's lovely to hear. Obviously did a good job.
I'm trying to do a good job as Director of the Oldest House right now, but
Director of the Bureau of Control, I should say, not the Oldest House.
But I'm going to pause the game so I can get questions in the chat because this is getting really hard.
I'm going to grab a question from the chat.
Brian Otto, who I believe is a speedrunner, Brian Otto would like to know,
has the speedrun for Control changed the way you all approach development at all?
I will stack on that question, which is speedrunning has been a thing for a few years.
I'm curious if speedrunning at all and its existence informed how you think about game development.
Mikhail?
Um, well...
First of all, I just want to say again how amazing that screen run was.
I really enjoyed it.
It's pretty incredible.
So it was a lot of fun.
I don't think it, at least to me, it doesn't really affect the way we work on the game.
I think it's a great thing to kind of observe and see,
and you see the game through different eyes,
so it's always great to have that perspective.
But I think fundamentally I'm not personally looking at the game from that angle.
And it's kind of hard to even imagine how that would work, because a huge part of speedrunning is
have this kind of attitude of, let's see how much we can essentially break the game.
That's the whole idea.
And it's weirdly enjoyable to see that happening,
even though it kind of makes your heart sink a bit, like,
oh no, that happened, and oh no, I didn't even know that was possible.
But it's also fun at the same time.
And what makes me personally excited about games is the improvisation.
when people do things that you don't expect with your game.
And actually now that I think about it, a huge part of Control's
vision for combat was that...
It is this physical space that we're giving to the player with a lot of low-level systems
that work in a predictable physical way.
So there's no like clean, clear rules that it always goes like this.
There's this sense of looseness to, like you can pick up any physical object you want.
We were not going to just like, we try to make everything functional and physical and
behave in the way that you expect.
And with understanding that the risk is that we might not have perfected every single bit.
We haven't probably checked every single possibility of what the players might do.
And in a way, that was the intent.
I wanted people to improvise, have fun,
and being able to see where people come up with ideas that you didn't think of is fantastic.
I love that, and especially speedrunners.
That's the essence of what they're doing.
So yeah, in a way we think about it, but I don't think it affects the game development per se, at least from my end.
That makes sense.
I'm very happy with a piece I did on Gamas for a while back,
interviewing some developers who work with speedrunners to get their game done.
But obviously, that's the exception. Not a rule.
Um, now, uh, while I beat these heads up, I'm going to repause to jump-
Oh, actually, yeah, there's a good question in chat from Ruchess.
Uh, who would like to know, did the layout of this game begin as more of an action game
with set-piece elements like Half-Life, or as a hero shooter combining powers like Prototype or Singularity?
Sorry, what was the actual question?
The question is how did this game sort of begin to come together?
Was it more set-piece driven, like okay, or was it more like we're going to develop these powers and then sort of develop set-pieces around them?
You mentioned in your answer just a second ago that this is a, you know, you have low-level powers with rules that work everywhere.
Right.
I say yeah, it wasn't about set pieces, it was about the world itself and then finding
compelling elements that you can discover yourself within this world and less about
constructing certain type of moments for the player and instead like, you know.
Let the player be the ones that figure out how to go through it, what to do and so on,
and kind of stay out from their way, I think, as much as possible.
Sure enough, when you look at set pieces in the kind of sense as, let's say, boss fights
or the objects of power that you discover,
In a way, yes, that kind of thinking existed early on, but the whole idea was that it's like, you know, the boss fights in Dark Souls, that they kind of exist there, you can discover them and so on, but they are not necessarily, like, a bigger set piece moments, like, connected to the story and so on, and more to the world and gameplay instead.
I think it's probably true, too, that...
We knew that we were going to make a game with gunplay and abilities, but we also knew
that the world would, well, it's all set inside one location, but it's a very interesting
kind of winding, shifting, strange location that you can explore.
And I know a lot of the world development that Stuart and the team did.
to build out the oldest house, thinking of it as a government bureau and going, okay,
well, if they're studying, you know, the supernatural and unexplained, what kind of departments
would they possibly have? And then, you know, then we had the research sector and then what
would go inside the research sector? And then it's also about the combination of making
that space large enough to be enjoyable with those abilities.
But also, for example, I know one of the reasons that Stuart and Yan-Nei sort of went with
Brutalism is because it's very straight, clean lines that actually works really well when
the players are running around, you know, kind of destroying things with their abilities.
Like, the environment is more readable in that way.
If the environment was super busy all the time.
it would be really hard. So it's all been really considered in terms of how it's designed.
For example, in the maintenance sector, you have the huge power reactor, which is sort
of a set piece in and of itself, I guess. So each area has its own character. I know
that style guides were put together for the colour palette of each sector, what the lines
on the floor will say.
what kind of signage the maintenance sector uses compared to the research sector, because
there would be different people there, they would need to know different things.
So yeah, and then how the oldest house opens up over time ties into the gameplay pretty
closely as well.
So you always have reason to come back through different sectors as well, so that influenced
the way that the game was created.
Um, I'm gonna ask a follow-up question kind of about the space of the game.
Uh, one of the cool things about the oldest house is that it sort of lets the player in on the script.
That level design game's a giant, you know, it doesn't...
Hallways aren't hallways, uh...
Area elevators aren't actually elevators, you know, like...
Yeah.
When levels in games are made, they do not follow real-world logic.
By knowing what the player sees and what's going on behind the scenes.
What was it like, like, sort of making a space for both of you?
I'd love to hear both your thoughts on this, that...
Uh...
Sometimes it's just...
This can...
Like, the opening area of the game when A.T. first unlocks the elevator for you is a perfect example.
Like, it doesn't make sense, and yet it's working.
Well, a huge part of the style or feel that we wanted to have, that there's this conflict
or collision of strange and mundane.
And we wanted to avoid, like, let's just have strange stuff and then acting strange.
What made it interesting is that it's familiar, something that you can recognize and understand,
like an elevator.
But then as you use it, you discover that something else, something more complicated is going on that you're having a hard time understanding.
So, you can see that through the entire game that most of the stuff is taking something that you can really understand and then turning it into something surprising and so on.
That's the feel of Unexpected.
Hmm.
And I know a lot of the...
level designers kind of really got creative with that as well.
You know, in the research sector, for example, there are quite a few environment secrets
and I remember working with Anna Marie and she was telling me all of these things that
was possible for players to do if they used the launch ability to stack things up and
they could be able to get into a certain area or something like that.
She was really thinking through how players would play the space, but then also what creative
things you could do given the strange nature of the oldest house.
So I think it sort of freed up level design a little bit in a way to do that.
But then also from a story perspective, so the motels are, basically the motel sequences
are a way for players to get from one area of the oldest house to another to open up
areas and spaces and this whole idea of having this transient space that you access with
a light switch cord, you go to a motel in a completely different area outside the oldest
house and solve some puzzles to then get the key to get back to a different part.
I don't think that would have been, you know, that's not, that's something that our world
allows for, which is, allows us to be more creative I would say.
So, yeah.
Um, Brooke, I think also while I'm here, I should mention that you're giving a talk at
GDC.
Uh...
I am, yes!
Which is a talk about the making of the Ocean View Motel.
So if you're going to GDC, or if you just like keeping an eye on our, uh, um, GDC Vault
and GDC YouTube channel, keep an eye out for that talk.
It is probably going to be good.
Um, while I am beating up the enemies, uh, I'm going to give, uh, this is going to be a tough question to sort out, but I'd like to give, uh,
Hackegel and Billy the Kit- er, uh, Maniac536 just a brief nod because they've been really good viewers today.
Um, they're asking about the possibility of either an artbook and also finding out what is behind the redacted sections of some of the art of the- of the, um, collectibles, which I have been skipping over.
Find that! They're redacted! The point of it is that you can't find out.
That being said, Brooke, I will let you as the narrative designer...
I'll take that one.
How do you feel about those redacted stuff and letting players find the information?
Well, I mean, we had a lot of fun writing them, but I would say that that is top secret information
that's probably been lost forever. Unfortunately.
It's been redacted for a reason.
It's been redacted for a reason. It's very top secret, important stuff that cannot be revealed.
Lower explanations on the game dev chat.
Okay, I need to move on.
For information about an art book, I would invite the folks from MIDI Games to...
Sorry, turtle that on you.
If you want to reply to that one, I need to leave that to you.
Anyway, Mikal, we only have so much time with you left, so I do want to squeeze in some more questions.
What, with a team like the one you have, uh, like you know this really talented team of creative people,
um, working as hard as they can to put out an interest, you know, to execute the vision that
you and Sam, uh, and your board director whose name I'm blanking on, came up with, um, what do
you feel, I like asking directors this question, what do you feel is essential to communicating
The reason behind your yeses and noes for people, because obviously you sort of have the authority to go yes, no, yes, no to everything they throw at you.
But what's the difference between just arbitrarily toss handing down yeses and noes on what they make versus explaining and shepherding, you know, and making an even better product, I guess?
That's totally right. You just drop the hammer and go, no.
Actually, he doesn't.
Well sometimes you need to start with that, but you're responsible for making people understand
the reasoning behind it, and you want to take the extra time to make sure that everybody's
comfortable with that decision.
What's tricky with control is that it embraces certain kind of...
philosophies and ideas that yes, you can say them out loud like early on in production
and say these are the key elements that we should all look at and think about and so
on.
But then when it comes to actual execution, when you actually start to build things, you
realize that there are a lot of things that are not clear cut.
There's grey zones and a lot of things that are less for interpretation.
And so that I think made it this tough and there was a need to quite often have these sit-downs
where we kind of like, okay, let's talk through this concept and kind of sometimes it is about
finding the answer together. And a huge part was very important to me with Control was that
We don't work in a way where me and Sam, like we producers, green-light, just give it to people.
Like, we're going to do this game. That's not what I want. I don't think that's what we wanted.
A huge part of it was to establish that this is the world we want to create.
Here are the high-level rules that we want to follow.
And then give the team this kind of a sandbox to play in.
That they can start building.
Their ideas on what kind of side missions we could have and so on.
A lot of the ideas in Control are actually directed from the team themselves.
And it's good for creativity. A lot of ideas I or Sam never come up with.
And that's wonderful. That's exactly what we want.
But then there's this importance to do a follow-up.
Like, you know, a huge part of my job is to ensure that the end result is cohesive.
It kind of makes sense. Sometimes it might be hard to see how it makes sense,
but you feel it and it's there.
even the weirder stuff that you see in the game
feels like it belongs there.
And that's not an accident,
that's us carefully considering
all these different aspects we're doing.
And that's the basis of reasoning that I'm trying to provide.
And sometimes there are things that are just...
I'll be honest, sometimes it's like
you just have to kind of...
You have to realise it. You kind of just know what's the right direction.
And of course I spend all this time trying to explain it, but sometimes it kind of can be like,
tonally this is the right way to go.
And there needs to be that kind of a higher level direction sometimes that adjusts different types of things.
So yeah, complicated, but yeah.
But it's time well spent, isn't it?
Because when you spend the time to explain why you're making a decision,
then it helps.
Clarify the direction and the mood and the thing that we're going for.
Now I remember when when I first came to Remedy
Sam took the time to take us through the narrative presentation
Which basically sort of summed up the world for us and like introduced us to you know
What you guys had been creating and sort of introduced us to the characters. I didn't sort of just
Oh, I'm here, I'll just, you know, go off and read about this I guess.
You know, they take the time and you even did a,
it was like a creative game overall overview update for us
and presented it to us, the whole team,
which was talking about the key pillars of the game and what you wanted to get
across and, you know, what it was about and like
the physicality of the powers and the...
You know, the strangeness of the entities in the world, all of that kind of stuff helps.
Like, I think that the leadership here spends a lot of time on that because it's such a remedy thing, I guess.
Like, we have these very interesting, complex worlds that, you know, take some time to, like, get, I guess, get across.
And especially because Control was a new IP and is doing different things gameplay and
world-wise, so that I imagine required a lot more considering on how you would communicate
that and get that across.
For sure.
That's, I think, one of the hardest parts when you're creating a new IP.
Basically none of it exists.
And you really have to do the legwork to justify your reasons.
You can't just come up with things.
You have to have the fundamental thinking to be solid behind everything that you're saying.
And yeah, that took a lot of time.
But at the same time, you want to leave wiggle room for the team to be creative and have
that little sandbox where they can come up with a lot of new ideas as well.
Right on, that was, I think, a really good answer.
Um, I'm gonna give a quick shoutout to BillyTheKid3, who says they bought two copies of this game for two of their friends for Christmas and got the special edition for themselves.
Nice, thank you!
Um, uh, uh, so I'm gonna shoutout to, uh, Maniac536, who seemed to have a big love for the easter eggs in this game.
My partner, who, uh, played this game with me and was a big Alan White fan, immediately made sure, uh, after, cause she played it and...
got ahead of me and she's like, okay you need to go to the Alan Wake room and I'm like, uh, I never played Alan Wake.
And I went, and she went, what? And she still made me go there. Um, uh, uh, I guess it's a
spoiler though, there's an Alan Wake room. Oh man, this is one of my, research, central research, this is one of my favorites.
Oh right, central research. I love. This is my favorite lobby, I really like this. Oh yeah, so you have this.
I just wanted to say it's my new.
I also, I also love the Dr Darling videos there.
Yeah, well man, we're getting into the Dr. Darling stuff.
It's so good.
Yeah.
Um, uh, yeah.
Uh, we only have a few minutes left with, uh, McCall.
So I'm going to, uh, Brooke, I'm gonna throw some questions your way in a moment,
but I want to give McCall a chance to talk with our audience today.
Um, McCall, uh, I am going to, um.
When I started playing this game, I realized that you could secretly call it a Metroidvania.
Because there's a sense of...
Just like in Metroid or Castlevania, you get upgrades. Those upgrades reopen areas in old fictions for you.
Oh no, there's too many rockets! Stop it!
Um, uh, and that means the level design for this game is a straightforward adventure, but a, you know,
uh, like you said, like you've described, it's a world that players can learn more about both
literally, they can learn narrative things, hold still, um, and uh, they can also learn how to move
within it, which is they when they revisit old zones and use their abilities to go new areas.
I do not like what's happening right now. Um, give me, give me help.
Would you mind explaining the process of creating areas that players can re-explore and backtrack through without feeling like they're wasting time?
Huge part of the thinking that we had from the get-go that, I mean, looking back, like,
we came from Quantum Break, and it's a linear story-driven game. A lot of spaces were built
with a purpose in mind, but you can't just run through them in 10 seconds, you never return,
and so on. It was actually interesting, I felt like when we were working on Quantum that we
spent actually a lot of time justifying the existence of different things you see in the
world. There's a lot of lore, there's a lot of stories behind them, and so on.
And to me at the time it almost felt like we spent all this time kind of building this framework,
this construct of ideas that is expressed within the place that you go through,
but then the play just kind of blasts through them, kills everybody and moves on to the next room.
And it was a bit of a shame, I felt.
And when you look at control, I think you're seeing elements that we've already been doing in our previous games,
in our more linear games.
So I think they kind of understand and know how to create a compelling environment that already existed.
But the problem that we've had is that we've always done a linear story-driven thing,
we're driven by the action, we're driven by the story, we need to move on to the next bit and so on.
So it was a big change, honestly, to us to kind of change that thinking that,
no, you're here for the world, you're here to explore.
It's like, let's give the players a chance to discover.
And when that landed, like when people...
really took it like, yes, it's not about thinking where the next trigger is, it's not about,
you know, where the next cinematic will happen, it is about the space itself. And through that
thinking, great things started to happen and we get these...
Things like the trees in the middle of this space, for instance, that kind of grounds it, that acts as a kind of an anchor point,
and it can lead you into different directions, you always return to this central area and so on.
It led to that kind of very visual thinking, it's connected to the lore of the world, it's connected to all these
different things that you discover, yes, in the story as well.
So...
Yeah, it kind of happened organically, but it had to happen through a process where everybody was able to
knowingly step back and away from how we thought about things before and embrace the idea that the focus should be on the space.
Instead of just a kind of a core narrative piece, that's kind of a linear arc that usually goes through.
And once that happened, and once we kind of continued iterating, it kind of just came together.
It's kind of weird when I think about it, because this is a massive change that we did in the way of thinking.
And yeah, I think a huge part of that is that kind of a know-how and understanding that we already created in the previous games that we did.
Right on, uh, oh man, I could tell so many questions, so many observations at you right now.
Um, just like, I couldn't get over just in this fight for instance, how this, they all spawn this corner,
you're fighting in this corner, the walls that you're looking at right here drive you, like, visually to look in this corner,
so it was easy for me, this fight was quote-unquote easy,
because I could, like, just sort of focus on everything.
Um, there's so much about Control that I think is so cool, about celebrating,
and that's probably why it picked up so many nominations.
Uh, at the Game Developers Twisters, which I forgot to mention, are on March 18th, and you can watch it on- here on Twitch,
or you can attend the show at GDC this year, if you come.
Uh, sorry for the- for the-
reshilling.
Um, Mikal, before you go, uh, we're gonna have some time with Brooke before I shut down the stream, uh-
Uh, I'm going to share one observation I had and I'm curious about your thoughts about it.
What separates Control for me from a lot of other video games is that this game kicks off with a different kind of empowering premise that ties back to what you talked about with this world that we're trying to explore and this, um, everything which is the idea that, um, you were right.
Like, it's a theme that I feel from the minute the game starts.
Uh, there's this sense of validation that comes with Jesse's story and, uh, the way you explore this world, which is.
You know, as you pass through dead letters, as you read the collectibles,
you get the sense that, you know, there was a conspiracy.
You were hurt as a kid.
There was a coverup.
You were separated from your brother.
People were acting with bad intentions around you.
There's something really empowering in a way for that.
It's different than other games I've played.
A lot of games, you know, you get stronger, you, or you start, you can become strong.
That's, that's a great kind of empowerment.
Um, you can look at games like Devil May Cry 5, where you start strong, lose your
powers, and then have to regain them.
And it's a huge part of our behavior and yeah, I think there's something really interesting and unique in that.
I was in love with that idea. I think the moment was set out loud.
So yeah, it's a huge part of the experience.
Oh man, this is a fun room, but I don't have time to do it.
That is a fun room.
Yeah, Old God of Asgard, that it.
Yeah.
Shout out to the Old Guards of Asgard, but you said they don't have time to witness your glory today.
With that, I call. Thank you for joining us. I understand you have to duck out. Thank you
for your insightful answers about directing control. Congratulations on all the nominations.
And yeah, that's about all I got for now. Brooke, we will chat with you for the rest of our time.
Okay, excellent.
Goodbye!
Alright, bye bye!
Thank you, it was a lot of fun!
Yes, I'm out.
I'll do my best.
Oh man, uh,
yeah, BillyTheKid wants to say
thanks to McCall for connecting.
Um,
it's funny, the stream going down broke my entire
flow of gameplay, so now I'm just wandering around this area
uselessly. Um,
No, you're doing well,
you can see an area that's a little bit...
Kind of interesting and curious over there.
Yeah, I'm trying to remember if this is something you do now or if you do it later.
Because it's the stupid...
That's a good question. I think it's later.
Yeah, well, let's try and get over there.
Oh!
No.
Ha ha ha ha! No.
Yeah, but that was actually an interesting challenge with, um...
With narrative and level design and game design all paired together is...
That question, which is, can the players access this now?
So that's not necessarily something we came up against in previous games, because of course they
were a little bit more linear in the way that you move through the spaces, like Mikhail was
talking about before. But we would have to work more closely with the other departments in terms
of, okay, so what does the player know in the story? Which characters have they met? What
could they potentially uncover?
and then make sure that we distributed, for example, the optional content,
all those documents accordingly,
and make sure we didn't spoil anything that might come later.
If players could sort of decided not to, you know,
do main missions one after another and explored and went to side missions,
we had to make sure that, you know, all of those secrets were well kept.
So, for example, there, Anna-Marie made sure that drop would kill you.
You didn't make the drop.
But mainly so that you don't necessarily spoil things for yourself either.
But yeah, we had to be careful about that actually.
So that was interesting.
That was an interesting challenge.
Brooke, while I've got you here, one of my favorite things to ask a narrative designer about is
I often feel very strongly that the content of games is informed by the tools they are made.
So I'm curious, especially as someone who gets to make the Oceanview motel,
how you felt working with, I don't know if you worked directly with the Northland Engine
or if you were using other tools with it,
but I'm curious how you felt as a storyteller your ability to
execute the vision that McCall was talking about was affected by how you were making it.
Yeah, I mean, I personally wasn't jumping into the engine.
I mean, I did a lot of playtesting, and I did a lot of build reviews and things like that.
One of our other narrative designers was doing a lot of the...
We have a tool that we use to do a lot of that stuff that had to do with dialogue and pacing.
I mean, well, I lie. I did use the tool to do a lot of the optional content setup and things like that.
So that was really interesting.
Funnily enough, there were some interesting limitations around how we could make the documents work with the text.
And I actually think that that was really helpful because it meant that we were like,
okay, so we can do a lot of documentation, but we can't put heaps of pictures on them because of the way the tool works.
We could put some, but it actually...
you know, made us be creative with the idea of what kind of funny, like, office documentation
would you find around, and actually being quite spare with the amount of words that
we could use as well.
So we really just had that sort of one page to use.
We, you know, some games sort of let you flick through pages.
So we had to be pretty sparing, which I think was good. I think that limitation meant that we had snappier
documents to read, and there are quite a few to read, but they don't take a long time in and of themselves.
So that was interesting. But then also for me, for my work, a lot of what I was doing was
doing a lot of the vision holding for the side missions and for the motel, which I'll talk about in my talk.
But for the side missions,
Clay, our writer, one of our writers would be in the room with me and they would be taking
notes of what Jessie needs to say or take note of or what she might say to help players
along in the particular side mission and a lot of what I was doing was often walking
between departments talking to the level designer and sound design.
Getting a list of animations that we need for those side missions,
getting lists of like, and getting that sent off so they could be mo-capped and things like that.
So a lot of like detail orientated work to make sure that the narrative is being carried across
in the whole mission, but it's not necessarily to do with just the dialogue. So yeah, making sure
all of that is accounted for.
letting Clay know that, you know, Jessie will need to do something in this side mission, I don't know, like
turn off the clog or, I don't know,
solve a puzzle with the radio, and so then she needs a line that's probably specific to that.
So a lot of that is feeding information to the people, you know, that what they need to be able to do their particular thing.
So that's a lot of my work in the development part anyway.
Let's close off this chat.
Folks in chat have been asking great questions.
But I'm going to close off with a little bit of a tease for your talk about the Oceanview Motel.
Um, what I would like to know is the Oceanview, you mentioned that the
Oceanview Motel is a transit space.
It lets you sort of pick up the player from one area and move them to another
with this in-between zone of passing through, you know, a sort of Pacific
Northwest-y motel and we're getting a great look at the lobby today.
In that space, you do some of the most interesting, like it sort of underlines the theme of the game in a very specific way,
which is, you know, the odd interacting with mundane objects creates dramatic consequences.
And I would just like to know, what was your process for architecting the little interactions and then the little,
I guess like, you know, they have these supernatural payoffs a little bit.
Yes.
Because the interior as you go on.
What was your process for coming up with some of those?
Yeah, so some of the...
So when I jumped onto the motels, there were prototypes for puzzles for them.
And some of them were really great, and I took elements of them and redesigned them,
only because some of them had fallen out of the narrative mood and tone.
So they were a little bit too...
obvious, but the reason for that was they were somewhat placeholder saying like put a mysterious cool puzzle here
and this is what it could look like.
And then I went ahead and worked with the different level designers and sort of proposed my own puzzle designs that were
simpler admittedly, but also a bit
weirder and then I can't completely take credit for the puzzles themselves because
I would have an idea and talk to the level designer about them, and then they would have
suggestions about how to make it more readable and work better technically, and then we would
go back and forth on that.
And a lot of what I would do is pitch the props for the motels and the environment and
talk about what it should look and feel like, and I worked with our environment artist,
Mikey, and sat with her, and we looked at things together and reviewed it together.
So that was really fun.
And then some of the motels are really specific and have a very specific theme.
I don't know how much I should say so as not to spoil.
But, um, so those ones...
If it's like from the first couple of motel levels, like, feel free to spoil it, just because the game has been out for a minute.
Okay. Well, so, um, well the Arkti motel for example, there's one that's got a very Finnish theme to it.
And so we were for the longest time thinking about what that should be.
feel like, and Sam had some pretty clear ideas for it, so it was making sure that we were
delivering on that for him.
And I also worked with the sound designer to design the stinger for when you successfully
solve a puzzle, like what that should sound like.
Because it's really tempting to be really obvious or on the nose, but because you're
getting a strange pyramid key from the board.
We sort of figured that something that sounded like that would be really cool.
And you know, some of my happiest moments on the game is, you know, sitting with these other
super talented people and helping them and them helping me realize the vision for the motel
sequences. So it's going to be a real pleasure to talk about it and delve into detail for the talk.
For folks who are able to GDC March 16th to the 20th, if you
look at your screen, you will see the date on the upper left
hand corner. You can check out Brooks's talk. It's not
scheduled yet. I don't know what day and time it is. I'm sorry.
But that's okay. I don't know either. So it would be a
complete mystery.
Yeah, uh, with that, I'm going to start wrapping up our stream.
Thank you all.
Oh my God.
I still have my connect plugged in and it thought I yelled it.
Um, uh, um, uh, with that, I'm going to start wrapping up our stream.
Thank you everyone for rolling.
Surprising technical difficulties today.
Congratulations to Brooke McCall and everyone else at Remedy, Sam, and a lot
of the folks who worked on this game.
Um.
I'm personal friends with one of the people who works in pre-production on the writing,
Abigail Threshold, who did all that.
Oh yeah, yeah. Oh my gosh, yeah.
I'm so sorry we didn't get to show them off today,
because they are one of my favorite things about this game too.
Yeah, shout out to them, shout out to everyone who worked really hard
to bring this game to life through all parts of the process.
With that, I need to do my shilling for who we are and what we do.
We are Game Developers Conference.
Thank you folks for tuning in.
If you're not a game developer, you should know that we go live regularly.
We're doing two streams today where we are going to be interviewing the folks from the Outer Wilds team.
Oh, amazing.
Yeah, that game is so cool.
Oh yeah, that'll be fun.
They have also been nominated for the Game Developers Choice Award.
I'm sorry, I guess you're competing with them, but hey, you know, everyone wins at the GCA.
What a compliment to be competing with them.
Yeah, um, yeah, so we're gonna be talking with them starting at 3pm EST, that's 12pm Pacific.
Um, I don't know any other time zones from that, but it's up to you to figure out.
Um, from there, uh, so if you hit the follow button you'll get a notification when we go live.
If you'd like to attend GDC, you can totally, um, uh, just hit the, uh, button at the bottom
of the screen. I've set up a button down there so you can get your pass.
Um, if you want to check out, uh, is your talk on the Nerdif Summit or is it somewhere else?
In the narrative summit.
If you're in the narrative summit, you'll want to get a summit's pass to see Brooks talk.
But if you get anything from an expo, you can attend the awards on the 18th, no matter
what badge you have.
So you should totally do that.
And if you're not going to attend the awards, if you're not going to attend the show in
person, like I said, it'll be streaming live on Twitch, so you can watch there.
So you should follow for that reason too.
That's what's happening.
There's more people spawning.
You're doing a good job!
Yeah, uh, talking, interviewing, and playing.
I know, I don't know how you do it.
This is a really good clip.
I'm just saying it's a good thing I played this game once already.
Dr. Darling, um...
There he is.
Maniac536, this stream will eventually be archived on YouTube.
That technical glitch we had earlier may mean I can't just push a button and send it over.
I may need to hop into a video editor and stitch it back together.
With that in mind, I would like to thank everyone for watching.
Thank you, Brooke and the folks at Remedy for setting this stream up.
And I cannot wait to see your talk at GDC.
Awesome. Thank you so much. It's been a pleasure.
Have a good day everyone and enjoy your ventures in the oldest house.
And if you're gonna stick with us for the Outer Wilds, uh, drop.
Hank.
See you in a couple hours.
Bye.