Hi everyone, my name is Brian Francis. I'm a contributing editor at GammaStructure.com and a community manager for GDC.
I am also today... oh no, I am in trouble.
I am in deep trouble.
I am playing The Church in the Darkness. This is a game that comes from Paranoid Productions, which is Richard Rouse 3's...
Richard Rouse 3. Richard Rouse the 3rd's game studio.
You don't have to say the 3rd out loud.
Yeah, just written.
Just written.
Richard Rouse is also the person who is in the lower left hand corner of the screen.
He is a veteran game designer who we have seen a lot on the GDC show floor.
We are here today.
Church in the Dark just finally came out.
We streamed this when we were doing this on the Gamma Sutra Twitch channel a while back.
We streamed this with him then.
You might have read about the game, you might have seen some stuff about the game,
and now we're here to play the game and talk about its development.
Richard, how are you doing? And how are the other two Richard Rouses?
Oh, right. The other two Richard Rouses are not with us anymore, as it happens.
Oh, I'm sorry.
It's been a while, so it's okay to say that, I guess.
But yeah, no, we're still, you know, we just shipped something like three weeks ago,
feels like. They're looking at the calendar. Maybe it's four weeks ago.
Not quite four weeks. And we're still...
Working on patches, stuff like that.
Also, getting ready for a panel at PAX that we're doing with the voice actors.
Oh yeah.
There's some, I don't know if you'll, folks let me know if you can hear or not hear the
voice actors in question.
John Patrick Lowery and Ellen McClain have lent their voices for this game.
Who you may know with them better as the Sniper from Team Fortress 2 and GLaDOS from Portal.
Yes, and they're lovely people at trade shows.
You know, if you're ever putting together a panel, you know, this being the GDC channel, you can talk about this.
You know, when you're putting together a group of speakers, you know, you want to get people with good content,
but also people who are, you know, charismatic, can talk on stage, that sort of thing.
And the great thing about actors is that's what they do.
You know, so there's no... they will outclass the most famous developer, given the chance.
Right on.
Richard, I could introduce your game for you, but why don't you do it?
What is The Church in the Darkness, and why did you make it?
Yeah, so as we can see from Bryant here, desperately trying not to be detected, it's a bit of an infiltration game with a top-down perspective, inspired by some games I loved before I was in the industry.
And it's set inside a religious cult in the 1970s, which you are infiltrating to look for your nephew, Alex.
And it does a lot of sort of dynamic story stuff.
So there's a ton of different endings you can get.
We can talk more about those later.
Because I could clarify some of the intention there,
which is a little bit different than how I've seen people taking it now that the game's out.
But there's a ton of different endings you can get based on choices you make.
But we also change up the personalities of the preachers each time.
So you're making choices based on different personalities to the cult leaders.
And that sort of makes it a...
Procedural story-ish sort of thing.
It is also, it's got roguelike qualities.
I believe you said you've been playing for a while and have been captured twice already.
So if you get shot again, oh yeah, you're running into the hornet's nest here.
But you're also, you know, been playing this long enough that you know that if you keep
moving you can get out of many scrapes.
Not all, but many.
I can't tell if the alarm is going off right now.
I would imagine it would be.
I believe it was, I think we got clear.
Yeah, cool.
So now I'm going to try to find Charles.
Not Charles Xavier, but just Charles.
Yeah, anyway, you were saying.
Not Charles Xavier.
That would be a different game.
But yeah, so it's you're infiltrating this group, trying to find your nephew.
You know, if you play your cards right, you may want to go confront the cult leaders.
There are scenarios where you may agree with what the cult leaders are doing and not think
they're so bad after all.
You know, when we hear about cults, we hear about, you know, the worst of them.
And groups that still would be described as a cult might, you know, not be dangerous.
You know, they might just really be earnest about whatever they're doing.
I've often joked that software companies are often like cults, particularly small ones,
or particularly ones that have a really strong leader at the center.
You know, that when that person shows up in the room, everyone quiets down and does what they say.
And that's kind of like, you know, what we would call a cult to be.
Yeah.
So it's an interesting sort of, obviously this is not a software company, you know,
it's a very different situation in a lot of ways, but whenever people would say,
have you had any experience with cults, I say, well not exactly, but yes, sort of.
Yeah, right on.
Um, what, um, uh, we talked about this, so you and I've had a couple conversations about this game.
Um, the first thing, Drew, we can loop back to is, um, I think what's striking about designing a systemic game around, uh, cults and cult compounds is, um, there's a direct inspiration of real life behavior, real life instances.
Uh, it's quickly comparable to Jonestown, um, uh, uh, and the tragedy that went down there in South America.
What was sort of your first instinct for systemizing the sort of the cult of like
the the central personality of the paranoia, the backstabbing, like what was sort of your
first instinct for taking that and making it playable? Yeah, the thing that, I mean there's
two things. Like I like the idea of a game that would...
have a narrative that was inherently different every time. It wasn't just your choices making
it different, but also just the story had different elements that you would have to
figure out, sort of like a murder, like a game, I often compare it to Clue, the board
game, you know, where, who did the murders different every time, and that's why you can
play it more than once. And so I just like the idea of exploring that. I don't think
the game is as replayable as Clue, but it's, you know, it's got some of those elements
to it.
So I've been fascinated by that.
And then looking at cults, you know, I've been fascinated by cults as a really interesting game topic
because it's a scary, dangerous place.
Like that note you just saw has some overtones of danger to it, you know,
that they're down in the, you know, how long was Chuck in the cage?
And that sort of thing.
It's an interesting place to set a game because I think people like to go to sort of taboo locations and explore them in the safe environment of a game.
But also because as I was sort of looking more at cults, it was interesting to me that they often start out with very altruistic intentions.
Like they're trying to improve society by building their own society.
Or they're trying to make something more equal.
Or their worried society is terrible in some way and they're going to finally...
You know, build the right version of society.
Or, you know, their people might have drug problems, or they might have other...
A lot of cults promise sort of self-improvement things.
So it was interesting to me that these groups that we think of as so bad can start out, you know,
in a really positive way, or at least so everybody thinks.
And then, by the time it has drifted into darker territory, people are too trapped to realize it even, let alone to leave.
So I just thought that was an interesting thing to explore, and then that dovetailed with the
how do you know if a cult is bad or not?
Because a lot of cult groups in the world won't end in a tragedy.
They'll just end in their people doing stuff until they run out of money, and then they'll go home or something like that.
Or they'll survive for decades, which happens as well.
Certain communes in the US are still going decades later.
So I just thought it was interesting to put you as a player into it.
Let you realize, like here you're talking to Charles, you know, why did he join the
group?
He has some pretty good reasons for wanting to join the group.
Pretty good reasons for not liking the US, or at least that's the intention that people
could, whether they agree with him, they can at least sympathize with why he's there.
And then make you think, you know, I like, I definitely like in all my media sort of
challenging expectations of what you expect.
To happen isn't necessarily what happens.
So often people think, oh, cult, they're going to be so crazy.
And then you get in, it's like, no, they're just people trying to do something
different and maybe it's going wrong and maybe it's not going wrong.
And you get to, to try to decide, you know, is it, is it, uh, as bad as, as
everyone in the outside world says it is.
Right on.
Um, uh, at Charles is talking about the Walkers, that is the two cult leaders who show up in
every run of the game that you make.
Um, the Walkers have kind of a top-down personality that informs your run, which is, um, uh, that
depending on what their moods are, and this one I can clearly specify because I've been
died a couple times in the scene, it seems like, um, the husband Walker is, uh,
pretty intent on getting apocalyptic with this.
Um, and, uh, um, uh, but his, but his wife, uh, I'm forgetting the first name.
I'm sorry.
Isaac and Rebecca, she's, she's made clear that, um, uh, she's a little nervous
about this and she doesn't want this to go down.
Um, could you break down from the top level, like where, how the, the procedural
design of this sort of works, um, and how like their transitions every time
change with the player experiences.
Yeah.
So, um,
You've laid it out pretty well so far, and I will say before going into that, that it's always interesting
when people are playing where they're like, I think this is happening because I saw this, you know,
I think I'm dealing with this version and and they're they're wrong as often as they're right,
particularly if they're just starting to play it. So
I feel good that it's like
slightly complex enough that people are not always guessing exactly what version they're dealing with each time.
But yeah, basically the the cult leaders
um
You know, the thing we change up is not their dogma.
So some people sort of expect, you know, when I say, oh, the story's different,
they expect like, well, this time it's a UFO cult.
And this time it's, uh, you know, some, some other wildly different thing.
It's like, well, no, they're basically always the same Christians with a
socialist message, um, thing that that's sort of inspired by some, some family
members who, who believe that sort of thing.
Um, and of mine, it's close to people's temple, right?
I mean, so the, uh, you know, obviously people's temple was an inspiration, but sort of one
of many and the, the cult leaders are, are pretty different than, than Jim Jones.
You know, by the time Jim Jones was in the jungle, he was, you know, he was no longer
a Christian really.
He was calling himself God and said the Bible was used to keep people down and stuff, which
is, you know, that's, I'm not going to say whether, you know, I agree with that statement
or not, but, uh, the, the walkers here.
The cult leader is here. Well, first of all, there's a man and a woman doing it, not just one guy.
But they're very much still Christians, and sort of interpreting the Bible, how they, you know,
how they see it leads to them building this compound in the jungle.
But like, the architecture and stuff like that is probably the closest to what you would expect out of a Jonestown.
Yeah, to get us back on topic, the architecture of the design was something I was asking about before.
If you're able to... Sorry, I'll get us back on track.
Yeah, no problem.
Yeah, so basically the cult leaders have a lot of the same dogma each time, but it's just how dangerous they are that we change up.
And it's not just they're both dangerous or both not, there's some differences beyond that.
So it's not just like...
to
what he said early on was something you could a lot of people could believe in.
seems sincere and seemed like it was addressing real problems in the world
and it's just he went too far with it but imagine another group where
he didn't go to these these too far uh reaches with it and and and really
brought the group in the the track leading to the tragedy
that that eventually that eventually happened um but you
could imagine someone having the same dogma not ending in tragedy and that's
sort of what we're doing here
Right on. So how do from the top down, how does that change? Like, how does the game sort of play out behind the scenes, like without giving away everything that was spoiled? Right, right. What's the what's the design? pin holding this whole thing together?
Yeah, so basically, once we've decided, you know, from from a collection of personality states that the game can start with for the cult leaders, then that impacts the game in a ton of different ways. So there's the voiceover that you're hearing over the PA system.
He won't talk to you until you get the alarm reset, by the way.
If you've got the permalarm going on because you've murdered too many people, you have to go reset it by hand.
Yes, if you can find an alarm box, you can go reset it now.
As long as that... uh oh. Yep, watch out.
But, what was I saying before we got into what you're doing on screen?
Oh, right, it manifests itself in a lot of different ways.
Like the voiceover you're hearing, that can change up in subtle ways
based on which version of the cult you're dealing with.
That can, you know, there's also those notes and documents you were finding.
Those can definitely change depending on which version of the cult you're dealing with that time.
Um, and then also the, uh...
Did you get it? Did you buy it?
I bought it.
Oh, yeah.
And since you've already been captured twice, it's all over.
So now we'll get to see how the restart works.
Anyway, so we change up the notes.
We change up the voiceover you hear on the PA system.
There's different scenes in the game that will change.
And it's not again, it's like there's there's always some dark elements to the cult.
where you'd say, oh, that looks really bad,
but maybe that's not as bad as another version of it that you might see.
And as, as you play it, the game is designed obviously to be played multiple times.
You see some of these differences and, uh, has a shorter play time for that reason.
I really hope that people play it like four or five times.
I feel is a pretty good, if you get four or five endings, you've,
you've experienced a lot of what, what is in there.
Obviously you can go on and try to be a completionist and collect even more
endings, but, um,
So we change up those things, that friendly character you saw earlier, Charles,
like he'll say different things based on which version of the cult you're dealing with.
And obviously the cult leaders themselves will say different things when they capture you,
or when you try to confront them later in the game.
Right on. Moving on down, we can talk about...
This is kind of a solo dev project, right? It's you, the voice actors,
and I assume you must have had some contracted help, right?
No, yeah, there were a bunch of people who worked on it.
Primarily in art, because I don't do art, so all the art you're seeing here was done by someone who is not me.
But I did the design and the writing and most of the gameplay programming.
I also had a couple of programmers doing the console versions and load-save system and stuff that was more technical.
But yeah, mostly I was the full-time guy on this for most of its development.
Yeah, let's talk about life as a solo developer because this is something our audience can relate to a lot because there's a lot of indie folks who write in.
How was it sort of like, how was your personal process for trying to wrangle your...
Your design intentions and also being the kind of the programmer who had to
figure out and implement them, right?
Cause it's one thing to go, Oh, here's a great idea for the F then clauses.
And then you dive into your own tools that you've made or you've borrowed or
gotten, uh, from the, from whatever tool store you're working with.
And then you're like, Oh no, this is, this is, uh, not what I intended.
Yeah. No, I hadn't programmed. I programmed games early on when I started in the industry.
And I sort of actually started with a project, a couple of projects very much like this,
where I was the lead programmer, lead designer, and leading the project. And then I went to work
at bigger projects where I mostly focused on design, but still did programming here and there.
And here getting back into doing programming was actually a lot of fun for me, just from a,
it's like a muscle I hadn't been using for a while that I enjoy.
I'm not someone who you want to have write your graphics engine or something like that.
But I think I'm persistent enough at the gameplay stuff.
Plus, there is a lot of advantage to being the designer as well,
where you can make those trade-offs.
I think as anyone who's done small projects know,
you don't have to spend as much time on documentation and meetings and stuff like that.
So the communication is a lot more seamless.
On the other hand...
You know, I did miss some of the push and pull and variety of ideas you get,
like collaborating with a programmer or something,
can definitely make things better in a lot of ways.
So I'm not discounting that or saying that's bad,
and would probably like to do that again in the future.
But for this one, it was just a very specific project that was very personal to me,
and I wanted to get my hands fully dirty on.
So it was fun to do.
It's definitely, I think,
I guess going back to having more of a team that's a team that's full-time there with you can really help with keeping the project balanced and helping prioritize things.
And of course everyone's going to have their own opinions on that, but then you discuss it and come to some sort of consensus and that can be very valuable.
So there are advantages in terms of communication to a small team and that you don't have to
communicate as much because you're right there, but you don't get the variety of viewpoints
and stuff that can be really cool on a larger project.
Right on.
My next question as I read this document, is there anything you've sort of like you
went into this project thinking this kind of design was going to work one way and then
it wound up working another way?
Do you have any examples of that you could point to?
Yeah, the biggest change probably from what I initially hoped for or thought of for the
game was it was less about the friendly characters who you meet at the beginning.
I think the early design, they didn't even exist.
It was going to be purely the voiceover and the notes and documents you found.
And there was just enough people who were saying, I wish I could talk to some of the
cult members.
that made me say, okay, we can add some cult members.
They're still fully voiced, so that sort of limited how many we could do,
just in terms of budget and stuff.
But we got enough of them in there that I think it provides a little flavor of who you're meeting in the group.
And we actually didn't add the conversation system that's in there was added really late,
where before when you went and talked to them, they would just sort of talk at you for a while,
and you weren't interacting with them.
Because I'm not a huge fan of conversation trees.
They're just kind of like making me press a bunch of buttons to read all the stuff sometimes.
But I decided in the end after getting feedback from some people that having them felt better
than not having them.
Having some control over what you're navigating in this conversation felt better than having
none, even if it's sort of fake control, if you know what I mean.
So that was a pretty big change from what we originally planned.
Yeah, let's dig into that.
You do a lot of great GDC panels about like sort of theoretical design, hypothetical design,
and tips for design.
So what do you think about dialog trees like?
Because it's a very commonly used mechanic.
As a designer, what do you think is their sort of strength?
Because you eventually just implement them, so there's some kind of strength.
What do you think are the strengths and weaknesses developers need to consider when creating
them?
Yeah, I mean, I think they're fundamentally...
Not as interesting as other mechanics that you can do because dialogue trees are basically
often and you can do more complex things with them than this. So I applaud those. But the most
basic implementation is, you know, here's four options. Press one of each one and you'll eventually
hear all this stuff, right? And it's just and it feels very canned. It doesn't feel like I can ask
them anything, you know, which is kind of what I want to do.
Like when you're wandering around this world right now as a player, you can go anywhere you want.
You can go to this building, you can go to this...
So there's just a ton of choices all the time about what you're doing.
On the conversation tree, we limit it down to like a pretty small number of choices.
And that's like less interesting to me, fundamentally.
But on the other hand, if you're having conversations with people, it's kind of the best thing we have right now.
And I think there are definitely conversation systems that have been done where that was more of a focus of the game, where they would have, you know, trust levels and like a wider swath of dialogue possibilities and more of a simulation element to the dialogue.
And that can be great, but was not something we had enough time.
But that can be a very time consuming thing to implement and not something we sort of had the time to do here.
So I think it's something to think about.
That I guess the takeaway I had why they ended up getting implemented was it just felt better than not having them.
Even though it is winnowing the choices down to this very small thing at that time, and it doesn't feel as robust as the rest of the gameplay in terms of, you know, choices per second that the player is making.
It's still choices and people still like them. So, you know, you do the thing people like, even if it's not like your best possible version of a feature.
I like choices per second as a phrase because it just feels like a speed, like how many
choices per second is the player making?
Oh no, there's a speed limit.
We have to limit the choices per second.
I've used that to talk about, you know, games that have really long cut scenes, like there's
zero choices per second going on during a cut scene off of right.
And that's...
You know, makes you not want to replay it as much because you're kind of watching the same thing or the same, you know, you're just not doing that much when you replay.
That was something we did in a patch actually that is coming out for the PlayStation version later this week but isn't up there yet so you're not seeing it in the Steam version and soon in the PlayStation version and the other console versions.
You can skip the dialogue on replays so you might come up to Teresa on another replay.
She's saying slightly different things, but maybe you just want to read the subtitle and go through it faster because you've done this before.
You now can do that in the newer, with the patch.
So that's an example of we implemented it, but we didn't implement the ability to skip.
It was on the wish list, and then a lot of people asked for it after we shipped.
So the option to skip is an interaction per second in a way as well.
Yeah, no, I think about that with games.
God, what was I just playing?
Oh yeah, Fire Emblem.
I'm playing Fire Emblem Three Houses and the choice to skip or not skip or like let, like
what am I observing?
What is this part?
Like am I getting anything by watching this full animated scene versus blazing through
the conversation getting the points?
The final prompt states that this is a game development transcript.
The dialogue was just so much like it was good. It was really good dialogue.
What I was like, I want to get back to hunting, jumping, climbing.
And skipping through it helped me get through it fast.
So the design implications are certainly, they're subtle.
If not, they're kind of quality of life, I guess.
Yeah, yeah.
I know.
And it's that trick where if, yeah, once you have a part of the game that you really like.
And then it shifts gears into what feels like you're just in another game.
You run that peril of either they want to get back to the first game,
or the new game you've put them in is the one they want to stick with.
And then when that ends, you're like, oh, but I like that other thing.
It is a sweet, there's a sweet science to figuring out,
you know, how to balance
how to balance those things so it doesn't feel like,
you know, two games grafted together or something.
We are coming up at our 30 minute mark.
We are, I should have mentioned a lot sooner, we are happy to take questions from folks
who are watching.
If there's anyone out there, feel free to give us a shout.
Richard, making games is hard, selling games is hard.
That should be, I said it like it's somehow profound, but it's...
Blindingly obvious, I think, to everyone who spends time in games.
How have you felt about communicating this game's existence to the world?
How have you felt? What do you think is done right?
What do you think you could have done differently?
I'm curious to know what your thoughts are about this.
Because this is a cool little game, and it's definitely just doing something different than what a lot of other games are doing out there.
But that's a lot of games.
Yeah, I mean, there's definitely a few things that...
It's among the like, well, we knew about this, but we didn't have time to get to it, that have come up.
Like the skipping dialogue thing, like that was on a wish list, but we hadn't done and then
enough people asked for it. Just like, great, let's do that.
And I think that's always the case that you've got your list of things and things that I thought
were like, oh, this is the first thing I should patch where totally nobody complains about it
at all. So, you know, we're not doing it. Definitely something we're focusing on is
Getting people's replays of the game to be more different every time to guarantee that,
and sort of the randomness, say for example in the dialogue that plays over the PA system,
right now it is random within the game you're playing, but if you start a new game it's only
random within that game. So if you played a game and died within five minutes and start a new game
there's a chance you might hear the same dialogue again pretty quickly and that sucks. So...
We've implemented a system where that won't happen anymore. That's a patch I'm sort of in testing right now and hoping to get out later this week.
That's one thing. There's definitely some stuff where I was so close to the controls on the game that they felt...
I mean, I sort of knew the controls weren't as good as I wanted and again, that was a thing on the feature list, but...
It was...
It's the person's first time experience with it is not what I hoped, often, with some of the control things, particularly firing the gun.
It's something that I think needs some work, so we've got that on the to-do list for a future patch as well.
So some control stuff, some of the repetitive stuff, and then maybe just, you know, we're looking at ways to like vary up some of the gameplay on repeat plays too, so it's a little bit more different than it is right now.
Right on, uh I think um uh I appreciate the way you're talking about, you know, like uh sometimes you just gotta um you just gotta
It's time to say go like uh, you gotta cut you can't work on it forever. Yeah, cut, beat and run
What was your thought process? Like this is kind of a producer brain question is what is your thought process for?
Um, this music's very nice by the way. Um, what is your thought process for?
Making sure you're not bogged down in those like on your that magical list and versus being able to look at something and say hey
This is great. We'll work on it after launch, but it's time to go or after a milestone or something
Yeah, I mean that's the million-dollar question right is how when is it done enough?
And I don't know that I have the perfect answer for that
I think you know when you have a bigger like the perfect answer for that at a bigger
company that has money to spend on things like that is doing a lot of usability testing
and doing it with people who can actually play the game for an extended amount of time.
Because some of the repetitiveness stuff is not something that people complained about
before we launched because most people who played it would play it for a couple of hours
and you don't really notice it.
It's when you get to the sixth or seventh hour or something and you're like, hey, why
am I hearing this again?
We have plenty of voiceover that you shouldn't be feeling that way,
but it's just making sure it happens.
So, like in a larger company that had budget for people to play it for 10 hours each or something,
that stuff would have come up and we could have addressed it.
But here we were, you know, having smaller resources, we did have people playing it,
but just not for that long period of time.
And that's just something, you know, next time I would definitely figure out
how to make sure that happens before shipping, just to catch some of those easy fixes.
that you can do to make things a lot better.
Richard, do you have any opinions on that?
Yeah, that's a good question for sure.
There's two types of replayability in this game in particular.
There's the narrative replayability and there's the core gameplay replayability.
And I think just having enough...
I think you have to have enough variety to the mechanics and the sort of challenge types that you face
that can lead to pretty good replayability, and that I think is something, again, we're going to be working on in the future.
So there's like, just having enough depth there and enough...
It's a combination of authored and random, depending on the nature of your game.
If your game is meant to be roguelike, you need to have enough variety to how it generates each time that you feel it.
And that's, again, something we're working on.
In terms of narrative, I feel like we probably do a better job at that,
other than those easy wins that I was just talking about, in terms of dialogue repeating when it shouldn't and stuff.
Things that are almost bugs, they're so annoying.
But, you know, in terms of replayability...
I think you have to have, when you're looking at a narrative,
you know, I like to say that in a lot of games that want you to replay for the narrative,
because you can make choices, get different endings,
often you're playing, you know, it's less common for games to have a story that changes every time as we do.
And so often you'll play the game once.
The way you want to play it, make the narrative choices you want to make,
and then the second time you'll basically play the game how you don't want to play it,
and you'll be, oh, you got captured again.
And you'll make the opposite of the choices you made before, which is kind of not as fun, I think.
But you want to see the content, so you do that.
Here we're actually changing the reason for you to make the choices,
so you'll actually see the different content because the world has changed,
and people have complimented the game for that.
for that type of replayability.
And I think having, you know, another thing that, you know, how the game presents narrative is not as...
how to say, it's not in a conventional way as much.
Like, you get little scenes like that one you just saw with Isaac capturing you, and that's...
not... you've been captured by an antagonist in a video game before,
and he talks to you, and then you get a chance to break out, and it's not like...
Oh my god, how is this narrative...
This is a very conventional, almost like a cutscene.
But a lot of the way the narrative is told in this game is just through the environmental storytelling and being in the world with these people, living their lives and hearing the PA and finding those documents and things.
This is what happens to me a lot when I get captured.
Yeah, it's you.
You're not super good at breaking out, sir.
The key is, let me tell you, the key here is to break out when he's not looking.
And now I'll tell you, this is the hardest one to break out of.
I'll give you some tips, we'll see if we can walk you through it.
Nah, it's fine, we gotta talk about it. The game is nice, but...
The key here is to, you really have to time it right. So once the guard comes up to talk to you, or look at you, he'll turn his back and that's the time to break out.
Then you gotta run up and get him right away from behind.
Keep spinning, spinning, spinning.
Yeah, don't do that. That's not gonna...
It's just gonna wear out your cardio, man.
There's no cardio in the game.
You were very close to putting a cardio system in, weren't you?
It was brought up a couple times.
And someone whose feedback I trusted was like,
nobody likes a sprint meter. Nobody.
You just put it in to annoy players.
I was like, eh, yeah, I kind of agree.
There is a version of this game that has a sprint meter that is okay.
It's just a choice we made not to do that.
Well it looks like meters, um...
Yeah?
Meters are weird, um, I probably should have killed that guy...
Um, whatever, I'm gonna put him in the cage, um...
There ya go.
Uh, uh, meters are...
What are the tools that you reach for as a designer when you're trying to create a...
Like, this is such a game that speaks to, like...
This is something that real people have done...
If you go watch, um, there's two great, uh...
You can either listen to some of their great podcasts like Last Podcast on the left, it's one of my favorites.
There's a Drunk History episode about the Children of Heaven, which is...
Children of God, not Children of Heaven. I'm getting all these cults mixed up in my head.
Children of God is a good one.
Real people have done this.
How do you think about simulating realistic sensations and experiences in games like this?
How do you...
Like, the sprint meter represents you get tired when you're running,
but sprint meters are there to annoy players.
You just said so.
Yeah, I mean, it's like a health bar is also an unrealistic thing,
but we've got one of those, right?
It's an approximation of a real life event, right?
Like a sprint meter is.
That's not exactly how cardio works, but it's close enough
that it feels like it.
It was just one of the ones we decided not to do.
And it's interesting that the game definitely has gamey
systems to it, like those sight cones you're seeing.
You can't see the health bar.
And some people really don't like that.
I've seen people say,
why can't the people see me in this case?
Why can't they do this other thing?
And I'm like, well, at the end of the day,
we made choices about
how realistic the game was going to be.
I think narratively, it feels pretty realistic to me.
This is really how you would
have a game.
Go about going into a cult versus if the game was a shooter or something, right?
And you would just murder everyone in the cult and then you'd find your nephew at the end, right?
But here that's impossible because in the real world that's also impossible, right?
Here if you get into a gunfight with three people you're in real trouble.
Whereas, uh, you know, in a shooter that would be something that happened every minute.
It's hard to incentivize.
Right, right. So here it's like we have meters and things that are a little gamey and that it's
why can't the guy see me past this point? Well, he can't. And some people can't get over and accept,
like some people would accept that in a game that was more like a cartoony setting or just a fantasy
setting or something like that. But in a game that's otherwise realistic, that feels dissonant
to them. To me, it doesn't. And some people, it certainly doesn't. So it's an interesting reaction
that I didn't expect to get quite as much as we did.
Interesting.
Tender and tender and tender and that's a body.
You found a body but I destroyed the alarm box. Hopefully that works out.
Okay. Yeah.
See, that's only each alarm box. So no one can set off that alarm box now, but
if they find another one, they can find another one. Why would they have more
than one alarm box? Yeah, right. People don't have more than one alarm system
in their house.
Yes, it's also a game like the way the alarm boxes is also a little gamey. And
it's certainly like there's
You know, I think for me, there's like a limit to how many vectors you can innovate on for sure.
And here we were putting it more in the trying to make the narrative replayable stuff.
Whereas a lot of the core gameplay here is like, Oh, I kind of remember this from Metal Gear, or I kind of remember this from Castle Wolfenstein, the very original Castle Wolfenstein.
That was a game I liked a lot a billion years ago.
Um, and still like, but.
It was just a choice to not innovate in that space, but we could have.
We could have said, well, we're trying to make the whole thing realistic,
so how would a really interesting health model work here, and what could we do with that?
And again, that would just have been, well, we're going to spend time on that
instead of spending time on making more narrative choices or something.
So usually we bias towards the narrative stuff when we came to those forks.
Right on. As I continue to migrate this world...
Um, Richard, let's talk about more fun game design things, I think.
Uh, let's talk about morality as a game design tool.
Um, we're all familiar with, I am a big fan of KOTOR, we're all a fan of light side and dark side bars.
Um, in this game, I had the option to, I was just mulling over the kill don't kill
of, uh, of what I was just dealing with.
Um, uh, I tend to play games like this less killy, I'm kind of of the opinion of a game.
If a game gives me the option to not kill, I am bound for the most part to do it.
I don't know quite why, it's not like a super great moral code.
I love shooting things in other games. If the game is only shooting and killing, I'm all about that.
I see my Apex Legends obsession.
But, uh, how is it you as a game designer, as your players have sorta, it's definitely made clear over the years, they want interesting games, they want interesting systems, they want to make tough moral choices.
What's your thought for designing them? There's like kind of a narrative component here, but I wouldn't mind holding off on narrative for a minute, because that has to do with character and relationships and stuff, and just talking about like systems and bars and meters and punishment, etc.
Yeah, well to me, you know, the...
I see the morality system as just hopelessly intertwined between narrative and gameplay
both.
And you can't really not talk about them both at the same time, to me, the way I think about
it.
And, you know, it's often like, you know, other games that are lovely but are different
than this one will have like a, you know, there's like a more of a wrist slap for every
bad thing you do, right?
And we definitely have, we definitely try to balance that here.
If you get captured, uh, you know, if you get shot, you get captured and then you
can break out and keep playing unless you have murdered a lot of people, in
which case they just kill you right away.
And that's a negative, that's a wrist slap for like a gameplay negative
for having made that choice, but it also makes a lot of sense, right?
That they wouldn't take a chance on you if you had not done that.
Whereas there are other.
You know, there's a, there's like, if you do non-lethal takedowns, people get back up again in this game.
Yeah.
Um, which is more, yeah.
Which is, go ahead.
That's an interesting one because like, for me, that system always frustrates me.
But you're right, it's very realistic.
Like when Metal Gear does it, I was like, oh, I guess this is realistic.
Right. And certainly there's other, like Dishonored I like a lot, but I believe in that game if you do a knockout on someone, they're out for the rest of the level, basically.
Yeah.
And again, that was just a case for me of...
Well, A, how does knocking someone out actually work?
You know, if you put a sleeper hold on someone, they're not asleep for that long.
Usually they usually wake up pretty quickly, like within a minute.
Um, it's like, doesn't put them into a blissful night slumber, right?
It's, it's, it's a different part of their brain.
Um, but so it made sense that they would get up again and I just wanted again to
have a.
benefit almost to taking the negative route there.
Whereas if you do, you know, actually break their neck and you take them down,
they're not going to get back up again.
And that might encourage you to break their neck. Cause you know,
often there is a raw mechanical benefit to doing terrible things,
but you're doing terrible things.
So then that makes it almost more of an interesting choice.
Like if the choice is like things always go badly, if I make negative choices,
then I guess I won't make negative choices. It has to be balanced of like.
There are some negative consequences to doing good things, and there are some positive consequences to doing good things.
And it's sort of tricky to decide.
You know, you have to decide as a player what you're willing to put up with
and how important, like, getting an ending where you haven't killed anyone is.
Yeah. In this game, I will assure viewers that it's quite difficult.
And that's another interesting thing is how how
The range of how difficult people find this game continues to fascinate me,
because some people will like, this game's too easy.
And that's always the case, that some people find it easy and some people find it too hard.
But I think it's worse in this game for, because of the nature of stealth mechanics, maybe.
And just like learning how the, if you figure out how the systems work really well,
it becomes a lot easier.
And if you just struggle with them, it stays hard, you know.
So there's a little bit more of a hump there than I wish there was.
So that may be something we look at in the future as well, in terms of like, slightly better tutorial for that stuff.
Yep, Richard, we're coming towards the end of our hour here, we've only got a little bit of time left with you.
I guess I'll just start off by asking, what's next for you as a game designer?
You've got a nice story, you've done some really cool games with companies, you've struck out on your own as an independent designer,
you've shipped a game that was kind of a passion project, what do you think is next for you on the horizon?
Yeah, that's a good question, that I do not have...
Um, perfect answer to, I'm sort of right now focused on these things that I wish
were in this game that aren't yet.
Um, we've got PAX coming up and the panel we're doing there and, um, things
sort of leading up after that.
And I, as I said, I see benefits to working on a large team that
I really liked and missed.
And, you know, working in your office by yourself can be really
isolating in a lot of ways, but can also be really rewarding because
it's more your personal thing.
So I see pluses and minuses and I can't say for sure which I'll do next.
It sort of depends what opportunities pop up.
But I'm definitely starting to think about that while right now just wishing I had finished
this patch already.
Yeah, and for those at home, we're just, as Scooby-Doo alluded to a couple times, we are
playing the PS4 version of the game, which is mostly just a, that was my own request
because it's how we can basically make the stream happen as we play these games on console.
The game is also on some other systems, Xbox, Switch, and PC, and Mac.
How do you feel about the Switch? We've been asking a lot of devs about it.
I mean, it's sort of... It's been a couple years now, so it's not quite as hot new,
but how do you feel about making games for the Switch?
Yeah, I mean, it's a delightful device.
I mean, my favorite thing about developing for the Switch is I can go play my game on the couch,
like literally play, which is the same thing that attracts a lot of people to it.
full featured modern console experience,
if a little less powerful than the other ones.
But, you know, when it's time to go do a play through there,
I can leave my desk and go relax somewhere while testing something.
So that's fun for as a developer.
You know, it's a it's a different system.
So it's like I'm definitely glad Nintendo didn't just make,
you know, a system that was exactly like their competitors.
And I think that's always good for the industry and Nintendo's.
I'm going to take us out a little early if you don't mind.
That's just fine.
Yeah.
Richard, if they've got questions for you about making games or about the great GDC
talks that you've been a part of, where should they ask them?
Yeah, so I'm on Twitter at RichardRouseIII, and you can come find me there.
I try to respond to as many people as possible, though it doesn't always happen, so you can
always hit me back.
Usually not in my DMs unless I already know you.
Sometimes the question is better there, that's fine too.
You can also, you know, the game has a website at paranoidproductions.com slash church.
We got a mailing list there.
There's also a Discord run by the game's publisher.
The game is published by Fellow Traveler, a lovely publisher of a variety of narrative indie games.
They have a Discord that you can find on their website.
So if you go to Fellow Traveler...
.games is their URL up on there, the community button and that'll take you to the discord.
And I try to get in there and answer. I'm not on there constantly.
Definitely had some really fun chats with fans and other developers on there. So come by there if you've got questions.
That's a good place for it.
Probably slightly better than Twitter, but Twitter is good too.
And you know those are the main places or you know come to a talk at GDC or just come up to me in the hall
at GDC if you happen to see me.
Right on. With that, I'm going to take us out.
If you're new to this channel, we'd appreciate it if you tossed the follow our way.
And if you are not new to this channel,
you know, you can join us at XRDC later this year if you're interested in VR content,
or if you are VR, AR, and beyond,
or if you're a game developer, please join us at the Game Developers Conference next year in March.
With that, have a good day everyone!
I'm glad you got to the pigs right at the end.
Yeah, I found the pigs.
One of my favorite things in the game.
They're very important.
Love the pigs.
Pigs are very important.
Bye, everybody.