Good afternoon, everyone, and welcome to Practical IP Law 301
for Indie Developers, Plain Scary Edition.
Before we get started, I just want to remind you,
this will be available in the vault like the previous two.
And please fill out your session evaluations afterwards.
I really appreciate the feedback.
My name is Chris Reed.
I am the founder at Chris Reed Law.
We're a boutique law firm that works with developers and game
industry professionals on a wide range of legal issues.
Before we get started, my co-counsel, Mr. Phoenix Wright,
would like to remind you that I am not your lawyer
and this is not legal advice.
When I did 101 and 201 in years past,
I kept underestimating how much time we would really need
to cover complex legal issues in detail.
Well, this year is IP, and that's as complex as they come.
So let's just, for safety's sake, about that much time.
And unfortunately, we only have enough time
for a game of PUBG, so let's get started.
My goal today is to teach indie developers how to protect and use their intellectual property.
What is intellectual property? It's real rights for intangible things.
That sounds abstract, so why should you care? Simple. Your game is IP.
For example, here are just some of the things in the game industry that are covered by IP.
So basically, everything.
To that end, we're going to cover the two big ones, copyright and trademark, for most
of this talk.
And then I'm going to spend a little bit of time on patents, trade secrets, and the right
of publicity, which sometimes come up for indies.
For each type of IP, I'm going to tell you what it is, how you can protect it, and when
and how you should enforce it, and how to avoid infringing it.
we're gonna start with copyright,
which is by far the most powerful
and important IP right for indies to understand.
I like to think of copyright as the pistol from Halo 1.
You get it instantly, it lasts almost forever,
it's useful in almost every situation,
and as you know if you played, it's massively overpowered.
So copyright will protect almost every individual aspect
of your game.
That means characters, code, art, music and sound assets,
animation, UI design, and writing.
All of these things are individually
protected by copyright.
And your completed game as a whole
is protected as an audiovisual work.
But there's one important exception for indies, and that is,
copyright does not protect abstract ideas.
And what that means for you is your game mechanics,
your idea, your theme.
That's why you can have a million match-three games.
It's why PUBG and Fortnite's Battle Royale mode can coexist.
If you need to protect your raw concept,
you want to use probably an NDA, like if you're, for example, pitching to somebody.
Because copyright is not going to do it.
What copyright will do is give you a host of exclusive and powerful rights.
The sole right to reproduce, to sell, distribute.
stream, and importantly, to make derivative works.
That means anything based off of your original content.
Sequels, prequels, DLC, merchandise of any sort,
adaptations to other medium.
So that sounds awesome, right?
How do we get some of that?
The basic rule, and if you remember one thing
about copyright, it should be this.
In the U.S. copyright, if you make it,
you own the copyright.
Period.
You do not need to register.
You do not need to file.
You own it instantly.
That's great if you're an artist.
But it's a problem for a game studio
because you don't want to have to have 10 people
with owning different pieces of copyright
that you have to get permission from to do anything,
like sell your game.
How do we solve this?
Contracts, contracts, contracts.
Written signed contracts are the single most important way
to guarantee the company's ownership over the copyright
and to effectively use and license it.
I went over a lot of these contracts in detail in 201,
but today we're just gonna cover
some of the specifics for copyright,
because
You cannot transfer the ownership of copyright without a signed, written agreement.
So, this is going to be important when we're gathering all the rights into the company
from people making the game.
Yes, the owners of the company, they need to sign contracts too.
It could be the operating agreement of the company.
It could be an invention assignment agreement.
But they need to do it.
all of the contractors and W2 employees, anyone who contributes to the game or material around
it, no matter how small, they should be signing a written agreement that provides that it's
work made for hire, that they're assigning that copyright to the company.
That means if you're an artist or someone working for a game studio, when you sign one
of these, you're saying, yes, my work is owned by the company, not by me.
Unless it's specified as a license, which does sometimes come up if, for example, you
have a musician and they're merely licensing the tracks to you.
That's fine.
But you need to know what the...
size of that licenses, what can you use it for.
In fact, while we're talking about licenses,
you should also note that if you're gonna use things
from the Unity Asset Store,
or if you are using open source software,
these things might be free for you,
but it doesn't mean they're not protected by copyright.
They're almost certainly subject to a license.
So you need to know what the terms of that are,
so that you know what you're allowed to use it for
and what you're not.
When you are using the rights you have and licensing them out,
your company is licensing the rights out,
you also need to pay attention to contracts.
So if your studio is doing a development agreement
where you're making a game for a client,
You don't want them to own everything.
They may own the completed game, but they shouldn't own
your core code libraries, your engine.
These sorts of things are things you want your company
to maintain copyright ownership over.
So instead, that contract should specify that these
developer tools are merely licensed to your client so
that you can use them in future projects.
If you're going to do a publishing agreement, that means that you're licensing one of those
cool rights to distribute and sell to a publisher.
But there's a lot of special settings that you need to think about.
Is that license forever?
Is it limited in time?
Is it exclusive?
Does it cover worldwide?
What platforms does it cover?
Are they involved in things like derivative works
and merchandise?
Are they involved in sequels?
Is there any chance, based on this agreement,
that you might actually end up assigning your copyright?
All of these things are important,
and you need to pay attention.
But no contract, no matter how good,
is going to enforce itself and stop people
from infringing copyright.
Copyright infringement is when someone uses your stuff
without your permission.
It comes in the obvious bad form of people stealing your assets and using them,
pirating your game directly,
and some forms of cloning might also be copyright infringement.
But there's a lot of things that go on with
your content that most developers are pretty okay with.
So things like machinima, streaming, fan art, let's play videos.
Most indie devs are great about this stuff. They like it.
So how do we make sure that we can allow that while stopping the bad stuff?
Well, good news.
Copyright gives you a very powerful and arbitrary right
to drop the hammer whenever.
and wherever you want.
So you can selectively stop just the stuff you want to stop.
For example, if someone is streaming your game
and that's awesome, and then you decide
maybe it's not so awesome,
then you can specifically enforce against just that person
and let everyone else keep going.
That's very helpful.
How do we do this enforcement?
Well, first off, a preventative measure.
Register your copyright.
I know, I said you don't have to do that to own it,
and that's true, but it's useful.
It is cheap, about $65.
It's fast.
You can do it online.
And when you do it, it upgrades your rights, especially
if you ever need to sue.
It means you can sue for ridiculous amounts of money.
And that is a very potent threat.
So do it within three months of launching your game
for the maximum coverage, or afterwards, as soon as you can.
And then we need to think about.
when people are actually infringing.
What do we do?
Well, the first step could be to decide,
hey, maybe what they're doing is okay
as long as I can control it.
And that means you might offer them a license.
Look, you can use this material,
but only under these certain terms.
It's on your terms.
But if you just wanna stop them,
the first step would be to send a cease and desist letter.
That's a formal letter that says,
look, you're infringing the following things.
You need to stop or else.
The next step would be to get that content pulled.
You might send a DMCA takedown notice to the content hosts,
so YouTube or Steam.
These companies take it very seriously.
They will comply almost immediately,
and they will pull that content.
It's a very potent tool to send a message.
And the final step, if you really are still
having a dispute, is to sue.
This is expensive, especially for indies.
It's gonna be thousands, if not tens of thousands of dollars
to prosecute a federal trademark,
or a federal, well, trademark case as well,
but a copyright lawsuit.
So it has to be worth it.
But the damages you can ask for are enormous.
So it is a potent and scary threat,
which is why you need to avoid infringing
other people's copyright.
So I know it's nice to use other things to reference things,
but let's talk about a couple ways you can be relatively safe.
First off, we said that the same idea or mechanic is not protectable.
So go for it.
Feel free to be inspired by other people's mechanics that you see.
Anything that's really just generic is not specific enough to be protected by copyright.
So having giant swords in your game or huge shoulder pad armor, I mean,
that's not going to be protected by copyright.
There's the public domain, which means anything that never had copyright protection
or has already fallen out of copyright protection.
Basically, it means old stuff.
Mythology, Alice in Wonderland, these are great sources of material because anyone is
free to use them.
And then of course we have Fair Use, which you all know about, of course, from arguing
about it on the internet.
There is a core rule that I have for fair use.
Just because it's cool doesn't mean it's fair use.
Fair use is what we lawyers call an affirmative defense
to copyright infringement.
That means three things for you.
One, you're only gonna get to raise it
if you're already standing in court,
and that means you've spent a ton of money.
Two, you have to admit that you committed copyright infringement,
which you might not want to do, especially if you end up losing.
And three, you don't know if you're going to lose
because every case is decided differently
based on four factors by a judge.
It's case by case, and there is absolutely no way to be certain.
Do not buy into the myth.
that there are specific easy buckets you can fit into and you're totally safe.
Oh, it's parody.
No, that's not always a safe bet.
Don't buy the myths.
And finally, I know that was a lot.
Let's sum it up.
It protects almost all of your content.
But you want to show that ownership and gather it using contracts,
license your copyright using contracts.
Your enforcement ability is powerful,
and you can be selective, but you need to respect it,
and don't get cute using other people's stuff.
Let's move on to the second big area of IP
that I think is relevant for indie developers,
and that is trademarks.
Trademarks protect game and company names, logos,
and slogans.
It is the power of your brand in the minds of consumers
when connected with the goods and services that you sell,
but not when connected with unrelated goods.
I mean, unless you also sell bungee cords.
So trademarks give you the right to stop other people
from using the same or a similar mark, name, logo
for the same kind of goods.
This is pretty important because you don't wanna have
to change the name of your game at the last minute.
Air Brigade.
You also don't want to have to spend a lot of money
if you have it to buy the rights to a game
that was already there when you didn't notice.
This is because trademark law.
is based on first come, first serve.
We call this priority.
It means whoever gets trademark rights first
is able to stop anyone who comes afterwards
from using that name or that logo
for the same kind of goods.
How do we get that?
You sell your game.
If you remember one thing about trademarks, it's this.
You have no trademark rights until you sell your game.
That means that there's a lot of cool stuff you might do
that doesn't count as selling your game
and it doesn't give you any trademark rights.
For instance, registering social media accounts
or website domains.
running a dev blog where you talk about it,
having a hugely successful Kickstarter,
being reviewed glowingly in the press,
having a big closed beta.
None of these things count as selling your game.
None of these things give you trademark rights.
Maybe early access, but it's not exactly clear,
so I wouldn't rely on it.
So wow, that means there is a lot of time
when you're working hard on your game during development
and you've got no guarantee of your trademark rights.
If only there were a way we could call dibs.
That is what
filing a trademark registration will let you do.
It reserves that priority date from the moment you file the registration.
You still have to sell your game eventually.
That's when you get your rights, but it lets you reserve the date.
So to be clear...
If you haven't registered and someone sells a game for the first time three days before
you launch, you're out of luck if they're using the same name as you.
They beat you.
If you've registered months before, you beat them.
So how do we do this registration?
we go to the Patent and Trademark Office,
where you have to file an application.
It lets you reserve those rights for up to three years,
though you have to pay a fee every six months
and keep filing.
It is still not going to be final rights
until you sell that game.
So you do have to launch eventually, it's not forever.
The process will cost you around $1,500.
It's strongly recommended you use an attorney
to navigate the system.
Once you get the registration though,
it gives you some neat benefits.
Obviously, it's let us reserve that priority date.
So anyone who came after when we filed,
they're out of luck.
But the rights you do get are upgraded
from just normal trademark rights.
They're gonna be much stronger
if you ever need to sue someone.
It's much harder for other people.
to contest your trademark.
And that means that, yes, it's still worth
registering your trademark even after launch.
If you're seeing this now and you think,
oh, I didn't register before,
it's still worth it for the upgrade in rights.
And finally, of course, it lets you use
the cool R in the circle symbol,
which everyone loves that.
You can have a couple of things to consider during registration,
especially on a limited indie budget.
If you can only pick one thing to register,
I would go with your game name, especially early on.
Why?
Because that's your brand.
That's what it's more likely someone's going to beat you out to.
Later on, you can register your studio if you want.
You also have to choose, if you're only doing one,
between a word mark, which is plain text, or a design mark, which is like a logo.
The wordmark is almost always broader protection.
So start with that if you can only register one thing.
And besides, your logo may change over time.
But I know indies are usually strapped for cash.
At a bare minimum, if you don't register,
here's what you should do.
Google early, Google often.
Search the Patent and Trademark Database.
These things are free.
It's not going to guarantee that the name is definitely available.
There might be something you didn't find,
but it will certainly help you avoid obvious pitfalls.
Also, you can use the TM symbol.
Unlike the R in the circle, which you must be registered to use,
the TM symbol, anyone can use it.
It doesn't really have any legal force,
but it acts like a no-trespassing sign.
It lets the world know, hey, we intend to protect this name.
And that can keep people away in a practical sense.
Ideally, though, just register your mark as soon as you can
if the name is important.
And also.
protect against infringement.
Once you have those rights,
you need to stop trademark infringement.
What is trademark infringement?
It's when people use the same name or logo
or something confusingly similar,
doesn't have to be identical,
to sell the same kind of goods or services.
And before you get clever about it,
I'm really sorry, but trademark law is a...
filthy casual. It does not understand the difference between genres, meaning all
video games are the same product as far as trademark protection is concerned. So
if anyone is using the same name or a similar name as you are to sell a video
game of any kind, that's a problem. How do we do this enforcement? Well, we've got
some preventative measures. Register your trademark, as we said. That's helpful.
Puts people on notice.
When you need to stop someone or deal with infringement that's out there, you've got
a couple of steps.
First off, consider whether what they're doing is okay with you as long as you control it.
Similar to copyright, you can offer a license for them to use.
Use it on your terms.
That counts as enforcement.
You can send a cease and desist letter, just like with
copyright, to tell them to stop.
And you can send a takedown request to the content hosts.
Now, this won't technically be a DMCA notice, but most of
these companies also have trademark policies in place,
and they will respect trademark claims as well.
And finally, of course, you can sue.
It's still very expensive to sue for trademark infringement.
But if your rights are registered, you're in a very
strong position, and you're likely to win.
And I should note, you can enforce your rights
even if they're not registered.
So if you've started selling your game,
you have trademark rights in that name.
They're called common law rights.
The registration upgrades them
and makes it better if you have to sue,
but you can enforce either way and you should
because trademark law says that
if you don't enforce your marks over time,
the protection that they give you narrows and could disappear.
Unlike copyright.
Copyright, you can sit on your copyright for 10 years
and do nothing and one day just enforce against one person.
With trademark, it shrinks over time,
can eventually disappear, you must enforce.
It doesn't mean you have to be a total jerk to everyone,
it just means you need to notice who's infringing
and you need to ask them to stop.
You need to maybe offer them a license.
And of course, you want to avoid infringing other people's
trademarks.
First step is easy.
Before you use a name, Google.
It's not that hard.
Make sure there clearly isn't someone already using this
name for a game.
As far as using trademarks deliberately, maybe you want
to reference someone, do an homage, whatever.
Just get permission.
Don't assume that they're OK with your use.
Yes, you can use people's trademarks in a comparative sense,
but if they don't like what you did,
they might decide that they wanna challenge it in court,
and nothing stops them from suing you.
That's an argument you're gonna make in court,
just like fair use.
That's expensive argument to have.
The safest, don't use it.
Without permission, if you're really gonna ignore me
and do it, at least put clear disclaimers
that say we don't own this, we're not endorsed by them,
we're not associated with them.
So to sum up trademarks, you should plan and search ahead
so that you know that name is available,
because you have no rights until you sell your game.
You can reserve that priority ahead of time by registering,
and you absolutely should.
And you need to enforce your rights to keep them strong.
So those are the two big ones.
Now let's cover a couple types of IP
that occasionally come up for indies,
but aren't nearly as relevant.
First, we're gonna start with patents.
Patents are a type of IP that protect novel, useful, and non-obvious inventions.
You can only get a patent by successfully applying to the Patent and Trademark Office.
It's going to cost you around $20,000 probably.
It takes about two to three years.
And when you eventually get it, you get 20 years of protection, but that protection's
really specific and narrow, and it might be really easy for people to design around it.
There are certainly examples of patents in the game industry.
Some kind of business methods, like monetization strategies,
certain parts of software algorithms might be patentable,
and of course, famously, some game mechanics
have been patented.
But, and of course, also Rock Band Guitar,
novel hardware interfaces, these things
can all be the subjects of patents.
But, first off, it's usually big companies that have them because of the cost, and you
don't know that they've actually been that helpful in enforcing.
So, for indies, is it worth it?
Nope.
It's just too much money and effort for not enough guaranteed protection.
Your time and your money are better spent elsewhere.
So let's move on to trade secrets, which are easily
the coolest sounding type of IP.
Trade secrets are any information
that you can keep secret and that
gives you a competitive advantage because you
kept it secret.
It's your special sauce.
So things in the game industry like customer mailing lists,
game design documents, a marketing strategy,
in-app pricing models, that sort of thing.
If you protect them, then the law
will let you sue someone who misappropriates them
without your permission.
How do we get that protection?
That's easy, you listen to Gandalf.
I mean, that's just good life advice in general,
but specifically that means you need to make
reasonable efforts to keep the information secret.
And you show this by limiting access to who can see it,
using technical security precautions,
you know, encrypted email,
don't just leave printouts lying around,
and by showing that you have contracts, i.e. NDAs,
with people before they get access to it.
That's how you keep your trade secrets safe.
But you also need to be careful about not being exposed
to other people's trade secrets.
It sounds great to learn what your competitors are doing,
but if an employee or a new contractor
tells you trade secrets from a previous job
and they don't have permission to do that,
they've dragged you into a fight.
You're now liable for misappropriation of trade secrets.
You don't want to hear that.
So you tell them not to share it.
You don't look at it if they try to share it.
And you have a contract in place that makes sure that
they are obligated not to share these things if they
don't have permission.
Finally, we have the right of publicity.
This is a right that individuals all
have in the commercial use of their name or their likeness.
In the game industry, we have some famous examples.
NCAA student athletes sued EA for their use of their name
in some of the sports games.
Lindsay Lohan sued Rockstar for the alleged use of her likeness
in some marketing materials.
It's also a messy kind of right because it's different in every state, it's different in
every country, so you don't know exactly what's going to apply.
And that's all the more reason why the core rule is simple, just get permission or don't
reference people, don't use their name, don't use their image.
Because while it's true that you can use a public figure's name or likeness for
newsworthy purposes or for historical purposes,
that's one of those arguments
you're gonna be making in court.
And that's right, you spent a lot of money.
And guess who's gonna have a lot more money
and a lot more lawyers than you?
The celebrity.
If they wanna sue, they will.
So if you absolutely feel that you must
be parodying a public figure,
You know that you're taking a risk,
and make sure that your reference to them
is as far away as possible,
so that you can plead deniability.
And never, ever admit in writing or out loud
that that's what you're doing.
That is a surefire way to lose a lawsuit
if they want to bring it.
Maybe just stick to original characters.
And that's it, we made it.
So, are you scared?
You don't have to be.
Remember, your product is IP.
The rights are powerful, but they're complex.
That means you need to gather the ownership with contracts
and protect it with registration,
and use those contracts to license those rights,
and remember that your rights don't enforce themselves.
You have to be vigilant and diligent about enforcing.
And that's the end.
I wanna thank my paralegal for all his hard work.
And please, please fill out your session evaluations.
I really, really appreciate the feedback.
Now I am happy to take some questions
as long as every single one is not about fair use.
Thanks.
Thank you.
I really enjoyed it as a fellow lawyer.
I learned a lot of good things.
Thankfully, we were doing things correctly.
I just didn't understand the technicalities.
But my question to you is, can you have trade secrets sort of
in something that doesn't belong to you?
Like if I'm working within Sony's hardware, my company
makes themes, and we do things that other people don't.
Can I have trade secrets when that software maybe doesn't
belong to me?
So are you asking if you personally, so you're asking...
Can our company protect our sort of techniques via trade secrets?
If they're in other people's material because you're working for them.
Yes.
interesting. Yes. In fact, that's that's one of those places where you want to protect trade secrets. Right. And
that's going to be taken care of in the contract. That might actually get lumped in when I said the developer
tools were important. Right. If you do work for someone else. I was talking about copyright there. But oftentimes
that clause in a contract.
will cover more than just copyright.
You kind of broadly define any of our special things,
proprietary techniques, we do not assign ownership
over them, and you make sure that later in that contract
there's probably confidentiality, so it says,
look, we're gonna use some of our special trade
secret techniques, you can't disclose them
and you don't own them, but you have a license
to use them inside this product that we're making for you.
So if I'm working with a larger company that has their own
sort of terrifying giant contract, is this something
that I need to insist that we just have in there?
Because there have been some people that have tried to
sneakily be like, we need this code.
And usually we've gotten around it like, no, you can
just have the package.
I think it's probably a good idea.
So there's the practical world and the legal world, right?
Practically, not giving them the code is a good way
for them not to steal it.
Legally, you're basically giving yourself a right,
A, you're scaring them by saying,
hey, you're promising in writing, you can't disclose this.
So that's a good idea to say you can have it,
but you need, if they don't already have that feature,
then maybe have an NDA specifically for it.
But also, it gives you recourse.
If they do end up stealing it, you can at least sue,
you can ask for an injunction, yeah.
Thank you.
Yeah, no problem.
So in order to enforce trademark,
you have to have sold the game.
Does it matter?
Is there a certain number of copies?
Or can you just have one copy sold with a receipt?
So you're asking, in order to get your trademark protection,
does it matter how many copies you sell?
Or can it just be one?
If you are truly selling it, and you've released it,
and it's out on Steam, then from the moment of the first copy,
that's when you get your rights.
Your rights are dated as of that.
If you haven't registered, those rights are going to be what are called common law rights.
So the more you sell, the more powerful your brand, the better the enforcement ability.
If what you're asking is, hey, I really want to reserve the date, can I just like sell
a copy to my friend?
No, no, it has to be like a...
Trademark law definitely does not let you do that,
and they know that people try to do that,
and there's all sorts of case law about not being,
that's why I said that early access is kind of a maybe,
like if it's early access where the game's basically done
and you're selling a finished copy,
and maybe you'll make some tweaks.
that you have a good argument.
If it's like a really early unstable alpha or beta
and it's totally gonna change,
they're not gonna see that as selling the game.
Right, so it just has to be on a store
where they're freaking ordering it.
Yeah, yeah, it has to be launched, yeah, available.
And also, by the way, it can be free.
I said sell, but it needs to be just available
in the normal channels of trade, whatever that means.
So if it's free on GOG or whatever,
as long as it's out and it's finished
and you're distributing it in the same place
that you would normally sell,
if the price is zero, that's okay.
Okay.
Thank you.
Yeah, no problem.
Hello.
I had a question about submitting a copyright
claim for your game.
So when you're doing that.
To the copyright office?
Yes, that's correct.
How much material do you have to submit to them?
So do you need to provide your entire code base and all
your art assets?
So this is why we often, even though I
say it's fairly straightforward, a lot of clients
end up doing it with us just to avoid the headache.
They do have instructions on there.
I think with the code, they want the first.
I want to say first 20 and last 20 of the source code.
And by the way, linking it up to trade secrets, they
actually have a thing where they say, look, if your code
involves what you consider trade secrets, you can redact
those portions.
And they've got pretty good instructions.
It's just not fun to read through them all.
Thank you.
Oh, and by the way, a pro tip.
If you're submitting the finished game along with art
assets and the code and all that, it's a pretty good idea
to also submit some footage of gameplay.
This has come up in some cases where judges do not
understand video games.
So you need there to be stuff for them to look at.
So the fact that the registration had some gameplay,
the judge was able to look at it and say, oh, I see.
This looks pretty similar to this.
So it's not a bad idea to put like 30 seconds of core
gameplay in there.
Just doesn't hurt.
Thank you.
Hi, Chris.
Hey, how you doing?
Nice to see you again.
So a quick question, or hopefully quick question,
regarding
the protection of trademark abroad as far as different countries and also potentially
different languages, especially if you have a title that doesn't necessarily transliterate
into other languages and just let you go with that.
Okay, so two questions.
One, what do you do about...
protecting your trademark in other jurisdictions, and two,
what if your title doesn't really translate into the
other language in a meaningful way.
So first off, I should just make doubly clear that this
presentation is based mostly on US law.
I mean, there's some general principles that are good.
I mean, contracts are always good.
But especially the IP law is country by country.
you can use a trademark registration in the US
or in another country as the basis
for grabbing that priority date
and applying it to other countries.
Now, that gets expensive.
You have to find attorney counsel
in every individual jurisdiction to do it for you,
but there is a treaty that allows for a process
where you can kind of use it to apply elsewhere.
I mean, you're not gonna do it
unless you really think you're gonna be launching
in those places.
As far as translation, I'm not sure how it works in all the many other jurisdictions,
but in the US we have a principle that basically says if the name of your game is totally fine
except that it means something else in a foreign language, and if you translated it, it would
totally be infringing something that already exists, right?
It's a foreign word and there's nothing in the database with that name except that it
means something and there's definitely someone there.
They actually have a principle that generally they will assume that it infringes.
They assume that people would stop and translate, because I guess they assume everyone speaks
every language.
But that's just, yeah.
So there's a lot more detail there, but that's...
Great.
Thanks.
Yep.
Thank you.
Hello.
Hello. I don't have all the right terms, so I hope I can get this across.
Sure. No problem.
The Trademark Office rejected our request because they said the name was too close to a general term.
Yes. But there was some secondary list that we were able to get on.
And I'm wondering what the difference in protection is.
Yeah. And secondly, can we use the R because we're on the secondary list?
Yeah.
I don't believe you can use the R in the secondary register.
This is, you got a rejection, and I didn't have time to go into this, but you shouldn't,
you can't infringe on other people's existing rights, but you also have to have a name that's
not what they call generic or descriptive.
So if your game is too descriptive, or the title is too descriptive of what the goods
are like, if Apple were a...
you know, fruit, apple company,
that would be, they would probably reject that trademark.
You can say, look, we still want to use it,
we know we can't get protection now,
they put you in a secondary list,
and you can come back in a number of years
and say, look, we've been so successful
that even though it initially was generic,
people have really started to associate
and you'd have to prove it with all this stuff.
I'm not 100% I'll look, but I don't believe
you can use the registered symbol for the secondary register.
And the difference in level of protection,
I mean is there less protection if you're on a secondary list?
Yeah, I mean it's not a registered trademark.
It's something that you're basically,
you're there so that you can come back later
and prove that you've acquired distinctiveness.
So you're just alerting people that you're using it basically.
What's that?
You're just alerting people that you're using it?
Yeah, and you're planting a flag
so that you can upgrade it later
with the Patent and Trademark Office.
Thank you.
Yeah, no problem.
And I think we're done.
Thank you so much.
I've got time in the overflow room if you want.
Thank you.