Buried deep under these bone-dry high plains, in a covert section of a massively hardened
centrifuge facility, a team is hard at work.
They are members of a breakaway faction of the country's security forces, and they are
busy enriching 40 kilograms of uranium.
By July 3rd, they achieved their target of 90% enrichment.
and then transfer the uranium to a nearby secret lab,
where another team of technicians assembles it into a crude nuclear block.
On August 31, they finished their work.
They put the bomb in a packing crate labeled agricultural equipment
and transported to a nearby airfield where it is stored in a warehouse.
Two weeks later, it is removed and loaded onto an aircraft
with civilian air cargo runners.
It flies to Dubai, where the crate is transferred.
along with other goods and equipment, to a global air transport freighter.
Destination? Washington, D.C.
The plane lands at Washington's Dulles International Airport at 2 47 a.m.
on September the 15th. By late afternoon,
the crate is delivered to a warehouse in the southeast part of the district.
Then, before daybreak on September the 17th,
the bomb is removed from the crate
and loaded onto a delivery truck.
Several hours later, an American citizen
eases the truck out into traffic.
She drives it to a location on Pennsylvania Avenue,
midway between the White House and the Capitol Building.
At 1109 AM, she stops in the middle of traffic.
climbs down onto the street and triggers the detonator.
The bomb explodes with a power of 15 kilotons.
There are more than 80,000 instant deaths,
including the President, the Vice President,
the Speaker of the House, and the 320 members of Congress
present when the bomb goes off.
There are also...
Okay, maybe that wasn't quite what you expected.
I would like to tell you all a story.
This story, I think, kind of encapsulates my experience
over the past four years as a person who
spent about 25 years making commercial games
and then entered what we might call the games for change
or serious game world.
And what would happen is pretty often
I'd be called into some meeting somewhere with people
I've never heard of and introduced as, you know,
that game guy.
And one day, a little over a year ago, I got called into just such a meeting and it was with
these folks. Some of whom I had heard of and a couple of them I hadn't. I thought, okay,
that's fine. They seemed friendly. A couple of them had interesting accents. And so let's
talk. And they introduced themselves and they were all experts in nuclear security issues.
And they said, can you make us a game?
And I said, actually, this problem's already solved.
There is a game.
It's called Defcon, right?
Haven't you seen it?
This game is excellent.
And they're like, no, no, no.
We know that game.
Actually, yeah, you're right.
It's a really good game.
And it's totally, actually, not what we're looking for.
And in fact, Defcon's kind of an example of the problem, not
the solution.
And I thought, well, that's odd.
I was a child of the Cold War.
And I remembered what this was like.
missile command, right?
They said, no, no, no, it's different now.
That was scary and we honor your fear, but actually it's worse now.
Since especially the collapse of the Soviet Union,
there is a tremendous amount of fissionable material
kind of out there, and a lot of it we don't actually know where it is.
And there's a lot of people that would like to have it and might
do all kinds of really bad things with it. Did you know
that? I said I did not know that. You know, okay, let's try.
And so we did a little workshop and I always started these
workshops with some kind of a, okay, this is game design thing
in about 30 minutes so let's make it 30 seconds because game
design is easy, right? And it goes something like games are
loops, the loops have.
a state, and then you take an action,
that action has an effect.
I know there's a certain group of students here
who have seen all this before.
The systems that we implemented have affordances,
actions, and feedbacks, and then we have verbs
that affect the system.
Right, cool, we're done, let's go make a game.
And, except, okay, it's a little harder than that,
but we'll get back to that in a second.
We broke into a couple of groups, these experts and I,
and they decided to put together some game ideas.
you know, helping them through their ideas, getting the verbs, getting the loops, getting
the state. And the winning pitch, we actually had them pitch to our group at Glass Lab,
which is where I was working at the time. Winning a pitch was something called Trinity.
Okay, obviously named after the original Manhattan Project. And their pitch was, the only way
to prove a point is to prove the point. It goes a little something like this, you're
someone with a lot of money. Let's say you're a...
really pissed off Silicon Valley entrepreneur and you're really
upset that no one is taking the nuclear threat seriously. I know
how to solve this. I will put together a bomb and I'll explode
it but not on Pennsylvania Avenue. I'll explode it just a
few miles off the coast of D.C. That should get everyone's
attention. And it turns out you can do this if you have enough
money. Today.
And they pitched that to us and they walked us through the
process of how you would do it and how you could turn that into
sort of a, oh, I don't know, point and click adventure? It
could be really interesting, right? And we said, actually,
holy shit. And kind of nobody talked to each other for the
rest of the day. And that concluded one of the strangest
days of my life. And that story inspired me to pitch this talk.
Because as a person coming from the games world...
from the commercial games world, I was inspired.
And I obviously was already doing this.
But I was really thinking, man, more people
should get involved with this.
More people should know that there
are things that we are being asked to look into.
So let's talk more about that.
This was kind of what was interesting.
Usually when I talk to this with, let's say,
government officials or educators,
they kind of go like, OK, yep, games, yep, we know that.
There's a story, or you click on stuff,
or definitely you shoot people in the face.
But they didn't really have a good sense of it.
But this group actually had a far better sense of it.
They understood it really quickly,
and I thought that's interesting.
And I had to think about that much later.
And really, if you think about this,
if we define games as verbs acting on a system,
this is what it means to be an activist.
They said, right.
The current state is what we don't like.
The system is what we know affects it.
The verbs are the change we're trying to create.
Got it.
So I thought, that's really cool.
And then it makes me think, a lot of you in this room
also get that.
And maybe this medium is even better suited
than we would think for this kind of action.
Now, when they do pitch something to me,
it usually came down to this, engagement, right?
Engagement.
We know that people play games for hours and hours and hours.
And we want all that eyeballs.
Yeah, OK.
It's true.
I don't think it's the best argument.
Another is we know that we reach a very, very large proportion
of the market, especially young people.
Also true.
Also, in my view, not the best reason
that games are well-suited to this.
Video games can be surprisingly subversive.
I don't know if anyone has played any of the work of Paolo
Pedrucini or Mo Industria.
It's incredibly subversive stuff and fantastic and really
makes you think in a way that just some sort of video or
linear media kind of can't.
And there's more.
Generally speaking, when we communicate with each other,
we use stories.
Stories are powerful.
Stories are how we remember things or how we communicate
with one another.
But they have a problem.
And that is stories are reductive.
A narrative of a thing tells you only one way that thing can be or how it happened.
I like to think of it as the most effective form of data compression in the world.
And when you have a situation of complexity, the story can only show us one aspect of that
complexity.
If the story says, well, that's complicated,
then that's also called a bad story.
Games, however, are different.
Games operate in complexity.
It is the complexity of games that makes them special.
It's that area of complexity that
makes games a new medium that is unlike any that came before.
But it's hard.
Setting up these systems is hard.
And when people have tried to do this,
and we've played maybe some of these attempts,
they often go awry.
And this is why I was in the room that day,
because I'm this person who has done it before.
Really, game design is not a 30-minute activity.
It's probably not a 30-second activity.
It's a 10,000-hour activity.
Which means that if we're going to do this effectively, it needs to be people that have
done it for those 10,000 hours. And the smart people are learning that who they want to
talk to is you. And some of them actually are in the audience today. I know because
they've been talking to me over the last three days. So what do I think is the outcome of
all this? Well, some of us remember this. This is the consumerist...
worst company in America? This would be the year that EA actually dropped off the chart.
You got a very favorable matchup. But what was interesting about 2014 was not this corner,
actually, it was this corner. I saw that and I went, SeaWorld, that's weird. That's family
entertainment. Why would they be in the worst company of America list? Why did they almost
win? I mean, Comcast, that's not fair. But they almost won.
And of course, the reason they almost won was this.
It was a movie, a documentary film called Blackfish.
It was a story.
It was a story of a particular killer whale named Tilikum.
And by the way, Tilikum is dying.
For those that saw this, he's dying as of the last couple
weeks.
It was very moving.
And it had quite a profound effect on SeaWorld.
SeaWorld actually this morning announced that they are no longer going to have killer whales
in their show in San Diego.
I had nothing to do with that.
But this is to emphasize the power of this kind of medium.
This got recently exposed.
They had planted spies in the activist organizations that were protesting against them.
SeaWorld folks are bad people. And they got brought down by
this documentary. But it's hard. And sometimes it doesn't work.
I personally think that An Inconvenient Truth, the book and
the movie were both extremely well done. This is the drama
moment of the film if you've seen it. With the hockey stick
and the scissors lift. And guess what? That did not work.
Since that was released, more people don't believe global
warming is real than before.
And what I'd like to do also is call attention to the
picture on the right.
That's James Inhofe, who now chairs the Senate Committee on
Science, telling a story that if there's a snowball in his
hand that he got off the street in Washington, DC,
global warming must not be real.
on the floor of the Senate. Maybe that's a little complicated for such a narrative and
maybe a game could do it better. Maybe it couldn't, I don't know, but I sure think it's
worth a try. There are other issues out there too that I think of as being complex and where
understanding the complexity of the issue might be the thing that can change the way
people think of it. Maybe they can change their behavior. Here's one.
The majority of the growth in antibiotic resistance comes from two places.
One is the fact that antibiotics are way over prescribed.
It's not going to help your flu ever.
The other is people don't take the full course of their antibiotics.
Who knew this?
That you have to take the full course of your antibiotics.
Yeah, bullshit.
If you don't take the whole thing,
you get a new strain that's actually slightly stronger.
And people keep doing that, and then they
pass it on to someone else.
The next thing you know, you've got a resistant bacterium
out there.
And the only way you can really understand why this happens
is understanding how evolution works,
which probably James Inhofe is not the best resource for that.
The game could show that really nicely.
This is where I was spending a few years in education.
This report came out last year.
It was not good news in terms of the level of competence of
math in our schools.
And by the way, Common Core is not the problem.
If I can soapbox for just a moment, Common Core is part of
the solution, but we'll move on.
This is a really interesting map.
The EPA just released recently this new tool.
And this is called Data That's Political.
On the left, that allows you to show the correlation between
poverty and pollution.
That's Manhattan.
And you can pretty much go anywhere in the United States
and see this happen.
You can make that little GIF.
When we made SimCity EDU and took it into schools, and we
did that at Glass Lab.
I think I saw Stone back there.
Thank you, Stone, for making that happen.
Quick story, we had a teacher who used SimCityEDU in her
class, and it was called SimCityEDU Pollution
Challenge.
And the idea was that kids learn to balance the trade-offs
between pollution and energy.
But something else happened.
One of the students came up to this teacher and said, now,
when I play this game.
What I'm doing is zoning, right?
And the teacher said, yes.
The student says, is that how they really
do it in the real world?
Yeah, that's how they do it.
So that means that that factory that's right by my house,
somebody made that zoning.
Yeah, that's true.
Oh, man.
This is a middle school kid who had never realized
that a person made that decision.
It didn't just happen.
And Sim City actually taught this kid that thing. And that's
profound. Or, back to our little starting moment, this guy, I'm
not sure, I think he might be ex-KGB, they're not quite sure
exactly who he is, sold a thermosized jug of real, highly
enriched uranium to an undercover police officer for
$330,000 last year. In November. He got caught.
But this is scary stuff.
This is just a kind of a fun game prototype
that I started to play around with.
I think it's probably stupid, and it's probably going to suck.
But it's based on the doomsday clock from my era,
and I wonder if there's some way of bridging that.
So what should you do?
Well, it's complicated.
I want to first warn everybody, you're
not going to get rich doing this.
If you want to get rich, knock yourself out.
Have fun.
There are lots of ways to do that, you're learning about
here. If you want to make art even better, please do. So this
is different. But here's a few resources. One is Games for
Change. Games for Change, this organization, has both a
conference, a website, they do lots of things and they are the
leading force in this space. And did anyone go to Colleen's talk
yesterday? Fantastic talk, she gave a fantastic talk. As soon
as it appears on the vault, if you're interested in this, go
watch her talk, it was terrific. It was also a lot of fun.
Games for Change along with N Square, which I learned was not
coincidence following the meeting I had with them, put up
basically a grand challenge, $10,000 for the winning game
design to come up with something around nuclear security. They
gave somebody $10,000 for that. How cool is that? They're doing
it again. They're doing it for financial literacy. That's the
one you see called Feed the Pig.
And just a couple days ago, Games4Change announced their
third grand challenge. This one's for climate. Again, $10,000
cash prize. Any and all of you can enter. Some other resources.
Mark Delora, who was, in case you don't know who Mark Delora
is, Mark was for several years our advocate in the White House.
He worked for the Obama administration as the game czar
after a long career including Nintendo, Sony and lots of other
places.
He publishes this called the Level Up Report.
It's fantastic.
Gamesandlearning.org is a nice resource
if you are interested in going into games for learning.
I want to give a shout out to Aaron, my colleague at UC Santa
Cruz, who runs the Beat the Dev fundraiser for the Sierra Club.
Yes.
I got another one of these funny phone calls about three weeks ago from this organization.
They're called Project Everyone.
You might know them as the people who run Comic Relief in the UK or this thing called
Red Nose Day, where people wear a red nose around to raise money for various charitable
causes.
And they would love to get into games.
And I had a long conversation with them.
And they actually shared this video with me.
I will promise you this is more uplifting than the last thing I showed you.
But it's around the 17 UN goals.
Who knows the 17 UN worldwide goals?
Who knows they even exist?
All right, we're doing better than average by far.
This is 17 goals for a sustainable planet.
They're a 15-year plan.
We're on our second 15 years of this, folks.
And nobody knows about it.
And so their goal is to spread the word.
The world leaders have signed on, but not the world
population.
How about that?
So here's a little film they made just to kind of get you all excited about the world
goals.
Video 1
Video 2
Video 3
Video 4
Video 5
Video 6
Video 7
Video 8
Video 9
Video 10
Video 11
Video 12
Video 13
Video 14
Video 15
Video 16
Video 17
Video 18
Video 19
Video 20
Despite what you hear in the American media, the world doesn't suck.
Apollo, you're on course. 226 hours to the moon orbit.
Okay, thanks Houston. But I think we'll be heading back now.
Coming, yeah?
Yeah, it was kind of fun. But I think halfway will do. Job done.
Stop!
Good night!
I would try to face you
Thank you.
Alright, not all linear mean is bad. That's pretty good.
So this is a group, they work with people like Usain Bolt.
With coldplay, gets totally involved in this stuff.
and they want to work with game developers. They want to work
with you guys. And they asked me if I would ask you to work with
them. And we're going to talk about it. We're going to do a
webinar. April 13th. Follow this Twitter handle. We made a
Facebook page for it. I would love for, I don't even know how
we're going to figure out the technology on this, but if we
get all of you to show up.
and talk to this organization about how we can make a game
that's as cool, that's as engaging, that's as awesome as
that video that will help bring these forward. That would be an
awesome start. And I'm going to maintain this Twitter account
for a while at least to keep posting these various things
that keep coming to me that I would love to all of you. And I
would love it if you would all join me and that's it. Thanks.
If anybody has any questions, we've just got like two minutes.
It's not a big Q&A topic.
All right, thanks.
I would love to see you all online on the 13th.