This is part of the level design workshop.
There's a lot of great level design talks,
so please check them out all through the day.
You'll get a lot of experience from a lot of great people.
I hope to be one of them,
and we're going to talk about God of War today.
So ...
It is a real joy to be here at GDC.
And actually, we have a lot of learnings from God of War.
It's a very big game, so we're going
to try and compress a lot of it down into some simpler
learnings for you today.
A little bit about myself.
I actually grew up in the Australian games industry.
You can probably tell from my accent.
And other than spending my late teenage years
working at a cheese store, working in games
is pretty much the only job I've ever had.
And so if you are just starting out with your career or just getting started in level design,
I put these kids games up here because it's a great way to get started.
And even though you might think that God of War would have tons of people from tons of different,
huge AAA games, which some people do, a lot of people actually come from smaller backgrounds
and from kids games, THQ games, even smaller games than that.
So, if you're ever wondering where to get started,
I always say just get your hands dirty
and maybe I can show you some tricks today on how to do that.
In addition, even though AAA games
themselves can be very big, heavy development experiences,
there's a lot of production behind them.
There's a lot of rules and level design tropes
that I learned on smaller games.
And I like to say that good design is effective
at any scale.
And I hope that you can see how some of the tricks we're
going to look at today work on big projects
or work on small projects.
Finally, we actually did have a lot of risks on this God of War game.
It's fabulous that it's come together so nicely.
We have a lot of fans, which is always a great feeling.
But a lot of the rules I'll show you today are actually what I would call very traditional.
And there's some that have been successful on many games, you know, other than God of War.
This talk is primarily about the Stonemason level.
You can see here this fabulous environment art
is from Isabella May.
It's one of my favorite levels in the game.
And it is about 50 percent of the way through the game.
So there's some minor spoilers, but nothing too major.
I won't go into anything too heavy.
But to talk about how the item use works in the game
and how the exploration works in the game,
I have to dive into it a little bit.
As we step through the Stone Mason level,
I will keep coming back here a lot.
This is what I call the level design rule slide.
We will come back here a few times.
Basically, what we are going to do is go over six major rules
from God of War's levels.
There will be a little bit of time for questions at the end.
If we run out of time, I can meet you at room 305 or 308,
and we can keep discussing.
My hope is that by showing you these rules
and by showing you the Stone Mason level,
I can sort of use it as a microcosm
for the level design of the game itself.
So we'll check back on this every now and then.
It's sort of the anchor to the presentation.
And then we'll go into the level.
I'll show you how the level rules work out in practice.
And I'll show you some of the beats leading up to level.
And you'll kind of get how the overall flow packages up
from level to level.
So to get us started, here's our first rule.
It's all about core pillars.
Sometimes a contentious topic in game design.
Some people really like to use core pillars, some people don't.
I think they're great.
I like core pillars because they let us know what to focus on.
You could sort of think of them maybe as a lens of focus
that help us to all start getting thinking
in the same direction together.
And we can't do everything in every game ever,
nor do we really want to, right?
Because if we do things with a bit of focus,
what we'll hopefully end up with is a few things
that make the game really special,
something that actually helps to separate it
from every other game out there.
And so you can think of the core pillars
as creative building blocks.
And as we step through this talk,
I'll be going over core pillars a lot.
But before we do, here's a quick history lesson.
God of War 1, 2, 3, and Ascension, the PSP versions,
they all have core pillars that focus on a few key areas
as well.
You might describe them as combat, platforming,
and puzzles.
And as you probably remember, God of War
was actually a game with a rail camera.
So it was often seen as this best-in-class bombastic action game, action adventure game.
But by 2014, there was a very strong feeling both inside the studio and outside the studio
that we needed to start looking at these core pillars and the anatomy that really makes
up the game itself.
Now, for a franchise to switch up its core pillars
is not the type of thing you want to do all the time, right?
Because what you're actually going to start to look at is,
are we reevaluating the things
that players find most fun about this game?
We're going to actually start unpackaging that.
We're going to take all the pieces of the engine,
spread them out on the floor, and see how they all fit together.
So, with that in mind, Cory Barlog, our creative director,
and a few key team members sort of siphoned themselves off
for a little while,
and they had the goal of creating a new set of pillars.
The three pillars that they came up with,
and I won't step you through the full process
of how this was generated,
but they were very successful,
were combat, narrative, and exploration.
And for level design, this is a very big change.
It's great.
It starts to give us a lot of things to start focusing on.
But it actually also starts tapping into a lot of things
that we sort of lack expertise in at Santa Monica Studio.
But it's a good opportunity to start thinking in new terms
and how we take on modern design challenges.
We can't keep doing the same thing forever,
so how do we start thinking with a new lens of focus?
You can start asking yourself, all right, well, what would Combat 2.0 even mean?
How does this work with a new camera? How do encounters work?
How do we build fight spaces?
Sure, a lot of people say they want to be a modern narrative game,
but what does that even mean?
How do you tell stories? What are the components that come together to make that happen?
And a lot of people think of exploration just in terms of larger spaces.
But how big is too big? How wide is too wide?
What do you even do other than just exploring or roaming?
And of course, at the center of all of this, you have Kratos and Atreus,
you know, trying to tell a father-son story.
So you're trying to take combat, narrative, and exploration
as your first pillars of focus.
And at the center of it, you're trying to think of
how this will all tie into a father-son story.
Here's a quick version of Vision Book.
This is the one that Corey put together.
I think it was fabulous.
In fact, you can see all through the book
that combat narrative and exploration
are very heavily represented.
In fact, Corey believed so strongly at these three pillars
that you pretty much can't get a cup of coffee at the studio
without having to look at it, which
is a particularly good way to start brainwashing everyone.
And I know this is something that designers really respected.
The fact that Corey stayed to these three pillars
gave us some really strong anchors through the project
that we could work on.
So, with these three pillars in mind,
as I step through the presentation,
start to try to think about combat, narrative,
and exploration a lot.
This stonemason level did take a long time to put together.
You know, we spent a long time tuning it and iterating on it,
even with these great pillars that we could focus on.
But the thing that's great about this level
is when it came together,
it sort of became a fully architected expression
that delivered on combat narrative and exploration.
And most importantly, it proved to us
that if you distribute those three pillars correctly,
you can actually deliver on the variety of pacing
that we're looking to master.
Not just an action game and not just an adventure game,
but a real mix of action and adventure, right?
So let's take a look with a bit of a deeper dive
how the game and how the level
delivers on those three pillars.
I'll start with the most obvious one, combat.
Well, this, of course, details everything
that is the most action-focused component of the game.
It's the capital A in action adventure.
And it's everything from Kratos' core attack loop
to the AI he faces, the upgrades that can be achieved,
and perhaps most importantly, how a support character
like Atreus might contribute to that fight.
You can see here inside the category of combat,
there's actually a lot of sub-archetypes.
It's not just arenas or fight spaces.
There's also sort of more wide linear scenarios
where you can take on the AI in more free-form ways.
Down the bottom on the left there,
you'll see what I call a special rules scenario.
This one has a timer that sort of gets the variety
a bit different from everything else.
Of course, you have boss battles,
you have lots of different things
that come together to just make combat
more than just fights, right?
So the core pillar of combat is great.
It gives us a lot that we can start thinking about early on,
but what's really good about it is it has enough versatility
that we can start to create sub-archetypes inside it.
It's a great place for level designers
to start to put their focus,
and if you look at the Mason level here,
you'll see that it's pretty heavily distributed
throughout the level, exactly what you'd expect.
There's a lot of different fights that take place,
and they're paced out really well.
Secondly, narrative.
Well, you might not expect that out of a God of War game,
especially with the history of the franchise.
God of War has actually always had a strong narrative
through it, but it's never really been narrative gameplay.
So what we can start thinking about now
is what is the father-son adventure
that Kratos and Atreus are actually going to go on?
It's
The tone, it's the level's purpose, it's the overall lore.
A good level has a story and has an adventure behind it, right?
So we can actually start thinking about how to deliver on that.
Again, there's a few sub-archetypes of narrative gameplay that we can look into.
You've got cut scenes, of course, but we tried to innovate on this
by having no camera cuts throughout these.
You can see there's sort of more slow-paced sections
where Kratos and Atreus can have conversations with one another.
Down the bottom, a lot of games are starting to become masters
of this right now, environmental storytelling.
How do we give the environment a sense of place?
How do we tie it into the overall law?
And of course, you can see on the bottom right,
even Atreus has little animations
that we put in the levels to try and emphasize
and accentuate his state of mind.
There's even little secrets that allow the player to find lore.
There's a lot of different categories inside that core pillar of narrative,
and that's great.
Again, like combat, it gives us a lot of different versatility
and variety that we can create inside the level.
If you look at it from the top-down perspective,
you might even be surprised how much narrative is inside this level.
And that doesn't even include the fact that you're in a level
with a giant, interesting-looking fallen giant, right?
So once again, you can see we're able to get a lot of variety
and density out of that sort of initial pillar of narrative.
And rounding out the three pillars is exploration.
And this is what I would consider
to be the most complicated of the three pillars.
The pillar of exploration is great.
It represents the desire for larger layouts, sure.
It represents the desire for more wide linear spaces,
of course.
But it also represents the design shift in the camera.
The fact that you can actually move the camera around now
means every space is more explorable than before.
There's a famous phrase taught to me earlier in my career
by Morgan Jaffa, which is, camera is genre.
Where you place the camera is possibly what type of game
you are making.
And when we shift the camera from a real camera game
to a fully 3D game, now we have very explorable game
just through the perspective of the camera.
So you can start to once again break down exploration
into sub-archetypes and start to look at how the camera
provides new opportunities.
It's more than just big spaces.
There's little puzzles that we can put all through the level
now that we can aim the camera in different perspectives.
We have optional fights that you can opt into.
Those are just great because they give you
a bit of player autonomy.
And finally, this level actually connects to the game's hub,
which is the Lake of Nine,
and we'll go into that a little bit later,
but it's a larger sort of discussion
about how exploration on level-to-level flow works.
So once again, you can see that exploration
is pretty heavily represented in this level.
Of course, it does bunch up a little bit
in the most explorable space,
which is the mason's mini hub right in front of his head.
But also, if you look at the back end of the level,
it's more than just building big spaces.
We want you to seek out nooks and crannies in every room,
even if it's a more linear space or a load hallway.
We want to fill that full of secrets, lore,
additional moments, and so forth.
So when you put it all together,
I think you have a level that accurately delivers on the three pillars, combat, narrative and
exploration.
And if you use these correctly, you can achieve the variety and pacing that I think we're
looking to master, a mix of action and adventure.
The stonemason level is sort of what you might call one of
the more level designer-y levels as well.
It's particularly good at this.
And it's not a full vertical slice, and we don't treat
every level like a template or anything like that.
But it was a particularly good level to get online early in
the project, because it really did prove to us that if you
mix and match these three pillars together, you can get
a lot of versatility, and you can get a lot of variety.
And this is, in essence, why I believe in
core pillars so much.
When you go to design spaces, front of mind for all designers
should really be, how do I use these?
How do I mix and match them?
How do I start to think about them to create a lot of focus?
And if you do this, you'll end up
with a level that feels, a game that feels very different
from level to level, but still feels consistent
from the overall level to level experience.
So with that in mind, we'll add rule number one to our deck.
And we can start to look into our next most important technique,
which is converting these pillars into recognizable metrics.
And that's where rule number two comes in.
Early on in the project, we had to make a decision
about what type of construction of this game we wanted to use.
And we made the decision that we were going to be a very metrics-focused game.
So we can start to think, how do our core pillars
and our metrics come together to help us architect spaces?
A lot of people talk about design metrics.
What does it even mean?
Quick definition.
I like to think of metrics as just a design measurement
that communicates gameplay.
If used correctly, you should start
to build a rhythm in your head as to what
the different measurements mean.
And all games have this.
If you're playing Tomb Raider, maybe jump heights and jump
widths might be super important.
Playing a racing game might be about width server.
paths or where we go on-road, off-road, all these types of things,
really important for what type of game you're making.
So of course the first question you should be asking is,
how do we make metrics that emphasize and accentuate the core pillars of the game?
Our task is to determine metrics that are most important
for highlighting and promoting the goals of the game.
So...
With that in mind, you can start to quickly route your head,
once again, through the core pillars of the game.
At a simplest level, well, for metrics for combat,
we don't want snags or frustrations.
OK, how do we create a metric that creates that?
For narrative, sure, it's easy enough
to say we want no camera cuts.
But how do we actually create a metric to deliver on that goal?
And for exploration, this is a game without a jump button.
When you're looking around the environments,
how do we create more explorable spaces while also allowing
you to scan the horizon and start
to get a quick snapshot in the back of your head
as to what those metrics might mean?
If you get to a dead end and it doesn't actually
reward exploration, you're going to be bummed out,
not going to want to explore anymore, right?
So those metrics start to put a lot of psychology in your head.
This here is one of our most important team documents.
It's called the Level Building Codes,
and it was created by Michael Chang and James Riding.
And it details all the metrics out in meters.
You can see here that Kratos, he mostly
uses one meters, two meters, and three meters.
And we try to really stick to those values
as much as possible, even in more organic spaces.
You can see that he has five meters as kind of his drop-off
heights and so forth.
And as we start to get more complicated,
all the different vaults and squeezes and wall presses,
all these things have very clearly laid out metrics.
So if done correctly, the visual archetypes are established
and layouts remain clear.
Once you're happy with the metrics,
they go into a test bed and you can examine them further.
Here's a quick example.
As he runs through, keep an eye on the three meters
and we'll come back to that in a moment.
So it's pretty straightforward stuff.
You can see everything's nicely laid out.
It's easy to test that the animations are going to line
up correctly.
And boom, there's our 3 meter one right in front of us.
Let's take a closer look at the 3 meter.
3 meter boost is, I love this one.
It's really simple because it's a vault that Kratos can
do to get to an upper ledge.
It's not so high that you might feel like you're going to move to the next space or trigger the next cinematic or move on to a big fight or anything like that.
But it is just high enough that it removes you from the planar space.
And it's perpendicular.
It's a very strong, sharp edge.
And it's roughly at Kratos' eye level.
So the 3-meter boost is great.
It can be used to separate the combat space a little bit.
It can be used to reward a secret.
And if used correctly, it starts to build a rhythm in your head
as to what the role of the three meter boost may be.
There's a lot of other archetypes.
This is why people call metrics sometimes level Legos
or similar like that.
Because when combined together, they
make a very traditional BSP layout, or sheet layout,
as we call it.
This is the stonemason level early on.
And you can see that these metrics were very early attempts
to start to see how these level rules may
start to come together.
Over here, you can see that there's some early attempts
to get combat spaces and combat metrics laid out correctly.
Up the top, you can see early examples of vaults.
And down on the bottom right,
you can see that these are some early attempts
to start working out what these climb metrics
and climb animations might look like.
As we get further into development,
these metrics were actually pretty successful,
and so we started to look into more advanced ones.
Over here, you can see that we added little jump gaps.
This is maybe a little bit more rhythm
that we can start to build into the nav metrics.
The environment artist told us that slopes
was something that was super important to them
based on their research of the Nordics.
So we started to look into what IK heights would be
and how we could build with those in mind.
And finally, a point of pride for me
is you'll see over on the right-hand side
that initial metric that we created for the fight space
has actually retained its design.
And even as it got a more sort of detailed pass,
it's actually held its structure.
That's spot on.
This is the value of laying it out correctly.
So when you step through the stonemason level,
you'll see there's a really basic core path.
And now we can start to think, once again,
how will these metrics come together
to make combat, narrative, and exploration?
Here's our three combat spaces.
You can see there is a more wide linear space
at the front of the level.
Up the back, we've got a more traditional arena scenario that takes place at the head where we can increase intensity.
And then actually, on the back right there, you'll see that this was a space that we also laid out to be another arena, which is a bit too similar back to back, right?
So we had to introduce a character there to spice it up and make it a bit more interesting.
In terms of the narrative pillar,
you'll see that the Mason himself is pretty much
a perfect narrative setup.
It's a fallen giant whose last breath
has frozen the entire world around him.
It's a great setup.
But despite what you may think, we
don't know every line of dialogue
or every piece of narrative that is written
at the start of the project, right?
So what we try to do is lay out the space so that there's tons of opportunity for banter or environmental storytelling or set pieces in general.
And that means that the writers can come in at different phases in the project and still make interesting moments between the characters.
And finally, up the back there, this
is one of the cinematic transitions.
This is a very early attempt to try and work out
how we were actually going to funnel you
from gameplay into cinematics with no camera cuts.
In this example, Kratos uses a climb.
And that's a great way to limit his movements
so that we can start to create blends between gameplay
and cinematics.
And in terms of exploration, you can actually see here,
this is where I showed you the jump gaps earlier.
This was kind of a failed experiment,
even though the level designer, Kai Zheng,
did an incredible job of this level.
Actually, we found out that if you are a game
without a jump button, it is just not that fun
to move around and lean into the nav.
So later on, we actually swapped these out
with little bonus puzzles that involved throwing the axe,
which we thought was a bit more in tune
with the game's strengths rather than maybe its limitations.
So once you string it all together,
you have a layout that can actually fit all in Maya,
which is great, because we don't have camera cuts
in this game, so it's really important
that we can actually fit it all in one scene,
and it's great for workflow.
So you can probably tell from how much I am going into this
that I am really proud of how the level designer,
Kai, did with this.
If you strip away the production of the level,
there is a lot of really simple rules that make up this space.
They are not super fancy, and they are not super complicated.
They are just a lot of repeatable metrics
and repeatable pieces that come together
to make an overall layout.
And ultimately, it is the core pillars
and those initial metrics that are the first building blocks
of level construction.
If you know your core pillars,
and you have a generally clear layout,
I believe you'll have a strong canvas
for more complicated decisions, right?
And if you do the groundwork to do that,
you can start to take on more complex things,
like variety, pacing, mixing it up, all these things.
Which brings us to our next set of rules,
achieving variety.
So,
I mentioned a lot that we're always looking for the mix of action and adventure, right?
Never leaning too hard into making the action fatiguing and never leaning too softly into
the adventuring elements.
And since the game's been out for a while now, we do hear from players that they feel
like it has a good mix of scenarios, including combat, narrative, and exploration.
Which is awesome.
I'm really glad to hear that.
And you never know until the game ships, right?
So when you hear that, you're very relieved in some ways.
And also, players often tell us that they
feel like it keeps moving from a moment-to-moment perspective,
that it stays fresh.
So with that in mind, I want to detail two rules
that I think are really important for achieving variety.
The first is that all levels sort of promote or sell
a major theme throughout the level.
I'm fond of saying good levels have a strong theme.
So put simply, to create a theme or variety,
there has to be some kind of unique gameplay element,
something that acts as a start point or an inception,
maybe like a nucleus for an idea.
And our hope is that that will give us
a breadth of different scenarios that we can create.
And once that unique gameplay element
or that unique level toy or whatever you wanna call it
has been established,
it sort of becomes an anchor for the level.
If you establish it correctly in the level
and you teach it correctly, then we can be confident
that we can start throwing more complex scenarios
at the player and more complexity
and more variety at the player through the course of the level.
And once you've got enough of these scenarios strung together,
you've got a theme, right?
So that brings us to our second rule.
All critical path levels unlock a new ability.
Put simply, these are distributed
about every 90 to 120 minutes or so.
And as above, these are the unique gameplay elements
that drive the theme throughout the level.
Most importantly, since a new one's unlocked
every 90 to 120 minutes, it helps the level
to make it feel different from the one before it,
and it helps the level to make it feel different
from the one after it.
It's a lot of good variety.
It prevents a lot of blandness, right,
which is always a little bit of the fear.
Making bland levels is not great.
So, you pair these two rules together, you've got a basic flow.
Every level unlocks a new ability, and then we can use that ability to drive a theme throughout
the level.
And once we know our unique ability, the level designer can sort of go hog-wild.
We can start to think about how this mechanic will work with combat, narrative, and exploration.
If it's a really great mechanic, it
should be able to talk to all three
of the most important elements of the game.
Personal favorite of mine is the hook shot.
Everyone loves the hook shot.
You can use it to navigate.
You can use it to fight.
You can grab rupees with it.
You can solve puzzles with it.
The hook shot literally talks to everything
in the game that is the most important element.
And that's why it is so meaningful to the player.
And so if paced correctly and the items are meaningful,
then players will actually get excited
and anticipate the next big unlock.
So here is the ability that's utilized in the Stone Mason
level.
It's called the Shock Arrow.
And Shock Arrows are super basic.
Shock Arrows are magic arrows that Atreus
can fire at red crystals.
And they go, boom.
That's pretty much it.
But it's actually awesome because its simple design
allows for a lot of versatility.
If it's too complex a level mechanic,
then we're really going to struggle
to create a lot of variety,
or we're going to struggle to have scenarios
where the player might be under duress
and actually be able to use the mechanic.
So its simplicity is actually terrific.
So, of course, before it looks like this in the game,
we do a really basic prototype
to make sure it's actually fun
and that it's going to deliver on this potential versatility
and variety.
And here is the prototype.
So this level prototype was actually created by John Marcello,
who's one of the senior designers at Santa Monica Studio.
We started this project so long ago,
he actually used the touch pad as the prototype.
And everyone thought it generally had potential.
So from there, it went through some additional iterations
to find out what the best controls and rules would be.
We have a whole systems design department
that are really masters of this domain.
And then as level designers, we try to use those mechanics.
But eventually, it was determined
that it would be even cooler if Atreus could help you out.
We might get back a little bit more combat, exploration,
and narrative.
Maybe we can actually get father-son connection out
of this mechanic as well.
So it was added to Atreus's bow.
Basically, you press square, and Atreus fires the arrow for you.
It's pretty simple, but as I mentioned,
our desire is to create father-son connection
and also give the level designers a lot of versatility
in scenario design.
As you can see here, this mechanic is awesome
because it can be used on tons of different stuff.
And the red material,
which does actually have some narrative in the game,
it's kind of the roots of the Yadraz school tree.
So between visual development and the level mechanic team,
and between the level designers and the environment artists,
we're able to create tons of versatility
as to how this red sap or this red material
can be placed around the level.
Spot on, because that's the thing
that's going to allow us to create an established theme
throughout the level.
In addition, it was thought that we had a pretty good mechanic,
but that we could get a bit of additional play out of it,
once again, to push variety.
So there was the decision made to add a throwable element,
which is awesome.
Now we can have static scenarios,
and we can have scenarios that allow a bit more player
creativity.
And finally, once we're really happy with it,
late in development, we polish it
so that it can accentuate its role
and be a very prominent theme throughout the level.
You can see here that it has an inner glow
so that it pops just a little bit more, tiny bit arcadey.
And you can also see that as you pass the camera
around this object, it has a little bit of sheen on it
so that it's likely to just catch your eye
as you move the camera.
So let's take a look at one of the scenarios in the level
and how it works with the core pillars.
Once again, try to think of this in terms of combat,
narrative, and exploration.
I'll start with narrative here.
This sort of concept of a puzzle is great
for slowing down the player
and just having narrative moments in general.
In fact, maybe after a little while,
the AI partner can even give you a hint.
This scenario is also terrific because it's been fabulously integrated by the environment art team.
It's actually the ring finger of the giant, so it foreshadows the narrative that you're going to see further on.
And you may not know this, but all the runes on the ring were actually translated by someone,
so they all actually have real meaning if you go back and translate them,
if you're really into the narrative of the game.
So in terms of exploration, well, you can see here
he's blowing up an additional secret,
and that may not be exploration per se, right?
It's not a super explorable space.
He didn't find a hidden dungeon or anything like that.
But really, it's kind of more of a gimme.
It's a tutorial for exploration.
It's teaching you, keep an eye out
for future scenarios like this,
and keep your brain checked for shock crystals,
because shock crystals can equal secrets, right?
And so...
This is a little bit of a gimme, but it does sort of train you on exploration.
And then finally, for combat, well the shock arrows are really great for combat in general.
That was already thought of because Atreus can actually use them in combat scenarios,
give you an advantage, they have a whole skill tree.
This is where I love this scenario because if you actually fire a shock arrow in combat,
at the ring, you can get an AOE and you can actually blast the AI.
So everything starts to talk to each other and you can even sort of experiment with it
while under duress.
That's part of the advantage of it being so simple.
Now, you may not remember these scenarios.
I actually showed you them at the top of the presentation.
But a lot of the scenarios I showed you
actually had shot crystals in the background.
Let's take a look.
You'll see that this is the first one I showed you,
where it's just in the background.
Maybe it hints to you that you can get a bit of damage
if you're experimental.
You can see that it can be used for throwable puzzles
in the top right.
Down below, it's actually used for a shot crystal chandelier section.
And the thing that's sort of nice about the shot crystals is even though they are kind of big and glowy,
we're able to get them into a lot of the environments.
So they can even be in the background of cinematics without being like too offensive or anything like that.
Let's take a look at it from a top-down perspective.
Once again, you'll see that the shock arrows are really nicely distributed throughout the level.
And I love that, because that is the thing that is making it a theme.
Some players even called it the shock arrow level when they would come at a playtest,
which if you're a level designer is the real compliment, right?
When they ignore everything else and just talk about the mechanics.
And it was also great from a production perspective and
a code perspective because as I mentioned at the top of the presentation,
we can't code every feature ever.
We're in a very fortunate situation to have so much support from Sony.
But even still, we have limitations and we don't want to code everything ever.
So using the shock arrow is still a very efficient use of the mechanic as well.
So you can probably tell from my pride and joy with all these scenarios that I think
the level designer, Kai, absolutely crushed it.
I think this is one of the best themes throughout the game.
This is what I love about level design.
And he really nailed the flow.
Level unlocks a key item, and then the level uses that item to create a strong theme throughout
the level.
But there is an additional detail to this.
As I alluded to, every level unlocks a key item, right?
And that starts to touch on how we think about more of the
level-to-level experience and what the
overarching experience is.
So with that in mind, the next rule is all
about creating a format.
What is a format?
Some people talk about format maybe like structure or
something like that.
I like to define it as the intuitive rules
by which levels flow into one another.
So, if the pieces are lined up correctly,
you can start to create some psychology and a mental layer,
and players can start to identify
with how they'll engage in sessions
and how they'll play levels.
In God of War, there's actually a lot of different types of content.
There's critical path levels, there's exploration levels,
even little puzzles that are optional.
There's actually entire areas you can discover on your own.
So it's really important that we start to build some expectations in the player's head.
If you enter a story mission in a game, how do you know intuitively that you're going
to maybe start like 60 minutes worth of content and start to get into it?
there's some psychology and consistency within the game
to start establishing that rhythm in your head.
And if you go down a side path and you think to yourself,
oh, awesome, here I go, down this little side path,
I know the main path's over there,
well, that means it was a correctly signaled B path.
That means it was correctly set up through the level design
to intuitively let you know
that you're going down the side path, not the main path.
Regardless, in God of War, we are often described
as maybe having a bit of a Metroidvania element
or something like that.
And we often hear from players that they
know when they can continue the story
and when they can go exploring, which is great.
That's exactly what I'm looking for.
So our next rule works with all the previous rules
before it to try and create those expectations
and deliver on those results for the player.
It's really simple.
It's just about giving the player a clear exploration
break.
As I mentioned before, all levels,
they give you a key item, right?
And our exploration break is the opportunity
for you to experiment with that.
It's the thing that lets you know that it's time to go
and use it in a more playful or freeform way.
So, I'll go into a step deeper on how that flow
achieves basically the Metroidvania element.
So, in the previous level, as I mentioned,
the theme is the shock arrow.
And we try to deliver on that all throughout the level.
But what you may not have noticed is that the shock arrow actually ceases around the
three-quarter point in the level.
On the way back out through the level, there's no more shock arrow scenarios.
So what's the deal?
Did we, like, run out of money or run out of ideas?
Something like that?
No, this is actually where the boss battle takes place in the level.
It's what you might describe as the key turning point.
So going back to our triangle, the first three quarters
of the level delivers on the theme.
And then we hit a key turning point.
Now, it doesn't have to be a boss battle.
It can be anything you want.
It can be a key story moment.
It can be a major chest or some kind of a choir.
It can even be a revelation for the character.
But what matters is the final quarter of the level
is dedicated to teaching the new item
or teaching the new ability.
If done correctly, it's an embedded tutorial of sorts.
It's sort of the type of thing where learning is fun.
It's a hard thing to accomplish.
But if you do it, then the player
is sort of fooled into the fact that they're doing a tutorial.
And then to wrap it up, our last rule
finishes with an exploration break.
So.
Going back to our top-down map, the first three quarters
of the level makes up the shock arrow distribution.
And then our boss battle here creates the key turning point.
And then we use the last 25% of the level
to reward the new item, which in this case is a magic chisel
that he can use to unlock different doors around the game.
There's three scenarios, so you confidently learn.
You know, three's always a great design number.
And then finally, we wrap up with an exploration break.
So in summary, we have everything we need now.
We've created a strong theme,
and we've given you an exciting item,
we've taught you how to use it,
and now we capitulate with an exploration break.
What is the net result here?
Why is this even important?
Well, it creates a very natural motivator to explore.
You are excited to go exploring because you got a new toy,
and you only got to use it three times,
so you might want to keep using it, right?
It's brand new.
And you're motivated to explore because you might have actually
seen areas in the game that use this ability.
That's great level design if we can plant it
in your head as you go.
And finally, you're given a very clearly signaled break.
You don't have to worry.
You know that this is a good time to explore.
You know that this is a good time to go off the path.
And you know this is a good time to confidently explore
an experiment.
To put it simply, it actually takes a lot of mental load
to plan a path around an exploration space,
to navigate by POIs, to look for secrets, to find things.
And I want you to use your entire mental energy on that.
I don't want you to be wondering if you
know how to use an ability or if you know if it's
the right time to be exploring.
So by threading you in the back part of the level
through the tutorial experience, we
can make sure that when you go exploring,
you have everything you need to go to the hub.
Now here's how we achieve a format.
You stack a few of these triangles back to back,
and you have a consistent format that
can be used to inspire and motivate from a level
to level perspective.
Our first level starts.
We teach a theme throughout the level.
We hit a key turning point, we reward a new item,
we give you a clear break to explore.
That item is then reutilized through the next level
so we can get a lot of value out of it.
We keep pushing the theme throughout the level.
Boom, key turning point again.
Just as you're getting fatigued with that item,
we try to give you a new item every 90 to 120 minutes
and so forth and so forth and so forth.
And if done correctly, players will start to learn this flow in the back of their head.
If there's ever a pacing dip or they feel like maybe they're tired of something,
they will be excited and inspired about the next big item or the next big unlock and the next big ability.
The promise of new and cool items also comes with the promise of varied themes and varied scenarios.
Because we've shown you that these new items and abilities give you lots of different gameplay in the different levels,
we hope that you'll enjoy the rest of the video.
And as always, thanks for watching.
the flow is motivating.
And most importantly, we can actually
use that motivation to prioritize exploration.
Here's a quick example.
I want you to watch what the player does here
as he boats around.
The taste of Vanir magic led him to new forms
of experimentation.
Brabam!
New levels of depravity.
Look where we are, Brabam.
OK, so in this example, the player is exploring the hub.
They're being correctly taught the shock arrow mechanic.
And thanks to the design work done by Kaizeng,
they've also been told that shock arrows mean
interesting themes and that there's
a lot of different variety and a lot of different gameplay,
right?
So we've made a convincing promise to the player.
So watch it one more time.
And I want you to watch just what the camera behavior does.
The taste of Vanir magic led him to new forms of experimentation.
Brabham!
New levels of depravity.
Look where we are, Brabham.
Boom, and there it is.
He saw a shock crystal, right?
He has been taught correctly.
He has been promised interesting gameplay.
And because he is returning to the hub, he is thinking,
oh, I feel like doing one of those.
I know how those work.
I'm in the mood for one of those.
Or he can just explore it on his own.
That is the benefit.
The result is that we do have a compass system,
and we do have a map, right?
But our hope is that players will be self-motivated,
and that self-discovery will drive their exploration
instead.
It's good for players to feel motivated via UI or completion
percentages.
These are very valid design techniques and tools.
But it's also good if players are self-motivated because they're actually seeking out interesting content.
If this player likes shot crystal scenarios, then he can go and find more of them on his own.
Players are trained that new abilities will be unlocked in the levels, and that in turn, interesting scenarios will be delivered.
So the promise becomes more than just completion percentages. The promise becomes interesting scenarios.
And that is pretty much our game's format.
You play the level.
You unlock a new item.
You play a variety of scenarios.
When you return back to the hub, you've
been taught how to use it.
You've been made the convincing promise of interesting
gameplay.
You can seek out more of those on your own if you like those
types of scenarios, which most players did, especially in
terms of the shock arrows.
And then when you're ready, you can start returning back to
the next level.
So.
That is why we give players such clear exploration breaks,
and that's why we set up so many expectations leading up
to those exploration breaks.
And now that we have a good, what you might call,
level-to-level flow or level-to-level philosophy,
our last rule details the final tool
we need to sort of tie it all together.
It's about creating an overarching layout
that can actually emphasize that psychology.
The difference between a hub and an open world
could maybe be a whole GDC presentation of its own.
There's a lot of different things to dive into there.
But for today, what I want to talk about
is how a hub, through its very physical design,
mirrors the level-to-level flow that I've shown you earlier.
It presents it as a playable layout, is the hope.
And the hub is our way of creating information in your head
as to where there's a playground for experimentation
and exploration versus where the critical path
will take over and continue the story.
So with that, we're over to rule number six.
Hubs are not open world.
Let's start with a quick definition
of what a hub actually is then.
A hub is a centralized location from which spokes emit.
And so while an open world may offer a sprawling simulation
or something like that, a hub is actually
a very specific layout, and one that
proved very effective for us.
Here's a quick image of a hub.
It's a pretty basic one.
And using this and the definition here,
you can see that the yellow center
acts as a central location.
The arrows coming out represent the.
represent the spokes, and the blue circles
represent the destinations, or the endpoints.
So a lot of people describe a hub as a wagon wheel.
That's a pretty popular comparison.
And using our definitions, we can
start to run that through quick sanity check, central core.
spokes, and endpoints.
Or in level design terms, you could maybe
recontextualize these.
And you might call them a centralized site or pathways,
and maybe the endpoints are destinations or levels
or dungeons or something like that.
Here's a popular example you're probably aware of,
Shadow of the Colossus, one of the greatest games of all time.
The player always returns back to the Colossus Temple
at the center of the level.
Then they start to go exploring.
And they find more destinations on their own.
And they're always reverted back to the central location.
In popular culture, Disneyland is probably
the most well-known example.
It has the Mickey Mouse statue in the middle.
You take pathways out.
You find the different lands, as they are called.
It's a very effective and fairly traditional level design technique, right?
And one for us that I think was the perfect canvas for our level-to-level flow.
So, let's take a look at it in a quick example using the Stonemason level.
As you can see here, the temple in the center represents the centralized core.
Coming off this is pathways.
These represent the directional spokes
to which the player can explore and go around.
And finally, our levels and our dungeons,
they sort of represent the destinations
or the endpoints of the hub-spoke diagram.
So now we can test it against our hub diagram.
You can see that's actually pretty familiar,
not just because I matched the colors.
And remember before, our level-to-level flow,
you know, establish a theme.
hit a key turning point, earn a new ability or item,
get a clear exploration break, continue, continue, continue.
Let's run this against the stonemason level.
In the previous level, the player goes up to the mountains,
and they use the previous level's mechanic,
which in this case,
let's just call it orange to avoid spoilers.
And they start to use this.
It also creates a theme throughout the level.
They hit a capitulation point,
and they are rewarded with the shock arrow
at the end of this level.
The player can now make their way back to the hub.
Having confidently been taught how to use the shock arrow,
they can now choose to explore with it if they want.
And then when they're ready,
they can explore back for a quick narrative beat.
There's a sort of mini mission that takes place here,
a mini level.
And when they're ready to go to the main critical path level,
they head back to the stonemason level.
We drive that theme all the way through the level,
create a lot of variety, a lot more pacing,
increase the complexity a little bit
of the shock arrow scenarios.
Boom, just as you're getting fatigued, key turning point,
new ability or item, teach you three scenarios,
and then you're back to the hub.
And as we strip all of this away,
it becomes apparent that this layout is very similar
to the big wagon wheel.
Overall, I believe the Lake of Nine
was great at delivering the goals of a hub.
And it's this hub design that, in turn,
is really successful at achieving
the sort of Metroidvania element that people often
enjoy in this game.
So there's your hope.
And with that, we're back to our rule slide.
I'll add it to the annex.
Let's go through all of these, and I'll quickly recap.
It's also a good time to mention that these are actually
sometimes really good design priorities.
As you step through a really big project or a lot of work,
you can also start to think of these
as maybe the order of operations that you might want to take
experiences on in a game.
Up front is just about how we start to think together
and how we work together to start creating some focus
as a design group, whether that's technically designers
or just people who we work with.
Rule number two represents our desire to represent those core pillars as metrics. How are we going to construct?
Effectively and consistently amongst one another rules three and four it's all about the backbone of creativity and the backbone of variety and pacing
Rule five ensures that we have clear exploration breaks and and that levels flow clearly from one another and finally our newest rule number six
It's sort of an overarching wrapper or an overarching layout for the whole experience and with that we have a game
But since it's GDC, and since we're
here to learn about the tricky nature of development,
I'll now step back through all of these
and show you where they all broke.
And not just because there was bad design,
or not just because something was wrong.
Sometimes it's also an opportunity.
Sometimes maybe a problem just didn't work out
the way we expected, or sometimes it's just common sense.
So here's rule number one.
What you might have noticed is that this game has a lot of puzzles,
and puzzles are not represented anywhere in the core pillars of the game.
So what's the deal?
Are puzzles a core pillar or not, right?
And this is a question that took us about four and a half years to work out.
So even though the puzzles take a lot of work,
and even though they do take a lot of play testing,
they're a great addition to the game
because they let us tap into the three pillars of the game
in really great ways.
I like to look at the puzzles in terms of sort of
emphasizers or subcategories
of combat narrative and exploration.
As I mentioned earlier,
puzzles are great for just slowing down
the action in general,
so we can get a lot of narrative between the characters.
There's a lot more father-son teamwork in a puzzle,
so that can be a good way to emphasize that pillar.
In terms of exploration, puzzles often make us rethink the space,
so they keep us in the space a little bit longer.
At Santa Monica Studios, we truly do have some of the best environment artists in the world,
so we're always looking for ways to get the player to soak in the space just a little bit more
and try to appreciate the spaces, not blow through them too quickly.
And finally, for combat, the puzzles actually teach you to learn.
I'll show you one more time this scenario.
This one is early in the game, and it's actually
tuned a little bit difficult.
Why?
Because we would rather that you fail on the scenario
a couple of times and learn how to throw the axe more
effectively, so that when you step
into the more complex scenarios in the game,
you have trained yourself how to do something that
doesn't really exist in any other game.
Throwing an axe and recalling it is fairly abstract.
It's something that makes this game unique.
And so by tuning this puzzle just a bit difficult,
we can be guaranteed that the types of players
who will engage with stretch content or more complex content
are also the types of players who might train and master.
more complex mechanics.
So in short, puzzles are a big part of the game,
but they're not a core pillar.
Number two, we are a metrics-based game.
So the Norse landscape itself is really organic
and really mysterious, and that was one thing
that was very obvious to us from day one.
But metrics are actually really rigid,
and they're deliberately so.
So how do you kind of tie these things together?
There's a natural conflict that emerges, right?
So here's a quick example of where it broke.
I've shown you my favorite example, which
is the 3-meter boost.
And on the right-hand side, you can
see that there's a lot of debris or shrub.
So in the test bed, it looks great.
You can see that it's a very clear perpendicular object.
It's kind of turreted in this example,
so we can accentuate the nature of it.
But by the time we put debris over it,
it sort of loses its ability to be an architectural piece.
What now?
What are we going to do?
Get mad at each other, blame each other,
scream at each other, go into each other's files,
pull out shrubs?
No.
What we actually did is come up with a style guide.
This indicates where shrubs and debris
should actually be placed and where design metrics need
to be kept important to keep things clear.
Fortunately, we have an environment team
who is extraordinarily talented and very
passionate about the game.
And you might think that pitching to a team, hey,
we're going to talk about rules for shrub placement
or where shrubs can't go might be the most boring conversation
ever.
But actually, everyone really rallied together
to talk about how we could create a style guide
for shrubs.
And the net result is that shrubs and debris
can actually be used not only to, uh,
When they're removed, they not only make spaces very clear,
but if you put them in certain places,
they can actually act as a deterrent as well.
So by creating these two style guide rules,
we could actually basically create organic placement,
where we didn't want you to go,
and architectural placement,
where we wanted to emphasize you going.
So there's a lot of positive and negative
visual expectations that you can actually create.
Also, what about rules 3 and 4?
Variety.
All levels have a theme, right?
Not in the back 25% of this game.
I'm not going to spoil anything for you,
but the reason is twofold.
What's the deal?
Did you run out of money again?
Did you run out of ideas?
Was four years too long to make a game?
Do you not want to go to five or six?
No.
We don't have an unlimited budget on features,
and we do try to use them as effectively as possible.
And when we started to paper plan the game,
we did realize that we were going to run out of mechanics
and that we didn't have an unlimited budget
and that we didn't want to spend forever just prototyping
and whatever.
The back part of the game are really more about mastery
than about newness.
Keep in mind all of the level theming that I mentioned earlier,
it's not specifically about creating new items all the time,
it's about creating variety.
There is more ways to create variety
than just adding more mechanics to the game.
Here's a quick example.
The Temple Flip level towards the end of the game is often,
oops, sorry, let me get that up for you.
Oh no.
Well, the Tempo Flip level of the game
is actually often described as final exam.
And what that means is that it uses
all the previous level mechanics of the game together.
And so let me get this back up and running.
I think we crashed.
Oh, there we go.
OK.
So in this example, it's the only time in the game
where Crusher Trap and Shock Arrow are used together.
The reason for this is that the Crusher Trap is a one-hit KO.
And so when we combine these two things together,
there is a different emotion and more variety
established through the combination of those two
elements.
So the deeper the player gets into the game,
the more they know about the game,
and the more you can promote challenge, strategy,
and metagaming through the existing mechanics.
And the net result is still interesting gameplay, right?
It's still variety.
Finally, I'll keep this one really quick.
Once we had good level-to-level flow,
players were still not really understanding,
or certain players were still not really understanding where
they could and couldn't explore.
And we believed pretty strongly from a level design
perspective that the hub was the right way to go,
that we'd done all the right work,
and that we'd created a good, overarching format.
But some players just really needed
to be hit over the head that they could explore.
They needed that final confirmation.
So to solve this, we collaborated with the writers
so that whenever the player re-enters the hub,
they're given an additional line of dialogue
from Kratos and Atreus, indicating that it
might be a good time to explore.
You can actually see here that whenever they step
through these two doors, they'll get a little line of dialogue,
and they'll say something like, hey, maybe we
should go exploring right now.
What do you think, Dad?
But the thing is.
We had to write them so many times so that it was never
mandating the player to do so.
And so with some of these things,
it really does come down to play testing and trying
a variety of different lines and trying
a different group of reads.
Finally, hubs are not open worlds.
Well, one interesting conflict here
is whether we needed to align too much to the purity
of a wheel-spoke format.
Let's take a look at it one more time.
You can see here that the hub-spoke is a literal circle.
which is great on paper.
It gives us a very clear understanding
of how it's meant to work.
It's a very clear design trope.
It's very clear on what we're trying to deliver.
But as you can see, the pure nature of a circle
doesn't really give the environment team
much wiggle room to deliver on the fantasy
of a fabulous Norse lush landscape, right?
So what we have to consider is, can we deliver on a hub
if the elements are made a bit more organic?
This is what it would look like if it was a pure circle.
And this is kind of what it ended up like.
So you have to start wondering, once we've
got this structural center and we have these pathways which
are retained very clearly, how else can we
accentuate the hub-like nature while also delivering
on the organics?
And the answer was that all around the Lake of Nine,
there's these additional towers.
And even though they may not necessarily
create a pure circle, per se, in terms of a barrier,
they do help to create an additional anchor that
helps us emphasize the hub.
So even though the level itself became more organic,
there's still enough hub-like elements
that we can retain the core design intent
while also supporting the needs of the environment art team.
So.
I mentioned at the top of the presentation
that this project actually did have a lot of risks, right?
And even though from a technical standpoint,
areas like the Lake of Nine, which
was created and led by Luis Sanchez and John Palamarchuk,
they worked on it for a long time.
And it was a huge technical task to get it up and running.
But the nice thing about some of these design rules
is that they're pretty easy for us to understand and get
excited about.
They're mostly what I would consider
to be design classics.
They're not that fancy.
You can see how having a unique item
and a lot of variety in each level
is going to drive themes and make things fun, right?
You can see how having a hub will be a good,
overarching wrapper to a game and to an exploration experience.
And that's why sometimes going with a design classic
is really great.
Amongst all the technical challenges
or additional creative challenges
that we're trying to solve together,
a design classic can sort of let you predict head a little bit.
You're confident that it's going to come together,
and you can focus a little bit more
on the day-over-day challenges.
So if I can leave you with one kind of wrap-up thought,
it's this.
I love a design classic.
They let you create foundation.
They're awesome.
They give you structure.
They give you canvas, all the building blocks for a game.
But they are pretty much just that.
From there, it's really over to the team
and over to creativity and over to variety.
You do need a strong foundation, and you
do need a strong design canvas.
But a canvas is not inherently interesting on its own.
So I'll leave you with one final rule.
Because the thing that elevates a design canvas
into an actual experience is a lot of creators
coming together to add texture.
Thank you.
I think we have a couple of quick minutes.
And I will mention at this point, we are hiring.
And we're trying to make a really big game again.
In some form or another, we're always excited about new people joining the team.
And they're not all from huge AAA backgrounds.
A lot of people come from different backgrounds.
Yes?
Hi.
So, one comment, one question.
I liked how you kept coming back to the six rules card.
That was inherently your hub in this presentation.
Thank you.
And then the second, the question is,
and you kind of spoke about this at the end.
But there was a very clear format for introducing new items, new abilities, and then carrying them forward.
But could you speak a little bit about how you brought items, like legacy items,
essentially that you'd already taught earlier in the game, and brought them back later in the game type thing?
Yes, wherever possible, we try to make sure that the level has an overarching theme,
but it should never come at the cost of additional variety.
So mixing and matching previous levels mechanics, as long as they're taught correctly,
and as long as we have confidence that the player knows how to use them,
again, you can create a lot of variety by mixing and matching those correctly.
So for example, Atreus and his rules are taught very early in the game,
and those are leveraged all the way through the course of the game with additional mechanics.
Okay, cool. Thank you.
Yeah.
Oh, let's go with the left side, maybe.
OK.
So I was wondering, actually, when
you mentioned that you use metrics
as a rule for the level design, did you also
support it with analytics or some sort of thing like that?
Or was it more like general metrical guidelines, really,
for level design?
Yeah, we use a few Maya tools, for example, for the slopes to detect whether something is actually to metric or not.
For the most part, it is down to the taste of the designer and the environment artists to stick to the rules.
If the game comes up with bugs, you'll know why, because it probably didn't hit the metrics.
And the analytics are mostly used for player feedback and for combat tuning, testing, economy,
and sort of more broader reaching things that are harder for us to test with our hands.
Gotcha. Thanks.
Yeah.
Hi, thanks for the talk.
I'm sorry if I spoiled this for someone.
You talked about the central hub at a horizontal level,
but one of the particularities of that central hub
is that it's also vertical.
It has a lot of verticality,
and I wonder if you could elaborate
on what went into designing
that sort of like water temple-ish theme.
Yes, very early on part of the fantasy of the lake of nine was that it would be a double-stacked hub and
That was a very early decision because as you're alluding to it's a huge amount of design work to plan for that and to account
For that so I wouldn't necessarily recommend retrofitting it at the last second
Because we didn't and it was thought about for a very long time
There were many experiments and prototypes in terms of the content
There's an overarching rule that it should be fun at level one and fun at level two, but for different reasons
So at level one, it's more about the questing experience
and reminding you how to fight,
teaching you the ropes of exploration in the game.
And at level two, as I mentioned, it's more about mastery.
And it's some of the more difficult puzzles
and difficult scenarios in the game.
Since they're optional, that's great for us
because a lot of the designers actually love
building those more complex scenarios.
So it was a perfect opportunity to put complexity
with optional drive matched together.
Thank you. Yeah.
Yes.
So, you mentioned that you introduced a new mechanic or ability about 90 minutes or 2
hours, something like that.
I was just wondering how do you make it so a player doesn't get bored of it?
Because a lot of times I've seen many games that you get a new ability and players just
like that half an hour and they're all, okay, what's next?
Right.
I think that's a great takeaway.
Goal should not be to come up with more mechanics.
If you run into that problem, the goal
should be to evaluate whether you've created
enough interesting scenarios.
So as I showed you earlier, even just
inside the pillar of combat, there's
a lot of different versatility you can create inside that.
If you're willing to add a timer to something or a depth
to something, you can take a look at that mechanic
and start to think, what vectors have we not utilized
this mechanic for already?
And if players are saying they're bored,
you can take a look at that mechanic
and start to think, what vectors have we not utilized
It might be the mechanic, but it might also be that the scenarios aren't pushing the player's brain in enough different directions, right?
Okay, thank you.
Yeah.
Hi, thank you for the talk.
One thing that was quite amazing in God of War was the fact that the collectible placement.
When I was looking for them, I couldn't find any.
And when I stopped looking for them, I usually ended up having 100% completion of levels.
And it felt like you had a really keen understanding of the player psychology, what they were going to look at.
And could you elaborate on the processes that come with that?
When did you add it?
the collectibles, where you're looking at playtest
and things like that.
Any collectibles in particular?
Ravens, mostly.
Which ones?
Ravens.
Oh, ravens.
Okay, I would say, put simply,
for some of the more bespoke collectibles,
hmm, how can I describe it?
The game rewards players who explore by beating the curve.
The game is not so huge.
It looks bigger than it is if you actually look at the geo.
So by circling around the space a lot,
you may feel like you're discovering it on your own.
But more likely scenario is that you've just
gone past that area a lot of times
or that you'd stumbled across it a little bit.
So for example, the language disks.
Most players feel like they discover them on their own,
and players who go exploring will discover them.
But there's an additional set in the critical path levels
for players who didn't go exploring,
and both groups of players will still stumble
across those advanced collectibles together.
For the runes, it's a little bit more complicated,
but I hope I've given you enough to go on.
Okay, thanks.
Yeah, I think, one more from each side, yeah.
In the level design process, I know it's really important,
especially in a game like this, you have a heavy combat side,
but you also have to really balance it out with puzzles,
puzzles with the characters.
At what point is it you really went combat first really heavy
and then you said, well, let's think about the puzzles,
or did you immediately say,
we have to think about both evenly?
And what was that process like for the team?
Great question. One of the solutions to this in the game was the triple chests, as they're called, or the Nornir chests.
They are a terrific addition to the game because they don't impact the layouts or the environment art the way, like, a full room scenario would,
and they let us look back at things that were maybe previously combat spaces that might not have as much adventuring or exploration in there as we'd like,
and they were a particularly good way to sort of...
bring the balance together in areas that were sort of maybe mismatched.
Hi, so I was curious, given the way that hubs work and how shared the mechanics were across
many of the levels, how difficult did that make pivoting in the design and direction for levels?
Like were there any special challenges with that?
Yes, and I would say that Santa Monica Studios is one studio where we value the environment
art very highly and the workflow environment artists very highly.
So that decision to make a hub was extraordinarily early in the project.
There were other different models that we looked at and other different ideas, but once
we committed to that hub design, there was sort of no going back.
We had to just...
Really nail it and all the way in the last six months of the project. It was nerve-wracking
But as I mentioned Luis Sanchez John Palamarchuk and Florian Strauss
They really pulled through on it
And I really respect how much everyone just kind of stuck to their guns and kept going
Because it was very integral to the game by that point
OK, last one.
Yeah.
Hi, Rob.
Thanks for the talk.
I was wondering if you have some guidelines in order
to design side missions or optional areas,
thinking about what you said, that at the end
of every critical pod level, you have to get a new ability.
So how you could design side missions,
making them interesting and satisfactory to the player
at the end?
I'll speak on behalf of our exploration lead a little bit here, and I hope I express his
philosophies correctly.
He has often mentioned to me that he believes once there was a strong narrative thread through
the side missions that it really created a lot more drive for players because they actually
liked Kratos and Atreus as a partnership together.
And when they lacked narrative, it was problematic.
the additional narrative through line of those side missions is critical.
And also the reward tuning on them.
If you have a bad reward at the end of those,
if players are giving you a one through five, if they don't like the reward,
it doesn't matter what happened.
They'll just give you a one or something like that.
They didn't like the reward.
So you got to really get the rewards correct.
And you really have to have it can't just live on gameplay.
There also has to be like a strong narrative through line as well.
Thank you. And happy GDC.