My name is Brian Francis. I am a contributing editor at gamasutra.com and at GDC.
I'm the community manager slash video person in general,
uh, who's around the office, uh, figuring out how to make things like this happen.
Um, it's lovely to see you all today.
I hope some of you are coming here from the Gamasutra...
channel which is where some of you may know my face and voice from. We are here
today because for the first time ever we're going to be using the GDC Twitch
channel to host conversations with game developers as we get ready for GDC 2019.
I think our game's coming into demand so I'm gonna turn it down just a little.
Usually, oh that's why it's loud, that's different.
Okay, fix that. Right, if you don't know what GDC is, it's the Game Developers Conference.
I can see in chat or can recognize CliftonB as someone who I've seen replying to our social media.
Just going to give a shout out to NovenWorks2.
We are here today with our first ever stream with a game called Return of the Obra Dinn.
This comes from developer Lucas Pope and normally I'm the person who is
Invisible in these chats so that you can see our guests face
But today our guest has opted to remain in the shadows and speak from a distance
Lucas how are you doing? I'm doing great. Hey everybody
We are here this game came out Return of the Obra Dinn came out a couple weeks ago
It's been in development for how many years Lucas?
four and a half from start to finish
four-and-a-half years and it is uh... the the is perpetually mercantile a
actually have over here
uh...
the uh...
uh... mercantile mystery i think is the phrasing on your insurance inspector
checking out the ship uh... the overdue images returned to harbor and using a
mysterious tool that lets you
uh... relive
uh... the events of certain people's death
to find out how they died and figure out what happened uh...
as you can see uh... today we're playing uh... we're playing the game but we're
looking at some footage i already captured of me playing it
so what you're seeing isn't
live, so you won't be able to yell at me if I'm getting stuff wrong, but you will be able
to ask Lucas about questions about what you're seeing if you had a similar experience.
Clifton, to answer your question in chat, this is the first hour of the game, we're
only going to go for an hour, so the only spoilers will be me figuring out a few of
the mysteries, or maybe I got them wrong.
Maybe the spoiler is that I am bad at video games.
In chat, quick shoutouts to Elka Hao, Sesshi, oh Sesshi we had you on the channel on the
Gamasutra a while back, I recognize your name.
Volkiller Games, Starlight Skies, a lot of great people in chat.
We really want your questions for Lucas today because as good as my questions are, if you
are in the business of making games yourself, you should absolutely be asking Lucas what
his experience was working on Obra Dinn.
Lucas, my first question for you today, I think a lot of people have heard of you because
of Papers, Please.
How did you transition from Papers, Please to working on Return of the Obra Dinn?
Good question.
I basically wanted to do something totally different from Papers, Please.
That's generally how I move on to the next project.
It's so tired of whatever I was doing before, I want to change everything up.
And Obra Dinn, Papers, Please was kind of designed first.
Projects where I had the idea for the mechanics and this one overden was visuals for some more art focused
I wanted to make something one bit. Mm-hmm and just kind of banging on that for a while ended up with this
Setting on the ship and then after a few months the core concept of figuring out how people died
Right on. I think it's actually, I think maybe it's worth stopping there on the art focus for a moment.
We have an old feature from gamasutra.com talking to you about the 1-bit ditherpunk, is the way we phrased it.
I don't know if that's entirely accurate.
What exactly is this 1-bit aesthetic? What inspired you to chase to work on a game with it?
And how does it work? Because it's really beautiful.
Thank you. Yeah, so Daedalic Punk is a great word, actually. I love that word.
And that article is the first time I heard it. It's basically me taking what I played as a kid,
which is Macintosh Plus games, which were one bit. And for the time they were actually
high resolution. It was only 512 by 342 or something crazy like that, but it's on a nine
inch screen. So it was very sharp, very striking for me as a kid. And I played a lot of games that
way. And I.
Specifically remember never thinking it's hard to members and not thinking something but for me I never thought I want more colors here
I to me it always looked beautiful in one bit and
so
Papers, please had some level of art in it, but it wasn't really art focused and I like to pretend I'm an artist
so I thought what I want to do is take this one bit style that I played as a kid and try to
Make it legible and playable now using modern technology. So that was
the idea and then I mocked up a few things which is interesting to me is
that title screen
for the game is the first thing I ever mocked up in one bit
in Photoshop. It's also the first thing that I made in Unity
and it didn't change for the entire four and a half years
so that basically once I got that working it taught me that
it was possible and it could look cool and that sent me four years down the line.
Nice. I think when I was doing some research for this game I found some great gifs about how you were trying to make this work for the ship itself.
We're looking now on screen at some really good people model, the architecture of the ship itself.
What's the process for starting at, it has to be a 1-bit ship, and making sure that these people, these objects are still legible.
Because you can kind of see a difference between the people and the gun.
Like the captain here, I guess it's a spoiler that he's the captain.
So careful about that. Literally everyone's identity on the stream is a spoiler, so if you're sensitive...
But yeah, the gun he's holding there is obviously very different from his own model himself.
What's... what's... what's... how come?
Yeah, okay, so the first thing I did was I played some old actual Mac first-person games,
and the best one that I could find was something called Colony.
And it's a very low-poly, just-the-walls kind of thing.
One of the things from playing that game and also playing some modern 1-bit games where they just take the render and they dither it.
And it looks cool, but you can't see what's going on. You can't see anything.
So in these modern games, in the colony you can see everything very clearly.
And I decided that everything is going to have an outline.
So geometric shapes are going to be outlined.
And if it's against white, they'll have a black outline. If it's against black, they'll have a white outline.
So there's always an inverse and there's always...
the shapes and geometry are always clear to see.
And the thing about that is that it removes any
mystery about where you are or the environment. Everything is perfectly
defined basically. Which was fine because I wasn't making a horror game so I
didn't want to hide things in the player. It was okay that everything was
was you could tell where you were at all times. It's kind of what I was going for.
So that's that that was on the surface a simple
thing that like how can I make this work? Okay everything is outlined.
But as the
the kind of production progress, the bigger problem became comfort, viewing comfort.
Because everything, you've only got two colors to work with and you need to make shades out
of those using dithering.
But dithering is not a technology that you want to use in a moving picture basically,
because it gives you a headache more or less.
There's too many flashing pixels, high contrast pixels.
The real magic for me in making this work was solving that dithering problem and figuring
out how to make it so people could play a four-hour game without getting massively uncomfortable.
Right on.
What were the first, you said it's uncomfortable to look at, what were the first solutions
that worked in terms of getting people, like in terms of lowering discomfort?
Which is, I don't think, usually I'm asking developers about that when we're in VR, but
I haven't asked a developer about that in conventional games in some time.
Yeah, the first solution is just to increase the resolution.
So your pixels are smaller, so that when you dither, your eyes
fold more into thinking it's a tone instead of just a bunch of
dots. But one of the other like, I want it to be one bit, but I
also want it to be low resolution. And that was partly
because of production, it makes it easier to create this thing
when it's not super high res.
But also, I just like that style more. I like the lower resolution. I like trying to do more with less pixels.
So when I decided I couldn't raise the resolution to solve that,
I put off the problem for a long time, a couple years.
And then finally when I started, I had enough to sort of sit down and play a lot of it full screen in front of me.
I changed the dither pattern basically.
So it wasn't trying to be shade so much as it was trying to be kind of a woodcut,
more patterned style.
Which worked okay. It worked fine to me. It looked okay.
But in the TIGSource devlog, which I kept for the game, nobody else liked it. Everybody hated it.
So I kind of went back to the drawing board and devised a dithering technique that keeps the dither sort of fixed when you're looking around.
So when you turn your head, the dither pattern is not sort of sliding across as you would expect. It's moving with the scene.
And that took a lot of time to get right.
And in the end, you don't really notice it.
Except that...
My hope is that you don't get sick as much as you would have with the other one.
I'm not saying I fixed everything, but it makes it much more comfortable to look at
when you're just standing there looking around.
Right on.
Moving on from the art, although if folks in questions have chat, feel free to...
Feel free to ask them. Clifton points out that NUendo Studios talks about how the 1-bit graphics of Obra Dinn are sort of different than the 1-bit graphics of the Macintosh games.
My next question is going to be about that process of moving from this art style into the design of the game. Because it's interesting to hear about you going from design first to art first.
After you had the art style...
what was your process for figuring out the like what was what was fun about
this style like what where did the where did the design interaction come from
uh originally i had big plans for this game that you would actually go back in time and you would
relive the death but everything was moving you'd have to replay how they died so there was this
idea that you go back in time someone's got to die it's either going to be you or the person
that you're sort of embodying anyways that was way too much work nothing i could do
But once I started getting this rendering technique down and started getting some visuals up and some characters on screen, I realized it looks good just as it is.
If you could walk around a still scene, that would look good.
So the idea sort of changed to be, just go back and hear the audio and then see the frozen scene.
And that took me through the initial demo.
I think there were four people in the initial demo for this in 2014.
And that was easy. Whatever dialogue or characters or text I wrote then was with nothing else in mind.
I didn't have any of the story written at that time. Just kind of,
okay, these guys will be fighting over something and the captain ends up killing a bunch of them or whatever.
That worked for the progress I'd made at that time.
And I kind of stuck with this idea that the game would be about figuring out how people died.
I stuck with that for a long time.
until I realized that's not hard to tell usually. You can usually see how people die pretty
easily. Like this guy. Yeah, I mean he's getting hit by somebody so not much challenge there.
But it wasn't until I kind of had a lot more of the game done that I realized the real
fun part would be figuring out who they are. That would lead into ways I can create clues
in the environment and have the player kind of work out a clue-like or a Moriarty-like
puzzle, like this old game, kind of logic puzzle to figure out who people are.
that design shifted. That shift happened kind of late, I want to say, because
working out the narrative structure for this game was pretty tough. You can only tell the story when
somebody dies, first off, and then I also needed to have this kind of almost unbroken chain of bodies
going back through time, which, you know, probably isn't that normal. And so I decided to break it
up into chapters or disasters and then lay everything out like that. That structure was
extremely difficult to figure out.
which tied my hands a bit because I might have changed design in a different way if
I hadn't gone and put all that work into the story.
But once I put all the work into the story, I was stuck with it and I had to figure out
a way to make it work.
And that way was basically the book and focusing more on the identities than the means of death.
That's really interesting.
So kind of the order is art, revisiting a death.
Figuring out who the people are who died not how they died although as you can see how they died is still part of it
And then segmenting and splintering the stories, and I just want to point out for everyone at home
I'm about just I think I'm about to know I didn't wind up scrolling through the whole list
But um it's 60 plus people right on the boat. That's 60 plus bodies. Yeah, and that's a case where it's a lot
Yeah, when I decided that it's gonna be on a ship because I thought that would be easy
I can model a ship four decks of the ship no problem. That was my first
Big mistake on the game.
But once I decided that, I did a lot of research on these ships, and I started building the ship.
And then, I don't know why, but I looked at the number of the people that you would need to
sail one of these ships, and it was maybe 120 people, 200 people.
And obviously I knew, okay, I'm smart enough, I can't do 120 people, but maybe I could do 80.
So my first number was 80 people.
And then when I actually made all the characters, I realized, damn, the most I can do is 60.
I'm going crazy doing his characters, so I'll stop at 60.
But this was all before I'd worked out the story.
So if I'd worked out the story first, there'd be 12 people on the tiny sailboat, basically.
But because I worked on the ship and the reality of what you would need to sail these ships,
I started super high, and I felt like every time I cut it down, I was going to compromise
the game, not realizing that I was still going to kill myself to try to finish 60 people.
I'm gonna have questions about quote-unquote killing yourself later on because you know production quality of life
These are things that developers are talking about
2018 but
Just to keep us roughly on track here
so I had another game developer on the stream once tell me that the difference between
Like the thing that I thought about especially when it comes to like the number of factors in making a game is
difference from zero to one is shorter than the distance from one to two
Um...
Uh...
And I guess I'm curious, every time, I mean...
You started off with 80 and then dropped down to 60.
How much does one character, like, increase the load, I guess?
Like, do you know roughly how, from a dev standpoint,
how much time that cutting those 20 people shaved off?
Uh, no, I couldn't say that.
Actually making the characters themselves is not hard.
The hard part is weaving that into a story that I felt wouldn't start dragging or...
Mm-hmm.
having too much for the player to worry about I mean at that point when I chose
60 I was awesome by the way sorry real just the scene right here when this pops
up this is incredible thank you yeah but continue at that time I wasn't I don't
know I wasn't thinking about much of arranging the story or the players
experience or anything I was just thinking about I need a bunch of people
for the ship and I'll figure out the rest later and I I had the manifest
still
And that's all I had, it was just a list of the names.
So the project kind of scaled at different times.
At some point, this doesn't scale, so I gotta scale it up.
And then I move over to some other thing,
and that doesn't scale, so I gotta scale it up.
And they all kind of scale in different ways
without really changing the other elements of the game,
because I didn't want to remake them.
Or I felt like I could still do something good with them,
so keep those and scale this guy up.
And that comment about zero to one and one to two,
for me, was absolutely true for the beginning of the game.
because I created the demo in just a few months, the initial demo,
but everything that I had for that demo did not scale.
So the fact that there are four characters there, I was already pushing
up against all the pipeline and tools, custom things I created to make those
four guys. So that there was no way that the tools and
the systems I had would scale up to 60 people. So
that added almost another year of scaling up to the point where I could
make the full game from the demo. And this is true of every game I've ever
worked on. If you look at like the first prototype of anything...
it's hard to imagine how much time it took to go from that to the final thing
because in a lot of cases it looks just like the final game with some small
differences
but in most cases you had to change everything about your production and the
way you made the game in order to get from that first initial thing to the end
right on uh... i i could
kinda i want to uh... i guess i want to lean into
you know having now like from papers please
What is your guiding star when you have a cool idea, you begin working on the idea,
you work on the demo, the prototype, and you think you have these sets of tools that will
get you through the whole game.
What's your guiding star when moving between demo to full game, or proof of concept to
full game that you think other indie developers could learn from?
For me, it was potential. So once I had made the demo, if I feel there's potential there,
and if other people who play it feel there's potential there, it doesn't matter if I can
reach that or if I have any idea how to reach it. If it has potential, then it's enough.
Because that's enough for me to get thinking about it more.
So...
When I transitioned from Papers, Please to Obertin,
during the development of Papers, Please,
I had collected a lot of game ideas.
I'm always writing down kind of game ideas
in a notebook somewhere or something,
just like quick, one-off ideas
of something that could become a game.
And the ones that I think about the most
are the ones that I work on next.
So even though there's lots of ideas there,
some of them, even without checking a notebook,
they keep coming back in my mind
and I'm thinking about them.
So that becomes the next game I work on.
And it was the case with this demo that,
If I release a demo, people enjoy it and they think it has a lot of potential and I keep thinking about it.
I keep working through my mind what that potential could be or how it could be executed.
Then that's it. That's good for me.
Nice. I guess, let me go really quick while I'm going through my question bucket.
I'm going to remind chat that you can ask questions too.
And especially if you are working on a game of your own, please ask them.
My game working experience is... I've got some, but it's not as much as I'm sure some of you folks at home have.
And we'd love to ask them for you. That's what GDC and Gamasutra are all about.
Which, I guess I should... I guess I need to give the obligatory that GDC and Gamasutra are both owned by the same parent organization, blah blah blah.
One question that comes from my good colleague Alex Walro, who's normally with me when we're doing these streams, but is sadly not with us today, because the hour is late here in California.
What has proven interesting about the plebeian and the mundane in your design? You've now made a game about an insurance agent, you've made a game about a border agent, newspaper editors.
Why do these genres catch your attention and what do you think...
What do you think it takes to translate the boring into the interesting for game design?
For the first question, when it comes to design, I'm a big fan of rigid core mechanics.
So something very basic and simple that you're doing, and you're kind of filling out a matrix
of features or a list of identities.
Something simple and core.
Just as a kind of...
slightly OCD engineer, I like that.
So that's where I come from on the design side.
On the other side, I really like taking those things
and making something interesting out of them, story-wise.
You know, there are people around the world
who do all kinds of jobs, all the time.
And many of those jobs are boring and mundane,
but those people have interesting lives to me.
So I like trying to capture the interesting parts
of a mundane experience.
And that's...
that works really well when you like mundane mechanics because the two of them
go together those two interests go together really well so that's kind of
what directs me to pick an idea and to develop it and then evolve it into a full game
and then the second part of that question was um uh or maybe you explained it was sort of
what is your mindset about taking those mundane parts or the the interesting parts of mundane
things and making them playable
There's a nice challenge there, I guess.
In every project I do, I approach it like an engineer.
So, as if there's a problem that needs to be solved.
So if there's no problem, then I'm not that interested.
But if there's a problem, if there's some restriction or some limitation,
then I'm interested suddenly.
That's why I have one bit.
That's why I have simple mechanics that you wouldn't expect
to build a story out of.
I try to do exactly that.
Just because solving those problems are the most interesting
and fun parts of game development for me.
Yeah, I guess that makes sense. I guess like it wouldn't, um, under that philosophy, it makes more sense to make games like this as opposed to games, you know, as opposed to like a very polished 2D side-scroller that, uh, that can do well on PS4, I guess.
Yeah, I wouldn't know how to make that kind of game, because I don't, I don't understand the problems that, yeah, I don't see the problems that would be fun to solve there, basically.
Right. Not to slam... my comment isn't to slam that genre of game, of course, because I really love those kind of games.
Like Owlboy is one of my favorites, for instance. But that was just a comparison.
I have more questions, but we're going to give chat a shot.
Starlight Skies says they work at IndieCade.
And they would like to know how much feedback from going to events has helped you out.
I would layer that question with how do you organize your event feedback so that it's useful,
and how do you make sure you're getting good feedback and not feedback from someone who would never buy the game in real life,
but they just happen to be there.
Oh, right, this scene.
First off, HiStar. We've met a couple times at different events.
So, that's a good question.
I live in the middle of nowhere.
I was telling you earlier, and I don't see anybody basically related to games for most
of the time.
So, I have an online presence, but physically I don't meet a lot of game developers or players
even.
So, events for me are mostly about getting feedback.
I don't publicize that much when I go to an event.
I don't do any marketing or anything.
I set up a booth and I try to watch people play the game.
And so, for me, that's critical.
And that's not necessarily perfect.
Showing a game at an event is very different than watching someone play it alone in their room or something like that.
But, it's for me a good way to gauge what's...
It's a good way to compare it against other games.
It's kind of a, are people playing this game compared to some other games?
In isolation it's not that useful, except if somebody gets stuck.
If everybody's getting stuck somewhere, okay I need to change this.
Or if everybody's confused about something, then I feel like okay I need to change that.
But it's more...
how many people are playing this game, how many people are interested, how many people come over to check it out,
because it's surrounded by other way cooler games and lots of people playing lots of different stuff.
So to me, the value of an event is mostly in just determining how it fits with other games.
And as far as organizing that feedback, I don't really.
It's whatever kind of bubbles to the top.
is what I think about and think of fixing. I'll write down some things usually if people are
getting stuck somewhere, but it's more kind of the general feeling of how it's going and how
the game is doing and what people think of it. And this ties in, this is kind of a general philosophy
of mine where I used to make games, I made a game for iOS called Helsing's Fire and back then, this
was in 2010 or something,
Back then it was really important to get analytics to record what everybody was doing, how far
they got, basically all this information that lets you design a better game.
And so I recorded a ton of analytics for everybody who played this game and I never looked at
them.
So after that incident where I put all this work into collecting information but never
actually looking at it, because I was, I'm always on to the next thing, I don't really
want to make a Hellsing's Fire 2 and to improve and to fix everything, I just want to do something
totally different.
So.
I kind of got into the situation where I'm not going to really...
I'm not going to do the analytic thing, basically, which a lot of people do for design.
I'm just going to try to hear the problems, understand the problems, and fix them as they
come up.
And if I don't hear it, then I never fix it, you know, which is kind of the downside of
that whole thing.
But so far, it's worked out okay, and it will probably crash and burn for the next one.
Uh, once again, I hate to feel like I'm just overly praising, but that was like the way these
scenes start, like the really striking images that you bash into. Holy crap, cow, like playing this
game, this experience that we're playing right here, you can see me just freeze and just stare
at it a minute before and sinking it in before like actually starting to move around. Cool.
That was one of the things that, yeah, about the very first demo that told me that this could work.
The way that the basic structure of hearing the audio.
and then slamming into the 3D scene with the music at the same time, I felt, okay, I could
do some cool stuff with that from the very beginning.
Clifton B would like to know, is the Memento Mortum at all inspired by the memory amulet
from Myst IV?
I never played Myst, actually.
Fair.
So, no.
It's a game that I wanted to play for a long time, but there's this thing where if you
miss a game when it first comes out, you almost never go back to it.
That was my case with Myst, unfortunately I never played it.
Um...
I guess that loosely wanders us over to game marketing,
because I assume, you know, it's very important for you to get Obra Dinn in people's hands now,
because later there will be, you know, Red Dead Redemption 3 or whatever, and not Obra Dinn.
How much time and energy did you spend on game marketing?
Since you said you didn't use events to market, you used them primarily for feedback.
And how did you set a sales expectation that you knew could keep you fed so that you could
work on making Papers, Please 2, Electric Boogaloo?
Let's see.
I didn't...
Papers, Please... so first off...
I'm not the marketing kind of guy. I didn't market Papers, Please at all and that was a huge success.
So, already I'm being trained that marketing is not critical to selling your game and to having people play it.
And Papers, Please sold really well and it still sells well.
And so, there was no real pressure on me over DIN to say I gotta market this thing and it's gotta sell a lot.
And so I didn't. And I kept the devlog because I like to talk about the stuff I'm working on.
when I work on different stuff in the game, when I finish something, it's cathartic for me to write a devlog post about it.
So it feels good and I like sharing that information.
So the devlog is really the only thing that I did that I would consider marketing, even though for me
it was a more of an engineering thing than it was a marketing thing.
And
Obra Dinn for me,
so I had Papers, Please and it was selling well, and it's kind of the only game I've made that sold really well.
But it's still selling well now. And so that tells me that if I can make the right kind of game,
then it's not something that needs to sell in the first three months only.
And then I don't need to make all my money at the beginning,
and I don't need to push this really hard to get it to sell or to make a return on it.
And so for Obra Dinn, I focus more on how can I make this game different enough from other games?
And Papers, Please is sort of like this too.
Make it different enough from other games that if you want this kind of game,
you pretty much just got to buy this one game. If you want a game where you check passports,
you got, there's one game on the market that's like that and it's Papers, Please.
So if you want a one-bit mystery game based on deduction, you know, or whatever kind of category
I wanted to put this in, if you want that, then you got, I mean, there's Overden and there's maybe
a few others, but really, like, I'm not competing with tons of different titles all the time that
they're coming out every month. So the urgency of selling immediately and of doing the typical big
marketing push with.
influencers and and whatever they do these days what was what was never really there for me from you know from internally it wasn't there
from my own personal satisfaction, and then I felt like
The way I was making the game over these years also didn't require that kind of that kind of push
right on I
Think that's a very valid answer
Poor unfortunately for poor sky yes guys like no I do marketing so ouch
It's, it's, um, I, I, I guess that I have, I wanna, I guess I'll, Astrodongs, which is quite a name,
um, just wants to say, uh, thanks for one of their favorite game experiences in years, so, uh, and it
felt like a game catered to their particular interests, which kinda speaks to what you talked
about of, like, making something that will appeal to, uh,
Someone and trusting that there are multiple someone's out there. I guess that's a lot of what you said today
Yeah, it's oh that someone has always been me first
Yeah
I try to make the game that I because I I do play a lot of triple-a games and I love triple-a games and I
Play all that stuff, but I I also really like these kind of very mechanical games that I make so
I'm always thinking okay. I would like this kind of game and I hope other people do too
And that's that was kind of a distant wish
Originally, but since paper is please I realized well, okay
There are enough people out there who like the same kinds of things that I do that will
That will buy the games basically that will enjoy them just a fair warning for folks at home Liam has entered the room
Liam do you want to say hi?
Liam?
Everyone can actually say hi to Liam for once
He's here. He's yelling. He has opinions. You may hear him any questions any questions for the cat?
I as a quick follow-up
It's interesting that you talk about how having there's only one passport checking game on the market
I guess there's two now because I don't know I don't know there might be more
I guess maybe a bunch of other people jumped on the papers. Please train that you built, but um for sure we streamed
Um not tonight
Forgetting the developer name, but it was published by normal robots
Which disclosure my boss Simon helps them out?
We gotta do a lot of disclaimers on this show. We're just trying to you know keep no Liam. Don't you that I need that controller
Please don't chew that.
Hang on.
Come here.
Okay, you're joining the stream now.
Okay.
Um, was there ever, this is something a couple other indies have been worried about now for
a couple years, like Donut County.
Was there ever any worry about, uh, about another debt, another company swooping in
and like also doing the one bit thing or also doing the detective thing?
Hmm, no.
No.
Okay.
I mean, I, I, yeah.
I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I,
I for not tonight for example I mean I'm happy to see that kind of game I'm
happy to see all the games that were based yeah and I you know I wish them
all the best and to be clear I'm not accusing not tonight of stealing your
style I'm just like yeah right they aren't and you know when I said the only
passport came out there I'm speaking of when I started over Dan and what you
know for the last couple years there are other games like it now but originally
if you wanted that kind of game you had to buy papers please so I get a couple
years of you know the only option out there which is what I was hoping for
over Dan and so if other people make one bit
games or detect the games totally fine I I will probably just do something totally
different next time anyway so I'm not competing with them or myself or anything like that later
so I personally I I have no problem with that and on sort of another level I when I make a game
I don't necessarily think about how hard it would make how hard it'd be for someone else
to make this game but I do think about
what other games could be transformed into this game and how hard would that be?
And I'm not aiming for something totally different because I'm always thinking
I don't want to compete with other people. I'm sort of always thinking how can I do this
thing differently than someone else would do it and that puts gives me a little bit more of a
buffer between my games and other games I think as well. Right on. I'm gonna I'm gonna quickly
check. Thank you all in chat for your love for Liam. He appreciates it. He's a sad boy.
ElCalho would like to know how experienced were you in Unity when you started development
and how much of the game's development time was spent learning Unity?
Unity I'd never used before this game.
Like I said, the title screen was the first thing I ever made in Unity.
I have written my own engines though, C++ engines, and I've been a programmer for a
long time in games, so picking up and using Unity was actually very quick.
And that quickness and speed with which I made the title screen convinced me that Unity was definitely the way to go for this project.
And
Based on my experience of making tools for AAA games and
Kind of working with lots of really good engines over time is that Unity is amazing
and
especially for me on the editor side the fact that you can
Add features to the editor and change things and then just alt tab back to the editor and in one second
It's compiled and updated and you can now use your new tools
was a revelation, and so learning Unity was easy because a lot of people use it, and then
using it was basically what allowed me to make this game.
Even if we talk about how long it took, it wasn't because of Unity.
Unity shaved a lot of time off this game, and a lot of energy and effort was saved by
using Unity basically, and I'm extremely happy with it.
Right on. We're moving on to the next subject of conversation. I want to follow up. You did say that you had to put a lot of work into making these 60 characters happen at the top of the stream.
2018 and 2017 have been years where developers have talked a lot about crunch, they've talked a lot about overwork. I think it's interesting in that the reason I think these two years of discussion have been particularly notable is that
It seems like a two years where a lot of developers big and small are trying to make concentrated
efforts to say it does not take 100 hour work weeks to make interesting video games.
Like they're trying to unhinge causation and correlation there.
What was your work-life balance like working on Obra Dinn, and did you learn anything from
your previous games that helped you take it easier on this project, make right decisions
about working long hours? What was your experience?
Well, I worked a lot on this game. One of the problems with this game is that when I started it, I thought it would take me 3-6 months to finish.
Well, that escalated quick.
Yeah, unrealistically quick. I'm extremely bad at judging deadlines like that, or judging progress.
So, imagine at 6 months, I'm basically crunching for a while to meet that first deadline.
I sailed past that, and things cooled down a little bit. But then I say, okay, I just need another 6 months.
and then we're good. So the next six months I'm crunching again for a month
to try to hit that deadline and I miss it. So things cool down again.
And imagine that repeated for four years. So I crunched a lot on this game and I
worked a lot on this. So this is unfortunately not a poster for
for easy work. You know it's one person did everything, all the modeling,
design, programming.
Anytime that I got tired of doing one thing, I could switch to the other thing conveniently.
Right? It's great. I could keep working all the time. But the unusual thing here is that it worked
for me. I love to work. It was only near the very end of the project when I could see that the game
was pretty much close to done and just needed some little extra work to finish or some final
polish or some play testing. That's when it got really hard. But every other time, I loved working
on the game. And I worked.
that was, you know, I define my own schedule, so because I love working on the game
I wanted to work on a lot. And then there was this other issue for me
personally, of this is my follow-up game after Papers, Please, which won some awards
and everybody
enjoyed it, so how am I gonna follow that up
basically, so that I can't just like quickly release some
some game I'm not happy with, I need to make it something that I like and I hope
other people will like, and that's
that ends up taking a little bit longer, I'll tell you.
Yeah, I think the only sort of bright side of that is that I define the schedule.
I'm the one who decided I'm going to work all these hours.
Personally, I work at home, so I could spend time with my family.
I wasn't leaving them behind all the time.
I could still just pop downstairs or into the next room and spend some time with them.
So these long work hours for me were something that worked.
It was something that I didn't regret in the end.
I think they were important to making the game, even in four years.
uh... even though i made different parts of the game
well many times over and cut many things and threw a lot of stuff out i feel like
it
generally worked okay for me
i have some regrets about working that much but
because
i am at home working at home
A lot of that stuff is just not as bad as it could have been if I had to go to office
somewhere.
I guess I was going to follow up what you sort of answered in there.
I guess there is a palpable difference between working at home and crunching for yourself
versus going to an office and crunching on a larger company's behalf.
Yeah.
I mean you can imagine like a hobby.
Imagine you have some hobby you really like.
Yeah.
You just do that all the time.
You're not killing yourself.
I mean it's hard physically as you get older.
you still enjoy what you're doing and that's kind of always my situation.
Yeah.
Um...
Uh...
Did you do the music?
Yeah, I did the music.
The cymbal crash, I was going to say, the cymbal crash that happens every time one pops up.
The spirit, you know, wanders around the ship. I was very impressed by that.
Speaking of people who want to talk about features they're impressed with,
Sasquatch, I'm assuming that's how you say your name, wants to say that they like the shake of the magnifying glass.
It helps clarify its use. Same with the stopwatch and the fade in time, which you can see the stopwatch doing that right now.
Talismaniac would like to know,
were you inspired at all by the vanishing of Ethan Carter?
Oh, Liam's back on camera. Say hi to Liam.
Did vanishing of Ethan Carter
influence your design at all here?
That's a good question. So when I released the first demo,
or I think maybe when I started talking about the mechanics in the devlog, people
asked me.
if I was basing this on Ethan Carter, and then the other one was Cryostasis, if this
is based on Cryostasis.
Those are two games I've never played, so no.
I've heard good things about both those games, though, and over the years, let me say it,
so working a lot on this game, I had very little time for other things, so I would give
up, say, playing new games, and I have a huge stack of games that I'm going to try to get
to now that the game is done, and two of those games are Cryostasis and Ethan Carter.
He did Finch as well, I really wanna play that.
So all those games have similar concepts, but I was not influenced by those because I never played them.
I think Liam knows he's on camera because he just walked off camera, but he's still hanging out here.
Sorry, this is the most engaged he's been with a game. I think he really likes you, Lucas.
Yeah, cats when they hear my voice, man. My cat, too. If he hears my voice, he starts, yeah.
Liam belongs to my good friend Kelsey. We're catsitting him, so unfortunately he's not going to be here permanently.
He's a very good pretty boy. These are very important discussions happening on the GDC Twitch channel right now.
I have more questions. We'll take some more from chat as they come.
I remember, I think I was reading through one of these things when I was doing research
and the dithering, to go back to the art and the dithering thing, since I think that's
something a lot of devs are curious about with this game.
How does, you said something that was a challenge early on, I think in some other interview
when it came to compressing video and being able to make trailers for this game.
How did that, how did the one bit resolution effect, like okay, it looks great when it's
running on a computer, but it's time to put a trailer up and oh no.
the Amazon smart machine woke up.
The, like, did that have a thing at all? Is that something you had to be worried about?
Yeah, for sure. This is one of the things where...
This is a really cool problem for me, actually, to have...
to realize there's a problem there and then to have to figure it out.
So I've got a low-resolution 1-bit game with high contrast, so
that does not compress well in any scenario.
So...
I need to think about ways to fix that.
And the first way was, the first thing I did was, this will be kind of technical, but there's
Bayer dither, which is a pattern dither, and there's a blue noise dither, which looks like
random noise dithering.
And Bayer performs really badly for compression.
Because it's a regular grid, it happens to be aliased with the compression blocks of
a video.
So, if you try to do everything Bayer dithered, pattern dithered, then it conflicts with the
pattern of the compression.
and it looks really terrible. But if you use noise dither, then it still looks terrible,
but it doesn't look as bad. So that was the first realization and first fix, and that
gave me hope that maybe this could work. In the end, it doesn't actually work that well,
but whatever, it's good enough.
Don't play it in a movie theater.
Yeah, I kind of like the idea that...
The only way to really see this game as it is, is to play it on a computer.
You can't watch a video of it.
To play the... oh yeah, I guess that's weird.
Like, I think a lot of... I mean, on the one hand, Twitch is good for marketing games.
On the other hand, story-driven games...
You know, people... devs wonder if they're losing customers because they get...
Not in that sense. I don't mind that at all.
Oh, yeah, no, I wasn't... I didn't want to...
People won't play it because it doesn't look good. I mean that...
If you want to see it as it really is...
You've got, you can't just keep cranking up the video res, you've got to play it on a real computer, which is...
It's kind of cool to me.
Yeah, I guess you could say you need to play it on the smallest, like, machine possible? Maybe?
Yeah, right. A 9-inch screen.
Yeah, I have a Windows Surface in the background. I should play it on that and see what happens.
It's probably fine. It's 1080p or whatever.
Actually, about that compression a little bit more.
What I realized at some point during development is that compressors work a lot like the eye works.
So that if your game doesn't compress well, then there's a good chance that it won't work well with your brain, basically.
So that's what led me to my second round of...
of dithering fix, which was to try to keep the dither from moving while you're looking
around.
Right on.
Diving back into the chat really quick.
Albino Gorilla, I'm going to ask the first part of your question, because we already
did sort of talk about the second part, but how do you stay motivated as a solo developer
long enough to actually finish the game?
Well, like I said earlier, it's always games that I'm interested in, or concepts that I'm
interested in.
If I'm not interested in it, that's a problem.
But so far I've been lucky that I've kept my interest in these games long enough to finish them.
And Sky, I think at the front, earlier you mentioned a couple of Mac games that you said directly influenced this game.
What were those again?
So visually, Beyond Dark Castle and Dark Castle were really an influence on me.
Shadowgate was also a big influence.
And there's another one called Fool's Errand.
Is was the one that's like really just beautiful all the screens are they're still screened but
the artist who created those was really really good and that's always been kind of a
Uh a milestone of what you can do with one bit for me
Right on. Um
I'm gonna dive back to my question sheet as the chat, uh fans freaks out about dark castle. Um
I never heard of that game before to be honest
You can't play it now. It's unplayable now, unfortunately, but at the time
It was
I just mean the concept design concepts are too hard to deal with but at the time it was really really good and it used
the mouse and the keyboard in the way that
Made you feel like I own a Macintosh and I'm special because no one else can play this sort of game
Right on. I think I'll show it later in the video. Like I said, this is pre-recorded, so I can't just call this up on command.
But also with Return of the Obra Dinn, you can pop in the options and change specifically what kind of monitor this is,
which mostly affects the color and shading. It doesn't even change a lot for gameplay.
to taste, like what's your retro computer of choice, I guess.
Why'd you do that, how'd you do that, and
was it worth it? What do you think was really valuable about that?
I
probably don't think through everything that well, actually. This was
a case where I'd release a demo and then people said it would be cool if they could choose the two
colors,
black or white. I'd choose two
Mac Plus style colors, basically.
And I thought, okay, well, I don't want people choosing from like an RGB control their two
colors because that's a lot of work to make a control and also most of those won't look
good.
So I'll just pick some colors myself and then, well, what colors can I pick?
The default colors are based on Mac+, so I'll just pick some other monitors, cool old monochrome
monitors from that period.
And I cheated a little bit because the Commodore is not monochrome, but I used the two Commodore
colors, blue and cyan.
So it was more or less just.
try to add a few in there and I researched a lot of those monitors and
there weren't that many color options so you know kind of just stopped where it was there and looked
and it was easy to put in it's only changing two variables in the shader so it was trivial to add
it and then it adds a little bit to the game. When I was playing the game at the end before
shipping we tested a lot one of the ways to sort of
change it up for me anyways, it's just to change the color filter while I play through.
I was going to ask why do you think people wanted that?
Why do you think developers should know that people wanted it?
That's a good question.
I think probably because it's a PC game.
PC gamers want options.
They just want to, because you can.
On PC you can open up the game files and do whatever you want so just throw that sucker
in the menu and save us all some trouble.
Right on. Let me see here.
I'm gonna grab some water real quick.
I'll be just give me like 10 seconds.
Oh, go for it.
Yeah, I guess I'll just hang out with chat.
Everyone I guess is talking about everyone's talking about
Dark Castle and being able to play it again on other
another platforms.
CliftonB, I kind of appreciate that too. This is one thing that really separates game dev from software dev.
Some things just sound like a cool idea, they don't need to be focus tested to heck before implementing them.
Yeah, if you guys want to cat count right now, Liam is just off camera.
Hey Liam.
Um, and Grunt, who's actually my cat.
Um, she walked into the room and she walked out of the room, so...
Um...
Alright, I'm back.
Welcome back, yeah.
I guess maybe now that we're on GDC Twitch, maybe we'll get some work into getting custom emotes for all the cats who show up.
Who might show up on camera.
Um, that might be fun.
Um...
Yeah, simply AJ we named grunt after grunt from Mass Effect, which I guess n7 day was yesterday
So happy n7 day if you're a Mass Effect fan like me
Let's see, I'm gonna quickly check my notes check my notes
Lucas I guess I've talked to a lot of developers lately and I've been talking to them about you know
Maintaining companies and you know figuring you know keeping them
Like, being able to successfully make one game after another.
Um, a lot of developers I talk to talk about taking techniques, code, um, uh, gameplay lessons.
Like, they take a lot of- when they move from game to game, they are...
adapting things they learned on their last game to their new game, either for marketability purposes,
because they know that their company's fans want, like, similar but different, or it's because it's
the way they can keep the cost down, is they don't have to teach themselves, you know,
going from a 2D to 3D, for instance, is...
something that one developer might choose not to do because they know a lot about 2D
and 3D would be very expensive to make. With your style of game making,
how do you, what do you retain between games that you think has proven most valuable?
Yeah, I don't, because I make different games every, I try to make different game every time.
There's nothing like, usually nothing like code. There are some snippets of code that I keep
around and I reuse, but...
And it's not assets, not much of the production gets reused, but some concepts get reused.
I will say on Papers, Please, one thing I learned is that game has a certain level of
jank to it, where some stuff is just a little bit not great.
And that was because I made the game in nine months and I wasn't thinking long term that
it's going to be a huge success.
So once that happened to me, I realized that a game does not need to be perfect to be good.
There's a saying I think it's perfect is the enemy of good
so
And I also learned that at Naughty Dog actually on uncharted 1 mm-hmm where?
My previous self before working there. I would say we got to fix all this shit
This is just totally too janky and looks like crap, but now I would say this is fine. This is I'm not trying to to
Make it perfect basically I what I have here is good and
If there are some janky things or slightly inconvenient things in this game, leave it
in.
Don't try to fix everything.
Because a lot of times when you try to fix things, you break other things.
In some way, you're messing with what you already have.
So that's something I learned through the years and I keep with me.
Marketing wise, I'm not thinking...
Okay, I'm a little bit thinking that I didn't do much marketing, it worked out okay.
So I don't need to do marketing next time. And the same is true of publishing as well.
I used to work with publishers. I worked with publishers in the late 90s when they had the
print discs and I worked with them on Helsing's Fire for iOS. And one of the things I did with
Papers, Please is I decided I'll just self-publish it. Valve is there, Steam is there now. It got
through green light, so this makes sense. It's easy, technically.
And so I self-published that. And then for Oberdin, there were a lot of opportunities where I could have had a,
could have worked with a publisher to do it and decided, well,
fuck it. I'll just self-publish it again. It's a lot of work and it's hard, but
there's a certain amount of satisfaction there just doing everything yourself. So I did it and it worked out.
Okay, so that's another lesson that I kind of tested and it worked out
okay, and so I'll probably be self-publishing from now on, kind of thing.
Right on. Sky kind of agrees that publishers, I think, have just changed so much. You named
three different eras of game publishing. And I think if there's one thing I've learned
interviewing developers is that each of those eras, the art of publishing and self-publishing
is so different. Companies that were created in the CD era don't know anything about mobile,
et cetera, et cetera.
Um, uh, Talismaniac, if you can't share this, you know, feel free to not feel pressured to share it.
But Talismaniac would like to know if, um, do you have any Steam analytics on the average age
of your purchasers? They are curious if it's higher than other games.
Average? No, I don't know. Does Steam tell you that? I haven't looked. I don't know. I haven't.
The only stat on Steam I looked at was how long people play.
It was above average. I don't remember even the number now, but it was above average for Steam games, which was satisfying.
Nice! Nice.
Um...
Let's see, we're coming up. I can't believe it, but we only have five minutes left in our hour.
If you're like me and you're on the West Coast, you're probably either eating dinner or thinking about dinner.
If you're on the east coast, thank you for sticking with us.
If you're in Europe, goodness, did you just wake up?
Do you need to go to bed still?
In any case, we're thankful that you've all joined us.
Now is the time to get your last questions in, because we'll try to get as many as we
can answered.
Ricardo DSC would like to know, what kind of software did you use to make the music?
I used Logic Pro X on the Mac.
Let's see, there's this orchestral library called Decapo by Sono Kinetic, which I use
for all the, most of the orchestral stuff.
I use some of the Logic built-in orchestral sounds as well.
And let's see, I use Roland Integra 7 for some of the orchestral leads.
And I think that's it.
MXbug would like to know, they say that one-bit graphics were a deliberate restriction, but did you find it liberating at the same time?
Like, once you pinned that down, did it broaden the scope of what you felt you could do graphically?
Yeah, definitely. And one other thing to help is low resolution.
So the game does not have a lot of particle effects, which is a common sort of special effects thing you see in games.
There's lots of particles everywhere.
But because it's one bit and because it's low resolution, it allowed me to use dots instead.
Just like one pixel particles, more or less, which you don't see in a lot of games.
And that opened up a lot of ideas about how to do effects and how to make things look in the game.
When you're not working from the same palette as everybody else, it gives me a lot of ideas
about what I can do. And this one bit stuff was definitely a different palette.
Right on. And I guess...
I guess before we go, uh, oh, we've got albino gorilla again.
Uh, are the raw assets created in monochrome or are they fully colored and textured and
then down res'd?
They are, they're created in RGB, but I use the different channels for different things.
So for instance, the texture would only go in the B channel and then the R and G channel
would be used to define the dithering type.
or to define where the outlines are going to be.
So, I mean, if you look at them, my development view was this kind of multicolored view of the ship at all times,
but it wasn't... there was encoded information in those colors.
It wasn't necessarily the normal tones you'd expect from the textures.
That's interesting. So the colors were sort of, like, when you were working in Unity,
the colors were there to tell you that a certain other thing was sitting under the color?
Yeah, I mean the shader itself will look at the different channels of the texture and say,
okay, for this pixel I'm going to use this dithering, for that pixel use this other dithering,
or they would define the edges of where the outlines are going to be. So if you just look
at it, it's hard to see that stuff because it's all combined into one RGB texture,
but the shader can suss that out.
Very cool. With that, I guess my last question, it's not different than one I ask a lot of game developers.
I guess, what do you kind of hope, you know, people pick up Obra Dinn, they play Obra Dinn,
what do you sort of hope they walk away from the game with when they're done?
I just hope they enjoy it.
As I said, I made the game mostly because that's the kind of game I wanted to play,
so if other people like it, that's a bonus on top.
Yeah, I hope they enjoy it, you know, and one of the kind of lighter elements I tried
to show in this game is that there's a lot of people on this boat and they're just names
and faces, but by the end of the game, I hope that you kind of have a sense of that they're
people with their own lives and stories and stuff like that.
I mean, that's not a main sort of force of the game or focus of the game, but I do want
to show that.
that a ship full of people from all over the world can both get along and fight and that
they're all, can be interesting and that grows out of not knowing detailed stories about them,
but sort of what you assign to them in your own playthrough. So that was kind of a thing that
I tried to add to the game, I tried to make, I tried to give the game this sense of you first
come on this and these are just names and you don't care, but in the end you kind of know,
recognize these people and see them in a different way.
Right on. Albino Gorilla adds that they appreciate that aspect of the game.
With that, thank you all for watching today. Thank you, Lucas, for coming on and talking with us.
Yeah, it was great. My pleasure. Thanks, everybody, in the chat.
Right. Hey, I'm just here. I'm just here to pet the cats and ask the questions.
Um, uh, you've been watching the GDC Twitch channel. Uh, thank you all for joining us on
this new adventure. If you know us from the Gamasutra Twitch channel, please follow this
channel now. Um, Gamasutra is mostly just going to be hosting this for the time being, though.
We'll still, uh, you know, we'll still use that for discussions whenever the Gama editors just
want to get on the horn and talk about, you know, how things are going in the year.
We would love it if you hit that follow button, because if you do, you'll get notifications when we go live,
and you can find out when you can ask questions to game developers.
about who make the games that you like. In the next couple weeks we've got the
Blackout Club. We're working on a chat with the...
What's this game called?
Mutant Year Zero? It looks really cool.
Mutant Year Zero Road to Eden. That's it.
I'm talking to some other PR and devs about getting their games on.
It's been interesting, you know, the end of the year is always interesting because big games come out and obviously those developers kind of want to go home and take vacations after they've watched their games, but there's a lot of devs who are down to talk and we're trying to talk to them right now.
Oh yeah, quick shoutouts to chat.
Alcahal Clifton B's sasquatch abana gorilla
Ricardia
Ricardia Ricardo Diaz see says thank you from Brazil. Thank you Ricardo. Thank you for tuning in from so far away
I honest to God um Lucas you're in Japan
I'm in California Ricardo's in Brazil if there's one thing that I've really been excited about doing these twitch streams
Is that we all get to talk together about making video games even though we are all
literally far away on the planet.
And then the awkward pitch that follows up on that is that
GDC will be March 18th to 22nd
in San Francisco. And if you'd like to join us at GDC,
you can scroll down and click the button,
and you can register for your pass.
There's all kinds of different pass options
for people from different backgrounds.
We sincerely hope to make sure no matter what kind of developer you are,
wherever you're coming from in the world,
that when you come to GDC you're going to get something super useful out there that
will help you make interesting and successful games.
With that, Lucas, and I always like to give devs a chance, if the folks at home watching
would like to ask you more detailed questions about making this game, where can they contact
you?
Twitter! On Twitter. Twitter, find him on Twitter.
Um, I think it's Duke Pope? Is that how you say it?
Ducope. Ducope. Uh, that's how you can find him on Twitter.
Um, with that, have a good day everyone, or good night, good day, wherever you are.
Bye! Bye.