Hi, thank you all for coming.
So before we begin, there are a few official GDC announcements,
one of which is to please put your phones on vibrate
unless you have an awesome ringtone, in which case,
turn it up as loud as you can.
We want to enjoy it.
The second is that there are speaker session evaluations
that have been emailed to you via your badge,
and we ask that you please fill those out.
So now that that's done, and Richard's sort of already
introduced me, so this might be redundant.
My name is CJ Kirshner.
I'm a freelance writer, designer, and the head of
Polyhedron Productions.
And the talk is The Lives of Others, How NPCs Can Increase
Player Empathy.
And I ask you to forgive in advance my nervousness.
This is my first time speaking at GDC.
And there's very little.
There is very little that you can do to prepare yourself to
stand up in front of a room of your peers and make a total fool
of yourself. So... Yesterday, Meg Giant, the writer on 80 Days
gave a fabulous talk called Forget Protagonists. How many of
you were there for that? That's a good...
representation. If you missed it, it's now in the past. So I
can't recommend that you go to it, but I can recommend that you
check it out when it's available on the vault. I'm told that will
happen in a few weeks. To quote Spaceballs, when will then be
now? Soon. So let's get started. Chapter 1. I am born. Whether I
shall turn out to be the hero of my own life.
or whether that station will be held by anybody else,
these pages must show.
That's the first sentence of Charles Dickens' 1850 novel
David Copperfield.
Now, I hope we all have enough self-esteem
to confidently say that we are the heroes
and heroines of our own lives.
But what about everybody else we encounter?
This thought most often strikes me
while traveling or riding public transit.
I'm so focused on where I need to be and what I need to do
that everyone else becomes part of the background.
But I imagine that's true of my fellow passengers as well.
They all have a goal, destination, complex emotions,
and social networks.
In short, they have their own views on life, the universe,
and everything.
But from this first-person perspective,
I'm the hero of my life.
I'm the main character.
I'm the player.
Which makes them my non-player characters?
And that's what I want to talk about today,
the lives of others.
I want to look at the ways that we can better recognize
and respect the NPCs who populate the worlds we create.
I want to discuss how we can give their lives and their
deaths meaning beyond basic gameplay or background
decoration. Because I strongly believe that when production
teams invest in robust NPC characterization, the result is
often increased player engagement and empathy.
I want to focus on three ways we can go about bringing more life to randomly generated characters.
The first concerns ways that we rally our production to the call of more NPC-focused content.
The second are techniques that my colleagues and I have employed in the past
to bring characterization to those NPCs.
And the last details with the somewhat touchy subject of how we treat the enemies
in our games and that our players encounter.
I'm going to draw heavily on my work from the Homefront games and titles I worked on during my four years at Ubisoft Montreal.
Now, over the course of my career, I've been fortunate to be able to explore the narrative value of traditionally undervalued characters and systems.
Or to put that another way, I'm usually the guy who gets stuck with the shit job of writing barks.
versus the seemingly more prestigious role of working on the main campaign.
But here's the thing, the barks are just as important, in some cases more so, than the main story.
If you consider that a 60-hour open world game with an hour of cut scenes,
the player spends just over 1% of their total playtime watching those scenes.
Now, granted, they're a captive audience, unless there's a...
Don't even get me started on that.
But the majority of the experience is spent outside
of those sequences, despite them commanding a large percentage
of the development's budget and attention.
And before we go any further, I wanna just throw out
a couple of quick caveats.
Most of my experience has been in big budget,
large team, open world games.
So a lot of the production methodologies I'm going to
describe are taken from and best suited for those games.
But I believe that the high-level takeaways are more
generally applicable to projects of any size. It's about what
you're trying to achieve with the resources that you have. And
second, people play games for a variety of reasons. And it
helps to accept up front that a percentage of them might not
notice or care about the extra effort that you're about to put
in. But you do need to care, and you need to care deeply,
because otherwise nobody else will. Tron fights for the user,
but we should fight for a bit as well.
So, okay, the first thing we need to do is get the writers and the rest of the team on board with the idea that NPCs should be an integral part of the game's world.
And the good news is that we can leverage a lot of pre-existing systems to make better systemic characters.
On Far Cry 4 we had the benefit of building off of the systems
developed for Far Cry 3, but the world of Karat is more
narratively dense and interwoven than the Rook Islands.
And additionally, there were technical complications that
shipped in Far Cry 3 that prevented or resulted in only a
limited number of barks ever playing, which is why everybody
is so familiar with the urinary problems of the pirates on that
island. Resolving that bug was one of our first tasks for the
AI team.
once that was done, the writing team, narrative team, could get
on the process of planning how we wanted to build upon the
systems that we'd previously established. But even with that
advantage, the current tools and design best practices mean that
the way that we build a living, breathing, systemic, plausible
open world is simply by throwing a lot of shitload of words into
a database. Um...
So for example, it was reported in Game Informer
that Dragon Age Origins, released in 2009,
shipped with roughly 62,000 lines of dialogue
for their characters.
And Grand Theft Auto, which was released a year,
Grand Theft Auto 4, which was released a year earlier,
had, just look at it, it's three New York City phone books
stacked one on top of the other.
And those are for games that came out almost five years ago.
Oh, I have a technical complication here, sorry.
There we go.
So with nearly yearly release cycles and companies
competing for player attention, the expectation
is that each new game needs to be bigger and better
than the one that came before it.
And the content requirements have just continued to grow.
Far Cry 4 shipped with about 20,000 unique barks,
roughly 2,000 printed pages.
And Assassin's Creed Syndicate had about 300 crowd vignettes
with between one and six actors each.
and sometimes lasting up to four and a half minutes.
And those numbers don't reflect the entire game.
Those are just those specific subsystems.
Pardon me for a moment.
Didn't spill it on myself.
We're off to a good start.
So that's a lot of words.
And if you're working on a game of comparable scale,
it's highly advisable to have a team of writers
dedicated to the systemic narrative content
rather than keeping it in a big pool
that writers can pull from as they become available.
But you're going to need the involvement of more than just the writers, because storytelling in games is a team sport.
The narrative team should drive high-level discussions with the producers, designers, AI programmers, the sound department, casting director, animators, localization,
as early as possible in the project's lifespan, and ideally when it's still in conception,
to determine what truths you want the NPCs to convey about your world.
how the different disciplines can contribute to and support this initiative,
and to build a production plan,
and that includes budget, deliverable dates, and recording schedules,
that accommodates this increased writing time and content.
This is an opportunity for you to get a head start on the situation
and build from the ground up,
rather than sort of have it imposed upon you from the top down.
Now common wisdom dictates that when faced with the sheer volume of barks
to write generic neutral lines that players don't notice if they hear
the same thing fifty times in as many hours
and productions sometimes cut corners by asking their NPC actors
to read from a bank of the same lines so that the voice rather than the line
itself provides the variation.
One of the techniques that we used that not only simplified the writing process,
but also brought more color to the NPCs was the creation of micro-personalities.
Each NPC was given a very brief character profile
that we could refer to while struggling to write the 10th variation of any given topic.
And these were generally pretty broad attributes.
things like personality types, are they aggressive,
are they a little bit more timid, are they confident?
But there were very specific attributes as well,
like the details of their family life
or their favorite food.
Do they have siblings, are they married,
do they have children?
Did my slide just advance itself?
Do I have a mouse?
Oh God!
All right, we're off the rails now.
So it should also be noted.
that under the Far Cry model, barks are broadly divided into
two categories, combats and idles. The combat lines cover
everything from the genre standard reloading to individual
and squad tactics, search loops, and damage and death states. The
idles are just that, the things that they say when they're
standing around doing nothing, not in combat, not even
detected. So in Barking on 4 we established a broader range of
conversation topics for the idols like war.
I'm going to try and scroll my notes here and it may just go...
Anyway, more conversations.
Conversation topics like the course of the war,
food, their family,
their equipment, and even things like rain or night time.
And midway through the production,
the system was modified to introduce a call and response
system.
So NPC A would randomly choose one of those categories
and play one of the lines that we've written.
And then NPC B would respond in kind.
Now, had we planned this from the start,
it might have spared us the shock
of having to write a few thousand new response lines.
But fortunately, we set up a system
of informal weekly reviews with the sound and AI teams
so that we would load up either a test map or the latest
version of the build and poke the systems,
try and introduce the stimuli to get the lines
that we wanted to fire, to find out
if they were working properly, to find out if the responses
matched the calls.
And the slides now go off again.
Whatever.
F it.
The benefit was that by the end, any of our characters
could have a short systemically assembled conversation
on a variety of topics.
And it allowed us to communicate more about the world
through them and for them to reveal their personalities
to the player when the player was just hanging around.
By assigning each NPC a unique voice and a set of character
traits in combination with hiring native language speaking
voice actors, we were able to create more well-rounded
characters that players actually wanted to hang around and
listen to.
Or maybe they didn't mind the occasional repetition if it
would reveal another line later that gave more information
about that character.
And occasionally, the irreverent response
garnered a chuckle.
And given the range of topics that NPCs could speak about,
any one of them could have been the player character
in a different version of the game.
When they boasted about finding a new weapon site
or where their allegiances with the factions lay,
their thoughts echoed those of the player.
So we made sure that everybody had something to talk about
while they were standing around,
and hopefully that those things were worth listening to,
but also by respecting that,
we realized that...
Any one of them could have been you in another life.
So you've decided you want to expand the scope
of your NPC content, you've specced out a system
for how the dialogue will play,
and you've built a production plan with your team
to allow for the additional writing,
recording, and reviewing.
The next step is to determine what you want your NPCs
to say, how they will act, and what their presence
in the game should mean.
In narrative and design, we lay sacrifices
on the altar of player agency,
but rarely do we ever talk about non-player agency.
Their function is to simply spawn, wander around, play some lines or animations,
and then die or despawn as soon as the player is out of range.
But if we want to build compelling characters from the common mobs,
each one of them should be invested in their own life and the outcome of their actions.
They should have wants, needs, desires, as well as the means to attain those things.
One of my favorite pieces of writing advice
comes from Kurt Vonnegut, who said,
every character should want something,
even if it is only a glass of water.
So let's assume the player's needs are well taken care of,
either through the objectives that we give them
or the ones that they set for themselves.
Part of the benefit of creating the micro-personalities,
each character's wants was at the top of that list
and everything else that followed was filtered through that.
These can be simple or complicated.
And we should find ways to communicate them to the player, even if it's an on-the-nose, outright line.
It's not the most elegant way, but it is fast and effective.
And beyond those wants, we should ask whether or not their basic needs are being met.
I mean, not as victims, but as characters worthy of dignity.
Vonnegut's quote is doubly salient when we consider that one in ten people in the world
don't have access to safe water, or that between 6,000 and 12,000 children in Flint, Michigan
have been potentially affected by the lead crisis there.
Resource scarcity plays a large role in the home front games, both of which are set in an occupied post-collapse America.
The backstories tend to focus on the availability of cheap oil,
but the NPCs often talk about and work towards access to clean water,
and rainwater collection systems form a core component of our environmental storytelling.
But beyond just a glass of water, which...
Beyond water, we all want different things,
and they can be tangible or not.
So determine what goals are important to your NPCs
and what tools you've designed to give them
agency to pursue them.
And if you haven't, perhaps ask why not.
When I talk about giving NPCs agency and the means
to fulfill their wants and needs,
I find that the current designs underserve these characters.
The player who is typically an outsider
has far more means to pursue goals and effect change
in the world than those who actually live there.
And the task of giving NPCs this agency
is no small technical undertaking,
but I believe it's one we'll need to meet
if we're to continue to make games the way that we do.
Today's talk mostly focuses on bringing
the illusion of agency through dialogue
and other narrative content,
but there is another avenue that merits investigation,
and that is deeper social simulations.
I don't see the approaches as being mutually exclusive.
I think they exist on a spectrum
and can and should work in complement with each other.
I'm a writer and not much of a programmer, so I'm not very qualified to speak about the social simulation side.
However, Mitu Kandekar-Kokoris at last year's GDC gave an excellent talk,
and that is available on the vault, about her work and research in social simulations for games.
But even with my limited technical understanding,
in the future, I can see the potential for layers of AI
running on top of a game which provides goals and directions
and schedules for every NPC in the world.
Our NPC should be able to perform
the same range of actions that are available to the player,
as well as have the ability to embark on quests or activities
without the player's prompting or presence.
Not dissimilar from the way that computer opponents
in a game of civilization choose strategies and make moves,
even when obscured by the fog of war.
Now, I'm not suggesting these needs need to overlap
with the player's goals, but they can instead
operate alongside and create a richer living world, one
in which the player can remain a central figure,
but that follows its own schedule.
For example, why is it in a game like Grand Theft Auto V,
the only time I ever see an illegal street race
is when I've agreed to do one myself?
There's one other thing I want to talk about,
and it's a corollary to all of this.
But in terms of character building,
I want to talk about possessions.
Tim O'Brien's book, The Things They Carried, is a great resource for writers who are looking to bring
personality to characters through everyday objects because each of us carries on us
certain items that say a lot about us. Like if you were to lose your backpack today and
somebody generously were to find it and not scavenge it, what would its contents say about you?
There are a few games with very deep world-centric loots.
Skyrim being a, what does that say about this player?
Um.
Where everyday objects are used to communicate truths
about the characters of the environment.
And it's just one more tool that we can use
to bring that life to our NPCs.
But many of the current loot systems,
unless there are also mechanics for theft or pickpocketing,
rely on a character to, well.
be dead before they can be searched, which sort of leads
into the next section. I'm going to get a little dark and ranty
here, because the subject of killing, death, and enemies in
games is one that I don't think is discussed often enough. When
we created the micro personalities for the NPCs in
Far Cry 4 and AC Syndicate, we didn't stop with the friendly or
neutral characters. Both of these games feature strong
stealth mechanics, so there are a lot of times when the players
will be in proximity to enemies but not engaged in combat.
So what do the enemies talk about while they're just standing around?
In the example of Far Cry 4, the gameplay takes place during a fictional civil war,
and like any war, each side and every soldier brings their own motivations to the battlefield.
It's overly simplistic to think that because we're opposed to them, they are necessarily
evil.
The micro-personalities allowed us to explore the reasons and emotions that drove the enemy soldiers to do what they did.
Some of the set-piece atrocities were a little outside of our control,
but if you hide in a bush for long enough,
you might discover that the people that you've been shooting for the past few hours are remarkably sympathetic.
In his book On Killing, Lieutenant Colonel Dave Grossman,
who I don't think is any relation to the game designer of the same name,
talks about the techniques the military has developed
to dehumanize the enemy.
Part of this is conditioning designed to desensitize soldiers
and allow them to overcome their innate reluctance
to kill another human.
And part of it is a coping mechanism those same soldiers
have to deal with the psychological trauma of taking another life.
He writes, oh, I am going to need my notes for this.
How do I make this work?
Nope.
Come on.
Does anybody know how to advance the notes
section in PowerPoint?
Weird, no.
This is all just going to break.
It's so fragile.
He writes that the burden of killing is so great that most try not to admit that they have killed.
They deny it to others and then they deny it to themselves.
And he further writes that part of this ability is a function of the language used,
something we call othering.
And I would quote, but it is now cut off.
I'm a deer in the headlights now. Basically, we assign other names to our enemy NPCs, we
cover their faces, we mask their voices, we create epithets for them and he says that
the language of Met at War is...
In order to facilitate this killing, the enemy is not killed.
They're neutralized, they're greased, they're knocked down.
And it's not a human being you're killing, it's a kraut, it's a Jap, it's somebody else.
We do this in games all the time.
We have orcs, we have norks, we have Middle Eastern extremists from Nowaristan.
So why on earth would we want our players to feel bad about shooting people?
I mean, we've worked so hard over the years to make the act of killing fun.
I mean, we've perfected the inputs and outputs
to enable players to shoot or stab
thousands of human-like figures for hours on end.
And we've been successful because we as developers
have refused to accept responsibility for it
and have shielded our players from feeling anything
that doesn't also come with a release of dopamine.
At an NYU Game Center lecture in 2009,
Warren Spector said, and I'm paraphrasing from my own notes
here, that games excel at the emotions of triumph and guilt,
but only ever really explore the first.
It's a very subtle difference between, I did that!
And I did that.
And I think guilt is a very powerful emotion.
It's central in theater.
It's a key component of catharsis.
And I want to make a distinction before we go further
between guilt and gotchas, which was a narrative technique that
was in vogue a few years ago.
my notes are cut off, but basically the gotcha is an unwinnable situation that the player needs to
complete before they're allowed to progress. And by doing it, often the designers then
condemn that action. And when the player asks, well, what other choice did I have, the
response is usually, you could have taken the disc out and brought it back to the store. I
don't think that's necessarily an effective method for getting players to feel things.
Guilt, on the other hand, is something
that players arrive at themselves
without the developer needing to pass judgment.
It basically asserts that performing violence
against characters who share an emotional investment
in the outcome of the story will naturally
lead players to recognize and take responsibility
for the destruction they cause.
It acknowledges that the act of killing
is necessarily an act of trauma.
In short, it creates empathy.
And that empathy is dissonant with the act.
And we never explore that.
But observation and anecdotal evidence
leads me to believe that this empathy can crack even
the hardest of gaming's hearts.
Rob Otten, one of the writers on Battlefield Hardline, said in an interview with Polygon
about the game's villains, I wrote this one guy getting back together with his ex-girlfriend
and someone on the team pointed out, hey idiot, this is someone you're about to shoot in the
head, not deliver flowers to.
So we decided, maybe let's not go down that route.
We had to cut the dialogue and make it more informative.
We had to make sure that the bad guys felt like bad guys so the player isn't as emotionally
conflicted about the gameplay.
No disrespect to Rob.
I believe his initial impulse was correct,
just as I believe that whoever asked him to change it
was also operating from our current best understanding
of what needs to be done to make a mass market shooter
for a publicly traded company.
But the compromise that was required
speaks to our continued inability
to create mature, nuanced work and why
we keep recycling the same action movie tropes.
And now that I've brought the entire mood down with all of
this death and destruction, here's a puppy.
It was not a polar bear.
That was totally...
The audience is always right.
My next slide is going to be bagel or dachshund.
So in conclusion for the high-level takeaways,
use your NPCs to tell truths about your world
and have a production plan to accommodate
the increased writing.
Give them their own personalities and agendas
because players gravitate towards well-developed characters
regardless of whether they're directly in front of them
in a cut scene or whether they're operating independently
in the world around them.
And offer those characters a degree of agency
because they will add life to the world
in interesting and emergent ways.
Acknowledge the humanity of your enemies, because violence without consequence is meaningless.
And allow players to feel responsible for the actions, because empathy and complex emotions
will help this industry to mature.
Special thanks to the people that offered feedback on this talk, even if they couldn't
save me from my own technical gaffes.
And thank you for coming.
And I don't know how much time we have, but I think we can take
some questions if there are... Huh? Four minutes. Okay. We can
take four one-minute questions, one four-minute question or two
two-minute questions. Uh, to the polar bear? Yes, of course.
Hi there.
From a game design and AI design standpoint,
do you have any ideas of things you wish you could convince
the higher-ups to put in the framework
to allow you to have more chances to give the AI to be
more, I don't know, empathetic?
Well, again, I think we can take a lot of the systems
that we already employ and modify the content in them.
to achieve, again, sort of the illusion of this.
The discussion about how you bring that more robust agency
is, again, a conversation that needs
to happen at a project level with animators,
with designers, because as writers,
we can put the words down.
But anything that we put down creates more work
for other departments.
And so they really need to know.
what we would like to achieve, they need to be on board with that, they need to believe it as strongly as we do.
I think we are making progress toward it
and I hope to see
more games coming out in the future
that offer NPCs that same
degree. Like I want to see an orc war camp
in Shadow of Mordor 2.
where they aren't just there to get cut down,
where they go off and have their own orc lives
and orc wives and orc babies, and they sing orc songs.
Thank you.
Hi there.
First thing I wanted to say was this is by far
one of the best talks I've listened to so far,
so thank you very much for that.
Thank you.
But from an execution standpoint, one of the things I just had a little question about was on Far Cry 4 you were talking about how you wrote kind of dialogue lines centered around war or family or food and how you would have two NPCs talking.
Just from a purely execution case, was that, would that be one NPC pulling from a pool and then another NPC pulling from the same subject matter but not necessarily related but close enough that it would feel organic?
or was it you would have to literally match up two lines,
like you would have a call and response, exactly?
So, that's actually a very good question.
The call lines that were about the topics of food
or whatever, you know, you would have something like,
I miss my mother's cooking.
Or, you know, my father makes the best naan.
And the response lines were...
generally a bit more generic, but again, because we had those micro personalities, we could
provide generic responses that would suit the calls reasonably well. So, you know, my
father makes the best naan. Somebody else will just chip in from that same bank of lines
about food or family and say, I haven't eaten in days.
you know, I don't think I've ever actually enjoyed that meal
as much as you have or you know I'm an orphan, right?
Right. So it wasn't specific for that time.
No, no, no. It wasn't like if you play line A,
then you will necessarily play line B.
It was if you play one of these ten lines,
then you will play one of these five responses.
And those five responses were generally in the range
of things that would work well with the calls.
Again, it was all found through reviews.
did initially write that one-to-one
and found that the repetition wasn't working
and that oftentimes even the responses didn't work.
And so it was by constantly iterating and looking at it
and minor course corrections here and there
that we were able to sort of arrive at lines
that were generally applicable
but still functional, flavorful,
and tailored to that particular topic.
Okay, thanks a lot.
Hey, Heather.
Um, I like the polar bear, by the way.
It's not a-
I'm going back.
I got it.
I got to know.
Forget, forget to take-
It's a polar bear.
It's a tall polar bear.
That's a polar bear.
It's a polar bear.
So you were talking about the mini personalities and the call and responses, and sorry, maybe
I didn't hear about it, but I was wondering if you were able to create specific animations
to go along with these call and responses, and if you didn't, do you think that would
be something that you would be able to do in future titles?
So with regard to the animations, that was one area where, because the...
operations were happening in parallel. The writing was
happening at the same time they were shooting a lot of the new
game play idols. The animation team...
put together a list of things that they wanted, design included things that they wanted, and then
we also got to include some things that we wanted, but in terms of like very custom
one-off animations for specific lines of dialogue, I don't think that we necessarily had those,
though again if you start early enough in the process it would not be too particularly
not uncomplicated, but you could easily...
include those in the production plan to have people sitting around having a meal,
you know, people trading cigarettes, people doing whatever. Again, it's about
getting on board early and then making your wants and needs known and then
getting the rest of the team on board with them. Okay, great, thanks. I think
that's it. Thank you.