Right now, I will now turn you over to Heather Albano and harvesting interactive fiction.
Thank you very much.
I think that's working.
You can all hear me?
Yeah?
All right.
I have been reminded to ask you to please turn off your cell phones or put them on silent
and to please remember to fill out your course evaluations.
All right.
Let's go.
This is the game Time Magazine named as its game of the year,
80 Days, released by Inkle.
This is the game that won the Apple Design Award of 2014,
Device 6, released by Simogo.
And this is the game that spent months
in its top RPG in the iTunes Store,
with a brief stint as top overall app,
A Darkroom by Amirali Rajan.
These games are all by anyone's definition interactive fiction,
which means that interactive fiction, long perceived
as a hobbyist niche, is starting to generate interest,
enthusiasm, awards, and dollars in the mainstream gaming
market.
Video games have a lot more tools at their disposal
to evoke player emotion.
camera angle, speed of play, the expressions on the faces of the NPCs, the tones of their
voices. When a game form without any of these elements at its disposal starts generating
genuine emotion on the part of its players, it's worthwhile to investigate why. When you
see these games sitting at Top RPG or Winning Times award, it is even more worthwhile to
investigate why.
We should discover what games like this have to teach us
about storytelling and how we can harvest those techniques
when designing narrative for other kinds of games.
And we're gonna do that today.
First though, we should take a step back
and define some terms.
To begin with, who am I?
I am a freelance narrative designer and game writer.
I do most of my work for Choice of Games.
I also was lead writer on Mission 1 of Codename Cygnus, and I've done some work on pen and
paper RPGs.
So that's me.
Now what do I mean when I say interactive fiction?
It's a pretty broad canvas.
If you take it to mean fiction that is interactive...
It can be applied to the choose your path type made famous by Choose Your Own Adventure,
to the parser-based type made famous by Infocom, to modern games built using Inform, Choice
Script, and Twine, to the audio-based code named Cygnus, to Inkle and Inkle Writer games,
to interactive visual novels, and there is a meaningful argument that any narrative-driven
game on any platform whatsoever is interactive fiction.
Generally, when people use the term IF, though,
they're talking about something pretty specific.
They're talking about either parser-based or choose-your-path.
So we will focus on those.
Quick history of parser-based.
In 1979, Dave Liebling, Mark Blank, Albert Veza,
and Joel Burez founded Infocom, which
produced Zork-style games, or adventure games,
or parser games, until the company's death in 1989.
These were games without graphics, which were pretty
limited in 1980 anyway.
Even if you haven't played one, I'm sure you know the format.
There's a chunk of text.
There is a cursor.
The player types in where they wish to go next or explore next
or what they want to do next in a noun and verb combination.
And the game responds, telling them what they see
or what happens in consequence of their action.
Infocom games were known for their storytelling.
They were, in fact, distributed via bookstores as well
as store selling software.
The company was acquired in 1986 and Activision, the acquirer, shut down the Infocom division in 1989.
But the game form didn't die.
The fans of the parser-based game reverse-engineered Infocom's technology
and created programming languages for developing parser IF,
the predominant example of which is Graham Nelson's Inform.
From 1995 onward, the parser IF community has been focused around competitions, especially
the annual IF comp, in which authors submit free games and vote for the best.
These competitions have resulted in considerable artistic innovation as people stretch the
boundaries of the art form.
The history of Choose Your Path is similar.
Game books, which were also sold in bookstores, were published first by Vermont Crossroads
Press then by Bantam.
If you were a kid in the 1980s and 90s,
you probably read slash played at least one.
And even if you didn't, you probably know the tropes.
There's a chunk of text, and then there
are multiple choice series of things you can do.
If you hit the troll, turn to page 17.
If you run away, turn to page 30.
If you try to negotiate, turn to page 45.
The problem with these early game books
was the explosive, exponential nature of branching narrative.
When you have this many branches,
you can't make every branch a long, in-depth story.
Not realistically, not practically.
And so these early game books were
restricted to telling short, simple stories,
mostly suitable for kids.
So the first Choose Your Path games, the game books.
were pitched to kids and young adults
and tended to explore safe, comfortable science
fiction and fantasy genres.
Fighting fantasy partway solved this problem
by representing the choices the player made
with a stored variable and the consequences of those choices
by calling that variable in lieu of strict branching.
The only problem was they did this through pencil, paper, dice, and the expectation that
the player's brain was going to function as the game computer, which works, but which
restricts their audience to people who are willing to do that kind of work.
The years between 2009 and 2012 saw a proliferation of free tools for writing branching narrative
games, including but not limited to ChoiceScript, Twine, and InkleWriter.
These tools were all designed to store and call variables within the game
instead of making the player do it with a pencil, thus completing fighting fantasy's solution.
The same years saw two different revolutions.
The first one was artistic, incited by twine.
People making twine games, most of which were small games given away for free,
made them on a hugely diverse range of topics and storylines and perspectives.
These were games made by people who were not previously making games.
Voices we hadn't heard before.
Games about things nobody writes games about.
An artistic expansion that deserves a presentation all by itself.
The second revolution happened in the commercial indie space.
Thanks to mobile app stores, Steam, Kickstarter, and Patreon,
it became feasible for small studios to make cost-effective text-based projects
that actually pay the rent.
Those studios include Choice of Games, Fail Better Games, Inkle, and Tin Man Games.
Most of them have developed their own tools for developing text-based games, most of which
are free for anyone to use.
The most popular among commercial authors seem to be Choice Script and Inkle Writer.
So examples of modern IF tend to be more or less like one grandparent or the other.
A spectrum.
I cut out for a second, I'm back.
From a purely parser-based, all the way to the far right, to the branching narrative
on the far left, to a variety of works in the fuzzy gray middle area.
What they have in common is that all of them are based on words.
They're all driven by narrative.
That's it.
That's all they've got.
Look at the reaction they're getting.
We're at the narrative summit.
Everybody in this room is in this room because they already
believe game narrative is important.
I don't have to cite statistics to convince you.
But the fact that there are statistics to cite
is really interesting.
It implies that the mainstream gaming market, or at least
some of it, is also coming around to the idea
that game narrative is really, really important.
We have objective evidence that might convince other people.
of the first time we can cite a business need,
not just an artistic need, for great narrative
and great storytelling and great prose in games.
So then, what can modern IF teach us
about game storytelling?
As I just described, modern IF is an enormous canvas,
very diverse, there are a lot of things I could talk about.
I only have 25 minutes, so I've picked three
of the most interesting techniques to cover today.
Poetry?
ambiguity and complicity.
By poetry, I mean the quality of the prose separate
from the quality of the narrative.
Poetry in this context has been defined by Choice
of Games co-founder Dan Fabulich
as short beautiful prose that hits hard.
When words are all you have to communicate world, character,
story.
you spend a lot of time making the words powerful.
Everyone has to count.
Here's an example taken from With Those We Love Alive
by Porpentine.
This is one of the first screens you see in the game.
All the pink words are links.
If you click on city, this is the only description
of the city you get.
32 words.
And it's 32 words that tell you a hell of a lot, or rather,
that poetically imply a whole lot.
Ropes are strung between the buildings.
I wonder why.
There's a temple.
OK, I wonder to who or to what?
Why is the canal dry?
What is a dream distillery?
That's 32 words doing an awful lot of work.
They do world building, they imply some backstory,
they open mysteries to investigate,
and they are enormously effective in communicating
the atmosphere of the game.
And one of the ways they do this is
by implying rather than delivering
utilitarian exposition.
These are short sentences with carefully chosen words
that suggest things to the player who then needs
to engage with the game, engage with the words,
engage with the world.
to fill in the blanks for themselves.
It's actually interesting I was making this point,
because the two speakers before me made the same point
about encouraging the player to fill in blanks for themselves
so that they're brought into the experience they're having.
Part of the strength of this text comes from its ambiguity,
which moves me on to my next topic.
To some degree, ambiguity in IF is unavoidable.
It's a byproduct of the medium.
Without graphics and without, obviously,
an infinite amount of space for text.
You cannot possibly cover every detail.
The player's imagination has to fill in some of the details.
There's obviously a degree to which this
is true for any game medium.
Daniel Greenberg, I think, phrased it best last year.
He said at GDC last year, the game world
does not exist on the screen.
The game world exists between the ears of the player.
This is more true for something text-based than something
not text-based, simply because there's only the one tool.
And this is a feature, not a bug.
It can be used deliberately.
You're going to have to omit some of the details,
so you pick which ones.
Decide where you want the player's imagination actively
filling in gaps.
I just showed how With Those We Love Alive does this.
A Darkroom, with its sparse description, does this.
Device 6 does this to great effect.
The review I quoted on the second slide up there
praises it for this very technique.
It calls the game one of those elusive stories you never quite
feel you've got a grip of.
The protagonist spends the entire game
trying to fathom what's going on around her,
and never quite does so.
And the experience all the more engrossing because of it.
Some questions are best left unanswered.
And the first choice of game, Choice of the Dragon,
did this by the way in which it asked the player
to specify their dragon's gender.
Not just you get to choose between a binary,
but you get to choose almost anything,
including a refusal to answer.
And the game works equally well in any of those,
if you pick any of those options,
because the game is designed for this
to be one of the spaces where the player's imagination is
filling in the blanks.
Ambiguity can also be used as a deliberate tool when the designer chooses not just what
to leave out, but chooses to make an aspect of the game deliberately unclear, requiring
the player to interpret it and act on his or her interpretation.
Emily Short's Blood and Laurels does this.
The motivations and allegiances of NPCs are variable, requiring the observation and interpretation
of minute clues to classify.
Andrew Plotkin's Hadean Lands does this with a variety of its world-building and character-interaction
elements, not to mention its ending.
And Alan De Niro's Solarium does it in multiple places within the text.
This one's my favorite.
Clicking on the word man changes it to woman.
Clicking on the second his changes it to her, but the middle his stays constant.
What exactly is the author saying?
Any one of four things, at least.
Four epigrams for the price of one.
Finally, there are those IF games
that use ambiguity as a deliberate tool,
not at the prose or the world-building level,
but at the narrative design level itself.
The second choice of game, choice of broad size,
used this technique.
In the final scene, the PC always
meets the enemy captain in battle.
But based on the player's earlier choices,
the enemy captain can be a star-crossed lover,
a dear friend, a rival of longstanding, or a bitter enemy.
The scene plays out the same way.
The same actions on the player's part
lead to promotion or to court-martial.
But precisely where the challenge lies,
the precise, the desirable outcome,
the way the scene looks, is variable
dependent on the way the player has previously
interacted with the game and the choices they have made,
the emotional connections they have formed.
Four stories for the price of one.
The game world does not exist on the screen.
It exists between the ears of the player.
Ambiguity leaves room for the player
to draw their own conclusions, provide
their own interpretation, insert themselves more meaningfully
into the narrative.
The choices you make in broadsides
make you complicit not only in the ending,
but the whole story, not just how the story ends,
but what the story is.
Allowing or forcing.
the player to fill in blanks themselves gives the player an absolutely incomparable sense
of involvement in the story.
Which brings us to the most interesting IF technique, the one I think has the greatest
promise when adapted into other types of game narrative, complicity.
Where complicity is defined as a feeling of ownership in the plot.
Now, I think we can all agree that's an important thing to have.
If we didn't think that was an important thing to have,
we would be writing some other kind of fiction, novels or screenplays.
We are writing interactive fiction because the space where the player interacts
with the story is part of what we're trying to do.
Complicity is part of what we're manufacturing.
There are multiple ways you can do this.
The first is you can give the player actual choices
and allow those choices to actually affect the narrative.
These are games that already do this.
Blood and Laurels, 80 Days, anything from Choice Games
are made using ChoiceScript.
There are obviously a number of video games
that do this as well.
There are more variables that need to be considered when your game has more elements than just words.
But there are ways to handle a player-choice-driven branching narrative so that it represents only an incremental and not an exponential increase in production cost.
Choice of Games has a few techniques for managing some of the perceived problems with branching narrative.
But again, I only have 25 minutes and that's another...
presentation, maybe next year. For the moment, whether or not you have the
budget and artistic scope to allow real choices, you can make much of what the
player does feel like a real choice by constructing a feeling of freedom for
the player. What do I mean by that?
This is a screenshot from Hadean Lands,
and this is a very typical Parser.if experience.
You have your description, and you have your cursor,
and you get to decide the verb and noun to type next
out of all the verbs and all the nouns in the universe.
Parser.if enthusiasts say this is
one of their favorite parts of the genre.
You can do anything.
except that is obviously not actually true.
You cannot do anything.
You can do what the game has been programmed
to allow you to do, but you feel like you can do anything.
To borrow the words of Carolyn Van Esseltyn,
the core parser experience grants
the illusion of infinite choice and an actual experience
of carefully restricted choice.
And to go on in Andrew Plotkin's own words,
the core value of parser IF is freedom of action.
The player approaches it as an open-end range of choice.
I could do anything, so what does it make sense to try?
And as soon as the player asks, what makes sense here,
they are immersed in the game world.
When you feel you can do anything,
what you choose to do is that much more meaningful.
If you're unable, unwilling, artistically restricted
to offering real choice or an illusion of freedom,
you can still make the player's inevitable action
feel like I did it rather than the game made it happen to me
if you pay attention to how the action is executed.
This is at a higher level philosophically
than storytelling technique.
We're talking about mechanics in its most mechanical sense,
the way your player interacts with your game.
So, parser enthusiasts say,
parser IF has this one great advantage
over multiple choice lists.
If you decide to do something, you have to type it.
Not just I did it, not just it happened to me,
but I did it.
Reactive Studios knows this too.
Anything you do in Codename Cygnus must be spoken out loud.
Now let's talk about the broader implication.
With the advent of motion sensing and voice activated
input devices such as the Kinect,
it has become possible to actually allow the player
to swing the sword, throw the punch, climb the ladder,
and say the word.
So let's say you have an input device
that can reliably interpret a player
reading off a dialogue tree.
Just think what words you could put in their mouths.
Short, beautiful prose that hits hard.
The Picard speech that brings peace to warring factions,
the order to kill the enemy captain who is also
your star-crossed lover.
These are the experiences.
This is the level of emotional experience
that we can be bringing to our players.
So to recap, looking at public response
to some of this year's interactive fiction offerings
suggests a growing interest in good story,
separate from any other considerations.
IF has evolved a number of storytelling techniques that can be harvested when writing for other
types of games.
And IF has evolved a number of tools for designing narrative.
This is not a tool for designing narrative.
This is optimized for other things.
It does them very well.
Numbers, graphs, formulas, got it knocked.
It is not optimized for storyboarding or prototyping narrative.
These are.
They are designed specifically for narrative structure,
branching or otherwise.
They are easy to use.
They are free to use for prototyping.
And they will make your life so much easier
than using a spreadsheet.
So there is the perception that the day of interactive fiction
has come and gone, that it gave birth to the graphics-based
game and then faded away, except for a small fandom
in a back room somewhere.
But that's not true.
Interactive fiction is a vibrant art form. It is still evolving. It is still trying new experiments. It is still developing new techniques.
And there is hard evidence to suggest it still has a hell of a following, growing all the time.
The established narrative techniques and new narrative experiments in IF are generating enthusiasm from your target market and from people who might become your target market
by using IF's narrative techniques in conjunction with other tools for
game development video games can be taken to new artistic heights
and perhaps also to new heights on Metacritic.
Thank you.