And also, I was reminded to remind everybody
to please fill out the evaluation forms at the end,
because that's what makes these talks possible.
So, thank you for that.
All right.
So we're going to get this started.
Thank you for coming here on a 10 AM on Tuesday.
We realize that getting game developers to do anything at
10 AM is difficult, much less to come to a talk.
So thank you for being here.
And we promise to make it worth your while.
I'm Rob Zubek.
This is Matt Vianey.
We are the founders of Somasim, an indie
studio in Chicago.
And this is our talk about running a post-apocalyptic
games indie studio, or should I say, running a
post-apocalyptic indie studio.
So what this means, we're going to unpack in just a little bit.
But generally speaking, this is going
to be a talk about the stuff we learned
in the process of developing our latest game called Project
Hanoveris.
It's released in September 2016, so last fall.
But when we started working on it several years ago, the
market was very different.
So we started with different assumptions, and we ended in a
market that was quite different.
And this is going to be a talk about the kind of stuff we've
learned in the process of doing this and the process of
doing the business side of it.
And it's going to be a talk about actually the business
and running a studio kind of things, and not so much about
design or programming, although those will show up a
little bit in there.
So what do I mean by the situation has changed?
So what happened was, as we know with the market changing
and so on, we're going to illustrate with just a few
numbers pulled off from the PC market.
We're going to talk about the PC market, because that's
traditionally been the most friendly one for indies such
as ourselves.
And specifically, I'm going to use numbers from Steam and
from Steam Spy because they are publicly available and
they are very easy to get.
But the lessons are not going to be limited
necessarily to Steam.
Similar things you can see in other storefronts and so on.
So without further ado, let's talk about how the situation
has changed over the last few years before we get to the
meat of the talk.
The first thing I want to look at is the number of games being
published.
And we've all seen the articles show up online about
how this year we've seen the number of games released this
year on Steam are the 30% of the total number of games and
so on.
But let's put it in perspective, right?
As a timeline, what happened over the years?
If we look back 2010, 11, and so on, very few games released
every year, maybe a few hundred.
I apologize.
And then 2013, something happens.
There's an inflection point.
At around that time, Steam introduces Greenlight, and
things change a little bit.
Now we see thousands of games released every year.
This past year, the estimate is about 4,700.
which is not unreasonable.
If we look at the shape of the curve,
it increases linearly,
and I was sort of extending it further,
trying to estimate where things will be.
If we keep the same velocity,
then we're looking at 6,000 games a year this year,
before end of this year.
So that's a lot of games, right?
And when we talk about the changing situation,
this is our competition, right?
These are the kinds of market situation
that we have to look at.
So.
Will this velocity keep increasing?
Who knows.
But what we've seen in other media, whether it's music or
e-books or whatever, is that once we have an electronic
distribution system that doesn't have limitations on
it, the amount of content increases.
The amount of music increases.
The amount of e-books increases.
There's no reason to think that we're going to see this
curve slow down.
So that's one kind of set of numbers.
I want to take a look at another set of numbers is what
happens with this once we start adding it over time,
which is the total number of games on Steam.
And the total number of games, since we have this nice linear
velocity, so adding it up, we get a nice
quadratic kind of a thing.
So it just keeps going up.
And again, there's no reason to think this will slow down.
And the reason to think about the total number of games is
because that's a different kind of competition, too.
On the previous slide, we saw the number of games being
released concurrently.
And that's important because we compete
with them for attention.
But the back catalog is what we compete against for sales.
So for example.
We released Project Hyruza in September of 2016.
When we released it, that week, I think there were 80
other games released just that week, plus DLCs and stuff.
So when we got onto the new releases list, we dropped off
immediately, right?
We got no traffic from that.
But the second consideration is the back catalog.
If the player is going to log into Steam or GOG or whatever,
and they're going to see our game, are they going to buy it?
Or are they going to look at their wish list and say, you
know what, that game is new, and it's out for $20.
But there's this game on my wish list that's 70% off that
I've been dying to buy it for two years now.
I'm going to buy that instead and wait for this one to go.
Right?
Who here hasn't done that?
This is a totally normal thing for players to do.
And I apologize.
My lap seems to be going out a little bit.
I'm going to move it right here.
So we're looking at the back catalog as
competition for sales.
And the one more thing that I want to look at is the demand
side, because we looked at the supply side, how many games
are there out there.
The supply side, what does that look like?
And we don't have good numbers from Steam about the total
number of accounts.
But what they do publish is the number of concurrent
players, for example, every Christmas or every New Year's.
And the exact number doesn't matter so much as the shape of
the curve, right?
The total number of concurrent players every
year grows linearly.
And if we use that as a standard for the total number
of players, then we can see that the
Demand side grows linearly, and then the supply side grows
like this, and this gap right there is the new situation
that we're in.
So given these kinds of numbers that we looked at,
what does that mean for us?
Well.
There's been a lot of talk about is the apocalypse happening, is
it really a thing, it's not happening. It doesn't matter.
We're not going to necessarily talk about this kind of thing.
It doesn't matter. The situation has changed. Numbers speak for
themselves. So today what we're going to talk about is given
that the situation has changed, what can we do, sort of
ourselves, you guys, all of us together, to adjust, to adapt
ourselves?
to this new situation. So just a little bit of background about us before we get too much
further into it. So we are, as I mentioned, Somasim. We started our studio in 2013. We
are based out of Chicago. And first of all, 2013 was a very good year for us. We started
Probably not the right time to start a studio, as you might
imagine.
We should have probably done this a few years earlier, but
hindsight is 20-20, as they say.
But nevertheless, we made our first game.
It was a small city builder called 1849.
We shipped that in one year, in 2014.
We were also working on a second game, which we shipped
last year, called Project High-Rise.
We released that.
And, you know, knocking on wood, this will allow us to make a third game and so on.
And the point of this thing is that the numbers are showing that the market is changing and
it's a tough market.
It's tough for different reasons than it used to be.
But we're still working on this.
We're still trying to make this into a business and a business.
an opportunity for us to make games
and make a living off of it.
And so are you, right?
I mean, we are all in this sort of together.
We all have the same goal of making this viable for us.
So let's figure out how can we together
deal with this situation.
So.
The meat of the talk is going to be three sections.
I'm going to start by talking about discoverability, how
things have changed, and how we can adjust
ourselves to that.
Then I'm going to hand this clicker over to Matt, who's
going to talk about self-publishing and how that
is changing.
And then he's going to talk about the effects on studio
and team organization.
So without further ado, I'm going to jump right into it.
So.
Discoverability is sort of a perennial problem for all of
us, and it has for a long time.
And when I talk about discoverability, it's the
problem of getting eyeballs on the game.
So how do we get players to find out about our game and to
know that this is actually something that exists that
they want to play?
Because we all know that we're making games for players.
There are players out there who will want our games.
We just need to find them.
No matter how small a game, there are
people who will want it.
But how do they find out about it?
And that's been the standard problem all along.
And there are sort of two parts of it.
One is discovering from the outside, bringing people into
your web page, storefront, whatever, and then
discoverability from the inside.
Like once they're in a store, again, whether it's iTunes or
Steam or Google Play or Gog or whatever, how do they find out
about this game once they're there?
And discoverability is always hard for indies because all
media follow a very power law distribution where the big
guys get all the attention and they get the players, they get
the money, and so on.
And the smaller studios or smaller teams end up in the
so-called long tail.
The idea of the long tail, as you know, is that given an
electronic distribution media where it's cheap to distribute
things, hopefully the small players will be able to
sell a smaller number of games to people who are interested.
So for indies, if we're looking at this long table,
we're somewhere on the floor over there, right?
And the challenge for us is to find those players who will
learn about us, because we don't have the marketing
budgets of the big guys.
So we're going to talk about pulling people from the outside
in a little bit.
Now, let's first talk about getting people to discover the
game once they're on the store page.
And traditionally, this means getting featured in some way,
whether it's getting featured through a featuring slot
that's hand-created, or maybe something like a top 10 list,
or new releases list, and so on.
And if you go and log into Steam or another store, you
will see this kind of a long list of different things that
the store is telling you about.
and a lot of the thinking is about how do we get ourselves featured on this?
And what I'm going to say is maybe that's not the focus anymore
because the amount of featuring that's actually likely to happen to us is relatively small.
If we look at what happens when the player logs into Steam,
opens up their Steam client, and they're going to go play a
game, but before they do that, they want to look at their
store and see what's there.
They're going to see the stuff above the fold first.
And that's the sort of newspaper metaphor.
Like if you have a newspaper, you see it in a store.
The stuff above the fold is the stuff right below the
masthead, and then the other stuff you don't see
necessarily immediately.
So above the fold, we have some featuring slots, which
is very good.
In fact, right now there are 12 of them in a carousel that
flips back and forth.
And that's the stuff that the player will see first.
These are the featured and recommended games, or maybe
manually curated and so on.
Then if the player scrolls further down, they're going to
see additional featuring slots.
So they might see a special offers section, for example.
And these things change, right?
Some things go up, some things go down.
And in a section like this, maybe there will be six games,
maybe there will be 12 games, and so on.
then the question is if the player was to be scrolling
further down and so on, they would probably see more
featuring slots, right?
But what I would actually say is that they won't.
Those other ones don't really matter so much because if a
player is going to the store page to play a game,
They're just gonna play a game.
They might see something above the fold,
but they're not gonna go exploring.
They will go exploring only if there's a sale
or something special going on.
So what we're really talking about is
the featuring slots that matter in any store
are the top ones.
And there's a limited number of them.
Very small, finite number of them.
So what this means is that for featuring, for bringing
players in from inside the store into our page, we're
running into two sort of competing forces, or two
forces that are both working against us.
One, the larger the stores grow, the more players they
get, which means that each of those featuring slots becomes
more valuable because there are more eyeballs looking at
it, therefore those featuring slots are going to go to the
best sellers, obviously because.
That's how we make money, right?
And then the second force is that the more games there are
on stores, the less likely, statistically, each game is to
get one of those featuring slots.
So these are two kind of forces that work against small
developers such as ourselves from getting visibility inside
a store.
So what happens in a situation like this is storefronts
develop different strategies.
And we've seen this with any other storefronts that have a
huge inventory of product, digital products such as
Amazon, Netflix, and so on.
They all end up.
going towards algorithmic recommendations.
And indeed, Steam has been doing the same.
So algorithmic recommendations do the sort of thing of
they look at what you've played before,
and then they give you a recommendation based on that.
And this is very good, as instead of human curation,
now we have
system that tells you, hey, if you like this, you might like that. And here's an example.
I was logging into my steam client the other day and it tells me right up front, hey, there's
this new game called stellar monarch. You play strategy games and simulation games and
forex games and indie games. Why don't you try this one?
So I thought to myself, why don't I try this one?
It sounds good.
So even without doing any research, just based on this,
I went and purchased it and loved it.
It was great.
I mean, and I was so happy that the automated system
gave me this recommendation right up top above the fold
because otherwise I would never have discovered it.
And it's an indie game. I think it's like a one or two person team. And what are the chances that they would have been selected by a human curation process?
Probably fairly low. But the automation system recommended it to me and I was very happy with the result.
And we see Steam sort of
going further with that, right?
They're sort of continuing with that,
and in fact right now,
looking at the featuring slots above the fold,
about half of them right now are algorithmically selected.
So, what does this mean?
This has an effect on us.
As we make games, we have to think about, all right, if
we're going to be looking for discoverability within a
store, how do we make life easier for ourselves to be
discovered through these algorithms?
How do we make ourselves algorithm friendly?
And here's the thing.
Recommendation algorithms, whether they're
or Netflix or whatever, they based on some kind of similarity
metrics. There's always a tension inside them. So Amazon
might work on purchase history, Netflix might work on stars,
Steam might work on tags and purchase history, et cetera. In
any case, there's always this tension between on one hand
looking at your history and giving you more of the same,
more of what you've already played, and also on the other
hand,
doing exploration, right?
Given what you've played,
maybe you wanna try something very different
that you wouldn't think of trying out yourself.
And this is a tension that historically
tends to swing towards giving you more of the same.
just because it's easier to know given your history,
given my history of strategy simulation 4X Indy,
that I'm gonna like these kinds of games.
And sure enough, I keep getting them over and over.
But who knows, maybe there's a racing, farming,
Indy 2D game out there that I would really love.
And chances are I would, right?
Because I like my racing games every now and then.
I like my farming games every now and then.
But it's hard for the algorithms to know
that this is the combo for me.
So here's my postulate.
I think that what we're going to see with the
recommendation systems is that it's going to be easier for
niche games and genre games to get recommended to players.
And it's going to be harder for esoteric games or games
that span multiple genres and multiple niches to get
recommended.
We'll see how this plays out for sure. But if this is the case,
then niches are starting to become more powerful.
In fact, we have ourselves defined ourselves as a genre
studio not because of this back in 2013.
Our thinking was we like simulation games.
We like strategy games.
We're going to concentrate on those because we like them and
we think we're good at them.
And it's even in the name, SomaSim.
But it's been an interesting kind of experience to follow
through with this and see how this grows.
So if this is something that you are considering, a couple
words about targeting a niche.
One, niches are sort of recapitulating the same difficulties of the larger market where
you're still competing against a number of games that are kind of similar to each other
and you're still competing for eyeballs just on a smaller scale.
And niches do get very faddish.
They get based on style.
If you're right now releasing a Proc Gen game, you're great.
But if you're just starting working on a Proc Gen open
world sandbox or something like that, where will the
market be when you finish this?
So this is something that we've thought of through the
process of development of our last game.
And it's something that stays on our mind.
You always have to be several years ahead of the market.
And in niches specifically, how are the fads going to go?
So always have to look at the future and also the other thing
that was kind of surprising to us but in retrospect shouldn't
have been is that niches are communities. They have their own
sets of expectations. They have their own ideas about anything
from UI conventions to mechanics to systems and so on. So you
have to be aware of them because otherwise you're going to get
very vocal feedback about that. So it helps to be a player
inside that niche.
All right, so we talked a lot about recommendation systems
and how to look at discoverability inside the
store, and I'm going to wrap up quickly looking at
discoverability from the outside.
So the problem of bringing eyeballs from the sort of
outside world looking at your game.
And that's a problem that never went away.
It's always been a problem.
Word of mouth is obviously the best.
way to get recommendations.
The thing that we've seen becoming very, very, very
important has been YouTube and Twitch.
And specifically, things like, again, if we're looking at
genres and specific kind of styles of games.
look at communities that orient around them. For example,
Project High Rise again, before we released the game we sent
out keys to YouTubers, Twitch players and so on and we were
very lucky to be picked up to catch the interest of a few
players who specifically play simulation strategy games.
and they had audiences who specifically
looked for simulation strategy games.
So that was sort of a match made in heaven.
We were lucky enough to attract their attention
and from that, players who look for these kinds of games
learned about them, learned about our game.
So we got some number of hundreds of thousands of views
on these videos that they made
and that's a huge number, right?
One, just the number itself is big, and two, the audience is looking for these kinds of
games.
This is a different audience than a mass market audience.
So this was very, very interesting and very valuable.
So in summary of this section, when we look at discoverability and getting our game out
getting eyeballs on our game and so on. I think the traditional ways of things like
getting selected by curators is going to be less likely. Things like new releases lists
are going to be much less valuable just because of the velocity. We've seen the numbers, new
releases lists, showing up on those is no longer useful.
But what is going to be increasingly important, I
think, is one, becoming algorithm friendly.
So keeping this in our mind from the very beginning of the
design process, how do we make our game easier to be
discovered for people?
And two, bringing in outside traffic from genre-specific
audiences, such as YouTubers, let's players, and so on, who
specialize in these kinds of games.
So that's that for my discoverability section.
Now I'm going to hand this over to Matt, who's going to
talk about.
Parts two and three.
Thank you.
Excellent.
Wasn't Rob great?
Thanks, Rob.
So Rob started to touch on how do you get traffic from
outside of the stores into your site?
How do you start building up the number of eyeballs that
you get on your game?
And that's where I'd like to move next in my next section
as we go the right way in the slide deck.
So I want to talk about publishing, about how the numbers that we've seen, the 6,000
games that are going to come out this year, added on to the 12,000 games that are already
on Steam, how that impacts publishing and getting eyeballs on.
Before we look at 2017, I want to go back in time to the halcyon days of 2011, when
there were a few hundred games that came out every year on Steam.
And back in those days, who needs publishers?
We're indies.
We're just going to put our game out there and we'll put it up on Steam, on IndieDB,
on Desura.
Then we'll flog it to death on social media, we'll get a lot of traffic, people will buy
our game, it'll be awesome, we'll make another one, it's Indie Paradise, yay!
Except that's not really true anymore.
And I also would argue that in 2011,
that wasn't really true either.
Platforms like Valve, like iTunes, like Google,
were picking games that they liked as curators,
they were putting them on prominent featuring slots,
they were doing a lot of promotion,
they were driving a lot of traffic there.
Sounds like a publisher to me, but that's just me.
So.
To come back to 2017, we've changed things a lot.
Valve is now acting like an online store.
There's a loose selection process
that's getting looser and looser all the time.
And it's up to us as the developers,
as the people who make the games,
to drive traffic, to get the eyeballs in the game,
to do the work that they were sort of doing for us in 2011.
And I'd like to take a break for a moment
and talk about the future of Steam.
Because Steam for us, at least for us as PC,
developers is an important platform.
So let's look at where Steam thinks
they wanna go in the future.
Back in 2013, around the time we saw that inflection point
where things began to change,
Gabe Newell said the following thing,
and I wanna read this one verbatim.
If we're thinking about this correctly,
anybody should be able to publish anything through Steam,
where Steam is just a whole bunch
of servers and network bandwidth.
Sync in, sync in, sync in, okay.
So.
Then this sort of came true last month,
or I guess it's still this month,
when Steam announced Steam Direct.
So, they're now getting rid of the greenlight process
that we saw in 2013 around that inflection point,
and now we see our goal is to provide developers
and publishers with a more direct publishing path
and ultimately connect gamers with even more great content.
So basically, Steam's vision of where their platform
should be in the future is the exact opposite
of where it was in 2011.
They don't want to do the curation.
They don't want to do the selection.
They want to let the market do that.
The games that sell well will be the games
that get the featuring.
So it's up to us to start to think about
how we're going to get those sales,
how are we gonna get those eyeballs onto our games?
And that becomes our job now.
So, can you still do this kind of self-publishing
that was being done in 2011?
You can put the game up on stores, but you've got to remember there are going to be 6,000
other people who are going to release new games next year, and that doesn't include
things like DLCs and content packs and sprite packs and everything else that junks up the
front page and the release pattern thing on Steam.
So there's that.
Can you flog it on social media?
Sure, but you've been on social media lately, right?
It's kind of a dumpster fire, so good luck with that.
So what are we talking about?
What's the solution here?
We still need to do this real PR,
this real marketing that has to be done.
And again, since Valve is no longer.
limiting the number of games and they want to broaden them, that becomes even more important.
It requires a great deal of skill. It requires connections. You need to have that person
at Valve, at Apple, at GOG that picks up your email, that replies to you in order to help
get that featuring going. So what I'm saying is this becomes a full-time job. This is something
that is really increasingly important. But what if you're terrible at it like us?
It's dangerous out there, so you should take some help with you.
So we think you should hire the right person for the job.
When we made 1849 in 2013, our first game, we decided we need
to do audio.
Let's go ahead and do audio.
We can do that ourselves.
I had never done audio before, I have no idea how to do it.
Rob had never done audio before either,
he had no idea how to do it, but we didn't let that stop us.
And we did it anyway.
And sure enough, when the game went out there,
we got a lot of replies in forum posts with things like,
those cows are terrible.
Make the cows stop.
Why is there so much mooing?
Why is the mixing like that?
So when it came time for us to do Project High Rise,
I think the third thing we did was find somebody
to do the audio for our game.
because we're not good at it. It's not a skill set that we have native to our team.
And we think that you should hire the right person for the right job, if that's audio,
if that's art, or if that's marketing. And so am I talking about the return of the publisher?
Because, you know, we're indies. Like, publishing and hiring a publisher sort of gives us all
the creeps a little bit.
Those numbers that Rob went over, those huge influx of games onto the market, they haven't
just changed us as developers, they've changed publishers too. So publishers have also changed,
they've evolved. Back in the battle days of 2006, we had old school publishers who did
things like this, and most of those things are fine, but I'm an indie dev and I really
hate those last two. Take the majority of the revs and own the IP. I made the game,
I want the revs, I made the game, I want the IP.
We've seen a new wave of publishers come on the scene
that are willing to do help for marketing,
that are willing to do help for PR,
that have Twitch and YouTube connections,
that just take a cut of the revenues and don't own the IP.
Which sounds great.
And we've seen a lot of indies begin to work
with these kind of new school publishers.
But how do we evaluate them?
Like, I know how to evaluate an artist,
a 3D artist, a 2D artist.
I know how to evaluate a sound person,
how to evaluate somebody to work with us
to help code the game.
How do you evaluate a publishing partner?
Like, how do you know if they're right for your game?
So, some things to consider.
Does their target audience match yours?
Did they put out eight, 10 strategy simulation games
in the past couple of years?
If so, they have eight or 10 games worth of players
that are right in your niche, right in your genre
to sell your, to market your game to.
That's one thing.
Do they have good distributor relationships?
When you go on to Steam and there's like a,
they do the publisher's weekends,
do you see them show up as one of them?
Do you see the games be,
featured in those, that means that they have an email, they have a contact at the publisher
that you can work and that is valuable for you.
Do they have a good player reputation? When you go on to discussion boards, do you see
the publishers interacting, in addition to the devs, with players? Do players respond
positively to their games when they come out? What are the reviews? What's the situation
for the other games that they've published?
Do they have a good game reputation within our community as game devs?
When you come to a conference like GDC and you say, hey, we're thinking about working
with these guys, is the reaction, oh, yeah, they're great people, you should definitely
work with them, or is it, you should talk to Rob?
That's not a good reaction that you get.
So what's the reputation like within the game dev community?
And do they fund games?
Do you need the funding?
If so, that's a very important consideration.
So there are also some parasites out there.
So be careful and look out for these publishers who will take
your game, tweet about it eight times on release day,
send 20 keys to YouTubers and say, we published your game.
That'll be 20%.
You can do that yourself and keep the 20%.
So they also have a bad reputation among players.
Players know who the shovelware publishers are.
So just avoid that, the nail on the head.
So just to summarize this section a little bit,
self-publishing is not as easy as it used to be anymore.
Standing out in this crowded market
where you have 6,000 games coming out next year
is going to be even more difficult than it used to be.
So if you're not good at it, outsource it.
It's what we would do for any other skill set
that we don't possess natively to our team.
And we need to start thinking about these things
like PR, like marketing,
like how we're gonna get the eyeballs on the game
as crucial parts of the game development process,
not things that we'll do later once we're done.
OK, so that said, I would like to talk about how we can work
together better as developers, how we can change the way that
we relate to one another within our teams, and how we can use
that to help cut through this noise as well, and how we can
use it to increase the number of eyeballs.
When we're talking about getting people to pay
attention to us, to follow our games.
People follow other people.
When I want to find a new piece of music or a new book
or something like that, I don't follow a publisher
or a platform or a studio.
I follow a musician or an author or a group or a TV star.
I follow the people who are behind making the product,
who are behind the creative voice.
So they stand out by emphasizing their own creative voice.
And we can stand out by emphasizing our creative voice.
And as indie developers, we need to do a better job at this.
What I'm saying is we need to find our inner Kubricks.
You can always tell a Kubrick movie,
everybody knows that's The Shining.
Yes?
Hope?
Okay, so this is sort of that iconic scene
from The Shining where he's racing down the hallway
on the big wheel and the camera's right behind him
and it's sharp corners, the suspense builds
until he runs into the creepy twins
and they say, come play with us.
The creepy scene, it's a very Kubrick.
And if I tell you that a movie you haven't seen before
is a Kubrick movie, you already know a lot about,
you know, Kubrick, you already know a lot about that movie
before you even see the movie.
We recognize Kubrick in the work.
So how do players recognize you and me in our games?
So like if, when Cliff Harris puts out a new Puzzletech game,
it comes out, just by knowing that it's a Cliff Harris
Puzzletech game, I already know lots about it.
In fact, when he put production line out for the alpha,
I bought it right away because I knew I would like it.
When a new Zachtronics game comes out,
know a lot about that already just because
they've done a good job of establishing
that creative voice and that creative style.
And I'm talking about you and we as in the whole team of people, not just us as the main
developers but ourselves, the people who did our audio, the people who did our sound.
They need credit, they need recognition because giving that to them increases everybody's
bandwidth, increases the volume of our creative voice collectively.
And I want to take an example from a different area,
from restaurants.
We live in Chicago, and there are lots and lots and lots
and lots and lots of restaurants in Chicago,
with new ones opening every week.
It's a crowded volatile market
that should sound familiar to us.
And within Mexican restaurants,
it's an even deeper problem,
because there are lots and lots and lots
of Mexican restaurants in Chicago,
so it's a crowded niche.
And that's Chef Rick Bayless,
who you may know from his PBS...
cooking show, and he does a really good job,
because he has a little empire of Mexican restaurants
in Chicago, of cutting through the noise of restaurants.
When he opened a new torta restaurant,
we went there right away, not because it was
a new torta restaurant, but because it was
Rick Bayless' restaurant.
And he also does a really good job of working with
and encouraging people he works with.
That's Anselmo Ramirez, who Rick Bayless calls
the king of mole.
He makes the best Mexican sauces I've ever had in my life.
So.
and he talks about it on his cooking shows,
in the media, whenever he's asked questions,
like, who are you following, who are you working with?
He encourages and promotes the people that he works with.
So when Chef Ramirez opened a new restaurant,
which is conveniently around the corner from my house,
we couldn't get in for three months.
So that kind of amplification of not just his own bandwidth,
but then helping his coworkers, his people who he works with,
is sort of a way of you can,
like, you know, the rising tide lifts all boats.
And that means that we need to think about
providing an equal share in rewards as well,
so that people who contribute to your game to its success,
and everybody contributes to that voice,
gets to enjoy the fruits of the labor.
So if you're working on a contract,
if you're working for a company,
you're getting a paycheck,
but is it what you're passionate about?
Not necessarily.
How does that increase your creative voice?
How does that get you going?
How does that get you talking?
And for us, that means everyone we work with,
we work with on a rev share basis.
So that leads to a long tail of revenues
that sort of lifts all of the boats
and helps everyone become more independent
with each game that comes out.
And that's abstract, so here's some specifics.
This is the...
sales chart for our first game, 1849.
And we're gonna ignore that big bump at the beginning
and look how we have the months of sales
that come after that.
That's the long tail that helped us as developers,
but also our artists that we worked with
make Project High Rise, which came out.
And we have, again, hopefully there's that big bump
at the beginning, and then we're seeing the beginning
of a long tail show up.
That's going to let us, the people we worked with,
our artists, become more independent
with each successive game that we release.
And more independence helps us develop our creative voice.
It helps us start to break through this noise
together as a team.
So these RevShare teams that we're talking about,
let's look into them a little bit more and how we do it.
All contributors participate in the spoils.
So we take the big chunk of money that comes in,
hopefully it's a big chunk of money,
and it's per title, so per game that comes out,
and then it's done by proportional contribution.
So my hour's worth the same as Rob's hour,
it's worth the same as our artist's hour.
We total the number of hours that were done,
and if I worked 35% of the hours,
I get 35% of the revenue.
And that's worked for us for two games so far.
And it was inspired by Randy Smith from Tiger Style,
and you can go see his talk from 2013,
from which I stole most of the slide.
So, some challenges.
These things aren't really fish nor fowl.
It's not a traditional contracting relationship.
It's not a salary, but it's somewhere in between.
So there's some challenges to this model.
How do you find the right people?
How do you find the person who's willing to, you know,
work for two years and maybe get paid later?
It's risky.
Like, no one knows if the game's gonna succeed.
Like one way you could do that to help mitigate things
is to offer some sort of advance on royalties,
but then you need the money up front to do that.
And that's sometimes hard to find.
and they have to trust, you have to trust that they can deliver what they say without
the motivation, the carrot of a salary to help drive their work, and they have to trust
that you're going to deliver and that your game can make enough revenue to make it worth
their while and that you pay them and stuff. So we're really talking about a limited pool.
ex-colleagues, friends, people you know, people who you can talk into taking the Rope Share
plunge with you. And that's kind of a problem, that local pool. We only find our collaborators
locally. When I start working on my next game, I'll find my collaborators through people
that I've worked with before at different jobs, different games, or through the network
of indies in Chicago.
But how can we sort of shift that
to be more global in collaboration?
How can we find that guy who's waiting to do art
for our game that would be perfect for it in Sweden
that can do RevShare?
Why do I need to know about that artist?
They should know about me.
How do we shift these collaborations,
these networks to be more global?
And unfortunately, there's not a slide
with an answer coming up.
That's sort of a problem that I want to put out there
for us as a community to think about.
How can we start to shift?
the way that we work from our local networks to more global networks. So that's something
I want to leave you with today and hopefully start a conversation about that going forward.
So sort of to wrap up this section a little bit, our players want our game, hopefully,
not just any game. They want the game that we're putting out next that we've been talking
about, that we've been encouraging our artists, our audio people, our whole team to talk about
and get passionate about and to really develop our next game.
And independence is what lets us develop that creative voice.
Being Indies is our strength.
It's what's going to help us get through the noise.
It's not what's going to keep us from getting through it.
By emphasizing and maintaining our independence,
that's what's going to help us get through the noise.
That's what's going to help us cut through this 6,000 games
that are coming out next year.
We need to maintain that.
We need to strengthen it.
We need to reinforce it.
And again, that distinct voice
is what's going to let us get through the noise.
So, we're gonna wrap up with whatever that is
and look at a few conclusions
before we jump to some questions
which we've hopefully left enough time for.
I think you can summarize our...
talk by the theme of the following. Noise changes everything. The number of games that
have come out last year and in the past few years and that we're going to see coming,
we can't stop. They're going to add on to the games that are already out there. The
noise level is going to increase dramatically in the coming years. How do we deal with that?
Hopefully we come up with some suggestions today that can help us deal with that.
You need to develop a unique voice that players will seek out.
Structure your team so that everybody that you work with becomes more independent.
Structure your team so that we're all becoming more independent as we go forward and all
developing that creative voice.
Find partners to amplify your voice.
If you're bad at PR, if you're bad at marketing, if you're bad at those things like I am,
Those skill sets aren't native to your team.
Find people who can help you.
Find people who can do that.
It's an important core skill set in this new world.
And finally, we need to plan for how players
are gonna find our games
from the very first commit of code to our game.
We need to know how they're going to get through the store,
how a player's gonna find them,
how are we going to do that kind of discoverability,
not later on, but as we're developing the game
from those very early concept stages.
So hopefully we now know how we can survive
this post-apocalyptic world a little bit better,
and we'd welcome some questions,
and you should all come see us in Chicago.
Thank you.
So if anyone has any questions,
please go to the mic in the center aisle.
Hi.
Hey.
So you mentioned following people as opposed to following brands, but then you also mentioned
collective voice of a studio as opposed to an individual voice.
How do you put those two together?
I mean, I think we're looking at it sort of from the indie perspective, like, you know,
this is our studio.
And I think...
we have to look at it more like a band,
like we're a band, you know,
like we're people who've come together to make this album
and that's our game.
So I think, you know, we're not talking about
like a big studio, like Blizzard or something like that.
Like, you know, think of yourselves more like a band
and, you know, everybody knows the guitarist,
the drummer and stuff like that.
So I think we need to think more like that.
Like there's the drummer, there's the guitarist,
there's the lead singer.
And we're all sort of coming together as a band
to make an album, which is our game.
And actually, if I can follow up on that, I think it works in both ways.
And there's a point about what to focus on.
For some people, it might be a single person who's sort of fronting everything
and they're developing their recognition.
For teams, like for example, Zetronix came up before.
And that's one person who works with collaborators, so it works behind a team name.
And I think these both work.
The major distinction is that they have a recognizable voice.
These are not teams that, for example, switch from genre to genre.
They don't try a lot of...
they don't have an unrecognizable style.
They have a style and the style hides, not hides,
but is represented either by a team name
or by a person name.
And that's the recognition of a style is the important part.
Thank you.
Yeah.
All right.
So you talk about how new school publishers
are not funding games in the same way
that old school publishers were.
And you also talk about how there's, on Steam at least,
a linear increase in consumers versus a quadratic increase
in the supply of games.
This seems to imply that market forces
are going to squeeze out a lot of people
who have less money, and that, or it could happen.
And that most of the games that are gonna be able
to achieve success are games that are gonna be made
by people who are basically richer.
a lot of people cannot afford to work for two years on the promise of revenue.
Some amount of capital is needed and if publishers are not providing it, where can that capital
come from in this current world?
There's been a lot of hand-wringing about the viability of crowdfunding and what not
and in particular how it's not viable.
It's not something that you guys have really touched on at all.
I'm wondering if you had any thoughts.
Yeah, I mean, in a certain sense it's a very similar situation to how it's been all along, right?
That for indies it's really hard to find funding, and people end up self-funding because they have to.
And sometimes when you have...
Sometimes you might be able to get something like PR
marketing help and so on on a ref share basis, for example.
So you don't have to pay up front, but the PR person will
take a cut of the cost.
But the problem of getting funding for a game is always a
hard one.
It used to be much easier to, if you made a game, to then
release it without publishing and recoup the costs in an easier way, but now it's harder.
So I guess the answer to that is that like in any other small business,
you need to have some kind of seed capital to start with.
And I mean, that ends up being somebody's savings, right?
Whether it's savings being spent on a contractor,
whether it's savings being spent on rent
while you work in your basement for two years, right?
I don't think there's a good way to get around that,
but also I don't think there's ever been a good way
to get around that, unfortunately.
Thank you.
I've got a two-part question for Dr. Z.
You had suggested that increasingly getting surface for algorithmic recommendations was
an area of focus and it's going to be increasingly important on STEAM.
How do you know that you're succeeding on that?
Do you get impression or funnel statistics
from recommendation servicing?
The second part is you had mentioned
that it favors niche games.
Seems like a lot of recent innovation has come
from like genre mashups.
How do you succeed in getting a mashup recommended?
Yeah, so to answer the first question, there are no numbers
publicly available right now, unfortunately.
So we can't do
It's a guessing game.
Yeah, we can't really do analytics on that.
I would love it if there were numbers.
I mean, that would be so amazing.
So I think one thing that's going to be useful going
forward is using a service like Steam Swipe, for example.
You can collect, for example, data on how many games are
tagged with different tags and what their sales were like.
And you could potentially do your own manual matchup of
like, hey, games that are strategy simulation have been
growing, and games that are strategy farming 2D racing
have been declining.
But that's not gonna be possible at least for another year
because Steam has only recently been
getting really, you know, doubling down
on this algorithmic recommendation.
And I apologize, I forgot the second one.
Sorry, second question is like,
you had mentioned that recommendations
favor niche-based games.
And it seems like that's counter to a lot
of recent innovation that's been really mashup-based.
Like, how do you build a mashup
that can also get recommended?
I guess is the question.
And maybe it's more rhetorical, like it's hard.
It's a finance error.
I think you have to start in a niche that's already strong
and then hopefully that sort of broadens out.
Like I think you still have to try to target
the niche to begin with.
And then hopefully that allows you to broaden out.
And as it gets more pick up and more word of mouth in
other communities, then hopefully you can leverage
other community.
I think you'd be strongest by trying to focus on your
coordination and then move to the neighboring one and start
to take over the neighbors.
And that looks to me like we're out of time.
Yeah, looks like that wraps it up.
Thank you so much, Robert and Matt.
Thank you.