Hello. Welcome. So, that's certainly live. Welcome to looking back and moving forward
with Pillars of Eternity. I'm your host, Josh Sawyer.
There's a few things I should say before we start.
First is, please silence your cell phones
if you happen to be, have not done that already.
Also, you should be receiving an email about a survey
for this session.
Please fill them out.
It helps GDC determine if my talk is good or a pile of trash
and if I should never, ever be invited back again.
So let's talk about what this talk is about.
It is about Pillars of Eternity, in fact.
I'm trying to make it about more than just
being a post-mortem of how the game went, what we did right
and what we did wrong.
It's trying to broaden the focus more to retro-styled games
overall, why they appeal to gamers,
some of the inherent dangers that
come with making a retro-classic game that
has a lot of very passionate fans from the beginning,
and about our learning experiences
in making this game.
By the way, Facebook reminded me that four years ago today, we
recorded the video for, this is a picture from the video for
our Kickstarter campaign for Pillars of Eternity, so that
little angel is long gone. So who am I? I am Josh Sawyer. I am
the design director at Obsidian Entertainment. Of particular
relevance to this talk, I was the director and system designer
on Pillars of Eternity, and I was the director and system
designer on Fall at New Vegas. And...
one of the expansions. Way back when at Black Isle Studios, I got my start as a level designer
on Icewind Dale, which was my first introduction to designing for Infinity Engine style games,
and then later I was the lead designer on Icewind Dale 2. And I got into gaming in part
because I've been playing tabletop games for about 30 years, so my love affair with this
style of game goes back a long way.
I've talked a lot about Pillars of Eternity in the past.
Hopefully you're familiar with it.
If you're not, it was a Kickstarter-backed project.
We had about 77,000 backers and raised about $4 million.
It was very, very successful.
We did not think making such a game would be possible at all until Double Fine Adventure
launched on Kickstarter.
Then we decided, no, we definitely have to make a game like this.
It took a while to get our owners convinced that this was a good idea, but they relented.
And we decided that we would make an Infinity Engine style game.
We wanted it to be a combination of elements from Icewind Dale, Baldur's Gate, and Planescape
Torment.
We wanted it to be Forgotten Realms-y and AD&DE, so similar to the Forgotten Realms
setting, similar to the Dungeons and Dragons rule set, without exactly copying them, because,
well, we don't have the rights to those.
The Kickstarter campaign was very successful very quickly.
We really, a lot of people don't believe us when we say this, but we did not, we were
not sure that it was going to be successful.
Our original goal was 1.1 million dollars, that was reached in 27 hours.
And at the end of the campaign, it was, I think, 3.9.
So very successful, very quickly.
And we had to do a lot of seat-of-our-pants design
for things like stretch goals, which wound up
being a little bit more than we could handle
in terms of development.
But we'll get to that.
So what's the appeal of retro gaming anyway?
There are three things I'll talk about here.
One is nostalgia.
That's one of the biggest ones.
It's about passion.
It's about a longing for a time where
we remember playing the games that we loved
and how great that made us feel.
It's about the challenge presented
by a lot of older games.
You can find games that are still challenging
that are made today, but it's not as common
since gaming has a broader fan base now.
And it's about wild cards, which is sort of the more human element and wacky things that
we as human being developers wind up putting in our games that in march of time and the
polishing of development has kind of erased a lot of.
First, let's talk about nostalgia.
These are images that are very nostalgic for me,
because I grew up in the 80s and early 90s
playing role-playing games like the original Bard's Tale.
I played all the Gold Box games from SSI.
Those were the AD&D games set in the Forgotten Realms
and the Dragonlance settings, which were a lot of fun.
And also Darklands, which is a game that almost no one has
ever heard of.
But it's a very cool historical role-playing game
set in the Holy Roman Empire.
and it's a lot of fun.
And whenever I see pictures like this, it draws me back to that time,
makes me very excited and passionate.
I forget all the bad things about those games.
I just remember all the good things,
and I wish someone would make more games like that.
And that's the way people feel when they see a lot of the Infinity Engine games,
is that feeling of nostalgia,
remembering how fun it was and how much they loved those games.
And the second part is challenge.
Like I said, you can still find games being made today
that are really emphasizing a very strong difficulty curve,
things like Dark Souls, games like that,
especially since we have a lot more smaller developers making
more focused games for niche audiences.
You can find very challenging games out there.
But role-playing games have also broadened their appeal and their fan base,
and you see a lot of games that are targeted for a very low level of difficulty,
a very shallow learning curve.
And when people think back to games like Baldur's Gate or Icewind Dale,
they think of very, very challenging fights that might have taken them hours
and a lot of cursing and reloading to get through.
The last thing are wild cards and this is sort of what I said
about human beings develop these games and when we were younger
we put things in these games that when we look back at we
kind of cringe. They're rough edges and goofy things, things
like Noober. I don't know if you guys remember Noober from
Baldur's Gate. He was an NPC that would approach you and he
would not stop talking to you and it was sort of like coaxing
you to kill him. Very, very obnoxious character but people
still have fond memories of this guy because he's just a wild and
wacky dude and then things like the golden pantaloons.
goofy clothing item that you can find in Baldur's Gate.
So, the modern development process in a lot of cases,
especially with large development teams,
it kind of files over the edges of these human elements
that people, they actually find very endearing
because they show that people have fun making games.
That's one of the reasons why we started making games.
So let's talk about the, some of the dangers of making a retro
revival game. You can hit the wrong targets. You can just
focus on the wrong things. You look at all the things that go
into a game and you spend your time working on the things that
no one gives a shit about.
That's bad.
You can design for a very tiny niche.
We sort of admit that we are designing for a niche audience.
We're not designing for everybody, clearly.
We're not even designing for most gamers.
We're designing for a smaller subset of people.
But within that niche, there are even
tinier and tinier niches of people
that are more interested in very, very narrow elements.
If you over-design toward one tiny niche,
you will never broaden your appeal at all,
which can also be bad because you presumably
want to continue making games.
You can also update too much.
You can look at everything and say, you know what, let's fix and update all of this stuff.
Some of that stuff you don't need to touch at all.
You can just leave it alone.
It's totally fine.
So you can be careful and just say, you know what, leave that alone.
Let's focus on things that really need to be improved and not, you know, not change
everything.
And the last part is missing the soul. This is a very ephemeral, feels-based thing, but it's very important.
It's possibly the most important thing, because again, the reason why you get a lot of people interested in these sort of retro-revival games in the first place
is because they're very passionate about the game itself.
And if it doesn't really have the feeling of those games,
if it doesn't evoke the sort of nostalgia
that you're looking for, you fail.
You can even make a good game that
is sort of good to some people, but you're
sort of making it for an audience in the first place.
And if you miss that, then you've missed the point.
Soul is elusive. So let's talk about soul, which is this very ephemeral thing.
When people remember the things that they love, their memory can be selective,
they can gloss over a lot of things,
and most of what they remember is their emotional attachment to it,
and little things that stick out to them.
The individual elements that go into it contribute to the whole picture.
So when you modify things, you have to be very careful about what you're modifying.
You could tweak one tiny thing that turns out to be a very key component of what made
that something very cool.
And ultimately, the spirit of something is more important than actually getting it technically
accurate.
And in many cases, it's healthier if you're trying to modernize a game.
The example, I'm wearing my Ducati shirt today, I'm glad I packed it, because I'm going to
talk about how Ducati, a motorcycle manufacturer, updated.
The bike on the left is Mike Halewood's Isle of Man TT bike from 1978, and the bike on
the right is a mid-2000s Sport Classic 1000.
They look fairly similar.
but they're not actually all that similar, but they capture the soul of the old bike. And
that's why that bike immediately sold out and why I can never find one for a good price and I'm
going to be mad for the rest of my life about it. But it goes to show that the spirit of the
thing is what's important. It's less important than the exact specific details. So let's
talk about some of the things we did in Pillars of Eternity and what went right and what went
very not right.
We decided from the beginning that we were going to be making 2D environments from an isometric rendered perspective.
That was a core component of all the Infinity Engine games.
We knew we were going to raise the resolution a lot,
but we were still going to hand touch most of our environments because we did a lot of...
After an environment would be rendered, we'd have 2D artists go back and touch them up.
And that we were also going to try to add in a 3D lighting element, which was challenging.
And I covered that in a little talk I did a few years ago.
But basically, we managed to get 3D lighting
into a 2D environment, and it was great.
And a lot of the art that we looked
at in terms of our inspiration was from the second edition
AD&D era.
So that, for me, is artists like Larry Elmore, Jeff Easley,
Keith Parkinson, Clyde Caldwell, Fred Fields, and Gerald Brom,
also just known as Brom.
Overall, those artists used less saturated palettes
than a lot of contemporary fantasy artists.
and relatively realistic weapons and armor.
So they look, you know, they're not, they don't really look historical,
but they're a little more on the subdued side, especially when compared
to a lot of contemporary fantasy art.
Here are a few key images that we looked at when we were looking at our style.
The one on the left is by Larry Elmore, it's from the second edition player's handbook.
The style of the character's weapons and armor is not realistic.
It's slightly fantastic, but the proportions are still semi-realistic.
And the palette overall for both of the images, both Keith Parkinson and Larry Elmore, is
relatively subdued.
You don't get a lot of really intense colors like you might see in a lot of contemporary
fantasy art.
And we wanted to capture the classic isometric look
and feel.
And as I'll show in the next image,
we didn't exactly emulate what we did in the first games,
but we came close.
Baldur's Gate 2 in Icewind Dale.
Baldur's Gate 2, that's a straight render.
The image from Icewind Dale, it was heavily painted over.
That's something that Black Isle did
that I don't think Bioware really did at all.
At Black Isle, we usually did a lot of painting on our images
after we rendered them and got in a lot of cool painterly
details.
So for Pillars of Eternity's isometric style,
we wanted to add dynamic lighting.
Of course, we raised the resolution quite a bit.
And we used a lower angle for how we rendered exteriors.
If you look back at this image and the angle that we used,
versus this image. This image, it's actually lower. Most players don't really notice it because it's a
I think it's only like a seven and a half a degree difference
But what it did it is allowed us to emphasize a lot of vertical structures that you see in exteriors
And since you don't necessarily get a lot of tight corridors
You don't wind up occluding the characters very much. When you go into interiors the camera actually goes up seven and a half degrees
players didn't really notice it.
So that's an example of something
where we didn't actually emulate it exactly,
but it created the experience that we wanted to.
Character art was a little more mixed.
We decided right away we're going
to use realistic proportions for things,
make them more sort of in the style of second edition AD&D.
But those realistic proportions made characters hard to read.
I mean, there's a reason why a lot of game artists.
exaggerate features, whether it's armor or body proportions on characters,
it's because when they're very small on the screen, you want to be able to read them very easily.
It's also why they tend to use a lot of saturated and contrasting colors,
because it makes characters a lot easier to read when they're very small.
But we committed to doing that, and so we ran into some challenges.
And then because we did not have a level of detail system, when those, you know, simple
little teeny characters got blown up on your inventory screen, the details look kind of
poor and clumsy.
So if you look at the scale armor on Adair, the scales are really big and kind of clunky
looking and we did that so they would read at a very small resolution, but then they
look kind of goofy when you see them in game and people criticize that, which they were
fair to criticize.
And it was also very frustrating for our character artists who always love building the most
complex things they possibly can.
So looking back on how we handled things,
the art overall was well-received,
but the environments were criticized for being too static.
So we had updated a few elements of them,
but they were still essentially 2D renders,
and they didn't have a lot of dynamic elements in them.
And people also criticized that the characters
weren't detailed enough.
Character customization is something that people really
enjoy in these games.
And so if you can't really deliver on that
and make the characters look good,
it's disappointing for people.
So in the future, things that we're looking to do
are improve the dynamic elements, the lighting,
shadows, dynamic foliage.
We actually tried a dynamic foliage test early
on Pillars of Eternity, and we just couldn't figure it out.
Dynamic weather is something that a lot of players
sort of expect to see in a lot of games now,
and dynamic cloth, which we used a little bit of pillars,
but we want to use more of.
The lesson there is that vintage style in a game
you can still improve upon with new features.
We want to use our LOD system to create higher resolution
and detailed character models, and also
physically-based rendering to improve material quality
and things like that.
Again, features that players expect
to see in contemporary games.
User interface and experience is a very big, big part of how
people sort of attach to these classic games.
Interface design was very different in the 90s
and the early 2000s, if you recall.
We decided right away that we were
going to use a skeuomorphic GUI, which I'll get to in a bit.
But it's a GUI style that was common to all the Infinity
Engine games.
We wanted to use similar hotkeys and a layout that borrowed from Icewind Dale 2 and Planescape
Torment.
We had to sort of pick a layout style that we wanted to do for our HUD.
And we determined that we would try to mimic cursors, icon style, but that we didn't have
time for item sketches.
Item sketches were in, I think, all the Infinity Engine games, and a lot of people remembered
and enjoyed them, and they missed them because we didn't include them.
And I'll get to that in a bit.
So here are interfaces from all five of the Infinity Engine
games.
As you can see, they're all skeuomorphic,
which means that they all look like they're
made of physical materials.
They're not wire frames.
They're not just floating sort of buttons.
They look like they're made of wood or metal or stone.
In Baldur's Gate, Baldur's Gate 2, and Icewind Dale,
it was a U-style interface where three sides of the screen
were covered with buttons with the portraits on one side,
one set of icons on another, and a third set
of icons along the bottom.
Planescape, Torment, and Icewind Dale 2
used a solid bar across the bottom.
I guess we could have tried to support both of these UI
layouts, but it was difficult enough
trying to build just one UI.
So we went with a compact style across the bottom.
That was the style that we used in Icewind Dale 2 and Planescape
Torment.
It allowed for pretty efficient mouse movement.
That's something that the U style makes very difficult.
A lot of players use hotkeys and they don't care about that.
But for people that mostly play with the mouse,
having a very small loop of movement
so you can access all of your icons in a very tiny area
was important.
Some people really did not like the fact that our HUD had a lot of open space in it
So we offered a solid HUD option where you just basically click an option and would ground the whole thing
So it made all the UI elements sort of go in front of a solid background and separated that from the playable space
Which is very much like the infinity engine games
This is another place where accuracy, people's memory is kind of interesting.
So there are a few people, more than a few people that told us that we had stolen our cursor assets directly from the Infinity Engine games.
Like they insisted that we had actually taken the art assets.
Which is weird because if you look at them side by side...
They're not really that similar.
I mean, they're sort of similar.
But people's memories insisted.
They were like, no, no, no, you directly use the art asset.
We intentionally made them very close
because there's nothing wrong with that icon style.
They all communicated what they needed to very well.
It captured the feeling.
And clearly, people felt that it was fitting with the style
that had preceded it.
The item sketches on the top are from Baldur's Gate 2.
They're some of the most powerful weapons that you can find in the game. Some of you probably recognize them.
Unfortunately when we had the first
the game come out, we did not have any item sketches.
We didn't have time to do all the item sketches and people really missed them.
It wasn't make or break for people, but we could tell that people were disappointed in it.
So when we made the expansion, the White March, we had a new type of item called soulbound items
and they were very powerful and you leveled them up over time and all those soulbound items had their own sketches
and we made them very detailed and cool and people really appreciated it.
So that was a case where we had omitted something from the beginning for scheduling purposes
and then later on we found a way to re-include it and people did really appreciate it.
One thing we did do a lot of in the game
is scripted interactions.
This is something that we added that was not
in the Infinity Engine games.
It was in Darklands, and I love Darklands.
And more than just loving Darklands,
it allows designers to create these really cool sequences
that would be extremely difficult to do
with a small budget on a game that's essentially
an isometric 2D game.
So in this case, you're on a mine cart ride.
I don't really want to do a party-based mine cart
ride in Unity in our RPG engine.
So, you can do it in a scripted interaction, which is a choose your own adventure sequence.
All the little sections are illustrated, the player chooses different options, and then
based on the characters they have or the stats they have, things go one way or another.
They have little sound effects, and people responded really well and very positively
to them, and they're not that expensive to make.
Also, the concept artists really love making them too, which is always a benefit.
Remember what I said about people not liking the UI in some cases? Yeah, some people really,
really liked having that U style interface. They don't care about how far away the icons are.
They don't care because they use hot keys or they just like the aesthetics and all they want
is just that classic style. So some modders made the IE mod which changed a number of rules
but it also changed how the UI worked. It really changed it quite a bit and as you can see
here you can drag the elements all over the screen.
And so people can have all sorts of crazy layouts.
People re-skinned the UI, which is all very cool.
Obviously, mods are not necessarily a solution
to your development choices, but it
is very cool when you have a fan community that
is interested enough to actually modify those things.
And I think the important thing here is that if people want to modify your game, this is
pretty common knowledge, but let them modify your game unless you're doing something multiplayer
where it's very important that they don't mess with it.
In a single player game, this stuff goes a long way and it adds a lot of longevity to
your game.
This is a comparison of our interfaces for inventory.
Baldur's Gate on the left and Pillars of Eternity on the right.
We kept the style largely the same.
We used the fact that we had a higher resolution to incorporate all the character inventories
onto one screen.
This made it a lot easier to manage a lot of that stuff.
We did find some classic gamers that didn't like that this was managed this way.
We also included a stash that allowed you to carry everything you found.
Again, some classic gamers did not really like that you could carry everything you found,
and so we included an option to disable that.
Some people just really want the super hardcore experience.
But most of the players that we found generally play with the stash on.
They like that it eliminated a lot of the tedium of moving things between a lot of party
members or hitting arbitrary limits, and that helped a great deal.
But overall, we kept the look and the feel and the style of it very similar to the original
Infinity Engine games.
So looking back, some backers really hated the GUI.
Oh, my holy cow.
If you could see some of the threads on the Obsidian forum,
some of the longest threads are about GUI mockups.
And people would mock up their own GUIs.
Some of them are really cool aesthetically.
A lot of them would never work in a million years.
Any UX designers would look at it and say, like.
You didn't include this, you didn't include that.
But they had a lot of fun talking about it,
and then they had a lot of fun modding it.
So no professional reviews that I saw ever
had negative feedback about it.
They'd say, like, yep, classic style interface.
Feels just like the old games.
So that part of it worked well.
People did miss our sketches, so we did bring them back.
And they loved scripted interactions.
So when we made the expansions, we
allocated a lot more time to doing
scripted interaction images, and people really enjoyed them.
The lesson we learned from all this is that, I mean, we kind of already knew this, but
UI can be extremely divisive.
You can't make everyone happy with your layout choices.
You can't make everyone happy with how the UI works.
So try to find something that you feel works well.
Obviously you don't want to do something that infuriates your audience, but if you find
something that works well, stick with it.
Obviously listen to feedback, but if you try to make everyone happy, you're actually going
to make everyone unhappy in the end.
In the future, we want to continue improving our GUI for usability.
We did make a lot of edits to it in our patches, organizing things better, offering better
tool tips, that's something you can always improve and look at.
We don't ever want to engineer out GUI modding because that's fun stuff for the fan community
to do.
Again, if someone wants to have their UI look a certain way, it's a single player game,
it's not affecting anything, great, let them go nuts.
And always more scripted interactions because we like making them and players seem to like
playing them.
When it comes to game mechanics, there are a few things that we knew right away we were
going to make something that was AD&D like, meaning sort of like second edition AD&D,
third edition D&D.
We wanted to have fewer arbitrary limitations and fewer exceptions in the rule set.
The reason I'm mentioning that is because I worked on the original Infinity Engine games,
or at least two of them, and I had a huge amount of experience playing Dungeons & Dragons
prior to coming to Black Isle, and I was sure that it was super easy to understand and easy
to get into.
If you watch people play these games who don't have experience with D&D, you find that is not true at all.
There's a lot of arcane lore built up in playing Dungeons & Dragons that is not intuitive to people.
It doesn't necessarily always need to be intuitive to people, but knowing that it was a huge stumbling block for a lot of players,
it was important to us to make a system that had fewer arbitrary sort of limitations and rule limitations.
You know, we didn't limit what races could be what classes, we didn't limit who could use certain types of gear or things like that.
And overall, we didn't rely on sort of hidden hard counters that would take players a long time to learn.
We also wanted to have a faster combat pace.
This was done to address a problem in the early parts of the Infinity Engine games where combat could be very slow.
It went on a six-second, each round was on a six-second timer, and each character would
typically only perform one action, and so at the beginning of the game, combat could
move very, very slowly and be very, very boring, so we wanted to speed that pace up.
We did not have party AI at launch, that's something a lot of people really missed.
It was unfortunate, we just didn't have time to do it.
And unfortunately we had limited modability.
The Infinity Engine games could be modded very heavily, ours could not, and that turned out to be not good.
And finally, the stronghold had a very limited time for content implementation,
so we went for a system-heavy implementation, and nobody liked it.
Well, I shouldn't say nobody, but almost nobody liked it.
The combat pacing changes we made were a mixed bag.
It did address the problems at the beginning of the game
where combat was very slowly paced.
But once you got a party of about five or six characters,
combat was very hard to follow.
It was exacerbated by the fact that we
had visual effects that were very overpowering and a lot
of monsters on the screen.
And so people almost all wound up
defaulting to the slow combat pace
after a few hours of gameplay.
That's not really the way we wanted it to go.
We wanted the normal combat pace to be the one
that you typically play at.
So we overcorrected in that regard.
These are examples of 2DAs.
These are two dimensional arrays.
This is what BioWare used to drive most of the data
in the Infinity Engine games, also
what they used in Neverwinter Nights
and what we used in Neverwinter Nights 2.
They're just, they're just.
two dimensional array, it's a tab delimited Excel file.
So you can open it in Notepad.
Some people just edit it, I edited things in Notepad when I was working on these games.
And then there are third party tools where you can open them up and edit them a lot more
easily.
The point is that it was really, really easy to change things.
If you didn't like, you know, the bonus that a 19 strength gave to a character, you could
just go in and change it.
It was very fast and very easy.
You modify the file, you put it in an override directory, you run the game and it works.
Our file formats were, we used Unity and they were all bound up in what Unity's file formats are and people had trouble getting to them.
So it made modding, not impossible, but very difficult and as a result, the fan community didn't really do a ton of modding on the game systems.
And even though I'm a game system designer, I love it when people modify that stuff.
Like, that's totally great and fine and I want people to do it, but we didn't have time to support it and I think it really hurt us in the long run.
About halfway through development, we realized that the stronghold that we had promised was
not going to have time for a lot of content.
We had only so many area designers and only so many writers, and they were all busy making
all the crit path areas and all their dialogues for companions and things like that.
So there was time on the system design side, so I made a little system for it.
And it had, you had prestige, and you had security.
and you got taxes and nobody cares, it's all stupid.
It wasn't very fun.
You can see all these little upgrades you can do, but they were the same for everybody.
So as soon as you were done with your stronghold, it looked like that.
It didn't matter what character you were playing,
it didn't really matter what choices you made along the way,
because ultimately, once your stronghold was repaired,
it would always look like that stronghold.
If you compare this to Baldur's Gate 2, Baldur's Gate 2 had a
bunch of smaller levels, but there were a bunch of them and
they had no system behind it. You're just like, hey, you took
over DRNE's keep, you're a fighter, this is your stronghold
now. Congratulations. Here's a quest. Great. That's what people
actually wanted in a stronghold was variety and options to pick
from and then cool content to play through. We didn't do that.
So when we finally got around to making our third, well it's not our third patch, but patch 3.0,
we incorporated a lot of new Stronghold content.
We had dilemmas where you as the Lord of the Keep would, people would come to you with problems
and you could sort of decide as the arbiter of the land, like, who got to do what,
or if a guy got hung outside your castle walls.
And we introduced a new quest line.
about someone who contends or contests your right to even own the stronghold that you have,
culminating in the Battle of Yen Wood Field.
And it didn't require a huge amount of development time,
but it was a really cool sequence.
We have a big scripted interaction where all these different forces that you marshal over time
sort of clash against each other,
and then after you sort of go through the opening stages of the battle,
you have this huge battlefield,
and depending on the circumstances, it plays out in all these different ways.
And people really liked it.
And that's what they wanted.
They wanted a stronghold with a cool quest associated with it.
So we learned from that.
So looking back on what we did, the game ultimately was easier to pick up than AD&D 2nd edition,
but it lost a lot of the tactical complexity that the hardcore gamers really enjoy, and
the combat became way too fast once you got to about 5 or more party members, and the
stronghold of course was disappointing.
So the lessons we learned about that are it's fine to have some rough edges and exceptions
and things, that's okay as long as the whole system isn't built around them.
Don't overcorrect, which is easier said than done.
When you look at a problem, it's easy to pull back way too far.
You have to be careful and make sure that you haven't done that, because otherwise you
will piss some people off.
Always allow for modding if possible.
I'll say this as much as I can, because every time I've worked on a game that has mods,
it's always good.
I've never seen it go badly.
Pay attention to why people like things.
That seems obvious, but people like strongholds, right?
Well, sure, but why do they like strongholds?
It's not just enough to have something there that's called a stronghold with a system attached
to it if it's not what people really liked about it.
So in the future, we're looking at, we already have done, adding back in layers of combat
complexity, especially over the course of the game.
Like once you've been playing the game for three, four, five hours, you can add in a
new layer of complexity.
After you've been playing the game for 20 hours, you can add in more layers of complexity.
That's why it's nice making RPGs.
You have a lot of hours over which to introduce new concepts.
Try to have more accessible file formats to support modding whenever possible and focusing on stronghold content and integration into the storyline
So they don't just feel like this separate thing that doesn't have anything to do with the rest of the game
Music and voice acting are all very important.
The Infinity Engine games had great music.
When our composer, Justin Bell, looked
at how to compose for Pillars of Eternity,
he looked at the composers that worked on the Icewind Dale
and Baldur's Gate games.
Inan Zur, who worked on Icewind Dale 2.
Jeremy Soule, who worked on Icewind Dale 1.
And Mikhail Honig, who worked on Baldur's Gate,
which is a great soundtrack.
But he also looked at some more contemporary fantasy composers like Howard Shore, who composed
for the Lord of the Rings trilogy.
And he really focused on capturing the mood and the feeling, and it went very well.
I think on the development side we were all very happy with it, and we got pretty good
feedback from our fans whenever we released music and on the game in general.
One problem though is that we had a very limited voice acting budget,
and so we allocated our resources, kind of spreading them out across a lot of characters in a kind of strange way.
So when people played the game, it seemed very random when lines would come in,
or when, like, you'd have a conversation start, and then people would say two lines,
and then they wouldn't talk anymore.
And so it seemed like a bug, but then in another conversation,
they might talk through the whole thing.
And that was kind of us just looking at these resources
and dicing them up way too far apart.
So the lesson we learned there is
that when you have limited resources, don't.
Don't spread them too thin.
Because in our case, once we played the game,
it was obvious.
But by the time we played the game, it was too late.
We played it, and we said, oh, jeez, this
sounds really awkward and buggy.
In the future, we are pretty happy with the style of music
that we wound up with.
But we want to experiment more with things like leitmotif,
incorporating themes of various characters
into key story moments and things
like that to reinforce the narrative flow of the game.
And just being smarter about allocating our voice acting
resources.
because it did really seem strange to a lot of people.
When we set out to design this world,
we knew that we were going to build a traditional fantasy
setting.
We knew from the beginning we weren't
trying to make something really wild and crazy.
By the way, I know that the Torment Tides of Numenera guys
are here, and they have a crazy world.
So if you get a chance to see those guys, bug them.
Especially bug Colin McComb, because I like it
when people bug Colin.
But our world is going to be pretty traditional, pretty standard fantasy setting.
We wanted to change a few elements.
So we didn't have halflings or gnomes or orcs.
We do have elves and dwarves.
We knew a lot of people wanted to play their elves and their dwarves, but not people like,
no, my gnome, I can't play my gnome.
So we do know that people like to play little characters and big characters, so we introduced
Orlins as our new small race and Omawa as our new big race, and they're not really like
halflings or orcs, but they're little and big guys, so people can play them.
And then we incorporated Godlike, and Godlike are just a ripoff of Ganassi.
So if you played Massive the Betrayer for Neverwinter 2, as soon as we included Ganassi,
everyone was playing Ganassi, and sure enough, when people had background PCs,
half of them were godlike. So people really liked the
aesthetic of those characters so we incorporated them.
We did decide we were going to have a Eurocentric type of setting, so a lot of the elements you see from constructed languages to architecture borrows from medieval central Europe, usually.
Very standard and traditional.
We did try to move the timeline of our setting forward a little bit.
A lot of fantasy settings are in this vaguely 12th to 15th century English, French, German kind of place.
We wanted to set it squarely.
in the 16th century with a renaissance zeitgeist that seemed to capture the feeling of a world in change.
That's something else that I think a lot of fantasy settings feel like.
For 2000 years we've had plate armor and people have been casting fireballs and that's it.
So we wanted to make it feel like this world was actually changing over time.
We did decide to go with a blank slate character versus pre-defining the character.
That's sort of a mixed thing because later on in the game you do find out that your character does have...
Spoilers, some things in a past life, because our setting is about reincarnation.
But in Baldur's Gate, you are a ball spawn, and that you are pursued right away as soon
as the game starts, so that's a part of who your character is.
And in Planescape Torment, you are the nameless one.
You can define a lot of things about the nameless one, but you're always that dude.
The companions, themes, quests, and the tone of our dialogue were pretty serious.
Obviously this is all relative, but if you compare them to the other Infinity Engine games,
it was like serious mode to the point of being too serious.
So if you look at our companions versus, for example,
the Baldur's Gate 2 companions, Baldur's Gate 2 companions
were pretty diverse in terms of you
had pretty serious characters, you had totally wacky dudes,
you had characters with long involved quest lines,
you had characters that had no quest at all,
you had characters with romances,
some characters that didn't have romances.
And those are pretty broad spectrum.
For pillars, we had initially eight companions
that we expanded to 11.
They were super serious.
That's not entirely true.
Horovius was kind of a goofy character,
but you find him very late in the game
compared to the other characters.
And Adair is a funny guy, but all of his humor is very dry.
So if you compare any of the Pillars of Eternity companions
to someone like Minsc, Minsc is a wacky, wacky dude.
By the way, I've seen Minsc show up in,
he was in like a new D&D comic that came out like a month ago.
That character is still around and doing things.
So clearly there's a place, and people really
like these zany, zany characters.
So looking back on what we did, players and reviewers
had mixed and favorable reactions
about the world and lore.
A lot of people wished that we had
done more experimental or adventurous or crazy things.
That's not really what we set out to do.
It is something we'd like to look at doing in the future.
There was a lot to learn and keep track of.
The beginning of the game especially was extremely dense with a lot of crazy constructed language
terms and new ideas and wacky stuff and it was just a lot to absorb very early in the
game.
And a lot of players missed the light-hearted and funny elements that were in, especially
the Baldur's Gate games.
The tone of your source material, the lesson to take away from this is that the tone of
your source material is very important.
If you strike the wrong tone with something, again, it's not going to really capture the
same feeling as what came before it.
So in the future we do want to introduce more diverse and interesting locations that are all not like the middle of central Europe
No offense
I like Central Europe.
But more diverse locations.
We have to be more attentive about how we pace lore.
Another game that we're working on at Obsidian
called Tyranny has a very cool system
for highlighting sort of keywords
and getting little pop-up blurbs about things for lore.
It's very useful.
We want to use something like that.
So when you see a term like brishalgwin or beowik,
and you're like, what the hell is that?
I've seen that word five times.
You can just hover it, and it'll tell you,
and then you can keep reading.
And then we also do want to include some sillier characters.
One thing we've even talked about is having essentially two types of companions.
One that's sort of a story companion that has their own quest and they're incorporated very directly in the crit path.
And other characters that are specifically designated, especially from the player's perspective,
as being there more for like, you know, just kind of their voice set, their appearance.
They're not as deep, but that would allow us to get a lot more variety in our characters.
Beta is in early access.
Early access, a very popular topic these days.
Lots of games coming out in early access.
So it was two years ago.
Actually, it was two years ago, literally today, that we,
I think, I think, that we went into open beta.
And, um, I'm sorry, it wasn't an open beta, it was a closed beta.
But it was immediately following Gamescom.
And because we were showing the game publicly, and because people could come play it,
we knew we had to launch the beta then, or else people would be very justifiably pissed off.
That beta was buggy as hell.
And we tried to offer a lot of caveats, but there's something you should learn,
is that no matter how much you say,
Hey everyone, keep in mind, this is a beta.
we're not done. There's still a lot of features to work on. We're still working on things.
That does not limit how angry people are going to get. They're going to get so mad. They're
going to get furious. Not everyone will, but a ton of people will be very, very upset. We
had people wanting their money back because we had betrayed them and all this stuff.
But the thing is, those betas are good, because no matter how strongly people react, you do
get a lot of good feedback out of them.
You do need time to iterate, though.
If you don't really have time to iterate, there's no point to doing a beta.
You need to take their feedback, let it wash over you, bury you in the ground, you resurrect
yourself, you come up, you address some of their concerns, and you say, how about now?
They punch you in the face, you fall down.
But you have to keep doing that.
And you can't, again, you can't make everyone happy,
but you can get a lot of good feedback.
The vocal minority sometimes does have a point.
Like, that's the thing is that don't,
just because they're a vocal minority,
does not mean, just like it doesn't mean that they're right
because they're loud.
and persistent, it doesn't mean they're wrong.
So sometimes they have a point, but also keep in mind
that you do have a broader audience, presumably,
that you want to meet.
It's not just 10 people on your forums arguing
about one aspect of your game.
So try to reach out and find more people to play your game.
Betas and early access are typically
for very hardcore people, like even among hardcore people.
So just be very conscious of.
of the type of people that are actually playing your game and try to reach out and find more
people that are in your audience that might be interested in it.
So despite the initial criticism that we had, our beta did allow
for a lot of iteration and early, a lot of iteration. And
the early feedback that was very negative, it didn't really seem
to affect the launch. Because the beta period went on for a
very long time. And once we launched, people had forgotten
about all the stupid beetles and horrible gooey bugs and stuff
like that. Like all that stuff kind of faded away. Now they're
focusing on new terrible bugs.
So the lesson there is that betas and early access are a great way to get feedback from your most passionate players,
but you have to remember that they're very passionate.
And so you have to take what they say with a grain of salt, you have to try to get other feedback.
We want to try to offer more betas in the future.
We want to improve the feedback loop,
because the faster we can turn around iterations and get people's feedback on it, the better.
and try to find ways to increase the player base.
What we found is that we still have patch betas, too.
So we've done a lot of post-release support.
And what we found, though, is that over time,
there are fewer and fewer people that
are interested in being beta testers for a patch.
So trying to find ways to increase the initial numbers
and then keep people interested in beta
testing in the future can be very helpful.
Post launch support is incredibly helpful.
So again, you have this very, very passionate group
of people, and you have new people coming in.
And when you launch, even if you've had a beta,
there's going to be things that people encounter
that make them very mad and very upset.
And a lot of times, it's justified.
Sometimes it's not.
Whatever.
So you have to pick and choose what you're going to address.
We've released 12 patches so far between April 3rd of 2015 and July 11th of this year.
And a lot of our focus is on play balance and UI, making the game easier to understand.
Even though it's not necessarily as complex of a system as AD&D 2nd edition, it still
requires a lot of number crunching and a lot of that stuff is not clear to people.
So we try to make that clearer.
We try to improve some classes that people perceive as being very weak, like the Ranger
and Paladin and later the Rogue.
And we also found that we just jammed too many fights in the game.
Like, exploration and combat are two big pillars of the game,
and we found that combat was very, very heavy, especially in the late parts of the game.
So we actually had a patch where we went through and we thinned out the encounters.
And then the encounters that remained, we tried to bolster them and make them more interesting.
And the last thing is that we focused on restoring some of the lost ingredients, the things that we just missed.
The stronghold, we knew when we launched that people were going to be disappointed with the stronghold,
so we tried to add in stronghold content in patch 3.
By the way, that was just patch, that was free.
We realized that we had not hit the mark on that, and we wanted people to just get the improvements,
so they didn't have to get the expansion for that.
We did introduce more hard counters into the combat AI, so you had creatures that were
completely immune to certain damage types, or they were completely immune to a certain
affliction type, and that would force players to change their tactics a little bit more
than the base game did.
And then more distinctive items and item sketches.
Some people were disappointed that our unique items were not interesting enough or compelling
enough, and the patches introduced either better properties on those weapons, or with
the expansions, the soulbound items that were pretty darn powerful.
So at the end of this long and winding road,
it's important to think about what you want to take
from the games that inspire your retro classic
and what you want to leave behind,
things that you're like, you know what,
that might have worked then, but it's not working anymore.
So, not every choice that you make when you're developing these games is going to actually
get at that soul.
It's really, really, I know, I mean this is really obvious, but like, play the game.
You have a bunch of ingredients that are going into this mix.
And if you're not like tasting the sauce every once in a while, you don't really know how that stuff is going together.
It's very important also that you play the original games that inspired this passion,
because then when you move from one to the other, you can see what things are actually improving the experience
versus either not improving it or worse or detrimental to the experience.
But everything that you're doing, you need to be able to grow for the future.
So, unless your goal is really to make a game just for one small audience and then say,
I'm never making a game again, or I'm never making a game like this again,
you do want to make something that you can improve on and build for the future.
So that's something to always keep in mind.
Don't back yourself into a corner with certain designer development choices.
And the last point is, listen to as many of your players as you can.
Obviously, you can only act on a small number of those people.
But don't ignore the vocal minority, and also don't ignore the larger player base.
They're all people who are interested in playing the game.
Some of them are going to be louder and more persistent than others,
but if you believe you understand who your audience is,
try to reach as many of those people as possible to make a game that they can all enjoy.
I want to thank...
My CEO and boss, Fergus Urquhart, for letting me go on this trip.
It was a lot of fun.
Kaz Aruga, who helped me collect a lot of art resources
for making this talk.
And of course, to all the Pillars of Eternity backers
and players and fans, we literally
would not have been able to make this game without them.
And their ongoing feedback and support
is helping us make the game even better for the future.
Thank you.
What's that?
Is there a queue at Q&A?
Cool.
Does anyone have any questions?
Hello?
So you talked about how the game is inspired
by D&D second edition and classical medieval fantasy,
which I feel like we've been doing for a really long time.
And as a tabletop player, you've probably
been playing all sorts of diverse and interesting
tabletop games.
As a player or a designer, what kind
of these kind of mechanics would you
like to see us bringing into it?
I'm sorry, could you?
So we're still kind of riffing on D&D second edition,
and tabletop gaming has gotten so much bigger and more
interesting than that over the last 20 or 30 years.
Is there any of those systems or mechanics
that you'd like to see us bring into our computer games
over the next while?
Yes, so that's a great question. I think for this specific type of game, there are a lot of mechanics that I enjoy from other RPGs that I don't think would necessarily fit in here.
For example, one aspect that I really like about Ars Magica is that it's based around a very long period of time. There's a lot of stuff that you do in downtime.
So every it's about wizards. It's about medieval wizards and you all have a covenant and the covenant is the place where you live and
you protect it and it's important and you have a library and you have resources and
Time is important and you read books to get more powerful reading is power
That's all really cool, but there's a very, very big focus on sort of managing the Covenant and the Grogs and all these other things that go into it.
I don't necessarily know that that's something that's appropriate for a D&D type game, but it's very cool.
I will say though that if you've played the Darkest Dungeon, there are a lot of elements from there that are really similar to Torchbearer, if you've played Torchbearer.
Torchbearer has a...
Imagine Torchbearer like low-level D&D, but...
I'm sorry, imagine Torchbearer like low level first edition D&D, but harsher.
It's really brutal, I mean that's sort of the darkest dungeon where everyone just spirals
down into insanity and death.
And so, and that's an example I think when you look at Torchbearer, the system design
is so tightly oriented around capturing that feeling, that's very, very cool.
Whereas I think when you look at something like D&D.
D&D, it evolved out of tabletop miniatures gaming.
There's a lot of ideas and systems
that are just not part of it, because the focus is really
on these murder hobos that wander the world just acquiring
power and loot.
So yeah, there's a ton of really cool games
out there that I think we can borrow elements from.
Any other questions?
Hey.
When you designed the game, it seemed
you had a pretty ambitious plan for the gold economy.
There's a lot of trains going on, a lot of consumers,
and so on.
And in the final game, it feels still
that the gold is really piling up.
So how did that happen?
How did the gold pile up? That's a good question. So when we
started designing the game, we initially had some more sinks in
the economy for where gold went. One of those was a durability
system.
Ooh, people didn't like that.
That was something that Tim Cain and I worked on and proposed
pretty early on.
And we had a backer update about it.
And there were, I mean, I won't say everyone.
But there was a significant number
of people that were like, this doesn't feel D&D-ish.
This doesn't feel like it belongs in an Infinity Engine
game.
One thing that came out of that conversation is that a lot of folks on our forum said,
you know, I don't really care that much if I wind up with a ton of gold toward the end
of the game.
That being said, I think we could have done a better job balancing the economy.
I think some of the higher level crafting recipes, like if you want to upgrade a weapon
to the really high tiers...
We could have had those cost a huge amount of copper, which would have been a big improvement.
And the stronghold, even though it wasn't very compelling for a lot of people, people
did buy those upgrades, and I think those upgrades probably could have served us better
to have those high-end upgrades be very, very expensive.
They don't necessarily have to be proportional as long as there is something of value that
the player can buy and they feel like, oh, okay, there's something to actually look forward
to spending my gold on.
But no, that was our fault.
We designed a few sinks.
people didn't like them. I think they're justified not liking
them. And we didn't do a good job of fixing the economy later
on.
Thanks for the talk. Do you have some features that for one
reason or another didn't make it in the final build?
Game mechanics?
Features or game mechanics that couldn't make it into the final build?
What you wanted to build.
Yeah, there were a lot of...
We wanted to have more diverse abilities for a lot of the characters.
People remember...
There were a lot of really weird and wacky spells and things like that in D&D.
And...
I can't remember specific ones off the top of my head, but...
If you look through the player's handbook as a developer,
there's a lot of things in D&D where you go like,
I don't know how I would ever implement that,
or wow, that would be like a week of someone's time
to implement that.
So there are things like that that we wanted to put in
where we're like, that's really cool,
but it's just so expensive to put in.
But then again, it is important to have
at least some of that stuff.
By the way, so Adam Brennecke, who's our lead,
he's our executive producer and our lead programmer.
He hates rangers so much in our game because the animal companions complicate everything
But the design of the class is sort of built around having that companion
And so that's like so fundamental to it that it was important that no you like we just got to fix it
We got to keep on going. This is kind of how the class works
We did also want to have familiars in the game
so that wizards could have their own little dudes.
That made Adam's mind explode because he's like, oh, cool.
We get to have two different types of animal companions
for twice the bugs.
So that felt less important for wizards,
and so we didn't incorporate that.
Thanks.
Any other questions?
All right.
Oh.
Actually, I have a question more about the tools you use to build a game.
Because if I looked at the Winter Nights, Infinity Engine games, or the Bethesda games,
a lot of them use global variables and plain text files.
And I'm just wondering if when building a game like that, doesn't that cause a lot of problems,
bugs which are difficult to trace?
Did you use any more custom solutions, something which
would validate that there are no bugs in the content,
like a missing global variable or something linking
to something disappearing?
So the question is about global variable tracking and things like that.
So we've tried to build better tools for tracking that stuff over time.
Most of our data editing used the built-in Unity tools, and that's something that we're
moving away from now.
Again, that goes back to file formats and accessibility.
We want our file formats to be very easy for people to edit.
But in terms of global variable tracking, we have our own tool set for writing dialogue.
Again, because Obsidian, Obsidian has, we put a lot of effort into writing and branching dialogues,
and also tracking quest states.
So we actually have a quest tool that is specifically for setting up quest flow,
so you can see how the quest is supposed to actually develop over time.
And we have a testing tool that allows us to set those variables and track them better.
So we develop tools for the specific needs of making a very complex role-playing game
so we can sort of define and track those variables more easily and also test them more easily.
Does that answer your question?
Yeah, thank you.
Any last questions?
Alright, everyone, thank you very much for coming. I really appreciate it.