Hey, everyone. Thank you so much for coming to our panel. The four day work week. We did
it. What now? We're super excited to share all the details of our four day work weeks
and how that went for each of us. We're four very different studios. We're all working
on very different things and have all had our different successes, challenges and
ways that we went about our four day work week. So this panel is really just an introduction,
starting point, a way to think about the four day formula, what has worked, not worked,
things you may be considering for your own studios and exposing all the whens,
whys and hows of operating every week like it's a.
three day weekend.
So with that in mind, I'll introduce myself
and then I will let the panel introduce themselves as well.
My name is John Cooney.
I go by he and him pronouns.
I'm the CEO of Armor Games,
which is a full remote 11 person studio.
We started 15 something years ago as a flash games website.
And now we're predominantly a publisher
for indies and small teams.
we're working on games like Baron Breakfast and Snacko and Spirit and the Mouse. We moved to a
four-day work week last October and we structured it as a 32-hour work week with Fridays becoming
part of the weekend. So I'm happy to moderate the panel. I'm going to chime in on some things,
but I'm mostly going to try to let our other panelists speak the most. So let's just roll down
the list in order starting with Selim.
Hey everyone, my name is Sadim Daboos.
I'm the co-founder of Co-op,
which is a worker-owned game studio,
and it's also a cooperative.
We're actually celebrating our 10th birthday in two months.
I'm really, really excited and proud about that.
And we started with our four-day work week in 2020,
and then went back to five days just to kind of feel it out.
And then we're like, oh yeah, four days is where it's at,
and permanently made the switch last year.
Uh, that's me.
Great and Tonya.
Hi, I'm Tanya Short and I'm the Captain, CEO,
Director of Kit Fox Games.
We're 11 people based in Montreal.
We released Boyfriend Engine and Moon Hunters
and we're working on some secrets
and we've also done some publishing.
So we're probably best known as the publishers
of the upcoming Graphical Dwarf Fortress,
but feel free to look also look up Paparazzi,
Six Ages and other things.
We went to four days, 32 hours starting last June
and the run up to the launch of Boyfriend Dungeon,
we decided that that was the best way
to have a sustainable pressure as launch was coming up.
And it was almost impossible to go back to five days.
We briefly discussed it, but nobody wanted to even try.
So it looks like we're four days at the very least
until the pandemic is actually over, but probably forever.
Great, and finally, Chris.
Yes, my name is Christopher Chancy.
I am the founder and CEO of Manavoid Entertainment, a studio based out of
Montreal. It's about 36 people now.
Amongst other things, we've recently released Rainbow Billy, The Curse of the
Leviathan. We're on the four day week since 2019.
So, you know, it was really part of our core values as a studio to.
have a no crunch culture and to try and give the best advantages to our staff.
And so we implemented it pretty early and it's been going great.
We've never went back to the five days since then.
Much like John, we're on the 32 hour week with Fridays off.
Great. Thank you, Chris. And thank you, everyone on the panel.
I'm going to go ahead and stop sharing my screen.
So we'll go back to just looking at our faces so you don't have to look at my presentation the whole time.
And yeah, thank you everyone who's come to our panel.
This is very roughly structured,
but the first part we're really gonna focus on
is thinking about how we planned
and dreamed out our four-day work week,
what that kind of how we arrived at those moments,
what did it look like,
what did initial planning look like for our work weeks.
And then after that, we'll move into more of
some of our respective challenges,
some of the things we found from moving through this process,
things that changed along the way.
And we'll end by talking about the future.
Where do we see it fitting in with our studios in the future?
Lasting impressions,
thoughts about how the four-day work week might fit in
to the larger indie space,
but also the game industry as a whole.
And then at the end, we'll have room for Q&A.
So feel free to save any questions you might have
for our panel.
We're very happy to answer any questions that there might be towards the end.
So thank you everyone. Let's go ahead and start with
you know, how we got here and how we started. So the first question for the panel is really
talking about, you know, what prompted this change? Like what was the point at which
you all decided that it was time to move and shift from a five-day workweek to a four-day workweek?
And maybe I'll just pick someone to start off with and then we can start that conversation.
So let's start with Salim.
Sure. So we started in the summer of 2020. And I don't know if you remember, but that was a pretty rough time. It was after the murder of George Floyd, we were going through pandemic, there was, you know, a lot of
A lot of stress on our team and on a personal level just of like what was happening in the world. And we just felt like just you know
keeping our heads down and working throughout didn't feel right for us. We really wanted to be engaged in social movements. We
really wanted to have more time to sort of engage with our families and our communities. And we felt like work was taking too
much from us to be able to to do that. And so that was where the conversation for four day work weeks.
began. It was a necessity for our well-being, our mental health, and our need to engage with
what was happening around us. Things that were just more important than frankly video games.
Yeah, I think I can chime in a little bit too. We had talked about it for some years before we did
it. I had always felt that the humans making the games matter.
at least as much to me as the business that is profiting from the game.
So when it became very clear to me last summer that giving bonus vacation days wasn't quite
cutting it, giving various perks wasn't quite cutting it, this seemed like a way that we could
give more.
more buffer in a way to the human side of Kit Fox
without losing, we could afford to risk
the potential losses from that.
And yeah, after we'd been enduring the pandemic
for that long and we were, like I said,
we were running up to the launch of Boyfriend Dungeon
and I really needed people to not burn out
and I needed them to stay on after launch
and really come with 100% of their health.
It seemed like the best at least temporary solution. And, and then we thought well why not continue.
We implemented it in a, in kind of a knee-jerk reaction to an article I had read when,
back in 2019, there was an article that came out of a study in Norway that it was all around
focused hours of work. And basically the article was saying that, you know, in a normal day,
on a five-day week, a human being can only have about four to four and a half hours of focused
work. The rest of the time you're a little bit distracted. You're on Facebook, you're, you know,
talking with colleagues, whatever it is.
And that they made a test and with a four day work week,
that four hours of focused work became five hours
to five hours and a half of focused work.
And so in a sense, in four days,
they felt like you could achieve as much as in five days
because the amount of focused work didn't change.
And so, you know, from that and also being in Montreal, there are a lot of studios here.
And so it is a competitive landscape to, you know, find staff, find senior talent and all
of that stuff and bring them into the studio.
And we were very much into already the idea of kind of trying to balance out work and
life together and kind of redefine what it means to work in, you know.
in the 21st century.
And so we decided to implement it at that time.
And as I said, the reception immediately was pretty crazy.
So we decided to keep it.
That's awesome.
And so as you were thinking about your, you know,
switch over to this new work week,
and as you were starting to plan things out,
what were your expectations around, you know,
the fact that there was no longer going to be a Friday
or whatever day you take off for the four-day work week?
Were you expecting productivity?
I know, Chris, you talked about this a little bit.
Were you expecting productivity to stay the same?
Were you expecting productivity to drop, you know,
a full 20% because there's that less time?
What were your expectations going into
rolling this out for your teams?
Our expectations were that we were going to probably lose a bit of efficiency in the short term.
Like I feel like I'm very aware of what I don't know in life. And so I was approaching it with the humility of knowing that we were going to have some some bumps down that road.
And so we decided to implement it for six months before we even decided to kind of look at what what the results were we decided to kind of give ourselves a really solid period of time and not stress out about it too early.
And so yeah we did expect some.
you know, some rough patches in the beginning.
There was a little bit of a slowdown at the start.
I think everyone was kind of getting into the groove.
You know, we can talk about this extensively,
but probably in the next section,
there's a lot of, you know,
challenges that come with the four-day workweek
that you need to be aware of.
And we kind of hit those face first every time.
But pretty quickly, I would say within three months,
I feel like we had reached a level of efficiency that
was similar to what we had in the past,
just with much happier people.
So it was a net positive for us.
Anyone else?
Um, I had very, uh, minimal expectations.
I wasn't really sure how things are going to play out.
I had a feeling that mental health was going to improve.
And then that was like a very drastic, uh, obvious shift for us.
Uh, so that was just really great.
I think something that I was unsure of is our team had scaled up during the
pandemic as a remote studio for the first time.
And so there are a lot of members, uh, of our studio that were, you know, people
I've never worked with, uh, in, in person.
And it definitely took a while to convince them to that the four day work week was real.
You know, it just when you're not a tight knit team, you have new members and they're just like,
oh, you're saying I can take off on Friday. Like, are you sure? And we noticed a couple
of people who were just like,
not doing that and that they're like well I can't finish my work if I don't continue working Fridays.
And so something we didn't anticipate was just how we were assigning work, how we were tracking it,
how much work was being assigned, and just a cultural level of
providing safety to those newer team members who just started with us and were suddenly being told they're okay to take time off on Fridays.
That was a, that was a bit of a surprise for us that that, like, need to kind of convince and make that feel safe for people.
Yeah, I know for us as a studio. One of the biggest things and we're already segwaying into the next section but for us one of the biggest things that I think.
we thought about and then ended up doing was framing it as a trial and really running with
it as a trial. That way, when things were not working, if things weren't going to work, or if
things were going really well or whatever it was in between, that it was recognized that this is
just a trial, that we're going to see if this fits us. And if it doesn't fit us, there's ways we can
roll back or change or figure out. Giving ourselves the room to fail a little bit was really kind of
critical in our planning and something that
helped alleviate a lot of the planning speed bumps that we were expecting but didn't know
were going to happen as we were moving along. Yeah, I just wanted to add that our expectations
where the productivity would slightly dip.
I don't really believe that, I mean, maybe some of us
on the team do work that can be properly quantified
and like have productivity that's comparable to widgets,
but I think most of us don't.
I'm not even sure most of my tasks are focused work tasks,
if it comes down to it.
Like, I think I do a lot of loose brain chaos emails
and like that doesn't really.
need or create focus. But we were willing to, that's why I put it in terms of risk,
rather than anything we felt was measurable. My expectation was more, what Selene was talking
about, the mental health would be a little bit more stable, that people would feel like more
able to put in those four days if they knew that they would have the three days at the end. And so
We expected to lose, I would say I expected to lose five to 10% just because I think most people,
most weeks check out Friday afternoons anyway, like even if they are doing work,
probably it's not the most focused. So that was my baseline expectation.
I can just riff off of what John, you mentioned before, I think it's super
important to leave yourself the room to fail at the four day workweek as well.
We implemented it, um, with a concept that was, this is a privilege that,
you know, that everyone has now.
Um, but you know, if ever shit hits the fan, you know, we could go back to the
five day week for a period of time.
if ever it doesn't work out for some reason, we could go back to the fight. Like, you know,
allowing yourself and telling everyone that this is kind of a trial thing is an important,
I think, aspect of it. And then the other thing for us that we had mentioned to everyone initially
was just in the concept of work using the agile method, you know, we're working on sprints with
tasks and all that stuff. And I think it is important to try and get some data out of it,
you know, velocity and trying to get, you know, an amount of hours that it takes to do a certain task.
But, you know, at the end of the day, I'm not asking people to log in hours.
I'm asking them to deliver their tasks for the sprint.
And so we were already in a dynamic with, with everyone on our team, where we trust
that, you know, they'll they're, they're responsible for the work that they need to
do.
And, you know, them understanding that this was the reasoning behind it was that we trusted them to be able to achieve what they needed to achieve within the four days instead of the five.
Also gave them the opportunity to decide if they wanted to work a few hours on the Friday, but maybe take the Thursday afternoon a little bit more, you know.
chill, it gave them the flexibility essentially to be able to kind of pick and choose when they
felt more creative and when they felt more focused or when they felt more in a work mode.
So I think that's also something that really worked out for us.
Thanks. And Chris, you were we can kind of move into like the next section talking about how we're measuring the things that we're doing.
And to the to thank you, Chris, for answering the questions on how you were measuring that success there.
Firstly, Martanya, how are you measuring success for your team?
How are you measuring whether or not the four day work week was working or not?
Was it productivity?
Was it general feel?
How's everyone doing like?
What were you using as like kind of the benchmarks for deciding if this was a fit for you?
Well, part of why I was dubious about measuring the productivity is I think it's Goddard's law.
As soon as you make something a measure of success, it becomes a useless measure.
Because people.
sometimes unconsciously. If I told them they have to do a certain number of points,
well, I think they'll do that number of points.
I really, I could go back and look at now historically because it's not a measure that
everyone's striving for. There's no punishment attached to it. I could see what the productivity
is, but realistically, we would take it off if people felt like they weren't making forward
enough momentum because that kills the morale of many game developers. If they can just feel
like the project is stagnating and they're not moving forward.
Um, now, what are the chances that it's the Friday? That's the problem in that case? It seems pretty unlikely, like they still have, you know, a good number of hours to move a project forward. So maybe there's some other issue at that point.
Um, but yeah, it was really it was more just a, it was not measurable. It was really asking the team like, what do we think is the benefit? Is it worth the fact that maybe we will take 10% more time to make our projects, potentially? Is everyone okay with that?
And so far everyone is.
How about you, Selim?
Yeah, I agree that there was a lot of a gut check feeling
kind of thing going on.
We did track, we like just for planning purposes,
we're like, okay, well, this is how much velocity
our programmers were hitting.
There's how many points that we're completing in a sprint.
Let's see what it's like in four days.
And then we found that there was kind of very little
like difference for us.
Some weeks there were more productive some weeks were less productive it just kind of seemed to follow the same kind of cadence as a five day work week.
And we also checked our art asset output and kind of found the exact same result as well. And so it was like, okay, well on a productivity side, it's pretty much plus or minus within the standard expectations so not much of a change there, which is great.
And then we just conducted a bunch of interviews and anonymous feedback and one on ones about the four day work week to see how people were reacting to that.
And it was pretty much, you know, maybe this sounds obvious, but it was really positive across the board.
And that was and I mean, just like me personally, like I was.
dying during the time.
Like I was fucking having a miserable time at work.
I was really stressed out.
I needed more time.
And so like just me on a personal level,
I could see the benefit to myself.
And that was, you know, co-op is a, it's a cooperative.
So we vote on our, on all of our policies,
but I'm just here representing the studio as myself.
And I could say easily that it had a significant impact
on my mental health.
So that was enough, honestly, for tracking.
Yeah, let's talk about that.
Let's talk about mental health impact on your team,
what you saw, like, especially as you were, you know,
going through your initial rollout
into like people feeling comfortable.
What were you seeing on your teams
in terms of mental health?
And were people coming fresh to work on Monday?
Were they feeling like the more time is better?
Was there anyone feeling anxiety
from the fact that it's a shorter week?
What were you seeing on your teams,
especially through the early stages
and going into the parts
where you're starting to become comfortable?
I can speak to that anxiety element because that was definitely present for us in our.
in our first attempt at the four-day workweek because we had I would say kind of poor production
planning as well as a milestone around when that was happening. So for some people they felt like
because of those such that scenario they felt like they couldn't as freely take that four-day
workweek and had to do overtime which we always track at co-op and also pay out at 1.5x salary.
So it was like
okay, if we're going to treat four days as the standard and the fifth day is overtime,
we need to also track that. And so there was anxiety around milestones and finishing things,
but I think those were really rooted in poor production practices because when we revisited
four-day workweek with a much stronger emphasis on smoothing out our production pipelines,
that anxiety kind of went away pretty quickly.
Yeah, on our side, it's similar.
You know, I think a lot of our processes
had to be reworked for the four-day work week.
But, you know, we did also do some interviews anonymously,
you know, sent out surveys and stuff like that.
And across the board, morale was up, you know,
and then I'm not sure what the stats are on this.
I'd have to go back and check, but, you know,
my gut feeling is there was a lot less absenteeism
during the week.
I think, you know,
There's a lot of appointments that you need to do during the week because things are closed on the weekends.
And then people are going to kind of pick and choose a moment in the week where they're going to do that thing.
Now everyone knows that they have the Friday to do whatever that is.
And so when they need to plan something in the week, they don't plan it on a Tuesday.
They know that the Friday is off, so they'll just do whatever they need to do on the Friday.
So.
The four days was really all hands on deck a lot more than what we would see before.
And I also feel like this might extend to just generally people taking sick days is
also something that I think we saw less of.
I think organically people just felt that they could be refreshed with the three-day
weekend and then come back into the work week ready to work, basically.
Tanya, is there anything you wanted to add?
I mean, it was very popular.
I don't think a single person ever complained.
I know that there is a little bit of a rough.
bit which I don't know if we're getting into the all the concerns yet but as far as mental health
goes um for me and my community manager we both have the kinds of things that might need us to
respond over the weekend uh for me it's more like an urgent business partner email for for her it's
like you know a discord fight breaks out something like that.
And so that's always been on our radar.
Like this doesn't really change that.
I know one thing we've adjusted for her
is she tends to leave a bit early Thursday afternoon
planning to do a bit on Friday
just because it helps break out that weekend silence.
It's really hard to be away from social media
for a whole three days.
Like that's like an eternity in Twitter time.
I think initially her mental health, maybe it was harder
because she was anxious about leaving it for three days.
And now that we've worked out this system,
she can leave it for the two days and feel better about it.
Yeah, we definitely had something similar to that,
where, especially with social media and partners,
there was a lot of anxiety around that.
I would say with partners, it's been a lot easier
because I've just...
people are like, are you available for a meeting on Friday?
I'll be like, nope, sorry.
Just no, I don't, I don't even say we don't work Friday.
I don't have availability, sorry.
Exactly. I'm just not, I'm not available.
I'm busy.
Yeah, exactly.
So that, that, that has worked pretty well for us.
In terms of social media,
something that we've just kind of realized is that
our
team and community management in general is vastly undervalued in terms of resources.
And so that actually brought up a really good conversation at our studio over the needs of
community management and that we were placing too much responsibility on one person to handle
so much. I think this is a common thread in a lot of community management roles.
And so it actually forced us to hire up for that role so that we have two people in that
and that they can alternate.
And we also have paid volunteers for our Discord and our Twitter so that we can have people kind of keep eyes on things when core stuff is not available or, you know, it's a Friday and stuff and that's like really helped.
I think spread the load instead of feeling like Twitter and discord are all one person's responsibility and it's always turned
on. We actually had really good conversations around boundaries around that. We also close our discord during high traffic
times in our marketing push like you know we'll close our discord from 2 a.m. to 8 a.m. or something so that people can't
talk so that.
even our mods can get some rest. And I think it just brought up a lot of conversations around
the boundaries and needs for rest versus the expectations of things like community management
and how that those were unfairly eating into people's personal time.
I think I have to mention that, you know,
organically, the leads ended up still doing a small meeting on Friday
mornings to kind of plan for the weeks ahead. And, you know, we don't stop them
from doing that, like, you know, as long as everyone is comfortable and they take
those hours off on another day in the week or whatever.
You know, anyone that kind of wants to have the peace and quiet of not being bothered by the entire staff on a Friday.
You know, the leads do meet up and admittedly, I don't really do the four day work week myself.
I'm still in the rigmarole of trying to, you know, make everything happen all the time with the company.
So.
I in that sense, like I'm not I'm not giving a good example of what the four
day work week should be.
I feel like everyone watching this should follow Salim and Tanya's example, not
mine, because, you know, and we had this discussion with our leads, but it's in
part it's important that people don't feel like they would need to work on a
Friday to advance in the company or become a leader in the company or, you
know, kind of get get a head.
So that was really, really important to kind of kill that vibe right away.
And again, it just comes back to.
know, working on deliverables and making people understand that, you know, this is just what
they do in their sprint. This is part of their tasks and that whenever they decide to do them,
it's the same for you. You could decide to work on the Friday if you wanted to, but we're not,
you know, be it on the Friday or Thursday, it doesn't matter to us.
I have one more note on mental health, which is I'm the first and so far only Kit Fox parent.
but I have found having a day where my kid is in daycare and I don't have to work, like it's a
massive mental health benefit that like all my my friends who have young children who don't
have Fridays off, like it seems like how do you get anything done and they're like I don't know.
So I mean it's I almost feel like it's something we should offer to all parents.
Yeah, I just a second that
fridays for me. I have tw
are two and four years ol
One of the things that's been really important to me is being a part of their lives as much as I can.
And what Fridays have done for me is, yes, the time away from them and having my own personal time to for my own mental health has been really good.
But I've also every single Friday morning I volunteer at my my older daughter's preschool.
And that's just been like one of the best things about the four day work week.
It's not even work related at that point.
It's just my time.
that I feel like I'm getting back.
And this only could happen unless I was taking
every Friday morning off from work normally.
So that was really important and great for me.
And speaking on like things that have been really.
good and beneficial. What are the benefits? What have you seen have been the major benefits for
your studios moving to a four-day workweek? And what are the big things that you've seen? And
what are the big picture things that you share when you want to talk about how great the four-day
workweek is? I mean, I feel like I've covered this, but for me, it's just like, it's a place
I want to work at, you know? It's a place I want to work at a lot more than I used to. And I think
that's a pretty big deal.
Yeah, I mean, sorry, I interrupted you, Chris.
No, no problem. I think one thing that we noticed was, so we started in 2019,
before the pandemic. And I'm really proud that our retention rate was very
close to 100%. Despite a worldwide pandemic in the past three years, I
haven't lost anyone on the team, be it to mental health or you know, whatever
reason, like everyone.
seems happy so everyone is sticking around, everyone seems healthy so they're sticking around.
We added a lot more during the pandemic to make sure that everyone was feeling
good and everything but still I think the...
the four-day workweek definitely helped everyone kind of be able to regroup, refocus, you know,
like talk with their families, do whatever they needed to do in those three days off.
That maybe on a five-day workweek would have just added a lot to the stress level of the team.
So retention, I think, is something, you know, as a studio owner, is a huge advantage
that we have versus other companies. And another thing I think
is that our employees are kind of getting used to the four-day work week as well.
So I think it's going to be hard for them to find, you know, that same lifestyle in another studio.
And so that also plays into, you know, trying again for us to have that best, you know,
work-life balance. I think studios that are going to offer that are going to have a unique
retention level with their employees and, you know, just generally have happier, healthier
employees working for them. And honestly, in the end,
People make games, you know, we need computers and brains.
I keep saying this all the time,
but I think it's really important to realize
that our primary resource to make video games
are human beings and, you know,
making sure those human beings feel as creative
and as focused and, you know, as ready as possible
to hit the ground running on a workday,
I think is all positive things that you wanna do.
Awesome. Yeah. And I know
just echoing a lot of wha
said here. Um, but I thin
that we saw is everyone w
on Monday with like stori
did over their weekend an
that they had going on and then just hit the ground running super hard. We saw that everyone
felt like they were coming to work happy and refreshed and then and I think for us, especially
framing it within the pandemic, everyone at Armor Games was struggling really hard, like really hard.
And we were at a moment at the company where we realized we weren't we were just trying to get everyone to the level of just being okay like okay was just the baseline we wanted to hit like can we get people to work going.
Okay, and I think the four day work week really helped us get beyond the okay bar and start moving towards.
like, what is ideal?
What is the ideal workplace?
And what does that look like?
And it really was that push for us.
And I think everyone feels those benefits
and feels a lot of the things that are positive
and good about the four-day work week.
But on the other note too,
there was a lot of things that challenged us as well
at Armor Games, especially around certain disciplines
had more trouble adjusting to a four-day work week
than others.
What were some of your,
What were some of the things that you saw from your teams as you were rolling out the four day work week. Were there certain disciplines or
certain groups that were more challenged. Was there. Was there. Was that the company as a whole that was working through certain
things. Did it expose anything that you weren't seeing before from your studio. I know we went into some of this more or less with
some of you. But I was just curious if there's anything else the group saw.
I'll start. I mean, Kit Fox has always been very, I would say, efficient about our communication. We're very focused. We didn't have a lot of excess meetings to cancel or get rid of or anything like that.
We, I think we did have a situation where,
like we believe in like being professionally respectful
is one of our pillars.
And for us, what professionalism means is like,
we have very, very synchronous work together
as collaborators.
We have core hours every day where everyone works
at the same time together.
And that's great, but in a five day week,
I think that sort of normalized nine to five working system, people sort of build in their own buffer, where they, because there isn't the flexibility of the schedule itself.
They build the flexibility in you know if I'm not feeling that great on Tuesday.
And I'll do the hours, but it'll be Friday that I then then maybe to get my tasks done I have Friday afternoon.
And that kind of flexibility had to shift in favor of the employees time and energy instead.
So for me, for example, if I have a bad Tuesday, it's sort of bad to work on Friday, right?
Like it's not when everybody's available. I can't collaborate with people properly on Friday.
I can't necessarily make it up because people won't be there. And I still could,
but it's, you know, it's overtime at that point. I'm working on the weekend, et cetera, et cetera.
And so one thing that I'm trying to encourage with my employees is to think of you can still do makeup Fridays, but, but it's tough because like I said like if your collaborators aren't there if your team members aren't there like it might not be a replacement
for that Tuesday afternoon you missed you might have to power through on Tuesday anyway somehow and how do you do that if you haven't slept.
So it's a, it's sometimes it's still a struggle, I think, to try and really feel like every day you're putting in that good 25% of a week.
I think for us, we actually have a mix of asynchronous work
that ends up working really well
for when people use Fridays as a makeup day
where it's actually like, oh great, there's no one here.
That's perfect.
When I, if I take a Monday or Tuesday off
and I work on a Friday or I do Friday overtime,
Those are days where I'm just like so efficient because I can focus on all the tasks that I put off during the week, where I have to communicate with a lot of people, just because of the complexity and inefficiencies that we may, we may have on our project.
But we've also gotten really our team is pretty distributed across different time zones and also have different needs, mental health, physical health, emotional health, etc. And so we still maintain a very flexible time off policy and like let people just kind of, you know.
take whatever time they need, even within the four days, I think it's really important to still
provide that level of flexibility. And so we've gotten into a bit more of a culture of scheduled
messages on Slack, asynchronous communication, and I think that those are really, really
beneficial in general for remote work as well. And in a way that the four-day workweek has
actually made that more normalized and easier for us. Yeah, I know. Oh, sorry. Go ahead, Chris.
I had an employee who said that he did not want to work the four-day work week and he absolutely
wanted to work five days a week which was a strange one to have to deal with because again
I don't want to give him anything more than the others for working the extra day because that
defeats the purpose of the four-day work week but at the same time I understand that a lot of people
you know have work as kind of their social life and work is very melded together.
And so do you stop someone from working on the fifth?
So we ended up kind of, you know, discussing it openly
and kind of having the fifth day be more of like a paid,
you know, if he wants training
or if anyone wants training on a Friday
and they want to kind of go through more schooling
or they want to go and like have this Udemy class
that we buy for them or.
stuff like that. We we're always open to doing that. And the
Friday is kind of a moment for that we had employees that
wanted to do their own personal projects, which we encourage
them to do on the Friday. And so that even if they had questions
or whatever during the Friday, you know, like, feel free to go
on discord and say whatever you need to say. But so that was a
bit of a challenge to where, you know, a lot of programmers told
me actually that they didn't need the three days off, which
was a strange one. I'm like, you're
you're serious right now, you don't want to take the three days, you absolutely want to work the
five days. So that was a weird one to deal with, but I think it's important to still stay the line
of not encouraging people to do the five days because it would defeat the purpose of the four
day week.
The other thing that was kind of just an obvious one, but that you only kind of have to think about once you're in it is how you how do you deal with holidays?
Is it suddenly a three day work week when there are, you know, there are eight weeks in Montreal where, you know, during the year where there's a national holiday?
And so we decided to that we were going to stick to the four day work week.
But when it's a holiday, you can decide to have that day.
If it's a Monday, you can decide to have the Monday off and then work the Friday
or you can keep the Friday off as usual.
But, you know, there's there was discussions around that as well.
You know, it not being an issue, just being like, OK, well, logistically,
what do we want to do with this situation?
In my mind, again, it all comes back down to.
sticking to the sprint, sticking to the deliverables, no matter the number of
days it takes you to do, that's kind of our expectation of work for the next two
or three weeks, depending on the sprint size.
And that's kind of how we ended up treating it.
I don't know if Salim or Tanya, you know, you have a different way
to deal with holidays or Joan.
Holidays has been, uh.
a big back and forth for us as well. I think where we landed was a similar thing of like,
yeah, either take them Monday or Friday, but also recognize because we are removing a day
and those holidays are kind of designed around a five-day workweek to like, that we need to
sort of accommodate the fact that that would maybe cut a lot of time off from our sprints
and getting things done. I think it's kind of an open conversation at our studio, honestly.
It's something that we might revisit.
Yeah, we're still trying to figure it out too.
So far we've just said sometimes it's a three-day week.
And that doesn't feel great as a product manager
because typically we forget when we plan the sprint.
I mean, if you remember when you're planning the sprint
then it's not as bad, but you still have to look at,
well, how much would we get done
if we added two more days or three more days, right?
Um, but I think when one reason why we keep defaulting back to, well, it's just
another day off is, uh, we have some people who are part-time in addition.
So they're only working three days a week or two days a week, and they
should have a day off too.
And it, right.
And it's like, well, if a three day a week person gets the day off, why don't I?
Right.
So then we're just like, well, I guess now you get off what 60 days a year,
52 plus the eight red days.
Yeah, I know for us, holidays have been like, like we've said before, like the moment you go from a four day work week to a three day work week, that's really, it gets really compressed, it gets really, it almost
in some ways it becomes li
you're like, oh, that's i
can be challenging. We, u
to keep all of our holida
them in ways that made th
the time that was availabl
start to squeeze the cale
does start to, especially
We're trying to plan, you know, an offsite.
A lot of us haven't actually met each other in person before.
We haven't actually seen each other in two or three years.
So as we're starting to plan that, we're also having to consider that as well, especially
as a publisher with lots of publishing partners.
We want to make sure that they're being taken care of as well.
And that's always been like.
Yes, holidays and extra days off and those kind of things have been really kind of a challenging thing and I think something that we're all kind of speaking to on this panel is we're learning a lot of things in real time, and we are.
There's no guidebook on how to do a four day work week with a with.
in the games industry or as an indie or it's just it's something where we kind of have to solve
these things on our own and see if they fit and all of our teams are different so we all have to
kind of fit it differently to our different needs. It's worth noting that part of this
conversation also started because our so we had somebody at three day work three day weeks and
paid appropriately like years and years before any of this.
And they pointed out that legally, they are still owed those eight days.
Like it's in the laws of Quebec at least.
But it'd be weird to then give them time off and not everybody else.
Yeah, we had to do a surprising amount of research
into US laws on how 40, like we just assume 40 hours
is a full week of work and it's bizarre.
Well, technically we do pay those hours, by the way.
I don't know if that's a different segment, I forget.
But technically we have 40 hour weeks
according to the government.
It's just, we have eight hours of self-improvement
or something is what it counts as.
Cool.
Let's get into the future of the four day work week.
We're starting to run out of time, so I want to make sure we cover this topic.
We all gave our various experiences on our four day work weeks.
We're all very different studios, but I'm curious from this group.
Do you think that, you know, Indies, Indie developers as a whole
will be able to move in this direction and do this?
Is this going to be a broader trend for the greater industry?
Where do you see
the difference between a four-day and five-day work week starting to shake out as more studios
jump on board? Huge question dude. Sorry. I think you know it's kind of a strange one but
I think it's going to need a big cultural shift in just the way work is perceived
in the general population for
for it to become something that's kind of normalized.
I think it's an arbitrary number to say that we should work
five days a week.
It could be two, it could be three.
Like who cares in the end, as long as you can live
and be happy.
I think also a lot more people are orienting their life.
I think the pandemic has put a lot of different perspective
on what it means to work and what it means to be happy
and at home and feel safe and secure and healthy.
I think people are maybe less career oriented now
that there's been a worldwide pandemic
and everything's gone to shit in some fashion.
I think a lot of people now might be saying,
well, maybe I wanna enjoy an extra day or two a week off
so that I can take care of my family,
do things that I enjoy, do things that I love,
maybe sacrifice even some salary to do that.
I think I know people that have gone.
from the AAA studios that have come into smaller studios that are on the four-day week or have
decided to like chop their hours to do a three-day week even if they were making the huge salary with
the AAAs. And you know I think we're going to see more and more people trying to go down that
lifestyle route instead of like the career you know money route.
And I think that's a good thing in general.
And if more and more people start doing that,
then I think it's going to get more normalized
and you will see more studios doing it.
I think it is another beast for a AAA studio
to tackle a four-day week than it is an indie studio.
Just the sheer scale and coordination
of like a 400-person team working on a game.
I don't know how that would work.
But I think for indies, I expect that it's going to be
like more and more regular to see studios
on the four-day work week.
Yeah, to speak back to something that Chris mentioned, in terms of, you know, hiring people and attracting talent. That is one of the main things that small studios can offer. I can't imagine that this won't become the norm in the future. And I think it should become the norm. I don't see any reason for it not to be.
And part of that is retaining talent, attracting talent, because, you know, as small companies,
we don't compete with the big studios in terms of salary or benefits or whatever.
So we have to find other ways to engage people in meaningful ways and make our
work environments attractive for them. Honestly, maybe this is the pandemic,
like existentialism speaking a little bit.
But I think that if there was a will,
any industry out there could go to 40 hours a week.
It's just, it's more a matter of everyone wanting to do it.
Like I think if all of the employees of Ubisoft
woke up tomorrow and said,
we only want to work four days or we quit.
Like suddenly it would be, they figure it out, right?
And that's like the magic of unions and co-ops
and all these other like worker forces.
It would be very, very difficult.
I'm not saying it's easy.
I'm not saying, I know that it would be even,
you know, exponentially harder,
the larger your organization is.
Hats off to Chris already for 30 people versus 11,
but I absolutely think it'll become more and more normal.
And I hope it does.
And I hope.
the most for our most vulnerable workers for like QA and community management and all the
people that are exploited more that they get to have more and more the kind of lifestyle that
they want for their talents. Sorry, Salim, you were going to say something in the middle of the
night. I kept talking. No, no, no. I forgot what I was going to say. Sorry.
Cool, so let's just wrap up and then we can go to Q&A.
But the last question I wanted to ask the group,
if there was just one thing that you'd recommend
to any team considering a four-day work week,
whether it's a piece of advice,
a thing that you keep thinking about,
what's that one thing that you would give to that group
who is thinking about that four-day work week shift?
Every single time that I run a postmortem in life, the one issue that keeps coming back in again and again is communication.
There's always issues with communication in some form. And so I think that's one thing that you really, really need to work on. So, you know, optimizing meetings and making sure the
There's a flow of communications from when things get decided to whoever needs to know those things, and not necessarily monopolizing everyone's time for meetings is something that's really important.
Also, you know, going into a meeting with a schedule instead of just with already talking points that are pre planned.
instead of kind of just winging it.
That's a big one.
Which was what we used to do, I think is really, really important because in the
end you, you realize that on a five day week, you were, you were kind of already
cheating on a lot of stuff, like, you know, cheating hours here and there with, you
know,
I'm going to attend this meeting, even though I have nothing to do with it, just because I wanted to see or understand what's going on, knowing that it was kind of going to be like a more relaxed hour where you might not need to have a brain as focused as you usually do.
So that's the kind of stuff that I think really needs to get worked on the asynchronous communication also like as Tanya mentioned, it can be an issue of.
someone's not there on a certain day or all that stuff are the things that we need to figure out.
But if you if you do put the time in that and you can fix that part of it,
the rest comes a lot much more naturally and easier than you might think to implement.
Salim, Tanya.
Yeah, I would say if you're a team considering the four day work week,
the most important thing I would suggest to you is to consider unionizing.
If you're a group of team members, you should
build collective power because you can't trust people like us
who are giving this talk right now as business owners.
You know, we might be nice bosses, we might be good people,
but there's nothing stopping us from reverting that or changing things
or exploiting in other ways. And so.
The four day workweek is a great place
to actually start organizing your workplace
because it's a really easy place to unify a lot of things
where you can be like, yeah, I would love that.
And my team would love that.
And that's a place where you find common ground
to building solidarity.
So I really recommend reaching out to organizations
like Game Workers Unite and other union organizations
on how to unionize, because then you can take some
of that power into the team's hand and enforce and ensure
proper boundaries and good work life balance in a way that you can't by just trusting the owners of a studio.
Well put. My number one advice to both the bosses who are listening and the workers is to set a goal for yourself.
If you're a boss, like know what your goals are. Like for us, if our goals were mental health, that's something we can look at and measure whether or not we should continue and it was successful for us so we continued.
But if, and as a worker, like what are your goals for those Fridays? Are you going to use them to relax? Are you going to use them to have a side project?
Like I think.
everybody feels better about it
when they know what their goals are for a change like this
and see the results through that lens
rather than after six weeks,
trying to look back and remember how it felt before.
Awesome, well, thank you all on the panel.
I think we have about nine minutes for Q&A.
Is there anyone who wants to ask any questions
for our panel?
Kit Fox might be hiring a programmer in the coming year
or so, if anyone wants to ask about that.
I don't have any details yet, but keep an eye
on our Twitter and website.
It is hard to hire programmers, I hear.
So I'm hoping this will be a benefit.
OK.
You hear me, I think.
I have actually a few questions.
First of all, it's about the leading people
because there are usually people
who are very focused and efficient,
and at the same time you work with people
who are not very efficient
and have some problems with time organization.
And how do you deal with that?
Where are the traps?
How do we deal with both attitudes?
And how did the people switch to the four days a week?
I mean, I can say for us, I mean, that has always been the case, right?
Like on a five day week, there are some people who flail with their time
and organization and other people who.
who are very good at it.
And it's always a question of working with each person.
Like I'm not gonna have the same system
that works for everybody.
Some people I gotta remind them
of other timesheets every two days.
And other people, I leave them alone for two weeks
and they come back with more spreadsheets
than I could have imagined.
And this does make it more evident,
but I think if you're worried about someone
not working hard enough,
like that's a separate conversation
from how many hours you expect them to work.
Yeah, something to add to that is you can always help enable people to be better with those things,
but also production needs to also be flexible enough to not treat every person as one size fits all.
And sometimes production actually has to just measure that different people have different outputs and you plan around that.
So yes, you give them support, you help them have the tools to improve where you think it's necessary,
but also production.
You can't just have like an artist and be like,
well, I need you to make, you know, 15 assets a week.
And if the artist can only make seven assets a week,
that's their pace.
You have to plan around that.
You know, I think it's very important to not treat people
as a, to just really not treat folks
with a one size fits all approach.
Yeah, and always giving feedback is also something
that I think is super important
and having that open conversation.
when you feel like someone might be underperforming or stuff like that are just like general things
but again that are those are issues that are as real on a five-day week than they are on a four-day week.
Okay another question is about scaling it because you work in these studios do you think or do you
feel that it can be scaled to bigger studios what are the possible traps there and do you have
anything to recommend?
I guess I would recommend trialing it
in the most isolated department.
I worked at a large studio many years ago,
so it's been a while,
but I imagine the more tightly integrated
and the more cross collaborative they are,
the harder that department will be to trial a four-day week
and doing it across the studio
would probably be a complete problem.
So yeah, maybe there's a particularly segregated group that can do a milestone on 40 weeks
and then compare notes.
What is the trial period?
For us, we started with six weeks and then we moved it to three months.
So we doubled it after six weeks were successful.
But I guess it would depend on the kind of milestones that that project has.
I'd be happy to talk with somebody in more depth.
If you want to email me or tweet at me, we can organize a chat.
I can give some advice.
I've never worked in a AAA studio, so I'm not really equipped to answer that question.
I know that in Montreal, Eidos Square Enix is looking at trying the four-day week or they're
implementing it in some form. So, you know, I would maybe reach out to them and see how they do it, but
I'm just, I don't have enough knowledge of the AAA space to be able to add anything.
Okay, and last question, I would like to ask about Agile. Do you work in Agile system? If so,
please elaborate on, did you squeeze all these meetings? This is pretty expensive,
you have planning, refinement, then you have to summarize all this up. And four-day weeks
seems to be pretty short to do all these things. How long your sprint lasts?
So before you answer, we have three more people with questions.
This is the last one.
So if you could keep the answer brief.
Yeah.
We can run over a little bit.
And hopefully, you were here at the beginning
to get their contact info.
And if not, we'll put it up at the end.
Can I take this one real quick?
I don't think Agile is designed for video games. I think you have to take Agile and make it work
for video games. There are elements of Agile that you take and implement but you cannot get away
from waterfall elements as well. I think you design the systems for your particular games
and teams. You don't just adhere to Agile blindly or religiously and that's how you make it work
with the times and the constraints that you have.
For what it's worth, we do two week sprints.
And yeah, Selim is correct, it's customized.
But we do cross department show off
and then sprint review and then sprint planning
on Wednesday mornings, every two weeks.
And the total is about two hours.
It's very unusual that it lasts more than two hours total.
Thank you.
Hello. Thank you so much for the talk.
I wanted to come back to a point I think Salim, you mentioned.
You had to hire another person for your community manager because they were, you know,
there was so much focus on that one person.
How do you have that conversation with that person without making them to feel
Like they're not doing enough or like that you're trying to replace them because I can
see how that can easily feel like you're being replaced.
Like, oh, we're hiring another person just to help you with your work.
Don't worry about it.
So how do you have that conversation that is meaningful?
Yeah, well, so at Co-op, the core full-time team members are co-owners of the studio.
So there's a level of job security that that I think already kind of brings in.
In our particular case, actually, our community manager was the person who was like,
this is insane, this is not fair, and this is too much.
And so that was a reaction to them bringing up their need for help.
But in other situations where we've noticed people need additional support,
it's kind of just like, hey, this is something we're noticing.
we think you need support. And if that's a threat or a problem or a fear for them then it's just a matter of having a
conversation being like let's lay it all down on the table and talk this out and just be mature about it. And I do think
being a co-op helps in a lot of ways towards that feeling of that fear of being replaced.
Yeah, I know for us, one of the things that we do
as a publisher is we do internal QA for our games
and we found that QA didn't kind of get the same kind
of productivity boost that some of the other pieces
of our publishing program did.
And so it became a conversation that got surfaced
by the QA team that like, hey, like we're falling short.
We're not, you know, we're not falling short 20%
but we are definitely falling short on QA.
You need, your team needs to be trusted
to bring those things up and be able to respond to it.
In fact, if your team member
is not highlighting those problems,
I would want to ask why,
I would dig into why that's not being surfaced to you.
What is actually scaring them and solving for that.
Thank you so much.
Hi, I'm curious, some of you mentioned pushback
from your studio members about not wanting to go
to four weeks, especially programmers.
Can you dive into some of the reasons they specified
and how you mitigated?
I feel like I'm part of this crowd.
So I'm gonna like venture a guess as to why,
like we didn't, you know, go delve into too much of it.
But my understanding is,
A lot of people come into the industry with a chip on their shoulder wanting to become the best at their craft, the best at what they do, and they understand that they need to put the practice hours in to be able to do that.
When you have that competitive mindset, or you have that
that drive, it's hard to stop someone from wanting to learn everything about the world, you know.
So I think it was mostly that kind of issue. I think programmers might be a more competitive
field in particular. It's a, I don't know why, I don't know if it's ingrained at school,
I don't know where it comes from.
But I think that's part of where it comes from.
It's just that drive of wanting to be the best that made them want to work the extra time in.
And then it's just having a conversation with them of making sure that it's a healthy.
it's a healthy thing that they're doing. You know, I was always that driven.
I was always, I'm a very competitive person. So I have that instinct in me.
And I understand that I do work more hours than a general person might in
general. That's why I started my company and I decided to do what I did, but
I'm very fulfilled in life.
I'm very happy.
I have a wife.
I have a very balanced, you know, social life.
And I think that's the important thing.
So you might want to, you know, you don't want to discourage necessarily
people from wanting to learn.
Um, but you do just need to track and make sure it's for the right reasons,
though, it just be my, my take.
In our situation, the pushback actually came from people who were using work as a coping mechanism for the pandemic.
And so when that kind of feedback came back to us, it was like, well, let's discuss that.
Is that really the best path forward for you?
Are there other solutions to?
find other ways to cope.
Because I personally don't believe using work
as a coping mechanism for the pandemic is healthy,
because in the long run, once things change,
if they change, you're left with nothing,
no support network.
You put all your resources into work
and you're kind of fucked and alone at the end
and have very little to show for it.
So it was a matter of just really pushing back
against that very strongly.
Got it.
So people just need therapy.
Thanks.
That's generally a very common piece of advice that we give our team.
Very quickly, so a lot of the criticism of the four-day workweek comes from the angle
of sort of like, oh, like the benefits are temporary because once people become acclimated
to it, you know, they're less excited about it, like that sort of thing.
I know stretching on two or three years, maybe some of your fears around that have been alleviated,
but could you talk a little bit about that and maybe some alternative schedules such
as like summer hours, like three days a week during like the summer or taking August off
or things like that?
Well, I can say that we also give five days a week,
five weeks a year of vacation.
If you've been at Kid Fox for at least a year
and four weeks for the first year.
So you can already take August off.
But I mean, honestly, I went into this
with the full expectation that people would normalize to it.
And I think that they have at this point,
like we're almost to one year.
And I think that's OK.
If this is their idea of normal, we've actually won.
We've improved their expectations
of what work and life should feel like
and how happy they should be as a baseline,
even in a difficult world situation.
And so yes, I actually think that the biggest
problem with these bigger companies
is that because I think the benefits are immeasurable
and because they're human-oriented,
And because maybe, yeah, it does mean that some departments,
especially, are gonna be five to 10% less productive,
it really has to come from the workers
to fight for this kind of thing,
because in the long run, it is probably a profit loss,
and somebody has to say that's okay.
Yeah, I think it's a win-win,
because anything that challenges the dominance of work
in our lives is for the best.
So if that's being normalized and so on,
then I think that that's just a good thing.
Might also be unique to Montreal, but there's a lot of video game studios as well.
So, you know, people talk.
So even though they might get acclimated to the four-day work week,
I think, you know, speaking with other studios and understanding that
they have something that other studios might not have that makes their life easier,
still makes it feel like it's something that's worthy or something that has value.
It's not like they suddenly stop caring the fact that they have it today.
I'm starting to hear about like board game meetings and D&D meetings and like moviegoers that are like all four day work week people.
And so I was like, maybe that will help.
Every, every single time I get to Thursday night or Friday, I'm just like, thank God.
Like, thank God it never gets, it never gets old.
It just never gets old.
It always feels good to get to Thursday or sorry to get to Friday.
So yeah, for sure.
I think that's all the time we have for the panel.
Thank you, everyone in San Francisco who came to see us.
Or thank you if you're watching this on the vault or YouTube
or wherever this video might be in the future.
Appreciate everyone's questions.
Appreciate the panel being here and sharing their topics.
And thank you, everyone.
Hope you have a good rest of your day.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Thanks, everybody.