Whatever.
I'll just do it the manual way.
So hello.
I'm Yuri Horniman.
Everyone has slides with their names on it,
but I have this.
So I've been making games since 1991,
and I've worn a lot of hats in that time.
And today I'm here wearing my game designer hat.
And so now I'd like to know a little bit more about you.
Who here thinks of themselves primarily as a writer?
OK, that's not as many as I expected.
Wrote the whole thing for you writers.
Narrative designer?
Okay, that's a bunch, yeah, okay.
Game designer?
Okay, all right.
Who here thinks storytelling in games would be better
if writers were consulted more often and especially earlier?
OK, that's enough people.
Great, great, great.
Because the whole talk collapses if people say, whatever.
So OK.
So that's a very pernicious problem, very complicated,
very systemic.
And I am not going to offer you the solution.
I'm not going to say, this is a silver bullet, those don't exist.
But hopefully, I can cast a new light on this problem
by showing you a design approach that I found extremely
useful in game design, and that sort of is
relevant to that problem.
So I'm going to start with some quick definitions, some examples, then I'll talk about the design
approach, and then I'm going to talk about what that means for storytelling in games.
So first, I'd like to ask you to suspend your disbelief for the duration of this talk and
to accept two simple, non-academic definitions of terms that I'm going to be using during
this talk, just for the sake of argument, because terminology in storytelling in games
I found to be a very complicated issue.
So...
When I talk about story, I talk about this.
I talk about something that was pre-offered,
and it's about something happening to someone.
Because people get confused by what
is meant by story in games, including me.
And so I mean pre-offered story.
I don't mean an emergent story.
I don't mean the story that you're
telling me about the game you played last night.
I don't mean the story as it's happening while you're playing.
I don't mean back story.
I mean this.
And so fictional, I'm going to talk about this a lot.
This is an important concept for this talk.
This is about willing suspension of disbelief,
so fictional means related to things I'm asking you
to pretend are true, right?
So I am, as designers, as game creators,
we are asking people to believe that this bunch of pixels
is a plumber and that's a barrel and that's a monkey, right?
And that's kind of a core.
Okay, so an example.
Let's say you have a game where you have hit points, right?
So we've been using hit points as a mechanic for decades.
Works very well.
It means that if the player hits an enemy,
she's not killed instantly.
You can sort of take that away a little bit.
So hit points.
OK.
So you need to show the player how many hit points
she has left, right?
Because otherwise, you don't get the right dynamic going.
Very common design problem.
So how do you do that?
Well, the easy solution is what Doom does
and what billions of games have done,
is just put the number on the screen, right?
There it is, very clear.
People know what's going on.
Works great.
Now let's say that you say you want to really immerse
the player in the world.
You don't want any gamey numbers on the screen
because you think that breaks suspension of disbelief, right?
So what do you do?
Well, if you're Valve and Half-Life,
working in Half-Life,
you find an explanation in your game setting, right?
You say, well, you know, this is slightly sort of sci-fi game
so what if the player character puts on this sort of
high-tech exosuit that has an actual heads-up display
and then we can show all the different numbers
that are important for gameplay right there?
Even though, you know, why an industrial exosuit would show the amount of bullets you have left in your gun,
you know, like, doesn't really make sense. But, you know, it's good enough, right?
So, beautiful solution, makes total sense, or, well, almost total sense, in the world of the game.
But now, let's say you love this idea of not having numbers on screen,
but your game has a fantasy setting and, you know, you don't want to try and come up with a fantasy exosuit, right?
So what do you do?
Well, if you're Team Ico, you take out hit points all together, right?
You think about, well, why do we even need hit points?
What are the dynamics we're trying to generate?
Why do we need, why do we want the player to know about them?
And so instead, you make all the situations in the game
very clearly deadly or not, right?
In ICO, I find it sort of cool, it's like,
if it looks like a kid would die falling from that height,
he'll probably die, right?
It's very obvious, right?
You don't need to think about it.
There's nothing to explain.
It's very clear.
And then, you know, the enemies, they
don't actually harm the player character.
They just slow him down while his companion, Princess Yorda,
is being dragged off into the void.
And then the game ends, right?
So they have this kind of delay mechanic in there.
And they have kind of the same dynamic and effects
as for midpoints.
in a different way and without requiring
any numbers on screen.
And I think it's great.
It's also a lot of work,
because they have to reinvent all this stuff.
You know, it's like, oh, let's get the off-the-shelf
hit point module.
And it affects the whole game.
There are certain things they cannot easily
put in their game by using this.
But, you know, it's a wonderful solution.
So what do we just see here?
We were looking at sort of two sides of the game,
the mechanical side, which is the rule side,
and then the fictional side, right?
And I find it an incredibly useful way
of looking at game design,
and I've been using this approach a lot.
since quite a long time.
I know other game designers have too,
it's not something particularly new,
but you know, and they may not use these exact words.
But it's very, very useful.
And you look at your games from these two sides,
you try to make things come together
into one sort of pleasing experience,
the experience that you want to achieve.
Because if you don't balance those two sides,
you get dissonance, or you can get dissonance,
which you usually don't want,
and you risk breaking the player suspension of this way.
The mechanical side of a game is really abstract, right?
It's the fiction that gives the game meaning.
And of course, the mechanical side
has a big effect on the experience,
because otherwise, why do it?
And also, they're games.
But if I just say, when this counter hits zero,
the game ends, that can sort of mean anything.
That is very cold, very abstract, right?
And so the fictional side is what we're asking,
like I said earlier, what we're asking players to believe when
we talk about suspension of disbelief.
And every design element can be seen from the mechanical and from the fictional side.
And it's important to realize that these are two sides of the same thing, right?
They're not separate.
They're aspects or dimensions or perspectives on one thing.
Right.
So to balance the fictional and the mechanical often involves explaining a mechanical element
and justifying it within the game setting.
And the sort of fancy word for this is diegesis,
which is a word that, the way I use it,
comes from sound design.
You know, if you watch a movie and you see a radio
and the radio's playing music,
and the characters in the movie can't hear that music,
that is called diegetic music.
And if you have like, you know,
like the typical Hollywood score that you can hear,
but the characters cannot unless they break the fourth wall,
that is called non-diegetic music, right?
And it's a very simple concept that's used in sound design,
but I also find it very useful for game design.
And what you do when you explain the mechanical,
when you make things diegetic, is really world building.
You're inventing how the world works.
You're inventing which creatures and characters
exist in the game, why they behave a certain way,
why they act a certain way.
So I wanna just show two more examples.
Actually three, just to show a couple of things
that you can make diegetic, that you can sort of explain
and justify inside your setting.
So character death is a convention of video games
and has been around for decades, right?
Your guy dies and you have to start all over again.
But actually it is harmful to suspension of disbelief.
And so various games over time have tried to sort of explain
it and integrate it.
And one solution that I find really cool
is the one they used in Prince of Persia, Sense of Time,
where the entire game has this framing story of like
the main character narrating his adventures,
which fits really well with the whole Arabian Nights setting.
And when you do die in the game, the character goes like,
no, no, no, no, that's not what happened.
And sort of goes back a little way and tells it again.
And I find it a really cool solution.
Now, another convention of video games that
we don't really think about a lot,
is that there are these levels, these situations,
which have been created for the player
to challenge the player and to test them.
And it's like, why?
Who does that?
The question I used to ask a lot
when I was doing role-playing games in the 90s was like,
well, who built this dungeon?
And why does it still work after thousands of years, right?
And, you know, it's a convention,
and you don't think about it that much, but it's there.
And so one game which has sort of,
explain that is Portal. And I think it's probably the most brilliant thing about Portal to me.
They have explained why these levels are there, and they have explained it in a completely unique
way, and they've even given a... they have put the level designer, in a way, the game designer,
as a character into the game, right, as GLaDOS.
And I think that's brilliant.
Another game which does the same thing is Manhunt,
where in the game, a very, I must stress this,
in the game, a very sick and disturbed individual
has created all these levels in a decrepit part of town
and is forcing your character to go through
and kill, I'm not gonna say innocent people,
but kill people for his amusement
while literally whispering in your ear, right?
And that makes Manhunt a very special experience.
So what happens when I use this approach in the design process?
I tend to go back and forth between the mechanical
and the fictional.
You find some explanations for mechanical elements.
And once you've done that, that may trigger new ideas
for the mechanical side.
Because you go like, OK, so we've
added this to the world so that this makes sense.
And then like, hey, but that means that blah.
And then, ah, that means these new mechanics.
This is super cool.
And it's not uncommon to go back and forth a couple of times.
And here's an example from, this is a screenshot from Deus Ex Invisible War.
In Deus Ex 1 and Deus Ex sequel, you have these biomods, right, these augmentations
that you can sort of slot into your body and they give you new powers, right?
And apparently one of the designers of Invisible War sort of went like, you know, here's something
deeply creepy about taking some machine and just slotting it into your body and then it
modifies you.
And you're like, ooh.
You know, and what if?
those machines don't come from a corporation
that you trust and that has QA processes
and all that stuff.
What if it comes from the black market, right?
What if it's like, you buy it from some guy,
you don't know, but it has really cool powers,
but it might have some downsides, you don't know.
And then that's how the idea
for the black market biomods came along.
So I find it very cool,
it's not always going from one side to the other,
it's definitely a back and forth,
because it needs to balance, right?
You can also decide not to explain a convention
and to leave the mechanical side as is,
because it is a convention, right?
And sometimes it's better that way.
Because sometimes the solution of making it diegetic
is worse than just leaving it.
So here's an example from a game called The Getaway for the PS2
done by Sony.
This is sort of a GTA-like game set
in a very realistic depiction of London.
And the game, you're on a mission.
The game is telling you where to go.
Can anyone tell where you have to go from screenshot?
Yeah, to the left, exactly.
It's the indicator light that shows you not
where you are going to go in real life,
but it shows you where you should go.
And so that is sort of like, it's not like real life,
and it's kind of subtle.
Whereas GTA did this.
It's like, oh, huge pink arrow.
It's not subtle, but it works, because it's
such a convention that it's not that grating.
You sort of ignore it very quickly.
So I think that's an important lesson.
Conventions also evolve over time, right?
Common justifications become too commonplace.
Think back on, do I have time?
Yeah, 11 minutes, I can talk this.
Think back of early novels where it was all like,
oh, I'm writing you this letter,
and then this letter's like novel length,
and just to explain why I'm talking to you.
And then later people are like, no,
readers can deal with the fact that
I'm just reading this text
and I don't know where it's coming from, right?
And it's the same in games.
Some things have just become a little bit too commonplace,
a bit cliche, in my opinion.
Conveniently placed audio diaries
as a way to optionally tell back story, like in Bioshock.
It was great in System Shock.
I think by the time of Bioshock, well, I must admit,
I played Bioshock very late, like a couple of months ago,
first time I played it.
So I was like, oh, really?
Audio diaries again?
So it's a great solution, but it has become,
in my opinion, it has become a bit of a cliche.
The same with the convention that technically
it is very, very hard to show another character
walking around with you and interacting with you
in a 3D space, right, that is super hard.
So the convention is not to have those characters
walk around with you, but maybe to have them
talk to you through walkie-talkies
or through loudspeakers, right?
And that is, for me, has also become
a little bit like, oh, again, you know?
And so when I see a game, and again, Bioshock, right?
All these loudspeakers everywhere,
and then sort of people are talking at you
through these loudspeakers, and it's like,
oh, you know, I've seen it.
And then, you know, players are smart,
and they can spot overused explanations.
They get used to certain things,
and then you don't have to explain it anymore.
So, what does this mean for game teams?
Well,
working on this fictional side of design,
requires skills that you probably know well if you're a writer.
And it requires world building,
inventing characters, places, situations,
reconciling rules and fiction, which is not unlike reconciling plot and
character, when you do when you write an actual story.
You know, you're adapting the game's fiction to the constraints of a medium, right?
And those are skills that every writer and every storyteller knows or should know, right?
But they have nothing to do per se with story,
you know, according to the definition.
I started with.
They are a subset of the skills that you require to tell a story.
So virtually all games, and if you want to talk about it virtually, then come to the
spillover room or whatever that room is.
If virtually all games have a fictional side, then all game teams need storytelling skills,
right?
So those skills become essential to game development for most games.
And most companies, in my opinion, will benefit from looking at game design this way and having
these skills in the team.
So, does that mean all game teams need writers?
No, I don't think so.
But, you know, because, don't hate me.
Each company is different, right?
The writers in game teams question goes beyond,
like I said, it's a very complicated problem.
It goes beyond what I've been talking about here.
And feel free to ask me after to my opinion
of the economic aspects of that problem
and the producer psychology aspect of that.
So, you know.
Should more game teams have writers?
Yes, probably, definitely.
So should more game teams have narrative designers?
Even though there's someone in the audience, Lee Sheldon,
who has strong opinions about the job title
of narrative designer, and I totally respect his opinion,
I invite you to ask him what it is later.
Yeah, there you go, he's sitting right there.
I think a lot of game teams could probably benefit
from having narrative designers, right?
So I think in general it's a positive development.
Should more game designers learn about storytelling?
Even though they don't work on games that have story in them?
I think yes.
I think it's important to be aware
that this is like a second part of the game.
You can't just look at the mechanics and at the systems.
Should more writers learn about game design?
Definitely yes, because that will help you.
First of all, maybe you can get to work on a game
without being called writer.
Also, it will help you work with game designers.
So I think really.
The important thing is to separate the skills
from the job titles and to separate the skills
from the ideas about writing that you might have,
which I know in my case and in other cases I've seen,
you know, my idea of writing,
your idea of writing as a writer, right,
those are not necessarily the same thing, right?
A lot of people, I didn't use the word writing much
because I know for some people it's like,
oh yeah, that's when I write an email, right?
So separate skills from ideas from writing,
ideas about writing and from job titles.
And that's it.
Right, thanks. So, thank you for listening. I'm on Twitter, I'm in e-mail. I want to thank a
friend of mine, Verena Riedel, who helped me with the images. You should hire her. She's a
kick-ass producer, mobile producer. Yeah, she's right there. Anyway.
you want to ask questions. Yeah. Yeah. Spillover room. I
don't know why. Yeah. Oh, yeah. MC Yuri. Hello. Hey, Yuri. So
you talked about conventions a bit and about the
stuff like that. I wonder, using the black market mod example in Deus Ex or any of your
examples, you talk about how this back and forth between the fictional framing and the
design gave this interesting element, but at the same time it would be my opinion that
the genre conventions, even of a genre bending or expanding game like Deus Ex, so grossly
over-powered the region of Double Decade and continued to have this erosion in both forms,
in a way.
It would be my opinion that DC's sort of scale project too, but this region of Double
Decade or West Wing was the future of the genre and if you're interested in some of
the interesting things that they've done as to almost make
the meaning of that black market mod almost irrelevant
in the context of how overwhelmingly powerful
the conventions that they're leveraging in terms
of hit points and mana and all of the other guns
and bullets and reloads and all of these other things
that are just distilled convention that define the game
way more than one minor little piece.
And I wonder what your thoughts are
versus how powerful convention is.
Yeah, thanks for not calling me out for saying that mechanics
have no meaning, because I was afraid you
were going to ask about that.
You're probably right.
The thing for me was I needed an example,
and I wanted to have an example of something actually happening
in actual game development.
And this was the only example I could find,
where Harvey told me this is the way it happened.
It went back.
So I know that when I do game design,
I do often go back and forth.
And, you know, but if I go like, well, this one game I worked on five years ago, blah,
you know, nobody knows about this.
So that's why I picked that example, right?
Because I figured people would know it.
You're probably right that the overall experience of Deus Ex, you know, it's not the most important
part, you know.
I guess I'm asking, do you think we could do a better job of tearing down the conventions
that are, you know, homogenizing some of our games and focus more on...
some of the more interesting things that we can get through this process.
Yeah, I've been, once I started working on this, I've definitely felt, you know,
certainly, you know, it's like one of those things where you start finding conventions everywhere,
and it helped me reframe sort of why I think Portal is interesting, you know, and Manhunt, right?
So suddenly you see stuff where you're like, hey, actually, we do that because that's a convention,
and then you go like, hey, what if you do it a different way, or, you know.
So yeah, so thanks for the question.
Anyone else?
Yeah, here.
Hi.
Where is?
Here, here.
Oh, sorry.
Yes, hi.
Sorry.
Do you have any recommendation as a game designer
on how to learn to write?
How to do what, sorry?
How to write.
How to learn to write.
I am a huge reader on how to write,
which if you know how to write, you will know
it's actually completely useless.
And the number one advice I've always...
have seen is just right, right?
Which is actually the same for game design.
It's probably the same for every skill.
So then the question is like, well, you know,
you don't just go sit down and just instantly go like,
hey, you know, like, I'll just write Moby Dick
or whatever, right?
So doing the right writing exercises in the right order
is not something I've personally cracked, you know?
I don't call myself a writer.
So, I don't know, immerse yourself in it, try doing it.
Maybe work on twine games.
I have started doing that recently
and I found it really useful as a sort of, yeah,
as a writing slash interactive storytelling exercise.
So I hope that helps.
I mean, there are definitely, again, if you,
I wouldn't want to recommend anything like,
you know, what do these people call them,
McKee and all those books,
because I know Leah will kill me.
All right, so, sorry.
I hope that helps a little bit.
Thanks.
Yeah, anyone else?
No?
All right.
Thanks.