My name is Jeff Engelstein, and thank you for joining me today
to talk a little bit about one of my favorite hobbies,
collecting interesting psychological trivia
and tricks.
And I've become obsessed over the last five or 10 years
about loss aversion and all of the aspects
that it has in human psychology.
So I'm excited to share some of that with you today.
So first, a little bit about myself.
So I am a board game designer.
I've done about 10 games now.
Some of my bigger ones were Space Cadets, Dragon and Flag,
and Fog of War, which was recently released.
And I have my first licensed game, The Expanse,
coming out, which I'm excited about probably around June.
Since this is a video game conference,
I will say that I also have two published video games
for the Apple II.
which you probably can't get anymore, Star Blaster and Panic Button,
both published in around 1982, 83, something like that.
And some of you also may know me from my podcasts.
I'm on the Dice Tower podcast.
I do the game tech segment there.
And also the long form, about an hour-long podcast called Ludology,
which talks about game design and...
gets into the nuts and bolts specifically around board game design, although we do get
into a lot of topics. And I also teach board game design at the NYU Game Center for about
I've done that for about two years. So, it's a game conference, so I'm going to be playing
a bunch of games throughout this, throughout this lecture. So why don't we start by
This one I usually do live and grab somebody,
but in the interest of time,
I planted a stooge in the audience.
Sorry, a volunteer in the audience, Mr. Rob Davio.
Before the conference, before this talk,
I asked Rob, I made him an offer.
I said, I asked him if he had 10 or $20.
He did say that he had a $20 bill,
and I offered to make him a wager
that I would put up $20, he can put up $20.
I'd flip a coin, he could call it in the air,
and the winner would take the $40.
And I asked him if that was a wager that he would like to take.
And you said...
Only if it'll help your gut.
Ha ha ha!
So I asked him to go with his gut, and he said, he said no.
He said he would not take that bet.
Um, that the $20 was his...
That was the lunch money that you had set aside for today.
Um...
And...
made him a couple of other offers.
I said, would you do it if I put up $21 against your $20?
Would you do it if I went up to $22?
And he said that he would do it at $25,
as I recall correctly.
Yes, $25 against my $20, he would take that bet.
And that gets to really the base illustration
of a concept called loss aversion.
And just kind of in a nutshell.
What it's saying is that getting something feels good,
gaining $20 feels good, losing $20 feels bad, okay?
But losing the $20 feels worse
than gaining the $20 feels good.
I've been trying to come up with a more elegant way
to say that for a long time and I have failed,
so I'm just gonna stick with that.
You know, if you're looking in graphical form,
again, gaining your 10 or $20 makes you happy,
and losing the $10 makes you unhappy, but in a.
arbitrary scale more unhappy.
Studies have shown, and we're going to get a little bit into the details of how we know
these numbers, but
studies have shown that losses are about two times as intense as gains.
The first research on this was done by Kahneman and Tversky
back in the eighties.
They were two Israeli psychologists, and they did a lot of really, really interesting work
about how people are really not acting rationally and act irrationally.
And they were approaching things in terms of what they called, in economics, there was
a principle called homo economicus, which is that all of the studies of economics was
based around the idea that people acted absolutely rationally and perfectly in their own interests.
And they found a lot of ways that people do not.
And this is one of the biggies.
Ultimately, they did win the Nobel Prize for this work.
Actually, Kahneman was awarded the Nobel Prize.
Tversky had passed away a couple years
before they were awarded it.
And as far as I know, he is the only non-economist
to win the Nobel Prize in economics for this work.
So the purpose of this talk,
and what I'm hoping that you're gonna bring out of it,
is that when I,
teach my game design students one of the questions that we
always talk about early is to start with a mechanic or do you
start with a theme or you know how do you want to start and I
always recommend that they start with an experience that they
want to give the players or they start with an emotion that they
want to give the players and for those of you that were here
for the talk prior to mine about pandemic legacy, you know,
learned a lot about the the beats and the emotional roller
coaster that was specifically kind of pre-programmed for the
players and the way that they interacted with that and
As a game designer, as game developers,
we want to manipulate the player's emotions.
So some of these are tools about things
that are gonna make the players upset,
things that are gonna make the players happy.
You don't wanna necessarily avoid loss aversion.
Sometimes you can use it in a very effective way
to manipulate the players.
Again, going back to pandemic legacy or risk legacy,
when that game first came out,
one of the very first things that it made you do
was tear up a card.
It was a sticker or it was a card, right?
Card, yes, you had to tear up a card.
And that's a very emotional thing for players,
not both because it kind of goes against
a social taboo of destroying the game,
but because it's tapping into that idea of loss.
This is something that I bought,
this is something that I own,
and the first thing that the game is asking me to do
is take a piece of it and rip it up.
So the idea is that by leveraging to this,
you can get the players to the point
that you want them to get at.
In that case, by having them tear something up,
it was telling them that you're invested in this
and it's gonna be an emotional experience.
Okay, this one is an all play.
It's this game.
By the way, in these games, in these little demonstrations,
it will go a lot smoother if you don't try to outthink.
What's being asked just look inside yourself and go with your first reaction
and think about what you would answer if you were at what your feelings are
because that's the way your players are going to react. They're not going to
necessarily see that there that it's manipulative or that is being framed in
a particular way. So just just kind of go with that.
So here's 2 choices that you've got choice a
I will give you $3,000 and in choice B.
you have an 80% chance to win $4,000
or a 20% chance to get nothing.
And the question is, would you take choice A or choice B?
And just as a little hint,
I'll tell you that the average winnings on choice B
is $3,200, just to take the math out of it.
So how many of you would take choice A?
And how many would take B?
Okay.
Almost all of you.
In actuality, when people are surveyed on this,
about 80% will choose choice A.
And now from an economic standpoint,
going back to our homo economicus,
choice B is better overall for you to do.
Yet people choose A.
We'll talk a little bit about the reasons
into that in a second.
But let's jump to two other choices now.
Choice A, you're guaranteed to lose $3,000.
And in choice B, you have an 80% chance of losing $4,000,
but a 20% chance of losing nothing.
So in this case, how many people would choose choice A?
And how many would choose choice B?
Okay.
We have a very average crowd here, this is good.
So 72% of people surveyed on this will choose B.
And again, those of you that chose A in the first one
and B in the second one, you have made choices
that are against your economic interests in both cases.
But most people will go with that.
The general rule is,
that people will take a sure gain over a gamble,
but people will gamble to avoid a loss.
That's a really, really important concept.
And I'm sure you're already thinking
about some of the game play implications of the way
that that works.
So to kind of just look into a little bit of a game example,
I know this is a board game talk, and this is.
a card from hearthstone which is not a board game, but I'm counting it as a board game.
Counting is a card game that can do some fancy things that regular card games can't do.
This is a card from the hunter class called tracking.
And the text on the card, in case it's not clear, says, look at the top three cards of
your deck, draw one and discard the others.
So you basically see, you draw the top three cards of your deck, you see one of them and
the other two are gone from the game forever.
And this card, if you go onto HearthPwn
or you go onto sites that talk about Hearthstone,
this card is not usually well-received,
especially by new players.
I pulled some comments out about tracking.
I see the use of tracking, but psychologically,
I've always disliked the idea of burning two cards
to get a third.
If I put a card in my deck, it means I wanna use it,
not to discard it in favor of something else.
Or the bottom one, tracking.
Burn two other cards to draw one
and possibly lose key parts of your deck.
This is tapping into that idea of,
it's giving anxiety to players.
They're worrying about, okay, I'm gonna draw three cards,
and that's a problem.
But the reality is,
from a particularly mathematical standpoint,
is that it really, discarding two cards from your deck
only becomes an issue if you get all the way
to the end of your deck.
The way Hearthstone works, you have 30 cards.
At the end of the 30 cards,
if you have to draw some more cards,
you start taking damage.
So yeah, I mean, discarding cards
can be a little bit of a problem.
But for those of you who have played Hearthstone,
if you're a hunter and you've reached the end of your deck,
you're probably in trouble anyway.
So mostly, it doesn't really factor into the game.
But psychologically, people are seeing those cards
and seeing those goods cards and knowing,
I'm never gonna get to play them again.
Here's an alternative reworking
that I've run by other people.
And most people are happier with this phrase,
with this wording of the tracking effect.
Look at the top three cards of your deck.
keep one and shuffle the other two back into your deck,
then discard the bottom two cards in your deck
without looking at them.
Now it's basically the same effect.
You get one card of your choice
and two other cards are gone from your deck.
But because they're at the bottom of your deck,
most people feel psychologically,
well, they're at the bottom of my deck.
I was never gonna see those cards anyway.
The reality is that this is actually a worse effect for you
than the real tracking effect,
because in the actual tracking effect,
you know two of the cards that are never gonna come up,
and so if you're planning your tactics or whatever,
you know that you're never gonna draw that,
and so you can work around that.
In this, you don't know what you've lost,
but people psychologically are happier with this effect.
Here's another case study that comes into loss aversion.
Level draining in RPGs.
I gave this presentation to my class about a month, a couple of weeks ago, and when I
put the level draining slide up, there was an audible moan that went through the class.
Again, these are some quotes from.
from some DND forums about draining levels.
And you can read that, but I've highlighted
some of the other stuff in there.
On the bottom, there is little you can do in DND
to viscerally terrify players,
but for whatever reason, level draining does it.
And a couple of more quotes.
This is all from the same thread.
All versions of DND have some form of raised dead,
not all versions have restoration.
Many players would rather die than lose 50% of their XP.
which I have verified with my daughter, she agreed with that.
Maybe this is a more emotional than sensible reaction,
but many players feel that way.
And my favorite quote of the whole thing on the bottom
there, but what I've always liked about level drain
is just how personal that loss can be,
as if part of the character's life
truly was just ripped away forever, lessening them for it.
That's a real visceral emotional response to losing something.
And people don't even really, like I said,
have that effect a lot of times if their characters die.
It's the ending of a story, it's in some service,
but level draining has a different aspect to it.
And interestingly, if you look at D&D
and what they've done over the years with level draining,
in Advanced Dungeons and Dragons,
which is the first version I got into,
level draining was there, it was an undead ability,
and there was no save against level draining.
You got hit by a white or a lich or something,
you were screwed.
In the third edition,
there was a saving roll that was allowed.
at least, but if it failed, you lost the level.
Then in fourth edition, they completely
got rid of level draining.
And if you go to Pathfinder, which
is kind of like sort of an offshoot of third edition,
they didn't make that many changes from third edition D&D,
but one of the ones that they did was they
got rid of level draining.
So it's obviously that over the years
that this was recognized as something that was not
something that players wanted that
put them into an emotional state that they found uncomfortable.
So giving something to a player and then taking it away
is really emotional.
And that goes back to that idea of,
from Risk Legacy, of forcing the players
to tear up a card in the very beginning.
Better not to have given them that card in the first place,
or just have them randomly draw one
and leave the other one in the box.
You know, it has the same effect
from a mechanical standpoint,
but it does not have the same effect
from an emotional standpoint.
I'd like to take a quick detour into a game show
that my family, including my in-laws,
will no longer watch with me.
Deal or no deal?
I'm assuming most of you are familiar with the show.
But for those of you that are not,
there's a bunch of suitcases that all have varying values
of money in them, ranging from $1 to $1 million.
You pick one case at random that you're going to keep.
And then you gradually open the cases,
showing the money so you know what you didn't get.
and then at various points in the game,
there's a banker that comes on, very shadowy figure,
and he offers you money for your case.
Now, from a purely mathematical standpoint,
there's, you know, you know the expectation value
of that case, you know the average value
of all the cases that are left,
and the expectation value that remains is, you know,
the average of that is what you should get for it.
If it's less than that, you're leaving money on the table.
But the reality is in the show is that the banker always offers less than the expectation value.
It's actually really interesting if you track the show is the first round they offer way, way less than the expectation value
and they gradually approach it.
It's just they don't want people walking away in the beginning of the game.
But why does anybody take the offer if they're leaving that money on the table?
And this goes back to the first one of the first examples that we did, which is
captured in a psychological theory called utility theory.
And that goes to the idea that if I'm offering you
a million dollars or two million dollars,
as far as you're concerned, it's probably not gonna,
getting the two million dollars is not gonna change your life
as much as getting that first million dollars is gonna be.
So in your mind, they're about the same amount of money.
And that's really what Deal or No Deal is playing on,
is it's playing on people's, okay,
this, you know, the guy's offering me $120,000,
but it could be a million dollars.
So for me personally,
where is that falling on my utility spectrum?
And that's what's interesting to watch.
It's interesting to watch people struggle
with that idea of, you know, it's not just the number,
it's not just going for the biggest number,
but it's the utility
and how that's gonna apply to your life.
Now if we go back to that first example that I gave you guys
about the chance to get $3,000
and the 80% chance to get $4,000,
our brains are not great at math for the most part.
Most people see $3,000 and $4,000
and put them in the same box in their brain.
So really, for most people from a utility theory standpoint,
this problem is really, I'm guaranteed to get X
or I have an 80% chance to get X.
And in that case, I'm always gonna take
the one that's guaranteed to get X.
The fact that it's $3,200 doesn't really apply
that the expectation value is higher.
So that's just another way of looking at these things,
and we'll talk in a bit about bigger numbers as well.
Okay.
This example is, for those of you that are here,
again, for the pandemic legacy talk.
This is actually, it was a real study that was done
that I did not choose because I did not know
that I was gonna be directly after the pandemic legacy talk.
But this is the problem.
A deadly disease is rapidly spreading.
If nothing is done, then 600 people will die.
So a cure has been developed.
But you have two choices of which cure you're going to do.
You can either do choice A, remember 600 people
will die if nothing is done.
So choice A is that 200 people will be saved.
And choice B is a 1 3rd chance that all 600 will be saved
and a 2 3rd chance that nobody will be saved.
So how many people here would do choice A?
And how many would do B?
Okay.
When surveyed, about three quarters of people will do A.
200 people will be saved.
Let's do another problem.
Same situation.
Deadly disease is rapidly spreading.
If nothing is done, 600 people will die.
In this case, you could take choice C,
400 people will die.
Or if you pick cure D,
then there's a one-third chance that nobody dies,
but a two-thirds chance that 600 people die.
So who will take C?
A lot fewer people.
And who would take D?
Okay.
So, in this case 78% choose D.
So most people are with you guys.
So these are the four choices put together here.
So, choice A, B, C, and D.
Now since 600 people are gonna die,
choice A and choice C, 200 people will be saved
and 400 people will die, are exactly the same.
And choice B and choice D are also exactly the same.
So did anybody here pick A for the first one
and D for the second one?
That's very common.
A lot of people do that.
And this leads to a concept that's called framing.
What is a gain or what is a loss?
And this is another great manipulation tool
for player psychology.
If you say 200 people will be saved,
that's a positive emotion.
People like that, 200 people will be saved.
And the other one is all probabilities.
The other one is 400 people will die.
So again, we're going back to that idea
that people will take a gain,
a sure gain over gambling to gain more.
But people will gamble to avoid a sure loss.
And that's exactly what's happening here.
Except in this case, the outcomes are exactly the same.
It's not, you know, losing money versus gaining money.
But if you express it as saving people
or express it as people dying,
then people will approach it differently
and will have a different response to it.
So in a board game context,
this can be used a lot of different ways.
One of my new games which is coming out in the spring is called pick crew and
it's about the players. It's a team based game where each team is trying to
repair their race car and get it back out onto the track as quickly as possible
against the other teams. If you make mistakes, it's a real time game. You're
trying to do things as fast as possible. If you make mistakes, you get penalty
points.
And we looked at a couple different ways to do this.
Originally, the way that we did it is you got points
for doing good things, and if you got penalty points,
you lost points.
And we found that when this is aimed at families,
and in a family game is, if you had a lot of kids playing
and stuff like that, they didn't like losing the points
if they made mistakes on the car.
There's also a strategy to intentionally make mistakes
to get back, you know, get your car out faster
because the first team that's out can get a bonus
and can earn extra things.
So what we did instead, when we kind of saw that,
is we flipped it around and we said,
okay, if you get a penalty, you don't lose points,
but all the other teams gain points.
And it was easy because it was a score track
and people just could move their tokens up on the track.
And that worked really, really well.
People enjoyed that.
It opened it up, it took away the negative feelings.
Okay, penalty points, I'm on there, it's fine.
It also fortuitously enabled us
to make the score track look like a racetrack.
So you have a little car running around the racetrack.
And just metaphorically, race cars don't usually go backwards.
So you push the other cars forward.
But it really just changed the whole dynamic of the game
and the way that people approach the penalty points,
that it helped your opponents instead of hurting you.
I mentioned the Expanse game that's coming out.
In that, there is a mechanic where you
can keep an event.
There's event cards, and you can save one for later.
But if you choose to save one for later,
it costs you a victory point.
Or there's other things you can do in the game
that cost you victory points.
And I considered applying the same kind of idea
that instead of costing you victory points,
it could give bonuses to all the other players.
But in that case, emotionally,
I wanted the players to feel invested
that they were really committing something
into getting this event and saving it.
So in that case, we chose to
have it apply as a specific penalty to players where you actually have to give up victory
points in order to do this action.
In general, we have seen a shifting away from losses and players losing things over the
years.
I mean, the old school games, you know, from the, that we all grew up with, Monopoly and
Risk, are very much about loss, but they're very much about a specific type of loss where
you gain and then you lose.
Okay, so in monopoly you start with no properties
and money, you get properties and you get hopefully a little more money and then
for everybody except for the winner you lose everything.
Same thing for risk. Risk, you start with territories and you'll take more
territories, you build up an empire and then it's taken away.
and that classically will give you all of those negative feelings about losing stuff.
Whereas the newer games and what the Euro games really brought to the table in the 90s
was this idea of constantly building.
In the Settlers of Catan,
everybody starts with more than what they ended up with.
Nobody is losing stuff. Once you build a city, you get it.
Even the bonuses that you get, the largest army...
If you get the largest army card,
you don't lose it because your army is defeated
and you shrink, you lose it because people
got bigger armies than you.
Same thing with the longest road.
If you have a long road, well, people can cut off your road
if they build a settlement in the middle,
but that's kind of an edge case.
But for the most part, if you got the longest road,
people are only going to take it away from you
by building an even longer road.
Okay, so given loss aversion,
why do people play in casinos?
Ultimately, they have to overcome this in a big way.
I mean, the $20 bet that I made with Rob in the beginning
was basically a roulette spin, was basically blackjack.
And there's a couple of different techniques
that they use.
The first is chips.
First thing you have to do when you walk into a casino
is you have to exchange your money for an abstract token.
And a lot of studies have shown
that when people start exchanging tokens
instead of exchanging money,
that they don't ascribe the same value to it.
It gets abstracted and.
they get subtracted and they don't assign as much value to it.
And casinos specifically will try to make it difficult for you to convert.
It's easy for one-way trip,
but you can't go back the other way also once you convert to chips.
If you sit down at a blackjack table,
I can give $200 to a blackjack dealer and they'll hand me a stack of chips,
but if I want to turn my chips back into money,
I can't do it right there.
I got to pick up and I got to walk across.
But the other big thing is also jackpots.
People are really bad at dealing with big numbers
and small probabilities,
and the casinos are starting to take advantage of that.
Most of the games now, if you go,
if you've been to casinos lately,
blackjack tables and a lot of these new games,
they all have these little jackpot bonus bets.
It's very common.
People like that.
People like the idea that they're gonna get a lot of money,
and that helps them overcome this idea of loss aversion.
Basically, the lottery as an example,
to put it into the same frame
that we've been using on these other things,
is that choice A is, I'm guaranteed to lose nothing.
Choice B is, I've got a 99.9999999% chance to lose a dollar
or a really, really tiny chance
to gain a half a million dollars.
And again, the expectation value choice B here is negative.
But this is a bet that people make all the time.
Whereas that $20 bet, people won't make it.
So,
What's going on here is that people are really bad
at that number, that .0000001%,
and the lotteries are all taking advantage of that.
Powerball used to be about 100 million to one odds to win,
and they keep changing the game every couple of years,
and now it's like 300 million to one to win.
because they like these big jackpots.
And if people pay .00001% chance to win
or .000001% chance to win,
mentally they put that in the same bucket.
Just like the $3,000 and the $4,000
or the $1 million and the $2 million.
Once probabilities get really high,
million to one, 200 million to one, 300 million to one,
people have no idea of what that is.
OK.
This is one of my favorite studies from 2012,
the Chicago Teacher Bonus Study.
They went into a classroom in Chicago,
and they gave three different.
bonus plans to different groups of teachers.
One was just the control group, no bonus plan.
The other one was a more traditional,
merit-based bonus plan,
was they gave the students tests at the beginning of the year
and the end of the year,
and if they got to a certain level,
then the teachers got a bonus.
Then group three got $10,000 at the beginning of the year,
and they told them,
if the students don't reach this test score,
you have to give it back.
And of the three groups,
only group number three actually showed
any improvement in test scores.
So, you know, there's a couple of issues with this study
and I always teach these things with a grain of salt.
You know, there's always a novelty factor.
I don't have time to go into details on that here,
but typically just changing things up,
doing something different will make people react differently.
You can't implement it in a large scale.
I actually tried to do this in my company
and I decided that it was just never gonna work.
But the point remains that giving something to people,
you know, just most people when they see this idea,
of getting a bonus at the start of the year and you have to give it back if you don't
perform. It's very stressful. Even though again financially it's really the same thing
you know if you just put it aside you put it in a box you can make it the same as group
number 2. But people just don't do that. So in a game as a game example if you're doing
a pick up and deliver board game. Just as a little twist on it is you could have your
players get paid in advance. You pick up a contract card and.
it says you get $100 for this card,
but you have to deliver this good in three turns.
If you don't deliver the good in three turns,
you have to give the $100 back.
Same idea as a really basic thing,
but just that little bit of a twist
is gonna change the emotional investment of the players.
Okay.
Need a volunteer.
You, sir.
This is what I'm gonna do.
I have here, because I always travel with dice, I have a red die and I have a white
die.
I'm going to put the red die in one cup and the white die in the other cup.
You have to try to guess.
You're trying to find the red die.
There's no trick here.
I'm just going to mix them up.
If you are correct, you will win $5.
Here we go. So which one would you like to pick?
It's cheating because I can already see.
Oh, you can tell.
Oh, jeez.
I need to get opaque cups.
Okay.
You sure win for me.
Well, I should give you five dollars just for playing the odds.
Okay.
Well,
pick, I think you pick a cup.
Most people when I do this demonstration,
when I use the correct materials,
this backlighting.
What I usually do is I will offer somebody to pick a cup
and they pick a cup and I will say,
okay, if you stick with this cup and it is correct,
I will give you $5, okay?
Or if you want to, you can switch to the other one
and I give them an opportunity to switch to the other cup.
And again, if you switch, you'll win the $5 either way.
Most people, a vast, vast number of people
will not switch away from their initial choice.
So.
The next thing is I will offer $6.
They will win $6 if they switch and they're right,
$5 if they stay, $7, $8, $9.
People don't like to switch their choice.
And this is a concept that's called regret.
And there's been a lot of studies about this
and this specific die in the cup study
used with actual opaque cups.
I'll have to remember that for next time.
They find that when the values are equal, $5 if you stay with your original pick, that
10% of people will switch.
If you triple the value of the offer, if I say $15 if you switch and you're right, $5
if you stay, 50% of people will switch.
And if you go to 10 times, that's when you can get 90% of people to switch.
I was surprised at how high it went on these things, but most people do not like to switch.
So switching to a wrong choice feels three times as bad
as making the wrong choice originally.
And this goes back, you remember in the beginning
I said that the loss feels twice as bad as the gain?
This is one of the studies that kind of feeds into this.
So the old advice that you get on a multiple choice test
to stick with your initial answer, if you pick A,
and later on you have second,
you're second guessing yourself, don't switch.
I really believe that it is mostly
because you don't wanna feel worse.
If you pick A and you switch to C and then A was right,
you're gonna feel worse than if you picked A,
stuck with A and it turned out C was right.
Most people will try to avoid this.
So from...
Okay, we'll come back to that in a second.
Okay, so.
This game I can play with these cups.
So in this case, although I'm not actually going to play it,
I'm going to offer you, what I'm going to do
is I'm going to roll a die.
Well, the game is that a die is going to be rolled,
and you have to decide whether it's even or odd.
That's your pick.
So you have a choice of two different games to play,
one of which we could actually play with this.
One is you make your pick, whether it's even or odd,
and then I roll the die.
Choice B is, I roll the die, I look at it,
I put it under a cup, but I don't tell you what it is,
and then I ask you to make your pick.
So how many people would rather take game A in this example?
And how many people would rather have B?
So again, you guys are pretty much in line.
About 2 thirds of people choose A.
And this is a concept that's called competence.
That's somewhat related to regret.
And the definition of competence is the amount
that you know in proportion to whatever can be known.
And this was originally, these studies and this idea
was put forth by Tversky and Heath,
that's the same Tversky of Kahneman and Tversky.
So in the first example, where I'm just gonna,
you guess and then I roll, you know everything
that there is to know in the world about this problem.
But on the second one, where I roll,
and it's under the cup and it's sitting there,
there's information that exists
that you don't have access to.
So you feel less comfortable making the choice.
So in a game perspective,
a very simple game,
if you have one player that's playing an attack card,
punch or kick,
and another plays playing a defense card,
block, punch, block, kick, okay.
Would you rather play your card first, play your card second?
I haven't actually done this study,
but I'm pretty confident that most people,
from my experience just anecdotally,
are happier playing the card first when
they make a choice like that.
And then the other person will stare them down
and try to figure it out.
But certainly, if you want to put the pressure
on the other person, picking your card first
is going to be an easier choice.
So relating to this is the idea of choice theory.
So giving players too many choices is not a good thing.
And there's been a lot of studies that have shown,
in spite of the number of salad dressings
that are available in the supermarket,
that when your choices get to about more than seven,
people's decision-making ability goes away
and gets much, much worse.
People avoid making a decision
rather than making a wrong one.
There was a study done on 401ks that,
as they presented people with more options
for where they put their investments,
fewer and fewer people participated in the plan.
From a game perspective, this is a game called Struggle of
Empires done by Martin Wallace, which is a really
terrific game for those of you who haven't played it.
But one of the things that Wallace did which wasn't so
great is there's these special ability tiles that you can
select from.
And the very first thing you have to do in the game is you
have to pick one of these tiles as what your special
power is going to be.
And they're all available at the start of the game.
And there's about 30 of them.
And it's a really overwhelming choice.
It's great once you get into the game,
and next time you play it,
and you know what all these options are.
But for new players, it's paralyzing.
You have to go through all of these cards,
and they're basically, you know,
people later posted online, it was like,
look, if you're playing this game,
these are the three that you want to present,
you know, for new players.
Pick one of these three, and then they'll go with it.
Having this many choices, especially for a new player that doesn't understand the context,
was a big mistake and fed right into this concept of regret and loss aversion.
So, the endowment effect is another really interesting offshoot of this.
And the idea of the endowment effect is that when you give something to somebody,
that they ascribe it more value
than if it was just off to the side or they didn't have it.
The classic study that they did on this
is they had participants do something
and just in the beginning of it,
they gave them a mug as a prize for it,
they gave them a candy bar as a prize for it,
and they then at the end of the study
asked people if they wanted to switch to the other prize.
Most people wouldn't switch.
Even if they asked them beforehand,
would you rather have a mug or would you rather have
a candy bar, and they got the one they didn't want.
Once they got that and they had it.
that it was something that they just wanted to stick with.
And this comes up a lot in games.
So before I get to games, let me just talk about this.
So this is the Rifleman's Creed.
I think it's from the Army.
I apologize if I'm wrong on that.
But the idea is that you take an object
and you personify it for the person who has it.
And the endowment effect is something
that happens naturally, but there are techniques
that you can use to emphasize it.
The Rifleman's Creed is one thing that does that.
Another game that does that really effectively
in the video game world is Portal.
In the game Portal,
For those that haven't played it,
there's lots of cubes that are around
that you push onto buttons and stuff like that.
But at one point, you are literally endowed
with a special cube called the companion cube,
which is a cube that has hearts on the side.
And you're told that for the whole level,
you have to carry it through the level.
And then.
you just very immediately naturally get attached
to the level, attached to the cube.
And they do certain tricks, they say certain things
throughout the level to get you more and more
attached to it.
It never says anything, it never does anything,
it just sits there.
But you get this attachment and then at the very end
of the level, famously, you have to,
everyone's played Portal, right, so spoiler.
You have to incinerate the companion cube.
You have to literally take it and throw it
into the incinerator.
And there's stories from the developers
about how people have agonized over this
and have waited, you know, tried to do other things
and see what they could do to avoid it.
And it's just such a great example of a way to take this
and use it as a way to manipulate the player experience
and the emotions that they're feeling.
You know, you could even do this in a board game.
And I don't think board games have really done this,
but you could certainly take, you know,
included in a really cute little stuffed animal
or something that goes to a certain player
for doing something and then other player,
you know, try to take away from it,
take it away from them.
You know, usually those type of tokens or totems
represent the players themselves,
so we tend not to take them away, the really cool stuff.
But there are certainly things that could be done with that.
But you could give your players something,
give them a pet, give them a sidekick,
give them something, and then threaten to take it away.
And that's gonna really up the emotional stakes
because of all of this psychology that we talked about.
OK.
The last thing I'd like to talk about, the last effect
that I'd like to talk about, is called the Endowed Progress
Effect.
This is one of my personal favorites.
So this is a car wash study that was done in 2006.
The team went to a car wash, and they gave half the people
that came to the car wash, they gave them the first ticket,
and said, if you punch it eight times,
you'll get a free car wash.
And the second group, the other half, they gave the second ticket, which had ten punches on it,
but two of them were already punched.
They said if you come back with, you know, the whole thing punched, you get a free car wash.
So both cases, you have to come back to the car wash eight more times.
And what they found was that
the first ticket was redeemed completely 19% of the time,
and the second one almost double that.
Twice as many people completed the second ticket than the first.
They had to do the same amount of effort.
But they were given some progress.
They were given what was called endowed progress.
And it had a very strong psychological effect on people.
People were on a journey already.
And once you're on that journey, you kind of
have to take effort to walk away from it.
But you're already given something,
and you're worried that you're going to lose it.
So it ties into all of that psychology.
So there's a board game actually that uses this
pretty famously, although I'm not sure
if he was really intended to,
but in the Settlers of Catan, or Catan,
I guess it's called now, I will never get used to that,
but you have to get 10 victory points to win
and the players start with two victory points.
So this is exactly the same case as the second
car wash coupon where you got to get 10 points, but you've got your first 2
punches. So you're already on the road to success.
Um, the cells of Catan actually came out before the car wash study was done,
obviously. So I'm sure that it wasn't influenced by that,
but I think it's really interesting to, uh, to, to,
to see the way that the players were already moved down the road. You know,
it would have been easy to say you have to get eight additional points or had a
little scoring track or something like that, but that's not what the game does.
The game says you got to get 10 points, but everybody starts at two.
So again, all of these things come out
of this concept of loss aversion.
And over the years, I've learned more and more about,
learned about these different psychologies
and it's just fascinating how it always comes back
to that basic idea that losing stuff feels bad
and feels worse than getting it does in the first place.
So framing, regret, the endowment effects,
all of this stuff comes into play.
It's a really, you know, when you're aware of it,
it's both interesting in your own life
when you see how it's affecting you
and things that you can do,
but also in terms of game design of using it
really as a tool, as a scalpel to push the players
into the emotional state that you're looking for them
to experience.
So that's all I have prepared.
Thank you very much.
And be happy to take any questions.
I think there's two microphones,
if anybody has any questions.
Yes.
So I feel like I'm the only person ever
who didn't get attached to the companion Cuban portal.
No, you're, yeah.
And just to kind of keep it in the...
the sort of the universe of what you've been talking about.
I feel like the reason that I didn't
is because the game up until that point,
I more felt like the game was framing
what I was doing as a relationship with GLaDOS
more than the companion cube.
And so this was like an instance of
kind of a point in that relationship.
So I guess if I were to take that
and turn it into a question, I would say,
what do you think about like,
how can framing kind of backfire, I guess?
Well, first off, I will say that my niece,
who's a lot younger than my kids,
came over about a year ago,
and my kids insisted on playing Portal with her,
and she like immediately took the companion cube
and threw it in the fire,
and they were, my kids were horrified.
I'd say, how could you do that?
And felt that she immediately needed
to be sent for some sort of psychological counseling.
But the key is to draw the line between,
you don't want to see the wizard behind,
the man behind the curtain.
You want to do it in a way that's subtle.
And if people start to feel that they're being manipulated,
they're going to push back against it.
And that's why, even at the beginning of this talk,
and I talk about this, just go with your gut.
Don't try to outthink it.
I think if people are doing that or in a different place
in a mindset, then you can have a problem.
So you want to use the tools,
I think you want to use them sparingly.
And you can get into a situation, yeah,
where people backfire.
We didn't talk about it a little bit,
but even there's a lot of techniques like this
that are used in free-to-play games or freemium-type games
where you're trying to get people to buy other stuff.
And if it's done in a real heavy-handed way,
it's gonna turn people off.
Yeah.
I guess this is related to loss aversion for often
like oblique multiplayer games where you may be adversarial
towards other players, but that may just be optional
and perhaps not.
When you can attribute the loss of something you care about
to the game itself, that's a fairly neutral feeling.
There's no villain there necessarily,
unless the game has an antagonist,
which is a non-player character.
When you're playing a multiplayer game
and perhaps sometimes you're...
you're attempting to avert loss tied to another player
or attempting to be the reason that someone else loses
something, this is something that I'm
interested to explore.
Have you done any studies which involve averting loss player
to player versus player to game?
I think that to a certain extent, I haven't specifically studied that or looked at that.
My initial instinct is that yeah, I mean there certainly is, like if you look at Monopoly
or there's plenty of games where players are taking stuff away from other players and that's
really the objective of the game.
And I think that it triggers this stuff, but I think if it's from...
from a systemic way, if it's done from the point of view of the game,
I think it can be a little bit more intimidating.
Almost like walking into a casino and there's this, you know,
you're playing against the house is different than if you're at a poker table
and you're playing against another player.
So I think the idea of authority also kind of factors into it in some sense.
But I think that it's...
So I think that you want to have the,
I think having the game do it is more effective
than having other players do it.
I think that the game telling you to take a card
and tear it up is perhaps more, I don't know, maybe not,
more effective than having another player
is allowed to reach into your hand
and pull out a card and rip it up.
It depends on the reaction.
Yeah, it depends on your relationship with your friends.
But, you know, I think that they,
there's a little bit of a subtle distinction there
in terms of how they trigger things.
Hi. With the card game example, you mentioned how there's cards that kind of have a negative
reaction, even though gameplay-wise they might be more beneficial than some other options.
And many people who play a lot of card games will actually kind of internalize those, you
know, it doesn't matter how many cards you pitch, it only matters about the cards you
need to win, et cetera, et cetera. Do you find that people who get into that mindset
typically only have that affect those particular situations with those card games or do you
find that they also...
in other risk aversion situations have maybe a lower threshold there.
I think first off, you can totally be habituated
away from loss aversion.
And there's tons of studies that have been done
like on stockbrokers, and maybe initially when they start,
you know, like the casual person that's buying
and selling stock will have an issue with, you know,
holding on for stock for too long
to avoid the loss aversion and the loss of selling the stock.
But with a stockbroker, they start out
with a little bit of loss aversion,
but if you just do it day in and day out
and day in and day out,
you get over it. The tracking example in Hearthstone, you know,
once you play the game a lot, you,
you get past that and you see the utility of the card. Um,
I am not aware of any studies specifically that says if,
you know,
if you're a stockbroker and you're used to doing this and you transplant into a
different environment about whether that goes with you, um, I would.
With no real evidence, I would speculate that it probably does, to a certain extent.
But the first part is you can definitely, you know, you will be habituated out of law
subversion if you're paying attention to it or doing it over and over again.
Hi, oh, sorry, yeah, that's quite high.
So I was just gonna ask, a lot of what you talked about
and the studies that you referenced
focus on specific sort of small scale choices
within a larger whole.
So you know, like the level draining being a mechanic
within, you know, obviously a wider game.
So I was wondering how you feel loss aversion applies.
across perhaps a game as a whole?
So the time investment or the sense of loss if you didn't,
you know, accumulate your victory points before everybody else or,
you know, that level?
I'm sorry, I'm not sure I totally understand the question.
You mean like on a, that the whole game
is kind of built around that?
Yeah, because it seemed like everything
that was mentioned in the talk
was about the specific steps within the whole.
Yeah.
But I was wondering whether there was kind of a broader
loss aversion that applies once all of these things
are folded in and it gets more complicated or more woolly.
Yeah, I mean, I think that you can certainly
take aspects of this and, you know, loss aversion
you know, perhaps, you know, at its sharpest is going to be,
you know, that critical pivot point in a game
or an experience, whether it's throwing away the companion cube
or Floyd the robot in Planetfall, where, you know,
you lose a companion or something like that
and you feel the loss immediately.
But, you know, I think you could,
and there have been some games like Brothers and others
that try to take that concept of loss and explore it.
But you have to go through that setup phase to tweak it
and then go from there.
OK, cool.
Thank you.
Sure.
Hi.
Going back to your example with the $3,000 against the $4,000,
I was wondering if we modified the $4,000 option so that even
with a lower expected value, or a higher expected value,
if the
Instead of getting nothing the partial time you just get less
so if it was
$1,000 and
5,000 as the two possible outcomes against the short 3,000 if it would be different and I don't know if yeah
I think that's a really interesting point. I you know nothing
Zero, there's some numbers that are really just go off
into different areas of people's brains
and nothing is one of them.
100% is something, you know, or like, you know,
so if I tell you that there's a 100% chance
that something's gonna happen versus a 99.99% chance
something's gonna happen, you don't focus on the fact
that it's 99.999%, you focus on the fact
that there's a chance that it may not happen.
and then you're really going to get hosed.
So, you know, 100% a guaranteed sure thing
is a totally different kind of part of your brain.
So, and it's the same thing with zero dollars.
And you even see that at, you know,
at trade shows and stuff like that.
You know, just yesterday over in the other hall,
this booth was giving away ViewMasters.
the little 3D ViewMaster clicky things.
I don't need a ViewMaster, but I got it
because it was there on the table, it was free.
If they turned to penny for the ViewMaster,
I never would have gotten it, but I stood on line,
I would talk to the guy, I wanted the ViewMaster
because it was free.
So I think, yeah, I mean, having,
there's certain things that are treated in a very,
free is different than a penny.
And 99.999 is different than 100.
And you can use that as part of the manipulation, sure.
Thank you.
Hi.
I was just wondering if you have any reading recommendations
about incorporating this either into games
or even just broader behavioral psychology.
Yeah, I mean, the best book on this
is written by Kahneman a couple of years ago called
Thinking, Fast and Slow.
I can't recommend that book highly enough.
It covers a lot of this territory
and goes even into deeper types of stuff.
He talks about endings, which is really just a whole other talk.
where he talks about colonoscopies and how that applies
to whether you enjoy an experience or not,
which is a whole other game development talk.
Spoiler alert, the ending is really, really important.
So yeah, I would definitely recommend that book,
Thinking Fast and Slow.
Thanks a lot. Sure.
Yeah.
Hi.
I was curious, when you were talking about the example of, say, the companion cube and
giving the player something and then taking it away, what is, or do you have any ideas
or studies about, like, the effect of then giving that back to the player, essentially?
Like, if the companion cube, for example, showed up, like, three levels later, what
would the emotional effect be on the player?
You want the Hollywood ending from...
when dramatically a singed companion cube
comes into the last scene of the game as it's brought back.
Yeah, I mean, I think that there's
certain expectations in movies and storytelling in general
that a lot of times that sometimes
those characters come back.
And that's used to varying effects in different genres.
You know, in the movies, I guess Obi-Wan comes back again
at the end of episode six as a ghost,
but at least he's there and stuff like that.
I think it may give the player a little bit
of a sense of completeness,
but I don't think it's really necessary to get the effect.
You know, they should have no expectation
that it's gonna come back,
and you should really convince them
that they're really gone,
otherwise it kinda cheapens the effect
if they think they could get it back.
that's a different situation because you've lost something but I have a method of getting it back.
Okay, thank you.
Hi, so you started your talk with the example of kind of making a bet on
a 50-50 chance, right, with the coin toss.
I'm interested in lots of multiplayer games now, you know, there is the concept of a zero-sum
scenario where you're betting something against your opponent.
And I'm wondering if you look, for instance, at the trophy mechanic in Clash Royale.
right, where if you win you gain certain amount of trophies and if you lose it actually takes
them away from you. Now that's not, it's not always the same number. Using your understanding
of kind of loss aversion and how to, you know, optimize the player psychology through this
process, I'm wondering if you have any kind of view on how to design such a trophy system
in that way, in terms of what you take away and what you give. Yeah, I think that
I'm not familiar with Clash Royale,
but there's a similar thing.
I showed the Hearthstone example,
and I think that Blizzard did a really nice job
with their ranked system in Hearthstone
with a couple of tricks to do that.
Where first off, there's the win streak mechanic.
So if you win a couple games in a row, you get bonus stars.
And the other thing is that also when you lose stars,
there's when you go up a level in in hearthstone there's when you go when you
get to level four or I've never made it to level of rank four but for me rank
19 when you're at rank 19 and you go to 18 if you lose immediately after getting
to 18 you stay at 18 there's like a weird little half level thing inside
there so from 19 you go up to like 18 and then you go down like 18 0 and if
you lose again you you go you drop down to the same step under 19
So I think that in that case, they also try to soften the blow because they're trying to be friendlier,
they want people to do it and gradually, you know, with the win streak thing, you'll, you know,
if you play long enough and you're, it's a coin flip over and over again,
eventually you'll get enough win streaks to advance through the ranks.
So, yeah, I think there's definitely manipulations that you can do in there to try to keep the,
you know, keep the players engaged and not get too discouraged.
We've got about two minutes left, so I guess we can get these last two questions in.
Yeah, really quick.
So for the cube in Portals, for example, the way it was described, almost as if it was
like a good design for the game, actually make the game better.
And in the talk, it seemed a lot about when you take something away, it hurts more, and
when you give it, it's not worth as much, so like the net gain being negative and not.
When is it a good game design idea to actually...
do the mechanic of giving something and taking it away?
And would you ever do it with real money?
Ha!
Um...
Real money games.
Sure there's games that do it with real money, but yeah.
Uh...
I think it depends on the effect that you're looking for in the player.
Like I said, when I was doing, um, a family game...
of which was pick crew is aimed at younger kids. I didn't want to do that. I specifically
soften the edges so that other people are getting instead of them losing. I don't want
to take things away from them. But if you want that emotional beat, if you're trying
to get that emotional state and give the experience to the players of, you know, this is, you
know, that that's kind of a point in portal where it's just really obvious that.
something weird is going on with this computer.
In the beginning, the computer is your friend
to steal a line from paranoia,
and then you gradually get the feeling
that things are not what they seem.
And so it's an important.
point to get across really clearly that hey, you know, this is not something that's looking
out for your best interest. So I think that that's why it's important in that. Interestingly,
the developers, the reason that they kind of did it, it wasn't, although it wasn't initially
as an emotional thing, they just, the problem initially they had was players kept forgetting
to bring the cube with them. And they would get into all these weird spots and they just,
they were looking for a way to.
get the players to remember to get the cube.
So they put the hearts on it,
and first they had the computer say,
make sure you remember,
and periodically to the level say, make sure you remember.
And they just kept ramping it up
until they crossed this threshold
where it stopped just being reminders
and created a true emotional attachment to it.
Thank you.
So I've been thinking a lot about the relationship between player loss aversion and wanting to
reward players and give them reward mechanics.
There's a free to play game that has a reward wheel, and so it's like, hey, every day if
you come and play, you can get a reward.
and most of the things in the reward wheel are tiny
and some of them are really awesome,
so you keep coming back to want to spin the wheel
to get the awesome thing,
but they kind of mess it up
because they give everybody an equal slot,
size on the wheel.
But the wheel's rigged.
Like, clearly you don't have a one in six chance
of winning the awesome thing.
And in fact, that's telegraphed by the fact
that you spin the wheel and it will like zoom past
the expensive thing and then slow down and stop.
And so it rotates in this way that makes it really obvious,
I don't think on purpose, to the player
that they're being messed with.
And so even though I only get a benefit from spinning the wheel every day, it's my least favorite part of the game.
There's a bunch of other really good mechanics.
So I'm experiencing loss aversion for something that I don't even have
because I have the perceived value being equal because of the way it's represented
and then I'm having that taken away because I know better.
They could have fixed that by either giving the more expensive things a smaller slot
so that I perceive my chances smaller.
or by really hiding the fact that it can't come up so that I just feel unlucky.
I mean, I would hate that less than knowing that I'm being manipulated in the way that it does.
That's a little harder in board games because you can't hide it as well, right?
Like, you can't have a wheel that spins that actually calculates where it's going to end up
and then gives an even spin and makes it feel natural.
If you want to reward players with a variable reward in a board game,
how would you do it without making them feel bad?
It's a lot harder to do because, like you say,
the problem with a board game is everything is there.
And even in a legacy game, you know the packets are available
and what you need to do to get there.
So there's not really true, true, totally hidden content.
So it is challenging to do.
I'm not sure off the top of my head of how you would do it.
you know, that other mechanic you're talking about
is interesting, in fact, slot machines,
I had a slot machine designer on our podcast
a couple months ago, and we talked about this,
and they map on the video slots, you know,
they decide what the final thing is gonna be at the end.
Before everything starts animating.
And they specifically program in the near miss.
They program in so that right off the line that scores,
you see the winning thing,
which is a very powerful psychological ploy,
which actually starting to get outlawed now.
There's some jurisdictions are not allowed
to do that in slot machines.
So yeah, there's ways to do that
that are better than others
that won't piss off the players.
If there's any other questions,
I will be around afterwards,
but thank you so much for your attention.
Really appreciate it.