Hi all, and welcome to our talk about the music for Ghost of Tsushima.
I'm Peter Scaturro, one of the score producers, and I'll be taking you through the process
of creating the score for this game.
We'll also hear from two other leads on the project, Bill Hempstapat, who is going to
cover the details that went into the musical arrangement choices, and you'll also hear
Andrew Barash, who will cover the development of the music
system.
This was a big production for our team.
And at times, this felt like as epic a journey
as our lead character, Jin Sakai.
We recorded on three different continents.
We had two composers, had some unplanned last minute recording
needs, and made some interesting advancements in the open world
music system.
So excited to get into all of this, these topics and show also how the recording,
editing and implementation of the music.
are related. So let's get into this the way that most all of our projects start, and that is with
a kickoff meeting with the developer. So in this case, that was done, of course, with Sucker Punch.
So a lot of good information we got during our initial meeting with them,
and this is where the creative leads there. So Nate Fox and also Jason Connell.
and Brad Meyer.
They gave us what was a really inspiring presentation,
and we covered the plot of the story.
And for those of you who may have not played the game,
it's about the Mongol invasion of Tsushima.
So this happened in the, I believe the 13th century,
and there's some historical basis for this.
What happens is the Mongols invade Tsushima
and the island is being run by 80 samurai there.
They all get slaughtered except for one of them.
And that one that survived is our hero, Jin Sakai.
And during the story, Jin goes through a struggle and some transformation.
He's got a conflict and the conflict is this.
He's struggling to adhere to his samurai code.
And his samurai code is a way of fighting or way of engaging enemies.
That was he was taught by his surrogate father, Lord Shimura.
But in order to be able to defend the island
and also protect his people, he devised,
he developed some other fighting techniques along the way
that are considered dishonorable.
Now, we also find out that Lord Shimura has survived as well
and has been taken captive.
And that kind of sets up the story.
So a lot of emotional stuff in there.
And that was a great takeaway for us to know that.
The other thing that we learned during this meeting
was what the look of the game and what the environment was,
how that was going to appear.
So you can see from some of the pictures that are in the slide here the world is absolutely gorgeous and for those of you who play the game you know this, and a lot of detail or time went into the detail of how these environments
look.
They're really stunning.
They also have a bit of a stylized look to them,
which was something that kind of stuck in our brain as well.
And we just thought, hmm, well, based on this look,
what would be the right music for this?
Circle Punch also came to this meeting
with some ideas about what they wanted from the score.
and what style they were aiming for.
They, of course, wanted something
that is going to reflect the time and place,
and that is feudal Japan.
So we immediately knew that this was
going to be a score that is going
to have quite a lot of Japanese influence,
particularly Japanese solo instruments and all the things
that are idiosyncratic about that.
Um, we, uh, also knew that, uh, or, or they, they let us know that they wanted
the score to, um, for the most part, be very minimalist and be very sparse at
times.
And they were, uh, not afraid of that at all.
In fact, they, they were really looking for that kind of execution from the music.
Now, we also knew from the story though, that there's going to be some emotional
moments, there's some big battle scenes and all of that.
So we wanted to, of course, have music that's going to.
support that epic portion of the story.
So armed with all of this, we got
on to what the next phase of our work is,
and that's to look for a composer,
or in this case composers, that would
be right for this project.
Initially, we talked to Shigeru Umebayashi, or Ume,
how he likes to be.
known. Now, Ume seemed like an obvious choice for us at the time.
And that's just based on his impressive body of work and his
experience with both Japanese and Chinese films.
Ume wrote some really, really beautiful music for Ghost.
We eventually settled on five fairly lengthy pieces
that he delivered to us and they had various moods.
We call them the Tsushima Suites
and you can hear them on the soundtrack.
They're really gorgeous.
Now this music you can really hear
when you're exploring the island.
So if you're just walking around and you wanna
just enjoy the environment there.
A lot of times what you're going to hear
is Ume's music is going to come up
and he did just an outstanding job
of giving us a sound for Tsushima.
We also, well, there's some of Ume's films.
We also reached out to Ilan Eskeri,
and we had, while Ume wrote some beautiful music for us
for the island, we also knew that we needed
some character themes and we also needed some combat music.
And Ilan, for the most part,
wound up taking charge of that territory.
He is known for his score to 47 Ronin,
which convinced us that he has some experience
with Japanese instruments, so he knows about that.
He is just a terrific melodic composer
and he really captured the Jin's inner conflict
and his struggles with Lord Shimura.
So.
You can also hear those themes on the soundtrack.
One of the things that really stood out to us about Alain
when we were doing this composer search
was this indie film that he wrote the score to,
and it's Coriolanus.
And it really has very little to do
with this particular project except for one aspect of it.
And that is that it has a minimalist sound.
It's very sparse, but also has a very stylized sound to it.
It's like when you're listening to the score,
the percussion in particular, it just sounds very arresting.
It feels like it's just coming off
of the edge of the speakers.
And.
It just, it's got that, I don't know, just sort of catches your ear in a very interesting way.
And we thought if we could take some of that sensibility and use that in the production of
the music for Ghost that we would have something that would reflect the environment of the game,
and of course, you know, support the story and support the setting.
After getting the composers on board, we set out to create a
recording plan for this. And as I mentioned earlier, we recorded
on three continents. Initially, we went to London and the UK.
This is a place that we're accustomed to recording.
We use the studios there a lot.
The orchestral musicians are absolutely fantastic in London.
And the studios are brilliant.
The engineering staff is familiar with some
of the technical requirements that we have for video game
production.
So we went there initially for the orchestral recording.
Air Studios, some of you might be familiar with that
if you recorded in London, it's just a brilliant location.
Converted Church, here are some pictures
of the control room.
I'm sorry, the recording room.
This is in the hall.
And you can clearly see here from the inside
that this is a converted church.
It has a really interesting sound to it.
It's reverberant, but it kind of has this sparkle to it.
It really lives up to its name, air.
and it just a very, very, very pleasant sound inside the hall,
especially when you've got a full string section
and brass section playing.
Here is a view of inside the control room there.
You can see Ume sort of center stage.
We also recorded at Abbey Road, which
is one of the other really.
well-known famous studios that's in London.
And I believe there was a week,
this was probably fall of 2019,
where we were recording with Umeh at Ayer
and simultaneously we were recording
at Abbey Road with Elan.
So that was just sort of an exciting thing for us
to have all of that action happening at once.
Here's another photo.
This is from one of the other studios,
a smaller rooms at Aire.
This is a Taiko ensemble that we recorded there.
These are some Japanese musicians,
obviously living in London.
and a lot of this particular ensemble,
which was a three-person ensemble we used
for a lot of the combat music.
Now, one of the things that,
you know, at the same time that we're recording this,
we're of course, you know, learning things
during our journey about Japanese music
and about, in this particular case,
learning about taiko ensembles.
So we wanted to have the sound of a larger ensemble.
You know, there's just something about that,
that you can't achieve by doing individual overdubs.
So we decided to look into recording in Japan.
And this was one of the reasons that we wound up.
recording globally was that we felt like we needed to go to Japan and we needed to go to the source and find a taiko ensemble that we thought would be reflective of the really, really big parts of the game, most of the battles.
So while we were there, we also recorded some Japanese soloists there playing some Japanese instruments.
and some of the performances there were absolutely incredible and really made the score.
This is Oyama-san playing the shamisen, which is a like a, as you can see, kind of like a
Japanese sort of guitar sounds a little bit like a banjo. It's
got its own unique sound though, and you you know it when you
hear it. This is Sogawa-san, who was just a master shakuhachi
player and just could not play a bad note. It was just absolutely
thrilling just to hear him play. He was he was incredible. This
is Yomada-san, who played the koto and also the bass koto.
And again, all of these masters at Japanese instruments.
We also had a scene in the game where it was a funeral scene.
And we wanted to have some monks singing
during this funeral scene.
So we
We're very lucky to have these two monks
who did some chanting for us.
They were actually from a Buddhist sect called Ichiren.
And there's historically, this sect actually connects
to the place in Japan where the Mongols originally invaded.
So it was interesting to get.
you know, that kind of level of authenticity there.
So really, really happy and delighted about that.
This is a Taiko ensemble, as I mentioned,
that we had, this was an eight-person ensemble,
and the sound in the studio for this was really thunderous
and really, really terrific,
really like kind of captured that power.
that you hear in a lot of Japanese music
or that use a taiko ensemble of this size.
So that's just a little bit about the recording process
and what we did.
I wanna hand it over now to Bill
and he's gonna do a deeper dive
into some of the creative and technical arranging
that we did and how that relates to our music system.
So over to you, Bill.
Cool. Thank you so much, Pete. Hi, everyone. My name is Bill. Thank you for watching this video today.
Now that we've talked about how the music was created and Pete gave a really great run-through
of our recording process and it was really actually one of my once-in-a-lifetime
experience that I got to be a part of those recordings. Definitely something that I won't
forget anytime soon. But now that we've talked about that, let's look at in general what
we have to do with them afterwards.
As an arranger of the project, I'm mostly going to focus on the creative and technical arranging
aspect of it, and I will elaborate as to why I have to be so specific to call out the creative
and technical terms separately. We'll understand that soon. But there's a huge bulk of work that
our team, myself and a few other folks on our team, that is kind of the bread and butter of
what we do. And there's a big bulk of work here that we do before the music even gets
implemented into the game.
But first, let's explain a little bit about where somebody like myself kind of sits into
the production here.
As you can see, I'm kind of slotted somewhere in the middle of music production and implementation
and testing.
The role that I play is to kind of act as a bridge between the composers of the game
and the game itself, making sure to adapt what's written and recorded and making sure that to see
the composer's vision through in the game. But at the same time, the reverse is always
is also true as well, where I'm constantly coordinating backwards about the feedback
from our early implementation and the prototypes.
which help inform what needs to get produced and recorded further. This is very important actually,
especially in creating systemic music. We had designed this system and directed a composer
to write a specific way, and then we put that in the game and realized that, oh, it's not working
quite as well as we thought it should. What do we do then? The music's already written and recorded.
But while this is kind of...
what game development is. There's a lot of iterative process and a lot of iterations.
It's bound to happen, but really it's how we tackle the iteration process that's really
key to success here. And we'll talk about that specifically in this talk.
Alright, so first off, let's actually talk about the three main pillars of the experience that
makes up Ghost of Tsushima as a whole. And I think more specifically, we want to focus on
the golden path, which is what we call for like the critical path storyline, essentially.
and it's okay by the way if you're not getting the picture right away there are some examples that
will come in after this but i just want to walk through these and then we'll explain more of them
as we go. So first off is the cinematics and a lot of people call these cut scenes right there
these are very non-linear it plays like a film from top to bottom and our main approach here
like what Pete said earlier is there
We tried to execute Sucker Punch's brief on creating a minimalistic Japanese aesthetic
as well as providing some epic story moment. And this is something that we want to infuse
into every part of it, but cinematics are one part that where I think we did this very well.
The second approach that we took was using a little bit of a free tempo approach that's
inspired by traditional Japanese music.
In traditional Japanese music, from my study and my interest in it that I find, there is this
play of fluctuation of time and space that is very much a part of their music. And this also includes
using silence as a musical device as well. So we had really incorporated that into the level
that is even more macro than that.
and that is picking where not to play music. And this has become equally as critical to use
as a device to set up big epic moments is to have moments without music that come before that.
The next pillar is the custom gameplay arrangements. And these are kind of being
talked about internally for us as kind of semi non-linear moments.
And with this, it's kind of like players have control, but you're not actively going outside
of this mission. There's not kind of this free agency that you could go do anything anywhere.
It's somewhat a little bit on rails, like you're in the middle of this big battle or a duel or
something like that. So these things will, like I said, will include special combat scenarios,
duels, and then
special singers, which in this case is something like, oh, you see a house getting burned down
and we want to play some reaction music to that. And there's kind of a framework for these things
and we want to make something that's tailored to that experience.
And lastly, we have the systemic music. And this is one of the most important
experiences in Ghost of Tsushima. Since this is an open world game,
there's a lot of things that are happening systemically with a large degree of variables,
like the player's progression, strength, and play style.
So now we're talking about a true non-linear experience.
and this includes the Music Encounter System, which Andrew is going to touch upon. This is
one of the very deep subjects of this. The Music Encounter System takes care of how we score combat
in Ghost of Tsushima, and combat is a really large part of Ghost of Tsushima.
Next up, we also have the Exploration Mood System, and this is something that
the players will hear as they walk through the game and this is something that we spent a lot
of time on as well to make sure that throughout the 30 hours to even 60 hours of experience that
you would never get tired of what this is. We'll show you some examples for this.
And lastly are just little stingers that are specifically tied to mechanics in the game like
the fox shrines, the haiku mechanics, the onsen, the shrine pillars of honors, and stuff like that.
So we won't dive into every little stinger today, but just know that this is something
that we use to score the game as well. So first off,
what's one of the most important thing that we need to get right away in order to execute all
those three main pillars? And the first thing is some really wide stemming. And this is partly why
I attended all the recording sessions.
because we not only want to split as many instruments as we could, but we also want to
make it make sense musically. For example, if the strings are playing something in unison
and they sound really good and big together, they should play together by all means. It's not that
like, oh violins have to be split, violas have to be split. This is split musically by the musical
devices that they play and the different colors that we have in the score.
As you can see in red there's some taiko there, in blue there is some Japanese soloist instruments,
and in green and yellow there we have orchestras, strings and brass there.
But if you look closely at the bottom, there are stems that are muted. There's actually a label
here that is too small you can't see, but it's actually called the additional soloist stem.
So what are these really?
Let's talk about that for a little bit.
And this is the last continent of recording that we did,
actually, which is in our home soil in the US
and completes the three continental recording thing.
So first of all, why did that need to be done?
Like I said earlier, the iterative process
and how we tackle the iteration is very important.
As we played the game, we realized that the game is way bigger than we thought. There's more content
and with the player's free agency to go do anything, you end up spending more time in
the game in general, which is a great thing. But we find that systemically,
it's getting tiring after a while. We don't have enough content to provide
variety in the music, especially in the Japanese instruments.
Next thing is also that the game's minimalistic approach also means that the orchestra has to be used sparingly.
And we'll show the example of this in a second, but essentially if we use the orchestra all the time, it becomes a wall of sound and noise at some point.
So because we pick and choose our moments, we ended up using more Japanese soloists than the orchestras, and that means we run out of content really quickly.
Now how we tackled that was we needed to get this done kind of quickly and in very specific ways
because we were running against the deadline and we really needed to do something functional so we
couldn't go really go back to Japan again. So we utilized first and second generation
Japanese talents in Los Angeles and that is Kozue Matsumoto on Kodo, Ko Umezaki on Shakuhachi,
Shoji Kamada on Taiko and then not Japanese but Mike Penney is a shamisen player who's
competed in Japan, become one of the very few non-Japanese to have won shamisen competitions
over there. He's very much involved within that community, can speak Japanese as well.
And lastly we have a solo cello recording as well. And if you can see this group really quickly,
you're starting to see like a really functional quintet, almost like a band that can kind of play
their own music. And with this, I have decided that we're going to build upon existing pieces
of music. And by existing pieces of music, this is specifically Ilan Eshgeri's combat music.
We know what we're missing now from playtesting the music in the game, and we've done a few
iterations of the implementation, tried different ways, and we know now that what kind of content
was missing, which is that kind of the medium intensity level of combat, where like we can go
really light, we can go really big with the orchestra, but what's going to be there in the
middle? And with this, we employ kind of the combination of written parts of improvisation.
By written parts I mean that we might be literally doubling the orchestral parts of this quintet
and at the same time making kind of almost like an alternate arrangement instead of playing the
full orchestra. We'll now play using this small five-piece band that we put together to play
and execute that arrangement.
And that with some improvisation, we've really provided even more Japanese colors
that can play with the track or play on its own as well.
So with this, we came up with a very target recording plans. There are some parts that
are written. There are some free form improvisation that's set to be played
with a certain track. Let's look at how the recording went down. Here's Ko.
Kozue and then Mike Penny. We did it all here at PlayStation Studios. We brought them in and then
each of them spent a day with us. And then we also went to Capitol Studios in Hollywood to
record some Taikos. We ended up using a lot of this for Legends Mode, which is
the multiplayer expansion that came out a few months after the game released.
Alright, now that you've heard a lot and seen a lot of wall of text and a lot of what I did,
let's actually hear what I did. So first example here is I want to play
a minimalistic scoring cinematic that I've been talking about, about how we're saving the
orchestra and we have just very few Japanese instruments. We use a free time approach and
we use some silence to create some tension. Let's see what this sounds like.
That's really great.
You can see that with so little, they're probably only like
five, six musical gestures in there. Here's some shakuhachi, some koto. But with so little,
we can create so much tension and focus as well as immersing the players in the Japanese aesthetic.
This is something that we used a lot throughout the game. But now let's look at the stark contrast
of that.
Here we have a scene, a very important story moment where Jin is announcing that he's embracing and fully becoming the ghost rather than being adopted as Shimura-san
And this is one of the really bigger moments where we've used the orchestras to really give some weight to the scene and make it even more gut-wrenching than it was. Let's hear that.
Renounce the ghost.
You must blame her for this outrage.
Tell them you are Jin Xingru, loyal servant to the Shogun.
My heir.
My son.
I am not your son.
I am the ghost.
And you will be judged for it.
Find the Khan.
Taka go
You can just see how much weight the orchestra can actually give a scene like this and what a stark contrast it is to a previous scene and how effective it is to not hear this so often but when it comes in you really do feel that this story moment is very special.
And a lot of the game...
is this balancing act between having the minimalistic Japanese aesthetic, just like how
the Sucker Punch brief came to us, as well as having an epic grand tale of the samurai story
that is very emotional to the player. Now up next is some custom arrangements and this is
really interesting because
It's utilizing the additional soloists that we talked about earlier.
Here in this Ronin duo, you will hear Ilan's combat music, but arranged slightly differently,
where we have thinned down the taiko to use a smaller taiko.
as well as instead of using the orchestra we use the solo cello to play the ostinato groove along
with the shamisen and the shakuhachi peppering on top and the special thing about this is you can
hear mike penney shredding on the shamisen which we did not plan for when we were recording but
he was just kind of playing during one of the breaks and we were just like let's record that
and this became this ronin duo here let's watch that
Ryuzo's stories don't do you justice.
They never did.
If you play the game, you notice that this is somewhat like you hear something that's kind of
familiar because you've heard this combat music elsewhere in your normal combat with the mongol,
but because of this different custom arrangement, it has really made this duo have a life of its own
and really feel special to the player. Now lastly, I want to give a little bit of an intro on the
systemic music before I hand it over to Andrew. And this is
the exploration mood system that I was talking about earlier, but the exploration itself,
it is one state out of the many states of our much larger open world system. But I will be
focusing on just the exploration part for now, and then like I said, Andrew will take us through the rest.
So we've gone through a lot of iterations of how do we want the players to feel if they're just
walking in exploration mode and explore the world. There's got to be a little bit of
this tranquility and serenity of the Tsushima Island, but as well as immersing you in this
Japanese samurai fantasy, making you really feel like you're in feudal Japan. Again, just trying to
execute a sucker punch's brief.
So what we came up with was kind of these multiple playlists of short musical segments that will play
depending on your location, time of day, and progression. Let's actually just look
go ahead and look at this video which will help demonstrate this even further.
you
You can hear there there's kind of these paddy strings that have been time stretched and have
been processed with reverb in such a way that they sound like their own thing, then peppered in with
some Japanese soloists like what we recorded earlier with the additional soloist stems, and then
with the variety of the states we have, you could walk around in this world for 30 hours, 60 hours,
and you'll never get tired of this exploration music. It's really become one of the things I
personally really enjoy playing the game, just to hear this explore music. And that wraps up my
section of it. Like I said, this is a much bigger system, and the next up part of it, which is
what we call the Music Encounter System, will be touched upon by Andrew Buresh.
Thanks, Bill. So we've heard a little bit about how the music for Ghost of Tsushima was conceived and recorded.
We've heard about, you know, some of the cool custom arrangements that we put together for some of the story-based content in the game.
But what about the open world? Ghost of Tsushima is an open world game after all.
And while we would like to go through and hand score every single encounter you can possibly get into in the game, you just can't do it.
There's not enough hours in the in the world to to do that.
So we need to build a system.
that can understand what's happening at any point in the game
and scale the music appropriately for the action that's on screen.
So for Ghost of Tsushima, we call that system the Music Encounter System.
It's on by default. It can be overridden when necessary.
And it's responsible for scoring the bulk of the open world experiences
you're having in the game and even a lot of the story based experiences as well.
So how does this system work?
Well, it consists of a number of different states.
These states are changed based on a couple of different criteria
from the game, namely the distance between Jin
and any nearby enemies and the awareness
states of those enemies.
Now, looking at this flowchart on screen,
if we read it from left to right.
Explorer would be the least intense music in the system.
Combat would be the most intense.
And as you go from left and right through the flow chart,
the music increases in intensity on the way to combat.
Each of these states has a playlist associated with it in Wwise, and each playlist consists
of a number of chunks, what we call musical chunks, that can be played back in any order
and are edited in a way to where that can play seamlessly without you ever knowing and
we can get these variety of arrangements as we hear the music playback in game.
And this is super important because we only have four Music Encounter System cues that were written
for the game, and we need to make sure that we have enough variety in here along with the help
of the soloist material that Bill was talking about earlier, so we're not hearing things
repeating too often and that the player isn't getting bored of what they're hearing in the
background.
So let's walk through these states here one by one.
The first state is explore.
Bill touched on this earlier.
It's the default state of the system.
It's what plays when you're just exploring
around the island unencumbered by any enemy encounters.
The next state approach is our first state that's
changed based on distance.
So if any enemy comes within 50 meters of Jin, we'll change to approach.
And we don't play any specific music in approach. It's really more of a buffer state
between Explorer and the more combat-oriented states in the system.
Any Explorer music that was playing will allow to play out.
And maybe more importantly, we make sure no new Explorer music starts playing.
This fixes a problem I've wrestled with on previous systems I've built for other games.
where we know we're near some enemy encounter,
but not close enough to trigger the music for that encounter.
And just as you're about to enter,
this beautiful piece of Explorer music starts playing.
And just as it's welling up, it gets
interrupted by the combat music.
And I just wanted a way to control that from happening.
So we implemented this approach state in between.
Before we go on, I want to take a closer look
at how we are measuring these distances in game
and deciding when to change between approach.
and infiltrate, which is another distance-based state.
So on screen here is a screen capture from the game
with our debug display up.
I've highlighted some of the debug circles,
so they're a little more visible on screen.
But you can see we have Jin here in the middle,
and then he has four concentric circles drawn out around him.
And these are the radii, the distances
at which we are choosing to change states for approach
and infiltrate.
So here's just another view of it.
So you might be asking yourself,
well, why are there four circles here?
Shouldn't there just be one?
You just need the one line to know
whether we're in the state or out of the state.
And this solves an issue,
I'm sure we've all run into playing other open world games.
You're sneaking up to an enemy area,
the tense encounter music starts playing.
You sneak away a little bit, it stops playing.
You sneak a little closer, it starts playing again.
And you can sort of play with this system,
turning it on and off,
listening as it's ping ponging back and forth
between states.
In this case, there's one invisible line that's saying,
on this side, we're playing the music,
on this side, we're not playing the music.
And we wanted to avoid this for Ghost of Tsushima.
So we ended up implementing two different radii
for each of the states infiltrate and approach.
One sets the state and a different one removes the state.
So let's take a look at this in the case of approach.
As I said, we set approach if an enemy comes
within 50 meters of Jin.
So.
We see we have our Mongol enemy there in the bottom left.
He's outside of the outer circles.
So we're in Explore.
if he moves within 50 meters of Jin, so inside that inner yellow circle, that's when we'll change
to approach. Now to change back from approach to explore, that same mongol would have to move 60
meters away from Jin. So we have this 10 meter buffer between the radii, and we've now eliminated
that ping-ponging issue where somebody could find that line and walk back and forth across it,
changing the music really quickly.
and we really feel like this helps smooth out any musical anomalies in our music system.
So back to our flowchart here, we're in approach.
The next state in the system would be infiltrate. So that's another distance-based change, so
a Mongol enemy has to come within 20 meters of Jin to change to infiltrate.
So back to our visual representation here, we've got our Mongol.
He's outside the zone.
He would have to move inside the innermost circle,
20 meters from Jen, to change to infiltrate.
Now, content wise for Infiltrate, we're really trying to stay true to that minimalistic scoring approach Bill mentioned earlier.
You're really only going to hear a couple of elements at any one time in Infiltrate.
They're going to be tense and sneaky.
We've got lots of space built into this playlist.
And that's all to stay with that minimal approach.
We really don't want to beat the player over the head with musical material here.
You're going to be hearing the state very often.
So we try and keep things rather sparse.
And I've got an audio example here for Infiltrate, so let's listen to what that sounds like.
So that's infiltrate, you know, really sort of sets that mood of of sneaky infiltration as Mongols are nearby.
So the next state. Well, actually, before I go there, there's there's two places where infiltrate can go from here.
First would be standoff. This would be if a player.
entered into a standoff with a nearby enemy.
We're not gonna dive too much into this today.
Suffice to say that it exists, it has its own music,
but we're gonna move on to the next state
in the system itself, which is alarmed.
Now, this state changes based on the awareness level
of the enemies in the encounter area.
An enemy will go into an alarm state
if they have a sense that there's a threat nearby,
but they haven't really identified where it is yet.
Maybe they've heard Jen running around through a camp.
Maybe they found a body in a yurt somewhere or you fired an arrow and missed your shot.
They know somebody is around, but they want to go and search and find where they are.
This heightened level of search that an enemy might go into causes a change in the music as well.
Content wise, we're still staying rather sparse here, but we will add a few more elements,
remove some of that space that might have been an infiltrate, add some more rhythmic elements,
just to up the excitement for this change in awareness in the Mongols that are in the area.
So I've got an audio example here of alarm that we can listen to.
Cool, so ups the excitement just a little bit,
but still that sparse minimal approach.
So the next state in our system would be combat.
We changed to combat when the enemies are fully aware
of Jin, they are actively engaged in combat with him.
Now, combat is a fair bit more complex
than the rest of the states in the system.
Right off the bat, you can see we have it divided
into two intensities, combat hard and combat easy.
Now we're picking which intensity of combat to play based on the perceived difficulty of the
encounter that Jin's in. I'm going to talk a little more about this in a few slides, but if
the encounter is less difficult, we'll play combat easy. If it's more difficult, we'll play combat hard.
And a big goal we had for combat was to have very smooth and musical transitions between the states. And we achieve this a number of different ways. First off, we have specific transitions for going between easy and hard, whether you're going up from easy to hard or down from hard to easy.
Additionally, we have special combat easy chunks that we call easy plus.
that will play after a combat hard down transition.
And this just gives a really smooth transition
when coming down.
We want the player to feel the difference in the music,
but we don't want it to be that hard ping pong-y change.
In addition to those special transitions,
we're also using custom cue markers and Ys.
So instead of saying, okay, transition on the next beat
or the next bar, we've actually gone through
each combat chunk in the game.
and handpicked where we think the most musically opportune places are to transition.
The big goals here are we don't want to interrupt any big sweeping melodies,
especially in the hard combat chunks.
And we also want to make sure any grooves that we leave are left at the most opportune moments.
So I have a musical example here to play for combat hard and easy.
It's a little bit longer.
I can walk you through now and I'll annotate while we play through.
But we start in alarms.
We move up to Combat Easy, transition up to Combat Hard,
and then transition back down.
And I'll try and call out those changes as they happen.
So we'll start in Alarmed here.
Now we're transitioning to Combat Easy.
Up to combat hard.
Great. And I did want to touch on the content that we have in each of these playlists.
So Combat Easy is more of that minimalist approach.
We're kind of falling back on that quintet Bill was talking about of the more Japanese
traditional instruments, maybe the smaller taiko ensembles.
perhaps solo cello instead of a full string section,
whereas combat hard will be a little denser.
We'll have those full orchestral sections playing together,
the large taiko ensembles, all the big drums,
which really gives us that difference in intensity
to play with when playing in combat.
So we're not just hitting the player
with the same combat music every time.
Just gives us that variety to play with.
And finally, rather self-explanatory, we've got our combat end tag.
This will transition us out of our combat material into one of the lower states,
depending on how you've exited.
If you've killed all the enemies, we'll go back to explore.
If you've just snuck away, we might go back to infiltrate or alarmed
if there are enemies still around.
And I wanted to circle back, we saw a slide earlier in Bill's presentation of the wide
stems of screenshot from Pro Tools.
This is what that same Pro Tools session looks like after our editors have edited everything
for one of these music encounter systems.
So this has all of the infiltrate chunks, all the alarm chunks, all the combat easy
and hard, all the transitions, and you can really see the level of detail we're going
to.
And using every one of those stems, making all sorts of different alt arrangements.
Again, just really trying to make as much variety as we can to make it an interesting
listening experience for the player. So I wanted to talk more about encounter
difficulty in Ghost of Tsushima, how we are calculating it and even how it's changing
as you play through the game. Being an open world game,
the player has free agency to go wherever they want, engage with content however they want.
And there can be a specific issue inherent in this that we've noticed on the PlayStation
music team and we were able to fix on Ghost of Tsushima. And that is that, you know, somebody
might play three quarters of the way through the game and then come back to an area around
where they started fighting some easier enemies.
well, they're all leveled up. They have all sorts of weapon upgrades, more XP. They just know the
game better. Those early encounters that you might run into are going to be a lot easier for those
players. They're not going to take as long. They're not going to feel as dangerous. And we wanted to
be able to scale the combat music that would play for those situations. So we asked ourselves,
how do we tell how difficult a particular encounter is for one player versus another,
depending on where they're at in the game?
And we came up with this equation that I'm going to walk through here.
So the first part of the equation, the sum of the encounter enemy values.
Well, we started out by asking Sucker Punch for a list of the enemy types that were in the game.
And we got this roughly this list back.
You can see we have a number of different tribes.
Essentially, those tribes from one to five, that denotes difficulty.
You would have seen this as the color of outfits that the Mongols were wearing in the game.
Tribe one Mongols were much easier to defeat than tribe five.
And then within those tribes, we've got different enemy types.
Melees are your grunt enemies, ranged are your archers or enemies who throw things.
the heavy enemies were the big brutes who were a lot harder to take out.
We also have bandits, ronin, samurai, animals, and we wanted to go through and assign a number
value to each one of these enemy types. And you can see we've done that here in this table.
And roughly as the tribes get more difficult, that number goes up.
And what happens when you get into an encounter is we look at how many
enemies are involved. We compare against this list.
Okay, we look at the intensity values for those enemies and we add those together to give a sense of you know how how difficult or what's going on in this encounter enemy wise.
You can see, next we then divide by a number we call the hero factor.
Now the hero factor is the key to this equation.
We did a lot of work trying to figure out
how we were going to track how strong or how powerful
Jin was to give us this idea of how easy or hard
an encounter might be.
And we landed on this hero factor.
Now the hero factor is a number we only
use for the music system itself.
But it's based on a parameter from the game
that we got from Sucker Punch called hero level.
Now this is an under the hood number in Ghost of Tsushima. I don't think you the player ever
see this anywhere in the game, but roughly it tracks along with the XP that you're gaining
as you are completing missions, completing side content, getting different upgrades,
different armor, so it gives us a sense of how strong Jin might be as he progresses.
But you'll see hero level it starts at zero and it goes up to up to 10. So there's 11 levels there, and that zero to 10 split just made the math really difficult to work with and really unwieldy and kind of hard to hone things into a place that made sense.
So right off the bat we knew we'd have to convert this into some other set of numbers and that's how we ended up with the hero factor.
So you see hero level goes from 0 to 10.
Our hero factor actually goes from 1 to 2.
Much simpler to deal with in this equation, especially.
We have our enemy encounter values,
we divide by our hero factor, and that
gives us a rough sense of the encounter difficulty.
If we compare that to some combat thresholds
that we've set, we can tell, OK, is this
a hard encounter for this player,
or is this an easy one, and then play specific combat music
based on that result. So let's walk through an example here.
We've got our equation.
Let's imagine we're early in the game.
We're just fighting a few tribe one Mongols on the road,
say two tribe one melee enemies
who have an intensity value of 12,
two tribe one ranged enemies
who have an intensity value of eight.
So two and two of each of those,
we have 12 plus 12 plus eight plus eight
gives us an enemy value of 40.
Now, like I said, we are early in the game.
Imagine we're just starting out.
So we haven't really done anything.
We're hero level zero.
We can see this pertains to the hero factor of one.
So we plug that in.
We now have enemy value 40 divided by hero factor of one.
Gives us an encounter difficulty of 40.
Okay, that's cool.
But what does this mean?
We need to compare it against something,
against our combat thresholds.
So we see we have our thresholds here.
Anything from 10 to 29 would be easy combat.
And it's worth saying anything that is below 10
would get no combat music.
We do have that option in our system.
anything 30 and above would be hard combat. So in this example we have here as a player just
starting out, this encounter of 40 would trigger hard combat and rightfully so. You're just starting
out, you're not as leveled up, that encounter is going to be more difficult, it's going to
take you longer, and it warrants that more bombastic arrangement of combat.
How does this change if we were somebody who finished the game
and then came back to the same area to clear out some content?
Well, the math changes drastically.
If we imagine that you're hero level 10, the highest level
you can be, that turns into a hero factor of 2.
So now we're taking that enemy value of 40
and we're cutting it in half.
Now the encounter difficulty is 20 instead of 40.
While comparing to our thresholds,
we're only getting above that easy threshold now.
So this same encounter, being engaged
by a player who's spent more time in the game
is more powerful, is only going to trigger easy combat.
And this differentiation of easy and hard
and the way it changes as you play the game,
I think is a real powerful tool in our game.
tool chest for Ghost of Tsushima. And it really helps, I think, immerse the player into the world
when the music really changes along with the action on screen. I think it really helps sell
that that feeling of immersion for the player. And we're really proud of the system we've put
together here for Ghost of Tsushima. And that is it in a nutshell. So I will hand it off to Pete
to close us out here. Thanks.
Thanks, Andrew. And thanks, Bill. And thanks, everyone. It's
been great to be here and to talk about the music for the
Ghost of Tsushima. This is a project that was, we really
enjoyed. It was huge for us and
It was really, really rewarding.
I also want to mention before we leave that,
while it's been a privilege for the three of us to be here
and to talk about this score,
that there were many, many other folks
within our department at Sony PlayStation
and outside of our department
that contributed to this score.
Like to thank my co-producer, Keith Leary,
all the musicians, engineers, the orchestrators.
particularly Chad Cannon, who contributed to the score,
just some absolutely beautiful playing
and some excellent work.
Thanks of course to Sucker Punch.
They were a brilliant partner in this
and we really appreciate the opportunity
to work together and collaborate on this.
And of course, last and certainly not least to Alon
and to Ume for having.
written some absolutely beautiful music, really inspiring and helped us to do our job at this
level. So we're really grateful for that and we really appreciate how truly special this project
was and the music for it was. So thanks everyone and appreciate you watching our presentation.
Thank you.