to designing over the top, Saints Row the Third post-mortem.
Thank you. A couple reminders, fill out your surveys.
They probably got sent to your spam folder like
they did to mine. So, you know, take a
look at them. Please fill them out. Send them
that, send that feedback in. That's helpful for us
speakers.
All right, so we'll start off with me.
My name is Scott Phillips.
I've been with Volition for 10 years.
Worked on several titles.
I was the design director on Saints Row the Third.
Basically what that meant was I was in charge of the high
level concept on the design side, the tone and the feeling
of the game, the overall experience, and basically the
quality bar of that gameplay.
I also did staffing and scheduling, so I spent a lot of
time in Excel and HandSoft and all those
joyous design tools.
I did some minor camera work, stuff like that, but in general I tried to stay out of that
work because I would generally break something and nobody wants their director in there messing
up with stuff they just finished.
Now Saints Row the Third, we started in 2008, just after Saints Row 2 had finished, the
directors of Saints Row 2 moved directly on to Saints Row the Third.
We had about a hundred and twenty-five people peak at
the end of the project, plus QA and outsourcers.
So needless to say, this was Volition and THQ's largest
project to date. So there was a lot riding
on it for both us and for THQ.
Now what does this talk about?
The postmortem is looking at what went right, what went wrong.
I'm going to talk about some of the really great moments that we had on the project,
some of the really painful ones that we had on the project.
I'm going to cover what we tried to do, what things worked, what didn't work, and my hope
is that you'll learn something from our pain and be able to use that on your future projects
as well.
You may have already known a lot of the stuff that I'm going to talk about.
You may know some of the ideas that we're going to do, that we're going to talk about.
But you'll at least see how we implemented them and, you know, where things went right
and where they went horribly wrong.
So I'm going to cover three main areas in this postmortem.
The first one is, why was the franchise successful?
Saints Row 1 and Saints Row 2 had both sold about 4 to 5 million units.
Saints Row 2 was just coming out when we started Saints Row 3.
It went on to sell 4 to 5 million units.
Both received relatively good review scores in the 80s.
But success wasn't certain. It's not certain with any sequel, and I think
some of the talks I saw yesterday put a nice point on this. I think the Portal 2 guys said,
you know, a new franchise is much easier, because you're breaking new ground, and people
don't know what to expect. With a sequel, there is a built-in set of expectations of,
you know, what is that game going to be, and what is the sequel going to be? How are you
going to change it? How are you going to keep it the same?
So for us, one of the biggest elements of that
was the over-the-top feeling, the tone of the game,
as I'm going to go on to talk about.
There's a great quote from Walt Disney about sequels.
He said, you can't top pigs with pigs.
Basically, he was talking about, they had done a
three blind pig short that had won an Oscar.
It was a huge success. And they were convinced
to continue making more of them. So they made
several more, and each was less and less successful.
Basically what he was saying is you can't give
people the same thing. And it's, it's not really
a problem that's new, but it's also not a
problem that has been solved, or can be solved,
really.
The second thing I'm gonna talk about is raising
the quality bar.
Visual and quality issues were the number one cited issues in reviews for Saints Row 2.
We got hit on things like inconsistent or repetitive missions and lack of creativity.
On the other side, we were praised for their fun factor, no holds barred action, and the
over the top crazy gameplay.
So we knew in three years when Saints Row the third was going to come out that we were
going to have to raise that bar to compete.
So I'm going to touch on three things here.
There's holy shit moments, our pacing, and our playtesting.
I'll get into those more a little later.
The third one is scope control. Now this is a really difficult issue to deal with. It's
really hard to define, you know, what's the right amount of stuff to have in the game.
We had just come off of Saints Row 2 where the mentality was, you know, let's put every
single feature we can possibly think of in the game. You know, if that game had it, well,
we need to put it in our game and we'll do it this slightly different way.
What ended up is that we wasted a lot of time near the end of the project adding in features
that we shouldn't have.
And because of this, we shipped with more bugs than we wanted, and we shipped with a
lower quality across the board than we wanted.
So at Saints Row the Third, we wanted to focus on fewer, better features.
So setting the tone. Tone is a pretty nebulous term. I think if you look at different mediums,
how they describe tone, how they talk about it, is not very specific. It's tough to define
what that feeling is. I think one of the best ways to talk about it is this quote. Tone
can be as important as text. Basically, what you're saying
what you're saying, how you're going to say something, is more
important, or can be more important than what you're saying.
Now I'm not really going to try and define what
tone is, but I'm going to use some descriptions and
then walk into how we use tone and how we
define it.
Let's look at an example of tone. Batman.
Now Batman's been around for 70 years.
He's been through numerous incarnations.
There's been, but there's always, you know, the Batsuit.
There's always Gotham City.
There's always the Joker.
Now when I said Batman, which one did you picture?
Did you picture the 1960s Batman?
Michael Keaton?
Val Kilmer?
George Clooney?
I always forget his name.
Christian Bale, that's it.
Or one of these many, many other types.
or incarnations of Batman. Now if you look at it, the 1960s Batman versus the Dark Knight,
they're incredibly different emotional experiences. But why? They cover the same characters, same
content, same general storylines.
they're different in the emotional impact that they have on on the viewer
you know the nineteen sixties batman was goofy was ridiculous you shark
repellent and
all these you know running around with bombs over his head
uh... the dark knight is a very serious very realistic movie
Now tone, for me, has two primary elements. There's the creative boundaries, and then
there's the emotional experience, or what you could also call the player experience
for us in games. And what you want is you want the team to be like Goldilocks. You want
everyone to be able to say, you know, no, that's too crazy, or no, that's too tame.
You know, let's find something right in the middle that's just right for what we're trying
to do with this game.
Now we had just come off of Saints Row 2, and Saints Row 2, we had a very difficult
time coming up with what is that creative box?
What are we going to fit into?
In a game where you go from running around nude, vehicle surfing on top of a car, to
the next minute.
you're chasing a lieutenant who's being dragged behind a car, mercilessly bloodied
and then you mercy kill him in order to put him out of his misery.
Now those are very, very different emotions.
The tone was not well defined in Saints Row 2.
We refined it through trial and error. We tried a bunch of different things. We
would throw out ideas. We would see what stuck.
The problem was that inconsistencies were all over the place, just as I mentioned there
with those examples.
Now, with Saints Row the Third, we wanted to have a cohesive experience.
That was one of our main goals, was the whole experience should feel like it's one note.
It's the same feeling you get throughout the entire game.
but that's difficult especially when you you want to have these crazy experiences
so we had uh... uh... fart in a jar was one of our weapons
initially
you know i thought this weapon was was ridiculous i thought there was no you
know it didn't make sense in the game
it didn't really make sense as a combat effective
uh... tool
but in the end we we put it in because well
partially because fans asked for it and partially because it's it's just a
pretty funny weapon it's it's it's enjoyable
as a player you're gonna have fun with it
Now if the tone is solid, everybody's going in the same direction.
You're all working towards the same goal.
If the tone is confused, you're constantly fighting each other.
You're going nowhere.
So our question was, what should SR3 be?
Should it be over the top?
Should it be serious but silly?
Or should it be self-aware and unrepentant, just there to have fun?
Should it be gangsta? Should it be gangster? Very different experiences for the player.
What should it feel like to be a third street saint?
Now our major problems, as I mentioned, was that the tone was ill-defined from the past
games. Saints Row 1 had a relatively set, they wanted to make, I think the description
of it was like an MTV music video.
but they also had insurance fraud. You could jump in front of, you got money to jump in
front of cars. Didn't really make a whole lot of sense with an MTV music video. Saints
Row 2, we kind of pushed that a little further where you're driving around in a truck spraying
shit on people.
you know, and then we also had that dark narrative, you know, where you, uh, put Mero's girlfriend
into the trunk of a car and then put her into the, uh, monster truck race and then Mero
smashes her to death. You know, that's pretty very different things. Now, since we didn't
have much to start from, we were kind of coming at it fresh.
and we're also coming at it fresh with our team
uh... because by the time Saints Row the Third shipped we had only twenty
percent of the team had shipped a past Saints Row title
that's a pretty huge amount
of uh... of difference between the past game
and Saints Row the Third
This meant that, you know, people didn't have that automatic knowledge of, you know, what
is Saints Row? Oh, well, we did it this last time. I think I have a good idea. You know,
it's not too bad. We were getting people from different teams within Volition. We were getting
people from outside of our studio. The problem was we had a lack of buy-in in what the game
was.
people didn't know what they were making and they were constantly confused about,
you know, is, is fart in a jar, is that too far? Well,
you know, what about this other thing that I'm working on? I'm trying to write a spec
for this.
I don't really know what, what I'm trying to make.
Now this, this led to, you know, what I...
I use the description of soft versus hard power.
There's, you know, you can guide someone, you can direct them,
which is what, you know, a director as myself should have been doing.
And then you can mandate things.
You can say, all right, bring me your problem, this is your answer.
Bring me your problem, this is your answer.
The problem with something like that is that you don't have people, you have people that
are renting those ideas. They don't really own what they're working on. And if they don't
own what they're working on, they don't really care as much. They're, they're not as invested
in the final product or even in that initial idea.
And since designers are advocates for the player, for the entire experience, if they're
not buying into what the game is going to be, who is? Who will?
Now our second problem was that for the first six months or so,
Saints Row the Third went a very different direction.
We started off with the idea that the player was an undercover agent infiltrating the Saints.
You were, you know, an FBI agent, something along those lines.
You were doing this in order to allow the player to make choices.
We wanted choice to be a much bigger part of the game.
So you were making these choices of, you know, oh, at the end of the mission we go and we
find there's a big bale of cocaine.
Should I turn it into the FBI?
Should I give it to the Saints?
You know, each of those had different paths.
And so we were making the game.
that I think it would have been, I would have been fun,
but the question was, is this a Saints Row game?
And the very clear answer was no,
this is not a Saints Row game.
So this caused about six months in, we reset.
We reset the story, we reset the idea
of a lot of the top level design.
That was good. We were back on a better track. We were back on the track that we would eventually
ship on. The problem was that was even more confusion. We were asking the team that had
just wasn't buying into the initial vision, we were asking them to now reset and look
at another vision and figure out how to make that game.
The result was confusion.
confusion people didn't know what to do
they weren't sure about what they were making
they had lack of confidence in the vision
uh... we had to explain and re-explain well myself i had to re-explain
constantly answer questions about
i'm doing this i don't i don't know what you want
It was, it was my problem. It was something that I needed to fix.
And the good news was that we could actually fix it.
We, we needed to resolve this as soon as possible, because if, if the team wasn't clear on what
the game was that we were making, we were never going to be able to make that game.
So how did we try to get everyone on the same page?
The first thing we did was we had a lot of brainstorming meetings.
We got the team, the design team together. We would sit down and we would talk about
what does over-the-top mean to you?
Now over the top had been used on Saints Row 1 and Saints Row 2 as a very general description
of this is what the game is.
It's over the top.
When we started Saints Row the Third, people started asking a lot more questions,
especially with the initial different direction.
They were asking the question of, you know, what does over-the-top mean?
Is it, you know, really vicious murder? Is it fart in the jar?
And the problem was it's somewhere in there,
and we can't put our finger on, you know, this is exactly what we're making.
So what we started to do was come up with a mantra.
We wanted people to be thinking about something as they were
working on systems.
We came to embrace the crazy, fun trumps all.
That kind of codified what we wanted designers to be
thinking about.
it was helpful, to be sure. And over the top,
you know, as luck would have it, was still kind
of the, the buzzword for the team, for the
rest of the project, and probably for, you know,
any future projects in that franchise. I think over
the top will be a key element of what
the game is.
The next thing we did was we did team presentations. We would, myself, the producer, we would sit
up in front of the entire team, ask them to come to lunch meetings or ask them to come
to, at the team meeting. We would just talk about, you know, here's what we're, here's
what our plan is for the crazy missions that we're going to do in the game. And then we
would talk about it. And this, this started to help getting people to ask those difficult
questions of, like, I don't understand why this fits. And getting that out in the open
helped greatly.
movie outings was a big help as well. Just getting people,
I think, the best one I think we saw was
the A-Team. I mean, that, that's a movie you
could call over the top. It was pretty ridiculous.
It was funny. It was a summer blockbuster.
The tone video is, is something I'm gonna, something
I'm gonna show in a minute here. Basically we
ripped up a bunch of movies, we put it
to a music track, and we wanted to capture
the feeling of Saints Row.
And then finally there's aha moments, or what I'm calling aha moments.
Basically, there are points in the game where something happened and we realized,
yes, that's it.
I think we've found something that is exactly what we want it to be,
what we want this game to be, and I can see it.
You know, everyone on the team can say, OK, I know where we're going.
Now the tone video, this might be a little loud, just as a warning. We ripped up a bunch
of movies including Shoot Em Up, Bad Boys 2. We looked for, myself and the producer,
looked for what should the player feel like as they're playing Saints Row the Third. We
also put it to a music track which our producer picked and I think, you know, initially I
fought him on it. I didn't think it, I thought it was too out of date. Now I know that I
was totally wrong. So here we go.
So, personally, I think that helped greatly. Like, that, I,
that still gets me psyched. I love, I love hearing
that, seeing all that crazy shit going on. It's,
it's good stuff. That, that is what we wanted
the game to feel like.
Now, aha moments. The dildo bat. I, I think
people have probably read about this. You know, marketing
definitely ran with it. They, they went nuts with
this.
initially it was just one bullet pointed weapon
on one mission spec out of
thirty to fifty mission specs it was
not a big part of the game
now when the weapon artist took it and and you know i think the line item
description was just
dildo weapon
so he took that and he made a giant six-foot long enormous dildo you know
push things beyond
there's games that have
have done dildo bats before we knew this everyone else you know that
that made games knew this as well
so we wanted something that was even even crazier
So he took that, brought it to the technical rigger who rigged it up, got it all floppy,
brought it to the audio guys who added in some wet, floppy slapping sounds, and then
we put this in game.
And the team just loved it.
It really felt like awesome.
I feel like I'm playing something that I'm not going to get anywhere else.
This is a really enjoyable game.
Now, interestingly, we showed this to our producer, who
was incredibly scared.
He was kind of like, oh my god, there's no way.
THQ's not going to buy this.
ESRB's not going to buy this.
So he sent it off to our marketing guys.
And I think their response back was, we love it.
They absolutely loved it.
And I think you can tell through our marketing campaign
that they really loved it.
It was a big differentiator.
I totally get why they used it.
uh... and this was a this was just a nice moment for i think the team to
to really gel and feel like
yes this is
we know what saint's row is now
now the lessons learned
the team
must own
the tone and the vision
This was something, you know, that I learned the hard way on Saint Jerome the Third.
I think there's a lot of other postmortems will talk about the things they did to set this up.
I saw the Deus Ex talk yesterday morning and I thought it was great.
They did a lot of really smart stuff and we did some stupid stuff.
But we learned from our mistakes and we've done a much better job.
you know tone is very tough especially for a game like Saints Row where we
still do have some discrepancies uh... looking back on it
you know we have the uh... we have insurance fraud we have
uh... the dildo bat
but we also have
uh... a moment where one of the enemies
uh... viciously cracks the neck of you know one of the other enemies i think
it's not as bad like one of my main uh... things coming out of Saints Row 2
was i didn't want the player to be a dick
I felt in Saints Row 2 that a lot of times, especially in the Brotherhood arc, for those
who remember it, the player did some pretty vicious things.
And I found myself saying, you know, that's not my player.
I'm playing this game to have fun.
Like I don't want to be a jerk.
But we still ended up with some of these things.
Tone is very tough for us.
It might not be as tough for other games.
You know, there's, let's see, what is it?
uncharted i think they have something on their tone is something along the lines
of play indiana jones
you know that that's
that's got it you don't need to do too much more than that that explains the
game
The final element was use multiple methods. Do a lot of
different things. You can't just have one thing that, you
know, this word is the tone. You need to
do a lot of things. There is no one
size fit all. There were people on our team
who felt, you know, the video was, didn't make
any sense. They didn't, they didn't understand it. They
didn't understand Embrace the Crazy. There, there were individuals
who, they liked that, but they didn't like this
element. So you gotta find something that can kind
of hit everybody. You gotta find multiple things that
can hit the entire team.
Now, design briefs are something we're using going forward.
The goal is, before you've written
what something is going to be, write down
the problem you're using that you're going to solve.
And I think I haven't used this personally very much, but I'm looking forward to seeing
what we're going to do with it. And I think probably in one of these coming GDCs we'll
talk about it a little bit. And then vision trailers are fantastic. I think probably everybody
in here, I would imagine we're all design professionals, saw the Splinter Cell, I don't
remember, no not Splinter Cell, Rainbow Six Patriots.
vision trailer that came out maybe four or five months ago.
You know, that was a obviously fantastic tool, something they felt so proud of that they
wanted to put out to the public, you know, years before the game is going to hit the
shelves. So these vision trailers are, it's tough to find the time to make them, but it's
absolutely worth every second of your time.
what the game is going to feel like, how are we going to make sure that the gameplay we
create is crazy. We want wow, we want more than wow, we want holy shit. Now Saints Row
2, we had kind of, you know, we had sections in our docs where we would write wow moments.
We wanted something that was cool, that was, players would remember. With Saints Row the
3rd, we wanted to up our, up our ante.
you know up our hyperbole and and call them holy shit moments they were things
that you're gonna remember forever
uh... their water cooler moments
In addition to that, we wanted every mission to contain some over-the-top element.
We didn't want any FedEx missions.
You know, FedEx would be, okay, I have to start here and then I have to drive there,
pick up something, and then deliver it to somebody else.
Those sorts of missions were not something we wanted any of.
We wanted even the smaller missions, even mini-missions.
We wanted to have some crazy element that players were going to be impressed by.
The major problem is that paper specs don't guarantee fun. We found this on Saints Row
2, and I'm sure everybody else has found it at some point. You know, you have this amazing
idea, you think it's going to be the best thing ever, you write it down, you feel really
proud of the spec, and then it gets in game and you're like, oh my god, this is awful.
Sometimes you won't admit it for a while. I know I'm, I'm guilty of that. But just writing
it down doesn't make it the best thing ever. We had a couple of these elements in Saints
Row 2.
the johnny get gurney mission there's a mission where you go to the hospital
johnny get one of your main lieutenants is injured
you have to get him on the gurney and then you have to fight your way out as
you're pushing him shooting here
machine gun that uh... enemies who are rushing in your you know running through
the hospital at top speed
it's it sounds like it could be pretty cool
but it wasn't. It wasn't very fun. And then we had this sword battle, a big sword battle
at the end of the Ronin arc, or in the middle of the Ronin arc, where the player was avenging
the people who attacked Johnny Gat. You were going to go and murder this, I think it was
Junichi, and you were going to do it using his own weapon. You were going to, you know,
you were going to stab him, you were going to slice up all the Ronin.
but we did it really late and it then, it also did not end up being very fun.
Now everything we do on a big game like this, you know, Saints Row was, like I said, over
a hundred people, takes a lot of time and costs a lot of money. So we can't just set
out a course lightly. We need to know as much as possible that what we're going to do is
going to work.
So our solution was pre-visualization.
you know this is avatar here i think everyone is has seen what they've done
they've seen uh... you know hollywood uses this to great effect
uh... and i think video games need to start using it more
uh... i'm a former animator so i kind of
i really like that sort of visual seeing things move as they're really going to
move
now previz is fantastic because it convinces skeptical groups
uh... it convinces programmers who often are
uh... very
not eager, shall we say, to take on very, very difficult things or things that, you
know, they don't think are gonna be possible. This all, it all leads into buy-in. You want
something that people can look at and say, that's cool. I, you know, I think if we change
this, we could make it even better. Showing them something makes it a lot easier to get
someone behind your idea. The other element was that we wanted to prototype things as
early as possible. You never know
what's gonna work and you want to figure out
you know fail early, fail often that's that sort of mantra
uh... and nothing
almost nothing we ever do is final the first time
i always fall into that trap where i think yes that i've got it the spec is
great we're not gonna need to change anything everything's gonna work out
perfectly
And then we get it in game.
And invariably, either I've left out something, or something
didn't get implemented, or oh my god, this other system,
because we're an open world game, is screwing with this
thing I wrote.
And so now it doesn't work.
I wanted to mention that there was a talk I saw, I think, three years ago by Mass Effect
2 level designers, which I really learned a lot from, about how they break down the
phases of development for their missions.
This was something that I took back to Volition and we kind of worked through, you know, how
do we set
different stages of you know is this is this ready is this fun
uh... how can we make it more fun and when is it really finished
it was it was a great help we didn't use exactly what they did because our
game is different but
it was great help
uh... and that's one of the reasons why i'd love gdc and why i wanna
you know hopefully give you something
Now, we did, I'm gonna show, I think, three previs movies here.
This first one is for the first mission in the game.
This is essentially at the end of the first mission.
The player is robbing a bank at the very beginning of the game, wearing a costume, so that you
wouldn't have to customize as the very first thing in the game.
Because I felt it was very important that the player get right into the action, not
that you're thrown, you know, you watch a cutscene and then you have to go through this
giant UI system.
That's not the feeling I wanted for the game. So the player starts off wearing a costume.
He gets on top of the vault, which is pulled out by a helicopter, and then it goes smashing
around the building, smashing through things, destroying stuff while the player is fighting
off waves and waves of SWAT. So here is the previs that we did, interspersed with, in
the background, is the actual game, the final shipping product. I think you'll see a lot
of similarities. And I'm going to stop it at one point here.
Alright, let's get rolling.
Now initially in the previs here, we had a boss, we ended it with the player throwing
a grenade at a helicopter and then in slow-mo you would shoot the grenade and the grenade
would blow up and the helicopter would lose its stabilization and would come crashing
into you. Because of co-op, we weren't going to really be able to do any sort of slow-mo.
And so, also through development we figured out like
okay this is all cool looking but for two minutes the player is just shooting
random people and doesn't feel any sort of progress doesn't feel like they've
uh... you know
who is their enemy why are they still here
and so in the final product i think you'll you'll notice
that there's a single helicopter that seems to keep coming back it's got this
we put a red marker over the top of it to make it clear like
this is your boss so we essentially added a boss once we got to uh...
Previs there is the, uh, here comes the grenade moment.
Well, shi-
So that was about two years before we got to that final product there, that we had that
previs. It was enormously helpful to say this is what we're trying to hit. It took us a
long, long time to get there, but because we knew this is what we want to do, it was
much, much easier to convince the team and to make sure that that happened.
Now, our second mission, we wanted to start off with some big moments.
So we got the bank vault, we got this, there's a skydiving.
I wanted the entrance to the city to kind of be this, you know,
what is the coolest, most over-the-top way to come to a city.
And it felt like skydiving out of a plane that you had just jumped out of
while shooting enemies, and then you land in the city.
Seemed like a pretty cool way to do it.
Alright, so let's hit this.
So we had just very brief snippets of, you know, this is what
general idea of what the camera's going to be, this is the enemies you're going to be shooting.
We got that in game and we pretty much realized like you're not going to want to do this for
three, five, six minutes.
And so in one of the gameplay reviews where we got, you know, all the different
disciplines to sit together and play through the mission.
somebody, I don't know where it came from, but the idea was we needed to get something
in the middle of the mission to break it up and kind of reset and up the stakes.
I thought back to the movie Eraser. I'm a big Arnold Schwarzenegger movie fan.
So if you remember that movie at all, there was a point where James Kahn
is the bad guy. Schwarzenegger has just jumped out of this plane that James Kahn took over.
James Kahn convinces the pilot to turn the plane around
and then for the next couple minutes you see that plane
coming right at Schwarzenegger as he's freaking out.
so he shoots at the plane the plane dodges him that moment was felt pretty
over the top it felt like something that would fit right in Saint's Row and so we
built this moment
that was uh...
even more ridiculous as you'll see
So, yeah, we made it just a tad more unrealistic than what Arnold did.
And the last one here went through a lot of iteration. This was
This is a moment at the end of the first act of the game where you finally get to reach your ultimate villain, Philippe Lorrain, who convinced you that he killed Johnny Gadd.
And now you're breaking into his tower, and this is the culmination of many hours of work, and you're going to kill him.
And so the idea was, you're going to drop one of these giant 600 ton skyscraper counterweights on top of him.
this moment it ended up that there is a technical difficulty with uh... animating the way we
the way we animate stuff
the further it moves away from the origin point of where the animation started,
the less accuracy it gets.
And so,
this tower wasn't actually big enough for us to create the gameplay we wanted to,
and so we had to
send you down to the bottom and then we
send you up to the top again and then you fall again.
And the animators were pulling their hair out. It just wasn't working.
So we ended up
compromising near the end of the project to get something cool in
there,
just to even have this moment.
Not this thing loose. I'm gonna crush that son of a bitch.
Leave it to me.
Hurry it up! He's getting away!
Initially you had to shoot the ball free, but in the final game, your buddies free it for you.
I'm coming for you, Reggie!
Get off my damn ball!
you
So halfway through the video there you saw what we call the brute, which is a giant eight
foot tall character, come and run up and jump up on the ball. This was another case of where
we didn't have a boss. Like this was a sequence that, you know, for a very short period of
time it looks very cool, but then when you actually want to play it or want to do any
sort of extended gameplay on it, it gets kind of tired. And so we introduced a boss character
that upped the ante, made it much more interesting.
So, lessons learned. Previs is great. I love it. I love, as a former animator, I love doing
this stuff. I didn't work on any of these. This was a cinematic artist and the animators
who did all these. And then the gameplay programmers made this, made this stuff happen, which was
phenomenal. Those guys spent a long, long time and a lot of hours, invested a lot of
their selves in making sure that these things came together.
It previs builds that buy-in that you need. It's vital.
And, you know, as the old saying goes, a picture is worth a thousand words.
So anytime you can show a picture to someone of what you're thinking versus sending them
an email or writing a spec, do that.
Now here's a terrible mock-up I did, mash-up for what ended up being our Johnny Gat, I
don't even know if it had a name, Johnny Gat Mobile, which was a giant Johnny Gat head
on the front of a van.
You know, this sort of thing is really simple and people enjoy it.
It's, you know, you take five or ten minutes, produce something that the team will be able
to look back on and will sell that idea really quickly.
You know, this seems obvious, but when you're busy, you don't always want to spend the time
to do that, but it is very worthwhile.
Now something we're doing at the studio moving forward with is sketching.
Our studio design director is pushing for all the projects to do sketches of,
basically instead of brainstorming, you all get together.
You don't work together at first.
You all draw out ideas.
You have a problem that you want to solve, you draw out ideas.
The idea is to get as many ideas out there as fast as possible.
and then work together to figure out what are the best ones.
The next step of previs, obviously, is then you want to animate that.
But if you can start with something very simple, just a drawing, that's the next step versus
trying to write a very detailed design spec.
Getting everyone involved early is vital.
uh... we wanted to include the art code
production we wanted to get everyone involved
it can happen
where design kind of isolates itself
and
becomes like a black box to the rest of the team
and that does not work well
you want everyone on the team to be invested in the entire game and all the
ideas that are there
they might have something that's better than what you thought up
And whenever you can, let the team that's working on it just go.
Don't try and drive things from above.
Be realistic. You can't do it all. We can't do it all.
As I'll talk a little bit later about scope control, it's really tough.
Now that we've got our big holy shit gameplay moment, let's go to how do we make it fun?
How do we make it paste well?
Now the goal with pacing is very simple, create better experiences.
That's, you know, you can't really define, it's going to change based on what your game
is, what your pacing is intended to be.
What I'm going to talk about is not the second to second pacing, or you know, putting an
enemy in the player's view, but you know, carrying their vision from left to right,
not that sort of stuff.
Ours was, where we focused on pacing was the overall experience, the emotion of playing
the game, the emotion of playing that mission.
The problem was that Volition did not have a lot of experience doing this.
There wasn't a lot to draw on from other projects.
We always ended up, we would put things in game and then we just, we would play them
until they felt fun.
And we ended up having to rely on, you know, just everybody hopefully having a good idea
of what pacing meant.
Additionally, open world makes this stuff very hard to pace.
Because anything can happen and you always have to have tons and tons of little...
optional things that you need to turn off, or, oh, well, I
don't want cars spawning in this area, or, you know, oh, we
don't need helicopters in this one, it screws up this thing
that I'm trying to do. We write a lot of mission specs, and
those are, those are good for asset identification, they're
good for, uh, getting the entire idea out there, but they're
not good for timing. They're not good for knowing how things
are gonna feel. The other problem was that we had no
common vocabulary. Pacing is a very difficult term to define.
and there's not a lot of uh... unity in terms of how people talk about pacing
there's not a lot of you know tension and
uh... tempo and
there's you can talk about it musically you can talk about it
uh... in all sorts of different ways and
just throughout the industry we don't have a good vocabulary of these are what
these terms mean and how they should be used
uh... just you know do a search on gama sutra for pacing you're gonna find
articles with all different sorts of things all different sorts of ideas
and you're gonna have to figure out for yourself what you're gonna do
So the way we went about it was I worked with the studio design director, Jason Scott, to
figure out what was available. What could we draw on? This was probably about two and
a half years into the three-year project that I really started pushing for, we need to solve
this. We don't have, our pacing is not good, we need to improve it.
So what we found, or I think what he found was the best example was this pacing visualization
of pacing as a cycle, as a circular cycle.
You know, going from building action, this is the basic gameplay, to the crisis where
something goes wrong and you need to react, to the climax where things get even worse
and you need to figure out how are you going to come back from that precipice.
and then the payoff where things go great and you figure out how to do it,
and then the reversal where, oh my god, you know, this new thing happened that's
gonna drive us back into that cycle.
All of these pieces flow together pretty well.
One issue is that you can't use this as a rule book. You can't
always have all of these elements, and you can't always use the same sort of
reversals.
There's definitely
times where you don't want the player to feel like, you know,
oh, that carrot is right there, I might be able to... No, you jerk, you pulled it away.
You don't always want the player to feel
like they just failed, but sometimes you do. So it's a very fine line.
This is what I came up with. This is using a program called MindManager.
This is a breakdown of the second mission in the game,
going from left to right, top to bottom.
Basically what I wanted to do was
visualize what a mission looked like so that we could figure out where we had
holes.
Where are we missing a reversal? Where are we missing a payoff?
what this helped us do was you can see
you know this was where we ship the mission
so i think we had a pretty good
idea of uh...
we had added in reversals we had added in that airplane
uh...
flying right towards you that was a great reversal that we added in
This is a little more detail.
There's one mission that I wanted to mention or use as an
example.
We had mission 11 was the player was fighting against
STAG, which was this military force that we brought in that
had these futuristic lasers and VTOL jets that could
transform from helicopters to airplanes.
initially at the end of this mission
you had you had been blowing up all these uh... all these tag bases all these
little
uh... pockets of of their uh... their troops and their their little base units
and then at the very end you went to save your buddy named Oleg
and you go to the park
and you kill a couple tanks and you kill a couple of VTOLs
the problem was it was
basically the same as everything you've been doing the rest of the mission so we
we didn't really pay it off you just kind of
oh mission's over
you saved your friends which is great
that was a great payoff but players didn't care
What we did was we ended up adding in, we moved that element earlier, we added in a
whole new element where you had to fly out over the sides of the city, you were put on
a timer, told, you know, oh my god, if you don't, if you don't get to this giant AWACS
plane and blow it up.
we're gonna all lose and the whole mission could be a failure at this point.
So we put a timer on the player, told them they have to do this under time pressure,
made the stakes important, and then
you had this cool airplane that you had never seen before flying over the city,
being escorted by other VTOLs. So it was a pretty good
sequence where we figured out, you know, this
is not ending well, and we only really figured it out once we had started doing
these
pacing maps.
Now the future of pacing is still a work in progress.
We're still figuring out what pacing means to us.
How do you pace open world?
Are we only pacing the missions?
We're still talking about it.
We have a group talking about it right now at the studio.
There's actually a GDC talk that was given by Jason Scott,
our studio design director, just an hour ago.
If you have the GDC vault, I would
suggest you go and watch it.
It's really interesting talk about the studio design groups
that Volition has, where we basically get all the designers
together, break them up into groups,
we figure out what topics we want to talk about as designers,
and then we work through them with clear end goals
on what we're going to figure out, what we're going to deliver
at the end of that.
Now, pacing was one of those where I felt it was really necessary for our project to
figure out better ways to do it.
Additionally this is, we've been, as we've been working on these pacing, I broke out
the pacing cycle and
I think I started to feel like we're not really in a cycle,
because the game is always moving forward.
We're always kind of ramping things up for the player.
And so I started to feel like it's more of a wave.
Like that wave can start small, it can get big.
The whole game, I think, will feel more like this.
You know, this is still a work in progress.
I'm still figuring out, you know, how do we even visualize with this?
Is this going to be fun?
You know, one of the other designers is not a big fan of how this works.
Now playtesting, I'm not going to go into it too much.
Lots of other talks have covered it.
We did, I think, cross-project critiques where groups of the designers got together from
another project.
They would play our game.
They would give us feedback within certain sets that we wanted to get feedback on.
They were very helpful. We ran those for about a year. So, looks like I'm getting short on
time, so I'm gonna speed up here. Lesson learned, GDC, our GDC talk on Jason Scott's talk, go
see that. Playtesting is fantastic. You know, everybody should use it if they don't already.
And then additionally, which you're not at, there's a Volition talk right now by Jordan
Lin who runs our playtesting lab. That you can also see on the vault.
Now, scope control is very tough. Saints Row 2, we added tons of stuff constantly. Now,
the problem is, who can tell me what exact size the game should be? How many features
should it have? How many missions should it have? You know, how are we going to sell twenty
million units? What, what is the right number? It's really difficult to define that. So what
we did was, we dumped everything we wanted to do onto our schedule, and then we started
figuring out.
we need to start cutting stuff. So every three to four months we would cut things.
We had twenty six of these in total. Some were meetings where all the directors would
get together and talk about, you know, I don't like this feature or I think this is going
to be too tough. Sometimes the producer would come to us and say, I don't think this feature
is really going to work or I don't think this is worthwhile, let's just kill it. We ended
up killing about four thousand man days of scheduled work throughout the project.
The project pillars helped us, you know, I think a lot of other projects do this. This
was a fun image of Johnny Cat doing the howling at the moon, or the three wolf moon playing
keyboard. But anyway, the pillars are the important part. They helped us to define what
are the important elements of the game.
We also did custom and core mission definitions.
We had some missions where we said, this is only
gonna use core features, we're not gonna add any
new functionality for it. We had missions like the
skydiving where we said, we're gonna do every awesome
thing, we're gonna make this the best mission we
possibly can.
yes so here is one of the features that we ended up cutting we called it free
gunning
this kind of a combination
of uh... you know the assassin's creed sort of parkour plus
shooting with a gun
pretty you know the name kind of defines it all
it was a pretty cool feature it looked really neat it was fun to slide over
cars
you know to run against walls and all that sort of stuff
but in an open world with
tons of A.I. tons of vehicles all kinds of crazy stuff going on
This feature, we spent about a year on it and we probably could have spent way, way longer.
We ended up cutting it, just like we cut, we had cover.
We cut cover because it didn't fit with what we wanted to do.
But free gunning really fit with our goals of fast, fluid and fun combat.
Now the outcomes of this, I think we shipped with a lot of really cool stuff.
I think we had a lot of variety.
We had cyberspace.
We had a stag helicarrier.
We had Professor Genki.
We had a mission on Mars.
We had a lot of really amazing stuff in the game.
Mars was something that was interesting because it was constantly on the cutting
board. It was a very difficult push for me. I wanted to have two endings to the game.
And that was very hard to sell the producer because
he's very much in, you know, you want every player to see every single thing
that you did because we're spending a ton of time making all this stuff.
In the end I think it was the right thing to keep it and I think a lot of that went to because the mission designer who owned that mission really wanted it to be in the game and spent a lot of his own time to make sure that it got in the game. He had that ownership of Mars.
The main problem was, at the end of the project, we didn't have enough people.
We grabbed most of the programmers, a lot of the artists and designers from other parts of the studio,
other parts of Volition.
We ended up with too much stuff.
We should have cut more.
It's a lesson that, you know, I need to learn, I need to get better at
personally, but at least, you know, like AA, admitting you have a problem is the first step.
It's really, really hard to do this.
Scope control is really, really difficult for me.
But we should have cut more.
Going forward, I find that I constantly
have to reevaluate and constantly think about this,
that it's really hard.
Now what I learned.
We'll end here.
We've got the tone and the pillars
are very, very important.
You want the entire team on board with what you're doing.
Prototyping is fantastic, previs is fantastic, you want to know what you're making before
you spend the time making it.
Figure out what your weaknesses are.
You know, whatever that is for your game, look at it, look at what's available in the
industry and start working on making it better.
For us, I would imagine for other people, it's really easy to have the best ideas ever
and want to get every single thing in the game because it's awesome. This thing is going
to be amazing. Every designer is going to envy me because this is the best thing ever.
But you can't do everything and you probably don't want to do everything because your game
won't ship until 2030.
And for us, specifically, it was don't fear, embrace your
content. You know, we are an over-the-top, polarizing game.
People, you know, some people love Saints Row, some people
hate Saints Row. But we wanted to make a Saints
Row game, and we, we ended up, I, in my
opinion, really building on what had been done in
the past.
And so that's my talk. Thank you very much.
If there are any questions, I think we've got a couple minutes, so.
Probably less than five.
Q Okay, I've got one.
So you were talking about tone earlier, and especially in Saints Row 2, that you had this
conflict between over-the-top and then very dramatic.
And now, playing Saints Row 3, loved it, I thought it was an amazing game, and certainly
based on your goals, it certainly seemed to achieve them.
But thinking about that, I mean, think about, say, just for argument's sake, your tone is
goofy comedy and you're doing a two-hour movie, you can pull that off and you'd be pretty
consistent. Maybe you need 10 minutes of a little drama to set the scene. But when we're now
talking about an open-world game where you're going from, you know, eight hours to 10 hours
to 12 or even 20 or, you know, even more.
Can you really stick to that tone?
Like, what do you feel about it?
Because, I mean, honestly, you say these things
about St. George II, and I played that,
but personally, I liked a lot of that drama,
even though it was a counterpoint,
because it felt like that gave
that really long experience some depth,
where if it's much more consistent in a particular tone,
it sort of gets a little stale over time.
Do you have any feelings on balancing between those two,
especially over that longer experience?
Yeah, so I mean the question is about Saints Row 2 had had that difference and so maybe that helped with an 8 to 10 hour experience.
My opinion is that because it's an open world game, there's so much stuff you can choose to do at any different point that in a lot of ways you set what you're going to experience.
I can totally see that point, and in the reviews, the one that I really found interesting was
the zero punctuation Yahtzee review, where he absolutely loved SR2, but then he felt
kind of disappointed by SR3 because it was too cohesive, like it was too much of the
same thing.
So, kind of to your point.
I don't know that there is a perfect way to do it.
I think if you start to switch between one and the other, or the player doesn't know
what to expect, like, I think with Saints Row 2 it was kind of nice that the story was
maybe a little more serious, and then the activities were goofy, so you kind of had
your choice of what it was, so I can see where that, maybe not criticism, but where that
opinion comes from.
you know, there's probably not a right answer for it.
Our goal was to make it cohesive,
and I think we did with the art and the gameplay
both kind of fitting with that over the top.
So, you know, maybe in the future it'll change back
to something more akin to Saints Row 2.
Who knows?
Thanks.
Hi.
Hi, I'm over here.
So I love the way that the...
you know, fun at all costs thing works not only into the aesthetic, but into like a lot of the individual systems designs.
And some of that stuff seemed like very, like once you saw it, it made perfect sense, like being able to dive into the wind,
like through the windshield of a car and not have to wait for the opening animation.
But, what were the decisions like for something like the upgrade system, where you, you know, you can essentially become invincible to things.
And oftentimes that's something that's very hard to work with the players, and you worry about it basically being a cheat code that can make...
experience stale or something? Did you guys wrestle with that at all? What was the process?
So the question is about making the player invincible, I guess. I think with the upgrades,
we wanted players who really put their time into it to get the kind of ultimate reward
out of it.
I do see the point about, especially for us with DLC, I think it was, honestly it was
a mistake. It was a mistake, it was an afterthought where we were like, you know, oh my god, we
didn't think about that player that played for 80 hours and is probably more likely to
buy DLC, and now DLC is not really balanced for them. I think that was kind of a mistake.
Well, wrap up now?
Last question. Um, yeah, I think, uh, I wanted to reward the player for spending all their time
and just make them feel that their effort had really been worth it and they got everything
they wanted out of that. And I felt, for me personally, that, you know, if I'm invincible,
if I've spent that, you know, 40, 50 hours, whatever, that I want to be invincible. I want
to just run around and kick ass. Maybe it is kind of a cheat code.
No, I mean, I think it was cool you guys did it.
I was just... it seemed like a departure, so...
Yeah. Thanks.