I would like to thank everybody for attending this talk.
There are a lot of great opportunities out there
and I'm flattered that you're here.
I'll let you know that there are a couple of bonus slides
at the end of this presentation
that I won't have time to cover.
However, this talk and its slides will be available
on the GDC Vault.
Or you can just reach out to me directly
if you're interested.
And also, please don't forget to fill out
your evaluation forms at the end.
I'm pretty sure I need the feedback.
So.
Now that you are here, whether intentional
or you just realized that you're in the wrong room,
you're most likely wondering who the hell is this guy?
Well, my name is Peter Dalton
and I am the technical director for Blue Point Games.
As you can tell from the gray in my beard,
I've been around for a little while.
I've been working in the games industry for over 18 years
and I will never leave.
I love my job, I love the insanely hard problems,
and I love the talented people that I'm surrounded by.
Over the 11 plus titles that I have shipped,
my specialties revolve around core engine development,
streaming, memory, performance.
I like to believe that it is my job
to basically make shit happen.
So.
Bluepoint Games, perhaps you've heard of us,
the masters of the remaster.
I have to thank Digital Foundry for that title.
Seriously, the Digital Foundry guys are amazing.
Their technical reviews are spot on,
and Bluepoint is tired of me ranting
about how our frame rate and frame pacing must be perfect,
or Digital Foundry will call us out.
Bluepoint has made a name for itself by remastering games,
many of which I'm hoping you've heard of.
We've been blessed to work with titles that we absolutely love, and from my perspective,
it is insanely awesome that I get to see exactly how these games were made.
At Bluepoint, there are two primary ideals that I try to promote,
with number one being, quality is the foundation of success.
I believe that it is absolutely true for our industry.
If you want long-term sustained success,
you must have quality to feed it.
And number two, every project that we release
must be better than our previous release.
And hopefully you can see this by looking at the titles
at our past projects.
The depth at which we remaster projects has grown exponentially.
Starting with the God of War collection, which involved texture cleanup,
to the Uncharted collection, which involved all aspects of the game being modified.
In fact, for Shadow, we don't call it a remaster.
We coin it a...
remake.
given the complexity of the project.
And moving forward to our next project,
we coin it a re-envisioning,
given that it goes well beyond
what we even thought was possible in Shadow.
Now I wanna take a minute to show you a video
from PSX 2017,
showing a comparison between the original Shadow
and the PS4 remake,
to give you a better sense of what we do.
you
I feel that it is important that people understand a couple of our overarching goals that we
take into each remastering project.
Number one, we have to be true to the design of the original game.
Number two, we have to respect the decisions of the original game team.
And number three, we must not lose the magic of the original game.
And if you say to yourself, I can't find the magic in the original, then what the hell
are you doing?
And number four, we have to acknowledge that it is rarely a black and white answer for
what we do, and as a result, there will be lots of internal debates.
These debates are good and healthy, and most importantly, they show passion.
To help explain our thought process, I like to use an analogy.
As a kid growing up, I used to love watching cartoons.
Who didn't?
I'm sure if you think about it, you had your favorites,
certain shows that stand out in your memories.
Well, in my case, I loved Thundercats and have fond memories.
However, if I go back and watch them now
or try to show them to my kids,
they aren't anything like I remember.
What we're trying to do is bring those memories back to life
and enable others to have similar experiences.
We're trying to recreate the game the original game developer
would have released if they had the technology that we have today.
So, let's take a technical look at the development process
that we use at Bluepoint when remastering a title.
Besides determining whether or not it makes business sense
to remaster a game, there are several key factors that must be considered.
Number one.
We absolutely must have the access to the release package.
For Shadow, this was the final package
that was delivered to Sony for distribution.
This should include all patches, back-end servers.
Basically, we need to be able to run
the retail project in-house.
And number two, we require all the final source code required to rebuild the game's final binaries.
Now, there are exceptions.
We can work around miscellaneous systems.
For example, if we are missing an audio library, chances are we're going to replace the entire system.
So, no biggie.
However, if we are missing gameplay code,
it quickly becomes cost prohibitive
to reverse engineer those libraries.
Other examples include server code, if required as a bonus.
However, we can work around not having it.
Tool pipeline code.
is a bonus. However, we usually don't build our processes around legacy tools and primarily
only use them for reference. And finally, any source assets that were used to build
the original final distribution package is a bonus, but not mandatory.
So, looking at the development process that we go through, the goal for the first month
is to obtain all the required pieces and to rebuild the game's binaries for the original
target platform.
We then send this build to our internal QA and run a whole suite of parity tests.
I should call out that it is critical to the success of the project that we get these first
steps correct.
Small errors here will be magnified as we get into full development, leading to wasted
time and incorrect decisions being made.
Here we feel that taking time to ensure correctness is preparing for success.
Moving forward, once we have parity, we upgrade the original title to its latest SDK to make
life easier, then rerun all parity tests.
Basically, we make incremental changes and verify parity through all steps.
Take Shadow, for example.
Very early on, we decided that we
were going to use the remastered PS3 version as our base.
At that point, QA ran extensive parity tests
between the PS2 and the PS3 version,
combed old bug databases, searched the web for user
feedback, et cetera.
Concurrently,
Engineering got the game up and running on the PS3, converted to the latest SDKs,
we localized all Japanese code comments, rearranged code libraries to make us happy,
and then re-ran all parity tests, and we fixed the issues before moving forward.
At Bluepoint, every developer at their desk has full access to our target platform,
which for Shadow was a PS4, and the original game, which in this case was a PS3 dev kit.
Programmers are expected to debug and play the game on the PS3 dev kit
to determine original code intent and purpose and to diagnose parity issues.
We do the same thing for all other departments.
ART always has full access to both platforms and are expected to be familiar with both.
And in the case of Shadow, QA went the extra mile and threw the PS2 into the mix.
Only after parity is verified do we start porting the code
to the target platform.
Porting is usually a one to two man project
that takes approximately two to three weeks
before we have the code compiling.
During this phase, we are more interested
in just getting everything to compile on the new platform,
not porting it.
Basically, we try not to lie to ourselves
and pretend that we know how everything works,
and instead we're using this time
to familiarize ourselves with the code base.
We create pound defines to disable whole systems,
markup changes we have made to the original code,
with the most important goals being number one,
to get the code to compile and link,
which is harder than it sounds,
and number two, make it trivial to identify
where we have modified original code.
So, congratulations.
After about two months, you have a binary
that you can launch on your target platform.
Not only did you get the game to compile,
you got it to link, which was a huge pain in the ass.
But you can't help but want to play the game,
so you hit run and boom.
Everything blows up.
In fact, the breakpoint that you put at main never got hit.
You blew up during preeminent.
The call stack doesn't make any sense,
and everything feels broken.
Memory is being requested.
You have 32 to 64-bit compatibility issues.
Plenty of code assumptions that a pointer fits in a uint32.
And resource files are being requested.
In fact, where the hell is the file system?
And you have Indian issues everywhere.
And how do you deal with memory map files
that assume a 32-bit pointer?
At this point, you can't help but wonder
what you've gotten yourself into,
and does it make sense to assign this task
to another engineer?
At this point, I must tell myself
to stop being a little bitch and just keep pushing forward.
So, given that the first step is just to get the game to compile on the target platform,
the next step is to get the game to main and then to the main loop.
The main loop will be pretty much commented out at this point, however, our goal is to
get the game running, displaying nothing but a black screen.
Getting to a black screen is a critical milestone for us.
It is really the point at which the entire team of engineers can really start piling
onto the project and looking at their respective domains.
it is the point at which momentum really starts to pick up.
So I want to stop for a second,
and I want to share a little bit of Bluepoint history.
With all the projects that we've worked on
before Shadow of the Colossus,
We would work within the realm of the original code base.
We would rewrite low-level platform code
to work on the new target platform.
We would build a new rendering system
to handle the needs of the game.
Tools and processes would be adapted
to closely fit those of the original development team.
The problem was that with every new project,
it felt like we were completely starting over.
Code would end up being very tied to a specific title
and thus not move from project to project.
The team, art, engineering, including QA,
all needed to relearn processes
as we moved from game to game.
Basically, it started to conflict with our ideal that each project needs to be better
than the previous.
So for Shadow of the Colossus, we completely revamped how we work.
We made a point of building reusable technology and processes that evolve from project to
project rather than being recreated.
This requires a deeper commitment to processes and long-term planning rather than just solely
focusing on immediate goals.
So we took our Bluepoint engine, dusted it off,
and started to make a major investment.
For reference, the Bluepoint engine is a proprietary engine
and has been around for quite a while.
In fact, it has been licensed and used
to ship several titles, however it was time for it to evolve.
Now, getting back to the goal of getting the game running.
We achieve this goal by merging the original code
with the Bluepoint Engine.
Basically, we structure the code libraries
so that the original game is built
on top of the Bluepoint Engine.
This allows the Bluepoint Engine to provide
all platform-centric systems, such as memory, threading,
file I O, rendering, et cetera.
For us, it is key to keep in mind which original game systems we want to port to the target
platforms and which ones will be replaced by Bluepoint systems.
Basically, we don't want to waste time porting a system that will just be replaced in the
future.
With that said, I think it is important to make one clarification.
When it comes to gameplay systems, AI, character logic, etc.,
we want to keep all of the original systems intact.
While we will fully replace core systems,
with gameplay we take a much more surgical approach to fixing and enhancing.
Next, I want to take a minute to discuss Bluepoint's approach to game assets.
While it is ideal that we get the source assets from the original game team,
and we do to varying levels of success, we do not depend upon them.
Rather, we only use them for reference.
The reason that we don't use source assets as a starting point
is that they're often wrong or incomplete.
Teams are notorious for not checking everything
into source control.
Often local file changes or P4 shelf changes
are used to build the final package,
creating very difficult to find parity issues.
This is exaggerated when dealing with patches
as the likelihood of a one-off local change increases.
To eliminate this concern, we spend around two months
extracting all the data within the original distribution
package to BBE-compatible formats.
We also assume that before we ship,
we will have the need to edit every type of data, not just
key file formats.
While this is time consuming, it has several key benefits.
Number one, we know that the data that we have
is exactly the data that's shipped.
And number two, we actually learn a lot about how the game is constructed,
allowing us to make smarter decisions moving forward.
Understanding the content greatly helps us understand the code,
enables us to make decisions that work with the original code,
as opposed to fighting it.
And number three, once we have extracted the key file formats and converted them to BPE formats,
such as models, animations, skeletons, textures, collision data,
these assets are immediately available within our BPE toolset.
And finally, because we are taking full ownership of the data,
We're no longer dependent upon the content pipeline
of the original team.
We don't need their tools,
and we don't need to follow unfamiliar practices.
It is actually quite liberating
that after the extraction is finished,
we follow Bluepoint processes
rather than the processes of a remote team
that we don't understand.
Now, to be completely honest, there are some game-specific file formats that we don't always extract and will take shortcuts.
We do, however, regenerate these files, addressing like Indianness and 64-bit compatibility issues,
and we spend the time to understand and document their purpose.
For example, in Shadow, we did not fully convert
all of the pathing data to BPE formats
because we figured that we would never change this data.
This came back to bite me in the ass,
and I'll tell you more about it later.
So let's take a look at the final results
that we achieved in Shadow in relationship
to how we integrate two distinct engines.
I like to call this the dance.
Without proper planning and coordination,
chaos would take over.
However, with each engine assuming specific
responsibilities, we can create a harmony of technology.
What this diagram is trying to illustrate
is the responsibilities of each engine.
The original shadow engine maintains sole responsibility
for the majority of all gameplay.
If there was a gameplay bug or a behavior
that we wanted to modify, chances are
that we were going to modify the original shadow code base.
On the other side, the Bluepoint engine
handles all core system responsibilities.
memory, threading, platform services,
along with anything visual.
The Bluepoint engine handles the management of the world,
the static geometry in the world,
the particle systems placed, the lighting, et cetera.
It remains the responsibility of the Shadow engine
to create all dynamic game objects,
such as Aggro, Wander, and Colossi,
within the Bluepoint engine
in order to build a complete scene,
which in turn feeds the render.
Take for example Wander, the main character in the game.
The original game has a concept, an object representing Wander,
and also a link to a BP engine representation of Wander.
The original game provides all the simulation logic and pushes matrices
and the required state information over to the Bluepoint representation.
In turn, the Bluepoint representation can add additional functionalities such as head
tracking and drives the render to ensure that everything shows up in the final scene.
So let's take a look at the game and break down a scene starring Colossus 6.
So who is responsible for what?
Shadow is responsible for all dynamic characters
in the scene, in this case, Wander and the Colossus.
Shadow is responsible for AI behaviors.
When QA would report behavioral problems,
we addressed it within the original code base.
Shadow is responsible for collision.
In retrospect, this was perhaps a mistake
and should have been brought over into BPE
in order to make it easier to work with.
And Shadow is responsible for building the animation blend trees and building the final pose.
Shadow has these responsibilities because the simulation is dependent upon the final pose.
It would have been better for us to use BPE systems for animation.
However, at the time, intertwining Shadow and BPE processes was very difficult.
The eye state of the Colossus was determined by shadow code,
passed to BPE code, where it was managed,
used to determine the correct eye color
and drive dynamic shader parameters.
It is the shadow code that handles the simulation
of the bones that hang around Wander's waist.
These were never lifted into BPE,
given that the original coder did such a great job.
So, that is about where the original Shadow Code ends and the BPE engine takes over.
BPE handles all rendering and scene management.
The entire environment and atmospherics that you see are all handled by BPE.
The physics simulation of Wander's poncho is handled by BPE.
It is purely visual and needed improvement,
and thus all aspects were removed from the shadow code
and moved into Bluepoint.
BPE is responsible for the dynamic rings
attached to the colossi.
In the original, the rings are static and misaligned.
They are now dynamic.
And finally, BPE is responsible for all audio
and particles within a scene.
One way to think about our approach
is that we are taking the original game
and overlaying visuals and enhanced gameplay.
Here's another scene with a path node's debug display enabled.
The blue lines simply show available connections
between nodes, while the purple line
shows the navigation path that aggro your horse
will take to get to you.
When we started the game, we figured
that we would not change the layout of the environments
enough that we would have to modify collision.
This game, this became perhaps the biggest lie
that we told ourselves.
Before shipping, all collision within the game
was completely rebuilt.
We also told ourselves that because we were not significantly changing the layout of the environments,
there would be no need for us to modify path information.
This was also a lie.
As the environment started to be finalized,
QA started flagging issues where Agro could no longer path to you
because someone placed a large tree on top of a path node.
In certain areas, Wander could not find lizards because they were now hidden under hills.
In other areas, the hawks and the birds in the game would start flying through mountains
that were now in their paths.
After a bit of digging, it became obvious
that it was not an acceptable solution
to require art to go back and fix the geometry
to match the constraints of the original.
Instead, within the last two months before shipping,
we wrote a tool that allowed for path nodes
to be visualized and edited directly in the game
and serialized back out.
Before this, the pathing logic was the last piece
of untouched code and data.
Well, we didn't necessarily set out to change
every single piece of data loaded by the game.
It became a necessity.
So I guess the moral of the story is to assume
that if something can bite you in the ass, it will.
I think that's a pretty safe mantra
for anyone in engineering.
So Shadow released a year ago this February.
I explicitly don't want this talk to feel like a postmortem,
but more of a sharing of our approach and processes.
My goal is to be completely transparent
and share what worked and where we fell short.
Well, on Shadow, we had a fairly sophisticated worker job system.
We were not able to retrofit enough code to take full advantage of it.
We had this notion of the Shadow code completing its full simulation before moving on to handling
BPE game objects.
The CPU frame was broken up so that Shadow took approximately 70% of the game frame,
and the Bluepoint engine took about the other 30%.
We could find areas to optimize Shadow code by jobifying, however, this basically just
moved code from one core to another and really, without really increasing the CPU saturation.
As a result, we did not get much parallelization within the game code.
Within the Bluepoint Engine, we represent a scene as a tree of game objects,
where each game object contains components that exposes functionality.
To update a scene, we would walk the game object tree and update all components.
The overhead of walking the tree quickly became time-consuming.
To make things worse, we would actually walk the GameObject tree a second time to build
a list of items to render.
This happened during the sync point between the game and the rendering threads, creating
a major bottleneck.
Well, towards the end of Shadow's development, we implemented a couple of Hail Marys to address
the problem.
They were Band-Aids at best.
Moving forward to our next project, we knew that we needed to re-architect how we coordinate the game loops between the two engines.
Basically, it was time to take what we had learned and evolve the dance.
The major breakthrough for us came when we decided to stop treating the original code
base as special, but rather as just another think process that happens at a specific point
in the frame.
You can think of the entire original shadow game code as a component on a game object
exposing functionality.
And fortunately, this is easier said than done.
To evolve to where we are today, beyond Shadow, we had to make the following changes.
Number one, the first thing that we did is we eliminated the need to walk game objects
to determine what needs to be rendered.
Rather, we make components responsible for adding and removing persistent render items,
and we support a command buffer style interface for changing render item parameters
to keep everything thread safe.
Number two, we no longer walk the game object tree
to update components.
Rather, components register think request delegates.
Think requests can be added or removed
at any point from any thread.
A single object can submit as many think requests
as desired based upon demand.
This makes it very easy to create objects
that only need to think for one frame
or under certain conditions.
Think requests can also be invoked at any point.
If not explicitly invoked, they will be invoked
when their bucket is processed.
However, it is trivial to be in the middle of a think request,
start an async job that you need to wait for,
and invoke other think requests to ensure that we never stall.
With these changes and looking back at shadow, now rather than merging the shadow game loop with the blue point game loop,
we would simply have the shadow code register a think request within the correct bucket,
eliminating the distinction between the shadow update and the BPE update.
When the original shadow code needed to wait for async jobs,
it would simply start processing other think requests rather than installing.
This type of behavior is proving to be critical
on our next project.
In fact, this last week, I spent a day rearranging
think request dependencies to fix stalls,
saving approximately two milliseconds within our game loop.
I didn't optimize any code.
Rather, I simply fixed scheduling issues
to increase CPU saturation.
Having the flexibility to easily rearrange a frame's work
to fill dead areas and remove contention
is proving to be awesome.
So here's a diagram showing our current running layout.
It is much easier to use and a lot more flexible.
At this point, my only regret is that we didn't implement
this system earlier.
So rather than looking at Shadow, let's take a look
at how we have evolved and what's next.
So, sorry, I hope you didn't think that I was going
to expose our next project.
I know this isn't funny, well, maybe it is a little bit to me.
While I'm super excited about our next project and the tech
that we are building, I'm pretty sure
Bluepoint would make me walk home all the way to Texas
just to shoot me if I screwed this up.
So next, I want to talk about what
we have learned from past projects
and how it affects our systems.
How we go about creating a harmony of technology
by doing a deep dive into our memory system.
how it is designed with flexibility,
and what steers those decisions.
Before I do so, here's a quick disclaimer.
All of the examples that I'm going to share
are based upon my personal experiences and memories.
And my examples are based on outdated technology
from the companies in question
and don't represent their current technology or processes.
And finally, I apologize in advance
if I misrepresent anyone's work.
So, memory, who needs it?
I'm pretty sure I do.
I've been working or dealing with memory systems
since I started my career.
Over this time, I have tried numerous approaches
and have shifted the way I view memory
based upon the games that I have shipped.
In fact, I wrote an article
for Game Programming Gems years ago.
As I look back, I still embrace the ideas presented,
but I'm a bit embarrassed
that the implementations were so short-sighted.
I actually got my first job in the games industry
working for Beyond Games, creating a Hot Wheels game.
The key to landing this job was a BSP collision system
that I had written that required less than half
the memory footprint of the current system,
basically cutting memory requirements
from six to two megs on a PS2.
If there's one lesson that I learned then
that is just as true today,
it is that proper memory management
is critical to achieving performance and shipping titles.
So let's take a look at Bluepoint's hardest title to date,
shipping Titanfall on the Xbox 360.
What an amazing game Respawn created,
and if you buy me a drink, I have a lot of stories.
If you don't recall, the original Titanfall
was developed by Respawn and released on the PC and Xbox One.
Bluepoint released the Xbox 360 version
approximately two months later.
Simple summary, if I ignore the performance aspect, it is not easy to ship a 5GB Xbox
One game on an Xbox 360 with 512MB.
So how did we do it?
A lot of hard work, or as we like to call it, Blue Point Magic.
The original game used a fixed-size bucket allocator for allocations less than 32 bytes
and DLMalloc for everything else, where all memory allocations were funneled into a single
allocator and dispatched from there, creating a choke point where thread contention became
a major issue.
I know that a lot of people love DLMalloc
and argue that it is sufficient.
Well, it has a lot of great features.
In practice on Titanfall, we found that,
number one, the version of DLMalloc we used
did not have any concept of virtual allocations,
and thus a custom system was required.
Number two, DLMalloc was not ideal for large page-aligned allocations.
DLMalloc works by placing tags at the beginning of allocations.
If you need a texture with 128-byte alignment, the tag can create memory waste.
And number three, due to DLMalloc not being ideal for small allocations, virtual allocs,
or page size allocations, we needed DLMalloc to release unused memory back to other memory
systems.
In practice, we found that DLMalloc held on to more memory than we thought was ideal.
The key to shipping Titanfall from a memory point of view
was memory tracking,
knowing exactly where all memory was at all times,
tracking fragmentation issues,
and tracking memory by category
so that the peaks could be compared from build to build
to determine trends.
From there, we were able to optimize data formats
in nearly every system to cut memory usage.
We reworked the memory system to,
we used a fixed block size allocator
for small allocations, less than 512 bytes.
We used DLMalloc for medium sized allocations,
and several changes were made to DLMalloc
to get it to aggressively release memory.
And we used a large page based allocator
used primarily for textures and large vertex buffers.
And we added a concept of a single frame allocation,
where small allocations would be placed
within unused DXT Mipmap memory.
This memory was only valid for a single frame
and coordinated with the texture streaming system.
Basically, every byte was used.
By the end, we had spreadsheets backed by more spreadsheets
for every level showing max memory usage,
how much memory was available for texture streaming,
et cetera.
Well, I'm still in shock that we pulled it off.
Looking back, the whole system was perhaps
a bit more complicated than it needed to be.
So, Uncharted, what a great project.
Going from a PS3 target to a PS4 target,
how could there be any memory considerations?
Well, there weren't any real memory considerations
provided we kept streaming textures reasonable.
However, there are a couple of key things that we learned.
Number one, all memory was allocated at startup
by the core memory system.
From here, all memory was assigned to specific allocators.
There was a hard-coded table within the code
dictating how much memory each allocator was allotted.
The downside is that when an allocator ran out of memory,
you would play the Russian roulette game
to push memory around until the problem went away,
often over-allocating.
There was no virtual memory support and fragmentation issues were evident.
There was code to handle the shuffling of memory and pointers when defragging,
however, it came across as error-prone and touched numerous systems.
The later Uncharted games adopted a rule
that memory could not be allocated before hitting main.
I loved this ideal, given that it was straightforward
when to create your memory allocator,
and at the end of main you could easily check
to ensure that there were no memory leaks.
And finally, Uncharted introduced the idea
of a tagged heap allocator, which is very similar
to a single frame allocator that we implemented
for Titanfall, just evolved.
So, what were some of the philosophies
that we felt were important when designing
the memory system for the Bluepoint engine?
Number one, we should never run out of memory.
Never expect null from an allocation request.
In fact, we explicitly halt the game if this happens.
Number two, we need smart allocation schemes
to allow for a wide variety of allocation patterns.
Basically, encourage small custom allocators
rather than an Uber allocator.
Number three, allocators should help to eliminate thread contention.
And four, ensure debuggability across all allocators without a lot of custom work.
To us, debuggability in this case means the ability to track and categorize all memory allocations
and tools to help detect and diagnose common memory issues, with the most common being memory stomps.
With these basic philosophies in place,
we built a list of our goals,
and I'm only gonna touch on a couple of the key points.
Number one, we determined that all allocators
should be platform agnostic.
We didn't wanna write custom allocators for each platform.
An allocator should deal with memory patterns,
not the specifics of where the memory came from.
Number two, allocators should be memory agnostic.
Basically, every allocator should work
with both CPU or GPU memory.
While this seems trivial, it does have implications.
During Shadow, our per-frame GPU memory allocators
benefited greatly by removing tags and markers
that were being written directly into the memory blocks
for memory tracking.
Assume that memory will be allocated at any point.
Programmers need power and flexibility
to create great systems.
Number four.
We wanted to eliminate the need for fixed-sized allocators.
Basically, allocators should work with fixed memory blocks,
but also should support growing and shrinking as required.
We want to avoid over-allocating
and the memory Russian roulette game.
To get started, let's look at how we ensure all memory allocations are routed through our memory systems.
We start by overriding system memory routines, which is pretty straightforward.
And second, we create BPE macros to wrap all memory requests.
We choose to use macros for a couple of reasons.
Number one, they are simple, straightforward, and require no additional steps.
Number two, some sort of redirection is required to support malloc and free.
And VirtualAlloc will also require custom wrappers to be platform agnostic, so it's nice to sort of standardize everything.
And then macros also allow us to provide additional features, such as location tracking and passing additional parameters directly to memory requests, such as alignment requirements and requesting specific allocators.
Converting to using macros is not a big undertaking.
I've done it about three times in my career,
and each time it takes about a week.
If you do not redirect and control all allocations
within your code, I highly recommend that you start,
and using macros is the cleanest method that I've found.
And even if you forget to wrap a new or a delete,
it doesn't matter, it'll still get picked up
to overriding the system memory routines.
And finally, to ensure we redirect all memory routines into our system, we simply control all memory.
On consoles, we allocate all physical memory upon initialization.
As a result, if we miss an allocation due to a third-party library, there simply isn't any memory for it to request.
Talking about third-party libraries,
whether audio, physics, video playback, or anything else,
I think there are a couple of mandates
that I believe that we should all insist upon.
Number one being, if a library does not
provide direct control for how it gets its memory,
don't use it.
If you can't control the threading behavior of a library,
And if you can't control how it loads files, don't use it.
There is one third-party library that I would like to call out that we use extensively.
The EASTL, which is a replacement for the standard containers.
I hope that anyone that has been in game development for any amount of time
has at least an opinion on the debate of whether or not to use standard containers.
For us, we don't.
However, we have found an awesome replacement
that provides a lot of really cool features
that, while not always safe, allow for smarter code.
If you haven't checked out the EASTL,
I strongly suggest you do.
So, let's take a look at a diagram
illustrating the flow of memory requests.
As you can see, it all starts
with overriding system allocation routines,
which are redirected into our memory coordinator.
From there, memory requests are funneled
into appropriate allocators.
These allocators manage their own memory pools to service memory requests and fall back to requesting memory pages from the platform page allocator.
Note that the only system that is platform specific is the platform page allocator.
This helps to ensure allocators only deal with memory usage patterns and ensure that we get consistency across all platforms.
So the MC contains some of the hardest hit code
in the entire code base.
Its primary purpose is to redirect memory requests
to the appropriate allocator,
all without creating thread contention.
Thus, it must avoid locking mechanisms.
We are able to achieve this goal by ensuring that the MC is
basically stateless and that the few stack-based variables
that it forwards into the allocators
are all stored using thread-local-storage.
There's one caveat to keep in mind.
Our threaded job system is constructed using fibers
that we switch in and out.
Because we are using thread-local-storage,
we need to prevent fibers from picking up
the wrong set of variables when switched.
So,
Within our job system, if we perform a context switch
and switch out a fiber, we also create a copy
of the memory local thread variables.
Then when the job system switches back
to the previously suspended fiber,
we restore the local thread variables.
That's keeping everyone happy and consistent.
By using thread local variables,
not only do we allow memory requests
to be redirected to any specific allocator,
but it is also at the heart of how we categorize memory.
In our engine, every single allocation is categorized,
even if it is just categorized as a general allocation.
Our strategy is once a category starts
to account for too much memory,
we simply start splitting the category
and refining our tracking.
And finally.
The MC gives us a great single location
to track all out-of-memory issues,
eliminating the need to spread that code
throughout the entire code base,
or throughout the allocators.
One tip that you can see from the code snippet
is that we create a special function
that is never inline to handle out-of-memory issues.
This has actually been really great.
If QA ever encounters a crash,
it is trivial to determine if it was an out-of-memory issue
by directly looking at the extracted call stack.
No need to look at the log
or try to interpret line numbers.
The allocator, or as I like to think about it,
the heart of the system.
This snippet shows a portion of the interface
that all allocators must provide.
The primary idea here that I want to call your attention to
is the fact that we declare all memory routines as protected.
Basically, we want to prevent code
from directly bypassing the memory coordinator.
This helps to ensure that all allocators follow
consistent conventions and are properly registered
with the memory coordinator.
I mentioned earlier, anytime an allocator needs to grow its memory pool to service a
request, it requests new memory pages from our platform page allocator.
For Shadow on the PS4, we determined that 64K pages were the ideal size.
We also aligned all requested pages to 1MB boundaries.
We wanted smaller pages to minimize waste and fragmentation,
but also minimize the TLB issues.
For us, 64K pages was the sweet spot.
I also want to point out that when coding allocators,
we strictly avoid the use of mutexes.
While allocators need to deal with threading issues,
we stick to using atomic locks.
These are significantly faster,
and the restriction of not being reentrant
is easy to work around.
So let's take a look at a few of the different types of allocators that we support.
The dispatch allocator is the default allocator that the majority of all allocations get redirected
to.
It is a very simple redirector that basically looks at the alignment and size requirements
of a request and forwards them to the appropriate allocator.
We use a bucket allocator for small allocations.
We use a heap allocator, which is similar to DLMalloc.
It uses an intrusive red-black tree to store free blocks
and uses a heuristic of preferring recently freed
memory followed by best fit, then adds headers and post
headers to the allocations to provide tracking information.
And to round it off, we use a page allocator for large memory
requests that fit nicely into our 64k pages.
We also have several special use allocators,
a simple ASCII allocator that is only used by tool code.
There is a virtual page allocator
to handle virtual memory requests.
And there is a frame allocator, which
is great for packing multiple requests together
to ensure memory coherency and creating
small blocks of reusable memory.
And let's not forget about the tagged frame allocator, which
is awesome.
Our tagged frame allocator is based upon an allocator
described by Christian Gerling in his 2015 GDC talk.
The basic idea behind the tagged frame allocator
is that we are creating an extremely fast allocators
where allocations are only valid for a short period of time.
These are basically temporary memory allocations
that are valid for n number of frames
where a frame is arbitrarily defined for each allocator.
The fact that we don't need to track the memory
or call free to release memory is a huge win.
Not only is the code requesting the memory easier to write,
the tag frame allocator can take a bunch of shortcuts
knowing that individual free calls do not need to be supported.
It is also impossible to create memory leaks with this allocator.
As we discussed earlier...
One of the primary goals behind allocators
is that they should help to minimize thread contention.
This is achieved using two strategies.
Number one, we use atomic locks rather than mutexes.
And number two,
by using thread local storage.
Several of our allocators use the pattern
illustrated in the code snippet.
For the tag frame allocator,
this allows it to service memory requests
for multiple threads simultaneously without ever locking.
If you've ever had to deal with multi-threaded performance,
this should jump out immediately as a huge win.
Within the Bluepoint Engine, there are more tag frame allocators than any other type of allocator.
Each tag frame allocator is built on top of a tag framed arena,
which allows all tag framed allocators to share a common memory pool,
eliminating over allocation issues.
The tag frame arena will also grow and shrink upon demand, thus all pool sizes are dynamic.
If you don't have anything similar to this in your code
base, I would highly recommend that you make it happen.
And finally, the platform page allocator, or the brains of
the operation.
As we have discussed, this class is responsible for
abstracting away the details of how 64K pages are managed.
In practice, we restrict anyone from accessing this
class directly.
The only customers of this class are the memory
allocators.
On Windows, this is a very simple class
and is built using Virtual Alloc.
The PS4 version is more complex
due to platform considerations.
At the heart of both implementations
is the concept of virtual memory
and mapping physical to virtual addresses on demand.
If you're not familiar with the differences
between virtual and physical memory,
you might want to investigate.
So looking at the platform page allocator,
there's one last problem that I would like to discuss,
which is a problem in every non-Uber memory system
that I've worked with.
Given that we are avoiding an Uber allocator
and embracing numerous allocation patterns,
we need to be able to take any random memory address
and determine which allocator it belongs to.
This is required to properly direct free calls.
While BPE macros allow us to optionally specify
which allocator owns memory when calling BPE free,
this is not ideal.
Instead, we need to support the getMemoryOwner routine.
So, how did we solve this problem?
We threw memory at it.
We break up the problem by realizing that we only need to determine which allocator owns the memory page that contains the memory address in question.
Within the platform page allocator, we use a 1MB block of memory to store a direct lookup table which maps 1TB of virtual memory to its owning allocator.
If you have a better solution, I'd love to hear it.
So what do you get when you put this all together?
Hopefully a game without performance issues
and runs within retail memory.
OK, that isn't going to happen.
But hopefully you have the flexibility and tools
necessary to get there from a memory perspective.
Here's a screenshot showing our memory statistics.
You can see the platform page allocator at the top
and each of the various allocators below.
Here's another screenshot that shows memory category tracking.
I want to call your attention to the outlined black boxes that I've marked up.
Most consoles have a concept of development memory.
Basically, the development kit has more memory
than the retail kits.
We make it very easy at all times
to see where memory usage is in regards to a retail kit.
From the screenshot, you can see that the closest
that we came to running out of memory on a retail kit
was 130 megs, or the equivalent of the max memory of four PS2
games.
There's no way we could run out of memory.
So to finish up, I want to share one additional feature
in Shadow of the Colossus.
It is related to memory and made a significant impact
on development.
Texture streaming.
I'm sure many of you have texture streaming solutions.
We use GPU-based feedback to determine what to stream
and specify a fixed streaming texture memory budget.
For Shadow, we initially set this budget to one gig,
and after some tweaking, most of the game looked great.
Some areas required a higher texture budget
to facilitate its needs.
And some areas would simply crash
due to running out of memory
before even hitting the one gig budget.
It was about halfway through the development
that the team began to stress about memory
and started getting flashbacks of previous projects.
So how did we solve the problem?
We set the texture streaming budget to unlimited.
Problem solved, and now everyone is happy.
Instead of relying upon a fixed memory budget,
the texture manager monitors the total available memory
by querying the platform page allocator
and acting appropriately.
If there is extra memory, stream in more textures.
If no more textures are required,
then there's nothing to do.
And if memory is low, start releasing textures.
I should note that this does require a bit of balancing to avoid ping pong effects and to determine proper memory thresholds.
However, these thresholds are game-specific, not area-specific, so they only needed to be calculated once.
This was really a major turning point for stability
as out-of-memory issues basically disappeared.
Of course, we still had to deal with memory usage issues
where memory was scarce.
However, these areas only needed to be pushed
to an acceptable level,
and the texture manager would auto-calibrate.
Moving forward, we were pushing
our texture streaming solution
beyond what was achievable in Shadow
by prioritizing and loading even higher resolution textures
when memory allows.
So here's a screenshot showing texture streaming stats
at the top of the screen.
Here you can see that we have over 2 gigs of textures loaded.
However, the scene only actually requires about 680 megs
of texture data as the texture manager
tries to maintain a buffer of about 220 megs free.
Here's a more demanding area.
There is 1.3 gigs of textures loaded,
however only 1.13 gigs are required.
During development, the art team would play the game
watching these statistics to verify
that the budgets were satisfied.
By the end, the only questionable area in the game
was the final cut scene where the secret garden is exposed.
And of course, the minute you tell anyone
that the texture budget has exceeded,
you need to be able to show them why and what is loaded.
It is only then that you can properly debate
how big must the eye texture be.
Y'all get that?
Okay, good.
So, once again, I would like to thank you
for your participation.
I'm flattered that I've had this opportunity to ramble on.
And yes, Blue Point Games is hiring.
Basically, if you are a badass,
and you know how to get shit done,
we want to work with you.
Use the email address on the slide and mention my name.
I'll let everyone know that we are best friends
so I can get the recruiting bonus.
And then perhaps it'll be time for me to buy you a beer.
Also remember to fill out the speaker evaluation forms so I know whether or not I should ever do this again.
With that I believe I'm done. I believe we have
eight minutes for questions if anybody has any questions.
I love it, the perfect talk, there's no questions.
That's perfect, let's wrap it up.
Get the hell out of here.
I had a question.
Yeah.
You talk about being lock-free
using atomics in your allocators.
So we still live in a world where there's no standard
lock-free container library that you can,
like, do you guys, did you use a third-party one?
Did you roll stuff in-house?
Yeah, so for the atomic locks,
we basically just sort of rolled our own.
Just using,
you know the, I'm drawing a blank right this second,
but basically just using the atomics that are available
on the different platforms.
It really comes down to like four or five lines of code.
If you were to send me an email, I could send it to you.
It's real simple.
Sure, now I mean, you didn't do unbounded spinning though,
did you, for some of your locks?
They will spin, yes.
Okay.
Did you ever see stuff where like,
I've seen like spin lock, it's all fun and games until.
you know, your spinning core is scheduled and the work you need to be done that it's waiting on to
get the lock back is, it's not, you know, have you, did you see some of that? Not really, and part of
it as well as any time that we use atomics, so we'll use the atomics anytime we want, we've got
a really small portion that we want to get in and out of really fast.
And we also try to lock it or try to make it so that we're really not calling other functions inside of it.
So we don't run into this case of I got a lock here, I call this function and then this guy wants to lock.
And so they're not re-entrant.
And so we keep those sections very, very small.
And so we really haven't had any problems with them,
or having problems of something waiting for any duration of time before it could get back in.
We also do a lot of performance profiling,
looking to make sure that in order to maximize CPU
saturation across all of our cores,
making sure that they're just for that fact
that there is nobody that's stalling
or waiting for too long.
I guess I've seen when spending goes bad is usually
when you're oversubscribed.
I don't know, did you work hard to avoid oversubscription
on the platform and stuff like that?
Yes.
I would say we work hard to avoid it.
You said your next game is going to be more of a re-envisioning.
I was wondering if we could get some color on what that kind of means.
What is a re-envisioning versus a remake?
Sure.
So, if you were to take a look at Shadow of the Colossus, it's a PS2 game, right?
And so, when that was built...
The side of the hills were very low triangle density.
Like, what was the environment,
what was the atmospherics
that they're actually trying to achieve?
And when you look at it, a lot of it,
you feel like your mind fills in a lot of those blanks.
You look at a green card that's filled on the back
and you're like, yeah, I assume that's a grass plane, right?
And so for Shadow, there's a lot of us looking at that
and then building it out, sort of trying to remake it,
but sort of figure out what the original was trying to do.
As we move forward in some of our other stuff,
we're taking stuff further with not just, you know,
trying to get the two engines to run simultaneously,
but more of bringing more and more stuff into our engine
and repurposing our technology
so that we have greater control of, you know,
redoing the complete animation systems.
upgrading, you know, besides graphics and other things,
but even starting to upgrade more of the gameplay paths and such,
which are all, for us, are always very, very tricky.
We've been very, very fortunate to work on games that we've absolutely loved.
And for Shadow, like, you wouldn't take that game and say,
I want to make it like Assassin's Creed, running around, doing stuff.
You wouldn't do that.
And so you want to maintain core pieces.
So it's a very difficult question, but it's just...
take shadow and I feel like we're about doubling the amount of involvement that we're putting into it.
Thank you.
Hi, I would like to ask you how do you deal with frame rate issues, especially with doing the sort of hybrid approach you took with like two game engines running at the same time?
So how do we deal with frame rate issues?
We as I mentioned anybody at Blue Point
has heard me rant about digital foundry at least
a bazillion times because I don't know if you've
seen their evaluations where they do the frame rate graph
and they show it going straight across the screen.
And I tell the team if we have a single dip
they're going to find it and I'll lose my mind.
And so we do a lot of profiling.
Our QA department is great.
They take our tools and our third-party PS4 tools,
and they'll have graphs that are running on their machine.
So they're playing the game with the frame rate graph,
and the minute they see any sort of spike
or anything like that, they go and they capture it,
create a bug, and off it goes to engineering.
On Shadow, we have a 60 FPS mode on the Pro Kits.
in performance mode.
That was not easy hitting that.
It's a lot of testing, a lot of looking at CPU captures,
and exactly what jobs are on what cores when and why,
and trying to load balance that out.
And for our next game,
the big thing that we're really looking at
is how do we maximize our CPU saturation.
I feel like we've got a good job system to break stuff up,
but you find at the same time, like during your frame,
you've got areas that are, here's the hot spot.
Everybody wants this last third quarter of the frame,
and nobody's doing anything over here.
So a lot of analyzing and rearranging code
in order to get it to fill in all those spots.
Yeah, I guess the second question is how,
when you convert from like 30 FPS game to 60,
how do you deal with game breaking issues?
Oh, uh, yes, so, the original game ticked the update at a hard-coded, you know, 30 FPS.
And so, on the PS2, I don't know, to be honest, I don't know if the game actually ever hit 30.
Um...
And so, yeah, the minute we went to 60 or the minute we even locked it at 30,
we found that you couldn't climb the colossi as well.
Your grip would fall before getting around some of the edges was twice as hard.
And so, I really got to, you know, give credit to that to our QA department.
They test the game like no other and are looking for parity issues.
They identify those sort of issues and then we go back and we fix them.
And a lot of times, programmers love when they look at a bug
and they're like, I don't know why it's behaving this way.
And it's like, well, go play it on the PS2,
on a PS2 dev kit.
And it's like, I don't even know how to make
that thing run anymore.
But it has to be done.
Okay, thank you.
Hey, Gretel, there's a lot of issues that speak close to my heart.
So I was wondering if you have any solution, any utility libraries or whatever
to deal with the 32-bit to 64-bit address space conversion.
Any libraries that deal with 32 to 64-bit conversions?
Yeah, any kind of like injection or, you know, remapping of the 32-bit address space
into 64-bit or something like that to ease the process of porting
and moving to a 64-bit platform.
Yeah.
We don't really use a third-party library to do that.
It's a lot, at the end it comes down to us
doing a lot of hard work and updating code.
The one thing that I would throw out
that I didn't really talk about,
but is mentioned in the slides,
is what we use is we call the T offset pointer.
Which basically allows us to represent any address
as a 32-bit number, and then when you actually
do the lookup, when you dereference it to a pointer,
we actually add an offset to it.
We use that a lot in memory mapped files that have to do that so that we don't break everything right out of the gate.
But even then by the end, they get annoying because now every single pointer dereference is basically a dereference and it's adding and
I don't know, it's stupid shit like that that just like, why are we wasting processor power drives me crazy.
And we end up going through and fixing most of them.
Alright, thanks.
Yeah, I'm curious about you have the BluePoint engine and then you've got the game engine and I presume you take the BluePoint engine from project to project?
That is correct.
And you have the game engine, does it call directly down into the BluePoint engine?
And how do you keep the BluePoint engine side of things from not having references up into the game that have to be cleaned up from project to project?
Right.
So.
You could say, I've been writing code for a really long time,
and you could say there's certain things,
like coding standards.
It's like a religion.
What side of the fence do you fall on?
There's certain things with coding standards
that I strongly believe in and drive me crazy.
One of those is dealing with library dependencies.
If I've got a base library, and I've got my game library,
there's no way in the code base that I
allow the core library to start calling up.
And so we make very explicit rules about what library is built on top of what,
so we have a very clear hierarchy.
Then it's going through and we'll add layers in the middle that's sort of like,
here's a wrapper piece that is basically the bridge between shadow code...
and the BPE engine working with our components and game objects.
It can basically go and do, like, reach into Shadow Code, or Shadow Code reaches into it a lot.
And then I'm okay with that, because at the end I know that whole piece gets thrown away.
And so I don't incur that debt.
So it's essentially just a wrapper for it, so that the game can preserve its original engine calls that wrap to calling into the actual Bluepoint engine?
And if you think about it, like any game engine, it all boils down to you've got a main loop somewhere, you've got a forever loop that's looping, doing whatever.
And then the Bluepoint engine is similar, it's got a forever loop, they're both basically looping.
Well now rather than looping, I'm just gonna make this one,
when it loops it calls in over here, does its thing,
comes back out over here, goes back to the top and calls,
and so it just sort of ping-pongs.
And the next thing you gotta do is come up with
areas of responsibility.
And so then you start going to the original game engine,
and you're like, no, no, no, you don't do anything with audio.
You don't do anything with rendering.
You don't do anything, you know, dealing with,
I don't know, scene management.
That's all gonna be over here.
That's the hardest part is defining all those rules and levels of responsibility.