So thank you so much for being here.
We came from Austria, as you might hear eventually,
and we're super excited to bring our knowledge to you guys.
Today, we want to talk about tackling
audience experiences in games.
So not looking at games from the typical player's
point of view, but there are also other people
who might be interested in the game.
But first things first, let me quickly introduce ourselves.
So my name is Johanna Birke.
And my name is Rainer Angewand.
I'm a researcher and I'm a lecturer at the Graz University of Technology in Austria.
So I'm coming from the academic side.
And I'm CEO and co-founder of the Austrian-based indie studio Rearbyte.
So my background, I have a PhD in computer science.
I love doing research, I love doing data analysis,
like machine learning.
I love looking at the player's point of view
through this data analysis.
I also do AI research.
So everything very academic versus very researchy.
Well, I'm not a doctor, but I've been working a lot in games
and our company has published about 25 titles
on all the major platforms.
So we're into creating, developing, and publishing games.
All I can publish is papers as an academic,
which is also lovely because I can gather knowledge
and bring it to the people by publishing those papers.
And to publish those papers, I obviously need data.
But again, when I do not develop games or publish games,
I don't have often access to this data.
So...
Yeah, luckily our games produce a lot of data
that can be used for analyzing them.
So we found that being a researcher at a research institution
and working together with an indie game studio
is a very, very good benefit for both of us
because I can use this data to help their studio
to improve their games.
On the other hand, I can also use this data
to publish interesting contributions for the community.
So we found this is something which we have in common,
but there's also something else we do have in common.
We both love streaming.
So I love streaming games.
I'm a streamer myself.
I'm not a good streamer or popular streamer,
but I enjoy it myself.
And what I found most interesting actually
was looking at the chat while streaming.
Because looking at the chat,
there's something going on which is so different
compared to what we have when designing games.
So there's the entire population of spectators.
and we wanted to find out more about those spectators through data analysis.
Yeah, well I've also gained a lot of experience in streaming. It's more about streaming development
and playtesting of our games. So, yeah, today...
We want to talk about this spectator.
Who is a spectator and how can we design
to engage spectators?
And last but not least, we want to give away
some evaluation strategies that we use together
in this field.
So we will give this talk a little bit from the researcher's perspective and then also
from the designer developer's perspective.
So when we think about a spectator, we need to first find a proper definition for a spectator.
A spectator can be found in so many different and several places.
A spectator can be someone watching a stream without any action, just being there and watching a streamer.
But it can be also someone who is really involved and really engaged, constantly interacting with the streamer
and with other spectators through the chat, for example, asking questions, making comments.
It can be also someone who is just sitting at home, maybe a parent watching over the shoulder of the child playing a video game,
maybe being invested, maybe not at all.
But it could be also a fan in a stadium filled with thousands of fans enjoying together a StarCraft play.
So spectators can be found in so many several places and we also need to consider the different
types of spectators with different backgrounds. For this talk we want to use a definition of
spectators, that spectators are basically people who follow the gameplay in real time without being
the main player in the game. Eventually they have impact on the game to some extent which
we'll hear later but it's not the main focus.
But first let us take a step back and see what is important for the player.
So the player wants to have a good playing and streaming experience.
And a player wants interaction possibilities with the viewers that are there in the chat or viewing on site for example.
It's all about entertaining those viewers and retaining those viewers.
And in the end, the goal is to build a community around the game, the player, and the stream, for example.
When you design a video game for a spectator, however,
you need to think of different aspects.
Because as soon as a player would enter a stream,
the spectator must immediately know what's going on,
understand the gameplay mechanics, and so on.
You should think of different interaction possibilities
with either the player or with the other viewers.
They want to be entertained, surprised,
so they have different motives for coming to the stream.
Or they just want to be part of the community
as a social aspect.
need to know that.
Fans and spectators is something different.
A fan can become to a, a spectator can become to a fan,
but they don't start off as a fan immediately.
So fans are usually motivated by a lot of achievements.
However, a spectator can be motivated
by so many different things
without the necessity that they are fans.
They can just enjoy the aesthetics of the game,
this drama or the skill of players.
There are different strategies which are definitely interesting for us as game designers,
how to make views to fans, but that's probably a different talk.
Today we want to focus on the motives for the spectators and what's interesting about that.
Spectators are motivated by different aspects of a streaming or game watching experience.
So some are eventually more interested in the game itself, some are eventually interested in
the streamer or player or team, esports team, as a person or as a team, and others are interested
in the social experiences and want to interact with other spectators or the community.
So, in literature we can find different motives for spectating.
Interestingly enough, there's not a lot of research yet on streaming or in eSports behavior.
It's...
growing and becoming more important.
But the most research we found,
and which is very similar to what we're interested in,
can be found in sports events.
So going to a football game, to a soccer game, for example,
and understanding the spectator's motives there
can help us also understand the motives
for people watching a stream or going to an e-sports mat.
So some of the motives can be, for example,
the identification, that a spectator really
wants to be associated with a successful player
and also wants to celebrate the success.
The aesthetics, this is really, really important.
They really enjoy the beauty of the game.
we have drama and excitement. This is this idea that you experience this thrill, maybe stress,
but a very pleasant form of stress while watching a game. Escape. Escape would be that you escape
from this daily routine and you come home from work and you just turn on a stream and watch the
stream just to getting relaxed again.
Knowledge. Eventually you're a gamer yourself and you want to learn more about the game.
You want to experience through the skills of the player and you want to learn the social interactions.
Especially on Twitch this is so important that you're able to communicate with other spectators.
This relation to some sort of a community, to some sort of a group.
And then the team or the player support.
That you're part of a community who is supporting a player.
Similar to player types, which all of you might know,
there are also different types of spectators.
This is one simple model we built,
where you have the player and the game
as main interest points for spectators.
Could be also other spectators.
And some people really want to interact.
Some, however, want to consume.
So those, for example, who want to interact with other players
or with the players are socializers.
Those who want to consume and learn from the skills
from a player, for example, can be learners.
Those who want to be part of the game,
make some sort of impact on the game, can be participators.
And those who are consuming the games,
they're just enjoying the beauty.
And based on that, in literature, we find nine different personas.
And what we all know, when we create games, it's always important to think about those
different personas who we are designing the games for.
Same can be done for spectators.
So there's for example the bystander. The bystander is someone who is still not very
interested in the game yet, who just happens to be there. This one is either uninformed about the
game or uninvested and not really engaged yet. However this can change.
If there's something happening which is engaging, for example some drama or some excitement,
this one can become to a curious one. The curious is suddenly interested in the game and then wants
to learn more about the game. It starts with a small fascination and they eventually start
watching and watching more and this one eventually becomes to the inspired. The inspired
feels like, oh, that's a cool game.
I also want to play this game.
This one would eventually, after the stream,
go to Steam and buy the game him or herself.
This is already a very, very nice process
when he got too inspired.
And as soon as you already know about the game, you eventually become the pupil.
A pupil, this one wants to learn. This one wants to understand specific techniques,
tricks of the player, or wants to learn about specific maps within the game.
He's or she's very interested in learning details, so this one would ask questions,
would interact with the player, or would interact with other spectators.
And then there's the unsatisfied, AKA the grumpy one,
who'd rather like to be playing him or herself,
which comes from a desire.
An example for that would be a dad playing with his son,
and the son wants to play and the dad has to watch,
but actually wants to play himself.
Next, there's the entertained and the entertained would rather prefer watching over playing.
So, there's this difference that content is being watched for entertainment basically like a movie.
Then we have the assistant.
The assistant wants to sort of impact the game progress.
They want to help, they want to be some sort of advisor.
This one would be, for example,
all the brothers sitting next to me
and trying to help me through the levels.
But this could be also someone
who wants to tell me about things
which I don't want to know
because I want to explore the game myself.
Then there's the commentator.
This is a very interesting one.
This one is a spectator and a performer or entertainer
at the same time.
This one wants to entertain other spectators.
This one would be constantly talking about the game,
giving comments, in the chat, in the Twitch chat,
also constantly talking about the game.
This can be some sort of a cameraman
telling a different perspective.
And last, the last one is a part of the crowd.
This one wants to be part of the community.
If something insane is happening
and the crowd would go wild or in a stream,
the entire chat will be flooded.
This is what the part of the crowd would enjoy.
Yeah, so now that we've learned about these different types of personas, of spectators,
how can we design to engage the spectators?
Well, first of all, our main goal as a game designer
would be to create a playable game.
But speaking of spectators, we also
want to create a watchable game.
So that means viewers need to be able to understand what's
going on in the game, and they need
to be able to keep track of everything that is going on
in the game at any time.
And also, we want to retain those viewers.
That means we want them to come back to our stream
or to our play session.
And they should keep watching.
What we identified were those three phases of spectator engagement.
First, we want to attract people to a game or to a stream, and we want to teach them about the game.
So, what is the game about? How is the game played? What are the rules of the game?
Next, we want to retain those viewers so that they come back and maybe tell others and watch again,
keep watching. And third, we want community involvement and engagement. So that means
we want people to interact with streamers and with each other.
And this is all to support the spectator's motives that we have heard before.
So, for example, we can attract with the aesthetics of a game,
or with drama, or just with basic simplicity,
so that people know how the game works.
And we can use drama for retaining viewers, for example, and we can try to build up knowledge
so that people come back, learn something more. And then we have social interaction for involvement
and engagement. We can encourage people to teach others about the game and we can support this
affiliation that viewers will be supporting a specific team, for example, or a special player
or a stream. So...
What happens when a viewer walks into a stream?
First question that pops up is, what is happening here?
And as I said before, the optimum thing
would be that the game is just very easy to pick up.
And from the very first second, you actually
know what's going on.
But we want to have viewers learn about the game
while watching the game or the stream.
So, our goal is first to design to attract viewers, and that should be seen in all the
different kind of areas of development of the game. Coming from game design, then graphics,
UI, all those features.
They should give spectators visual hints and experiences
about all the actions that are currently
happening in the game.
People should know about the tactics and even emotions
the players are going through.
A good example for that is in League of Legends,
there is a color scheme indicating
what is happening at the time.
So you just jump into a stream, and then you
see a certain color, and you know, OK,
this is the current phase, or this is maybe
what's going on at the moment.
And people or viewers should understand the current situation of the game, for example, if the team is winning or losing.
Next, we want to design to teach viewers.
This is an example we did in one of our games at Rarebyte.
There's a difference between UI done for players
versus UI for spectators.
So for a player, it's maybe important
to really focus on the player's character
and see what's going on with the character
and around the character and give a lot of feedback there.
But for spectators,
Maybe they want an overview of all the players in multiplayer and they want to be able to
compare player skills or player stats.
One element which is very exciting here is one method called information asymmetry.
Here the idea is that the player and the spectator have different pieces of information.
A very obvious one as a streamer or as a player, I do know for example what strategy I'm planning at the moment.
This is just in my head, so obviously this is something I as a player know, but the spectator doesn't.
I as a streamer can now decide whether or not it makes my stream more interesting,
or whether or not it makes my stream more interesting.
to tell the spectators this piece of information
or to keep it for myself to keep the spectators
full of tension and excitement what's happening next.
So keep this element of surprise.
As a game designer, I can also add elements
to make this happen.
For example, what we just heard,
to add specific UI elements or give specific overviews
which are just seen by a spectator.
So for example, I can see an entire map
of all the different players competing to each other,
and I know what's going on, but the players do not.
So this is also helping me to get excited.
Or I know as a spectator,
there's a specific trap over there,
and the player is just running over there.
And I, as a spectator, get very excited about that.
So why do viewers stay or come back to a game or stream?
Well, first, there's just this fierce competition
that you know from sports.
People like to see competition and see teams or players
competing and basically playing against each other.
And then there is drama, of course.
You never know who's going to win this game.
Is it this player?
Is it this team?
Is it another one?
And then there's this affiliation that we want to support, that viewers get engaged and will support their favorite streamer, performer, player or team.
What we want to do is, we want to design for drama.
So we want to create an intense playthrough and intense matches to support that drama.
And if you think of esports, that's...
Basically what is happening there is that players that are very similar in skill play
against each other.
So there's a natural drama coming from that.
But if you have games that are played by just random players, this is different.
And maybe you have to think about integrating mechanics to rebalance different player skills.
There's this infamous example of rubber banding in Mario Kart,
where you can basically, if you fall behind, you can catch up
because you just get faster.
We even used that in a hoverboard racing game.
You just had to, like, move onto a trail
and then you were able to catch up
and there was just an intense race coming from that
with completely different kind of players or skilled players.
Also, we want to design to create the unexpected.
So a viewer comes to stream and should never know exactly
what will happen next.
And that's one of the reasons this viewer will probably
stay to find out.
We can add random events or story twists to our games
to change this kind of balance within the game.
We can add surprise boxes, crates, or loot to do that.
For example, this here is from We Are Screwed,
a game we're currently working on.
We have procedural content generation
and random events in that game.
And it's a space co-op game
where people take on different roles.
And we use this, kind of, those random elements
to force people to change roles all the time.
Something which is also very interesting is how to make it happen that viewers can be part of the experience.
So there could be, for example, a passive mechanic to give streamers the option to involve
the spectators in the game.
So for example, what I use in Darkest Dungeon,
there's this option that you have those different
characters which you can play,
and I would always look at the stream
and look who's most active,
and then I would name the in-game characters
based on my spectators, based on my viewers.
So this is, they're basically getting involved
in a very passive way, but I as a player,
I have the mechanic to involve them.
On the other hand.
being as a spectator active in a game experience can be also very engaging.
This would mean that spectators can vote for specific things happening in the game,
or now it becomes increasingly interesting to also make mechanics that you can for example
cheer for specific players within a game, and then they get a specific boost in the game as a game
mechanic or a specific item.
In the end, it's about building a community around the game
and making it accessible to all those viewers,
all those different kind of spectator personas.
The audience should feel welcome at all times,
while players should still feel safe.
And the goal is to let viewers be a part of something.
Next, we want to go, or quickly go through some strategies we used on our projects. So first...
So there's so many evaluation strategies.
I mean, coming from a UX background,
there are so many ways how you can think
of evaluating the player experience,
and all those can be also used, basically,
to evaluate the spectator's experience.
Those can be things like observations,
think-out-loud tests, working with data,
in-game data, in-game metrics, interviews, you name it.
But we want to introduce two specific models which we used in our collaboration basically.
And the first one is the in this point of view.
Yeah, let's start with the indie point of view.
And of course, this is called the party test.
And it looks exactly like in this picture here.
This works in a way, and this is very simple.
We would just invite 15 to 20 people to our office
and do something called a play party.
And we would just start a game
and then have some people play this game.
and other people watch those people play.
And then we evaluate and we record that
and we collect data basically.
And we can identify issues like with onboarding,
with usability and playability.
And this is both for player
and spectator engagement and experience.
And my point, the academics point of view,
I love, again, I love working with data.
And I do a lot of big data analysis,
so I really try to gather a lot of data,
either qualitative or quantitative data.
But what's very interesting is, for example,
to build different models based on the interactions
of spectators with the game, or with the stream,
with the player, or with other spectators.
This can be usually, can be data locked in the game,
can be locked in the stream, can be Twitch data,
or can be even Twitter data,
which is just related to the game.
I want to introduce you to models which we use,
or two processes we often use.
The first one is graph-based analysis.
Here we built, based on the interaction of the spectators
with each other or with the player, we built a graph.
This means if as soon as two.
spectators would interact in a chat at a very similar time. We assume this might be some sort
of communication, so we would make a connection between two nodes within this graph, which means
okay they're connected, they have some sort of relationship within this graph, and we can make
sense out of this data.
So, looking at a lot of data, this could be a graph, this is how such a graph looks like.
And what we can see, there are some nodes with a lot of connections. Those nodes could be very
relevant and important points to look at. Those can be, for example, those personas of commentators
who want to entertain the others and are really important.
as an engagement starting point.
So, can we use this information to give those a specific reward, for example,
to make sure to keep them engaged and keep them in our stream or part of our game experience?
And then we can also identify the weaker points, those with not a lot of connections.
And we can think of ways how to integrate those and help them to connect to other spectators.
On the other hand, this is one of the more traditional ways to do data analysis.
This is basically where you look at the number of interactions over time.
So this is when you look at the Twitch chat, for example, you can see in minute 40,
there was something going on, something very important was going on.
And we can find out by looking at the in-game data, here was a specific boss fight.
Apparently also the streamer did something very well.
Can we use this information to make the engagement even better for the next stream?
So just to summarize, we can also say that those different relations strategies can actually work
together. Again, so that I can do my data analysis, I need a lot of data.
The point is that very, very often when we work with studios, it's becoming very expensive and
it's becoming very complicated because the data the studio locked in the game just was not right,
was not locked in a correct way or just not locked at all.
Yeah, and the idea is just to work together from the very beginning of the project and do a data definition together.
And then we as a studio would take this definition and build it right into the very foundation of the game.
And we then plan and prototype our game.
And when a build is ready of the game, we would start a play testing session.
And then we would be able to collect data that is then given back to the research institution.
And since the data already fits what we sort of need,
because of this definition phase,
for us it's so much easier and much more cost-effective
to make sense out of the data and help the studio,
even if it's a small studio or a big studio,
to help to improve the game.
All right, a short recap of what we talked about today.
Keep in mind, not every spectator has the same motives.
There are different motives for viewing a stream or a game.
Then also keep in mind that you need to design
for different spectator personas.
And also, as we just said, seize the opportunity
of collaborations between your indie studio
or your game studio and research institutions.
All right, that's it.
Thank you very much.
If you have any questions.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
I think we have time for one or two questions.
Afterwards we will be in the wrap-up area.
Hi, I was wondering if to combat the problem you're having with data sources like that
being locked down by different studios, are there any emerging standards that are being
adopted across the Indy platforms?
Yeah, that's a very good point actually.
So that's one of the issues we're having right now.
We are actually trying to build one of such standards
at the moment because yeah,
it is actually pretty easy and straightforward,
but yeah, there's exactly a lack of things like that.
So thanks for pointing that out also.
Hi. So have you found that designing a game with this, making it spectator approved or
liked that streamers will like quickly recognize that the game is made for that and will adopt
it?
Yeah, so the idea would be to build features into the game that would just enable streamers to use that to engage more with their audience, for example.
Of course. Yeah.
Thank you.
Okay, so thank you so much and have a lovely evening.