This is GDC Podcast.
Uh, that's a big pop.
Hey everybody, I'm Chris Graft.
I'm here with Alyssa McElhune.
Hello.
I'm Alyssa.
I'm a news editor at Gamasutra.
Oh yeah.
Forgot to say what I do.
I am editor in chief of Gamasutra.
At least I try to be.
And this is the second episode of GDC podcast, right?
Yeah.
Second episode.
I know that, that, uh, it's got that fresh podcast smell.
Just open it up and just take that whiff.
That's the fun thing about doing this monthly so far is it feels like it's been a week since
we recorded this.
I know, it feels like we've been doing this for about 30 years now.
Oh yeah, seasoned podcasters over here.
Very seasoned, there's been no editing at all in all of these.
All of this is exactly how it happened.
So again, we're here for GDC, that stands for Game Developers Conference.
And we kind of started this so that we could give people some insight into these fascinating
people who make video games and kind of let people know how they make them.
I think that's a pretty, that's a noble goal.
Oh yeah, turns out they don't just will themselves into existence.
There's hardworking teams of dedicated people behind all those many, many, many
games that are coming out in quick succession this year.
It's, it's true.
Uh, well, not all of them will themselves into existence.
I think that Will Wright actually willed himself into existence.
And that's how he got his name.
Thank you.
Because Sims content this week.
Oh yeah.
Well, let's talk about all we get.
We have to talk real quick about like, well, all right.
What are you playing?
right now. I'm killing time. As we're recording this, a new Sims game pack comes out like three
hours ago, and it is killing me that I can't be playing it right now. So it'll be that for
the rest of the week. You're that dedicated of a podcaster.
And you have waited this long to play the new Sims.
Oh yeah, it's installing.
Like on my lunch I went to go start installing it.
So it's, it pains me.
What do you like so much about The Sims?
I mean it's a great game, but you're obsessed with it.
I am a micromanager.
And it gives me a way to productively micromanage without pissing anyone off.
Without pissing anyone off?
I don't know, it's one of those weird kind of like, with like Sardine Valley and Animal
Crossing where you have a bunch of like small little tasks you just kind of like focus on
and get into routines and set up all this and there's like creative output in it.
It's just really relaxing.
So none of your sims are pissed off?
No, no, they're all very happy and I hold them to very high standards individually.
Do you ever do the cruel thing where you just kind of build them into a room and, you know,
punish them like that?
Are you...
They make it harder in these ones.
You can't just like delete the pool ladder anymore, but...
Yeah.
We treat our sims humanely in the year 2019.
That's good.
And then I'm playing games too.
Yeah, I was going to ask, do you play any video games?
Um, do I game? Am I a gamer?
Are you a gamer?
Am I a gamer? I'm actually playing Astral Chain from Platinum, and it's a lot less Bayonetta,
and it's a lot more kind of...
More detective stuff than I thought there would be.
You're basically demon police, and there are these things called chimera that keep on coming through portals
and infecting people and doing all this weird stuff to people.
But I'm surprised how much of a mix of action and detective work is in there.
Yeah, from the E3, I think, trailer, it looked like it'd be this really kind of like niche
little game that not a lot of people would get into, but a lot of people have been talking
about that one.
Yeah, and also there is a toilet fairy in it.
Oh, is that the one that talks about your tweets?
Yeah, yeah, that's, uh, well, yeah, that was my hilarious tweet joke.
Like, I contributed, um, something to the toilet fairy.
I don't know what it was, it was an item.
It wasn't, it wasn't any, uh, yeah, anyway, the toilet fairy thanked me for blessing it.
Video games are art.
They are.
And speaking of video games, the Game Developers Conference, there is actually some stuff happening
with it.
So we opened up the call for summits.
So if you have ideas for talks that involve AI, animation, independent games, game narrative,
math in game dev, then you should submit a talk on the website.
You can find that information at gdconf.com.
There's also VRDC, game career development.
You can submit your talks before midnight.
On September 30th at that website, that's midnight, uh, before you turn into a pumpkin.
There's also, there's also more, uh, there's also a XRDC coming up in October.
That's 14th through 15th at Fort Mason Festival Pavilion.
And, uh, that's in San Francisco.
That has to do with all of the fancy visual computing stuff where, uh, virtual
things are overlaid on reality.
AR, XR, VR, MR, the various R's, the XR's.
Yeah, all the R's.
All the R's.
2020 IGF submissions are now open as well.
Those are due by midnight on September 30th.
Students and non-students can submit games.
judged on excellence in visual art, audio, design, narrative, and best student game,
with finalists in all of those categories.
And there is a program going where underrepresented groups can apply for a fee waiver.
More details on that can be found at igf.com slash submit hyphen your hyphen game.
All right. This is where we start to tease the next guest here.
Well, not tease our next guest.
Uh, tease what he does, right?
Yeah.
Don't tease me.
A little background.
This person is a past.
This is like going to be one of my things on this podcast now.
Huge hype.
Right before we introduce the person.
All right.
Our next guest is a past GDC speaker.
He's written for Gamma Sutra and Game Developer Magazine.
What?
A writer and composer and a game dev at Zachtronics, where he worked on such
cool system-y type games like Opus Magnum, Xapunks, Shenzhen I-O, and also in a past life
worked AAA at Bungie, Treyarch, 343 Industries. They made some games. Some of those games were
Halo and Call of Duty, including Call of Duty 2 Big Red 1.
Which I enjoy.
And I also...
Where are you getting this bio from?
Oh my god.
It's all on the internet, sir.
Okay.
Yeah.
I enjoy...
I like saying Big Red One as in Big Red One.
Big red one.
Yeah, big red one.
And so, if you, oh, he also did the great Twine game, The Writer Will Do Something.
That is about floundering development of a AAA game.
And the latest game to come out is Eliza from Zachtronics.
So if you'll join me in unveiling our guest.
Matthew Burns. Hi, Matthew. Hi. Hi. Well, you have a long storied past in the game industry.
I've actually known of you for a while. I feel like now I know you a bit.
After all that research that you've done. Yeah, yeah.
After stalking me on the internet, yeah. Yeah, this is what Alyssa and I are getting
really good at. We are better at internet stalking than we are at podcasting.
Which, you know, that's okay.
That'll hopefully that'll pay off someday.
Now you started in the game industry.
It seems like you must've started pretty early on in your life.
Uh, like in your, in your career, can you talk about how it all started?
How I got started?
Sure.
Yeah.
Um, I think it was 2000 or 2001, something like that.
Um, so I guess it's coming up on like 18 years now.
Um, started right out of school.
As a tester in the basement of Activision in Santa Monica, the same building that they
still are in right now.
But I was absolutely just a temp tester, kind of starting on the lowest rung, and eventually
became a producer.
And I was a producer the entire time I was on AAA and went through the various studios
that you mentioned and various franchises that you mentioned.
And then I...
I tried to go indie once, that didn't work out, and I went back to AAA, and then I tried
to go indie again, and now I'm here at Zachtronics where I do the writing and music, which is
more interesting to me than the production stuff for right now, because it's new and
it's stuff I haven't done before.
So I guess that's the short version of my journey through the game industry.
Just taking notes here, basically you crawled out of the basement of Activision is how I
heard it.
Yes.
Mm-hmm.
And made your way.
So the test department at Activision is literally in the basement of the building.
Like there's...
Of course it is.
It's like metaphorical.
And it's kind of funny.
It's also a little bit, you know, like sad, but like it's always been in the literal basement.
Can you describe this basement?
Was it dank, damp?
It's, you know, there's no windows obviously and it's just sort of this large open space
that is the underground floor of like a large office-y building and there's fluorescent
lights that buzz faintly and a break room with vending machines in it with, you know,
bags of...
There's a slightly more upbeat metaphor there, like, oh, testers are the foundation of game
development.
If you really want to put that on a cat poster, you can get there, I think.
That's true.
It's an important job, yeah.
I mean, it's like, we're making fun of it, but it is, yes, absolutely an important job
and absolutely not something that shouldn't be taken seriously, like it should be taken
very seriously.
But Windows are also kind of beneficial to mental health.
Yeah, exactly.
I think, I mean, I'm totally willing to go on the record and say that Activision probably
could stand to treat their testers better, both then and now.
The AAA though, working in that for years, just to dig into that a little bit more,
was it anything near what you expected? Because I bet that there are listeners that are thinking,
you know, there are still people out there, despite the news of how hard it can be in this industry,
do you have a romanticized idea of it? Were you like that?
Um, I think so. I think for like people who are going into AAA now,
they definitely have a better sense of like,
Crunch and work-life balance issues and things like that.
Like when I talk to students now, a lot of them are familiar with the,
with the stories and reporting that has been done on that.
And that's a great credit to like the reporters who've been willing to like
try to put these stories out there.
When I started, there was less of that, like less of like, here's what
to expect when you do AAA.
So I didn't necessarily have like a specific notion of like, this
is what it was going to be like.
It was more just like, okay, now I'm working on a big,
Call of Duty is like a big game, seems important, and I'll just do what it takes to get it done.
So at that time the industry was just a little bit less established and there was just more kind of fly by the seat of your pants.
Not that it's amazing now, right, but there's just like...
smaller teams and less developed processes, and just doing things and hoping that they work.
So I didn't have this specific idea of, like, it's going to be like this. I just
kind of went in hoping to be useful.
Well, you've had a lot of different jobs in games.
You said that you're a producer.
That was the QA and producer side is what you were focusing on.
Now what kind of drew you more towards...
uh, the focus on the writing and you're also a composer who writes excellent music for these
games. You know, what, yeah, what drew you towards that? Well, so I, you know, it's like I joined
games because I was interested in them creatively. Like I actually was a tester for three years and
a producer for like 10 years, but the entire time I had been doing like my own writing on the side
and my own music on the side.
Because I think fundamentally I am a creative person and I always was.
But the thing about like working in, in games on AAA games, I actually, there
was a point at which I could decide whether I wanted to be like a designer.
Like I want to, if I wanted to follow like the design track
on stuff like Call of Duty.
And to be super honest, like.
The design problems that you have to solve on a game like Call of Duty were not as interesting
to me as the logistical problems that you have to solve on how to put the team together
and how to do the voice recording and how to coordinate all the designers and all the
assets and stuff like that.
So I pursued the production track in AAA because I thought I would like...
be able to learn more of the kinds of things that I was interested in, and see a lot of
the different disciplines, and stand in on a mocap session, and make a big list of animations,
or be in the recording studio, participate in all of that kind of stuff, as opposed to
the kinds of design problems that you solve in Call of Duty, which are interesting, but
were just less what I wanted to pursue at that time.
When you went indie for the first time, did you stick with kind of a production side of it?
Or were you more in the design trenches?
Yeah, no, at that point, then I was like, oh, I want to like, it was, it was tough.
So the first time I tried to go indie was like around 2011 or 12.
So that was like when indie stuff was really, really early on.
And it was like, maybe this is a thing that can be done.
And I myself didn't necessarily have a great idea of exactly how it was going to work.
Like.
You had to sort of be entrepreneurial too at the same time and like pitch your game.
And there wasn't necessarily like a, a great pipeline for how to pitch the pitch stuff.
Um, so I thought, you know, I have to be like some sort of business guy too.
And then also like be involved in like design and like creative direct the
game as well at the same time.
And, um, it was a super, super artsy game that I think.
wasn't the type of game that a big publisher would pay a lot of money for, especially back
then.
I think maybe now there's more interest in that type of game and there's more models
for how that type of thing could work.
But at the time it didn't quite come together.
But yeah, it was always like trying to be creative.
The Twine games that I've made were made while I was not working at Zachtronics and working
at other jobs, and I would go home and work on my Twine games and that kind of thing.
You had mentioned that you, you tried to go indie first.
Uh, can you talk about what happened there?
Because there was that period and then you had, then you went back to AAA.
Yeah.
Um, uh, I saved up some, I had saved up a bunch of money and I
was like, I'm going to do it.
I'm going to pursue the indie dream.
And so in like 2011 or 12, something like that, me and some friends that I
had met were like, yeah, we're going to make a game and I said I had saved up
money, but it was like,
to
pay everyone for their contribution.
Um, but so we worked on it and we, we came, we had like this, um, sort of demo of, of the game.
It was this musical shooter, uh, that we were calling Plonk at the time after the named after
the physicist Max, Max Plonk.
Um, and it was like, it was kind of like inspired by like, uh, Rez and Tetsuya Mizuguchi kind of
games where it's like cool electronic music and, and sound and stuff.
And I was trying to get money to finish it.
And this was, again, this was a time when there weren't a ton of indie publishers.
I think like Devolver was around at this time, but many of the other ones weren't.
And so then I would like try to, I was like, try to pitch to like, you know.
Konami or something, right? And it was just like, why would I, it doesn't make any sense. And,
and so it was just, it just didn't, like, it didn't happen. Like people were just not interested
enough in the game. It was like too artsy, too out there, not enough precedent for the type of
game it was. And to like, um, the, the deals that were out there for this, this type of thing,
we're just like, we're just kind of almost condescending, you know, it would be like,
I would go to like a publisher and they would be like,
And I would be like, hey, I have this game and I need this amount of money to make it.
And then I, and then I'll give the game to you.
And then they would come back with their counter offer and they would be like, how
about this?
We don't give you any money and you still give us the game.
And it would just be like, okay, that's not, you know, that's not like a real thing.
So eventually the money that I had saved up to like pay my rent was running out and I
was like, okay, sorry, I guess this didn't work.
So I had, I got another job in AAA to kind of like continue it.
But I still felt like, you know.
that I had failed in some way, because I didn't finish the game that I was trying to make at that time.
Yeah, well, I guess join the club, right?
Sure, yeah, absolutely.
Yeah, I forget about those times, and you said this was around 2011?
I think so, yeah, 10, 11, or 12, something like that.
So to me, I'm pushing 40 now, 2011 does not seem like that long ago, and it was such a
different time, where this kind of rise of the mid-tier, or the more boutique-style publishers
like Devolver.
Uh, weren't really, uh, established as they are now, or a lot of them,
not even around at all.
So the idea, the idea of you, uh, and you know, your little team pitching
to the same company that publishes like Metal Gear Solid, uh, you know, or
triple A games like that.
It's, I mean, it's almost comical these days.
It really was a clear, it really was a clear like mismatch.
And it was like, hey, I want to do this artsy thing.
And they were just like, I don't know what to do with this.
I think now there's much more of like a framework that you can be like, Hey, I
am this type of game and they understand where you're coming from a little bit
better.
It really was a different, it was super different time.
And you're right.
It wasn't that long ago.
Yeah.
Now, Zachtronics, uh, you, you joined Zachtronics in 2016.
Is that right?
Yeah, so I had worked with Zach prior to that. I'd done the music for
Infinifactory and written some stuff for TAS100, but in 2016 is when I joined,
basically full-time, to do both the writing and music for Zachtronics games.
So Shenzhen IO was the first Zachtronics game that I did both the writing and music for.
So this always struck me as an interesting pairing too, because you are kind of shaping
the future of Zacatronics.
As you know, Matthew, I interviewed Zac at GDC a couple years ago, and we talked about
the influence that...
you're having on it. When you're going into Zachtronics, so if our listeners who don't know,
Zachtronics does very systems-based doohickey type of games where you add and subtract things
from systems and you basically, in some of them you press go and then the system just starts going
and it might collapse in on itself or it might magically work and it just gives this amazing
sense of
uh, progression, like intellectual progression, intrinsic reward is a big thing with these games.
Now, bringing you on, what was the goal with you?
I mean, many of the Zachtronics games mechanically, I mean, they, they come,
so with the exception of Eliza, like the mechanics of the Zachtronics games definitely
continue to just come from Zach. Um, I don't really try to like...
make any design contributions to stuff, especially the more hardcore ones, the ones where you
just do assembly language programming.
I don't really have anything to offer there from a design standpoint.
What we do talk about, especially early on in the design process, is just the overall
story of the game and the world that the game takes place in, and the arc that we take players
on as they do these tasks.
And that's something that's very important, I think, to us as a studio.
It's important to Zach.
He doesn't want to make games that are just about manipulating abstract symbols in a vacuum.
They have to connect back to the real world in some way.
And that's where I really get involved, and I think that that's something we talk about from the very get-go.
We don't design a game and then put a skin on it.
Like, oh, maybe this could take place in medieval times.
medieval stuff on it.
It's really about designing the mechanics and the world and the story all together,
all at once.
And hopefully, by doing that, they all reflect on each other and reinforce each other.
Now the latest Zachtronics game, Eliza is a game that just came out recently and it's
quite a departure in that it is a visual novel.
It's not one of these super mechanic-savvy games that Zachtronics has become known for.
Can you talk about the...
How about this, Alyssa, what are you thinking?
We're both playing this game right now.
What are you thinking of Eliza? I was not emotionally ready to start it at like 10
p.m. at night. That was a mistake. But I feel kind of bad because my preconception of
Zachtronic games prior before this conversation and before doing a
research and leading up to this had been like, these are puzzle games that are
way too tough for me. I had no idea of like the the element of kind of world
creation that went into that.
Had compartmentalized them away as puzzle games.
And I'm going to go back and recheck some of them now.
No, that's okay. I think absolutely the most memorable thing about them is the fact that they are these sort of programmy puzzle games or engineering puzzle games.
Where you literally have to do engineering. You literally have to do an engineering job to finish the level.
One of the descriptions I read for them was, oh, they're puzzle games for programmers.
And I'm like, that is so technical.
Right, yeah.
But there's value in technical stuff as well.
Then you go to Eliza, which is a visual novel, which is a very niche genre on its own,
and entirely different from puzzle games altogether.
So how did the...
idea to be like, here's a story I want to tell with these kind of mechanics about all of this.
And how did that kind of snap into visual novel for you guys?
Yeah. And can you just give kind of our listeners, just the background of the story of what Eliza is about?
Oh yeah, that too.
Sure. Yeah. So Eliza is a visual novel. It's kind of about this therapy app that a large
tech company based in Seattle has developed.
The way I pitch it to people often is saying, imagine Amazon added a therapy
function to Amazon Alexa.
So you would come home after a day at work and just be like, Alexa, I don't
feel so good.
And Alexa would be like, why don't you feel so good?
And then you could just talk to your Amazon Alexa and it would listen to you
and creepily record you and upload all of your deep thoughts to Amazon.
And so it's a little bit like that, although there's a twist in that.
The AI responses provided to it are supposed to be read by real human beings called proxies.
And proxy work is maybe analogous to like Uber or Lyft or DoorDash or something like that, where
you as a proxy, your job is to just kind of show up and like read these words that are provided to
you at someone who is in for therapy.
So it's about these therapy clients that come in, it's about you being the proxy and not really
having a choice about what you say to them, and it's also about the people who make this technology
and whether they're really helping or not, and the choices that you make when you work
in technology and the effect that you have on the world as an engineer.
So that's kind of in a nutshell what Eliza is all about.
There's a lot of other stuff too.
There's stuff about, you know, burnout and working in the, in the tech industry.
There's stuff about all this other stuff.
There are so, there's so much stuff in it.
It touches on.
All this stuff like AI bias, you know, you're talking about, like you said, burnout, work-life
balance, this responsibility that people developing technology feel or don't feel about it, what
they're making.
What got you thinking about all this?
Did you just watch a bunch of Black Mirror?
Or, I mean, like a lot of this stuff is very realistic.
That's one thing.
This is a believable world.
Well, I mean, living in Seattle for the past decade or so, seeing the city
transform pretty dramatically as Amazon has taken over more and more
of it is one thread of that.
Because I work in games, many of the people that I'm, you know,
Professional colleagues with or friends work at companies like Microsoft or Amazon.
You know, Microsoft has a big, has Xbox, right?
And Amazon has Amazon game studios.
So there are plenty of Microsoft, Amazon, and Google has a big campus up here as well.
Employees of these big tech companies in this area and people that I know.
I also, you know, I mentioned earlier, I work on my own stories in my own time.
And.
When I, during one job that I had had, like five or six years ago, I think I'm
going to say like 2014, I saw a demo of a real therapy application developed
with funding from DARPA that was cameras on people's faces.
And there was like a, a, a 3d avatar that was talking at them, like this,
like kind of old school, like second life looking 3d person.
And it was like, you know, how are you doing?
And then the person would be like, Oh, I don't know.
And then all these like metrics would be like on their face, like if they were
blinking or smiling or, you know, all of that kind of stuff.
And it was the point of the system was to determine if people maybe had
signs of PTSD or something like that.
And the reason why it was funded by DARPA, which is part of the defense
department, was because maybe they were going to like, use it on soldiers who
we like.
came back from Afghanistan or whatever, and then they would like sit them in
front of this like computer system and it would like scan their face while they
talked to see if they were, if they had PTSD or not.
So I saw that demo and it was just like, really stuck with me, right.
For, for whatever reason, it was just like the, the idea of that, you know,
you send some 20 year old kid into war and give them PTSD and then they come
back and they have to talk to a robot about it.
Like.
I really wanted to do something with that, or make a story about it.
And this was before Black Mirror, but it just felt really arresting.
And so I was thinking about, maybe I'll make this a twine game or something like that.
And so I had written a bunch of stuff about it.
So one day, Zach and I were talking.
I think this was after Opus Magnum.
We were just talking about future stuff that we could do.
I think that Zach feels that we can always make more puzzle programming games.
Like, we feel like we understand that genre pretty well.
Zach is basically the inventor of that genre.
But it's cool to try new things and do new things.
And so I told him about this idea that I'd had,
and then I was like, kind of pitched him on this idea of doing it as a visual novel
that takes a little bit of art and a little bit of programming time and stuff.
And he was like, yeah, let's do it.
Let's make it, let's make this as a Zachtronics game and sort
of put it through our process.
And so that allowed the art to happen and that allowed like the voice recording
to happen and things like that.
So I totally jumped at the chance to be able to, to do it that way.
Did, did Zach have any reservations whatsoever that it might not resonate
with the typical Zachtronics audience?
Absolutely. Yeah, we talked about that a lot. There were a lot of like, we had no
idea if anyone would like this at all. We had no idea if like, Zachtronics fans
would like yell at us and be mad and you know, show up at our at our homes or
something like that. Right?
You made a visual novel.
Yeah, right. Like, we were concerned about that. We were also concerned that
like by by making a visual novel about like, kind of just
30-somethings talking about their careers and stuff?
Like, that's not really typical visual novel fare, right?
And so maybe fans of visual novels won't like it,
and then also people who are not fans of visual novels
won't play it anyway, because it's a visual novel.
So it's like, maybe we're making a game for nobody.
And that was a real fear.
And then also, yeah, how would people who associate Xectronics with this very specific genre, how would they feel about it as well?
I mean, isn't Grey's Anatomy about people talking about work in their 30s and 40s and people like that, right?
Sort of?
The Grey's Anatomy of video games, is that what you're getting at?
Yeah, I don't know. It's definitely like, you know, it's about like adult...
things and I mean adult in the sense of like paying your mortgage adult not the other kind
of adult. Yeah, it's and Alyssa and I were talking about how um and this isn't uh this is a this is
a compliment to the game. It is it's it's depressing and um it's but in in a way that
I want games to make me feel something real, and I think that a lot of people will agree
with me that that comes along not very often.
And when you're sitting there with the initial patient, you're sitting there as the proxy,
and then you start to realize that...
You can only read out what the Eliza AI is telling you to say or else you'll get fired.
Like right there, it just, it, that takes away your agency.
It takes away your, uh, your, uh, your propensity to help people.
It takes away, uh, any.
empathetic action that you could possibly take. And that's what's interesting. Like,
and you've talked about this before at GDC, about choice and how you handle choice. And a lot of
times it's not about the choices that are interesting, it's about how they're presented.
So can you talk about that, about designing for choice in a game that doesn't have much of it?
Yeah, so I mean, I'll just come out and say it, that the way Eliza is designed is that you don't
have a choice for a very long time. I want to say the first two thirds of the entire game are just
completely linear. And then it opens up towards the end, and you do have a choice. And that's a
very, very deliberate design strategy that I'm using from a narrative design standpoint of using
all of that time at the beginning to set up
Like a very, what I think is a very interesting and complex choice at the end.
So instead of bombarding you with small incremental choices throughout the duration of your play,
what you get is kind of an interesting situation and an interesting story and an interesting world, hopefully.
And then you are presented with the chance to make a choice.
It's a lot more resonating.
That's my theory anyway.
The choice itself becomes a lot more resonating when you
understand all of the factors around it, instead of you just
start the game and you're presented with a choice
immediately with no context of I don't know what I'm choosing
to do if I make these choices.
Really.
It's like you're... yeah. That fills me with anxiety.
There's six chapters in the game, I'm on chapter five.
You're getting there.
What you're describing is kind of like blowing up a party balloon.
And, you know, your decision is like, should I stop blowing into it?
Or should I just like keep going?
It's like all of it, all of this is just building up to one big thing.
And I think that's a completely fascinating design decision.
Yeah.
I think it really allows you to do stuff that you couldn't do in any other way.
I remember, and so I was, I did talk about this at GDC.
I think that's like an interesting approach to think about.
And it, the game itself, like.
It's not really very fantastical in a lot of ways.
Like it's really just like modern day kind of life.
Um, there's nothing about it.
That's like made up except for the therapy stuff.
And even then, since the game came out, everybody's been like.
emailing me like these apps they found on the app store that are like chatbot for for
Cognitive behavioral therapy or whatever like it's a lot of believable. It's totally a thing now
Yeah, I think like going into that very first so you start like the your character is
a first day as this proxy right when you play, and they're going through and talking through
their entire, like, okay, so you have to go in this room and listen to this person and
stick to the script.
It's very important that you stick to the script.
And then it's hammered in, and I'm like, oh, here's the mechanic.
It's going to be I have to sit here and right away I'm going to have to decide if I'm going
to stick to the script or if I'm going to take a different option.
Because that's a very visual, novel-y kind of binary choice, is like, do I do A, go down
this road, or do I do B and go down the other path?
But right away you don't get that.
And I think that kind of...
You get resigned to that same kind of anxiety that Chris was talking about, but at the same
time in other...
Outside of the ELIZA therapy office, you have your text conversations or your face-to-face
conversations where you can choose between two answers, and the answers might not necessarily
be different outside of tone.
The outcome will be the same.
And those two, like, the difference between those two kinds of decision, and also the
subtle differences between the actual choices you make really do a lot to define the character
you're playing as, it feels like.
Especially because in visual novels, the ones I've played have been, like, anime nonsense
because that's me in a past life.
But a lot of times your protagonist becomes this empty vessel that you fill with your
own personality.
And the protagonist in Eliza has her own motivations, her own goals, and her own backstory that
you uncover through these unique kind of narrative design choices.
I don't have a question I'm building up to here other than that it's very impressive
how all of that was kind of drip-fed to me by subverting what I expected of visual novels
in a way.
Yeah, for sure.
I think that any textbook that you open about game design will say, well basically will
say games are different because they're interactive.
Games are different from other mediums because they present you with choices.
That's like the defining feature of games.
You hear any pundit talking about games will say this.
And so what's so powerful to me...
Like in that is like actually denying someone a choice like that can be such a powerful
like move because like it's a game you would think that you would want to give people a
choice and so going going against that is like kind of a really interesting.
way to use the tools that you have as a game designer. It's like using silence as a composer
or blank space as a writer. I don't know. But the absence of the thing that makes the medium
what it is, I think, can enhance the other parts of... It can enhance the choices that come later,
and it can contrast with...
Like you said, the moments in her daily life, in Evelyn, the main character's daily life,
where she does have a little bit of choice, and then at work where she has absolutely
none at all.
Let's just sit here dead air for five minutes to subvert the notion of a podcast.
We can do that in our intro, I think.
So when Sid Meier says, you know, a game is a series of interesting choices or decisions,
you don't necessarily agree with that.
Um, I think it's, well...
Sid Meier's going to be listening, so you better be careful.
Okay.
Well then, no, I don't, I don't, I actually don't agree that a game is a
series of interesting choices.
I think that what a game is, is actually very difficult to define.
And, and once you, you know, when you read game theory, uh, stuff like people
are like, oh, um, Ludwig.
Wittgenstein picked the word game as an example of a word that's impossible to define,
and he had all these examples about how you can't define the word game.
It's worth reading. Everyone has their own definition of game, I think.
A lot of people think that visual novels are not games at all.
But I think that Eliza does have interesting choices in it.
Or at least one interesting choice in it.
And so if Eliza is a series of one very interesting choice, is it a game or not?
I don't know.
I'll let you decide as long as you buy it and play it.
Well, I, it's, you know, whatever you think of it is like, it's, uh, I think that what
it's doing to me, what it's, how it's making me think about the topics at hand, how it's
making me think about the world around me.
I don't think that that could be done as effectively if it were a game that were,
you know, as soon as I say this, some like Indy is going to release an amazing game
with lots of like stuff like that.
But like this game, I just don't, it would, like the fact that it takes away the agency from me,
that really, that grabs me and it's compelling.
It's a deliberate, yeah, it's a deliberate choice. Like again, like I said, like,
you know, at Zachtronics, like we've made the, we make these extremely mechanics heavy games,
right? So it's not like beyond us to design a therapy game where like procedurally generated
people come in.
who have like four or five conditions and you like have to like give them procedurally
generated like prescriptions or like figure out what to say to make them feel better.
And then we've created this like weird like simulation-y kind of model of like mental
health which is like weird and not something I wanted to get into, right?
Because then you're making as soon as you start designing a system around that, then
you're then you're starting to make this procedural argument that like, oh, if someone is depressed,
they need...
this, right? Like, if someone has X problem, then they need Y.
And if, if you don't give them that, then they're bad.
And if you do give them that, then they're better. And it's like,
I didn't want to like every person in, in Eliza is just their own person.
They're their own specific, like case.
And that and the reason why that's true is because it's a completely linear and
there's no choice. And again, that's a deliberate decision.
Modeling mental health just seems like such a minefield of unintended consequences and
things and arguments that I didn't want to make.
It's a deliberate decision that kind of makes a commentary on that way of thinking.
Because there's one specific person in general where Chris and I both talked about it and
we're like, yeah, she just came in to have a chat and the AI is like, well, here's a pill for you.
Right. And like a lot of that is just kind of like you sit there at your computer going like oh
Oh, this is a commentary. My eyes like pop out of my head. Yeah
Wait a minute, and then you know you have you have to sit there and then you have to repeat what the AI says and
It feels like you are making things worse
That you're contributing to something bad. Mm-hmm. And then you get into all of this stuff like
You know, what am I, you start thinking, what am I involved in?
Uh, what am I doing?
You know, the, to this world, what's my impact on this world?
Uh, is like the, these little things that you do, uh, is that making it better?
Is that helping people?
Right.
And that's kind of the ultimate like question that the game asks, right.
It was, which is what are you, how are you contributing to the world and how do
you feel good about what you're doing?
Um, yeah.
I'm gonna... no, no, don't wrap it up. I'm gonna hijack. I have one more question I want to ask before... I know we're running short on time.
But it's like, it's half a credit to the voice acting and half a credit to the writing that like, all of those characters and all those situations in like, the Eliza therapy sessions all seem human.
And not like...
People really... I think it's easy when you're dealing with mental health topics and trauma
and anxieties and stuff like that to write characters that are just those traits. But like,
so far all the people I've encountered feel like they...
have rounded out lives and that everything seems like amazingly human in actuality.
And I guess I wonder if you can talk a little bit about writing human characters or the voice
acting process of coaching into getting this really genuine feeling in each of those very
personal intimate moments. Yeah, totally. I mean, I could talk about both of those things for a
really long time. But I'll say.
In terms of, I'll start with the voice acting, like, when the voice actors came in, I, we just talked about how I told them that I was
interested in getting very naturalistic performances and not, you know, stagy performances, and
not to worry about like where one line begins and where one line ends. Oftentimes in game scripts,
the lines have to be very separate, and actors who know how to act for games know to like pause
between lines because they're going to be cut up into the dialogue stuff. And I said, well,
If it feels natural to just run into the next sentence, just do that, and I'll fix it on
my end so that the one line becomes two lines, or two lines become one line.
And stuff like that.
And sentences that I had written that were weirdly stilted or whatever, we fixed in the
recording booth as we went, just to find that really natural delivery and that really natural
performance.
And a lot of that was the actors responding to me,
like trusting them with the material.
Like I didn't try to say it this way
or come at it this exact way.
It was more like providing a space
to let them find a place to take it.
So that's the voice acting part.
And again, I could talk about that for a really long time.
The other thing was,
I did some, you know, when I was doing my research before or during writing this, I
spoke to some, some people, some mental health professionals, interviewed them.
I also drew on my own experience going to therapy and sort of like what I what I know
from my friends as well who have experienced similar things.
And I think it was important to me to like show that people you don't you don't talk
about.
Your deepest problem, like the first thing when you walk into your therapist's office,
right? You don't just immediately bring up the thing that's lurking underneath everything at
all. You don't just like, you know, you're not like, it's not like your therapist is like,
how are you? And you're like, Oh, my parents disowned me.
That's like lurking in the background. And sometimes it takes like.
multiple sessions to even get anywhere near there. A lot of people don't talk, like, they
don't even feel comfortable talking about the real issue. And so like, showing that
people don't necessarily just like, do that was also very important to me. That there's
always like something, you know, the real issue is kind of lurking in the background
a lot of the time. And then and if if the therapy clients feel more human for that reason,
I think it's that
Transcribed by https://otter.ai
It's that part of that approach, you know, in the writing to get there.
Last question, uh, before we let you go, is there any happy ending in this
relationship between humans and technology?
Like in the real world, like in the real world, you know, I think, I, I
think that, that it is possible.
Um, I'm, I'm not sure if it is probable, but I think that it is possible because
I, I believe.
The technology itself on its own is neutral, right?
And that's really just how we use it.
Like technology on its own is not good or bad.
It's how it's applied.
And if we are careful and think about how we apply technology, then we can benefit from
it.
And of course, we're all being very careful.
And we're doing a great job of it so far.
You hear that Amazon Alexa in the corner.
Yeah, right.
Nothing to worry about.
I feel like everything's going smoothly.
I don't know about you guys, but I think everything's going great.
Love that technology.
Right, you love that technology.
On that note, we all love technology.
We also all love Eliza.
And thank you so much, Matthew, for joining us.
And best of luck with the game.
Thank you.
Thank you for having me.
Alright, Matthew's out of the room now.
Uh, that's heavy stuff.
Yeah.
Right?
I kinda just wanna swoop back to my notes that started off with visual novels.
What a genre.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
I wanna swoop back into the fetal position.
No, it's such a good game and hopefully it doesn't, you know, turn people off who might
be listening to this.
That it is, there's some profound stuff in there, right?
Yeah, the last thing we want to do is get guests on the show and then discourage people
from playing their games.
But I think the one thing that I tried to get out of it when we were all chatting, but
the one nice thing about Eliza is that it feels like it deals with a lot of heavy topics
but it gives them...
the weight that they deserve and the amount of thought they deserve and the entire game's
about the same questions that you're asking as you're playing it.
So in that note, the writing is very
I have the word meaningful written a million times throughout my notes here, because everything
just feels meaningful and feels very cared about.
Yeah, absolutely. And, you know, a lot of sci-fi, which, you know, this is, it's very
near future sci-fi, I think, is really kind of, there's kind of one point of view and
it's technology sucks and we're all doomed.
This isn't like that.
There are characters who really believe in this kind of AI-based therapy.
There's a character that really believes that this is going to help people.
And that's the reason that they're in it.
So you have a spectrum of people who think of Eliza, the AI,
in all these different ways.
You have the extreme, who is this character Nora,
who used to work on the project.
And then she left to lead the life of a musician and an artist.
And then she becomes one of the harshest critics of it.
Whereas you have the big CEOs of these tech companies who are all about it.
And then you have the people in the middle who are somewhere in between.
Yeah, if you break it down to its most basic parts, there are these very clear, against,
for, chaotic in the middle, these very clear sides, but in the actual implementation of
it it's really human and believable and just a really good game.
Visual novels are good.
Yeah, and it reminds me of, and people see this, or people have seen it if they've played the game,
it reminded me of when I was in college a little bit and I was telemarketing and it's like stick
to the script and then you have your boss. Yes, I was a telemarketer. I was one of those
awful people. Shaking my head, you can't see it, but I hope you can feel it.
It was college, I needed the money.
Which is probably what a lot of these proxies in ELIZA thought.
It was college, I needed the money, so I became a proxy for machine learning robot thing.
But yeah, stick to the script.
You have no agency, and by the way, your boss is listening in on you.
Make sure that you're doing the job right.
I think my one big high-level takeaway from this conversation is just the benefit of not
sticking to your brand, I guess, in a way.
In a million years, everywell, three weeks ago when this was announced, every single
headline was like, Zachtronics is making a visual novel?
No one could believe it, because it's such an out-there game based on the past library
that they'd put out before.
But like, they did it and they went for it and it just, it resonates in such a great way where
like sometimes you have to step out of your comfort zone and everyone should make a visual novel is
what I'm getting at. And I've seen some of the user reviews, you know, pray for me, I went into
the Steam user review section. Brave. But yeah, I was just looking at it and there are Zachtronics
fans of the previous games who really like this one. So, you know, there might be more overlap
than you think.
It's interesting how the theme of...
They went from puzzle games for programmers
to a game about big...
The programming morality question is there.
There's always this underlying beat
that's very interesting
to see when they deviate from genre.
It's just a very cool outcome.
When, when I talked to Zach at GDC, uh, he was, he was very much like, I mean,
they have, they released a huge, uh, instruction manual for, uh, I think it's
for TIS, um, and it.
It's actually like an engineering manual.
It's like meant to be like an actual electronics, like engineering manual.
And so, you know, you got that novelty thing and Matthew did work on that as well.
Uh, but you do have this, this reputation, like even Zach was like, if you don't,
if you don't understand our games, uh, you know, I don't care.
And you know, the crowd at GDC were just like, yeah!
Because it does give you kind of a special thing.
Like, I understand this.
Like, this is a game for me, for my brain.
And then you come out with this that, you know, kind of that questions a lot of things
that programming lays the foundation for.
Oh yeah, that's cool.
Yeah, I think like all of my in the conversation notes are just like things I wanted to dig in
on more because there's just so much so much cool surrounding how this came to be.
Yeah, it touches on so many different things. Now, we're not talking spoilers here. So
yeah, keep listening. But it talks about it touches on things like, as a society in today's world,
where
Coding, yes, is important, you know, STEM is very important and all that, but at the
same time we are devaluing the arts, for example.
You know, we are associating intelligence with one skill set.
You know what I'm saying?
Which is, you know, coding.
That's a smart thing to do and then, you know, if you don't know how to code, you just, you
know, write books, you know?
One of those in our society is valued over the other.
Yeah there's Nora, I'm so bad with names, that applies to game characters as well, but
Nora the programmer turned really cool DJ.
Yeah, the musician.
And like her, there's a conversation early on, it's all early on, no spoilers, that kind
of equates certain things in her programming life to using those same skills as artistic
expression as a musician and just a lot of really cool kind of little conversation starters
in there to really make you think.
Yeah, she's like an electronic musician and she's using all of this stuff.
You know, her music is about input and output.
I meant to mention it when Matthew was still on the call, but that song was really good
and I wanted to mention it, but the music's really great too and there's a lot of subtle
things to it and I should have said that when he was on the call.
Matthew is too good at too many things.
This podcast isn't long enough to go through all of his talents.
The game is great.
It's Eliza.
I think that's it.
So we should wind her down here, right?
Yeah.
We're actually on iTunes and Google Play, which
I don't think anybody uses.
So shout out to people who use.
Google Play for podcasts.
And also Spotify.
We're actually getting some followers off of our first one, which is good.
Spotify's podcast stuff has apparently gotten a lot better just in the past couple months.
Not just because the GDC podcast is now on the platform, but like...
I think that it was us.
We pushed, we kicked it off, but yeah.
Yeah, it was us.
All you people who want to do a new podcast, ride the wave of the GDC podcast.
So we're gonna go now.
I'm Chris Graft.
I'm Alyssa McAloon.
Thanks for listening.
Don't forget to subscribe or on Spotify, follow.
And if you love us, rate us, we'd really appreciate that.
Have a good one.
See you next time.