Hello, and welcome to the Indie Mega Booth GDC Flash Forward video.
My name is Kelly Wallach, and I'll be your host for this video.
I'm the CEO and founder of Indie Mega Booth, and also the chairman of the IGF here at GDC.
So in case you missed the news, Indie Mega Booth Showcase has doubled this year.
So we're gonna have 24 totally amazing indie games for you to come and check out.
We're in the same place that we've been.
We're up on the third floor, Moscone West,
and we're open Monday through Friday to all badge holders.
So Monday, Tuesday, we're going to have one set of 12 games.
And then on Wednesday, we're going to switch it up
to another set of 12 games that'll be there
Wednesday through Friday.
So by this point, you might be asking yourself,
what in the world is the Indie Mega Booth?
Don't worry.
I also ask myself that sometimes, too.
So, at its core, we're a showcase for independent game developers.
But, over the last six years, it's grown into more than that.
It's an incredibly tight-knit community of developers who work together to help each other out.
We also work really hard to connect up teams with folks who might want to work with them.
So partners, sponsors, platform holders, publishers.
In essence, it's a way to help gain a foothold into the games industry.
We started off as a relatively simple, but kind of crazy idea,
to gather up a bunch of really cool games and developers and all work together.
So at PAX East 2012, we ran the first ever Indie Megabooth Showcase.
It had 12 developers, we were plopped in the middle of the show floor,
and we had a bunch of confused people walking by, not totally sure what to make of all these small, independent games.
But from there, we did one at PAX West, and we doubled our size, and then we did another one at PAX East, and we doubled our size again.
Then, after that, we stopped doubling in size, because if we kept going at that rate, I think that we would be taking over the entire planet by now.
But, we did keep growing, and not only did we keep growing in size, but we kept growing in strength.
We moved from being an all-volunteer effort to a full-fledged company, and suddenly I became a CEO.
So we hired on another person, and we started doing shows outside of the U.S.
We eventually started doing work with BitSummit, which is a premier indie festival located in Kyoto, Japan.
And from there, we started to really build the foundation that is the community that you see today.
So what makes our GDC showcase so special?
Well, one of the really cool things about this showcase for us is that we get to curate it in a way that's different from the other shows that we do.
Normally, we're going to really big consumer-facing events, which is great and it's really fun, but since GDC is developer-focused, we get to pick games that we think other developers are going to find fun.
Not only does it give a chance for other developers to discover something new,
talk to some upcoming developers, maybe get inspired to create or make something of their own,
but the teams that we select for the showcase also get a chance to attend GDC,
which is a super important way for them to be able to network and make more connections.
Our developer lineup this year features games from 10 different countries.
We also have 8 titles that are going to be playable for the very first time,
and 2 of them that were announced through our showcase reveal.
On top of that, 13 games are going to have brand new content in some way, shape, or form.
So, that means if you come by, you are definitely going to see something
that you haven't seen before and that you can't see anywhere else.
On top of that, you're going to get to meet some really cool folks.
And we have some pretty comfy couches, so you can sit down and take a load off,
take a bit of a breather, and check out some really cool games.
If you'd like to find out more, you can go to IndieMegaBooth.com.
You can also follow us, we're at IndieMegaBooth, on Twitter, Instagram, Facebook, and Discord.
Plus, we also have a really rad newsletter.
So if you'd like to find out what we're up to or what cool games are coming out,
you can sign up on the website, or you can drop by and do it in person at our showcase this year.
Thanks for watching, and see you soon!