Hi, so we're going to get started.
Everybody ready?
All right.
All right, so hopefully you guys are all in the right location.
Our presentation today is Marketing Indie Style.
And why don't you introduce yourselves?
My name is Justin Woodward.
I am the founder and creative director
at Interrobang Entertainment.
I'm also a part-time marketer.
And I help to co-found The Mix.
The Media in the Exchange.
And we'll talk a little bit about what the Media India
Exchange is during our presentation today.
My name is Joel Dreskin.
I'm an independent marketer.
I work with Justin on the Mix, which
we will tell you a little bit about as sort
of a piece of our presentation.
And I'm just finishing up a book on indie game marketing, which
is going to be coming out later this year.
There's a link at the end of the presentation
with more information about Justin and myself
and where you can get more information on some
of the things we talked about today.
So for today's presentation, we've
got two different perspectives.
My background is in marketing.
I've done product marketing for LucasArts.
I did work with Telltale from their second
through their seventh year.
I've worked in tech and other different places.
So I come to this, and I do work now for Indies,
helping them with their marketing programs.
So I bring that perspective to the presentation.
And then Justin's going to talk about.
how this all affects him is he's working as an indie game developer and other things that he does as well.
And we'll also talk about how our experiences have come together in different ways and sort of intersected and overlapped.
So let's start with a quick question in terms of
how many people here have released an indie game?
Great. And how many of you have marketed on your own?
And how many have worked with someone outside of your studio
to market your game?
OK, so it's a smaller number.
So we're going to try and, you know,
when we're putting this together, we have an hour,
and there's only so much you can cover.
And so we're trying to get the right level of content
that will hopefully help with.
where you start and some of the fundamentals.
So I think some of this might be information
that has a level of awareness already with you,
but I think it's also important to think about things
in a very fundamental way.
You might have marketed a game,
but you might not have approached it this way.
So while it feels like maybe I've already done that,
what I'd like to try and do is encourage you
to step back a little and think about
your planning process a little bit different
and see if that might affect how you shape
your marketing plan as it comes together.
So I'm going to talk about where, when, and how to start.
Some things to think about as you're
developing your marketing plan.
I'll talk about different kinds of programs and vehicles
you can use while you're marketing a game.
We're going to use some specific examples,
both from a launch that I recently worked on,
as well as a launch that Justin did,
and also fold in some other examples too.
And importantly, don't be this guy.
I still have people come to me and say,
oh, I just released my game yesterday.
Can you help me market this game?
Or my game's coming out tomorrow.
Or it's coming out in a couple days.
And I think the main point is, think about it
as early as you possibly can.
And you might not actually be actively marketing your game
from the very beginning.
It surprises me that I still get a good number of people who don't integrate this into their plans at an early stage and then the game is coming out.
And it's much, you have a much easier task starting, you know, six months out, nine months out and further in terms of how you're going to approach your marketing.
You might not actually do active programs at that point.
Also important, there's not really a magic bullet.
you see games out there and you say,
man, that game is amazing, and look what it did,
and it's so awesome, and they just did this one thing.
But that's really, that's kind of a rarity.
There are people who do get that magic bullet,
and they do have a program that just hits,
or they have a game that just hits.
But I think way more often, it takes a lot of persistence.
It takes a lot of
you know, some trial and error, and not every program's going to be right for every single game.
So you've sort of got to work your way around that and see what's going to,
you know, understand your game and who it's going to appeal to
and what's going to be the best fit for a marketing program for your game.
In terms of...
starting. I mean, I think there's some fundamental concepts that will really help you as you
work your way through the marketing plan development process. And I tried to avoid, you know, some
of the jargon, but I'm going to lapse into that briefly because it's useful. You know,
I mean, some of the jargon is useful because it's been around for a while. And, you know,
traditional marketers will talk about the four Ps. And when you're starting your marketing
plan, you think about, um...
What is my product?
Let me define it.
What are the features?
What's going to be compelling about it?
Where am I going to distribute my product?
I think the way that you would market a casual game on mobile
is going to be very different than you would market a deep.
game to a core audience, a more experienced audience, on something like Steam or Humble.
It's a really important thing about the price. I think that's another thing that becomes
an afterthought for people sometimes. The day before launch, they say, I'm just going
to sell it for a dollar, or $5, or $20. So there's some ways that you can be really intelligent
about how you approach your pricing and survey the field and see who's performing well.
price points that work better and worse than others,
and not just say, oh, everyone's doing free-to-play,
I'd better do free-to-play.
So I think it's really important to think about that P,
of the four Ps, and then promotion.
What are the vehicles and initiatives you're going to use
to get visibility for your game?
Also, as part of the fundamentals early on,
is who's my game for?
The kind of audience is really going
to affect the kind of program you do.
If it's a casual game, if it's a core game,
if it's a quick pick up and play game,
or if it's a game that has an established audience
or a specialized genre.
Your game pitch we'll talk a little bit more about
in a few minutes.
What's your elevator pitch?
How do you describe it to people
in a succinct and compelling way?
Think about environmental factors
and the release landscape, seasonality,
and then who's gonna drive marketing for your game,
whether it's gonna be you,
or it's gonna be someone in your studio,
or are you gonna think about hiring somebody?
Also, as you're developing your plan,
another helpful building block is thinking about
what shape do I want my initiatives to take?
A great model is, I definitely encourage you guys
to take pictures, there's no problem with that at all,
but I also want you to know that this is all gonna be
posted on the GDC Vault shortly after the show.
So yeah, it's gonna be online somewhere,
but definitely take as many pictures as you want.
And I forgot to mention too that if anyone hasn't
turned off the ringers on their cell phone,
please do that so that phones don't ring
in the middle of the presentation.
So yeah, so getting back to this point, I mean, I think you want to have your activities peak right as your game is launching.
So be smart and strategic about...
you know, what are your best kind of assets?
You know, what are the best things that you can have
to generate interest?
You know, trailers tend to be really good,
or you might have an announcement about, you know,
some really cool content that's in there,
or you might sort of stagger out features
so that you're kind of building to a critical mass,
or you might have some contributors.
So, you know, again, just sort of thinking about
all the things that you're gonna talk about from...
your announce time to launch and how are you going to stage those in such a way that you're
kind of fueling this ramp.
And also important to think about how long you can sustain those communications.
There might be a tendency of people to get so excited about their game that they just
want to announce it and the game's not actually coming out, you know, realistically it's maybe
not going to come out for two years or three years or four years and you sort of...
it's hard to keep that interest sustained
over a long period of time.
So sometimes it's important to restrain yourself a little bit
and say, I'm going to announce it when I really
feel like I've got all my ducks in a row,
and I can build this launch and have a sustainable communication
plan leading up to my release date.
And just a quick last point here is just
kind of thinking about that last two to four weeks
as kind of the critical mass as you're building interest.
When you create the plan, I think
it can be helpful to think about it the same way you
think about your game development.
I imagine a lot of people in this room are game developers.
The indie studios tend to be the programmers and game designers
and artists and so on.
So take that same rigorous and structured approach,
calendarize it all out, and say,
These are the things I need to do to get my marketing plan in place
to have an effective launch.
I'm going to have the plan done at this time.
I'm going to do my announcements at this time.
I'm going to stage my releases at this time.
And so on. Just kind of really be kind of smart and intelligent
in the same way you are about your game development.
And while you're doing that, too, think about the calendar.
Think about seasonality.
What is the right time to launch my game?
November is really, really crowded,
and there's lots of AAA games, so think about that.
Summer can be a little bit quiet,
so there's kind of some pros and cons of that,
but think about that, think about big holidays.
Launching on July 4th is maybe not great,
unless you've got a game about American independence.
Maybe that might be an OK time.
But also, like the Steam Christmas sale.
If you want to launch on Steam and the Christmas sale is going
on, they take over the whole website
and it's all about discounted games.
So think about all those things and just kind of
be as complete as you can while you're plotting out your launch
and then kind of build back from that.
Also think about other competitive games,
similar games or games that you think
might be vying for attention against your game.
I'm going to briefly touch on the marketing mix here, and we're going to get into more
detail as we get into some examples.
But as you're approaching your plan, think about all the different kinds of things you
could do.
And this is sort of tuned for Indies.
Some vehicles, I think, can lend themselves to Indies a little bit more than AAA.
So PR can work really well.
I always encourage people to develop their audience as early as they possibly can.
And what I mean by that is...
get an email sign up front and center on your website.
And if someone's interested, then you
could get their information and have a conduit
to communicate with them.
And nowadays, Twitter works really well.
Facebook works really well.
So build your followers, and then you've
got a direct channel of communication
to all these people.
While PR can be great, you've got gatekeepers at PR.
And it's all up to the editors about whether you
get covered or not.
But when you start having your audience of hundreds, thousands,
and more of followers.
you can sort of have another supplemental form
of communication if PR is not firing for you.
We'll talk a little bit about events and promotions.
You know, these are kind of all the different things
that you could do in your marketing mix.
And you, not all these initiatives are right for every game
so you should think about this
and what's gonna be most appropriate for your game.
And also think about how the landscape is changing
and how new vehicles are emerging.
And a lot of these things are very great for indies
and not so appropriate for AAA games.
So Game Jams, editors pay attention to Game Jams
and they look for those content coming from there.
YouTube and Twitch, I think the visibility of those
is getting really well established with indies now.
I think three, six months ago.
people weren't thinking about the video channels as much as they are now, but I'll just kind of re-emphasize again that that is a super important and impactful channel that also can supplement traditional PR and can work just as well as traditional PR in a lot of cases.
Again, I'm not going to go through every bullet here
because we've got limited time, but I
wanted to get these in front of you
and also say, pay attention to other things that are emerging.
I find Twitter to be one of the most useful news sources.
And so follow a lot of indies and see what they're doing
and see what's working for them and what's resonating.
And when someone announces something,
that can spark some ideas for you.
So I think that's been one of the most useful vehicles
I've found, not only for communication,
but also for getting intelligence in the space.
So now I'm going to segue into an example of a campaign that I worked on and sort of
walk through some of the points that I was just relaying.
So Mini Motor Racing was released by a game, by a company called The Binary Mill, they're
based in Australia.
They had done a variety of games in different genres, all the way from...
you know, kind of a comedy game to, you know, an action game.
And so this was a brand new genre, a new franchise that they were looking to establish,
but they didn't have visibility in racing games,
or this mini motor franchise was kind of an unknown entity.
They were planning for a December launch, which as I talked about seasonality,
I think there can be pros of cons of that, but that was their plan.
And so I think we thought about how are we going to work with that
and see if that could work towards our advantage.
And so that's kind of the broad strokes of Minimotor Racing.
It launched first on iOS, was the lead platform.
So we thought about what are the fundamental components
of mini motor racing.
It's an arcade style casual game.
It's RC radio control games, and it's
got some breadth and depth.
It's a small studio.
At peak, it was about 17 people.
But as we looked at the game, I think indie,
there could be a long discussion about what's
indie and what's not indie.
But I think a lot of times, you'll
kind of see these alternative, crafty, artistic games.
And that can really.
work well for the indie terminology in the press.
So while we talked about indie to some degree,
that wasn't our main messaging point.
And we landed at a quick messaging line,
which was Little Cards, Big Fun.
Developing the marketing plan, we
thought about some of the considerations
I mentioned before, the nature of the game,
seasonality, the genre.
what we thought was going to work best for it, whether it was going to be, you know,
we had some good partner opportunities, which I'll talk about in a second.
We looked at the channel.
We put together some timed promotions, which I'll talk about.
And then the team was also very nimble, so they were able to take advantage
of different opportunities as they emerge.
So one of the first things we decided to do was, you know, at the December launch, we
came up with some seasonal content.
When I say we, it was them.
It was the game developers.
So there was a, but we had that conversation and said, you know, is there something we
could do to fit there?
And they came up with a great holiday themed track and, you know, Santa's sleigh was one
of the vehicles.
And, you know, this thing had so much legs that one year later we did it again.
They actually, they used the gyroscope on the phone,
so it was like a snow globe on the main interface.
So they did some fun things with that
to really help that connect with the seasonality.
They also knew the half-brick folks well,
so they, and Fruit Ninja was kind of at its peak
at the time, it still is really well,
but they were able to get some Fruit Ninja content
in there with a track and a car
that was loaned out from the folks there.
So that was helpful.
PR, I think a lot of times you'll pitch things
and see how it resonates with people.
And we were fortunate that IGN responded well to the game,
and they put it on their home page.
But again, we needed a balanced marketing plan.
So if PR hits, that's great.
But if it doesn't, we needed other things in our arsenal
if that wasn't going to hit.
But we had the good fortune of getting
on the home page of IGN by pitching them.
Reviewed well, which helps tremendously.
I think game quality is always kind of spoken about repeatedly
is a really important thing, but I'll just
kind of re-emphasize that here.
And then we worked with the folks on the App Store,
and we got a great slot at launch day, which, again, when
it works, it's fantastic, but it doesn't always work,
so you've got to have other things in your arsenal.
And then that carried over into best of 2012
on the App Store, and it was a choice on Google Play.
We also came up with a plan that had different components over time.
So we launched in December, so we had a really nice peak.
We went full price at $2.99 on tablet and $1.99 on phone.
And then we had kind of a staged promotion where we were going to go discounted about
two to three months in.
So you could see we had a nice peak as we got into February.
And then that peak you see in May,
we were back at full price.
And the team was thinking about an update.
And what we did was we collected some features
and we turned it into not just 1.1, but we turned it in 1.5.
And we made it a bigger release.
And we got more attention.
And we got another feature on the App Store.
And I think part of the point here
is not thinking just about the launch,
but thinking about what's your sustaining plan.
And don't have everything just about day one,
because.
again, when it works, it's great, but you've spent, you know, one, two, three years on
your game, and, you know, if you don't make it all in the first week, think about monetizing
it over a longer period of time.
So I think that's a really important part of the planning process as well.
We subsequently launched on Android,
which simultaneous releases can be great.
And I recommend that as often as possible,
but I know it's not always possible.
So fortunately, it worked out well for this game.
We got another wave of interest, and activity, and reviews,
and app store placements.
And when I talk about opportunism,
interest grew to such a degree that someone came to them
and wanted to do arcade cabinets and different arcades
around there.
around the world.
So that's a little visual you see off to the side.
Ultimately, the game's gone on to do
6 million downloads, which is great.
There was a free app of the day promotion,
which worked out really well.
And they had in-app purchasing to help monetize that.
So I think the summary point here
is think about your plan holistically
and think about all the different things
that you could layer into it and come up
with a plan over time that could be strategic.
With that, I will turn things over to Justin.
Hey, what's happening?
I'm going to tell everything, or tell the main points
through my perspective, which is an indie.
I believe that marketing and sales
emanates from the inside out.
So when you're marketing, you're not only
marketing to the consumer.
You're also marketing towards your team.
You're marketing towards your publisher,
anyone you're going to work with.
So.
These are my main points for the whole talk.
Socialize and relate to people.
Add value to people's lives.
Cultivate mentors.
Be persistent, resilient, and tenacious.
Pursue visibility.
And what works for them works for them.
So I say that because when we spoke last time,
people had questions about.
you know, specific points and it didn't quite relate to what we did. It only relates to
you. So this is, the game that we released is called Super Combo Man. This is our elevator
pitch and it is 2D side-scrolling fighters set in a sticker world with custom combos
and hand-drawn animations. And it took us a while to get to the point where that our
vision was complete.
I'm going to explain everything through chapters of my journey.
And the journey was the plan, the journey, the hustle,
and the launch.
And it took us four years to complete this game,
and many struggles, a lot of pitches.
And this is how we rolled and did things.
So as Joel mentioned, we, so my background
was a graphic designer, I had a graphic design business.
I graduated from the Art Institute as a game artist,
environment game artist, and I went and worked for THQ
for a few months and I hated it.
So then I turned to develop, someone laughing.
But, yeah, so I started a graphic design business, and I cultivated some mentors that helped
me through the strategies of business operation. And we released the first game, which was
on iOS, and we said as a team, let's create something that's bigger, has more production
value, and that we can release on a console.
So we created a marketing plan, we created a business plan,
and the marketing plan kind of rolled into the business plan.
And we wanted to spend most of our time on the game production,
because, you know, we're artists first, and then, you know, business people second.
So one of the things that we wanted to do early on
was figure out how we can market with someone else.
And we figured early on that we would work with a publisher.
We weren't sure how we were going to do that,
but the numbers kind of spoke for themselves.
So when we talked to mentors and we created a business plan,
we understood that it would cost a lot for us
to just pay someone to outright market for us.
So we decided that may be the next, the best step.
We did a lot of market research, figured out the visibility mechanisms for each platform,
and that's basically how we talked to, I talked to a lot of mentors.
I had a mentor, Clinton Keith, who brought agile development to the games industry,
and he helped me with the business plan as well,
and it showed us, you know, concrete details on how we were going to press forward with this game.
So in the early stages, we had our business plan.
There was a contest for Nexon where
they wanted to create the next Maple story.
And they had like a $100,000 pot for the winner.
And we felt that our art style was perfect.
That's our little character.
Struggles with the talking fanny pack
and the mullet nuggets on top.
We were going for this anime, wacky feel.
And we had this whole idea that
the characters were all going to be stickers.
And so when we pitched it to Nexon, we were like, OK,
so they have these Nexon cards at Walmart and at Target,
which they have different keys on them
to get different abilities or just money for their store.
And so the way we pitched it was we had little animations and different characters and we
had our business plan and the idea was you peel the stickers back and you get a key for
different abilities and items that you can use.
We didn't, it didn't work out well, we didn't win the contest, but we did get some good
feedback from that and we knew where to move forward with our next steps.
And it was a very iterative process as far as our marketing plan was concerned and that
really helped us because we understood
who they were trying to reach at that moment.
The next thing we did was we did a Kickstarter campaign,
and this was in the early days before, this was 2010,
so you could see how long this game stretched back.
We released the game in July 2014.
But we did a video and the video was super ridiculous. It didn't have a lot of game play. We
showed a lot of the team. We were marketing our team to people and I think like our moms and
uncles were the only ones who actually, you know, put in. You could see the total amount was
a thousand bucks. So it really didn't get us far but it did give us a, you know, a good video
that we can, and the video was really ridiculous. I went to Walmart and had, you know, those
little styrofoam earths and stuff, you know, the planets.
And I wore those on my head to be this character.
So it was very entertaining, and we just
kept iterating on our process for marketing.
And that's what I was talking about,
is we were marketing not only for the people who
were going to buy the game, but to the publishers
that we were talking to.
Right here, you see the product positioning chart,
which my mentor showed me how to do.
It was a good exercise to show where our target market was.
You see at the very end, it's.
A more of a hardcore game on the other side,
it's more of a casual, ours fit in between.
It was like a combination of Marvel vs. Capcom,
Street Fighter meets Streets of Rage.
Those are some of the stickers,
and we have our product plan right here,
our development plan.
So different key points in time were like GDC,
where we thought we were gonna show PAX.
We thought we would show,
those were some of our milestones.
And how we also created the elevator statement
is there to the left too.
So as a graphic designer, I knew the importance of presentation
and how presentation plays into who you're marketing towards
and who you're contacting.
So we were talking to PlayStation.
So I created this two-sheet with the Sony Vita
and how it would work when you're swiping
and the stickers would peel back.
And it really resonated with them.
at the time, I don't even know why they did this, but Gamefly had an Android program and we were
trying to find any opportunities possible to, you know, get the money and the marketing to move
forward with our game. So that kind of talks about the, you know, the pre-production and the
plans that we came up with.
it obviously doesn't turn out the way you want to exactly.
So I'm going to tell you a little bit about my team story.
So after I was in my master's program for production
and design and management.
And the opportunity came up to help my mentor with a leadership forum at the IGDA.
And during that time, we also, there was also a contest to be at IGN Game Spy and have office
space.
They had an incubator.
And when that happened, we pitched to them and we used everything that we gathered beforehand
and they saw our video, they saw our marketing plan and really dug it.
So they gave us an opportunity.
They gave us the go ahead, they loved our pitch,
and they were like, come up here.
So we had to figure out within a week's time
whether we were going to take that opportunity.
And one of my mentors was, he's like,
you got to take life by the balls
and just go with it because it's a once in a lifetime
opportunity.
So I took the opportunity.
I'm a very opportunistic person, and every time I see something,
I'll go for it.
And it ended up turning out well.
We were in IGN, and we worked for three months
straight on the prototype.
Um, so this, this goes to the training.
So we had GDC after the three months of, of hard development, we, uh, had a GDC demo
space.
and that was a great opportunity to talk to press and 47 communications which is actually
here in San Francisco, they had their lead Kramer who used to work with Capcom and they
trained us. They actually came in and told us how to talk to people because I had a,
I was very nervous to talk to press about our game or just to talk to people in general
and I didn't know exactly what to say. I would fumble my words or I would give these lengthy
explanations of things and they helped me become succinct and concise.
They also had press pitch sessions at IGN where they had like seven people from members
of the press come in and just rapidly fire off different questions, take pictures of
us and talk to us in a press junket type of fashion.
I remember at one point I completely froze up in front of everyone and I didn't know
if I was going to jump back from that, but it wasn't as bad as I thought.
So it was really interesting to do that training.
just to understand how you market towards other people because marketing towards other people,
each member of the press, each publisher that you talk to, each person that you're selling to
has a different story, a different background, and you want to make sure that you create that story
that, you know, works with them, you know, and reflects their ideals.
So these images represent our time there,
my mentor in the middle, Clinton Keith,
and we were at the Indy Open House.
We won the next Game Boss, which was this reality show on IGN.
We worked very hard.
You see the cast of the Indy Open House,
and just different people playing the game.
So I'll say this is the hustle phase one,
even though this is like the hustle phase eight.
We showed at multiple events
and try to figure out how we can show free.
And that's really important too,
is when you're pitching, you show your plan
and you figure out how you align
with specific products and product holders.
We, we at that time, you know, I lost my team so I jumped back and had to figure
out how we were going to pitch and raise more money.
And, um, there, you know, there was a lot of rejection and I had to figure
out how to bounce back from that.
We jumped, uh, to a second Kickstarter fundraising campaign.
At the end of the Indie Open House, we had a large presentation and it gathered the attention
of Adam Boyes, who is now one of the VPs at Sony.
And he just took me under his wing and he was like, I want you to pitch to every publisher
possible because that was one of the only ways I felt that we were going to actually
get the game out and market it towards a broad audience.
So he took me to Capcom.
He took me to Sega, he took me to EA,
all these different places.
Some people I just went to on my own,
I was just pitching, pitching, pitching.
And also, my other mentor who was in business,
she knew nothing about video games.
So she was teaching it from a different standpoint,
which is very interesting.
And it's good to get multiple angles and paradigms
when you're trying to figure out.
your road to success with marketing and developing your game. So at one point I was in
Berkeley and I was like there's this place called Cream, I don't know if you guys know of
it, it's an ice cream sandwich stop, ice cream sandwich store and I was like yeah my
character eats cookies and it would be a perfect mascot for your marketing campaigns and
they totally got it. They dug it and they wanted to do it but the thing was we actually
wanted.
We needed money too, so marketing wasn't the only thing we were searching after.
So it didn't completely fit, but us pitching how the marketing would work
completely fit with their campaign. It was a good experience.
These are some of the other events that we showed at.
Hot Import Nights, they had a Dead or Alive 5 booth there.
The Comic Con, Evo, our game's a fighting game,
so we went to the biggest fighting game competition in Vegas in July.
So this is Hustle phase 100.
So we were going 100%.
We just raised more investment, and we
started a second Kickstarter fundraiser campaign.
The second fundraiser campaign, I
understood how the media and the press worked more,
and I already had a lot of different contacts there.
So all I did was reach back to them,
told them that we were making this game,
or we progressed in our game.
further, showed them new builds, and they were really interested in it. It got a lot of buzz
that way. I also talked to the publishers as well. So I always reached back at different stages of
development when we were trying to move forward with marketing, investment, whatever.
At this time, the mix was born.
So as Joel spoke about, we created this media indie
exchange at IGN where just the press and the indies
got together.
And they were able to vibe off of each other.
The press got to see games they've never seen
from the hottest indies.
And the indies who, some of them don't really
speak out to press, even though they have great content
and great tech.
we're able to talk to them in a more closed manner, you know?
So we did a second Kickstarter. It was, it ended up being successful.
We, I reached back to publishers. Capcom really liked the game,
but the deal wasn't really, didn't really fit with us.
And at the second GDC we were at, I went and pitched to Adult Swim Games.
They loved the idea, and they, they didn't take it right away,
because they weren't working with Steam.
But when they did start working with Steam, they were like,
OK, let's...
let's do this. And it was good because we understood their marketing. They already had
influencer marketing campaigns and people on Twitch and that's kind of where things
were going. And it really helped us to push the game along and get other people interested
because once they got interested, we were able to get more investor support, more press
support and the people that I contacted before, I used that as leverage.
So this is like, so we were supposed to launch,
I believe, in April, and it took a little longer
to release, because this was our first large game.
And we launched on Steam and Humble.
There was initial PR fumble with the publisher
and the production staff there.
Early build got sent out to all of the press, but.
Marketing wise it was a complete success because we got hit by every single
Not every single but most of major press
checked our game out, gave our game previews or reviews.
We had Northern Lion, some of the largest YouTubers
checked our game out.
And regardless if they liked it or not,
because they got a buggy build, it still got a lot of press.
And the whole education of what we did in that four years
kind of escalated to that point, which was really good.
We maximized coverage.
We built a mix out of it.
We had our initial Humble Bundle with Adult Swim,
and I cultivated a relationship with Humble Bundle.
So what ended up happening was we got our rights back
from Adult Swim because we wanted
to start doing things on our own because they didn't want
to support it anymore.
And we released all of these updates,
and we did another Humble Bundle,
which was a Brawler Humble Bundle,
which was pretty successful.
And it also built our foundation for the next game.
All right, so yeah, so just kind of, you know, quick, quick point to sort of wrap
them, things together from my part and Justin's point, part.
You know, I think there are two different approaches to marketing and I think some
really great takeaways from Justin's presentation is, you know, a lot of
persistence and, and creating things that could be leveraged for another program
later on and just being really open and nimble and flexible and, and thinking how
you could kind of keep things going and.
you know, kind of forge your way to launch.
And as Justin was saying too,
they came out with the game, they got the rights back,
they kind of keep plowing ahead,
you know, they kind of think about the longer tail
as opposed to just the launch burst
if it didn't go exactly how they wanted.
And, you know, part of the end result is,
you know, here we are post-launch
and now they're working on their next game.
So I think that's part of the vision of the indie world
is, you know, best case, your launch comes out
and it fires on all cylinders,
but kind of next best is, you know,
you do well enough so you can keep going on to your next game.
Something else that comes out of the indie world is that it's a great community, and
I think there's great opportunities to think about programs that not only help your game,
but also help other games.
And I think it's excellent how people work together.
And The Mix is a great example.
As Justin was saying, he was working at IGN.
GDC rolled around, and they said, hey, let's have some journalists in here, and let's get
some other indie games, too.
And here we are.
So that was in 2012.
Here we are years later.
And that's really turned into a tremendous platform
for indie game developers.
We do it every year now.
And we have expanded from four events last year.
We're planning to do six or seven this year,
including E3.
We're going to South by Southwest next week, Comic-Con,
SIGGRAPH.
And so we're doing things that not only help
some of the Justin's game and other games,
but we're helping other indies and give them a platform.
So that's kind of a little bit about the mix and how things tie together.
And how we started working together was, I was thinking as a marketer,
it's great to work with individual indies, but how could I do programs
that benefit multiple people at the same time and get some efficiency?
So that's part of the connection with how our worlds have come together.
And it happens a number of times.
It's been fantastic.
The Humble Bundle started, as some of you may well know,
as that was Wolfire.
And they were marketing their game.
And they were inspired by what World of Goo
did with the pay what you want.
And things kind of evolved and evolved.
And they were just thinking, hey, let's do a bundle.
And then next thing you know, it was tremendously successful.
And it became its own business.
So, yeah, so that's one example.
Yeah, some of the developers at the IGN in the open house, we started meetups and a lot
of the developers came and cultivated and we worked together.
contacted Tim Schafer and that presented an option to have an incubator there as well,
a double fine. Someone in the audience, Dylan, has Games Nest and that's blowing up too.
And that's how some of the indies work together.
So yeah, so I think it's interesting that you market
your game, but as you're doing it,
there could be opportunities that not only help your game,
but also can benefit others in the community.
I think a lot of people know about Rami Ismail's Press Kit.
It was something he developed to start his game,
but now a lot of people use it to help make their press
communications efficient.
And there's some other examples here that I think
people are familiar with.
I'm going to segue into.
one more example for you that is connected with this not on Steam icon that you see here.
And this is a case of another studio that created their game.
released it and found that it didn't perform how they wanted.
And you'll see the first couple months,
if this was you in your game studio,
it might be a little bit discouraging.
But they kept plowing ahead.
And they were really tenacious and persistent.
And I'll talk about some of the things
they did to be successful.
But one big takeaway here is that of their year one
revenues.
they got 90% of the revenue in months four through 12.
So I think people might stereotypically think,
you know, everything I'm going to make
is going to be in the first month,
or the first three months.
And if I don't do it then, I'm sunk.
And I think these guys are a great example.
I don't know when they're speaking,
but they might have already spoken.
But if you hear GDC, if they're speaking tomorrow,
I would suggest check them out, and they'll
talk more about what they did.
And so, you know, so they launched.
It didn't perform what they wanted.
they did a blog on Gamasutra and on their own website.
And it was one month later, losing Steam.
And I think their takeaway was, we self-released,
but we weren't able to get on Steam.
And that's been a big part of why we're not
performing how we want.
That got some press attention.
And Greenlight was going on.
And they launched this.
I'm just going back to the icon real quick.
They launched the Not On Steam sale.
And that was their own creation.
And they said, we're not on Steam.
And here's a whole bunch of other game developers that aren't on Steam,
and how can we kind of come up with a program?"
So they did what you know about Steam sales.
They did discounted pricing.
They had a Humble widget on there,
so people can buy directly through this, not on Steam sale.
And they also had a link to everyone's Greenlight page,
so they can help kind of build their
fuel their Greenlight campaign.
And, um...
And so that really resonated.
Press found it interesting and they wrote about it.
They had dozens of developers over the course of this promotion.
And then the other thing that happened was not only did
Race the Sun get greenlit, but a number of other games got greenlit.
And so you'll see this bump in December.
And then they finally came out on Steam.
They monetized it, they did really well.
They kept plugging ahead.
They decided to add Steam Workshop in March.
And that gave them another really nice bump
in their promotional pricing.
And then they had other promotions as time went on.
And they're continuing on, and they're
getting ready for a PlayStation release and so on.
So again, quick summary point here is just,
while it can be discouraging, sometimes
there's some trial and error, and sometimes just
kind of trying and experimenting with different things
to go after success.
Just kind of quickly here, this is just,
we talked about channel, we talked about PR,
this is just kind of really quickly,
there's examples of people who have done well
with advertising, there's some people who have done well
with releasing playable code with early access.
There's people who've achieved their success
through promotions, and not just price promotions,
but sometimes working with other indies
to have compelling content, and PR.
So,
Some of these examples are written up in more detail on the link that I'm going to have in a couple slides, so you can read more about these.
And in conclusion, just a couple of takeaways to take with you.
Going back to earlier points from the presentation, begin early.
Be nimble, be flexible, the plan is very likely going to change.
Be flexible, be nimble, and stay tenacious.
Just go after it.
This is important.
You're spending months and years of your life in this game, working on this game.
Stay after it.
It can be discouraging sometimes, but tenacity will help you be successful.
And if not the first time, maybe the next time.
We talked a lot about relationship building and networking.
You know, Justin talked about how he was just so aggressive
and persistent in talking to as many people as possible,
and you never know what's gonna pan out for you.
So get out there, go to shows,
cultivate your relationships,
meet people in person as often as possible,
and that can bear tremendous fruit for you.
Have a mix of vehicles in your marketing plan.
While it can be tempting to rely on just one thing,
it's useful to have a balance so that if one thing doesn't fire,
you've got other things to support your program.
And I'm sorry to end with a clich, but it's a marathon, not a sprint.
Just think about it in the long term.
This would be a great place to take pictures,
because these are some links where we've got a little bit
more information.
I know this is going to be posted soon,
but there's more examples from what
we talked about the presentation in the second link.
So that's my blog.
It's not super populated right now,
but I've got some resources and some other links in there.
The last URL here is Justin's studio in Terabang.
And mediainexchange.com is the events
that we run together that we talked a little bit about.
And with that, we have time.
I'm just going to check my clock real quick.
We have 15 minutes for questions.
So invite people to come up to the microphone.
And if you ask questions, please make
sure you ask your question in the microphone
so it'll be recorded for the video.
Is the microphone on for the audience?
Doesn't seem to be.
OK, there it goes.
So briefly, right at the end, you mentioned early access.
And early access, there seems to be a desire from it
on the consumer side.
Like there have been several games
that have been really successful.
It also seems to have tanked games when it's been botched.
So I wondered if you had any more thoughts
you could expand upon with early access
and how it ties into marketing and eventual success
of the game.
Yeah, I think part of it is, if I can,
I'm going to try and flip back real quick.
is uh...
if I could briefly like I think you gotta sometimes when you're looking at early access
you gotta think of it like a kickstarter campaign
some of your sales will migrate from the actual sales when you release the game
to the early access so it won't dictate
how the the margin of sales you'll get later
does that make any sense?
yes
So, and you know, I think the point I was going to make with this slide is, you know,
think about the shape of your marketing plan.
If you do early access 12 months before you're really going to release the game, you know,
you have the potential to lose momentum.
And I think another thing that I, like Clay was talking about, how when they did early
access and were successful with something like Don't Starve, they had a really good
schedule and communication plan about how they were doing it.
I believe it was every month they had a new content release and they told people what they were doing and when they were going to do it.
And there's a lot of things that made Don't Starve successful, but I think in terms of how they did early access, there's some good lessons learned there.
I think it's important to think about having a good game experience.
I think some people might fall down with...
putting a game on early access that's not representative
of their final game, it creates a bad impression.
And so that doesn't work well for them.
So I think there's a lot of considerations that go into it.
But I think the ones who have done it well,
they think about their timing.
They think about updates to communications.
They think about the experience.
So I think there's pros and cons.
But when you do it well, you've got the opportunity
to start generating revenue before you
do the full game release and then can do kind of a polish.
Another quick thing there is.
if all the content is there in early access,
then there's kind of nothing to follow through on
when you release the full game.
So you want to think about that part of it.
So when all those things work well,
then you can prepare yourself
for a successful launch afterwards.
All right, thank you.
Yep.
Hello, thank you.
This is strong.
Thank you for the talk.
I want to, I feel, I don't know how to ask this.
I feel maybe for some people, I'm from Argentina,
and
Maybe I feel some of those tips are not reachable for us,
because being on festivals, or maybe in GDC, for us
it's really difficult. And when you need your resources
to develop your game, it's really hard to.
you know, use those resources for marketing.
And the thing is, what do you think about,
you didn't talk too much about creativity, I think,
because it's like, those are the ways of marketing
your game, but I think there are a lot of more ways
of marketing that doesn't exist yet, you know?
So I could talk about Supercommon Man.
So Supercommon Man was a fighter.
There's something called influencer marketing.
And we geared a lot of our marketing
towards the fighting game community.
And we got top fighting game personalities to play our game.
We showed at different fighting game
festivals and tournaments.
And we creatively tried to figure out
where it would fit within that audience.
So yeah, you definitely, while you're marketing your game or anything, you got to think of like
how to get in where you fit in, you know what I mean? Like, so to speak. So is that what you're
talking about as far as the creative aspects of... I mean, for example, do you know Dumb Boys Today?
Yeah. Okay.
the video was something that they created previously, but what if it were like the other, you know?
I have the game done with today, and then I make the video.
The video goes viral, and then I have my game.
Yeah, I mean, I think...
Different ways, you know?
Yeah, if I'm getting your point, I think it's creative content is sort of a...
a way of attracting people.
I mean, I've been talking about programs a lot,
and you're talking about sometimes it's
the creative content.
Am I understanding your point correctly, the content?
It's like I felt like that technique
of marketing your product, it was out of the talk.
And I think creativity, when you don't have those resources,
is the main thing you have to, as indie developers,
creativity is our main strength.
I think you're absolutely right.
Sometimes you have just this incredibly compelling concept,
and you have something that really resonates,
and the job becomes a lot easier.
And sometimes you have this incredibly compelling piece
of marketing content.
Maybe it's like this great viral video,
or maybe it's a program.
So absolutely, I think there's.
There's tons of value in that, and thank you
for bringing that into the conversation.
If I can, I would just one more thing.
As game designers and developers,
I think we have to ask the game to marketing itself.
Like tools like Twitter, or I don't know.
There's a lot of ways of making your game create content
automatically by the user content,
or other ways that you don't have
to work for creating that content.
Yeah. I mean, I think there's, you know, there's people who want to believe in the field of dreams, you know, where you, if you build it, they will come. And, and, uh, when you're lucky that works. But I think depending on that can be a challenge. And so I, I guess from a marketer perspective, I encourage you to, you know, to think about what else you could do. I mean, if you're lucky, it's great. And I, and I think also from the outside, it, it looks easier than it really is. You know, you, you see these great examples and you say, Oh, that was super easy for them. But in reality,
they might have done like five games before that, or they might have done 20 other things
for that game before the thing really fired. So, yeah, so next question.
Hey guys. Holy, whoa. Good to see you. So you talked about all the things that you shouldn't
do, and we just released a game a little less than a month ago, and we did all of those
things. We didn't advertise it at all, and we built it and they haven't really come.
the big reason for that, oh by the way the game is called Blitz Keep, it's on IOS and Android,
go get it right now. Please. Okay. Thank you. It's creative right? That's what he's talking
about. It's a new thing. Anyway. So we work on it totally part time. That's kind of a big
challenge I've had. I've always been making indie games part time. And yeah, I've gone to
some of your events and stuff. And how do you really ever, is there kind of like,
few things that you can do when you're someone who's working on a game 10 15 hours a week like to get this stuff rather than
You know someone who's got all of their time like would you say what's like the top things or something? Well, I'm gonna hire somebody
like Joel or John, there's a lot of people out there now that used to be, you know, full time
marketers and now want to do it for indie game companies and they will take that off your
hands. Because that was an issue I had. I mean, I didn't market full time at all. You know, I
wanted to spend most of my time in production. I was producing full time.
But I wanted to figure out different ways
to implement marking without me spending as much time.
So I completely understand what you're talking about.
And I think part of it is having the discipline to just,
even if you're not going to be spending
a lot of time executing, just having a discipline
to think about.
what do I want my marketing plan to be?
Like, you have your milestones in development,
and you have your development tasks,
and either you're doing it yourself
or someone's helping you,
but having the discipline to say,
you know, six, nine, 12 months before launch,
what do I want to do?
And I might not have time to do it every week,
but you could at least think about the content,
you could think about kind of the big beats,
I'm sorry I'm using another...
cliche, but you could, you know, think about what are the big beats you want to have.
And that can help, um, you know, it can help drive a program, even if you can't
spend a lot of time doing it.
And then you think, you know, but I'm really going to like three months before
launch, I'm going to do X, Y, and Z, you know, the previous time I've only got 15
hours a week, I'm going to be developing like.
90% of the time.
But you would say, I'm going to do 10% on marketing.
And that'll give you some structure
and kind of an intelligent approach to it,
even if your time is limited.
And as Justin was saying, at some point,
maybe two months before launch or three months before launch,
I'm going to allocate some money to, if I can't do it myself,
have someone help me with it.
You could also have someone on your team spearhead it.
Or work with, create a plan.
Spend like a week creating a plan.
for marketing and then have some interns help you with some of the social outreach, work
with someone on Elance, and or have someone on your team who's really good at that, vocalizing
that to help you with your marketing campaign.
Hello? Okay, good. How abstract or rigid should your marketing plan be when you're
developing or when you're brainstorming on it in the beginning of development? I was going to
say I think your plan should be really rigid but you should be flexible on your plan if that
makes any sense. So you create a concrete plan. Right, you create a guideline.
It's just, yeah, you create guidelines and you have to iterate on it. It's just like game
production. It's just another aspect of game production. When you create your plan for
producing a game, you're going to have an idea and a vision of what you want, but you're never
going to stick to that. Because you know some things aren't going to work, the timing doesn't
work, the press that you wanted to
to look at your game, aren't going to look at it when you want it, but at least you have these guidelines to go by.
And then you, you know, adjust accordingly.
Yeah, I think there's very few marketing plans that I've done that have held up from like development time to execution time.
You know, almost all the time, you know, date shift or detail shift and, you know, great
military quote is, you know, there's very few battle plans that survive contact with
the enemy.
You know, it's the same kind of thing that create a plan, give yourself structure, but
it's just the same, be flexible and be ready to...
you know, adjust it as you go. Yeah, you would drive yourself crazy if you just create a plan.
You're like, oh, this isn't working. You know what I mean? You can't force stuff. You got to go
with the flow. And I think development is probably the same way. I don't know anything about it as a
developer, but I suspect, you know, that same kind of mentality is useful. It's exactly the same.
Yeah. All right. Thank you. Yep. Thanks. Hey, guys. Great talk.
I'm currently building a fairly hardcore PC title,
and I find most marketing resources are geared
towards casual and mobile game sort of platforms,
where I think the consumers are much less educated
about the product they're buying,
and can be much more influenced by marketing.
You talked about Super Combo Man
being more on the hardcore side.
Have you got any other tips for influencing
the more hardcore market?
I think that's changing and you know casual was where mobile was and now that's shifting to more hardcore
you can see it in the Korean and Japanese markets and you're getting a lot more people who used to work in the industry
that want to help market hardcore games. You got to kind of figure your niche.
And so I've been working part-time as an influencer
marketer.
And what that means is working with YouTubers and Twitch
streamers and people in the Vine community, Instagram community,
to help boost up your community for your game.
So you've got to kind of figure the different chess pieces
that will help boost.
the visibility of your game. And if you create a plan, you could work with someone like Joel,
or I keep like, you know, boosting him up, but you could work with someone who's strategic
that can help that, help you with that. When I was working with Adult Swim, just an example
of when I was working with them, they were just shooting it out to every,
Twitch streamer and it like that didn't really help us.
So I was, I had to, I actually formulated a plan that I wanted to work with them on
that would shoot it to, to the right trajectory.
Unfortunately we did it a little late, but when, if you're even thinking about
working with a publisher or outside, you should kind of cultivate a vision of
where you're, who your gamer is and you want to connect with that person.
So, you know, personality is key in figuring out how you want to.
relate to them and connect with them with different influencers in the market.
Yeah, so this, um, you know, in terms of YouTubers, there's this, uh, YouTubers
mega list that, um, I have a, I have a link from it on the, the indie game, uh,
IndieMarketer.com.
Um, so that's a tremendous resource.
It's got, um, all the, a lot of YouTubers by follower size.
It's got contact information you could get, and it also talks
about genres they follow.
Um, events can be super useful for getting to core gamers.
You know, PAX is amazing.
The Indie Megabooth at PAX is a great avenue to get there.
PR is another great way to reach core gamers.
Again, it's like, can you get through to them, I think,
is it can be challenging, but it's important.
So it's worth the attention, but also
have other things in your marketing mix
that can help supplement you if you're not
getting the coverage.
I think we might have one last question we could cover,
and then we're going to get to the end of our time.
Or are we out of time?
One more.
Time or no?
Oh, yeah, we have time for the last question.
What's a good percentage of your budget
to dedicate towards a launch?
Traditional would be 10% to 15%.
For marketing is your question, right?
Yeah, just for the launch or the whole year?
Well, I would say marketing 10% to 15% of what
you want your revenues to be is the way I would approach it.
Like, what's my target revenues?
And then carve out 10% to 15%.
That's sort of a formula that's used in the marketing world.
And.
But I'm sorry, before revenue.
Before revenue.
I think budget.
It'd be 10% to 15% of your budget, straight up.
That's why I was trying to figure out,
when I was working with my marketing plan,
it really brought light to that.
I was like, oh, shit.
Oh, crap, sorry.
But from a practical point of view,
I think there's so many startup studios that they're
bootstrap, and they're living day to day and week to week.
And the majority of the time, there's
people just.
and they don't have the budget to support it.
So that's why the programs that we talked about here
and the programs that will often get executed are,
you know, I try and go for lean programs.
I mean, I'm used to working in bigger studios
and I had to sort of adapt my approach
when I'm working with indies.
And what is the AAA budget for like a launch?
Well, again, that's like the 10 to 15%
of expected revenues is the number
that I would work on in that world, so.
So same for an indie?
Yeah.
Okay.
So I want to remind you to please fill out your evaluations.
They're super useful to us as well as GDC.
I think you'll be getting an email right after this session,
so I encourage you to please do that.
And we'll stick around for a few minutes.
And thank you all for coming.