Hi, I'm Matt Del Bosque, team lead programmer at Ubisoft Toronto.
Watch Dogs 2's Bounty Mode is a hell of a lot of fun.
When you get four players getting into a car chase at high speeds,
crashing into police cars, it's a lot of fun to play.
But it wasn't a lot of fun to get those vehicles to replicate nicely.
In my talk entitled Replicating Chaos, Vehicle Replication for Watch Dogs 2,
I'm going to go over some of the techniques that we used to coordinate all of that and make it look nice.
We're going to talk about some of the standard techniques such as projective velocity blending or snapshot buffers
that we used and adapted for our purposes and made them a bit more specific to vehicles.
Some of the things that we did to deal with collisions and other various problems that we had to face and solve along the way.
This talk is aimed at online programmers of any ability levels, and I really hope to see you there.