So now it's working.
So hi.
Welcome, everyone.
First of all, I'm supposed to tell you
that you should turn off the sound on your mobile phones.
My name is Mikkel.
I'm a graphics programmer.
This is Mikkel.
He's a very technical artist.
We work at Playdead, which is a Danish company that did a game.
ages ago, it was called Limbo.
And neither of us worked on that,
but we worked on the follow-up title called Inside
that's been in production for some six years or so.
And that's what we'll be talking about today.
More specifically, we'll be talking about the rendering.
And we sort of selected some topics
that we think would be relevant to other games
that you can steal and implement in your own games,
the same as we stole all your stuff.
So yeah, before sort of diving into that,
I'll show the trailer from E3 a couple years ago,
so you sort of have an idea about the game
that will be rented.
REMEMBER NOT TO SEE
Right.
So as you can see, it's a 2 and 1 half D side-scrolling game.
That means that we have full control over everything
the player ever sees, because we're only ever moving
rightwards.
That means that our artists can go in and tweak every pixel.
And in turn, that means that our art style heavily
relies on these very subtle details of the art.
That also means that from sort of a rendering point of view,
we can't have too many artifacts that distract
from these subtle details in the art.
That's kind of a point that this whole
will be revolving around.
So from sort of a technical point of view, just to get that out of the way, we are releasing at 60Hz at 1080p on current consoles.
And the engine we're using is a custom Uni-Z 5.0. We have source access for that, so we made some modifications.
The rendering that we're doing is like a light pre-pass.
renderer so that means that we have a base pass that outputs depth and normals
we then have a light pass that that calculates light from those steps and
normals and then we have a final pass that re-renders the entire frame and
then applies the light and materials we then have a translucency pass and then
we sort of wrap the whole thing up with a post effects pass.
Alright, so one of the things, one of the effects I suppose, that's really sort of central to our art style and showed to be central to our art style quite early on is the fog.
So actually, initially, we had a lot of scenes
that were just geometry and fog.
So we had like, everything was comprised of silhouettes
and then this like depth fog.
So to sort of show you how much mileage we get out of that,
here's the scene without any fog.
As you can see, that's quite bare.
And then adding just a like a linear depth fog,
we get
actually quite a sort of moody scene from that.
The only interesting bit we're really doing with this
is that we're capping the fog at like a maximum level.
So if we have really intense lights in the background,
then those will still shine through.
But otherwise, it's just like an open gel 1.0 linear fog
that we use in the depth.
Then we have this sort of light scattering post-effects emulation pass, and I kind of
say that with a smile because really what we're doing is just blurring the entire scene
and then blending that back on.
So really it's just like a glow pass that our artists then used to sort of simulate
this misty atmosphere.
And that works surprisingly well, and is what we're using throughout the game.
So now that we're using glow for this scattering effect,
then how do we do glow?
Well, we have a second pass where
we do these really narrow, high intensity glows.
So what we do is, like many have done before us,
is that we write out a mask for emissive objects in the scene.
And we then remap the intensity of that mask
to a 0 to 7 HDR value and calculate bloom from that.
So this is obvious in hindsight,
but it wasn't really when we implemented it.
it's, so when you calculate bloom from a pixel
with a certain intensity, like if the bloom
shows a certain intensity, then of course
we need to render the source pixel with that intensity
as well, otherwise there's like a difference
between the two.
So it's really like you just need to,
if you use HDR, you of course need to calculate bloom
from an HDR pixel, you of course need to actually
show that pixel in with the HDR value as well.
So the way we do the actual bloom filtering is the same as
Jimenez in the Call of Duty presentation and Martin
Mittring, I think from the Samaritan demo before him, in
that we just downsample the image a number of times and
blur while downsampling, and then we upsample and blur as
well afterwards.
So the way Jimenez did this was that during downsampling,
he had this 13-tab filter that used to,
like where every tab would sample four,
for texels, but as you can see, even though he's doing that,
he's still sampling some of the texels multiple times.
So what we did then was to fit a nine tab,
or nine tabs to these 13 tabs.
And that actually works pretty well.
So we get an error of like 8% at most
on the bilinear weights, but in the end,
we can't really tell the difference.
Of course, one important thing about this
is that this only works if you
if you downsample to a size that's exactly half your original size.
But that's not really an issue because you get the most benefit during the first couple of downsamples,
like from full resolution to half resolution.
So what we did was just to detect whether or not that was the case
and then use the full 13 samples if it wasn't.
Alright, so that means that we have a post-effects setup that looks like this.
So we have all our light pre-pass rendering and translucency.
We then run temporal anti-aliasing on top of all of that.
We then run our two glow passes, which are separate but interleaved for performance reasons.
And then in the end we do the HDR resolve, color resolve, and apply the glow and some other effects.
All right, so back to the fog that we were talking about before.
So it became apparent quite early on that we needed more control than just this global
linear fog that we were using.
So we implemented this local fog, like local light scattering.
I'll talk a bit about how that worked.
So in this scene, we have this guy with a flashlight,
and that flashlight is calculated using this effect.
So what we do is that for every pixel on screen,
we ray march through the world,
and for every step, we assemble the light function,
so we assemble the shadow map and the projected texture
and the falloff and that sort of thing.
And if you do an uneven implementation of this,
you end up with something that's really slow.
So this, if you don't want artifacts,
you need something along the lines of 128 samples.
And if you sort of try to make that faster
by reducing the number of samples,
you get these horrific stair-stepping artifacts.
And still it's quite slow.
So what you can do then, of course,
is you can add a little bit of noise into your ray offsets.
But you,
Yeah, so now it's actually even slower than it was before.
And the reason for that, of course,
is that we're now completely destroying texture cache
because our neighboring pixels are sampling
different points of the light textures.
But there's something interesting about this
because the eye is actually quite forgiving to the noise.
So we can actually tell what it was supposed to look like.
So that's an interesting property.
So we should explore that further.
So this is the same scene, except rather than using
24 steps, we're using just three.
And as you can see, that's a lot of noise
that we get in the image.
We can still kind of make out what it's supposed to be in,
but not really.
So what we can do instead is that we can use a biometrics.
And that has, of course, it has less noise
because there's no random in this.
It's an entirely homogeneous pattern.
And we also get better sampling because we now have,
like within a small region, we have all possible values.
So that means that sort of spatially,
before, maybe we were sampling everywhere
from each sample, but maybe we're not.
Now we're certain that we're always,
like within a small region,
we're always sampling at all distances.
But we get quite a lot of structure in this,
and whereas the eye is quite forgiving towards noise,
it definitely isn't towards patterns.
So really what we want is something that has this property
of changing at quite a high frequency
while not being a pattern.
So what we did then was that we used what's called
blue noise, which is high-pass filtered noise,
so obviously, which is high frequency.
And that sort of has both these properties.
So we get something that doesn't have the pattern
and at the same time it changes quite rapidly, spatially.
So, sort of stepping a little bit away from the noise
and looking at how to best use these samples.
The way we place, define fog volumes in the game
is that we place boxes in the world.
So of course, there's no reason for us
to sample outside those boxes,
and also there's no reason to sample outside of the light.
So what we do then is that we do a geometric intersection
between the geometry of the box
and the geometry of the light frustum.
And that essentially boils down to just
intersecting the light frustum with all the planes
of the box and then patching up the holes.
All right, so that means we have like a two-pass algorithm
where the first pass renders out the front faces
and then the second pass does the actual ray marching
and the first pass renders front faces,
second pass renders the back faces
and samples the front face texture.
So we now have like the start and end for our ray.
So this thing about using a box to define the fog volume
is something we actually use for effects.
So this is a scene where above water,
we have one volume that just uses the.
the textures from the light and sort of properties that makes it look like air.
And below water we use an animated projected texture to simulate caustics.
And then of course we change the fog properties to look like water instead.
So one thing you may have noticed
and that many others have noticed before us
is that of course this is quite a smooth effect.
We don't really need to calculate this per pixel.
We can at least get away with sampling it
at half resolution.
So we do that, of course.
So now we have a three-pass algorithm.
Two passes are the same as before,
but at half resolution.
So we write out the front face depth,
we do the ray matching,
and then we have like a third pass
that does a resolve to full resolution
at a later stage.
So while doing this opsampling,
we add a little bit of blurring,
and we do like an undersampled,
an undersampled sort of noisy blur
to break up the patterns that we would otherwise get
from the half-resolution sampling.
So one of the reasons why we do this is that
we have temporal anti-aliasing running afterwards.
So temporal anti-aliasing, at least in our implementation,
is using neighborhood clipping.
And that means that if we have a lot of different values
within a neighborhood, it will accept more values.
And so it's easier for it to smooth out per pixel noise,
like at full resolution, rather than half resolution noise.
So this is sort of a final image.
This is six samples at half resolution.
It's running at just below one millisecond
if we sample every pixel on screen,
which of course we don't.
Actually, most of the time we're using
just three samples per pixel.
So that means that we are using just below
one sample per full resolution pixel.
So one of the reasons why we've been obsessing about the number of samples here is because
this effect is bandwidth bound.
Sampling the shadow maps and the projected textures is really what bottlenecking is.
So we of course also do all the other things to reduce bandwidth.
Like we use a lower resolution shadow map,
we use lower resolution projected textures.
to, yeah, and of course the shadow map
can be lower resolution than for the opaque lighting passes
because it's such a smooth effect.
So the way that fits into our render pipeline is like this.
So the lighting pass, during the lighting pass
we save off the shadow maps that we'll need later on.
We then do our two initial passes
and end up with a volume light texture.
and then during the translucency pass,
we re-render the clipped geometry
and solve that with other translucencies.
So this thing about sort of playing into the hand
of temporal anti-aliasing is something
that we actually do in quite a lot of places.
So this example is the depth of field we're doing.
We have sort of planes that we can put into the world
that will calculate depth of field.
And we do like an undersampled blur again
and the temporal anti-aliasing will come
and pick up all the noise and smooth it out.
We also do that for shadows.
And an interesting thing here is that even though this sort of jittered sampling entirely destroys the texture cache,
it's still actually faster than doing just a single sample,
because we can render the shadow maps at a lower resolution,
because the soft penumbra is larger than the...
than otherwise, which is why we can get away with it.
So I just wanted to show how,
like this is sort of our go-to pattern
for doing this undersampled blurring.
And essentially it just boils down to
to having each sample cover the same area as,
well, all samples cover equal areas.
Right, so I'll talk about another effect that was really important to get the look of the
game, which is dithering.
So this is a frame from the game,
and I've sort of adjusted the luminance
so we can see what's going on a little bit better.
This is actually a really good example
of this sort of subtle detail I was talking about,
where we have a lot of really fine sort of gradients
out in the background.
This image actually contains quite a lot of noise.
You probably can't see that,
but if we turn it off, it looks like this.
See if that, yeah, I think that looks horrible.
That's good.
So what we get here is quite a lot of banding really.
So we have these really high frequency changes,
all these sharp lines during the image,
throughout the image.
And we also have these sort of rainbow-like effects
where the color is completely destroyed.
And of course that happens because our red, green,
and blue quantizes at different points.
And also it animates, so it's really quite distracting,
not really something we can live with
and or use with the art style that we intend.
So the reason why this happens is of course
that we are writing into 8-bit per channel render targets.
So as you can see on the line,
that means that we get this sort of
stair-stepping artifact, which looks like banding.
The reason for that, of course, is that 8 bits are not enough,
like nearly the human eye is able to perceive something
along the lines of 16 bits.
So we could have, of course, just used higher precision
render targets, but then for performance reasons
on some platforms, that will be an issue.
There are other ways of sort of getting about this.
We could use sRGB color compression instead, but...
Again, on some platforms that has interesting
implementations and so we chose to explore
dithering a bit further.
So an example of how this works is that you just add like one bit of noise.
So if we look at this, we look at the value of 0.75 bits and add one bit of noise, that
means that 75% of the time, because it's an entirely uniform noise, we end up at quantizing
to the...
the value above and 25% of the time we end up quantizing to the value below.
So on average we actually get exactly the signal that we put into it.
So just to sort of show how to do this, this is a fragment program or pixel shader
and how to do the dithering is you just add a random number that is 1 bit.
big on output. So just keep this in mind that this is actually spectacularly easy to add
and there's no real reason why games should ship with banding these days.
All right, so let's look a little bit more
about at what's going on.
So here in the top, we have the signal,
then we have the quantized band D output,
and then the third row shows the error
between the signal and the output.
So if we add noise to it, we then see that already
we have something that's a lot smoother.
We see the error is not very uniform,
and if we look at the variance at the bottom,
we can see that definitely we have these sort of weird humps.
If we animate the signal, we can see that we have these,
it becomes quite apparent that we have these areas
of no noise, which is interesting.
So what's going on there is something called
noise modulation.
that means that the resulting noise is actually dependent on the signal.
It turns out that's a property of the type of noise we're using.
So rather than using this uniform white noise,
we can switch to a triangulately distributed noise
that has a little bit like two bits worth of that,
and we get an output that...
where the noise is independent of the original signal.
So if we go back and apply that instead,
we can see that we now have an error
that is much more uniform.
And if we animate it, we can see that these sort of bands
of less noise have disappeared.
All right, but we've then added quite a lot of noise
to the signal, so what can we do about that?
Well, we can go back and then look,
try different types of noise,
like the blue noise that we were using for the sampling.
And that actually works out really well.
So again, if we animate it, we can see that we now
still don't have these bands of no noise,
and also we have much less noise
than just using the triangularly distributed regular noise.
All right, so what we've done is that we've baked
a blue noise, a high-pass filter noise, into a texture,
and we just sampled that and add that,
the same as the example before.
In the cases where we are bandwidth limited,
we use an ALU-based version instead,
which is essentially just adding
two random numbers together.
Alright, so now that we know how to dither, we should look at what to dither.
So this is an example of a single spotlight shining very bandy light into the scene.
And so of course the first thing we do is that we dither the light path.
So that looks like this, and that's already really good,
but we can see that we have these sort of,
like the noise is not entirely uniform,
we have these sort of waves in the noise.
And the reason for this is not, as you could expect,
because of the type of noise we're using,
it's just because we are sampling the light buffer
in the final pass and then writing that out
into an 8-bit buffer, again, or 20-bit buffer,
but 8 bits per channel.
So if we did that as well, we get this result,
which has entirely uniform noise, which is much better.
So of course, we need to do the translucency pass as well,
maybe even more important than all the other passes,
because during blending, we tend to write to each pixel
quite a lot, and then of course, re-quantize.
So it's quite important that we add noise
to all those passes, because each pixel
will get re-quantized quite a lot.
The post effects passes tend to read and write from buffers
quite a lot as well, so of course we need to dither those
as well to sort of make sure that this really wide,
light fog scattering, light scattering glow
was entirely banding free.
We actually ended up using 10 bits
and sort of power of two compressing the colors
and also dithering, and then that means
that we are entirely banding free for those as well.
So far we've been talking about banding in colors,
but really this is an artifact of the quantization.
Doesn't really have anything to do with colors.
So of course this affects our normals as well,
so when writing out the normals in the first pass,
we write those out to low-precision buffers as well,
and we of course need to do that as well.
We don't actually do that everywhere,
we just do it in sort of the specific spots where we
where we have really high intensity speculars where that's actually an issue.
Alright, so now we know everything that writes into 8-bit per channel buffers.
Is there anything else?
Well, animating the noise is a really good idea because if you don't, then you sort of
get this sort of dusty lens effect that's static when you move around, which looks weird.
Another reason to animate the noise is that we are running this temporal anti-aliasing
pass afterwards, so animating it means that the temporal anti-aliasing will actually go
and soak up a lot of this noise because it's integrating it over time.
Something else to think about is that your device when outputting to TV or other device
may convert the signal if you're not using the right output. So you should make sure
to, you know,
match the expected output as closely as possible.
For example, limited range RGB.
If you know that that's what your device will be outputting
then make sure that you do that
so you can properly dither the signal yourself.
And also, of course, UI tends to be transparent
and have lots of layers and fade in and out,
so it's quite important to dither that as well.
All right, I'll end here and hand it over
to the other maker.
Thanks.
Hi.
So the first thing I wanna show a little bit
and talk about a bit is custom lighting
or lights with custom light functions.
And we do these and we can do these
because we're using light pre-pass as our rendering loop.
From that, we can then not just render our points,
our spots, and our directs.
We can actually just render about any piece of geometry
with any shader that we'd like,
as long as it contributes to lighting in some way.
So we have a few of these.
I'm just gonna go into depth of three of our types.
The first one is the bounce light.
So the bounce light is pretty much
just something that we use for subtle lighting
or global illumination in some cases.
as the name suggests, and it's pretty much just a normal
Lambertini in point light, but with a small twist.
And that small twist is we have a slider that can
take that end of the product and wrap it all the way
to the back, making it a half Lambert at the half point,
or slide it all the way behind and just make it a fully
sort of ambient turn with just a fall off.
which gives much smoother, softer results
when you really don't want it to be obvious
where the light is actually coming from in these cases.
They get used in somewhat creative ways
because they're not static,
so typically for windows that open and let light in,
we put one there and fade it in,
or spotlights that hit the ground
and want to cast something off from there
when appropriate.
And one thing about putting these around is
we could just distribute them along a line
if we had a corridor or a range of windows,
but creating this sort of sausage of point lights
would be a little bit redundant,
both setup-wise and also overdraw-wise.
So simple trick, we actually just let you scale it
non-uniformly by using the scaling matrix
that we have already been granted so far.
And yeah, it just fits rooms much better.
Second of all, and a little more interesting,
is our AO decals.
So we cannot just render any shader we want here.
We can actually render whatever blend mode we want as well.
So rather than using additive lights,
we actually have multiplicative lights, if you will,
to draw other types of things.
And the reason we're doing ambient occlusion with decals
instead of screen spaces is because we would like
local control, we want to know which objects
are casting these things, and we want to control
our intensity, and we don't want any screen space
artifacts, like things being off, out of bounds,
or occluded by something, so it doesn't cast well.
So we end up with these.
And we have three types, and let's dive in a little bit.
The first one is the point.
So points is something we use mostly,
or typically for characters,
to ground them to the ground,
and themselves, and each other.
And in this particular screenshot,
I think there are about 100 of them or so,
because we actually put one on each limb,
or each bone of the character,
and just stretch them to fit as well as possible,
and it gives these results.
and the implementation is really, really simple.
If you have a bounce light, you know,
a half-lambert point light,
and you just make a move, it's applicative,
you're actually there.
So, in this case, we don't expose a wrap-around parameter.
We just, you know, made a half Lambert,
and we have a fixed falloff.
We really want the control to be simple.
We're placing hundreds of these,
so we don't really want to have
too many sliders to worry about.
It's a really effective way of
getting ambient occlusion on our characters for cheap Cs.
Second of all, we have a sphere.
So very similar to the point,
except with a little bit more added to it.
So we use this for larger occluders
like this here Submarino.
And the difference is we want harder contact shadows
as the light, or as the submarine gets close to the ground.
So you can really see that contact happening there.
If you have a regular Lambert point,
the code will look something like this.
It's gonna end with a little dot product.
And with this you just get the angle between the point and the surface and that's not really what we're interested in.
What we're interested in is getting the solid angle
between these things, the coverage,
that the sphere has on our hemisphere
in sort of a cone-based coverage fashion.
And the way we do that is,
if we have this normalization term
that we would apply to our local position
to make it a direction,
we just take that version
and turn it into this version, actually.
And that.
actually gives us what we need to achieve this result.
Assuming that we don't have any intersecting geometry,
assuming that that sub-brain doesn't clip
through the world, and we do assume
that that's not happening.
And finally, boxes.
So we have a few boxes around the game
that we drag around for puzzles and such.
And we needed a specific implementation for these guys.
So implementation for boxes, quite empirical,
and it looks like this.
It starts off with an unsigned distance function,
and we then get the angle around that distance
to get the sides.
But the unsigned distance actually gives us
too hard of an angle,
like there's a real hard cut there at the midpoint.
So what we instead do is get the square distance instead,
which is still unsigned,
but it has the first gradient just smoothed right out.
giving a much better result.
And if you want to see what one of those sides looks like,
it's up there on the top.
Kind of looks like an area light caster.
And composing all six sides together
gives us the result below.
And this is not physically correct in any way.
It's empirically based by all means.
It just kind of looks like a box occlusion, you know?
Finally, shadow decals. This is actually the simplest of all these light types.
They don't have any light function really, they're just a projected texture that we project into the world.
Here, they're obviously not there, but if we wanted to ground that, it would look like this.
So the good thing about these is we can actually get some grounding on scenes that have no
shadow casting lights and just have ambient lighting and still get our objects look not
floaty.
They can be any shape or form and they can be super soft without any sampling artifacts
and we like to place a lot of them around.
And sometimes, because of their non-staticness,
they get used in somewhat creative ways.
Again, so for putting on boxes together with a boxeo,
or for anchoring to the feet of the buoy
to cast shadows off of a torch
so we don't have to do point light shadows.
Or to go off of a big platform,
of a big shield that fades in and out nicely
when it moves up and down.
Now, like I said, we do a lot of these,
so we also want to get away with them pretty cheaply.
The standard implementation for doing these
would be something like you get a view array
in your vertex program,
and then in the fragment program,
multiply that by your depth,
and then transform it using a matrix.
But that's got a matrix in it, and I don't like it.
So luckily there's a solution to this one,
and it's real easy if you've done,
well, it's based on corner interpolation.
What you do to do that is in your vertex program,
you get your view array, rotate it into world space,
and the fragment program, multiply by depth
and add an offset.
So now we're down to an FMA or a MAD instruction
for our world space position.
That's real nice.
But we want a decal space position,
so that would still require a matrix.
That doesn't solve our problem.
But you can probably guess where this is going.
So we have a view array,
and then we rotate it into object space.
which also includes scale, and then we multiply that by the depth and add an offset.
And now we're down to an FMA or MAD instruction, which is pretty nice.
Another thing we do with decals is screen space reflections.
So we have screen space reflections in the game, and they're not a post effect.
We place them down locally just because we only need them in certain places,
no reason to make the whole world chromy.
And we like them because they have quite a simple setup.
We don't need to tag objects that we need to reflect.
We don't need to render a separate off-screen camera.
We don't need to bake any cube maps.
So for that reason, we like them.
What you see is what's reflected.
That's a nice advantage.
And set up wise, that's black.
Well, we just have a color and a backup color
in case our array misses something,
we have a color that gets displayed in that case,
which sort of represents some fog in some cases.
And a texture, Fresnel power,
that's pretty much it, four parameters.
But, like I said, what you see is what's reflected,
which means that the disadvantage is obviously
what you don't see is not reflected.
And in this case, at the screen edges,
we fade out because we're not sure
whether or not we're gonna get that information.
on our screen, so just to be sure we fade out.
And it looks horrible when the puddle gets
to the edge of the screen.
This is, of course, happening because we're not sure
whether or not the ray might go in that direction.
And if it does, we do need to fade
to avoid repeating or clamping or whatever
our screen texture might be set to.
Luckily, this is a side-scrolling game and the camera is pretty much pointing in towards the world at most times
So we can just force our rays to always point up and inward
and have no divergence on the x-axis which eliminates the need for
fading on the x-axis altogether and
It's a hack. It works
The other big problem of what you cannot see is not reflected is occluders.
And the worst occluder of all is this guy.
As soon as you figure out that you can make little ghosts in haystacks by jumping around
in the puddle, you're probably going to do that.
for no other reason than to piss me off.
And the way we want to solve this,
just for him, we don't want to solve every occluder,
but we can figure out a solution for this guy,
because you can control him.
So if we just stop him there,
well, the way we stop this is
we first find a bounding box in screen space where he is,
And we determine that a ray is behind the buoy if it's within that bounding box and behind the depth buffer.
This is a pretty safe case for ray is behind buoy.
And if a ray gets into this case, all we do is tell the rays to please go to the nearest exit of this bounding box and keep on tracing.
And since it's a very low detail game, we actually get away with that.
All right, so because of my hatred for matrices
in the pixel shader, let's just talk about this again.
This time not with decal projection,
but with ray projection.
So in this case we want to take a view space ray
and make it a screen space ray,
or put it into frustum space.
The simple way to do this would be to take your
your view space direction, your view space position,
and put it through a matrix,
and subtract another position, and you're there.
But it's got that matrix in it.
So we cheat a little bit,
and on the CPU we generate a,
sort of the size of the bounding box of your screen.
And then in the pixel shader, we can get away with something like this instead.
And it actually handles an edge case that the other one doesn't, which is rays going behind the near plane.
We don't have issues with that in this case.
We don't like banding in our undersampled stochastic effects
so obviously we add random numbers to this one as well.
The first step just gets multiplied by a random number
and that takes care of our stair-stepping artifacts
that you see on the left.
Of course, we don't use white noise or Bayer matrices.
We use blue noise and temporality is really cool.
and finally
there is the problem of wall thickness.
So we can't really tell whether or not
we're inside something.
We all just have a shell that's our depth buffer
for colliding against with our rays.
So we need to have some sort of analog
for determining whether or not
we're colliding with something.
We started with just a number
that you would set up per decal,
but that's too much setup
and it's not accurate enough anyway.
The second iteration was we took the delta
that a ray travels in z and used that as our
wall thickness.
Like if between the last step and the current
we have moved behind a piece of wall
that's as thick as that size.
we're pretty happy with it.
But it's got an edge case where if you hit a wall
that's 45 degrees to your view,
you're gonna be traveling in x and y space only,
and you have no delta, and every wall is paper thin.
That's no good.
If I unwrap that little expression there,
it looks something like this.
And the center is actually just the reflection ray itself.
So if we take that out of the equation,
And just get our, by the way underscore project is the thing that we generated on the CPU earlier,
a couple slides ago. Divide that by the depth. Now we have one that's independent from the rays direction
and we are pretty sure at this point that we're going to hit something. At least if it was visible.
That's real nice.
Another thing that uses reflections are, of course, water.
We have a bunch of water that you can swim in.
And we render it out in three layers
because that's how we think about water.
We think about it as being a layer of dirt or murk or fog
that's inside the water medium.
It's dirty.
and a refraction and a reflection, of course.
And it's actually pretty nice to render them out
as these layers of abstraction that we have,
as the actual render layers.
So we start with a fog, that's our first one.
Then we render any transparencies that we've tagged
as being under the water.
And we render these now because we want to refract those
when we take a snapshot of the screen to distort it.
And now we refract it.
And finally, we add the reflection on top of this.
This is not a screen space reflection.
This is a camera based, like an off screen camera
using an oblique clipping plane reflection
because there's just way too much that can go wrong in water.
And the case for when the camera is underwater is similar,
but shuffled around a little bit,
because the order of which you see things
has now been changed.
So the first thing we render now is reflection,
then fog, then refraction,
and then the transparencies to keep them crisp.
Now for each of these layers, we actually render out
three pieces of geometry.
And the first one is an edge that's from the near plane
of the camera and six to 12 meters into the scene.
This is to avoid pancake water
when the camera passes through.
It's just a tessellated mesh that's stuck right at your nose and follows you around
wherever you go and creates just a little bit of depth to the water.
Next up, we rendered the outside of a box,
because this water is a box volume.
And by the outside of a box,
I mean the front faces of a box.
So something like this.
We're not rendering on top of the displacement edge
we've already rendered,
and the way we avoid that is just by using
a single stencil bit for rejecting any layers
that come after the ones we've already rendered.
And then we render the inside faces of that same box.
So the back faces, which look like this.
And again, we're not rendering on top of anything
because of that stencil bit that we've been using so far.
And yeah, we just get something that looks like
a full volume, but in reality was three passes.
Now, for some visual effects.
Gonna start out with smoke particles.
All right, so that uses a few effects.
Now let's try to break them down.
Get some motion and some light in there.
Even though I've frozen it, you might be able to see
that the particles are still moving a little bit.
We have some sub-particle motion,
just to try and make it non-obvious
where one particle starts and another,
where one particle ends and another starts.
And we got some lighting coming from the floor.
and a gradient just to ground it a little bit.
If I remove all the effects, it looks like this.
If I add back in the light from the floor,
which is the most obvious of the effects,
it looks like this.
Now, I wanna have each particle be lighter
at the top than at the bottom.
I don't have any diffuse detail in any of these sprites
because I want them to blend well together.
So if we add that gradient, it's very subtle,
it looks like this.
And finally, make them wobble.
and we wobble them around with a texture that looks like this.
It's basically just a UV gradient in Photoshop
with a twirl effect applied to it,
and then paste that around as a stamp a few times.
It makes it kind of look like wind swirls, essentially.
And then we take that texture,
map it in world space to the particles,
and scroll them downwards in this case.
And we chose downwards for this example because, well,
The smoke is kind of getting shot up from above and down below, so that works for this one.
So next up, some fire.
Turn up!
Thanks!
So yeah, I'm just throwing around the box,
showing how it looks in a dynamic setting.
Yeah, so it's using some of the techniques from the smoke.
It's using UV distortion again,
but the most important here is the colors, actually.
Because we don't want to have any bright blues or any bright purples.
We don't want to have any dark whites especially.
By any means we want to have a consistent luminance to color ratio.
So the way we do that is by rendering fire into a fire buffer of sorts.
So this is just the alpha channel
of what we're rendering to actually,
which is now the deferred fire buffer for this scene.
We just render each sprite in here to accumulate additively
and then we apply a lookup table to it.
And now we'll be sure that any value of luminance
of the fire becomes a specific color
and never gets the wrong color of fire at any given point.
any given sprite it might look like this.
Other than UV distortion, we're also using flipbooks here
because we need more motion than we did with the smoke.
So for most of these sprites,
we have three by three different textures we can go with.
We started with just selecting them sequentially,
one through nine, but that takes about a second,
which means the animation will repeat once a second,
and that becomes real jarring to look at.
The second thing we tried was just pick a random one,
but there's a really high chance
that you'll pick the same one twice in a row,
actually higher than 10%, so that would happen.
once in every 10 seconds, and it will look like lag,
and it's awful.
What we chose to do was both,
so we go sequentially on the x-axis
and randomly on the y-axis.
So we just choose, just go through columns A, B, C,
and then a random row, one through three,
at any given frame.
So we don't get any lag,
and repetition becomes more unlikely.
Now between these different things we of course don't just snap between layers, we fade between
them.
No, we fade on a vertical gradient in the direction of the fire.
No, we don't do that either.
We do it with noise and a gradient just because we might as well and it just ends up looking
more fiery in the end.
Now some lens flares.
So lens flares are just points that you put up around
in the scenes for us that are not the post effect,
but just I want to have this flashlight
be super duper bright.
So you put a lens flare in there.
And of course we need it to be occluded by things
so it's not set over there.
It doesn't depth test or anything like that.
And for fading it out, we didn't want to collide
against the scene's geometry colliders
because we don't want to,
the character's not gonna bump into any of these trees,
so why would we set up colliders for them?
A lot of setup and expensive.
So instead, for each of the vertices,
we sampled the depth buffer in the vertex shader
a bunch of times on a Poisson disk.
We only have four vertices,
so doing 30 samples per vertex
is very little to get away with.
Of course, we don't sample from the corners,
we sample from the center instead, from the pivots.
but just to get a little bit of a gradient going on,
because it's free, we sample somewhere in between
to get a horizontal gradient going across them
as they pass behind and get disincluded.
And now, some water effects.
All right, so this column here of foam
is using the exact same techniques and shader
as the smoke before, it's basically
our particle uber shader.
Just to demonstrate quickly here,
if I remove the motion, it looks like this.
And if I kick back the motion and remove the lighting,
which is just making it lighter at the top
and darker at the bottom, it looks like this, super flat.
So over here, the most important thing to look at is this spotlight here.
If the boy swims into it, he gonna die, so we want to emphasis that as much as possible.
We have three main effects to remind you of this spotlight.
And the first one is some rain.
So the rain, we've gone through three different versions.
One that was just generating lots and lots of particles,
but once you get to about 10,000 raindrops,
it's pretty heavy.
And then we tried some scrolling billboards,
but the overdraw was also terrific.
So we ended up actually using a mesh
that we put in there with a vertex C shader.
So the wireframe of that rain looks like this,
and the animation is literally just
for every whole number of time,
we reposition the particle at some place
or reposition the sprite somewhere else,
and for the fractional part of time,
we either scale it up or fade it out
or scroll it down depending on which particle it is.
Next up, we got some volume lights.
Above here, it's not using any textures,
but look at below.
And finally, we have some specular light
on the water surface.
Real simple, just to reflect that off.
And down below, we use a similar but different effect
than the rain for dust particles.
So same thing here, we just have like,
I don't know, a thousand of these little dots there
that just float around and fade out
and move somewhere else and fade in
and then move somewhere else and fade out again.
And down here, the...
Down here the volume light uses an animated texture
to simulate caustics or simulate being
messed up by the water waves.
And it's of course, each of these
volume lights are sorted differently.
The one that's above the water is being refracted
and the one that's below is not,
and the other way around when you're up there.
And finally, the specular reflection has now turned
into a specular refraction, which just makes it
super bright from the point of, you know, casting.
Now as we swim up, the buoy also generates
some wave particles that we use to distort the surface.
The shading of them is just resampling the refraction
and the reflection again,
but with a different normal this time.
And the normals we generate come from
the shape of these particles.
So each particle is just a ring,
and we use the local particle position of these rings
as the normals, just normalizing them,
and then we multiply that by a sine
that goes from zero to two pi
from the center to the outer rim of it,
which would mean that the inside of the wave
becomes negative and the outside becomes positive,
and zero in between.
now a different shape of water
so this is not a square, this is not a crate shaped piece of water, this is a cylindrical water
it's quite high poly because we want to have
some very specific texture coordinates here.
We're not just putting the texture down flat,
we're actually mapping it radially around the water,
like so.
And then we're scrolling it on the y-axis.
And the reason we're doing this is we
don't want to fade out expanding foam textures,
because that would be more obvious.
Yeah, we're doing this scrolling instead
to have a really consistent motion.
And the texture looks something like this.
We needed something that tiles, but in not such an obvious way.
So the inspiration we got here was from European fan.
cobblestone looks something like this. They tile perfectly well but in a more
non-obvious way and they just happen to look like waves. So if you kind of draw
some lines on top of that and then put some waves under those lines and remove
the lines you kind of get some tiling waves. That's great. And finally
So this is using pretty much the effects that we've talked about up until now.
Water, particles, lighting and screen space reflections, and superfoam textures.
The first one, and most important, is the water volume itself.
which without any other effects looks like this.
It's got the same scrolling,
cobblestone foam texture on top of it.
And of course it animates this time,
but otherwise it's using our standard water shading code.
The way we animate it is using just three blend shapes,
one from before the crash,
and one when it's crashing,
and then one when it's finishing.
And below that of course is a puddle.
And the puddle looks like this.
You can see the foam stretching a lot in the beginning
and then becoming more and more easy as it goes out.
And also we're using screen-based reflections on that.
And the way we're getting that stretching done
is very simple.
We wanna make it look like it's really pushing
the foam out in the beginning
and then easing out as it gets to the end.
And the simple way to do this was just
add power to the Y
Y gradient of this of this UV map and then take it from the power of four or eight or something and then down to just linear
when the effect is done
and finally a most apparent are is this foam carpet of
Particles on top which is using the same particles smoke foam shader that we've been using so far
Gets this from the light from behind
And to blend in the decal on the ground and the wave itself,
we've got these impacts here.
And just to make the effect a little bit more powerful
in the beginning, we've got these foam sprays
coming out the sides in the beginning,
that quickly fade off.
So in conclusion, and the rules to live your life by,
we really like blue noise, and so should you.
We like temporal anti-aliasing,
it really gives a stable image
and makes all kinds of nice effects possible.
That's it.
and you should data all your things and you should do it with a triangular pdf if you can afford it
and your lights if you're if at all possible should have custom light functions and get
your tech artists to do some it's really cool and we like screen space reflections and we
don't like screen space and manipulation and
Thanks to all these wonderful people who helped
make this talk possible.
And thanks to the Unity team,
and thanks to Double11 for supporting our stuffs,
and thanks to the Twitterverse for improving our slides.
And thanks to you guys for listening.
And we're hiring.
Also, we're taking questions, you can go up to the mics.
If you have some.
We can also, sorry, if you'd rather like that.
Yeah, if you don't have questions,
yeah, you can just come ask us afterwards
the questions that you don't have.
All right.
Cool, thanks for coming.