So, my name is Dave Weinstein, with me is Angela Gunn.
And we're going to talk about what to do in the event of a security issue.
Now, my background is in development and security, including services at scale,
and I'll be talking to you about operational roles and planning.
Angela's background is in journalism and communications,
and she'll be talking to you about crisis communications,
which are not quite the same thing as marketing, PR, or community management,
but overlap all of them.
All right.
Bluntly, this is a talk about operational and communications
planning and emergency response.
This is not a technical talk, and we're not
going to talk to you about how to do security right.
We are, in fact, just assuming that you
are doing security right.
Please be doing security right.
So our intent in this talk is to give you
tools you can put into action.
You should be able to apply these techniques immediately
and with the resources you already have on your team.
I'm going to talk about logical roles in this.
In many cases, especially for small shops,
people will wear multiple hats.
We're going to talk about planning and training,
including how to build playbooks for incident response,
and how to use those even before an incident occurs
to help identify critical paths and resource issues.
Angela will talk to you about the security community, which
you're probably not in touch with,
and crisis communications and outreach.
Now, there is an important thing.
I am not your lawyer.
In fact, if you want to get right down to it, I'm not actually a lawyer.
And if you really want to get technical, I don't have a degree.
So Angela has a degree, that's the good news.
The bad news is it's in philosophy, so totally do not get Socrates as your defense attorney.
And neither one of us stayed at Holiday Inn Express last night, so you are totally 0 for 4.
Now, unless you happen to have a lawyer turned game developer on your team, the odds are
very good you don't have an in-house counsel.
And that's fine. Whenever I talk about legal roles in the scope of this, what I'm really
talking about is a person who's wearing that as an additional hat.
This is someone on the team who's familiar with your contractual and other legal obligations.
These may be the terms you have with a credit card company about protecting card information in PII.
It may be a relationship you have with your sales channel and distribution channel,
or with an IP holder whose work you've licensed.
And in the case of things like the Children, Online, Privacy, and Protection Act,
actual legal requirements imposed by the government by statute.
That being said, when you're working on playbooks that involve legal issues,
you probably do want to consult with an actual attorney brand attorney.
What we're gonna do is we're gonna take a look at the operational roles that the
model uses.
Many people will fall into more than one logical role, especially in smaller
companies,
and that's expected.
One of the things that happens in any small company is people wear multiple hats.
You usually find that out when they go somewhere else and you discover
that you actually needed two or three people to do the work they were doing.
To make this work, we're going to go over a set of terms and roles and other things
that will help frame the discussion.
The first one is the notion of a DRI or directly responsible individual.
And the DRI model is a little different than what you're used to.
On most teams, either the producer or the lead programmer will make a decision about
whether or not an update goes live, whether something makes it into the build, whether
the build is safe to prop to beta.
All these decisions in a DRI model are made by the DRI.
This person calls the shot usually a week at a time.
So if you are the DRI, you are the one wearing the beeper, you are the one on call if something goes wrong at 4 in the morning,
and you are the one who says, wow, this is really, really buggy, I don't think we want to push it to beta or even to internal testing or friendly testers.
The DRI does not need to be a programmer.
Any member of the team should be able to fulfill this role.
After all, we're historically used to having producers
fulfill a lot of this role, and most of them
are not programmers.
And the ones that were programmers
haven't been programmers, as a general rule,
for long enough that their skills are rusted out anyway
as far as that goes.
You don't need to be technical for this role.
It's a matter of training and responsibility.
And that's something that we're going to talk about throughout this discussion
is that it's really important if you're going to put people in a position to make
decisions that have real impact to train them and not just put them out there to
fail.
The DRI does not make decisions in a vacuum.
Decisions about the status of bills are going to be taken after discussion with
the leads.
The DRI is responsible for the decisions they make but you need to support them.
Don't hang your people out to dry.
and you want the DRI role to rotate.
It's stressful and you need anyone to be able to act in that role as needed.
Otherwise, you can't take a vacation, go to a wedding, get married,
have any kind of a life if you are always the person who has to be there.
And again, we're going to see that more when we look at critical paths.
Finally, you probably want to have an internal only email
address that's just DRI that can be reached
by anyone on your team.
And then you don't have to worry about who is DRI this week.
If something comes up, you send it
to DRI at your domain any time.
Now, we're going to talk a lot about communications
in this role, internally and externally, or more
specifically, Angela is going to talk a lot about this role.
Now, assuming you're large enough to actually have a comms team,
what this means is your technical staff don't actually have to learn to speak to
the outside world if they don't want to.
Some of them will. Generally speaking, because of the demographics of the industry,
most of them are introverted and really don't want to talk to other human beings
if they can possibly help it.
Now for smaller teams and certainly for single-person shops this doesn't apply.
You'll be wearing this hat among many others.
But the whole idea is again, we're trying to give people responsibilities that they are comfortable with and trained for.
And so you'll find people who are like,
I'm perfectly fine with making decisions about whether or not the build goes out,
but I don't want to be the one to talk to the player base and tell them there's no update this week.
And you'll have other people who don't want to make the decision but are fine putting
things into terms that the players or the press or anyone else can understand.
And in fact, comms, in addition to keeping the DRI in the loop of anything they find,
comms will often be the transition point between multiple DRIs if it's rolling off at the end
of the week saying, hey, this is what we were working on last week, just so you know.
In a smaller shop, you'll probably know anyway.
General staff.
This is everybody else.
Now, there's an old folk expression, you have two ears and one mouth for a reason.
I've not personally done well with that advice, but it's there.
The key point is that you want to have a way for your team members to be ears for the company,
and you don't want to have them speaking for the company accidentally.
If you're speaking as a representative of the company, it should be something planned
and deliberate.
Now, there are a couple ways to do this. The biggest one is to have an internal only email address, essentially fire.
Or, fire's a good one. Basically, something has gone wrong.
And this something doesn't have to be technical. It can be, hey, there's a report of a bug on the internet, are we vulnerable?
It can be, hey, someone is pirating our game.
It can be, hey, someone got upset about a design decision we made and Reddit is exploding.
It's just a way for people on your team who happen to be out looking at something on Twitter
or Reddit or anywhere else to go, oh, they're talking about us.
I don't know what to do.
They email to FHIR.
FHIR goes usually to the DRI and comms and whoever else is responsible for monitoring
things at the moment.
Now, as a practical standpoint, unless you have really strong reason to believe that
someone is deliberately pranking your internal FHIR account...
There can be no penalties for a false alarm.
What you want here is for your people
to have a way to let whoever has to be the adult this week
to know about it.
And if you penalize them for not doing
the research ahead of time, well, they're
not going to tell you what you need to know,
and you don't want to drown out that signal.
As always, you want to support your people with training.
If they're going to be speaking for communications
or another role for the company.
If you're a small company, you may actually have no general staff who aren't leadership,
in which case, support yourselves.
You should be good to yourselves.
Which brings us to leadership.
Now, Angela's going to talk about how this can go wrong in more detail when we talk about
crisis communications, but seriously, the biggest thing for leadership to do is do no
harm.
Even off-the-cuff comments by someone who is perceived as having a strong identity as a founder or leader of the company
can do damage that your communications and community management people cannot overcome.
If the head of the company says something that drives people away, or offends them, or otherwise causes problems,
No one is going to believe that the community manager saying,
oh no, that was a problem, has any authority whatsoever.
They're clearly there as a puppet saying whatever
they were supposed to say to make everybody happy.
If you are in a leadership role strongly identified
with the company, what you say has disproportionate weight.
On the flip side, you can use this power to back up your people.
If you've got someone saying, wow, yeah, we know we promised you a patch this week,
but it turned out it was a really difficult problem and it's going to be next month.
well that's not good news you want to be giving out but someone's giving it out
you're probably gonna catch a lot of grief from your customer base of people
calling them everything but you know
a sweet child of God and
that's okay but now you can come in as a leader with your established authority
and the weight of your reputation and say no this is a really good person they
were doing the right thing we just misjudged we're sorry
and you can lend that credibility there it's good to be able to have that but
it's more important to just not make things worse
And we've talked enough about training, we should probably talk in more detail about training.
So I love playbooks. Flat out, they're wonderful.
One of the nice things about playbooks is that they are a fail-soft solution.
Having one playbook is always better than having none, two is better than one, and so on.
This means you don't need to solve the problem right away.
You can order in pizza, have a staff party occasionally at the end of the week,
and say, hey, let's brainstorm a problem and then do a playbook for it.
Playbooks need to be focused and short.
If they're complex, they won't get used.
The end result of a playbook is either an action
or a pointer to another playbook.
Now, the other thing you'll find
is if you're making playbooks,
they're gonna shape both how you manage your infrastructure
and build your software,
and they'll have real ramifications
when you realize what your critical paths are.
And we're gonna see that as we walk through one right now.
And yes, if you've ever done customer support,
a playbook looks an awful lot
like a customer support flowchart.
All right.
The example I'm going to use is Heartbleed.
And the reason I'm using Heartbleed as an example
is because the developers didn't actually do anything wrong.
They used cryptography.
They used it appropriately.
They did not invent their own.
They did not even implement their own.
They used the industry standard library for their platform.
Everything we tell people to do from a security perspective.
But because of a vulnerability in the platform,
They were absolutely flat-out vulnerable,
and the fix was horrific because the keys were compromised,
or potentially compromised.
And so we're going to use that as an example,
because the whole point of this is your ability
to protect yourself from being compromised
is pretty much gone.
You can make it harder, but something like Heartbleed,
there was nothing you could do as a developer.
Unless you are a cryptographer who was auditing Heartbleed,
or auditing OpenSSL and found it,
you didn't really have an option.
And so the whole purpose of this talk is to plan for what happens afterwards.
And that's why I said it was not a security talk or a technical talk per se.
So let's walk down the tree.
There are reports of a critical vulnerability in a library or component.
And the first question is, do we use it?
And you'll note that don't know is defaulting to we're vulnerable.
We'll talk about this again when we talk about planning and assets, but this not only puts
us in a safer security posture overall, it also acts as negative feedback against skimping
on your upfront analysis because suddenly you have more work.
Because if we know that we don't use that, you log it as not affected and you're done.
You can go back to sleep, it's four in the morning on a Saturday and you're over.
Problem solved.
Well, if we use it or we don't know, we go to page two.
Now, this may come as a surprise coming from a security specialist, but not everything
is drop everything now.
If the attack is not being exploited in the wild, it can wait until the start of the next
business day.
However, there should be a monitored situation.
If it does start being exploited, this decision point should also be revisited.
And again, you have to look at the ramifications.
For those familiar with the recent Drupalageddon bug,
Drupal has said, basically, if you did not
patch your site within seven hours of the update being
available, they considered almost certain
that your site was compromised.
Because seven hours later, they were
seeing automated attacks hitting servers they manage.
Now, obviously, as we said earlier, most studios do not have in-house lawyers or legal staff,
so the legal role is likely to be someone who is informed as to the studio's contractual
legal obligations and is authorized to call a real lawyer if the case requires it.
So it's not being exploited in the wild.
We're going to schedule a meeting with our DRI, our QA, our legal, engineering, and comms
for the start of the next business day.
Otherwise, well, we go straight to the meeting.
And this is all hands on deck.
First of all, we need to produce tests that verify the vulnerability.
And the reason for this is, first you want to make sure you have it,
and second of all, you want to make sure you fixed it.
So, right now, verify that you've got it.
While that's going on, engineering ops and QA need to start preparing the fix and prepare for deployment.
And at the same time, ops, comms, and legal are busy working on the scope of damage,
communications, business partners, and any other remediation.
You'll note this playbook does not have replace all of our website certificates
and we probably didn't have a what to do when our SSL for our site is now completely compromised
but in the wake of Heartbleed, we probably want to sit down and write another playbook for that
and we do that as a separate callout.
We check for remediation specific playbooks, specific remediation playbooks.
Now, there's something you may have noticed here.
We've got QA and engineering in two, ops in two,
and comms and legal in one.
And if you only have one person in each of those roles,
you have a problem.
It may not be a problem you can get away with,
or that you can avoid because you're a very small shop.
But you want to look at what your critical path looks
like when things go pear-shaped.
And the critical path says I need these people.
And if I only have one of them and they
need to be doing two things at once, that's a problem.
And that may indicate cross-training,
or it may indicate a hiring need.
Now, we'll cover it a little bit more when we talk about critical paths,
but there's an anti-pattern that crops up in development very often,
and I just call it Build Boy.
No one wants to be stuck doing the build,
so whoever does it first tends to get stuck with it.
Now, that's problematic in the best cases,
but having your critical path for all updates go through one person
is an absolute disaster waiting to happen.
So, how long does a build test cycle take?
If it takes 96 hours for you to do a build and complete regress, that's the minimum amount
of time, even if the patch were available, before you could have everything out.
How automated is your build test cycle?
Does someone have to keep puttering at it or you can simply put something up there and
fire it up and let automated tests start running?
And who is available to build and deploy?
Now, deployment of updates is not necessarily something you control.
Some sales channels give you the opportunity to update whenever you feel like.
If you want to update twice a day and three times on Sunday, that's fine with them.
Others, you have a real approval process.
The time to find out if there's a way to expedite that is not when your house is on fire.
So, during your planning, reach out to your sales partners and figure out,
is there a way, if things were really bad, that we could get an expedited review
so we could get this up there?
If things are catastrophically bad, there's a vulnerability in the software that's letting you compromise backend servers,
you may need to shut things down. Can you do that?
If you had to, in an emergency, what are the ramifications?
Can you just shut down multiplayer, or would you have to shut down the whole thing?
All of this is planning for deployment that you should do as part of making your playbooks,
and also just ahead of time, know what your requirements and capabilities are.
If you show up that you have a problem, that we can't get an update deployed fast enough, well...
That has to go back and close the loop and inform your playbooks because now we have
more of a lead time before we can fix something.
As we saw in the playbook example, we need to know what we use and what we protect when
building our playbooks.
One thing to recall is that some of the incidents that would trigger a playbook will also involve some of our assets being unavailable.
Having the playbook or asset lists on a wiki is nice, but if the incident is internal network failure or VPN failure, that wiki is suddenly a lot less useful.
You probably actually do want to have hard copies of your asset lists in your playbooks and at least have the DRI have them.
Now, another thing, we're talking about what customer data do we have?
Disk space is cheap, liability is not.
When you're looking at things like customer data, ask yourself what is the business case
for having it?
Because if you don't have it, they can't steal it.
Just because you think you might need something someday does not make keeping it now a good
idea.
For example...
It may be that we don't want to take the credit cards ourselves, we want to use a third-party
payment, whether that's Apple or Google or Microsoft or Pay by Cash or any one of a number
of other places, PayPal.
Now all of those places will take a cut.
They're going to step in and they're going to take a cut.
What you're basically doing is buying yourself a hedge against liability.
But here's the thing.
If I don't need their credit card number, then I may not need their real name and physical
address.
If I don't need it...
don't keep it. Again, if you look at the data breaches,
what are people worried about losing? Credit cards, addresses, email addresses.
Depending on the
platform you're on, you may not even need the real email address. Again,
unless you have a business case to hold on to something, when you're doing your
planning, try and get rid of as many consumer assets as you possibly can.
because that's your liability. If our database doesn't have anything that the consumer would
be hurt if it got out, it doesn't have their email, it doesn't have their address, it doesn't
have their credit card, then even if someone pops the back-end database, I don't need to
say anything about it, I don't need to go into a comms emergency because we didn't lose
anything that anybody else cares about. Great. They got our source code, they got our assets,
whatever. That's our loss, it's not your loss as a customer, and therefore I don't need
to tell you.
And as I said earlier, one of the things that comes out of this is we're trying to find out what roles need to be filled,
and we may discover that there are going to be some categories of problems that only have one person who can act.
Now sometimes this is unavoidable.
Either the studio is small enough that this is inevitable,
or the role requires someone to speak formally
on behalf of the company, which is by definition
a limited number of people, but often it indicates
a dangerous critical path.
If only one person can release a new build,
you're in a precarious situation.
Vacations, illness, bus, offer letter.
This is a problem.
This will inform your need to cross-train and hire.
And that's good.
For one thing, it's really easy to say, look,
we're going to make everybody learn how to do the build so
that everyone can go on vacation.
You don't necessarily have to say,
so that if anyone leaves, we don't discover we have
no ability to ever update again.
And when we get down to the rest of the roles,
we're talking about communications.
And so I'll turn things over to Angela.
Thanks, Dave.
Again, my name's Angela, and I'm here
to talk about a role that lies outside the comfort
zone of most tech folk, and that's communications.
Because comms has some unique dealings
with not just developers, but with legal
and the outside world, and because comms functions,
as Dave mentioned, as the handoff entity between DRIs,
there are some things we need to talk about separately.
So here I am.
Most of us are pretty good communicators under normal circumstances, thanks to e-book and Facebook and Tumblr and text and the Twitters and the phones and having conversations now and then with normal human beings, which is nice.
But in a crisis, communications become something that benefits from a lot of structure and as much planning and expertise as possible.
I assume most of you would rather be working on the technical problem.
as opposed to explaining it to the least technical,
most hostile user who can manage to personally reach you,
probably at three in the morning at home, am I right?
Believe it or not, some folks do actually specialize
in handling communications in crisis situations,
and my half of the talk explains what those folks
need to function and what you will need to do
if there's no one around to do that job.
Before we start, does anybody here watch Scandal?
Familiar with Scandal?
No. Oh, that's so good. We're going to live in the real world and not be TV crisis comms people.
They dress so much better than me.
Okay. The job of the crisis communications person is to tell your story in difficult situations.
One of the leading crisis comms practitioners describes his job as making terrible news just bad, and bad news good.
So let's look at this slide.
Questions and answers, that should be clear enough, right?
Give your comps people the facts.
Trust them to tell your story.
and give them the facts. This is really important. We have current events to talk about in this one.
Crisis comms folk do not have the privileged communication status that you would have with, say, legal counsel,
but they still need to be operating with as much of the truth as they possibly can.
Anybody following the John Gomeshi scandal up in Canada right now?
a fellow who, a broadcaster for CBC before that.
He ran a band called Moxie Fruvist.
Anyway, he's in some personal trouble right now.
And the guy was not forthright to his exceedingly expensive
crisis comms team.
And went out on Facebook with a long thing
about how he didn't do what he's accused of doing, and no, no,
it didn't happen, and it didn't happen the way they said.
And because he's a really articulate, charming guy.
It sounded good and they were winning and then more effects came out and they were losing
and then the crisis comps team fired their client.
Here's a word of advice. If your crisis comps team, the people who specialize in trouble,
don't want your brand of trouble, you have a very interesting brand of trouble.
Outreach and response. Outreach is to use a terrible word, proactive.
Response is reacting to questions and statements made by others.
Comms faces outward to the public, inward to the company.
Again, lawyers, execs, as well as devs.
And again, as Dave said, we can't always count on lawyers being in-house,
but they will be dealing with probably whoever you have to be liaison to real counsel and real counsel itself.
Now, to be honest, comms is a game.
There are objectives, there are success conditions,
and because this is a crisis, you have time pressures,
you have achievement pressures.
In the Gomeshi case, you can win the news cycle,
you can get your story out there,
and then you can lose the next news cycle,
or you can lose all the news cycles,
and the snowball keeps getting bigger.
Most importantly, there is a terrain map for this process,
and even if you're not familiar with it,
everyone else you will deal with in a crisis is.
The press especially has its way of doing things and the better you are at
understanding and countering how they operate and how social networks operate with your story and so forth,
the more effective your comms effort will be. You cannot beat the system that exists.
All you can do is convince it that you're winning.
I want to take two slides and run through the components you will need to build in a
crisis comps plan.
You will need these for both outreach and reactive.
This first slide covers the three must-have items.
After that, we're going to go through a few fancier additions.
I want to go back and disagree with something Dave said about playbooks.
In the case of comms, I'm a big fan of set it and forget it as much as you possibly can.
Build your playbook and don't touch it unless you really, unless there is an extraordinary circumstance.
Because if you have a flowchart memorized for that, if you have your playbook memorized, everything's going to flow.
Trust me, comms will have enough drama dealing with the specifics of the incident, including trying to understand it.
Your comms people are probably not technical.
Learn the components. Do not reinvent the wheel here.
Okay, talking points.
These are the basis of everything else you would develop.
They are sentences your spokespeople
and anyone else you engage with,
anybody on the company who might be speaking,
should be able to pretty much recite word for word.
I'm not joking about that.
They are your point.
A comms person on average spends more time and care
per word building talking points
than on any other of the many components you will see.
Each of these sentences conveys one point.
They are simple, unambiguous, precise.
They are short, 20 words apiece is too many,
which means all my slides fail my own metric there.
Your comms team should be doing everything in its power
to make sure that these statements get out perfectly,
are not misquoted.
I'm going to give you a test now.
What, do you think, would be the problem with a talking point that says,
there are reports that our foo game is causing eye blisters, but no proof exists that this is true.
What did I do wrong there? Anybody?
Oh, you're so quiet.
The problem is, I put words in a row that said,
our foo game is causing eye blisters.
That's awesome, and that's the quote the news picks up.
Present the facts. We are aware of reports that customers are experiencing issues with one of our popular games.
Really, really dry. But do you see how the gotcha quote people can't do anything with that?
If somebody's going to hang in with that, where do they start? You gave them no hook.
It's business writing. There's a place for memorable language in this process. The talking points ain't it.
The statement, on the other hand, is it.
The statement's interesting because it's the one thing that
sounds like humans are speaking.
It's also the first and often the only thing
you can send out intact to press or anybody asking you
questions.
It's a nice paragraph, but you can do two, whatever,
that you can mail to reporters, post it on your website,
put it on social media, anywhere you
need to make the statement.
Clear, accurate, quotable, serious, respectful, positive.
Your goal is to assure people that you are on the case and as much as you can to give them the information they need to settle the problem in their own mind.
As we, the Gnomeschi case we just discussed, the statement was beautiful, memorable, positive, and was not written with enough knowledge to get out in front of what the next news cycle would be.
So, and it was long, it was extremely long, but most importantly,
It lacked understanding of what was to come.
Wouldn't have said what was to come,
but would have been aware and started countering.
Think chess.
Some folks use the statement to bring in third party voices who
are independent that can support what you're saying,
either in a quote in the statement itself,
or more usually by getting permission
to include their names and contact information.
in mailings to the press, not social media but the press.
The right independent voice can make a big difference to a reporter who's just
sifting through a lot of opinions on the situation.
Yours is only one, even if it is your product. A tough part about doing this is
that someone's got to go line that guy up
and talk to them, figure out what they might say.
A good example of how this works well in the tech world is that there are certain companies that make a point of briefing analyst firms before a major release, especially with security bulletins.
They brief them, they figure out who's kind of on the same page as they are with what's going on, and they will suggest to the press that, oh, talk to this analyst, this analyst, and this analyst.
Now, when I was a reporter, I did not trust those because I knew how the sausage was made.
But you will find that especially in a crisis situation where things are moving quickly,
other reporters have different opinions on that. So, always good.
A FAQ, as we seem to be saying these days, some comps folk will call this a Q&A, but that kind of implies a linearity that doesn't exist.
This consists basically of pretty much every question a comps person can get with a well-crafted, full-sentence answer to a question.
all the questions possible.
I actually really like doing this component
when I have these little projects,
because it helps everybody see what the parameters are,
and sometimes raises issues that the DRI or legal or others
haven't really, you get a lot of,
really, somebody's going to ask that?
Yes, really, they are.
How long has your foo game been shipping?
Complete sentence response.
Will you be offering refunds for buyers of the foo game?
How could the foo game have shipped without review
from the Centers for Disease Control?
Whatever.
full sentence response.
Not necessarily an answer.
The goal is to sound informed about the progress
of the investigation and to give information
that has been internally vetted as accurate and safe
to discuss.
You never want to say, we don't know, or please, God,
no comment.
Don't do this.
The end of the FAQ is always, I'll
have to check on that and get back to you, and then do it.
As you have guessed from all that, not for publication.
You use the parts you need, and you keep the rest
under your hat.
Quickly on these, these are some specialized tools available.
If your team already does video, like if you put a lot of demos
up on YouTube, and you feel you have something that's
communicated well, I think Dave's design,
no, this is not exploded.
It's just different, is a good example of that.
That might be a way you can make your point very efficiently.
I'm not personally a fan of podcasts for this purpose,
but there are a few podcasters from the Nerdist on down
worth talking to.
For crisis purposes, you treat those guys as press.
An open letter.
If you have a big name on your leadership team, very big name
on leadership team, this is why you pay them money
to go out and be this guy.
the corollary to Dave's putting your leadership out there to add veracity to whatever you're saying.
The trick here is that a lot of times your confs folk are writing it.
You are sock puppeting your leadership team.
Your confs people write it.
The person whose name is going on it goes,
Yeah, that sounds like something I'd say, and you proceed.
It gives them more time to actually work the problem.
Tweets post-social.
More on that in a second, but the short thing here is
if you are already active on those, that's great.
If you are not, now is really, really not the time to start.
I threw a backgrounder on here.
I go back and forth on whether I should have.
This is a really bold tactic if you're in the
best defense is a good offense stance.
If you have someone on here, staff,
who is well-versed on a topic.
Let's take OpenSSL to use Dave's example on Heartbleed.
And if your company is not actively involved in the crisis,
you know, heart bleed, but you knew you weren't affected,
if you feel you have the bandwidth
to speak out and be experts,
you know what, that's marketing to me,
but some people feel that's a good time to act.
And let's move on.
Okay, staffing, personnel, access.
You know what you need.
Who does the work?
How does it get to the people that it needs to see?
First off, about this slide, these venue bullets, whatever,
are in ascending order of both the ease
with which comms can be done and the lack of control
you will have over the output once it's out there.
Most importantly, these are really, really fluid
these days.
The pressed read Twitter, a random email guy
can put your entire correspondence on blast
on Tumblr.
Things move around.
At every one of these levels of engagement,
it's important to, again, know your map, have your plan.
Email. We talked about having a DRI box. We talked about some public-facing emails. Everybody comfortable with the idea of having a public-facing email that sometimes says stuff to the outside world?
It's quiet out there.
Keep an eye on it. The email addresses Dave mentioned, such as fire, I think those are a wonderful idea. You don't make those public.
By that, you need to have something where people can tell you things.
Some companies use the secure at metric, or eBay and PayPal do spoof.
That's also a useful tool if you're set up to notify users of changes or whatnot through
that address.
Active or at least actively monitored presence on social media is important, and I think most of you probably do that to some extent.
How many of you have somebody on your staff who just kind of does it anyway?
They blog or they're posting to Tumblr or they're Facebooking or they're tweeting about work stuff on a regular basis.
This may have a massive intersection with your rock stars.
Anybody have that guy?
We're going to need to talk about that guy.
And the rest of you, pay attention, because you've probably got that guy and you don't know it.
Now there's the press.
If you have PR folk who are already in touch with the press,
they have the contact information,
the business relationship to handle the outputs.
If not, press will probably reach out to you
through social media or through any phone
or contact information they can find.
That thing you put on your main webpage
a million years ago is probably gonna get a workout.
If you are contacted by press in a strange situation,
ask for their contact info.
Tell them you will phone or email them back.
Google them. For the love of God, Google them to find out if they are who they say they are and what sort of entity they are, what they cover.
Learn a little bit about this person and then reach out.
The objective in any case is to funnel all this action to a manageable field of play.
So that's going to be managing where you engage, where your comps person engages, and what you're saying and putting out there.
That's your messaging.
In good comps, people can usually prioritize outreach and response efforts and have the
patience to remember that the loudest voice is not always the truest measure of landscape.
That's how, so who.
So proprietors, here's your list of hats.
Be strong.
We have three roles.
First role, comms.
You may have someone in-house with some or all
of the expertise.
As I said, it's a specialized field.
A lot of companies aren't staffed like that.
Related to crisis comms, you have PR, public relations.
Actually, it's more accurately press relations.
Some of you may do that in-house already. For those of you who use a firm outside, they may in turn have crisis comms folks on staff to specialize in meltdowns.
And then further afield of marketing, I don't find marketing folk as a rule very comfortable with these activities because bad things are happening and you know how marketing folk get and bad things get weird.
But this may be your first line of defense on things like wordsmithing or social media presence.
COMS folks are good at communicating information, but you do not want them working in a vacuum.
So this means that not only are COMS folks talking to the outside world,
they have got to have access to someone on staff who has a deep understanding of the problem.
Now, that should be your DRI.
These conversations, I will warn you ahead of time, are not always fun for the DRI.
You are tired, you are stressed,
and you feel like the questions you're getting are the dumbest thing you've ever heard.
But, you know, bear with it, the comps person probably agrees, but they can't tell you that right now.
And as a reminder, as Dave pointed out, if you keep comps looped in, you get a payback
because it's the continuity you need to hand off between DRIs.
You have a class of creatures with comps that lives to document stuff.
So use that superpower of theirs.
In some situations you're going to want a public spokesperson.
That could be super simple, just having some quotes out there attributed to one of your
leadership team or whatever.
Again, the comps people tend to sock puppet leadership teams on those.
On the other end of the scale, you could have a spokesperson who's talking directly to reporters.
You may have them on camera.
And if somebody in your company is already media trained in that process, fantastic.
That's your guy.
Do not get cute and decide that the current crisis would be a good time for one of your
leaders to do his first television appearance.
As Dave put it, do not put your people in a position to fail.
And if you're not sure about this, here's a rule of thumb.
If you do not know what pivot to talking point means
by the time I get to the comma, you
are not ready to speak in public.
Talk about that later.
But if you have any doubts, no, you are not ready.
Sole proprietors, you poor kids.
If you have no comps team, have the playbook at least.
The parts I listed before are what a crisis comps team would develop on your behalf
and stick to pretty closely.
If you have the presence of mind to develop them and stick to them, you might be okay.
It's business writing like any other thing, and you can learn to do this.
It is a learnable skill and not a difficult learnable skill.
That said, I want to say that there are occasions on which you take a deep breath and you buy some expertise.
And you don't have to keep them on staff. This is ad hoc expertise you're buying.
When I was a reporter, I was covering a story in which a very small business that posited itself as family friendly managed to hire a guy who had a thing for teenage girls.
very small company and it was going to be an absolute disaster when the news got out.
And they called their lawyers and their lawyers told them to hire crisis comms.
I never talked to the people, the family who ran the company without the crisis comms person acting as a mediator there.
And that person had enough distance on the subject to be able to handle it, to be able to handle the family's...
extreme distress at what this person had done to their business, to handle the different legal questions that were coming up,
to handle the fact that I was one of about 40 reporters who felt they needed to talk to them every hour on the hour.
Kept everything calm, kept everything clear, and in the end, the business survived.
That was not a foregone conclusion going into that one by any stretch.
The family got to present their side of what happened,
and they dealt with the things they needed to deal with.
Didn't let themselves get sidetracked.
You know, I can't do that cost-benefit analysis for you,
but it's something to keep in mind
that sometimes you're gonna drop a dime,
and if your company is at stake,
this is worth spending the money on.
So let's talk about how you know you're in trouble.
Call is coming from inside the house.
Possible that fire ad address Dave discussed
will be your first sign of trouble.
You'll hear about something in the news.
Later that day, somebody walks up and says, guess what?
Given all your givens, that's really not bad.
It gives you the head start.
And for comms, that's really crucial.
Dave talked about speed of response.
And this sort of conforms to the idea
of wait till the next business day.
First thing everybody on staff needs to do, to quote the wise men of Insane Clown Posse, is stop talking.
I believe it might have been do nothing or sit down or something.
But anyway, first thing you need to do is stop talking outside.
You have your playbooks in place, it's time to work it.
Everybody, above all things, needs to understand this is not the time for tweeting,
not the time for thinking aloud online in your blogs, on Twitter with friends.
not saying anything flippant or casual,
or even talking about how bad your workload is today.
You remember that guy we talked about?
The one who kind of does his own thing,
tweets about work stuff on his own?
Yeah, go find him.
Tell him no.
Tell him to sit down.
Put it as clearly as you can.
Because somebody's gonna ask him.
If he's out there and getting good feedback from this,
this is, as a reporter,
that was the first guy I went looking for.
I didn't want to talk to PR people.
I wanted to talk to the loudmouth.
This is sometimes, by the way, when you figure out who on your staff is looking out for their own brand rather than yours.
Hashtag firing offense.
The advantages you gain, again, it's framing your narrative, choosing your playing field, and that head start.
These are all preferable start conditions to what could happen.
Oh, those pleasant calls from the friendly hackers.
People at Dave's group, for instance.
Here's a friendly hacker now.
Doesn't he look good?
So if it's not someone on your stack, you get an email from someone like Dave who says,
hey, I found a problem with your product. You know, it's not ideal, but you still have
a really good chance of everything being okay as long as you keep it cool, keep the
conversation civil, and keep it private. On the other hand, in-house, behind the scenes,
you are accelerating your activity. At this point, all comms hands should be on deck and
briefed, but, you know, at like parade rest or whatever. Your hair is not yet on fire.
One person, probably DRI, should be engaging with this researcher, and that should either be by email or, if you must, by phone or by Skype.
Ask them for confidentiality, but assume that anything goes wrong, your conversations will be made public.
Or even if it didn't go wrong. Sometimes you'll get somebody who's so excited to hear from a company they really care about.
they will go out on Twitter and put on blast everything you thought you said privately about the bug.
It hurts, but it happens. Keep your cool.
In-house, again, you're keeping comms looped in, you're keeping legal looped in.
I will point out that both comms and legal are not just good at documents,
but very good at keeping quiet when things are on speakerphone. Just saying.
When dealing with outsiders, do not whine. Do not lie to them.
And don't gloat if it turns out the researcher was wrong.
This is really important.
Try, above all things, to keep in mind that this person reached out to you, which by definition,
they're your friend, or at least your ally, at least for now.
If your investigation finds that the problem isn't your fault, you be clear with them and be very specific about that.
Treat them as collaborators, is what I tell people.
Am I understanding the thing you found correctly?
Anything our analysis missed?
Did you see something we're not seeing?
In most cases, I advise more carrot and less stick with these guys.
They know you have lawyers and they know you have power in this situation.
If they start making details public in an aggressive way, if they start demanding money or whatever, that's different and they know that.
At that point, your legal folk are going to have some thoughts on how to proceed.
But above all things, remember that reaching out to you, that call that says,
Hey, I found something in your product, no matter how...
you aggressively worded, no matter how, you know,
na, na, na, na, na.
It's not an aggressive act.
These are your friends.
These people are not your friends.
Once the press and the general public
have taken an interest in your situation,
the risk of damage is higher.
If you play your cards right, you
may at least come out no worse than you are.
And by the way, yes, your hair is on fire.
At this point, you need your comps plan locked and loaded.
And a good rule of thumb in this case is the wider the interest in your situation
spreads, the simpler you're going to have to make your message.
So you may be going back and making it even simpler,
adding talking points going.
A video game is.
You'd be amazed.
Odds are really good that interest in your situation
will stay with the press you're already used to, the gaming press.
you may be computer press.
But if the mainstream for some reason takes an interest,
New York Times comes calling,
prepare to explain everything as simply as possible.
If they don't know your product,
if they don't know the gaming space at all,
there are a lot of things you're gonna have to spell out.
Be patient, especially since you're going to find
some of them are very arrogant
about their lack of knowledge.
Always be polite, always be responsive, always, you know,
I'll get back to you instead of I don't know,
never say no comment, we talked about that.
For the most part, if things get to this condition, you're in response only mode.
You're not doing outreach.
There's one exception to that.
If you are forced to shut down some or all of your servers or any kind of access as part
of deployment, as Dave was describing, I think, you want to communicate that to anybody who
will listen.
No surprises on outages.
It looks so much worse if they don't know it's coming.
If your, by the way, if your DRI fails to warn the comps person about an outage,
the comps person is legally allowed to kick them really hard.
You can look that up, it's true.
Friends in faraway places.
If you've previously had good interactions with somebody
in the press or somebody in the industry who's high profile,
as we discussed, consider reaching out.
With reporters, that can be as simple as an email.
So, hey, I know you probably heard about this thing
and I wondered if you had any questions for me.
Don't be pushy.
Just once, one email is more than sufficient.
Do not mail bomb your reporters.
But if you have that good credit build up, at this point,
it might be a really good time to spend that.
Maybe you got lucky.
Maybe by now your investigation, you guys have come back.
It's like, nope, not us.
We're not affected.
It's not a bug.
It's somebody else's bug.
Say so.
Just say so.
Write another statement.
It says the investigation has concluded.
Here's the situation.
You make sure it gets to all the people and places
that you have interacted with in this process.
Again, your comms person is keeping a list of that
or should be.
I advise you through SAT experience to say that you'll continue to monitor the situation
because that's the safest thing to say in case it decides to claw its way back out of the grave.
But I'm not here to tell you what that might mean in your case.
Just put it out there for closure, though.
So there's one more possibility, and you know, I saved the best for last.
With any luck, none of the things on this slide will ever happen to you.
The plan works the same, but even your best efforts in these situations are probably not going to come to more than a draw.
Sorry about it.
You can break into jail and put yourself in a bad situation.
Anybody follow Satya Nadella talking at the Grace Hopper conference a couple weeks ago?
Our good CEO of Microsoft decided to get in there and
talk about being nice and having good karma when asked
about how to improve salaries for women.
It did not go well at the Women in Tech Conference for him.
And the saddest thing about that, by the way, was about
two days before that, Satya had been the subject of a
really positive piece from Vanity Fair.
And for comms, that's a huge win.
That is your entire year of.
We won.
It's an elaborate process.
There's interviews.
There's fact checking.
There's background work with the reporter.
It is the highest profile thing.
Your boss's mom reads Vanity Fair.
And it all blew up in two days because their boss
opened his mouth.
If the security version of this happens to you,
you work the map.
You get a decent open letter out there.
It may take several, as it did with Microsoft.
And you just kind of hope the news cycle goes and does
something else pretty soon.
you could be the victim of an actually hostile security
reporter, as opposed to the socially inept security
reporter from before.
Those of you who don't know about Pastebin,
it's a site where some of your more black-headed researchers
will drop information about vulnerabilities,
or more pertinent here, perhaps, names and password
and other information they've ganked from a.
from insecure sites or services.
In cases like those, you have some work to do to figure out what happened over on the tech side,
but a lot of your comms will be following the lead of legal.
And in some cases, the regulations covering breach notifications,
if you didn't find your way clear to not keeping the credit card info.
Let your lawyers lead. Just follow.
Finally, there are some pretty random events where all you can do is work the plan and start thinking about how to rebuild.
Everybody here know what Arby's is? The fast food chain restaurant? Yeah, okay.
They're having a really weird year.
Both Jon Stewart and Stephen Colbert have been using them as a punchline for a little minute now.
Saying some really mean, funny things about the quality of the food.
And Arby's clearly has some really smart crisis comps people on retainer
because instead of lawyering up and making them stop, they started sending over sandwiches.
Here's some food, free food, total charm offensive.
And it seems to be working.
In the last few messages, Stewart and Colbert are saying,
oh, hey, they sent over these sandwiches.
They're forthright about it.
But the comments have been kinder.
And so now Arby's is in this interesting transition
between being this mean punchline
to this sort of recipient of free advertising.
These mean things are said, but the edge is definitely off.
I wouldn't say it's positive yet,
as far as making lemonade out of.
Beef, lemons, sorry.
It's not bad.
Sometimes that is exactly what a win looks like.
And I, to the end of my slides.
Questions, questions for Dave especially?
He has an open mic, I think.
Would you like to stand at this mic?
We'll both stand up here because someone
might actually have questions.
But there's an edge.
Who will win the edge of the podium?
The edge will win.
So are there any questions?
There's a microphone up there or you can raise your hand and we'll ask and then we'll repeat
the question.
Any questions?
Terrify them into submission.
Or there's napping after lunch.
It's one of the two.
All right.
Well, for a second I thought someone was going to ask a question.
Well, in that case, thank you very much and have a great show.
you