Hey everyone, I am Tor Frigg, I'm the creative director and general art person at Neon Giant.
And welcome to my talk, Building the World of the Ascent.
And this talk is diving into how we approached and solved some of the specific challenges we faced when we built the world of the ascent.
And a big chunk of it is talking about the...
the process that made us arrive where we are with our pipeline
and deep dive into some of the tools we created to make the world
and some general Unreal advice sprinkled in.
So this is like a short trailer of the game.
You have shown an aptitude for applying lethal solutions to conflicted
situations.
It looks like we're gonna have to work together on this one.
Let's get it done!
So what is The Ascent? It's a solo and co-op action RPG set in a dystopian cyberpunk future
and it's made in Unreal Engine 4 and it's available on PC, Xbox One, Xbox Series, PS4 and 5.
And we released it last year on Xbox and PC and yesterday on PlayStation, so please go and buy it.
And it's the first game from Neon Giant.
And we are a small indie studio from Uppsala in Sweden.
And we are 11 people, a team of extremely talented
and awesome developers that I'm very honored to work alongside.
And we all come from AAA, various parts of the AAA industry.
And we've been around as a studio for about four years now.
So.
From the very beginning when we made this game,
like, we had a couple of both, you know,
really obvious and some non-obvious challenges ahead of us.
Being a new small developer,
of course, we made it easy for ourselves
and we picked the easiest subject,
an open-world dense sci-fi cityscape,
you know, handcrafted and rich with storytelling.
And we started with one artist, that was me,
and we peaked with four artists,
including TechArt and VFX.
And this meant of course several things.
I mean, we are a small team and we're working with what is essentially one of the most time-consuming topics.
An urban imaginary environment where every single object needs to be both designed and built.
And making sci-fi means that almost every asset needs to be...
It needs to be designed and we didn't have any concept artists at all on the team,
which means it's very demanding from a design point of view,
so the subject itself.
And we needed a very fast and flexible content pipeline,
a very fast pipeline because we needed to build a lot of objects to cover the world.
And also the art style, because we're making a dirty, slummy,
lived-in kind of cityscape.
And we have to push shaders and content a lot further.
If you make something that is a bit more clean and shiny,
it will be a lot easier to find a suitable pipeline.
So not only do we need to find a fast pipeline,
we also need to find a pipeline that
didn't sacrifice the art style.
And then the third major challenge we had,
which is assembling the world itself.
It's a...
It's a large scale game with a very, very high asset density.
And not only that, we also wanted
to make a world that feel alive and handcrafted
with a lot of storytelling.
So that in itself was another challenge.
How do we make a large urban world
and achieve the high degree of world building
that we want to aim for?
So.
To give you an idea of the scale of the world,
this is maybe like a third of the game world or so.
And then we go full CSI and start zooming in a little bit
and into the city.
This is one of the hubs in the game, cluster 13.
And we zoom in closer.
We start to see the asset density.
This is a weapon shop.
And then inside the weapon shop, and then enhance.
So that's kind of the scale that we were working with.
So we always knew that there was no way we could compete with larger titles without picking
our battles extremely carefully.
And we needed a very fast and transparent pipeline that allowed artists to not only
create art very quickly, but also stay in the creative flow.
And not just being fast, but also removing distractions.
The two main themes that allowed us to do that was simplicity and limitations.
And that might sound a little bit counterintuitive considering, you know, the complex subject matter.
But what it allowed us to do was to focus on the big picture and leave room to polish.
And it's also not the sexiest words to use to, you know, pitch a pipeline to artists.
But we're a studio with a pretty strong background in technical art.
So like an alternative title for this talk would have been, you know,
tech art, all the things, because that's what we did.
So if we start with the very building blocks of the game,
the 3D models themselves.
So from the very beginning, we knew
that we couldn't have a traditional approach
to making models.
We needed speed.
And we also needed something that
would help in making visuals consistent with a minimum
of iteration.
So we needed to support art direction at every turn
so we could just maintain momentum.
And thankfully there was no point in making AAA quality assets because of the camera distance.
So we had a lot of options to explore different approaches.
So let's look at the options.
So first of all a traditional method like with, you know, high poly, low poly modeling.
That just wouldn't work for several reasons.
First of all, the whole thing, you're
building two different models, you need to bake,
you need to import textures.
It's just too many steps.
It's like, no way.
Another problem with that is that the traditional concept
art to in-game model workflow doesn't work either,
because we don't have any concept art.
So we built the entire world and all the assets
without any concept art.
And we need a workflow where we can iterate on assets
really, really quickly without bakes and so on.
So, you know, how about tiling materials and decals,
which is, you know, great for like cleaner art styles,
but it doesn't really, you know, with more abstract shapes,
but it doesn't work for the kind of detail level
and the busy art style that we're going for.
And we want lots of paneling, fine detail,
and the workload would just be intense
if we were doing it like that way,
plus that we couldn't really support that amount of geometry
that will be needed.
So we can't rely on the title of textures.
So how about trim sheets?
I mean, they are standard sci-fi solution, right?
Like, they're great for getting a lot of shapes and details,
perfect for sci-fi panels, streams like that.
And it also helps a lot with the art direction,
because you get a lot of the art direction built
into the texture.
So it's very good for keeping down the iteration
and maintaining a shared shape language.
But trim sheets on their own, they
are too expensive to make the kind of granular detail
that we wanted.
We wanted a lot of mechanical pieces, chunky engine bits.
And it's a pain in the ass to unwrap those.
Plus, you get a lot of.
To get that kind of density, you need so many polygons.
And the only real way to have shapes
that are smoother than the amount of polygons you have
is to bake them.
But we already said that we didn't want to bake things.
So that was a bit of a problem.
So how about we use one set of baked assets
and one set of trim sheets?
That could work, but then we would need to have two
materials for each asset.
And we're going for a very, very dense world,
so that would just explode the amount of draw calls.
And not to mention the setup time,
because then we need to set up two materials for each asset,
and that would also just be very time consuming.
But at the same time we really need those baked bits to get the detail level that we wanted.
So we solved that by just putting the baked parts in the trim sheet.
And that was, you know, problem solved.
So we sacrificed a bit of space in our trim sheet and then put the baked bits in there.
That was great, I mean, because then we can do both, but at the same time that also makes it
a little bit less flexible because you have a, you know, essentially a 4k texture and you can't
really scale that however much you want. You can't make giant assets because, you know, it's a,
it can't scale, you know, forever, right?
It also makes it really, really time consuming to make a set of textures
because not only do you make a trim sheet, which is pretty simple,
but you also need to make all those little mechanical bits and baked bits.
And that's a bit of a pain in the ass.
So we just didn't.
So we made this texture.
And then we left some space in it even, so because we thought, well, we surely know the texture is not perfect.
We're going to need lots of different bits, which we then never did.
So we just have like a semi-finished texture.
And this is where the limitations and the simplicity comes in.
So with a modern engine and modern workflows,
I mean, you have basically infinite possibilities.
You know, how do we approach each asset?
Like, do you use a unique texture?
Do you use, you know, a mix of the tiling textures?
Do you have, like, multiple detail normal maps?
Do I make the details in painter or in the mesh?
You know, like, do artists pick different workflows?
And, you know, how do you keep them consistent?
So, when you're dealing with assets, that's not necessarily a great thing.
We want to focus on the big picture and get there as quickly as possible so we can iterate on it.
That's the goal. The assets don't actually matter that much compared to the big picture.
So, what we did was that we enforced this single workflow for the vast, vast majority of all the assets in the game.
And that meant we had to cut a lot of corners visually,
but the speed was very high.
So if you look at certain assets,
they don't look very good.
And that's on purpose.
And since we knew the camera distance,
we can kind of put a cap on how detailed
do we want to make our assets,
because there are details that you can't just see, right?
It's just wasteful.
So we picked a polygon density
and like a detail density that fit our camera distance,
because we have a bit of a zoomed out camera, right?
And this puts a little bit of a cap on the fidelity that we could reach, but at the same time...
there was no reason to stop and think.
We put this limitation on ourselves
so that we could stop second guessing
and always just focus on creating.
And since we're using a shared texture sheet and a KitMesh
library, a lot of the design language
just comes from that, which cuts down on the design feedback
and the iteration on assets a lot.
But once we do need to iterate, we
have a shared system for the assets.
So every hard surface object in the entire game
is using the same texture.
So every mech, every vehicle, every sci-fi wall,
computer, plastic chair, box, whatever,
is using the same texture and the same shader.
So for example, in this scene,
you have the ship in the background,
you have the railings, the, yeah,
everything basically is using the same texture.
So to summarize it, we split between a modular trim sheet
for the flexibility, but then we used the baked parts
for the fidelity.
And then we used weighted normals
because it's the year 2022 and we're not barbarians.
And then we just only used one texture for all objects,
all hard-surfaced objects in the entire game.
And we only used low-poly geometry.
It was like, or like mid-poly.
Like, there was no high polys and so on.
And then we extended this with, you know, mesh decals
that we could, for flexibility, to hide the fact
that we only have one texture in the entire game.
Sometimes you want a little bit of extra.
So, that's good, because then you can have normal decals
and you can all bend and stretch them, and that works great.
So we used that a lot for, like, more intricate pieces, right?
But now that we have the modeling in place,
the second challenge we needed to face was,
how do we even texture this?
How do we even shade this?
So like I said before, we were aiming
for a very dirty and gritty art style, full of detail.
And clean is a little bit more simple and more predictable.
Dirt is very contextual.
You can't just put random dirt everywhere, right?
It needs to be in the right places.
So we needed to find a way of doing this
with as little to no work.
We also need a lot of variety.
So, for example, how do we even have colors?
So we can't just use one color per Asset,
because that's boring,
and several Materials are out of the question.
So how about we just use a Mask for different Textures,
or different colors?
That would mean creating thousands of Textures,
and just adding them in per Force
would be a giant pain in the ass,
and we don't have time for that.
So what we did was we essentially used the UV sets for the meshes
and then we just basically used a UDIM approach where we just offset the UVs
and used that as a mask.
And that way we could just have different colors without having any textures.
So using that, you know, the primary materials we needed in the game was, you know, because it's hard surface.
So it's either, you know, bare or painted metal or sometimes plastic, you know, when we're going a bit crazy.
And the main shading difference is basically, you know, either metal or non metals, right?
So we use the same method of just shifting the UVs to mask between metals.
So that was kind of our key base feature set.
And now that we had those basic in place,
we could focus on adding rust, dirt, and other effects
in a decently believable way.
And we wanted to have something that
looked as close to hand-authored as possible,
but without putting in any work.
So we ended up experimenting and adding several layers.
So first of all, I mean, we're using a trim sheet, so it's very easy to just ask, you know, to add some texture masks that can drive things like details around bolts and like, you know, very fine detail like dirt and wear and tear and so on.
Like, but.
And that's great. It gives you a little bit of a base pass, right?
But it doesn't give you any contextual dirt.
It doesn't use the shapes of the mesh.
You know, you want dirt behind some pipes.
You want dirt in some little hatch.
You want some scratched metal on the exposed parts of a mech.
So we still can't use textures.
So we just use vertex colors.
So we baked down the ambient occlusion and the convexity,
and we used that to drive dirt, wear and tear, and rust,
just in a generalized way.
So assets now work much better on their own.
But.
We're still thinking about the scene and the big picture.
It's not about the assets, it's about the scene.
So now we have the case where like, you know,
I have some very clean surfaces
that meet some very dirty ones.
And you know, like the, this is not a world where,
you know, everything is not a bunch of clean objects.
So we just put in a pile, right?
Like it's dirty.
Things have been sitting there for a while.
So we needed to get like that cohesion in.
And we can't just vertex paint the entire world manually,
because first of all, it would take an insane amount of time.
And it would also eat up all the memory for all the instances.
So that was out of the question.
So this is where the light baking in Unreal comes in handy.
So when you bake light in Unreal,
you can use the option to also bake out
an ambient occlusion mask.
So that's what we use to just drive the third aspect of the dirt.
So assets that are next to each other are actually getting the dirt under the crates, behind some pipe meshes, things like that.
We'll swap back and forth, you can see some of the objects there in the background, for example.
And it comes with a pretty hefty texture cost, but more on that later.
And it also doesn't require any hand authoring, which is good, so we don't need to put in any actual work.
But even with this, it's still sci-fi. We need glowy bits, we need decals.
So what we did was that... and this is the little guy that you use.
So we used a secondary UV set and then we used the same approach with the UDIMs to just mask between decals and emissive surfaces.
And that, you know, now we have like a whole bunch of little tricks to use to make the asset look handcrafted without, you know, actually, you know, doing anything.
And once we have the dirt, it's very easy to turn it back off again.
So we could share the materials across a very wide range of props and assets.
So for example, we have this slum scene,
and then we have this little lab from later in the game.
And they're sharing the same textures, the same materials, the same assets.
So it gives us a lot of perceived variety,
because we didn't actually have the time to create that much variety.
And...
Now that we have a pretty flexible approach that can give us all these different things,
we need to speed it back up again.
Because we're back to having super many choices and a very complicated setup.
And we needed this very fast pipeline.
So to tackle this, we set a lot of limitations on what we could do on ourselves.
So we set the amount of colors to three colors and three metals.
And that was the maximum amount that we had in our shader.
And that was on purpose.
And then we built our tools to fit that pipeline.
Because.
We have a very simple tagging system in Modo with just a little pie chart,
like pie menu to just complete with a preview shading like that,
so you can just see roughly what it looks like.
And then we combine that just with a very simple preset vertex color bake.
And all of that is just applied when we export the model.
So it's like a one-click thing.
And one of the additional benefits is because, you know, we...
we made the pipeline simpler by putting a limitation on the amount of colors, but
what it also does with that is that
it helps with the art direction because it sets a very simple framework on the
assets. You only have three colors, so
when you're designing the assets you already know the limitations. You start
designing your assets with the
primary, secondary, tertiary color
because that's all you get.
And uh...
this was one of the uh...
one of the tools that were like, it just helped with the visual polish and the design of the game
because we needed to balance the visuals.
So with all these things in place there was like quite a few things that happened
like automatically. First of all, a very low texture usage.
It's very easy to have 4k textures when you only have one.
So we managed to lower the texture pool on console,
for example, from the default is like one gig in Unreal.
We had 400 megabytes, and the vast, vast majority of that
was things like reflection probes, light maps,
and the volumetric light, for example.
So we had less, way less than 100 megs
spent on the actual textures for the game at any time.
So it was very easy to scale it down to basically whatever.
But we also have the additional benefit
of having reusable materials.
And this was a very, very big thing.
And we didn't really intend for this to happen either.
Because we enforced this limited palette and a single workflow,
what happened is that we have the same texture
set for all the assets.
We have the same shader setup for all the assets.
So we can just swap materials back and forth.
And we can iterate on the look of an area
really, really quickly.
Because if you make one material for a mech,
it's going to fit the railings as well.
So if you want to share the color palettes, that's very easy.
And also, we're using material instances in Unreal.
And the way that works is that you make an instance of something.
It inherits from the properties, any properties that you don't override from the parent.
So what you can do is that you can very simply make a chain of inheritance.
And then you can iterate on, for example, how dirty is a scene,
the color balance, and you can do that on an entire scene
with just a few sliders.
So that's also something that we're like, well, that makes a lot of sense
now that we have built it, but it wasn't really on purpose.
So we could reuse a lot of content really, really quickly.
So for example, we have this data core,
but we also have this dirty sewer.
And it's using the same models, same textures,
same base materials.
But it's just very different setups.
So that gives us a lot of extra mileage.
We also have the benefit of enforcing the art direction.
So texture details and kitbash pieces,
they are forced to be shared, which
means that everything will have the same artistic direction
by default. No one will make pieces that stand out,
because they will be consistent.
The shape language will be shared
without having any concept art and without anyone
having to point that out.
It also made it very easy to tweak because all the materials, all the meshes are using the same setup.
So if you ever wanted to grab someone else's model, someone else's materials,
you always know where to look because it's the same setup.
It also cuts down on things like iteration.
And we also have very iteratable models because there's no baking process.
So, you know, I built a mech and now it needs like a hatch that can open and a new gun.
It's just go in, build it, export, done.
Same thing, like, you know, we need more guns for the game.
We just grab a gun, add some more stuff to it, you know, done.
It was very, very efficient.
And it also feeds into like a loop of everything you do,
since everything is sharing the same texture, like...
we made this cool looking pipe into the Kitbash library.
We made this cool chunk of cables
that looks really nice into the Kitbash library.
Every time we found a nice pleasing shape,
something that looked good, we could just reuse that.
Just copy paste it to a different model.
So you find all these new ways to make cool details
and then you can just reuse that instantly
in any other model.
So we also had the benefit of no technical surprises.
Everything was built with the same polygon density, shader complexity, amount of materials.
So it was very easy to extend the feature set.
We wanted to have rain puddles, we wanted to have little randomized blinky bits, better
shading, details, detail normal maps.
Very easy to just add it because it's just one place to do so.
And this took out a very big chunk of work when it comes to optimizing because, you know,
we never had to care about polygon density, material complexity, like for almost any scene.
And when we did, it was very easy because there was only one place to go.
So very easy to optimize.
It also allowed us to go beyond what we thought was the limit visually.
As I said before, we were very smart and we were like,
okay, we know our camera distance, so we're going to put a cap on how much detail we have.
And that was completely wrong, because it turns out when we're kitbashing, we could just,
for example, we have this little...
Well, it's called Fuel Station, but I don't know what it is.
And then you're like, well, you can put it on the sci-fi pillar
thing, and it still looks good.
And it's actually really detailed.
But that's not at all what we intended to do.
So it kind of allowed us to push beyond what we thought
we should do visually.
And same thing, we made these pipes, pipe sets,
and things like that that were meant to be like this big.
And then we just scaled them down to half the size.
And we're like, OK.
actually looks better.
So we were a bit wrong in a good way.
And the end result is that we created over 8,000 assets,
which is like roughly three assets per artist per day.
But most of the time, we did not make any assets.
So it's a bit of a skewed number.
And even the biggest assets, like the biggest set pieces,
took like three days.
Like the big mechs took like one and a half day.
So it was very, very quick.
So that really achieved what we wanted.
So armed with this very large pile of models,
we had the next challenge, which is assembling the world itself.
And it's a very cluttered cityscape,
full with layers, movable parts, and a very lived in feeling.
That was a challenge in itself because not only do we have a lot of literal ground to cover,
we also wanted to make a game full of life and world building and movement.
I mean, it's a sci-fi metropolis. It's not an empty forest, right?
We need a lot of shit happening.
So that meant not only did we have to build the world really quickly,
we had to build it quickly enough that we had time to go back and just add lots of life.
So...
we need to get to the part where we put the cherry on top really quickly.
And this is where all these limitations that we put in earlier in the pipeline comes in.
We had a lot of content to create and place in the world,
so we tried to create tools that allowed us to get rid of monotonous tasks.
So we didn't create, you know, like this giant advanced things, you know, to solve big problems.
We tried to get rid of all the monotonous boring tasks for artists
so that they can focus more on the creative parts and less on the monotonous stuff.
And we used Houdini for a lot of this, and we created multiple tools to help us.
So, for example, our pipe generation tool.
So, this is for making modular sets of pipes.
And it started as a very simple... well, not very simple, it's amazing.
but just used the profile of the pipe
and it created an entire modular set of pipes from that.
And then Magnus worked some black magic,
so not only is it a simple set of pipes,
but it also fits the art direction of the game.
You have all these little bendy bits
and tons and tons of extra detail.
And then it all tiles both mesh-wise and texture-wise.
And that's the kind of stuff, you don't want to create 20 variations of the same pipe, right?
It's pretty boring.
So what we then did was we also had the placement of the pipes.
Placing lots and lots and lots of pipes in a game is really, really boring.
So we have a tool that is using splines to place those sets of modular assets that we made.
And we can also just change sets for changing visuals instantly and swap between different visuals.
And what this allowed us to do was not only does this speed up placing pipes,
but since placing pipes is now less boring and more satisfying,
artists can now create things that they didn't think about creating before,
because it lowered the mental barrier of like,
oh god, I don't want to place more pipes.
So the game looks a lot better for it, because we have a lot of pipes in our game.
We also have the aptly named RoomMaker, which just makes rooms or buildings based on sets of defined assets.
Same thing there, we have modular sets that have all the pieces.
And then we can just add cubes and basically make Boolean operations and it would just make...
make buildings out of that.
So we use this a lot in some places in the game,
like in the sewers, for example.
A big, big chunk of the set dressing
is basically just these boxes that then just
placed all of these assets in an optimal fashion automatically.
And then we have the destruction.
We love destruction.
But it's also very time consuming to make.
So we had two main goals with the destruction.
First of all, making it very, very fast to author
and also make it very, very cheap to render.
So since the game is like essentially taking place in a two-dimensional plane,
you know, we always know which direction, like the direction the shots will come from.
What we could do is just cheat. So instead of having actual destruction,
what we're doing is that we're playing animations based on the direction that you hit the meshes.
So we just baked out simulations based on multiple directions and then we just pick
which one to play. So it looks like destruction, but it's just an animation, right?
So that allowed us to have a lot of destruction
that looked like it was reacting to the players,
you know, explosions, you know,
shooting rocket launchers and stuff,
but actually it's just fake.
And, you know, to take things further,
like what you can do, for example,
is that you can have, you know, an animation blueprint,
and you can just blend between different animations
to make it, you know, even more precise.
But we didn't do that because we thought
this looked good enough, but you could.
And then we had the cables.
We have a lot of cables in our world.
We love cables.
They're also very tedious to make, just drawing splines.
So we had a whole array of tools for making
different types of cables.
We had everything from fake simulated ones on the ground
to making cables between just two different walls.
You could just.
but, you know, add lots of cables.
And what made this work really well is because the tool itself, you know, was...
The hard part is making it look good and fit the art direction.
And that's, I think, where they really shine,
because the amount of complexity we can have in the cables...
to making them by hand would be very time consuming.
But we also here made a whole bunch of smaller tools
instead of having one enormous mega tool.
We just had four or five different cable tools.
And we mostly limited ourselves to not making any custom models,
because we just didn't have time.
But when we did, we tried to use tools to speed up the process
so we can help with the world building.
So for example, we have the decal tool,
which does exactly what it says on the box.
You type out text, and you get decals,
mesh decals in the editor.
And it's very, very efficient because this is one of those things that takes you out of the flow.
You're going to make a sign, you have to go back to your content application,
you're going to make that, you're going to export it, you're going to set it up.
Instead, we could just type things directly in the editor and just output mesh decals.
And then we had a bunch of features in it to make them a bit more visually interesting than just text.
But this also allowed us to do a lot more world building and context-specific decals really, really quickly.
And we also had, you know, lots and lots of signs because, you know, it's a cyberpunk cityscape.
So everything from neon signs with model letters to, you know, different kind of generic plastic signs, handmade signs.
And these tools, you know, ended up being pretty much of a...
a beast but it could handle like everything from like the simpler signs to even you know complicated
animated signs we're using like preset vertex shaders so you can have like blinky signs so
you can just we can just type out whatever we wanted into the editor and get output geometry
so
With the basic construction of the world out of the way,
we could focus on adding life to the world.
And something we noticed during the project
was that whenever we tried doing these things
and adding more life and movement to the world,
it was never enough.
We always had to revisit it over and over again.
And we evaluated it.
We realized we wanted or needed more.
And then we went back.
And then we improved what we had.
And the running theme that happened was that we ended up
doing multiple solutions for almost every single thing.
Instead of having these mega complex advanced systems,
we instead would just made multiple things
to solve each problem.
Because we didn't have a separate team
that would go in and add stuff after the artists were done.
Like everything needed to be functional and usable
enough for the artist to just go crazy with it.
Because they did all of it.
So it was very much a collaborative and iterative effort.
And we worked a lot on adding new features and options
to extend the tools so that we could get
more mileage out of them.
We developed many ways to add life to a scene and these are some of the highlights.
So one of the things that we did different was that we had a big goal that we wanted to have was to make the vistas in the world not feel like a vista.
And even when we used the same kind of art and it was very high fidelity, the vistas still felt pretty dead.
You had this enormous cityscape.
nothing in it, right? So we needed to add people. And we started adding, you know, NPCs standing on
the balconies, which, you know, you couldn't really appreciate that they were moving. So we added,
you know, more wavy animations and, you know, that worked. But, you know, still not enough.
So we added, you know, NPCs walking on splines in the background, which, you know, give you a lot
more movement in the background, feels a bit alive. But then we got this weird thing that...
This city is completely dead where you are,
and everyone is just walking over there in the background.
So the goal was always to have those characters
in the playable space.
And eventually, we added AIs for this.
So here's before and after, for example,
before we added more life to the world.
So we added lots and lots of people everywhere.
And as we added them, we kept adding more visual variations,
setups, reactions.
So what we could now do is that we could set dress using NPCs.
So instead of, you know, like, you know,
lots of people talking, fighting,
going about their business and, you know,
this helped a lot with making the world more alive because
Instead of having some system that would place crowds
in the scene, we made them part of the set dressing process
so that the artist could actually start
when they're making a scene,
they would plan for using the NPCs
and they would make all these little setups,
like, oh, here are the hobos
and here's the guys in the cafe.
So they could actually build the scene up in one go
using all of these kind of features
that normally artists would not use.
So the best part of getting them into the game was really making them part of the set dressing
and then making sure that they actually just worked.
And another thing, when it comes to mind, when you're thinking of Cyberpunk, Cityscapes,
it's like all these big commercials, animated things.
So I thought I was going to make shaders for that.
But that's super time consuming.
So we're like, OK, let's use actual movies instead
and just play those because you have a lot more potential
there, right?
But they're super expensive to render in Unreal.
And each movie you have have a fixed cost on the CPU threads,
especially on consoles.
So you can't just have 10 movies.
You have a fixed limitation of how many you can have.
So what we did was that we just made a whole pile of models,
and then we, or like models, movies,
and we put them into one movie,
and we had made sure that they were equal length.
And then we just scaled that down,
like to like be a small movie.
And that meant that we can actually have like this,
you know, different commercials playing.
But the problem was that they didn't cast light.
And with our camera, we don't get so much screen space
reflections and things like that.
So we really wanted this feeling where they're
casting light dynamically.
We wanted to use the colors from the movies to drive a light source.
But when you have the light functions in Unreal, they don't support RGB.
So what we did instead was that we took the movies, each movie,
and we blurred them down to one pixel, the average color in Houdini,
and then we outputted that as a CSV file.
And then we just animate the light source using that CSV file.
And that allowed us to have this light animate.
And it looks like they're casting light from the movie,
but they are not.
And since we then had all these movies in one texture,
what we could do is that we could just move the texture
in UV space.
And we're swapping channels.
So we just made a very simple playlist system
and then just swapping the color curve at the same time.
So it could look like you have randomized movies
playing on these big screens
and you have giant blimps flying past
and casting light with the commercials.
And it's basically just a shader
that just moves around in UV space.
And an additional benefit was then, well, we have all these cool blinky color curves.
So then we start adding them to like the window shaders, so it looks like people are watching
TVs or other light sources that are off-screen, so we can have, you know, big dynamic light
that changes color all the time.
So we get a lot of usage out of that.
Another thing we added as well was things like traffic and moving parts.
And the same thing there, we just realized that the amount of stuff you need is just insane
because it's the variety, right? So we kept adding layers and layers.
So for the traffic, we also had like three types of traffic.
We had like five types of random spinny moving bits for all the different sci-fi stuff.
And it's really like the variety that is the key.
So we needed a lot of very simple things.
So having successfully, you know, built all these things,
like we're like, we have so much stuff,
we have too much stuff.
So we removed a lot of the technical guesswork
from the asset pipeline with our workflow, right?
Problem was that we just moved that forward
into later into the chain,
because our ambition grew throughout the project.
So...
Thanks to the very simple content pipeline,
we had a very, very limited part of optimizations
that we could focus on.
So we had draw calls.
They were a major problem.
Same thing with streaming.
So for draw calls, what we did was a bunch of,
you know, a combination of tech art,
some hand optimization, and lighting optimization.
So I'm gonna focus on the lighting optimizations.
So it's an extremely, extremely important part of the game,
the lighting.
We have artificial light at all times.
There's almost no sunlight.
And we wanted to have a softer look,
but also have a very, very scalable game
in terms of rendering.
And we evaluated both dynamic and static light.
And you know, dynamic is great,
but it doesn't really scale very well.
So we ended up with a hybrid mix.
So we used very, very large scale static lights
that we hand placed. We couldn't use a skylight
because we wanted to have a different feeling
in different areas, right?
And then when we optimized, we actually switched
a lot of lights to static
because we basically used the default texture,
like the default light map resolution in Unreal.
with some tweaks, which you know, doesn't work great when you're making FPS, but when you're making this kind of game
it works really well. And we don't really have any textures, so we have plenty of space for lightmaps.
So we actually used a lot of static lighting.
But static lighting actually doesn't look very good if you don't have reflection probes.
And they are like the real heroes of the lighting.
So this is how it looks like without reflection probes.
And making a game from this camera angle, you can't really use reflection probes in the regular way.
Because it looks kind of meh.
So what we did essentially was that we hand-painted the world using reflection probes.
Because you just pick where they look good.
Because, I mean, it doesn't matter because you're not going to be the first person to see if they align well.
So we just like, we just placed like, here's a water puddle.
We can have a reflection probe and it's going to look all nice and dynamic.
So a lot of what people think is dynamic lighting is actually just reflection probes.
But they're super expensive.
They take like a megabyte of memory.
But once again, with our camera distance,
we don't really care because we don't need that resolution.
So we just put them to like 64 by 64 cubemaps.
And then we just maxed out the amount at all times.
And we just basically painted lighting.
And then to fight the draw calls,
another thing we did was that.
The lightmap resolution by default in Unreal is 1K,
and we increased it to 2K.
And that saved us 10% of draw calls.
And why does that happen?
Well, by default, when you increase the lightmap
resolution in Unreal, it doesn't actually
increase the resolution.
It packs all the assets into a texture.
So you just pack more assets into the same texture.
And Unreal have an automated or automatic instancing.
But you can only instance if it's
the same mesh, same material.
also the same lightmap.
So by increasing the lightmap size,
you just have more assets on the same texture.
So the likelihood that they can auto instance is just higher.
But that means we also needed, you know,
to load more lightmaps.
That was, once again, very okay
because we didn't really use textures.
So it cost us about 50 megs on Xbox One,
but cut the draw calls by 10%.
So that allowed us to really have,
you know, that kind of density that we wanted.
And then another key part of the lighting was the volumetric light.
And we wanted to have this Blade Runner feeling, lots of volumetric lights all the time.
But that's also really expensive, so we used the baked light for that.
But that's also a bit challenging because...
It's built for making like, you know, a first person or things like that.
And all the volumetric light is like, it keeps close to the geometry to keep the density high.
The problem is that we have a lot of vistas and we don't really need like, you know, probes every like one meter, like a hundred meters into the background.
So, so we use these, the volumetric lightmap density volumes to optimize all of that.
And you know, that was great.
It freed up some memory, but it still
took an enormous chunk of memory.
Because the default lighting grid just
doesn't go any lower by default. It's not really
built for making an open world game with base lighting.
So, we just like, you know, I googled it, and I just added an extra MIP to the volumetric light grid,
which is just changing a variable, and that allowed it to optimize itself a lot heavier,
which took the cost down from like 150 to 40 megs.
but we also had to optimize the lighting.
And one of the things that, you know,
you think about like culling,
I mean, we're making basically having a isometric type game.
So you don't think that you have to use culling a lot,
but Unreal is very, very forgiving.
So what we did was we actually went in
and we just placed like a distance based fading
on all the lights so that they would fade out nicely
at the edge of the screen.
And that was like the biggest optimization we did
because
And like I said, Unreal is very forgiving and they have a fading for light, but it's super, super conservative.
So we just did that because we thought, surely we don't need to do that with a top-down camera,
but it was actually the single biggest optimization we did in the entire project.
That was like the biggest optimization.
And the other was just basically turning lights static.
But we also didn't want to sacrifice fidelity
on any platform.
So we built tools so we could turn off shadows
per platform per light, because you can't really do that.
Either you turn on shadows or you turn them off.
And there's not really anything that you can do there.
So we made tools and then we basically made a hand pass
on the entire world and turned off shadows
in problematic areas.
No one noticed, so it worked.
But that allowed us to really have the shadows on everything
on next gen, shadows on not really anything
on the current gen.
So in the end, our enforced limitations
was a great success.
It allowed us to maintain momentum
when we're building things.
And it allowed us to focus our attention.
But it also removed a lot of visual and technical noise,
because you know.
We didn't have many colors, we have a very busy game visually,
and we restrained the use of colors
and helped the art direction along the way.
And we also unlocked a lot of new possibilities,
like the sharing of materials, which also helped
with reinforcing the art direction.
And it's a...
It saved us a lot of time that you normally spend on assets,
so we can focus on creating the world.
Because that was the whole thing we wanted to do.
We wanted to move a lot of the time spent from the assets
to working on the world and making sure the world felt alive and polished.
So we moved a lot of those savings along the line.
It's some of the downsides of working with a pipeline
like this.
It's that it's really scary.
Because you're making a prototype,
and you're like, this is really cool.
But you don't really know, well, in six months,
will we be really, really tired of using
the same kind of rivets, the same kind of sci-fi bits
that we're using all the time?
So it's a little bit scary to commit to it,
because you don't know.
But I think it worked out well.
And it's also very easy to set rules, and it's very, very
boring to follow them.
If there's one thing I know, it's that everyone loves
making really, really smart systems, and then no one likes
to use them.
And it takes discipline, and it's not always fun.
Because sometimes you're like, I want to do this thing.
Like, well, I can't do exactly that thing.
And you're like, and they're like, no, I'm
going to abandon the pipeline.
It takes a lot of discipline to maintain
that throughout the entire project
and thinking of the big picture.
But if I would do all of this again, which, spoiler alert,
we are, because we're making another game,
we definitely underestimated the end result.
And I have a pie chart.
We focused a lot of the.
time on quantity instead of quality because in the end, you know, we instead of spending
like one month setting everything up and then just like three years just like we could have
spent you know maybe five months making sure the game actually looked a lot better and then
focus less on the quantity so that would probably made the game look better.
We also didn't apply the same kind of similar thinking that we did on the asset pipeline.
The asset pipeline was very, very thought out, but the rest of the pipeline was very reactive.
We were like, we're adding some stuff. Not enough, we're adding more stuff.
So we didn't really have the same kind of discipline.
So that's something that I hope that we can improve on.
That's it, and if you think this sounds very exciting and cool and you want to do that,
we are hiring for basically all positions and working on our next game, which is a next-gen
sci-fi slash cyberpunk immersive sim.
So thank you!
And please remember to leave feedback on the way out.
And questions?
Thank you. Could you talk a bit more about why you guys decided not to use skylights?
Or was there at least any HDR used? Because it looks like the light is very nicely filled and a lot of bounce light.
Basically a bit more about your lighting process and iterations and you know.
Basically we wanted to have a soft look to the lighting.
So that's why we had a very, very soft base pass.
And then we used the dynamic lighting,
like much more for spot lighting,
because it was like having the kind of camera distance
that we have, it doesn't really work nicely
to have like full screen light.
So it was very much divided up into smaller spotlights
for like, you know, shadows and, you know,
high fidelity lighting.
And then we had like a very, very,
like a strong base pass with the bake lighting.
And then we just abused the reflection probes like crazy.
Like instead of just having them by default,
we just cranked up the intensity
to whatever we felt looked good.
So it's like 100% not physically correct.
Thank you.
All right.