Thank you all for coming. I'm going to go ahead and jump right in.
This is a presentation about esports journalism.
The challenges we face as writers in that space
and the opportunities we're provided.
Hence, challenges and opportunities of esports journalism.
The second story part, I'll get to in a bit.
But I'd like to open with a quote from Paul Gallico, a legendary writer from the golden
age of sports journalism.
Daily, I was in contact with those necessary elements of drama.
Good against evil, suspense, frustration, climax, and success.
Every contest had its villain as well as its hero.
Nowadays, writing from the golden age of sports journalism can feel a little purple and maudlin
and theatrical.
But I think it's important to remember that Gallico and his ilk created the world of sports
journalism from almost nothing.
So over here in the fledgling years of esports journalism, we might want to see what we can
learn.
I'm going to go ahead and assume that the people in this room know that eSports is on
an uphill trajectory.
According to Newzoo, who you just heard from, one in four millennials now watches eSports.
22% of men and 15% of women watch eSports at least once a month.
That's between the ages of 21 and 35, specifically.
Among male millennials, eSports is now more popular than ice hockey and right underneath
baseball in terms of viewership.
More people watch the League of Legends World Championship in 2016 than the NBA Finals.
The point is, eSports is big.
And it's getting bigger.
It's not like writers up until now have sat on their hands exactly, waiting for the right
time to start covering eSports, but we do seem to be reaching a breaking point recently
where the platforms on which eSports are covered are ballooning seriously in size.
Early in 2016, ESPN, the Roman empire of traditional sports journalism, launched a dedicated eSports
section.
They did have some run up, like Mina Kheim's profile on Faker.
But still, for one of the largest sports journalism publications in the world, and one whose president
has gone on record as saying that eSports aren't real sports, to make this leap had
big implications.
Simultaneously, you could see traditional gaming sites start to pick up eSports as well.
PC Gamer has a ProTab now.
Rock Paper Shotgun has had an eSports section for a while.
Kotaku and Deadspin working together just released their compete vertical.
And even newer sites like Rolling Stone's Glixel have been covering major players like
Loda and Hungrybox right out of the gate.
We've also seen the arrival of a new kind of site enter the publishing landscape, the
developer-backed eSports site.
Which offers both official announcements while also profiling players and covering events.
All under the watchful eye of a PR department.
All these sites, an unprecedented spread, I think, when you have sport jockeys sharing
a web page with game writers, are grabbing over some piece of the eSports media landscape.
Which I would venture to say is still unclaimed.
Undoubtedly, they saw the opportunity to enter into a $490 million industry, or I think more
since I last checked.
But maybe this is being generous.
I think they probably saw something more.
A chance to shine a light on and find new language for a whole new realm in which narratives
of passion and excellence play out.
I can't speak to the challenges they faced in that pursuit, but I can offer some observations
on the obstacles I faced in my experience.
What that experience is, I'll fill you in on, but don't worry, it will be brief by necessity.
My name is Roy Graham.
I've been writing about video games since 2014, and that is not my dog.
In 2016, I was brought on as the editor of the meta, Kill Screen's dedicated site which
we launched in partnership with Twitch.
And that's it.
I did warn you it would be brief.
Which actually brings me nicely to my first point.
Those of you who are game writers are probably familiar with some portion of the internet
crowd not really getting the games thing.
But in the world of eSports, the divide between your informed audience and your casual audience
is probably broader than you've ever experienced before.
It's that divide that lets me, a guy with less than three years of post-college experience,
be on this stage right now, having opinions about an industry.
So what do the people on either side of this divide look like?
Well, let's start with eSports fans.
eSports fans are by and large vocal, devoted, and intensely knowledgeable about their past
time.
They're usually experts in one or two games which they play in addition to watching them,
meaning that their understanding of them is very deep.
This is one of the big difficulties we encounter writing about eSports, especially when you
have to write about more than one.
There will inevitably be someone who knows much more than you in your audience.
The history of the most popular eSports and their corresponding professional scenes is
not only complicated, it's nuanced.
And it is very poorly documented.
You can do your homework as a writer, but research can only take you so far.
And if you screw up...
It's very likely you're going to be called out, as I certainly have been.
But you don't even need to get the details wrong to stir the ire of devoted eSports fans.
Tone plays a major role in this, too.
How many times over the last few years have you seen a headline like this?
That'll win you some portion of the casual crowd, but it'll make anyone who actually
cares about eSports roll their eyes.
Mainstream writers tend to approach games with this intense level of apprehension, as
I'm sure a lot of you know, and this goes doubly for eSports.
You can blame that on our puritanical roots as a country or on gatekeeping among the highest
echelons of media writers, but it's something that we do have to confront as eSports writers.
ESports fans demand a lot from you as a writer.
But this audience is also the most passionate and in that way if you're writing about esports
in the first place, they're probably the most like you.
They'll debate the hell out of you.
Don't get me wrong.
Esports fans love to win.
But they'll also follow you into the strangest and best places.
Whether you're comparing the world of competitive smash to David Foster Wallace's tennis epic
talking about the architecture of Overwatch.
So what about on the other side of the chasm?
If you want to write for people who might lie outside the definition of eSports fans,
we run into a very different set of problems.
To start, most eSports have a big literacy requirement to understand what's happening
that you don't see as much in traditional sports.
In soccer or basketball?
If the ball goes in the hoop or the net, it's safe to say it's a point.
You don't really have to know a huge amount to follow what's going on.
Even in the more complicated sports like American football, there's a level of cultural literacy
that eSports just haven't managed to achieve yet.
I, for example, know what a first down is.
I cannot say who ever explained that to me or when it was explained to me, but that's
in there.
Our first challenge is just conveying how these games work quickly and painlessly, but
this is important, without being condescending to dedicated fans.
Second, and this is easier now than it used to be, we still have to convince some people
that these players are athletes.
For some, the amount of money and attention generated by the esports world has been enough.
They don't need more convincing.
But that isn't true across the board.
There's absolutely still a stigma against taking games seriously.
This stigma runs so deep that many esports players themselves, people who have dedicated
their lives up until now practicing, experience it.
I remember interviewing Marcus Dyrus Hill, the retired League of Legends player, for
Kill Screen last year.
Dyrus, for those of you unfamiliar, qualified for every world championship that happened
over the course of his career.
He's a legendary North American LCS player.
When I asked Dyrus why he found such success in the early years of competitive League of
Legends, his response was telling, particularly his choice of words.
He said it was because he was completely addicted to the game.
Addicted.
I'm willing to bet that if Dyrus had been a competitive athlete in a major sport, that
word probably would have been something closer to relentless or dedicated.
Because he was an esports player, though.
It was addicted. Can you imagine a championship fighter saying he was addicted to boxing? There's
that stigma, that notion that video games are in some way a waste of time, even when
you're better than 99.99% of an enormous selection of people. As big as the obstacles are, though,
with this audience, the opportunities are at the same scale. Simply put, there are far
more non-esports fans than there are esports fans.
Winning over even a portion of the ordinary sport audience or the traditional gaming audience
would do wonders for our reach.
At the end of the day, there's no easy way to bridge the gap between your informed readers
and your casual ones.
But that is something that publications will eventually have to do if they want to remain
financially viable.
For a moment, though, let's forget about the finances.
Let's pretend they don't matter.
Because outside of audience goals, outside of traffic numbers, we actually have a bigger
problem on our plate.
We have to figure out what the purpose of writing about eSports is.
And I don't mean a broad corporate purpose like connect with the youth.
I mean existentially.
Because while you can make a lot of comparisons between the world of sports journalism and
this burgeoning new world of esports journalism, you have to remember that they really came
about in entirely different ecosystems.
The original purpose of sports writing was simply to inform people about the outcome
of a game or more specifically about the outcome of a horse race.
Good sports writing did that vividly.
It brought to life something that distant fans might not be able to see.
Today, though, subreddits deliver the outcome of a game much faster than the sports page.
And as for feeling like you're part of the action, they can just watch a live stream.
Which brings me to my next point.
Another big function of sports journalism was to give access to the athletes.
To hear what they think and feel, what they're like, what they have to say.
Now, though, Twitch exists.
Esports fans already have access to most of their biggest heroes on a regular basis.
They can see what they're like when they're bored or anxious or in training or drunk or
whatever.
They can ask them questions.
They already have a more intimate window into their life than a reporter with a microphone
could ever provide.
So what do we bring to the table as journalists?
What can we offer the world of esports?
I'd like to quote here for the first, and you can hold me to this, last time in my life,
Malcolm Gladwell, who in a conversation with Bill Simmons on the Ringer, had something
pretty insightful to say about the world of sports journalism.
There is now a second conversation about baseball, the money ball conversation, that is interesting
even to people who don't follow the first conversation, the one that takes place on
the field.
Same thing for basketball.
There's an obsessive first conversation about a beautiful game and a great second conversation
about how basketball has become a mixed up culture of personality and celebrity.
Boxing had a wonderful second conversation in its glory years.
It was a metaphor of social mobility.
Jack Dempsey, one of the most popular boxers of all time, dropped out of school before
he even got to high school.
Joe Lewis' family got chased out of Alabama by the Ku Klux Klan.
That underlying narrative made what happened in the ring matter.
So what can we offer the world of esports journalism?
We could offer the same thing that great sports writers have always offered.
To start, that means keeping our perspective broad, not tunneling in on what happens in
the field, but making sure we understand the wider context in which all this is happening.
Second, we need to maintain a certain level of craftsmanship and pride in our work.
I've already noticed a fair bit of eSports writing start to slide into mindless hype-based
enthusiast press, and we're certainly not immune to the worst tendencies of sports writing
either.
Vagueness, recycled phrasing, a certain cloying quality.
We need to strive to remain great writers in addition to eSports experts.
And finally, we could use a bit of that myth making that Paul Gallico was doing almost
a hundred years ago.
Now as eSports rise in power, prominence, and popularity, I feel like we need this lens
more than ever before.
You can't talk about the world of competitive Smash without talking about this small, scrappy
community's fight for survival against the very developer that made the game they excel
at.
When fans in the audience of a major Call of Duty tournament shout racial slurs at an
African American player, that's not a random isolated incident.
That's part of a larger culture of intolerance surrounding the game.
Everybody knows that the best eSports players in the world come from South Korea, but fewer
people know that that's because of the Asian financial crisis in the 1990s, which led the
government to invest hugely in telecommunications and Internet infrastructure, leading eventually
to the PC bang.
When you just talk about scores and stats, you're missing a fundamental part of eSports.
Usually, it's the most human, powerful, and important part.
It's this underlying narrative, this second story, that we as eSports writers should try
and grab at.
Because it might give us a bit of purpose.
And it might be the thing which unites eSports fans with people who just want to read a good
story.
Stock Car Fanatics probably enjoyed Tom Wolfe's thorough profile of their hero, Junior Johnson.
But even if you don't know anything about stock cars, it's still a great read.
There's something about a young bootlegger becoming a star racer that's almost mythical.
And that's because the best sports writers, the ones we go back to over and over again,
knew a secret.
The best sports writing is only ever partially about the sport.
Look at Gay Talese's profile of Joe DiMaggio, one of the best pieces of sports writing ever
written.
Out of its 8,000 total words, it has perhaps a few paragraphs devoted to baseball.
It's a story about fame and the diminishing years of an American hero.
String theory, David Foster Wallace's second most famous piece of sports writing probably.
isn't really about his subject, Michael Joyce, it's about what becomes of the people who
are trained from a young age in something as frivolous and as difficult as tennis.
I contend we've done something similar with the very first feature we published on the
meta, Agony and Ecstasy at the Biggest Tournament Ever by the very talented Justin Groot.
Which isn't really about the international as much as it's about the fear and anxiety
that's accompanied the rise in eSports power and popularity among its fans.
Obviously, there's still a lot we need to figure out.
But that's the most exciting thing right now about being an eSports writer.
There are a few landmarks to go by.
But by and large, we're charting unknown territory.
If I could leave you with one thing, it would be this.
If you want to be the best sports writer in the world or the best music writer in the
world, good luck climbing that mountain.
But here is a vibrant culture full of human stories just waiting to be told.
And we're only now figuring out how to talk about it.
The best writing in the world of eSports is still waiting to be done.
So get out and do it.
Thank you for your time.
I'll be using however much time I have left to answer a few questions.
So feel free to come up to the microphone.
I'll ask a quick question.
So earlier you alluded to the existence of publisher-supported media outlets, like you
had LoL Esports in your deck.
I was curious, as someone coming from a more independent outlet than a publisher in your
case, how do you find the context of the meta's work?
being changed by the existence of publisher driven publications.
Because now whatever story you're trying to tell that involves a League of Legends player
is going to be in the same news ecosystem as a whole bunch of stuff that is created
by Riot Games to tell the story that they would want to tell about that player.
Sure.
Well, I mean, obviously that's a complicated question because I think a lot of the stuff
that we're seeing in terms of like developer backed esports sites versus like
more traditional publications, partially comes down to a ‑‑ I believe this to be sort
of a transitory period in some ways. You can see even with like the recent PEA scandal
which was sort of aping the NBA in terms of structure, which everyone ‑‑ I sort of
thought was an inevitable direction for e‑sports to go in. That fell through.
The shape that eSports will take in five years is hard to say in terms of traditional media
outlets versus developer-packed publications.
But I think a lot of it, at least for us in the moment, comes down to the tone and the
direction that we take the article and the sort of...
I guess where we put the focus.
Because at the end of the day, while eSports does some good stuff, they're fundamentally
a PR-backed organization that are trying to at the end of the day make Riot more money,
whether that comes from sponsors or from players purchasing in-game items or what have you.
Our divorced perspective from that.
And our focus on, you know, just at the end of the day telling a good story and telling
a true story, I think, will always set us aside.
I don't believe people read LoL eSports and the meta for the same purpose, in other words.
Yeah, go ahead.
So strange question here.
Would you consider eSports journalism an enthusiast press or traditional formal press?
I don't know if you can qualify the whole of eSports journalism as either of those things.
I think that there's certainly room for enthusiast press within the wider net of eSports journalism.
But there also needs to be a critical, sort of culturally thinking model like Grantland or Deadspin,
which is...
Less about like, eSports is so awesome, let's all hop on the eSports bandwagon, which, you
know, nothing wrong with that and it should exist.
But there also needs to be someone being like, it's ridiculous how many Totino's products
I see on a regular basis as an eSports writer.
Do you have to write about them too?
I sure do.
But I get to trash them in my writing.
There you go.
All right.
Thanks, man.
Of course.
Hey, great talk. Just talking about, you're alluding to the quality of eSports journalism currently.
Do you think, my question is, do you think more conformity in eSports as far as like the organizations and tournaments, would that help the journalism quality kind of persevere or is it just solely on the publications?
I think ultimately the onus has to be on the publications.
When you see ridiculous kind of shit shows like the Shanghai Major in Dota 2's not too
recent past, I think
At the end of the day, it's on the publications to write about that
in as much detail and with as much flourish as they can.
I wish I had read more elaborate 4,000-word takedowns of the Shanghai Major.
More like paintings of this terribly run event as Shakespearean tragedy.
Until eSports events shape up across the board in terms of production quality, I guess, is
what you're alluding to, I would just ‑‑ yeah, the quality of the writing on them has
no bearing on whether or not they were produced well, but the takedowns on them should be
even finer and more glorious now while we have the opportunity.
Hey, great talk by the way.
Thank you.
How do you think eSport journalists can help empower emerging new potential eSport with
much smaller community, for example, like Rocket League or Vainglory, perhaps through
the potential virality of the article they publish?
Right. I mean, this is definitely ‑‑ this is a tricky question because on one hand,
you do have to balance, like, traffic considerations when you're covering something, but, you know,
not every article has to be the thing that pulls in, like, a million likes.
I guess the short answer there would just be if they covered it.
If eSports journalists cover Rocket League, if they sort of find the dynamic firebrand
Towerfall player that wants to talk about how everyone else is trash and how she's going
to destroy the world, that's ‑‑ it's on ‑‑ yeah.
Just write about the stuff that you think is cool.
that you think maybe has the potential to be something bigger and better.
Yeah, and if the community shares your view, I guess they'll just follow and the game will grow.
Yeah, I think so.
Cool, thanks.
Of course.
I have sort of a two part question, I guess.
Yeah, sure.
I'd like to know a little bit how you think about, like,
the fact that some of these sports are incredibly controlled
by singular companies, and some of them do their best
to sort of control the entire experience
and don't really want anyone to come in
and be a real journalist about it.
And the other question is kind of,
how would you like...
eSports or companies that make games that are potential eSports to behave so that they can like encourage you to do
Your job as well as possible. Okay, I think I understand what you're what you're asking
So just just so I could repeat it back to you and make sure it's I have it, right?
How?
How do I wish companies?
Handled their their competitive scenes and their games
And how do they, how does the fact that these are sports that are controlled by essentially
one gigantic company factor into that?
Is that about right?
Well, I mean, obviously, I just, access is key to a lot of this.
I feel pretty confident that a journalist worth his or her salt can find the story,
even if it's sort of being bodyguarded by, like, a PR person who maybe doesn't want you
to get at a player's deepest, darkest secrets, as long as they just have the opportunity
to speak with the player.
As far as the question of one company sort of controlling a sport and trying to control
not only the rules of the game itself but also the experience of watching it, it just
makes covering it a very...
A very unique experience but I don't know if it's that much different than what the
NBA does with basketball.
You can talk about patch notes obviously change the game more in League of Legends than they
do in basketball but basketball still does get pretty regular small changes to the game
and there's obviously like the NBA and the NFL tried very, very hard to control every
moment of broadcast of a major game like that.
I hope that answers the question.
Thanks.
So being a person who plays Super Smash Bros. Melee and how the different scenes are, say
it's a legal version of Cell, so I'm very familiar with, I kind of find it interesting
that people always talk about the narrative, the players, the narrative, like the stories
and like ‑‑
So that would be the second story you'd be having.
But in a lot of situations, the only people you ever hear about in certain games are the people who are at the top,
the pinnacle, or in our case, the gods of the game, or maybe the top few teams, like the TSM, the C9, or whatever.
But you don't really see many people covering, say, EnVyUs or something like that.
In your opinion, is there a way to foster some sort of narrative, maybe like a smaller
scene or something like that, like maybe an up-and-coming player who hasn't really gotten
much exposure or anything and is starting to travel or something like that?
Yeah, absolutely.
I mean, I guess, I think this again comes down to the question of like, the journalist
has to find the story in the first place.
Actually, I remember we ran a profile also by Justin Greer on Axe, who is a great melee
player but is not usually considered a god, is not one of the top five.
The story just focused on the fact that he had played this game for years and years
basically without winning more than a couple hundred dollars at a tournament here and there
while holding down a job at CVS.
That's as much a second story as these sort of globetrotting rivalries
that you see in some of the major sports.
It's interesting, it's compelling, it's got a human element to it.
I think a lot of it is just that...
Players or reporters aren't always given the time or don't always elect to take the time
to chase down these kind of stories and find the, as you're saying, the sort of smaller
scale up and coming narratives.
And I guess one quick thing about that, so the Smash documentary is also a big thing
for Smash.
I was wondering if you had any opinions on where documentaries kind of sit in the idea
of I guess journalism.
It's somewhat.
I think.
A lot of the ideas that I tried to toss out in this talk can be applied to ‑‑ I said
writing a whole lot because that's my trade. But I think you can apply a lot of the same
ideas to documentary. Yeah. In terms of like the challenges of ‑‑ I think probably
it's easier in some ways to convey the ‑‑ just how the game works in a documentary form.
But you run into a lot of the same challenges. And I think that's a really good point.
like obstacles, I would imagine.
I haven't personally worked on any sports documentary,
so I can only theorize.
Thank you.
I just had a question of what you thought as far as casual games and casual gamers.
They don't self-identify as gamers often, but my aunt is on level 2185 of Candy Crush
and probably plays it more than I play any of the other games I play.
But she's like, I'm not a gamer.
Do you think there's space or are we close to where we would start writing about casual
Is there, is that, is there, is that eSport?
So if I, okay, can I repeat this question back to you to make sure I have it right?
It's kind of disconnected.
I think I know what you mean.
Do you mean that like, is any writing about a game that is played at professional caliber
considered eSports writing?
Or could it be?
Do we need to recategorize eSports writing and call it something else to be palatable
to the mom crowd, for example?
I think that's an interesting question.
Falling back on the idea of looking at sports journalism for some clues there, you don't
You don't see much writing about the casual side of football or baseball, for example.
But you have college games, which are certainly played at a lesser level than the major leagues.
Maybe that's where sort of more casual games could, or more casual levels of play, I suppose,
could see profit in.
eSports journalism is like more coverage of collegiate events as colleges start to pick
up eSports programs.
I think that maybe the secondary, the corollary question is like, for example, if we found
out that a 55-year-old woman had a Flappy Birds run of like 11,000 or something like
that.
So not played at a level, but literally someone who doesn't consider themselves part of the
eSports blanket.
It demonstrates an ability that would certainly warrant that in the top five game.
I think that at that point, it doesn't matter whether you identify as a gamer or not.
I mean, skill is skill, and that situation you described absolutely seems like something that esports writers should cover.
Thanks.
Of course.
It looks like that is all the questions.
So thank you guys.
Have a great rest of your GDC.