So this is Precision of Emotion, a new kind of fun approach.
So I like to do stupidly hard things.
And so this is my first game design talk.
And I have what I think is a new approach to defining
what fun is.
And there's a new word associated with it.
Both of these are stupid things to do in game design theory.
And I know what you're thinking.
It's like, oh god, another one.
And it's going to be another word.
Somebody shoot me.
But just stay with me, and we'll see if I
can defend this thesis.
So you all know Raph Koster's Theory of Fun, one of the great works on game design, right?
Everybody knows this?
Okay, good.
So Raph is over there, and he said,
that's what games are in the end.
Teachers, fun is just another word for learning.
So when I went to work at the Glass Lab, we thought,
well, holy cow, this is our chance.
We're making educational games.
Fun is learning. Therefore, this should be super easy.
And this is based on a lot of thinking from James Paul Gee's work, I hope you know as well.
Going all the way back to Lev Vygotsky, most known
for the flow state, or the zone of proximal development,
a.k.a.
what we all do in games.
And so if you dig deep into this,
you get Jesse Schell at the top, who says fun isn't important,
which I think is a valid thesis about game design.
Raph saying fun is learning.
Jim G saying fun is the scientific method.
And then Piaget, Fred Rogers, all the way down to Vygotsky,
play as a self-actualizing tool of the mind that maximizes
the zone of proximal development.
You can keep going all the way down, and you get down to neuroscience, which I'd like to get into, but that's a completely different talk.
She might be wondering who the heck I am.
So, I said I like to do stupidly hard things.
This graph I use to display why I kind of tend to jump around between subjects.
I like things that are really difficult before they've taken off.
As soon as they start to become financially successful, I flee.
So, two years ago I joined the Glass Lab, and this is one of the longest times I think I've been with a company, except for the very first company I was with.
We recently released Mars Generation 1, our Gubot Academy, which is set on Mars in collaboration with NASA and the National Writing Project.
An RPG Pokemon game with robots to teach argumentation
to middle schoolers.
And we recently released a finding study
on that that shows a great leap forward up
to a year of gain in argumentation
based on about three hours of play
and two hours of curriculum.
So we're really pleased with that.
Glass Lab, just to give you a bit more detail,
people tend to get very curious, was started in 2012
and was a three-year grant from the Bill and Melinda Gates
Foundation and the MacArthur Foundation
to create formative assessment-based learning
games.
We can talk a lot about that later,
but that's also another big topic.
So when GlassLab started, we were
given SimCity by Electronic Arts,
which was an amazing thing.
And we looked at SimCity and thought,
we can teach anything with SimCity.
There's so many things.
We can teach water systems.
We can teach civics.
We can teach argumentation.
Anything is possible within SimCity
because it is an innately learning-oriented product.
It's the thing that teachers think about when they think
about learning in games.
It'll be perfect.
And so then we put the game in front of kids all by itself
in a school setting.
And they said, well, this is pretty fun,
but we weren't learning anything.
So why are you wasting our time?
And it was really surprising to us
that kids in that particular setting
are hungry for learning.
There was a deep satisfaction and actually
a deep affective state that they went
into when they were learning that was not
what we were used to seeing from when they were playing games
and when they were having fun.
And so I realized fun is learning is the beginning.
It's not the end.
And there is so much more that we
have to learn about the learning process
and how it applies to fun, how it is distinctive emotionally
from fun.
And this affective state that kids went into
was incredibly fascinating to me.
I couldn't place it.
It was actually kind of a new state.
And you need really good teachers to create it,
or really good products to create it.
And I was talking to one of our learning designers
about how you might look at that affective state.
And I said, you know, has anybody ever tried
to identify a palette of universal emotions?
And he said, yeah.
There's a guy named Paul Ekman, who
did a study, probably one of the studies
that he's most well-known for.
He's actually the basis for the show Lie to Me,
where he was connecting emotional states
to facial expressions.
And he took a whole bunch of photographs
all over the world of people having different emotions
and asked people in all different countries
to identify what was going on.
And then they dropped all of this all the way down
and found seven universal emotions.
It was six initially, and then a seventh one was added.
So there's disgust, contempt, sadness, happiness, fear,
anger, and surprise, universal across all cultures
and all people.
But where's fun?
None of these seemed individually to be fun.
Some of them were sort of related,
like definitely sadness sometimes.
Like if you played Final Fantasy VII,
you would experience this terrible sadness.
Happiness seemed to be pretty close.
Surprise seemed really important,
but none of them individually seemed
to be hitting this thing that was fun.
And eventually what I realized was that fun wasn't one emotion.
It was a process between multiple emotions.
It was something that was arrived on,
or an affective state that was emergent out
of multiple emotions that actually
seemed to have a consistent sequence.
And that seemed really interesting.
So here comes the word.
I call it SOFIA, the Game Learn Emotion.
And I think it's the cognitive process by which we convert
fear into happiness through surprise.
So you can look at it as this transitional state where
initially you're fearful, and then you have this moment
of realization and delight, and then you feel super happy.
And this process actually deeply does
connect with a lot of the stuff that Lev Vygotsky said
and Piaget has said about what happens when kids play.
So I want to talk about microbes.
So how many microbes live in your body?
Are there biologists in the room or people who are bio nerds?
They might know.
Any guesses?
A lot.
How many lot?
A trillion?
All right.
You guys are ringers.
Yeah.
Actually, it's 100 trillion microbes per person.
They outnumber human cells 10 to 1.
You have 1,000 species of microbes in your gut alone
and 200 on the surface of your eye.
So you're disrupting a lot of them when you blink.
How do you guys feel?
How do you feel?
Creepy.
Creepy?
It's gross, right?
Blech.
Do not want.
Right?
So, if you think about the Milky Way, there's 100 billion stars in the galaxy.
Your body has 100 trillion microbes in it.
Biologists call this the microbiome.
And there have been recent studies, including this one,
that says this, Piper Hoffman, no relation,
red meat changes your gut bacteria to cause heart disease.
So basically, when you eat red meat,
if you're a meat eater,
you get this bloom of chemical in your body
that then is converted into stuff
that will eventually give you heart disease.
However, if you're a vegan and you eat a steak,
doesn't happen.
So biologists noticed this and they said,
dude, what is going on?
And it turns out there's a gut bacteria
that releases that bloom.
And they think now that that might
be what causes heart disease.
So if you kind of oscillate back and forth
between eating meat and not eating meat,
you probably could avoid heart disease.
So there's really interesting things
that are now just being discovered
out of what's called the second genome.
This biome that's inside of us is really more
like a coral reef and is 10 to one,
more than we are in our human cells ourselves.
Oh, I'm missing a slide.
Sadness.
How do you feel now?
Good.
Thumbs up.
Right?
Better.
Yeah.
Man, I got a grip on it.
It's a super weird thing, and I understand it now.
And again, that's what I think SOFIA is.
I think it's the process by which you confront
this creepiness and this, oh, man, something foreign.
Go, go away.
I don't want it.
And then you realize, wait a minute,
I'm starting to get a grip on this.
And then you say, oh, now I know more about the world.
My slide was out of order.
Sorry about that.
So games, some games have more Sophia than others,
which is interesting.
And I think these are the games that we
tend to think about as either smart fun or learning fun games.
And if we kind of put them all together and look at them,
I think partly what we see is that they
have some sort of connection to the real world.
There's some kind of exploration that's going on
and some kind of discovery.
And you're creating order out of chaos.
And then when you have that ordered state
that you've created in the world,
you have this deep satisfaction about yourself.
You feel mastery.
You feel understanding.
you feel actually like you have a bit more of a grip on your life.
And by the way, these feelings might
be missing from formal education today,
which might be part of why there's so much effort
to bring games into education.
So at Glass Lab, we talk about meaningful games.
And I gave a keynote at Meaningful Play.
I think Casey might be here somewhere.
When we talk about a meaningful game,
we draw a distinction between a game that
connects to the real world and a game that does not
connect to the real world.
So Candy Crush is a great game.
I played a lot of Candy Crush.
It's very engaging, and it has a certain kind of satisfaction
because it is so completely disconnected
from the real world.
It's an escape.
But it's not sticky.
I'm not sure I'm going to remember
that I played Candy Crush a lot five or 10 years from now.
However, Journey I will remember forever,
because the systems inside of Journey changed me.
And I think about my relationship
to eternal recurrence and the rest of the world
differently now that I've finished playing Journey.
So I think that's an important distinction
to make within games, not in terms of quality,
but in terms of the effect that it's having on the player.
And if some games have more Sophia than others,
it got me thinking about how can we actually
categorize games differently than just
according to their mechanics.
I think that if you look at games
as a comparison between the core emotion
that the game itself is evoking, you
start to get a really interesting hierarchy.
And I would like to see the rest of this built out.
There's the fear genre of Silent Hill.
and amnesia that just makes you feel afraid in so many ways
and has you confront all of these horror concepts.
There's the together genre, which
you can see this kind of esoteric collection of games
that really evoke this emotion of togetherness
and knowing other people and knowing how human beings work.
And then there's, I think, a relatively new,
or there's some old games, but these games
are becoming bigger, the complicity genre with Papers,
Please and Sweatshop in it, which
is my favorite new genre that actually
has this very complex emotion of.
initial engagement, and then mastery over a system,
and then, shit, what have I done?
This is a very complex emotion, really fascinating.
But within all of those genres, because Sophia
is the game emotion, there's Sophia in all of them.
So you can take two games, like God of War and Animal Crossing.
In God of War, you're going to discover controls.
It has this really elegant tutorial system
that leads you to think that you are achieving your own mastery
over these controls.
that are eventually going to make you feel extremely powerful
once you have them.
In Animal Crossing, even though it's a completely open sandbox
game with all of the emergent narrative very whimsical,
it has this fish loop in it and many other loops,
such as digging up fossils, that give you
a mastery sense that make you feel very grounded and mastered
in that world.
So, and I think in both of these games, you're still finding the fear in God of War getting
destroyed.
And then you're getting surprised and delighted, and eventually you're reaching happiness because
you have this feeling of mastery.
So Sophia is the process, and it drives the core.
The feelings of mastery in God of War create fear.
They create dominance.
Feelings of mastery in Animal Crossing create a sense of togetherness, a feeling of understanding
people and being connected to them.
Oops, so when we follow this down,
I just gave that away completely.
That sucked.
OK, I was going to see if you could
identify these games based on their loops themselves.
Let's take, I guess, the one on it's my left.
I'm not sure if it's your left.
Aim, shoot, and watch.
Anybody who did not see the slide want to guess.
No, it's too much anyway.
So these two loops, I think, are very interesting
because you can take the individual mechanics that
form their core loop and bring them back together
to create a core emotion.
Now, in the case of Angry Birds on the left,
the dissonance between these core mechanics
creates this wackiness in combination
with destruction that gives the game an extremely unique feel.
However, the World of Warcraft loop
creates something that's this fantasy adventure power feeling
that's a very widely and deeply explored
genre in games in general.
So you could apply the World of Warcraft loop
to all kinds of different games.
What unifies them is their core emotion.
But that core emotion emerges from
the individual mechanical connections
between the verbs that form the heart of the game.
So when we're making learning games,
and I think it's very integral to why all of these thoughts
emerge from the process of making learning games,
we have an effect we want to achieve,
which is that the player at the end
should actually be able to perform something
that prior to playing the game they could not perform.
It's very specific.
But it is not effective.
Mostly, it's not emotional, not unless you force it to be.
So, when we thought about how could we make this into an actual great game,
instead of something that's just very performance-based,
and a lot of the sort of educational games that we think of as not being...
When we say they're not games, there's a lot of things that we're saying,
but partly I think what we're saying is that they're not very emotional,
and they're not creating an emotional effect.
So when we thought about argumentation...
we thought about what progression of emotions
do we want to have that would make you feel
as though you had mastery over this competency.
It's a little bit tricky because there's a lot we have to do
to achieve the actual effect of increasing
your argumentation competency,
but I think there's an emotional progression
we have to take the player through too if we're doing well,
which is to say, here's the feeling of mastery
over this particular competency
that's really more in a guitar hero space.
Guitar hero is not gonna make you better at playing guitar,
but you will feel like you're better at playing guitar.
And that's very motivating, right?
It makes you think, I want that thing.
And emotions, it turns out, can be pretty complicated.
I think our approach in what we're
trying to do with these games is actually ultimately
to alleviate suffering.
If you look at Sophia Loop, that fear
is already existing inside of a person.
They just kind of don't know that it's there.
If you have an absence in your world model,
you actually are going to be feeling
bad things about that absence.
If we can identify what that is, then we
can create a context by which we can tell a player,
here's why you want to do this thing.
For the most part, in games that are pure entertainment games,
we don't have to say why you should do something.
I don't need a why for why I'm going to kill the dragon.
I'm going to kill the dragon because the dragon is there.
And that's a lot harder when you're
talking about Pascal's triangle or the quadratic equation.
And the thing is, what if Pascal's triangle is actually
way more important than killing the dragon?
You have a problem.
You have to actually articulate the why.
So the why for us with argumentation was,
If you don't have argumentation, you're a little bit helpless
in the world of people.
You're socially not effective.
You can't persuade people that what you think is important.
You're confused.
You can't articulate the things that are important to you.
So if we could reverse this and address
the pain of absence of argumentation,
we would create something that makes clarity and structure,
wittiness, and that you have this compelling effect
on the people around you because you're so persuasive
and that persuasion is grounded in reason and logic.
So the theory of this is nice, but what do we do with it?
I think that Sophia is a lens through which
we can view games.
I think that we can identify lots of problems
that emerge from the absence of this process
being clearly articulated.
This is sort of adjacent to ideas about
ludonarrative dissonance, if the performance of something
is different than the narrative that is given to the player.
It's more abstract to say, what if your core emotion is either
not what you intend it to be or is out of alignment
with itself?
What if the core verbs that you're asking a player
to perform over and over don't create the emotion
that you hope that you want players to achieve?
I've seen a lot of games and a lot of processes of games
where we don't even really think about how do we want
the player to feel at the end.
Or how we want the player to feel at the end
is.
good, or having fun, or engaged,
and not something very precise,
which has to do with the absence of the game
before the presence of it and how it changes you.
I think a lot of times there can be not enough surprise
preceding satisfaction.
This is a particular problem inside of educational games
where you can guide a player through something,
actually it's in social games too,
but if you don't allow them to discover for themselves
what is supposed to happen next,
the experience feels very flat.
If you don't clearly illuminate the fear and the why,
you can also have a lack of tension in the game,
a lack of reason to play that ultimately manifests
as lost retention.
And by the way, all of these things together
are the same problems you would have
if you were trying to teach someone something.
So I wanted to leave some time for Q and A
because this is a very prototype idea
and I'm hoping to get some help with it.
So I think that's where we are.
Oh, hi Erin, great talk.
Edwin McCray, narrative designer.
I was wanting to know how important you feel
story and narrative is in the,
creating the, sort of, Sophia process.
That's a really interesting and difficult question.
I think, you know, it's funny, when I came to Glass Lab,
I believed very strongly that it should be
all about the mechanics, and that if we leaned on story,
we were going to be, it would be because
we had an absence in our mechanics.
And I came to realize through watching a lot of kids play
that human beings learn through story.
It's how we learn everything.
And so to leave that behind and to resist it was very foolish.
I think it's incredibly important,
and I think it falls into that ludonarrative dissonance
place, where you want the narrative to be serving
the performance of the game.
You can't not have that performance and mechanic
present, but you also can't have the story absent either.
Thank you.
Thanks, Lee.
Okay, no other questions. I guess that's it.
Oh, no.
I don't know what my question is yet, but I know that I have a question.
So, let me try to struggle through this.
Um, sorry.
So, you're talking a lot about emotions in games, and I'm trying to identify for myself with the themes I'm experiencing here at GDC,
one of which is the threat of, like,
Should we as game designers be starting to look at emotions other than the emotions that we are
sort of using as a crutch for the majority of games that we're working on?
We should probably fall into the Fiero genre a lot.
And then I remembered from the Microtalks of the...
Oh, I have the notes right here. I swear.
Take your time, we've got a few minutes.
The microtalk on interpersonal...
Somebody help me out.
The person was talking about specifically,
for example, in games like Shadow of the Colossus,
where you feel a connection to an NPC that is
sort of beyond the connection that you would have to a normal...
Yeah, Matt Fock, interpersonal subjectivity, but there is also Kara Ellison's intersubjectivity,
the moment when a feeling is shared between characters, such as an out of this world,
when the alien sort of boops you on the nose.
I wondered what, basically my question is, what you think the Sophia sort of definition
and how it interacts with moments like that.
I'm not sure, not having seen the talk, it's tricky.
So do you mean specifically emotional exchanges
that are happening between other characters,
or between the player character, or breaking the fourth wall?
So there was one quote from Kara where she's talking specifically about how games that have intersubjectivity
have moments when you realize the designer thinks of you as human.
Ah, okay.
Yeah. Hopefully that helps. Again, I'm just trying to sort of...
It does. I mean, I think that's a very complex thing that's happening where you're having this authorial relationship.
So, um...
I think it's one of many moments in games
that we seem to be having more often,
like with games like The Stanley Parable, where we're reflecting
back on what the game is doing itself,
and then pulling back and breaking the fourth wall
on that and saying, let's think about that
as a relationship between.
human beings. How Sophia interacts with that is an interesting question. I probably would have to think more about it.
But basically I think Sophia is what's going on in the game and what you're experiencing, which is going to create this kind of an immediate
affective layer, and then you're reversing that. So it's a, you could call it a narrative technique.
where you're saying, I'm going to trick you
into doing these things.
Papers, Please does this, too.
If you get into the flow of the performance of Papers, Please,
you have one emotional layer.
And then you have another layer on top of that that
is actually running against it.
So what you have in the net is this complex interaction
between multiple layers of emotion.
OK.
Thanks.
So in the description, it said that this model was
around taking stress to happiness.
But in the presentation, it said taking fear into happiness.
So I'm not asking for my money back.
I'm just curious.
I'm just curious, why the distinction?
And why did you choose fear specifically as opposed
to stress?
Yeah, that's an interesting question.
I'm going to actually run back to the diagram of that.
Because I actually think that when we say fear,
we mean a whole lot of things.
And there are many layers within fear itself, anxiety and worry and frustration.
And I think, you know, I was talking, is Mark here?
I don't know if he's, yes, there he is.
I was talking to Mark about this,
and he's my great cognitive science devil's advocate person,
and he was saying, this seems like a bad feeling.
Why would you wanna create a bad feeling?
And I think the lowest level of fear is actually curiosity.
So I think there are many gradations
of these major emotions
that create different subtle affects.
And I would say that stress is probably
in that anxiety-fear space.
It just isn't as archetypal, because eventually,
if you get all the way up to fear,
it's something that's very clear.
And you could argue that by the time you're creating fear,
you've gone too far,
probably especially in a commercial game,
unless you're actually deliberately creating fear.
It's a good question, though.
Oh no, it's Nicole.
I think he was...
Yeah, go ahead.
Oh, sorry.
I didn't even see you guys.
So a lot of these emotional loops that I've seen
have some model of feeding back into themselves.
I'm aware that for a specific interaction in the game,
someone could go through the entire Sophia loop
you have on the slides right there and receive some insight.
But they're still playing the game.
So could you elaborate on how it could cycle back into itself,
what the player still wants, craves,
after receiving some insight?
Sure.
That's a really good point.
I mean, I think I use the gear icon here deliberately
because I think that effective games are
these interconnected gears.
So there are many Sophia loops that
are going to move between each other.
Often in a complex interconnected game
that has one experience, the gears
are going to touch each other.
But in a lot of experiences, Animal Crossing is one of them.
They can be completely separate.
You can actually do what you can do,
nothing but fossil hunting in Animal Crossing.
Or you could do nothing but fishing.
And it's the choice between what you do that makes
the experience interesting.
So there are lots and lots of these loops.
There should be probably one arc,
which is why we look at a core loop,
just to keep focus.
But that's almost more of a production tool
than it is design.
Does that make sense?
Yes, thank you.
Great.
Wonderful talk.
I love this model.
And I think, Fiero.
That's super high praise.
I really appreciate that.
Thank you.
So Nicole Lazaro from Zio Design.
Invented Fiero, for those who are wondering.
Yeah.
And so the relationship between emotion and action
is really key.
And I love what you're doing with the idea
of emotional progression, that there being
a core emotion to a game.
And I was just curious.
This opens up a lot of, it's a really great way,
we think of things a lot at Zio in these gear type
looping fashions.
So awesome.
What do you think the future, I just wanted to ask you about,
what new kinds of things could you use this model to build, do you think?
What's the next step?
That's an excellent question.
Actually, can I turn it around on you?
Can I say, what do you think?
Well, maybe you should come next year.
We'll see you next year?
All right.
Yeah, well what I think you can do is you can, obviously you can deconstruct.
We could simply deconstruct the genres, which you've already done.
We've done a lot of really interesting work going into Netflix and deconstructing the emotional profiles,
the emotion profiles of, you know, different genre.
So comedy is made out of, you know, a couple core emotions, which is great.
I think that just having the intent,
creating an emotion profile, so imagine that gear,
you can maybe, with labeling it with various emotions,
with your motion profile, and then running that gear
kind of like a four-wheel drive or something,
put a couple of those gears onto a little truck
and then drive it over the terrain of your game,
and swap out those gears, you know, as a way of thing.
So I think that that would be an interesting way
to model something in the future.
And just in general, if we have intentional emotional outcomes
from our mechanics, I think that's going to be a really
great thing.
So maybe I'll talk a little bit about it next year.
I was just curious.
That would be awesome.
I think you're right.
I think near term, where this has been useful to me
is where it intersects with learning.
where it intersects with analyzing games
and what they need, especially when you're about
midway through and you're kind of not sure
what it's going to be.
It's just a way of focusing yourself.
But ultimately, from what you're saying,
I think you can look at the application
of the gear model itself as varying
depending on the core emotion,
and then leading to suggestions of new mechanics,
potentially, or even new types of emotion.
It's almost like a kaleidoscope,
like depending on which direction
the gear is turned, I suppose.
Exactly.
And then if I could just add on what you're saying,
with a loop and with a gear, the reason why it's a gear
is it's a circle.
And one of the ways that we find when
we consult on game projects in our client business
is that those loops are often broken.
So we get good curiosity to get you in,
some challenge to get you over the hump with the success.
And then we get really weak feedback,
and it doesn't feel like you've won.
And that's important in learning games especially,
because the winning in learning games
is that I'm learning something.
And so being able to close that loop.
Cool.
Thank you so much.
Great talk.
I love it.
Thank you.
Hi, one of the things that I have been,
recently I've been doing a lot of stuff
with middle schoolers and high schoolers,
and I have been noticing that this particular group
is hypersensitive to feeling disrespected by the designer.
Oh yeah, so much.
Fairness, it's not fair.
And it feels like there's something,
it's not even just fairness,
it's like if you don't respect my ability
to understand the nuances of this story, I'm done.
And yet we tend to very strongly as designers...
do that a lot. Like we feel like we have to lay out every breadcrumb for them. And I feel
like that is very closely connected to this in some way. It's almost like they can't even
get to the point where they're feeling the fear or the stress if they don't feel that
respect and if they, like they start to disrespect the designer or the game and they can't take
that first step. And then everything from there is downhill. And I'm wondering if you
have any thoughts about that or ways to sort of
as designers to bust through our own fear that they won't understand the more complex
nuances of what we're trying to bring to them?
Yeah, absolutely.
I mean, I think the answer is Minecraft, right?
As the answer to all things for middle schoolers is Minecraft.
Minecraft throws them in and shows them nothing.
It is hard.
It is broken.
It is like when we look at that from a UX standpoint, we go, what is going on in this
game?
And yet the middle schoolers love it.
because they're deeply hungry.
I think it's about understanding the emotional state
of your player.
And we try and do this a lot at Glass Lab,
is really put ourselves in the state
where this very complex thing is going on, where kids are
becoming socially aware, overwhelmed by the world,
but aware of it, beginning to challenge authority.
So you build this model of your student,
and you get it's completely predictable that that's
how they would react.
And yet you have the contrast of all
of these breadcrumby, hand-holdy tutorial experiences.
And I wonder why they're bored and they don't play them.
So I think it's partly.
that very tricky dynamic between building for scale, which then
means you're going for a lowest common denominator, which
means you're over the head of most of them,
versus throwing them in by themselves.
We are actually at, thank you so much,
by the way, for that question.
And middle schoolers are the best players.
I think we have to go to the wrap up room,
because we're at 12 o'clock right now.
But I will go next door to 2002 for anybody
who wants to continue talking.
Sorry, Link.