Great, thank you very much.
It's lovely to be here at the AI Summit.
I'm really thrilled and honored.
And the opportunity, I'd love the opportunity
to sort of expand the conversation
to some new areas that we've been thinking about
really deeply at our studio at Xeo Design.
within the realm of what player experiences are
and how computers can create richer and deeper emotions.
So we're gonna talk today about Red Pill,
Red Pill, Blue Pill, Narrative AI for Deeper Emotions.
And in it we're taking,
we're gonna leverage some experiences that I've had
and you also have had,
in one of the most emotional medium we have,
which is of course cinema.
So I'm one of the leading experts on emotion in games.
And I have a model called the Four Keys to Fun, which I
used, I basically measured emotion on people's faces
while they played.
And I created a model about what kinds of actions players
did to create different emotions.
So from that perspective is what we're going to do today.
I've also studied psychology at Stanford and a little bit
of filmmaking.
The Four Keys has been used to inspire the AI for the Sims.
We brought Wonder to Myst.
We actually created some AR and VR UI for iFluence
and did Star Wars on Star Wars games.
And the Four Keys is actually going
beyond the realm of games in a sense
that this model of how action and emotion interact.
I don't work with everyone from Samantha Bee to Ted,
IBM Watson, the semantic analysis,
sentiment analysis on IBM Watson is inspired by my work.
And then we're doing stuff on emotion,
a lot of emotion in XR and VR.
So we're gonna talk a little tiny, tiny bit about that.
Because I think that on the computer side,
AI plays a key role in some of these newer game platforms,
especially with AR.
This is a montage from one of the games I'm working on
called Aladdin's Cave of Wonder.
We're doing it on Magic Leap.
So a combination of real-world item recognition
and being able to recognize your hand gestures
is gonna create a much deeper experience.
for players, but not out of the box.
We really have to understand what emotion is
and how it gets done.
So this is the Four Keys to Fun.
You can download it on our website.
There's some white papers and other talks.
We're gonna go into not so much the four keys,
but how it applies to AI.
We're in the process of a many year journey
of developing in our studio an emotion engine,
we like to call it.
It's a way of creating emotions from the actions in games.
A few quick things on emotion.
The first thing is that in games, best-selling games,
people's favorite games, that mechanics tend to fall into
nested loops.
Here are four of them.
There is a micro loop, a core loop, a meta loop, and a social
re-engagement loop.
and that emotion and cognition are intertwined.
So that may not necessarily be represented
in your AI implementation,
but we need to know on the wetware,
they definitely coexist.
Sense making and emotions are the same.
Actions and feeling are also related,
and so if we ignore the player action
as a vital agent in our AI systems,
then we are ignoring a lot of what they feel.
And so interaction, in a sense, designs emotion.
as well as art and acting and other things that you may have already built AI systems
around.
Now, just like birds and planes, they both fly, but they fly differently.
Same thing is true with games.
Both movies create emotion and games create emotion.
But they also have different mechanics, different ways of going about it.
Now, when we start any genre, any new genre often leverages the old genre.
So we have a lot to learn from film, but we also want to take and, you know, scrape away
the stuff that maybe we don't need.
So this is some scenes from Detroit, which has got an amazing narrative design for the
characters, the three main characters especially.
But there are 3,000 pages of shooting script, which took two and a half years to shoot,
which is way beyond the production length of most feature films.
And we've got a very labor intensive branching narrative
that you have to design by hand, construct by hand
to create the compelling character
arcs and other things.
So in thinking for this talk, what I wanted to do
was look at, well, what could we do
instead of branching narrative?
How could we apply other systems to the core of the game?
So narrative is what, interactive narrative
is what got me into games 26 years ago.
And it's still what keeps me coming back.
So what would that narrative AI look like?
Well, some simple, very simple AI systems
that we already have that increases engagement.
So the rubber banding that in Mario Kart
keeps it engaging even if you're working with an NPC
or if you're playing with your friends.
But then let's say we do,
but AI, modern AI has done some really interesting things.
And I stopped for inspiration.
Here's where my sort of talk begins.
If we think about the fake faces,
how many people have seen this video?
Yeah, not too many?
OK.
So there are three layers to the generative adversarial
networks.
There are three layers.
And what they're able to do is they're
able to create real looking faces that actually
don't exist.
So there are different features that they are leveraging
at the three layers.
And then they can apply this also technique to other things
to create believable styles.
So on the right, you have hotel rooms that don't exist
and on the left, cars that don't exist.
So what might this mean in terms of gameplay?
Might we be able to create AI systems
that actually designed game mechanics for us
or created more robust things for us?
Well, I think that we wanna look at it
like a peanut butter cup.
I like chocolate, I don't know about you, but.
You know, there's a center of game, which I think is still going to be the game mechanic,
but as a first step, we could probably design the chocolate coating.
We could probably design a layer of AI, of narrative AI, surrounding the core experience
that expands the emotional palette, the emotion architecture, the ebb and flow of the emotions
in the player.
So, but here's a few more things to do that.
The first is that in cognition and emotion, there's really, you know, threat of life is
just one way of generating emotion.
It just generates one emotion.
And the other thing is that in the neocortex and the lizard brain,
the neocortex is where we take action,
whereas the lizard brain, your emotion centers are deeper down.
You make decisions in the forebrain.
You feel the result of them in your inner brain, your older brain.
And so it is the interaction between the key
to creating emotions for people,
is the key is really making those choices.
So going from between those two parts of your brain,
back and forth, and how you feel before, during, and after.
So when we're designing a narrative AI,
we wanna think about that whole sequence
if we wanna think about the problem
as a whole from the top down.
So in a game, what we have is a dungeon master, an NPC,
choices that we make, items in the world, and players.
Might all five of these be a inspiration or a layer
or a set of layers inside an AI system?
for designing game mechanics?
And I think they can.
And if we wanted to approach an AI-driven game mechanic,
AI narrative, we'd want to think about layered AI.
And where the player experience,
because the player experience comes
from these multiple layers as they move through,
I think that the AI coordinating the effect
of these different levels of AI is super essential
for creating intense emotional responses on the player.
So as a model for this, we might take the four keys,
for example, because it's a reliable way
of creating emotion through mechanics,
and look at the different types of fun.
So you might have easy fun,
I call it the bubble wrap of game design,
just running around the world.
You know, it's curiosity, wonder, and surprise,
emotion-driven.
You might have the hard fun,
which is usually your core mechanic,
the frustration that leads to Fiero,
the feeling of winning.
You might also have people fun, which is a social interaction.
Amusement naches, schadenfreude, the social interactions which make games a lot more fun.
It's a game to play on the couch, not so much on the screen on a console game.
And then of course serious fun.
Well, it's like people going up to Fortnite and they're not there to play the game, they're
just there to hang out.
The Fortnite is the shopping mall of the current generation.
So serious fun.
You know, creating the desire to acquire,
the zen-like focus, it makes winning
feel more winning. It also makes the game
feel less like a waste of time.
So they're all great game mechanics, and again,
you can find out more about the four keys
elsewhere. But for today, I really want to focus
us back on AI.
So for the AI, what we've got is we want to look at an AI system, AI layers, that might
generate or provide the opportunity to generate these different emotion sets.
And I should say another thing about emotion is we can't actually generate an emotion specifically.
I can't just, you know, hey, here's an emotion.
But as a game designer, I could give you a little lever and say, hey, you know, as a
game designer, I say, like, hey, pull this lever and you might feel something.
And so that's what we mean.
So the AI could dynamically offer choices,
offer opportunities to interact in a way over time
that then could be orchestrated along several layers
to hit a number of different emotional responses.
And then to do that, many AI approaches now
might focus on the meta, like the Dungeon Master,
might focus just on NPC, believable NPCs,
might just focus on inter-player collaboration.
But what we want is we want each layer of the AI
to work together.
And it kind of, my vision of this,
and obviously this is not code,
but my vision is like if you have the player
and they're very emotional,
they're going down the path, right?
And it encounters your AI system,
and then that has multiple layers,
which have different emotional responses,
potential for different emotional responses
coming from those layers.
It senses that the player is nearby and also the emotional state of the player,
and in context, moves its opportunity for emotions more towards a certain direction
that might be compatible with what the player is feeling.
The player feels that way.
And then a second AI might come in to that
and then add an additional emotion
as the player moves through.
So the player moves through,
they might encounter another item,
have an emotional response to that,
and then an AI could come in,
the AI layer could come in
and maybe offer different opportunities
for different emotions,
or perhaps redirect from the candlestick
in our murder mystery, AR murder mystery,
to maybe the tennis shoe,
which is the actual clue.
And that could result in the player being more emotional
or more happy.
So these four patterns for layered AI
is what I'd like to finish the talk with.
And so we're going to look at some films
and talk about these different frameworks.
The first one is a frame.
We're going to talk about making choices,
sort of onions and layering and arcs, character arcs,
as well as the opportunity to create emotion from items.
So we'll talk about frames.
I don't know how many people have really thought about
this, but I thought there's a remarkable familiarity or
similarity between Hunger Games and Fortnite.
And so what's interesting is that with the Hunger Games,
there's actually a framework, if you know Minsky's frames.
That frame of the movie actually tells you how to
feel about the game.
So if you had an AI that was filled with a number of different frames of encounters,
you could predict the emotional response of what the player was going to feel, and dynamically
change within that frame, within that paradigm, how the player feels.
This is, in a very simple sense, the revenge mechanic for Clash of Clans and, of course,
the Super Bowl commercial.
Another game that has a very strong frame is Beat Saber.
How many people have played Beat Saber?
And so you go in, you have lightsabers and boxes.
You know exactly what to do because you've seen
Star Wars episode five.
The scene with Vader and Luke Skywalker.
And then you might come to mind other things.
But that tells you how to feel.
So a framework can add emotion to this.
And if your AI is dynamically exchanging frames, then you
could actually create emotion over time, which is, in a
sense, narrative.
The second one is of course choice,
which is what I named the talk after.
Red pill, blue pill.
And the interesting thing about this
is it's not just about a choice,
like A or B in a branching narrative.
But if you think about what red pill
and blue pill really means,
it's this really represents values, right?
What are your core values?
And the red pill is of course harsh truth
and the blue pill is the convenient fantasy.
What about these decisions and what about these values
could be mixed at?
So there could be a whole layer of AI
looking at the emotional values and worldviews about,
maybe, how you see the world.
Or even your capabilities could go in
to make a much richer type of choice.
Another film, Sophie's Choice, is named after the very gut-wrenching scene where she has
to choose between one of her two children.
Spoiler there, my apologies.
But it basically then affects everything that you do thereafter.
You might think of this as just, you know, you design that, you could design that as a branching
narrative, but what if an AI had that ability to provide you with a series of these choices
dynamically as the game went through? So my murder mystery, my AR murder mystery,
could have quite a different playthrough time and time again.
The character's choice affects the past, the present,
and their future.
There's a mystery in the player's mind
about the connections with these kinds of choices.
And there's implied emotion around the events.
Those would all be key traits to bake into the AI.
And you could provide different perspectives,
like who you play might change how
you feel about that particular event,
if you played a different role.
And then speaking of characters, we go to the onion.
And we've got different types of choices that are revealed.
So this is a way out of the branching narrative.
I first thought of it when I worked on the Myst series.
I worked on three of the Myst games back in the day.
And they have a lovely device, especially in the first one
of a book, where the characters are gradually revealed,
page after page.
And you have two brothers that you don't end up not wanting.
At least I don't want to help either of them,
but you want to finish the game.
So they create tension that way.
The players are just, those characters are pre-baked.
You're just deciding by how much you help each one,
how much you learn about them, and then of course,
how much power they have in the world.
Schindler's List has a character arc.
Have people watched Schindler's List?
How many people have watched?
Okay, okay, good.
How many people watched Sophie's Choice?
Anyone seen Choice?
Okay, not as many.
All right, Schindler's List then.
Yeah, so for Schindler's List,
what's interesting about him is he is part of the Nazi party
at the beginning of the film,
and then he arcs from that state
to becoming, to hiring out, you know,
a thousand, rescuing a thousand Jews
from the concentration camps to work in his factory.
So he arcs as a character, which makes the film interesting.
Crouching Tiger's Hidden Dragon also has two character arcs,
and they're counter to each other.
And so the character details revealed gradually over time
like an onion, and that their moral and their values
and their goals are at cross purposes,
which makes it quite an interesting,
much more interesting kind of journey
for the two characters.
And then in terms of AI, there would be the character design,
but then also the action and environment
could be reflect that.
So this is a piece of a fighting scene.
where again, these characters are arcing.
The two women are arcing in different directions
than the guy is.
And so you see that in the environment,
it's actually, there is a bit of verbal,
I mean, a visual play on what the characters
are actually doing.
So what kind of an AI system can generate that?
Creating conflict and adversaries is a very crucial role
for an AI as well.
And Killmonger, and this is Black Panther,
Killmonger and Nakia, if you think about it
from a narrative design perspective,
they're actually the same, they have the same goals, right?
They just have different methods
and they've taken them to different extremes.
I love this quote by Joe Robert Cole,
who's the screenwriter.
And he says, I think the best villains
have a point of view that's relatable
that you can empathize with.
Right, and that's how he built the character for Killmonger.
And then it can also, but it's not necessarily,
you share their perspective,
but you don't exactly agree with it.
If we go deeper into like an AI for character interaction,
also the relationships are key.
This is another scene from Black Panther.
I would love to see an AI do this, create this on the fly.
Ah!
So there's an understanding of humor, there's an understanding of the relationships of the
different characters, there's a, you know, and then how they all relate.
That would be a really amazing experience.
So the relationships affect the outcome of that battle in a very strong way.
So lastly, I wanted to talk about items.
And items can have an emotion profile,
and they can be built into what we call an emotion
architecture, which is the actions, the whole structure
of the way in which we interact, just
like your interactive architecture for your game.
You might be able to express that with the choices
that you offer a player.
So here the Black Panther is being offered
two different high-tech new Panther suits.
He's tempted by the gold one, but he chooses the silver,
the more sedate one.
Whereas, of course, the Golden Jaguar,
his adversary, Killmonger, chooses the gold one.
And that relates a lot to different emotions
and their different perspectives on the world.
In Lone Echo, which is a VR title, VR game, character
details are revealed gradually through the use of items.
So you see different items that you can pick up and find
out a story.
So again, this is almost like an onion where you're just
finding more about people.
It's already pre-baked.
but you can get more into them,
and you can also skip the story if you want to.
But what would it take for an AI,
not just to leave around power-ups,
but to create items that were particularly meaningful
and significant and worked with that particular character?
A story AI might also,
and this is something that we're experimenting with at Xeo,
also use props to tell part of the story.
This is Shape of Water.
How many people have seen that?
Okay, good.
It's a, yeah, so it's a very fascinating,
she's a princess that has no voice.
She's a cleaner in a secret lab.
And the props that she uses, the visual items in the world
are amazing storytelling tools.
They actually change the story as you move over time.
It's a lot of it is told visually.
And so that's another way of not having a lot of narrative.
And if there were really deep semantic understanding
of items in the AI, and then certainly for AR,
a deep ability to recognize objects
and understand not only the object,
like this is a microphone or that's a tennis shoe
or that's a bottle of soda,
but what is the semantic meaning of it?
And most of us have probably felt something about an object,
like this is the companion cube.
Yeah, any portal fans out there?
And so AR, as I've said, semantic recognition and use
is going to be very, very crucial.
Because if I want my murder mystery in AR, in my living
room, it's going to be much more fun if there are,
in addition to virtual props, they're actually
using the real props.
And it is going to need to know from us, from our play styles,
understand us as players, whether it's more interesting
to hide the clue under the coffee table or under the
chair.
And then we've got AI understanding the room around you, so we're playing with that.
This is a Latin scale of wonders.
And that's really, again, going to be really crucial for understanding AR.
I mean, understanding the world for AR.
So just imagine, to wrap up, let's reimagine, you know, say, God of War,
which is a very emotional, very wonderful, wonderful, wonderful game,
is what sort of frames does it bring, right?
So this is, you know, clearly a combat frame.
And the fact that it breaks a lot of the frames for the franchise
created a lot of interest in the game.
And I think it's...
is a big part of why it was such a success.
The frames that you're exploring in the game,
you explore puzzles and you explore,
there's an RPG element as well,
but maybe we can explore relationships
and items in more detail
if we were going to frame it with more AI.
You obviously have choices about things to protect.
And so that creates a lot of social emotions.
But then why not complicate things and then
have more interesting relationships
between the different characters?
So now you have to make some more interesting choices.
What kind of character onions would be,
what could you do dynamically to create these characters
as they arc over time?
Most of the AI here is pre-built in, in terms of what they're going to do, the script, it
has a standard structure.
But if we had something that was more dynamic, what could happen?
And I think what we're going to do is, we're going to win in this, is a narrative AI that
could create something as compelling as the pyre scene, gathering his wife's ashes in
God of War, but dynamically, without any human intervention.
So that's it.
Those are the four frames for narrative AI.
Frames, they do a lot of the work for you
because by association, you're automatically bringing
a lot to the table as a player.
A lot of emotions are going to come from association.
Your choice, you're going to engage your belief systems
of players through their system,
through their philosophy, their worldview.
Onions and arcs will either deepen your relationship
or arc your characters over time.
And items will all add in layers of emotional resonance
and meaning, as well as bonuses and stats.
So we've got the idea of layered AI,
but then a word of caution is we can also do sentiment analysis.
And as we've done with social media, for better or worse,
there's some really great opportunities
to create really compelling player engagement
from sentiment analysis of chat or utterances,
or some of the, obviously, we could
measure emotional people's faces as well.
So thank you very much, thank you for your time.
Do we have time for questions?
Any questions?
So I was curious, there is a Paradox Games Crusader Kings which is known for ability to generate a lot of stories to AI.
So have you used it in your research and how does it fit in your scheme?
So could you say the beginning of the question?
The game Crusader Kings is able to generate a lot of stories like true to eye.
Have you used it as an example? How does it fit in this game?
Yeah, we haven't done a specific study on that one, unfortunately.
Yeah. On that particular title.
Sorry, it's just like, it's one of the games which is like,
has a central feature,
there's an ability to generate stories.
Yeah, so what we want to look at is the,
so there's an interesting point in terms of stories,
is do we take it from the, I think a first step,
in addition, instead of trying to create a story generator,
would be to create a moment-to-moment generator,
because if you think about the birds and the planes
for a moment, is that the reason why a story might move us
is that it is from our, it is its ability
to move us emotionally.
And so if we, and that's, all of the techniques
from character, from three act structure
and that sort of thing are all about designing ways
of creating emotions.
And so if we look from the game design,
we're gonna actually be able to do more than stories do
by looking at, by being able to trigger emotions
in our own unique ways, as well as, you know,
with more traditional story arcs.
Yeah, thank you.
Hi, first of all, great talk.
Thanks for coming out.
So I'm familiar with games like Gone Home and Tacoma,
where the stories are very linearly driven,
but you're interacting with environmental objects
to build that kind of core narrative.
And that kind of reminded me of a lot of the onion arcs
that you were talking about during your talk
about peeling those layers back.
So I was wondering how we could integrate generative AI
and that kind of deep level of thinking to
kind of pre-populate worlds with those narrative aspects
to drive maybe a linear and even a more dynamic
narrative story.
Yeah, well I think that what we're exploring
is we're looking at, say, a room like in
Follow the White Rabbit, it starts in Paris,
you know, a cafe in Paris, and it's about a magician
who's been a charlatan like all his life
until one day the magic actually works.
So we start with some as reference,
some planned out ways in which you get out,
it's an escape room,
so ways that you would get out of the room
and then narrative arcs that would get you there.
And then to break that up into more
the micro moment to moment,
and then a micro moment to moment system.
so that players could, in a sense, sort of mix and match
their way out of it.
There is a feeling, a tension that I feel in games that have
a very strong narrative where I'm trying to second guess the
designer, whereas in like a murder mystery, when I have a
murder mystery dinner at home with my friends, we can be much
more freeform.
And we're trusting that there's going to be something
interesting around the next corner, but not that we have
to finish the maze in the same way each time.
So I don't think that we have language to describe these other patterns,
but every time we bring something in from film, I think there's an opportunity to use it, to leverage it,
and then there's also an opportunity to break it.
So I try and have both of those design sessions to make it much more rich.
And again, we're just getting started, so I'm really looking forward to what people come up with.
Awesome, thank you.
Thank you.
Which of the devices to create emotions that you described were the most fruitful?
Which one, if you only had to use one, which one gives the biggest bang for your buck for amount of effort?
Well, the most effortless one would be the one I started with, would be frames, because
frames are also icons.
I talk a lot in my other talks about iconic design.
If you use something that has an emotional resonance, you instantly get it.
Disney in their line design will often do that, so like the old Pirates of the Caribbean,
new Pirates a little bit, but as you're waiting for, and then as you get on these dark rides,
you're hit with, you know, here's a pirate, here's a pirate chasing a lady, here's a lady
chasing a pirate.
They're taking all these memes, all these tropes.
And that is fairly easy.
If you had a library of those, you could put those
into the player thing.
But I think the second easiest one would, of course, be
onions, where it's a character arc that's already built.
And you might be able to have three or four different
onions, and being able to shuffle those decks.
and you would have some very interesting characters
that change over time.
And that would be a very, much easier
than trying to recognize the difference between a dollar
bill and this box of water.
Thank you.
OK, I think we're just at time.
So thank you.
But if you want to, I'll be here in the back, I guess,
after there's a speaker thing.
Thanks very much for having me here.
All right.
I look forward to making what you all get.