So we're going to go ahead and get started now.
My name is Dave Mark.
The thing is, though, I am going to represent,
for what it's worth, all of the AI devs in the world.
Kill me now.
And I don't have, hang on, oh, my slide's disappeared now.
Let me do this, restart that, and send it over,
and now it should show up.
because I am going to get bombarded with a wish list and hopefully no foul language from
my five panelists up here who have many things to say on this particular subject. So introducing
really quick, Noah Falstein on the left, Robin Hunnecke, Raph Koster, Laura McWilliams, and
I've heard your name before, right?
Richard Lemarchand.
I wish, now it's Richard Lemarchand, isn't it?
He sounded a bit like one of those Ubisoft devs for a second.
Mais oui.
Yeah.
Anyway, back when we first started the summit, we did something in 2010 very similar to this,
where we asked designers via email a whole bunch of questions.
What limitations are you sick of hearing about?
What can film directors do with cast and crew
that you can only dream of with your AI characters?
Things like that.
And then we actually had a panel up here
of some really, really nifty, out-of-the-box thinking
AI devs.
So it's kind of the reverse of this.
And so we iterated through those answers
that those designers gave us and kind of batted around,
well, how would we handle that?
Now, in.
to some extent or another, many of those issues have been solved.
Yes, it's in quotes.
Because we have advanced quite a bit in the past nine years or so
since we did this.
But apparently not well enough, or there's new issues.
Because in 2012, Warren Spector made waves amongst us AI folks
in a Eurogamer interview where he says,
I've been actively trying to shame my fellow developers,
specifically John Carmack and Tim Sweeney.
Can you imagine what games would look like if those two guys spent as much time working on non-combat AI as on rendering?
Can you imagine what they would look like if they wanted to create a believable character as opposed to a believable gun?
I mean, oh my god, these guys are way smarter than I. I don't know how to solve the problem,
but they could figure it out. Stop rendering, start creating humans or mice. I don't care which. Of course, he was working at Disney at the time.
So, but then...
I don't know what the state of mice AI is right now.
But he went on here at GDC, down the hall from us,
and I got wind of this later that day.
Warren was trashing on the AI summit
down at the narrative summit.
Where he says, we have to spend time on non-combat AI.
We figure out pathfinding and not
having characters fall into holes in the ground
and stuff like that.
How do we outflank the enemy?
We spend no time on going to the women's bathroom
and having people notice.
which is interestingly topical. People still come up to me and say, wow, that was so cool.
That was 13 years ago. Apparently it was something he had done in one of his prior games I was not
aware of. Have you seen a game where a drink was spilled and a character responded appropriately?
I think not. Have you seen a game where there was a spurned lover that mattered and it wasn't just
a movie masquerading as a game, like a cut scene? Have you ever seen a game where there was a would
be lover that you could interact with?
If anybody knows how to create a virtual game master,
putting me in a box or you in a box, I want to know.
Good stories are constructed, not found.
Emergence can only get us so far.
And if we can dynamically modify stories
based on what players want to do, a good D&D campaign,
you want to screw around with the dungeon master.
And he actually responds.
So this is what he had said down the hall.
And we chatted later that week about this and a couple
of times since then.
Were you shamed?
Were you appropriately shamed by Warren?
Yeah, that I'm not John Carmack.
That's what you get for representing all AI devs
everywhere, I guess.
So anyway, Warren wanted to be on this panel desperately,
but this is apparently the first GDC he's going
to miss since the Civil War.
He's old.
He wanted me to let him watch this video.
Warren's one of my closest friends and mentors, so I'm just teasing him because he's not here.
But he did answer a number of questions that I posed to him through email.
We'll see those sprinkled through.
But we have a number of different topics that we have talked about over the past couple of weeks that we want to cover.
that subscribe to kind of their wish list.
And so we're just going to go through them in a topical order
and see who has what to say on these things.
We're not going to dive deep into technical solutions,
other than I may prod them, OK, wait a minute, hold on.
What would that look like?
What do you mean by that?
To get a little bit more information.
The goal of this is for us to sit here and go,
how would we solve that?
Because that would make our games better.
So the first topic I want to talk about is character AI.
Just which is normally what we do whether it be combat or non-combat and just have you folks throw out a couple of things
Just in general what would make?
Characters better that you're not seeing that you sit there and go off if we could only pull this off hit me. What do you got?
Well one of the things that I would love to see is recognition from characters that I am
Playing the game in a unique way. Yeah, so for example
I have a follower in Skyrim or in Fallout, and they comment on things in the world, and
they comment when we're attacked, but they comment in a general way.
They don't comment at all about what I do.
They don't comment on how I solve problems, on the fact that I had to take a healing potion,
on the fact that I tripped over something, or I got stuck on a rock, or changed weapons.
They don't seem to understand that I'm playing the game in a way that somebody else, you
know, is unique, versus somebody else.
And that's something that we can gather.
I mean, we know if we watch patterns of player behavior
when players are behaving differently
under certain circumstances.
And there's no reason that,
I mean, it's even as simple as recognizing
when I go to turn in a quest in a game like Destiny
that my group, or when I go to turn in after a strike,
that my fire team wiped three times,
but finished it anyway, right?
We know that because I literally just did it.
there's no reason not to track it. I'm sure they're tracking it in metrics too, so if you have it from metrics,
why not have the game reflect that back to me and let me feel special, like the game recognizes me as a unique player?
Yeah, I think we focus, we over-focus on false plasticity with the character representation itself,
rather than actually looking at the data that we're constantly ignoring. I think it's really, it's really bad.
I mean, you can just even just track what, how often they press the controller and find out whether they're frustrated.
And Journey, a lot of the stuff that we did to edit down
the relationship between two people
involved paying attention to both people
and then sort of smoothing over their differences.
And a lot of people thought that the other character was an AI.
Like, if it had been an AI, it would then
have been the best fucking AI programming in the whole world,
you know?
Because it actually paid attention to you.
It was fake plastic, right?
We do a lot of fake plastic in games.
And that kind of plasticity would be really fantastic.
I have a little bit though actually around the fake plasticity because I think that I
don't think this is as important as what you've been discussing but I do see a lot of low
hanging fruit around the way that NPCs, whether they are enemies or allies.
perform their kind of individual identities.
And across the course of the Uncharted games,
you know, we did a little bit more each game around sort of,
I think a lot of it has to do with head tracking,
gaze tracking, whether people,
somebody gives somebody the side eye,
gait and the way that characters hold themselves
in idle animations and these kinds of things.
I think a lot of it has to do with the spatial distances
that sort of non-hostile NPCs in particular maintain
to the player character.
And the kind of surprise reactions that they do when the player character comes right up to them and gets in their face and how they jump back and how quickly they jump back.
I know some of this is sort of processing time related and we're able to get more and more prompt with sort of NPC reactions all the time.
I still think there's lots and lots of low hanging fruit right there.
So what I'm hearing is from you is a reactivity to just immediate stimulus.
Yes. Your recent past stimulus.
Mm-hmm. Play patterns, really.
So yeah, exactly. You know, I really loved the example when we were chatting about the way you play Fallout.
Yeah, so when I... Tell that, that's great.
So when I play Fallout, I have a pretty reliable pattern that I always play sniper.
So I stay sighted even when enemies are getting pretty close.
They have to get really up in my face before I'll switch to shotgun or something.
Except radscorpions, because they freak me out.
And so...
When a rad scorpion is approaching me, my play pattern radically changes.
I am shooting wildly, I'm fumbling, I'm backpedaling like a mad woman, and that's why I say tripping.
That NPCs should notice when I'm tripping because I'm constantly tripping over things
because I'm backpedaling.
I'll get up on rocks to try to avoid it.
I'll go unsighted much faster and switch to the shotgun much faster.
If the game paid any attention at all, it would be totally clear that rad scorpions
freaked me out.
There's no reason that the NPC with me could not comment on that.
Or if you want to be terrible, if you're making a horror game,
that you couldn't take advantage of that.
Because now you know what in the game scares me the most.
And that's evil.
And when you mentioned this, Lauren,
there's something that I learned a couple of years ago
from the world of improv theater relating
to high and low status characters that
seem totally actionable in the world of AI
for characters in games.
It comes out of the work of Keith Johnston, who identified
that sort of.
People who perceive themselves as high status are more still, their gaze is a little higher.
People who perceive themselves as low status are sort of a bit more turned in on themselves,
their toes point in, they touch their face a lot and they act kind of quickly and more
nervously and I think we could do a lot of that quite easily.
But that's bullshit. That's total bullshit. That's like paying attention to how people actually are and then building systems that reflect how people actually are.
And like the difference between AI that is plastic for real and AI that is fake plastic is paying attention to what real is.
Like get out of your head and the problem space of how do I respond in a relatively short time loop?
How do I get this animation cycle to work and have the foot planting be perfect?
that kind of paying attention is not paying attention to the level where it's really going
to make an emotional impact.
And you can actually fake a lot of that other stuff with art style.
The thing you can't fake is what Richard's talking about, which is the way that humans
actually respond to one another.
And I think, just to be contrary about this, thinking about this panel, a lot of my sense
of these questions of how do we make computers do these things.
They suck at a lot of this stuff.
Yeah, they do.
And we have millions of years of evolution
having us focus on the kind of stuff
that Richard was just talking about, our primate ancestors.
There's all sorts of, my sister used to work with chimps.
And being with a group of chimps and being
with a group of game developers, it
can be really hard to tell the difference.
Ha, ha, ha.
But he made that joke and not me.
No, no, no.
This is, I've, you know.
realize my own kind of body language is
completely compatible with what the chimps are doing.
But the point being, have the AI control
you know, scorpions or animals or have them control computers.
You know, I would love, at Google we had a
proposal for this game called Bot or Not.
And the idea was that you didn't know if the other characters were bots or humans, but
your job as a human was to be the most convincing bot you could be.
So why make, you know, have the AI make the humans seem more realistic, make it do realistic
robots.
And granted, we would love to have it do a lot more than that, but, you know, I look
for the low hanging fruit.
But when do we start, when do we really start looking?
I mean, when do we really start trying to figure out?
the subtle thing that people already do with hand animation to make a character seem real
when it's clearly a bunch of lines moving on a flat screen.
We don't even do it with other players.
There are ways to cheat.
Yeah, we can cheat.
Yeah, we don't even do it with other players, right?
Like the amount of emotional bandwidth that comes through with another player in an online
game is basically nil.
It's terrible.
We don't do the simple things like eye tracking.
We don't do the simple things like gaze and head moving to whoever spoke most recently.
We don't do body language for precedence or any of that.
But I think fundamentally, though, if I kind of summed up what all of these comments add
up to me is we are in a habit for a whole bunch of reasons of building our characters
as props that are primarily reactive.
And if we want to exploit AI, they need to have their own inner lives, out of which this
stuff arises organically.
They should be scared of you because they remember you and go, oh crap, this guy kills
random civilians.
Right?
I mean.
None of us ever do that.
Yeah, but that requires, it's not that we lack, we have, we have the CPU, we have the
RAM these days.
Okay.
It's not a question of capability.
I think a lot of what we just said is actually trivially easy and not a challenge for you
guys.
Instead, it's a matter of will.
we have to actually choose to prioritize characters over props.
And I think we have...
I want to read this quote because it's exactly what you were just saying.
This is, I wish for better non-combat AI.
We do really well now in creating convincing combat behaviors individually in groups,
but our characters can't do the simplest real-world things
in response to different kinds of inputs that games typically allow.
there's a reason why love stories and intimate dramas aren't getting made and
AI is a big part of that. And it comes down to that subtlety of who are they?
Is that an accurate? Yeah, so I mean I haven't made MMOs in a long time, right? But the big
challenge in making MMOs is the fact that you need to make thousands of NPCs, right? And so
that meant that the answers that single-player gaming uses, which is make
you know, props that are scripted, you just can't do it, right? So either you end up with
a thousand of the same NPC, or you are driven to have to do stuff that is procedural or
AI driven or whatever, right? And the solutions to get some of that inner life are actually
not hard at all. A couple of floating scalar variables for fear, anger, greed, whatever.
And it doesn't take very much, but...
the pressure is towards what I would call a stagecrafty,
narrativist approach.
And so you end up prescripting the NPCs to such a degree.
Like, you know, in Ultima Online, we did this.
We had that kind of behavior stuff.
And by the time we got to Star Wars Galaxies,
the pressure on it was so much that we just said,
we don't need NPCs.
Let's just have players do all the jobs.
And we turned what would have been NPCs into terminals.
Because.
we were like, well, you can't actually do better right now.
They might as well just actually be a physical prop
with a button.
And defense quest, please, beep.
I think your philosophical point is well made, Raph.
The other end of the spectrum,
so I think there's some simple hacky things that we can do
by looking at the expressive affordances
that the game gives the player.
Like even something like, you know, just crouching.
I have crouched in front of so many dogs
in Breath of the Wild.
hoping for that, hoping to be led to some treasure actually I'm afraid, hoping to
get something from that. But the way that Zelda Breath of the Wild rewards you
with this little moment of interaction where my attempt to
take a kind of a spatial stance that is possibly socially expressive in some way
is just met by the game and even though it's just simplest of mechanisms.
Yeah I also want to say that games about love and romance are being made
they're just not being made with characters so I think
you know when you think about games as you know mechanics as rules
and aesthetics is the outcome the feeling experience that you get in the
middle is the dynamics and like what we're talking about
is the player NPC dynamic.
It doesn't really have good juicy affordances for romance,
but you can build a game like Florence,
which is all about falling in love.
And it could do really well and be really lovely.
And people can love it if you turn
the mechanics and the aesthetics into the main part of the game.
And the disappeared dynamics are in your mind, right?
So we know how to do it as game designers.
It's just we don't know how to do it with, you know.
first-person shooters and third-person role-playing games.
And VR actually is giving us some of those affordances.
Specifically, we've been talking about gaze,
and it's better, particularly when eye tracking comes in,
which is certainly getting close.
We're going to have excellent gaze,
not just on are they looking at me,
but I saw, I think it was Fove did this demo.
where you're being interrogated, and I happen to look at the water, the cup on the table,
and the guy bashes it out of the way and says, look at me, and it was one of the scariest moments
I've had. You can trip that around because the same part of our brain that processes some of
that fear and fight or flight stuff deals with arousal too, and the intimacy of VR, the physical
proximity that you're acutely aware when you're within arm's reach of somebody compared to
across the room, and VR actually gives you that feeling.
if the AI is feeding off of those things,
realizes that a character is right next to you,
and it's very different if the character looks at you
and the character looks at you like this.
Exactly.
Or if it's another player,
and I think this is actually one of the things
that we should always think about as developers,
and particularly if you're working in AI right now,
this idea that gaze is gonna be so easy to track.
Like, the machine is much better
at actually catching the things that we're looking at
and our micro-expressions than we are.
Just like you can observe a date from a different table
and tell whether.
one of the people is not into it.
Like a computer can look at your face through a headset
and tell whether you're scared
or whether you're looking for a solution
or whether you're like really intensely focusing.
And there's a huge potential to abuse that.
So like one of the things that it's,
I think it's very important for all of you to be doing
is making work at that level
because if you don't do it,
then someone who cares less about players will.
And I'd like to add one small thing.
which is at the heart of this though is the need to study and understand human behavior.
Yeah. Because without it, it's all stupid pet tricks. And the example that I would give is
anyone who played Oblivion, especially, I'm sure all the women felt this way, but I bet a lot of
men did too, found it super creepy when you'd walk by a guard and he would say, you know how to move
in light armor. I'm like, stop it. What are you doing? Right. They just harassed me. Weird.
Eye tracking you no matter what and commenting on you.
just apropos of nothing, right?
And then they do it again in Skyrim.
They still do the same thing, right?
It's a stupid pet trick.
It's trying to make the AI look smart and responsive,
but in fact, not looking at what people actually do
and making something really creepy as a result, right?
So I think you have to study people and understand people
for anything we're talking about here to work.
And then if the game doesn't give the player
an opportunity to respond in context to the NPC,
to the sexual harassment,
then that game is taking a kind of philosophical stance.
I want to jump off the moment because this next section selling the NPC.
Here at the AI summit last year, our very own Alicia Laid Acker during the rant
session had a segment that almost got a standing ovation from the room.
I do want to play that here real quick.
have this great opportunity because we can actually interact with them.
But honestly, I barely give a shit about any of the NPCs in our games.
They're too simple. They're designed to either protect someone,
kill someone, or roam around in a big city like a zombie.
In short, our NPCs are lacking empathy and intelligence.
And this is what makes us really care about characters in cinema and TV.
I'm going to call this artificial intelligence.
I love that term artificial intelligence and you'll find out in my rant tomorrow.
But what would that look like?
You just talked about the empathy of realizing, OK, wow, maybe I just as an NPC said something
that was OK, a little bit off.
I probably should not have done that.
But there's plenty of other examples.
Um of well that that would require the writer not having done it. I mean that's like that's the fundamental point that we're just making
Yeah, it's like I mean, it's not like it has the capability of knowing what it shouldn't say. I mean, this is the whole point example
Yeah, there's thing. I used one that if I walk into the tavern
Uh, or or the shop or something in in a game like a skyrim and i've got arrows poke through me
I'm dragging i'm at one percent health
Hi
What can I sell you today?
No, dude, I'm bleeding. I've lost an arm.
What's that, Bloody Mary? Sure.
Yes, thank you. Dragons blood. Two of them, please. I'm trying to keep my volume up.
So, yeah, what would artificial intelligence, as Alicia briefly described it last year in that clip,
what would that look like to you? The empathy, the understanding that...
you're caring for them because they're caring about something as well, possibly even you.
Well, I mean, part of the writer's job is going to be to identify what each character cares about,
because maybe he actually genuinely doesn't give a crap about you bleeding,
other than don't do it on my floor, right? And now that makes him a person. I believe in this
guy because he's like, take that out of here. I don't want your trouble. And won't sell to me
until I've cleaned up, right? Those are the kinds of things. And I guess the point for me is that
In order to accomplish this, it takes the team working in lockstep.
It takes animators and AI engineers and designers and writers all understanding together
that we're trying to create something.
It's not any one job's responsibility to magically make an NPC who will do what I just said, right?
That's a group of people.
I'm not representing all the animators, designers, and writers.
Yeah.
So I want to challenge that just a little bit.
the challenge I would be offering would be,
okay, let's cut the writers for a minute.
Just cut them all, sorry.
And think about, okay,
what can we get across without the writers?
Because I think that's the way we need to think about this.
We need to think, what can I get across?
Now, let's take away the animations too.
Do I have anything to get across?
Like, if I had a text output, is there any there there?
I think often the answer is no.
Right? Like, we put all the burden on the writers.
So, just for a minute, do the thought experiment of,
there is no writing, right? There just isn't any.
Do the NPCs have any brain at all? And that, I guess, is what I mean,
really, when I think of artificial intelligence, I go,
but none of them have hearts, right? How about, let's use some AI to try building
at least a rudimentary heart, right? And see if they do anything?
Right? I mean, that would be the challenge I would want.
Because even just, what I hear you saying, is even if just in data,
someplace there was a number that was changing because it felt, you know, happy with you,
sad, in a similar sort of way, but on a deeper level?
Right.
And then we can hook it up to writing and animation later.
Right. So...
I think it's important that you've actually recognized that, like,
one of the things that makes us care for others is that they're broken.
Like, one of the most compelling characters...
in your favorite book is probably someone who has a serious character flaw.
Maybe you've seen that flaw in yourself and then you identify with that character.
When we do write well, we generally focus on
specifications for humanity that are slightly off in one of several vectors, maybe even
meeting DSM criteria, right? I mean, like, it's really, it's really unusual people.
histrionic people, people that are emotionally unstable, people that are
clinging and then cold, those are the ones that we write about and care about.
And I think one of the things we always do as an industry is we try to build
either friend or foe, but like what about the middle space? The person that
you're in love with who suddenly gets angry and doesn't know how to not throw
things, or the parent that wants to raise the child but was abused and so
therefore is just constantly difficult.
with a little kid, you know?
What about an animal that's been beaten
that you're trying to win back to trust?
You know, that kind of a relationship
is I think the thing where you really do have
to do the juicy work of,
it's not that they don't have lines
or that they aren't written,
it's that they're actually something interesting to us.
Trying to solve the problem and be perfect.
you're trying to create a version of a human that isn't really real or maybe is real somewhere.
I don't know any of them, but I love all my friends, I do.
But you know, we all have our difficulties.
So I think it really is about actually really recognizing that when you're broken, you're
more interesting and it's the ways that you're broken that make people care for you.
I think that's absolutely right, Robin, and I think that the kind of intimacy and empathy
that Alicia's talking about comes from when characters make themselves emotionally vulnerable
to one another.
And just thinking out loud, we've been talking about NPCs noticing what the player does do,
I think that vulnerability is often associated with avoidance.
And so maybe there's some mileage in noticing what the player doesn't do or it seems uncomfortable
doing and that might open the door to...
Well, it's more or less the...
Ah, the wonderful scorpions example, yeah.
Yeah, it's exactly that of commenting, wow, you really don't like those, do you?
You know, and either then cackling at you every, it's glee every time you run away from
a... or saying, hey, let me help you avoid those or something to that effect.
Yeah.
Excellent.
Warren I've left this up here for a little bit, but he was actually touching on a lot of the same things his spilled milk
Thing how do characters react?
It's gonna be whether it was knocked over by mistake that the NPC might respond whether the player was playing the role of a child
Well, that's okay, honey. You spilled the milk. It's okay
Or whether the player just revealed that she was sleeping with the NPCs husband and so on you know
There's all these different contexts to one
physical event in the world and having an NPC understand and react accordingly would be monumental.
How do we define that in such a way that we can even build that? I guess that's my job, isn't it?
Our job. Well, you know, one thing I'd point out, I think if we polled the room about whether or
not they felt emotional connection with, let's say, their Nintendogs or their Sims,
The answer would start being yes.
Okay.
And it's worth pointing out that those are simulation driven, AI driven, little entities
with inner lives of their own, their own needs, their own desires.
And yeah, we do let them down.
We forget to feed them and we set them on fire and trap them in swimming pools.
At that point, that's not letting them down.
I feel like I let them down when I, I'm so sorry.
Let me fill the pool now.
I guess my point is we have seen this work.
Yeah.
And, come on, Sims is what?
Eight little variables on a scale that probably only need a bite each, right?
I mean, come on.
Not a lot.
We can afford to Simsify every NPC in World of Warcraft.
Right?
Like, easily.
That's tweet-worthy.
Do it.
Quick.
But I do think it's also a problematic game.
I mean, Sims was the first game I worked on.
And my first job was building objects for the Sims expansion
packs on Sims 2.
And trying to design things to go into that system
was incredibly difficult. Because what ends up happening
is you hack together a terrain, basically,
of interest for all the AIs.
And then they're all running around on this terrain.
And basically, what they're doing
is they're listening to the objects which
are echoing affordances back to them.
And then they're choosing those affordances based on a stack
based ranking on the sliders.
But then when you try to build a new object and insert it into that system, it has to get along with all the other objects in the system.
So every expansion pack is like, it's like if you think of the Death Star and you have to peel one panel off and then like wire in a thing and then put the panel back on and then it just fucking breaks.
So the game, like 90% of the design on the expansion pack team was idealized what an object would do, then have someone try to make it and shove it into the game.
and then fix all the ways that it breaks by tuning it.
And we used to call Edith the thing
that you used to tune that game, the Crippler,
because you just had to do all this ninnying, tweaking,
and constantly evaluating what they were doing.
And a lot of times, you were just guessing.
You were literally guessing what they were doing.
They were like creatures of their own will.
And bugs that I had to deal with on that game
included time passing differently on different lots,
broke the treadmill so that people just
were always stinky when they were working out at a gym,
you know, or working out at home.
And so, like, it seems so easy,
but there's a reason no one has done it,
because it is actually incredibly difficult
to sort of deal with that mesh.
So that sounds like something to throw
at the machine learning system,
so that we don't have to do it anymore.
Dave, go fix that.
Yeah, fix it.
I'm just saying design better tools for your utility system.
But anyway, I do want to move on because we've
got a couple other topics that we want to cover.
Narrative is something that we hear a lot about
over the past few years lately.
And a lot of people in academia are working on this,
of how do we create stories, how do we
create dynamic dialogue, contextual dialogue.
Matter of fact, we're going to be having a talk here tomorrow
on exactly that.
But dialogue and narrative.
are two different things. Taking a pre-written story arc and saying, well, we're just going to
fill in different words, compared to creating a story arc of two different things, what would
you want to see? Give me a vignette of, it would be cool if... So I don't want to miss the middle
spot, right? Because on the one hand you have the, hey, the entire narrative is crafted and I'm just
along for the ride. On the other side, you have procedural narrative, right? There is a middle
point where within Mass Effect, I'm telling my own story.
along with playing the story that they created.
So that's, I think, something that doesn't really
get addressed enough.
I think everybody who thinks we really want more player agency
starts to lean toward procedural, which is difficult
and a lot of times can't, right now,
achieve the same level of quality,
generally, as you get from a more written story.
But that doesn't mean, again, that we can't spend our AI
dollars and time on having.
my path to a story have more meaning and more recognition from the other elements? And again,
it's having the NPCs talk to me about the choices that I made, right? Because I love mass effect,
but it's always super clear to me that, oh, I just triggered the threshold where he likes me now.
Right? And I imagine even like normal people who aren't designers recognize that too, right? Oh,
I just finally won his love, which is not how people really work, right? So how can you make
that relationship more interesting and more dynamic and have...
you know, Morden actually recognized more of the small things they do in the game
and not just the obvious things that are set up to make Morden either like me or dislike me.
I just want to draw a circle on one thing in the middle you said is
every player can go off and play his own story in any game.
I'm going to screw with the game this way, I'm going to do this,
but it was the part about having the characters recognize that you have
gone off the beaten path and adapt to that and react to that and join you,
again going with the improv.
Yes, and.
And looking at things in the macro too, right?
Because a lot of times there's no recognition among multiple characters and multiple systems
about what I'm doing in the game as a whole.
You're trying to befriend everybody, right?
And I think designers tend to look at it like, okay, I'll do factions then, where if you
like this person, this person hates you.
But again, life doesn't really work that way.
So some sort of macro knowledge of an idea, I guess the closest I can come is the director
in Left 4 Dead.
The director in Left 4 Dead has an idea about what a good experience is.
You're making your own experience and he's kind of rolling things out for you.
You could think of almost all games that way.
As the player's going through it, looking at the macro of the player's behavior,
what sort of world is he creating, what sort of experience is he having?
Is he being an asshole in his actions but talking nice to people?
That's a play style. Someone should call him on that bullshit.
Or not necessarily leaning so hard on the character to do that job, but letting the environment do it for you.
So, you know, the simplest version of this would be a game in which your choices actually change the way the world looks to you.
And like, you know, my next game is actually going to be procedural and procedural narrative and really large.
And I'm thinking a lot about this stuff right now.
And I think there are just a lot of good ways
to clip back on the things.
Like, one of the things I keep thinking about,
if you look at a game like Destiny, which is beautiful,
but why model the buttons on the jacket of a body
that you're going to shoot from 30 feet away and then loot?
Like, just why do it?
Like, that's someone's life.
Like, someone somewhere is modeling those buttons.
Like, don't do it.
Just stop.
Like, just cut.
Cut with the detail at the level that it has no impact on gameplay.
We're not making a fully rendered, you know, 60 frames per second
Hobbit movie that needs to be badly edited. Or are we?
You know, like, why do that? Just don't do the useless stuff and then spend, like Raph is sort
of saying, just copy someone else's eight slider thing and put it on everybody and see what that
does and skip the buttons.
Anybody else?
Briefly on narrative, I do want to keep moving.
So kind of riffing on what Laryllyn was saying,
I think that anyone working in AI
who wants to look at screenwriting education
would find a lot of good stuff there.
We've all heard of the hero's quest,
and there's that kind of systematization of story.
But there's things like sequence structure.
You can break feature films down often
into sort of.
eight or ten, twelve minute sequences, and each sequence is kind of a mini-story.
I think it would appeal to anyone with a mathematical bent, because there's this kind of fractal
aspect to it, stories within stories within stories, right?
Like the beat of a single emotional exchange that unfolds over ten seconds between two
characters builds into...
You want to press the Save the Cat button to generate?
So that's one of the books to have a look at, Save the Cat.
And I just throw in one last thing that I, you know, back to what I was saying before
that human computer interactions are difficult, but why not do computer-computer interactions?
And some of the most interesting proposals I've seen are having AIs that can talk to
each other.
And, you know, maybe there's some prescriptive parts, but the kinds of stuff Robin was talking
about that those AIs can be sensitive to the flaws that the other ones have.
they can be tested within the rigid area of what they know about each other and not have
the incredible difficulty of some random human that can come in and ask them any question at all.
And they can respond to each other in ways that make the environment around you, including the
NPCs, feel more realistic without you having to actually interact with them and have a dialogue
and all the flaws of the fact that it's...
the fourth time you ask them that question,
they say the same thing, and they never say,
why do you keep asking me the same question?
If you can do that well with computer-to-computer NPCs,
then you can sort of get around that whole limitation.
Yeah, we're designing a world where the narrative
is about you're all fragments of saved data
at the bottom of a giant post-apocalyptic server
somewhere where everyone's been uploaded into a metaverse,
and you're just all fragmenting,
and everyone you interact with is like,
fragmented in some really fucked up way.
And then you're trying to figure out
how to get something done in that space,
but people are glitching in a way that makes their flaws
exactly stop.
They'll know we're in it already.
But there's ways to write around it,
but it really, what I'm saying, skip the buttons.
I'm not talking about the actual buttons.
I'm talking about all the ways in which we imagine
there's data where there isn't data.
Like, what you're talking about is there's three vectors in this person that I need to
figure out in order to get something from them and then move on in my quest.
And maybe they're not a person, maybe they're an AI, maybe they're a ghost, maybe they're
like a random, you know, half a robot, half person, who knows?
You know, like, they could be anything.
They could be another species.
But the point would be to, like, figure out how to lower the valence that I need to think
about in order to get at the thing that really matters.
And I do think that that's...
It's like systems writing.
It's not writing and it's not systems.
It's both.
Which is one of the reasons why people don't buy AI tools,
which I think we're gonna talk about in a little bit.
So, you know, but it takes us to systems.
Well, actually I put up a slide that says systems.
Yeah, so let's do that.
Conveniently, you, fantastic segue.
Systems, you know, it's a broad term, right?
And I'm talking, you brought up the AI director
from in Lafayette, it was the most famous one.
changed the audio, changed the coloring on the sides of the screen, it changed how the content was being delivered and the pacing and everything.
So that's a classic example. Is there anything either that you would go beyond with something like systems
or it could do better or something that we haven't thought of that if the game...
We've hit a few of them here so I don't want to rehash.
But is there something we haven't mentioned that if the game system under...
was changing something and how we were experiencing it.
Well, what I think made the Left 4 Dead director so special
and that I haven't really seen used again,
disappointingly, since that was, what, 10 years ago?
Yeah, a long time ago.
Late, right?
Is that the whole point of the director
is managing your emotional experience, right?
It's all about your emotional experience.
I'm going to take you up, and then I'm
going to let you have a lull.
And then right at the right moment,
I'm going to fill you with dread.
And then.
nothing's going to happen so you're going to relax and then oh my god there it is right
it was an entire AI system built around emotion emotional experience and I can't really think of
other games that have done that since and that's where the magic is because the magic is in the
players emotional moment to moment experience and you understanding that as a developer whether
you're a designer or an artist or an engineer is key to you making something that's really going
to stick with players.
And so any of the AI we talk about here, I think, at the heart of that system has to
be that it's about the player's emotional experience and not just about mechanics or
pushing buttons or dialogue or anything else.
I think it's easy to do with scary things.
I think that pacing curve is easier to do with fear narratives and really high action
games.
And then I think to Raf's point, we've leaned on other players and we've just
I mean, in many ways, the sort of popularity of multiplayer games is reinforced by our
realization that it's just easier to let other people do it.
I mean, like I wasn't joking, we couldn't have written an AI that would have been as
good to play with for Journey as another player.
There's just no way.
And it would have been obviously glitchy and failed all the time.
And that, like, you know, the fact that people read it as another, as an AI, was, you know,
I think it was kind of a deep commentary.
on what people expect from entertainment experiences.
They expect to be sort of lauded
and have everything be about them
and it's all about them winning.
But to Raf's point, I think we've leaned really hard
on other players and moved away
from that kind of scripting of experiences.
And fear is one that is actually pretty easy to guess
because you can do things to scare people really easily.
We have very easy fear triggers.
It's like at our lowest level of cognition.
It's much harder to hook us with romance
or to hook us with mystery
or to hook us with.
you know, some sort of innuendo and like kind of guessing,
because that's when you start to see that,
oh, it would be very difficult
to really execute at that level.
So I really wish somebody would build
even just a basic soap opera.
Like a soap system.
I was thinking that during the narrative,
the first narrative talk today.
Like telenovela type stuff.
Yeah, I had a bit on,
one of the segments in it was about romance games
and about the tropes that they rely on
in making romance games.
And those tropes map directly to the emotional experience
and the ups and downs and valleys
in the.
red herrings and all of that, right? Mysteries have the same pattern.
So really understanding those very human patterns I think are the key to
you know mapping out the emotional experience of the player in your game.
Warren in his thing, narrative summit, he used the the term game master and then
again in his answers to me this morning he
talked about wouldn't it be amazing if we could create a virtual dungeon master
capable of dynamically changing the gameplay to meet the needs, fulfill the
desires.
And so in the Left 4 Dead, as you rightly pointed out,
it was a horror thing.
I'm not fulfilling the desires.
I'm saying, is it time for me to hurt you again?
Yeah, but I think also, why make the player
the center of the narrative in this way
where you're fulfilling their desires
and making them feel like a rock star and like,
blah, blah, blah.
I think actually that's what our games already do.
Like, winner, winner, chicken dinner.
Like, you're the one.
And then just like, ooh, I want another one of those.
Ooh, I want another one of those.
Oh, Jesus Christ, I'm drunk and it's 4 a.m.
and I have to go to work tomorrow.
Damn you, PUBG.
Murder Island, I hate you!
I was thinking Civ V.
Yeah, but we're so good at it.
We're so good at giving people that experience.
I think actually one of the harder things is to do the stuff that Alyssa's talking about.
You know, let's try and make it happen.
Build something a little bit softer with a little less resolution in the graphics,
but where the system is really trying to tell that story.
Yeah, I think, so, I mean, I'm totally on board with cutting the buttons.
And more than the buttons, frankly. Again, I think it's not an accident that
Sims, Nintendogs, and many other games that achieve emotional connection
use iconic communication, use different levels of graphics resolution, right?
We have chased fidelity, and all that's done is create a large gap
between visual fidelity and emotional fidelity.
you know, today we have servers for these games that are
literally thousands of times more powerful.
than what we had 20 years ago.
Like, insanely more powerful.
And we're actually using the server CPU cycles
on rendering the buttons on the server
so that we can do bullet collision against them.
Which is like, why?
Why?
And I think if it's a hard problem,
people get like, ooh, that's a hard problem, let's do it.
It's not.
It's not actually.
Most of these things aren't hard problems.
When we talk about.
recognizing emotional facts about human nature,
things like body language, or
in a minute we're going to talk about content generation, and recognizing
things like there are patterns in architecture.
or you know whatever the fact is most of these things if people are just willing
to you know venture a little bit outside of the field of game design
have been studied by people for hundreds or thousands of years
they actually already boil down into convenient mathematical equations
that could very easily be modeled and generated right
the idea that oh well how do we make a pet react or
how do we provide narrative or whatever okay
you know you want to start studying procedural narrative
Gosh, go back to Vladimir Prop and start there and work your way forward.
There is such an enormous body of this material out there.
It isn't that we can't go find this stuff to build systems around.
I agree.
It's that we are choosing to build other systems, mostly rendering.
The ones that interest the developers personally.
Right.
And there's a reason that the Sims and Nintendogs were so successful.
It's because they are beyond what you're saying.
It's because they are so accessible,
and the average person can't attach to them.
Because they were made by diverse teams.
When I worked on The Sims, it was 50-50.
It was the first job I had in the games industry.
There was 50% women in the studio.
I've never worked anywhere else that was 50-50.
Not even in my own studio is it that good.
Like, people from all over the world,
fans that had loved The Sims,
they just came right into the pipeline and became creators.
Like, you know, I can't say it enough, man.
The narrowness with which our schools train us in computer science and AI,
the narrowness with which we create the community of people in this room,
affect the breadth of the things that we make.
And like, I think it would be interesting to think about the systems that you're all part of
and how you could broaden those systems and make them more diverse and more inclusive
so that you would get different perspectives on what was interesting.
So Dave, we need you to take all of the A programmers.
and give them a liberal arts degree please.
Yes.
Educate everyone.
Personally?
You are here standing in for all the AI developers,
so yeah, it's on you.
I didn't even graduate college.
I think actually, by the way,
before we get too much farther,
it's time to give Dave credit for,
how many people here are at their first GDC?
Okay, so we knew there'd be a lot of you,
and you've been really attentive.
If we had to make up some,
you know, presence who really wasn't here but kept saying these sage things and he was
kind of this ghostly thing. And it was the narrative summit. Wouldn't the narrative come
up with someone and call him a specter?
You've all fallen for it really well.
I love it.
You probably got some more of this Warren Spector person, but I'd love to hear it.
I've never heard of him.
Oh, God.
I can't wait until he watches this and emails me.
We love you, Warren.
That's it.
Don't break character.
I love it.
All right.
So, moving on, I do want to blast through this section on content generation.
There's been a lot over the past number of years, even here in the AI Summit.
about procedural content generation, which of course means so many different things,
whether it be art styles or texturing or creating buildings.
Even just it started by roguelikes, we're going to create random mazes or something like that.
But it's gone beyond that.
And a lot of the things we talk about, how do we create?
you know these huge worlds without you know artists and designers sitting there and doing
you know every single building or copy and pasting you know five thousand of the same
building.
But I feel that there's something else that we could generate it.
What is it that you in your design.
God, if we could only just push a button and have this stuff appear, what would it be?
One of the coolest things I've seen with using AI for content generation was the deep dream
stuff that allows you to take one picture and combine it with usually some artist, some
abstract artist, and you get some beautiful mashup of those two.
And imagine if the structure of a level was, you know...
the same for everyone, but each player could pick their own art style
and have that be reflected in how that level looked.
It's something we can individualize right now and it's one of those things
that computers do really well that
doesn't get into the sort of squishy stuff that we're all
having trouble doing. Yeah, I mean just if you think about like a basic RPG where you
pick like,
okay, I'm gonna be the Goth Lolita costume person, then just like everything in the
world has got candy cane stripes and ribbons on it,
you know, like just make everything cute.
you know, but dead.
That took a turn.
Yeah, for me a lot of this is about making a data-rich environment, right, because again
it feels to me like we basically settle for worlds made out of stage props and cardboard
most of the time, and to me one of the big advantages of AI is actually that it's basically
it's patient in that sense.
It can keep recursing and adding detail.
that is actually real detail, right?
So to me, it's kind of obvious and trivial
that we can procedurally generate better trees using AI
or that we can even procedurally generate
a better forest using AI.
Sure, fine, but that's just kind of linear extrapolation
off of what we already do.
You know, it's like speed tree, forest edition, whatever.
What's more interesting to me is
Can you do that but in a way that is data rich?
Instead of just going for, no, let's plot thousands of trees.
How about when I go look at a tree, it's way more detailed.
Now there's an ecosystem in that tree.
Now there is a burrow in this one,
and the gophers live under it, and there's a woodpecker
over in that one.
That's the kind of detail that, frankly, we will never, ever
be manually able to do.
We just can't afford it.
It's ridiculous.
and it's exactly the kind of intelligently constructed, realistic, responsive environment.
You want the woodpecker to know there's a gopher, right? Like, I'm not talking just shallowly,
again, it's not just splatting the textures, it's can we actually create a data-rich environment,
right? Because when we build worlds today, we build really big worlds that, again,
if you strip out the graphics, actually have very few objects in them. We actually do not
make dense environments.
when our notion of a dense environment is even Skyrim or Battlefield or something like
that, and you tally the objects, you actually end up down in like, what, three digits?
And the objects that actually interact with each other.
Is nothing.
It's miniscule.
It's very miniscule.
That piece is made out of cardboard.
Yeah.
Fantastically rendered to cardboard, however.
What AI could do, even in a way that like, because it's...
it's kind of a fractal or segmented thing. We don't actually need each tree to know about each
tree, but we could do something really interesting within the tree, if that makes sense. Each one of
them could have variations. Especially if you move away, like how many of you have seen annihilation?
Any of you?
Okay, so like...
It's amazing.
Go and see it before it leaves theaters.
If you've seen Solaris or Stalker, it has some similar themes, so there's both the old
Tartofsky movies, but there's a fundamental notion of humanity and what we try to model,
and what do we hope for with contact, like going into outer space?
And Solaris is a perfect example.
You get to the planet, the planet is sentient, but the only way it can communicate with you
is by making up vague approximations of what your memories are, and then making those physical
for you.
And all that really reifies is the fact that you miss being on planet Earth.
So like the whole point was like you left and now you wish you could go back.
But when you do, all your family will be dead, right?
Like there's a thing that we do where we recreate the reality that we see right now.
If you the tree example is perfect.
Just don't make it a real tree, like make it that you go to a foreign planet
and then you find an object.
And when you look inside the object, there's more objects
and you look inside those objects and then like come up with the design of mechanics.
that are like interesting from the exploratory perspective
that's very similar to when you're a child
and you wander out into your backyard
and then into the woods behind there
and you find a stream and then you look in the stream
and you see the tadpoles and then you poke the tadpoles.
Like think of it from a mechanical perspective,
not an aesthetic perspective.
And then you get the dynamics that are so interesting.
I think we over focus on the aesthetic qualities
because it short circuits the kind of creativity
that you have to do as a designer.
And if you partner with a designer who has the kind of abstract imagination about systems
and mechanics and how they create dynamics, you can move away from an aesthetic that is
really costly, like the buttons, and move towards the tree.
But you just have to abstract away from your natural sort ofyou know, like when you
first pick up a pen, you're like, I'm going to draw a tree.
The tree that you imagine drawing on the paper is like Raphael drew it or something.
You imagine being able to draw Leonardo da Vinci.
But the truth of the matter is that you draw like a kid,
and the tree is still a tree.
It's just a kid's version of a tree.
So if we made a kid's version of that experience
of finding the tadpoles, that journey is a really fun one.
But it doesn't have to be here on planet Earth.
It doesn't have to be this stuff.
It can be abstractly related.
And I think that content generation is about, I think,
getting away from this notion of reality
and towards the notion of experience.
We're down to about five minutes and I wanted to play this next clip because it actually does speak to the difference between
The the set pieces the the art of the stuff that the rendering the world that we're creating
And what would be the equivalent of that? This comes from the critical. What is it called?
critical play project
which is a whole bunch of video clips of a variety of designers. I think some of you have actually been part of them too.
And this is from Clint Hocking.
And he was talking about his experiences in Far Cry 2 and something he encountered in his own game.
I'll go ahead and play the clip here.
criminal.
The first time we got in the weather system, we were driving around through this dusty
savannah area and running a little gunfight in some little shack.
A little shack to look for some health supplies.
We sort of tossed the place and when I turned to walk out, this storm had come in and it
was pouring.
Suddenly it was pouring rain out of the sky and I stopped.
I stopped myself at the threshold of the doorway because I didn't want to get wet.
Like that was like, oh, and there was a moment where I was like,
I'm not going to get wet, it's a video game.
But the world was so visually compellingly real
that that first instinct I had was to not step out into the pouring rain.
All right, I love that because we've all had that experience
in games where it's like, oh, because of the sound and the
and the visuals and, you know, this.
it made us realize, it's the suspension of disbelief that we all talk about in this.
My question is, okay, I didn't want to get wet. Wait, I'm not going to get wet. That moment,
what would be an equivalent feeling that AI might provide? Give me just a little vignette of
if I was in this situation, I could not stop myself, but from feeling this way.
I didn't want to kill it. Oh, yeah.
I just didn't want it. I couldn't put it down.
Can I piggyback on that?
I was gonna ask to go first,
because mine's such a downer.
And it would be to,
and it highlights what I think is a burgeoning problem
for us all as developers of action games
and some other kinds of games,
which is that I think we're rapidly converging on the point
where because of our representations,
both in terms of assets and animation and dialogue
and visual fidelity,
where the violence in our games becomes intolerable to us.
And so my answer to this question was going to be like,
that the characters react to the violence in our games
in ways that feel more authentic.
Because right now they either don't really react at all,
because they're tough guys
and they've got to keep fighting you,
or they kind of do these kind of pantomimed,
over the top, hysterical reactions.
We've all seen that animation, right?
Character doing that and then running away.
But I think that,
I'm fortunate to not have seen very much violence in my own life, but through the representations
of it that I've seen maybe in storytelling or in documentary evidence, human beings'
reaction to violence is much more complex.
Our reaction to trauma is often very unpredictable.
It either looks like no reaction or it looks like something unusual and unexpected.
And so I think there is a cluster of hard issues for us here.
It's not a complete downer because I think that it's going to inevitably mean that we
have to steer in the directions that we've been talking about mainly for the last hour
towards other kinds of subject matter, other models of human experience, right?
And that is the solution.
To build on what Robin said before about caring about damaged characters, if you are responsible
for creating post-traumatic stress disorder in some character you actually care about,
and you're not responsible for creating post-traumatic stress disorder, you're not responsible for
creating post-traumatic stress disorder.
And I think that's a really important part of that.
an eco-style game where you're really responsible for someone else and things that you do maybe
just to see, oh what would happen if I blew this up and all of a sudden this character
doesn't trust you anymore because a terrible explosion happened when you used your weapon.
That might be an interesting way of, you know, very simple ways to make you care about some
of these things.
I think maybe the difference between what you said originally, I didn't want to kill
it.
Yeah.
oh my god I didn't mean to kill it look what I have done and having the game
sell that to you of you like what Noah was saying of oh I have just affected something.
Yeah this is I mean I think this is the beauty of games like Shadow of the Colossus and Ico is
that they do and and you know Last Guardian they build a relationship between you and a character.
I mean, yes, the cameras suck.
And there are a lot of problems with those games.
That's another AI problem.
But there are definitely control issues
in those games, which are usually
related to budget and timelines more than anything else.
But those games do really focus on these narratives
where the surface of your control and your power
is it's a gambit between conscious reaction
from the system or an unconscious or unwanted
consequence.
And I do think that that's just good writing.
But if you could really build an animal that was an enemy that you also could create, you know,
some kind of a relationship with through some sort of hardship at the end, like,
it's going to eat you because it's hungry and you have to put it down, but you don't want to.
Like, that would be a really, like, like a bear that you raise that will eventually eat you
and then you have to make a decision at the end.
Do you sacrifice yourself and let it live or do you take its life?
Like, that's a, that would be a really interesting game to play
and I think it would create a lot of conversation about what.
you know, what games are about and empowering users.
I don't think these things are impossible to imagine.
I just think that we're focused on the wrong things.
A friendly robot named, I don't know,
Floyd who sacrifices himself for you.
Like we've been doing it the whole time.
You know, Chris Crawford actually
in The Art of Computer Game Design,
there is like a direct quote about this.
He's just like, the more fixed bits there are in your game,
the less of a good game it is.
There should not be fixed data in your game.
It should be dynamic.
It should always be changing.
The story should be changing.
The character should be changing.
The art should be changing.
He said this in 1982.
You know?
Kind of the corollary to Sid's game
is a series of interesting choices.
Yes.
Interesting ramifications.
Or responses.
Yeah, responses.
So Warren, he says the easy answer
is just an NPC would hesitate to go out in the rain, too.
I imagine that, whoa, jeez, it's raining.
and have that be unscripted, or encourage the player to go out,
oh, would you just get out there?
I could see that.
But what's another way that the AI would just blow you away,
that, oh, wow, that just happened?
Well, the thing I don't like about Warren's answer
is that it comes back down to the player at the bottom.
And I want to de-center the player, frankly.
The reason I love games like, um,
the stuff done by David Reilly, right?
Or Mountain and everything and so on,
is because they make you realize, well, you're not it, okay?
Inside the game, there is an inner life.
Inside the game, there are systems,
there are parts that are moving,
there is clockwork and magic and soul,
and all this is gonna go on whether you are here or not, okay?
And so, to a degree, I almost go,
the game that makes you feel guilty over killing something,
or the game...
That's almost just like, that's the baby step to getting you to realize that there is an
inner life back there.
Yeah, that's true.
The step beyond would be, I want to be proud of that thing.
I want to, you know, feel good because that thing did something without me, right?
That it's alive, that it's doing things on its own, right?
I want to de-center the player from this.
The parenting game.
The raising a child game.
Yeah, the AI, the systems, they're about conjuring a kind of life.
And if that's the case, then the thing that would blow me away is actually not just the realization,
holy shit that's alive, but it's doing things I didn't expect that weren't about me.
And as an individual with a point of view.
Yes.
Kate and Sergio earlier today in this very room had a really great example about
Navmesh that's flagged for keep off the grass signs so that NPCs will only go on the grass under certain circumstances
Unless they know all the words to this is your land
We are over time and I did I'm just not even gonna put this up but for a second Harvey Smith
Had jumped onto something talking about relationships and everything. But this bit right here is
every time we start a new project, we have to almost start from scratch.
We need to kind of, I'm not talking about, you know,
coming up with the one way of doing everything,
but he touches on the fact that why are we starting over and over and over and over again?
And because of that, it becomes prohibitive,
because we don't have three years to iterate on this system.
So there could be a quite simple answer to this, if I can dive straight in,
because we lack something that other creative industries have, which is consortiums.
or consortia perhaps, where the movie studios get together
and they agree on technical standards
around what the cameras are gonna do,
and then the hardware manufacturers manufacture that.
And we have the beginnings of that
with the stability of our hardware platforms.
I think we lack it right now, except in rendering.
The world representations are all different,
and so how do we plug into all that?
We have to establish not just the AI,
how do we represent stuff?
Right, right, and it is happening, right?
I mean in places, it happens in places like this room where we agree on the name of something like a piece of NavMesh and
share our best practices, but I wonder as we go forward
we could be benefited by getting together on an industrial scale.
Do more industrial organization.
Real quick, give me two sentences, your final wishes if you had your AI team,
me, all of the AI programmers in the world,
And you said, I need this out of you,
so I can make that thing that I want to get.
What would it be?
I'm here.
I'm thousands of AI devs.
And I've been putting in greatly.
I want you to help me build a very intimate romance
about two strong black women who fall in love.
Oddly specific.
OK.
I'm embarrassed to say that I just, and maybe this is the most important thing, I realize
that all my experience as a designer has led me to think, don't solve the problem, I'll
just have to design around the limitations.
So maybe that's just a statement, you know, not to make enemies, but the limitations of
where we're at right now.
That's why we're here, is we're trying to figure out what, what are we missing?
So you folks over here.
I'll go.
I, help me.
Give me.
tools to help me illustrate in my games the way that human beings struggle and we're all
just trying to get through.
I think there's a lot of good literary meaningful stuff.
It's going back to the empathy thing of the characters, you being able to be malleable
and...
Connect to a lot of different things, but yeah, more human stuff.
Okay.
Laureline?
So almost all games are online in some capacity now and gathering metrics, but certainly and
especially for all the games that actually are online and gathering metrics now...
Please take some of that effort you're
using toward gathering metrics and looking at play patterns.
And please use them to help the player experience,
and not just to make money.
OK, yeah, absolutely.
Raf, what do you got?
I want it all.
I mean, I want it all.
You're a big help.
This guy here.
I want to have the tools, the machine learning, the AI,
the rich data environment, to be able to make
a single.
probably online connected universe that we are in fact simulating down to the point where
the little pink alien gophers on the 13th planet around that particular green sun, which
was entirely procedurally generated, actually have a history and care about one another.
And I wanted to have all of that stuff and have all of it be alive specifically because
I want to drop a player into that world and have them realize.
as they play, that they are touching lives,
messing with things that are alive,
they are trampling grass that struggled to grow,
God damn it, and you're stepping on me again
to realize that when they build their virtual cities,
when they conquer their virtual enemies
that they are being colonialist about,
you know, all of those things,
I want them to realize that in their daily lives
they do the same thing in the real world
because I want.
the AI and the machine learning and the code and the systems out there to hold a mirror
back up to us as humans.
I want them to use that space as practice for being better here.
So give me all of it so that people can wake up and realize what they do day to day.
Earlier this evening I said, oh I don't have an end slide to put up on the screen and I
just made this up.
But tell me if this resonates.
Not more of the same, more of the different.
Not just better NPC AI, but better AI NPCs and a better game AI that makes the whole
game better.
Slash S. S slash game slash world.
Okay.
Yeah.
Right.
Replace game with world and I'm on board with that lesson. All right. Excellent again. I'm sorry. We're over time
But was this informative and inspirational?
And real quick
who here said some point in the past hour and nine minutes said I
Have an idea of what I could do to possibly start solving some of these
That's why we're here
Go forth and do it.
But be back here at 10 o'clock in the morning for the second day of the AI Summit.
Thank you folks.
Appreciate it.