And we're back for day three.
Day three.
Three of GDC Podcast Live.
I am your co-host Chris Graft, editor-in-chief of Gamasutra.
I'm here with...
Fellow co-host, news editor, and associate publisher at Gamasutra, Alyssa Macklin.
Hello.
Hey, so why does it feel like, you know, this is a virtual event, you know, and it's
the last day.
Why does it feel like we were just at physical GDC for five days, staying up until
3 a.m.
and drinking?
Yeah, like my energy level is about the same as it would be on like a final day of GDC,
but like my legs feel a lot better because I'm not like running up and down escalators.
So notable improvement there.
Yeah, yeah. My legs are my legs are doing OK.
All things considered.
Stay out of my yearly workout, though.
So yeah, yeah.
I didn't get too many steps in during the virtual.
But what do you think?
I mean, I really like it.
Yeah, no, it's great. It's been a great event as someone who writes talk coverage, the ability
to watch an on-demand talk right away or like within 15 minutes is just like, I'm not going
to be able to come back from this. It's I'm spoiled. It's too good, which is something
that more people should be talking about. If there was a talk you liked earlier on,
you can go back and just watch it on demand. Or if you missed it, you can watch it on demand.
It's great. It's amazing. Yeah, we are completely unrestrained by physical
boundaries now.
We have transcended.
That is right.
So I am hello everybody in chat.
Uh, thanks for joining us.
Uh, we have a really great guest, uh, that I can't wait to get on.
So I'm not gonna wait.
Uh, except I'm going to make you wait because I want to do this intro.
Uh,
She co-founded the highly influential web-based gaming site and publisher Congregate with her
brother in 2006 and sold it to GameStop, as one does. She's a free-to-play games expert.
She's an International Game Developers Association board member.
Former and current GDC speaker whose talk should be available for free like right now on the platform.
Founder of the newly minted Double Loop Games and according to her Twitter profile
is a figure skater and according to her just because like I'm gonna be the judge here
she's just a fun person to hang out with so let's welcome Emily Greer. Hey Emily.
Hello.
Hello!
Yes.
I hung out with you Chris, it was fun.
Thanks so much for joining us, really appreciate it.
And great talk by the way, which we will get into.
Thank you very much.
As an aside, we've now had a pilot and a figure skater on the podcast, right?
Do we have Skydiver or was it pilot?
David Gardner? Yeah, David Gardner flies planes, does not jump out of them.
Okay. As far as I know, he didn't bring them up.
So interesting athletic copies you're fitting right in.
Yes. I hope that whoever is the pilot is a better pilot than I am a figure skater.
I have more love than capabilities, which is not a good thing when you're a pilot,
but it's just fine when you're a figure skater. It's the part that counts.
Yeah, but airplanes have wings.
They can kind of coast if the engine dies.
Figure skater just fall on...
I know what I'm talking about.
You slide.
That's the thing that people don't under appreciate.
It actually hurts so much less to fall on ice
than on pavement.
I look at skateboarders and I'm like, how can you do it?
With a figure skater, you just like slide 10 feet
and it's not that bad.
It truly is not that bad.
That sounds painful.
Thank everyone for joining us for the ice skating.
I feel like there's a game dev metaphor there, but I'm not gonna go down that whole rabbit hole.
Yeah, sliding on your butt on ice is not that bad.
So, okay, Emily, anyway, can you tell us a little bit about your story and history in games?
How did you become involved in the game industry?
I came in a kind of a weird way.
I think actually that's true of a lot of people,
but I think mine was particularly weird.
I had a 10-year career in catalogs and e-commerce
doing what would now be called data science and UA,
but it was called direct marketing then.
And then my brother, who'd been in the game industry
since he dropped out of college to work on Ultima VII,
had the idea to start Kongregate.
And I started helping him with his business plan
and thought this is a good idea.
This is going to be a lot more fun than mailing the next million catalogs to somebody.
Let's why don't I work in games instead of cutting down trees and volunteer to his co-founder?
So that was my first entry into games.
And I played games all along, but I, you know, I'm not I don't have that core gamer
identity that most people in the industry have, which is, I think, something that is.
Unusual about me, but also I think has been a strength through the career.
So yeah, we built, as you talked about, we built up Congregate as the web platform.
After we sold the GameStop, I ended up taking over as CEO, living out, you know,
every younger sibling's fantasy of like toppling their brother, you know, off the throne.
And then we built a mobile publishing business and published things like Adventure Capitalist
and Animation Throwdown.
And then, you know, after 13 years, I'd been in the game industry and I'd done platform and I'd done publishing, but I'd never actually made games.
And I really wanted to make games.
So I ended up leaving Kongregate last year, took a little time off and then co-founded a studio with my friend Shelby Molodina called Double Loop Games, making games for mobile.
Very awesome. I mean, like, Kongregate, like, hugely, hugely influential, like, of course.
So we can, we can get back to that in a little bit, but since we don't have unlimited time with
you, I want to talk about your, we want to talk about your session that you gave about workplace
Trust and team building and really anti-harassment steps that you can take. Can you tell us a little
bit about the talk for those who weren't able to attend? Yeah, you know, we've, over the last few
years, there's been kind of wave after wave, maybe about every six months, of stories coming out from
different companies and really all over the industry of different MeToo stories and different
harassment stories. And
I, you know, I had every time one of those came out, I was feeling I would feel really depressed and sort of hopeless.
And then I started thinking about, you know, all the things that we did at Congregate to make things better and to make employees feel safe and make it a place where we could stop harassment.
And I was like, actually, that's probably useful advice for everybody.
So I wanted to put together a talk that.
Really gives a bigger picture of the problem of abuse and harassment, you know, why it happens,
why it's really damaging to the company more than people realize. And just really practical,
pragmatic things you can do just to make the everyday experience of your employees better,
but also to prevent abuse and harassment. So that was sort of the genesis of this talk. And yeah.
It's good. And it also draws on some of my own experiences in the game industry with harassment.
That's the crazy thing is even though I've only ever been a founder in my own company,
I still actually had, you know, multiple cases of, you know, gender and sexual harassment that
I've experienced. So that combination of being both a leader and, you know, survivor of it,
I think is a kind of a gave me a great lens to talk about it.
And I know the people who watch it really appreciate, you know, you coming forward about those things because those are those incidents that happen because I know that's, you know, difficult to talk about, but it does make people feel not alone, you know, so we all appreciate that.
I know with, you said that you built this based on, or your talk was kind of built around your own experiences and kind of things that you've come to realize from your own time in the industry.
Why do you, why do you think that like other companies have maybe not been able to come to the same realizations on their own? Is there just missing conversations or just the company buildup or what's the common factor there?
You know, when you're, when you're running a company,
There is so much day to day just to survive and to build and deal with immediate crises, it's hard to take that step back and really think about how the system is working more broadly. Well, I did come a lot of it from my own experiences and things that
That we've done at Congregate, a lot of that was reacting to my own experience. And again,
the fact that I had experienced it, I think made it easier for me as a leader
to intuit what would make, what kind of steps would make it better for employees.
There's also a lot that I talk about that really doesn't have to do with abuse management. It's
just good practices from team building. I talk about Google and their research on psychological
safety and how it makes more effective teams, the game's outcomes, projects we do.
You guys at Gamasutra had a great series of blog posts and was a GDC talk.
They've also looked at it.
So some of these things are people are already figuring out.
They're just not necessarily connecting it to the abuse and harassment.
The other thing is, is that I did rely a lot on research.
I had when I decided to do this talk, I took time over actually probably about six
months reading as much literature as I could.
I got my professor mother to download all sorts of academic articles for me off of JSTOR.
I didn't link to any of them because they're not freely available, but they were helpful for me in
terms of understanding it more broadly. And in particular, there was a US EEOC, the Equal
Employment Opportunity Commission, did a study in 2016, which is just a wealth of knowledge
and information, and I linked to that on Twitter.
And from the talk and that that was a real really big big help to sort of get my brain around it.
Those wider kind of academic articles for other industries and for just like
employment as a whole do those have a lot of parallels with game development or is it
quite different? For the most part it's really similar. Now there's some situations where they
where they talk about you know domestic domestic workers or you know satellite retail stores which
are
You know, relevant to something like GameStop, but not,
it's rare to have sort of two or three person little pods
that are remote in game industry.
So some of that stuff is specific to them.
Some of that stuff is specific to manufacturing.
But because the core of the problem comes back
to humans' desire for power
and desire to push people down to raise themselves up,
That's just incredibly universal. And so it doesn't matter whether you're looking at high
fashion or movies or games or a retail store, a lot of the same themes keep coming out.
The way that you talked about the power dynamic was really interesting to me.
You say that we have some misconceptions of what drives harassment. Can you explain that?
Yeah, so especially when you're talking about Me Too, you, and all the stories, a lot of the stories involve kind of sort of lurid sexual type of stuff.
And it's very easy to think that's about sex and about people being driven by sex and wanting sex.
Because, you know, again, that's a universal thing that we feel.
But the more that you look at individual stories and you look at the individual patterns, sex is almost a symptom rather than the cause.
It is.
A, about that feeling of power that you have when you force somebody into something,
when you put them on their feet, when you control them. And so with women,
when it's male to female in particular, it's nearly always power, sort of oppression and power
dynamics. When you're trying to push somebody down, you use sexual language. It seems to be very common.
Men to men, it will often happen as well.
And then it tends to be, you know, like homophobic slurs and other other types of things,
but also pushing men into, you know, female gender as a way to push them down.
And then it gets into all sorts of other things.
So sex and sexual language is often just a just a way similar behavior is expressed.
I'm trying to keep this clean because it's a podcast.
When male to male, it might be, you know, you're a total fucking idiot, right? And, you know,
homophobic slurs, niggers, and then with women, it's about sex. But it is always about you're
less than me. I'm making myself bigger in relation.
So I also want to ask about this whole theory of one bad apple, which you talked about.
And, you know, people say, oh, the bad apples are gone now. You see it happening in companies now.
There's a little tiny bit of a culling of like people who've been caught.
But what's your, what are your thoughts on the one bad apple idea?
Yeah. One is that.
It can't be just one bad apple if we're seeing it in so many companies of so many different sizes and so many different regions. It's coming up again and again.
It's you know, the actual analogy for one bad apple is that one bad apple spoils the whole whole bunch. It's actually about.
One poisonous thing making everything around it worse.
And that's actually a better analogy.
If you think about it, that is much more what is going on.
The other thing is, you know, there's a lot of denial about it.
You know, when Me Too really broke in 2017, I think a lot of people were
surprised at how really common these kinds of experiences were.
And.
We've been pushing things kind of under the surface for a while.
And so the, um, there's a desire.
And part of that is that there's a real desire for things to be okay, for things
to not be a problem and to not have to think, you know, bad things about your
coworker or bad things about your friend.
It's also much easier just to blame, to put things all in one individual than
think about.
systemic problems and how things interact. And one of the things I talk about in my talk is that
you know harassment isn't binary where you know it happens or it hasn't happened, it's illegal or
it isn't illegal. There's a whole spectrum of behavior that starts with like you know mean
trash talking that
Is it, you know, nobody would ever consider illegal, but is sort of the beginning of that kind of, you know, abusive talk.
And then you can, you know, get to, you know, people giving each other ball taps and other things like that before you get to harassment.
And that's the other problem.
When you, when you say something is one bad apple, you can just, it's just this easy problem.
You get rid of them, you find them, it's over.
But when you really look at it, and it's this whole spectrum of behavior, and a lot of people have behaved that way to some degree, then it's just much harder to deal with.
And that's one of the things where I think it's really important to understand is that we all live up or down to our environment and surroundings to some degree.
Nobody's a saint. Nobody is completely evil. I mean, there's probably...
I think it's a great.
Yeah, people were just just doing the best that we can in
environments that we are in. And we're looking around us to
figure out what's right and what's wrong. And so when things
are sort of gradually moving in a bad direction, a lot of us
will move with it too. And
But that also means that if we, we can move things in a good direction, and we can move a lot of people to as well so that's the sort of the upside and downside there is that we're moving as a group one way or another group norms are really powerful, and that you need to think about the group behavior and not just the individual.
Yeah.
Somebody in chat, Cherry, said almost like we have a systemic problem, eh?
Yeah. Can you talk a little bit about Emily's general theory of human behavior? That was
interesting, and it's good that you, you know, name a theory after us. I haven't done that yet,
but, you know, I need to figure mine out. Well, I, I...
I didn't mostly as much as possible.
I try to give references.
I try to give back up,
but this is just me talking and graphs and everything.
I mean, I am a stats geek.
I'm going to, I had a chance to spell curve in.
Of course I'm going to do that.
Spell curve and Emily's theory.
That's me.
I'm staying on brand
given what I'm talking about a heavy subject.
So, but yeah, I talked about it a little bit before.
It's essentially that there's some percentage of people
that will always be good in some situation.
And there's some people who will always be predatory,
but most of us are in the middle,
in a kind of bell curve
around whatever the group norms were in.
And group norms are set by leaders
and by kind of the culture that we live in.
And we, there's not only so much we can do about the culture that we live in, but leaders can have
a really disproportionate impact on what, how group norms in bringing in, bringing them for
good. In some cases, I talk about big, huge games and what they've done there, or Uber being the
example of leaders pulling sort of a lawlessness and sort of disregard for harm.
And I think, you know, I grew up moving all over the world and living a lot of different places.
And I think when you have that experience of going, seeing people are people, but also how they behave,
organize is really differently in different places.
It really helps give you that kind of distance of, oh, culture is not one thing.
Culture is us coming together.
And.
Not consciously deciding it's one thing, but iteratively deciding it's one thing.
So, oh sorry. I was reading in chat, someone's bullying the Gamma Suture website design right
now and I was getting defensive. Oh wait, let's look at this real quick.
Yeah, I want to follow up on that, but like you just gave a really excellent talk on that.
So the better option would be just to have people get your full thoughts
and the thought or thoughts in your talk that I had time to rehearse.
And I was going to be like, all right, what are your quick tips for fixing studio cultures?
And like, that's not the way to handle it.
Sure it is. Yeah.
Yeah, okay, so I think that maybe we should talk a little bit about, you know, double loop games
and things that, you know, on the business side of what you do. Can you talk about,
tell us a little bit about double loop and what you're trying to do differently there?
Yeah, so double loop is, sort of comes back to kind of my experience as
As a gamer, somebody who plays games a lot, who really enjoys them, but doesn't have that core identity, that core gamer identity.
And for a long time, in the game industry, I sort of felt like I had a...
certain level of imposter syndrome.
And then we started doing mobile publishing
and the team would joke about the Emily test,
the games that I played more than six or seven sessions
were always our hits.
I was like, the team wasn't gonna sign Adventure Capitalist
for mobile and I was like, no, we have to,
I can't stop playing it, right?
And that made me realize that what it felt like,
What was giving me imposter syndrome was actually a strength. I represent the big mass market of
mobile players who play games and love games but don't think of themselves as gamers. And
you know, there's no part of the games industry that's not competitive, but if there's one part
of the market that's underserved, it's that part. And I want to make games for that audience. You
know, I want to do what most people in the games industry want to do. I want to make games for
myself. And that...
It really focuses a lot around why I play games, which is when I'm most stressed.
That's when I'm on my couch playing, you know, match threes and tower defense and
idle games and have basketball or the British baking show in the background.
And so I want to make really the relaxing games and I want to make games that are
really social and that help connect us to people and bring those two things together.
So we're not talking about the title that we're making yet because of there's a lot of cloning
in mobile. So when you do something innovative you try to, you know, keep it close to your chest
until you absolutely have to show it. But that's the general sort of mindset that we're taking to
it. We're still a small team which is really fun. Congregate was like 120 people towards the end
and it's lovely to be back to, you know, the number of people you can fit around a table and really
talk to. We're about eight people right now.
And yeah, we're hoping to launch sometime in 2021.
I feel like when you hear people talk about games in that category
that are like the casual games, like the farm bills
or like sitting on your couch with your mobile phone, kind of like the mom games.
I don't I don't like that term, but I know like kind of where it comes from
that you hear about it as like, oh, here's this untapped market market.
Here's how to get women into games and how to make money off of them.
But you guys seem to be taking a lot more like personal.
We just want to create something enjoyable approach with it.
Yeah, you know, I think the best games are always made with real emotion and real respect and understanding for the audience.
And I want to take advantage of the fact that I am that sort of mom gamer.
in the games industry. There's not a lot of us in the games industry for lots of reasons.
I really think that we, and Shelby is also, my co-founder is also a mom. I'm not a mom,
actually. I'm a mom. I love those types of, I'm not a mom either, but that term defines me.
Because we're the audience, we can make better games.
And more sort of authentic and joyful games because we're not guessing what somebody likes.
We are, we know what we like. We know who they are and we think we can make better games.
It's a refreshing perspective. I'll say that much about it. It's nice to like hear
how you guys have phrased it and like your press release when you guys announced your
seed funding was just like this really heartwarming way of describing a market
that I feel like doesn't usually get that kind of loving attention.
That's, I don't want to call anybody out
because there's lots of amazing games out there
that I've played a lot of, but I also,
but I, it's something that I struggled with
in the industry is feeling like the kind of player
that I am and that kind of audience is less respected.
And I think it's equally, it's a-
It's a great audience.
I don't lie.
And you know, and our needs are just as valid.
And-
You know, I'm here and I want to make games on that premise.
Yeah. Well, when you're going around and you're trying to raise funding for this,
when you tell them what kind of audience you are targeting, is there a reservation? Do you have to
really, like, argue for it? Or... No, I mean, you know, the numbers are just there, you know.
Mobile is half of the game industry now.
I mean, and that's just meteoric growth
in the last decade.
And when you look at surveys of the US market,
70% of people who play games on mobile
don't think of themselves as gamers.
You know, you're talking about 70% of the market.
You know, it's hard to deny it.
And I also think that one of the changes that I've seen
since we raised money for Congregate,
And I think that's a really important thing to remember.
And I think that's one of the things that we learned in 2006 is that there is more appreciation of.
That the audience game audience is broader than it was originally was thought to be.
And that.
Diverse founders and diverse voices.
Can help fill that gap.
It was.
I didn't really believe in sexism.
Until.
We raised money for congregate.
Going through the double loop process, just to feel a big reversal on that.
Now, you know, it helps that, you know, I'm a repeat founder.
VC is always like that, but I, but I think that there was an attitude
shift, even independent of that.
And I have a lot of female friends who are starting studios now and
able to raise money in publishing.
Um, there's a, you know, there, there's just a whole wave of us that I think,
um, will be helping to change the industry going forward.
What parallels do you see right now versus 2006
when you founded Kongregate?
Are there any parallels you see with like mobile,
the mobile game market,
or is it just a completely different ball game?
You know, it's really, it's such a different ball game.
And you know, in 2006,
we were all still on feature phones, right?
Like I was playing Bejeweled on, you know, my little Nokia.
Snake.
And,
and that,
The mobile games market was controlled by the carriers and jammed at, you know, EA had just bought Jamdat.
And mobile was really just like not even a gleam in the eye of, or barely a gleam in the eye in
terms of like, you know, could being half of the industry. And the other thing was that free-to-play
was not, was nascent. It was really growing in China and Korea, but it hadn't come to the West
yet. And so.
The amount of change that's happened in the industry in 14 years is kind of astounding.
And it's been a fun ride.
And it's also been one where every year it's been about expanding the game industry
and expanding the audience and getting bigger.
And it's lovely to be in an expanding market as opposed to one where it's a shrinking market
where everybody's defensive.
This is
In a growing market, it's easier to be optimistic and collaborative and
lots of things like that that I like.
I'm kind of like keeping an eye on chat at the same time, so I apologize if I'm like re-asking the same thing that Chris just asked, but considering how much experience you have in like the PC and like browser-based games, are there a lot of parallels to mobile games in those kind of like how the players are, how the games are formulated?
Yeah, I mean the browser games in the late 2000s or you know, sorry, late 2000s.
Like 2007 when we launched through 2013,
you know, that was where you went to play
sort of the quick games, you know,
when you wanted to play a game for like 10 minute sessions
and to, you know, to feel that,
see the innovation in terms of mechanics.
And it was sort of the most accessible path
compared to consoles or, you know,
doing a big heavy download when you're.
Your internet sucked. Browser games was the accessible format. And now mobile is the most
accessible format, so that's where you see the biggest audience. But, you know, browser games
aren't dead. They're the most accessible format of PC. You know, it's been pretty traumatizing
to have Flash go away. Yeah.
But you know HTML5 and a lot of other technologies have really developed and you can make
you know quite good games for browser now and as long as that as kids are allowed to do their
schoolwork on computers when but not allowed to play on on phones or consoles browser games will
never die. Yeah.
I think my circle in high school definitely got all of the good
like congregate level sites blocked because of just the sheer volume of time we spent on there.
So one of the secrets of congregate is I think we,
because we didn't have name, our name and our title,
we were less likely to get blocked by school administrators than other sites.
So we were kind of like the stealth game site you could play.
Generations appreciate that.
We stumbled into it.
Olivia Schwerz and Chad agrees, I grew up playing browser games.
I didn't have a console for a while and no handhelds.
So they were my gaming experiences.
Some really innovative flash games that I remember playing
that just had like that really good influence on you.
Yeah, I actually kind of heartening that flash games were such the,
you know, disrespected backwater back when, you know, Kongregate was at the payday.
It's like, oh, flash games, they're not real games.
But now.
With Flash dying, there's been so much appreciation of how much innovation there was and how much it was really like the birth of indies.
And when you look both at mobile and at PC indie, there's so many threads of big hits that came out of Flash.
You know, Meat Boy being an example, or, you know, Angry Birds is essentially, you know,
a re-skin of Crush the Castle. Like, there's just, there's so much, Flash Games gave so much to the
rest of the industry, and I feel like it's getting a little bit more appreciated now that it's
almost dead, because that's... Sorry, I know someone just mentioned elf-fooling in chat,
and I just went all the way back. Oh, yeah.
It's nice to see the preservation efforts that people have stepped up to to archive
these games.
And that's really important.
And it's that same heartwarming feeling you were just talking about, that people do care
about these still.
Yeah, absolutely.
Yeah.
And so what's your take on overall on the, we've got like a couple of minutes here,
what's your take on the mobile game market right now? Because there is a lot of reach obviously,
but that also means, you know, there's a lot, it's inundated, it's very crowded. How do you
deal with that as a startup? I'm gonna
Raise quite a bit of money is the one.
You have to break through the noise, but there's a lot of opportunity there.
You are seeing new hits break out every year and get up into the top 10 and top 20.
And if you look at it, you know, because the market is so big, a lot of games.
are not necessarily famous, but are able to break through to a significant level and,
you know, really sustain a studio and grow. But, you know, you have to, you know, you have to make
a great game that resonates emotionally, which is always hard, and you have to figure out the
marketing side. And both of those are important. It's been, you used to get a lot more out of
featuring. And that was one of the things that was sort of, it's been very hard.
To watch in the last few years is how much the value of featuring has decreased.
So you can't just build a business off of that.
You have to figure out marketing.
Now, I've spent my whole career in marketing, right?
Like I did that.
That was what I did for 10 years before I even got into games.
So it, you know, it's sort of comfortable and familiar territory,
but it's challenging and it requires both, you know,
infrastructure and capital.
That makes it hard for a small indie to break out in a big way.
But that's the story, unfortunately, of most of the game industry.
Consoles and other things where consolidation towards bigger players.
We were in some ways I think we were kind of spoiled for a while with how much diversity
we could sustain but that's not how markets work. They tend to crush that. But it is really
great to still see you know how much diversity and how much interesting stuff goes on in especially
the PC world and you know both on Steam and places like Itch. There's you know there's a lot of
there's a lot of
Good small games. I think a lot of games doing well on Switch, so there's still a market there.
Mobile though is definitely pretty dominated by big players.
Well, I think that you're going to do great.
Got a pretty good track record and you're pretty good with a bell curve.
So I think that, uh, we want to be on the good side of that.
And then also we want that hockey stick curve.
That's actually, that's the kind of curve I want to, I want to drop.
We're going to have you back just to talk about different
graphs and things like that.
But only in the audio format, you'll have to describe them verbally.
Yeah.
The graphs with the Chris graft.
So, well, thank you so much for joining us.
Just a reminder, this, Emily's Talk is free on this platform.
So if you're listening to this right now live, you can go to it.
Just look for Emily's Talk from Thursday.
It's also going to be, I mean, it's free for anyone to, like, register and watch it, too.
Emily's talk, which was called RESPECT, Practical Tips to Prevent Abuse and Build Team Trust,
if you want keywords to look for.
Yeah.
And that talk, ever since I learned the name of it, RESPECT, like that, the song has been
stuck in my head ever since.
So effective marketing.
You are a marketer.
So.
And also there is a write-up on gamasutra.com, and it's kind of, it touches on a few points,
but it also includes a link to Emily's full presentation deck along with notes. So please,
you know, take advantage of that, show that to your co-workers, you know, that's,
and that's what it's there for.
I really had to squeeze to get it into 45 minutes, so there's stuff in the notes that I had to cut out and not say.
It's good to watch it all, but it's also good to read the notes and see what things I had to cut.
Yeah, absolutely. So, well, thanks again. So, we're going to take a break for a few minutes
for a word from our sponsor, and then the Yamasutra team will be back to just hang out.
So, we'll be in chat. Please don't go anywhere. And thanks again, Emily. Really appreciate it.
Thank you so much.
Thank you. I really appreciate the opportunity.
Next, we'd like to welcome one of our sponsors, Julie Shoemaker,
VP of Operate Solutions at Unity.
Hey, Julie, thanks for joining us.
Thank you so much, Chris. Good to be here.
Yeah, awesome. So, can you tell us a little bit about yourself,
your background in the game industry and what you do at Unity?
Great. Well, I've had the pleasure to be in the game industry now 20 years.
I joined Electronic Arts in 2001
on the licensing and advertising side
and have followed a journey through games,
multi-platform from social play and mobile,
largely on the game publisher side.
And in 2016, I was able to take that learning
and come over to Unity.
And help do those services on behalf of the industry.
In essence, my revenue responsibility in Operate Solutions
spans from monetization products,
largely the part of the business we're going to talk about today
with the COVID-19 study,
as well as cloud services, player engagement,
which was one area where we pulled a lot of data about game behavior,
and finally, of course, advertising.
So...
My primary mission at Unity is to enable developer success
so that they can build strong and profitable businesses.
Interesting. So you mentioned the COVID-19 report,
and of course that's top of mind for a lot of people in games right now
and why we're doing this on video. So can you talk about
that report and how Unity gathered that data?
Yeah, so Chris, I think when you and I started this call,
before we clicked the video,
we were just chatting about the new normal.
And of course, we were watching what was happening
in predominantly Asia as they were sheltering in place
in January and February.
So the week of March 8th,
when World Health Organization declared global pandemic
is really when what we consider in the COVID report,
the...
The bulk of the shift in behavior and some of the data behind this.
The methodology of the COVID-19 report is that we first started with a baseline
growth to compare against 2019 as our baseline number. So in essence to normalize what is
already a growing industry of games, we took a normalized data set starting in Jan 1 and then we
added mobile information that we secure
from the Unity monetization platform on usage in mobile.
We then also complemented that data
with a source of information on PC and console gaming
from our Made with Unity content as a development platform.
And finally, we took player engagement data
anonymized through our Delta DNA product
that helped us see engagement rates
as well as the revenue implications of COVID-19.
Okay, so when you're reviewing this data, what was the most surprising aspects of it
that jumped out to you?
Well, first of all, many.
I mean, we were humbled by, you know, this very difficult time in the world that games
have
Shown that they're bringing a real bright spot.
And so a couple of the data points that jumped out was,
first of all, 46% increase in daily active users
in PC and console gaming.
And that data jumped out because it really shines a light on families.
You know, what we used to call, like, the virtual...
Card or board game is now your Xbox in the living room
with your family members.
The bright spot in even mobile gaming,
17% increase in daily active users
just showed that people wanted this sense of community,
sense of play, and of course,
ability to focus on something that might be more positive
for their mindshare than what was happening
in the world at the time.
And I saw the survey also showed increases in ad viewing and really like huge increase in app downloads 84% increase and increase in downloads.
So.
Can all, like all of this is, you know, just because people are at home and having more downtime then?
Is that the conclusion or is there any other factors?
Well, I think what we look at is, first of all, if we think about the ad impressions.
So ad impressions increase 57%.
Okay.
And in our category, ad impressions are often an opportunity of discovery for players.
So if you're going to increase impressions, you're actually increasing the likelihood
that they're discovering new apps and downloading those apps.
So that's one thing.
Another area, when we go back to that 17% increase in daily active players also means new players.
And new players have more room to grow in their what games I'm going to play.
So we see that the increase in downloads is connected to many of the behaviors combined.
So when you're looking at this data, what are some practical ways,
you know, some takeaways that game developers can take from, you know,
they look at this report, how can they apply the information that they have,
like to what they're doing?
Well, I think first of all, we would say, um,
many of the game developers that have benefited greatly
have been dual economy and they have IEP based revenues, which have increased as well.
And actually, IEP went up 24%.
during this window.
So that means consumer pay increased, as did ad pay.
So the developers that have both economies
did have greater opportunity during this time.
And of course, also greater opportunity to engage the player,
because often a player who doesn't want to pay.
has an opportunity to get a new level or grow their experience and engagement with the game
through the rewarded ad business. So that would be one. Certainly on a forward-looking basis,
our biggest guidance is that this is the opportunity for great game makers
to engage this new pandemic player.
So what do you think happens after things, you know, hopefully sooner rather than later go back to normal, whatever that looks like?
Do these numbers go back down, you know, or do they go back down to where they were before lockdown happened?
Well, we see that the data shows during this now, you know, what, five and a half windows,
five and a half months of the window of deep look at the data that we're.
that the users are continuing to engage.
So our guidance would be,
we won't make a forward-looking statement
on what players are going to do in the long run,
but we will encourage our developer economy
to take advantage of this opportunity
to engage these players.
Thanks, that was really interesting.
Thank you for joining us
and best of luck out there and stay safe.
Wonderful, thank you, Chris.
Thanks.
Hey, we're back.
Thanks for sticking around with Julie Shoemaker from Unity.
And thank you, Unity, for sponsoring this.
I put a link in chat for that COVID-19 report,
so make sure to check it out.
And there will also be a link in the video on demand of this.
So you can look at it then.
So we're actually joined.
by Bryant, Francis, and Alex.
Can you all introduce yourselves a little bit more in depth?
I'm Bryant Francis, sometimes known in the Gamasutra world as Bront.
I'm a contributing editor at Gamasutra, and as today has shown,
I love Star Wars a lot, if you were watching the speedrun.
I'm Alex Waro, an editor at Gamasutra.com, and I gotta say the Gamasutra retro design is about to come back into style.
Yeah, let's let's let's we had we had a question in the middle of our chat with with Emily Greer, which she's amazing, isn't she?
Yeah, I wish you were able to join us for this last segment, but prior engagements and busy, important people and important things.
Yeah, I mean, we're lucky to have we are neither busy nor important.
I wasn't going to say it, but...
Yeah, I know. We wouldn't be doing this if we were actually busy.
Yeah.
Cult Zone Games.
That's weird. Is that on the birth certificate, you think?
Cult Zone Games?
Where, like, when's Gamasutra
going to renew the old site?
Do you have any idea what they're talking about?
I mean, what-
I think the blinking eye Gamasutra logo
that pops up every like six months in Slack
should be, that should be front and center on our site.
I haven't noticed that there's anything outdated.
On the site.
No.
When did our site get named again?
When did we name it after a Southeast Asian Indian document?
We did not name it.
No, we were all later in the team.
But I was looking this up yesterday in 1997 is when Gamma Suture was founded.
So what a fun fact.
We should have all known that we worked for this freaking city.
I was looking it up to see how old I was.
What were you all doing in 1997?
Yeah, let's talk about this.
Brian, you go first.
Bronson in 1987.
Let's see. Seven years old.
I may not have even seen Star Wars yet because I think my mom
may have made me wait until I was eight.
So I would have definitely been playing with Batman figures.
I would have been in about second grade, which means I moved to late
until Maryland by that point.
And I was getting bullied a lot in school.
That's what I'm pretty sure of.
I was watching anime and eating rocks because I was like five.
I don't know what five year old do.
They're hardcore, apparently.
Damn.
Wait, Alex, what were you doing?
You know, I was just working a job,
just punching a clock like any average.
I must have been 11, 12, I don't know.
No, I was-
You were writing content?
Yes, right, I was just writing content
from the day I came out of the,
isn't that the year of the Symphony that I came out?
I feel like, 97?
That's probably what I was doing.
That's probably just spending my whole summer
reading Final Fantasy VII and Symphony of the Night.
Speaking of timely things, favorite talk so far. What have you guys covered? What do you like?
What's going good at the show? I'll be going to, I know Emily Greer, we already, she brought up a
lot of points in her talks, but I have to make it, put that as one of my favorite talks I covered.
She said something here on the podcast that she said specifically in the talk, which is
Harassment is sometimes about sex,
but it's always about power.
And when she said that, and I'm just sitting there,
you know, clacky clacky, and I wrote it,
I swear to God, like mentally,
my brain like shot backwards across the room into the wall
from like linking things.
Only because like, if I can get a little personal here,
I've lived that over and over again.
I have been,
because it happens to men in the workplace too,
and these aren't mostly gaming companies
because I've worked in other places,
but.
I have been sexually harassed while I've been at work.
I've been yelled at and screamed at at different jobs.
I've had people like, I've had different kinds of like threats thrown at me in different
contexts and it's so weird because you spend a lot of time going like, holy, whoa, that
was rough.
And like, you take a day, like you cool off, you're back at work for something or another.
And, and the line, like, it's not about.
It's sometimes about sex.
It's always about power and her story in the talk, which if you go watch is about
the the random game exec who was inappropriately hitting on her dinner.
Just like the connection there, like finally clicked in my head.
And like, I think I started like I've spent this year, like processing
a lot of what happened to me in that context, because when the news about
a lot of game companies being called out this year for behavior that.
People have experienced it, them hit.
Like I started like when writing up some of it, I was like, oh, wait,
I guess I've experienced this, too.
And like that turned out you need you need to like process that
and you need to like go deal with that in therapy.
Like you can't just keep acting like, oh, yeah, like it's just something I cover.
It's not something I live through.
And it's like, oh, no, I lived through that.
And her framing of it that way, like I think about all the companies
that where people were power hungry, where people were like fighting for placement
or favor.
And I'm just like, even when it wasn't sexual harassment, I was just like,
Oh wow, like Lisa Simpson staring.jpg.
And that just, I cannot stress enough.
She talked about it earlier in the podcast
and that's why I was hoping she'd be here
to mention it to her that like,
whoa, like that hit me like a truck.
But you know, she's not here,
so I can just share with you, you know,
some deep, dramatic secrets.
And over to Alex.
Alex, no pressure.
What's your favorite talk?
Men are garbage.
That's my favorite talk.
Wow, so woke.
Yeah.
Um, no, that's that's rough buddy. I, uh, I'm sorry to hear that.
It's bad times. I, yeah, I agree. Emily's talk was fantastic. I have not watched it yet. I was
watching some other talks today, including a really good talk on Hardspace Shipbreaker.
I love that game.
A sharp right turn.
I would have mentioned that talk if I hadn't because I love the game.
The name of that game just like twists my brain sideways.
Are you going to spoil the end of a game right now that just recently came out?
What end?
I can't beat it.
I'm too busy carving spaceships.
I can tell you why there's no end because I just watched a talk all about how that team
had to pivot multiple times, including at one point moving from...
What was maybe going to be a more narrative heavy and shorter game into like a longer and more broad, like systemic game.
And I don't know, people should go watch that talk on the platform because it's packed. It is really packed with a lot of key learnings.
Yeah, it's just it's it's a remarkable chart of how an idea goes from a game jam internally to a ship product that seems to have like a huge fan base.
I think it's really cool, really neat. It's, it's nice to see studios thriving, you know, like the folks that are Blackbird. A key part of the talk was that they see themselves much in the vein of like a blizzard or digital extremes or a psionics and that, you know, they work for other companies and they work on other IP but they really are always trying to make their own original games and like, strike it big.
And so go watch that talk because it would take me 10 minutes to sum up here, but basically they chart the four year journey from original idea to successful original IP. I think that's really relevant these days where so many devs are trying to get noticed with their own ideas.
Yeah. Yeah. Can I talk about mine real quick, the one that I was like, I, I covered.
Karen Stevens from EA Sports, who is the lead accessibility lead.
And the point that she kept driving home was that legibility is, like she said,
if you get anything out of this talk, font-like legibility.
You know, fix that.
And that's my own, that's me, like,
showing my own privilege there,
because, like, I've got good, you know, I got good sight.
But I do remember in 2006,
when the HD consoles were hitting Dead Rising,
like, nobody could read the text in Rising 1 on Xbox 360.
And here we are in 2020,
Right? Are we still? Yeah.
Yes, we will always be in 2020.
Some part of us.
So basically when Emily Greer was getting her career started up until now,
font legibility has been like crap.
And then...
What do you mean? Karen Stevens or Emily Greer?
No, I'm talking about Emily Greer's career.
She started in 2006.
Oh, OK.
Yeah, yeah.
Frame of reference.
Yeah, we're trying to figure out frames of reference for time.
So yeah, just the fact that that's not a fixed thing yet
is kind of mind-blowing.
And of course, her point is, you can add all these accessibility
options.
But.
If I can't, you know, see the menu or recognize like where those options are living, where they're buried in the game.
Then they don't really matter to so many people.
So, yeah, I mean, and then the thing about Comic Comic Sans, like
I think I'd heard that before and forgot about it.
But looking up Comic Sans, I know that it's like maligned and stuff
and made fun of, but it's good for dyslexia.
And like designers, you know, are like, shut up.
Stop making fun of Comic Sans.
Like, this is good design.
Yeah, good idea.
Yeah, and then to have, um, and then, you know, I know that there's probably, you know, developers and like, uh, designers out there just imagining their game just covered in comic sans, uh, you know, but she's, she said, you know, the option would be good.
You know, you can have the fancy font and you can turn on a more legible font.
as well.
And she also brought up the point, like, you know, a game like Outer Worlds, it defaults
to very small font.
And then they released a patch that increases it.
But it still defaults to that original tiny font.
And she said, just because you add a size option
doesn't mean that you're off the hook for making it illegible
from when you start the game.
So I'm like, after watching that,
that's just changed my viewpoint on.
on legibility and really accessibility overall.
It's been really enlightening this week.
So yeah, that's me.
Alyssa, do you have a talk you wanna bring up?
Yeah, but I also just want to comment.
It's not a question, more of a comment.
But it's I love talks like that because they re-contextualize accessibility.
It's people have this very like, oh, it's colorblind settings,
but no, it's this wider range thing that affects like people who think that they might not need accessibility features,
but no, they benefit from them too.
All right.
That's done. So now I will save my piece while we have two minutes left on the clock.
I covered a talk by private divisions, Kari Toyama, about
she set up a QA studio and it was talking about how to set that up
from scratch to kind of give your your dev team the best chance
and get like a really good, really productive environment.
And I think my working title for when I was writing the article is
Breaking QAer People Too.
Because a lot of her talk just comes down to treating developers like human beings
and building community. Yeah.
It's a really great talk that focuses on her five pillars,
six pillars that I can't find
because I didn't organize my notes.
Culture, diversity, relationships, advocacy, and trust.
And there's a lot of advice that is focused
on setting up a QA studio
to make them feel included in the process.
Because you hear horror stories of like,
oh, they're kept in the basement with no lights
and they're not allowed to make eye contact
with the programmers.
And that doesn't foster a great working relationship
for people whose jobs actually overlap quite a bit.
Got it. That's so frustrating, especially when you think about what Emily said.
You read stories about how Activision used to be, or other companies.
And if you start at the beginning of her talk too, she talked a lot about how
Emily was talking about her own experiences with sexism, even as a high up in games companies,
and Akari was talking about a lot of her experiences. And it's just like,
you're sitting there kind of like, no, I can see this happening, but that really sucks.
And those bad, negative, and often sexist experiences kind of informed her philosophy
for setting up the studio.
I think there's a lot of really great advice in that talk that applies not only to QA,
but just to like studio culture in general.
So please check that out.
It was a really great conversation.
Yeah, sounds like it.
And all these, these, like we wrote them up.
on gamasutra.com. A website with a name.
So let's wrap it up. Thank you so much everybody, especially people who showed up here in chat.
I feel like, you know, some of you have shown up every time and we really appreciate that.
This is a first time thing for us doing a live...
So, hopefully we do it again.
See some of you on Twitter and all that.
So I think that's it.
We're going to sign off on the very first GDC summer GDC podcast live.
So thanks, everybody.
Have a good rest of your GDC.
Bye.