Hello. My name is Ian. I'm an accessibility specialist, and I'm here to talk to you about
subtitles. And I'm going to start with a little bit of audience participation, because I know
everybody loves that. So I'd like to see a show of hands of how many of you have played
with subtitles turned on. That's a healthy slice of the crowd. And that actually tallies
up.
with usage data.
There's a game a few of you might have heard of
called Assassin's Creed Origins.
Assassin's Creed Origins actually tracked usage data
on how many of their players played with subtitles turned on
and it was averaged across all platforms,
just over 60% of their players.
So this is of all kinds of reasons.
I mean, I know there's at least two people
in the audience here who are deaf and hard of hearing.
I bet there are a lot of people here who aren't as well.
Maybe your subtitles,
because they're playing in a noisy room.
because they're playing on low-quality audio hardware,
because audio mixes in games are unpredictable.
You never know when there's going to be an explosion.
At the same time, it's an important exposition.
Also, because your baby's asleep.
The only chance you get to play is when your baby's asleep,
and you don't want to wake him up, so you play on mute.
There's all kinds of reasons why people use subtitles.
So they can have a really, really profound impact
on how enjoyable the experience of your game
is for most of your players.
So it obviously justifies doing a good job of them.
But nobody does.
There are no good subtitles in the games industry.
And I do mean in all of your games.
So who am I to be here judging your games?
I'm sure there's people feeling defensive, right?
I probably haven't.
Well, I may not have played your game.
But I'm actually not talking from my perspective.
I am quoting gamers.
So this is a selection of quotes just
from one single NeoGAF thread.
So most gaming subtitles are ass.
I think you get the general idea.
So what is it people are complaining about?
Well, they're complaining about stuff like this.
So there is going to be quite a bit of this in this
presentation.
There are going to be quite a few examples of games that are
not doing things so well.
I'm not going to name these games, even if you do
recognize them, even if they are a game you worked on.
I don't want to do anyone down at all.
There's reasons.
There's production issues.
There's lack of awareness.
If you're doing this kind of stuff,
you're not a bad person at all.
I'm just trying to give you some information
so you can do better in the future.
So this is the kind of things people are complaining about.
There's three main issues above all else
that people complain about.
It's size, contrast, amount of text that's on the screen.
It's really not rocket science to sort out.
So this is an example of more what you should be aiming for
as a base level.
So you can see here there's a clear, easy-to-read font.
There isn't too much text on the screen.
It's easy to distinguish from the background.
And the reason why I said as a base level
is because there is actually different use cases
for subtitles, right?
So some people are deaf and need to understand
every single word that's on the screen
and need them to be as clear and obvious as possible.
Other end of the spectrum.
people who just have subtitles on to glance at occasionally,
just in case, like I said earlier, an explosion goes off
in the middle of some exposition.
You want the subtitles to be really unnoticeable
until that moment they glance at them.
So, actually, each one of these examples
is the preferred approach for a certain group,
which gives you a bit of a problem, right?
Which one do you choose?
Well, the joy of digital media, including games,
is you don't have to choose.
you can just provide options and let people choose themselves.
So as I go through these practices,
keep that in mind, the principle of options.
I'm going to revisit the principle of options
at the end as well.
So I'm going to move on to practices now.
There's a whole bunch of good practices you can use.
A lot of these are just from other industries,
from TV and film, who've been doing this stuff for decades.
And people have been talking about these good practices
in the games industry for a long time.
So why am I here now in 2019 talking to you about this stuff?
It's because the industry is changing.
It's because finally, after all that advocacy by so many people,
studios are starting to do this stuff.
Subtitles are beginning to evolve from terrible to bad.
Soon they'll be good, soon they'll be great.
And when games like Spider-Man, like Assassin's Creed,
like Shadow the Tomb Raider.
Shadow the Tomb Raider, sorry.
Like when big AAA-named games like that do stuff like this,
people notice.
Other developers notice and copy them.
Gamers notice, and their expectations change.
So I'm sure everyone's familiar with WoW and with Spyro.
It doesn't just apply to Weather and Lucky Gobstar titles, though.
It goes into the fine details.
So when Assassin's Creed Origins that I showed,
when that came out a couple of years ago,
it had options for text size, it had options for backgrounds,
it had options for speaker name.
It won awards because of that.
Fast forward to today, Metro Exodus comes out,
reaction for the community, yeah, cool.
It kind of does what we expect.
So expectations change, they change quickly.
So I can guarantee you that if you're starting work
in a game now, there are things that are not even seen
in games yet that will be expected
by the time the game launches.
So that's what I'm hoping from this, that this is a good time to revisit all those principles
and hopefully allow you to get a bit ahead of that curve.
And rather than fall victim to those changing expectations, actually be the people setting
those expectations.
So as you can see, three basics, also some best practices, and if we've got time as well,
a couple of closing thoughts on some other related things.
Basics number one, size.
Size.
Obvious problem here.
And the thing is that kind of text size, that can look entirely reasonable to you
when you're developing on your nice big screen
about a foot away from your face.
Even for people who've got no kind of vision loss whatsoever,
if you're sat ten feet from a 40-inch screen,
it's a very, very different story.
So this is what you should be aiming for.
This is from Far Cry New Dawn.
And there is actually a size to design to as well.
So again, if you look outside at other industries,
if you look at Amazon's 10-fit UI guidelines,
if you look at Channel 4's sub-targeting guidelines,
this kind of stuff is already defined.
So this is the figure to work to, at least 46 pixels at 1080p.
I'm sure there's people in the room who
are imagining some interesting discussions with art directors
over including text of that size.
But again, options.
If somebody wants to have tiny, tiny subtitles in their game,
let them design that, but at least offer the option
so that people who can't read that can bump it up.
Like this.
So, basic number two, contrast.
Again, this is an obvious issue.
So there are a few techniques you can use to get around this.
You could try putting an outline on the text,
you could put a drop shadow on the text,
but those approaches themselves have issues,
particularly for dyslexia.
So there's a lot of people who,
if there's some kind of imagery behind the text,
that interferes with letter shapes
and makes it really difficult to read.
So if you are offering outlines,
if you are offering drop shadows, great,
but also offer something like this in Spider-Man.
So they have the option to turn on.
a black box behind it, which is called letterboxing, and ideally allow people to adjust the transparency
of that as well. Basic number three, the amount of text per
subtitle. And this relates to two things, really. The first one is the amount of text
that is in a single line. Like this. It also relates to the number of lines that are in
a subtitle. Like this.
So again, you can see from the reaction
that these seems like obvious problems, but they still appear.
And this is what you should be aiming for instead.
So this is an example from The Witness.
And you can see here, as well as having
a reasonable amount of text per line, a reasonable number
of lines, it's also got a sensible line break
in the middle.
That text string has been manually broken at a point
that makes editorial sense.
And again, from looking at other industries,
just looking slightly sideways at other screen-based
industries.
you can find guidelines to work to.
And this is what should be.
Maximum of two lines per subtitle, maybe three sometimes.
Try and avoid it, though.
And a maximum of 38 characters per line.
So that's the basics.
Those are the things that you really, really
have to be considering.
And you can see from those examples,
if you don't consider those things, what you have
really isn't subtitles.
They are not functional.
So next I'm going to talk about some good practices.
So this is the way to go a bit above and beyond
and move from beyond functional subtitles
to actually usable subtitles, enjoyable subtitles,
subtitles that are useful and pleasant to read.
And the first one is accuracy.
Make sure that your subtitles
actually match what's being said.
You can't rely on your voice actors
having perfectly stuck to the script.
And people really do notice.
And you can guarantee, as well as it being a pain to use,
you can guarantee that every single typo,
there will be somebody posting a screenshot of it,
correcting the typos in there.
You can look up examples from Last of Us if you really want to.
So yeah, make sure that you really need to do a QA pass
on your subtitle text to make sure it all matches up.
Second one, comprehensive.
Make sure that everything is actually subtitled.
Seems kind of obvious, but often you see games where...
either the gameplay of subtitles and the cutscenes aren't,
or vice versa, or a really, really common one,
the opening cinematic isn't subtitles.
Often that can be because the option to turn on the subtitles
isn't available until you get to the options screen,
which doesn't appear until after the cutscene.
So based on the usage data I was talking about earlier,
you know, Assassin's Creed Origins,
60% of their players playing with subtitles turned on,
the usage data actually supports having subtitles turned on by default.
But if you don't, at least allow people the means of doing so.
Like in Infamous.
So in Infamous, as soon as, or just before the first person starts speaking
the opening cinematic, you get that little prompt
to allow people to turn them on.
Number three, central.
Put your subtitles at the bottom in the middle.
Not up the top, not down at the bottom right.
So I don't mind using this example of Forza
because actually John Knowles gave a talk on Monday
highlighting the same thing and telling people,
don't do what we did, so don't do what they did.
Number four, add them from the bottom.
This doesn't actually come up very often.
It came up here.
So in this example, you can see
there's two different people speaking,
actually with indication of which speaker is which,
which is nice.
In this game, they were aiming at consistency.
So when each person spoke, they tried
to keep the position consistent.
So they tried to keep speaker two always at the bottom,
speaker one always at the top.
Really, really confused people.
So generally speaking, most of the time,
you'll only have one subtitle on the screen.
That's how most subtitle systems work.
If you don't, if for some reason you need to have lots on there,
like in the Division 2 or way back in Left 4 Dead,
where you have lots of subtitles, just keep scrolling them up from the bottom
and knocking the top one off.
Number five, indicate who is speaking.
Like this. So this example from the start.
Simply putting the name of the speaker on there.
And there's other games that have variations on this,
sometimes showing the little portrait next to the name as well.
Some games, again, back to the last example,
do it by using color to separate the speakers.
Color can be really preferential for some people.
It's an instant quick recognition.
But people who use subtitles
are no less likely to be colorblind than anyone else.
So if you are taking this approach,
at least give people the option to have the written speaker names as well.
Number six, indicate direction.
This is something that is very, very rarely seen in games,
but in other media, it's standard.
Like if you watch a TV, in the UK at least,
if you watch a TV program on the BBC,
anytime there is a speaker who is out of shot,
it shows a little arrow next to their name,
pointing to the direction where they are.
An example of a game that does this is Minecraft.
So you can see here, that little arrow.
to the left and to the right to show you which direction something's in.
Now, Minecraft, actually, in the early stages of development,
they had a much more complex, comprehensive approach than this.
They basically had, like, a 3D compass
showing you exactly where the sound effects were.
They actually took that out and stripped it back
on the basis of competition.
They figured out that if people are playing online,
that level of information is actually way, way more accurate
than what you get from sound.
So they scaled it back a bit to make the amount of information
you get through the text equivalent to what you get through stereo speakers.
But not every game strips it back like that. Division 2 has this.
It's a little bit hard to see from the screenshot,
but Division 2 basically does exactly the same thing
as the early prototype of Minecraft.
So their captions actually update to show you
exactly where in 3D space they're coming from.
Number seven, give people enough time to read the subtitles.
So this, on the surface of it, seems pretty straightforward.
Don't have them flying past really quickly.
But the reality of it is that people speak quickly.
You are going to be in situations where there is just loads of audio
going on at the same time.
And in those circumstances, meeting these guidelines.
can be tricky.
And what you need to resort to in those circumstances
is editing the subtitles.
Now, editing the subtitles is something
that you shouldn't do unless it's a real last resort.
Wherever possible, it should always
match exactly what's being spoken.
But in those circumstances where there's lots of stuff going on,
you can edit.
For example, if someone's saying, like, no, no, no, no,
no, like edit that down to just one line, that kind of thing
can just about get away with.
It's a bit of an art.
There are actually professional captioners who do this kind of stuff day in, day out,
who know exactly how to do this stuff.
If you can hire one of those people, amazing.
If you can't, check out the BBC's guidelines.
That's actually where these guidelines themselves come from.
But they also have a ton of good information on exactly how to do all those tricky bits
of editing.
And these are their guidelines.
And even just in general, please check out these guidelines.
There's a ton of really, really good stuff.
And like I said, this is an industry that's been doing subtitling for decades.
There's a lot of good information behind this, so please, please read this.
There's a lot of good stuff you can take out of that for your games.
Number eight, clear font.
This is where we start getting into interesting discussions
with art directors again,
about things like this.
So in this game, the reason for this text
was to keep it on brand.
This was a text that was used throughout the rest of the game's interface.
It was keeping it consistent with the feel.
But that clashes directly with it being easy to read,
especially using full caps.
If you're using full caps, that means you lose out on word shape, everything is just
like a plain rectangle, the outline of the word, which is quite a big deal if you're
expecting people to read it at speed.
And also it's a bit hard to tell in the screenshot, it's a bit low resolution, sorry, but that's
actually in copperplate font, which is like a serif font as well.
So this is what you should be aiming for.
Clear Sans Serif font.
and in sentence case, not full caps.
And again, like I said, this might lead to some interesting discussions with art directors.
Like, if art directors really want to do this kind of stuff,
and, you know, there are people who literally, obviously, it is their job to ensure,
like, brand consistency and emotional impact and that kind of stuff.
You know, if you've got people in your team who want to do this kind of stuff, let them do it.
But also have an option so that people who can't read that
can customize it to something that suits their needs.
Number nine, this is a biggie, captions.
So the definitions, the terminology,
vary a little bit from country to country.
But in most places, the difference
in terminology between subtitles and between captions
is that subtitles relates to speech specifically.
And that can be for localization as well as accessibility.
Captions refers to audio as well.
It refers to translating everything
that you need to be able to hear.
into text. Things like this. So this is from Shadow of the Tomb Raider. You can see where
it says wind screaming there. So this is something that's been really, really rare in games.
Not in other media. So in TV, cinema. Honestly, when you're flying back from, I'm seeing most
of you flying back from GDC.
Turn on the movie, watch it, you'll see a lot of the things I'm talking about here,
decent text size, speaker indication, closed captions for background sounds,
are there.
We just need to bring it across into this industry as well.
There have been some examples.
Early pioneer of this was Valve.
And Valve, it was kind of reactive.
So the first Half-Life game, it had no subtitles at all.
And this was in the days before social media, the days before Reddit.
So they didn't have lots of angry people on social media.
They had people writing polite letters to them, saying, you know,
I'm deaf. Do you have a transcript?
I've heard Half-Life has got a good story.
I'd love to know what they're saying.
So Valve were like, no, no, OK, forget transcripts.
From now on, we are going to do this properly.
And from that point, just ensure that any time they do user research,
they include people with hearing loss in their user research.
That resulted in them having closed captioning.
But all the background sounds in Half-Life 2,
in Portal, and Portal 2 really pushed the industry forward.
And it's only now that we're starting
to see more games doing this.
So Shadow of the Tomb Raider, a really nice example.
Division 2, another really nice example.
So I already showed that screenshot earlier
of those captions with the direction arrows on.
Ubisoft are doing really nice work on this.
I'd also recommend checking out Far Cry New Dawn.
That has similar functionality to Division 2.
and just tons of really good accessibility stuff in general.
So for a really nice showcase, just those two Ubisoft games.
I don't want to big up Ubisoft too much, there's loads of other people doing good things,
but Division 2, Far Cry New Dawn, please check them out.
And there's something else that's really, really nice here
that I've only seen a few games do, which is at the bottom,
it actually shows you an example of what it's going to look like.
It shows you a preview of the actual presentation, the actual size,
so that people can see it in-situ without having to do trial and error
of going back and forwards. So please do that as well.
And that kind of brings me on to the last one neatly,
which is options.
So in all these various different ones,
I've been talking about options, talking about customizing.
This is an example set of the kind of things
that you can offer.
And in some industries, this kind of stuff isn't optional.
So if you are actually, it may apply to games.
I don't want to say it won't ever apply to games,
because.
somebody somewhere is going to have some idea about shoving
broadcast video into games.
But basically, if any video footage
has previously been shown on TV and is then shown digitally,
there is a set of features quite similar to this, which
is actually required by law for the playback.
So that's why if you open up the settings of YouTube,
you open up the settings of Netflix,
you see settings very similar to this.
You also see it within the system options of the Xbox,
PlayStation, iOS, Android.
I don't know if that kind of stuff will come to games someday,
but it's sensible to think about this kind of stuff,
just in case it does.
It's also sensible to think about this kind of stuff
because it's good for your players.
I think something's worth mentioning when it comes to options,
and this applies to accessibility options in general,
is that the more you add,
that is actually the accessibility barrier in itself,
like navigating, configuring.
It's for some people difficult and confusing.
and presets come to the rescue.
So if you are starting to put in lots of configuration options,
just think of it in the same way that you would do with controls.
So like with controls, you might have like default, bumper jumper,
custom, custom lets you do remapping.
Just think of subtitles in the same way.
So I have five minutes left.
Should I talk about VR?
Does anyone want me to talk about VR?
Yeah?
OK.
Right, so VR.
VR presents some interesting issues.
Firstly, because in all other media,
what I was saying about putting the subtitles at the bottom, in the middle,
in VR, there is no bottom, there is no screen.
Also, in other media, the subtitles, regardless of what happens within the game,
in the actual physical world, the subtitles are exactly the same depth
as the gameplay footage or the TV footage or anything else.
In VR, that's no longer an issue.
They're actually floating in the virtual space.
That results in problems. Where do you put them?
you could have them floating in front of your face
in roughly the same kind of position as they would be
if you were looking at a screen.
That means to avoid occlusion, like my subtitles are here,
I'm in front of the mic,
the mic is now in the middle of the subtitles, right?
So you need to put them really, really close to your face.
That means that the subtitles themselves
and the thing making the noise,
there's a big difference in depth between them.
So if you go like this
and focus on your two fingers in front of you,
shift focus near and far,
it strains your eyes really quickly.
So you're risking the same thing in VR,
and you really don't want to give people eye strain in VR.
That's a good way to induce simulation sickness.
So that option has problems.
So what else can you do?
Next thing people often think about
is maybe I could attach them to the source of the audio.
So if, so where's the speaker?
Here we go.
So the sound from my voice is coming out from that speaker.
Physically attach a subtitle to that speaker, which is great.
That the text is at the same depth
as the source of the audio.
Then I turn over here, and I can't see the subtitles
anymore.
So that approach has issues as well.
So that's something that I think there's
going to be a nice solution that has come to.
I don't think we're there yet.
The most promising solution I've seen so far
is a modal approach, something that switches between the two.
So something that's attached to the audio source
when it's within your field of vision.
When you move away, it detaches from that
and snaps into your vision.
you do get that issue with having to focus on something close to you,
but at least if it indicates where it is, you know to then turn back
so it snaps back to the right depth again.
So, like I said, that's like an early approach to it,
but that's something that I think is going to grow and evolve.
But if you want to see that in action,
have a look at a game called Virtual Virtual Reality.
That's got an example of that approach in it.
So, I'm going to finish on...
this question, reinventing the wheel.
That's what everybody's doing at the moment.
Every example I've shown you,
these are all bespoke custom-rolled solutions,
despite the approaches being the same across all these different games.
That's wasted work. People shouldn't be repeating this work all the time.
So wouldn't it be nice if there was just a centralized tool
that took care of this stuff for you?
Like this.
So this is a $20 Unreal plugin.
It includes most of the accommodations
that I've been talking about so far.
It also includes some other ones as well.
So things like the, like at the, sorry,
what the appropriate gap is to have in between each subtitle
to avoid simulation sickness from them flicking in.
And so this is available for Unreal.
Plenty of people in the room aren't using Unreal.
On that page, he also links to a free PDF
which details the full specification he built it to.
So you can take that and apply it to your own game as well.
So great, plug-in, $20, low barrier to entry.
But this is not where it needs to be.
This is where it needs to be, built directly into the engines.
I mean, saving the $20, that'd be nice,
but the real benefit is that it's on by default.
So if within Unity and Unreal, in particular,
particularly Unity because of so much games,
I'm sure most of the people in the room are aware of what percentage
of games are built in Unity.
Like if Unity had a nice subtitling system baked in
that took care of these requirements,
you would get people who would just be like,
oh, I've got to put subtitles in my game.
Cool, Unity has a system, I'll use it.
And then without ever even having thought
about accessibility, they'd have a ton
of good stuff in their game.
So that's the thought I want to leave you on,
the call to action.
Please, please, please, if you want your lives
to be easier with subtitling, harass these guys.
Get them to do it at engine level.
If Unity and Unreal are in the room,
sorry for getting people to harass you,
but...
they kind of should.
So quick summary.
Basics, size, contrast, and amount of text.
Best practices, accurate, comprehension is essential.
Add from the bottom, indicate speakers and direction,
let people have enough time to read them,
use a clear font, offer captions, and offer options.
Thank you.