Hello. Welcome to the most amazing talk at GDC. This talk
is called Gods and Dumps. I'll get to why it's called that in a
bit. It's about attribute tuning. Specifically this is
very narrowly focused on tuning attributes in Pillars of
Eternity. Who am I? Who are any of us really? I am a game
director, Josh Sawyer. I'm at Obsidian Entertainment where I
have been for the past 11 years.
I've been a tabletop role playing gamer for about 30
years. I started with basic Dungeons and Dragons. I've been
a CRPG developer for the past 17 years starting at Black Isle
Studios. Actually this month. And I started out doing area and
narrative design. But I primarily focus on system design
and direction these days. What are we even talking about?
We're talking about Pillars of Eternity. If you're not familiar with the game, it was a Kickstarter-funded game that is inspired by the Infinity Engine role-playing games from the late 90s, early 2000s.
That means Baldur's Gate, Icewind Dale, and Planescape Torment.
And we had 77,000 amazing backers who helped us raise over $4 million.
And we released the game in 2015, and we just finished releasing the second part of our expansion, The White March, earlier this year.
We are specifically talking about attributes,
or what is commonly called ability scores
in Dungeons and Dragons.
This is your strength, dex, constitution,
all that sort of stuff.
I'm amazed this talk was approved,
because this is easily the most narrowly focused talk
I've ever given.
I'm gonna be talking about things
using the terms viable and optimal.
I'd like to define those,
just so it's clear what I'm talking about.
Viable means you can actually get through the game with it,
like your character will live.
And I don't really mean by the skin of your teeth, I mean like you can actually do it. It's not a nightmare of frustration.
Optimal means the sort of high end where a min-maxer will take a character by, you know,
scrimping and scraping and finding every single bonus they can possibly get.
A big focus that we had on pillars was to kind of try to reduce the gulf between viability and the optimal end.
It makes it a lot easier to balance, but obviously we want min-maxers to be able to go crazy because that's fun.
even though I hate fun by the way. What I mean by gods and dumps is it's kind of
common when people are talking about stats in games to talk about things in
terms of a god stat or a dump stat. A god stat is a stat that is extremely
extremely good for the class or a build. You always want to max that out as much
as possible. A dump stat is a stat that you can just
Put it in the toilet like nobody cares.
It's not going to really affect your character, how you play the game.
Maybe a class doesn't rely on that stat at all.
And that's something that we are watching out for
throughout the course of development of Pillars.
So I'm going to go back into the archives because Pillars of
Eternity is a very nostalgia-driven game.
Obviously, we were inspired by the Infinity Engine games.
The Infinity Engine games were based on Advanced Dungeons and
Dragons second edition, except for Icewind Dale 2, which was
third edition D&D. So there's a big legacy there that we had to
pay attention to.
We didn't have to do exactly what those games did.
But if we strayed too far away, then understandably our
backers would be kind of annoyed at a minimum.
So what we're really talking about when we mean attributes and class-based role-playing games is AD&D.
Dungeons & Dragons and Advanced Dungeons & Dragons.
A lot of games have their own variations on this, but really it started with pre-Basic.
It started before Basic.
There's a version of Dungeons & Dragons that's just after Chainmail, which was the...
sort of hardcore tactical tabletop war game.
And even that had stats back then.
So they go back a very long way,
but lots of games have them now.
Ultima, Final Fantasy games have them, Dark Souls have them.
Lots of games that have classes also have ability scores.
Those can come into conflict, which I'll be talking about,
but it's very widespread in role-playing games
for these things to exist.
They're used to define and distinguish
the fundamental things about a character.
So how strong they are, how tough they are,
how smart they are.
how well-spoken they are, these sort of very basic concepts of a character.
Originally, in the olden days, they were always random.
Actually, what I found when I was doing some research is that
in the first Dungeons & Dragons before BASIC,
the dungeon master actually rolled the stats for the player's characters,
which is kind of crazy.
But yeah, there's a big emphasis on randomization,
but eventually, over time, it shifted to point-by.
Computer role-playing games tend to have things as point-by because,
you know, otherwise people just sit there and they roll and roll and roll and roll,
which some people have fun with, but it makes it kind of hard to balance the game that way.
And yeah, so the traditional stats in Dungeons & Dragons are strength, constitution, dexterity, intelligence, wisdom, charisma, and can anyone remember the seventh attribute that was in...
Thank you.
Seventh attribute that was introduced in Unearthed Arcana was comeliness, and it went away immediately in second edition.
Yeah, because how beautiful your character was is not necessarily the most important stat to have in D&D.
So in the olden times, meaning from basic through second edition, you would roll your dice and then you would figure out what class you could be.
So it wasn't, and it's actually interesting, if you go back and you look at the text in the old player's handbooks, it really does say roll your stats, then think about what character you want to make.
Whereas I think now, especially in the language of player's handbooks and things like that, you sort of conceive a character.
and then maybe you roller your allocate stats, but you kind of do it in that order.
But in the olden days, it really was like, well, maybe you can play a paladin.
I mean, can you get a 17 charisma? Because then you can play a paladin.
If not, you're not playing a paladin.
There were lots of dump stats, a whole bunch of them.
So there were plenty of stats that classes could ignore, it didn't really matter.
And there were big dead ranges.
I'll talk about scaling of values, but in a lot of cases D&D, AD&D, between 8 and 14,
not a lot really changed.
Or if they did change, they were really minor secondary things like carry weight and stuff
like that.
Oh, you know what?
I just forgot to tell you guys.
We do have review forms.
I'm sorry, I'm completely ruining the flow of time.
We do have review forms for this. Please fill out the evaluations at the end.
And if you have cell phones, please silence them. I was supposed to say that at the beginning, but I screwed up. Anyway.
So because of the fact that you were rolling these, and because you had these big dead zones,
and you have these requirements for how you play the class, viability was always in question.
You might not be able to play a character of a certain class, or if you allocated stats,
they might be so bad that that character would either immediately die.
like in the first session or they would eventually just run
out of steam and you couldn't practically speaking play them
anymore. I'll give a few examples of how this might work.
So here's one. The reasonably intelligent wizard in AD&D. Make
a wizard with a 14 intelligence. It's a bad idea. You might say
like, well, 14 on a scale of 3 to 18, 14 sounds pretty high.
According to the player's handbook, I have 140 IQ. I'm a
genius. I'm an amazing wizard. Wrong. You suck.
Because as soon as you advance to 13th level, you're going to
realize you can't cast 7th level spells or higher. So you can
keep advancing, but you're not doing crap. I mean, you can find
ways to boost your intelligence, but if you built your character
that way, you're going to run into some trouble. You thought
you were going to be this dude. You're this dude.
reasonably strong fighter in AD&D. This is not quite as bad.
So you start with a 15 strength. By the way, Khalid in Baldur's
Gate had a 15 strength. I'm just going to mention that because
it's not a very good strength score. And then you take
specialization because fighters specialize in weapons.
And your damage is really, really bad.
So if you use a two-handed sword
against medium or small creatures,
just in case anyone's wondering,
you'll do 1d10 plus two,
because you have specialization,
which is 7.5 average damage,
versus 1d10 plus eight, which is 13.5 average damage.
That's pretty bad.
And you might say, well, I'm gonna get some more stuff later
so I can work my way out of this hole.
So you get up to 13th level, you take grand mastery,
you're using combat and tactics rules, whatever.
So, and then you get a plus four weapon
and your damage is still terrible.
And the thing is now it's even worse
because this is being multiplied across multiple attacks.
So this gulf is like, you can play this way,
but this character is way worse
than the character that's sort of maxed out.
So.
You thought you were going to be this guy, but you're this guy.
In 3rd edition there was a shift.
The explicit class requirements went away.
So it no longer said, hey, you have to have a 17 charisma to be a paladin.
There were lots of implicit things that you were supposed to do.
Usually you could see them if you read the abilities and said,
oh wow, a lot of my abilities are based off of wisdom or charisma.
I should probably focus on that.
Bonus XP for your class disappeared. So there was a thing in AD&D where if you had higher than a certain thing in your main stats
Then you'd get more XP which is giving a reward to someone that's already doing really well
So they got rid of that because that's weird
Also a third edition got rid of the the nonlinear progression
So they went to every even point every even step you would get plus one so that changed the feeling of it
It is much more consistent, but that sort of massive ramp up at each end went away
There were multiple builds that were viable.
You could build characters in a few different ways.
Not necessarily optimal,
especially as you get to higher level in third edition.
That stuff gets really tricky.
Some of the classes arguably required
only three stats to be pretty good.
Others like monks and paladins are very notable
because they need four to be at least kind of good.
Or if you do not do that,
then some of your class abilities will be stinky poo poo.
And then D&D introduced Splatbooks.
If you're not familiar with the term Splatbook, it's an expansion book that usually introduces a bunch of crazy stuff.
Like cool new prestige classes and insane feats that your DM should say no to.
But they introduced lots of neat gimmick build possibilities because
you could do something like make a high intelligence fighter
that was actually a good character. Whereas if you made a high charisma or a high intelligence fighter in core third edition
That's a shitty fighter.
Like, that might be a really cool character to role play with.
That character is very bad at doing their job,
which is fighting.
3.5, or 3E and 3.5 is really a min-maxer's delight.
It clarified a lot of rules,
but it left a lot of room for optimization.
So, you know, it said, well here are all the rules,
but here are all these bonus types.
So if you can search through every single source book
and combine bonuses in the right way,
you can just really go crazy.
People made a lot of character builders for 3EN 3.5 and for Pathfinder.
Those character builders allow you to rapidly see where all these stats can come from.
And people are insane on online forums.
They're crazy. They'll come up with really, really crazy stuff.
As an example of this, I like to use the example of Lollerskate.
there is a forum, something awful, and in their traditional games forum they had this
ultra high level
character contest to see who could make the most insane character
and the winner was an insane australian person
who
made this
you can't see the stats super clearly but this is ludicrous
he's like a yontianathema and he had like seven classes or six classes
and seven hundred and fifty five hit points
uh... so yeah you could go
you can go really really really crazy in third edition D&D
And so people really like to min-max, but we also know that
when the potential for min-maxing the optimal character,
when that character gets too far away from the viable character,
it's really hard to balance content in any meaningful way
because the gulf is so huge.
So in Pillars of Eternity, when we set out to make our ability scores,
we had a few goals.
These things were not necessarily things that we started out with,
but that we moved toward them over time.
Six attributes.
which is very, is D&D's,
class abilities that are not explicitly associated
with attributes.
So for example, if you look at
third edition Dungeons and Dragons,
a paladin's smite is in part based off
of their charisma score.
We didn't do things like that where classes
have very specific abilities keyed
to specific ability scores.
The statistics, the attributes would influence statistics of importance to all classes.
And obviously, there's variability in there as to how significant that is,
but our goal was to say, try to influence things that all classes use,
rather than things that classes can safely, some classes can safely ignore,
or they don't have any meaning to them, because then you get into situations where
you can just dump stuff, or certain classes really need stats, more stats than other classes.
A primary goal is no bad builds.
What that really means in practice is that if you have an idea for a wacky character,
like the super genius barbarian, that is a viable character.
Doesn't mean it's necessarily an optimal character, but it is a viable character.
So we wanted people to be able to make the crazy characters like their charismatic fighter, or their clumsy rogue, or whatever sort of weird thing they wanted to come up with.
And instead of that being a character that is just fundamentally, you're not going to get anywhere with it, it was viable.
Not optimal, but viable.
And we had a secondary goal, which was to ensure that dumping stats stung a little bit.
This was kind of a reality check on our systems, just to make sure that, you know, like if we thought a benefit from a stat was really important, if people dumped it...
Then really they didn't think the bonus that was being granted was that important.
So we needed to go back and look at it again.
So why did we do these things?
Why do we have six attributes?
Tradition.
I mean that's the main thing.
We asked our fans on our forums and
they'd be like, you know, somewhere between five and seven.
I don't know, maybe...
six, I guess. But it was pretty common. I mean, some people
genuinely did say like 05 or 07, but a lot of people said six.
They wanted six. It felt comfortable. It fit this type
of game. So that's what we did.
Also, there were some nice things though that pairs worked out well for our three secondary defenses
Which are fortitude, reflex, and will. And defenses are not opt-out
I saw someone who made a more elegant sort of way of saying this but
Defenses are things that you use when you're attacked and as long as the content actually
Attacks these different defenses with some regularity the player can't
They can't not participate in that, if that makes sense.
Whereas certain things in D&D, like if you say like,
I don't care how long the duration of anything is,
so I'm gonna just dump this stat.
Defenses, as long as they're being attacked,
you don't want them to be bad because you will suffer for it.
So six attributes worked into three pairs
and that worked out pretty well.
Classibility is not associated with attributes. The reason we did this is
if you make explicit ties between certain stats and fundamental classibilities
then there's an emphasis there on viability. So it's sort of saying if you
don't max out a stat or if you don't
have the stat at at least a pretty decent value
this character sucks.
So for comparison if you think about the example of
the wizard with the 14 intelligence and D&D
versus intellect and pillars of eternity
intellect affects durations and it affects area of effect.
for all characters in Pillars of Eternity.
So you can make a wizard that has small, low durations and small area of effect.
That's actually fine.
It's not going to prevent the character from learning spells or casting spells or anything like that.
So there's a big difference there.
Similarly, if you look at Charisma in 3rd edition D&D, it's extremely important for paladins.
It affects their defenses, it affects their smite, it affects all sorts of things.
Resolve is not anywhere near the same for paladins.
It's a nice defensive stat, it boosts their deflection, increases their concentration,
so if they're on the front lines, it's important,
but it's not vital and it's not associated with any of their class abilities directly.
And the sort of question that I ask is, if something is required for viable play, why is it an option?
Like, we want players to make meaningful choices and not put in gotchas and traps that say like,
well yeah, you can kind of put these stats wherever you want, but not really.
Like, you can dump this. No, you can't.
So if something's required for viability, that shouldn't be an option.
So rather we would say, no, none of these are required for viable play, so it is really an option.
So, influencing statistics of importance to all classes.
This took a long time, and as I'll say later,
we had to actually revise this during beta and post-launch
and into a couple of patches, so that process was fun.
But this is, someone put this together
on the Pillars of Eternity Gamepedia site,
which is very nice.
But it shows how things are affected.
So you can see that each pair of stats
contributes to one of the secondary defenses.
Two of the stats, or actually one of the stats
contributes to two defenses, which is resolve.
Those defenses are important to everyone.
Even if you have a character, for example,
that's not on the front lines,
deflection is still attacked by arrows
and guns and things like that.
So you don't want to tank any of those.
Endurance and health are important to everyone.
Obviously for frontline characters,
they're a little more important,
but if you're playing a class like a wizard
that already does not have much endurance or health,
dumping that will be not good,
and giving it a boost will be nice
if you want to be a character
that wades into the front lines.
Damage and healing is important to everyone.
Action speed is important to everyone.
Interrupt and basically the ability
to interrupt someone with an attack.
Concentration, which is the ability to resist that.
Accuracy, which is used for resolving every attack.
You get the point.
So the idea is that this is stuff that all classes use
because they all have abilities that rely on them broadly.
And that was to make sure that if you wanted to build
a character of a certain type,
you could play towards those strengths.
So why do we not want to have bad builds?
Well, role-playing is about building and expressing
a character both through social interactions
and through mechanics.
And viability limitations, as I suggested before, can result in mid or late game roadblocks.
You know, as the challenge sort of ramps up, you may find that how you built your character doesn't work.
And, you know, I've seen so many people playing a lot of role-playing games that said like,
I got eight hours in, and I realized I did this all wrong, and now I have to start all over.
Some people think that's fun. I don't think most people do.
And if we have fewer viability limitations, then we have more viable character concepts.
So you can make the perceptive genius barbarian, which is actually a pretty darn good character in Pillars of Eternity,
because they affect a very large area with their carnage and they're very accurate.
You can make the idiot muscle wizard, which is a favorite of mine.
So that's a wizard that has a low intellect but has a very high might.
So they don't have big areas of effect, they don't have long durations, but they do a huge amount of damage.
Because might in Pillars of Eternity affects all damage, not just weapon damage.
But spell damage. All sorts of damage.
Or you can make the clumsy Determined Rogue, who has a low dexterity and a high resolve.
They go into the front lines, they have good defense, good concentration.
They don't attack that quickly, but they can still do a lot of damage.
And they have good defenses for frontline attacks.
We wanted to avoid the cool concept, bad character problem.
So I have been a dungeon master for most of the time that I've been playing D&D
and I really hate the feeling when someone has a really cool idea for a character that is a sucky character.
Because they have a dream of playing this wacky dude or lady
and I have to kind of say like, there's nothing...
Like the game doesn't support that.
Like you're not going to be able to make anything like that.
That character's going to die.
Or you're going to be frustrated playing them because they're going to fail all their checks. It's not going to be good.
So how does this happen?
How it happens is that ability scores in classes can conflict.
If you say class A is good at X, Y, and Z.
For example, causing damage.
Rogues are good at causing damage.
But ability B drastically impacts X and Z,
then those are in conflict.
Because it means that if you set ability B to some low value,
you're basically torpedoing the thing that your class is supposed to be good at.
The mechanics and the content balanced around one another run into problems when these things are sort of, you know, converging.
So in D&D terms, a warrior's two-hit armor class zero, or base attack bonus, goes up,
and their strength is kind of supposed to be high, and probably will get higher,
and thus armor classes for monsters increase, assuming that those things are going up together.
If they're not, then that character is going to fall behind and they're not going to be able to actually hit those characters as much as they should.
So the example of the reasonably strong fighter I gave before.
The other thing is that strength also affects your chance to hit.
So that character not only is doing less damage per hit, but is hitting less frequently, so they're even further behind.
Another example is rogues and reflex saves.
They're already high.
They have skills that are very good and based off of dexterity.
They assume that your dexterity is high, so reflex saving throws
and the difficulty classes of the skills that they use
assume that those are both high.
If you're not min-maxing them,
then it's very difficult for the DM, or in our case,
as people designing a computer role-playing game that doesn't adapt
to the player's stats,
it's very difficult to find a difficulty class that actually works.
So you get this thing, the cool concept, the smart fighter that is bad in practice.
The failure to min-max your key attributes means that your totals are lower overall,
and the content that scales assuming that the player is min-maxing
will just leave suboptimal characters behind. And that's where you get that
mid-game non-viability or late-game mid-viability. Both are very frustrating.
We wanted to ensure that dumping would sting.
So dumping a stat is again like if you,
you know it starts at 10 and you're like,
I don't need this and you take it down to three
and then you put the point somewhere else.
So why did we want to ensure that dumping stings?
It wasn't to be punitive.
We weren't trying to say like, we'll get you player.
But it was supposed to be a reality check.
So again, if we said, hey, we put this stat
or this thing on this attribute, for example,
area of effect and duration.
So we think area of effect and duration are important, and we think the value we give to it is important.
But if we see players continually dumping them, then clearly it is not important to them.
That might be a perception problem, which I should also say that a huge part of balance is actually just the player's perception.
Whatever the sort of... there's no objective sort of understanding of it. It's all what they perceive of it.
So if they're dumping it, you have to find a way to either communicate it better, or you have to look at the values of what it's affecting.
If people don't care about dumping it, it's not that important. Go back.
And choice and consequence is important to obsidian games.
We make role-playing games and in our role-playing games we think that if you make choices
there should be consequences for those. Good consequences and also bad consequences.
So that is another part of it is how you build your character.
There are trade-offs to how you do that.
Here's some good things about how this all turned out.
I'll start with good things and then I'll go to the things people didn't like.
It is hard to make non-viable characters.
Unless you're playing on the path of the dam difficulty, which is
the highest level of difficulty,
it's pretty hard to make a character that can't
get through the game.
And as long as you play toward the strengths of whatever the build of the
character is, like again, if you make a barbarian that has a high
intellect...
You want to emphasize your carnage, which is your big AoE melee attack.
And other things that have an area of effect and duration-based effects, because that's what int affects.
It's easy to build a lot of unusual and viable character concepts.
I've seen lots of people that propose a lot of the weird, weird characters that if you tried to make them in D&D would just be bad characters.
But they're able to play them in Pillars of Eternity and they're just fine.
And they love playing them because they had that fantasy and that's part of why we allow people to do these things.
It is not hard to make different optimal builds that emphasize different things.
Again, I'm not going to say that everything can be made into an optimal build
because then they wouldn't be optimal. Optimal is sort of the cream of the crop.
So I've seen people make an interrupt-focused barbarian,
so a barbarian that really focuses on just...
Causing hit reactions on a lot of enemies at once they ramp up their int they ramp up their perception
And they just smack those guys all day long
A lot of people will make gish muscle wizards gishes are sort of the fighter wizard combos
They emphasize personal buffs and summoning spell weapons super strong and powerful
Versus a crowd control wizard this is someone who focuses very heavily on big AoEs stun locking enemies keeping them locked down lots of debuffs
And minmaxers can still go wild. Like, you can't make Lawler skate in this.
No one can make Lawler skate.
By the way, did I mention that that guy lost a semester of his university making that character?
I personally admire that a hell of a lot because I was a terrible student.
But yeah, minmaxers can still go crazy on this stuff.
Yeah, it does not get as wild as 3E or 3.5, but there's a lot of room for optimization in it.
And despite the relative simplicity, the mechanics still allow for a lot of interesting analysis.
So for example, accuracy and damage is a common trade-off.
Each point of perception that a character has in Pillars of Eternity adds one on a 100 point scale.
to accuracy. And that shifts your miss, graze, hit, and crit ranges for all attacks. Now one point is
not very much, but it's shifting that whole, all those attack windows. And so people do perceive
that as being valuable. It's not, you know, crazy powerful, but it does make a difference.
Each point of might adds three percent to damage and healing from any source.
So again, casting spells, shooting a gun, stabbing someone with a knife, whatever, those
are all affected by your Might Score.
If a character casts a healing spell, casts Lay on Hands, or Cure Samana, then that is
affected by your Might Score.
So certain builds will rely more heavily on accuracy than damage output.
So for example, the crowd control wizard that I mentioned,
they're not really focusing on doing damage, but they really want to hit.
They want their accuracy to be as high as possible.
So with that you can say like, well, my might doesn't really need to be that high
because I'm not really focusing on doing damage, that's other characters doing that,
I'm debuffing people, and I just want to make sure that they're more likely to hit or crit.
And so people do breakdowns and analyses of these, and a lot of it comes down to personal preference.
What sort of character do you want to make, and how do you want to make that, or how do you want to play that character?
So that's always good, is that we do want that room for interpretation in there.
If it's really open and shut, well this is superior all the time, then we kind of screwed up.
So here are some common criticisms.
Things people either didn't like, or continue to not like about Pillars of Eternity attributes.
They aren't realistic.
I'm not going to argue that they are.
They don't have enough of an impact.
Certainly compared to D&D, I think that's a fair criticism.
Perceived lack of value, when again this goes back to
the difference between what the numerical value is
and what people really understand of that value.
And the companions are awful, oh my god.
The worst stats you've ever seen.
We'll see about that.
So they aren't realistic.
Well, AD&D is not super realistic either, which is kind of our starting point.
AD&D kind of has some interesting things.
There are certain things that it seems like it is really trying to simulate.
Like it is really trying to say, like, no, this is like things work in the real world.
Also, you can jump off of a cloud castle.
fall and take 20d6 damage and get up and dust yourself off and that's fine
so it's not super concerned necessarily with verisimilitude
being really like reality
pillars already abstracts a lot there's a lot of stuff we already knew we were
going to abstract so for us realism was not a priority
so you know for players who say that it is not realistic and and we go
even we i would say we go even
uh... further in some cases so for example might
affects gun damage, it affects spell damage, it affects, you know, melee weapon damage.
That's not realistic. That's done so that all that stuff is on one stat rather than being spread out in a way that
certain classes can kind of ignore certain stats or it doubles up for certain people,
which is what happens in D&D. Like if you get things that align on one stat,
then you're always supposed to max that and it doesn't make any sense to, you know,
focus on the thing that affects the damage types that you don't use.
So, our focus was to try to make good gameplay out of these stats and realism was not really a priority for us.
Not enough impact.
So, because we wanted these characters to be ensured to be viable, that means that that limited their relative impact.
If you have something that goes up this high at the highest end and it drops down this low,
there's a big chance, because that gulf is so huge, that something about the viability of the character is dropping into the netherworld.
So, whereas if you keep it in a more constrained range, it's much more likely to avoid viability problems.
If you dump that stat, the character will suffer, but they're not an unplayable character.
If you give a wizard in D&D a three constitution, they get one hit point per level and will die.
Linear scaling means that we have a regular progression.
So if you look at the strength table that I'm going to show you in a bit,
you'll notice that there's a big dead zone,
and then it ramps up pretty quickly at the ends.
And so there is a much more significant sense of progression
once you start really ramping up things like strength.
You're like, wow, like, the difference between these scores is really, really huge.
But it kind of ignores the dead zone in the middle.
So when you have a linear scaling, that does mean that it just kind of goes up at a very regular pace.
Third edition skips the odd numbers.
So they actually get a sort of skewed thing where
every two points it goes up.
So it's a different feeling than having a little teeny increment every single point.
And we were trying to avoid what we already were known,
and when I say known, I mean by the designers of D&D,
imbalances in the scores.
So if you look at some of the ways that things were designed
in third edition or 3.5,
they understand that strength is an insane stat.
It affects two hit, it affects damage,
or rather it affects base attack bonus,
or being added to attack bonus, and damage.
And so, for example, half-orcs get twice as many penalties
as they get bonuses because they get a plus two to strength.
because they knew that if you give a half-orc a 20 strength and give them a great axe, they are going to chop through the entire world.
So we knew, based on looking at how they designed those mechanics by reverse engineering how they tried to solve those problems,
that they knew that they were too powerful.
So we said like, well, you know, we know that these things are crazy, so let's scale them back so that they're more balanced across the spectrum.
So as an example, if you look at strength in D&D,
if you have a two-handed sword with an 1800 strength,
which is sort of like, you know,
good times, top human strength,
you're doing 1D 10 plus six.
One to 10 plus six is a lot better in terms of percentage
than 14 to 20 plus 24%.
So yes, much bigger impact in D&D.
So if you want your stats to have a huge impact,
we decided to err on the side of viability,
not making characters really swing really wildly
in terms of how their stats were built up.
So this table shows AD&D strength damage adjustment.
This is for comparison.
You can see that big dead zone in the middle
where it's just flat.
That means there's no damage bonus.
This is only looking at damage bonuses.
There are other things that strength affects,
but it's primarily damage.
Assuming a two-handed sword because it's 1 to 10 that means I can do percentage modification. It's easy
If you use d8 then suddenly that's an even bigger percentage modification
But you can see how it it kind of has some spots where it'll go to points
And flatten out and then it you know keeps going up and then at 25 strength
They just go and get an extra you get an extra plus one for fun
So there's not really a lot of rhyme or reason to it. I should also note that
Before 3rd edition, strength had this weird percentile system.
So if you were a warrior and you had an 18 strength, you'd get...
you'd roll percentile, and that's how they incremented above 18 until you got to 19.
That's why this chart is weird.
D&D is weird.
You got it.
Now if you look at Pillars of Eternity strength damage adjustment,
you can see that this is extremely linear.
It's going up by 3%
just so you can go back. You can see 140 is the top end
at 25 strength. For us, 30 is the top end and that's 60 strength.
So it is quite a bit
less of an impact,
but again that is by design.
Some people don't like that and that is
okay,
but we're not changing it.
And then there's problems with perceived lack of value.
And again, balance and perception of value is
not just about what you set up, but about what the player actually perceives about it.
And lots of stuff goes into perception of strength.
I mean, I talked to someone, one of our system designers, who had worked on a game where
a gun was in a test and everyone was like,
God, this gun sucks.
Like, this is so horrible.
Everything about it is just junk.
I never want to use it.
And then they went through a tuning phase
and they changed the audio effects on the gun.
And they did not change any of the stats.
And they put it, you know, they did another test.
And the player's like, oh man, that gun's so good now.
It's, you guys got it.
And it was just purely, it was purely audio.
So lots of things go into perception of these things.
So why did people have problems perceiving the impact of stuff or continue to have trouble perceiving them?
One is that percentages are hard if you ask people to do percentile modifiers like yeah, this is
23% better like they're not immediately like
Yeah, I got it.
So, you know, they kind of round off, but sometimes it gets difficult to do those versus
oh, 1 to 10 plus 6, that is a little easier to conceive.
Larger numerical values pose problems.
So for various reasons we used bigger numerical ranges.
I think you noticed before our greatswords do 14 to 20 points of damage.
So once you start saying like, hey, you have two or three digit numbers that you're supposed
to do percentile operators on, players kind of start going like, I don't...
I kind of get that, but I don't really get it.
And we didn't have great feedback in the UI initially.
Thankfully, Brian McIntosh and Kez Uruga
have improved this a great deal
so that players can actually see comparisons,
like this is the base, this is the modified version,
these are all the things that are contributing to this value.
Transparency within the UI is extremely important.
And that was a reason why, though,
is that early on, people were just like,
I don't, I mean, it says this damage value,
I don't know what the base is,
I don't know what's modifying it,
I don't know how much my strength
is actually contributing to this.
And the companions are awful.
So, people complain about the stats
of our companions a bunch.
When we designed the companions,
we did them this way for a few reasons.
One is that the companions attributes
are reflecting who they are as characters.
So, we'll go back to the Khaleed example.
Khaleed's not a super tough guy.
He's got a 15 strength, that's okay man.
Our attributes are designed to be middle of the road.
So, you know, if you make your...
Let's say you have a paladin,
and that paladin is superminmaxed for damage.
Our companion paladin, Paladina,
is set up to be kind of like,
well, you can use her for healing,
you can use her for damage,
you can use her for defensive stuff.
Her stats are kind of more evenly balanced
across what paladins can do.
And despite the fact that players, you know, plenty of players have played through On Path of the Damned
the hardest difficulty using just the stock vanilla companions without modifying them, and they're just fine.
A lot of players are still like, no, I want to change these stats.
So I'll give an example of how people kind of change these stats.
First example is Pallagina. She is our paladin companion.
Her character is described as being very willful.
She's tough, but she describes failing her physical
examinations in the Brotherhood more than once.
Sure she's not especially strong.
She is an avian godlike, meaning that she sort of has these bird-like features.
She has heightened senses and her eyes are frequently described in reaction text,
like she's very perceptive of things.
So the way that I statted this character, because this is the character that I made,
it's kind of hard to see there, but she has a 12 might, 13 constitution,
you know, nothing too crazy.
And then 14 perception, because she's avian godlike.
And, what is that, a 13 intellect and a 15 resolve,
because she's very, very strong-willed.
So this is from a mod called Better Companions.
She has a 21 might. She's incredibly strong. She has a
15 con. Okay, that's fair. She has a 4 dexterity. Extremely,
extremely clumsy. A 3 perception, which is about as
bad as you could possibly get. She's a genius. She has a 20
intellect and an 18 resolve. So clearly this person wanted to do
like one thing. Or actually two things. They wanted to cast land
hands.
and they wanted to use their auras, because paladins have nice auras.
If you want to hit something, good luck, because you have a three perception, so you're tanking
your main attack stat. You can play a paladin this way,
but this is like the way that you have to play this paladin.
So our stance on this is we don't really care about people adjusting their companion stats.
Maybe a little. It does seem weird to see that character who's described in that way be so different from how she's described.
But the attribute system is designed to handle it.
Again, it's robust enough that it doesn't...
It's not that that character can't be played, you just have to play them a certain way.
So...
Sure.
Like, knock yourself out.
Here's an example of how you could go crazy with another companion, DevilOfCarrick.
is a rogue that you get in the White March.
A lot of people like to complain about her stats and her armor.
She has a relatively modest might score. It's 13.
Might bonuses to damage are not multiplicative, but they add up.
So every bonus to damage, they just kind of add up as a percentage modifier.
So if you set her might to 18, you'd get an additional 15% damage.
But a rogue sneak attack, which is their common, like they just get it all the time, they do it to anyone who's vulnerable to it, is plus 50% damage.
So that alone is a huge bonus.
Most rogue active abilities add 25% damage, and you get a bunch of those.
So just netting 15% more damage is not really... I mean, it's making a difference, but it's not that big of a difference.
If you dumped her might down to three, that would be, actually it wouldn't be 30%, I think it'd be, it's about 30% though, I think it's actually 27.
But you, it's not that big of a deal, because you're already doing plus 50 from your sneak attack,
and you're doing plus 25 on any active ability.
So rogues are good at doing damage, even if you tank their might, they're still pretty good at doing damage.
And you probably put those stats somewhere else, so they're getting a bonus somewhere else.
Significantly lower damage, but it's certainly not non-viable.
So I'd like to talk a little bit now about the changes that we made during the development cycle and after launch.
So we did have a pretty extensive beta, which is great. We got a lot of feedback.
A lot of feedback on attributes.
Initially, all attributes granted bonuses from one.
So, if you looked at the scale before, like D&D,
D&D kind of is balanced around nine as being neutral,
and then things above that give a bonus,
things below it give a penalty.
So we said, no, no, no.
Or actually, I should say, it's my responsibility.
I said, yeah, at one, that gives you a bonus.
And it just keeps getting better.
Well, people didn't really dig that.
It was different from D&D, which in itself,
some people don't respond well to.
The other thing is that we have this concept
of perceived loss, like our perception of loss
is way stronger than our perception of value.
So with that sense of we want people to feel
like dumping a stat is not really a great thing.
As soon as we set those, like we basically
just normalized all the math and then said,
oh yeah, a 10 is zero, and if you go down one,
you're at minus 3% damage.
And immediately people are like,
you're getting out of here.
You're getting out.
Like oh my god, I can't put anything to nine and if you look at people's builds a lot of people are really like
They'll take everything down to ten
But that perception of badness from going negative is extremely strong and powerful and I knew that at the beginning
I should have probably just had them at ten to begin with but well, I didn't
We also had perception and resolve both contributed to a deflection. So though we have two things feeding into that stat
Perception initially granted plus two to accuracy per point.
Everyone maxed this out as much as possible.
It was really dumb.
Like everyone in QA made max perception characters,
every little teeny bonus they could get to perception
because it's shifting your miss,
graze, hit, and crit chances.
It slides the whole thing up.
So that was dumb.
Constitution's bonus to endurance and health was only 3%.
This was a minor thing that we adjusted later.
Perception modified range.
That felt terrible.
Intellect modified radius, not area.
Those are different things.
And I did it in 3% increments.
So, throughout the course of the beta and into launch, and I don't remember when each of these things happened.
Like I said, we were, I think we continued patching attributes through patch 2.0 maybe, or maybe even later than that.
We averaged attributes around 10, with lesser values inflicting penalties.
Perception now contributes to accuracy at one point per, and people seem to find that worthwhile.
And resolve contributes to deflection, just by itself.
We increased the constitution bonus to 5% and that actually did make a significant difference in how people perceived it.
3% to 5% doesn't seem like it would be that big of a deal, but people perceived it as being a bigger deal.
And so they actually kind of said, okay, I'm not going to dump this so much anymore.
And intellect modifies area in 5% increments.
So you can't make everybody happy. Obviously not everyone was super thrilled with how this worked out.
It's true of any design, but we did not set out to try to make everyone happy.
We knew that we had an audience with a variety of tastes.
Our implementation was within what we believed our audience's tolerance threshold were.
So we know that some people that play our games,
they would rather not have attributes at all.
There are role-playing games, like Mass Effect, that has classes,
but it doesn't have attributes at all. You don't have to do that.
It's easier when you're not making a fantasy game.
It's easier when you're not making a fantasy game based on D&D very clearly.
So we know that some people just sort of ideologically or because of their preferences for system design
They'd rather have no attributes at all. That's fine
We understand that and we know that a lot of people wish that there were stronger or different attributes and during our beta phase
There were people that got real real upset about how we
Initially specced out attributes how we change attributes. There are some people that sort of forswore the game. They're like I'm over this
So people have really strong feelings about this stuff
But we knew that there was a big group within our core audience that we could probably make something for them where most of those people would be happy.
So usually, you know, I still hear people criticize that, which is sort of like, we wish this were different but it's not a deal breaker.
And so that applies to class design, that applies to armor design, like all the stuff that we have in our game.
There's a lot of stuff that people will say like, well, we wish this were not quite this way, but we're okay with it as it is.
No data to support this. This is just anecdotes.
We do have very active forums, lots of people that give feedback, a lot.
Also there are lots of off-sites.
NeoGAF, RPG Codex, Something Awful, lots of very active communities there that have very robust discussions about this stuff.
And ultimately ideological purity doesn't necessarily mean the players are going to be happy.
I think it's important to have ideology for what you're doing as a designer,
but at a certain point, if what you're trying to accomplish
sort of hits the players and the players go,
I don't like this, this isn't fun.
Whatever your ideology is, you kind of have to step back and say,
am I approaching this wrong? Is this a bad goal?
Is this not really accomplishing what the players needed to accomplish?
So start with an ideological point, but then you know move toward the players
In a sense of like you want them to have fun with it. So yeah, that should always be a goal
Would we do it this way again?
Probably
The benefits seem to outweigh the drawbacks. I will say that I spent
an obscene amount of time talking with people about how to set up these attributes, how to tune these attributes
going back and forth with programmers on it because the math gets really complicated
seemingly it wouldn't because we have a simpler system in many ways but it does get very complicated
listening to forum feedback and all that stuff
It really did take a lot of time and effort to make something that actually accomplished all the goals that we set out to do.
And even there, we didn't necessarily do a perfect job on it, obviously.
But the benefits of it do seem to outweigh the drawbacks.
We were happy with the gameplay. So internally, people seemed to like, overall, how stats work.
They like adjusting and getting little stat-boosting bonuses, and using spells and buffs to raise those up.
That's fun gameplay.
And most of the players seemed happy too.
Like I said, there are some players that really don't like it.
That is okay.
Would I do this personally? No.
I don't like that stuff.
Like I don't...
I think attributes conflict with classes. They have a lot of problems. I don't even like
class-based systems. So
I've been playing Ars Magica for the past two and a half years.
That's a goofy, goofy game.
So yeah, this isn't really about like my personal preferences though. Like as a
designer I'm looking at the audience, I'm looking at their expectations.
Obviously we kick-started a game
based on nostalgia and that, you know, that's based in
a lot of memories and feelings and emotions that people have.
You know, the point of designing this stuff is not to make something exactly as I want it,
but to make something that I think will make a good game that sort of fulfills the expectations of the people that backed it
and the people that want to come into the genre for the first time.
I do want to thank a bunch of people that helped out with this stuff.
I want to thank all of our backers. Obviously we wouldn't have been able to make this game if it were not for them.
Our beta testers, we had a subgroup of beta testers,
and we still have beta testers that beta test our patches,
they give a lot of great feedback.
And players, we have a lot of players,
we have great YouTubers, a lot of us at work,
you know, we watch these YouTubers
and we see their breakdowns of their analyses of the classes.
Sometimes it's very interesting
to see how they perceive things,
and we understand like, oh crap,
like, they think it works like this.
What are we doing wrong here?
Yeah, but players give us a lot of really fantastic feedback.
Our QA testers, I know that, I think that especially in the non-development world, people don't really give QA enough credit.
I think that, you know, in development also, I think there are a lot of places where QA is underappreciated.
I spent a lot of time talking with our testers, and I still continue to spend a lot of time talking with our testers.
They play the game all the time. They're trying to min-max and break everything. They have really good insight.
into how the game is played.
You know, I don't always agree with their analysis of things,
but again, that's the point though,
it's like you want to listen to their viewpoint
and hear where they're coming from on that stuff.
But they were extremely valuable in how we built this stuff.
And lastly, to Brenda Romero.
So I had given up on trying to pitch talks
that were this narrowly focused
because every time I did, they were like,
this is really niche, like no one's gonna,
no one cares about this stuff.
So I had gone broader and broader
and kind of stopped submitting things
and Brenda Romero actually contacted me and said,
hey, I want you to do.
are considered doing a really narrowly focused
niche RPG talk, so thanks to her, I was able to do this.
We have some time for questions, if anyone has anything.
Oh, thanks.
Hello.
Hey.
Thanks for a great presentation.
Thank you.
In the old, like, Baldur's Gate games,
you usually had dumb stats.
And I remember specifically that you had.
if you could have a low charisma you can dump that down to three and
Like in the first tenth outsider in Akers Dungeon, you can get a ring that set charisma to 18
Yeah, so lots of people did that was like
Go to strategy for many classes. How did you work with items?
to
Yeah affect attributes and balance
So the question was, sort of compared to Baldur's Gate where there were lots of items that influenced stats and in fact would set stats to certain values regardless of what their starting value was, how do we approach that in Pillars of Eternity?
So in Pillars, we did something that's more like 3rd edition D&D in the sense that we don't have items that
that set stats to certain values.
Instead they give bonuses and there are stacking rules for those.
So you can min-max them a little bit, but at a certain point
it's only going to take the highest value from that.
Part of that is also because if you think about
especially in the context of a single player CRPG
if a person has a strat guide or if a person
read a forum and they already know
oh there's a griddle of hill giant strength right here
well then they can start dump the points that they would have put in strength
they can put them in another stat
go straight to that griddle of hill giant strength
and effectively they're playing with many more points
in their attributes than other players are
so that kind of stinks
like obviously it's cool to have game knowledge and like knowledge of the world
and be able to beeline for things and get that cool stuff
but that advantage
I think should be a marginal advantage. It shouldn't be so gross.
Because the difference...
Girdle of Hill Giant Strength is 19 Strength.
If you set your Strength to 3, you just got 16 free attribute points.
So, yeah, we tried to keep those bonuses a little more constrained.
I know that, again, some people would like those to be more significant.
In the White March expansion, we added plus 4 items, which...
Oh my god!
You know, people really like when those step up and they can keep ramping them up.
Thank you.
Hello.
First of all, thanks for the game.
It's great.
Thank you.
And I just had a question, actually,
about the early process of design
and the prototyping process.
Since you were so steeped in tabletop design,
what it was like to test such a complex system,
if you went straight to digital or if you did paper prototyping
or even a tabletop session, and how that sort of looked like
and how you kind of got to where you are before the code
happened.
We did not do any, so the question is if we, how we prototype prior to implementation.
Yep.
And since we had a lot of basis in tabletop, did we do any tabletop gaming?
We did not. Part of that is because these stats would be a nightmare.
That's funny too, because some people say like,
hey, when's the tabletop version of this coming out?
I'm like, you want to do percentile operations on damage ranges that are like double digit?
I don't think you actually do.
So we didn't do that.
We sort of charted things out in Excel to see like,
what are the boundaries of this?
How is this really mapping out with how we're planning out abilities and damage ranges and things like that.
So it was mostly sort of, it was theoretical for a very long time
But we also, we looked outside of D&D, we looked to other games and said, you know
How do we feel about balance in these games?
And what are the sort of margins of influence? Like how impactful are these attributes on that?
And how does that feel for the type of game that we're trying to make?
And the nice thing was that
You know, Tim Cain did a lot of the implementation of the attribute things and it was usually pretty easy if I went to him and I said,
I was wrong, like these values are bad, we need to adjust this up or down or whatever.
It was usually pretty quick turnaround.
So we could test out those changes relatively rapidly.
But, yeah, I would have done tabletop sort of testing of that stuff.
but the mechanics were really designed and we wanted to design them for a CRPG.
We wanted to say like, we got a computer here, we can do lots of calculations really easily
for you, we don't have to base things on dice, you know, and so that's why our damage ranges
are more things like, you know, 14 to 20.
So yeah.
Great, thank you.
Thank you.
Hi.
So obviously...
the tributes are a pretty big exception, but was there anything else that came up kind of organically
while you were designing the game that you wanted to put in, but you thought the nostalgia focus wouldn't allow?
Were there things that we wanted to put in that we thought the nostalgia focus wouldn't allow?
I...
Not really. There were certain things that we put in that people resisted very strongly
because they weren't kind of part of their vision of what the experience was.
So for example, we have firearms in Pillars of Eternity, but they're all like 16th century era firearms.
While Forgotten Realms did have guns as early as second edition
They weren't part of the Infinity Engine games at all
And so a lot of people thought that that was just like they were like that's no that doesn't work that that feels completely wrong
And there were certain things that early on we decided
We should probably have these because we think of people a lot of people will miss them if they're not there
So for example, we have humans we have elves we have dwarves
I think a lot of people like humans, elves, and dwarves.
We don't have halflings, we don't have half-orcs.
So we were like, eh, we don't need to have those.
We can put in a maw, they're our big race.
And then we have orlins as our small race.
So we kind of figured that people like that idea
of like the sort of big race and small race.
We didn't think people were that attached
to the idea of like, I must play my halfling
or gnome in this game, so.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Hi.
I was wondering if you could elaborate on the different difficulty options in your game
and kind of how that influenced your attribute design.
I find that the higher difficulty goes, usually that leans more towards min-maxing, less towards
viable characters.
And since some of your most dedicated players are going to be interacting with those systems,
I feel like it's better to always look there and not look at viable characters.
I was wondering what your experience with that was.
So the question is about our difficulty design and how that influenced our attribute design.
And so we have easy, normal, hard.
And then we have a few other crazy ones.
The most significant of which is Path of the Damned.
And we, except for Path of the Damned, we did not do stat modifications on creatures.
Instead, we changed the composition of encounters.
So if you're on normal, you might see, you know, like a wizard and two...
paladins but on hard it's like an archmage it's a completely different like more powerful wizard
and two paladins and you know like a rogue gets added into the group and and it's in a weird
position where it makes it more tactically difficult for you to deal with it but path of
the damned was specifically designed for the most aggressive players and so we said like this mode
not only does it have all the creatures from all levels of difficulty but they all have increased
stats so they have better defenses and better accuracy
And we kind of said with Path of the Damned, we know that there is a gulf between viable and optimal.
And this is where the players who want to push that envelope, they need to do that.
If you just kind of stumble and like, hey, Path of the Damned, what's this?
And you just kind of try to stumble and bumble through, you're probably going to die.
So, yeah, we wanted to make sure that viability for...
characters didn't require crazy optimization even on hard,
but on Path of the Damned,
there are some really good Path of the Damned players
who don't even feel like you need to optimize
that much on Path of the Damned,
but they're really good players.
Most people have to get a little more ambitious
with how they're looking at their stat spreads
and things like that.
Their gearing becomes much more important
on Path of the Damned.
So that's how it tied together.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Yeah, so talking about dump stats, I get the feeling that a lot of RPG players kind of naturally assume that
You know if you're playing a fighter you want to dump charisma if you're playing, you know wizard
You want to dump like dexterity or something like that?
How did you guys communicate to new players of your game that you don't necessarily want to you know, just dump all your perception?
Yeah, so that is a tricky thing. And we did have to deal with that a lot. Thanks for bringing that up.
We did have a thing where people would look at something and they're like, wizard strength? I don't think so.
And then they're like casting their damage spells and we're like, what the heck is going on?
In D&D, usually stats don't affect your spell damage at all.
So they had no expectation of that.
So one is again, trying to make the UI reflect,
clearly say this affects damage, like all damage.
But the other thing we did is,
one of our programmers, Robbie, put in a thing where we could
add little stars next to character attributes
in certain classes to say,
this is kind of important.
To sort of say, you might think this is not important.
Look again.
So I think Wizards had like a either a silver or gold star next to might to sort of say like this is more
Significant than you might think it is. You can still dump might but if you dump might you're gonna make a crowd control character
Or something like that. You're not gonna be focusing on damage
But yeah, it is a difficult problem because again, you're dealing with a lot of expectations. We also we called it might
Hopefully to make a player go like, wait a minute, isn't that normally strength?
Is this something different?
It is something different, friend.
It's something that affects
damage and healing for everything.
So sometimes it's the nomenclature like
charisma we got rid of and replaced it with resolve.
It's sort of similar but it affects like deflection, it affects concentration.
Very different from how charisma works.
mechanically in D&D although resolve is also used in conversations for you know
being like a real intense kind of a person so it's difficult but we tried to
use naming and UI sort of signaling to help guide people in that direction
thanks any last questions all right thank you everyone for coming