Hello, hello, hello.
Wow, people turned up, that's cool.
Put my Mountain Dew down there.
Nice and indie.
Hello, I'm Mike.
I'm a game developer.
I made Thomas Was Alone.
People in the room know what Thomas Was Alone is?
Yeah, hands up.
In England, you'd get more of a groan at the self-promotion than an applause, but let's go with it.
Those of you who want to hear about Polish game development, my friends, you've walked into the wrong room.
This is about Polish.
Something we don't talk about a great deal as indie game developments.
Indie game developments? Indie game developers.
I've got a sweet because my throat is killed by telling Glitchmob very loudly last night how much I enjoyed their music.
Screaming seemed like a good idea at the time.
A lot of indies don't really talk about
what polish is, because it's not the part of the conversation
that we necessarily think is cool.
We do a lot of game jams and a lot of ideas
and a lot of cool inspirational stuff,
which is massively important and massively lovely.
However, I think there's other stuff that we can talk about.
This is a question. Should indies polish?
Indies, obviously we have a cool opportunity to do whatever we want.
To push aesthetics to do different, weird, cool, whatever stuff.
We usually associate polish with kind of AAA stuff,
or more corporation kind of developed stuff.
And therefore when you mention polish in rooms full of indie game developers,
sometimes you can get either, well, at best a bored look, at worst anger.
So polish. The purpose of polish is to make a game more approachable, obviously,
and make it immediately pleasing on an aesthetic level or even on an interactive level.
It's the thing that makes games fun, which is a word with lots of connotations. There are lots
of reasons to make games. Fun is not the only reason. Well, it's a pretty good one.
So there's lots of arguments, I think, for doing indie polish.
There's obviously, there's the capitalist argument.
I need to pay my rent.
My staff, my team members, my colleagues, my friends,
they also need to pay their rent.
To pay rent currently we need money.
In order to make money we need to sell our games
to enough people to cover all those bills.
Therefore, we need enough people to like the game, play the game, talk about the game,
show the game to their friends on YouTube, enjoy trailers, all these kinds of things.
There is a good, very obvious argument for polishing a game if you want it to make money.
There's also the design argument.
We've seen kind of playtesting and polish in general go in and out of fashion,
generally depending on how much Valve are talking about it,
which is fine.
But playtesting's awesome.
Playtesting's a great way of finding out where things go wrong,
where things don't go wrong,
and making sure that the experience that you're creating is the one you want to create.
I don't think we should use playtesting to find out what a game is.
It's useful sometimes if you're not sure what the focus should be,
to put it in front of players and let them tell you.
But generally I'm more of the slightly arrogant auteur type,
that I have a vision and I have an objective with my games.
And playtesting's really useful to find out how badly I'm achieving that.
It's good at pointing me in the right direction
of achieving what my goals are as a creator.
Usually I'm miles and miles off.
We've had this with volume.
I've been demoing that to press for a year and a half now,
and it's only just at a point where people seem to be getting it
and getting what I'm trying to do with it.
That's not their fault.
But we've solved it because we've had that feedback over a year and a half.
There's also, of course, the ego argument, which we're not allowed to admit to, but obviously,
if you make accessible, polished, clean games, people will think you're awesome.
And they will fist bump you at events and things like that.
And we all pretend we don't care about that, but it is quite nice.
So there's lots of arguments for it.
Of course you don't have to. Obviously, Indy has an enormous capacity to be punk,
to be different, to fight, to not be the way that anyone wants it to be.
We can create stuff that is not designed to appeal to anyone but ourselves.
We can do that. That's an absolutely objective that's fair.
It's cool, it's fine, and it's actually where a lot of the more interesting stuff
in the Indy space is being done.
The stuff that is genuinely pushing the medium forward.
is often the stuff that is riskiest.
And if those people had subscribed to polish
to the degree that I do,
or to the degree that designers like me do,
maybe they would not have achieved
the enormously impressive work that they did.
It's more prone to failure, obviously,
because it is riskier,
but when it succeeds, you can create new genres,
new ideas, new everything.
However, and it's very important that as creators,
we never make the mistake of thinking
that punk work is without intent.
The person who sits down and makes a game
that breaks the rules, that does something different,
if they're just doing it because they didn't bother
to check what the rules were
or to see how players reacted to what they were doing
and just went for it anyway, then they're not punks.
They're people who haven't invested the time
and effort in their design.
Punk intentionally produced is fantastic.
Punk, which is an excuse for not really thinking through what it is you're trying to do,
is less exciting.
And I'd also even argue that punk is in itself an aesthetic polish.
We are making a choice.
We're making a choice to do something.
We're testing the water, be it through playtesting, through releasing screenshots,
through making videos, whatever,
and we're seeing if it has the result for players that we want.
It doesn't matter if that's, you know,
aiming for a mainstream audience
who like free-to-play farming games,
or if it's making something for ten people
who you think are cool.
It's the same idea.
So I'd argue that actually,
the should we, shouldn't we debate
is a bit off the mark.
I don't think,
I think we're all talking about the same thing,
basically just we have different goals.
So, it's GDC, so obviously I have to give you
a list of things you have to do.
So,
Animating squares. So this is what I'm known for. I'm the rectangle guy.
That's okay. There's worse kinds of guy you could be.
But it's fine.
So why? Why was Thomas was alone rectangles? Well, the very obvious answer,
which is guessed by the average 14-year-old on YouTube absolutely accurately,
is I can't draw.
I could, I'm sure. I'm not a massive believer in innate talent.
I'm sure if I put in the energy and effort that every artist who's good has done,
I could probably reach some level of mediocrity,
but I've not invested that time, I've not invested that energy,
so therefore I'm not an artist.
But what I am is I'm a reasonably half-decent graphic designer
who worked for years producing pitch documentation for AAA games.
That means I'm very good at putting a gun on a page
so it looks really nice next to a cool typeface.
I can't make the image of the gun, but I can make sure the gun kind of fits well compositionally,
and I can make the colors work so that it looks more brutal and impressive and AAA.
These are things I can do, and those are the things I focused on when Thomas was alone.
They're squares because squares are what I can do.
Now, initially that might sound like I wasn't pushing myself.
But I was pushing myself. I'd never made a game on my own before.
I was definitely trying to do storytelling stuff I'd never done before.
I was trying to do various different things.
I was making a game on my own time around a full-time day job.
I was pushing myself plenty.
So I chose an area that made sense, that actually I can be the rectangle game.
And it struck me as weird at the time that more people hadn't done it.
And it strikes me as even more weird now.
that no one else has. Now, this slide actually became out of date
about two days ago when there was a game announced on Greedlight,
which is some aesthetic similarities to Thomas Was Alone,
which I'm not going to talk about.
But yeah, it was a way, it was a way of getting the thing done.
Now, this is where polish comes in, is if I'd just done a game without rectangles,
I think people would rightly have reacted to it kind of negatively.
They would have, they would have seen it as lazy.
But so what I did was I decided to do, you know, good animation.
Now the first page of any animation textbook you can pick up
is about squash and stretch.
It's about this idea that objects retain their mass,
but as they move around, if they impact things, they squish a bit.
Usually when they move away from something,
there's a moment of elongation,
although it's not as strong as most animation textbooks show.
We just elongate it more to sell it,
to make it look more impressive.
So I read the first two pages of every animation textbook I could find.
Um, just, just because, you know, I'm an overachiever.
Um, so I, I, I did squash and stretch those rectangles.
Now, what's cool about the second page of any animation textbook
is it tells you that eyes are really easy to trick.
Um, I've never been called up for this by anyone
before I pointed it out, but Thomas was Alone
doesn't actually have squash and stretch.
It has stretch.
Uh, the characters, when they impact, when they land.
You never actually see the impact squish the character.
The reason, because from a gameplay point of view,
it messed up the kind of the footprint of the character
and made it awful.
When you're jumping, the footprint doesn't matter
because you're moving vertically.
So it's fine.
So I got away with that.
And that's going to be a big theme of this,
is things we can get away with.
The human eye is very easy to trick,
and you can actually usually,
through a little sleight of hand,
achieve massive benefits from smaller beginnings.
Speaking of big benefits, this is my voice actor from Thomas Was Alone, Danny Wallace,
who is actually legally a king of a small country that he set up in the UK in his flat
as part of a hilarious TV show. And it's true, he actually does, well I think actually he moved
out of that flat. I've not followed up with him what happened to that, but that's fine.
He's a voice actor. He's a very good voice actor.
He does a lot of TV in the UK.
He's very cool.
To Americans, he's usually more known as, well,
some people think he's Wheatley from Portal, which he isn't.
He really isn't.
But he's Sean Hastings in the Assassin's Creed series,
so that's where a lot of people know him from.
And they do a reasonably good approximation of his face
in that game as well, so people tend to recognize him from that.
Now, voiceover was interesting.
Voiceover's something that came to me
very late in the day when Thomas was alone,
and again, it's something that I'm very surprised
more indies don't take advantage of.
Three years ago, it wasn't being done by many games,
and to be honest, it's still not being done.
We see a few.
There's a Wil Wheaton-voiced tactical shooter
that looks really cool.
There's a few things.
But voiceover isn't often used,
and I think the reason for that
is that people think it's expensive.
People think that voice acting's expensive.
They look at, you know,
actors, movie stars, and you hear how much so-and-so gets paid for a movie.
They don't really think about actually how much it costs to get a very talented person
into a room for an afternoon to record some voiceover for you.
I'm not going to talk about actors' rates on stage in front of a GDC audience, but it's
lower than you think, and it's fair.
Frankly, it's fair for what they're bringing to the game.
If you compare it to the budget for an animator, or the budget for an artist or a coder...
It's an easy trade to make. You can actually look at it and go,
you know what, I am getting that amount of value from the actor.
It's also scalable.
More so, actually, than artists or animators
is the difference in wages, because obviously you have,
you know, a jobbing voice actor, like, who's not famous.
will do X amount, right up to, you know, if you want to get a Hollywood movie star in
your game, obviously the price goes up.
And it's variable because actors are often used to taking roles that they want at a lower
pay.
So there's a few ways around it.
And a good voice actor who understands the medium can really elevate a game.
Danny Wallace actually used to be a video game critic many years ago.
So he got the game. He played the game a lot before he voiced it.
He had the soundtrack playing to him in the booth,
so he could kind of judge where his voice would sit with it.
He took it very seriously and, you know,
created an after-winning performance as a result of that.
I just had to slip that in.
I apologize.
Also, I had to make a joke about it,
because I needed to inhale some air.
And I hoped you'd laugh, and you did,
which helped me there.
So thank you.
But I didn't inhale enough, so I made another joke.
So, anyway, it was fine.
And then I, no, this, this too,
we're busy. We've got stuff to do.
So it's possible, is my point.
And it scales as the budget does.
So as you find yourself hopefully making
subsequent games with maybe a little bit more cash,
you can scale that up.
So Danny did Thomas Was Alone.
He's back in volume, but now we have Charlie MacDonald in it,
and Andy Serkis doing the villain, and he's awesome,
and I can't wait to share that stuff.
It's possible to scale that up, but you can start very cheap
with voiceover, and it immediately makes your game feel much more polished.
Color, or color.
Yeah, I don't feel good about this slide.
It's an overlooked issue.
Color theory is old.
There's lots of color theory out there.
It's reasonably accessible.
You walk into any bookshop,
there's gonna be five books targeted at A-level students,
sorry, college students.
about it. You can learn in an afternoon the very basics of, you know, secondary tertiary color palettes
and, you know, how to actually think about color. And yet none of us do. We look at, we either work
with the color palettes that come by default in the software we use. We leave the shadows in Unity
to black while they should be blue. If the scene is outdoors, shadows are not black, as my art
director tells me on a daily basis. We don't think about this stuff, but it's actually, again, very
easy to do. Thomas was alone.
I'm not going to claim a level of skill at this.
I had the guy who's now my art director on volume
created a palette for it that was cool and consistent
and worked across the game.
And it made the game look great.
Thomas Was Alone has, I believe, 24 colors in it.
That's it.
That's all we use in Thomas Was Alone.
It's a game that everyone thinks we go through the whole palette.
But we actually use 24 colors.
What that does is that means every color in the game
sits well with every other color in the game.
Really straightforward stuff that,
at Indie Budget, we often don't think about doing.
Volume's the same. Volume is, again, 24 colors.
I think we're using the same palette or something very similar.
What's great about doing that is every screenshot
looks good when next to every other screenshot
when you're on the Steam shop or whatever.
Everything ties together. It looks consistent.
I believe I worked for Nickelodeon at one point on a project.
I think every Nickelodeon cartoon is 16 colors total.
Which means they can take any character from any Nickelodeon cartoon and put them next to any other character from any other Nickelodeon cartoon, and it all works.
This is stuff that was invented 50 to 100 years ago.
Well, it was invented thousands of years ago, but we wrote it down in pretentious textbooks about 50 years ago.
We should use that, is my point. It's useful.
And you can, you know, there's lots of cheats.
You don't have to have a best mate who's good at color theory.
You can use things like Adobe Cooler as a good shortcut.
I think that's actually where Thomas Was Alone's main characters
were just me using a default palette on Cooler when we started.
Real games.
And what that even means.
We're not doing that conversation, don't worry.
We're not doing the whole what makes a game a real game thing.
We're not talking about that debate.
We're talking about the much more
Well, simultaneously more interesting and less interesting debate, which is the average player, how they view a game when they open it up.
Whether a game is real or not. Whether it's a professional game. Whether it's something that they can assume is a good game off the bat.
That first impression. It's nothing to do with photorealism. It's nothing to do with walking simulators.
Polish does this.
And there's lots of little bits of Polish that we can do.
They take time, they take a little bit of money,
but they create a much better first impression.
I made a list asking a few YouTuber friends,
and I got the usual, you know, field of view,
in-game control rebinding,
in-game settings for graphics, effects, windows,
full screen UI scaling on desktop,
mouse control on menus,
raw mouse input versus averaged input,
splash screens, tutorial information, credits.
Stuff like that is really good at making things look right.
Because, you know, as with this slightly creepy image I found on the Internet,
the second you remove one thing...
It just doesn't quite feel like a real game to the person playing,
and you kind of can lose them at the menu screen.
Or at least you can put them in a bad position early on.
Anyone who's released a game commercially knows this
because you will have an inbox full of emails
about the one thing you forgot to put in your game.
With me, it was there was no mouse control
in Thomas Was Alone's menu on the desktop.
I still get an email every day.
I'm not fixing it, though, because I'm an artist.
So, the next step really is know what not to polish.
This is, I think, if you take nothing else
away from this talk, this is the big one for me.
This is the really, really important one.
The easiest way to polish something
is not to make something unpolished.
It's something that we're all, as game developers, prone to do.
Feature creep is real.
It's the reason you're not playing volume in 2014.
It's everywhere in the industry.
It's fine.
It's good.
It's where good stuff comes from.
But also, with good planning, we can avoid some of the pitfalls.
We can actually polish the game by doing less work.
Which, when you're putting the energy and effort that you should be putting into color
palettes, getting animation working with the skills you have.
getting all the menu settings working right.
Not having other jobs to do is a big help.
So, I do this all the time.
I work around the limitations of the team.
I tend to try and choose two or three skills
or things I want to push forward for us on a project
because otherwise I'm just making boring things.
For myself, I mean, not for the audience.
Hopefully I'm never making boring things for the audience.
But once I've chosen those things, I'm not going to make risks in other areas.
So, for example, Volume is a game, it's a passion project for me.
It's a stealth game kind of owed to the stuff I loved as a kid,
which is a story Indies have been telling journalists for a good 20 years now.
It's that, but it is that really.
It's that 15-year-old game I've always wanted to make.
I knew I wanted to do quite complex server stuff
so we could have user-editable levels.
I knew I wanted to be bigger.
I knew I wanted to be more complex
from a puzzle point of view
and from a mechanic point of view.
I knew I wanted to be less linear than Thomas was alone was.
I had a laundry list of lots of things I wanted to do.
But I also knew some areas I could stop.
One great thing that I'm incredibly happy with
is we realized very early on
how much storytelling we wanted to do in the game.
We wanted, so Thomas was learning to do like a narration,
but we wanted to have dialogue,
we wanted characters talking to each other in this space.
The problem that presented was lip sync.
I don't know the exact number off the top of my head, but about two hours worth of spoken dialogue in the game.
To lip-sync all of that up for each character would present both a technical challenge in terms of rigging up that stuff for the first time,
but also a population challenge, and also lip-sync.
It's one of those things that you can't half-do.
You know, if you make it, if it's just a flapping jaw, it doesn't work.
If it's, you know, if it's GTA, it costs a lot of money.
So it was a big scary thing when we were looking at the project at the start.
We put a mask on the main character.
And that worked.
And that really significantly improved the facial animation we found.
And then other characters became disembodied voices because they were AIs.
We had, yeah, characters with masks.
We have one character in the game who's lip-synced.
He's on screen for two minutes.
So that's quite a good reduction on the lip-sync costs.
And what it meant was our animators...
and our rigors and all these other kind of professions that would have been
hit by that could go and do other things and polish up what we had better.
I mean in the end we, through development, we've been pulling the camera angle
further and further back.
So really we did, if we'd done lip sync at the start,
we'd basically have about three pixels shimmering here
for quite a lot of money. Likewise the environment of the game, we knew we wanted to
make something that looked
A big visual jump up from Thomas was alone.
We wanted something that a more mainstream audience could look at and go, yes, I get
this.
This is not photorealistic, but it looks like a modern game.
But also we knew the budget that would be associated with that kind of choice.
So we came up with a story about a character, one character who's a quote-unquote real character
in a big room, a big warehouse.
simulating crimes over and over.
Now, what we did was we spent all of our money
on the character and the cool environment,
but then the rooms you're robbing,
the simulated environments were all very low-poly artwork.
We actually hired a PS1 environment artist
who's now a teacher in Wales.
We were his hobby project.
Every Saturday, he'd basically lock himself away
in his office and he'd fiddle
and make PlayStation 1 art again
because it was something he...
he always loved and he wanted to get back to it.
And it was great because we could basically pay
for all his family's holidays for a couple of years
and we got a very efficient person
who knew exactly what they were doing
because this is how it used to be done.
Using skills that a lot of people are having to relearn
to get that kind of polygon aesthetic nowadays.
So that was cool.
My point is choices worked in this case.
Choices allowed us to polish the game through a mission
and also through what we chose to put our focus on.
So that's all of it, really.
The summary is I think polish is important.
I think it's crucial to game development.
Whether or not you're going for a punk aesthetic,
because I'm absolutely certain every successful punk in history
has been intentional in their practice.
They have tried to do the thing they wanted to do,
and they have used every tool at their disposal to do it.
I think it's cool. I'm going to ask you all, if you want to ask any questions,
to go up to the microphones, and we will get started.
I think that's how we do things.
So if you want to run up to the microphone, please do.
And we can get started.
And thank you all for coming. This is my first GDC talk.
I hope it was useful.
Awesome, I'm going to try and get through as many as I can.
Yes, sir?
OK, hello.
So we're also working on a game right now.
And like everyone else, we want polish,
but we don't have so much time.
So I was wondering what your process is.
Do you make a first pass of everything
and then go back and polish?
Or do you try to get a certain level on certain things
and then just cut in the end?
Or what is your process?
So my process is that I make something and I leave it until I get so sick of how awful it looks that I fix it.
I'm not sure that's very good advice though, because that leads to, yes, volume coming 2015.
So I don't know what the answer is.
I think I'm a big believer that we need to take things to a certain point to know whether they're fun.
I mean, I don't believe that you can prototype a game very quickly and know whether that's
going to work because it's an audio-visual medium.
Things aren't as fun as they're going to be until they have, you know, audio attached
to them and the right animation and the right feel.
I like my approach of iterating, so I throw something in, I fiddle with it when I'm unhappy with it,
I'm also throwing new things in, and eventually stuff seems to kind of fall into place,
and you realize, yeah, I think there's about nine user gadgets in this game,
and there's about 20 environmental interactions, and yeah, that feels about right.
Oh, actually, that one's horrible, get rid of that.
But now we need something to do that, so I'm a bit more...
I'm hoping that that will improve over time, but I've been working in games for eight years
now and it hasn't, so I might have to deal with that.
But there is no right answer, is basically the answer to the question.
I can only tell you my solution.
Thanks.
No worries.
Yes, sir?
Hi.
I was just wondering, how do you approach creating a library of sounds for your game?
Because when I've been working on games, I find if I'm trying to source sounds from the
internet, it's incredibly hard to find the one that fits the game just right.
No, it is, especially if you're looking at free libraries
and things like that.
So, Thomas Was Alone was a zero budget game.
So I used, is it CFX, this is a room of indies,
it's CFXR, right?
That's that one, SFXR.
Actually, no, I think it's CFXR, the one I use,
because it's on the Mac.
Anyway, it doesn't matter.
Okay, they know I'm wrong.
So, yes, I used that, which just made some bleeps and bloops,
which was right for Thomas was alone.
It really annoys my musician, my composer,
when he gets complimented on those sound effects
because he hates them.
So please, if you ever see him, just say,
I loved your sound work in Thomas was alone.
It was me in an afternoon on a Sunday sometime.
With volume, I hired a sound engineer.
Now, what's good about that
is if you're working with a freelancer,
Usually they will have licenses to massive libraries, so they will have bought kind of access to one of the big sound libraries
and they will have access immediately to
1,000 footsteps
Much better than any free resource you're going to find online or any kind of Google thing
So if you have the budget for a sound engineer
They're probably going to be cheaper to get them to use their access to a sound library and create the thing that's right for you
But if you haven't got that budget, I would, this is where I would say this is one of the Kermit the Frog moments.
You go maybe in the left angle and you go, well, is there another way of doing sound design on this game that uses found audio or abstract audio or...
something else.
There's not very good library access for us.
I would actually look, though, if you can,
at getting library access to those professional libraries,
because it might, again, be cheaper than you'd imagine,
and we'll just give you everything you need
almost instantly.
Hope that's useful.
Cheers.
Hello.
Hi.
Can you talk about polish in the writing?
The writing in the narration is really crisp and beautiful
and kind of what your polish process was there.
And then anything you did with your composer
that you would consider polish?
I play the score in my car while I drive.
Like, how do you get it to that?
Well, that's very kind.
So, I'll answer the music one first,
because that's easy.
My composer's a genius.
That's the answer.
I honestly, the process I have with the composer
is we start a project.
I send him kind of a Spotify playlist of,
hey, here's 10 tracks I think are about right for the game.
Can you do something along those lines, please?
He then ignores that email.
He gets to the bottom of what I don't know that I want, but actually I want.
And then he produces over the course of a year or two the music I need for the game.
And very rarely I give feedback.
Sometimes if something feels like it jars with gameplay, I'll say something.
But on the whole...
Yeah, sorry, it's a really bad advice because...
Hire David J. Houston, would be my tip.
But don't for a while, because he's got quite a few bits more to do on volume.
The other part, the writing, that's just iteration.
And writing is very iterative, if you do it right.
I think Thomas Was Alone's script was about 30 redrafts.
That's quite light, actually, on a volume we went through.
I don't want to think about how many redrafts Volume had.
And actually I brought in a story consultant,
Mattie Bryce.
That's my second name drop of her on stage.
She's brilliant. Hire her.
She came in for a few days and kind of
went, well, maybe this bit's not working,
or maybe you should dodge that.
That kind of thing.
So it's really just iteration.
It's just you start, you just write the awful hack version
of the script, and then you go through and go,
yeah, it makes, why is he doing that?
You know when you watch a movie, and you're like,
I don't understand why that character's behavior has changed?
You do that to your own work for about 40 times,
and you'll introduce problems, you'll fix it.
It's honestly like bug fixing,
only you get slightly more praise for it than bug fixing,
which is nice.
But yes, that's it basically.
Cheers. I've been doing this whole talk, and I've just realized this isn't my mic. This is my mic.
I could be over here.
Yes, you mentioned the voiceover as being a big part of the polish and I agree and for our project we plan to do
Things of that nature. We're wondering about localization and being an indie game
You might not have to think about translating your voice over to many languages
But I was wondering if it affected the reach of your product or if you had to do anything after the fact to make sure
That your game was still understandable to other audiences that speak different languages
That's incredibly, I'm really liking the movement.
That's incredibly, that's actually,
it actually feels weird now I'm calling attention to it.
That's, it's incredibly true of actually conversations
we're having now with volume,
and whether we're gonna do voiceover localization.
When Thomas was alone, I was a bit of a,
a bit of an asshole really.
I basically went, no, it's Danny Wallace,
or it's not at all, and Danny Wallace
doesn't speak all those languages.
So we went, well, then we're not doing
voiceover localization.
And we did, you know, the standard e-figs.
Sorry, English, French, Italian, Spanish, German,
everywhere.
But, you know, it was only text.
With volume, we're taking a couple approaches.
We're thinking about voiceover,
and we're currently looking at some of the pricing on that.
It's quite expensive.
We're not going to do it at launch, though.
I would suggest voiceover is something
you can actually do as updates later.
And from a PR point of view,
there's probably a good argument
for launching the game, making a lot of noise,
and then as you do each VO kind of update...
You can then target the press in each of those countries and go,
and now it's in whatever, you know.
Insert the name of the language there.
So do you suggest, say if our native language is going to be English for the game,
should we ship the game with no voiceover at all?
No, I would ship it with English voiceover.
Because actually, and it's embarrassing as an English speaker,
other countries are far better at putting up with our crap than we would be.
They are fine with English voiceover,
to the extent that actually I find it embarrassing
that I'm not okay with, you know, with subtitles in games
when it's spoken in a different language.
But they are.
The other thing we're doing with volume is user-editable language.
So you're going to be...
So on console it's different, but on PC players will be able to
literally open up the text file for the subtitles
and make their own fan subtitles.
That's amazing.
Which is going to be great for the people who take us seriously,
but the Klingon version is going to be awesome.
I'm getting a gesture, I don't know what it means.
Does that mean stop, or does that mean one more question?
One more question.
You're the lucky guy.
Oh, awesome.
So just more on voiceover, did you do pickups for Thomas Was Alone and what was your process
for doing essentially retakes of pickups?
Pickups. So Thomas was alone, we had no budget.
Like we literally did a crowdfund, and we got enough money to basically,
because VO Studio, if you do it right, costs quite a bit of money as well.
And I would recommend that people do.
You can tell when something's recorded, even if it's that nice mic that's in all of the
podcasting videos, even then you can tell the difference between that and a professional studio.
So we basically got enough money for a professional studio and four hours.
Three hours of Danny's time so we had no pickups on that game at all
That was just simply not an option
Luckily Danny's really good
And did a good job, but even then like those you know things
I listen back to Thomas was alone and just a couple of reads that I would tweak and change with volume
We decided not to do pickups. What I did instead was I did rehearsals
So we got Danny and Charlie we rented out a drama studio
Like, I say drama, we owned our small office in London for the day and then we had these
two going through, repeating over and over again, going through, having big conversations
about what the arcs of the characters were, getting their performances right between us.
And Danny was awesome because Charlie hadn't acted in a game before.
So he was kind of nervous and Danny kind of helped him kind of work things out
Which was amazing of him and way beyond kind of what we were paying him for frankly, which is great
Andy circus is Andy circus
So he just kind of came in with a three-hour slot recorded all those lines in two hours
It was amazing and then he left so that was an easier process
But yeah, so we don't do pickups now. I think actually honestly
That's a gap in our process and that's something I'd like to address with future games.
Because I think it's something that, again, for the cost of actually doing it, it would be worth it.
So don't take my advice. Do pickups. Not like me.
And I think that's all we have time for. Thank you so much. You've been an amazing audience. Cheers.
And I still think this is the mic.