Hi, I'm Richard Carillo, a game director at Ubisoft Toronto.
Back in 2015, I gave a talk titled,
Designing Your Design Team.
It was my theory that there's four different types
of game designers, each with unique perspectives
when solving problems, with the idea
that if you understand your design team,
you'll make better games.
This time around, I wanted to make a talk that was more practical
and could be used to solve problems like we're facing in our studio
with interviewing game designers.
Some interviewers will focus on the experience of the candidate,
others will focus on the processes and documentation,
while many more will say,
hey, can you design a cool idea for your favorite game?
But most of these interviewers will miss out on one fundamental question.
Are you a game designer?
My talk, titled Interviewing for Game Design,
will focus on that question
and help you understand what to look for in the answers.
This talk is for interviewers and candidates alike.
Hope to see you there.