Hi, everyone.
Thank you for joining us for the Raid on Ryze panel.
We're going to be going over a little bit about the process
and the challenges we faced when creating the narrative for Ryze
of the Tomb Raider.
Before I begin, this is critically important.
We're going to be talking frankly and openly
about the story.
There will be spoilers.
We will say elements about the ending.
And I am deadly serious.
We are going to spoil this game.
So before we begin, let me introduce our panel real quick.
We have Noah Hughes, who is our creative director.
Rhianna Pratchett, our lead writer.
John Stafford, our lead narrative designer.
We have Tor, who is our performance director.
That's his real name, I swear.
And Jeff Adams, who's our lead story designer.
And I'm Cameron Sui, I'm a narrative designer.
lead story artist.
Cameron Sui, I'm a narrative designer,
and I drew the short straw,
so I'll be moderating the panel today.
Now we come from a diverse background of games,
some of the samples of our past history are up there,
but we've all come together for this game.
Now this talk, we're gonna talk about
how we go about creating stories at Crystal Dynamics,
how we work across disciplines.
Now this team up here is the
the main narrative team that is in charge and responsible for
the implementation of the story but
the real story is created by everybody across the entire studio in every
department
uh... now a quick note
we sort of look at this as a uh... a raid in an MMO fashion we all come from
very diverse backgrounds we have very
diverse skills and we really learned to trust each other's strengths in this
process
and so we each had unique roles and we're going to be talking a little bit about that
as we go through our process
Now we're going to talk a little bit how we get from this,
the very beginning of our first ideas on the page
and our first beginnings of sketching out
the rough framework of a story, to this.
My dearest Lara, I often think about a shame
I have brought upon our family's name.
Croft, what does it even mean?
When I was young, he was just my father and I.
In his last years, he was obsessed with myths about immortality.
I may have found the next piece to the puzzle, but they're following me.
I know them by name now.
Trinity. Of course, no one believed him,
including me.
OK.
We're going to cover very briefly the Crystal Dynamics
story pillars.
These are the underpinning philosophies and ideas that we
use when creating any narrative at our studio.
Then we're going to talk a little bit about what we
learned from the prior Tomb Raider game in 2013, which
Rihanna, John, and Noah are veterans of.
Tor, Jeff, and myself are new to the party.
And then finally, we're going to talk a little bit
about our process and the eight steps
that we go from starting our very earliest discussions
of themes to the very final finished product.
We're going to walk you through using examples
and illustrate how this works.
And hopefully, you'll be able to take some of our process
or some of our takeaways and create
your own unique and fulfilling narratives.
Now, Crystal Dynamics uses a high-level framework
when approaching a narrative,
and we're gonna call them the story pillars.
We're gonna discuss the four key ones right now.
And we develop all stories for games
at our studio using these as a guide.
I'm gonna turn it over to Noah here,
who's gonna talk a little bit about our story pillars.
Thanks, Kim.
The first thing to note is we do apply a three-act structure.
So it ends up being a very long act two in the middle.
But those transitions from act one to act two
and from act two to act three are what you'd
expect from that structure.
But beyond that, to put our characters at the center,
we sort of commit to the idea of the character arc
being the backbone of that story.
So we'll take our point of view character, in this case, Lara,
and we'll put her in the middle of the story.
and make sure that she's different at the end of the story
than at the beginning of the story.
And she has an internal conflict
which forces her to ultimately change
in order to be successful.
And that's, of course, in addition to an external conflict.
So we have basically this transition of a character
that comes to a head in the climax
where both these external and internal conflicts
get resolved.
So that's just a sense of how we place our characters
at the center of our story structure.
Hi everybody, can you hear me, or do I need to get closer?
I'm always worried no one can hear me in the back.
I'm John.
So we have a very collaborative approach at Crystal Dynamics.
For us, it's really important that the entire team
is involved in the story, everyone across the team.
So everyone participates.
We recognize that good ideas can come from anywhere,
so we're always looking out for the good ideas.
because that might lead to something great in your game.
So you need to include your team.
Everybody is involved in story at Crystal.
So that's how we approach story.
Just a note also, we don't subscribe to this idea
of a genius in a box.
Like no one, we don't send a writer
or a story person off to the mountain
to chisel the tablets and come down
and deliver story to the team.
It's not that we don't have vision,
we just have a collaborative vision
in the way we approach story.
So that's important to us.
We also strive for relatable human heroes in a grounded world.
So this in particular was important with the 2013 reboot because one of our goals was to take Lara Croft,
who had become almost an icon more than a person,
and really start to peel back those layers and understand who she was as a character.
So we take that philosophy into each of our stories in saying,
what would it really be like to be thrust into this situation?
And we try to put that position of Lara being closer to you or I and going on that journey like her.
Similarly, we include a lot of maybe supernatural and over-the-top elements,
but we try to do that in a way that makes you believe that they could be real.
So in a lot of cases, that means a ramp of the supernatural.
And before we ever reveal that big reveal, we're going to try to get you there.
We're going to try to make you believe that this really could be possible
somewhere in the darkest corners of the world.
So...
Basically, taking those human heroes and thrusting them into this grounded experience for us
makes it more relatable.
So, feeding back into that idea of collaboration, we consider the world a character in our games.
When we approach building levels, when we approach sound and music and the stuff that you find in the environment and the artifice,
everything, we think about that as a deep character. It's layered, it has roots, and we want it to speak to the main narrative that we're trying to tell.
So everything we do in the game, in the game world,
is kind of supporting our main narrative.
So that's a big pillar for us.
We're always concentrating on making the world
tell the story.
Yeah, hi.
I'm Thor.
I'm the, probably the latest member of the narrative team.
And I was coming into Crystal at the busiest time
of the project when kind of pants on fire.
Everybody was just running around
trying to make things work.
And yeah, I guess you could say the raid was kind of,
at a challenged place.
And I came from a very different background from a sister studio in Copenhagen doing the
Hitman games.
And the way that Crystal did it was kind of different.
It was a very ambitious narrative team.
And I mean, up front and center was the cinematic story, like the one hour of...
of cinematics where every second counts, and around that was the whole kind of supporting
narrative of the, like John was talking about, the world as a character, like the layers
of history in the world, all the secondary characters, all the documents and everything,
this kind of rich tapestry of stories that all needed to be put in the right place at
the right time and fit in with the main narrative.
But the big front and center, having a main character like Lara, where literally everything that goes on in the story is revolving around her and her as a personality.
Every piece of story is an opportunity to build up her as a character and give her more depth.
So that was a really big challenge coming into and also seeing how the narrative team was structured in a way to kind of support a character like that.
We were very lucky to have Tor join us, our pants absolutely were on fire.
And he was a cold bucket of water to dip them in.
So we're going to talk a little bit about Tomb Raider 13.
Rihanna, would you like to talk about what we learned from 2013?
Hi, I'm Rihanna, I'm the lead writer on Rise and I was the lead writer on the previous game as well.
I have spent about five years with John and Noah and these guys being my polygamous work husbands.
And we always consider our story to be a work in progress.
And we try and do better with every iteration.
And believe me, there are a lot of iterations.
I think there's one scene that got 47 rewrites.
I am not even kidding.
And we listen to our players and our postmortems and our...
testing feedback for the first game,
and we decided to try and make some improvements
to the narrative moving on to Rise.
So I'm just gonna talk to you a little bit about those.
So the first one was,
Bring back the tombs?
Oh, yeah.
Oh, it is, yeah.
Couldn't see it.
So, bringing back the tombs, and that was one of the big feedbacks from the first game
that people wanted to see more tombs.
And one of the reasons we didn't have too many tombs in it was because she was on the
road to being a tomb raider.
She wasn't a tomb raider yet.
And so that meant that the raiding she did was more kind of accidental.
So...
This time it was more purposeful tomb raiding,
but it's actually more than just mechanics
and more than just level design.
It's about her character as well,
and the fact that she is,
she glimpsed something in the first game,
which really sort of propels her onwards
into the second game,
and makes it much more deliberate tomb raiding,
because she's after information,
she's after answers.
So we wanted the next chapter to really respect what had come before,
but at the same time we couldn't be too beholden to everything in the first story
because we didn't want to alienate players that maybe hadn't played the first game
or had completely forgotten what we did
because they'd skipped cut scenes and made writers cry everywhere.
So Rise was very much a continuation
of Lara's arc, which started in the first game.
So one of the other things we wanted to address
is that we had far too many characters, really,
in the first game.
And we really wanted to have fewer characters in this one,
so we could realize them better.
So we pared down our cast quite a lot.
And we have a very limited cinematic canvas.
We have about 60 minutes of cinematics in the game
and that's the same for the first one as well.
So that's not really a lot of space
when you consider it's like half a movie,
two thirds of a movie to kind of
showcase all your characters.
So we had fewer characters
and we tried to make them more meaningful
in the world and in Lara's story.
One of the big things we wanted to do was make the player's actions match the character's intentions
and balancing that level between player character and player is always really, really difficult in games.
So we wanted to up the player, Lara and player synchronicity in other words.
So we gave Lara more agency in her path and a laser focus.
So in the first game she's very reactive to things that are happening to her.
In Rise, she's proactive.
She's kind of out there.
She's going after the adventure.
She's making a choice.
And as part of that choice, yet again,
she has to kill to survive.
And we've always tried to embrace that style of gameplay
a little bit in her character.
This time around we have to kind of up the level of nastiness in the enemies.
They're up to no good, they're going to kill her.
She's very much in a mode, very focused on what she's doing,
and she's much more able to meet fire with fire than she was in the first game.
So, yeah, making the enemies more violent,
making her not killing innocents and giving her a bit of a moral compass
really helped with that sort of...
player synchronicity.
So using those learnings from 2013's Tomb Raider as well as our Crystal Dynamics story
pillars, I want to talk a little bit about our process and sort of eight basic steps.
Hopefully you'll see how those story pillars and those learnings that we attempted to bring
into Rise of the Tomb Raider really informed our decision making throughout the whole process.
So Noah, what is the very beginning of our process?
Yeah, it starts with some high concept discussion.
So we know we want to tell the next chapter in Lara's story.
One of the techniques we use to sort of build
that foundation for Lara, especially
her internal conflict and her journey as a character.
is this controlling idea.
So what that does is suggest that there's a key value
at stake and some action is going to change that value.
In particular, to give our example,
we made the statement, we become who we are meant to be
when we let go of who we are supposed to be.
So this is not only thematic, but it defines the actions that Lara takes, and ultimately the result of that is the forging of her identity.
So identity is what's at stake in this story, and Lara comes into it with this notion that she is a discoverer,
that she is going to find something great and bring it back to the world, and that is going to make the world a better place.
But over the course of the story, she has to confront what her actions will result in,
and ultimately through doing that will...
to redefine her relationship with these ancient secrets
that she's pursuing.
This is also a theme that runs through other facets
of the game.
So in a lot of ways, the story becomes
sort of a debate over this facet of the human condition,
that should you fulfill your destiny as you believed it was,
or should you let go of that and sort of jump and become
that new person?
And that's something that we see not only in Lara,
but our additional characters, the remnants.
who are defined as protectors of this secret.
And by the end of that,
they have to change their relationship,
and ultimately in doing so,
sort of move forward as a people.
So this is a theme that helps guide us through,
even as we go through many iterations,
which we'll talk about,
we sort of have this notion of what our story is,
is really about.
Yeah, and with that, we can start doing research on the plot.
And in our case, it's the myth.
What is Lara going after?
We know what kind of drives her.
We know the kind of debate she's going
to have in her character arc.
So we were looking at myths that had
you know, danger as well as benefit to humanity.
So that choice that she makes,
there's a bit of a gray area there.
It's kind of like the atom, you know,
that you can make an atom bomb
or you can create limitless energy.
This idea that, you know, what she's going after
will cause a debate for her.
And since she kind of encountered an immortality myth
in the first game,
like this kind of crazy soul-sucking Japanese queen,
We assumed that she's going to be interested in that idea of immortality.
So we started looking at immortality myths.
These are some of the ones we kind of discarded out of hand.
Not out of hand, we did some research.
But, you know, there was Noah's Ark and Fountain of Youth and Garden of Eden.
For various reasons, these didn't really work for us.
So we landed on two myths that we kind of mashed together.
The city, Velocity of Kitezh, which is sort of unknown in popular culture,
at least in the West.
We had this guy on the team from Russia who was like, oh,
my grandmother used to tell me this story.
So it's quite popular in the East, but it's basically this Atlantis of the East,
this city that sinks into a lake and disappears.
And it was a great setting for us because we could build tombs out of this.
It has connections to history.
And the other myth that was important for us was this myth of Koschei the Deathless,
who
was another obscure Russian myth, maybe not so obscure to some people, but this myth is
about a man who takes his soul, puts it in an object, and attains immortality.
And so that gave us a nice MacGuffin for Lara to go after, what is this object?
But also gave us another interesting character, and we actually didn't use Kostya, the actual
name, we just based our character Jacob on him.
This idea that Jacob has something to lose as well,
something that he has to debate in his arc.
So by the end, when he gives up his immortality,
he becomes who he's meant to be, which is dead.
And the immortality myths also gave us a nice lens to look at
Laura's relationship with her father.
Absolutely.
Yes.
Forgot about that note, but yes, so we, we basically mirrored that on her father
as well, because that's a primary motivator for Laura and she's, she's not
only trying to find this, this, this ancient secret and prove it to the world.
She's also kind of trying to live up to her father.
So.
So after we'd sort of established the high concept,
it was time to sort of move on to the treatment.
And our treatments are similar to what you might find
in a movie treatment.
They're sort of halfway between a traditional movie treatment
and something that's very game specific.
So the treatment was about nailing down the broad strokes,
Lara's arc, looking at all the characters.
We spent a lot of time focusing on the characters
and their wants and their needs,
which are often different things,
and how does the...
The gameplay and the story clash with those wants and needs and how they tie into everyone else.
And so we were sort of putting that together with the broad strokes, with the arc.
And that was largely myself and John and Noah and some special guests from Square and XHQ,
just really sitting in a room kind of hashing everything out.
and then kind of me just sitting and pulling everything together into a document,
which helped guide the first part of the production process.
And from that we could sort of start putting together a skeleton.
of the script, sorry.
And from those, I could do more of an outline.
And as I say, we looked at the characters first and foremost.
And because we had fewer characters to deal with,
we could make them count.
We could spend a lot of time focusing
on how their particular journeys intersected
and how they affected one another.
So, you know, I went back and I looked over all the documents that we had done at the time
because you produce so much and you iterate so much, it's very difficult to remember where you came from.
But a lot of our ideas that we were doing at this stage made it through to the end game in some form.
But one of the ones I missed in particular was when we blew up UCL's archaeology department.
which terrified and excited me in equal measure.
And that was in the script for a while,
but that was kind of one of the ones
I sort of missed a little bit, to be honest.
Okay, so once we have a treatment and we've got our bedrock of controlling idea, we go
into what we call our metascripting phase, and that's what we call it. I don't know if
we can coin that term, but we do a lot of exercises to start bringing the story to a
state where we can start making a game. And the first thing we do is we create a giant
Word document, which is sort of a description of every cinematic scene and...
all descriptions of gameplay in just one sort of written document from top to bottom.
And it's about 100 pages.
This is kind of the first place that narrative and gameplay kind of shake hands.
They have a stake in this.
I'm working with our narrative leads, or our game design leads,
and we basically put together a high-level skeleton of,
yeah, this is the story from beginning to end, how it interfaces with gameplay.
We can start looking at pacing, start looking at how much time we're talking about between scenes.
It's great to plan things out, but then you should also plan for it to change, because it's going to change.
And then, from the Metascript, we start creating beat documents, and these are...
they can be considered your standard level design documents, but for us what's important is
these are written experientially, so...
to help the team imagine and visualize the experience
so that they can be inspired to build and inspired to create.
So these aren't, they're kind of blueprints,
but they're also inspiration pieces for the team.
We give them to a large group of team responsible
for bringing the levels to life.
And we expect these to come back to us as leads
or as a narrative team with changes or ideas
because like I said, the entire team is involved
in the story and we want them to do that.
So this is a guide for them to be creative
and to be, to engage in the story.
And as you mentioned, this is the first time that the story and game player put side by side,
and they really are never decoupled after that.
We always look at them as a holistic experience in concert.
So another exercise for us is, we take all the major character arcs and plot threads
and break them down into their component parts and hashtag them.
and throw them up on a board.
We usually start with just a Post-it board,
and then it goes digital so the team
can access it on the network.
But this allows us to track everything
that's happening in the story.
And this is both a proactive and reactive exercise.
And when we do it initially, it's
liable to change along the process,
and we update it as we go through.
But it's a tool for us to start looking at.
tension, emotional pacing, log jams of ideas.
We might see a scene has 10 hashtags,
and we realize that's going to be a monster scene that
has to have a lot of this stuff.
And it's also a way to inform Rihanna, myself,
the people who are writing the scenes, what's happening.
As an example of how we use this to, I think, great effect.
For a while in our game, we were noticing on our board that the dad hashtag, which you saw in the last one,
the dad hashtag, because her dad is important to her, the arc of her mirroring her father is very much part of her motivation.
And for about two hours, two, three hours in the beginning of the game, it was just gone.
It wasn't anywhere. It wasn't in-game, it wasn't in any scenes.
She talked about him in that first scene, and then there was this gulf.
And people were... we were worried people were just going to lose that thread.
So we came up with this mechanic to bring in-game.
We called it our dictaphone mechanic.
The dictaphone is that thing there.
My dad had one. I don't know if you guys have any idea what this is, but it's a tape recorder.
Where you'd...
Raise your hand if you've used it.
No.
Anyways, she picks us up.
Lara's kind of a lutter.
You've maybe noticed she doesn't even have a phone.
We did that deliberately.
We don't give her a phone because that just opens a whole world of mechanics we don't
want to deal with, like Twitter.
We don't want her to tweet, ah, I found the tomb.
Maybe we'll do that, but I don't know.
So we kind of think of her as a Luddite.
She has this thing.
She's walking around the environment.
We hear dad talking from the past.
They're connected.
It's on the sticks.
It's in her inventory.
It's a mechanic.
So that uptick was great.
It was like, cool.
And we found that with our hashtag board.
We used that as like, oh, we need to put something here.
And it kind of got everyone thinking about,
like, what are the, you know,
instead of just having her say,
dad, in a cinematic, which she does,
we also have something in game.
And we actually probably used it too much.
At some point, the team was like,
she needs to shut up about dad.
Because it was like, dad, dad, dad, let's talk.
Yeah.
And then that leads us to the script.
So another purpose of the meta-script is to basically give me a road map going into the
first draft of the script.
So I write the script more or less like a movie script, so it's usually in chronological
order, which certainly isn't the case for all games, but it's always been for the Tomb
Raider ones.
So I get to see the pacing and the tone and the gameplay and how everything is folding
in together.
So that's when we really start getting the big beats down on paper, and it's really important
to give...
writer's time and space to do this because so many things are worked out on the page.
You can write all the explanations you like, but when you get into the scene and get your
hands dirty, then you start seeing what's working and what's not.
So another step in the process we did with Rise was get it tested out with our actors
early on.
So we had...
We took the version of the script that we had down to LA and did a table read with our actors down there.
And that was really useful for seeing how everything sounded, getting feedback from the actors,
doing some edits on the fly as well, and in some cases we actually...
we mic'd up the actors and used their VO
as kind of test VO in the game
because it sounded a lot better
than getting the other people at our studio to do it.
So it was really useful.
And of course, getting feedback from the actors themselves
because we used Camilla again for Lara
and obviously she was very, much more in tune
with the character this time around.
She definitely had a Lara mode.
She was really great at giving us feedback
on how she felt the character was developing.
And then as an added bonus, we can also record those table reads.
Jeff, we found, was pretty invaluable in this process.
Jeff, you want to talk a little bit about how we kept the team appraised of all of our
changes?
Absolutely.
Can everyone hear me?
I think I got too close last time.
During this phase, while the story is developing, the standard practice was usually to send
out some emails to the team.
kind of keeping them abreast of what was changing in the story so everyone knew that.
But at this time it was important for us to also get that thing, get a graphical representation
of what we were building so far up so that the team would just see it on a day-to-day basis.
And so we would create things like on the left we have a character board,
Lara being the center line and every branching character.
coming off of that line showing some form of relationship to her and their relationships to each other.
This was great to get the team talking about the characters that were the stars of this game.
And this would encourage a lot of feedback coming from the floor
and would allow us to be able to at any time have a conversation about how the story was progressing
and everyone was on the same page.
And we noticed when we put these up in high traffic areas,
we had people immediately coming over and asking us questions,
talking about the story and engaging with it.
Absolutely, and as a matter of fact,
Tor even mentioned it on his first day,
and you saw this board in the hallway.
Yeah, I was very excited coming into Crystal
for the first day, seeing this, and saying,
hey, these guys know what they're doing.
They have everything mapped out,
and then realizing that, yeah, it was there,
but it needed a lot of work to kind of fall into place.
It was actually fun to see this because you put these up on the floor and people are walking around.
Next thing you know, they're getting their coffee and they're hanging around and they're talking about,
hey, I didn't know that and I'm going to go over and talk to these guys and tell them what I think.
Yeah, I mean, it's always about the strategy for getting your team involved.
I hesitate to say that people don't like to read,
but when you've got chunks and chunks,
huge amounts of written text, there's
ways to get people involved that don't involve
handing them 100 pages of text.
Some people on your team will absolutely engage with that.
But figuring out ways to engage with your team
and getting people involved, go for those shortcuts.
Find an artist and get things into pretty pictures,
and you're good to go.
And the more people got involved,
the more they were actually giving us feedback
and giving us great ideas that we probably never
would have come up with.
Yeah, and one thing also is that, real quick,
if we go back, the graph on the right
was pretty imperative to help illustrate.
plot thread issues that people were having a hard time getting their head wrapped around.
So we found that if we would illustrate it and kind of break it down to its core pieces,
we could identify where things were working well and sometimes where things were kind
of getting mashed together.
So it helped feed back into the writing team, their ability to be able to kind of streamline
the story.
Absolutely.
Previously, John talked a little bit about the world as a character.
It's one of our major pillars.
Now, the main story obviously focuses on Lara.
But when we talk about the world as a character,
we often talk about something called supporting or secondary narrative.
This includes everything outside of Lara.
This is overheard enemy conversations.
This is collectible relics and documents.
This is the history and the layers in the game.
All of these support Lara's story, but they also flesh out the world and give us a variety of other lenses to look through.
We talk a lot about canvas for narrative, in the sense that everything in the game is a potential to tell some aspect of the story.
Even an animation cycle tells something important about how that character is acting.
SecondaryNative is a great place that we can sort of spread our wings and play in a little bit wider margin.
The main story obviously focuses on Lara, but when we talk about the world, we talk about first layers of history.
And this is something we do through a pretty exhaustive research process.
Once we had our initial myth of Katesh...
and we knew that we were focusing on Russian and Siberian history.
That allowed us to make what we call layers of history.
Now, the first layer, obviously, is Lara and the current story with Trinity,
but just beneath that, about 50 years prior,
we have a Soviet Cold War era layer,
and then beneath that we have the layer of the Remnant living off the land.
Prior to that, there's the layer of the Mongol invasion
and the Golden Age of Kutaish before that.
And then even beneath that there's a layer of ancient history.
Now that ancient history doesn't so much support the main narratives
if it gives Lara a chance to say and think smart things about archaeology,
which helps put another lens on her character.
Obviously the world is telling a story
and always we want to be aware of all the layers of history in every area.
From this amount of research we would create exhaustive documentation.
Sometimes we would create short stories from the point of view of certain characters
that would give a sense of a tone for that area of history that we wanted to explore.
On the right there you'll see a fairly detailed history of the birth of our immortal prophet, Jacob.
Starting with exactly where he was born and what he did as a child.
Now none of this stuff actually made it into the game, but it...
It created a very solid bedrock of real research
that we could connect his life to,
gave us things to hook onto.
We talk a lot about plausible Googleability
when we talk about using history, which
is that we want to include things that people can latch
onto, go right to the internet, and look up,
and at least there's a sense of veracity
that we have connected a real world thing
and then adapted it for a video game.
And the funny thing is, when we were working on the project,
we would try to Google certain things,
and we couldn't get an answer.
So we'd walk over to Cam, and we'd ask him,
and he would pretty much have the answer almost every time.
So after a while, we're like, why Google it?
Just Cam it.
Yeah, unfortunately, Jeff, I was just smiling and Googling
it under the desk.
He types faster, and he could do it without looking.
I'm just like.
So obviously you may not be working on a project that is a historical fiction grounded archaeology
adventure, but it is important that you have a sense of internal consistency and logic
to your world.
And I think research is the place where we create that solid bedrock that we can all
go back to and make sure we're on solid ground.
Bringing these connections into context, this is an interesting story, is during the creation
of the game we knew that we wanted to have an enemy near the end of the game that we
had called internally the Deathless Ones, that were an immortal army that could not
be killed.
Now in my research I discovered that right around the time that we have our immortal
prophet leaving the city of Constantinople, there is also an elite imperial guard called
the Afanatoi.
that vanished from the historical record with the death of one emperor and the ascendancy
of the emperor Basil I. Interestingly, the word athanatoi in Greek literally means without
death. So once I realized that we had a missing army with the exact same name as our army
that we were going to put in the game, it was obviously a no-brainer to combine those
two things. It gave us a historical record that we could base those characters on. The
real historical athanatoi were the sons of noble houses, so they were resplendent in
very non-functional golden armor.
So we use that as a part of an aesthetic guide
in the creation of those characters.
Grounding that foundation in plausible Googleability,
being able to leave the game and look that up in the real world
was something we always strove towards.
And now secondary narrative, I don't want to say that it just
explores the margins of the world.
We also can use secondary narrative
to really clearly focus back on Lara and where she is.
So we wanted to find a place where
there was sort of low engagement gameplay
that we could deliver a lot more of Lara's internal voice.
Marina, do you want to talk a little bit
about the campsite diaries and how we use those?
Yeah, I mean this is something that we carried over from the first game.
Lara can kind of sit down at a campsite and it would be a quieter, more thoughtful moment
where she'd just be digesting kind of what's going on and how she feels about it and what's coming up.
And they proved pretty popular in the first game so we carried those over.
and they were a really great way of getting into Lara's head.
So I did a lot of the in-Lara's-head-based stuff.
So these were campsite diaries, there was therapy sessions,
and there was also Lara's father's diaries.
So I did the, they were split into two,
so our additional writer, Philip Gillette,
he did the father's work diaries,
and I did the kind of more personal diaries
to Lara when she was a kid.
And those were.
really quite fruitful for me as a writer because initially I was a little bit
concerned about the father plotline and I didn't warm to it.
I've been open about this, I didn't warm to it initially.
But sometimes you have to work through things and find peace with it
and I did that by pulling on real-world influences in my relationship with my own father.
and I even channeled that literally into one of the diaries.
My father passed away from Alzheimer's last year
and in one of the interviews he talked about
the memory he didn't want to lose and that was that the day
or the night that I was born and so I took that memory and I sort of merged it
with Lara's father's memories of her when she was born and even though that is
totally Mary suing
it really helped me to kind of
find some peace with the narrative
and get inside Lara's head and her father's head
and just, it all started working for me
when I discovered that.
And I just wanted to mention one thing about it.
From a gameplay perspective, what's happening in campsites
is the player is upgrading equipment and doing,
when we say low impact or low engagement gameplay,
it's not combat.
It's not, you're not completely, your attention
isn't completely on the screen.
So you can split it a little bit.
And this is a good place where we can deliver narrative
content as well as gameplay.
We know the player is doing something.
They're going to be engaged.
So it's kind of a nice way to hit both narrative and gameplay
at the same time.
Yeah, identifying that space as a really good canvas
early on for narrative was a really good thing.
The important thing about supporting narrative
is that everything in your game that is not your main story
should be supporting and can be supporting your narrative.
Your combat VO, overheard conversations
between enemies or NPCs, even the placement of objects
in the environment are telling a story for a player who's
engaged and looking for those connections.
All right, Jeff.
So at this point.
We've got all this great narrative content
that's been built. We've got scenes that we can start
working on. And the rubber hits the road.
And it's time to get this in front of players.
And so translating words to images
becomes a very important part of the process.
Now, we use these for multiple purposes.
We would use them, obviously, for performance shoots
at digital domain.
But we would also use them on the floor
for gameplay scenarios.
But specific to narrative, cinematics
is where a bulk of my work went into.
What we found is that the expressive nature of a drawing for users was a lot more efficient
for conveying what our intent was for the final cinematic than just proxy models that were posed.
You can give a hint of atmosphere, you can give a hint of the anguish that a player is going through,
and you don't have to task the character team with a lot of work to create temporary rigs
that are just going to be thrown away for the final.
And so by putting a scene like this one here, which is rock bottom, which was originally meant to be the opening cinematic for the game,
we were able to quickly run through scenarios based on the scene directives.
Here, originally, Lara was meant to be on a tube.
She's meant to be on a train.
and having a very traumatic dream when all of a sudden she's awakened and
she's all of a sudden surrounded by all these people that are looking at her
like she's not quite all there. And this was
satisfying one of the hashtags that the narrative team had established which is
to basically establish a... the rock bottom portion of
Lara's arc so far. You know, she's been through a lot in the last game, she's been...
going around the world trying to find answers, and now she's come back to London and she's
trying to get back into a normal life and she's having a hard time fitting in.
So we ran through several iterations of this on paper, and at some point we were like,
okay, we've changed things around, we're ready to get this into an animated form,
and that's when...
the table reads came in really handy,
as well as some of our internal talent
to help kind of make that a reality.
And I'll kick it back over to Cam for that.
Yeah.
Just as Jeff mentioned, that an expressive drawing
is a lot better at communicating an emotionality of a scene
than a posed model.
What we discovered really rapidly
was that when we recorded temp VO for these scenes
and for in-game, is that if we were just
recording somebody reading the words verbatim
off the piece of paper, a lot of the focus
was on a performance that we knew was not good.
And that didn't allow us to focus on the words and the context in the game.
So we were incredibly fortunate at Crystal Dynamics to have more than two, but two very
incredibly talented actors who also had real jobs in the studio as well, and who were always
willing to come in and do rapid iterations of VO with sort of intense direction.
I think is Megan here?
We have one of our stars here.
Yeah.
There she is.
Megan.
No, come on.
You have an excellent voice for radio.
She's available for casting immediately.
Life saver.
Thank you.
So, yeah, I mean, I just wanted to clarify, I mean, like, the important thing is to get as close to as final as possible on screen for your players to react to, and that includes emotionality.
So, you know, we were pushing these guys to try to be pretty emotional in their VO, and, you know, we would go through cycles where we would just do it fast with...
straight reads and it just wasn't working.
So it's worth the extra effort.
I guarantee you if you can get it to a state
where it's almost representative of what you're trying for,
then that's going to save you a lot of time on the back end.
Yeah, we even had processes of auditioning people
internally in the studio to make sure that we had the best.
We didn't tell them they were auditions.
We just didn't use the bad takes.
But it was very important having rapid iteration of really high
quality VO, especially with the folks that wrote the dialogue
being there, we were able to give the exact context.
Now, the scene we're going to show you, ironically enough,
has no dialogue in it.
So great segue, and we're not really paying off.
I apologize for that.
But rock bottom is such a great scene
to talk about because I think this was one of our most
heavily iterated on scenes.
47 times.
And so it's just such a great case study for not only
the process, but also the endurance of the team
and the team as a whole at the studio.
So we finally ended up taking Lara off the tube stop and we condensed that story to take place
between the tube stop and her apartment. And it was very important here to basically put the player
in the driver's seat with Lara and really make them feel like they were seeing creepy crawlies
coming out of the shadows on this street.
You can see how high quality these animatics that Jeff was able to put together very quickly
are at establishing a tone, a sense of motion, and the aesthetics.
Yeah, I mean our audio guys knocked it out too.
They would go in and they would score this with music and with great sound effects.
And these were intended for the team but also to go in front of users.
We did this intentionally.
We'll get into that point soon.
But the whole point of this is so that we can start testing our story.
And testing narrative is very difficult.
But when you actually have visuals, it's a lot easier.
And absolutely.
The testing stuff is so important,
because for a long time, we stayed with this version.
And we thought this is what was going to happen.
And after several play tests, we started
to realize that a shuffling of the intro was important.
So when you play the game, you'll
notice that we start directly into the action on a mountain.
And then we come to this about, I think, about 20 minutes in.
Yeah, I mean, we basically had a six minute block
of cinematics at the front end of the game.
And anybody who's worked on a game here
knows that's just a complete nonstarter.
You know, people are going to pick up your controller.
They want to play your game.
So we wanted to get people on the sticks as soon as possible.
And just even in the middle of the game,
six minutes is kind of a nonstarter.
So we needed to cut it down.
And we just started condensing.
Let's take moments from scenes and condense them.
So in this scene here, we took that moment
and condensed it into another scene to get the same effect.
So we basically moved everything off the street and moved it into Lara's apartment,
and we were able to satisfy some other hashtags that you didn't see in the original animatic,
but that took place in the apartment.
We were able to put it into one setting and just get the player right into the action in the meat of the matter.
By tracking those themes and hashtags and concepts and metadata,
we knew it was important about those scenes.
So it was, we had the documentation for knowing what we needed to say in this scene,
even as we drastically rewrote and restaged it.
Absolutely. And one thing I didn't mention earlier too is before we even start drawing anything,
I mean, we're, I mean, I'm going and I'm talking to these, these guys on a daily basis. And before
I even will make a drawing, sometimes I'm offering feedback because I'm seeing in my head how things
might play out. So we're distilling and we're, we're honing. And eventually we land up with
something that we feel is the intent of what the scene needs to express.
And just to add to that, I used the original rock bottom scene in the comics as well.
So all the thinking about it did not go wasted, because I kind of used it in there and folded
in some of the characters in the game to it.
So even stuff that falls by the wayside, you can find other uses for.
That makes my comic book fan heart happy.
Yeah, so talking a bit about iterations and feedback loops,
we were in a game like this, story
is very important in channeling the player
through the game itself.
And standing up to story is a very central part of that.
So Jeff was doing a lot of that work.
But it was very iterative.
It was changing weekly or even daily.
And we were very lucky to have a.
a very strong focus on testing this with real users,
so having, and having a commitment from the team
to always have the story stood up
so we could show it on a weekly basis for real users
and getting results back from that.
And as Jeff was speaking to, I mean, it's...
One of the most central parts, of course,
is to deliver on the emotionality of the story,
that people can relate to the characters,
they understand their journey,
they're interested, invested in them,
which is super hard to get across in an animatic state
with two or three different temp video actors
that are hacked together in the scene
to just get the scene across.
So we're asking a lot from the users
who are actually giving proper feedback.
But on the flip side of that, just the pure functionality of the story, understanding what's going on from one scene to the next and tracking these hashtags that John was talking about is the most useful we got out of a user test for a long time.
It's like seeing the different threads going through and the...
One of the things people had a problem with was tracking what we had a hashtag called
the hashtag robot army, which literally was the kind of the code word for the kind of
enemy, the trinity, our enemy through the game, the villains, and what was their project.
And having it as a mystery story,
it was kind of, we tried to kind of raise the stakes
and just giving the player little by little information
throughout the project, throughout the game,
so they wouldn't get,
you can, the stakes wouldn't be raised too high too quickly,
but we would lose track of it
and people wouldn't really get it.
And we'll have to kind of shuffle scenes around
to try to, or invent new scenes or new little beats
that would support the arcs of these different stories.
Robot Army was internally facing, obviously.
Yeah, I mean, we lifted right out of Terminator.
And we often would have these meetings
where we were incredibly jealous of franchises that
had things like Robot Armies, because everyone
gets a Robot Army.
It's going to kill everybody.
That's a pretty high stake.
And we had a very.
nuanced, complicated villain who, you know, essentially they were going to make an immoral
robot army and kill everybody eventually, but, you know, we were trying to track that
in a way that didn't just drop that on people's laps in the first five minutes.
So yeah, robot army, robot army.
And then it's worth noting that we're fond of those internal conflicts and the internal stakes,
but one of the things that happens is the story starts not working at some point if the external stakes aren't there.
And that's for us, for an action-adventure genre where you are, for example, killing people,
that if you're just conflicted internally and you're dealing with that by...
by killing fools, then it's less relatable than trying to understand that these people
are actually going to do very bad things if you don't stop them.
So there becomes some amount of pressure to layer in those external stakes in addition
to those internal stakes early enough to drive the motivation of the players beyond just
the characterization itself.
Jumping into, yes, this process is just as chaotic as it looks.
We should probably start by saying if your story is anything like ours,
it will be very broken until it's not.
And I would emphasize the play testing part of this
and the things that Jeff was able to do,
putting the words to pictures and getting performances
that were what we would say is above the bar.
Because the problem is if you have an extremely
bad performance or no moving pictures,
oftentimes...
what players are seeing isn't actually landing with them. So
what you need to do in this, in these previous steps is get the
story to a point where people, where you can trust the
feedback. Cause what you'll find is you'll get a playtest
feedback and it's like kids don't understand this at all.
And you'll go, oh, well, that's just because it's not a final cinematic.
Well, it's going to be really expensive to change once it is a final cinematic.
So you have to find that cheaper representation of story so you can start
testing it sooner and you can trust the results.
And then we started to go, oh, you know what?
actually we really do have a problem.
We need more presence of the father
or a greater presence of the external threat.
So this is then how we start finding canvases
to speak to these things.
So now you're really in a loop where,
and an important part of this is having someone like John.
So our narrative lead becomes the writer room.
He runs that sort of center there.
And what that allows us to do is he can take feedback
from myself, from a creative direction level.
He can work with Cam.
in the secondary narrative stuff, working with Rihanna,
who's external, so he becomes a bridge for her
into the project and vice versa,
our additional consultants, so having someone like John
at the center of it, who's basically able to run
this crazy process, get that feedback in,
stand up a new version of the scene.
Jeff's gonna sadly draw it again for the 47th time as well.
Megan's gonna read it again for the 47th time.
And eventually you start getting the results
you want from the story.
Ow, my hand.
Just hurts thinking about it.
Yeah, which leads to the actual performances.
And like Noah was saying, this is
where it gets really expensive and really tough
to change things.
So having that very agile process up to the point
where we go to the set and shoot it,
and even
Like, we try to be prepared, we try to say,
okay, we have to be two days early,
because of everybody's schedules and stuff,
to deliver all the scripts, to deliver the boards,
so we have them on set so the actors can be prepared.
But there were times we would come to the set
with new boards from Jeff that he'd been drawing all night,
stick them on the walls, okay, sorry, we change it again,
and the actors would be...
cool with it it would take a little more time to rehearse it on stage but we were very very
fortunate to have Camilla Luddington as our our star that was very well calibrated from the previous
game and like Rihanna was saying she was part of the table read she was
She was part of, how to say, putting the words to Lara,
how she would react in the different situations.
And the other actors on set would kind of key off her.
She would be kind of a linchpin for the performance
in the big moments of the story.
But we did have
reshoots of some of the scenes we had to go back.
When we came back we found out it didn't work out
in the user tests and so we would continuously
kind of making this kind of puzzle of what are we reshooting?
What are we kind of picking up in different ways
through VO or through the performances?
And sometimes having to even recast actors
because it didn't work.
We're trying to make a very, as I said, relatable world with kind of grounded characters and
sometimes with the VO sessions it would be hard to find actors that would be kind of
differently calibrated for different kinds of games to get that voice that was more kind
of in sync with the rest of the direction of the game.
So sometimes we would bring people back and say, okay, all that kind of bad guy voice,
just please get rid of it and just do your own voice and it would be actually a lot better.
Tor was critical in that he was able to be in most of the VO sessions,
and since he had such a strong understanding of the story,
was able to provide all that context for the actors, which is key,
because you can have a very well-written line and a very good actor.
And if they deliver it in the wrong context or in the wrong tone,
the scene completely falls flat.
So we were very lucky to have Tor in that position.
Now we try to obviously minimize those recasting and reshoots
by following this process and rigorously iterating.
But those things are going to happen,
and it was important that we embrace them and were agile
and willing to make those changes when we needed to.
Yeah, I mean, if you do your job right and you get to the end of this, then those, those reshoots are minimal.
And obviously not everyone's working on these giant projects, but, you know, I still think that the benefit of having, you know, a firm idea of your story before you start doing whatever version of the final assets is going to help you.
Yeah.
And speaking about finaling, uh, we had a, we were lucky enough to have an extremely talented cinematics team that was located in Montreal, uh, led by Dave Hubert, who, uh, helped.
bring all of this together in the package that you actually see when you play the game.
And Tor was talking about recasting, and sometimes we would have to make changes even after reshoots
were done.
And at that time, we had the animators up there, and they were very diligent and very
passionate about making sure that every detail on Lara's face and her actions was communicated
correctly.
And so...
As much as we have all this great motion capture technology and performance capture technology,
there's still an animator that's sitting there and is hand keying certain things in order to
bring it all together. And so we were just extremely fortunate to be working with them
up there and I just want to give a big shout out to them.
All right, so we've talked about our core story pillars
of Crystal Dynamics, the learnings we took from 2013's
Tomb Raider reboot, and a little bit about our process.
So here's our key takeaways we'd like
you to take from this talk.
The very important thing is that your process is key.
Create and embrace that process, whatever the project.
Obviously, your process isn't going to look exactly like
ours, but adapt or create one from the ground up, and stick
to it, and you're going to be able to make yourself a
roadmap to get there in the end.
Cultivate feedback from every area of the team.
Don't hold anything too precious.
Everybody's feedback is important.
And you need to be able to defend your ideas.
If you can't defend them, then they're not
worth keeping on the page.
You can't have a thin skin.
You've got to let everybody speak their mind bluntly,
however they're going to speak it, and take that to heart.
And then finally, be inclusive.
The entire team has a stake in the story.
Everything in the game tells a story.
I said that we are the team responsible
for the ultimate presentation of the narrative
in Rise of the Tomb Raider.
In reality, the entire team is the narrative team.
We are all telling the story of Lara and the world at the same time.
So thank you guys very much for coming.
I think we have a few moments for questions and then we'll be able to be in the wrap-up
area afterwards.
We have five minutes.
Does anybody want to step up and ask a question?
There we go, right to the mic.
Hi, so I'm a one-person team for a small game I'm working on, and I want to know what you would suggest for the feedback, the inclusive part, because if I'm a one-person team, I don't really have a lot of people to ask for feedback, so I'm just curious on what you would recommend for that.
Absolutely.
Well, I think my recommendation would
be to seek feedback from people that you know and you trust,
and people who are going to be honest to you.
If at all possible, get it in front of people
who aren't gamers, who are going to bring a different viewpoint
to it.
I think some of the most interesting story advice I got
was from environment artists, who
were telling me about the placement of objects
that I didn't even think about.
So being able to find somebody who maybe
has a unique viewpoint, you really
have to seek that out if you're on a team of one, absolutely.
Anybody else?
You like that answer, huh?
Yeah, good answer.
All right, terrific.
I would also recommend just making
sure to track your feedback.
Don't just have a casual conversation
and then just kind of retain it by asking the document where
they can, keep an Excel sheet or whatever tools
you use to track it.
But always go back and evaluate and make
sure that you're marking those things off the list
as you're developing.
Yeah, absolutely.
And even if you don't agree with the feedback,
you should understand it and put it down and internalize it.
Thank you.
Of course.
Hey.
Hi there.
So you talked about receiving feedback from the whole team.
I was wondering at what points in the process
you got feedback because sometimes early on,
small teams are good, and how you bring people in.
John, you want to take that?
Well, I try to seek feedback at every step,
even in that early phase.
I would tend to have meetings every week
where anybody on the team could come
and I would do an overview of the story.
And I'm all about taking the feedback and assessing it.
But I don't feel like excluding is something that
is ever going to be helpful.
I can separate the ideas that I'm getting from people, that we're getting from people,
and still hold on to our vision, and still have that small team. I mean, I understand what you're
saying, but I do think even, you know, you want the whole team to be with you, and you're going
to have a team, no matter how small your team is at the beginning, they're, you know, they're going
to be with you to the end, and you want them to carry the vision with you, and always be able,
you know, you want people on your team.
You want them challenging you, but you don't want them off the same page.
You all want to be kind of carrying the vision together, so I think it's important at every step.
And it blossoms when you get it in the game.
So we talk about standing it up for user test.
It's actually also, there's the small group who will give you
feedback on the page.
But as soon as it's on the screen, and even before we
would do moving pictures, sometimes we just put slates
up there so that people understood the story beat that
was going to be there.
And all of a sudden, everyone is now playing their game with
the story in it and having all kinds of ideas of how it could
be better or what they're not understanding yet.
So just dropping it in is an explosion of feedback.
And I would say it's definitely not a comfortable feeling.
I mean, it was insanely frustrating as a writer
and as a story person to get that constantly.
Like, you feel like you're under attack,
but you just kind of have to let it all come in.
And you know it's broken at that point.
This is early enough that it is not your perfect version.
And you have to stand there and hear about how
you know it's broken.
But occasionally, you'll hear about how
you don't know it's broken yet also.
And those are the precious ones.
It does make you really robust for writing for any other entertainment medium.
You are just writing in a headwind of feedback all the time.
Over & over again.
But yeah, it is really good for kind of thickening your skin.
And it became very important to us to open the process earlier.
And that was something that we took from Rise
so we could identify problems earlier in the process
and smooth things out.
Because we didn't always do that with the first game.
And that was something that we definitely carried through.
Open it up early.
Their problems will be there.
Those problems will be there.
So let's get to them early and sort them out early.
And I think that really helped.
OK, I think we're going to be available for more questions
in the wrap-up area after this.
But everybody, thank you so much for coming.
I'm supposed to remind you to fill out
an evaluation of some sort.
So please do that.
And thank you again.