so
So little primer, I was given half hour initially to do this talk and now I have a full hour.
So we're gonna just go through this and then we'll have a lot of time for Q and A after.
So hopefully we can just kind of glide through this and have some interesting discussions on what we're talking about today.
So what are we talking about today?
I'm gonna guide you through a framework I've been really enjoying thinking about design with, which is treating the player as a performer.
So what does this mean?
When we talk about performers, this is a pretty wide range of skills and styles and behaviors.
But the unifying thing is that it is something that requires rehearsal.
It requires understanding.
It requires communication.
And most importantly, I think this lens brings us an approach that treats the player as fundamentally adding something to our design.
we
fundamentally
generated something special.
But before we go too far into that, who the heck am I?
My name is Evan Hill.
I've had about 10 years experience in the game industry as a designer.
Currently, I'm at Obsidian working on Outer Worlds 2.
And before that, I was at Naughty Dog making The Last of Us Part 2.
I've also worked on a few other titles like Torment Tides of Numenera, Solar Ash, Palea, and I've even done a couple talks here before on some of my work on the museum of Last of Us 2 and how we used improv to make a bunch of the weird moments.
So, how do we understand gameplay as performance?
The best way I've been able to sum it up is no matter what type of game you're making, be it a rhythm game, a fighting game, or
cinematic third person action game, you've cast the player as the lead actor, and they haven't read the script.
This takes us to the first layer, where I think a lot of level design focuses its understanding, which is this demonstration and communication of what and where.
Where does the player stand?
What are they trying to do?
We construct space, craft lighting, and otherwise sculpt the experience to guide the player through the stage,
you know, as if we're just gesturing off to stage left, trying to get them to stand where we want them to stand and do what we want them to do.
And this is excellent and helpful and essential to all good level design.
But the thing I want to talk about today is a layer beyond that.
Not just the layer of telling the player where to go, what to do, but giving them space to discover how to feel while they're doing it.
as well.
in theater and film.
She's basically known as the director whisperer.
She comes in and essentially teaches people who manage actors, performers, and the whole range of a production to be better at collaboration, to provide more consistent, positive relationships between all the collaborators on a project.
And I think some of her ideas are massively applicable to our relationship with our players.
Also, thanks to the work of renowned dog haver and game liker, Tim Rogers, who I think in a lot of his videos has summed this up very elegantly.
He talks at length about playing games multiple times just to, on the second or third time, get it right.
To do Cloud Strife justice by performing him the best way possible.
And this goes beyond just
beating the boss as quickly as possible, but literally walking around the right way, noticing the right things, being there for Eris or Tifa, depending on the situation, just with his controller and minor interactions.
So again, you've cast the player as lead actor.
They haven't read the script.
It's our job to be an effective director to the player.
But how do we actually do this?
So the first thing we need to consider is the dramatic persona.
What is the player to this production?
What are they trying to do?
Who are they?
A lot of games, it's a pretty clear and simple answer.
And the result is the often you feel like X. We've all seen it.
We've all played it.
We all like it.
But what are the things that take us there?
What takes us to what I call a critical moment where it goes from, oh, I'm role-playing as Batman to I am Batman.
and elevates a performance, even on stage, from just a recitation or a rote rehearsal of a set of gestures into a transformative performance.
That's the whole goal of this talk.
How do we build towards these critical moments?
It doesn't matter what we really call it, whether it's a flow, climax, alignment, or vicarity.
We all know what I'm talking about here.
We've all kind of experienced it.
It's that moment where you feel like you have lived a powerful fictional moment as a character.
And it doesn't matter that there was a controller involved.
It's that gliding on stage, nailing a performance type feeling.
It's when you are playing Batman or Spider-Man where you were just in it, when you're kicking ass or saving the day.
And again, we're gonna be using Judith Weston to help get us there.
Her core philosophy is one of connection and vulnerability, and letting go of control.
One of the number one things that I think as designers we can relate to is something that directors also feel, is this idea of dictating or micromanaging the experience or just the moment-to-moment delivery of what we've crafted.
And I think if you read anything from her book, one of the best takeaways is just letting go of that.
kind of synthesize that into like a six step process.
The first is pretty much the easiest.
It's going to be communication.
That's the clarity and the type of what and where we've talked about earlier.
The next, though, is this idea of cultivation, not only just providing the player with space to navigate, but space to rehearse, space to express and experiment and kind of
do the dry run of, say, the boss fight, do the dry run of that big, intense story moment so that when they finally get there, they feel prepared, they feel aligned.
And then we take that alignment and we push on it and push on it and push on it with pressure that takes the player from just doing rote rehearsals to actively being the thing, doing the thing without having to consider or plan
They're just in it.
And that all comes together through our composition to create that critical moment.
Let's get started.
What do we mean by communication?
For me, the best way we can describe it is facts and motivation.
Facts are just the stuff on the ground.
What is happening?
What are the obstacles?
But motivation is the much more difficult element of that, which is how do I actually convince the player that they should do the thing that I built the level for?
like to want to save the day, to want to get to the end, to want to mess with the gardener.
And I think the first step to that is clarity.
Again, going back to like this essential core of most level design.
This clarity is the fundamental.
If you do not have this, you're going to be lost.
Players will not be able to navigate.
They will not be able to advance the story, advance the game.
It's critical, essential.
But beyond that, I think we need to focus on the clarity about the facts of the world.
What are the stakes, the characters, the obstacles?
And how we convey that is vital.
So a good example of this to me is Pathologic 2.
It's excellent at directing the player on where to go, but it's even better at directing them on how to feel.
And instead of saying, you should feel desperate and afraid, alone, isolated, constantly on the brink of death,
doesn't need to say that to you.
Instead it communicates something very simple.
As emphatically as humanly possible.
And then the next step is not only just communicating what's going on in the world, but what are the limits of the world?
Where are the boundaries?
We all hate it when we deal with invisible walls, but there's more to invisible walls than geometry.
There are the gaps in expression, the things that we can't do because we didn't have the scope or the mechanics don't allow for it.
And that's
of the game.
Cultivate this sense of communication between us and the player where even if in Legend of Zelda I can't say destroy buildings.
It doesn't matter because I understand that it's not about destruction.
It's not about Cultivating or building a settlement like in Minecraft.
It's about exploration and the game conveys this it establishes the facts of this world and then Critically it lets the player find their motivation it doesn't grab you by the wrist and say explore and
It doesn't tell you, oh man, puzzles are great.
You should do them.
It just puts them in front of you and leaves you alone.
And then maybe kind of glances backwards as you mess with your Sheikah slate and start moving magnets around and just kind of nods happily to itself because it's done well.
And I think a really good example of this is Goose Game.
There is nothing intrinsically in this game that is telling you to be a chaos gremlin.
And yet we all really, really just gravitate towards it.
Really the only piece of guidance and signposting this game provides is just the psychotic notebook of this goose.
We could ignore it.
But instead of telling us to, the game just leaves it there.
Just as an option.
And then knows that the player, being a human being who likes fun, will take them up on it.
So there's no need to try and force or tell the player how to feel.
It's all about cultivation.
So when we've established these facts, when we've let go of this idea of demanding the player to feel a certain way and let them feel it themselves, we have that first bit of the engine, about this momentum.
They're not only engaged, but they're actively adding to our design.
So the next step is channeling that motivation
into the character's dramatic persona.
There is a process of rehearsal.
There are multiple steps to rehearsal.
There's isolating certain elements, certain deliveries, character perspectives, rhythm between actors.
All of these things are this long list of checks, like, honestly, like a technical check on an airplane often, that all are required to produce the intended outlook.
And games really aren't that different.
What is core combat except a rehearsal for a boss fight?
What is a low-stakes entry area other than an invitation to experiment and evolve how you view your toolkit and your character?
When you're playing Metal Gear Solid, it's not a matter of, oh, what would Snake do in this situation?
It's the player deciding who Snake is.
Is he the type to constantly fuck with people, leave dirty magazines around, and then shoot people in the back of the head, or sneak in without anybody knowing?
and core combat
how disagreeable does he come off?
Or is he much more of a quiet threatening presence?
Like you only just need to look at how many different variations of Shakespeare characters there are to understand the depth and the breadth that this perspective can lend us.
And you see it a lot in games too, like really what is a skill tree and a perk tree, but providing the player with ways to validate their choices for the dramatic persona in the context of our systems.
what is crafting, if not preparing and customizing for what's to come.
Like there's this pre-engagement, this idea of like, oh, we're gonna have a fight scene later apparently, I'm gonna have 18 explosive arrows and it's gonna get messy.
And it all leads to this idea of playable choices.
And this is actually Judith Weston's terminology, not something I'm synthesizing for games.
It's the idea that you are presenting your actor or your player with
this open space, a blank page to help render out what they feel is valid for this character.
This does not necessarily mean dialogue choices or any kind of branching narrative at all.
This is the thing that I was talking about earlier, the expressions, the gestures, the rhythm of how a person's delivery goes because fundamentally most theater is linear.
Most theater is not some kind of branching dialogue and yet
People love acting.
People like all the variations of the performance.
And I think games can better utilize this framework for interactivity.
Great example of this is seen all over Naughty Dog.
Take, for example, Last of Us 2.
We just have this seemingly small throwaway moment with Bear.
He brings you a ball.
You're able to interact with him.
And there is nothing stopping you from playing with him for 20 solid minutes.
There's nothing stopping you from ignoring him entirely.
There's nothing stopping you from taking the ball and throwing it over the fence and listening to him whine.
And all of these things help you, as a player, define to yourself who Abby is.
It's not to say, like, oh, Abby's evil or all these other things.
Like, this is right after you get control over her.
Like, there's a strong argument that all of those options are valid for Abby.
Like, she's having such a bad day or she doesn't want this dog to have a good day, throw.
She needs to pick me up.
She's going to play with him for 20 solid minutes while everybody else around her is waiting for her to get the mission started.
Or just ignoring the little guy because she's a little too busy.
But notice, the player is the one designing that.
That is not the narrative team.
That is not the level design team.
They simply provided the stage for them to act this out.
So we've channeled the player's motivation.
We've given them tools to express themselves.
What's the next step?
It'd be one thing to just let the player go off in any direction and kind of scribble all over the screenplay and make edits and additions wherever they want.
But fundamentally, we're still putting on a show.
We're still putting on a game.
We're still trying to build on our vision.
So the next step is one of alignment.
Alignment is when the player's dramatic persona adds to the designer's vision.
And I think this is a really
Really important way to look at it.
A lot of us, even myself included, early on in my career, it was much more about, oh, how do I get the player to do what I want?
How do I get the player to just do the thing so that they feel the way I want them to feel and do the things that I want them to do because they're my, you know, little dollhouse toy and I am the master of this world versus, holy crap, they did what?
I never even, that to me is way more interesting and way more vital and way more,
a lot.
live streamers are as big as they are, even for linear games, for any type of thing.
There's this performance quality just intrinsic to any genre, any style that is compelling in and of itself.
Even if you don't have an audience, even if you're just playing by yourself at home, I think all of us can relate to Tim Rogers' expression that wanting to play a game the right way, to be the character the right way
authentic to them, authentic to the story.
And this goes way further than just your standard, you know, premium narrative games.
I think the best example is Doom.
The original Doom did not need a story and yet many people came away from it with this deranged vibe.
and it just fed back into itself into the modern era where it just owns it and provides every tool in the kit to make sure that you like to rip and tear.
And the way it does that is with good feedback.
Different games have different styles of feedback, too.
Some games can be pretty harsh, intense even, where there's this almost clawing quality to it where it's just going to grab you by the heartstrings and rattle you.
Some games are kind of like Hitchcock.
Toby Fox, I'm looking at you.
I don't know if I still forgive him for making me cry that much and the way that he did it.
Pathologic is also a very good example of this.
But other games can be more like Naoko Yamada or Jodorowsky, where they're much more hands-off.
They're much more about letting the player just write their own story, just giving a concise sandbox to build the mood and the character that they want.
Legend of Zelda is perfect for that.
Think about the choice that you can either beeline to Ganon's castle or spend 600 hours collecting every single Korok Seed while Zelda just waits in the dungeon.
What is good feedback?
Like, it's very hands-off, it doesn't punish you in any way for not doing all the gremlin stuff, but the positive feedback, the immediate joy of watching somebody scramble around dealing with your shenanigans is just so enticing that you eventually just opt in to this mental framework that the game asks you to.
The Last of Us, also an excellent example of this.
Again, not this deeply punishing sense where if you do something wrong, we're just gonna
blow an air horn in your face and say, do it again.
We let you rehearse and linger and meander about, get to know the characters, approach combat in the best way that you think.
Same with Resident Evil and Dune.
They just throw you into an environment and let you deal with what emotions come.
Metal Gear, Souls, Hitman.
But another example that we can dig into is what kind of constitutes bad feedback.
And to me, that's when it's really just too narrow, or too general, or worse, contradictory and confusing.
I could go on for a bit too long, so I'm just gonna cut through this.
I don't like Red Dead Redemption 2 because the feedback is so strict and so narrow.
If I linger too long in a train heist, air horn, do it again.
If I'm circumnavigating around an enemy encampment and wanna go the opposite direction or cut through guns blazing,
air horn, do it again.
There's a very specific, narrow way to do every one of the story missions.
And it honestly just takes me out of it because like, I want to maybe play my cool slick cowboy as this meandering kind of Smith and Weston style character who just does not give a shit
But I need to, as Arthur Morgan, give a sufficient amount of shit so that this timer doesn't run out.
And I've always not really gelled with it.
I think Bioshock Infinite's an example of something being too broad.
You don't really have any feedback that's guiding you towards a general mindset in that game.
It's just make it through, get to the end of the level.
There's not much about the combat system or any environment that
gets you thinking about who Booker is as a guy, what his combat choices reflect about his perspective or his ideology, or just even a vibe.
Like, is he angry?
Is he melancholic?
Or is he just kind of put upon or, uh,
Yeah, you contrast it with something like Gordon Freeman.
This guy feels still like a scientist.
These solving puzzles, coming up with unique solutions, taking a gravity gun into a zombie-infested hellhole and coming out the other side coated in blood.
That's interesting.
That conveys character.
That lets you feel like this kind of mad scientist energy that I think Infinite unfortunately doesn't.
Another example is contradiction.
you know, standard ludonarrative dissonance.
Like, who is Nathan Drake?
Oh, he's the chipper, good guy, Indiana Jones type character who will also pull off a guy off a cliff and then joke about him as he careens to his death.
That's mixed signals.
But that then kind of drifts us to pressure.
So we've given the player feedback.
We've gotten them to align with our vision.
We've gotten them to express motivation.
We've given them clear sets of what to do, what the boundaries of the game are.
And then we push them.
We throw them into intense situations.
We limit their choices.
We limit their time to react.
And this is where things get interesting.
Because, just like with Judith Weston's framework, this type of pressured, risky situation leads to extreme or unconscious actions.
And that's where the most interesting performances come from, where the player
has to just scramble.
They're not overthinking it.
They're not underthinking it.
They're just existing.
So how do we do this?
It's pretty simple, honestly.
It's intensity, surprise, it's uncertainty.
It's anything that destabilizes this rigorous set of rehearsal that we've given them.
We've created a safe space for them, and then we break it in some way.
We ask them to perform when they're not expecting to.
We change the game up on them.
We push
three times as much as we said we were on top of them.
And it leads them to these unique experiences where you're not going to perform perfectly.
You're going to maybe use too much ammo or get hit or run away or figure out a new technique just by flailing at the buttons.
But a really important thing to understand about this dynamic is what we're essentially forcing the player to do and asking them to do is be vulnerable in these situations.
And when we don't
at all.
But I think Resident Evil is a perfect example of doing this right.
Resident Evil, the remake especially with Mr. X, is this constant shifting guide of pressure where you were thinking that you understand the assignment, you understand the layout, you understand the environment, I've got all of my resources, so God, footsteps.
Scrambling, running into zombies, turning the corner and seeing him hanging out with a licker.
Great.
That's what I'm going to remember.
That's what I'm going to feel.
That's when I'm not myself playing a game.
That's when I'm Leon, scared for his life.
And so the important thing is kind of mentioned with
The player is fundamentally being vulnerable in these moments.
I'm kind of raw at this point.
So we as designers need to understand how to reward these risks, to reward this moment of vulnerability.
And this isn't necessarily to say like, oh, give them resources, oh, give them flashy things, but just cultivate ways to give good feedback, to acknowledge that risk, to acknowledge, to make it feel that like, oh yeah, you got murdered by a licker and Mr. X,
but it's fine.
But I think this is really critical because this understanding not of just of, oh, the player's cognition, but their emotional cycle through your game is what can then lead us to this holy grail that I've been talking about, this critical moment where we put pressure, we've aligned them, all of these things are in there.
They understand this character now.
And then the next step,
on
Moments are allowed to do one thing.
You can have downbeats.
You can have spaces to build rehearsal, teach the player new skills.
You can have moments where you're just dedicated to pressure.
You can have moments that are dedicated to alignment, where you're testing to see if the player is understanding some core element of the combat loop or some core element of the character, cut scenes or the variations.
Just look at what you're doing, keep it simple, and ask, what is it doing?
And is it doing it well?
because as I've kind of been talking through this entire thing, like when we're talking about theater production, it's not a simple, straightforward process.
There are different facets.
There's table reads, there's live dress rehearsals, there's one-on-one sessions with the director.
All of these things are key steps in building that final production.
But I think also importantly of like this doing one thing at a time thing is we're able to present the player new facets to explore.
It's when we do things like increase complexity, demonstrate diverse content, we're able to allow the player to sink further and further in to the breadth of a dramatic persona or style of play.
You know, we give them places to rehearse and prepare to kind of, again, cultivate this character.
And for like some really in-depth process on this, I recommend my two other talks on Last of Us 2 Museum.
There's basically a lot of what we're talking about just straight there.
That style of composition, that rhythm of storytelling that then leads us from who am I, what am I doing to I am Ellie or I am Joel, I'm living in this moment.
And that's where we finally get the critical moment itself.
because I've talked about.
This is that space where you feel like you're living a fictional moment.
It's more than maximum pressure or the climax of a sequence.
It's a substantial act that changes or radically defines this persona that the player has been cultivating for this entire time.
Really key examples of this, it's like the end of The Last of Us.
This is you, being Joel,
demonstrating to yourself, to him, and the world what that means.
And I think most critically is what's not in this screen.
There is no Cress-X to kill the surgeon.
There is no direction.
The player can do it without it.
Because they've built trust with us as designers and them as performers that they got this.
They understand what's going on.
and that authenticity that that style, that format of moment brings is some of the stuff that stuck with me the most in my entire gaming career.
Like, I'm still not over the end of Metal Gear Solid 3, where you're just lingering and the game waits for you to pull the trigger on the boss.
Of course I did it.
Or dealing with Old King Alant in the first Demon's Souls game.
Like, everything up to that point felt like a dress rehearsal for that motherfucker.
The fact that he teleports still is not okay to me.
Or dealing with the Rachni in Mass Effect.
For me personally, I did an entire second Renegade playthrough and broke at this moment.
I could not bring myself to do it.
Even though I had intentionally tried to be this hard, evil character.
At that moment I realized I was lying.
that my character was just an asshole with a heart of gold.
And then I played through the other two games with this new deepened understanding of a pseudo renegade character that always broke into the right thing at the last moment.
And that was because this game provided all of this lead up.
It provided space to explore and attempt and experiment and tweak.
And the result was electric.
You know, the director doesn't need to be off stage whispering certain notes on the final night of release.
They get to be in the audience because the actors know what they're doing.
They've done a good job.
They've directed them.
And I hope this helps you develop that in your own games.
And I kind of want to close out just giving a second, like very big thank you to Judith Weston.
I can't recommend this book enough.
Special thanks to Tim Rogers and all of his amazing work on YouTube.
If you like anything I've ever talked about, he does this but more for hours.
And it's kind of messed up that he's so good at it.
But thanks for listening.
We're going to shift to Q&A so we can just kind of use this next half hour to kind of discuss or poke at any questions in this framework and stuff.
Like I said, the original plan for this was a half hour talk.
I thought it'd be good to just kind of
do some discussion on this framework, see what you guys think about it.
But before we do that, though, I have one last little thing, a bit of a teaser on something I'm working on soon.
We're gonna be announcing this project tomorrow, but it's not a video game, but it's an experimental thing with audio drama that me and some close friends are doing, so keep an eye out for it.
We're gonna be doing a story-focused studio in addition to a lot of our game work.
But yeah, Q&A time.
Thank you for the talk, it was very good, thank you.
So I wanted to ask about the idea of building up the dramatic persona as the main character.
An example, like Last of Us, most of the game is played with a companion, and throughout that time, the companion is kind of building its own persona, but there are moments where you get to personify that companion.
What's your take on how to handle that situation?
So how do we deal with situations where you have a key companion character, an NPC, that you have for most of the game, but then suddenly are presented with control of this character?
I think there are a few good ways to do it, but I don't think there's many wrong ways to go about it.
I think all of the same ideas apply.
what
in
for the game.
Hi, thank you so much for the talk, especially as a user researcher, like seeing the player become the actor just like was words for the soul.
And I was wondering actually how like play testing or concept testing and like speaking to players kind of led you to this, you know, players as an actor.
Yeah, so I think you did actually hit on what really did lead me to this framework.
So the question was, how does talking to playtesters and players kind of inform this perspective?
And I think fundamentally, it was seeing how similar the conversations I was having with not only my colleagues who were playing things, but players of work that I've built and contributed and hearing it over the years or just in the cycle of playtests, where it started clicking that, oh, hey, I've
read about
you
relationship, that feedback loop to somebody to help them not just perform well, but also articulate the emotions that are embodied with that character well.
And that's the other thing that maybe like if I were to expand this talk about that importance for the player themselves to perform a character.
It's not just a matter of like, oh, I'm doing something on stage, but there's something cathartic and deeply therapeutic about
performance and that we get to provide that to players with this vulnerable consistent relationship through game design.
Thank you so much.
I was wondering if you had any thoughts in terms of
allowing the player to feel comfortable being vulnerable with the emotions that they may feel or that you may want them to feel however you want to think about it when playing games especially maybe ones that are not that actually do require more vulnerability for you to feel just as a person you need to feel more comfortable to feel sorrow or melancholy or whatever it is than the joy over killing monsters in doom or whatever
How do you apply the ideas in your framework to like priming players to get there the time that you want them to rather than just kind of dumping this request upon them?
I think that's a great question.
So for the audio's sake, the question is, how do you compensate or build towards environments or situations that are fundamentally more emotionally taxing or vulnerable?
It's one thing to get the player aligned with having the joy of killing a cool monster, and another to deal with the loss of a loved one.
And I think the question itself I think kind of leads us to where I think doing it right is achieved, which is being very considerate of that fact, realizing that certain emotions need more lead up than others, and that if you don't do that sometimes you do risk
alienating or losing people through the shock or intensity of it.
I think we took that risk, specifically on The Last of Us 2, and a lot of the negative feedback and intensity around it really resulted from that.
Not to say that I regret or don't think we should have done it the way that we did, but it's more a demonstration of what happens when we do just slam the big red button and let those intense emotions flow.
And for those that have played the game and enjoyed it, I think the aftermath, the grieving scene where Ellie cuts to Ellie at the grave and exploring the house is what we tried to do to provide that space to feel very vulnerable.
It'd be one thing if we just cut directly midday to Seattle to Ellie slicing and dicing up people.
That would not have worked.
Instead, we let you grieve.
But for some people, the lack of a lead up
was going to be fundamentally alienating, and that was a risk that we deliberately took.
Thank you.
Hi, I was curious about your thoughts on games that sort of start with that pressure moment before you give the actor a chance to rehearse the role, so like games that start with you fighting a boss you're supposed to lose to or like Dead Space, where almost the first scene is when everything goes wrong and you don't really have a chance to get into the character first.
So the question is, what do you think about games where it just starts with pressure?
Like an example of being classic Demon's Souls, classic Dark Souls, where here's a big bad monster, you're going to lose to it immediately, or Dead Space where it just starts with the alarm on.
I think it really varies on genre.
In both of those cases, I think you can see that it's fairly successful in that, like,
disruptive tone.
Like Dead Space, I think is very well suited to that because you are never meant to feel comfortable.
It is not a game about the violation of your comfort.
It is the constant destabilization of identity and self and your abilities do not get eaten.
And it just starts there.
And it provides the same thing within this framework, which is it's helping align the player with the tone and the direction and the style of the genre.
And then the same thing with Demon's Souls where
Yeah, you can't win this boss fight.
And even if you do, we're going to kill you with a chest afterwards because we are not playing the game that you think we're playing.
This is a game about failure.
And so cutting to that, getting that as quickly as possible, I think is vital.
If it was the same setup, but an hour into the game after drip feeding and being only positively reinforcing to the player, I don't think the franchise would have kicked off.
It would have just been, well, it was fun for the first bit and then,
derailed the entire thing with the giant demon.
So I think there's a time and a place for that.
And it really is just why I think approaching it as a framework is important because depending on the genre, depending on your goals, starting with pressure works or doesn't.
It's very contextual.
Awesome.
Thank you.
So when it comes to, first of all, great talk, just phenomenal.
But when it comes to perfect or true endings, do you feel like that hinders player like improvisation or their ability to kind of co-contribute to this work?
So the question is for linear or like perfect endings or good endings, do we feel like that limits the player's ability to express in this framework?
I would argue mostly no, honestly.
Kind of expanding on what I was talking about, like with the end of Last of Us 2, and like with any good performance, it's often less about the branch or the final state of the world versus what is the actor actually contributing?
They're contributing timing, tone,
approach, and it cannot be in, I think, games that have a perfect ending or a linear ending.
It's important that that critical moment is not, do I choose to end this race or blow up this building or save these people?
And more like Metal Gear Solid 3, which is all about how long does it take you to pull that trigger?
How many times do the gears spin in Snake's head before the game ends?
And that's the type of thing that I find most compelling to me as a player.
You know, the ending of Mass Effect 3 was not the part that hooked me the most.
The most interesting thing was a lot of the preamble, a lot of the moments where I'm in the thick of it, performing Commander Shepard, even in combat, where I'm deciding how he's navigating through a situation.
What's the timing?
What's the tone?
What's the approach?
And I think, yeah, servicing that is the way to go when you have a perfect or linear ending.
How do you think this framework applies to games without an explicit dramatic persona?
Games where you are creating or projecting into the character and there really isn't a whole backstory or character that's provided.
Do you think this framework works for that or does it not?
So the question is, what about games without an explicit dramatic persona, where there is no Spider-Man for you to be?
I think from hearing your question, you can add to this.
A good example of this might be things like a rhythm game or a fighting game, where there's less a explicit character for you to inhabit.
Another example might be Civilization or Rimworld, where you are more this overseeing manager.
But I think even in discussing that, we can start outlining that even in the case of something like a rhythm game,
One of the most popular rhythm games of all time is Guitar Hero.
There is still this intrinsic property by the fact that you have a human playing your game that they're going to play as somebody.
Be it as the superstar version of themselves or the maestro on the DJ Maxx panel, there's this quality of it where they're cultivating and trying to perform as somebody.
Thank you.
Yeah, so my question is kind of building off of a couple other ones that I think just got asked, but in terms, actually almost sort of an opposite case from the last one, and just that in the case of strongly linear games, right, often ones that have really strong themes or messages, like, for example, The Last of Us Part Two, I think there's a lot, there's a big camp of people that sometimes feel like
Well,
to use kind of the techniques you were talking about too, rather than letting the player sort of express that character in their own way, sort of putting them in the shoes of that character and getting them ready to think like that character and feel like, oh, I did do that thing, even if they didn't really actually have a choice to do it.
Yeah.
and
create a situation like the beginning of Last of Us 1 where, yeah, sure, you could stand around holding Sarah, but everything is on fire and zombies are running at you.
Those are facts of the matter.
So you run to the place that's not on fire.
You don't need any kind of prompting or alignment with that.
But as with the previous question, that's also a much more immediate, easy to ramp into emotion than I'm going to kill every person I see in Seattle.
And I think fundamentally, there's also something that
I think like applies to theater casting as well, which is kind of being okay with that
a lot of people are going to have different needs and timelines for that.
And it's essentially impossible to cover everybody in the same way that like certain actors might not be good for certain roles, not because they're bad actors, but because the range or the style of the character just doesn't align with their personality or their style of performance or their range.
And I think last of us two kind of presents something that reached a scale where
enough people play it where we couldn't ever produce a wide enough bucket to get everybody totally aligned with it 100% of the time.
And I think, not to say that I think the process of doing that was perfect.
I feel that, yeah, there are some valid critiques on how quickly we try to get you to shift into Ellie's mindset because I think there was, I think, fundamentally an interesting disconnect between the way
the designers of the first game were writing Ellie and understood Ellie and how people playing as Joel perceived Ellie, which is kind of an interesting dichotomy there.
Like Ellie was always this like violent, intense type of person.
That's why she mauled David the way that she did.
Like she was always this on edge, kind of vindictive individual who by interacting with Joel was raised to become better.
But a lot of people's perception of Ellie was in that myopic view that Joel had for her too.
and I think there was a little bit of a disconnect there that yeah some people maybe needed more of a ramp because they weren't just reckoning with Ellie as herself but Ellie as them as Joel remembering her.
Cool, thank you so much.
Hi, so I wanted to ask something that might not be following a similar train of thought but how do you feel about
Things that bring single player experiences, players experiences kind of together without having to directly interact with one another.
The example I'm thinking of is like the end credit scene of Nier Automata where you're asked to wipe your save in order to help players actually finish the bullet hell to complete the game.
Are these sorts of things gimmicks?
Are there like meaningful ways to connect players together?
So the question is, are pseudo-multiplayer experiences like the end of Nier Automata interesting ways to connect people together?
I would say most often, more often than not, yes.
But I think it's worth kind of emphasizing how interesting and poignant of an ending that was to Nier Automata, because I think it fits really well into this critical moment framework.
The game presents you with a choice that the entire game feels like a rehearsal towards making.
Like this idea of sacrificing yourself to help somebody else, giving instead of just going through, after especially being helped.
You do the end credits first with all this help from all these other people.
And I think the fact that it's multiplayer or not is almost immaterial to the alignment and the delivery of the central message to it.
I think it is a brilliant piece of design to do something so outside of the box.
because the game up until that point was in no way multiplayer, was in no way linked.
So it creates this extra layer of grandiosity, of surprise where it's like, Oh, this is network.
This has been, you know, you've all been living in the same world this entire time.
Oh my God.
It's almost like we've been talking about that this whole time.
But, uh,
I think yeah, multiplayer connectivity, I think a good example of that is like the entire Souls series.
Like it has that kind of pseudo single player quality.
Death Stranding I think does it well.
I think basically as a tool it can be utilized for almost every piece of this framework, giving players space to rehearse, giving players feedback and alignment, letting them perform to others.
Like I think it's a really good tool overall.
I don't see any negatives in approaching it like that.
Thank you.
One of the more, with Last of Us in that example, one of the big things about that game, at least for me, was that the motivation for Joel and the dramatic persona that the player inhabits changes throughout the game.
I mean, it goes from like, this is a job that you have to do to, oh, here's like a daughter figure.
How do you cultivate a change in motivation and a change in the dramatic persona of the player without just kind of forcing it on them?
So the question is, how do you kind of guide the player towards a change in persona without forcing it on them?
I think it's really just using the same exact tools to build the persona in the first place.
Like the player is coming from a point of not being one way and then becoming one way, and then as the hours tick by and the game develops and the story turns,
you keep providing those same tools to take Joel from dramatic persona A to B, from Joel the hardened smuggler to Joel the very protective loving dad, because not only are you living through those moments of change with him, because you're fundamentally already aligned, you're already being guided through these things, but then we're just using the same tools over again to not just affect you, but affect Joel.
He's given feedback from the world.
He takes risks and is receiving like punishment and reward for it.
He is interacting with Ellie and it is inviting how he sees the world and how he changes.
He's basically going through this exact same framework at the same time as we are and in a way of building a new persona out of it.
Cool.
Thank you.
I was curious what you think about the designer as a director in a multiplayer experience.
Is there anything that you would do to effectively model this for a multiplayer game?
Yes.
So the question is, how do we look at this framework specifically as the designer's director for multiplayer games?
And I think there's a lot that can be applied.
It's really just a matter of how the community and the extra material around it gets structured.
Personally, as a fan of Valorant, I think Riot has done an excellent job kind of cultivating and building what it means to play Valorant, what it means to be an agent, what it means to operate inside of this sport.
by a lot of its marketing material, a lot of its design choices, its aesthetics, and then also just how it runs its esports, how it cultivates and builds certain types of character stories and player stories so that when you sit down to play Valorant, you have that sense of like, all right, we are going to be this intense tactical team.
Nobody's going into Valorant to be like, we're gonna goof off like it's Among Us.
We're gonna throw grenades all at once.
A lot of people just kind of buy in
and align to this way of playing the sport well.
And I think, yeah, the best way to think about that is as a multiplayer game, I think fundamentally, you have to consider a lot of the stuff outside of the core experience itself and really deal with things like community management, marketing, extra material, and that can provide a lot of these same things.
But you have place to rehearse, you have training modes, all these same types of things, and I think it's all relevant.
Hi there.
I want to thank you for your talk.
I really enjoyed it.
I wanted to ask you if you feel like there might be some inherent risk by playing so hard into all of these different methodologies to get the player aligned with the character, especially in instances like Prototype 2 with Alex Mercer or Last of Us Part 2, where then it feels like a different actor is playing a similar character because it's a computer-controlled character at that point, and it feels like there's that dissonance of what you felt like when playing that character in a new story.
So the question is, do you feel any risk of trying to align the player to this character, giving them ownership over something that then you rip away from?
So an example is you play Alex Mercer in Prototype 1, you define who he is, but he's a very different character potentially in Prototype 2.
In Last of Us 2, you play as Ellie and then perceive Ellie outside of your control,
and what happens when there's a misalignment there.
I think, yeah, fundamentally there's a lot of risk in that.
Anytime that you're, like I said, it's the same amount of risk I'd feel that you recast a main character with a different actor.
I think there are ways to approach doing it, which is, again, being really tight and concise with the alignment, with the style, with the focus of what's happening.
so far?
Showcase how your actions were perceived more than like oh Ellie's doing three more days in Seattle and she's getting even more murdery than you wanted to be murdery with her instead It's feeling more of like the consequences for your actions.
So I think that's a very fine line and an interesting consideration because it's fairly uncommon, but Definitely pretty relevant and I felt that in a lot of other games like Metal Gear Solid 2 is kind of a good example where snakes kind of a dick Yeah
like Devil May Cry 4, you got Dante who's just super silent all of a sudden.
Thank you.
So I think we're running out of time and it doesn't look like we have any more questions, so I can let you guys out a bit early.
Thank you again so much for listening.
If you found this format and this talk really helpful, I hope you guys rate it pretty well and I'll see you around the convention soon.
you