Welcome to the party, thanks for coming through.
My name is Dave Yonaguden, I'm the creative director over at Studios of Year, and today
we're going to talk about how my newbie solo self somehow landed on Xbox Game Pass.
Still not really sure how that happened, but I have a few very educated guesses.
So that's what we're going to talk about today.
First off, as a little brief disclaimer, I'm just speaking from my own personal experiences,
yours might be very different, and I'm still figuring out this whole thing because video
games are weird.
I'll also be talking a lot about Xbox Game Pass, but all the advice I'm giving still
applies to any type of platform holder talks or just any company negotiation or relationship
in general.
So with that out of the way, a little context about myself.
I'm a 22-year-old Cleveland-based developer.
I've been making games for about 10 years now, but She Dreams Elsewhere is my first
commercial big boy title, so to speak.
I've also worked in film, directing, screenwriting, photography, and just all types of weird,
creative, DIY stuff in general.
As for She Dreams Elsewhere itself, it's a surreal adventure RPG.
You're playing as a woman named Dahlia, and you're in a coma.
And you gotta figure out how you got into a coma, find a way to wake up, confront your
own inner nightmares, and have a horrible trip you experienced throughout the entire
way.
So I'm a little bit biased.
I think it looks pretty cool, sounds pretty cool, but I definitely didn't start out like
that at first.
So flashback to four and a half years ago when I first started development.
I was a wee young lad in my senior year of high school
and I was like, hey, I want to make this big game
and I think I can finish it in five months while also being a senior and
making a feature film for my senior project, so needless to say
that didn't work out, but hey, you know, we'll get there.
But still, I knew that if I wanted some metric of success, I had to get the word out there
somehow while having no money or resources of my own, as one does while being a broke
high schooler.
So, as you can see, when the game first started out in development, it was a lot more colorful
and cartoony, but also a bit rough on polish and a little bit generic, if I'm being totally
honest.
But still, I was like, gotta get the word out there somehow, and I gotta get on Steam.
so i posted the game on steam greenlight when it was still active back in the day
and the results were uh...
not too hot
uh...
there's some good comments here and there but
a lot of it was pretty negative
a lot of it justifiably so
And it was a real shocker to me because I had never, I had never like posted any of
my games on such a big mainstream site with such a wide audience.
So yeah, it was rough at first, but still in my eyes, feedback is still feedback, so
I took it.
And what I really ended up realizing is that the game really didn't have its own unique
personality yet.
And the audience reacted to that and they realized that I really had to do a lot better
with the game itself, but I also had to do a lot better when it came to game as marketing
and doing a better job of communicating my vision to potential players.
So I kept at the game, kept developing it throughout the next few years, get the cool
black and white aesthetic purely by accident one day, so that was fun.
So yeah, as the game...
development progressed, and I grew as a person, the game grew too, and eventually it found
its own unique voice and became something that was actually worth paying attention to.
So if I had any one big piece of advice throughout this entire talk, it's that if you want to
get attention, the game itself has to deserve it first.
I think the big thing why Sheenus Elsword had that really negative reaction at first
was because it really came across as a low-effort RPG-maker game.
So yeah, it took me a while to find that unique voice, but eventually I got there.
So definitely be patient, but it is key to actually find that unique voice first.
Because nothing is worse than spending all these years on your precious little child,
only for them to get bullied and ignored on their first day of school.
So yeah, that's uh, that was fun.
Also, stay hydrated, y'all.
It's a rough year out here.
You gotta stay safe, stay healthy, all that fun stuff.
So yeah, I had to get the word out there somehow still, even with finding my own unique voice.
And I still had no money, no resources, and also no clue what I was doing.
But still, I had to do something about it, so I went to social media.
And that's kind of ironic because I hate social media, still do to this day, but hey, what
can you do?
So I mainly posted on social media sites like Twitter, Reddit, Instagram, all that stuff.
And I utilized hashtags a lot.
Stuff like hashtag Screenshot Saturday, IndieDev, GameDev, anything that could really just take
the game out into a wider audience so I wasn't just, you know, yelling to the two people
who followed me at the time.
I kept it pretty low-key.
There was no big press feeds or big review or any...
Any type of hype building, it was just more of me slowly posting bits and pieces of progress
and slowly getting traction as the month progressed.
I also leaned on my RPG Maker community a lot too, because the game is also built in
RPG Maker.
They were great both for support and advice and tips, but also for just having that small
initial group of first adopters who will really champion the game in the years to come.
So yeah, after I found my, again, unique voice so to speak,
I officially announced it in summer 2018
with the nice little teaser trailer
and the launch of the Steam page,
which another pro tip if you're using Steam,
get your page up as soon as possible.
Definitely get that sweet wishlist action going.
I'm really glad I had that huge head start now
because if I put that page up like a month before launch,
it would just be a pretty bad time.
So yeah, it was a much better reaction this time around.
But still, even though it looked and sounded good, so to speak,
it still had to play good, since, you know, it's a video game.
And at that point, I hadn't really done a lot of external play tests.
So I went off to my local game dev group, the Cleveland Game Dev.
Shout out to them.
And I found out through them that they were going to be splitting up booth costs in an
upcoming convention.
And I was like, oh, that's pretty cool.
You know, never really been to a convention before, so might as well give it a shot, see
what's happening.
So a few months later, I went off to GDEX 2018, my very first convention, and it was
a rough, rough shitshow.
But it was very necessary.
Like I had absolutely no clue what I was doing,
no clue what to do before showing up.
I came with just only the bare essentials,
the monitor, the game, a controller,
a few business cards, and that was really it.
And also candy too, because that works every time.
And yeah, it was also first come, first serve,
so I only had the small end of a table,
because I arrived like really late.
So yeah, that was pretty rough.
But still, even in that little dinky state, it accomplished my goal of getting players
hands-on with the game and directly getting their feedback.
It also helped that it was still pretty cheap to attend to.
The cost overall was about $300 for the weekend, mainly because it was a two-hour bus ride
down the road, and I stayed with a college friend while I was there, split the booth
costs, and just basically kept things pretty low.
But either way, it confirmed to me that there was actually an audience for this game, and
that somehow...
they actually liked it, which is pretty cool. I'm not used to compliments, so
it was pretty new to me.
So the next convention will be DreamHack Atlanta, two months later.
And here are the organizers. They actually reached out to me first,
because they had found my game through some weird channel that they had been
doing their thing on. And that was kind of a shocker too, because...
I'm not really used to attention, I'm still not.
It was just crazy to see like
who's watching you from afar even when you don't know it.
So yeah, I went down to Atlanta, got a carpool from a friend.
And this one was a much bigger convention.
And it was also a weird dynamic too, because it was like, heavily eSports focused.
So you had like these big names like Halo, Overwatch, CSGO, like on one side, and then
right across the aisle was just my tiny ass pixel art narrative based indie game, and
I'm just like, please just play my game, like I'm just, I don't know what I'm doing, just
give me something.
Um, so that was weird.
But even still, I got really great feedback.
I even won best art house that year.
And it was a great chance for me to just go outside my comfort zone.
Both in terms of event setting and also just socializing with players.
Because of G-Dex, I didn't really know what to do when people were playing the game.
I would just kind of stand back and watch them from afar.
didn't really know what to do with my hands or like how to talk to people like that
um but here it was a lot more natural and i was just talking with players
getting their feedback making friends uh just had a pretty good time in general
um not sure if i would have done it again if it wasn't as close by or as
cheap because this one was a little bit more
expensive but still pretty cheap around like 600 bucks
um
But yeah, it was one of those neat little learning experiences.
And it was good practice for what was to come next, which would be the biggie, GDC 2019.
I got into the Indie Mega Booth here.
And this is also where I met Microsoft and the Xbox reps.
And this is a totally different rodeo compared to the past two events.
Like it had actual networking involved, it was like
all these developers, some big and large, I had no clue what I was doing, I was just some rando there.
So yeah, it was definitely a pretty interesting experience.
Definitely the most expensive trip up to this point too.
A lot of my costs were subsidized thanks to the Indian Megabooth.
They provided the actual TV, some audio, the headset.
I really just had to like just bring myself from the game.
And it was a much different atmosphere compared to the previous two.
Like it had a much more like triple A feel, if we're talking in gaming terms.
It was also a lot more precise feedback wise, because like it was other developers.
And it was great too, because I actually got to meet a ton of contacts there,
like publishers, porting houses, PR companies, just new friends in general.
So that was pretty cool.
So I showed off the game for the first two days there,
and the rest of the week was just free for me to just do
whatever I wanted to and just make as many connections
as possible.
And that's kind of a toughie because at that point,
I was cool and comfortable,
like just showing off the game itself.
But when it came to actually like networking separately,
I was like, I have no clue what I'm doing.
I have mad anxiety.
All these people seem to like know each other already.
And meanwhile, I'm just in the corner being like,
Hey, how do I talk to y'all? I don't know what I'm doing.
Help.
But somehow, we made it happen.
But yeah, here's a very brief guide to networking, how I did it.
Well, first off, just remember that you're always networking, even when you don't realize it.
Like, the way you present yourself, the way you talk to other people, the words that gets around about you,
you're always pitching, and you're always networking, no matter what you're doing.
So yeah, other tip I would have is go out there and talk to people already.
It's a networking event, people are there to meet other people.
And ask them questions.
Ask them about their favorite games, their own games.
People love talking about themselves.
And it was also great for me because I've always just been a listener in general.
So it was important to just be an active listener and actually engage with them and see what
they're actually saying and all that fun stuff.
It goes without saying, but treat people as people.
Don't be an asshole.
You think it would be pretty obvious, but you'd be very, very surprised.
But yeah, definitely go into any of these relationships, business or otherwise, just
try to make a friend first and foremost.
At least that's how I always do it.
And definitely don't be afraid to reach out to other friends or contacts to help you make those conventions.
Have them go out with you when it's safe to do so.
Have them introduce you to other people. All that fun stuff.
Master the art of following up.
If you are looking for something, give them a way to contact you.
Don't waste your time. It's very clear when someone wants something and is just waiting for that time to just slip in and set that bomb off.
Yeah, this is a very, very brief guide.
If you want a much bigger and much better and much more fleshed out guide, definitely
check out Victoria Trant's Introvert's Guide to Networking article, because it's great
and she's great.
And yeah, so as you can see in the picture, it was my first time meeting Xbox and that
whole rep over there.
And yeah, when it came to actually getting onto Xbox and talking to them, I didn't really
know what I was doing. I didn't really know how the whole process went. So it was really good to
have like a rep there in person to kind of like walk me through step by step just to like see
how to get those initial steps started.
So we kept in contact throughout the coming months.
We met in person again during the Game Desert Color Expo,
another great expo because it was a very targeted,
very niche event.
So I was able to directly connect with my target audience.
And so Xbox was a sponsor there.
So we got there in person together
and I received word that they were gonna be
having a little open house before PAX West next month.
And I had never been to PAX West, never been to Seattle.
So I was like, hey, like, you know, you know, definitely consider me if you want to. Let's just keep in touch,
you know, keeping it pretty casual.
But eventually I was formally offered a spot at the show and I made my way off to Seattle.
The open house itself went really well, if not pretty overwhelming.
It was directly on their main campus.
And again, still having no clue what I was doing, which is to say, I was just there with
the game.
But again, at this point I was still pretty comfortable showing it off, having learned
those lessons in the past few events.
And one of the perks of showcasing there was I got a free entry to the first day of PAX,
but didn't have a pass for the rest of the weekend until another contact hooked me up.
Shoutout Jen.
But even with that free pass, I had no permanent booth, no way to actually straw off my game
other than a few scattered events here and there.
But I was like, hey, I'm still at PAX, my audience is here, I still want to straw off
the game somehow.
So with that, my phone and Instagram became an absolute godsend.
My Instagram page is essentially a little mini-portfolio of the game itself.
So I'd walk around with that, show it to people, casually of course, like not just, you know,
having it out, you know, shilling my game everywhere.
And yeah, I just use it as an opportunity to casually connect with other devs and people
within the industry.
So after the idea of Xbox Open House, I received a few hints that I was going to get a Game
Pass deal, but I didn't really know what that meant.
and what that involved.
But it was formally offered in early October 2019.
And it was pretty huge.
It's still the biggest financial deal I've ever gotten, ever,
to the point where I had to ask them to repeat the numbers
that I got on our phone call.
And while I can't go into specifics, I was given upfront support in addition to the rest
of the actual licensing fee.
And it was really cool because up until that point, I had just been bootstrapping.
The game was just funded out of pocket just through videography gigs and other just random
one-off hustles.
And I was also doing publisher negotiations at the time too, and the Game Pass deal allowed me to fund the rest of the game,
make it profitable, and still do everything I wanted to do with a publisher without even having to get a publisher.
So yeah, it was a pretty big deal, but
if a big number like that comes certain challenges, and that's where we get into the fun, boring, complicated, legal fun time bit.
What joy, what joy.
So yeah, I actually had to really get deep in the biz dev around this time.
The very first thing I did was to get a lawyer, and I cannot stress that enough.
Please get a lawyer.
I can't read legalese at all, so it was really important that I didn't miss out on anything
that could have impacted the game negatively down the line.
So definitely get a lawyer, have them look over everything, have them tell you exactly
what the contract is saying and what you have to do, and yada yada.
This also goes without saying, but definitely double check that your other company and business
elements are also in order.
Like have your company set up, your bank account, all the tax info, all that stuff.
So yeah, the entire process from the initial offer to the signed deal was actually pretty
short in my case.
It was about like three weeks.
From what I hear, that's actually pretty atypical.
For a lot of devs, it can be weeks if not months before anything really happens.
So yeah, it really just depends on the situation and just luck too.
So be patient, be persistent.
Nothing's wrong with giving them a little poke if they haven't answered for a while.
and don't feel bad about it like at the end of the day like
it's your baby it's your game you gotta do what's best
for it and you gotta like have all as much info as you want to with it
uh so with that being said this did take up
all of my time at certain points um which really kind of sucks when you're
a solo dev because
when I'm like heavy in like biz dev tasks or even any tasks that's like not directly making the game
my mind is like, hell hey here's a bunch of ideas and like other stuff for the game itself
that you can't work on because you're doing boring business stuff.
So if I had to do it all over again I honestly might have just hired someone to just take care
of all that stuff if not for just a few weeks just so I could like focus on what actually matters
which is like actually finishing the game.
And yeah, like I said earlier, I was also going through publishing negotiations too.
And it was weird because compared to that, the Game Pass offer was a lot more straightforward
and simple and so much less stressful.
like poster negotiations
all required so much extra materials like
demos
pitch decks timelines all this type of stuff
versus xbox they were just like hey
we want you on game pass
here's a contract you can go with the paperwork cool alright
feel free to sign it when you want to
yeah it was
pretty simple and straight forward
but yeah overall it was
a lot to handle in general and it came with some unforeseen downsides too.
Like one of the feelings that popped up is that there was a much more increased sense
of pressure and depression regarding the actual development of the game.
Like I often felt like I wasn't even good enough to be a developer, let alone to be
on Game Pass or even anywhere else and that I would let everyone down, I would get exposed
for being a fake developer or all that stuff.
Yeah, imposter syndrome, it's not fun.
But that's a whole other separate talk where you get into.
I was also pretty burnt out at the time too,
because I was doing so much traveling and promo
and all this other stuff unrelated to the actual game.
I didn't really have a good balance of actual development
and biz dev, PR, and actually taking care of myself,
which is like the most important part of anything.
And because of everything surrounding the deal, I didn't really have much time to actually decompress myself and just chill out for once.
Especially since X-19 was coming up in the next month that I had to prep for, separately.
So yeah, wasn't really having a very fun time.
But one day I chatted with a friend and mentor about it, and he reminded me that ultimately, they wanted me on the service, and that tons of people already seemed to love the game.
So, clearly I was doing something right?
I don't know.
I always just think negatively about just myself and everything that I'm going through.
But in any case,
he reminded me to just take breaks,
love yourself, love the game, and just
take things one day at a time, because we're all human.
So yeah, definitely talk about these things with someone.
It's hard to keep these things close inside, especially when you're a solo dev,
and you don't really have...
really anybody on your team to talk to you about that.
So yeah, just let it all out.
Don't keep it in,
because eventually it'll just eat at you,
and it'll just negatively impact both just the biz dev side
and just the development side too.
And remember that ultimately,
they want the best for you, the game, and the players.
So yeah, it can be hard advice to actually practice
if you're someone like me,
who is very bad to even take their own advice, but hey.
We're all trying our best out here, y'all.
So yeah, even with all that stress, a few weeks later,
the deal was actually officially signed, and it was a done-zo.
The actual inclusion was announced the very next month
at X19 a few weeks later.
And yeah, even with all that time and stress
to finalize the deal, it was still
pretty dope to actually have it announced at an actual Xbox
event and have it on stage in front of an audience.
It was really cool.
So yeah, ever since then I've done a few other deals with both big and small companies.
And it was really good to have all this knowledge acquired from that whole shenanigan.
So yeah, the actual results of Game Pass will be seen when the game actually releases, which
it's still a few months away, so stay tuned for that.
But yeah, what did we learn today?
So yeah, definitely have a project that's actually worth the attention first and foremost.
Remember that you're always pitching, even if you don't know it.
You never know who's in the corner just watching you from afar, and you never know who actually
knows about your game.
Treat your contacts as people first.
Check in with them.
Not just to see, like...
any progress on like an actual biz there front but like hey like how are you doing how are the
kids how's your mental health especially in uh the year of covid uh especially important just
remember that human element and just treat people as people first um and find and embrace those
champions of your game like i said earlier like having that small rpg maker community first that
could champion the game it's like this other uh to my target audience first and foremost was dope
But it also applies to just platform holders in general.
There are a lot of people within the ID at Xbox team
that knew about the game and were just hustling about it,
talking about it within their internal meetings.
So I think that was really important
to keep up that relationship and just really just embrace them.
Be proactive about any opportunities coming up.
You know, what I like to do on Twitter is to, like, search and submit your game and, like, see what's happening and see what's upcoming and just
any way I can, like, get the game out there in front of, like, any new eyes was pretty important.
Because again, you never know what opportunities will come up.
You never know what's going to happen.
But with that being said, take care of yourself.
Don't burn out like I did and don't overextend yourself.
I did a lot of events, both in-person and virtual last year, and I was just pooped by the end of it.
Definitely look out for that unique money too.
And by unique money I mean the money that can only...that's very specific to your situation
rather than the standard publishing deals or crowdfunding or stuff like that.
And you never know where it'll come from so just be on the lookout for it.
If you have questions, ask them.
Ask for help.
Ask for tips and advice.
As my Nana once said, rest in peace, closed mouths don't get fed.
So open your mouth and speak up.
And honestly, sometimes a lot of it was just luck and some of it was like unluckiness too.
I would never, like I never would have even gotten this deal if, you know, the one Microsoft
rep actually came by my booth when I was at GDC last year.
So you never really know.
It just, it takes weird stuff like that happening.
And again, be patient and persistent.
It's a marathon, not a sprint.
Take care of yourself, take things one day at a time.
And like these business deals and stuff like that,
they don't happen overnight.
So just keep it chill, be patient.
And again, and I can't stress this enough,
remember the human element of it all.
Cause again, we're all trying our best out here.
So yeah, that's my weird little story about Xbox Game Pass.
and how I somehow went from being a scrappy, dinky little one-man show to being a slightly
bigger but still one-man show and still having no clue what I'm really doing.
So yeah, game will be coming out pretty soon.
I hope it does well.
But yeah, I guess we'll cross that bridge between Conewood.
But for right now, I got a game to get back to.
So yeah, thanks for coming to my talk.
Well, coming to my talk.
Watching my talk, really.
Have a good one. Stay safe out there. Wear your mask and be excellent to each other.