My name is David Whaley, and I made a game called The First
Tree.
And as you can see from the title,
it was no time, no budget, no problem.
But it's kind of a, I don't know why I wrote that,
because there was a lot of problems in finishing my game.
There was a lot of sacrifices.
But it worked out.
It was successful.
And that's what I'm going to talk about with you guys today.
So if you don't know what it is, The First Tree,
I should be playing.
So The First Tree is a third-person exploration game
about a fox looking for her missing cubs,
and also about a second parallel story being told
about a son reconnecting with his father in Alaska.
And this was a project I made to get out
these emotions of me losing my own father
to a heart attack early in life, or in 2010.
And so I made this, and I wanted to share
that story with people.
And for a hobbyist project, it did a little better
than I thought.
I was able to show it at the Smithsonian American Art Museum,
showed it at PAX West.
And it was cool to let that little story
and gain traction with people.
And maybe you're thinking, that's not a super unique story
for an indie game, an indie game success story.
But what usually gets people's attention
is that I finished the game.
while working full-time as a technical artist
at a VR company called The Void.
I was raising two kids and making sure that my partner,
Elise, had time for her art career.
And then I made the game without very much money at all.
So when the game launched on Steam, September 14, 2017,
it cost me $10,000 to make.
And that includes my website, conventions, music, everything.
The time was about 18 months of nights and weekends, or about a thousand hours.
And its first year it made $150,000.
That was my gross revenue.
And consoles came a year later, I was able to use those funds to pay for a console port
with the assistance of Doogames.
And that made $150,000 in its first month on all three consoles.
So yeah, it was awesome.
It was like a dream come true.
And a lot of people ask me, how did you do that with so little time and money?
What you've probably heard about is how the game
had a lot of Reddit traction.
And I got good at submitting this content, these GIFs,
and seeing how they would perform.
And so when on launch day,
I could have the marketing dream come true
and then get on the front page of Reddit,
which got me about three million views on that GIF
and 200,000 Steam page visits.
And so, and then on consoles in November 2018,
when the console release came out,
I was able to do it again.
And so, why did it do so well?
That's a question I ask myself a lot.
And I would say luck did have a big part to it,
but it's not the entire answer.
The facts are that I submitted a lot of gifts everywhere.
And it was consistent posting over 18 months.
Some of the posts did great, some of them didn't.
And it basically comes down to how do you eat an elephant?
Or a fox, in this case.
You eat it one bite at a time.
So those years of experimenting,
that taught me what works.
What also taught me a lot is that I made another game
before the first tree, just to challenge myself,
because I come from a film and design background.
I'm not much of a coder at all.
So I made my first game.
It was a first-person exploration game
called Home is Where One Starts.
And I used mostly just Unity assets and PlayMaker.
And through a lot of bundles and extreme discount,
I was able to make $15,000.
And it also taught me what not to do
when releasing your first indie game.
I launched at midnight because I was like,
oh, that's what movies do.
They do a midnight premiere.
I'll try that.
I changed my launch date last minute for some reason.
I had no one covered the game on day one.
I had no email list, only 200 Twitter followers.
And there was a lot of popularly requested features
for Steam, like trading cards and subtitles
that I waited to patch in later.
So I've distilled what I learned from that first experience
into my launch plan for the first tree.
And how would I sum up my launch plan for the first tree?
The best thing is, I would say, is it's low time,
high impact strategies.
I'm not sure that won't be taught in business schools
anytime soon.
But what it just means to me is you don't have a lot of time,
you need to be as productive as possible,
and try to take that risk of making a high impact,
even if it's a little more risky.
So the rest of my talk's divided into two sections,
how I developed the game with little time and money
and how I marketed it.
So first, just finding that time to finish your game.
That's hard, especially if you're a parent,
you know how exhausting life can be.
So this was kind of our rough plan with me
and my wife, Elise.
I'd work full time, and then also,
Elise needed time for her art career.
So we hired neighborhood teens to see
if they could watch our kids for about $7 an hour.
So I had to get home from work, work 45 minutes.
and then get the quality time together.
And then at the end of the night,
probably fit in two hours of development.
And that gave me about 10 hours a week.
And usually, you know, there were sacrifices there.
Like I couldn't, I wish I've played more
of all of your guys' indie games, but I definitely haven't.
I didn't play many games or watch many movies.
Usually like to get quality time with Elise,
we'd watch like a people getting hurt
on YouTube compilation video at the end of the night.
And at The Void, I don't think you need
a game development day job to make
your passion project come to life.
I will say though, there is some crossover benefit.
I remember, again, I'm not much of a programmer,
but I was learning about singletons the first time,
and I was reusing that in a project at The Void.
And just learning about that helped me fix
a Steamworks initialization bug
that had caused me a ton of grief.
So that's cool when that stuff crosses over,
but I don't know if it's necessarily required.
Okay, so you found the time.
Now, what do you do with that?
Now this is something, I would even say
like I used to be a little embarrassed about this,
but I'm now a huge believer in using
publicly available assets that you can license.
And prototyping, it's great,
but just using it as a springboard
to save yourself valuable time
and like creating it, like revising it
and changing it to add your own creative twist,
that's the reason my game was finished.
That's why my game released,
is because of these resources.
I probably could have made a lot of this stuff myself,
but I estimated it saved me roughly 600 hours.
And while I did have to spend a little bit of money,
it was nothing compared to like hiring a full-time composer
or even voice actors.
I did the voice acting.
I pressured my wife to do the voice acting.
She did great.
I wish I didn't do that.
So maybe we should have hired an actor,
but you just gotta do what's best for you.
This is like an example of how I tried to make these,
you know, this beautiful environment pack
by Michael Gustafson.
Tried to make it my own.
And so, yeah, I would even say it helped other artists too
when the game was successful in the marketing.
All the music was done by a composer named Josh Kramer,
and his music is gorgeous,
and it was only $30 to $50 a song.
And so when the game did well,
we were able to kind of form a partnership
and help get his music out there more.
So this is the third thing about finishing your game,
is I tried to challenge myself never to have a 0% day.
I have this GIF running because I love UX and UI design.
And I remember I was so burnt out,
I did not want to work on the game anymore,
but I love doing this stuff.
So my thought was if you can work,
just aim for a 1% day and get those small wins,
then it will encourage you to do the harder stuff
that you hate to do.
So whether it was just answering an email
or doing a small color change,
I tried to work on my game every single day.
So what are the cons of doing these low-time,
high-impact strategies for development?
Well, I did have to compromise my vision a little bit.
Like, I'm inspired by the games like Firewatch and Journey.
But of course it couldn't be like that.
It was just me using licensed assets.
So I tried to, you know, my game had to reflect that.
It was a shorter game.
It was like one and a half hours to two hours long
and I launched it for $8 on Steam when it came out.
Another problem is recognizable stock assets,
which I am surprised that it wasn't as a big of a deal
as I would have thought.
I probably skimmed about 10,000 comments about my game
and only about 10 to 15 even mentioned
that they recognize the art assets or the music.
So, and even usually commenters would say,
get mad at those people making fun of it,
saying, it's not an asset flip, dude,
he's trying to make it his own.
So that's pretty cool.
I will say, though, with music,
especially with YouTube copyright IDs,
if you're using stock music, those will get flagged,
and that could make content creators a little upset.
So if your game is dependent on that,
sharing those videos online, that's
something to keep in mind.
And then a really big problem was the
extremely messy project.
It was like a dumpster fire of a Unity project.
And that caused a lot of problems with the console
porting, but luckily, Do Games, they were awesome.
And they helped a lot with fixing it, working with my
work style.
So that's something to keep in mind as well.
That was one of the original pack.
So what's the one pro for all those cons?
Well, the one pro is you finished your game.
And that's the most important thing ever.
And it doesn't mean it's perfect.
Just means it's presentable.
So in this day and age, you all know that marketing, you
have to do that concurrently.
And so that's what I tried to do with a typical week.
I would do about three hours of making a GIF.
and posting that GIF and then doing that for like 12 to 18 months.
And what I usually do every week was I'd share it on Twitter, usually using the game, the
hashtags screenshot Saturday and then made with Unity on Friday.
Unity retweeted me several times and that's probably how I got like a third of my followers.
I posted on Tumblr with hashtags, the Reddit game dev,
there's screenshot Saturday, threads in that.
And yeah, at the beginning,
did have a lot more marketing work,
it was top heavy in that regard.
But that's why I would encourage you guys
to make your trailer as soon as possible,
create your website as soon as possible,
and create your Steam page with tags.
And so you can just get those organic wishlists.
So that's what I tried to do,
it just took a long time,
it was a drop by drop accumulation.
Now with the marketing, I wanted to first focus on
finding your hook before development,
which people ask me, what was like the magic ingredient
that your game was able to resonate with people so much?
And this one, it kind of happened by accident.
The cynical side is it's like,
if you took two popular things, people would love it.
But if you take a brand new original thing,
then people like, they don't know how to react.
And so with the first tree, you know,
I took my love of journey.
and I also, there was a people, there were people out there
who were like fans of anything that had a fox in it.
And you know, I picked a fox because it was,
you know, there was a personal connection.
It was like a wife, my wife's family name.
But people like, they marketed it for me
because they loved the idea so much.
And so I don't think, you know,
I think the optimistic side of that is,
I think it's good to remind gamers of things that they love.
I don't think it's a bad thing.
The other thing is because I come from an artist background,
Visual's first development took priority,
and that was something that the makers of Ooblets said
as well, they tried to make GIFs as soon as possible
so they can market it.
And that's why I would encourage you guys
to get the website and trailer and Steam page.
I wouldn't even waste time on screenshots.
When I would share screenshots online,
GIFs were shared 10 times more.
And the best part of all this is doing this first
is it gives you data.
Like what game ideas, what scenes from your game
resonate best with people?
And that's the data you can use when you make your trailer.
and then you can make a really killer trailer
because you have the data of like,
oh, that post has so many likes,
people really like that shot.
So anyway, what is like the point of all this?
What's the call to action for all that marketing?
Well.
My plan was, with the email list and the wish list,
and something I called the social media blitz,
which happens on launch day,
I would get on the new and trending tab.
That was the goal of all this,
was to gather those wish lists.
And it's because of, in this day and age,
how important Steam is with day one purchases,
and even first hour purchases,
because that's how you please the algorithm gods,
and that's how you get on the front page of Steam.
And you wanna get on the front page of Steam,
because the amount of traffic is insane.
Even with a viral Reddit post,
which had hundreds of thousands of views,
the Steam traffic on the first day,
I think that's the first two days,
it was 88% of everything.
And so the new and trending tab, you need to get on it.
And that was my goal with that,
and that's why I went to Reddit,
was to get a huge influx of traffic
to catch the algorithm's attention.
And so that's kind of what happened,
and that's what's happened with a lot of other indie games.
There's a lot of great GIFs that have been shared
on the gaming subreddit, which has 20 million subscribers.
And if you know where to look, you can find good examples.
I know a data scientist,
he analyzed a lot of the top Reddit posts.
And he said, he mentioned that there's usually time
involved, like, I've been working on my game for three years
or there's emotion in the title.
Like even in this, what the golf GIF that says like,
for people who hate golf.
catches people's attention.
I think it's important not to be a sales guy,
but just be like a friend,
showing off something that you're really proud of.
Part of this, I guess, part of what I learned
is that it's not just Reddit.
There's a lot of places you can post,
and I had to do it a lot.
Like, just in one year, I posted 41 times on Imgur,
and I'd say, like, most of those didn't do well,
but then a few would gain traction
and get on the front page of Imgur,
and then that's what would help build up my wish list
and my email list.
So here's some examples of good Reddit posts that I posted.
As a kid, I always dreamed of releasing a game
on a Nintendo console.
Today it happened.
After two years of work and no knowledge of code,
I still launched my Fox adventure game today,
The First Tree.
It doesn't seem like much,
but getting footprints working in my game is huge for me,
which it really was.
And this one has kind of a comedy angle.
Stress testing bunny herds in a game
with unforeseen consequences.
That one was retweeted by David Bowie's son on Twitter.
So that got a lot of attention.
Here are some posts that didn't do well.
The first tree launch trailer,
releasing on Steam September 14th.
Super Fox, the first tree.
Points of light towards the first tree.
Some other things that helped me is I've never seen a post
on the gaming server at DoWell that links to a store page
or even a website, always link to a GIF.
And then in the comments you can have a call to action,
just one link to your store page.
I've had comments removed for linking
to too many store pages
because it reeked of self-promotion.
And that leads me to a problem a lot of developers have
with Reddit is the self-promotional rules.
And I would say it just takes a little bit of preparation.
But that yes, you can use Reddit.
You just need to create an account
one to three months prior to your launch.
Hopefully you're posting more before that.
And you just have to remember that only 10%
of your submissions can be about your project.
Comments don't count.
You have to submit things.
So that's what I did.
I loved music.
I loved the game dev subreddit.
So I'd post once a day of stuff I liked
so that I was legal.
And then I would say remember the call to action.
I did do on my website, I did an email list
that was like one time email, no spam.
I was a little worried, like I hate spam
and I thought that would help get more emails
but comparing my numbers to other developers,
I didn't see any difference in that.
So I would say just say you won't spam them
and just get those emails
because those are the people that,
those are your like dedicated fans
and they'll probably buy the game
the first couple hours of launch.
This is my website traffic, and this kind of shows you
what those marketing efforts did.
Like, Imgur was nice, and it would happen pretty regularly.
But of course, getting on the front page of Reddit,
that was a huge bump.
Had 15,000 visits that day.
Something I dropped the ball on is I should have had my Steam store page up by the time that viral Reddit post was up
Because it came out a month later, and so my Steam store page could have got wishlist
And so yeah, that's why I need to get that Steam store page done ASAP
So leading up to launch, these were my numbers,
and this was in 2017, indie game development,
like the marketing world moves fast,
but my numbers were 12,000 Steam Wish lists,
4,700 Twitter followers, 4,400 mailing list subscribers,
1,300 Tumblr followers, and then I had 100,000 views
on my YouTube trailer.
And what that equated to was 11,000 sales my first week.
And then that was also a 7% conversion rate of my wishlist,
because I also gained an additional 50,000 wishlists
for being on the new and trending tab for five days.
So my social media blitz, what I was talking about earlier,
was my plan was the biggest problem
that my indie game could face
is that it would fade into obscurity
and would become invisible and get buried.
So bug fixes were gonna wait, parties were gonna wait.
My whole goal on launch day was just
to get the visibility out there, to get people aware of it.
and I wasn't gonna stop until something stuck,
which that Reddit GIF, it did stick,
so that's when I took a break,
but these were all low-time, high-impact strategies,
and I was just really hoping for one of those things
to push me over the edge to get on the new and trending tab.
Now, you're probably saying,
well, what if that big launch Reddit post failed?
Well, I don't want you guys to get too bummed out
because I was on the new and trending tab
before that Reddit post took off, actually,
which kind of surprised me,
and I attribute that to my mailing list.
Those number one fans, they bought the game immediately.
And just in the first hour, that made a difference.
If your gaming subreddit post fails,
then I would encourage you to use smaller subreddits,
like the Unity subreddit and Indie Gaming.
That can drive traffic.
And just keep at it during all of launch day.
So anyway, in conclusion, I started this as a hobbyist.
I was doing it on the side while taking care of my family.
And it was interesting how one thing led to another,
like my successful Steam launch,
it led to me getting access to Switch publishing
and helped me pay for porting the game,
which led to a successful console launch.
And now I wasn't planning on it,
but I was able to quit my job at The Void
to be a full-time indie developer,
which is amazing to me.
Thank you.
I will say life isn't that different from when I was working at night.
I'm actually like, I thought there would be a linear graph of my productivity from getting
that much more time and it hasn't been that way.
I feel like I was just as productive with 10 hours a week than I am with 40 hours.
And so it's pretty cool.
It just, there was one foot in front of the other and that's what led to me being a full
time indie developer.
And just doing it this way of what we talked about, it taught me a lot on what corners
can be cut.
And when.
what can't be cut, and how working to launch
makes all the difference.
And then I wanted to end with this quote
from an anonymous player.
I've gotten hundreds of emails from people
who've really like, they've just shared how much the game meant
to them.
And this is what she said.
Said, in that moment, it all resolved for me.
Everything, the game, my life the last couple months,
the loss of my mother, all of it.
Thank you so much for the first tree,
for closure, for peace,
for even if only in a video game
and for the briefest moment,
giving me a chance to speak to her again.
So, I guess you would say I'm begging you guys
to finish your game,
because other people need your game
just like other people needed the first tree.
And I'm so glad I was able to finish that
and to share it with people.
Thank you for listening.
I think we have time for a few questions.
Hi, I'm Garrett.
Hi.
So on your Reddit post, you said all of the very successful
game launches are like.
I've never made a game before.
I did this in like two years or whatever.
Did you use that title as intentionally as like this is
like a formula sort of?
Or was it more organic?
I would say it was organic.
I will say people on Reddit, they know when
you're being fake.
They want you to be sincere.
And that was something I tried to focus on,
was just, this came from my heart.
I didn't try to follow a formula,
but I think it's interesting to analyze that data.
Yeah.
So, yeah.
Thank you for your question.
I really like the art style of the game,
I just wanted to ask you about how you achieved
a pretty consistent art style while using stock assets.
So, oh, I should be repeating the question.
He asked, how did I make consistent art style
with using public assets?
And that's a good question.
I think it helps with me because I feel like I could make
a lot of those assets as a technical artist
and as a, you know, as a artist.
But I was able to like, I just use it as a springboard
to save time.
Like I'm not good at rigging, so I'd
buy like those animations with the fox.
But I can change a texture map.
And so I was able to do that.
I was able to change the trees to what I need
and modify the rocks like that came in the asset pack.
So I will say like it takes work.
Like I needed to modify those assets,
but it saved me time instead of making everything from scratch.
Cool, thanks a lot.
Thank you.
And just to make sure I understood, oh, right.
You do have it released on the Switch?
Yes.
OK.
Then my question was, while it sounded like getting on the
Steam page was what gave you access to releasing on the
Switch store, I was just wondering what the comparison
in buys was from the Steam store versus the Switch store.
Because you know, they're two very
different audiences, usually.
So you're asking about sales figures?
Yeah.
Um, Switch did well for me, and I've learned a lot about the console marketing efforts.
With Steam, it's so, like, algorithm-driven, and with the consoles, there's people behind
the games they feature.
So they give you opportunities to submit trailers to the
official Nintendo YouTube channel and submit blog posts
for their websites.
So I would say, yeah, they're a little different, but still
getting that organic traffic.
It boosts you on the top sellers list on the Switch
eShop.
And then that gets the attention of the marketing team
at Nintendo.
And then they were able to feature my game also
in top indie games of November or December or something.
And so again, that helped a lot.
It's just the point of the successful Steam launch
is to prove that, oh, my game has legs.
And that's why they were able to take a risk
and give me a valuable dev kit.
Because, oh, the game did well on Steam.
That's great.
So thank you.
Hi.
So.
First of all, I was wondering, I haven't played your game.
I think it looks great, but I haven't played it.
You said that you have to compromise,
because of course, the scope of the game, that's natural.
So how, how am I going to say it?
Can I ask you a small question
and a little longer question?
Sure.
Okay, so first of all,
like how long was the average of um how long was the regain because of all this compromise?
So uh yeah he asks if if I try to compromise a vision how long how long would it have been if I
didn't compromise anything is that what you're asking? Or can you tell us both versions how
long it would have been if you hadn't compromised and how long it is now? If I didn't have to
compromise anything and then I got like a team of employees working for me
I think I would have liked polished controls, I would have had more levels.
Right now it's about two hours to complete, and I think four to five hours is good for
a consumable type of game like this.
It is minimalistic gameplay, it's lots of exploration.
I would have liked more puzzles in my game, and that was something I just didn't have
time to polish.
So I guess, yeah, that's the best way
I can answer your question.
Yes, one more thing.
How much I, because I know you have been developing
and marketing the game, how long,
or when you started marketing your game,
were you exclusively spending your time on market,
or were you also marketing and developing at the same time?
I was doing it at the same time,
which I think's really important.
And that's why, like I said, visuals first, development style.
Like that's when you have something to show as early as possible.
So I would spend about three hours a week marketing the game, and then about seven hours
doing development and getting the game ready for prime time.
Thank you.
Yeah, thank you.
Thank you for the insightful talk.
Thank you.
Did you maintain a personal Twitter and separate game Twitter, or one and the same?
What's your reasoning?
I didn't. I mean I had the same Twitter for both my game. I guess this guy gets into another
topic of like, I love, I love like seeing games as like
You know, we have game studio names, which is fine.
That's awesome.
But because it was a very personal story and a very
personal game, I wanted to be with my name on it.
Because it was my story, my voice acting.
Also with the help of several assets, which was really
amazing that these artists and programmers
let people license it.
But the story was written by me.
I think it's fine to have a separate Twitter.
especially if it's like your game studio and that future games will be coming out of it.
Because for me I expect that like my future games will still like be like personal stories
from me. That's what I want. If I was like creating a new studio with friends I'd probably do
something different. I keep that my personal one but yeah your mileage may vary of course.
Thank you. Thank you.
So your talk appealed a lot to me because I'm in the same boat, so thank you.
You're welcome.
I want to ask you about the music and how you found the music that you were interested in,
how you sort of like created the relationship with the actual musician
and what medium you used to find that specific music.
Sure. So Pond5, you know, as I come from a film editing background, so I'm very used to
finding stock music available to license on Pond5 and Musicbed and Audio Jungle.
There wasn't a personal connection at first.
That's kind of the funny part.
Josh Kramer, he had his library of music,
his gorgeous orchestral music,
and again, it was really affordable.
And so I was able to just find that,
and I was like, oh, I like everything he does.
I'm gonna buy all of his songs and put it in my game.
And then he reached out to me afterwards,
because he was like, oh, I'm seeing a lot of news articles
with this game with my music in it.
And I was like, is that okay with you?
He's like, of course.
Like, I put it on there to be licensed
in projects like this.
So specifically, I don't know, I just,
it's almost like meditative for me to like,
browse these asset libraries and just be like,
oh, would that work in my game?
Oh, would that work?
Oh, that sounds good.
So that's what I did.
I just went through Pond5,
and I also, I splurged on two songs from Musicbed,
which they do like, bigger artists,
and so two of the final songs in the game,
which were more expensive, is from Musicbed.
And I think it was worth it.
The music's such an important part
of a story-driven game like that.
So yeah, that's all I did.
I just looked around, Google searched.
All right, thanks so much.
Yeah, thank you.
If a game was going to have audio or voice acting,
do you think that the GIF, if that was a big part of it,
would the GIF still have the same amount of traction
opposed to screenshots, do you think?
Maybe, like, sometimes people would say online,
I'd say, oh, like I love that,
it looks like a desktop wallpaper,
I'm gonna save it to my computer,
and that works for a still screenshot.
I think the movement, it inspires imagination.
People say, we're talking about people
who are a built-in fan base,
people who love Journey and people who love Foxes.
They would see the game and be like,
oh, that looks like something I would like,
and they would market it for myself.
So yeah, I think still screenshots can still help you know,
give you an idea of, oh, does this project have legs?
Does it kinda gain traction?
Do we have time for one more question?
Okay, yeah, one more question.
Sorry, um, thanks for the talk, it was awesome. Um, you showed
both posts that like did really well as well as some ones that
didn't. Was there a key underlying, uh, kind of thing
that you saw of what made those posts not do as well as others?
I think being, in my personal opinion, I think being too vague, it hurt the post.
I think like, not like having a human connection was important.
I think that's a cool thing that indies have,
that a AAA company can't really do,
is you're like a friend next door making a game.
You're not a company with a PR department
trying to market a game.
And that gets people excited.
People put themselves in your shoes.
It's like, oh, he made a game.
That's my dream, is to make a game like he did.
And they kinda wanna celebrate with you, too.
And that's what happened, I noticed, was just...
Being human, I think saying, this is my dream,
because it was, to see my game on a Nintendo Switch.
And it got people excited, and they
wanted to celebrate with you.
So yeah, I would say the human connection is most important.
Thanks.
Thank you, everybody.
Appreciate it.