Oh, hello.
Oh, first thing, if somebody else is coming,
please sit in the middle, because I
think it's going to be pretty full.
So yeah, I'm going to be talking about my work at Supergiant
Games.
This is my first job in the industry, basically.
I've been there for five and a half years.
So basically, what I'm going to be showing
is some of the key elements during these five years,
what I consider is something important,
what I do every day at work.
A little bit about me.
I'm from Colombia.
I studied visual arts in Colombia, and I also did a master's in animation here in San Francisco.
I previously worked in video editing, motion graphics, 3D illustration, 3D animation.
As many of you, I think bringing characters to life is my passion, and then sort of exploring
their personality and how they deal with internal and external conflicts through design and
animation.
I think this part, like the animation, sorry, the design.
part of the process because I think it's like something that a lot of, especially a lot of animators, they tend to forget about those things very often.
Yeah, I joined Supergiant Games in 2012. That was my first, I was the first and only in-house 3D artist in the company.
I didn't have any previous experience in games, so basically I had to figure out like my workflow for every project and then figure out my schedule.
um, create my own rules for like the 3D production and also dealing with my self-doubt since I was
very new to the industry, I didn't know much and everybody in the company they have like
five to ten years experience and they were like already rock stars so I was like pretty intimidating
at the beginning. So basically I'm in charge of all the 3D path line from modeling to rendering.
At the beginning I worked with Greg Kassarin, he's the creative director, and Jen Seed, our director.
I tried to figure out with them the design of the character design and tried to figure out
what kind of elements we want to keep that are important for the story, but also what kind of
things we have to get rid of, because I don't want to deal with that many tiny details in the
character, so I kind of have to find a balance between what we can do in production and the
things that we can keep.
connected to the story, basically.
I do also some of the rigging.
Some of the rigging is done from scratch.
Some other ones, I use other rig tools.
It depends on what kind of character I'm gonna be doing.
The animation part, I work with Amir Rauf.
He's one of the designers and also the studio director.
This is a key part also for me
because since I didn't know anything about video games,
I learned a lot from Amir about game mechanics.
how to implement them and how to combine,
how actually every animation is gonna,
how they work together, like for example,
how all the attacks, they work together,
things like that.
So, and rendering.
Well, okay, first thing, modeling.
So, three things that I wanna emphasize in this talk
is like, first of all, character design mindset
to entire pipeline.
This is something that I'm always very,
aware of in the process, because actually when people,
sometimes when people ask me questions
about how I build the characters,
it's, oh, when somebody asks me for feedback in their work,
it's like, it's always, I go to the same point,
like, there are some principles that you,
a lot of people just tend to forget very easy.
Problem solving is your most valuable skill
when working in a small team,
because in my case, I was the,
I was pretty much the only one working in Maya,
so if I have a problem with Maya,
it's up to me to figure it out.
Also, since the project is secret,
so there is no way for me to ask somebody else.
I'm pretty much on my own in that sense.
Expand your skill sets in the interest
of expressing the character's personality.
I think I learned modeling, but that was like,
I was actually, that was not my major,
but something that I was curious to see
how I can actually improve the...
the appeal of the characters, how can I actually get them to look and to feel more real in
a sense.
So we have a 2D engine, so all the characters are rendered from multiple camera angles.
The modeling and rigging have a similar approach to TV or film, which is like we use high poly
models.
That means fewer technical problems for me in that sense.
Modeling part, as I was saying, like design, I started with a ZBrush exploration of the
modeling, like for the modeling.
In this part, there is still, even though I already get like a design concept for like
from the art director, I still trying to figure out how can we improve the design.
So I know, so like what kind of elements we want to emphasize in the isometric view, because
that's a totally different.
When you're thinking about the character,
it's a totally different beast.
Again, principles of character design,
it's all the way in straight versus curved
and contrast, rhythm,
and all those things are actually applied
in every part of the design,
like the arms, the legs, the head, everything.
This is early exploration for Pyre.
Again, I'm still thinking about all those things
in the character,
trying to facilitate the line of action,
the flow of the shapes.
What is the part of the center of attention in the character?
Like what kind of things I want to emphasize in the design and also like in this case
I'm hoping like this kind of shapes are actually showing more of the personality like for this one
It was like something that feels more elegant in that sense
So my part of my process is also I mean like once I receive the concept
I part of my process is actually to improve it in some way like try to figure out
So for some of the problems and why it's not working
Why it's not like a fully like something that we love exactly so I
here's that sketch that I received from the
from the art director and then
Kind of like she gave me an opportunity to actually sort of like explore
our design
options for the sword.
So I went and I just did a lot of tapering on the shape,
and then I added some real on the lower part of the sword.
So those kind of small elements, later on,
we start to improve.
But it's still my job to actually add
the original design.
Next thing is rigging.
This is super cliche, but I think
it's very important, at least for me,
since I'm not the only one working on this,
is to keep it simple.
Like, a lot of animators, they tend
to be intimidated by this process.
But as long as you have a basic understanding,
like the basic principles of rigging,
you can get to build pretty much anything you want.
And to me, some pen and paper planning,
actually going to try to figure out what I really need
and what kind of contours I really need.
So it's kind of like saved me a lot of time.
And then I get to realize that with very simple tools,
I get to build any kind of character.
Yeah, plenty of plugins out there for that.
So you need to explore the tools that you can find outside.
I still, in this process, I'm still, again, considering design principles, because I want
to make sure that some of those concepts are still applied in the character in animation.
So I need to figure out how many contours I'm going to have based on that.
If I want to get more straight and curves in the character, in the poses, the contrast,
rhythm, readability, personality, all those things are considered during the reading process.
I need to figure out how many contours I'm gonna have,
how many plane shapes I need to add
to the character and things like that.
Yeah, so basically also, again,
it's another thing that I need to keep in mind,
really, what kind of parts I want them to be.
The principle is something solid versus flexible.
That's something that I add in the character
to make sure that some parts are still very rigid,
but you have the freedom to,
there are parts to be more flexible.
The way that I approach this is basically
I break everything into models.
I think it's, for example, for this camera,
everything was built in three sections.
It was the main body, the platform, and the horn.
And then I worked individually in every piece.
That was, for me, very easy just to soften a rigging problem
without thinking about the whole thing, which
is kind of like, it can be very overwhelming.
So dividing it this way was way easier.
And later on, during production, the designers
decided they wanted the caravan to fly.
So in the same sense, because everything
was built this way, it was very easy for me
to add another model to the rig, and then just add wings.
And then later on, they wanted to be underwater.
So.
That was another option.
So it was like, by having everything breaking down this way,
it was way easier just for me to add and then to animate.
So some of those things, like for example,
for the caravan in Pyre, that was something
that I learned from working in Transistor,
which is basically all the same principles,
like once you break the rig into very simple models,
simple sections, like the eyebrows are just one section,
eyelids are another section.
the jaw is another section, so kind of like that,
this mindset kind of helped me to just do it again
and again in different rigs.
Like in this case, the other thing,
like it's a very small company.
So basically, sometimes if I want to try something,
like in this case, the facial rig,
it's pretty much like, I mean, it's up to me in many cases,
like I have the freedom to just explore whatever I want to
in the character, so.
in some point that there were like a period of time
I didn't have that much to do,
so I decided to figure out how to rig the face.
And then that's sort of like,
I've been using that for a while after that.
Next is animation.
So everything is,
basically everything is like between 60 to 64 camera angles.
And average is like 2,500 PNGs per animation.
Everything is rendered.
Like I just be ready for all the rendering.
All the lighting is attached to the camera.
So this is like the way that I
produce all the animations basically.
Yeah, the lighting is attached to the camera,
so basically the lighting is also rotating
around the character the whole time.
So some of the key lengths for.
For animating isometric, for me, it's like,
at least eight angles should communicate
the main idea of the animation.
So I start with the basic eight angles
that the character's gonna be in.
And I draw in the viewport in those eight angles
to figure out the shape.
This is super, this is one of the key things for me
because every time that I'm not actually animating.
And I'm stuck, because I feel like it doesn't look as good
as I was expecting it to be.
I just go back and I draw over that,
and that's completely different.
You immediately see a difference between what you were thinking
and when you actually draw on the viewport.
Yeah, so in this process, I'm still
continuing adjusting the main angles,
like line of action, tilt, twist, flow, shapes,
all those things.
There is still color adjustment that
are happening in this process because at this point,
we're starting to see a character in the isometric
and in the game, combined with all the other assets,
the environment.
So we need to adjust it.
I work with the art director to figure out
how can we improve the color in the character.
And the last part of this process, to me,
is adding a lot of in-between blend shapes.
So I use a tool that is called Shapes for Maya.
It's been very useful for me
because I like it to do like corrective blend shapes
and sometimes like actually,
and I get to animate between them
and blend them doing that process.
So,
it's sort of like, because my rigging is still,
sometimes in the rigging process is not enough
but you have the shape that you can get.
This is the last step in the process where I go
and actually polish the silhouette more.
Polish the shape that I want more.
Performance, this is another part.
Since we are doing RPGs, there are moments in the story
where we need very specific animations
that follow the story.
The way that I work on this is I break down the main ideas
of the animation.
Those main ideas define how much it's going
to take me to produce them.
Of course, I need to answer all the questions about what
is the character emotional state, where
is the character coming from, and how much time do
I have to animate those things.
So based on that, I need to find a balance between what I can
do in the time that I have.
Yeah, OK.
Another key thing for me, like working at Supergiant Games,
I think I'm working with designers.
I start to use locators a lot.
That was something that I learned way before,
but I never actually got to implement it.
Like in every animation that I do now,
there is at least one or two locators.
Because this is the way that I can actually work,
like figure out the timing for the animations very quick.
And then also, I just the timing, work with the designers,
see if it's working, see if it's like combined
with other animations is working well.
And then after that, I can actually go and animate
the rest of the body.
So that way, like I'm not spending a huge amount of time
animating the whole character.
I just like animating like simple locators.
And then I define like the, I just add like a box.
I parent them to a box so I can sort of get a sense of the volume.
That's enough for me to actually work to show the designers basically.
So yeah, okay, so basically in this case there is one locator that is sort of defining the translation and the character.
Translation in Y and then there is another one for the rotation
and then there is a third one for the translation in C of the main character.
That's happened from the beginning, like at the beginning I was just exploring just with one simple locator, then I add like another one.
Still I was not happy with the result, so I add the third one, move the character and start to change the position of the character.
So that was like pretty useful.
See if I want to, in this case, if I want to, for some reason the designer want me to, they want the character to jump even higher,
it was very, very simple for me to just adjust that, like very quick.
Similar idea here, this is a main locator
that is actually driving the main animation.
And then there's another one for the character going down.
I'm gonna show you another one.
This is a, like, this is a, in Transistor,
this is what, like, one of the key elements,
like, I was using the locator just to drive the sword.
The sword was so big that it was the main thing that when you see an isometric,
you are like the main thing that you're going to see.
So to me, I was like the most important for the designers.
Also very important that you get like.
You get to read what is happening with the sword from the beginning.
So this is what I what we render and we tested in the game.
And after that, I just go and animate the rest of the body.
Some cases.
It's fine because in some cases I didn't even know what it was going to do.
I just knew exactly what we wanted the sword to do and then based on that I have to figure
out the rest.
So it's like an inverse process in this case, which works really well because the designers
just get an idea of what is going to happen in that animation way before I animate anything
else.
So yeah, I keep with the locators,
it kind of helps me to keep everything very clean.
Like here's an example of one of the locators,
like this is figuring out when the character is going down
and then also the hips are like the intersection
and then you can see how here,
all I transfer everything to the locators
and also the rotation of the character is one,
it's based on one locator and then the hips are like,
I add extra small details to what I want the character to do.
That was like.
During part, that was very important,
because the timing of those locators,
actually, I just reused them for every other animation.
Since everything here has to be synced with the effects,
with all the elements that designers are doing,
so the timing has to be very specific.
So to make sure that we don't waste a lot of time
like trying to adjust the timing
to a very specific animation,
it was very serious to me to replace the character.
the time is already there, so it was very easy to just add
a new character to those locators.
So OK, so yeah, that's part of the process for me
is rendering.
We have a render farm in the office.
Everything is exported in EXR format.
multi channels. I combine all those layers in After Effects and also the shadows are
baked into the final render. Canvas size is between 300 by 300, 1024 by 1024. It takes
like three to seven hours of rendering per animation. That's something I need to be aware
when I'm working because I have to wait like three hours to see an animation actually working
in the game. So I usually have like...
Plenty of other animations at the same time that I'm doing,
because I have to wait for rendering time.
This is the last part of the process.
After that, so I still, after that,
so basically we need to, we are trying to also,
as part of my job, we are also trying to figure out
what kind of merchandise we can do for the fans.
So.
like this is like the art direction that I go in this in this project was to make it look like candy that was like
the main concept
and then based on that I still have to keep all those ideas that we had in the original design like all
all those shapes and how they combine
if you have everything very like it's still very clear, so it's very
It should be very easy just to translate those to something new
Yeah, this is another example of all the things that I do when we are not working in any game at all.
Things that we do for PAX.
I'm still exploring, like 3D printing, see how the characters look, like a real figure, things like that.
This is, yeah, so again, I think when you are working with external contractors,
I think it's very important that you are very specific about...
about the design because a lot of, probably 80% of the time,
they will do something different.
So the more information you give them, the better.
So they actually don't let them come up
with some interpretations of what they think it is.
Because it's usually, I mean, it took a long time
to figure this out, so you try to make sure
that it stills be true to the.
to the game.
Last thing I want to mention here, I think it's like, I think it's important that you
still have a point of view of what you do, because I think for me at least, when I got
hired to design games, I didn't have any experience in games, and I actually didn't have any proof
of previous work, but I think what I feel the main reason
for them to hire me was because I have like a very specific voice in the work that I was doing.
So even though I didn't have anything, I didn't understand at all how to make a game basically.
So yeah, I think and basically you still need to have a specific point of view what you do,
but also work with the constraints of the of the product because it's still at the end.
Even though it's a very small team, you are still part of a group of people and we are
trying, all of us, we are trying to push a specific idea.
So like right now, actually right now we are looking for a 3D artist in the company and
then one of the things that I'm considering a lot is like somebody that can actually understand
drawing very well because that's, even though the modeling part is not really good, but
if they actually understand.
if you can see in the drawing and you can see how they interpreted those shapes in drawing
and then you can tell that, I mean you can see how they are the way they are thinking
so it's very easy for if they are not really good at ZBrush but they get the idea so it's
very easy just to translate that into 3D layer, just a matter of time.
Things that I like also I want to mention like
Took me a while while working on Supergiant, I think it took me like two years to actually understand like that.
Other parts of your life are actually affecting the quality of your work.
So
You have to deal with all the stuff like apart from like life that for some reason
Yeah, it's not working.
I'm very careful about not having crutch time, like I haven't had any crutch time in five and a half years at Supergiant Games.
I, at 6 p.m., I leave the office,
and no matter what happens.
I have worked remotely from five different countries.
I think the company is very small, it's very flexible.
The rules are very flexible, so you are,
it's give me a free one to actually go and travel,
and still do my work from any place.
I'm actually also working on other art projects
and exhibitions, toy design, video, photography.
And I'm still taking classes.
Because it's already like five and a half years,
but still there's a lot of things that I need to improve.
So the main things for me to do,
that I want to emphasize, of course,
was character design mindset to entire pipeline.
So I need to be aware in the whole process.
And keep that always in mind in the entire production.
Problem solving is your most valuable skill.
This is going to show every time at work, like every week,
there is something that you need to figure out in the time.
Usually, it's usually Maya with some crash or something.
Seek opportunities to expand your skill set.
I think it's also, I see a lot of people that get stuck
in being an animator, and then they
don't try to explore any other options.
And then I see there's a lot of companies now,
they just hire people for like a specific task.
So I think it's expanding those skills,
it's always like valuable for the team,
valuable for the way that you work with other people.
So I think it's important to just like,
it's something that you can try on your own,
like from time to time, so it's not,
so you are not getting stuck in just animating.
And it's all in the interest
of expressing the character's personality.
So, yeah.
That's it.
APPLAUSE
Yeah. Any questions?
Questions?
Is this working?
So you were saying about the render time thing.
I was just curious.
But you also showed more pre-busy thing where, hey,
it's just the sword moving.
I assume that doing a render with just the one element
moving, whatever, you could test that in game quicker than three
hours or whatever the timing was.
Yeah.
Yeah, you still have to render it.
But basically, it's quicker because I
don't have to animate the rest of the body.
So I can do that in like probably 10 minutes,
render that, and then show it to the designers.
And then from that, we decided to give the time,
and it's right.
And after that, I go and I do the animation,
which the animation will take like a day or two or three,
whatever it takes.
Yeah.
Just if I could have one more question as well.
You seem to essentially own the
Entire pipeline and I'm curious because there's a there's another person at the studio who's the like arts director. Is that correct?
yeah, so how does the
How do the two of you work together because you have like such an incredible fine-grained control over the end
product presumably you you guys must have to have a
Very good working relationship because she's it's I don't know who is but
Yeah, it's like you are this single focused point through which everything is getting put on screen.
Wait, again, it's about how I work with like...
Yeah, yeah, how does that relationship work, like making these games?
Because it's unusual for someone to so entirely own the pipeline.
Well, it's... I think...
It's...
I don't even know how to put it, because I think it's like, it's...
It's been a while.
At the beginning, it was like,
we get, I just like to understand what the 2D is,
like the concept, like the art director,
what she was doing and the style.
So I need to like, I still need to like think about that,
but like in some point,
we know each other very well.
So it's very easy just for us to,
I got, I'm already guessing what she's gonna say.
And she's already guessing what I'm gonna say.
So kind of like at this point,
it's
We don't need to communicate that much about that kind of stuff because we already know
what is going to happen more or less.
If that makes sense.
Thank you.
That's great.
Hi.
You were saying you're from Colombia?
Yeah.
I'm from Latin America too.
Many of the shapes and color choices and way to stylize some of the characters ring very
familiar.
from Colombia that bleeds through the project,
like that ends up being part of like your work?
There is, I mean,
there is some characters actually,
I don't have them here,
but like there is some characters actually there.
I actually did them dancing on salsa.
It's, but yeah, so from time to time,
there's stuff like that that I do.
Yeah, definitely.
Oh yeah?
Yeah.
Oh, okay.
We're good.
Is it cool if I ask a question?
We're just confirming.
We want really quick.
One more.
Yeah.
So what kind of training resources would you recommend to artists because the part
where you were emphasizing improving your skills really resonates to me as a professional
in the industry.
Well, I...
I take classes everywhere, but I think it's like I'm always trying to figure out, I try
to find the right teachers because that's like the key element.
Sometimes you find a good class, but it's probably not, I mean you have to find the
right mentors basically.
So you have to find and then which ones are the kind of people that you want to learn
from.
So I don't have like a specific resources that I will suggest.
You need to explore.
depends on animation, it's always different.
But like, rigging is also different.
Like, some of the rigging that I learned
was from a guy from Naughty Dog,
was a really amazing teacher.
But like, there is also, I mean,
it's always like different places, so.
And then you have to be very open, like sometimes,
like some of the classes that I take,
they are like, terrible.
But it happens, but you stay, I mean,
you always find something out there, but yeah.
Okay, so trial and error.
Yeah, pretty much.
Are you going online or in person typically?
Yeah.
Okay, thanks.