Hi everyone, welcome to Designing for AR, a post-mortem on the development of World.
So before I get started, I want to introduce you to myself, what World is, and possibly
what AR is for those who are unfamiliar.
So my name is Vu, I'm a software engineer at Phenomena, I work on World and Wattam.
Before that I was a software engineer at Maxis for three years, I worked on The Sim City
that came out in 2013, and a bunch of other gameplay prototypes that you probably won't
see the light of day.
Before that I worked on an AR game called Nerd Herder where you try to get office workers
back into their cubicles. You can kind of see it there. And even before that I worked on a
Rock'em Sock'em AR game that was shown at the release of the V4ia SDK back in 2010.
Let's clarify some things about this talk. It's not going to be a technical talk where I'm
going to show code or anything like that. It's going to be more about the lessons that we
learned and the techniques that worked for us in the development world. So what is
augmented reality? I'm sure a lot of you guys know, otherwise you wouldn't be here, but I'm
going to clarify just for those that might not.
In general, I like to think that augmented reality is like the layering of virtual content
onto the real world versus VR where it's more like immersing yourself into another world,
taking you out of this reality. Some of the examples of AR that you might have used in
your current day-to-day could be like Pokemon Go or Snapchat lenses or the line of
scrimmage visualization in football. Just probably one of the most common versions. So
what is world?
World is a whimsical AR game designed by Kira Takahashi. He's well known for games like
Katamari Damacy and Nobby Nobby Boy. It took about three to four months to develop and a
small team of about five people, an animator, a designer, producer and audio designer and
engineer myself. World is built on Unity using Tango as the augmented reality platform. Here's
a video of World to get you guys to have a better understanding of what it is.
Hello, I'm Takahashi.
Today, I'll be showing you an AR game called World.
At first glance, it looks like nothing much,
but if you play through World and Mob2Pro,
you'll see that this world is spread out.
This is the protagonist of the game.
And to teach this girl the shape of the air,
I'll be mapping it.
The wall with the ? mark is green.
If the game becomes a rain pattern, mapping is success.
After mapping, the game starts.
Place the eyes on the table.
And let the rain fall from the clouds hanging in the sky.
Let the flowers bloom.
When the flowers bloom, a new item is obtained, and the next development begins from that item.
Once you reach a certain goal, the sandbox mode will be unlocked.
It's possible to do anything with this game.
It's crazy.
I hope that gave you an idea of how weird and silly this game
is. Okay. So let's move on to what is Tango. What is Tango?
So Tangimo is Google's augmented reality platform that helps you
do AR without the use of markers or GPS or anything like that.
It uses an infrared technology similar to like Kinect or
HoloLens to scan the environment and let you do what you see
here, kind of imagining surfaces rather than discrete images.
There's two devices that support Tango right now. The Tango dev kit is one of them and the
Fab 2 Pro by Lenovo that just came out this week for consumer purchase. They're both
Android-based devices. You hold them in your hands. They're basically normal phones. That
means you have a touch screen. So that gives us interactions unlike HoloLens or Magic Leap
where you have to do gestures or have some kind of controller.
When you start designing for Tango in general and AR in general, there are some
constraints you should think about, such as the player having full control of the
camera. A lot of people when they get it, they'll just stand there and look at the
floor, for example, because they don't know what to do. They've never experienced it
before.
So unlike normal games where they have, the developer has
control of like the ability to show cut scenes or animations,
you can't really. You have to introduce players to look at
things and find ways to get them to pay attention to what you
really want them to pay attention to. I'm going to guide
you guys through some of the techniques that we used and that
worked for us.
The next thing that you should consider is the environment itself. So unlike traditional VR
games, traditional games and VR games, the content isn't completely authored. To make a
really good AR game, you want to use the environment around you directly. Tango is
capable of mapping everything, including the ceilings, the walls, chairs, tables, whatever.
So you don't have any control. Someone could play in a messy room like that.
I'll be talking about some visualizations and ways to use the environment to give a
more meaningful AR experience.
In addition to camera controls and environments, you have to
deal with the regular limitations of Android devices
and mobile devices today. That means worrying about
performance from physics, straw calls and things like that. But
also thinking about how the tracking algorithms and
scanning algorithms, meshing algorithms affect the total
performance of your application.
You have to think about heat and battery also since this is a handheld device. This is
someone's daily phone potentially. So if you drain their battery in like five seconds,
they're not going to play your app ever again. You also have to think about comfort. These
current devices are pretty big. Imagine a phablet. That's bigger than an iPhone 7 plus
today. And they're heavy. So let's first talk about player attention. So the first thing
In world there's a story mode that we made that players have
to do specific actions and look at specific things or go to
specific places to advance through the story. So I'm going
to give you guys some of the techniques that we use. I break
them up into two categories. One is direct techniques or methods
where they're independent of where the player is looking. The
other is indirect techniques where it kind of helps guide the
player's view to what you want them to see.
The first technique is just displaying UI on the screen.
Since we have a screen and people are already used to
looking at it, you have that ability to just show flat UI.
We try to make it more effective by showing animations
as to grab players' attention.
In this case, we have the menu person, which is actually like
a character that talks to you.
It kind of catches people off guard, and so people pay
attention to it more.
The second method we use is attaching objects to the camera. So here we have our character
called person. He's attached to the camera and giving instructions to teach people how to
scan a room for the first time. And we found this to be much more engaging than just like
showing a text prompt. People like really respond to the character's requests.
The next method is camera tracking. So we have objects that fly around and try to stay in
front of the camera within view. In this case, we have a rocket character that once you
unlock him, he flies to the camera and delivers you some meaningful dialogue about what to do
next in the story. In general, these methods are used to convey really important
information about how to even use Tango and devices and also advance the storyline.
The next set of methods are indirect methods.
The first one we use is teleportation into view,
where as the player is doing an action,
we teleport our main character next to that action
within view so that they get the proper feedback they need.
Okay.
Next we also use the movement of characters to guide players. We found in our play test that
people really like to look at this little guy and just follow him everywhere, like watch him
climb walls and things like that. So we use this advantage to spawn, meaning like the next
steps nearby. This allowed people to kind of organically discover their space instead of just
being told exactly where to go. Okay. Finally we have...
VFX trails. And this is kind of interesting because since the viewport is so small you have to
guide the player to look at other things within that viewport. So they could be looking at this
flower, for example, and do an action. In this case, we have the cloud that they've placed
earlier produce these raindrops, which actually causes them to look up and remember that they
put the cloud there in the first place. So here's an example of all the techniques in
combination. So here's an example of all the techniques in combination. So here's an
At first, I'll let this repeat. The player is guided to this rocket by the character walking
to it. When he uses the rocket, it teleports the character so that the action is really
meaningful and they know something is about to happen. And then we use a VFX trail to help
people see the results of their actions and then move on to the next steps.
In addition to this we use a visual metaphor to show points of interest. Like these
question mark textures appear on anything that has interesting interactions that they haven't
used before or forgot about to help remind them that these are interesting things that they
could check out again.
So now that people are looking at the things you want them to look at, we have to teach them
how to interact with those objects in real, in 3D space. The first thing we have is tapping.
Since we have a touch screen, tapping is a natural interaction that people already
understand. So a lot of objects have unique behaviors such as breaking a rock to reveal a
new item. Or maybe they'll play a sound or let you nudge them around the physics in the world.
We also have touch and drag which lets you move objects
around really intuitively. You can just touch it and drag it.
It's this immediate response that's really effective to get
people to see the virtual space that you've created for them.
Okay. And then we also have, you know, we have a lot of
These magic hands that we tried early on that kind of act as indirect placement mechanisms. So
you grab something by tapping on the hand and then you tap the hand again to place it down
in the world. We decided not to use this in the end because it was kind of confusing for people
that are used to touch and drag. They're not used to controller based games and things like
that. We also have these grow and shrink rays. We wanted to explore like, you know,
different mechanisms for interacting with objects. These rays let you grow and shrink
things arbitrarily. It's super fun to do, just seeing a giant pyramid in your room. And then we
also have this context menu that lets people easily discover new abilities and items and
helped us design items so that you can have super unique behaviors and multiple behaviors.
Okay. So let's look at some environmental interactions. When you're doing an AR game, you
don't want the environment to just be static. You don't want them to just float a Pokemon in
space and have them not interact with the world in any way.
So, and also you want them to show like you're using the space in a meaningful way. So one of
the things we did is programmatically spawn objects into the world. One of the techniques we
use is relative placement to the camera. A lot of, since we know where the camera is and what
you're looking at and we also have a good idea that you're looking at the person or something
nearby, we can spawn another object using a ray cast from the camera into the nearby location.
This kind of ensures that the player is able to see this object.
This image did not load.
So OK, hold on.
I'm going to restart the.
OK, so this is using relative placement.
So instead of using a ray cast from the camera, we're using
a ray cast from an object that the player recently placed
into the world.
We know that this is a valid location, since
they just did it.
And the only way to actively play something is to put it on
a valid surface.
Where's my mouse?
Okay, next we have placement smoothing.
So normally if you just scan an environment,
it's super bumpy, super noisy in many cases.
If you just only use one recast,
you get this kind of jittered movement
where the object's orienting all over the place.
So here on the bottom, we're using a multi-sampling technique
where we're casting a ray from the center
and also like four rays at the perimeter
to average out a better position for the objects.
Okay. We also wanted to let the player feel like they're embodied in the space. Here we've
attached a collider to the camera allowing players to push away physical objects such as
the cloud. This also illustrates presence by having the house open up as you get closer and
all the flowers actually turn to look at you wherever you are.
So we also wanted the player to feel like it's really easy to hold the game, hold the device
and play the game. So one of the things we wanted to do was make sure that any orientation
worked. So you could play it in portrait or landscape. And beyond that, we also wanted to
teach players how to actually interact with AR in general and how to interact with our game.
At first we had all the interactions available with simple text prompts to show what did
what.
This was super confusing for people and also paralyzing.
They just didn't know what to do because there's so much.
So instead we made a staggered tutorial.
And I'm going to walk briefly through what we did.
Why isn't it loading?
I'm going to open up a different slide show.
Okay.
So here we introduce the player to room scanning. We use a
texture that shows question marks to kind of show where
they haven't been and a grid to show where they have been and
scanned. This is super effective because people really like to
try to get rid of all of the question marks. We also use
this percentage to give an idea of like you've scanned enough
so you're ready to play.
In addition to this, we also did a first time user experience for people that have never
tried AR and this is the first time they've opened the app where a person comes out and
talks to you. I believe I showed an image earlier. Next we teach object placement. So we
intentionally give the player only one object at the bottom of their menu and show a drag
indicator to help them understand that they can touch and drag this and put it in their
world. When they do it, we immediately instantiate it and it follows their finger around.
You can see here. Next we also teach players that it's safe and okay to move around. So we
first try to get the player to move by just showing a cute animation of the character
popping out and enticing you to come closer. But a lot of people don't move. They're totally
paralyzed. They don't know that they can move for some reason. So we show the move closer
pop up and that tends to always get them to move.
Next we show tapping as a common interaction. This unlocks their first object which is the
cloud and then we teach them that it's okay to drag things to any surface. So part of the
tutorial is we have them drag the cloud to the ceiling and this really opens up their world to
more than just playing on the floor.
And then at that point they have almost all they need to know except the context menu
where we teach them to use it to grow the sprout. So they tap the sprout, press the rain icon,
and then see for the first time particles raining on the sprout. And it's a really nice moment.
Okay. So... I'm running out of time, but I'm almost there.
Okay. So there's, we wanted a really flexible game play. Tango is kind of iffy sometimes when
you're scanning. It can be really noisy. It might miss areas and make holes in the mesh.
And then objects can be lost all the time. So we wanted super flexible and easy to approach
game play. So first there's no loose condition. There's no wrong way to play. You can place
anything anywhere. Next is...
Auto saving, so if you accidentally close your app or
something like that, we do an auto save so you can easily
recover. Then object recovery, so we have a mechanism for say
if you lost an object behind a wall somehow, you can easily
bring it back in front of you and then place it again in the
world. And then we have a sandbox mode that's completely
free and lets people explore AR for whatever they want to do.
Virtual spaces, so this is early rendering of our space. We
wanted to see if we could do something.
where we generated a virtual land. This really destroys the
effect of AR. This is much more VR. So here's the same image
with our current technique. We use a triplanar texture shader
and so we shade different materials based on the surface
of the mesh. Here we
During game play we only render a small radius around your cursor and around the player so
that it's not so noisy when you play. We're also dynamically continuously meshing so you can
actually expand your play space as you play. We also experimented with some subtraction
techniques. So here you can see this hole is actually looks like it's cutting into the
world. And here's a more extreme example where we have this huge cavernous space in the
ceiling.
Next we also experimented with tinting the image itself to give this global lighting change
effect which is really surprising to a lot of people. And further enhance the feel of the
world. We make sure the 3D cursor orients properly and also when you tap it shows an effect
where it needs to be. Do you want to take a picture?
And also, using the visual aesthetic that Kata designed,
it's very simple and stylized,
so it's really easy to accept this unrealistic movement
of this character climbing walls
and just going up surfaces.
We also tried to do a lot of physicality
to really drive in the fact that this is in your real world.
So here we have a cloud on a spring that reacts
as if you expect it, the same way you expect it to.
And we have some basic buoyancy simulation
to further enhance this feel.
One thing we discovered pretty late was thinking about object
permanence. So in an AR game, you kind of want things to
include virtual objects to make them feel more like they're
actually in the space. But this is adverse to gameplay because
players will lose the objects they place. They forget where
they put it. So we did this silhouette rendering to help
them find things. All right.
So one of the technical limitations of Tango was saving
and loading. They wanted us to use their area description file
to save an area but instead it didn't really give much feedback
that it was working and when it did work it just happened or
not. There's no percentage or anything like that. So we came
up with this technique where we take an image of the place that
you're playing and then we do an edge detection algorithm to let
the player self-align their world back in place. And this was
actually really effective and people found it to be kind of
fun.
So quickly go over some optimization techniques for just mobile and Unity in general.
So make sure you're doing pretty low poly.
This has just the same limitations of any 3D game on mobile.
Low poly share shaders and materials.
Also try to batch objects to reduce rendering.
And also, the newer devices have extremely high resolution, so we're actually rendering the
game in a much smaller resolution and upscaling it to gain a lot of performance. So in Unity, we
had issues with our load times. It used to take like 12, 10 seconds. And we discovered that if
you set your audio to asynchronously load, it's much, much faster.
You can also crunch textures to reduce your APK size.
This really helped us.
And then Atlas sprites to get tons of draw callback, like a lot of games might not do
this for, because it's not completely obvious and automatic.
And also use physics layers.
These are, these will help you filter out the hits you want and also improve performance
significantly.
Okay. One thing in Unity, you can also modify it really well to kind of simulate real world
scanning, different orientations and we even added like a debug console that lets you change
languages and clear meshes and things like that. It might be useful for you in iteration time
and things like that. So you basically can play the entire game in the editor.
And also, don't forget about localization.
This is something we kind of left to the end,
but luckily we found a really good package on Asset Store
to help us with this.
All right.
So some of the final takeaways.
Just remember, be aware of the player's presence
and what they're looking at, and the techniques
that I just talked about to guide them to see what you
want them to see.
And then also be very adaptive to the environment. You're not going to know where your
player is going to play. They could be in a bathroom, they could be in a plane. And whatever
you're doing needs to work anywhere basically. And also remember to test. You don't know
what's working until you give it to someone that's brand new to this technology and have
never played your game before. You're always so close to it that you understand it
intuitively but other people will not.
And that's it. Do you guys have any questions?
APPLAUSE
The first slide? Okay. Oops, what?
Oh no, I have to go all the way. The unity one or the mobile one? Okay. So I'm going to
So Atlas Sprites is like combining all your 2D textures into one large texture to make it so it
can do basically all your UI rendering in one draw call. Yes?
So it's not super precise, but since the game is so adaptable
and we do a rescan anyways, the objects usually landed close
to where you originally put them.
And so because of our game's design, it was OK.
But it also allowed you to just place things arbitrarily.
So you could go load in a different room if you wanted
to. Yes?
Yeah, I have a question.
When you are developing in Unity.
Do you need to have a webcam and scan every time or do you have a pre-generated?
So what we did was create a dynamic mesh that was procedurally generated within the editor
and so you could walk around and do things within the editor.
So we simulated a real room instead of using a webcam or anything like that.
This isn't like Vuforia where that would work.
This uses different technology that emits infrared rays to scan the room.
Yeah, well, I mean, so you need to have something pre-generated.
And how do you do that in Unity?
Is part of your game, or?
We did it procedurally.
But you could pull in a different model
and have that be on, say, a different layer or something
like that.
We're not using exactly the tech when we're doing it in Unity.
We're simulating an approximation.
Yeah.
My final question is, when you load the scene,
do you have to be on the same room?
Or what happens if you are in a very, very different room?
So like I said, since we're using not the area description
file, you can just arbitrary load anywhere. It won't align
perfectly, but it will let you have those objects again. No
problem. When you load into a new scene, do you follow the
physics of the room so that things will fall onto the ground
right.
Yeah, so...
I'm not sure if this picture really showed it, but if you did have clouds and things, these
would rise again if they were in the balloon mode or if you had balls, then they would fall
into the water and things like that. So everything, I save out the physics forces and
everything too. So they just kind of restore. What middleware did you use other than
Unity and the standard stuff that comes with it?
I only really use lean tween and a lean tween for a lot of these UI animations and I2
localization for our localization support. It has integration of Google docs and Google
sheets. Everything else is custom. We even wrote our own audio system because WI wasn't
working on the devices at the time.
Even the UI orientation stuff is custom because we wanted certain elements to stay in place and
didn't want the hardware to handle it. I think we're almost out of time. I don't know. I guess
that's it.