Hi everyone, welcome to the GDC Twitch channel.
My name is Brian Francis, the invisible voice inside your head, here as always talking about
interesting games and how they get made with the people who make them.
We are here today playing a game called Overland, though we aren't exactly playing it, unfortunately.
I have to give two disclaimers up front.
One, the footage you're looking at is pre-recorded.
Um, and the other disclaimer is that, uh, I need to give a trigger warning for today's episode slightly,
in that we are, uh, going to be discussing and looking at footage of, uh, not real footage,
it's game footage, but like the footage of animals dying in this game.
The only reason I give that warning is that that was pretty...
In the lower left hand corner of the screen is Adam Saltzman of FingyCo.
Is it Fingy or FingyCo or Fingy Company?
Usually just Fingy because of squatted accounts and things.
We have a lot of online identities that are FingyCo.
But, uh, yeah, just Fingy's fine.
Yeah, so the first important thing we have to talk about, this dog's name is Potato,
and it has put on a hat.
That's the first important thing to discuss.
The second thing to discuss is Overland, uh, the actual game.
Overland is a, uh, turn-based strategy game, uh, kind of looks a little, it reminds me of XCOM
when I look at it, because there's aliens and humans, but the vibe is very much more,
uh, Walking Dead in that.
The world is bleak, the monsters are scary, you are not an amazing alien killer, you are a bunch of fleshy humans and dogs trying to survive, and you are on a road trip across America trying to make it to the West Coast.
You're going to see two runs here today from our gameplay yesterday.
They are really, I think they're really good explanations of what...
So Adam, that's going to bring me to my first question for you.
I saw Rebecca Saltzman talk at GDC this year where she talked about what the first versions of Overland looked like.
What was the first inspiration that you thought, me and my team can make Overland and we can sell this game?
What was kind of the first thing that you were thinking about when that thought crossed your mind?
Oh boy. I mean, it was, I think it was a, uh,
it was a very different scope of game when we started thinking about it, uh,
for sure. But, um, you know,
I think it was my initial inspiration mostly came from,
um, other games. I usually, uh, I like,
usually think kind of in terms of screenshots first, which is kind of a weird.
process maybe, but like it helps me a lot like to be able to sort of imagine what a game might look like and then I
Try to get a sense of like, oh would that be kind of like fun to play? I don't know
Uh, and I was i'm definitely playing a lot of x-com at the time. We started working on this game like six years ago
um, so the um
That first kind of big x-com reboot from pharaxis, uh had just come out and I was playing a lot of that
on prohibitively difficult settings and game-overing a lot.
And I was also playing a lot of...
And I still play a lot of Michael Bro's mobile games.
And at the time, I was playing a lot of a particular one called 868 Hack,
which is this just very elegant kind of...
I guess procedural puzzle game, sort of a rogue-like, sort of a dungeon crawl, but kind of abstract.
But basically, an 868 level is kind of a turn-based, move-through-the-level, zap some guys, collect some treasure kind of experience.
Maybe presented a little abstractly, but it all plays out on this teeny tiny space.
I think it's like a 6x6 grid or something like that.
And it's just...
elegant and compelling and beautiful and interesting and it was I felt like it was getting at a lot of the
kind of
Things that were exciting about XCOM a lot of the things that are exciting about XCOM for me
But it was getting at them in this very
compact
kind of package or presentation. Like literally compact. Like in XCOM you might, which is a game
that just to be clear I adore, you know the first 20-25 minutes of a level sometimes are just this
very very careful anticipatory exploration period and then you start making life or death decisions.
And
That's sort of a maybe unfair generalization, but 868-HACK, like the first time you swipe the screen and move your little computer chip or whatever,
that was a life-or-death decision. And then whether to move left or up next is a life-or-death decision, essentially.
It's got that kind of like... like it's been really, really boiled down.
And I think maybe not in terms of trying to replicate...
other strategy experiences, but that's just kind of the shape the game took and so it's interesting to play like a like a bigger
More maximalist more spread out kind of turn-based strategy game at the same time is like a very very compact
abstract strategy game
both of which had generative elements
both of which were these turn-based games with these big trade-offs for short-term decisions versus long-term decisions and
That kind of thing.
And so yeah, the very first versions of this were just kind of me thinking about,
trying to think about like, you know, if you mash these things up, like what do you end up with?
And the original sort of doodle of like what a screenshot of this game might look like is a very
like, thinking about like old John Carpenter movies and like a handful of iconic characters
out in the middle of nowhere at night.
Trying to get some gas and get back in their car.
Which is what's happening right now.
That's pretty much what's going on right here.
That part of the game has carried through since about week one.
A long, long, long, long, long, long, long time ago.
But that was the piece of it that was really interesting to me.
It was like, okay, what if...
A lot of things fell out of that.
It was like, oh, if it's this teeny, teeny, tiny board
and everybody on the board has superpowers
that's going to be kind of weird.
And also, you know, I tend to like science fiction stories that are less about some kind of
super-powered hero character and more about kind of average people trying to deal with
very unaverage things. And yeah, and sort of a lot of different little bits and pieces
kind of like grew out of that. A lot of the games that I have made historically are
Not games where you're a very powerful person and they are often not games where you are fighting to
beat something but maybe like running away from something and I think
a lot of those interests kind of carried over into earlier versions of the game as well
where it became more about like almost these little like nighttime heists like get out of the
car and steal these valuables before the creatures get you and jump back in the car and drive away
kind of a feel.
As opposed to like a, you know, go in guns blazing and kick all the aliens butts and wear their skulls for hats and collect their alien guts for treasure or whatever.
Even though I enjoy playing those kinds of games.
Right on.
It's worth then before digging into my other questions asking about, I mean, just to ask
how Overland evolved is to ask how have you spent the last three, four, five years of
your life?
Because I saw this thing at IndieCade in 2015, 20-ish?
I forget when.
I forget exactly when.
Whoops.
Sorry.
Uh oh.
I'm good. I'm good.
Oh boy, we're about to watch a very rough first couple of levels here.
That's good news.
So if I'm going to ask how this game evolved, I'll ask you for a compact version from that initial vision of
compact XCOM, of elegant XCOM, kind of fear-based running away.
What did the development process bring out of that initial design that wasn't there before?
I think probably the main thing was bringing in a bunch of collaborators
who I think have kind of more interesting ideas than I do
and sort of bringing them to bear on this thing
and seeing where that went after that.
So I think the...
While there are aspects of the original prototype that probably would be recognizable in this game,
the small group of people, limited inventory, limited actions, every choice is pretty important,
even if it's not life or death. And, you know, grab the fuel, get back in the car,
let's get out of here. Like a lot of that focus has stayed intact, but a lot of the things that
have changed have been like, you know, what is the actual mood?
of the game and what does the actual game look like and why and you know how do you go about trying to
um like one thing that you run into if you're trying to make kind of a a a dense game you know
a game where you have a lot of interesting complicated choices but they all exist in a
small space is you get these kind of like information problems like how many hit points
does that thing have and what's going to happen if i do this and
What are my options with this character now?
And a huge amount of time was spent trying to figure out
what we wanted to do with that and what made sense for this game.
There aren't a lot of games that are squad-based,
where each character has their own inventory, for example.
And in retrospect, it seems like,
oh, maybe there's a reason that people were avoiding that.
It's really hard to do well.
And so, like, a lot of iteration and...
development time went into trying to figure out how to
just kind of like help people, especially people who maybe don't play a ton of strategy games,
to roughly have an idea of what's going on right now and what's at stake.
So like the idea that, you know, someone who maybe isn't an expert level Final Fantasy tactics player
could see this screenshot that's right here and go like...
Oh boy, that dog is surrounded by scary looking things,
and the road is blocked, and the car is damaged now.
And that's probably bad.
And I hope that they can get in the car
and drive away and escape and be OK.
And that's something that you can extract just
from one screenshot, which I think is kind of cool.
There's a lot of strategy games where
if you weren't really thoroughly
um, versed in all of the pros and cons of the different stat systems and so on,
uh, you wouldn't be able to tell even which, like, team was winning or something.
Um, and I think it's a thing that, um, Beck and I both love about, um, uh.
You know, I think board games was another big inspiration for this project, but
pandemic in particular, and pandemic is this kind of like, imagine like risk, except instead of armies,
it's viruses, and you're trying to control these kind of virus breakouts around the world, these
epidemics. And as soon as you know that the game is about epidemics, the
Basic game board is really communicative, even if you don't know a lot about board games.
You can see that it's a map of the earth.
You can see that certain cities have a lot of cubes on them. You may not necessarily know right off the bat which
whether or not it's good to have a lot of cubes, but you can certainly tell that there are big differences between certain cities
on this world map that you know, because you can recognize these places. They're real actual places.
And so
I think developing, especially developing the visual look and feel of the game
was motivated by a lot of those concerns,
wanting a lot of the places in the game to be kind of recognizable
and for the stakes to be easy to understand.
And that all kind of is connected to, I think, the way that the gameplay evolved,
which was an ongoing increasing interest in
Maybe initially making what we felt was a challenging strategy game, but over time realizing that
that was only kind of interesting because you were worried about these little characters,
and you wanted them to be okay.
And Beck and I started calling it, like, Tuning for Drama, which is a...
A possibly ridiculous way of talking about this kind of game design, but it was things like,
you know, in older versions of the game, the characters couldn't move diagonally.
They could only move kind of orthogonally along the grid, like a, you know, most chess pieces,
or like all the sort of monsters in the game. They can only move up, down, left, right. And
that seemed like a reasonable thing to do. Everything follows the same rules.
Cars go up, down, left, right. Monsters go up, down, left, right.
And characters go up, down, left, right. And that feels fine.
Because, you know, you want consistency and you want fairness.
But it turns out it's much more fun if the characters can move diagonally.
You get, like you're seeing here...
Yeah, literally, that moment was like the only reason Anton makes it out of here is because of that.
Yep, exactly. And it's like, oh, you get really cool close calls now.
I guess it didn't matter in this case, maybe, but...
Oh, watch, watch.
Oh, is he going to pull a move here?
He's going to pull a...
Oh, maybe he doesn't pull a move. No, he just gets...
Maybe not.
Oh, he had a good run.
And he took care of that plant to the very end. That's beautiful.
You were saying, sorry.
Oh no, it's fine. But yeah, like this moving diagonally feels like it's breaking rules and making the game unfair
and maybe making the player too powerful.
We wanted players to feel kind of scared and vulnerable, but what it really does is it gives you all these opportunities
to have even more close calls and even more narrow escapes.
And that started to become the metric by which we judged what sorts of decisions we were going to make about...
Game mechanics or game rules or game actions or whatever it was like does this
Help you does this give you a way to
It's kind of like you know
What sorts of tools can you give the player to make them to give them ways to cleverly take care of these?
like lost little puppies
and so letting them move diagonally and push things around and repair things and heal each other and revive each other and
Shove things away from you and sometimes, you know, really fight back or manipulate the environment by starting fires or whatever.
Anything that felt like it was not just systemically interesting and a good fit for the setting,
but also that played into these kinds of fantasies of taking care of these lost little people on their road trip.
Those started to be things where we felt like,
okay, maybe this is a slightly unconventional decision
in terms of the mathematics about this game mechanic,
but it kind of elevates this,
squeaking out by the skin of your teeth kind of experience.
Or either because it's an interesting mechanic, like,
oh, I can squeeze between these two things and barely make it to safety.
Or because it's something that makes you feel sympathy toward the little characters,
like trying to come up with a good system for generating their backstories,
or when our art director Heather made sure that everyone had eyebrows,
or coming up with a couple of cute items that they can carry around,
like all these little bits and pieces that make you feel more connected to the little characters.
Those are things that help elevate this too.
And it seemed like it was these two things,
coming up with kind of gameplay opportunities
for people to feel like they have agency
in orchestrating these narrow escapes,
but also just taking time and effort
to make the little characters feel like they're people that are worth saving
and that you feel like you want to protect.
That is quite an answer.
Sorry, did I cut you off?
Oh, no, no, no.
That's a lot of answer.
My immediate follow-up is to ask, and for folks in chat, I'm going to give a quick
shout out to Sean Peoples, to Sam Falavin, to Clifton B, who I saw in there.
We are going to take your questions.
We're going to, for a minute though,
we're just going to be focusing on
this discussion about the game's design.
Adam, that leads to
my immediate follow-up question,
which is sort of born
explained by the
answer you just gave, but
why is this game so hard, and why is this game so
sad, then? Like, it's
interesting, because Narrow Escapes,
you're going to see a ton, like,
we've seen a ton of these in the stream already, and there's going to be
more happening.
Like the game, what you described is almost eerily playing out in echo with your answer in my footage, which is just like, I feel like I'm being haunted by you.
You are. It's okay.
But difficult and sad are still the two immediate vibes I got when I came away from this game after this hour yesterday. And I'm curious, why is that? It feels very intentional.
It is intentional and I feel like historically a lot of my game ideas are pretty gloomy.
And I think that comes from a few different places but partly like
there are a lot of games that are kind of ostensibly about the end of the world and they are
Uh...
Very...
If not upbeat, then very, like, action-oriented.
Or they're very...
Not even action-oriented.
They're still about conquering.
It's like, there's a lot of end-of-the-world games
where you win by engaging in the kind of, like, actions and morals
that tend to bring about the end of the world in the first place.
Mm-hmm.
And then that's how you win, sort of.
So, you know, I think a classic, like a classic game loop that we accidentally ended up not using,
but then I think retroactively felt kind of good about, is, you know, like a classic dungeon crawly game loop,
is you kill all the monsters on the floor that you're on, and then you go collect all the treasure that all the monsters had,
and then you proceed down to the next floor.
Which is...
I don't know. I feel like that...
It's something that makes you feel powerful, which is a big part of what makes it fun
for a lot of players. It's also been done a lot.
And...
Something that has been a preoccupation for this whole project
is, you know, what if you made...
A game that had the post-apocalyptic setting like you're maybe sort of familiar with,
and also had this kind of turn-based, kind of tactical gameplay
that maybe is familiar from other games in the genre.
But the emotional palette wasn't that you were leveling up overwhelming power
in order to save the world,
but instead you were just sort of there when the world was ending.
And what would you do? And I think, like...
The short answer is I think it's extremely appropriate for a game about the end of the world to be challenging and sad.
I think the world ending is challenging and sad.
And...
But I also think that it's not necessarily the only...
I don't think it's a one-note emotional experience.
Like a lot of the mechanics in this game are reactions to mechanics in other procedural
long-form strategy games where, you know, having a crushing defeat in one level means
your campaign is over and you really fundamentally have to restart the game in order to proceed.
And in Overland, you can have a crushing defeat.
You can.
have to abandon your very favorite dog, even though they're named Potato.
And it feels bad, but it does not end your campaign.
You can meet other people, and you can recover.
And you can have another hard loss, and you can recover from that too.
And I feel like...
I guess I totally agree that it is a challenging game and is a game with a lot of sad parts,
but I think it has... I think there's a lot of hopeful things in it, and that the
the palette is definitely not intended to be one of complete hopelessness.
That there are...
good things to do and things worth doing and there are people in the game that you can help
and there are, you know, positive things that you can do even though the world is ending.
Right on. We are going to move on through our stream. I have more questions about
this game's design but Adam, I do think those were very eloquent answers about tone and
designing for toning games. I really liked your phrase earlier, tuning for drama.
In particular, I just wanted to add one comment about, you said in there, like, you know,
in games about the end of the world, you're often participating in the behavior of ending
the world.
I think that even strangely loops back to your bit about dungeon crawling and how the
dungeon crawling loop is loot things and then, or kill the monsters, loot things.
Even though those settings are not apocalyptic, you're kind of creating an apocalypse for
Oh, anybody who lived in the dungeon is having their world ended by you, definitely.
I think that's an insightful... I hadn't thought about that before, which isn't to condemn that kind of mechanic.
It's just to... I understand your... I think your framing goes broader than you stated originally.
CliftonB would like to know, what's one feature you've had to cut for some reason that you really wanted to keep in the game?
Ooh...
I think we didn't... well, oh boy, good...
Good question, Clifton.
Yes, good question. There were... there's... we got pretty lucky in a bunch of ways.
One is that there wasn't that much stuff that we ended up cutting.
There were a lot of things that were planned, but never actually got started.
One thing that was in a bunch of the early prototypes was...
Basically like a dirt bike.
Mm-hmm.
So especially for doing solo runs through the game,
it was this sort of weird vehicle
that you could drive all over the map.
And you didn't have to stay on the road.
And it had a bunch of weird properties
compared to the other vehicles.
And it ended up feeling like, A, it
was going to be a lot of animation work
to get all that set up and feeling good.
And B, it kind of, we.
Playing with that vehicle and exploring that thing would kind of miss out on a lot of the
sort of hunkered down inside the car in the rain while things move around outside feelings.
But it was kind of cool and fun. There was a bunch of planned stuff that I think would have
been interesting to investigate and we might still get a chance to do. My favorite one was
I wanted to put horses in.
Uh, like you could ride horses from place to place and they wouldn't need gas, but you would have to like find
grass instead
And like get off and like defend the horses while they munched and then like hop on and ride some more
um, and I was really jazzed about that right up to the point that I realized that was like almost
A completely separate game than the one we were building and that probably we would have to set that aside
uh
I'm sure I'm forgetting a bunch of other stuff, but those are the two that come to mind.
Overland 1, you pet dogs. Overland 2, you pet horses.
It's still pretty tempting.
Oh man, Overland Expansion Pack.
There's a lot of ways you could implement horses.
Clifton, thank you for the question. I'll just share a few other quick comments here.
Chris Graft at Gamasutra Editor-in-Chief is hanging out in chat.
Had a perspective of, from our comments earlier about Worlds Ending,
Fallout is a game where you nuke the world in response to the world being nuked.
Sean Peeples is hanging out in chat making geometry jokes.
Sam Palavan has a question, how does one get good at Overland?
Sam Palavan, I would say that this current stream is about 40 minutes of decent gameplay advice for getting good at Overland.
So maybe that'll help you. I hope it does.
We'd love to do gameplay advice, but I think the Fingie Discord has been a good place for that, right?
Yeah, there's a pretty active community of players on there.
And there are, I think, you know, when you start building a game that is about
not nuking the world in a genre, and a little bit more broadly for this genre, or this, you know,
both gameplay genre and story genre.
You end up with different mechanics and different things that you're trying to do.
And those are not always intuitive.
And so, you know, things like,
oh, it's really important to protect the car.
Cars are not a completely disposable asset that you can simply lose and carry on the game as if nothing happened.
That's a new idea to some players. But yeah, hopping on the Discord and talking to
the players on there and we also like some of the design crew are on there from time to time as well
and super happy to
help give tips and feedback and hear stories about how
They thought that they had left Harold behind, but in fact they hadn't and were very upset to see him later.
Right on.
Going to go back to my question pile real quick.
Let's talk about procedural generation.
Adam, I think we've had a good chat about mood, tone, vibe, and making specific artistic, aesthetic, and design, like, interactive choices to drive that mood.
But at the end of the day, the computer has to dive into some base of logic in order to make something procedural spit out.
Would you mind outlining?
I'm going to dive into one question.
How does the game know to say in a level like the one we're looking at to spit out a house
that takes up a quarter of the map, a fifth of the map, I don't know, an eighth?
That's like one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, a ninth of the map.
It takes up a ninth of the map and effectively says this area is not play space.
How does the game know to do that and what is the game trying to do when it makes procedural
stuff?
Yeah, so we went through a few iterations on that also,
but the current system, the base system is one that I'm really happy with.
And I don't know if other games do it or not,
but basically, because we know that every level is going to take place
in this little nine by nine space, we've got like 81 tiles there.
I think you could do this at larger scales too,
but it's a little bit more manageable at smaller sizes
in terms of defining these things.
But basically...
Every object in the game, we call them placement masks, but they're essentially gradients based on existing level features.
So the primary ones are, where are the edges of the level, and where are the roads.
And we can sort of make a little kind of blurry gradient out of that information
and then start to overlap it with the placement masks that these different objects have.
So, for example, the placement mask for houses says,
you know what, these things really do, these things don't look good if they're in the very bottom corner,
right there in the middle of the camera, taking up the whole level.
They also don't look good when they're in the road.
And they don't look great if they're too close to the road. Something about it feels off.
And so we can define a placement mask for the house
that's like you should be at least this far away from the road and you should stay out of that
what is it?
Southwest corner of the level.
And then
the level generator can... oh, we also can keep track of how hilly the terrain is.
And so we can have it kind of check, you know, is this on a, is this part too slopey?
Or is this part kind of flat enough to, uh, uh, believably place a human domestic structure?
Uh, and then, um, so the, I guess the very first step is the terrain that this level
takes place on is actually quite large.
This road goes on and on off the screen, both ways.
Um, we pick out the slice of it that we want to use first, and then we
start populating it with objects.
So once we've cut out that little square, the level generator will usually go through
and roughly from largest to smallest, we'll start to populate the level with key items.
So there are many arrangements of roads and hills that will prohibit the appearance of a house entirely,
and so it simply won't happen.
And then it might go through...
We usually prioritize your kind of mission-critical resources, so...
This is, I think, like a scavenging level probably.
And so we'll go and place in a few objects where you can go and open them up and get some items out of them.
And each of those objects has its own placement mask.
So smashed up cars usually show up near the road or on the road.
Sheds usually show up kind of back toward the edge of the level with their door facing outward.
Fences tend to be arranged along specific lines near the edges of levels, that kind of thing.
So we're able to give that information to those objects, which is great.
And there's a few special cases where we have some code that does something a little more complicated,
but most of the placement is controlled by those things.
But the ingredients that it chooses from are all based on where you are in the game
and what kind of level you're going into.
So on this stream here, they're going to a level where you can get a hopefully undamaged vehicle
with a little bit of gas in it and maybe find a cool upgrade for a car too.
This is a special set of ingredients where we're saying,
okay, you're in the woodlands, that means we're looking at these kinds of ingredients for the level.
We know that you are a little ways off the main road,
so we're going to use kind of a medium difficulty level enemy set instead of a high difficulty enemy set.
We are going to also... oh, it's nighttime. Okay, we're going to make sure that...
In this zone, maybe there's a streetlight that you can activate. That might be kind of interesting.
And then also you're supposed to be scavenging a vehicle, so somewhere on this map we're also
going to place a car that you can maybe collect and drive out of there. And somewhere down the
chain you can also have kind of like wild cards. So wild cards are sort of these late stage
modifiers for the kinds of ingredients that go into the level.
So it might be to populate the level with a forest, or to add a little, like, farmhouse vignette, or to...
It turns out you're in kind of an open space with a lot of dry, flammable things, and there's a fire in the corner, and so on and so forth.
But those kind of...
Sort of, I guess, like a...
Cascading overrides for the kinds of situations that you might or might not run into,
plus these placement masks, plus paying attention to where you are in the game and what kind of resources you're getting.
Those are all factors that feed into how it generates the level and where things go.
Right on. This level is really, really, this is such an interesting bit of game we're seeing here because
in two, the fact that the game is going to keep going after this one is such a testament to the
work you all have put in. Because in an instant, the light of the explosion showed me where the car was.
My principal character, who I started this run with, was killed by one of these creatures.
My dog goes on a rampage.
Invent of vengeance and my new survivor...
Good job Patches.
Patches is a good dog.
And this other survivor is gonna get them both out by the skin of his teeth.
Ooh!
Samplevan...
Would like to know how do you deal with some of the feedback...
The RNG of the game can feel unforgiving.
And I have a follow-up question for that but I'm gonna let you answer his question first.
I think it's a super understandable response that I sympathize with to a great degree.
There's a lot of things in this game where you learn by doing.
There's not a huge formal tutorial process where you have to read lots of text before you go out into the world.
It's a lot of sort of, you know, actually thinking about what you're doing.
Trying to make good guesses, but also paying a lot of attention to what happens.
Those are things that are hard to do.
Not saying that this is the right way to make a game, obviously,
but there are lots of games where that's not really a thing that they demand that you do.
There are a lot of games where the...
I guess progress is determined mostly by doing one very straightforward task at a time,
and that's how you move forward.
And I play a lot of games that are built that way,
and I enjoy a lot of games that are built that way,
and I think there's a lot of people who...
don't need a game to ask them to think really hard about what to do next.
That's like, that's not why they play games. And I think that's a completely fair stance.
And it is something that Overland asks you to do, and I think it does create a little bit of a
gap between two player bases, where one player base feels like, wow, this game is so attentive.
From just feedback we've been getting, like, this is an attentive, detailed game,
and almost any situation you get into, if, you know, you can figure out a sneaky way to escape.
That's so rewarding, this is the kind of game I've always wanted to play.
Something to that effect, right?
And then you have another audience of people who are like,
well, I had a big car, and I rammed the thing really hard and killed it,
and then my car blew up, and I got game over,
and...
Um, frankly, uh, this isn't fun for me.
Um, and like, I don't know, I guess I feel like that's a pretty fair reaction
to a video game, but I also think there's a little bit of a culture of like really
needing or wanting to, um, assign that dislike some, uh, you know, something
that sounds more.
like justified or intellectual or something. In film theory this is sometimes called like,
at least like in like pop film theory, like there's this idea of tangible details
and tangible details is like you're watching a movie, you're not really gelling with it for
lots of different reasons and then there's like one scene in it where a character has a
really deliberately stylized costume or something.
And you'll start to see a lot of feedback about this movie, which is like, this movie's, um, uh, look at this costume.
Look at this one specific thing about this movie that is just like completely preposterous.
And this is what makes this movie bad is this costume choice.
Um, when really it's like, maybe, uh, you know, just not your kind of movie.
And there's a lot of different reasons that you feel that way, but you've found.
You have this one thing that you can kind of say is like,
oh, you know what it is though? It's really this. It's this one thing.
It's a, uh, you know,
there's one simple reason that I feel this way. Um,
and I think for this game so far, there's definitely like, um,
a subset of players who have decided that it's the RNG. Um,
so I guess our floating point numbers are not the kind that they want.
a game like this to have.
Which, I don't know. I guess that's...
I think it's a totally valid feeling to have, and I understand how people get there if they haven't
sort of discovered
all the things that you can do in the game.
Or sometimes I think it's just like this reboot. Like the thing we were talking about about like
I...
Actually, you know what? Let me put it this way.
If your totally reasonable assumption on picking up this strategy game is that you're going to kill all the monsters, get all the treasure, and proceed to the next level,
the RNG in this game probably feels very unfair.
Because that's not what you can or should do in this game.
Um, so I guess, yeah, I think I, I would stop short of saying that people are,
um, wrong or misinformed or, you know, um, entitled or anything like that.
I don't think those things are true, but I think if you turn this game on,
fully anticipating, um, something very similar to a game that you've
played many times before.
and you start playing it that way, that it probably is going to feel unfair.
And that is a completely intentional design decision. I don't know that it's
the best one for every audience or anything, but that definitely is a...
I guess like we were talking about before, we wanted to tell stories about the end of the world.
I think it's pretty appropriate for those stories to not be stories where you obliterate everything and you get lots of awards for doing it.
I don't know. Sorry, that was a bit of a roundabout answer.
I like roundabout answers because I feel genuinely as though when people are making roundabout
answers they are letting us share in the thought process that help make these decisions happen
because at some point, you know, you had to ask yourselves that question because you were
talking about XCOM and talking about that hack game earlier.
Definitely, yeah. And it's funny because my relationship with those games is very much a relationship with trying to understand their approach to randomness.
One thing we deliberately omitted from this game was percentage to hit.
That was a thing that I wanted to not be part of the equation for a wide variety of reasons.
And, you know, there's a lot of...
I think pretty...
Stuff that I hope I can reuse on later projects,
but sort of ways of thinking about, like,
okay, we've got a compact space.
How do we make sure that
once people have learned the ropes
that they do have a ton of agency
and that they can interact with all the random systems
in this game in a valid and interesting way?
And what does that mean for, for example,
we do want...
Random events are great, technically.
They create a good sense of anticipation and surprise,
and they ask the player to improvise, and all of those things.
But how do you make those feel fair,
once you understand what's going on?
And I think a big part of that is things like delays.
So...
A big mechanic in Overland is that if you choose to fight off these creatures, or you're forced to fight off the creatures,
they usually make a ton of racket, and it attracts reinforcements.
But reinforcements showing up is a big deal in this game.
That's a really bad thing to happen to you while you play, even if it's frequently necessary.
And so there's like kind of this big stepped out delay.
There's like two or three turns before the creatures actually appear in the level
and you can see exactly where they're going to appear ahead of time.
And trying to maintain, we always thought of it internally as like proportional distance.
So if something is going to happen that was going to have a big outcome on the gameplay,
and it has a random element to it, that you get warning.
You get some kind of proportional warning in terms of turns or steps or distance or something.
Right?
You'll almost never have something actually random happen right in front of you with no way to react
to it and no way to engage with it.
Even if the way to react to it or dodge it is not wildly obvious.
RumbleRumbleRumbleRumbleRumbleRumbleRumbleRumbleRumbleRumbleRumbleRumbleRumbleRumbleRumbleRumbleRumbleRumble
I am going to briefly turn back to chat and let folks know we only have, we started late today, so we only have about I'd say 15 more minutes?
Let me see, how long has this video been running for?
Yeah, about 14 minutes left.
So we've only got about 14 minutes left to chat about Overland.
If you have questions, drop them in chat, we'll get them in.
Adam, I would like to know...
God, I have too many questions.
Okay, I'm going to prioritize a question that I saw Chris Graff ask before I move on to my question.
This game launched on... I counted it at four platforms.
If the number's five and I forgot one...
But you guys launched on Apple Arcade, which is a brand new platform for everyone.
And the Switch is still relatively new for everyone too.
Trying to figure out how to make and sell appealing games on Switch is certainly not an easy thing.
What did it take for a small company like Finji to be able to make sure this game worked on all
five of those platforms? Because it's not as simple as going into Unity and pushing export,
despite what nobody believes. Nobody believes that. I just make up that hypothetical.
Right, right. Maybe slightly straw software issue.
It was tricky. So we launched simultaneously on Apple Arcade,
PC, Mac, Linux, Switch, PS4, and Xbox.
There we go, yeah. So expand PCM into several dimensions.
Yes.
And it was...
And also, like, technically three different PC storefronts.
So either by platforms or storefronts,
PC was its own complicated beast, for sure.
It was tricky. We had a lot of help, so
Mike Lee from Lodoco has been...
working on the Apple Arcade version of the game full-time for months now.
We get to collaborate with a porting studio in Austin, Texas called 22nd Century.
And they have full-time engineers there who have been helping us build the console versions.
And Mike spent a ton of time doing performance profiling stuff for us
throughout the porting process, which started months ago at this rate.
And our lead architect and engineer, Caitlin Culley and I, spent buckets of time just trying to figure out how to get this game running as smooth as we could on as many things as we could.
I think the Overland's presentation, I think, is pretty elegant and pretty clean, thanks to our art director, Heather Penn.
It is not necessarily a super game engine-friendly
target visual in the sense that
it's a procedurally generated game that usually imposes some
tricky performance issues one way or another on some platforms.
But in addition to that, it was...
You know, one of the big goals was to make a game
where the procedural levels didn't necessarily look terribly procedural.
We wanted to have something where there was a certain amount of composition.
And to a point where, I guess, speaking to earlier things
about procedural generation and level generation,
once we got the level generator working well enough to create...
valid gameplay scenarios, almost the second half of working on the level generator was to
push those playable scenarios into being pleasantly visually composed scenarios.
So for example this scenario here, there's a bunch of like grass and weeds on the ground.
Those have all been dynamically colored at
level load time to match the terrain.
But the train also is on fire, which is spreading at the moment,
systemically through these dried patches of grass.
So we actually need to dynamically recolor everything that's on the ground
to match the new burned ground color or else it looks wrong.
So that's a whole nother
like stack of the tech, but then also the diorama effect
is done dynamically and non-destructively
and at load time also.
So this piece of terrain extends far beyond the 9x9 boundaries here,
but we need to present it to look as if it's, you know,
a nice clean kind of model train diorama sort of situation.
And doing that was interesting.
That was a trick in and of itself.
When I was googling around for advice about how to do it,
I finally found a link to a Unity Forums post
asking about diorama cutaway tech.
It needed to be non-destructive for a bunch of weird reasons.
But I opened the post and there was a screenshot
of an older version of Overland.
And the person was asking,
hey, how do you get this effect to work?
And I was like, oh, this is hopeless.
So, um...
That's the most self-looping problem.
Yeah, it was a little bit terrifying.
That's when, like, kind of like, all caution to the wind and started trying really weird ideas.
And the way we ended up building this is, um...
Pretty odd, but works really, really well for our purposes.
We do not have time to get into that today, but I hope either A, you've submitted a GDC talk about it, or B,
we forgot to mention you're on the GDC board. Man, I'm good at this.
Oh, yeah.
Or B, if you're able to blog about it on Gamasutra, our sister website.
Yeah, I can share a link. I blogged about a part of the stack a year or two ago,
and
But yeah, there's a lot of things like that where there's like, you know, game
engines don't like cutaways of 3d models. It's not what game engines are
designed to do. Game engines don't like you dynamically recoloring everything in
the scene to look just a certain way. And there was a lot of...
a lot more, I think, work to support that technology in a console-friendly way
across the board than hopefully is obvious. Hopefully nobody notices.
The ideal situation is people turn on the game and they go, oh nice.
And that's the maximum depth of appreciation they have for the kinds of weird things that
we had to do to get it working. But yeah, there was a significant amount of experimentation and
Sort of new approaches behind the scenes to get something that could be, you know,
You know, we love game consoles, but a lot of them are like four years old now or something
and
You know weren't exactly the most powerful computers in the world when they came out anyway, and so trying to
Try to put something together that breaks a lot of kind of basic game engine art rules in the first place and then also
You know, runs at a nice, kind of satisfying 60fps clip on kind of medium-end consumer computers from four or five years ago is, I found it tricky at the very least.
Right on. We're coming up on the end of our hour and sadly, sadly we're coming up at the end of our time with Russell here.
Russell's about to take one for the team, guys.
Um, uh, is that kind of spoiling my own gameplay footage? I don't know.
I was actually going to try something really weird here for Russell.
But, um, so, uh, uh...
My next question then, because we only have a few minutes left,
Russell did nothing wrong, Sean Peoples, I don't know what you're talking about.
My next question then is, will the game like Overland,
oh, this is where I accidentally had my dog get out of the car, good job, Brian.
Um, how do you make sure every when every time the game opens up and starts generating,
like what a player's run will be, how do you make sure that that run is 100% beatable?
Like, say I was a player who was so good at this game, who understood every logic and
every time, and I understand it's part of the game for it to end tragically, like it's
about to see poor Russell gets left behind, but he has a car with no gas.
Bye Russell.
Bye, Russell.
He's definitely not going to make it.
Tragedy is...
Well, no, this is actually a good point.
In theory, this is where the game...
You just said earlier, this is where the game should go.
The game should go through the hard points.
There is no acing this game.
Maybe if you're lucky you can do some kind of version of 100%.
Certainly, you should be able to make a run from east to west coast.
But how as a designer do you make sure that's still possible?
Because to me, it feels almost like some runs are designed to be...
As a player, my bad perspective is sometimes it feels unbeatable,
but I also know I watch the stream again and I'm like, I made so many mistakes.
Right, right.
Yeah, like short of coming out and just telling people, it's a lot like as a designer it feels very like faith-based.
Like I'm hoping that they may be, you know, that we've indicated through being very very careful about the art and design and controls and all of these things that maybe, you know, it's okay for them to...
have expectations about how careful we were with other components of the game.
But it's really, I think, something that people have to, you know, figure out for themselves,
or hear from a friend that they trust, or something like that, in a lot of ways.
But as a designer, like, especially for Overland, that was like the easiest part of this game.
You know, like you just like just on the stream right here,
um, pulled up into a night level, horrible monsters everywhere,
no thanks, I'm driving away. You can just leave.
And a lot of strategy games aren't built that way, especially like, you know, these dungeon crawl scenarios where it's like,
oh, you have to go from this entrance over to this entrance, and you have to make sure it's navigable,
and that the number of monsters and power-ups are balanced or whatever.
And really all we have to do, like, every level you come into, the road starts clear.
Except for one. Our boss levels are the only exception.
The kind of blockades at the end of each zone.
And so those were their own kind of design problem that is kind of almost separate from a lot of the other generative stuff that we were working on.
But, you know, every level that you go to initially, the road is clear and you can leave if you need to.
And that.
As a procedural designer, I feel like it gave me a huge amount of wiggle room for what to do with the level designs.
I think we tried as much as possible.
Perversely, not wildly dissimilar from Wilmot's, but a lot of Overland levels are levels where you make your own problem.
And...
Speaking of making my own problems...
Yeah, for example...
You have this situation, right?
And I think it takes a little while to sort of feel that out and get a sense for whether or not
what is kind of like your culpability
and exactly what's going down here. But I think
a great example, our community manager, Harris Foster, was running a stream
a few days ago and he got stuck at the blockade in the mountains.
And things do get, I think, legitimately challenging at that point in the game.
And he started the roadblock, and it was a catastrophic failure.
He had level restart turned on, so he restarted the level,
and started making different choices,
and got a completely different, but equally catastrophic outcome.
So he restarted the level again, and made different choices,
and got a completely different, super successful outcome.
So, you know, this is a game where there are a lot of feedback loops.
And if you're not careful, you absolutely can back yourself into a corner.
But I think the basic building blocks of the game were essentially, like,
we will never back the player into a corner on our own.
That is not the game's job.
Players can do that, for example, very effectively.
We don't have to back them into a corner. They can handle that.
That just happens.
Adam, we could keep going, but I literally only have about 30 seconds of footage left.
So unfortunately it is time to wrap things up.
Thank you, everyone. Thank you, Informal Attire.
Stay mighty. Sean Peoples. Chris Graff. Thank you for dropping by.
Thank you, Adam, for joining us today.
Overland is out now. You can play it on all the platforms we mentioned earlier.
If you yourself are a game developer, a game designer, we would love to have you at GDC next year.
We just closed our sub-talks edition, so unfortunately we aren't going to be able to take your great talk ideas.
But if you submitted a talk to the Indie Summit, Adams Holtzman, Indie Summit board member, will be reviewing it. Has reviewed it, maybe.
That'll be tricky. I am not an Indie Summit board member, but they might let me peek at the talks anyway.
What are you a board member on again?
I'm on the design and business tracks for the main conference, but because of putting this game out,
they graciously allowed me to take a year hiatus, which is great.
I don't like... I've been on the board for about 10 years, and I do not like not being able to give the talks the attention that they deserve,
and that was just going to be impossible this year.
But I'll be back next year and I'm very eager to see everyone's design submissions then.
Right on. Sorry about the confusion, folks.
Yeah, so if in the future you are submitting a talk to GDC
and it's in the design or business track,
Adam will be helping you make a better talk.
With that, I'd like to just give a quick shout-out
for everyone in the chat.
If you liked this conversation with Adam,
we would love to have you follow us
on this Twitch here, Twitch channel,
because we're regularly going live
trying to have the conversations like the one we just had
to learn more about how games get made,
how games get so...
It's sold and other topics of conversation.
You can read more, you'll be able to find the stream video for this on Gamasutra.
And our own Twitch channel after this, on our YouTube channel too.
And we would absolutely love to have you at GDC next year.
Keep your eyes peeled, registration will be opening soon, trademark.
With that, that's all I've got. Adam, if they have more questions about how this game got made, where should they ask them?
Oh, welcome to Ask on Twitter, even though it's the worst website in the world.
We have an account for the game called at Overland Game,
and the official Finji is at FinjiCO, at Finjico.
But I'm a lot more likely to hang out and talk about game design on the Finji Discord,
which you can probably Google at this point,
but just in case you can also just type in discord.gg slash Finji.
And that should take you right to a little invite page.
And it's probably, it's our community manager and community designer's biggest project since we hired him.
And it's become like a really marvelous place for lots of folks, game designers and otherwise,
to kind of hang out and have a cozy place on the internet that is not horrible.
Not Nazi.
And yeah, not, it is a completely Nazi-free hangout.
It's just, it's become like a really nice online community.
So, especially if folks have a little bit of interest in game design
or working on small projects,
we have a channel that's kind of just for that.
And we would love for people to stop by and talk about game design
and share the stuff that they're building.
And we have a couple of dope emojis.
That's a thing, I guess.
So...
We could use some emojis.
Admittedly, I've been slacking on that front.
Yeah, there...
I was about to say they're important, and that's not true.
But they are fun.
Right on.
Well, I believe we're in the business where fun is important, Adam, but I'm not going
to tell you how to do that.
You literally sit on the design board.
With that, I wish everyone have a good Wednesday.
Have a good week.
Happy October.
Heck, be spooky season.
Make your Twitter handles, if you have them, if you're in the Nazi infested hellhole.
Make them spooky.
Celebrate games, and we will see you all next week, hopefully.
Maybe.
Maybe next week? Yeah, I'm trying to get something for next week. If not, it's going to be later this month.
Because at some point I'm going to Sweden and I can't stream from Sweden.
Have a good day everyone. Bye!